<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="correspondence"
    xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Correspondence</title>
                <title type="sub"/>
                <author/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>compiled by</resp>
                    <name>Ian Bent</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
        <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
        <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>This resource is publicly available and free at the point of access and it is
                        registered under a a <ref type="external"
                            target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">Creative Commons
                            license Attribution-Share Alike 3.0</ref>
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at
                http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/about/encoding/</p>
        </encodingDesc>

        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2009-08-06</date>

                <name>TL</name>

                <desc>Template Created</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date/>
                <name/>
                <desc/>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>

        <body>
            <head>Correspondence</head>

            <div>
                <p>In a period spanning nearly half a century, from 1888 to 1935, Heinrich Schenker
                    wrote to and received letters, postcards, calling cards, telegrams, etc. from
                    about 400 correspondents—journal editors, publishers, professional musicians,
                    librarians, archivists, Viennese officials and institutions, societies, members
                    of the Brahms circle, patrons, composers, visual artists, music critics,
                    authors, scholars, pupils, followers, family members, and personal friends. </p>

                <p>This correspondence is now widely dispersed in Europe and the USA. Much of it is
                    preserved in two dedicated Schenker archives (Riverside, California; New York),
                    in public libraries and archives (Vienna, Berlin, Marburg, etc.), in the
                    archives of commercial companies and private institutions, and in private family
                    possession. Some 7,500 documents are known to survive. </p>

                <p>In fact, Schenker corresponded with many more people and organizations than the
                    400 represented in the surviving materials. There are many “ghost”
                    correspondences, i.e. written exchanges that no longer survive but which are
                    noted in the diaries and whose content can be at least partly reconstructed with
                    the aid of summaries recorded in the diaries. In addition, <hi rend="italic"
                    >SDO</hi> regularly tracks down hitherto unidentified caches of correspondence
                    and brings them to publication. </p>

                <p>Correspondences range from a single item to over a thousand. The most extensive
                    are those with Universal Edition and its representatives (1,260 items), Moriz,
                    Valerie, and Fanny Violin (1,026), Drei Masken Verlag and its representatives
                    (384), J. G. Cotta (293), Reinhard Oppel (225), and Hans Weisse (214). They
                    include renowned people from many walks of life: the composers Paul Hindemith,
                    Ferruccio Busoni, and Arnold Schoenberg, the musicians Wilhelm Furtwängler,
                    Johannes Messchaert, Moriz Rosenthal, and Paul Wittgenstein, the musicologists
                    Guido Adler, Otto Erich Deutsch, Alfred Einstein, and Anthony van Hoboken, the
                    critics and editors Eduard Hanslick and Maximilian Harden, and the military
                    leaders Erich Ludendorff and Paul von Hindenburg.</p>

                <p>These encompass everything from the most formalized official missives to the most
                    personal intimations: a vast spectrum of communications reflecting everything
                    from technical music theory, through aesthetics, through political and economic
                    affairs, to details of family and domestic life. They represent every
                    conceivable type of relationship between two correspondents, and as such afford
                    deep insight in Schenker's personal psychology, life, and work. </p>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
