<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="1930" sdoID="CA-12-13">CA 12-13</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2005, 2017</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2005, 2017</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2017</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2012-11-02" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>

  </sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002724">Cotta ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cotta, dated February 5, 1906</dc:title>
      <dcterms:created>1906-02-05T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2017-06-24</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker discusses the pros and cons of placement of music examples in
        Harmonielehre and of the captions; he asks to receive in future
        galley-proofs.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Correcturen; proofs; Beispiel; example; Notenbeispiel; music example; Erläuterung;
        elucidation; Bürstenabzug; proof; Titel; signature; Manuscript; Umfang; extent; Notendruck;
        music printing; Format; Fahnencorrectur; galley-proof</dc:subject>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-002405">Cotta</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-50">Wien, <tei:date when="1906-02-05">5. II.
          06</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Sehr geehrter <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002405"
          >Herr</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Ich bestätige dankend den Empfang der Correcturen u. Ihres Briefes vom 27<tei:hi
          rend="supralinear">d.M.</tei:hi><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
          place="foot">= <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-31_6">OJ 9/31,
          [6]</tei:ref>.</tei:note> Die gewünschten Beispiele werde ich baldigst nachsenden.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Was den Setz der Notenbeispiele anbelangt,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot">"Setz" ("setting"): Cotta used single-impression typesetting
          for music (i.e. small pieces of metal type combining note heads, stems, and stavelines: a
          system developed by Breitkopf in the 1750s), rather than engraving (as used for Schenker’s
          later publications).</tei:note> so verkenne ich zwar nicht Ihre Absicht, durch Trennung
        der vielen Beispiele den äußeren Eindruck zu steigern, dennoch habe ich nach reiflicher
        Überlegung mich entschlossen, sie lieber doch an der Stelle, wo sie eben citiert werden, zu
        bringen, um den doppelten Übelstand zu vermeiden, daß sie zu früh gebracht und mir störend
        wirken u. andererseits daß man <tei:add place="interlinear-above">dann</tei:add> nötig hätte
        zurückzublättern. Nun aber dennnoch dem richtigen Gedanken <tei:pb n="2"/> der sich in Ihrer
        Setzweise kundgibt, entgegenzukommen, gedenke ich ‒ allerdings nach Notwendigkeit u.
        Möglichkeit ‒ die Beispiele durch Einstreuung<tei:del rend="overstrike">en</tei:del> von
        kurzen Erläuterungen zu trennen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Instances of what Schenker has in mind are presumably the paragraphs in smaller type (as
          he suggests here in paragraph 4) that appear on pp. 25 and 26, describing the preceding
          music examples (C. P. E. Bach, Keyboard Concerto in A minor and Sonata in D minor). (In
          the published English translation, the former is omitted along with its preceding example;
          the latter paragraph appears as the first on p. 17, in regular type.)</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Selbstverständlich ist dann die Nennung des Autors des betreffenden Beispieles <tei:hi
          rend="underline">unmittelbar über dem Beispiele</tei:hi>, wie ich glaube, am besten, in
        der Ecke rechts, angezeigt.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Die Erläuterungen zu den Beispielen könnten indessen in einem veränderten, <tei:hi
          rend="underline">kleineren</tei:hi> Druck gesetzt werden.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In den mir bisher zugekommenen 4 Bogen Bürstenabzug habe ich die oben geschilderte
        Änderung mit roter Tinte selbst durchgeführt, <tei:pb n="3"/> bis worauf ich den Setzer
        aufmerksam zu machen bitte. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Bei der Angabe des Titels auf den Bogen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial"
          place="foot">. i.e. the signature of each gathering, which appears in the bottom left-hand
          corner of each first <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>, and reads in the finished book
          "Theorien und Phantasien."</tei:note> hat <tei:hi rend="underline">mein Name zu
          entfallen</tei:hi>, wegen der Anonymität. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Um auf Ihren w. Brief zurückzukommen, so wird es doch praktischer sein, wenn Sie die
        Güte haben wollten, mir das <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Manuscript</tei:hi> der betreffenden
        Stellen vorläufig zur Verfügung stellen, damit kein Irrtum in Bezug auf den <tei:hi
          rend="underline lateinschr">Umfang</tei:hi> der fehlenden Beispiele sich
        einschleiche.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Beiliegend die ersten 2 Korrektur-Bögen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial"
          place="foot"> "Bögen": South-German form of plural "Bogen." The two forms are both used in
          this letter. Gathering 1 = pp. 1–16; gathering 2 = pp. 17‒32 of the finished book, but
          that is with the music examples incorporated at points of discussion.</tei:note>
        <tei:add place="interlinear-above">bei</tei:add> denen wegen der Änderung in der Fassung ‒
        auch <tei:add place="interlinear-above">wegen</tei:add> des großen Notendrucks u. des
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">kleinen</tei:add> Formates ‒ mehr Correkturen <tei:pb
          n="4"/> als vielleicht erwartet wurde, notwendig waren. Gerade dieser Umstand nahet mich
        aber zur Vorsicht, u. veranläßt mich, Sie zu bitten, ob Sie die Freundlichkeit haben
        möchten, mir statt der umbrochenen Bögen lieber vorerst Fahnencorrecturen zu
          schicken.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker is asking
          for the typeset material to be sent to him first as galley-proofs (i.e. long strips of
          type), before decisions have been made as to where pages begin and end (= page-makeup), so
          that he would have greater control over layout. He is also implicitly asking for an
          additional proof stage, since ("vorerst") he clearly still expects later to see the proofs
          made up into pages ("umbrochen"). This tells us (as do his references to "gatherings" of
          proofs) that he has so far been receiving page proofs, a gathering at a time, complete
          with gathering signatures.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Im übrigen beweisen die 3. u. 4. Bogen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Gathering 3 = pp. 33–48, and gathering 4 = pp. 49‒64 of the finished
          book.</tei:note>
        <tei:del rend="overstrike">schon, daß</tei:del> die demnächst nachfolgen, daß die
        Correcturen im weiteren Verlauf nicht so überaus zahlreich <tei:unclear reason="reading"
          >finden</tei:unclear> dürften, wie in dem ersten zwei Bogen.</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mit ausgez. Hochachtung</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ir ergeb.</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"><tei:hi
              rend="lateinschr">H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-50">Vienna, <tei:date when="1906-02-05">February 5,
            1906</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002405">Sir</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>I confirm with thanks receipt of the proofs and of your letter of the 27th of last
          month.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> I will send on the examples that
        you require as soon as I possibly can.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>As concerns the setting of the music examples,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> while I can well appreciate your plan to enhance the outward appearance
        of the many examples by placing them separately <tei:supplied reason="clarity">from the
          text</tei:supplied>, I have nevertheless, after careful consideration, come to the
        conclusion that it would be preferable to locate them where they are actually discussed, in
        order to avoid the doubly undesirable situation of their occurring too early on (to my mind
        disturbingly so), and on the other hand of the reader <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >then</tei:add> being obliged to leaf back to them. However, in order to come some way
        toward the right idea <tei:pb n="2"/> conveyed by your manner of setting, I am considering ‒
        for reasons of necessity and feasibility, if nothing else ‒ separating the examples by
        interspersing short elucidations.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Then, the best place to identify the composer of any given example is obviously, in my
        view, <tei:hi rend="underline">directly above the example</tei:hi>, in the right-hand
        corner.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>The elucidations of the examples could then be set in different, <tei:hi
          rend="underline">smaller</tei:hi> type.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In the four gatherings of proofs that have so far reached me, I have myself carried out
        the change outlined above in red ink, <tei:pb n="3"/> and I ask <tei:supplied
          reason="clarity">you</tei:supplied> to draw the attention of the typesetter to
        this.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Where the title is given on each gathering,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
          type="footnote"/>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">my name must be removed</tei:hi>, for reasons of anonymity.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>To get back to your esteemed letter: it will clearly be more practicable if you will
        very kindly make the manuscript of the relevant passages available to me for a short time so
        as to avoid any errors from creeping in as regards the <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >extent</tei:hi> of the missing examples.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Enclosed are the first two gatherings<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/>
        of proofs, <tei:add place="interlinear-above">for</tei:add> which more corrections were
        needed <tei:pb n="4"/> than had perhaps been expected on account of the change in layout ‒
        and also on <tei:add place="interlinear-above">account</tei:add> of the large type-size of
        the notation and the <tei:add place="interlinear-above">small</tei:add> format. It is
        precisely this situation that inclines me toward caution and prompts me to ask if you would
        very kindly first send me galley-proofs rather than gatherings in page-makeup.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>For the rest, gatherings 3 and 4,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> which
        will follow next, show that as the volume proceeds the corrections should not be so
        extremely numerous as they are in the first two gatherings.</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">With kind regards,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.
          Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
