<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2097" sdoID="CA-106-107">CA 106-107</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2005, 2018</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2005, 2018</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2018</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2012-11-02" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>

  </sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002724">Cotta ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cotta, dated December 2, 1909</dc:title>
      <dcterms:created>1909-12-02T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2018-08-02</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker explains the necessity for some late interpolations into Kontrapunkt
        I. — He may be able to include the title "Professor of Composition and Theory" against his
        name on the title-pages of his works, and debates the advantages of such an appointment at
        the Vienna Academy against the loss of independence. — Only anonymity has prevented
        Harmonielehre from success so far.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Korrektur; corrected proofs; Einschaltung; interpolation; Fertigstellung;
        completion; Spaltung; subdivision; Polemik; polemic; Verzögerung; delay; Vorteil; advantage;
        Titel; title; Professor; Differenz; difference; Freiheit; freedom; Schicksal; fate; Mäzen;
        patron; Renaissance; Gesammtwerk; collective work; Erfolg; success; Musikunterricht; music
        instruction; Einsamkeit; isolation; Geldvorteil; financial advantage; Reibung; friction;
        Anonymität; anonymity; geistiger Raubbau; intellectual property theft; Verbreitung;
        distribution; Auffassung; concept; Nomenklatur; terminology; Erscheinen;
        publication</dc:subject>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-002405">Cotta</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Sehr geehrter <tei:rs key="entity-002405"
            type="organization">Herr</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
            place="foot">A full draft of this letter exists at OJ 5/6, [4]. There are some 50 minor
            variants between the two. This edition does not attempt record the variants in the
            draft.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Die Absendung der Korrektur, die am <tei:date when="1909-11-29">29/11</tei:date> bei
        Ihnen eingetroffen sein dürfte, nehme ich zur Veranlassung, mich wegen der neuerlichen
        Einschaltung, u. des gleichsam in letzter Stunde dadurch etwas verzögerten Tempo in der
        Fertigstellung des <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001726"
          ><tei:title>Halbbands</tei:title></tei:rs> zu entschuldigen. So sehr ich zunächst doch
        selbst das größte Interesse habe, den letzteren endlich der Öffentlichkeit zu übergeben,
        zwingen mich besondere Umstände zu kleineren Einschaltungen dennoch unvermeidlich. Erstens
        ist die Spaltung des Bandes Ursache davon, daß ich dem Leser ersparen muß, ein Jahr lang auf
        die dringende Lösung eines besonders wichtigen Problems zu warten; d.h. wo es durchaus
        notwendig war, müßte ich Einiges aus dem <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001727"
              ><tei:title><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">II. Hbd</tei:hi></tei:title></tei:rs>
        vorausnehmen, der ja erst ein Jahr später folgen kann. (Solcher kleinen Einschaltungen aber
        wird es bis ans Ende des Halbbandes nur mehr 2 geben.) Zweitens mußte ich mit den neuesten
        Publikationen Schritt halten, <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overwritten">d</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="superimposed">u.</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> gerade rechtzeitig einige Polemik anbringen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Anderseits aber könnte eine kleine Verzögerung für den <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001726"><tei:title><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">I
          Hbd</tei:hi></tei:title></tei:rs> – ich verplichte mich dieser spätestens in 6 Wochen
        vollständig druckfertig zu machen – <tei:pb n="2"/> vielleicht sogar von Vorteil sein. Dann
        möglicherweise bin ich bis dahin in der Lage, schon den <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001726"><tei:title><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">I
          Hbd</tei:hi></tei:title></tei:rs> mit dem Titel eines K. K. Professors für Komposition u.
        Theorie an der <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002591">Hochschule (<tei:hi
            rend="lateinschr">Akademie</tei:hi></tei:rs>) in <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
          >Wien</tei:hi><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"> i.e. the Vienna
          Conservatory of Music, which had since January 1, 1909 acquired the title
          Kaiserlich-königliche Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst. See Schenker's diary, OJ
          1/7, p.78, February 15, 1908, which reports Schenker's interview with its president Dr.
          Karl von Wiener "on the matter of the Imperial-Royal Professorship in Theory." Schenker
          reports there one objection that was made to the plans he outlined, and his response. It
          is interesting that Schenker is still holding out hopes of this appointment so long
          (twenty-two months) after that "awkward conversation." (Cf the discussion of a possible
          grant from the Academy in 1914 in which Schenker says to Hertzka "Meanwhile, do not set
          any store by the Academy front, for the two un-notables of the institution, Messrs. Bopp
          and Wiener, are hostile to me since I have not been prepared to "kowtow" to their
          knaveries and incivilities toward me." ‒ WSLB 214, May 25, 1914.) <tei:lb/>It is notable
          that Schenker calls the new Academy "Hochschule": to Schenker, who associated the term
          with what he regarded as the superior educational system of Germany, the term signified
          something higher than a (grade) school and something more intellectual than a
          "conservatory," "college," or "academy." — This sentence and that which follows it
          together offer a revealing glimpse of Schenker's aspirations and of his conflicted
          relationship with academic authority. </tei:note> zu zeichnen. Es besteht nämlich die
        Absicht, gerade mich für diese leitende Stelle mit allen möglichen Vorteilen an Ehre u.
          <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Honorar</tei:hi> zu wählen, meinen Theorien die <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002591">Hochschule</tei:rs> vorbehaltlos zu öffnen u. dgl.
        mehr. Freilich giebt es da auch noch Differenzen, u. erst von der Beilegung der letzteren
        wird es aber abhängen, ob ich die Freiheit zu opfern endgiltig mich werde entschließen
        können. Denn in erster Linie strebe ich an, die Gunst des Schicksals, das mir einen Mäzen
        geschenkt hat,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">This is
          undoubtedly an allusion to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000743">Baron Alphons von
            Rothschild</tei:rs>, who paid the publications costs of <tei:title level="m"
            >Harmonielehre</tei:title> and <tei:title level="m">Kontrapunkt I</tei:title>. (By this
          time, Schenker had accumulated several other private patrons.)</tei:note> auszunützen, u.
        zum Wohl u. Besten einer kommenden Musik<tei:hi rend="lateinschr">renaissance</tei:hi> das
        einmal begonnene Werk zu vollenden u. namentlich doch den <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001759"><tei:title><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Bd.
          III</tei:hi></tei:title></tei:rs>, als den Mittelpunkt des Gesammtwerkes<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">By "Gesammtwerk" ("collective work")
          here Schenker means his <tei:title level="m">Neue musikalische Theorien und
            Phantasien</tei:title> as a whole. He had been planning to release his <tei:title
            level="m">Der Niedergang der Kompositionskunst</tei:title> ("The Decline of the Art of
          Composition"), originally intended as an Afterword to <tei:title level="m"
            >Harmonielehre</tei:title> (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="CA-5-6">CA
            5–6</tei:ref>, November 22, 1905), but which had expanded such that it was subsequently
          due to appear six months after <tei:title level="m">Harmonielehre</tei:title> (i.e. in May
          1907: <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-31_9">OJ 9/31, [9]</tei:ref>, June 5,
          1906), as volume III of <tei:title level="m">NMTP</tei:title>. In 1908 he was still
          speaking of it as the "culmination" of the work (<tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="CA-87">CA 87</tei:ref>, October 13, 1908); now, with the splitting of <tei:title
            level="m">Kontrapunkt</tei:title> into two half-volumes, he speaks of it, interestingly,
          as the <tei:hi rend="italic">Mittelpunkt</tei:hi> ("mid-point", or "fulcrum" as translated
          here) of the work. The work was not published in his lifetime.</tei:note> auf den Markt zu
        bringen. Auch bin ich übrigens des Erfolges schon des <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001725"><tei:title><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">II
          Bd</tei:hi>.</tei:title></tei:rs>, des „<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001725"
            ><tei:title>Kontrapunkt</tei:title></tei:rs>es“ – u. zw. des Erfolges auch, in
        buchhändlerischer, pekuniärer Hinsicht – damit sicher, daß ich derzeit bei privaten Erteilen
        von Musikunterricht u. in Einsamkeit lieber noch wirtschaftliche Nachteile erleide, also mit
        persönlicher Aufopferung die Arbeit fortsetze, bevor ich diese, wohl bei Ehre u. Geldvorteil
        nach außen, doch allerhand unvermeidliche Reibungen dennoch gefährde. Es ist ja nur die
          <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Anonymität</tei:hi>, die den <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001724"><tei:title>Bd. I</tei:title></tei:rs> vorläufig um der
        buchhändlerischen Erfolg gebracht hat. Denn, wie ich es hier<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05"
          type="editorial" place="foot">"hier" (here): by this Schenker means Vienna, as against
          Stuttgart, or Germany as a whole. Schenker makes this allegation of intellectual theft in
          Viennese circles frequently.</tei:note>
        <tei:pb n="3"/> täglich selbst erfahre, dozieren mehrere der angesehensten u. radikalsten
        Lehrer bereits nach meinen Theorien über „<tei:term>Stufe</tei:term>“,
          „<tei:term>Tonart</tei:term>“ <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">etc.</tei:hi> u. nur eben die
          <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Anonymität</tei:hi> giebt ihnen leider noch die Möglichkeit, den
        Urheber der Theorien selbst vor den Schülern verschweigen zu können, welch letzteres Mittel
        ja übrigens zu allen Zeiten das hauptsächlichste Element eines geistigen Raubbaues gebildet
        hat. Und mehr als das: der Verfasser einer Harmonielehre, die sich heute einer großen
        Verbreitung erfreut, H. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000540"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
            >Louis</tei:hi></tei:rs> in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002286">München</tei:rs>
        (der verstorbene H. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000888"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
            >Thuille</tei:hi></tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Draft has "H. <tei:hi rend="italic">R. Louis</tei:hi>" and "Komponist <tei:hi
            rend="italic">Thuille</tei:hi>." Schenker's allusion is to <tei:bibl><tei:author>Rudolf
              Louis</tei:author> and <tei:author>Ludwig Thuille</tei:author>: <tei:title level="m"
              >Harmonielehre</tei:title> (Stuttgart: Carl Grüninger Nachf., 1907, 2/1908, 3/1910,
            10/1933)</tei:bibl>. See also <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="CA-68">CA
            68</tei:ref>, September 13, 1907 for a reference to Thuille and the dispute with Riemann
          over prior claim.</tei:note> war <tei:del rend="overstrike">dessen</tei:del> sein
        Mitarbeiter am Werke) hat vor wenigen Tagen in einem Konzertreferent der „<tei:rs
          type="journal" key="entity-002552"><tei:title>Münchener. N.
          Nachrichten</tei:title></tei:rs>“ bereits einen von mir zum 1. Male kreierten Begriff
        sowie die dazu gehörige <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Nomenklatur</tei:hi> angewendet, obgleich
        er selbst in seinem eigenen Werk dafür noch eine ganz andere Auffassung u. <tei:hi
          rend="lateinschr">Nomenklatur</tei:hi> hatte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07"
          type="editorial" place="foot">No paragraph-break in either version, though in the finished
          letter "Ich" begins a new line.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich freue mich daher ordentlich darauf, daß, wie wir seinerzeit vereinbart haben, bei
        Gelegenheit des Erscheinens des <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001726"><tei:title><tei:hi
              rend="lateinschr">I Hbd.</tei:hi></tei:title></tei:rs> auch der Titel des <tei:rs
          type="work" key="entity-001724"><tei:title><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">I
            Bd.</tei:hi></tei:title></tei:rs> umgedruckt u. meinen Namen zeigen wird. In Verbindung
        mit dem „<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001725"><tei:title><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
              >Kp.</tei:hi></tei:title></tei:rs>“ wird dann auch das <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001724"><tei:title><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">I
          Bd</tei:hi></tei:title></tei:rs> – dessen bin ich sicher – trotz seiner unleugbar
        größeren, mit dem Stoff selbst leider naturgemäß verbundenen Schwierigkeiten, bessere
        Forschritte machen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nochmals also Entschuldigung wegen der kleinen Verzögerung erbittend</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Zeichne hochachtungsvoll ergeben</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60">
          <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">H
            Schenker</tei:hi></tei:rs>
        </tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1909-12-02">2. Dezember 09</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">


      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Dear <tei:rs key="entity-002405" type="organization"
            >Sir</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Since the batch of corrected proofs that I sent on <tei:date when="1909-11-29">November
          29</tei:date> should by now have reached you, I take this opportunity to apologize for the
        recent incorporation of new material, and the so-to-speak last-minute, somewhat reduced
        speed of completion of the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001726"
            ><tei:title>half-volume</tei:title></tei:rs> that has resulted from this. While having
        the very greatest possible interest in surrendering the latter at long last for publication,
        particular circumstances have driven me unavoidably to make some small-scale insertions.
        First of all, the subdiving of the volume has obliged me to save the reader from having to
        wait a whole year for the urgently needed solution to a particularly important problem; that
        is, where absolutely imperative, I have had to anticipate some things from the <tei:rs
          type="work" key="entity-001727"><tei:title>second half-volume</tei:title></tei:rs>, since
        the latter has no chance of appearing in less than a year's time. (There will, however, be
        only two more such short insertions between here and the end of the volume.) Secondly, I
        needed to keep abreast of the newest publications, and insert some polemical passages at the
        right points.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">On the other hand, however, a short delay for the <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001726"><tei:title>first half-volume</tei:title></tei:rs> ‒ which I undertake
        to have completely ready for printing by at most six weeks from now ‒ <tei:pb n="2"/> may
        actually turn out to be beneficial. By that time, I may well be in a position to identify
        myself even in the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001726"><tei:title>first
            half-volume</tei:title></tei:rs> with the title of an Imperial-Royal Professor of
        Composition and Theory at the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002591">High School
          (Academy)</tei:rs> in Vienna.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> That is,
        there is a plan to appoint me to this leading post with all the possible advantages of honor
        and remuneration, to open up the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002591">High
          School</tei:rs> to my theories without impediment, and other suchlike things. Admittedly,
        differences still remain over this, and on the reconciling of these will entirely depend,
        however, whether I shall ultimately be able to make up my mind to sacrifice my freedom. For
        in the first place I aspire to take advantage of the favor that fate has granted me in
        sending me a patron<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/>; and to complete the
        work I have already begun in the interests of bringing about a musical renaissance; and that
        means in particular putting on the market <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001759"
            ><tei:title>volume III</tei:title></tei:rs>, the fulcrum of the collective work.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> Incidentally, so confident am I of the success of
          <tei:title>second volume</tei:title>, of <tei:title level="m">Counterpoint</tei:title> ‒
        of its success in commercial and pecuniary terms, too, moreover ‒ that at the present time I
        still prefer to suffer commercial disadvantages by giving private music instruction and
        working in isolation, hence pursuing my work with personal sacrifice, than to jeopardize
        that work, albeit with outward honor and financial advantage, through a host of inevitable
        frictions. It is in fact only its anonymity that has robbed <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001724"><tei:title>volume I</tei:title></tei:rs> temporarily of commercial
        success in the book trade. For, as I know from my own daily experience <tei:pb n="3"/>
          here,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> several of the most reputed and
        radical teachers already lecture according to my theories of
          "<tei:term>scale-degree</tei:term>," "<tei:term>key</tei:term>," etc., and it is that
        anonymity alone that unfortunately still makes it possible for them to conceal the identity
        of the actual originator of those theories from their pupils. And this, incidentally,
        amounts for all time to the nub of any exploitation of intellectual property. And more than
        that: the author of a theory of harmony that today enjoys wide distribution, Mr. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000540">Louis</tei:rs> in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002286">Munich</tei:rs> (the late Mr. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000888">Thuille</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> was
        his coauthor in the work) only a few days ago in a concert review in the <tei:rs
          type="journal" key="entity-002552"><tei:title level="j">Münchner Neueste
            Nachrichten</tei:title></tei:rs> used a concept that was first invented by myself along
        with the terminology belonging to it, although he himself had used a quite different concept
        and terminology for it in his own book.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"
        /></tei:p>

      <tei:p>I am awfully delighted that, as we agreed previously, on the occasion of the appearance
        of the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001726"><tei:title>first
          half-volume</tei:title></tei:rs> the title-page of <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724"
            ><tei:title>volume I</tei:title></tei:rs> will also be reprinted and will bear my name.
          <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724"><tei:title>Volume I</tei:title></tei:rs> ‒ I am
        sure of this ‒ will then, in conjunction with <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001725"
            ><tei:title level="m">Counterpoint</tei:title></tei:rs>, also make progress despite its
        undeniably greater difficulties, which are unfortunately associated with the very nature of
        its subject-matter.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Once again, asking your forgiveness for the short delay,</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">I remain respectfully your devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60">
          <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">H. Schenker</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1909-12-02">December 2, 1909</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
