<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="1921" sdoID="CA-41-42">CA 41-42</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2005, 2017</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2005, 2017</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2017</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2012-11-02" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>

  </sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002724">Cotta ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cotta, dated October 1, 1906</dc:title>
      <dcterms:created>1906-10-01T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2017-06-28</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker goes back on his earlier agreement with Cotta, and makes an
        impassioned case for including the "Nachwort" as Section 3 of Part II of
        Harmonielehre.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>kaufmännisch; commercial; Nachwort; Afterword; Notenbeispiel; music example;
        Drucklegung; printing; Satz; setting; Konzept; draft; Kritik; criticism; Kunstwerk; artwork;
        Künstler; artist; Theoretiker; theorist; Theorie; theory; Dilletantismus; dilettantism;
        Publikum; public; Erfolg; success; Kampf; battle; Waffen; weapons; Essay; Referent;
        reviewer; critic; moralisch; moral; Pflicht; duty</dc:subject>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-002405">Cotta</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60">Wien, <tei:date when="1906-10-01">1. 10.
          06</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Sehr geehrter <tei:rs key="entity-002405" type="organization"
            >Herr</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of
            this letter is not recorded in Schenker's diary. It was the first day of the season of
            lessons.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Im Besitze Ihres w. von <tei:date when="1906-09-24">24. 9. 06</tei:date><tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-9-31_12">OJ 9/31, [12]</tei:ref>, which warns Schenker that, because of the
          increased length of the book and the extensive changes at proof stage, both the costs for
          which he will be answerable and also the retail price of the book will be higher than
          originally estimated. </tei:note> bemerke ich, daß ich selbstverständlich darauf gefaßt
        sein mußte, die verursachte Mehrarbeit zu honorieren.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Was mir aber besonders am Herzen liegt, ist Ihnen klar zu machen, daß ich schon aus
        kaufmännisch praktischen Gründen den für das „Nachwort“ reservierten Stoff in irgend einer
        Form dem Werke einverleiben muß.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >A "Nachwort" ("Afterword") estimated at one gathering (16 pages) in length was originally
          declared but not submitted with the rest of the manuscript (<tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="CA-5-6">CA 5-6</tei:ref>, November 22, 1905), but subsequently increased to around
          5‒7 gatherings (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="CA-25">CA 25</tei:ref>, May 29,
          1906). It was agreed that this should be published as a separate item about six months
          after the release of <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724"><tei:title level="m"
              >Harmonielehre</tei:title></tei:rs> (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="CA-27">CA
            27</tei:ref>, June 4, 1906), entitled "'<tei:title><tei:hi rend="italic"
              >Beethoven</tei:hi> oder <tei:hi rend="italic">Wagner</tei:hi>?': ein Nachwort zu den
              <tei:hi rend="italic">Neuen musikalischen Theorien und
          Phantasien</tei:hi></tei:title>." ("<tei:title>'Beethoven or Wagner?' An Afterword to the
              <tei:hi rend="italic">New Musical Theories and Fantasies</tei:hi></tei:title>"). It is
          this agreement on which Schenker is now attempting to renege. — For "reserviert"
          ("reserved"), see <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="CA-31">CA 31</tei:ref>, footnote 4
          regarding portions of type already set, which Schenker instructed should be held back and
          used for the separate item.</tei:note> In Anbetracht dessen, daß dieser Theil (den ich
        übrigens nicht als Nachwort <tei:add place="interlinear-above">sondern</tei:add> als
        organisch verbundenen III .h. letzten Abschnitt des praktischen Teiles geben will<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">The structure of <tei:rs type="work"
            key="entity-001724"><tei:title level="m">Harmonielehre</tei:title></tei:rs> is: Part I
          (Theoretical Application): Section 1 (Systems, their Basis, and their Differentiation in
          Relation to Position and Purity), Section 2 (Theory of Intervals and Harmonies); Part II
          (Practical Application): Section 1 (Theory of Motion and Succession of Scale-Degrees),
          Section 2 (Theory of the Succession of Keys).</tei:note>) fast keine Notenbeispiele mit
        sich führt, u. sich dessen Drucklegung somit sehr rasch abwickeln kann, erlaube ich mir,
        noch einige Geduld mit mir u. meinem Werke zu haben. Ich bin überzeugt, daß dieser Satz
        alledem noch rechtzeitig vor Weihnachten wird erscheinen können, da das Konzept bereits
        fertig ist.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Was in musikalischen Schriften aller Art (Lehrbüchern, Führern, <tei:pb n="2"/>
        Geschichtswerken, u. dgl.) in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482"
            ><tei:country>Deutschland</tei:country></tei:rs> u. sonst überall fehlt, ist eine Kritik
        der Kunstwerke auf Grund von kompositionellen Momenten, – u. was man zu lesen u. zu hören
        kriegt, ist kunstunkundiger <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Journalismus</tei:hi> oder – so bei
        Künstlern u. Theoretikern – eine theoretisch gern protzende, wegen falscher Theorien aber
        ganz irregehende, bald kleinliche, bald devote Betrachtung. Nun scheint mir gerade jetzt, da
        der <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Dilletantismus</tei:hi> der komponierenden
          ungeheu<tei:supplied reason="misspelling">e</tei:supplied>re Kreise zieht, der Drang im
        deutschen Publikum nach Orientierung in den geschaffenen Werten am gespanntesten, wobei ich
        gar nicht untersuchen will, ob der Drang blos gewöhnliche Neugier oder höhere Teilnahme an
        der Kunst bedeutet: der Beweis davon liegt in der starken Nachfrage nach Büchern aller Art
        über Musik, die nicht wegzuleugnen ist. Daß sich aber diese Nachfrage gleichwohl nicht in
        einem ganz außerordentlichen buchhändlerischen Erfolg irgend eines bisher erschienenen
        Werkes ausgesprochen hat, liegt nicht am Publikum, sondern an den Werken, die, wie ich schon
        oben sagte, völlig unkünstlerisch u. <tei:hi rend="underline">naiv</tei:hi> sind. So
        ungenügend sind die aus der Natur der Musik u. der Praxis unserer größten Meister gewonnenen
          <tei:pb n="3"/> Abstraktionen u. Nutzanwendungen ausgefallen, daß man die Meister, wie
        z.B. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
          >Brahms</tei:hi></tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055"><tei:hi
            rend="lateinschr">Beethoven</tei:hi></tei:rs> zu <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000556"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Mahler</tei:hi></tei:rs>, <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000695"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Reger</tei:hi></tei:rs>,
          <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">etc</tei:hi>. heruntercompromittiert, ohne zu merken, daß die
        letzteren Dilletanten sind, die lange noch keine Künstler, geschweige „Meister“
        sind.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun habe ich im Verlaufe des I u. II. Theiles meines <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001724">Buch</tei:rs>es, indem ich stets den Weg zur Kunst suchte, oft genug
        einzelne <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Argumente</tei:hi> wider den modernen <tei:hi
          rend="lateinschr">Dilletantismus</tei:hi> zu kreiren Gelegenheit gehabt, – d.h. ich habe
        mir selbst die Waffen geschmiedet, um den Kampf eröffnen zu können, u. so brenne ich denn
        begreiflicherweise darauf, von den Waffen Gebrauch zu machen. Oft genug wurde ich in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002484"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Wien</tei:hi></tei:rs>, <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002501"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Berlin</tei:hi></tei:rs>,
          <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">etc</tei:hi>. eingeladen, meine Ablehnung des modernen musik.
        Treibens zu begründen, in Vorträgen, oder <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Essays</tei:hi>, – ich
        habe alle Anträge abgelehnt, weil mir das Publikum im Zustand seines unvorbereiteten Hörens
        oder Lesens niemals hätte folgen können : nun habe ich endlich die Gelegenheit, das von mir
        ziemlich allgemein Erwartete, in organischer <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Form</tei:hi> zum
        Nutzen des Publikums, der Künstler u. der Referenten bieten zu können, u. sollte diese
        einzige Gelegenheit <tei:pb n="4"/> fallen lassen? Wie könnte ich das?! Ich halte es als
        meine moralische Pflicht, zu sagen, was ich weiß, u. darf vor Kosten u. sonstigen
        Rücksichten nicht zurückschrecken. Und wer weiß, ob nicht für die meisten Leser gerade der
        letzte Abschnitt die Hauptanziehung bilden wird?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In diesem Sinne bitte ich nochmals um ein klein wenig Geduld; in den nächsten Tagen
        schon werde ich mit etwa einem 1/3 des letzten Abschnittes, mit Titel des <tei:rs
          type="work" key="entity-001724">Buch</tei:rs>es u. der gewünschten Voranzeige
        aufwarten.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Mit vorzüglicher Hochachtung</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Ihr ergeb.</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"><tei:hi
              rend="lateinschr">H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">


      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60">Vienna, <tei:date when="1906-10-01">October 1,
            1906</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear <tei:rs key="entity-002405" type="organization">Sir</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>In receipt of your esteemed letter of <tei:date when="1906-09-24">September 24,
          1906</tei:date>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> let me make plain that I
        would of course be prepared to honor the additional work that has been created.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>What I am particularly concerned to do, however, is make clear to you that I must, not
        least for practical, commercial reasons, incorporate the material that has been reserved for
        the "Afterword" in some form into the work.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/>
        In view of the fact that this material (which, moreover, I will present not as an
        "Afterword" <tei:add place="interlinear-above">but</tei:add> as an organically integrated
        Third (= last) Section of <tei:supplied reason="clarity">Part II,</tei:supplied> "Practical
          Application"<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/>) includes virtually no music
        examples, and hence its printing could happen very fast, I take the liberty of asking you to
        be patient with me and my book just a little longer. I am convinced that, despite this, it
        will still be possible for the book to appear on the right side of Christmas, since the
        draft is already done.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>What is lacking in musical writings of all kinds (textbooks, guides, <tei:pb n="2"/>
        historical works, and the like) in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482"
            ><tei:country>Germany</tei:country></tei:rs> and everywhere else is a mode of criticism
        for art works that is based on compositional factors. ‒ What one usually reads and hears is
        a journalism ignorant of artistic matters; or ‒ as in the case of artists and theorists ‒ a
        way of thinking that is theoretically pretentiousness (because based on false theories) but
        wholly erroneous, sometimes pedantic, sometimes obsequious. The clamor among the German
        public for guidance in the creative values appears to me, precisely now when the
        dilettantism of those who compose attracts huge crowds, to be at its most intense, though I
        have no desire to inquire whether that clamor betokens merely the usual curiosity or a
        higher engagement with art. The proof of this lies in the keen demand for books of all kinds
        on music ‒ something that is undeniable. However, the fact that this demand has not hitherto
        resulted in any extraordinary commercial success on the part of any published book is not to
        be attributed to the public, but rather to the works themselves, which, as I have already
        said above, are utterly inartistic and <tei:hi rend="underline">naive</tei:hi>. The <tei:pb
          n="3"/> abstractions from the nature and practice of our greatest masters, and the
        redeployment of these, have proved so inadequate that masters such as <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055"
          >Beethoven</tei:rs> are dragged down to the level of <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000556">Mahler</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000695"
          >Reger</tei:rs>, etc., without realization that the latter are dilettantes, and far, far
        from being artists, let alone "masters."</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In the course of Parts I and II of my <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724"
          >book</tei:rs>, while constantly seeking the way toward art, I have frequently had
        occasion to devise specific arguments against modern dilettantism. That is, I have forged
        the weapons with my own hands in order to be able to commence battle, so it is only natural
        that I should burn to make use of those weapons. I have frequently been invited, in<tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002484"> Vienna</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>, and elsewhere, to account for my disapproval of
        modern musical goings-on in lectures and essays. I have turned down all such requests
        because the public, its hearing and reading in so parlous a state, could never have followed
        me. Now at last I have an opportunity to offer what has been quite widely awaited from me in
        an organic form for the use of the public, artists, and critics. Should I let this unique
        opportunity <tei:pb n="4"/> go? How could I possibly do that?! I take it as my moral duty to
        say what I know, and not to be deterred by costs and other suchlike considerations. And who
        knows whether it will not be just the final Section that will be the principal attraction
        for most of my readers?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>For this reason, ask you to be patient with me just a little longer. Within a day or
        two I will present you with about a third of the final Section, together with the title-page
        of the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724">book</tei:rs> and the preliminary
        announcement for which you ask.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">With kind regards</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Your devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.
          Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
