<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="870" sdoID="DLA-69.930-11">DLA 69.930/11</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB-LR">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent and Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="LR">
   <tei:persName>Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2013</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2013-04-15" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002698">Halm ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Halm, dated November 2, 1922</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1922-11-02T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2013-04-15</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker acknowledges receipt of two booklets on youth and the new republic,
    returns them, comments on them critically: idealistic German democrats desire maximal
    remuneration with minimal work; illustrates point by difficulties with maids in Schenker
    household; German democrats naively overestimate social and intellectual status of non-German
    commoners (French, British, American); Schenker decries cosmopolitanism and those Germans who
    advocate individuality at the expense of society; Schenker praises the fascists as countering
    communism and social leveling, compares Mussolini's Italy favorably with present-day
    Germany.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject> </dc:subject>
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000326">Halm</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Lieber u. verehrter Herr Professor <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000326">Halm</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/4, p. 2472, November 1, 1922:
      "An Halm (Br.): über Demokratie u. die eingesandten Hefte, die ich zurückstelle." ("To Halm
      (letter): about democracy and the [journal] issues sent, which I return."). This text is
      highly problematic, with many illegible or questionable words, and great difficulties of
      translation. Thanks are due to William Drabkin for help in deciphering and translating this
      difficult text.</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Mit bestem Dank sende ich die beiden Hefte „<tei:title>Rp. u. Jgd</tei:title>“
     zurück.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">"Republik und Jugend" is the
     title of an aphorism by Novalis that reads "Republik ist das Fluidum deferens der Jugend. Wo
     junge Leute sind, ist Republik." Reference here is to the journal <tei:bibl><tei:title level="j">Republik und Jugend: Blätter zur staatsbürgerlichen Aufklärung und
       Bildung</tei:title> (Weimar: Thüringen Ministerium für Volksbildung, 1922–23)</tei:bibl>. In
     it in the summer of 1922, Gustav Wyneken advocated a policy of political enlightenment among
     the upper classes in the higher schools with the aim of warding off right-radical tendencies in
     the aftermath of the assassination of Walter Rathenau on June 24, 1922.
       (<tei:bibl><tei:author>Heinrich Kuppfer</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Gustav
       Wyneken</tei:title> (Stuttgart: Klett, 1970), p. 241</tei:bibl>).</tei:note> Ich kenne u.
    besitze derlei Stücke schon seit langem; sie erreichen immer das Gegenteil davon, was der
    Verfasser unter die Menschen bringen will. Und alle sind sie heute überholt u. <tei:hi rend="underline">entlüftet</tei:hi><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">This must be "entlüftet"(deflated), even though there is a letter between "l" and
     "ü".</tei:note> durch den Vorstoß D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi>
    <tei:rs key="entity-000969" type="person">Wirth</tei:rs>’s<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">On April 16, 1922, Wirth and foreign minister Walther Rathenau
     negotiated the Treaty of Rapallo with the Soviet Union. Rathenau was assassinated on June 24; a
     secret agreement was signed between Germany and the Soviet Union on July 29; then Wirth
     resigned over the reparations question on November 14. Schenker writes this letter twelve days
     before the resignation.</tei:note> u. der Reichsregierung, die durch ihre Veröffentlichungen
    vor der ganzen Welt erweisen, daß die Schuld durchaus nicht <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>D.</tei:country></tei:rs> allein trifft, die von russischen u. franz.
    „Fälschungen“ ohne Schau sprechen. Wenn schon die Jugend in <tei:rs key="entity-002679" type="place"><tei:region>Thürg.</tei:region></tei:rs> politisiert werden muß, so wäre, unter
    dem Motto: Wahrheit ist nicht Haß, gerade von den Dingen <tei:hi rend="underline">zuerst</tei:hi> zu sprechen nötig gewesen, die der Verfasser <tei:hi rend="lateinschrift">ad
     calendas graecas</tei:hi> vertagt,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">"To the Greek Kalends": Said by Emperor Augustus, in Suetonius, with the sense of "never."
     Kalends were part of the Roman calendar, not of the Greek, so the "Greek kalends" are "a date
     that will never happen."</tei:note> u. nicht vom Zusammenbruch u. Dolchstoß, der in zehnter
    Reihe steht. In einer würdigeren Form hätte das Ministerium die Lage <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Deutschland</tei:country></tei:rs>s zwischen Franzosen, Eng., u.
    Slaven zum Bewußtsein bringen sollen, die Beschaffenheit dieser Völker, die das deutsche aus
    tiefsten Herzen hassen, die Notwendigkeit, den Taten des Hasses Widerstand zu leisten. Aber der
    deutsche Demokrat denkt zuerst an sich, seine Stellung, u. verteidigt sie gegen „Umschichtung,“
    obwohl er selbst nur durch eine Fracht-Umschichtung emporgekommen ist; daher obige Hefte . .
    .</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Ich spreche so offen zu Ihnen, weil ich Sie als Aristokraten empfinde,
    mögen Sie auch selbst sich für einen Demokraten halten. Ein Demokrat ist etwas völlig anderes
    als Sie. Hier einige Kennzeichen.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Vor Allem ist er bestechlich. Die Führergauner wissen ganz genau, was sie tun, wenn sie
    vor Allem die Löhne erhöhen u. Geld unter die Massen bringen, die käufliche Seele ist gleich mit
    Geld gewonnen! Selbst ein geistig vorgeschrittener <tei:rs key="entity-003235" type="organization">Philharmoniker</tei:rs>, auch von Haus aus vermögend, war von der Partei
    begeistert, als sie die Löhne in der <tei:rs key="entity-002778" type="organization">Oper</tei:rs> hinaufsetzte, u. es gieng ihm nicht ein, daß das hinaufremunerierte Geld weniger
    wert wird („Inflation“.) Wenn das Geld die Menschenwürde ausmacht, warum verargt der Dem. dem
    Fabrikanten, Kapitalisten ihr Geld? Und wie mißbraucht der Führer die unschuldige Seele des
    „Volkes,“ wenn er die Gelderhöhung als gebührende Lohn anbietet: muß da nicht sein Opfer
    glauben, seine Arbeit sei allein die schöpferische? Wo ohnehin der Mensch, je kleiner <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overwritten">der</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="superimposed">er</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> ist, von dem Wenigen, das er leistet, bis an den Rand voll ist, sich u. die Arbeit
    überschätzt, tritt noch von außen eine Partei, die dem Größenwahn ins Tollster fördert! Was
    Wunder, daß der Dem. sich für den Alleskönner hält, der nur durch tausend „Wenn“ <tei:add place="interlinear-above">sich</tei:add> verhindert fühlt: es ist der ewig verhinderte große
    Staatsmann, Dichter, Entdecker, Ingenieur usw. u. verlangt nach immer unser Geld, um zunächst
    einmal die <tei:add place="interlinear-above">angeblichen</tei:add> Hindernisse aus dem Wege zu
    räumen. Und hier beginnt der Wucher, der Betrug. <tei:pb n="3"/> Der Dem. haßt so seinen wahren
    Lebensinhalt, u. läßt sich zum Voraus für einen bezahlen, den er nur träumt. Er fühlt sich,
    durch Geld verführt, zu höherem Berufen u. will die andere Arbeit nicht mehr leisten, u. so
    zerfällt er mit sich selbst. Das Weib will nicht Kinder, denn sie möchte, – was? komponieren?
    dichten? entdecken? – sie weiß selbst nicht was, nur keine Kinder; sie träumt von Menschenwürde
    . . der Arbeiter will nicht arbeiten, was will er aber? – entdecken, dichten? nein, das kann er
    ja nicht, er will <tei:hi rend="underline">gut bezahlte Menschenwürde ohne
    Arbeit</tei:hi>.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Der Dem. hält „Umschichtung“ für Auslese; Menschenantlitz schon für Würde. Er schämt sich
    seiner niedrigen Arbeit, begehrt aber Lohn <tei:add place="interlinear-above">immer</tei:add>
    für eine höchste. Bei uns erscheint eine Hausgehilfin, u. verlangt den höchsten Lohn: wir
    gewähren diesen u. zuletzt fragt die <tei:rs key="entity-000916" type="person">Voltaire</tei:rs>‒<tei:rs key="entity-000578" type="person">Marx</tei:rs>‒Würdenträgerin: „muß
    ich auch kochen?“ Eine andere Hausgehilfin schämt sich Brot„aufschnitt“ zu essen, sie fürchtet
    ihre reine Würde etwas damit zu vergeben. Eine dritte will keine Kartoffeln essen, bei uns
    nicht, wo meine Frau so wunderbar die Mahlzeiten bereitet, diesselbe <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Frau</tei:rs>, die wie ich Kartoffel ißt u. noch überdies vollkommen gerüstet
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">mir</tei:add> auch geistig zur Seite steht. Eine vierte (aus
     <tei:rs key="entity-002479" type="place"><tei:hi rend="lateinschrift">Leipzig</tei:hi></tei:rs>) behauptet, <tei:rs key="entity-000963" type="person">Wilhelm
     II</tei:rs> wäre ein Landstreicher geworden, wenn er nicht zufällig Kaiser gewesen wäre. Arme
    Opfer vor gewissenlosen Schurken, Opfer, denen Arbeit wie Essen schon ganz vereckelt
    wurden.</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> Ein Demokr. ist der gerissene amerikanische Banquieur, der als „<tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:hi rend="lateinschrift">Philantrop</tei:hi></tei:hi>“ reist, der franz.
    Spitzbube, der den <tei:rs key="entity-003015" type="place"><tei:region><tei:hi rend="lateinschrift">Rhein</tei:hi></tei:region></tei:rs> stehlen geht (u. die Rheinländer so
    herabsetzt wie H. <tei:unclear reason="reading"><tei:hi rend="lateinschrift">Darine</tei:hi></tei:unclear> z.B.), der englische „<tei:hi rend="lateinschrift">Liberale</tei:hi>“,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">English
     liberal: David Lloyd George (1863–1945), British prime minister 1916–22; "steal[ing] the
     Rhine": the 15-year inter-Allied occupation of the Rhineland and its bridgeheads, with a
     demilitarized zone and the possibility that the region might be occupied if the Germans failed
     to pay reparations (to all of which Lloyd George was a reluctant signatory), decreed by the
     Treaty of Versailles, 1919.</tei:note> den <tei:rs key="entity-000100" type="person"><tei:hi rend="underline">Lujo Brentano</tei:hi></tei:rs> (ein radikaler Sozialist!) beschuldigt, die
    Mäntelchen von Lügen<tei:supplied reason="syntax">,</tei:supplied> Heuchelei um den Raubzug
    geschlagen zu haben. Ein Demok. ist mein <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Verleger</tei:rs>, trieft mir so von dem international. <tei:hi rend="lateinschrift">kosmop</tei:hi>. Fett, aber multipliziert in meiner u. meiner <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Frau</tei:rs> Gegenwart mit 4 nachdem er, vor einer Sekunde, die 5 als den
    Schlüssel angegeben hat, fälscht den Absatz (erwiesen, <tei:gap reason="illegible" extent="8" unit="chars"/>), usw., usw.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Wie ein Roß nach dem Huftritt an den Peiniger dennoch ein Roß bleibt, genau so bleibt die
    Masse Masse auch nach einem Revolutionshuftritt. Der deutsche Dem. will die Masse „entmassen“?
    Es entesle sich der Esel, entochse sich der Ochse zuvor, dann vielleicht.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>All diese Lüge, dieser Betrug kam uns aus dem Westen. Ein märchendichtender <tei:hi rend="underline">Knabe</tei:hi>
    <tei:rs key="entity-000294" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschrift">Goethe</tei:hi></tei:rs>,
    ein komponierender <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person"><tei:hi rend="underline">Bach</tei:hi></tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000612" type="person">Mozart</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000589" type="person">Mendelssohn</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person">Beeth</tei:rs>, im Westen? Nie gab es dort ein <tei:hi rend="underline">Wunder</tei:hi>, nie wird es Wunder geben.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Sie müssten aus Stein sein, wenn Sie nach der Lektüre des <tei:rs key="entity-001742" type="work">3. Heftes <tei:title>Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>, das einen <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person">Haydn</tei:rs> bringt,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Schenker</tei:author>, <tei:title level="a">Haydn: Sonate Es-Dur,</tei:title> pp.3–21 (Eng. trans., vol. I,
     99–117</tei:bibl>).</tei:note> nicht wie ich bis ins Innerste erschauern; fragen Sie sich dann
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ob</tei:add> so etwas im Westen möglich war, ist oder sein
    wird?</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Aber während kein Franzose, Engl., Amerik. den deutschen für etwas mehr als eben einen
    deutschen nimmt, glaubt der deutsche in <tei:hi rend="underline">jeden</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">Franzosen</tei:hi> H. <tei:rs key="entity-000916" type="person">Voltaire</tei:rs> zu sprechen, in jedem Droguisten, Tanzlehrer, Jour- <tei:pb n="5"/>
    nalisten, in <tei:hi rend="underline">jedem</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">Eng.</tei:hi> H. <tei:rs key="entity-000823" type="person">Shakspeare</tei:rs> selbst, in jedem Amerik. H. <tei:rs key="entity-000935" type="person">Washington</tei:rs>, u.s.f. daher diese (<tei:rs key="entity-000403" type="person">J.
     Paul</tei:rs>) Hausknechtsnatur. Und dieses große, herrliche Volk begeht den Widerspruch, für
    jedes Individuum das „Fürsich“ (<tei:rs key="entity-000294" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschrift">Goethe</tei:hi></tei:rs>) anzustreben, ein solches „Fürsich“ im Sinne
    eines Eigenseparaten, würdig in sich ruhenden Nation aber abzulehnen: der Einzelene soll
    individuell sein; die Gesammtheit aber – keine Individualität!! Dann die Auslandsfutterei ist
    nichts anderes als eine Minderung des „Fürsich“, eine Zerstörung der Individualität. <tei:rs key="entity-000294" type="person">Goethe</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000784" type="person">Schiller</tei:rs>, die z.B. <tei:rs key="entity-000685" type="person">Racine</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000916" type="person">Voltaire</tei:rs> ab<tei:add place="interlinear-above">zu</tei:add>lehnen <tei:add place="interlinear-above">wissen</tei:add>, mögen <tei:add place="interlinear-above">auch</tei:add> bei deutschem „Fürsich“ Früchte pflücken, wo sie
    wollen, aber das ganze Volk macht, das es nicht schöpferisch ist, den Kosmopolitismus zu Unrecht
    mit, auch mit Unverstand. <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">cued from lower
     margin:</tei:note> Wozu <tei:gap reason="illegible" extent="4" unit="chars"/> auf einen
     <tei:unclear reason="reading">Knochen</tei:unclear> haben sich da kürzlich 3 oder 4 <tei:gap reason="illegible" extent="4" unit="chars"/>, u. Übersetzter auf <tei:rs key="entity-000035" type="person">Barbusse</tei:rs> gestützt, von dem ich nicht einen Satz noch wirklich geistvoll
    gefunden hatte. Er spielt <tei:unclear reason="reading">den</tei:unclear> „<tei:gap reason="illegible" extent="10" unit="chars"/>“ u. lockt die deutschen Gelder heraus. <tei:hi rend="lateinschrift">Clarté</tei:hi> macht es ebenso. Wir bezahlen die Kanonen, mit denen
     <tei:rs key="entity-002520" type="place"><tei:country>Frankreich</tei:country></tei:rs> den
    Krieg führt.<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end cue</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Der deutsche Dem. sehnte sich nach Armut, nun hat er sie, u. mag begreifen, daß dem
    Einzelnen es geziemt, Reichtümer abzulehnen, aber nicht einer Gesammtheit von 60 Mill., denn
    dann geht Alles zu Grunde. Unser armer D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi>
    <tei:rs key="entity-000643" type="person">Oppel</tei:rs> (<tei:rs key="entity-002757" type="place">Kiel</tei:rs>) muß bei zahllosen Stunden noch nur <tei:hi rend="underline">Kino</tei:hi> spielen!! Und so tausend Beispiele. Niemals aber wird es einem <tei:supplied reason="punctuation">„</tei:supplied>Umschichtler“ gelingen, auch nur soweit es zu bringen,
    wie[?] D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi>
    <tei:rs key="entity-000643" type="person">Oppel</tei:rs> es gebracht hat.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Daher lobe ich nur die Faszisten!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot">To understand this astonishing and deeply ironic statement, we must remember that
     at this point Schenker considered Communism to be the principal enemy and social evil, and saw
     the Fascists as the only force likely to overcome it.</tei:note> Weg mit der „Klasse“ aus dem
    Fleisch der Nation, – gedacht, <tei:pb n="6"/> getan, u. schon <tei:add place="interlinear-above">sind</tei:add> die Gaunerführer feig entflohen (sie sind ja uns nach
     <tei:rs key="entity-002506" type="place"><tei:country>Österr.</tei:country></tei:rs> gekommen)
    u. schon haben sich die Kommunistenverbände aufgelöst, u. schon sind die Arbeiter <tei:hi rend="underline">begeisterte Fascisten geworden</tei:hi>! Das Volk jauchzt voll Stolz auf, – in
    der That <tei:rs key="entity-002988" type="person">Mussolini</tei:rs>s Werk: <tei:supplied reason="punctuation">„</tei:supplied>Ich bin Diener Euerer Majestät“, „Ich werde selbst ein
    Beispiel geben.“ sind wahrer Kaviar für das Volk, u. mehr als alles Demokratentreiben, das um
    Geduld fleht: “Warten Sie, wir sind in den Anfängen erst, in <tei:supplied reason="clarity">ein</tei:supplied> paar Generationen wird es besser werden.“</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Sagte <tei:rs key="entity-000578" type="person">Marx</tei:rs>: <tei:supplied reason="syntax">„</tei:supplied>die Religion ist Opium für die Völker,“ sage ich: Demokr. ist
    Opium.</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Deutschl.</tei:country></tei:rs>
    braucht Faszisten, die die Lüge der „Klasse“ vertilgen, jener Fertig-Fresser, denen man Arbeit
    u. Gelegenheit verschafft, u. die zum Lohn für dieses Schlaraffenleben Alles niedertrampeln. Der
    gottverlassenste Habsburger hat mehr Kulturwert als die ganze „Lohnerhöhungsmaschinerie“, wie
    der Führer der öst. Sozdem. selbst die Partei benannte. Durch Geld geht es nicht. Das ital. Volk
    lebt schöne Tage der Erhebung! Und im deutschen Volk geht noch immer der Dolchstoß um!
    Seelenmord um Seelenmord! Was habe ich für Dokumente für den Dolchstoß seit <tei:hi rend="double-underline">1915</tei:hi> (!), geschweige 1917–1918!</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in left margin, written sideways:</tei:note> Nun
    Alles endgiltig an die Pflicht des Tages in so trüben Tagen! Helfen Sie der deutschen Jugend aus
    den Fängen des Westens, der „Klasse“</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Vielen Dank u. beste Grüße</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihres</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50">
     <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">H
      Schenker</tei:hi></tei:rs><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end left
     margin</tei:note><tei:lb/>
    </tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>



  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dear and revered Professor <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000326">Halm</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>With many thanks I am sending back the two booklets <tei:title level="j">Republic and
     Youth</tei:title>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> I have long since known and
    possessed such pieces. They always achieve the opposite of what the author wants to get across
    to people. All are outmoded and <tei:hi rend="underline">deflated</tei:hi><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> today by the initiative of Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000969" type="person">Wirth</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> and of the imperial government, who prove before the whole world by means of their
    publications that the fault does not apply to <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Germany</tei:country></tei:rs> alone, who speak without fanfare of Russian and
    French "falsifications." If even the young in <tei:rs key="entity-002679" type="place"><tei:region>Thuringia</tei:region></tei:rs> has to be politicized, then under the motto "truth
    is not hate" it would have been necessary <tei:hi rend="underline">first</tei:hi> to speak
    precisely of those things that the author defers to the Greek Kalends,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> and not of the collapse and stab of the dagger, which
    is at the tail end. The Ministry should have brought <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Germany</tei:country></tei:rs>'s situation among the French, English, and Slavs
    to awareness in a more dignified form, the nature of those nations that hate what is German deep
    in their hearts, the necessity to put up resistance to the acts of hate. But the German democrat
    thinks first of himself, of his position, and defends it against "social reordering," although
    he himself has risen to prominence only through a social reordering that came about because of
    post-war chaos and opportunism. Therefore the aforementioned booklets.</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> I speak to you so openly because I perceive you as an aristocrat, though
    you may consider yourself a democrat. A democrat is something completely different than you.
    Here, some characteristics.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>He is above all bribable. The leading crooks know absolutely precisely what they are doing
    when, above all, they raise wages and get money to the masses. The purchasable soul is acquired
    instantly with money! Even an intellectually advanced <tei:rs key="entity-003235" type="organization">Philharmonic</tei:rs> musician, well-to-do by background, was enthusiastic
    about the party when it raised salaries at the <tei:rs key="entity-002778" type="organization">Opera House</tei:rs>, and it didn't dawn on him that the money of increased remuneration will
    be worth less ("inflation"). If money is the substance of human dignity, why does the democrat
    hold it against the manufacturer, the capitalist? And how the leader abuses the innocent soul of
    the "folk" when he offers the increased money as due wages. Must not his victim believe his work
    alone is productive? Where a person, the smaller he is, is full to the brim with that little bit
    that he accomplishes, overestimates himself and his labor, a party from the outside enters which
    escalates the delusion of grandeur to the worst madness! What wonder that the democrat considers
    himself someone capable of everything, who feels inhibited only by a thousand "if's." It is the
    eternally obstructed great statesman, poet, discoverer, engineer, etc. and always demands our
    money in order to clear the <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ostensible</tei:add> hindrances
    out of the way. And the profiteering, the deception begins there. <tei:pb n="3"/> The democrat
    hates his true life's purpose so much and allows himself to be paid in advance for a purpose of
    which he merely dreams. Seduced by money, he feels summoned to a higher calling and no longer
    wants to do the other labor, and so he falls apart. The wife wants no children because she would
    like ‒ what? to compose? write poetry? make discoveries? She doesn't know herself what she wants
    to do, just no children. She dreams of human dignity. The worker doesn't want to work. What does
    he want, though? To make discoveries, to write poetry? No, he certainly can't do that. He wants
     <tei:hi rend="underline">well-paid human dignity without work</tei:hi>.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>The democrat takes "regrouping" to be selection, human countenance simply to be dignity.
    He is ashamed of his lowly labor, but <tei:add place="interlinear-above">always</tei:add>
    desires a salary that is the highest possible. A housemaid shows up at our home and demands the
    highest wage. We grant it and in the end the <tei:rs key="entity-000916" type="person">Voltaire</tei:rs>‒<tei:rs key="entity-000578" type="person">Marx</tei:rs> bearer of dignity
    asks: "Do I also have to cook?" Another maid is ashamed to eat "cold cuts" with bread. She is
    afraid of giving up something of her pristine dignity. A third will eat no potatoes, not in our
    home, though my <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs> prepares such wonderful
    meals, the same wife who, like me, eats potatoes and moreover also stands fully equipped at
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">my</tei:add> side intellectually. A fourth (from <tei:rs key="entity-002479" type="place">Leipzig</tei:rs>) claims that <tei:rs key="entity-000963" type="person">Wilhelm II</tei:rs> would have become a hobo if he were not coincidentally
    emperor. Poor victims at the hands of unscrupulous scoundrels, victims whose work as well as
    meals have been made completely revolting.</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> A democrat is the crafty American banker who travels as a "<tei:hi rend="underline">philanthropist</tei:hi>," the French rascal who goes out to steal the <tei:rs key="entity-003015" type="place">Rhine</tei:rs> (and so demean the Rhinelanders, e.g. like H.
     <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">Darine</tei:unclear>), the English "liberal,"<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> whom <tei:rs key="entity-000100" type="person"><tei:hi rend="underline">Lujo Brentano</tei:hi></tei:rs> (a radical socialist!) blames for having
    wrapped the robbery in a tissue of lies <tei:supplied reason="clarity">and</tei:supplied>
    hypocrisy. My <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">publisher</tei:rs> is a democrat, he
    oozes internationalist, cosmopolitan grease so much to my face, but in mine and my <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs>'s presence <tei:supplied reason="clarity">he</tei:supplied> multiplies by four after he has given five as the factor a moment before,
     <tei:supplied reason="clarity">thus</tei:supplied> falsifies the sales (proven, <tei:gap reason="illegible" extent="8" unit="chars"/>), etc., etc.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Just as a steed nevertheless remains a steed after kicking its tormentor, so too the
    masses remain the masses even after the kick of a revolution. The German democrat wants to
    "de-mass" the masses? If the donkey can de-donkey and the ox de-ox itself, then perhaps.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>All of these lies, this deception, came to us from the west. A fairytale-telling <tei:hi rend="underline">boy</tei:hi>
    <tei:rs key="entity-000294" type="person">Goethe</tei:rs>, a composer <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person"><tei:hi rend="underline">Bach</tei:hi></tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000612" type="person">Mozart</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000589" type="person">Mendelssohn</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs>, in the
    west? A <tei:hi rend="underline">miracle</tei:hi> never occurred there, never will there be
    miracles.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>You would have to be made of stone if, like me, you don't shiver to the core after reading
    the <tei:rs key="entity-001742" type="work">third issue of <tei:title level="j">Der
      Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>, which presents a <tei:supplied reason="clarity">work
     by</tei:supplied>
    <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person">Haydn</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> Do you ask yourself <tei:add place="interlinear-above">whether</tei:add>
    something like that was possible in the west, is or will be?</tei:p>

   <tei:p>But while no Frenchman, Englishman <tei:supplied reason="clarity">or</tei:supplied>
    American takes a German for anything more than just a German, the German believes he's talking
    to <tei:rs key="entity-000916" type="person">Voltaire</tei:rs> in <tei:hi rend="underline">every
     Frenchman</tei:hi>, every pharmacist, dance instructor, journalist, <tei:pb n="5"/> with Mr.
     <tei:rs key="entity-000823" type="person">Shakespeare</tei:rs> himself in <tei:hi rend="underline">every Englishman</tei:hi>, with Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000935" type="person">Washington</tei:rs> in every American, and so forth. Hence this (<tei:rs key="entity-000403" type="person">Jean-Paul</tei:rs>) house-servant mentality. And this great, magnificent people
    commits the contradiction of striving toward a "For-himself" (<tei:rs key="entity-000294" type="person">Goethe</tei:rs>) for every individual, but rejecting such a "For-himself" in the
    sense of a self-separated, enobled nation at peace with itself. The individual person should be
    individualized, but the totality ‒ not an individuality!! Then the foreign fodder is nothing
    other than a diminishment of "For-himself," a destruction of individuality. <tei:rs key="entity-000294" type="person">Goethe</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000784" type="person">Schiller</tei:rs>, who knew to reject for example <tei:rs key="entity-000685" type="person">Racine</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000916" type="person">Voltaire</tei:rs>, may <tei:add place="interlinear-above">also</tei:add> harvest fruit where they will with the German "for
    himself," but the entire people wrongly goes along with the cosmopolitanism because it is not
    creative, also in ignorance. <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">cued from lower
     margin:</tei:note> To which three or four <tei:gap reason="illegible" extent="4" unit="chars"/>
    and translators recently with one accord based themselves on <tei:rs key="entity-000035" type="person">Barbusse</tei:rs>, from whom I had not found a single intellectually stimulating
    sentence. He plays the role of an "<tei:gap reason="illegible" extent="10" unit="chars"/>" and
    lures German money. <tei:hi rend="italic">Clarté</tei:hi> does it the same way. We pay for the
    canons with which <tei:rs key="entity-002520" type="place"><tei:country>France</tei:country></tei:rs> makes war.<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end cue</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>The German democrat longed for poverty. Now, he has it and may grasp that it befits the
    individual to refuse riches, but not a totality of 60 million. For them everything then goes
    down the drain. Our poor Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000643" type="person">Oppel</tei:rs> (<tei:rs key="entity-002757" type="place">Kiel</tei:rs>), with countless private lessons, must yet play
    for <tei:hi rend="underline">movies</tei:hi>!! And a thousand such examples. But a "regrouper"
    will never succeed in getting even as far as Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000643" type="person">Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Consequently, I praise the fascists exclusively!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/> Get rid of "class" from the flesh of the nation ‒ no sooner thought than
     <tei:pb n="6"/> done. And the swindling <tei:supplied reason="clarity">Italian</tei:supplied>
    leaders <tei:add place="interlinear-above">have</tei:add> already fled like cowards (they have
    come to us in <tei:rs key="entity-002506" type="place"><tei:country>Austria</tei:country></tei:rs>, of course), and the communist federations have
    already disbanded, and already the workers have <tei:hi rend="underline">become enthusiastic
     fascists</tei:hi>! The people rejoice full of pride, which is indeed <tei:rs key="entity-002988" type="person">Mussolini</tei:rs>'s doing. "I am your majesty's obedient
    servant," "I myself will set an example." ‒ <tei:supplied reason="clarity">such
     declarations</tei:supplied> are music to the ears of the people, and more than all the democrat
    bustle that appeals for patience. "Wait, we are just at the beginning, in a few generations it
    will get better."</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:rs key="entity-000578" type="person">Marx</tei:rs> said: "Religion is the opium of
    the people." I say democracy is opium.</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Germany</tei:country></tei:rs> needs
    facists who will destroy the lie of "class," of those on-the-spot gluttons for whom we provide
    work and opportunity, and who as salary for this cushy life trample everything. The most
    god-forsaken Habsburger has more cultural value than the entire wage-raising machinery, as the
    leader himself of the Austrian social democrats called the party. It won't work by means of
    money. The Italian people are living lovely days of elation! And with the German people the
    knife in the back still goes on. Murdering soul after soul! The documents I have for the knife
    in the back since <tei:hi rend="double-underline">1915</tei:hi> (!), not to mention
    1917-1918!</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in left margin, written sideways:</tei:note>
    Everything now definitively toward the obligation of the day in such dismal days! Help the
    German youth to get out of the claws of the west, of "class."</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">With many thanks and best wishes</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">From your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50">
     <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">H. Schenker</tei:rs><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end left margin</tei:note><tei:lb/>
    </tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>