<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="50" sdoID="DLA-69.930-4">DLA 69.930/4</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB-LR">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent and Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="LR">
   <tei:persName>Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2010</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
   <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
   <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-03-06" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002698">Halm ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   
   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Halm, dated December 9, 1918</dc:title>
   
   <dcterms:created>1918-12-09T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-05-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker recounts to Halm how Sofie Deutsch had set up a trust for needy artists,
    leaving Schenker to identify beneficiaries. Schenker offers to transfer 1,600 Kroner to him from
    this trust. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>will; testament; trust; foundation; needy artists; stipend; exchange rate; transfer;
    bank</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000326">Halm</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Sehr geehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000326">Herr
      Halm</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Vor<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is
     recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/12, p. 2019, December 8, 1918: "An Halm (recomm. Br.):
     frage wegen des Stipendiums an, dessen Geschichte ich kurz erzähle, zum Beschluß
     Wagner-Marx-Parallele." ("To Halm (registered letter"): I ask about the stipend, the story of
     which I briefly recount; at the end, Wagner-Marx parallel.").<!-- XR -->
    </tei:note> zwei Jahren ist eine <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Schülerin</tei:rs> von
    mir verstorben, eine ältere Dame, die etwa 16 Jahre hindurch meinen Unterricht genoß. Sie
    hinterließ ein <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Testament</tei:hi>, in dem sie einen Verein zum
    Haupterben einsetzte, daneben aber auch 2 Stipendien für Künstler errichtete, über die zu
    verfügen sie ausschließlich mir allein auftrug. Wäre die musikalische Gegenwart nicht so
    trostlos, welche Freude müßte es da einem<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"> "einem“: i.e. Schenker, using the impersonal pronoun to refer to
     himself.</tei:note> bereiten, vom Vertrauen der Erblasserin getragen, überall dort
    beizuspringen, wo Hindernisse (Verleger!) diesen oder jenen Plan lähmen! So aber hatte ich wenig
    Neigung, das schöne Amt mich zu nehmen, wie ich auch in einem anderen Falle es abgelehnt habe,
    mit unserem Musikhistoriker <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000003">
     Prof. Guido Adler
    </tei:rs> das <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Jury-Amt</tei:hi> zu teilen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"> The Rothschild Artists’ Foundation had
     written to Schenker on December 3, 1916, inviting him to join its panel of jury members along
     with Guido Adler and Alfred Grünfeld (OJ 12/26, [2]). Schenker declined. The President of the
     Jewish Community wrote to Schenker regretting his decision (Federhofer, <tei:title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern und Briefen ...</tei:title>, p.54, n.8).</tei:note> Doch
    gelang es dem <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000590">Bruder der Erblasserin</tei:rs> sowie dem
     Testaments<tei:hi rend="lateinschr">executor</tei:hi> mich zumindest zu einem Versuch zu
    überreden. Ich faßte nun dies Künstler ins Auge u. harrte der ersten Gelder der
     Verlassenschaft<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">
     <tei:hi rend="italic">Verlassenschaft</tei:hi>: Austrian for <tei:hi rend="italic">Hinterlassenschaft</tei:hi>.</tei:note>, um zur Tat zu schreiten. Da kamen aber allerhand
    (mir fremd gebliebene) Verwicklungen in die Verlassenschaftsabhandlung, die bewirkten, daß diese
    noch bis zur Stunde das Gericht beschäftigt, u. daß auch die Stiftung der Stipendien <tei:pb n="2"/> überhaupt ganz ins Wasser gefallen. Obzwar der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000590">Bruder</tei:rs> der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">verstorbenen Dame</tei:rs>
    einer der reichsten Großindustriellen <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002506">Österreich</tei:rs>s ist, fiel es ihm dennoch nicht ein,
    die Konsequenz aus seiner ersten Geltung zu ziehen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot"> The translation of this last clause is admittedly interpretive; its literal
     meaning is more like: "it still did not occur to him [i.e. Mendl] to draw the consequence from
     his initial importance." </tei:note> Glücklicherweise hat mich eine andere reiche <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000201">Schülerin</tei:rs>, die zu mir nun über 18 Jahre kommt, in die Lage
    versetzt, mir selbst Wort zu halten in jenen <tei:gap reason="illegible"/> Fällen, die ich im
    Auge hatte.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Am 5. Januar als am Todestage der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Erblasserin</tei:rs> soll der Betrag zur Auszahlung kommen. Und da frage ich Sie nun, ob
    es Ihnen angenehm wäre, wenn ich <tei:add place="interlinear-above">Ihnen</tei:add> um diese
    Zeit den Betrag von 1600 Kronen für Ihre Zwecke überweisen würde? Im Vorjahre hat das noch über
    1000 Mk. ausgemacht; ob bei dem niedrigen Kurse der Kronen auch heuer<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot"> „heuer“: South German and Austria
     usage.</tei:note> derselbe Betrag in Mk. sich ergeben wird, weiß ich nicht.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Indem ich Sie um Ihre frdl. Zustimmung bitte, erbitte ich zugleich Auskunft, auf welche
    Weise ich Ihnen die Summe zukommen lassen könnte. Haben Sie vielleicht hier in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">
     Wien
    </tei:rs> einen Vertrauensmann? Wenn nicht, würde ich den Versuch machen, durch eine Bank
    die <tei:hi rend="underline">Erlaubnis</tei:hi> (eine solche ist nämlich <tei:hi rend="underline">unter</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">allen</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">Umständen</tei:hi> nötig) von der maßgebenden Stelle zu
    erlangen.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich frage, wie Sie sehen, schon heute an, um, Ihre Zustimmung vorausgesetzt, sobald als
    möglich die Sache in Angriff zu nehmen. Der Sicherheit halber bitte ich Sie auch Ihre Antwort an
     <tei:pb n="3"/> mich <tei:hi rend="underline">eingeschrieben</tei:hi> zu senden.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Sind Sie in Ihren Arbeiten doch die Verhältnisse sehr gehemmt, oder gewinnen Sie Oberhand
    über die unsäglich traurige Verwirrung in politischen Dingen, die meines Erachtens, wie die
    musikalische auf <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000924">R. Wagner</tei:rs>, lediglich auf
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000578">K. Marx</tei:rs> zurückzuführen ist?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot"> This paragraph is quoted in Federhofer,
      <tei:title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern und Briefen ...</tei:title>, p.139,
     saying. Schenker's antipathy to Wagner, latent in <tei:title level="m">Harmonielehre</tei:title> (1906), emerged clearly first in the unpublished <tei:title level="m">Über den Niedergang der Kompositionskunst</tei:title> (c. 1906-09), and his critique
     of Wagner continued in his <tei:title level="m">Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie</tei:title> and
      <tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title>; Wagner is brought into conjunction with Marx in
     the latter: "In shattering the Urlinie and destroying musical truth, Wagner readied a fate for
     music similar to that which Karl Marx readied for society by demolishing every tradition and
     the truths that rested therein ..." (<tei:title level="j">Tw1</tei:title>, p.25; trans., I,
     p.24). Halm, on the other hand, while considering Bruckner to be the epitome of high
     romanticism, held Wagner in high regard. This is a matter on which Schenker and Halm held
     sharply differing opinions. </tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Mit besten Gruß</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-55">Ihr sehr ergebener</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50">
     <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">H Schenker</tei:hi>
    </tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline>
     <tei:placeName>Wien, </tei:placeName>
     <tei:date when="1918-12-09">9. Dezember 1918</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000326">Mr.
     Halm</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>


   <tei:p>Two<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> years ago a <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">female student</tei:rs> of mine died, an older women who had the
    benefit of my instruction for sixteen years. She left a will in which she designated an
    association as primary beneficiary, as well as established two stipends for artists, the
    disposition of which she assigned exclusively to me. If the present circumstances in music were
    not so hopeless, what happiness it would have to bring for someone,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> supported by the trust of the deceased, to jump to aid wherever obstacles
    (publishers!) foil this or that plan! However, I had little desire to take on the pleasant duty,
    just as in another case I declined to share jury duty with our music historian, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000003">Professor Guido Adler</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> But the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000590">brother</tei:rs> of the
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165"> deceased woman</tei:rs> and the executor of the will
    succeeded at least in coaxing me into a trial. I had some artists in mind and awaited the first
    distribution of money<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> from the bequest in order to
    take action. However, all manner of complications (external to me) came up in the handling of
    the bequest, such that it still occupies the court up to this moment, and such that the
    endowment of the stipends <tei:pb n="2"/> has fallen through altogether. Even though the
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000590">brother</tei:rs> of the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">deceased woman</tei:rs> is one of <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002506">Austria</tei:rs>’s richest big industrialists, it
    nevertheless did not occur to him to take advantage of his high rank in society.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> Fortunately, another rich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000201">female student</tei:rs>, who has been coming to me for over eighteen
    years, has put me in the position of keeping my word in those cases that I had in mind.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>On January 5, as the death date of the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">deceased</tei:rs>, the amount is to be paid out. I therefore ask you whether it would be
    agreeable if around that time I were to transfer the sum of 1,600 Kronen <tei:add place="interlinear-above">to you</tei:add> for your purposes? Last year, that still amounted to
    over 1,000 Marks. With the low exchange rate of Kronen, I do not know whether this year<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> the same amount in Marks would result.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>In asking for your friendly consent, I also request information as to what manner I could
    convey the sum to you. Do you perhaps have a representative here in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Vienna</tei:rs>? If not, I would make an attempt to secure <tei:hi rend="underline">permission</tei:hi> from the regulatory agency (such is of course necessary
     <tei:hi rend="underline">in all circumstances</tei:hi>).</tei:p>

   <tei:p>As you see, assuming your consent, I am inquiring today in order to undertake the matter
    as soon as possible. To be safe, I ask that you send your reply to me <tei:pb n="3"/> by <tei:hi rend="underline">registered mail</tei:hi>.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Are the circumstances of your activities very constrained, or are you getting the upper
    hand on the untold woeful confusion in political matters, which in my opinion is to be traced
    solely to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000578">Karl Marx</tei:rs>, just as the musical
    confusion is to be traced to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000924">Richard
     Wagner</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">With cordial greetings, </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-55">Yours very truly, </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50">H. Schenker</tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline>
     <tei:placeName>Vienna, </tei:placeName>
     <tei:date when="1918-12-09">December 9, 1918</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>