<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="1318" sdoID="GdM-Briefe-HS_1">GdM Briefe HS, [1]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="ME">
   <tei:persName>Martin Eybl</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2009</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2009</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2014</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>


  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2011-06-07" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-005520">BoesendorferL ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Ludwig Bösendorfer, undated [1889/1890]</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1889-12-01T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2014-11-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker asks for hire of a better piano.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Clavier; piano; Leistung; achievement; Anforderungen; demands; Promotion; promotion;
    Zustand; condition; Rigorosum; examination</dc:subject>



   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000090">Ludwig Bösendorfer</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Euer <tei:rs key="entity-000090" type="person">Wohlgeboren</tei:rs>!<tei:note
      xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Dating: Schenker's doctoral examination took
      place between May 1889 and January 1890: May 15, 1889 Austrian Law, July 10, 1889 German Law,
      January 8, 1890 political science (source: University of Vienna archive, Faculty of Law 1890,
      doctoral examination protocol No. 133, cited from <tei:bibl><tei:author>Yu-Ring
        Chiang</tei:author>, <tei:title level="a">Heinrich Schenkers Wiener Gedenkstätten: Gedanken
        zu seinem sechzigsten Todesjahr,</tei:title> in <tei:title level="m">Mitteilungen der
        Österreichischen Gesellschaft für Musikwissenschaft</tei:title> 30 (September 1996), pp.
       41–51; 42–43</tei:bibl>). His promotion occurred on February 1, 1890 (see
        <tei:bibl><tei:author>Federhofer</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
        Tagebüchern und Briefen …</tei:title>, p. 5</tei:bibl>; <tei:bibl><tei:author>Wayne
        Alpern</tei:author>, <tei:title level="a">The Triad of the True, the Good, and the
        Beautiful,</tei:title>
       <tei:title level="m">Essays from the Fourth International Schenker Symposium</tei:title>,
       vol. II, pp. 7‒48, esp. p. 9</tei:bibl>). Schenker signs himself " Doktorandus juris" and is,
      as he writes, about to be (in a few weeks or months) promoted. In addition, he reports a
      conversation with Eduard Seuffert that must have happened "a few weeks after I had passed the
      gruelling examination for the doctorate," thus earliest mid-June 1889. The letter must
      therefore have been written between June 1889 and January 1890. On p. 1 of the letter, the
      presumed addressee of the letter is given, in a later hand, as "an Bösendorfer." The piano
      manufacturer Ludwig Bösendorfer had since 1878 been a member of the Board of Directors of the
      Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde in Wien, which is presumably why the letter is preserved in the
      latter's archive. </tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Auf meines hochgeehrten Lehrers, Herrn <tei:rs key="entity-000545" type="person">E.
     Ludwig</tei:rs> Rath erlaube ich mir Euer <tei:rs key="entity-000090" type="person"
     >Wohlgeboren</tei:rs> folgendes vorzubringen.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Vor mehr als einem Jahre hatten Euer <tei:rs key="entity-000090" type="person"
     >Wohlgeb.</tei:rs> die Güte mir ein Clavier zu überlassen, das mir zunächst bei den
     <tei:term>theoretischen Studien</tei:term> behilflich sein sollte. Es ist nicht bombastisch,
    wenn ich sage, daß dies eine Wohlthat für mich gewesen. Zu gleicher Zeit erhielt ich auch von
    Euer Wohlgeb. das Versprechen, daß das Clavier durch ein besseres ersetzt werde, sobald ein
    solches frei wäre. Inzwischen sind meine Leistungen, was Herr Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000545"
     type="person">Ludwig</tei:rs> jederzeit bekräftigen wird, sehr gestiegen, und die an mich
    gestellten Anforderungen <tei:pb n="2"/> dementsprechend gewachsen. Ich fühle Kraft genug in
    mir, fortzuschreiten und will es auch thun, zumal mir in nicht weiter Ferne die Promotion zum
     <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Doctor juris</tei:hi></tei:foreign>
    winkt. Nur eine Bedingung scheint zu defiziren: es ist dies nämlich ein besseres Clavier, als
    ich jetzt habe. Euer Wohlgeboren kannten den Zustand desselben offenbar, denn die eigene Kritik
    lautete zu jener Zeit: „sehr elend.“ Tasten versagen schon, kurz es wird unmöglich zu spielen
    und da soll ich mit besten <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
      >Intentionen</tei:hi></tei:foreign> einen erhabenen <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person"
      ><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Bach</tei:hi></tei:rs> spielen.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Als ich einige Wochen nach dem bestandenen schwierigsten <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat"
     >Rigorosum</tei:foreign> Muth fasste, den hochgeehrten Herrn <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Secretär
      <tei:rs key="entity-000821" type="person">Seuffert</tei:rs></tei:hi> in dieser Angelegenheit
    zu befragen, erhielt ich zur Antwort, daß Anfangs <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Mai</tei:hi>
    wahrscheinlich Claviere frei werden. Wenn ich mich nun trotzdem an Euer Wohlgeb. wende, so gelte
    das <tei:add place="interlinear-above">nur</tei:add> als Beweis <tei:add
     place="interlinear-above">dafür</tei:add>, wie ungenügend das Clavier ist, wie ich aber
    zugleich hoffe, daß es Euer <tei:rs key="entity-000090" type="person">Wohlgeb.</tei:rs> doch
    möglich sein werde, mir ein um wenig besseres Instrument <tei:pb n="3"/> gütigst zu überlassen.
    Ich würde dafür unendlich dankbar sein!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich fühle mich noch verpflichtet, am Schlusse zu bemerken, daß Herr Prof. <tei:rs
     key="entity-000104" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Bruckner</tei:hi></tei:rs> nicht
    mehr sagen könnte, „daß er für mich nicht garantiren könne“ (was er seinerzeit Euer <tei:rs
     key="entity-000090" type="person">Wohlgeb.</tei:rs> gegenüber geäußert haben soll), wohl aber
    bin ich der Ueberzeugung, daß er jetzt, abgesehen von schlechter Stimmung, ehrlich das beste
    Zeugnis mir ausstellen würde.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The
     final sentence of the letter is quoted in <tei:bibl><tei:author>Federhofer</tei:author>,
       <tei:title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern und Briefen …</tei:title>
      (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), p. 6, footnote 17</tei:bibl>, where "stud. iur." is given
     incorrectly instead of "D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">rd</tei:hi>. juris."</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Indem ich mich der angenehmsten Hoffnung ergebe zeichne</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">in Dankbarkeit</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Heinrich
      Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">D<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
      >rd</tei:hi>. juris</tei:foreign>.</tei:signed>
    <tei:address rend="indent-40">
     <tei:addrLine>VIII. Lenaugasse 16<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"
       >Schenker lived in the eighth district, Lenaugasse 16/I/8 from the summer semester of 1887
       (Yu-Ring Chiang, s. fn1, S. 43 und 49).</tei:note></tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>

  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Respected <tei:rs key="entity-000090" type="person">Sir</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
      corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Upon the advice of my revered teacher, Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000545" type="person">E.
     Ludwig</tei:rs>, I take the liberty of bringing the following to the attention of your
    respected self.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Over a year ago, respected <tei:rs key="entity-000090" type="person">Sir</tei:rs>, you
    were so good as to make a piano available to me that would be of help to me first and foremost
    in my <tei:term>theoretical studies</tei:term>. It is no exaggeration to say that this has been
    a boon to me. At the same time, I also received from your respected self the promise that the
    piano would be replaced by a better one as soon as one such were available. In the meanwhile, as
    Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000545" type="person">Ludwig</tei:rs> will at any time affirm, the
    level of my achievement has increased greatly, and the demands placed upon me have <tei:pb n="2"
    /> intensified accordingly. I feel I have sufficient strength to make progress, and am
    determined to do so, especially because of the promotion to Doctor of Law that will occur in the
    not too distant future. Only one condition seems to be lacking, namely a better piano than I
    currently have. You were clearly aware, respected Sir, of the state of this one, for your own
    assessment of it at the time was "utterly wretched." Already keys fail to speak; in short, it
    will be impossible to play, and there with the best of intentions I shall play a sublime <tei:rs
     key="entity-000027" type="person">Bach</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>When, a few weeks after I had passed the most gruelling of the examinations for the
    doctorate, I summoned up the courage to tackle Secretary <tei:rs key="entity-000821"
     type="person">Seuffert</tei:rs> on this subject, I received the answer that pianos might
    possibly be free at the beginning of May. If nevertheless I now turn to you, respected <tei:rs
     key="entity-000090" type="person">Sir</tei:rs>, then that is <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
     >only</tei:add> evidence of how unsatisfactory the piano is, and of how I at the same time hope
    that it will be possible for you, respected Sir, <tei:pb n="3"/> very kindly to make available
    to me a somewhat better instrument. I should be infinitely grateful if so!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>In closing, furthermore, I feel in duty bound to point out that Prof. <tei:rs
     key="entity-000104" type="person">Bruckner</tei:rs> could no longer say "that he could not
    vouch for me" (as he is said to have declared to you at the time); however, I am convinced that,
    so long as he is not in a bad mood, he would now honestly speak in most positive terms about
     me.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>In entertaining the highest hopes, I remain,</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">In gratitude,</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Heinrich
      Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60">Cand. Dr. Juris</tei:signed>
    <tei:address rend="indent-40">
     <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied reason="place">Vienna</tei:supplied> VIII, Lenaugasse 16<tei:ptr
       corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
