<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2046" sdoID="JOB-94-3_6">JOB 94-3, [6]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="HS-SP">
      <tei:persName>Hedi Siegel &amp; Stephanie Probst</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2017</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2017</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2017</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2011-02-12" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006186">HammerV ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Hammer dated December 2, 1923</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1923-12-02T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2018-01-26</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker has heard nothing from Eugen Steinhof; — he commends Hammer's
        reaction to Halm's work, and comments unfavorably on the latter's musicianship, character,
        and opinions; — he writes disparagingly of Robert Brünauer.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Schwangerschaft; pregnancy; Buch; book; Widmungsexemplar; dedication copy; Urteil;
        judgment; Prachtkerl; fine fellow; Unschuld; innocence; Schuld; guilt; Wort-fortpflanzung;
        word-propagation; Mitleid; compassion; Opfer; sacrifice; Reiche; rich man; Stütze; support;
        Geldstolz; moneyed pride</dc:subject>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000327">Viktor Hammer</marcrel:recipient>

    </sdo:itemDesc>



    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:note type="editorial" place="pre-text">A photocopy of this postcard (which is preserved
        at the New York Public Library) exists in the Oswald Jonas Collection as OJ 5/15a,
        [6].</tei:note>

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Verehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000327"
            >Hammer</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/6, p. 2603, December 2, 1923: "An
            Hammer (Br.): Professor Steinhof ist nicht gekommen; stimme seinem Urteil über Halm zu
            u. deute letzteren als echten, deutschen Oberlehrer; erzähle das Geschichtchen, wie er
            mich wegen des Ausfalls gegen die Franzosen gerügt hat, gestützt auf Briand u. Harden;
            wie er gänzlich ununterrichtet dahinlebt, der erste Augenaufschlag aber sich wider die
            eigenen Leute richtet. Komme noch einmal auf Brünauer-Hammer zurück u. begründe, weshalb
            es mir unmöglich war zu gestatten, daß ein von mir Beschenkter mit meinem Gelde mein
            Portrait zahlt." ("To Hammer (letter): Professor Steinhof did not turn up; agree with
            his judgment of Halm and interpret the latter as a true German schoolmaster; tell the
            little story about how he reprimanded me for getting abusive toward the French, based on
            Briand and Harden; how he plods along through life totally uninformed, but the first
            time his eyes are opened it is against his own people. I come back to Brünauer-Hammer
            again and provide the reasons why it was not possible for me to permit someone to whom I
            had given money to pay for my portrait with my money.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>H. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006726">Professor Steinhof</tei:rs> hat mir nicht
        geschrieben, ohnehin eine abnorme Schwangerschaft diese 15 Jahre, von denen Sie
          sprechen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">In his letter of
          November 25, 1923 (<tei:ref type="correspondence" ana="OJ-11-36_10">OJ 11/36,
            [10]</tei:ref>), Hammer asked if an acquaintance, Eugen Steinhof, could now contact
          Schenker, after having wished to become his pupil for over fifteen years. </tei:note> u.
        wenn er Sie <tei:add place="interlinear-above">nicht</tei:add> durch „Zufall“ getroffen
        hätte, was wäre gewesen?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Daß ich Ihnen <tei:rs key="entity-000326" type="person">Halm</tei:rs>’s Buch in die
        Hand gespielt habe, wo Sie seinen „<tei:title>Lehrgang</tei:title>“ meinten, tut mir
          leid.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker had mistakenly
          lent Hammer <tei:bibl><tei:author>Halm</tei:author>'s <tei:title level="m">Von zwei
              Kulturen der Musik</tei:title> (Munich: G. Müller, 1913)</tei:bibl>; Hammer had wanted
          to borrow <tei:bibl><tei:author>Halm</tei:author>'s <tei:title level="m">Klavierübung ‒
              Ein Lehrgang des Klavierspiels nach neuen Grundsätzen, zugleich erste Einführung in
              die Musik</tei:title> (Stuttgart: G. A. Zumsteeg, 1918–19)</tei:bibl>. </tei:note>
        Letzteren hätte ich Ihnen ohnehin nicht mitgeben können, weil ich öfter davon
          spreche;<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker made
          favorable mention of Halm's <tei:title level="m">Klavierübung</tei:title> in the
              <tei:bibl><tei:title level="a">Miscellanea</tei:title> section of <tei:title level="j"
              >Der Tonwille</tei:title>, Heft 4, p. 25, fn (Eng. transl., vol. I, p. 164, fn
            18)</tei:bibl>; see also his letter to Halm of September 25, 1922 (<tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="DLA-69.930-10">DLA 69.930/10</tei:ref>). He did eventually
          lend the <tei:title level="m">Klavierübung</tei:title> to Hammer, as indicated by the
          diary entry of February 27, 1924 (OJ 3/6, p. 2639): "Von Hammer durch eine Botin die
          Klavierschule von Halm zurück, . . ." ("From Hammer via a female messenger the piano
          method by Halm returned, . . .").</tei:note> außerdem ists ein Widmungsexemplar. Mit ihrem
        Urteil über <tei:rs key="entity-000326" type="person">H.</tei:rs> treffen Sie erstaunlich
        ins Schwarze. An Reinheit u. Gradheit ein Prachtkerl, aber <tei:del rend="overstrike"
          >über</tei:del> Kunst machen oder nur über Kunst schreiben, verlangt Mehreres außerdem. Er
        lebt in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002674">Wickersdorf</tei:rs>, völlig einsam, aber
        das macht es auch nicht. Er komponiert in Unschuld, die schon arge Schuld ist, sehr linkisch
        überhaupt, dazu linkisch in <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person">Bach</tei:rs>, – er
        weiß (wie er mir vor paar Tagen schrieb),<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial"
          place="foot">See Halm's letter to Schenker of November 6‒10, 1923 (<tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OC-12-7-9">OC 12/7-9</tei:ref>): "Ein Wort von Ihnen über
          meine Musik habe ich vermißt, aber ohne Ihnen deshalb etwa gram zu sein, da ich doch weiß
          wie viel Sie mit dringenden Arbeiten in Anspruch genommen sind. Immerhin bekam ich mit der
          Zeit so etwas wie eine Ahnung, daß Sie wohl nicht recht mit diesen Sachen einverstanden
          sein möchten, was mir zwar leid wäre, mich Ihnen und Ihrem Schaffen aber keineswegs
          entfremden könnte." ("I am lacking some comment from you on my music, but without
          therefore being annoyed at you because I do know how much you are occupied with urgent
          projects. Still, over time I have gotten something like a suspicion that you may not
          exactly be in agreement with these pieces, which would be a shame for me, to be sure, but
          could in no way alienate me from you and your work.").</tei:note> daß ich nicht dafür bin,
        aber wie soll ich es dem Kinde sagen? <tei:rs key="entity-000104" type="person"
          >Bruckner</tei:rs> ist das ihm völlig <tei:hi rend="underline">Entgegen<tei:supplied
            reason="omission">ge</tei:supplied>setzte</tei:hi>, Unbegreifliche, daher seine
        Sehnsucht zu <tei:rs key="entity-000104" type="person">Br.</tei:rs> Er hört nicht gut, daher
        saugt er, wenn er über Noten schreibt, <tei:pb n="2"/> die Worte zwar nicht „aus den
        Fingern“ – er schreibt ja fließend –, wohl aber aus Worten, d. i. Wort aus Wort, was nicht
        besser ist. Leere Wort-fortpflanzung. Nicht ohne Humor ist folgendes: meine Arbeiten sagen
        ihm zu u. er bekennt sich zu ihnen, obgleich selbst „interessiert“, wie Keiner, so tapfer.
        Aber nur – meine „allotria“! Er verzeiht sie mir um des Restes Willen. Nach Erscheinen des
          <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001727"><tei:title>3. Band</tei:title></tei:rs>es und
        zugleich das <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001742"><tei:hi rend="underline">3.
            Heft</tei:hi>es „<tei:title>Tw</tei:title>“</tei:rs> schreibt er mir plötzlich, nach
        einem Hymnus über dies und jenes, ich hätte doch besser getan, gegen die Franzosen nicht zu
        schreiben, denn z. B. wie er soeben in <tei:rs key="entity-000333" type="person"
          >Harden</tei:rs>s <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002566"
            ><tei:title>„Zukunft</tei:title></tei:rs>“ lese, habe <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000101">Briand</tei:rs> nicht so Unrecht usw.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker is most likely referring to Halm's letter dated
          July 24/August 19, 1922 (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-11-35-20">OJ 11/35,
            20</tei:ref>). See also Schenker's comments on Harden and Briand in his reply to Halm of
          September 25, 1922 (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="DLA-69.930-10">DLA
            69.930/10</tei:ref>).</tei:note> Mir war zum Lachen, zum Weinen. <tei:rs
          key="entity-000326" type="person">H.</tei:rs> kümmert sich um die Welt nicht, lebt völlig
        ununterrichtet dahin, scheint übrigens die übliche deutsche-internationale (ich sage:
        unternationale) Gesinnung zu haben [wogegen ich nichts habe, wenn <tei:hi
          rend="double-underline">es</tei:hi>
        <tei:add place="interlinear-above">nur</tei:add> ein deutscher Künstler <tei:hi
          rend="underline">von</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">selbst</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">national</tei:hi> denkt],<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07"
          type="editorial" place="foot">The square-brackets round this passage appear in the
          original.</tei:note> gefällt sich in Objectivität, aber sein erster Augenaufschlag
        sozusagen ist – <tei:hi rend="underline">gegen</tei:hi> seine eigenen Leute, für die Freunde
        u. Beweis? <tei:rs key="entity-000333" type="person">Harden</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000101">Briand</tei:rs>! Solche Purzelbäume leistet sich die
        Natur in Deutschen! <tei:rs key="entity-000326" type="person">H.</tei:rs> ist ein großes
        Kind u. weiter nichts, ein echt deutscher Oberlehrer.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Regarding the complex relationship between Schenker and Halm
          see <tei:bibl><tei:author>Lee Rothfarb</tei:author>, <tei:title level="a">Halm and
              Schenker: Culture Politics, Aesthetics,</tei:title>
            <tei:title level="m">Festschrift Hellmut Federhofer zum 100. Geburtstag</tei:title>, ed.
              <tei:editor>Axel Beer</tei:editor> (Tutzing: Hans Schneider, 2011), pp.
            401–17</tei:bibl> and <tei:bibl><tei:author>Rothfarb</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m"
              >August Halm: A Critical and Creative Life in Music</tei:title> (Rochester: University
            of Rochester Press, 2009), especially pp. 34–40</tei:bibl>.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"> Und bei dieser Gelegenheit auch eines: Als Sie jüngst bei uns waren,
        kamen wir zufällig auf <tei:rs key="entity-000107" type="person">D<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
            >r.</tei:hi> Brn.</tei:rs>, vielmehr auf den Fall Hammer-Brün-Schenker zu sprechen. Nach
        alledem, wie ich zu Ihrer Kunst stehe, die ich aufrichtig sehr hoch schätze, aus innerlichen
        Gründen, <tei:pb n="3"/> – sachliche Gründe anzuführen, würde ich <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">mir</tei:add> nicht nur von Ihnen, auch schon von mir selbst
        nicht herausnehmen – glauben Sie es gewiß, daß es mich sehr gefreut hätte, Ihnen, gerade
        Ihnen meine Züge anzuvertrauen. Aber <tei:rs key="entity-000107" type="person">D<tei:hi
            rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Brn.</tei:rs> dürfte es nicht sein: es wäre
        Hammer-Schenker eine zu unverdiente Ehre für <tei:hi rend="underline">ihn</tei:hi> gewesen.
        Ich behalte diesen wirklich höchst bedauernswerten Menschen aus reinem Mitleid schon 20
        Jahre, bringe ihm (nur ihm, u. wieder aus Mitleid) schwerste Opfer an Zeit u. <tei:hi
          rend="underline">Geld</tei:hi> (da schütteln Sie Ihr Haupt, was?) –, als er mir vor so u.
        sovielen Jahren antrug: 5000 K oder Hammer,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Schenker may be saying that Brünauer offered him either a publication
          subvention of 5,000 Kronen (see the diary entry of June 1, 1918, OJ 2/10, pp. 896–97) or
          the sponsorship of a portrait by Hammer (see the entries of June 11 and June 21, 1918, OJ
          2/10, p. 900 and OJ 2/11, pp. 906–7). Brünauer's offers are discussed in
              <tei:bibl><tei:author>Ian Bent</tei:author>, <tei:title level="a">Heinrich Schenker
              and Robert Brünauer: Relations with a Musical Industrialist,</tei:title> in <tei:title
              level="m">Festschrift Hellmut Federhofer zum 100. Geburtstag</tei:title>, ed.
              <tei:editor>Axel Beer</tei:editor> (Tutzing: Hans Schneider, 2011), pp.
            33‒34</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> da schlug ich mit der Faust auf das Klavier, daß es beinahe
        zerbricht und der Rest kam nach, Sie können sichs denken. Ich lasse mir mein eigenes Geld
        doch nicht „schenken“ vom Beschenkten! Hie u. da dämmert auch in anderen Schülern der Wunsch
        auf, mein Bild zu besitzen, aber da käme es heraus, was sie vor mir so gerne verbergen,
        nämlich daß sie es könnten. Das wollte ich nur gesagt haben, um auch einen letzten Re<tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overwritten">ch</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="superimposed">s</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>t von Verdacht aus der Welt zu schaffen, als richte sich meine Ablehnung an
          <tei:rs key="entity-000107" type="person">Brn.</tei:rs> irgendwie gegen Sie. Ich habe aus
        Discretion schon zu Hause nichts mehr darüber gesagt, lassen Sie mich auch jetzt schweigen.
        Schmerzlich ists genug zu sehen, wie <tei:del rend="overstrike">sich</tei:del> wenig sich
        die Reichen <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">al pari</tei:foreign> mit einem armen Künstler
        stellen können, auch wenn dieser mit ihnen, ihrem Gelde <tei:pb n="4"/> nichts gemein hat,
        auch nicht haben will. Aber Sie sehen, wie ich sie behandle. <tei:rs key="entity-000107"
          type="person">Brn.</tei:rs> behalte ich ja aus Mitleid – ich bin immer besorgt, daß er
        sich niederknallt, bin auch heute seine einzige Stütze –, die anderen Reichen <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">aber</tei:add> werfe ich zur Türe hinaus, wenn sie ihren
        Geldstolz <tei:add place="interlinear-above">nicht</tei:add> vor meiner Türe draußen lassen.
        Ich habe es nicht anders in mir. Hauptsache bleibt, wie Epiktet<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn10" type="editorial" place="foot">Another saying of Epictetus, a Greek
          Stoic philosopher of the first and early second centuries, is cited in the
              <tei:bibl><tei:title level="a">Vermischtes</tei:title> ["Miscellanea"] section of
              <tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title>, Heft 5, pp. 43–44 (Eng. transl., vol.
            I, p. 211)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> sagt, daß „ich meinem Vermögen entspreche“, dann ist
        alles gut. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Angenehmen Winter wünschen wir Beide Ihnen und Ihrer <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003571">Frau</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr herzlich ergebener</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"><tei:hi
              rend="lateinschr">H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1923-12-02">2 Dezember 1923</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dear Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000327"
            >Hammer</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006726">Professor Steinhof</tei:rs> didn't write to
        me, in any case the fifteen years you spoke about<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> are an abnormal pregnancy, and what would have happened if he <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">hadn't</tei:add> met you by "coincidence"?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I am sorry that I handed you <tei:rs key="entity-000326" type="person">Halm</tei:rs>'s
        book when you meant his <tei:title level="m">Method</tei:title>.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> In any case, I couldn't have given you the latter
        to take away with you, because I often speak about it;<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
          type="footnote"/> besides, it's a dedication copy. Your assessment of <tei:rs
          key="entity-000326" type="person">Halm</tei:rs> is amazingly on target. A fine fellow as
        regards purity and uprightness, but creating art or even just writing about it demands more
        than that. He lives in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002674">Wickersdorf</tei:rs>,
        completely isolated, but that doesn't account for it. He composes in innocence, which is
        already proof of guilt; generally very clumsy, what's more, clumsy in regard to <tei:rs
          key="entity-000027" type="person">Bach</tei:rs> ‒ he knows (as he wrote to me a few days
          ago),<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> that I don't approve, but how can I
        tell the child? <tei:rs key="entity-000104" type="person">Bruckner</tei:rs> is something
        that is completely <tei:hi rend="underline">antithetical</tei:hi>, incomprehensible to him,
        hence his craving for <tei:rs key="entity-000104" type="person">Bruckner</tei:rs>. He
        doesn't hear well, so when he writes about musical notes, <tei:pb n="2"/> rather than
        randomly making up words ‒ for he writes fluently, after all ‒, he instead fabricates them
        from other words, i.e. words from words, which is no better. Empty word-propagation. The
        following is not without its humorous side: My works appeal to him and he professes himself
        a follower of them, although declaring himself "interested" as none other, so courageously.
        But only ‒ my "frivolities"! He pardons me for them, condoning them for the sake of all the
        rest. After the publication of <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001727"><tei:title>Volume
            3</tei:title></tei:rs> and likewise the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001742"><tei:hi
            rend="underline">third issue</tei:hi> of <tei:title level="j"
          >Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs> he wrote to me suddenly, after a paean about this and that,
        that it would have been better if I hadn't criticized the French, since for instance, as he
        had just read in <tei:rs key="entity-000333" type="person">Harden</tei:rs>'s <tei:rs
          type="journal" key="entity-002566"><tei:title level="j">Die Zukunft</tei:title></tei:rs>,
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000101">Briand</tei:rs> was not so wrong etc.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> I had to laugh, to cry. <tei:rs
          key="entity-000326" type="person">Halm</tei:rs> gives no thought to the world, he inhabits
        it totally uninformed, moreover he seems to have the usual German-international (I say:
        undernational) attitude [I have nothing against <tei:hi rend="double-underline"
          >this</tei:hi>, as long as a German artist is guided <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >only</tei:add> by <tei:hi rend="underline">intuitive nationalism</tei:hi>].<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> He fancies his own objectivity, but when his eyes
        are first opened, so to speak, it is ‒ <tei:hi rend="underline">against</tei:hi> his own
        people. For supporters and proof? <tei:rs key="entity-000333" type="person">Harden</tei:rs>
        and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000101">Briand</tei:rs>! Such are the somersaults
        performed by the German character! <tei:rs key="entity-000326" type="person">Halm</tei:rs>
        is a big child and nothing more, a true German schoolmaster.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08"
          type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">And l take this opportunity to add one more thing: when you last visited
        us, we by chance came to speak about <tei:rs key="entity-000107" type="person">Dr.
          Brünauer</tei:rs>, or rather about the Hammer–Brünauer–Schenker matter. In light of all that
        I feel about your art, which I sincerely value very highly, for inner reasons <tei:pb
          n="3"/> ‒ bringing up materialistic reasons is something I would never expect of you and
        even less of myself ‒ you can believe without question that it would have greatly pleased me
        to entrust my features to you, specifically you. But it must not be <tei:rs
          key="entity-000107" type="person">Dr. Brünauer</tei:rs>: Hammer–Schenker would have been
        too much of an undeserved honor for <tei:hi rend="underline">him</tei:hi>. I have held on to
        this truly pitiable person out of pure compassion for twenty years now, making for him (only
        for him, and once again out of compassion) the greatest sacrifices of time and <tei:hi
          rend="underline">money</tei:hi> (you are shaking your head, aren't you?) ‒, when he
        offered me so many years ago: 5,000 Kronen or Hammer,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09"
          type="footnote"/> then I pounded the piano with my fist so that it very nearly broke and
        you can imagine the rest. I will not allow my own money to be "donated" to me by the
        recipient of my donation! From time to time the wish to own a portrait of me also dawns on
        other students, but here what they would prefer to conceal from me came to light, namely
        that they could make it happen. I just wanted to have said this, in order to dispel any
        trace of suspicion that my condemnation of <tei:rs key="entity-000107" type="person"
          >Brünauer</tei:rs> was in any way directed at you. For the sake of discretion I have even
        said nothing more about this at home, so let me now also say no more. It's painful enough to
        see how seldom the rich can consider themselves <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat"><tei:hi
            rend="italic">al pari</tei:hi></tei:foreign>
        <tei:supplied reason="translation">on an even footing</tei:supplied> with a poor artist,
        even when the latter does not have, and has no desire to have, <tei:pb n="4"/> anything in
        common with them or with their money. But you see how I treat them. I keep <tei:rs
          key="entity-000107" type="person">Brünauer</tei:rs> on just out of compassion ‒ I always
        worry that he will do away with himself, even today I am his only advocate ‒ <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">but</tei:add> I kick out the other rich men if they <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">don't</tei:add> leave their moneyed pride at my door. I don't
        have it in me to do otherwise. The main thing is, as Epictetus<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn10"
          type="footnote"/> says, that "I live within my means" then all is well.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Both of us wish you and your <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003571">wife</tei:rs> a
        pleasant winter,</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your cordially devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">H.
          Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1923-12-02">December 2, 1923</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
