<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2370" sdoID="JOB-94-3_8">JOB 94-3, [8]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="HS-SP">
      <tei:persName>Hedi Siegel &amp; Stephanie Probst</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2019</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2019</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2020</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2011-02-12" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006186">HammerV ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Hammer dated May 3, 1924</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1924-05-03T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-01-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker agrees to come on May 27 to sit for his portrait, and tells Hammer of
        the forthcoming historical Beethoven Ninth Symphony concert.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Konzert; concert; Original-Besetzung; original make-up of the orchestra;
        Original-Instrumentierung; original instrumentation; Original-Zeitmaß; original tempos;
        Dirigent; conductor; Probe; rehearsal; Aufführung; performance; Eröffnungsfeier; opening </dc:subject>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000327">Viktor Hammer</marcrel:recipient>

    </sdo:itemDesc>



    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Lieber, verehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000327">Hammer</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
            place="foot">Writing of this letter is not recorded in Schenker's diary. — A photocopy
            of this letter (which is preserved at the New York Public Library) exists as OJ 5/15a,
            [8].</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Freudig will ich Ihrem Rufe folgen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Schenker is responding to Hammer's letter of May 1, 1924 (<tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-11-36_12">OJ 11/36, [12]</tei:ref>), inviting him to come
          to his studio on May 7 to begin the sittings for his portrait.</tei:note> Rechne ich doch
        darauf, daß Ihre treue Hand u. mein treues Ohr sich gut aufeinander stimmen werden, wie
        könnte es anders sein? Haben wir doch beide <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >außer</tei:add> unseren besonderen Berufen des Malers, des Musikers, gewissermaßen einen
          <tei:hi rend="underline">gemeinsamen</tei:hi> Beruf vor der Welt als Kreuzungen von ewigen
        Gesetzen der Kunst.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wir kommen um 2<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h.</tei:hi> Nchm., da wir denken, daß Ihnen
        diese Zeit vielleicht am besten paßt. Doch könnte es, da ich am Mittwoch Schüler nicht
        empfange, auch zu einer anderen Stunde sein, auch am Vormittag. Wenn Sie nicht absagen u.
        anders ansetzen, <tei:hi rend="underline">kommen wir um 2<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
            >h.</tei:hi></tei:hi><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">The
          first sitting is described in the diary on May 7, 1924 (p. 2663): "2–3½<tei:hi
            rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> bei Hammer: recht anstrengend; hat ein Schabblatt vor. Die
          gezwungene Haltung hat auch meine Rede gezwungen gemacht." ("2:00–3:30 at Hammer's: really
          strenuous; intends to do a mezzotint. The forced pose also made my speech forced."). The
          next two sittings are described on May 10 (p. 2665): "Um 4<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
            >h</tei:hi> zu Hammer bis 6¼<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi>; zweite Sitzung –
          schon weniger anstrengend; teilt den Plan mit, mir ein Stück zu geben u. den Rest für den
          Verkauf zu halten." ("At 4:00 to Hammer's until 6:15; second sitting – already less
          strenuous; discloses his plan to give me a copy and keep the rest for selling."); and on
          May 14 (p. 2667): "Bei Hammer von 4½–5¾<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi>; Lie-Liechen
          will bemerkt haben, daß Hammer unter dem Eindruck einer Bewegung eine neue Skizze begonnen
          hat." ("At Hammer's from 4:30 to 5; Lie-Liechen believes she noticed that Hammer began a
          new sketch, a movement making an impression on him."). Hammer left Vienna the following
          week (see the postcard received by Schenker on May 22, <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-11-36_13">OJ 11/36, [13]</tei:ref>); the sittings resumed on his return in
          mid-June (see the postcards sent by Hammer on June 16 and 17, <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-11-36_15">OJ 11/36, [15]</tei:ref> and <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-11-36_16">OJ 11/36, [16]</tei:ref>).</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Abends des <tei:date when="1924-05-07">Mittwoch</tei:date> spielt sich im
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003998">Konzerthaus</tei:rs> ein seltsames Konzert ab,
        die <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001269"><tei:title>IX Sinf.</tei:title></tei:rs>
        <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>s zur Erinnerung an 7. Mai 1824,
        an dem die Sinf. zum 1. Mal gespielt wurde. Die Sinf. wird <tei:pb n="2"/> diesmal in
        Original-Gestalt vorgeführt werden: 1) <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >Original-Instrumentierung</tei:hi> (ohne <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000924"
          >Wagner</tei:rs>s Retouchen) 2) <tei:hi rend="underline">Original-Besetzung</tei:hi> u. 3)
        über meiner Anregung auch das <tei:hi rend="underline">Original-Zeitmaß</tei:hi>. Mit dem
        letzteren ist der Dirigent auf die allerhärteste Probe gestellt, auch der Genie wird, selbst
        eine beste Aufführung zugegeben, die diesmal ja gewiß nicht zu erwarten ist, viel Mühe haben
        mitzukommen. An den Proben der Sinf. teilzunehmen, habe ich abgelehnt, aber zur Aufführung,
        abds 7<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h.</tei:hi>, gehe ich, um zu hören, wie H. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000443">v. Klenau</tei:rs> meine Anregungen verwertet, die sehr
        schwieriger Art sind.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker
          gave a detailed critique of the conductor Paul von Klenau's performance in the <tei:ref
            type="diaries" cRef="OJ-03-06_1924-05:r0007">diary entry of May 7, 1924</tei:ref> (pp.
          2663‒2664). He wrote about the event, "Hundert Jahre IX. Sinfonie: Zur Festaufführung der
            <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-003270">Wiener Konzerthaus-Gesellschaft</tei:rs>
          am 7. Mai 1924" ("One Hundred Years of the Ninth Symphony: On the jubilee performance of
          the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-003270">Vienna Concert House Society</tei:rs>,
          May 7, 1924"), in the <tei:title level="a">Vermischtes</tei:title> (<tei:title level="a"
            >Miscellania</tei:title>) section of <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001747"><tei:title
              level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title> Heft 8/9</tei:rs> (= IV/2–3, April–Sept 1924), pp.
          53–54; Eng. transl., vol. II, pp. 121–22; the diary indicates that he dictated this text
          on August 1, 1924 (p. 2700).</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ihre Ausstellung habe ich natürlich gesehen. An der Eröffnungsfeier
        teilzunehmen war mir leider versagt, da mich ein Entsetzliches befiel, das mich nicht aus
        dem Hause gehen ließ.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker
          recorded in his diary on February 5, 1924 (p. 2630) that he received Hammer's invitation
            (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-11-37_2">OJ 11/37, [2]</tei:ref>) to the
          opening of 76th exhibition by Artists of the Vienna Secession. The event took place on
          February 7, 1924; the diary entry for that day (pp. 2632‒2633) indicates: "Wegen
          Unwohlseins der Eröffnung der Ausstellung nicht beigewohnt." ("Because of sickness, did
          not attend the opening of the exhibition."). The Schenkers went to see the exhibition on
          February 9, as is recorded in the diary at p. 2633: "In die Ausstellung der Secession:
          Hammer’s Arbeiten machen einen vorzüglichen Eindruck, wenn auch die Beschränkung auf das
          Portrait einen Blick in die Welt des Künstlers, mir wenigsten[s], nicht gestattet, zumal
          große Portraits in Oel auch fehlen. Freilich, die Portraits in Bleistift oder die
          Tempera-Bilder sind alle sehr peinlich gehalten, nicht schreiend nach außen – aber wie
          viel Kraft in dieser Selbstbeherrschung zugleich Beherrschung der Kunst ist, ist nicht zu
          entscheiden. Die übrigen Bilder machen – bis auf wenige Stücke – einen trostlosen
          Eindruck: Gesuchtheit waltet vor, jeder will die Natur anders sehen, anders wiedergeben!"
          <tei:lb/>("At the exhibition in the Secession: Hammer's works make a first rate
          impression, even if their limitation to portraiture does not afford us, at least myself, a
          glimpse into the artist's world, particularly as large portraits in oil are also lacking.
          Admittedly, the portraits in pencil or the tempera are all somewhat embarrassingly
          reserved, not out-going ‒ but it cannot be ascertained how much this power of self-command
          equates to a command of the art. The remaining pictures ‒ apart from a few works ‒ make a
          bleak impression: exertion prevails, everyone wishing to see Nature differently, to render
          it differently!").</tei:note> Über all das mündlich.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="ident-40">Auf Wiedersehen</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"><tei:hi
              rend="lateinschr">H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p>Von meiner <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Frau</tei:rs> herzlichste Grüße<tei:lb/>
          <tei:date when="1924-05-03">3. Mai 1924</tei:date></tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Dear, revered Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000327"
            >Hammer</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>I answer your summons with pleasure.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> I
        fully expect that your trusty hand and my trusty ear will be in agreement ‒ how could it be
        otherwise? Surely we both have, <tei:add place="interlinear-above">apart from</tei:add> our
        distinct professions as painter and musician, a <tei:hi rend="underline">mutual</tei:hi>
        profession that the world sees, in some measure, as the intermingling of the eternal laws of
        art.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>We will come at two in the afternoon, since we think this time will suit you the best.
        But since I don't see students on Wednesdays, it could be at another time, also in the
        morning. If you don't cancel and reschedule, <tei:hi rend="underline">we will come at two
          o'clock</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">On <tei:date when="1924-05-07">Wednesday</tei:date> evening an unusual
        concert will take place at the <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003998">Concert
          House</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>'s <tei:rs
          type="composition" key="entity-001269"><tei:title>Ninth Symphony</tei:title></tei:rs> as a
        remembrance of May 7, 1824, when the symphony was performed for the first time. <tei:pb
          n="2"/> This time the symphony will be performed as it was originally, having: 1) the
          <tei:hi rend="underline">original instrumentation</tei:hi> (without <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000924">Wagner</tei:rs>'s retouchings), 2) the <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >original make-up of the orchestra</tei:hi>, and 3) at my suggestion, the <tei:hi
          rend="underline">original tempos</tei:hi>. With the latter the conductor is put to the
        most grueling test; the listener too, even given an optimal performance, which is surely not
        to be expected this time, will find it very hard to follow along. I declined to take part in
        the rehearsal, but I will go to the performance, at seven in the evening, in order to hear
        how Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000443">von Klenau</tei:rs> will apply my
        suggestions, which involve great difficulties.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"
        /></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I have of course seen your exhibition. Regrettably, I was unable to attend
        the opening, since a nasty ailment prevented me from leaving the house.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> More about all of this when we talk.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="ident-40">Until we see each other,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">H.
          Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p>Most cordial greetings from my <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
            >wife</tei:rs><tei:lb/>
          <tei:date when="1924-05-03">May 3, 1924</tei:date></tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
