<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2045" sdoID="JOB-94-3_5">JOB 94-3, [5]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="HS-SP">
      <tei:persName>Hedi Siegel &amp; Stephanie Probst</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2017</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2017</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2017</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2011-02-12" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006186">HammerV ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Hammer dated October 24, 1923</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1923-10-24T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2018-01-25</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker invites Hammer and his wife for November 7; — The problem of the
        "middleman" (performer, etc.) in music, by contrast with painting; — he reports on Hertzka's
        proposal to make Tonwille a quarterly publication.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Jause; tea; Bild; painting; verrücken; distort; zerreissen; tear up; Unfähigkeit;
        incapacity; Publikum; public; Maler; painter; Kenner; connoisseur; Laie; layman; Linie;
        line; Farbe; color; Tonkünstler; composer; Neume; Partitur; score; Dirigent; conductor;
        Klavierspieler; pianist; Violinspieler; violinist; Sänger; singer; Mittelsmann; middleman;
        Fluch; curse; Geniewerk; work of genius; Handschrift; manuscript</dc:subject>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000327">Viktor Hammer</marcrel:recipient>

    </sdo:itemDesc>



    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:note type="editorial" place="pre-text">A photocopy of this postcard (which is preserved
        at the New York Public Library) exists in the Oswald Jonas Collection as OJ 5/15a,
        [5].</tei:note>

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Verehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000327"
            >Hammer</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/6, p. 2589, October 24, 1923: "An
            Hammer (Br.): bitte ihn u. Frau für Mittwoch den 7. XI. zur Jause; verspreche Sanftmut
            in Fülle; berühre die Hauptschwierigkeit der Tonkunst, das Angewiesensein auf einen
            Mittelsmann, der eigentlich immer ungeeignet ist; der Maler dagegen hat mit einem
            solchen Mittelsmann nichts zu schaffen." ("To Hammer (letter): I ask him and his wife to
            come for tea on Wednesday, November 7; I promise an abundance of gentleness; touch on
            the primary difficulty of music, the dependence on a middleman, who actually is always
            unsuitable; in contrast, the painter has nothing to do with a middleman of this sort.").
          </tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Den Postverhältnissen in Wien u. auf dem Lande Rechnung tragend beeile ich mich, Sie u.
        Ihre Frau <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003571">Gemalin</tei:rs> zu uns für den
          <tei:date when="1923-11-07"><tei:hi rend="underline">7.</tei:hi> Nov.</tei:date>
        (Mittwoch!) zur Jause zu bitten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Schenker had just received Hammer's request, in his letter of October 22, 1923 (<tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-11-36_8">OJ 11/36, [8]</tei:ref>), to visit in early
          November</tei:note> Ich verspreche <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000326"
        >Halm</tei:rs>’s Buch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">There was a
          misunderstanding about the book by Halm that Hammer wanted to borrow; see Hammer's letter
          of November 25, 1923 (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-11-36_10">OJ 11/36,
            [10]</tei:ref>), and Schenker's reply of December 2, 1923 (<tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="JOB-94-3_6">JOB 94-3, [6]</tei:ref>).</tei:note> u.
        „Sanftmut“ in Fülle.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">See Hammer's
          letter of October 22, 1923 (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-11-36_8">OJ 11/36,
            [8]</tei:ref>), where he quotes Herder's "Rede sanfter. . . " ("Speak more gently. .
          .").</tei:note> Mit Ihrer Verschollenheit wußte ich lange nichts anzufangen, u. ich weiß
        nicht, ob H. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006471"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
            >Gartenberg</tei:hi></tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Gartenberg is mentioned in connection with Hammer in Schenker's diary entry of March 5,
          1923, at OJ 3/4, p. 2499: "Abends holt uns Weisse zu Steiners ab; nach Tisch erscheint
          dort Herr Gartenberg; über Hammer gesprochen u. dessen Schrift, die Herr G. finanziert . .
          ." ("In the evening, Weisse picks us up to go to the Steiners; Mr. Gartenberg shows up
          there after dinner; talks about Hammer and his monograph, which Mr. Gartenberg is
          financing . . .").</tei:note> oder <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000107">D<tei:hi
            rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi>
          <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Brünauer</tei:hi></tei:rs> es mir zuerst sagten, daß Sie in
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002823">Florenz</tei:rs> weilen. Dazu konnte ich mir
        freilich schon etwas mehr denken.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Bei dieser Gelegenheit möchte ich nur <tei:add place="interlinear-above">noch</tei:add>
        Folgendes anmerken: Nehmen Sie an, irgend ein Schenker würde es sich herausnehmen, Ihre
        schönen Bilder zu überpinseln, die Linien zu verrücken, die Köpfe auf- u. zerreißen, die
        Perspektiven zu vernichten, u. dieses Kauderwelsch, dieses Monstrum an Unfähigkeit zur Kunst
        als einen <tei:hi rend="underline">echten</tei:hi> „<tei:hi rend="underline"
        >Hammer</tei:hi>“ anzupreisen u. dem Publikum vorzuführen; u. mehr als das, er würde in
        Anspruch nehmen, für einen bedeutenden Maler, für einen echten <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000327">Hammer</tei:rs>-Kenner u. dgl. sich legitimiert <tei:pb n="2"/> zu
        haben. Ist der Fall aber denkbar? Als ich zum ersten Mal vor Ihren Bildern stand (sehr lange
        her, lange bevor ich Sie kennen gelernt habe),<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial"
          place="foot">It is possible that Schenker is referring to his visit with Jeanette to the
          47th exhibition of the Vienna Secession, which included five oil paintings by Hammer. The
          diary records his evaluation of the paintings at OJ 1/14, p. 542, March 21, 1914,
          transcription and translation from <tei:bibl><tei:author>Ian Bent</tei:author>, <tei:title
              level="a">Heinrich Schenker and Robert Brünauer: Relations with a Musical
              Industrialist,</tei:title> in <tei:title level="m">Festschrift Hellmut Federhofer zum
              100. Geburtstag</tei:title>, ed. <tei:editor>Axel Beer</tei:editor> (Tutzing: Hans
            Schneider, 2011), p. 34</tei:bibl>: "Herrn Hammers Bilder . . . gefallen uns beiden ganz
          gut besonders das Selbstportrait. Mir scheint im allerletzten Kern seiner Gestalten etwas
          allzu Steifes zu liegen: die Linien, die Umrisse, Knochen, Rücken ‒ kurz ein
          undefinierbares Etwas gibt den Figuren eine überflüssig steife Haltung. Gewissermaßen
          fehlt den Körpern der Wohllaut einer Auseinandersetzung zwischen Knochen u. Fleisch."
          ("The pictures of Mr. Hammer . . . are quite pleasing to us, especially the self-portrait.
          To me, something unduly stiff seems to lie right at the heart of his forms: the lines, the
          outlines, of the sketches, bones, backs ‒ in short, an indefinable something gives his
          figures a needlessly stiff bearing."). The self-portrait in the exhibition may have been
          that of 1912, which is reproduced in <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Victor Hammer: Artist
              and Printer</tei:title>, compiled by <tei:editor>Carolyn R. Hammer</tei:editor>
            (Lexington, Kentucky: The Anvil Press, 1981), p. 97</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> war ich auf
        meine Laienweise überrascht, gerührt und entzückt, zugleich aber auch nicht einen Augenblick
        in Zweifel, daß ich echte Genie vor mir habe. Das ist das schöne Los des Malers: er bringt
        seine Linien u. Farben auf die Leinwand u. der Rest mag ihm gleichgültig sein, sein Bild ist
        u. bleibt so.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Dagegen der arme Tonkünstler! Er drückt sich auch immer in <tei:hi
          rend="lateinschr underline">Neumen</tei:hi> aus, in Zeichen, u. hat er schon alles getan,
        ist er erst recht förmlich auf das <tei:hi rend="underline">Mitschaffen</tei:hi> des
        Partiturenlesers, des Dirigenten, des Klavier-, Violinspielers, Sängers angewiesen, u. auf
          <tei:hi rend="underline">seine</tei:hi> Rechnung geht alles, was diese von sich geben.
        Können Sie sich das furchtbare Los der Musik vorstellen?! Auf der ganzen Welt, zu allen
        Zeiten, Tagen, Stunden, Minuten hören Sie die verschiedensten, widrigsten, <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>s’ als „<tei:hi rend="underline"
          >den</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Beethoven</tei:hi>“ usw. (Um wie viel besser haben Sie es!
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">?</tei:del>)</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Und es geht so weiter: habe ich als Erster es endlich dahin gebracht, daß die Leute
        dieses Unerhörte begreifen, u. wenden sich demgemäß Dirigenten (besuchend, brieflich
        anfragend) <tei:pb n="3"/> Violin-, Klavierspieler, Professoren etc. um Rath an mich, oder
        gar werden in meinem Namen Bücher, Abhandlungen geschrieben (u. das geschieht immer mehr),
        ich bin entsetzt über die Ausführung, über die Verdrehungen usw.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Was ist das alles nur? Der <tei:hi rend="underline">Fluch</tei:hi> des <tei:hi
          rend="underline">Mittelsmanns</tei:hi> ruht auf der Musik, wie ihn die Malerei nicht
        kennt. Der Mittelsmann ist eitel, er tut was u. gefällt sich drin u. will immer mehr auch
        den Anderen gefallen, er will verdienen usw. u. so ist das Werk eines Tonkünstlers über u.
        über beschmutzt von solchem Parasitentum.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Es hätte nichts auf sich, wenn die Vermittler Eignung hätten. Aber sie haben nicht die
        geringste. Was ist da also zu tun, wenn die Musik, das Geniewerk gerettet werden soll? Die
        Leute zur Bescheidenheit mahnen, ist ja vergeblich, das ist wider ihre Natur, bescheiden zu
        seien, u. doch ‒ entbehren kann man sie nicht.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich zeige <tei:add place="interlinear-above">Ihnen</tei:add>
        <tei:del rend="overstrike">ich</tei:del>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">Hand</tei:hi>schriften von <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000803">Schubert</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000612"
          >Mozart</tei:rs>, u. was draus die Musiker — so wollen sie ja heißen — gemacht haben.
          „<tei:title>Gretchen am Spinnrad</tei:title>“ sollen Sie sehen!<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker is referring to his essay that
          compares Schubert's autograph score with what he considered an inauthentic first edition:
              <tei:bibl><tei:title level="a">Franz Schubert: Gretchen am Spinnrade: Neue Ergebnisse
              einer Handschrift-Studie</tei:title> ["Schubert's 'Gretchen am Spinnrade': Latest
            Results of a Manuscript Study"], <tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title>, Heft 6
            (1923), pp. 3–8; Eng. transl., vol. II, pp. 3‒7</tei:bibl>.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> Sie wissen nicht, wie gut Sie es haben u. darum . .</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:sic>Allmälich</tei:sic> drückt sich allgemein die Überzeugung aus, daß ich viel ‒
        zu gütig bin für dieses Ausmaß an Nichtskönnen, u. Unbescheidenheit, ja sogar mein Verleger
        bot mir <tei:hi rend="underline">aus Eigenem</tei:hi> den „<tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001739"><tei:title>Tonw.</tei:title></tei:rs>“ als „<tei:hi rend="underline"
          >Vierteljahr</tei:hi>sschrift“ an (!),<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial"
          place="foot"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356">Emil Hertzka</tei:rs>'s offer at
          meeting on October 10, 1923, thus shortly before this letter was written, is described in
          the diary at 3/6, p. 2581: ". . . er mich mit dem Antrag überrascht . . . mit einer
          ‘Vierteljahrschrift’ einzusetzen, auch auf dem Titel als solche einbekannt." (" . . . he
          surprises me with the offer . . . to start releasing a 'quarterly publication' right away,
          also reflecting this in the title."). See <tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title>,
          Eng. transl. vol. 2, p. v. </tei:note> u. wie so viele werden sicher auch Sie einmal mir
        sagen: „Sie sind ein Engel, der Friede, die Liebe, die Güte, – ich hab’s nur nicht so
        gewußt.“</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Die Musik ist an ihrem harten Los eben zugrunde gegangen, sie kehrt nie wieder, nie,
        nie . .</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ist das nicht zum Weinen? Zum Rasen?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Und dennoch, am <tei:date when="1923-11-07">7.<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
          >ten</tei:hi></tei:date> verspreche „sanft“ zu sein.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09"
          type="editorial" place="foot">See note 4 above.</tei:note> Ihr u. Ihrer Frau <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-003571">Gemalin</tei:rs>
      </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">bestens grüßend</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"><tei:hi
              rend="lateinschr">H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1923-10-24">24. X. 1923</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p><tei:lb/>Meine <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Frau</tei:rs> schließt sich
          den Grüßen an.</tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Revered Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000327"
            >Hammer</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Taking into account the postal situation in Vienna and in the countryside, I hasten to
        invite you and your <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003571">wife</tei:rs> for tea on
          <tei:date when="1923-11-07">November <tei:hi rend="underline">7</tei:hi></tei:date>
          (Wednesday!).<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> I promise <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000326">Halm</tei:rs>'s book<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
          type="footnote"/> and an abundance of “gentleness.”<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
          type="footnote"/> For quite some time I didn't know what to make of your disappearance,
        and I don't know if it was Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006471"
          >Gartenberg</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> or <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000107">Dr. Brünauer</tei:rs> who first told me that you were in
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002823">Florence</tei:rs>. Then I could of course imagine
        some more details.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I would like to take this opportunity to make only the following <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">additional</tei:add> comment: Just suppose that some kind of
        Schenker would have the presumption to paint over your beautiful pictures, to distort the
        lines, to rip open and rip up the heads, to destroy the perspective and to extol this
        rubbish, this monstrous example of deficient artistic ability, as a <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >genuine</tei:hi> "<tei:hi rend="underline">Hammer</tei:hi>" and exhibit it to the public;
        and more than that, he would claim he had proven himself to be a notable painter, a true
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000327">Hammer</tei:rs>-connoisseur and the like.
          <tei:pb n="2"/> Is such a case even conceivable? When I stood in front of your paintings
        for the first time (a long time ago, long before I got to know you),<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> I was, in my amateurish way, surprised, moved and
        delighted, and at the same time I did not doubt for a moment that I was faced by true
        genius. That is the fortunate fate of the painter: he puts his lines and colors on the
        canvas and the rest doesn't matter to him, his picture is and remains what it is.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Contrast this to the poor musician! He invariably expresses himself in <tei:hi
          rend="underline">neumes</tei:hi>, in signs, and, having done everything he could, he is
        quite literally dependent on the <tei:hi rend="underline">collaborative work</tei:hi> of the
        score-reader, the conductor, the pianist, violinist, singer, and all of their contributions
        are ascribed to <tei:hi rend="underline">him</tei:hi>. Can you imagine the dreadful fate of
        music?! In the whole world, at all times, days, hours, minutes, you hear the most diverse,
        the most contrary <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>s as "<tei:hi
          rend="underline">the</tei:hi> Beethoven" etc. (How much better is your situation!<tei:del
          rend="overstrike">?</tei:del>)</tei:p>

      <tei:p>And so it goes on: as the first to do so, I have finally prevailed on people to grasp
        the meaning of this outrage, and thus conductors (inquiring during visits, in letters),
          <tei:pb n="3"/> violinists, pianists, professors etc. turn to me for advice, or books,
        treatises are even written in my name (and this happens more and more); I am appalled at the
        interpretation, distortions etc.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>What could all of this mean? Music is plagued by the <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >curse</tei:hi> of the <tei:hi rend="underline">middleman</tei:hi>, a curse unknown to
        painting. The middleman is vain, he does something and is pleased by his own appearance and
        also wants to please others more and more, he wants to make money etc. and so the work of a
        musician is defiled again and again by such parasitism.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>This would be of no consequence if the intermediaries had any ability. But they have
        not the slightest. Then what can be done to save music, to save works of genius? Urging
        these people to be modest is futile; modesty goes against their nature, and yet ‒ one cannot
        do without them.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I show <tei:add place="interlinear-above">you</tei:add>
        <tei:del rend="overstrike">I</tei:del>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">manu</tei:hi>scripts by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000803"
          >Schubert</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000612">Mozart</tei:rs>, and what
        musicians ‒ as they wish to be called ‒ have made of them. You should look at
          "<tei:title>Gretchen am Spinnrad</tei:title>"!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07"
          type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> You don't know how lucky you are and therefore . .</tei:p>

      <tei:p>The belief that I am much ‒ too generous toward this degree of know-nothingness and
        immodesty is gradually being widely expressed, indeed my publisher, <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >of his own accord</tei:hi>, offered to make <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001739"
            ><tei:title level="j">Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs> a "<tei:hi rend="underline"
          >quarterly</tei:hi> publication" (!),<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/> and
        like so many others you will surely say to me one day "You are an angel, you are peace,
        love, kindness itself ‒ I just didn't realize it."</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Its cruel fate has in fact destroyed music, never, never will it rise again . .</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Isn't that enough to make you weep? To rant and rave?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>And yet, on the <tei:date when="1923-11-07">7th</tei:date> I promise to be
          "gentle."<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Best greetings to you and your <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-003571">wife</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">H.
          Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1923-10-24">October 24, 1923</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p><tei:lb/>My <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">wife</tei:rs> joins me in
          sending greetings.</tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
