<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2526" sdoID="LC-ASC-27-45_22">LC ASC 27/45, [22]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="MV" scope="sole">Moriz Violin's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2020</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2020</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2020</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-07-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-007495">ViolinM ~
        ASchoenberg</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Moriz Violin to Schoenberg, dated October 23,
        1940</dc:title>
      <dcterms:created>1940-10-23T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-09-04</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Violin says that he is completely without work, but is not giving in to
        despair.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Stolz; pride; Licht; light; Verzweiflung; despair; tragisch; tragic;
        arbeitsunfähig; out of work; Klavierstückchen; small piano piece; Schrei; cry; Kind; child;
        Preis; fee</dc:subject>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000798">ASchoenberg</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address rend="indent-50">
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#MV"/><tei:placeName>S. F.</tei:placeName>
            <tei:date when="1940-10-23">23. Okt. 40</tei:date>.</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>253 Buenavista Ave.</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>Liebster u. verehrtester <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798"
            >Freund</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Vor einer Viertelstunde bekam ich Ihre lieben, lieben Worte.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">No immediately preceding letter from
          Schoenberg appears to survive.</tei:note> Daß Sie Ihre langen Arbeitszeit etwas abknüpfen
        mir so gutes zu sagen, erfüllt mich mit aufrichtigem Stolz. Daß ich immer von Ihnen so oft
        von dem einzigen Licht daß mir in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002510"
            ><tei:country>America</tei:country></tei:rs> scheint immer u. zu jedermann rede, mögen
        Sie als unübertriebene Tatsache freundlichst zur Ken<tei:supplied reason="misspelling"
          >n</tei:supplied>tnis nehmen. Die Freude an Ihrem Briefe ist mir nur durch einen <tei:hi
          rend="underline">einzigen</tei:hi> Gedankengang darin, getrübt. Daß ich einmal ärgerlich
        sein könnte, warum sollte das nicht möglich sein, ebenso wie es bei Ihnen möglich wäre? In
        solchem Falle würde ich, würden Sie reden. Das wäre ein Gebot unserer Überzeugung u.
        Lebensführung. Daß ich Ihnen aber <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">per forma</tei:foreign> etwas
        sage, nehmen Sie bitte nie u. nimmer <tei:add place="interlinear-above">an</tei:add>. So
        eine abgefeimte Manier eines Weltmannes würde ich nie <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >Ihnen</tei:hi> gegenüber anwenden. Daß wäre eine große Mißachtung meinerseits! Zweifeln
        Sie an der Sonne Klarheit u. Wahrheit, nur nicht <tei:hi rend="underline">an meine
          Geradlinigkeit</tei:hi> Ihnen gegenüber!</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Nun nur Weniges über mich!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich lebe nur weiter, weil mir das Wort „Verzweiflung“ in geistigen Dingen ein Fremdwort
        ist.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Daß ich unter tragischen Umständen arbeitsunfähig bin, trifft mich hart. (Ich meine da
        nicht Klavierspielen<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">.</tei:supplied>) Ich habe am meisten
          <tei:hi rend="underline">für</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">mich</tei:hi> gearbeitet wenn ich im Kunstleben am beschäftigsten
        war. Jetzt, wo ich nichts zu tun habe, von meiner <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000914"
          >Frau</tei:rs> Arbeit lebe, arbeite ich <tei:hi rend="underline">nichts</tei:hi>, ein
        kurzes Klavierstückchen, mehr ein Schrei, ist die einzige <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overwritten">a</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="superimposed">E</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>rnte.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich habe meine kleine 11jährige Freundin <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-007504">Irene Schreier</tei:rs> zum ersten mal in die Öffentlichkeit gestellt.
        Es war ein <tei:hi rend="underline">außergewöhnlicher</tei:hi> Erfolg für das Kind<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Irene Schreier Scott recalls (email,
          March 18, 2020): "I remember the concert Violin presented me in very well indeed. It was
          in San Francisco's Temple Emanuel and must have been a fundraiser ‒ perhaps at that time
          for the Russian War Relief? Of this I am not certain ‒ it might also have been for a
          Jewish refugee organization. Temple Emanuel, a beautiful structure, still plays a role in
          San Francisco's cultural life. Violin himself played at the occasion, I believe in the
          Mendelssohn D minor Trio, but I have no recollection who the string players were. I
          believe I opened the program with the Gavotte from the G minor English Suite of Bach, a
          Mendelssohn Song without Words and the Chopin C<tei:g type="sharp"/> minor
          Waltz."</tei:note> ‒ ‒ ich glaube aber an keine Nachwirkung für mich. Ich komme gegen die
        Schmachtfetzenmusiker nicht auf. Für was soll man kämpfen? Ich bekomme nicht einmal
        Gelegenheit zu spielen!!!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="3"/> Vielleicht bekommen Sie manche Erken<tei:supplied
          reason="spelling">n</tei:supplied>tnis von folgendem Vorfall:</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Letzthin sagte jemand in amerikanischer Gesellschaft: „Violin kann keine
        Schüler bekommen, weil er nicht unter $5 eine Stunde giebt.“ <tei:lb/>1.) finde ich den
        Preis gar nicht so abenteuerlich <tei:lb/>u. 2.) besser aber <tei:choice>
          <tei:sic>wieder</tei:sic>
          <tei:corr>wider</tei:corr>
        </tei:choice> 1.) kam ich <tei:hi rend="underline">nie</tei:hi> in die Lage diesen Preis zu
        nennen, weil mich niemand anfragte. Es ist also überhaupt nicht wahr. Ich glaube wenn man
        nicht direkt von jemandem sagen kann, er sei ein Idiot, so ist <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >das</tei:hi> ein ganz feines Mittel???</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Sollte ich nächstens in einem Kino<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot">"gewinnen" ("win") suggests that Violin might mean "Kasino."
          Alternatively, he may have in mind securing a regular job playing organ in a
          cinema.</tei:note> gewinnen, (meine einzige Chance!) so komme ich Sie u. Ihre liebe
        Familie zu sehen.</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Das allerherzlichste von Haus zu Haus,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">getreuest Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">M Violin</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/>
          <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">written sideways:</tei:note> Ich wohne jetzt wie
          angegeben im Boarding house meiner Freundin <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-007656"
            >Schreier</tei:rs>! <tei:cit>
            <tei:q>253 Buena Vista Ave.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot"
                >This change of address marks Violin's unstated separation from his family. Valerie
                took a live-in housekeeping job in a wealthy household, while Genovefa (Eva)
                eventually established herself in Los Angeles. (Irene Schreier Scott, email, March
                18, 2020)</tei:note></tei:q>
          </tei:cit></tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>

    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address rend="indent-50">
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#MV"/><tei:placeName>San Francisco</tei:placeName>,
              <tei:date when="1940-10-23">October 23, 1940</tei:date>.</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>253 Buenavista Ave.</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>Dearest and most revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798"
            >Friend</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">I received your very precious words a quarter of an hour ago.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> I am filled with utter pride that you curtailed
        your long work time to say such good things to me. I speak always and to everyone of you as
        the sole light that shines upon me so often in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002510"
            ><tei:country>America</tei:country></tei:rs> – please kindly take that as the
        unexaggerated truth. My joy at your letter is diminished by only one <tei:hi
          rend="underline">single</tei:hi> train of thought. There was a time when I could get
        annoyed <tei:supplied reason="clarity">thinking</tei:supplied>: Why should what was possible
        for you not be equally possible for me? In such a case, you and I would talk it through.
        That was to be a precept of our convictions and of the way we would run our lives. But
        please accept that I would never say something to you <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat"><tei:hi
            rend="italic">per forma</tei:hi></tei:foreign>. I would never adopt such a crafty
        man-of-the-world manner <tei:hi rend="underline">toward you</tei:hi>. That would be an act
        of great disrespect on my part. Doubt the clarity and truth of the sun, but do not doubt
          <tei:hi rend="underline">my straightforwardess</tei:hi> toward you!</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Now a little about me!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I continue to live on only because the word "despair" is to me in matters intellectual
        an alien one.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>It cuts me to the quick that I am, under tragic circumstances, out of work. (I'm not
        referring there to playing the piano.) I worked hardest <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >for</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">myself</tei:hi> when I was most fully employed in the world of
        music. Now, when I have nothing to do, when I am living off my <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000914">wife</tei:rs>'s work, I work on <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >nothing</tei:hi>, a tiny, fragmentary piano piece, more a cry than anything else, is my
        sole harvest.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I have presented my eleven-year-old friend <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-007504">Irene Schreier</tei:rs> to the public for the first time. It was an
          <tei:hi rend="underline">extraordinary</tei:hi> success for the child<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> – – but I believe of no benefit for myself. I am
        no match for musicians who wear their heart on their sleeve. What should one fight for? I
        get no opportunities to play!!!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="3"/> Perhaps the following incident will come as a surprise to
        you:</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Recently someone in American society said: "Violin can't get any pupils
        because he won't give a lesson for under $5." <tei:lb/>1.) I find the price not at all
        unbelievable, <tei:lb/>and 2.) better, but counter to 1.) I was <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >never</tei:hi> in a position to name this price because no one ever asked me. It is thus
        categorically untrue. I believe that if one cannot say outright of someone that he is an
        idiot, then <tei:hi rend="underline">that</tei:hi> is a pretty neat way of doing the same
        thing??? </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">If I were before long to win in a cinema<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
          type="footnote"/> (my only chance!), then I would come and see you and your dear
        family.</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">The most cordial greetings from my family to
          yours,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Most faithfully your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">M. Violin</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/>
          <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">written sideways:</tei:note> I am now living, as
          indicated, in the boarding house of my friend <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-007656"
              ><tei:supplied reason="title">Mrs.</tei:supplied> Schreier</tei:rs>: <tei:cit>
            <tei:q>253 Buena Vista Ave!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:q>
          </tei:cit></tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
