<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2531" sdoID="LC-ASC-27-45_26">LC ASC 27/45, [26]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="MV" scope="sole">Moriz Violin's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2020</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2020</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2020</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-07-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-007495">ViolinM ~
        ASchoenberg</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Moriz Violin to Schoenberg, dated March 29, 1941</dc:title>
      <dcterms:created>1941-03-29T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-09-07</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Violin thanks Schoenberg for his recent stay in Los Angeles, and comments on
        Schoenberg's lecture "Composition with Twelve Tones," which he attended during that stay. —
        He reminds Schoenberg to advocate for him for an engagement with the New York New Friends of
        Music; and he mentions for the first time his plan to found an institute in San
        Francisco.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Vortrag; lecture; Manuscript; Beispiel; music example; Werturteil; value
        judgement; Skelett; skeleton; Inhalt; content; System; Entwurf; sketch; Idee; idea;
        Engagement; Klavierkonzert; piano concerto; Kammermusik; chamber music; Unterredung;
        discussion; Institut; institute</dc:subject>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000798">ASchoenberg</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address rend="indent-50">
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#MV"/><tei:placeName>S. F.</tei:placeName>
            <tei:date when="1941-03-29">29 März 1941</tei:date>.</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>Lieber u. verehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798"
          >Freund</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Haben Sie wieder innigsten Dank für die lebenserfrischenden Los Angeleser
        Tage!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich bekam durch Ihren Vortrag<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Violin had attended Schoenberg's lecture <tei:title
            level="a">Composition with Twelve Tones,</tei:title> given at the University of
          California, Los Angeles on March 26, 1941, apparently spending a few days in the company
          of the Schoenbergs. Schoenberg had given the lecture twice before, at Princeton University
          ("translated from German") on March 6, 1934, then at the University of Southern California
          in the summer of 1935. The text was published in <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Style
              &amp; Idea</tei:title>, ed. <tei:editor>Dika Newlin</tei:editor> (New York:
            Philosophical Library, 1950)</tei:bibl>, and reprinted in <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m"
              >Style and Idea: Selected Writings of Arnold Schoenberg</tei:title>, ed.
              <tei:editor>Leonard Stein</tei:editor> (Pacific Palisades, CA: Belmont Music
            Publishers; London: Faber &amp; Faber, 1975), pp. 214‒45</tei:bibl>, where it is
          followed by a second article, written c. 1948, with source notes on p. 523.</tei:note> den
        ersten verlässlichen, authentischen Einblick in Ihre <tei:term>12 Ton Theorie</tei:term> u.
        fand, so weit man bei erstem Hören es wagen darf, völlige Klarheit Ihrer Ideen. Ich möchte
        meine innere Einstellung festlegen (für mich!) bis Sie mir das Manuscript mit Beispielen
        freundlichst senden werden.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Schoenberg had sent Violin a copy of what was perhaps an earlier version of the text of
          this lecture with <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="LC-ASC-7-50_13">LC ASC 7/50,
            [13]</tei:ref> on May 19, 1940, which Violin seems to have forgotten or never
          received.</tei:note> Wenn ich ein paar Dinge, die mir beim ersten “<tei:foreign
          xml:lang="eng">Glimpse</tei:foreign>”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
          place="foot">"glance" (English transl.): Violin uses the English "glimpse", a word he had
          used in the title of a course he had then been about to teach; see <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="LC-ASC-27-45_23">LC ASC 27/45, [23]</tei:ref>, December 19,
          1940.</tei:note> auffielen nun sagen werde, so möchte ich Sie bitten, dies nur als
        Bemerkung von Musiker zu Musiker zu betrachten, nicht als Werturteil u. meine Courage darin
        begründet finden, daß ich mich mit all den Dingen immer sehr seriös beschäftigte.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">1.) Wenn Sie die Ziffern 1‒12 benützen, so bezeichnen Sie damit die Folge
        die Sie in dem Skelett-Inhaltsentwurf für die Fleischwerdung des Stückes benützen. Also ein
          <tei:term> Motiv</tei:term>-Skelett im Gegensatz zu dem früheren Raum-Skelett
          (<tei:term>Stufe</tei:term>nbegriff etc) des früheren Systems. Deshalb nenne ich Ihre Art
        ein <tei:term>Motiv</tei:term>-Skelett-entwurf u. das andere, alte, einen
          Systementwurf.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Violin is
          reading Schoenberg but thinking in Schenkerian terms, seeing the "Raum-Skelett" as the
          outline of a tonal space, close to the concept of the Urlinie. (By "earlier system" he
          means that of Schenkerian theory.) We should remember, though, that Violin is trying to
          make sense of a lecture that he had heard delivered in English and to adapt its
          terminology and concepts to German terms with which he is familiar.</tei:note>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in left margin:</tei:note> nur als Behelf für
          Erklärung<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">.</tei:supplied></tei:p>

      <tei:p>2.) Ich möchte es begründen damit, daß ich keinen logischen Grund für den differenten
        Gebrauch von <tei:g type="flat"/> u. <tei:g type="sharp"/> fühlen konnte. Sie haben einen
        Weg der 12 Töne konstruirt, seine <tei:term>Umkehrung</tei:term> u.
          <tei:term>Transposition</tei:term>en. In einem Weg haben Sie einen abwärtsgehenden Weg
        z.B. mit “ges” bezeichnet, einen anderen Weg, vielleicht in der Umkehrung, aufwärtsgehend
        mit “fis” bezeichnet.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">The closest
          to this in the published version of the lecture is Example 3, the two principal themes of
          Schoenberg's <tei:title>First Chamber Symphony</tei:title> (which is not a twelve-tone
          work), from which Schoenberg extracts two underlying successions, an ascending one
          beginning on G<tei:g type="sharp"/> and a descending one beginning on A<tei:g type="flat"
          />, the choices clearly being determined tonally (E major and F minor).</tei:note> Diese
        Differenz kenne ich nur vom Zwange der Tonalität. Also von einer vertikalen Idee
        stammend.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>3.) Ein solcher Anklang an die <tei:hi rend="underline">vertikale Idee</tei:hi> schien
        mir auch Ihre Bezeichnung von <tei:term><tei:hi rend="underline"
          >Haupttönen</tei:hi></tei:term> in einem der gezeigten ausgeführten Beispiele aus Ihrem
        Werk. Nur eine verticale Idee kann mich zum Verständnis von deren sicheren Erkenntis
        bringen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> 4.) In keiner Weise kann ich Ihr Gleichnis mit den <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000924">Wagner</tei:rs>’schen <tei:term>Leitmotiv</tei:term>en
          billigen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">In the published
          text, Schoenberg retained the connection between the tone row and the leitmotive: "I
          believe that when Richard Wagner introduced his <tei:hi rend="italic">Leitmotiv</tei:hi> ‒
          for the same purpose as that for which I introduced my Basic Set ‒ he may have said: ‛Let
          there be unity.’" (p. 244).</tei:note> Da haben Sie sich <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >viel</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">zu</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">wenig</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">Ehre</tei:hi> angetan. Das <tei:term>Leitmotiv</tei:term> war weder
        eine Idee, noch ein System oder sonst was; es war nur ein einseitiges Theatertechnisches
        Hilfsmittel, nicht neu dazu (siehe das schöne Zitat im
          <tei:title>Fidelio</tei:title><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Violin may be referring to Beethoven's quotation from Florestan's aria in his opera
            <tei:title level="m">Fidelio</tei:title> in his "Leonora" Overtures 2 and 3, the latter
          being a work that attracted Schenker's attention, especially in <tei:title level="m">Der
            freie Satz</tei:title>.</tei:note>). Das Angreifbare war das mechanisierte einer Idee.
        Also: Ich warte freudigst auf das Manuscript!!!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Nun erlaube ich mir Sie verabredeterweise zu erinnern, in irgend einer
        Weise für ein <tei:foreign xml:lang="eng">Engagement</tei:foreign> für den Herbst (New
        Friends of music<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot">New Friends of
          Music, the New York organization the orchestra of which, under its conductor <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-007673">Fritz Stiedry</tei:rs>, gave the first performance of
          Schoenberg's Kammersymphonie No. 2 in New York on December 14, 1940, which performance
          Violin heard and commented on in <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="LC-ASC-27-45_23">LC
            ASC 27/45, [23]</tei:ref>, December 19, 1940.</tei:note>) für mich “fürzusprechen”. Ich
        verspreche mir unendlich viel davon. Entweder ein seltenes Klavierkonzert von <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000612">Mozart</tei:rs>. Lieber wäre mir ein Kammermusik Abend
        mit Bläsern. Z.B. <tei:title>Horn-Trio</tei:title> von <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs>, <tei:title>Trio für Clarinette, Cello u.
          Klavier</tei:title> von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs> u.
        (entweder) <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> oder <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000612">Mozart</tei:rs> Bläser Quintett mit Klavier. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000612">Mozart</tei:rs> ist das schwerere, bedeutendere u.
        seltener gespielte Quintett.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">In den nächsten Tagen werde ich hier die erste Unterredung wegen meiner
        Instituts-Idee in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002921">S. F.</tei:rs> haben. Ich glaube
        es wäre das erste dieser Art in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002510"
            ><tei:country>Amerika</tei:country></tei:rs>. Ich werde Ihnen von irgend einem Ergebnis
        berichten u. Sie können dann Stellung nehmen. Ich halte viel von der Idee u. ich glaube Sie
        müssten viel Freude daran haben.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Alles Schönste von Haus zu Haus!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr aufrichtig dankbarer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">M Violin</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address rend="indent-50">
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#MV"/><tei:placeName>San Francisco</tei:placeName>,
              <tei:date when="1941-03-29">March 29, 1941</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>Dear and revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798"
          >Friend</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Most heartfelt thanks again for the life-restoring days in Los
        Angeles!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">From your lecture<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> I gained
        my first trustworthy, authentic insight into your <tei:term>twelve-tone theory</tei:term>,
        and understood your ideas – insofar as one can venture at first hearing – with total
        clarity. I should like to formulate my inner thoughts (for myself!) if you would most kindly
        send me the manuscript with music examples.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/>
        If I may say a couple of things that occurred to me at first glance,<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> then I should like to ask you – only as a comment
        from one musician to another, not as a value judgement – to find my courage founded in the
        fact that I always concern myself very seriously with all these matters.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">1.) When you use the numbers 1 to 12, you are denoting by that the
        succession that you employ in the skeleton-content-outline for the fleshing-out of the
        piece. Thus, a <tei:term>motive</tei:term>-skeleton, in contrast to the earlier
        space-skeleton (<tei:term>scale-degree</tei:term> concept, etc.) of the earlier system.
        Therefore I call your type a "<tei:term>motive</tei:term>-skeleton-outline" and the other,
        earlier one, a "system-outline."<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in left margin:</tei:note> only as an aid to
        clarification.[end]</tei:p>

      <tei:p>2.) I should like to determine from this that I could see no logical basis for your
        different use of <tei:g type="flat"/> and <tei:g type="sharp"/>. You have constructed a
        pathway through the twelve tones, its <tei:term>inversion</tei:term> and
          <tei:term>transposition</tei:term>s. In one pathway you have a downward-leading path, e.g.
        denoted by "G<tei:g type="flat"/>", and another pathway, let's say in the inversion,
        upward-leading, denoted by "F<tei:g type="sharp"/>."<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05"
          type="footnote"/> I recognize this difference only according to the constraints of
        tonality. Thus deriving from a vertical idea.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>3.) You notation of the <tei:term><tei:hi rend="underline">principal
          tones</tei:hi></tei:term> in one of the examples that you showed, extracted from your
        work, seemed to me to be an invocation of the <tei:hi rend="underline">vertical
          idea</tei:hi>. Only a vertical idea can enable me to understand their concrete
        rationale.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> 4.) I can in no way assent to your analogy with <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000924">Wagner</tei:rs>ian <tei:term>leitmotive</tei:term>s.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> You have done yourself <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >very</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">little</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">credit</tei:hi> by that. The <tei:term>leitmotive</tei:term> was
        neither an idea nor a system or anything else; it was merely a one-sided technical
        theatrical device, and not new for that purpose (see the lovely quotation in <tei:title
          level="m">Fidelio</tei:title><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/>). What is
        open to criticism was the mechanised <tei:supplied reason="clarity">result</tei:supplied> of
        an idea. So then: I look forward most joyously to receiving the manuscript!!!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Now permit me to remind you in arranged fashion to "intercede" for me in
        some way or another for an <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="italic"
            >in English:</tei:hi></tei:note> engagement <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"
            ><tei:hi rend="italic">in German:</tei:hi></tei:note> in the fall (New Friends of
          Music<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/>). I set infinitely great store by
        that: either a rare piano concerto by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000612"
          >Mozart</tei:rs>; <tei:supplied reason="clarity">or</tei:supplied> preferable would be an
        evening of chamber music with winds, e.g. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094"
          >Brahms</tei:rs>'s <tei:title>Horn Trio</tei:title> or his <tei:title>Trio for clarinet,
          cello and piano</tei:title>, and (either) the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055"
          >Beethoven</tei:rs> or the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000612">Mozart</tei:rs>
        Quintet for winds and piano. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000612">Mozart</tei:rs> is
        the harder, the more important, and the more rarely played quintet.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">In the coming days I will have the first discussion here about my idea of
        an institute in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002921">San Francisco</tei:rs>. I believe
        it would be the first of its kind in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002510"
            ><tei:country>America</tei:country></tei:rs>. I will report to you on any outcome, and
        you can then see how you stand. I think very well of the idea, and I feel sure you will be
        delighted by what you see.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">All best wishes from my family to yours!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your sincerely grateful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">M. Violin</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
