<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2515" sdoID="LC-ASC-7-50_8">LC ASC 7/50, [8]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPas" scope="sole">Arnold Schoenberg as typist</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2020</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2020</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2020</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-07-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-007495">ViolinM ~
        ASchoenberg</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Typewritten letter (carbon copy) from Schoenberg to Moriz Violin, dated January 16,
        1940</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1940-01-16T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-08-31</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schoenberg informs Violin of a conversation he has had with [Robert Emmett]
        Stuart about a position that is open [at the St. Louis Institute of Music] for which
        Schoenberg would like to recommend him. He asks for the return of the general recommendation
        he wrote for Violin earlier.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Geburtstag; birthday; Stelle; position; Anfänger; beginners; Schüler; pupils;
        Gehalt; salary; Konzerttätigkeit; concert work; concertizing; Generalempfehlung; general
        recommendation; Pionierzeit; pioneer age</dc:subject>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000798">ASchoenberg</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#TPas"/>Mr. Moriz Violin</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>115 Divisadero Street,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
              place="foot">Schoenberg has omitted the first digit from "1115" and failed to correct
              it. See <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="LC-ASC-7-50_9">LC ASC 7/50,
              [9]</tei:ref>, January 23, 1940, concerning this error. — This is a carbon copy; the
              top, signed copy is not known to survive.</tei:note></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>San Francisco</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:date when="1940-01-16">January 16,
          1940</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Freund</tei:rs>,<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Several obvious minor typing errors in
            this letter (which may have been corrected in top copy) have here been silently
            corrected.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>ich habe so lange nichts von Ihnen gehört und ich selbst bin so beschäftigt, dass es
        für mich keine Möglichkeit giebt andere als die unabweisliche Korrespondenz zu erledigen. ‒
        Wie geht es Ihnen? Mir geht es besser seit mein (5mal 13ter) 65ter Geburtstag vorüber ist. ‒
        Haben Sie eine Verdienstmöglichkeit gefunden?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Diese Frage ist es auf die ich Antwort haben möchte. Denn es bietet sich mir jetzt ‒
        endlich ‒ vielleicht die Möglichkeit, Ihnen eine Stelle zu verschaffen.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">The position was in composition, and at
          the St. Louis Institute of Music, St. Louis, Missouri.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Lesen Sie bitte den beiliegenden Brief<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial"
          place="foot">According to Violin in <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="LC-ASC-27-45_19"
            >LC ASC 27/45, [19]</tei:ref>, February 12, 1940, Schoenberg neglected to enclose this
          letter from Robert Emmett Stuart, hence Violin wrote a letter direct to Stuart.</tei:note>
        und seien Sie nicht beleidigt, dass Ihnen da eventuell zugemutet würde, Anfänger zu
        unterrichten: ich muss das auch tun und es sind zu 2/3 Anfänger, die man lieber in Aufhörer
        verwandeln möchte.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich muss Ihnen noch sagen, was Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-007671"
            >Stua<tei:supplied reason="mistyping">r</tei:supplied>t</tei:rs> mir in
          Kansa<tei:supplied reason="mistyping">s</tei:supplied> City<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Schoenberg had met Stuart at a meeting of the Music
          Teachers' National Convention in December 1939 in Kansas City, and had received a letter
          from Stuart dated January 13, 1940 (<tei:bibl><tei:editor>Auner</tei:editor>,
              <tei:title>Schoenberg Reader</tei:title>, pp. 283‒84</tei:bibl>, where passages from
          the letter are quoted).</tei:note> mündlich gesagt hat: Er wollte eigentlich einen meiner
        Schüler. Aber da solche die in Betracht kämen augenblicklich hier sind und, vor allem, weil
        mir Ihr Fall so besonders wichtig ist, biete ich meine Vermittlung als erstem Ihnen an. Wenn
        ich recht verstanden habe, so ist der Gehalt $250 monatlich. Aber es ist möglich dass ich
        das verwechsle und es nur $200 sind. Jedenfalls kann man mit beidem, wenn auch bescheiden
        leben. Und da Sie ja doch auch mit einer Konzerttätigkeit rechnen dürfen, so ist
        Nebenverdienst auch möglich.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wenn Sie Lust haben, dass ich Sie hiefür vorschlage, so bitte ich Sie, mir diese
        "Generalempfehlung" zu senden die ich Ihnen seinerzeit geschrieben habe.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">= <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-70-35_6">OJ 70/35, [6]</tei:ref>, July 21, 1939.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Auf alle Fälle, bitte, antworten Sie sofort.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Und, senden Sie das beiliegende Material umgehend an mich zurück.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich bitte Sie nicht definitiv auf eine günstige Entscheidung zu rechnen und jedenfalls
        vorher nichts aufzugeben. Sie sind ja wohl, so wie ich, von Europa her gewitzigt genug, um
        das selbst zu wissen. Aber hier ist es in dieser Hinsicht noch schlimmer. Es sind <tei:pb
          n="2"/> hier eben noch immer Zustände aus der Pionierzeit, wo der Verlust einer Stellung
        kaum mehr bedeutete, als den Verlust einer <tei:foreign xml:lang="eng">Chance</tei:foreign>
        unter tausenden. Für uns leider ist das etwas härter worden.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich wünsche sehnlichst, dass Sie das nicht brauchen, oder es bekommen. Ich bin sehr
        gespannt auf Ihre Antwort.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Viele herzlichste Grüsse von uns Allen,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">Ihr</tei:salute><tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">unsigned</tei:note>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#TPas"/>Mr. Moriz Violin</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>115 Divisadero Street<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"
            /></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>San Francisco</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:date when="1940-01-16">January 16,
          1940</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Friend</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>It is so long since I heard anything from you, and I myself am so busy that it is
        impossible for me to deal with anything other than the most demanding correspondence. — How
        are things with you? Things are better with me now that my (5 x 13th) 65th birthday is
        behind me. – Have you found any means of making a living?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>This is the question to which I should like to have an answer. For the possibility has
        perhaps presented itself to me – at long last – of procuring a position for you.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Please read the enclosed letter,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> and do
        not take offense that you might be required to teach beginners: I myself have to do that,
        too, and it is to 2/3 beginners that one might prefer to transform into listeners.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I must tell you what Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-007671">Stuart</tei:rs> said
        to me in person in Kansas City<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/>: what he
        really wanted was one of my pupils. But since those who might come into consideration are
          <tei:supplied reason="clarity">not?</tei:supplied> here at the moment, and above all
        because your case is so particularly important to me, I give you first refusal of my
        mediation. If I have rightly understood, the salary is $250 a month; but I may have got
        confused and it may be only $200. In any case, one can live with either, albeit modestly.
        And since you should certainly be able also to reckon with concert work as well,
        supplementary earnings are possible.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>If you wish me to propose you for this, then please send me the "general
        recommendation" that I wrote for you some time ago.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06"
          type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>At all events, please reply immediately.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>And send me the enclosed material back by return.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Please don't set too much store by a favorable outcome, and in any case don't give up
        on anything <tei:supplied reason="clarity">else</tei:supplied> before then. Like me, I'm
        sure, coming from Europe you are wise enough to know that yourself. But in this respect it
        is even tougher here. Here <tei:pb n="2"/> there are still, even now, always conditions from
        the pioneer age where the loss of a job means scarcely more than the loss of one chance in a
        thousand. For us, that has unfortunately become still harder.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I ardently do not wish this upon you. I am very anxious to have your reply.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Most cordial greetings from us all,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">Your</tei:salute><tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">unsigned</tei:note>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
