<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2497" sdoID="LC-ASC-7-50_1">LC ASC 7/50, [1]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPas" scope="sole">Arnold Schoenberg as typist</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2020</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2020</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2020</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-07-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-007495">ViolinM ~
        ASchoenberg</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Typewritten letter (carbon copy) from Schoenberg to Moriz Violin, dated May 2,
        1938</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1938-05-02T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-08-21</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schoenberg reflects on his own relationship with Heinrich Schenker. — He is
        willing to write a recommendation to Hertz for Violin and asks to whom to send it, and warns
        Violin that it will not be easy to establish himself in San Francisco.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Zusammenhang; relationship; Situation; Einfluss; influence; Empfehlung; letter of
        recommendation; Kopie; copy; Brief; letter; Geld; money; Arbeitsnot; unemployment; geistig;
        intellectual; Aussichten; prospects</dc:subject>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000798">ASchoenberg</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#TPas"/>Herrn M. Violin</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>IX. Liechtensteinstrasse 20/13</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Wien.</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:date when="1938-05-02">2. May,
          1938</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Freund</tei:rs>,<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Typing errors have been reproduced;
            they would most likely have been corrected by hand in the final copy (the whereabouts of
            which is unknown).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">ich habe oft an Sie gedacht, nicht <tei:sic>bloss</tei:sic> in diesen
        letzten Monaten, sondern meist im Zusammenhang mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
          >Heinrich Schenker</tei:rs>, den ich ja über alle Differenzen hinweg, hochschätzte. Es
          <tei:supplied reason="clarity">ist</tei:supplied> traurig in welche Situation wir geraten
        sind und ich muss nicht besonders erwähnen, wie sehr ich darunter leide.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich will selbstverständlich alles tun, was in meiner leider sehr geringen
        Macht steht. Aber ich kann nicht unerwähnt lassen, dass ich bereits eine Liste von etwa 15
        menschlich und künstlerisch hochstehenden Freunden und Bekannten habe, die alle meinen
        Einfluss überschätzen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Da Sie mir nicht schreiben, ob ich die Empfehlung für <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-007664">Herz</tei:rs> an Sie oder an ihn senden soll, so tue ich
        beides, d.h. ich sende Ihnen eine Kopie meines Briefes an ihn.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Wenn Sie Geld <tei:sic>genung</tei:sic> haben, um einige Zeit (das wäre
        allerdings unter Umständen vielleicht ein Jahr) hier aushalten zu können, so müsste sich
        wohl für Sie etwas finden lassen. Ein Mann Ihres Könnens und Wissens würde nicht lange
        unbenützt bleiben. Aber leicht ist es nicht, denn hier herrscht grosse Arbeitsnot und
        geistige Arbeiter sind, wie überall, darin am ungünstigsten.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Haben Sie nicht einmal auch an Südamerika und Mexico gedacht? Man
        versichert mir, dass es dort viel bessere Aussichten geben soll.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Lassen Sie mich, bitte, hören, was Sie zu tun gedenken. Ich bin immer zu
        Ihrer Verfügung.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">mit vielen herzlichsten Grüssen, Ihr</tei:salute><tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">unsigned</tei:note>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#TPas"/>Mr. M. Violin</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Vienna IX</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Liechtensteinstrasse 20/13</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-58"><tei:date when="1938-05-02">May 2,
          1938</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Friend</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">I have often thought of you, not merely during these past months but most
        of all in connection with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich
          Schenker</tei:rs> whom, in spite of all our differences, I valued highly. It is sad that
        we have ended up in such a situation; I should not mention especially how I am suffering as
        a result of it.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I shall of course do everything that is within my very limited power. But
        I cannot leave unmentioned the fact that I already have a list of about fifteen friends and
        acquaintances who, humanly and artistically, are of high standing and who all overestimate
        my influence.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Since you do not tell me whether I should send the testimonial for <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-007664">Hertz</tei:rs> to you or to him, I shall do both; that
        is, I shall send you a copy of my letter to him.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">You should have enough money to survive here for some time (that would, at
        any rate, be perhaps a year), when something will probably turn up for you. A man of your
        ability and knowledge would not remain unneeded for long. But it will not be easy, for there
        is a great deal of unemployment here, and intellectual workers are – as everywhere – the
        most unfavorably placed.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Have you thought at all about South America or Mexico. People assure me
        that there the prospects are much better.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Please let me know what you are planning to do. I am always at your
        service.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">With most cordial greetings, Your</tei:salute><tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">unsigned</tei:note>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
