<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2525" sdoID="LC-ASC-27-45_21">LC ASC 27/45, [21]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="MV" scope="sole">Moriz Violin's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2020</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2020</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2020</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-07-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-007495">ViolinM ~
        ASchoenberg</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Moriz Violin to Schoenberg, dated June 8, 1940</dc:title>
      <dcterms:created>1940-06-08T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-09-03</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Violin asks Schoenberg to write to Elizabeth Sprague Coolidge recommending him
        to play with the Coolidge Quartet. </dc:description>
      <dc:subject>idiotisch; idiotic; Hilflosigkeit; helplessness; Kaliber; caliber; Aufforderung;
        invitation; Öffentlichkeit; public; Kammermusik; chamber music; spielen; play; Evolution;
        Revolution</dc:subject>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000798">ASchoenberg</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address rend="indent-50">
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#MV"/><tei:placeName>S. F.</tei:placeName>
            <tei:date when="1940-06-08">8 Juni 40</tei:date>.</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>1703 Scott Street</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>Lieber u. verehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798"
            >Freund</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">No reply to
              <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="LC-ASC-7-50_13">LC ASC 7/50, [13]</tei:ref>, May
            19, 1940 seems to survive. There are passages in this letter in which it is hard to see
            the underlying sense. The translator makes no claim to have read Violin's mind
            accurately.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Wenn Sie mit Folgendem den idiotischesten Brief erhalten, der je in Ihre
        Hände kam, so ist es zum größten Teil nicht meine Schuld. Heute schreibt Ihnen nur meine
        commandierte Hilflosigkeit! D.h. die <tei:hi rend="underline">guten</tei:hi> Freunde kommen
        immer auf Ideen (?) u. wenn man die Letzteren verwirft, so kommen die Vorwürfe über
        Lebensfremdheit, falsche Einstellung u.s.w. Dummheit u. Gedankenlosigkeit muss sich die
        Schädeln einrennen. Heute soll ich meinen Schädel auf Commando einrennen.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">"sich den Schädel einrennen" can mean
          "to run (<tei:hi rend="italic">or</tei:hi> dash) one's head against a wall." That usage
          may have been in Violin's thoughts as he wrote this.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Also: Da ist ein Coolidge Streich-Quartett.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Coolidge Quartet: string quartet resident at the Coolidge
          Auditorium in the Library of Congress, Washington. It was in existence from c.1936 to
          1943, its initial members William Kroll and Nicolai Berezowsky (vln), Nicholas Moldavan
          (vla), Victor Gottlieb (vcl). In addition to standard repertory, it played 20th-century
          works, including commissions by the Coolidge Foundation. (<tei:title level="m">Grove Music
            Online</tei:title>, Elizabeth Osatrow, revd Christina Taylor Gibson).</tei:note> Es
        erhält sich durch eine Mrs. Coolidge. Man behauptet ein Mann Ihres Kalibers muss diese Frau
          kennen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Schoenberg was well
          acquainted with Elizabeth Sprague Coolidge, since she had commissioned his Third and
          Fourth String Quartets. There is substantial correspondence from Schoenberg to Mrs.
          Coolidge 1936–41, and contact extends back to at least 1927, but there is no sign of a
          letter concerning Moriz Violin.</tei:note> Und wenn dies nicht der Fall ist, so wären Sie
        trotzdem im Stande ihr zu schreiben, daß in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002921">S.
          F.</tei:rs> jemand lebt, der Gelegenheit bekommen müsste durch Aufforderung mit dem
        Quartett zu spielen, der aufgeregter amerikanischen Öffentlichkeit zu <tei:pb n="2"/>
        beweisen, wie interessant man Kammermusik spielen kann. Der “Jemand” wäre ich.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich gebe zu, daß ich es ganz fein kann, aber ich bezweifle daß Sie das tun
        können. Gewiß verspreche ich mir was von einer Gelegenheit, die ich persönlich nicht
        erreichen kann. Hier ist ein Competitor Spieler, der überall hineinkommt, wenn auch ohne
        Erfolg. Ich bin eben nicht „geschickt"!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Bitte wenn Sie <tei:hi rend="underline">nichts</tei:hi> machen können,
        verwüsten Sie nicht Ihre Zeit u. antworten Sie mir gar nicht. Ich weiß <tei:foreign
          xml:lang="lat">a priori</tei:foreign> alles was Sie mir dann sagen müssten.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Die “Freunde” halten es für eine <tei:hi rend="underline">großartige</tei:hi>
        Idee!!!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="3"/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">written sideways:</tei:note> Wenn ich aber, mit
        Umgehung dieses Briefthemas, <tei:foreign xml:lang="eng">in spite of</tei:foreign>, über Ihr
        u. Ihrer l. Familie Wohlergehen einmal was hören würde, könnten Sie sich keinen dankbareren
        Empfänger vorstellen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich glaube nur an Evolution u. nicht an Revolution. Letztere ist nur das
        mehr weniger retardierende oder fördernde Handlangermittel der ersteren. Soweit ich nicht
        über das Schmerzliche der Grausamkeit kommen kann, bin ich durch nichts anderes gehindert
        absolut desinteressiert an dem heutigen „Weltgeschehen“ zu sein!</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Herzlichst Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">jüngster Idiot</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">M Violin</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address rend="indent-50">
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#MV"/><tei:placeName>San Francisco</tei:placeName>,
              <tei:date when="1940-06-08">June 8, 1940</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>1703 Scott Street</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>Dear and revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798"
            >Friend</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">If, with what follows, you receive the most idiotic letter that ever came
        your way, then it is for the most part not my fault. Today it is only my obligatory
        helplessness that is writing. That is, <tei:hi rend="underline">good</tei:hi> friends come
        up constantly with ideas (?), and when I reject the last of these, back come the reproaches
        for being out of touch with reality, and having a wrong attitude to life, etc. Stupidity and
        thoughtlessness inevitably come flooding into my skull. Today I can only let my skull take
          command.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>However: there is a Coolidge String Quartet.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
          type="footnote"/> It is supported by a Mrs. Coolidge. People assert that a man of your
        caliber is bound to be acquainted with this lady.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
          type="footnote"/> And if this is not the case, then you would nevertheless be in a
        position to write to her that there is someone living in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002921">San Francisco</tei:rs> who ought to have the opportunity to play by
        invitation with the Quartet, to demonstrate to the excited American public <tei:pb n="2"/>
        how interestingly chamber music can be played. That "someone" is me.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I agree that I am well up to the task, but I doubt that you would be able
        to do it. Certainly I expect something from an opportunity that I cannot attain on my own.
        Here is a competitor performer who crops up all over the place, albeit without success. I am
        just not "skilled"!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">If there is <tei:hi rend="underline">nothing</tei:hi> you can do, please
        don't squander your time – don't answer me at all. I know <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat"
            ><tei:hi rend="italic">a priori</tei:hi></tei:foreign> all that you would have to say to
        me.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>The "friends" think it a <tei:hi rend="underline">splendid</tei:hi> idea!!!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="3"/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">written sideways:</tei:note> But if – setting
        aside the topic of this letter, <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi
            rend="italic">in English:</tei:hi></tei:note> in spite of, – <tei:note type="editorial"
          place="inline"><tei:hi rend="italic">in German:</tei:hi></tei:note> I were to hear
        something about the well-being of yourself and your dear family, you could not imagine a
        more grateful recipient.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I believe only in evolution, not in revolution. The latter is only the
        more-or-less retarding or advancing stooge of the former. So long as I cannot overcome the
        agony of cruelty, I am hindered by nothing else, totally disinterested in being today's
        "world phenomenon"!</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Most cordially your </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">youngest idiot,</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">M. Violin</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
