<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2511" sdoID="LC-ASC-7-50_4">LC ASC 7/50, [4]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPas" scope="sole">Arnold Schoenberg as typist</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2020</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2020</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2020</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-07-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-007495">ViolinM ~
        ASchoenberg</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Typewritten letter (carbon copy) from Schoenberg to Moriz Violin, dated June 6,
        1939</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1939-06-06T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-08-25</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schoenberg writes to Violin in New York, advises him on the trip to San
        Francisco via Los Angeles, and hopes to be able to accommodate him/them in Los Angeles. — He
        regrets his powerlessness [over the affidavit].</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Mehrkosten; additional costs; Weg; route; Bahn; train station; Machtlosigkeit;
        powerlessness </dc:subject>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000798">ASchoenberg</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#TPas"/>Herrn Moriz Violin</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>care of Dr. Edith Liebling</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>684 Park Place,</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Brooklyn, New York</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:date when="1939-06-06">6. Juni,
          1939</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Freund</tei:rs>,<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Some typing errors have been
            reproduced, others silently corrected. They would most likely have been corrected by
            hand in the final, signed copy, the whereabouts of which is
          unknown.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>ich bin froh zu erfahren, dass Sie nun endlich doch hier sind. Ihr Brief kam erst heute
        frueh, aber ich sende diesen Luftpost und bin sicher, dass Sie ihn noch rec<tei:supplied
          reason="mistyping">h</tei:supplied>tzeitig bekommen. Ich kann in der Eile noch nicht
        vorschlagen, wo Sie wohnen sollen, aber es wird sich schon finden in der
        Zwischenzeit.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Das ist mir eine grosse Freude, dass Sie über Los Angeles fahren wollen. Ich freue mich
        sehr Sie wieder zu sehen und ich muss hören, wie es Ihnen gegangen ist. Sie müssen ja
        Furchtbares mitgemacht haben.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wenn ich nicht irre, so verursacht die Reise über Los Angeles <tei:hi rend="sperr"
          >keine</tei:hi> Mehrkosten. Ich glaube, man darf sowohl den einen, als auch den anderen
        Weg für denselben Betrag gehen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wenn es Ihnen möglich ist uns rechtzeitig zu verständigen, so möchten wir Sie gerne von
        der Bahn abholen. Schreiben Sie jedenfalls Luftpost, was allerdings auch etwa 36 Stunden
        beansprucht.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich freue mich ausserordentlich Sie wiederzusehen und ich finde, es ist wahrhaftig ein
        grosses Glück, in allem Unglück, dass das schliesslich doch möglich worden ist. Ich bin sehr
        traurig, dass nicht ich derjenige sein sollte, der Ihnen helfen konnte und ich war über
        meine Machtlosigkeit,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Schoenberg
          had worked for several weeks to obtain an affidavit for Violin's emigration, but
          ultimately Violin obtained one from another source: see <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="LC-ASC-27-45_6">LC ASC 27/45, [6]</tei:ref>, January 17, 1939 and <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="LC-ASC-7-50_3">LC ASC 7/50, [3]</tei:ref>, March 2,
          1939.</tei:note> die sich in so vielen Fällen bewi<tei:supplied reason="mistyping"
          >e</tei:supplied>sen hat, nie mehr deprimiert, als eben jetzt. Aber die Hauptsache ist
        doch, dass Sie nun da sind – vielleicht habe ich mit anderen derzeit noch sehr Unglücklichen,
        besseren Erfolg.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Also: auf Wiedersehen in wenigen Tagen. Viele Grüsse, auch an Ihre <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000914">Frau</tei:rs> und auch von meiner <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-007657">Frau</tei:rs>, die mir eben sagt, sie hat doch eine Idee, wie sie es
        arrangiren kann, dass Sie bei uns wohnen. Ich hoffe zuversichtlich, dass das möglich sein
        wird. Falls es aber doch nicht geht, dann bitte nehmen Sie mit unserem guten Willen
        vorlieb.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Ihr</tei:salute><tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">unsigned</tei:note>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#TPas"/>Mr. Moriz Violin</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>c/o Dr. Edith Liebling</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>684 Park Place</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Brooklyn, New York</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:date when="1939-06-06">June 6,
          1939</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Friend</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>I am glad to hear that you are finally here now. Your letter did not arrive until early
        today, but I am sending this airmail and am sure that you will receive it in good time. I
        cannot yet, in haste, advise you where to live; something will turn up in the
        meantime.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>It is a great pleasure for me that you would like to travel via Los Angeles. I look
        forward to seeing you again, and I must hear how things have gone for you. You must have
        experienced frightful things indeed.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>If I am not mistaken, the trip via Los Angeles does not incur <tei:hi rend="italic"
          >any</tei:hi> additional costs. I believe that one can take one route or the other for the
        same price.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>If it is possible for us to come to an understanding in good time, we would gladly
        collect you from the train station. Write to me in any event by airmail, which at any rate
        requires about thirty-six hours.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I am exceedingly looking forward to seeing you again and think that it is a great
        fortune, amid all misfortune, that this has finally become possible. I am very sad not to
        have been the one who was able to help you, and I have never been more depressed about my
          powerlessness,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> which has been demonstrated
        in so many cases, as in the present matter. But the main thing is that you are now here –
        perhaps I shall have greater success with others who are at present still very
        unfortunate.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>And so: till we see each other in a few days. Many greetings, also to your <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000914">wife</tei:rs>, and also from my <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-007657">wife</tei:rs>, who this moment is saying that she has an idea as to
        how she could arrange for you to stay with us. I am confidently hopeful that this will be
        possible. But if it does not work out, then please make do with our goodwill.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Your</tei:salute><tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">unsigned</tei:note>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
