<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2519" sdoID="LC-ASC-27-45_18">LC ASC 27/45, [18]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="MV" scope="sole">Moriz Violin's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2020</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2020</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2020</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-07-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-007495">ViolinM ~
        ASchoenberg</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Moriz Violin to Schoenberg, dated January 29,
        1940</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1940-01-29T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-09-01</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Violin expresses pain that his wife has to do menial work to support them
        both. He prefers not to apply for the St. Louis job because he feels Schoenberg was insulted
        by Stuart's letter. He hopes to gain entrée to the performance world.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Enttäuschung; disappointment; Chance; opportunity; climatisch; climatic;
        Experiment; Schmerz; pain; Abortputzen; cleaning toilets; dishes waschen; to wash dishes;
        Absage; rejection; insult; empfehlen; to recommend; acceptieren; to accept; Rat; advice;
        Schüler; pupils; Prospekt; prospectus; Lehprogramm; syllabus; Öffentlichkeit; public realm;
        world of performance; Kammermusik; chamber music </dc:subject>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000798">ASchoenberg</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address rend="indent-50">
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#MV"/><tei:placeName>S. F.</tei:placeName>
            <tei:date when="1940-01-29">29. Jänner 40</tei:date>.</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>Lieber u. verehrtester <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798"
          >Freund</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich glaube unsere Briefe<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
          place="foot">i. e. <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="LC-ASC-27-45_17">LC ASC 27/45,
            [17]</tei:ref> (from Violin), January 26, and <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="LC-ASC-7-50_10">LC ASC 7/50, [10]</tei:ref> (from Schoenberg), January 27, 1940.
        </tei:note> haben sich exact gekreuzt. Ich glaube Enttäuschung ist unser einziges
        Nahrungsmittel. Anstatt Hoffnung, die man ohne Unbescheidenheit hegte, stellt sich ein
        billiger Aberglaube ein, der einem zuflüstert: „wer weiß wozu etwas gut ist“. Und so werden
        Sie verstehen, nachdem ich absolut glücklich war eine Chance zu finden, die mir ein Leben
        ermöglicht hätte, ich mit Verlust dieser Chance den einen Grund verstärkt fühle, einem
        climatischen Experiment entronnen zu sein.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Reference may be to Violin's having turned down the opportunity for work in
          New York City on grounds of the climate (see <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="LC-ASC-27-45_17">LC ASC 27/45, [17]</tei:ref>, January 26, 1940), or to his having
          decided not to submit an application to the St. Louis Institute of Music, where the
          climate would have been more extreme than that in San Francisco. We know the latter from a
          letter from Stuart to Schoenberg of February 7, 1940, in which Stuart states: "As yet we
          have heard nothing from Mr. Violin. From your letters we understood that you had notified
          him to communicate with us." (<tei:ref type="external"
            target="https://www.schoenberg.at/scans/DVD104/15550.jpg"
          >ASI-Stuart</tei:ref>)</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Es ist mir keine Schande vom Verdienst meiner <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000914"
          >Frau</tei:rs> leben zu müssen, dafür aber ein besonders großer Schmerz, weil sie nicht
        jung genug für ihre tapfere Arbeit ist u. weil das auch kein Ding einer Zukunft darstellt.
        Ich würde selbst bereit sein vom Abortputzen bis zum <tei:foreign xml:lang="eng"
          >dishes</tei:foreign> waschen jede Arbeit anzunehmen, aber <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >dafür</tei:hi> finde ich noch weniger Gehör u. nicht die geringste Möglichkeit.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Apparently, Valerie Violin did cleaning
          for wealthy households in the area.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">In einem Punkt Ihres lieben Briefes bin ich anderer Meinung<tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">.</tei:supplied> Ich möchte den angedeuteten Versuch nicht
          machen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Schoenberg suggested in
            <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="LC-ASC-7-50_10">LC ASC 7/50, [10]</tei:ref> that
          Violin would have nothing to lose in writing direct to Robert Stuart ("It's worth the
          attempt anyway").</tei:note> Nicht aus einem unangebrachten falschen Stolz heraus. Ich
        halte es nur für nutzlos. Denn sehen Sie, <tei:hi rend="underline">ich</tei:hi> fühlte mich
        von der Absage nicht betroffen, aber ich fühlte in ihr ein „<tei:foreign xml:lang="eng"
          >insult against you</tei:foreign>“. Sie werden mir recht geben, wenn Sie den letzten Satz
        des Briefes<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Not Schoenberg's
          letter, but a letter that he forwarded to Violin and that the latter presumably returned.
          No letter from Stuart to Schoenberg now in the Library of Congress contains these or
          similar words.</tei:note> noch einmal durchlesen, worin Ihnen der „Dean of the school“
        schreibt: „Seien Sie sicher daß jeder den Sie empfehlen werden von uns acceptiert wird.“
        Wenn nun gleich beim ersten Versuch <tei:pb n="2"/> es möglich war, daß durch Einfluß von
        Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000271">Galstone</tei:rs> recte Galizenstein, Ihr Rat
        in den Wind geschlagen wird, so heiße ich das Schindluder mit Ihrer Autorität treiben. Bei
        einem Ihrer Schüler wird denn plötzlich die Nase nicht passen! Wenn Sie die Paragraphen
        lesen werden, was ich in Klavier hätte unterrichten müssen, so waren es Dinge, die für uns
        Inbegriff der Kunst sind. Ich kenne Herrn <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000271"
          >Galston</tei:rs> aus Wien, (er war nach <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000523"
          >Leschetizky</tei:rs> bei <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000116">Busoni</tei:rs> sehr
        attachierter Schüler u. wunderlicher Weise, laut Prospekt, „<tei:foreign xml:lang="eng"
          >friend of</tei:foreign>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000116">Busoni</tei:rs><tei:supplied reason="punctuation"
          >“</tei:supplied>) u. kann mir vorstellen daß er bei dem mir vorgeschriebenen Lehrprogramm
        erst recht Konkurrenz fürchtet.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich werde u. will nicht verzweifeln u. hoffe doch noch einen Schleichweg
        in die Öffentlichkeit zu finden u. hoffentlich weiter Ihre sorgende Güte erwarten <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">zu</tei:add> dürfen? Wenn ich nur Kammermusik spielen könnte!
        Ich glaube ich mache das in einer Art, die für mich erfolgreich sein könnte.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ihr liebes, liebes Haus grüße ich innigst u. würde viel Lebenshoffnung
        gewinnen, könnte ich in einem Gespräch mit Ihnen mich von meiner Faulenzerei
        erholen.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent=40">Getreuest Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">dankbarster</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">M Violin</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address rend="indent-50">
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#MV"/><tei:placeName>San Francisco</tei:placeName>,
              <tei:date when="1940-01-29">January 29, 1940</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>Dear and most revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798"
          >Friend</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">I think our letters<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> have
        exactly crossed in the post. I believe disappointment is our sole source of nourishment. In
        place of hope, which one entertained without immodesty, a cheap delusion has taken hold,
        whispering in one's ear: "Who knows what anything is good for." Thus you will understand,
        since I was incredibly lucky to find an opportunity that would have enabled me to have a
        life, with the loss of this opportunity I feel that the sole reason for having escaped a
        climatic experiment is strengthened.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>It is no shame for me to have to live off my <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000914"
          >wife</tei:rs>'s earnings, but it is especially painful that she is no youngster when it
        comes to the valiant work she does, and also because it offers nothing for the future. I
        would be prepared to take over any job, from cleaning toilets to washing dishes, but I find
        even less calling and not the slightest possibility <tei:hi rend="underline">for
          that</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">On one point in your kind letter I take a different view. I would prefer
        not to make the attempt that you suggest<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> –
        not out of misplaced false pride <tei:supplied reason="clarity">but because</tei:supplied> I
        consider it futile. You see, <tei:hi rend="underline">I myself</tei:hi> wasn't dismayed by
        being turned down, but I felt it was an <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi
            rend="italic">in English:</tei:hi></tei:note> "insult against you." <tei:note
          type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="italic">in German:</tei:hi></tei:note> You
        will see I am right if you will read once again the final sentence of the letter,<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> in which the "Dean of the School" writes to you:
        "Be assured that anyone whom you recommend will be accepted by us." If it was possible at
        the very first attempt <tei:pb n="2"/> for your advice to be thrown to the winds through the
        influence of Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000271">Galstone</tei:rs> (real name
        "Galizenstein"), then I call that playing fast and loose with your authority. With one of
        your pupils suddenly his face won't fit!" If you will read the paragraphs stating what I
        would have had to teach in piano, they were things that for us are the embodiment of the
        art. I know Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000271">Galston</tei:rs> from Vienna,
        (after <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000523">Leschetizky</tei:rs> he was a very devoted
        pupil of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000116">Busoni</tei:rs>, and lo and behold!
        according to the prospectus: "friend of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000116"
          >Busoni</tei:rs>"), and I can well imagine that with the teaching program I provided he
        would fear competition all the more.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I will not despair, and will continue to seek entrée into the public
        domain, and, let us hope, to have to turn <tei:add place="interlinear-above">to</tei:add>
        you again for your good offices. If only I could play chamber music! I believe that I do
        that in a way that could bring success for me.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I send most sincere greetings to your dear, dear family, and would regain
        much of my zest for life if only I could drag myself out of my indolence in a conversation
        with you.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent=40">Most loyally, your</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">most grateful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">M. Violin</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
