<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2512" sdoID="LC-ASC-7-50_6">LC ASC 7/50, [6]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPas" scope="sole">Arnold Schoenberg as typist</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2020</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2020</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2020</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-07-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-007495">ViolinM ~
        ASchoenberg</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Typewritten letter (carbon copy) from Schoenberg to Moriz Violin, dated July 21,
        1939</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1939-07-21T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-08-26</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schoenberg has written a letter of introduction and modified Violin's draft
        c.v., explains how he has done the latter, and advises Violin what to do with the materials.
        — He asks advice on how to get the best exchange rate for Mark/Dollar.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>geisting; intellectual; Reproduzierende; performer; Produzierende; creative
        artist; Talent; Einführungsbrief; letter of introduction; apppointment; Lebenslauf;
        curriculum vitae; Transparentpapier; graph paper; Blueprint; Kopie; copy; Beziehungen;
        connections; Jude; jew; Geld; money; Schulden; debts; Delogierung; eviction</dc:subject>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000798">ASchoenberg</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:date when="1939-07-21">21, Juli,
          1939</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Freund</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">lassen Sie mich zuerst Ihnen sagen, dass ich es sehr bedaure, Sie an
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002921">San Francisco</tei:rs> abgeben zu müssen. Sie
        glauben gar nicht, wie wohl es einem tut, nach langen Pausen über geistige Angelegenheiten
        in geistiger Form zu sprechen. Die besseren Menschen, mit denen ich hier zusammenkomme, sind
          Reproduzierende,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >"Reproduzierende": i.e. performers, those who "reproduce" the creative work of others, as
          apart from the "Schaffende", the creative artists (as in Schoenberg's Vereinigung
          schaffender Tonkünstler, Society for Creative Musicians, 1904–05).</tei:note> die
        Produzierenden machen, sofern sie Talent haben, jede denkbare Konzession oder sind bereits
        so geboren, wie es die weitgehendsten Ansprüche nicht besser wünschen könnten.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Es ist ja doch eine Wüste.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich habe lange gebraucht, bis ich die Form für die Einführungsbriefe
        gefunden hatte. Ich sende Ihnen vier und wenn ich ihn rechtzeitig fertig bekomme, werde ich
        noch einen fünften, an Dr. Jellinek<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Not the Austrian composer Hanns Jelinek (1901‒69), who remained and died in
          Austria. This "Jellinek" was previously listed in <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="LC-ASC-27-45_12">LC ASC 27/45, [12]</tei:ref>, July 20, 1939.</tei:note> beilegen:
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-007498">Franckenstein</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-007666">Deutsch</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-007665"
          >Elkus</tei:rs>, Rheinhardt. Lesen Sie sie, denn ich habe in jedem den Punkt erwähnt, der
        am meisten Aussicht bietet. Ob Sie die Briefe persönlich übergeben sollen, nach
        telephonischer Anfrage oder per Post, kann ich schwer entscheiden. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-007664">Hertz</tei:rs> wird das besser wissen. Aber erscheint mir am besten,
        wenn Sie zuerst telephonieren und unter Berufung auf "<tei:foreign xml:lang="eng">a personal
          letter of introduction to you from Mr. Arnold Schoenberg</tei:foreign>" um ein
          <tei:foreign xml:lang="eng">appointment</tei:foreign> ersuchen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Diese "Generalempfehlung" (verzeihen Sie den harten Ausdruck) habe ich auf
        Transparentpapier geschrieben. Sie können in jedem Blueprint Geschäft davon <tei:foreign
          xml:lang="eng"><tei:hi rend="underline">Blueprints, black on white</tei:hi></tei:foreign>
        für 5‒7 cents die Kopie machen lassen. Das leere Blatt kann abgetrennt werden; es dient nur
        als Schutzblatt.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich habe ihren Lebenslauf auf das Hier-Wirksame reduziert <tei:choice>
          <tei:sic>uns</tei:sic>
          <tei:corr>und</tei:corr>
        </tei:choice> habe das ein bischen dramatisiert.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot">= <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-70-35_6">OJ 70/35,
            [6]</tei:ref>, July 21, 1939.</tei:note> Ich glaube, ohne direkt geschmacklos zu sein,
        ist es für <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002510"
          ><tei:country>Amerika</tei:country></tei:rs> sehr geeignet.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich wünsche sehr, dass die Briefe Ihnen nützlich sein mögen. Es wurde mir
        gesagt dass <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-007665">Elkus</tei:rs>, der wie <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-007666">Deutsch</tei:rs> und <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-007498">Franckenstein</tei:rs>, Jude ist, sehr einflussreiche Beziehungen in
        reichen Kreisen hat und vielleicht viel helfen könnte, insbesondere, wenn er sich mit
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-007666">Deutsch</tei:rs> berät ‒ ich habe ja auf das in
        meinem Brief angespielt.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Nun habe ich auch eine Bitte an Sie:</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich habe gestern schon wieder einen jener Briefe von meinem Sohn bekommen
        in denen er Geld von mir verlangt. Ich möchte ihm durch <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-000786">Schirmer</tei:rs> etwas senden lassen. Da Sie mir aber sagten, dass
        man einen weit besseren, als den offiziellen Dollarkurs bekommen kann, würde ich gerne davon
        Gebrauch machen und bitte Sie mir zu sagen, wie ich das tun kann. Mein Sohn schreibt er hat
        500 Mark Schulden und is<tei:supplied reason="mistyping">t</tei:supplied> mit Delogierung
        bedroht. Ich kann <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-000786">Schirmer</tei:rs> um nicht
        mehr, als 50$ ersuchen und möchte doch soviel als möglich damit ausrichten.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Lassen Sie bald von sich hören und grüssen Sie unbekannterweise<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">"unbekannterweise": this seems to
          confirm what was hinted in the postscript to <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="LC-ASC-27-45_11">LC ASC 27/45, [11]</tei:ref>, July 19, 1939, namely that, when
          Violin stayed at the Schoenbergs' house, his wife was not with him, illogical as that may
          seem.</tei:note> Ihre <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000914">Frau</tei:rs> von uns
        allen.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Viele herzlichste Grüsse, Ihr</tei:salute><tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">unsigned</tei:note>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:date when="1939-07-21">July 21,
          1939</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Friend</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Let me tell you first that I am very sorry to have had to abandon you to
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002921">San Francisco</tei:rs>. You cannot imagine how
        much good it does one, after a long hiatus, to speak about intellectual matters in an
        intellectual form. The better persons with whom I associate here are of the reproducing
          sort,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> who create producing persons,
        insofar as they have talent, every imaginable privilege; or they have already been born in a
        way that the most far-reaching demands could have not wished better.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">It is actually a desert here.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">It has taken a long time for me to find a suitable form for your letters
        of introduction. I am sending you four, and if I receive it promptly I shall enclose a fifth
        one for Dr. Jellinek:<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-007498">Frankenstein</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-007666">Deutsch</tei:rs>, Elkus, Rheinhardt. Read them, for in each I have
        mentioned the point that will offer the best prospects. Whether you ought to hand over the
        letters personally, after having made a telephone enquiry, or send them by post, is
        something I would have difficulty in deciding. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-007664"
          >Hertz</tei:rs> will know better what to do. But it seems to me best to telephone first
        and to seek an appointment with reference to <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"
            ><tei:hi rend="italic">in English:</tei:hi></tei:note> "a personal letter of
        introduction to you from Mr. Arnold Schoenberg."</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="italic">in
            German:</tei:hi></tei:note> This "generic recommendation" (pardon the crude expression)
        I have written on tracing paper. In any blueprint shop, you can have <tei:note
          type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="italic">in English:</tei:hi></tei:note>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">blueprints black on white</tei:hi>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="italic">in
          German:</tei:hi></tei:note> made from it for 5 to 7 cents per copy. The empty leaf can be
        removed; it serves only as a protective cover.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I reduced your curriculum vitae to what will be effective in the here and
        now, and have dramatized it a bit.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> I believe
        that, without being downright tasteless, it is very appropriate for <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002510"><tei:country>America</tei:country></tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I very much wish that these letters may be useful for you. I was told that
        Elkus, who like <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-007666">Deutsch</tei:rs> and <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-007498">Frankenstein</tei:rs> is Jewish, has very influential
        connections in wealthy circles and could perhaps help a great deal, especially if he seeks
        advice from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-007666">Deutsch</tei:rs> ‒ I have indeed
        alluded to this in my letter.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Now I have a request for you:</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Yesterday I received yet another of those letters from my son, in which he
        asks for money from me. I would like to have something sent to him by way of <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-000786">Schirmer</tei:rs>. But since you say that one can
        do better than the official dollar exchange rate, I would like to make use of this and I ask
        you to tell me how I can do so. My son writes that he has debts of 500 Marks and has been
        threatened with eviction. I cannot ask <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-000786"
          >Schirmer</tei:rs> for more than $50 and yet I would like to obtain as much as possible
        from them.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Let me hear from you soon; and send greetings to your <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000914">wife</tei:rs> from all of us, though we have not
          met.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Most cordial greetings, Your</tei:salute><tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">unsigned</tei:note>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
