<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2532" sdoID="LC-ASC-27-45_27">LC ASC 27/45, [27]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="MV" scope="sole">Moriz Violin's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2020</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2020</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2020</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-07-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-007495">ViolinM ~
        ASchoenberg</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Moriz Violin to Schoenberg, dated April 14, 1941</dc:title>
      <dcterms:created>1941-04-14T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-09-07</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Violin reports encouraging news on his planned "institute," spells out some of
        his ideas, and seeks to discuss further with Schoenberg.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Institut; institute; Einstellung; position; standpoint; Besprechung; discussion;
        crazy; Advertisements; künstlerisches; artistic matters; Erfolg; success; Selbstkosten;
        personal expenses; Tätigkeit; engagement; theoretisch; theoretical; Kunstleben; artistic
        life; Budget; Klavier; piano; Darstellung; offerings; Spezialist; specialist;
        Memorandum</dc:subject>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000798">ASchoenberg</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#MV"/><tei:placeName>S.
              F.</tei:placeName>
            <tei:date when="1941-04-14">14. April 1941</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">253 Buena Vista Ave.</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>Lieber u. verehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798"
          >Freund</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Nun, nach 14 Tagen will ich Sie leise erinnern! Bitte um Ihren Vortrag
        (mit Beispielen!).<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Violin had
          asked for the text of Schoenberg's <tei:title level="a">Composition with Twelve
            Tones</tei:title> lecture of March 26 in <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="LC-ASC-27-45_26">LC ASC 27/45, [26]</tei:ref>, March 29, 1941.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:hi rend="underline">Eine</tei:hi> Sache müssen Sie aber freundlichst
        mit Darstellung Ihrer Einstellung beantworten.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Das erste, viel wichtigere als <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-007673"
          >Stidry</tei:rs>, was ich Ihnen bei meinem letzten Besuche<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot">His visit to Los Angeles to witness Schoenberg's lecture on
          March 26, 1941 (see <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="LC-ASC-27-45_26">LC ASC 27/45,
            [26]</tei:ref>, March 29, 1941), during which visit he may have raised again the
          possibility of procuring performance work in New York, as adumbrated in <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="LC-ASC-27-45_23">LC ASC 27/45, [23]</tei:ref>, December 19,
          1940, and in <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="LC-ASC-27-45_24">LC ASC 27/45,
            [24]</tei:ref>, January 16, 1941.</tei:note> andeutete; meine Institutsidee für <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002921">San Francisco</tei:rs>, ist inzwischen durch eine
        wichtige Besprechung wesentlich gefördert worden. Ich konnte meine Idee in so klarer Form
        entwickeln, daß die Leute ziemlich <tei:foreign xml:lang="eng">crazy about</tei:foreign>
        wurden. Das war noch nicht in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003147"
            ><tei:region>Europa</tei:region></tei:rs> u. ist nicht in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002510"><tei:country>Amerika</tei:country></tei:rs> natürlich. <tei:foreign
          xml:lang="eng">Advertisements</tei:foreign> sind im ganzen Osten gedacht u.s.w. Ich würde,
        wenn es so weit kommt, nach Los Angeles kommen, um alles künstlerisches mit Ihnen
        festzulegen u. zu besprechen. Den richtigen Eindruck würden Sie erst bekommen, wenn ich eine
        Stunde lang Ihnen alles was an Hohem in meiner Idee ist, vortragen würde.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Violin writes continuously, without
          paragraph-break.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ein<tei:del rend="overstrike">e</tei:del>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">wirkliches</tei:hi> Gelingen, glaube ich nur, ist für Ihre Sache
          <tei:hi rend="underline">nur</tei:hi> in <tei:hi rend="underline">Ihnen</tei:hi> gelegen
        u. ich glaube nicht an Erfolg der Gründung wenn Sie sich vertreten lassen würden. Könnten
        Sie es schaffen 1 mal die Woche <tei:hi rend="underline">einen</tei:hi> Tag zu lehren? Für
        diese Sache glaube ich in Anrechnung Ihrer Selbstkosten (minimal!) $4,000. für eine 9‒10
        monatliche Tätigkeit erreichen zu können.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial"
          place="foot">With the first three sentences of this paragraph it becomes clear that Violin
          seeks to create an institute to advance the cause ("für Ihre Sache", "for your cause") of
          Schoenberg's ideas, and to offer the latter a higher level of teaching than he currently
          has in Los Angeles. Whether the institute is to be devoted entirely to Schoenbergian
          theory, or whether Violin has in mind a mix of Schoenbergian and Schenkerian theory, is
          unclear at this stage. The enterprise has reminiscences of the Schenker Institut that he
          established in Hamburg in 1931. Violin gives no hint of the intended relationship between
          this institute and the San Francisco Conservatory.</tei:note> Um alles ermöglichen u
        können, stelle ich meine Person <tei:hi rend="underline">ganz</tei:hi> zur Verfügung
        (ganztägig, ganzwöchentlich) u. verlange $3000. dafür. Ich werde nur alle praktischen Zweige
        innerhalb meiner Sphäre bestreiten u. habe noch die Wahl der Persönlichkeit für die
        theoretische Leute nicht getroffen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial"
          place="foot">A puzzling remark: is he talking of faculty or students ("Leute," "people")
          at this point? And what role did he have in mind for Schoenberg? In this letter he speaks
          of three roles: that of Schoenberg himself (composition?), that of piano studies
          (Steuermann, or is he hinting that he wants a hand in that himself?), and that of theory,
          with himself as administrator?</tei:note> Es ist <tei:hi rend="underline">allen</tei:hi>
        hier klar, daß alles nur zum Benefit des amerikanischen Kunstlebens gedacht ist, u. daß die
        Erweiterung u. Zuziehung in Zukunft den herangebildeten Amerikanern zu Gute kommen wird u.
          soll.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Violin writes
          continuously, without paragraph-break.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>An eine Sache habe ich gedacht, die aber erst erreichbar sein wird, wenn wir bereit u.
        einig werden. Ich habe des Budget wegens erst von oben angedeutete<tei:supplied
          reason="agreement">n</tei:supplied>
        <tei:pb n="2"/>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">3</tei:hi> Lehrkräfter gesprochen. Was Klavier anbelangt, weiß ich
        nicht ob Sie auch derselben Meinung sind, daß Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005228"
          >Steuermann</tei:rs> wie keiner berufen ist, die praktische Liste der Darstellung zu
          über<tei:supplied reason="spelling">r</tei:supplied>eichen. Ich meine natürlich nicht
        Herrn <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005228">St.</tei:rs> als „Spezialisten!“ Er könnte
        alles machen. Aber er kann etwas machen was ich nicht kann u. vielleicht ich manches wieder
        was nicht <tei:hi rend="underline">sein</tei:hi> Stärkstes ist. <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >Das</tei:hi> möchte ich erst anschneiden bis ich <tei:hi rend="underline">Ihre</tei:hi>
        prinzipielle Einstellung kenne. Ich glaube wir könnten was Großes aufbauen, was finanziell
        nach 1‒2 Jahren nicht <tei:hi rend="underline">so</tei:hi> bescheiden zu sein
        braucht.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Wie gesagt: Wenn ich Ihre prinzipielle Einstellung kenne, würde ich nach
        L. A. kommen um ideologische u. praktische Festsetzung in Form eines Memorandums mit Ihnen
        besprechen. Ich weiß Sie werden von der <tei:hi rend="underline">Idee</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">sehr</tei:hi> begeistert sein. Ich habe das letzte mal nur
        angedeutet was ich meinte, weil ich noch vor meinen <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002921"
          >S. F.</tei:rs> Besprechung war.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Höre ich dann ein Wort von Ihnen?</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Herzlichstes von Haus zu Haus!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">getreuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">M Violin</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#MV"/><tei:placeName>San
              Francisco</tei:placeName>, <tei:date when="1941-04-14">April 14,
            1941</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">253 Buena Vista Ave.</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>Dear and revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798"
          >Friend</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Now, two weeks later, I should like to give you a gentle reminder! Your
        lecture, please (with music examples!).<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"
        /></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">There is <tei:hi rend="underline">one</tei:hi> matter that you must,
        however, very kindly answer by outlining your thoughts.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">The first – much more important than <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-007673">Stiedry</tei:rs> – is what I raised with you on my last visit<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/>: my idea of an institute for <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002921">San Francisco</tei:rs> has been advanced considerably in the meantime
        as a result of an important conversation. I was able to elaborate my idea in so clear a form
        that the people became quite <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="italic"
            >in English:</tei:hi></tei:note> crazy about <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"
            ><tei:hi rend="italic">in German:</tei:hi></tei:note> it. There is no such institution
        in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003147"><tei:region>Europe</tei:region></tei:rs> and of
        course none in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002510"
          ><tei:country>America</tei:country></tei:rs>. There are thoughts of placing <tei:note
          type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="italic">in English:</tei:hi></tei:note>
        advertisements <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="italic">in
            German:</tei:hi></tei:note> throughout the east, etc. If it gets to that point, I would
        come to Los Angeles to lay out the whole artistic side with you and discuss it. You would
        begin to form the right impression, were I to spend an hour talking through with you all the
        key points of my idea.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>A <tei:hi rend="underline">real</tei:hi> success for your cause depends, I believe,
          <tei:hi rend="underline">entirely</tei:hi> on your involvement <tei:hi rend="underline">in
          person</tei:hi>; I do not believe we would achieve success for the institution if you were
        represented by proxy. Could you see your way to teaching once a week for a <tei:hi
          rend="underline">whole</tei:hi> day? For this, I reckon that, taking into account your
        personal expenses, <tei:supplied reason="clarity">we could stretch to</tei:supplied>
        (minimally!) $4,000 for a nine- to ten-month engagement.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
          type="footnote"/> To make all of this possible, I place myself <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >entirely</tei:hi> at its disposal (full-time, seven days a week), for which I ask $3,000.
        I will take care only of all practical aspects within my own sphere, and have not yet made
        the selection of the individual for the theory people.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05"
          type="footnote"/> It is clear to <tei:hi rend="underline">everybody</tei:hi> here that
        everything is thought of as solely for the benefit of American musical life, and that
        expansion and contraction in the future will and should be to the advantage of the Americans
        that are trained <tei:supplied reason="clarity">here</tei:supplied>.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>There is one matter to which I have given thought, but which will be achievable only
        when we are ready and in agreement. On account of the budget I have spoken only of <tei:pb
          n="2"/>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">three</tei:hi> teachers, as indicated above. As concerns piano, I
        don't know whether you are of the same mind as myself that Mr. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-005228">Steuermann</tei:rs> is qualified as no other to deliver the practical
        list of offerings. I don't mean, of course, Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005228"
          >Steuermann</tei:rs> as "specialist"! He would be capable of doing all sides. But he can
        do some things that I can't, and then again perhaps I <tei:supplied reason="clarity">can
          do</tei:supplied> a few things that aren't <tei:hi rend="underline">his</tei:hi> greatest
        strengths. <tei:hi rend="underline">That</tei:hi> is what I should like to bring up first
        until I know <tei:hi rend="underline">your</tei:hi> standpoint in principle. I believe we
        could build up something big, which in a couple of years' time won't need to be financially
          <tei:hi rend="underline">so very</tei:hi> modest.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">As I've said, once I know your standpoint in principle, I would come to
        Los Angeles to discuss with you finalizing ideological and practical matters in the form of
        a memorandum. I know you will be <tei:hi rend="underline">very</tei:hi> excited by the
          <tei:hi rend="underline">idea</tei:hi>. Last time I merely indicated what I had in mind,
        because I had yet to have my conversation with <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002921">San
          Francisco</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">So will I have word from you?</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Most cordial best wishes from my family to yours!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">M. Violin</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
