<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2169" sdoID="MP-0008-01-1-1-4">NYnscl MP.0008.01/1/1, 4</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="major">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="RW">
      <tei:persName>Robert Wason</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2007</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2007</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2011-02-07" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006961">WaldeckA ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Jeanette Schenker to Arthur Waldeck and Nathan Broder, dated
        March 9, 1936</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1936-03-09T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-01-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Jeanette has received an article about Schenker written by Waldeck and Broder
        and thanks the authors for the article and accompanying message. — She informs them that the
        Wiener Schenker-Institut has successfully started up.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Artikel; article; Uebersetzer; translator; Absatz; paragraph; Musikerkreise;
        musical circles; Begriff; concept; ideas; Schülerzahl; student enrolment; kunstfeindlich;
        anti-artistic; Ableben; death; Gattin; wife; Freundin; (female) friend; Gehilfin (female)
        helper</dc:subject>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000927">Arthur Waldeck</marcrel:recipient>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000102">Nathan Broder</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>Sehr geehrter Herren,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01"
            type="editorial" place="foot">The addressees are <tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000927">Arthur Waldeck</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000102">Nathan Broder</tei:rs>.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>nehmen Sie meinen verbindlichsten Dank für die Uebersendung Ihres Artikels, vor allem
        aber für den umfänglichen Artikel selbst,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
          place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Arthur Waldeck</tei:author> &amp; <tei:author>Nathan
              Broder</tei:author>, <tei:title level="a">Musical Synthesis as Expounded by Heinrich
              Schenker,</tei:title>
            <tei:title level="j">Musical Mercury</tei:title> 2/4 (1935): 56–64</tei:bibl>: a copy,
          along with a two-page typescript summary in German, both catalogued among Jonas's personal
          teaching materials, survives as OJ 58/22. The cataloguing appears to be correct, since the
          article is a negative photocopy, not a "presentation copy" from the mid-1930s. Most
          likely, the presentation copy is lost. In any case, there can be no doubt of the identity
          of the article to which Mrs. Schenker refers: Waldeck and Broder start their work by
          citing the only three articles in English that they know of (agreeing with modern
          bibliographers), and all others are by single authors. Furthermore, the authors write that
          Schenker himself has recommended to them (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-44_4"
            >OJ 5/44 [4]</tei:ref>) <tei:bibl><tei:author>Oswald Jonas</tei:author>, <tei:title
              level="m">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks: Eine Einführung in die Lehre
              Heinrich Schenkers</tei:title> (Vienna and Leipzig: Saturn Verlag, 1934)</tei:bibl>.
        </tei:note> der eben bei einem Uebersetzer ist, weil mein Englisch noch nicht auf der
        erforderlichen Stufe ist.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Jedenfalls ist es so, wie Sie im letzten Absatz es zusammengefaßt haben:
        Weiteste Musikerkreise müssen für die Ideen Schenkers, für den Begriff Schenker gewonnen
          werden<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Mrs. Schenker likely
          refers to the last two paragraphs of the article, which read: "Even if Schenker had
          stopped short of the basic line, his works would be of incalculable value to the musician.
          For even the earliest books are full of flashes of the keenest insight into the nature of
          the music in hand. And while it is difficult to trace the course of the basic line, few
          difficulties are offered by the smaller spans; and it is these, as has been said, that
          constitute the most important means for gaining inner coherence. <tei:title level="m">Der
            freie Satz</tei:title> presents a systematic exposition of Schenker's technique. We have
          not attempted to summarize all of that technique. We have not even exhausted the subject
          of the span. We have tried only to give the reader an indication of the nature of
          Schenker's work. If the reader's interest and curiosity have been aroused, our goal has
          been attained." (<tei:title level="a">Musical Synthesis ...,</tei:title> p.
          64).</tei:note> u. ich wünsche Ihnen, daß Ihr Aufsatz kräftigstes Echo finde!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Es dürfte Sie interessiren zu erfahren , daß das <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-006970">Wiener Schenker-Institut</tei:rs> sich <tei:pb
          n="2"/> ganz schön einführt u. die Schülerzahl, wenn man die kunstfeindlichen Verhältnisse
        bedenkt, ziemlich befriedigend ist.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich danke Ihnen auch herzlich für Ihre guten Wünsche – ich trauere wie am
        ersten Tag nach dem Ableben um den gütigen, großen Menschen u. Künstler, dem Gattin,
        Freundin u. Gehilfin zu sein mir ein gütiges Geschick vergönnt hatte.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Beste Empfehlungen von</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-30"><tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Frau D<tei:hi
              rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Heinrich Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:placeName>Wien</tei:placeName>, den <tei:date when="1936-03-09">9. März
            1936</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>Dear Gentlemen,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
            type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Please accept my most sincere thanks for sending your article, and above all, for the
        extensive article itself,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> which is presently
        with a translator, since my English is not yet at the necessary level. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">In any case, it is just as you have summarized the matter in the last
        paragraph: musical circles far and wide must be won over to Schenker's ideas, and to the
        very idea of Schenker<tei:supplied reason="clarity">'s work</tei:supplied>.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> I hope that your article finds strong
        response.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">It may interest you to know that the <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-006970">Vienna Schenker Institute</tei:rs>
        <tei:pb n="2"/> has started up smoothly, and the number of students ‒ when one considers the
        anti-artistic situation ‒ is reasonably satisfactory.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I also thank you cordially for your good wishes. I mourn just as on the
        first day after the passing of that good and great man and artist; a gracious destiny has
        permitted me to be wife, friend and helper to him.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Best regards from</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-30"><tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Mrs. Heinrich
            Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:placeName> Vienna</tei:placeName>, <tei:date when="1936-03-09">March 9,
            1936</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
