<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="3811" sdoID="NMI-C-176-01">NMI C 176-01</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="KK">
   <tei:persName>Kevin Karnes</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IDB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-09-15" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008521">RoentgenJ ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Julius Röntgen, dated April 13, 1901</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1901-04-13T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-10-04</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker advises Röntgen on intellectual property and honorarium in dealing with
    Weinberger [UE], and extols the beauty of the C. P. E. Bach keyboard sonatas he is to edit,
    decrying Hans von Bülow in the process. -- He hopes that his own Zweistimmige Inventionen Op. 5
    and Sechs Lieder Op. 3 will appeal to Röntgen with a view to performance, mentioning the names
    of singers Eduard Gärtner and Johannes Messchaert. -- He sings the praises of certain works of
    Schumann, Brahms, and Beethoven for their handling of tonality, and deplores the tendency [of
    current composers] to seek constant change (modulation, chromaticism, enharmonicism) rather than
    synthesis.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>



   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-008632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000724">RöntgenJ</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Wien, den <tei:date when="1901-04-13"
      >13 April 1901</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute>Verehrtester u. lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000724"
      >Professor</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">This letter is
      published in English in <tei:bibl><tei:editor>Bent, Ian</tei:editor>, <tei:editor>David
        Bretherton</tei:editor> and <tei:editor>William Drabkin</tei:editor>, eds, <tei:title
        level="m">Heinrich Schenker: Selected Correspondence</tei:title> (Woodbridge: Boydell Press,
       2014), pp. 62–64</tei:bibl>. — <tei:bibl><tei:author>Federhofer</tei:author> quotes the
       entire letter in German in <tei:title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern und
        Briefen</tei:title> (Hildesheim: Olms, 1985), pp. 189–92</tei:bibl>. The differences between
      Federhofer’s text and that given here are largely matters of house-style. — This letter
      responds to <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-13-27_1">OJ 13/27, [1]</tei:ref>, March
      18, 1901. My thanks to Maximilian Aue for his help with a number of passages in this
      letter.</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Für Ihre Zusage der Mitarbeiterschaft besten Dank! Hoffentlich sind Sie mit <tei:rs
     type="organization" key="entity-006149">Weinberger &amp; Comp.</tei:rs><tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker had sought to secure Röntgen’s
     collaboration in the latter endeavor in a letter of March 15, 1901, <tei:ref
      type="correspondence" cRef="NMI-C-176-02">NMI C 176-02</tei:ref>.</tei:note> auch handelseins
    geworden: ich sah <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000946">W.</tei:rs> seit jener Stunde nicht
    mehr, u. weiss um das Ende der Sache daher gar nichts. Sie dürfen sich, wenn Sie sagen, dass,
    was Sie zu leisten haben, Ihr geistiges Eigentum sei [in höherem Sinne, als gewöhnliche
    Leistungen der allzuvielen Herausgeber)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
     place="foot">Square bracket used in place of left-hand parenthesis in original.</tei:note> auch
     <tei:hi rend="underline">ein höheres Honorar</tei:hi>, als das usuelle, ausbedingen. Und
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000946">Weinberger</tei:rs> wird es auch gewähren. Wenigstens
    werde ich es so halten mit der <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001720">Ausgabe von P. E.
     Bach</tei:rs>, die ich zu leisten versprochen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial"
     place="foot">Schenker’s edition of selected works by C. P. E. Bach would be published as
       <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Klavierwerke von Philipp Emanuel Bach: Neue kritische Ausgabe
       von Heinrich Schenker</tei:title> (Vienna: UE, [1903])</tei:bibl>. (On the history and dating
     of this publication, see <tei:bibl><tei:author>Ian D. Bent</tei:author>, <tei:title level="a"
       >‘That Bright, New Light’: Schenker, Universal Edition, and the Origins of the Erläuterung
       Series, 1901-1910,</tei:title>
      <tei:title level="j">Journal of the American Musicological Society</tei:title> 58/1 (2005),
      74-75)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> Ich weiss wahrhaftig nicht, soll ich mehr <tei:add
     place="interlinear-above">mich</tei:add> fürchten vor der Riesenarbeit, oder freuen auf das
    viele Schöne. Kennen Sie die Sonate F<tei:hi rend="supralinear">dur</tei:hi>
    <tei:pb n="2"/> im <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002890">Br &amp; H.</tei:rs>’s Urtext
    die zweite? Wie unendlich fein, u. ganz im Gegensatz zu den modernen Haupt- u.
    Seitensatzschreibern so frei u. überreich, so mannigfaltig sich darstellend! Wer schreibt heute
    so genial, wie gleich im T. 4 des ersten Satzes das letzte Achtel? Wie himmlisch geht das
    hinüber, kommend, gehend, wie eine leichte Muskelbewegung, ein Zucken nur! Nichts ist dick,
    nichts grob, kein Grund aufgedonnert, – Wille u. Ausführung, beide zart functionirend,
    herrlich!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Dass <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000110">Bülow</tei:rs> diese Sonate weglassen
    konnte, wäre mir unbegreiflich, hätte ich nicht den Drang, ihn eher etwas tiefer, als höher zu
    schätzen. Und habe ich Ihr<tei:del rend="overstrike">e</tei:del> reizendes <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000110">Bülow</tei:rs>pamphlet verstanden, so scheinen auch Sie ihn weniger zu
    verhimmeln, weniger ernst zu nehmen, als die grosse, namengierige Menge. Bei dieser Gelegenheit
    möchte ich Ihnen wohl sagen, dass auch <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs>
    ihn nicht überschätzte: war doch <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094">Br.</tei:rs>
    derjenige, der den <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">Furor Teutonicus</tei:foreign> gedämpft hat, als
    die Ger- <tei:pb n="3"/> manen nach <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000110">Bülow</tei:rs>’s
    Tode ein Nationaldenkmal verlangten. Ich kam damals, im Auftrage <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000333">Harden</tei:rs>’s aus <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501"
     >Berlin</tei:rs>, zu <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs>, u. er sagte:
    „Ach, was! ich habe Geld u. Mitwirkung zugesagt, aber nur für ein Friedhofsdenkmal in <tei:rs
     type="place" key="entity-002589">Hamburg</tei:rs>. Mehr verdient <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000110">B.</tei:rs> nicht; er war jar nur ein Kapellmeister! Hat denn schon <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000924">Wagner</tei:rs> ein denkmal? u.s.w.” Wie schön, dass <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000094">Br.</tei:rs> trotz allem Dankgefühl so was zu sagen Muth
    hatte. Es ging dann auch nach seiner Meinung, die denkmalsfrage.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Und nun noch einige Worte zu meiner Sendung an Sie, die ich Ihnen
    versprochen. Ich bitte Sie um Ihr Interesse für die <tei:title>Invention</tei:title> N<tei:hi
     rend="supralinear">o</tei:hi> 2, auf die ich sehr stolz bin.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05"
     type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Schenker</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m"
       >Zweistimmige Inventionen</tei:title>, Op. 5 (Leipzig: Breitkopf &amp; Härtel,
      1901)</tei:bibl>. </tei:note> Sie ist sogar ziemlich rasch, ich meine passionirt, gedacht,
    sehr ausdrucksvoll! Hier ist es hauptsächlich, wo ich das Moderne brachte. Es würde mich sehr
    freuen, wenn diese <tei:title>Inv.</tei:title> Ihnen gefallen wollte.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Dagegen zweifle ich gar nicht, – so fest überzeugt bin ich davon, u. sage es dennoch mit
    aller Bescheidenheit, die mir vor mir selbst u. vor Ihnen doch zukommt, – dass Ihnen unter
     <tei:pb n="4"/> den Liedern ein einziges gefallen muss, ja, gefallen muss: „<tei:title>Der
     Ausklang</tei:title>”.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot"
       ><tei:bibl><tei:author>Schenker</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Sechs Lieder für eine
       Singstimme mit Begleitung des Pianoforte</tei:title>, Op. 3 (Leipzig: Breitkopf &amp; Härtel,
      1898, 1901)</tei:bibl>, No. 4, “<tei:title level="m">Ausklang</tei:title>” (text by Ludwig
     Jacobowski).</tei:note> Damit hat es übrigens eine düstere, unheimliche Bewandtnis. Denken Sie:
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000274">Prof. Gärtner</tei:rs>, der heuer einen Liederabend
    der „Jungen”, mit Einschluss <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000871">R. Strauss</tei:rs>’, gab
    (etwa 14–16 Lieder vortrug von 8–10 Autoren), wollte zwei Lieder von mir singen: unter allen
    Umständen das „<tei:title>Wiegenliedchen</tei:title>“,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07"
     type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker, <tei:title level="m">Sechs Lieder</tei:title>, Op. 3,
     No. 2, “<tei:title level="m">Wiegenlied</tei:title>” (text by Detlev von
     Liliencron).</tei:note> weil es ihm besonders durch dass pp, u. sonst angenehm lag, u. überdies
    ein angenehmes Gegengewicht gegen die übrigen Novitäten bot, die, wie schon heute einmal usus,
    allen Liedstyl sprengten, die Stimmbänder in Fetzen rissen, Tonarten u. Tonalitäten für
    überwunden erklärten, u – ausserdem noch den obergenanten „<tei:title>Ausklang</tei:title>”. Nun
    fügte es sich, dass er mehr Lieder seines Accompagnateurs, <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-003005">H. v. Zemlinsky</tei:rs>, singen müsste, weil dieser in nächster Woche, in
    seiner Eigenschaft als Capellmeister am Carltheater die Operette <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000274">Gärtner</tei:rs>’s zu dirigiren hatte, – „eine Hand wäscht die andere”, u.
    er konnte nur das „<tei:title>Wiegen</tei:title>- <tei:pb n="5"/>
    <tei:title>liedchen</tei:title>” singen, womit er, nebenbei gesagt, fast den besten Erfolg der
    Abends hatte . .</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Nun aber, – hier setzt eine Tragik ein – denken Sie: am selben Abend des Concertes, fast
    auf die Stunde, auf die Minute genau, in der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000274"
     >Gärtner</tei:rs> mich vortrug, starb in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501"
     >Berlin</tei:rs> der <tei:choice>
     <tei:sic>umgemein</tei:sic>
     <tei:corr>ungemein</tei:corr>
    </tei:choice> sympatische Dichter der „<tei:title>Leuchtenden Tage</tei:title>“, der Autor des
     „<tei:title>Ausklangs</tei:title>“ in Alter von nicht 32 Jahren!!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08"
     type="editorial" place="foot">The poetic text of Schenker’s “<tei:title level="m"
      >Ausklang</tei:title>” was written by Ludwig Jacobowski (1868-1900).</tei:note> Hätte <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000274">Gärtner</tei:rs> um diese Minute den
     „<tei:title>Ausklang</tei:title>“ gesungen, wie eigentümlich wäre diese Zusammentreffen
    gewesen! </tei:p>

   <tei:p>O! Lesen Sie Jakobowskis Gedichtsammlung. Ein so reiner, liebevoller Mensch! Ein
    ergreifendes <tei:foreign xml:lang="fre">Naturell</tei:foreign>.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Aus Allem Eingesandten aber werden Sie ersehen, dass es mir kein Spass ist, mit
     <tei:term>Enharmonik</tei:term> u <tei:term>Chromatik</tei:term> umzuspringen, so, wie man es
    gerne in kindischester Weise heute thut. Die Ursache alles heutigen Treibens ist meiner Ansicht
    nach wohl die: <tei:pb n="6"/> Keiner hat ein so geniales Tonartgefühl, keine so geniale
    Mannigfaltigkeit der <tei:term>Erfindung</tei:term> u. was dasselbe Mannigfaltigkeit der
     <tei:term>Form</tei:term>, um so schreiben zu können, wie z. B. sagen wir: <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000808">Schumann</tei:rs> im Intermezzo op. 4 N<tei:hi
     rend="supralinear">o</tei:hi> 5, wo erst im Takt 20<tei:hi rend="supralinear">-21</tei:hi> –
     <tei:hi rend="underline">nach langer, schönster F<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
     >dur</tei:hi>-haltung</tei:hi>! – die eigentliche D-moll Tonica, <tei:add
     place="interlinear-above">u. zwar</tei:add> sich bereits einen <tei:hi rend="double-underline"
     >anderen</tei:hi>
    <tei:term>Motiv</tei:term> unterstellend, erscheint!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Und zunächst <tei:hi rend="double-underline">pp!</tei:hi> Erst im T. 29 <tei:hi
     rend="underline">ff</tei:hi>, Dmoll, das Achtelmotiv ff u. drüber hin <tei:add
     place="interlinear-above">aber</tei:add> eine <tei:hi rend="double-underline">neue</tei:hi>
    Ballade <tei:hi rend="double-underline">aus D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">m</tei:hi></tei:hi>. – –
    Oder <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001343">Brahms’ G<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
      >moll</tei:hi> Rhapsodie</tei:rs>, die Sie so schön spielen: Erst im T. 9 erscheint die Tonica
    G(dur) (u. wie versteckt!) im T. 11 endlich die eigentliche Tonica G<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
     >m</tei:hi>! Was ging der Alles voraus! Wie ging es zur Tonica hin! Ohne viel Federlesens dann
    auch von der Tonart weg nach D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">m</tei:hi>!</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Und ein genialstes Beispiel der <tei:term>Enharmonik</tei:term> aus der
     <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001218">E<tei:hi rend="supralinear">m</tei:hi> Sonate
     Beethoven’s</tei:rs>, im ersten Satz etwa T. 37 u ff. <tei:pb n="7"/> Dieses b, dieses B<tei:hi
     rend="supralinear">dur</tei:hi>!!!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Und so meine ich: die meisten von heute müssen, da ihre Talentlosigkeit vor der Kunst sich
    leider nicht in Talent verwandeln will, u. sich doch <tei:hi rend="double-underline"
     >etwas</tei:hi> verändern muss rastlos in der Kunst, wenn nicht scheussliche Langeweile
    eintreten soll, eben die Töne raschestens verwandeln u. verändern. Wenn sie selbst in
     <tei:term>Erfindung</tei:term> u. Talent monoton, so sollen die Töne desto mehr sich verändern
    u. desto rascher, um die Monotonie des Autors nicht zu verrathen.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich halte fest daran: Tonart, <tei:term>Tonalität</tei:term>,
     <tei:term>Modulation</tei:term>, <tei:term>Chromatik</tei:term>,
     <tei:term>Enharmonik</tei:term> dürfe man Kindern nicht in die Hand geben, ebensowenig als
    Feuer. Das ist ja kein Spass. Und vor Allem <tei:term>Synthese</tei:term>! die muss Geist in
    jedem Winkel haben, u. desto schöner, je weniger auffallend, aufdringlich, je
     stylvoller!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09" type="editorial" place="foot">This sentence is
     syntactically complex and elliptical, so its rendering is tentative. Additionally, “je
     stylvoller” might be interpreted in a favorable light as “the greater the richness of style”;
     however, Schenker had a low opinion of the notion of “style,” believing the repertory to be
     made up of single masterpieces created by individual masters, not styles created by schools of
     composers, hence the adverse reading adopted here.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Zum Schluss, verehrter, lieber H. Professor noch Eins: Sollte <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000592">Prof. Meschaert</tei:rs> gelegentlich Lust haben, den
     „<tei:title>Ausklang</tei:title>“ zu singen (<tei:hi rend="underline">nur bei </tei:hi><tei:hi
     rend="double-underline">aufrichtigster</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">Ge-</tei:hi>
    <tei:pb n="8"/>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">sinnung</tei:hi> natürlich!), so wird, hoffe ich, H. <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-002456">Gutmann</tei:rs> keine Schwierigkeiten machen. Denn als H.
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000150">E. d’Albert</tei:rs> vor paar Jahren Clavierstücke
    von mir hier spielte, zahlte H. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002456">Gutmann</tei:rs> aus
    eigener Tasche sogar 15Fl Tantièmen (Novitätentantième), ohne nur ein Wort <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000150">d’Albert</tei:rs> oder mir zu sagen. Ich erfuhr davon nach 2 Jahren in
    Gegenwart <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in left margin:</tei:note> Prf.<tei:note
     type="editorial" place="inline">end cue</tei:note>
    <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003551">Becker</tei:rs>s u. <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000744">D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Rottenberg</tei:rs>’s aus <tei:rs
     type="place" key="entity-002495">Frankfurt</tei:rs>; <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002456"
     >Gutmann</tei:rs> war aber nicht zu bewegen, sich das Geld von <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000150">d’Albert</tei:rs> oder mir retourniren zu lassen. Dies also nur
     eventuell.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10" type="editorial" place="foot">The circumstances to
     which this discussion refers are not entirely clear, but it seems as though a concert by
     d’Albert, arranged by Gutmann and at which one of Schenker’s works was performed, was not
     financially successful. Rather than acknowledging this fact to either d’Albert or Schenker,
     Gutmann apparently absorbed the loss himself, and paid Schenker’s royalty “out of his own
     pocket.” Schenker’s concern regarding Messchaert’s possible interest in performing some of his
     Lieder might be explained by the fact that Messchaert, like d’Albert, was also represented by
     Gutmann (as we learn in Röntgen’s letter to Schenker, <tei:ref type="correspondence"
      cRef="OJ-13-27_4">OJ 13/27, [4]</tei:ref>, October 14, 1901).</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Nächstens kommt aber ganz grosses, vielleicht gelingt es mir dann damit, mich bekannter zu
    machen.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Tausend Grüsse</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">von Ihrem Sie verehrenden</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H
     Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>


  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Vienna, <tei:date when="1901-04-13"
      >April 13, 1901</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute>Most revered and dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000724"
      >Professor</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Many thanks for your acceptance <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of my
     invitation</tei:supplied> to contribute! I hope you have also reached an agreement with <tei:rs
     type="organization" key="entity-006149">Weinberger &amp; Co</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> I have not seen <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000946">W.</tei:rs> for some time and I know virtually nothing about how it turned
    out. If you assert that what you have to offer is your intellectual property (in a higher sense
    than the typical services of all too many editors),<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
     type="footnote"/> you may indeed insist on <tei:hi rend="underline">a higher
     honorarium</tei:hi> than the usual. And <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000946"
     >Weinberger</tei:rs> will approve it. At least that’s what I will do with regard to my <tei:rs
     type="work" key="entity-001720">edition of C. P. E. Bach</tei:rs> that I’ve promised to
     undertake.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> In truth, I do not know if I should
    be more fearful of the colossal task ahead or overjoyed at so much beauty. Do you know the
    Sonata in F major, <tei:pb n="2"/> the second in <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002890"
     >Breitkopf &amp; Härtel</tei:rs>’s Urtext volume? It is so endlessly fine and, in stark
    contrast to the modern first-and-second-subject merchants, presented so freely and lavishly, in
    such a multifarious manner! Who today writes with such genius as we see on the last eighth-note
    of bar 4 in the first movement? How exquisitely it moves back and forth, coming and going, like
    a slight muscular movement, like the merest twitch! Nothing is thick, nothing coarse, in no way
    dolled up. Will and execution, both working delicately, marvelously!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>The fact that <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000110">Bülow</tei:rs> could leave this
    sonata aside would be incomprehensible to me if I had not earlier been inclined to judge him
    somewhat more lowly than highly. And if I have understood your teasing lampoon of <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000110">Bülow</tei:rs>, you too feel that he is a figure less worthy
    of beatification, less worthy of being taken seriously, than the great star-struck masses
    believe. I might take this opportunity to say that even <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs> too did not overestimate him; it was indeed <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs> who threw a wet towel on the <tei:foreign
     xml:lang="lat"><tei:hi rend="italic">furor teutonicus</tei:hi></tei:foreign> when the Germans
     <tei:pb n="3"/> were clamoring for a national monument after <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000110">Bülow</tei:rs>’s death. I went to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094"
     >Brahms</tei:rs> then, at the behest of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000333"
     >Harden</tei:rs> in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>, and he said, “Eh,
    what’s all this? I have pledged money and support, but only for a cemetery monument in <tei:rs
     type="place" key="entity-002589">Hamburg</tei:rs>. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000110"
     >Bülow</tei:rs> deserves no more; he was only a Kapellmeister! Does <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000924">Wagner</tei:rs> have a monument? etc.” How lovely that <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs>, despite all his feelings of thankfulness,
    had the courage to say it. This is my view too regarding the question of a monument.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">And now a few more words about what I’ve sent you as promised. I hope that my
     <tei:title>Invention</tei:title> No. 2, of which I am very proud, may arouse your
     interest.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> It is indeed rather quick –
    passionate, I think, deliberate, very expressive! It is here, primarily, where I’ve breached
    modernism. It would make me very happy if this <tei:title>invention</tei:title> pleased
    you.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>In contrast, I am absolutely certain that you must – that you simply must – find one of
     <tei:pb n="4"/> the Lieder pleasing (so firmly am I convinced of this, and I say so
    nevertheless with all the modesty that you and I both deserve): “<tei:title>Der
     Ausklang</tei:title>.”<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> There is, incidentally,
    a strange, uncanny reason for this. Consider this: <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000274"
     >Prof. Gärtner</tei:rs>, who just this year hosted a <tei:hi rend="italic">Liederabend</tei:hi>
    of the “young,” which included works by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000871">Richard
     Strauss</tei:rs> (around 14–16 Lieder by 8–10 composers were performed), wanted to sing two of
    my Lieder – “<tei:title>Wiegenliedchen</tei:title>,”<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07"
     type="footnote"/> of course, because he found the <tei:hi rend="bold italic">pp</tei:hi> and so
    forth so agreeable (and moreover because it provided a pleasant counterbalance to the other
    novelties, which, as is common practice today, obliterate the Lied style completely, tear the
    vocal cords to shreds, and regard key and tonality as vanquished), and also the above-mentioned
     “<tei:title>Ausklang</tei:title>.” Now, it happened that he needed to sing more Lieder by his
    accompanist, Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003005">von Zemlinsky</tei:rs>, because the
    following week, in his capacity as music director of the Carltheater, the latter was to conduct
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000274">Gärtner</tei:rs>’s operetta (“one hand washes the
    other”). And so he could only sing “<tei:title>Wiegenliedchen</tei:title>,” <tei:pb n="5"/> with
    which, by the way, he scored perhaps the greatest success of the evening . . .</tei:p>

   <tei:p>But now consider this (and here comes the tragedy): On the same evening as the concert,
    almost the same hour, even the same minute in which <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000274"
     >Gärtner</tei:rs> performed <tei:supplied reason="clarity">my work</tei:supplied>, the
    uncommonly congenial author of the poem “<tei:title>Leuchtende Tage</tei:title>” – the author of
     “<tei:title>Ausklang</tei:title>” – died in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501"
     >Berlin</tei:rs>, before the end of his thirty-second year!!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08"
     type="footnote"/> If <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000274">Gärtner</tei:rs> had sung
     “<tei:title>Ausklang</tei:title>” at that moment, how strange the coincidence would have
    been!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Oh! Read Jakobowski’s book of poetry! — What a pure, loving man! A touching
    disposition.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>From everything I’ve sent, it will be obvious to you that I take no pleasure in getting
    wrapped up in <tei:term>enharmonicism</tei:term> and <tei:term>chromaticism</tei:term>, as
    people are so fond of doing today in the most childish of ways. The reason for all the present
    carrying on is the following view of mine: <tei:pb n="6"/> No one has such a brilliant sense of
    tonality that he is able to write with such brilliant, multifaceted
     <tei:term>inventiveness</tei:term> (and, in turn, in such multifaceted
     <tei:term>form</tei:term>s) as, e.g., <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000808"
     >Schumann</tei:rs>, in the Intermezzo, Op. 4, No. 5, where the actual tonic, D minor, makes its
    first appearance in mm. 20<tei:hi rend="supralinear">-21</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="underline"
     >after a long, utterly beautiful tarrying in F major</tei:hi> – <tei:add
     place="interlinear-above">and indeed</tei:add> undergirded by a <tei:hi rend="double-underline"
     >different</tei:hi>
    <tei:term>motive</tei:term>!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>And at first, <tei:hi rend="double-underline"><tei:hi rend="bold italic"
     >pp</tei:hi>!</tei:hi> Only in m. 29 is it <tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:hi rend="bold italic"
      >ff</tei:hi></tei:hi>, D minor, the eighth-note motive <tei:hi rend="bold italic">ff</tei:hi>,
    and above it, <tei:add place="interlinear-above">however,</tei:add> a <tei:hi
     rend="double underline">new</tei:hi> ballad <tei:hi rend="double-underline">from out of this D
     minor</tei:hi>. – – Or <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001343">Brahms’s G-minor
     Rhapsody</tei:rs>, which you play so well: The tonic G (major) first appears in bar 9 (and how
    it is hidden!), and the actual tonic, G minor, finally in bar 11! How it all unfolds! How it
    moves toward the tonic! And then without much ado, the tonality makes its way toward D
    minor!</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">And a most brilliant example of enharmonicism in the <tei:rs
     type="composition" key="entity-001218">E-minor Sonata of Beethoven</tei:rs>, in the first
    movement around bar 37 and after. <tei:pb n="7"/> This B<tei:g type="flat"/>, this B<tei:g
     type="flat"/> major!!!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>And so I say: Most people today, because their lack of talent in art cannot unfortunately
    transform itself into talent, and restlessly sensing that <tei:hi rend="double-underline"
     >something</tei:hi> must be changed in <tei:supplied reason="clarity">their</tei:supplied> art
    if dreaded boredom is to be avoided, feel that they must transform and alter – most rashly –
    even the tones themselves. The more monotonous they are themselves in terms of
     <tei:term>invention</tei:term> and talent, the more the notes must be altered, and ever more
    rashly, so that the monotony of the composer is not betrayed.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>I firmly believe that one must not hand a child key, <tei:term>tonality</tei:term>,
     <tei:term>modulation</tei:term>, <tei:term>chromaticism</tei:term>, or
     <tei:term>enharmonicism</tei:term> any more readily than one hands a child fire. It is indeed
    no joke. And above all, <tei:term>synthesis</tei:term>! – which must have spirit in every nook
    and cranny, and the less conspicuous <tei:supplied reason="clarity">it is</tei:supplied>, the
    more beautiful; if obtrusive, then all the more contrived.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09"
     type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>In conclusion, honored, dear Professor, one more thing: Should <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000592">Prof. Messchaert</tei:rs>, at some point, feel like singing
     “<tei:title>Ausklang</tei:title>” (<tei:hi rend="underline">only out of the </tei:hi><tei:hi
     rend="double-underline">most sincere</tei:hi>
    <tei:pb n="8"/>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">convictions</tei:hi>, of course!), I hope that Mr. <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-002456">Gutmann</tei:rs> will not make trouble. Because when Mr.
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000150">Eugen d’Albert</tei:rs> played some of my piano
    pieces here a couple years ago, Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002456">Gutmann</tei:rs>
    paid the 15-Florin royalty (novelty royalty) out of his own pocket, without saying a word to
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000150">d’Albert</tei:rs> or to me. I learned about it two
    years later in the presence of Prof. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003551">Becker</tei:rs>
    and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000744">Dr. Rottenberg</tei:rs> from <tei:rs type="place"
     key="entity-002495">Frankfurt</tei:rs>; <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002456"
     >Gutmann</tei:rs>, however, could not be persuaded to let the money be returned by <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000150">d’Albert</tei:rs> or myself. I hope this will be
     resolved.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn10" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>If this is getting overly long, then perhaps it has succeeded in making <tei:supplied
     reason="clarity">you</tei:supplied> more acquainted with me.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">A thousand greetings,</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Yours in admiration</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H
     Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
