<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3624" sdoID="OC-1-B-12">OC 1 B/12</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="sole">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>


    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2025</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-23" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008509">RetiR ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Rudolf Réti, dated July 5, 1913</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1913-07-05T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-06-19</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker offers an explanation for having declined Réti's invitation to a
        lecture on March 5, 1913; he then takes up an issue concerning the nature of truth that Réti
        had raised in a letter.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000706">RetiR</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-20"><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>H D<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
              >r.</tei:hi> Rudolf Réti</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="ident-10">Tonkünstler</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>Sehr geehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000706">Herr</tei:rs>!<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">The writing of this letter is not
            recorded in Schenker’s diary. It was written when the Schenkers were in the Tyrol, and
            on July 4 and 5 they were on excursions to nearby areas. The letter is entirely in
            Jeanette Schenker’s hand. The “invitation” mentioned here would appear to be that which
            Schenker received on March 4 to a lecture that Réti was giving on March 5, and which
            Schenker turned down the same day, alluding to Guido Adler’s likely presence as one
            obstacle (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-13-22_1">OJ 13/22, [1]</tei:ref>).
            However, four months have elapsed since that time, and it is strange that the matter
            should have continued to rankle in Schenker’s mind, and strange, too, that the diary
            makes no mention of so forthright a letter. Could it have been an exercise in private
            self-justification that Schenker did not send? There is no known further communication
            between the two men.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Ihre freundliche Einladung<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Presumably that received on March 4, to which Schenker responded negatively, <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-13-22_1">OJ 13/22, [1]</tei:ref>, the same
          day.</tei:note> verpflichtet mich zu folgender freimütiger Erklärung: Von der <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002429">intern. Musikgesellschaft</tei:rs> hielt ich mich
        (von aller Arbeitsüberbürdung abgesehen) allezeit auch aus dem Grunde fern, weil ich unter
        Geschichte d. Musik lediglich die Geschichte d. Technik verstehe, unter letzterer aber
        ungleich mehr, als ob man bis heute in Lehrbüchern d. Komposition u. in Analysen dafür
        ausgibt. Dazu kommt ein persönliches Moment. Von verläßlicher Seite erfuhr ich, daß <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000003">Prof. Guido Adler</tei:rs>, den ich 2, 3mal im Leben
        gesprochen, u. bei dieser Gelegenheit einen feinen Mann kennen gelernt habe, im Seminar mich
        einfach einen „Dilettanten“ des Öfteren nannte,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot">An estrangement occurred between Schenker and Adler at some
          point in 1913; Schenker reported in his diary for January 31, 1913: “What a contrast
            <tei:supplied reason="context">from Hugo Riemann’s attitude toward me</tei:supplied>! –
          assuming that the communication is true – with the attitude of Guido Adler, who damages
          the dignity of a Seminar Institute by taking a simple rumor already for proof! Meanwhile,
          in the last instance the disgrace finds its way back to the originator.” Schenker was to
          hear many unfavorable reports of Adler’s conduct from Hans Weisse while the latter was a
          student in Adler’s seminar in 1914 and 1915.</tei:note> obgleich das Seminar, die Tugend,
        seine eigene Unabhängigkeit ihm statt einer Beschimpfung die Pflicht zu sachlichen Beweisen
        hätte auferlegen müssen. Schließlich ist die Welt der Irrtümer so groß, daß man aus ihr
        leicht ein paar Argumente holen kann, wenn es sich darum handelt, eine
          <tei:sic>misliebige</tei:sic> Erscheinung discreditiren. Und hat man gar die Wahrheit für
        sich, so fliegen die Be- <tei:pb n="2"/> weise ja von selbst zu. Ich würde mich schämen,
        Jemandes abweichende Meinung anders als durch Beweise entkräften. Schließlich ist die
        Wahrheit ein Gebiet, Rechthaberei als solch keine Geltung auf die Dauer behält. Sie
        begreifen, daß ich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000003">Prof. Adler</tei:rs> nicht in
        Befangenheit mir gegenüber setzen möchte, die aber unvermeidlich wäre, wenn ich Ihrer
        Einladung folgen würde.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wollen Sie es mir nicht für Rechthaberei auslegen, wenn ich endlich bemerke: Halten Sie
        es für möglich, daß eine Wahrheit partiell ist? Ich glaube, daß alle Ausstrahlungen der
        Wahrheit wieder Wahrheiten sind, wie umgekehrt alle Ausstrahlungen eines Irrthums wiederum
        nur Irrtümer sein müssen. Nun, da Sie mir teilweise, „zustimmen“ (wie Sie selbst
          andeuten),<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Reference is to the
          last words of paragraph 6 of <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-13-22_1">OJ 13/22,
            [1]</tei:ref>: “teils zuzustimmen teils zu entgegnen.” </tei:note> scheinen Sie dort –
        psychologisch kann der Prozess nicht anders gedeutet werden – mindestens subjektiv eine
        Wahrheit zu finden; sollte<tei:add place="interlinear-above">n</tei:add> nun mit dieser auch
        von Ihnen selbst als Wahrheit angenommenen Erkenntnis zugleich Irrtümer verbunden sein
          können?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">No paragraph-break is
          original.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Jedenfalls danke ich Ihnen herzlichst für Ihre freundliche Gesinnung, die in der
        teilweisen Zustimmung u. in der Einladung zum Ausdruck kommt u. zeichne </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-80">Ihr ergebener</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70">H. Schenker</tei:signed><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1913-07-05">5. 7. 1913</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>Dr. Rudolf Réti</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="ident-10">Musician</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000706"
            >Sir</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Your friendly invitation<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> obligates me
        to <tei:supplied reason="clarity">offer</tei:supplied> the following candid explanation: I
        have (leaving aside the travails of overwork) also always kept my distance from the <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002429">International Music Society</tei:rs> on the
        grounds that by the history of music I understand simply the history of technique, but under
        the latter <tei:supplied reason="clarity">I understand</tei:supplied> somewhat more than it
        is made out to be in textbooks of composition and analyses up to the present day. Added to
        that there is a personal aspect. From reliable quarters I heard that <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000003">Professor Guido Adler</tei:rs> – to whom I have spoken
          <tei:supplied>only</tei:supplied> two or three times in my life, and from this have come
        to know him as a fine man – in his seminar dubbed me many times a mere “dilettante,” in
        spite of the fact that the seminar, virtue, and<tei:supplied/> his own independence
          <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of mind</tei:supplied> ought, instead of an insult, to have
        imposed on him the duty of <tei:supplied reason="clarity">relying on</tei:supplied>
        objective evidence.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> Ultimately, the world of
        errors is so great that one can easily drum up a couple of arguments when it is a matter of
        discrediting something uncongenial. And if one genuinely has truth on one’s side, then the
        evidence <tei:pb n="2"/> falls into place of its own accord. I would be ashamed were I to
        invalidate someone else’s dissenting opinion by any other means than through evidence.
        Ultimately truth is a region, dogmatism as such does not retain its validity for any length
        of time. Please understand that I don’t wish to embarrass <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000003">Professor Adler</tei:rs> vis-á-vis myself, and that that would be
        unavoidable if I were to accept your invitation.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Please do not take it as dogmatism on my part, in conclusion, if I observe: Do you
        consider it possible that a truth can be partial? I believe that all things that emanate
        from a truth are themselves truths, just as conversely all things that emanate from an error
        must themselves be nothing more than errors. Now since you partly “agree” with me (as you
        yourself intimate),<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> on that point you appear
        – the process cannot be interpreted other than psychologically – at least subjectively to
        find a truth. Should, then, errors at the same time be bound up with that insight, which you
        yourself have accepted as truth?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>At any rate, I thank you most cordially for your friendly attitude, which finds
        expression in your partial agreement <tei:supplied reason="clarity">with me</tei:supplied>
        and in your invitation.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-80">Your devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70">H. Schenker</tei:signed><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1913-07-05">July 5, 1913</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
