<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2566" sdoID="OC-1-B-19-20">OC 1 B/19-20</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="JK" scope="sole">Jeanette Kornfeld's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006, 2021</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2006, 2021</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2021</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2011-03-05" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002705">FriedmannH ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002699">DeutschS ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">letter</tei:rs>
      <dc:title>Handwritten draft letter from Schenker to Hugo Friedmann, dated March 12,
        1917</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1917-03-12T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2021-09-23</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>In light of the bequests to him in Mrs. Deutsch's will, Schenker seems to
        remind Friedmann that she had also placed at his disposal in 1916 a sum of 10,000 Marks to
        support his future publications. He wishes to make clear that that sum remains in place in
        addition to the legacy and pension bestowed on him now in her will. He also expresses the
        misgivings he has on the stipends implemented via the will. He is also anxious not to have
        lost the first pension payment.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Kurator; curator; Verlassenschaft; estate; Legat; legacy; Geld; money;
        Erblasserin; deceased; Schülerin; female pupil; theoretisch; theoretical; Arbeit; work;
        project; Honorar; honorarium; fee; Verleger; publisher; Antrag; proposal; imansipieren;
        emancipate; Betrag; sum; Risiko; risk; Verewigte; deceased female; Vorteil; advantage; Zins;
        interest; Vergeltung; reciprocation; Stipendium; stipend; Mangel; shortage; Kandidat;
        candidate; Juror; Rente; payout; Saison; teaching year</dc:subject>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000257">Hugo Friedmann</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address rend="indent-80">
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#JK"/>(<tei:hi rend="underline">an <tei:rs type="person"
                key="entity-000257">D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi>
              Friedmann</tei:rs></tei:hi>)</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Verlassenschafts-<tei:unclear reason="reading"
            >Wirkung</tei:unclear></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Sophie
            Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000257"
            >Doktor</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">The final
            version of this letter – if indeed one was made and sent – is not known to survive. No
            response to such a letter is preserved. The draft is entirely clean, with none of the
            usual editings in Henrich's hand.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Dem letzten Schreiben des <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002453"
          >Bankverein</tei:rs>s, Keplerplatz 11, an mich entnehme ich, daß Sie in Ihrer Eigenschaft
        als Kurator der Verlassenschaft<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >“Verlassenschaft”: archaic term for “Hinterlassenschaft.”</tei:note> nach <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000165">Frau Sophie <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >Deutsch</tei:hi></tei:rs> vermutlich schon im Kenntnis daran sind, daß ich abgesehen von
        einem kleinen Legat, einer Rente, auch noch ein Akkreditiv in der Höhe von ursprünglich
        10.000 Mark hatte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker is
          referring to Sofie Deutsch’s letter of January 26, 1916 (<tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-10-4_1">OJ 10/4, [1]</tei:ref>), in which she placed at his disposal at the
          Vienna Banking Association a total sum of 10,000 Marks. – In her will, she left him a
          legacy of 5,000 Kronen and a pension of 2,000 Kronen a year, and also endowed stipends
          with a capital of 20,000,000 Kronen. These latter were first set out in <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-12-52_1">OJ 12/52, [1]</tei:ref>, January 12, 1917, from
          Fritz Mendl. Schenker does not want the 10,000-Mark dispostion to be lost sight
          of.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ohne irgendwie mit nachfolgenden Zeilen eine Entscheidung beeinflüssen zu wollen,
        drängt es mich augenblicklich, blos von dem <tei:hi rend="underline">Sinn</tei:hi> dieser
          Urkunde<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">“Urkunde”: presumably
          Sofie Deutsch’s will.</tei:note> Mitteilung zu machen, da ich aus Gründen öffentlicher
        Natur strengstens darüber wache, daß mein Name in Verbindung mit Geld jeglichem
        Mißverständnis entrückt sei. Die <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165"
          >Erblasserin</tei:rs> war wohl über 15 Jahre meine Schülerin u. konnte so in nächster Nähe
        von Erfolgen meiner theoretischen Arbeiten in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482"
          >Deutschland</tei:rs>, im weiteren Ausland sich leicht überzeugen, obgleich ich ihr nicht
        eben Alles vorzeigte. Nun ging es ihr sehr nahe, daß ich Arbeiten von bereits so anerkannten
        Werth einfach nur verschleudere u. mich mit einem mäßigen Honorar des <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002408">Verleger</tei:rs>s begnügte. Zwar wies dieses
        Honorar für <tei:pb n="2"/> österreichische Verhältnisse u. am schwierigen Absatz so überaus
        anspruchsvoller Arbeiten wie der meinen gemessen gewiß eine beträchtliche Höhe auf, dennoch
        hatte <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Fr. D.</tei:rs> mit ihrer Empfindung Recht.
        So hat sie denn an einem Neujahrstage<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial"
          place="foot">There is no diary entry corresponding to this account. According to
          Schenker’s diary, the event took place on September 9, 1915. </tei:note> im Gasthaus, wo
        sie mit mir nach den Stunden zu speisen pflegte, mich mit dem Antrag überrascht, meine
        künftigen großen Werke auf meine eigene Rechnung zu stellen, um mich vom Verleger zu
        imansipieren, wozu sie eben den erforderlichen Betrag beistellen wolle. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Mir fiel es gewiß nicht leicht, auf das jährlich stipulierte Honorar des <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002408">Verleger</tei:rs>s zu verzichten, dessen ich ja
        jenseits aller Absatzsorgen sicher war. Umsoweniger, als bis zum Erscheinen des <tei:rs
          type="work" key="entity-001727">nächsten großen Bandes</tei:rs>, sagen wir im J. 1920,
        1921 schon 5–6 Jahre vorflossen sein würden, die mir den Betrag schon in beinahe derselben
        Höhe unmittelbar in meine Tasche eingebracht hätten, wie ihn <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000165">Fr. D.</tei:rs> ausgesetzt hatte. Zudem kam das Risiko, daß wegen
        Erkrankung oder Todesfalls der nächste Band gar nicht hätte fertiggestellt werden können, so
        daß ich bis dahin eben nur den Verlust des <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408"
          >Verleger</tei:rs>honorars hätte tragen müssen. <tei:pb n="3"/> Nichtsdestoweniger habe
        ich, schon aus rein ethischen Gründen, den Antrag der <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000165">Erblasserin</tei:rs> dankbar angenommen, u. mich über ihren Wunsch vom
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">Verleger</tei:rs> losgesagt, den sie
          <tei:hi rend="underline">wiederholt</tei:hi> auch <tei:hi rend="underline">vor</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">Zeugen</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">aussprach</tei:hi>. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Die Form, die die <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Verewigte</tei:rs> wählte,
        mag in erster Linie davon herrühren, daß ich jeglichen <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >persönlichen</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">Vorteil</tei:hi>, sogar den Zinsengenuß der Summe <tei:hi
          rend="underline">ablehnte</tei:hi> u. diese lediglich, ohne Zinsen u. auch nur eben
        eventuell dem Werk zudachte. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Daß <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Fr. D.</tei:rs> meiner eigenen großen
        materiellen Opfer sich völlig bewußt war, geht aus dem Wortlaut ihres Schreibens an
          mich<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Presumably <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-10-4_1">OJ 10/4, [1]</tei:ref>, January 26, 1916, in
          which she speaks of his “selfless work in the interests of his sacred art.”</tei:note>
        selbst hervor, worin sie jene ausdrücklich selbst bestätigt. Das Schreiben habe ich im
        Original Herrn Dr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000902">S. Türkel</tei:rs> übergeben. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wenn ich den Antrag der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Fr. D.</tei:rs>
        überhaupt akseptiert habe, so tat ich es außerdem aus dem Bewußtsein, ihr damit Gelegenheit
        zur Vergeltung so vieler Mühen außerhalb der Stunden u. jenseits des Unterrichtes, die ich
        um sie so viele Jahre trug, zu geben. Aus demselben Bewußtsein heraus werde ich das kleine
        Legat sowie die Rente beziehen, da es meine Art ist, erst <tei:pb n="4"/> dann ein Gebotenes
        anzunehmen, nachdem ich es schon vorher vielfach vorausgegeben. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Die Gelegenheit dieser Zeilen ergreife ich, sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000257">Doktor</tei:rs>, gerne noch dazu, Ihnen meinen Standpunkt in der
          <tei:hi rend="underline">Stipendialangelegenheit</tei:hi> anzudeuten. Diese ist eine
        Ueberraschung auch für mich gewesen, wenn auch eine erste sehr flüchtige gesprächsweise
        Anregung von mir den Anstoß gegeben haben mag, die schon vielleicht 10 Jahre zurückliegt.
        Bis zur Stunde kenne ich weder die Höhe, noch die weitere Form der Stipendien. Dennoch muß
        ich auch Ihnen gegenüber wiederholen, was ich schon dem Herrn Kammerrat <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000590">Mendl</tei:rs> u. Herrn Dr. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000902">Türkel</tei:rs> darüber sagte: ich befürchte, daß ich den Wunsch
          <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="italic">inverted material (opening
            draft letter to Hertzka) canceled</tei:hi></tei:note> der <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000165">Erblasserin</tei:rs>, so sehr er mich ehrt, kaum werde erfüllen
        können, u. zw. nur aus Mangel an geeignetem Kandidaten- <tei:pb n="5"/> Material. Vor kurzem
        habe ich aus demselben Grunde die sehr schmeichelhafte Berufung zum Juroramt der <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-006973">Frh. Rothschild’schen Künstlerstiftung</tei:rs>
        (mit Prof. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000003">Guido Adler</tei:rs> u. Pr. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000310">Alfr. Grünfeld</tei:rs>) abgelehnt.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">The Rothschild Artists’ Foundation had
          written to Schenker on December 3, 1916, inviting him to join its panel of jury members
          along with Guido Adler and Alfred Grünfeld (OJ 12/26, [2]). Schenker declined. It may be
          that reluctance to serve alongside Adler played a part in his refusal. The President of
          the Jewish Community wrote to Schenker regretting his decision
              (<tei:bibl><tei:author>Hellmut Federhofer</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Heinrich
              Schenker nach Tagebüchern ...</tei:title></tei:bibl>, p. 54, n. 8). Also mentioned in
          DLA 69.930/4, September 12, 1918, to August Halm.</tei:note> Wieder sind es Gründe, die in
        meiner öffentlichen Wirksamkeit liegen, die mir verbieten, Arbeiten zu prämieren, die nicht
        den von mir selbst aufgestellten Forderungen genügen. Schon jetzt, in Verbindung mit
        mehreren Instanzen gebe ich mir die erdenklichste Mühe, nach würdigen Kandidaten
        auszuspähen, aber ob ich über 3–4 Personen hinauskomme, bezweifle ich. Noch will ich nicht
        das letzte Wort gesprochen haben. Ich höre, daß im Falle der Nichtvergebung das Stipendium
        an den <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-0002425">Verein z. Aussp.</tei:rs>
        zurückfiele; es ist recht so, denn besser hungernde Kinder sättigen, als unfähige Musiker
        überflüssigerweise züchten. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Endlich noch ein Wort: ich warte nur die Entscheidung darüber ab, ob die Rente
        Jänner–Juli 1917 zur Auszahlung gelangt, selbstverständlich <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >nach</tei:hi> Erledigung aller Abhandlungen, gelangen wird. Sollte dies nicht der Fall
        sein, so müßte ich freilich nachträglich die <tei:hi rend="underline">Honorar</tei:hi>-
          <tei:pb n="6"/> forderung auch für Jänner bis Ende Juni anmelden,<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot">As encouraged by Türkel in <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OC-16-27-29">OC 16/27-29</tei:ref>, March 10,
          1917.</tei:note> da ich ein <tei:hi rend="underline">Saison</tei:hi>honorar<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn09" type="editorial" place="foot">“Saisonhonorar”: by “Saison” Schenker
          means his teaching year, October to June; the “Honorar” is the fee that each pupil pays at
          specified points during that year.</tei:note> von meinen Schülern beziehe, u. es auch von
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Fr. D.</tei:rs> all die vielen Jahre her bezogen
        habe </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mit ausgezeichneter Hochachtung</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20"><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"
          >unsigned</tei:note></tei:salute><tei:lb/>
        <tei:date when="1917-03-12">12. März. 1917.</tei:date>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#JK"/>(<tei:hi rend="underline">to <tei:rs type="person"
                key="entity-000257">Dr. Friedmann</tei:rs></tei:hi>)</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">Operation</tei:unclear> of estate
            of</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Sophie
            Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Dear Dr. <tei:supplied><tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000257">Friedmann</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
            type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>From the most recent letter of the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002453">Bank
          Association</tei:rs>, Keplerlatz 11, to me, I gather that you in your capacity as Curator
        of the estate<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> of <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000165">Mrs Sofie <tei:hi rend="underline">Deutsch</tei:hi></tei:rs> are
        probably aware of the fact that I, besides a small legacy and a pension, also had a letter
        of credit in the amount originally of 10,000 Marks.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
          type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Without in any way wishing to influence a decision with what I am about to write, I
        feel compelled at this moment to acquaint you with just the <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >spirit</tei:hi> of this document,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> since
        for reasons that are public in nature I am acutely concerned that my name be clear of any
        misunderstanding in connection with money. The <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165"
          >deceased</tei:rs> was a pupil of mine for well over fifteen years and was readily
        convinced of the imminent successes of my theoretical works in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002482">Germany</tei:rs> and further afield, albeit I did not show her
        absolutely everything. Now it irked her greatly that I sell off at simply rock-bottom prices
        works the value of which is already so well-recognized, and contented myself with a mediocre
        honorarium from my <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">publisher</tei:rs>. True
        enough, this honorarium certainly represents a tidy sum by <tei:pb n="2"/> Austrian
        standards, and measured in terms of the difficult sales of such thoroughly highbrow works as
        my own; nevertheless <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Mrs. D.</tei:rs> was right in
        what she felt. Thus it was that one New Year’s Day<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05"
          type="footnote"/> in a restaurant where she used to eat with me after lessons she
        surprised me with a proposal to place my future major works on an independent financial
        footing for me in order to emancipate me from the publisher, for which purpose she wished to
        provide the requisite sum of money.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>It did not come easily to me to forego the <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002408">publisher</tei:rs>’s annually stipulated honorarium, with which I was
        at least secure against all worries about sales. All the less so since by the time the
          <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001727">next large volume</tei:rs> came out – let’s say in
        1920 or 1921 – five or six years would have gone by that would already have netted me direct
        to my pocket almost the same figure as <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Mrs.
          D.</tei:rs> had settled <tei:supplied reason="clarity">on me</tei:supplied>. Add to that
        the risk that through illness or death the next volume might never be completed, so that by
        that time I would have had to bear just the loss of the <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002408">publisher</tei:rs>’s honorarium. <tei:pb n="3"/> Nonetheless, on
        purely ethical grounds alone, I accepted the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165"
          >deceased</tei:rs>’s proposal with gratitude, and on the basis of her wish relinquished my
        claim upon the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">publisher</tei:rs> – a wish
        that she expressed <tei:hi rend="underline">repeatedly</tei:hi>, even <tei:hi
          rend="underline">in front of witnesses</tei:hi>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>The form that the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">deceased</tei:rs> chose may
        primarily be due to the fact that I <tei:hi rend="underline">declined</tei:hi> any <tei:hi
          rend="underline">personal advantage</tei:hi>, even the benefit of interest on the sum, and
        intended the latter simply, without interest and even perhaps only for the work.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>That <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Mrs. D.</tei:rs> was fully aware of my
        own great material sacrifice is evident from the very wording of her letter to me,<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> in which she herself asserts the former expressly.
        I have handed the letter over in the original to Dr. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000902">S. Türkel</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>If I accepted Mrs. D.’s proposal at all, I did so, what is more, consciously in order
        thereby to give her the opportunity to reciprocate the so very many troubles that I took on
        her behalf over so many years outside the lessons and above and beyond my teaching. Out of
        the same consciousness, I shall accept the small legacy as well as the pension, for it is my
        way to accept <tei:pb n="4"/> what is offered me only after I have already given of myself
        many times over.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I am glad to seize this opportunity also, dear Dr. <tei:supplied><tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000257">Friedmann</tei:rs></tei:supplied>, to indicate to you where I stand
          <tei:hi rend="underline">on the matter of the stipends</tei:hi>. The latter has taken even
        me by surprise, albeit the impetus for it may have come from a first suggestion from me made
        very fleetingly in conversation, which probably goes back all of ten years. Still now, I
        know neither the amount nor the precise form of the stipends. Nevertheless, I must reiterate
        also to you what I have already said on the subject to Chamber Counsellor <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000590">Mendl</tei:rs> and Dr. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000902">Türkel</tei:rs>: I fear that I will scarcely be able to fulfill
          <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="italic">inverted material (opening
            draft letter to Hertzka) canceled</tei:hi></tei:note> the wishes of the <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000165">deceased</tei:rs>, greatly though it does me honor, for
        the specific reason of the shortage of suitably qualified <tei:pb n="5"/> candidate
        material. I recently declined for the same reasons the most flattering summons to serve on
        the jury of the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-006973">Rothschild Artists’
          Foundation</tei:rs> (with Prof. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000003">Guido
          Adler</tei:rs> and Prof. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000310">Alfred
          Grünfeld</tei:rs>).<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> Once again, these are
        reasons that lie in my public field of operation, and which prohibit me from awarding prizes
        to works that do not meet the demands that I myself set up. Already, now, in connection with
        several instances I take the greatest imaginable trouble to keep a lookout for worthy
        candidates, but I doubt if I will come up with more than three or four people. This is not,
        however, my last word on the subject. I hear that in the event of the stipend not being
        awarded it is to revert to the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-0002425">Association
          for the Feeding</tei:rs>. – and rightly so, for better to feed up hungry children than
        gratuitously to nurture unskilled musicians.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Just one final word: I await the decision as to whether the pension for January–July
        1917 will be paid out, naturally <tei:hi rend="underline">after</tei:hi> all the
        transactions have been completed. Should this not be the case, then I would be obliged,
        admittedly belatedly, to submit my <tei:pb n="6"/> claim for the <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >honorarium</tei:hi> also for January to end of June,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08"
          type="footnote"/> since I receive a <tei:hi rend="underline">seasonal</tei:hi> fee<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn09" type="footnote"/> from my pupils and have received this for all of
        the many years from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Mrs. D.</tei:rs></tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">With kind regards,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20"><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"
          >unsigned</tei:note></tei:salute><tei:lb/>
        <tei:date when="1917-03-12">March 12, 1917</tei:date>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
