<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2142" sdoID="OC-18-32-33">OC 18/32-33</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HW" scope="sole">Hans Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2008</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2018</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-10-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated November 28, 1932</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1932-11-28T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2018-10-16</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Weisse is uneasy about disparity among translations of Schenker's writings
        into English, and suggests that he work with potential translators to arrive at an agreed
        set of technical terms. He has renewed contact with Vrieslander, who has sent him a copy of
        his recently published songs and Ländler. His work in New York is going well and his family
        is thriving, but he sees and hears about a great deal of suffering, on account of the
        economic collapse in America.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Übersetzung; Uebersetzung; translation; Vortrag; lecture; Schüler; pupil;
        Ausdruck; term; Deutung; interpretation; Version; Terminus; technical term; Theorie; theory;
        Eindeutigkeit; clarity; Wirkung; effect; Lehre; theory; teaching; Übersetzungsantrag;
        translation proposal; Entscheidung; decision; Einheitlichkeit; uniformity; ominös; ominous;
        Korrespondenz; correspondence; Verbitterung; bitterness; gestorben; dead; Klasse; class;
        postgraduate; Elend; suffering; Zusammenbruch; collapse; Kinder; children; Kurs; course;
        Studenzahl; enrollment</dc:subject>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:lb/><tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#HW"/><tei:date
            when="1932-11-28">28. Nov. 32</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber verehrter <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"
            >Meister</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">This
            letter is kept in a batch of correspondence concerning an English edition of <tei:title
              level="m">Harmonielehre</tei:title>, and so is separated from the bulk of letters from
            Weisse to Schenker in OJ 15/16. (In the OC Finding List, it is wrongly dated as November
            28, 1933.) Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/6, p. 3796,
            December 9, 1932: "Von Weisse (Br.): schlechtere Verhältnisse auch in Amerika; er möchte
            mit dem Uebersetzer verbunden sein wegen Einheitlichkeit der termini; hält Kurse an der
            Universität ab." ("From Weisse (letter): financial circumstances are also very bad in
            America; he would like to make contact with the translator with regard to uniformity of
            terminology; he is giving courses at the University.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>ich habe mit meiner ersten Nachricht absichtlich ein bischen zurückgehalten, weil ich
        mir dachte, dass erst „was geschen sein muss“ bevor ich Ihnen schreibe. Nun, so viel ist
        bisher auch nicht geschehn, aber ich möchte Ihnen meine Freude darüber ausdrücken, dass nun
        der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000577">Marx</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Joseph Marx, Professor of Theory at the Vienna Akademie, had
          hoped to use an updated version of Schenker's <tei:title level="m"
            >Harmonielehre</tei:title> for his pupils.</tei:note> den Weg zu Ihnen gefunden hat, und
        bin sehr neugierig zu erfahren, zu welchen Ergebnissen Ihre Untersuchung geführt hat. Es ist
        freilich lächerlich, wenn man denkt, was Sie inzwischen alles geleistet haben – aber man
        findet da erst den richtigen Massstab um sich vorzustellen, dass die, die heute Ihre <tei:rs
          type="work" key="entity-001724"><tei:title>Harmonielehre</tei:title></tei:rs> propagieren
        in dreissig Jahren vielleicht die Eroica lesen können werden (nämlich Ihre!)<tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">.</tei:supplied><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Nearly thirty years have passed since <tei:title level="m"
            >Harmonielehre</tei:title> was first published; Weisse is hoping that, thirty years from
          now, people will have read and understood Schenker's analysis of the "Eroica" Symphony,
          recently published in <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001752"><tei:title level="j"
              >Meisterwerk</tei:title> III</tei:rs> (1930).</tei:note> Die Aussicht wäre gar nicht
        so schlecht. —<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">No paragraph-break
          at this point in the original, merely em-rule.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Was den <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000927">Herrn aus Brooklyn</tei:rs><tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Arthur Waldeck had approached Schenker
          by letter first on August 27, 1929 (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-15-7_1">OJ
            15/7, [1]</tei:ref>), to which Schenker replied on September 23 (<tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-44_1">OJ 5/44, [1]</tei:ref>). Waldeck had written to
          Schenker on September 22, 1932 (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-18-34">OC
            18/34</tei:ref>), specifically regarding a translation of <tei:title level="m"
            >Harmonielehre</tei:title>, to which Schenker had responded by postcard on October 16
          (NYma [1]) and more fully on November 8 (NYma [2]), specifying terms and conditions. To
          this Waldeck had replied on November 21 (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-18-35">OC
            18/35</tei:ref>), promising a sample translation, which Schenker received on December
          27, and passed on to Weisse on December 31 (<tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-5-44_3">OJ 5/44, [3]</tei:ref>).</tei:note> angeht, so erinnere ich mich, dass
        er meinen Vorträgen voriges Jahr beigewohnt hat. Sie schreiben mir, Sie hätten ihm
        geantwortet, was Ihnen <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000420">Kalmus</tei:rs> geraten
        hat: was aber war das, ich wüsste das gar zu gern. Aus folgendem Grunde:<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">No paragraph-break at this point in the
          original.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Hier hat sich nun ein anderer Schüler von mir (der) <tei:pb n="2"/> erst heuer
        angefangen hat) zum Worte gemeldet und möchte auch übersetzen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Probably <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000021">Frederick
            Auslander</tei:rs>, who also lived in Brooklyn and who wrote to Schenker on January 5
          and April 8, 1933 (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-18-29">OC 18/29</tei:ref> and
            <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-18-30">OC 18/30</tei:ref>).</tei:note> Viele
        Dinge besonders spätere Ausdrücke wie <tei:term>Ursatz</tei:term> –
          <tei:term>U.-Linie</tei:term> – <tei:term>Übergreifstechnik</tei:term> etc. lassen sich
        nun nicht übersetzen und es besteht die Gefahr<tei:supplied reason="punctuation"
          >,</tei:supplied> dass je mehr Leute übersetzen, desto mehr Deutungen, Versionen und
        Termini auftauchen können, was meiner Ansicht nach, der Eindeutigkeit der Lehre gar nicht
        entsprechend wäre und die Wirkung ungünstig beeinflüssen könnte. Nun bin ich der erster, der
        Ihre Lehre hier öffentlich lehrt. Wäre es also nicht besser<tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> durch den <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002408">Verlag</tei:rs> zu erwirken, dass alle diejenigen, die mit
        Übersetzungsanträgen auftauchen, sich an mich wenden müssen, damit wir in gegenseitiger
        Einvernahme die Entscheidung über die Übersetzung gewisser Ausdrücke Ihrer Lehre treffen und
        so die Einheitlichkeit der Ausdrücke auch in englischer Sprache sicherstellen können. Das
        ist etwas<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> was mir für die Übersetzung
        Ihrer Schriften sehr wesentlich erscheint.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich behaupte gar nicht, dass die Übersetzer meine Ausdrücke und Übersetzungen stets
        übernehmen müssen; im Gegenteil<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> ich bin
        mir bewusst<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> vieles nur behalfsmässig zu
        übertragen. Jedenfalls wäre ich froh, wenn ich was von ihnen lernen könnte – obgleich ich
        das nicht erwarte. Aber der Sache wäre sicherlich gedient, würde man von allem Anfang an,
        die Einheitlichkeit der Ausdrücke auch für die Übersetzung ins Auge fassen. —</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> Mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> bin
        ich inzwischen selbst in Verbindung getreten. Seit der ominösen Korrespondenz während des
        Krieges (es handelte sich um die zugedachte Festschrift<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Weisse's opposition to a Festschrift for Schenker's 50th
          birthday in June 1918, advocated by Vrieslander and others, is articulated in a letter of
          February 26, 1918 (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-15-16_34">OJ 15/16,
            [34]</tei:ref>).</tei:note>) habe ich nichts mehr von ihm gehört gehabt. Seine
        Verbitterung, die hinter jedem Wort, das er schreibt, fühlbar wird<tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> ist nur zu begreiflich. Er hat mir seine Lieder und
        Ländler geschickt.[<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09" type="editorial" place="foot">Vrieslander's
          recently published songs and ländler were highly commended in a review by
            <tei:bibl>Schenker, <tei:title level="a">Eine Anzeige und eine
              Selbstanzeige,</tei:title>
            <tei:title level="j">Der Kunstwart</tei:title> 46 (December 1932), 194‒96</tei:bibl>.
          Weisse wrote a long letter to Vrieslander about them, which is mentioned in <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-15-16_89">OJ 15/16, [89]</tei:ref> and subsequent letters
          from early 1933.</tei:note>]</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wie es mit <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title>dem Freien
            Satz</tei:title></tei:rs> steht bin ich schon sehr begierig zu erfahren.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Gestern traf mich die Nachricht, dass <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005758"
          >Khuner</tei:rs> gestorben sei, ich habe aber von seiner Familie noch gar nichts gehört.
        Es tut mir sehr, sehr leid um den lieben und feinen Menschen, der er war. Ob Sie wohl das
        Geld schon erhalten haben?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich freue mich sehr, Ihnen mitteilen zu können, dass ich nun Ihre Flagge auch auf
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-005886">Universitätsboden</tei:rs> gehisst habe:
        Ich habe eine Klasse von 20 Hörern da, die Leute sind all recht arg mitgenommen von dem
        ganzen, ich meine, es geht <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overwritten">I</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="superimposed">i</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>hnen sehr nah (so viel mir scheint), umsomehr als es schon alle zum Diplom
        gebracht haben. (Meine Klasse ist eine sogenannte: postgraduate work <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">Klasse</tei:add>.) —<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10"
          type="editorial" place="foot">No paragraph-break at this point in the original, merely
          em-rule.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002873">New York</tei:rs> und <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002510"><tei:country>Amerika</tei:country></tei:rs> haben sich sehr stark
        verändert seit dem Vorjahr: Das Elend ist grenzenlos auch hier, wohin man hört und blickt
        das Gleiche wie bei uns.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11" type="editorial" place="foot">"bei
          uns": Weisse means his (and Schenker's) homeland, i.e. Austria.</tei:note> Die
        Zusammenbrüche sind den Dimensionen des Landes und des ehemaligen Wohlstandes angepasst und
        deshalb auch viel gewaltiger als bei uns.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> Der Besuch der Schüle, alles geht erschreckend zurück. – Es ist
        wirklich mit dem Vorjahr kaum zu vergleichen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Uns geht es aber doch noch ganz gut. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000952"
          >Hertha</tei:rs> beginnt sich einzuleben. Das Wirtschaften ist doch umso vieles angenehmer
        und leichter. Wir haben ein sehr nettes deutsches Mädchen, die vormittags den Dienst im
        Hause versieht und nachmittag die Kinder überwacht. Die Kinder selbst gedeihen und sind
        täglich zu ihrer grössten Freude in dem sehr schönen Central Park, wo es Schaukeln und
        Rutschbahn und dsgl. mehr gibt.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>An der <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002454">Mannes Schule</tei:rs> beginne
        ich die öffentl. Vorträge erst im Jänner. Einen Kurs will ich ja ganz Ihrer Lehre widmen. Ob
        der zu stande kommt hängt aber von der Anzahl der Subscribenten ab.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>An der <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002454">Mannes Schule</tei:rs> hab ich
        mein kontraktlich ausbedungene Stundenzahl nocht nicht voll<tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> doch habe ich gegen 17 Stunden wöchentlich
        besetzt.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich hoffe wieder bald einmal von Ihnen zu hören.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">An Sie beide die herzlichsten Grüsse, auch von <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000952">Hertha</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person"
          >Hans</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:lb/><tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#HW"/><tei:date
            when="1932-11-28">November 28, 1932</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear, revered <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>I intentionally held a bit back from my first report, because I thought I should see
        how things are unfolding before writing to you. Now, not much has happened yet, but I should
        like to express my delight in hearing that now <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000577"
          >Marx</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> has found his way to you,
        and I am very curious to learn of the results to which your investigation has led. It is of
        course ludicrous, when one considers all that you have accomplished in the meantime, but it
        is only now that people have found that correct yardstick so that one can imagine that those
        who today are propounding your <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724"><tei:title level="m"
            >Theory of Harmony</tei:title></tei:rs> will perhaps be able to read the "Eroica" (i.e.
          <tei:hi rend="italic">your</tei:hi> "Eroica"!) in thirty years' time.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> The prospects do not seem so bad after
          all.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Regarding the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000927">gentleman from
          Brooklyn</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> I recall that he
        attended my lectures last year. You wrote to me that you replied to him, on the advice of
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000420">Kalmus</tei:rs>; what you said is something I
        would only too gladly like to know, for the following reason:<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06"
          type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Here, another pupil of mine <tei:pb n="2"/> (who just began this year) has written to
        say that he would also like to translate.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/>
        Many things, especially the later terms like <tei:term>Ursatz</tei:term>,
          <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> and <tei:term>Übergreifstechnik</tei:term>, simply cannot be
        translated, and the danger arises that, the more people who are involved in translating, the
        more the interpretations, versions and technical terms could proliferate; this is something
        which, in my view, would not be good for the clarity of the theory and could have an
        unfavorable effect upon it. Now, I am the first person to teach your theory here in public:
        would it not be better to arrange through the <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002408">publisher</tei:rs> that all those who come up with translation
        proposals be required to apply to me, so that we can come to an agreement, through
        reciprocal study, about the translation of specific terms in your theory, thus being able to
        secure the unity of the terminology also in the English language? That is something that
        seems very important for the translation of your writings.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I am most certainly not insisting that the translators must always adopt my expressions
        and translations; on the contrary I am conscious of having translated much only in a
        provisional manner. In any event, I would be happy if I could learn something from them ‒
        although I don't expect that I will. But the cause would surely be served if, at the very
        outset, one could face the problem of unity of terminology also for the translation
          <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of your work</tei:supplied>. —</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> As to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>, I
        have in the meantime been in contact with him myself. After the ominous correspondence
        during the war (concerning the planned Festschrift<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08"
          type="footnote"/>) I had not heard anything more from him. His bitterness, which is
        palpable in every word that he writes, is only too understandable. He sent me a copy of his
        songs and Ländler.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>I am most keen to learn how things are going with <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001728"><tei:title level="m">Free Composition</tei:title></tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Yesterday I heard the news that <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005758"
          >Khuner</tei:rs> has died; I have not, however, heard anything from his family. I am truly
        very sorry for the dear, worthy man that he was. Have you already received the money from
        him?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>It gives me great joy to be able to report to you that your flag has also been hoisted
        over <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-005886">university territory</tei:rs>: I have a
        class of twenty there; the people are all intensely involved with everything: I mean that
        they seem quite attracted to it (as far as I can see), which is all the more impressive
        given that they have already reached the diploma stage. (My class is a so-called
        "postgraduate work" <tei:add place="interlinear-above">class</tei:add>.) —<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn10" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002873">New York</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002510"><tei:country>America</tei:country></tei:rs> have changed radically
        since last year. The suffering is boundless, wherever one looks and listens, the same as
        with us.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn11" type="footnote"/> The collapse has affected the
        length and breadth of the country, and because of the previous state of prosperty the
        situation is much more brutal than it is with us. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> The number of pupils attending schools, everything is in a frightful
        decline ‒ one can hardly compare things with the previous year.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>And yet we are still faring very well. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000952"
          >Hertha</tei:rs> is beginning to acclimate herself. Getting things done is so much more
        agreeable and easier. We have a nice German girl, who sees to the house in the morning and
        looks after the children in the evening. The children themselves are thriving and spend
        every time, to their great delight, in the beautiful Central Park, where there are swings
        and slides and suchlike.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>At the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002454">Mannes School</tei:rs>, I shall
        begin my official lectures only in January. One of my courses is to be dedicated entirely to
        your theory: whether it materializes will, however, depend on the number of
        subscribers.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>My contractually agreed number of hours at the <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002454">Mannes School</tei:rs> is still not full, but I am occupied
        approximately seventeen hours per week.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I hope I shall hear again soon from you.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">To both of you my most cordial greetings, also from <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000952">Hertha</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person"
          >Hans</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
