<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="1474" sdoID="OC-1-B-9">OC 1B/9</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="major">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="minor">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="OJ" scope="minor">Oswald Jonas's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="LR">
   <tei:persName>Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2015</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
   <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
   <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-03-04" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002698">Halm ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten draft letter from Schenker to Halm, dated by later hand [December 29,
    1916]</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1916-12-29T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2015-04-01</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>In his first letter to Halm, Schenker knows Halm's work and regards him as an
    ally; he affirms that music has few primal laws (Urgesetze) that are immutable. — He cannot
    intercede on Halm's behalf with Universal Edition.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Arbeiten; works; Presse; press; Gegner; opponents; Bazillus; bacterium; Irrtum;
    error; Waffe; weapon; Tendenz; tendency; Könner; able [person]; Kenner; knowledgeable
    [person];Verhältnis; relation; Kreis; circle; Mißverhältnis; disparity; Wissender; informed;
    Unwissender; uninformed; Zerrüttung; disruption; Geplapper; babble; Sterne; stars; Firmament;
    Kern; core; Veränderlichkeit; mutability; Generation; Jugend; youth; Aufsatz; essay; Plan;
    Verleger; publisher</dc:subject>



   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000326">Halm</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:note type="editorial" place="pre-text">This letter is written in pencil in Jeanette
    Schenker’s hand, with pencilled interlinear corrections and additions in Heinrich's hand, and
    with an added paragraph at the bottom in ink in Heinrich's hand. The version given below
    represents only the initial draft in Jeanette's hand, with the later annotation at the end in
    Heinrich's hand.</tei:note>

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#OJ"/>OC 1/B9 Dec. 29, 1916 (see Federhofer,
     134)</tei:dateline><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>In Beantwortung Ihres freundlichen Schreibens,<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Halm's letter is not known to survive. The
     present letter comprises a full sheet of paper, below which are pasted three horizontal strips
     of lined paper. The full sheet is written on the verso of a typed letter from the
     Kriegshilfsbüro (Office for War Relief) dated October 25, 1916. The finished letter is not known to survive.</tei:note> für das ich Ihnen
    herzlichen Dank sage, beeile ich mich zu bestätigen, daß ich Ihre Arbeiten schon seit langem
    kenne u. deren Schicksal in der Presse auch aufmerksam verfolgt habe. Auch stimme ich Ihnen
    vollkommen bei, wenn Sie meinen, daß was uns einigt vorläufig wichtiger zu sein habe, als
    dasjenige was uns trennt; im großen u. ganzen werden Sie indessen wohl bemerkt haben, daß ich im
    Grunde nur sehr unfreiwillig wider Gegner ins Feld ziehe u. es nur dort tue, wo der Gegner im
    spezifisch gefärbter Bazillus des Irrtums ist oder gar selbst zuerst aggressiv geworden
    (darunter verstehe ich natürlich auch das Verschweigen) meine Waffe herausfordert.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Meine Tendenz geht dahin, im seit 2–300 Jahren so übermächtig angewachsenen Kreise der
    Kunstbeflissenen wirkliche Könner u. Kenner der <tei:term>Stimmführung</tei:term> u.
     <tei:term>Harmonie</tei:term> wenn nicht in demselben, so doch zumindest in einem ähnlichen
    Verhältnis hervorzutreiben u. zu erzielen, als es ihrer vor so vielen Jahrhunderten innerhalb
    des kleineren Kreises immerhin noch gegeben hat. Nur in dem leidigen Mißverhältnis zwischen
    Wissenden u. Unwissenden erblicke ich die Ursache der gegenwärtigen Zerrüttung, der Uebermacht
    unserer Gegner, des ewigen Geplappers von Fortschritt u. dgl. m<tei:supplied
     reason="abbreviation">ehr</tei:supplied>. So kommt es denn freilich in letztem Grunde nur eben
    darauf an, wessen Begriffe von <tei:term>Stimmführung</tei:term> u.
     <tei:term>Harmonie</tei:term> die richtigen sind, das heißt mehr im Einklang mit den Werken
    unserer großen Meister, die meinen oder die der Gegner. In dem der Druckerei bald zu
    übergebenden <tei:rs key="entity-001727" type="work">II. Bd. des
      <tei:title>Kontrapunkt</tei:title></tei:rs>es, der sich hauptsächlich mit dem <tei:term>freien
     Satz</tei:term><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">At the date of the
     letter (1916), Schenker was still planning to include the material in <tei:title level="m"
      >Kontrapunkt</tei:title> II as "Part 7," after Part 6, the <tei:title level="a">Bridges to
      Free Composition,</tei:title> but it ended up being greatly expanded to become <tei:title
      level="m">Der freie Satz</tei:title> (see <tei:bibl><tei:author>H. Siegel</tei:author>,
       <tei:title level="a">When 'Freier Satz' was Part of Kontrapunkt: A Preliminary
       Report,</tei:title>
      <tei:title level="j">Schenker Studies 2</tei:title>, ed. <tei:editor>Carl
       Schachter</tei:editor> and <tei:editor>Hedi Siegel</tei:editor> (Cambridge: Cambridge
      University Press, 1999), pp.12–25</tei:bibl>).</tei:note> beschäftigt, glaube ich den Nachweis
    dafür erbracht zu haben, daß auch die Töne, genau so wie z. B. die Sterne am Firmament, nur
    wenige <tei:term>Urgesetz</tei:term>e haben, die desto unverändlicher im Kerne selbst bleiben,
    je veränderlicher, ja in ihrer Veränderlichkeit verwirrend<tei:supplied reason="punctuation"
     >,</tei:supplied> sie sich in den einzelnen Erscheinungen objektivieren. Niemals, davon bin
    mindestens ich selbst überzeugt, kann je eine neue Generation, eine neue Jugend den wenigen
     <tei:term>Urgesetz</tei:term>en auch nur noch eines hinzufügen. Und es wird der Welt das
    überaus beglückende u. dankbare Geschäft harren, sich mit der unendlichen Veränderlichkeit zu
    bescheiden u. in ihr sicher zu wirken, statt nach Regionen zu gelangen in denen auch nichts uns
    wahrnehmbar ist. Nach all dem begreifen Sie, daß ich dem mir angekundigten Aufsatz mit
    wirklichem Interesse entgegensehe.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Was Ihren Plan anlangt, die Klavierübung<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
     place="foot">Piano method: discussed in <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-11-35-2">OJ
      11/35, 2</tei:ref>, January 27, 1917.</tei:note> eventuell bei der “<tei:rs
     key="entity-002408" type="organization">U. E.</tei:rs>“ hier anzubringen, darf ich Ihnen nicht
    verhehlen, daß ich selbst mindestens vorläufig – wie das ja so häufig verkommt – in einem etwas
    gespanntem Verhältnis zum Verleger stehe, so daß sogar meine Ausgabe in <tei:rs
     key="entity-001737" type="work">op. 101</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs key="entity-001738" type="work"
     >106</tei:rs> dadurch in Frage gestellt ist. Doch wäre – wie auch dies so häufig vorkommt –
    möglich, daß sich die Beziehung neuerdings bessert, was ich Ihnen dann selbstverständlich zur
    Mitteilung bringen werde, gerne bereit, Ihnen den Verleger gefügig zu machen.</tei:p>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p><tei:handShift new="#HS"/><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in red
      crayon:</tei:note> Halm, Dez. 1916?</tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#OJ"/>OC 1/B9 Dec. 29, 1916 (see Federhofer,
     134)</tei:dateline><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>In reply to your cordial letter,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
     type="footnote"/> for which I warmly thank you, I hasten to confirm that I have known about
    your works for some time already and have attentively followed their fate in the press. Further,
    I concur with you completely when you say that which unites us must for now be more important
    than that which divides us. All in all, you will meanwhile have noticed that in principle I take
    the field against opponents only very unwillingly, and do it only when the opponent manifests a
    specifically tinged bacterium of the error or, in becoming aggressive themselves first (I
    understand here naturally also remaining silent), provokes my weaponry.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>My tendency is to think that, in the enormously enlarged circle of art enthusiasts over
    the last 200-300 years the genuinely able and knowledgeable in
     <tei:term>voice-leading</tei:term> and <tei:term>harmony</tei:term> can be cultivated and
    achieved, if not in the same relation, then at least in a similar one as still existed, after
    all, so many centuries ago within the smaller circle. I see the cause of the current disruption,
    of the predominance of our opponents, of the unceasing babble about progress and the like,
    solely in the lamentable disparity between the informed and the uninformed. At bottom,
    therefore, it simply depends on whose concepts of <tei:term>voice-leading</tei:term> and
     <tei:term>harmony</tei:term> are the correct ones, that is, are more in accordance with the
    works of our great masters, mine or those of the opponents. In the <tei:rs key="entity-001727"
     type="work">second volume of <tei:title level="m">Counterpoint</tei:title></tei:rs>, soon to be
    delivered to the printer, which deals mainly with <tei:term>free composition</tei:term>,<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> I believe I have adduced evidence that tones, just like
    stars in the firmament, for example, have but few <tei:term>primal law</tei:term>s which remain
    at their core all the more immutable the more mutably ‒ indeed, bewildering in their mutability
    ‒ they manifest themselves in the individual phenomena. Never ‒ of this at least I am convinced
    ‒ can a new generation, a new youth, add even a single law to the few <tei:term>primal
     law</tei:term>s. And awaiting the world will be the exceedingly happy and gratifying business
    of contenting itself with the endless mutability and to work securely within it, instead of
    ending up in regions where nothing is even perceptible to us. After all this, you will
    understand that I look forward to the announced essay with genuine interest.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Regarding your plan possibly to submit the piano method<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
     type="footnote"/> to <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">UE</tei:rs>, I cannot
    conceal from you that for the time being I myself am in a strained relationship with the
    publisher ‒ as so often occurs ‒ so that, accordingly, even my edition of <tei:rs
     key="entity-001737" type="work">Opp. 101</tei:rs> and <tei:rs key="entity-001738" type="work"
     >106</tei:rs> is in question. However, it would be possible ‒ as this too so often happens ‒
    that the relationship will presently improve, which I will of course communicate to you,
     <tei:supplied reason="clarity">and am</tei:supplied> gladly willing to make the publisher
    amenable toward you.</tei:p>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p><tei:handShift new="#HS"/><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in red
      crayon:</tei:note> Halm, Dec. 1916?</tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
