<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="31" sdoID="OC-1-B-34r">OC 1 B/34r</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2101</tei:resp>

  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
   <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
   <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-02-26" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002699">DeutschS ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   
   <dc:title>Handwritten draft letter from Schenker to Türkel, dated February 24, 1918</dc:title>
   
   <dcterms:created>1918-02-24T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-09-25</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker addresses legal obstructions regarding Sofie Deutsch's will, and
    threatens to go back on an earlier disclaimer if he continues to be deprived of the inheritance
    due to him; notifies Türkel that he has already paid out the first stipend, to Otto Vrieslander,
    and has promised the second and third to two composers (unnamed). </dc:description>
   <dc:subject> Verzicht; disclaimer; legacy; honorarium; stipend; pension; Wiener Bank-Verein;
    Vienna Bank Association; Vrieslander, Otto; Ebersberg; München; Munich; Japan; Berlin;
    Vienna</dc:subject>

   
   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000165">DeutschS</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-50">
     <tei:date when="1918-02-24">24. II. 1918</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000902">Doktor</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>


   <tei:p>Indem<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of Türkel's letter
     to Schenker and the writing of this reply are recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/10, p. 845:
     "Von Türkel (Br.): fragt an, ob ich auf dem Standpunkt des Verzichtes vom 1. VI. vergangenen
     Jahres bleibe, anderen Falls müßte ich eine Klage erheben, allerdings aber durch einen andern
     Anwalt, da er selbst Frau Figdor in diesem Falle zu vertreten gesonnen sei; erwähnt, allerdings
     unverbindlich, daß das Legat sichergestellt zu sein scheint. — An Türkel (Br.): wiederhole den
     Verzicht, da ich den Prozess zu vermeiden wünsche, in dem ich unter Anführung von Zeugen die
     Vorausgabe des Wertes erweisen müßte usw. (s. Beilage). Melde bei dieser Gelegenheit die
     Absendung von M. 1020 an Vrieslander nebst Erklärung einer Ehrennotwehr." ("From Türkel
     (letter): inquiring as to whether I intend to abide by my waiver from June 1 of last year,
     otherwise I would have to file a suit, albeit through another lawyer, since he would be
     disposed to represent Mrs. Figdor in the case; he mentions, without however committing himself,
     that the bequest already seemed to be assured. ― To Türkel (letter): I abide by the waiver,
     since I wish to avoid a court case, in that I would use citations from witnesses to prove that
     I have already had to expend the sum etc. (see enclosure). Take the occasion to register that I
     have sent 1,020 Marks to Vrieslander accompanied by a statement in defense of my honor..").
     <!-- XR -->
    </tei:note> ich Ihnen bestens dafür danke, daß Sie mich des Weges zu Ihnen überhoben haben, der
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">wäre</tei:del> mir heute <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ohnehin</tei:add> unausführbar <tei:add place="interlinear-above">gewesen war</tei:add> –,
    beeile ich mich, Ihnen postwendend den von mir schon am 1. 6. 1917 abgegebenen Verzicht<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The disclaimer in question is not known to
     have survived. </tei:note> hiemit <tei:del rend="overstrike">zum zweitenmal u. wieder auch
     schriftlich zu bestätigen</tei:del>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">wiederholen</tei:hi><tei:supplied reason="syntax">.</tei:supplied>
    Abgesehen davon, daß ich der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000223">Frau Figdor</tei:rs>
    <tei:add place="interlinear-above">durchaus</tei:add> nicht im Wege stehen <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">will</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">mag</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> (umsoweniger, als diese Dame Ihrer Mitteilung gemäß seinerzeit gegen das Akkreditiv
    keine Einwände ihrerseits erhob), will ich jeden Prozess <tei:hi rend="underline">vermeiden</tei:hi>, in dem ich unter Anführung von Zeugen den Nachweis dafür erbringen müßte,
    daß ich den Betrag des Akkreditivs <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">im gewissen Sinn</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">eigentlich</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> schon mit meinen Leistungen vorausgegeben, u. durch das Versagen des Schriftstückes
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">auch außerdem</tei:add> beträchtlichste Schaden – zumal
    mitten im Kriege – erlitt.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich würde, sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000902">Doktor</tei:rs>, den
    Verzicht <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">gewiß</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">wohl</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> auch sonst wiederholt haben, auch wenn Sie nicht in der Lage gewesen wären, mir den
    günstigen Stand der Legatsfrage (allerdings unverbindlich) mitzuteilen. <tei:note type="editorial">cued from lower margin:</tei:note> Nach all den gemachten Erfahrungen bin ich
    heute <tei:del rend="overstrike">nach mir</tei:del> auf dieser Frd. Eröffnung gegenüber nur
     praktisch.<tei:note>end cue</tei:note> Den Verzicht sprach ich <tei:del rend="overstrike">schon</tei:del> seinerzeit <tei:add place="interlinear-above">eben schon</tei:add> aus den
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">oben</tei:del> erwähnten Gründen aus; muß <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">ich</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">mir</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> aber freilich vorbehalten, darauf gelegentlich auch öffentlich zurückzukommen für
    den Fall, daß ich über den Gerüsten, <tei:pb n="2"/> die mir die Erbschaft nach der Verewigten
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ganz oder teilweise</tei:add> zu schieben u. zu denen sie
    durch ihre <tei:add place="interlinear-above">große</tei:add> Schätzung meiner Leistung
    unschuldigste Veranlassung gegeben haben mag, noch weiteren Schaden leiden müssten. Wie ich
    schon einmal lange, lange Schaden dadurch leiden mußte, daß man mir blos daraufhin, daß ich den
    jungen <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000743">
     Baron Rothschild
    </tei:rs> unterwies, eine Rente aufdichtete, von der ich weder damals noch heute je eine
    Spur gesehen.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Bei dieser Gelegenheit erlaube ich mir, Ihnen auch mitzuteilen, daß ich am 5. Januar als
    dem Sterbetage der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Frau Deutsch</tei:rs> aus den Mitteln
    des mir <tei:add place="interlinear-above">seinerzeit</tei:add> durch den H. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000590">Kammerrat Mendl</tei:rs> frdl. <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">zudienten</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ausbezahlten</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> Beilegates den <tei:hi rend="underline">ersten</tei:hi> Betrag durch den
     <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002453">
     Wiener Bankverein
    </tei:rs> an H. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">
      Otto Vrieslander
     </tei:rs>, Tonkünstler in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002326">
     Ebersberg
    </tei:rs> b. <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002286">München</tei:rs> zur Auszahlung
    gebracht habe. Damit lüfte ich <tei:add place="interlinear-above">endlich</tei:add> das
    Geheimnis der Ursache, weshalb ich seinerzeit gerade auf diesem Legat mehr <tei:add place="interlinear-above">als</tei:add> auf meinem eigenem Honorar bestand: die „dritte
    Person,“ von der ich Ihnen seinerzeit <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">
     <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">sub rosa</tei:hi>
    </tei:foreign> schrieb, bin nämlich ich selbst.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Sofie Deutsch left Schenker a legacy of 5,000 Kroner to support the printing costs
     of future publications, and a pension of 2,000 Kroner a year; : see OC 12/52, January 12, 1917
     (Mendl to Schenker).</tei:note> Gewissermaßen lag eine Notwehr der Ehre vor, nicht nur meiner
    eigenen, sondern auch <tei:add place="interlinear-above">die</tei:add> der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Frau Deutsch</tei:rs> wie des H. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000590">Kammerrates</tei:rs>. Sie erinnern sich, daß ich keine Lust hatte, die <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Stipendien</tei:hi>sache anzugehen, u. daß ich mich hiezu <tei:add place="interlinear-above">nur</tei:add> durch unendliches Zureden von des <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000590">H. Kammerrats</tei:rs> Seite wie von der Ihren bestimmen
     ließ.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker’s doubts about the
     viability of the stipends are expressed in his letter to Hugo Friedmann, OC 1/19–20, March 12,
     1917, in which he says that he has expressed these also to Fritz Mendel and Siegfried
     Türkel.</tei:note> Angesichts des Schreibens des H. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000590">Kammerrat</tei:rs>s an mich, wie dann auch angesichts des Vorhaltens im Mündlichen hatte
    wohl ich am wenigsten Ursache, je am Zustandekommen der Sti- <tei:pb n="3"/> pendien <tei:add place="interlinear-above">überhaupt</tei:add> zu zweifeln. Nun einmal aber in der Sache,
    verfügte ich über das <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Stipend</tei:hi>ialgeld so, wie es <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Frau Deutsch</tei:rs> von mir erwarten konnte u. wohl auch erwartet
    hat: statt zweifelhafte Produkte zu prämieren, <tei:hi rend="underline">bestellte</tei:hi> ich
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">lieber</tei:add> bei <tei:del rend="overstrike">bei</tei:del> zwei angesehenen Künstlern mir wichtig scheinende Arbeiten u. sagte einem
    dritten Künstler, dessen Namen Sie wohl oft genug in <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000471">Korngold</tei:rs>’s <tei:foreign xml:lang="fre">
     <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Feuilletons</tei:hi>
    </tei:foreign> nebst Zitaten aus seinen autoritativen Urteilen gefunden haben mögen, u. dem
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Frau Deutsch</tei:rs> selbst für die Dauer ihrer Reise
    nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002534">Japan</tei:rs> ihre
    eigenen Stunden <tei:hi rend="underline">zu übergeben vorhatte</tei:hi>, (der auch Referent
    einer der angesehnsten Tagesblätter in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">
     Berlin
    </tei:rs> ist) aufs bestimmteste zu, ihm den Aufenthalt in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Wien</tei:rs> durch das Stiftungsgeld zu erleichtern, wo ich dann
    freilich den Unterricht selbst nur unentgeltlich erteilen wollte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Perhaps Walter Dahms. </tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Diesen Herren gegenüber nannte ich <tei:add place="interlinear-above">nun</tei:add>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">mit</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">Namen</tei:hi> die <tei:hi rend="underline">Quelle der</tei:hi>
    Bescherung – ich mußte es schon darum tun, weil ich nicht in den Verruf auch noch eines
    Geldmäzens kommen wollte, wo ich als Mäzen des Unterrichts ohnehin überbürdet bin. Als die
    Zweifel auftauchten, war es zumindest vor <tei:hi rend="underline">diesen</tei:hi> drei Herren
     <tei:hi rend="underline">zu spät</tei:hi>, einzulenken oder zurückzutreten. Ein anderes war
    dort, wo ich nach Fühlungnahme mit einzelnen Vorlagen mich gleichwohl auf keinen Autor, kein
    Werk noch festlegte.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Der Betrag leitete auf 1020 MK, auf den dritten Teil <tei:pb n="4"/> jenes
     Legates<tei:supplied reason="syntax">.</tei:supplied> Am nächsten 5. Jänner soll dann der
    nächste Musiker drankommen, u. endlich <tei:del rend="overstrike">am überreichsten</tei:del>,
    als dritter, der <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Berliner</tei:hi> Künstler.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="indent-10">Ich konnte leider nicht anders, wie Sie es wohl auch selbst zugeben
    werden.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Mit besten Empfehlungen Ihr ergebener </tei:salute>
    <tei:note type="editorial">unsigned</tei:note>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p>P. S. Sie werden mich <tei:add place="interlinear-above">sehr g. H D</tei:add> sehr
     verbinden, wenn Sie in Ihrem Zuschrift an <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000257">Dr.
      Friedm.</tei:rs> den Verzicht <tei:hi rend="underline">auch von dem Tage aus</tei:hi>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">1. 6. 1917</tei:add>
     <tei:hi rend="underline"> datiere</tei:hi>, an dem ich ihm schrieb zum 1. Male gegeben habe –
     sofern dies nicht irgendwie wider Ihren Interessen streitet. Mir läge an dieser Feststellung
      <tei:hi rend="underline">sehr viel</tei:hi> für jetzt sowohl als für später.</tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-50">
     <tei:date when="1918-02-24">February 24, 1918</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000902">Dr. Türkel</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>In<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> thanking you most warmly for having eased
    my access to you, which <tei:add place="interlinear-above">had without that been</tei:add>
    impossible for me recently, I hasten by return post herewith <tei:del rend="overstrike">for the
     second time and once again in written form to confirm</tei:del> to <tei:hi rend="underline">abide by</tei:hi> the disclaimer already surrendered by me on June 1, 1917.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"/> Apart from the fact that I <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">will</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">may</tei:add>
    </tei:subst>
    <tei:add place="interlinear-above">by no means</tei:add> stand in the way of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000223">Mrs. Figdor</tei:rs> (all the less so as in accordance with your
    communication the latter lady raised no objections at the time on her own part against the
    letter of credit), I will <tei:hi rend="underline">avoid</tei:hi> any legal proceeding that
    would have required my putting forward evidence by summoning witnesses <tei:supplied reason="clarity">to show</tei:supplied> that I have <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">in the strict sense</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">in fact</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> already given the amount of the letter of credit in advance with my
    accomplishments, and have <tei:add place="interlinear-above">in addition also</tei:add> suffered
    the most considerable damage – what’s more, in the midst of the war – through the failure of the
    piece of writing.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>I would, dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000902">Dr. Türkel</tei:rs>, <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">certainly</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">surely</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> otherwise have repeated the disclaimer, even if you had not been in a position to
    convey to me (at any rate without obligation) the favorable position on the legacy question.
     <tei:note type="editorial">cued from lower margin:</tei:note> In the light of all the
    experiences I have had, I am today merely being practical as regards this kind granting of
     access.<tei:note type="editorial">end cue</tei:note> I gave my disclaimer purely for the
    reasons <tei:del rend="overstrike">already</tei:del> then stated <tei:del rend="overstrike">above</tei:del>; but I must freely reserve <tei:add place="interlinear-above">to
     myself</tei:add> the right to go back on it, possibly even publicly, in the event that I were
    to have to suffer still further damage with respect to the <tei:unclear reason="meaning">frameworks</tei:unclear>
    <tei:pb n="2"/> that may deprive me <tei:add place="interlinear-above">in part or
     whole</tei:add> of the inheritance <tei:supplied reason="clarity">due</tei:supplied> to me in
    accordance with the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">deceased</tei:rs>'s wishes, and to
    which she through her <tei:add place="interlinear-above">high</tei:add> valuation of my
    accomplishments may wholly unintentionally have given rise. How once before I had to suffer
    damage for a long, long time as a result of the fact that a pension was <tei:unclear reason="meaning">conjured up</tei:unclear> for me purely on the basis that I gave lessons to
    the young <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000743">Baron Rothschild</tei:rs>, a pension of which
    I neither then nor to this day have ever seen a penny.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>I also take this opportunity to inform you that, on January 5, i.e. the death date of
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Mrs. Deutsch</tei:rs>, I disbursed out of the resources
    of the <tei:unclear reason="meaning">part-legacy</tei:unclear> kindly <tei:add place="interlinear-above">paid out</tei:add> to me <tei:add place="interlinear-above">at that
     time</tei:add> by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000590">Chamber Counsellor Mendl</tei:rs> the
     <tei:hi rend="underline">first</tei:hi> sum through the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002453">Vienna Bank Association</tei:rs> to Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Otto Vrieslander</tei:rs>,
    composer, of <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002326">Ebersberg</tei:rs>, nr. <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002286">Munich</tei:rs>. In so doing, I <tei:add place="interlinear-above">at long last</tei:add> lift the veil of secrecy from why I at the time insisted on precisely
    this legacy more <tei:add place="interlinear-above">than</tei:add> on my own honorarium: for it
    is I myself who am the "third person" of whom I wrote to you at the time <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">
     <tei:hi rend="italic">sub rosa</tei:hi>
    </tei:foreign>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> To a certain degree I had in mind
    a defense of honor, not only my own but also <tei:add place="interlinear-above">that</tei:add>
    of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Mrs. Deutsch</tei:rs> as well as of the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000590">Chamber Counsellor</tei:rs>. You will recall that I had no desire to
    take on the matter of the stipends, and that <tei:add place="interlinear-above">only</tei:add>
    through endless persuasion on the part of the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000590">Chamber
     Counsellor</tei:rs>, as too from yourself, did I let myself be talked into it.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> Faced with the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000590">Chamber
     Counsellor</tei:rs>’s letter to me, and then also faced with its being held up to me in
    conversation, I surely at least had cause to doubt <tei:add place="interlinear-above">altogether</tei:add> that the stipends would ever be viable. <tei:pb n="3"/> But once
    committed to the matter, I dispensed the stipend money in the manner in which <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Mrs. Deutsch</tei:rs> had reason to expect me, and indeed did expect
    me, to do; instead of awarding it to questionable products, I <tei:hi rend="underline">bestowed</tei:hi> it <tei:add place="interlinear-above">by preference</tei:add> upon two
    reputable composers whose works appeared to me important, and promised a third composer, whose
    name you may quite frequently have encountered in <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000471">Korngold</tei:rs>’s <tei:foreign xml:lang="fre">feuilletons</tei:foreign> along with
    quotations from his authoritative opinions, and to whom <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Mrs.
     Deutsch</tei:rs> herself <tei:hi rend="underline">had contemplated giving over</tei:hi>
    her own lesson-hours for the duration of her journey to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002534">Japan</tei:rs> (<tei:supplied reason="clarity">and</tei:supplied> who is the critic for one of the most highly respected daily papers in
     <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>), quite specifically that I would
    facilitate his stay in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Vienna</tei:rs> by means of
    money from the foundation, in which case I myself then fully intended to give him instruction
    free of charge.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:add place="interlinear-above">Now,</tei:add> I divulged to these gentlemen <tei:hi rend="underline">by name</tei:hi> the <tei:hi rend="underline">source</tei:hi> of the award – I
    had to do that because I did not want to get a bad name for myself <tei:supplied reason="clarity">by appearing to be</tei:supplied> a benefactor of money when I am in any case
    overburdened as a benefactor of instruction. As the doubts arose, it was <tei:hi rend="underline">too late</tei:hi>, at least in the cases of <tei:hi rend="underline">these</tei:hi> three gentlemen, to deviate or to go back on the commitment. It was a different
    matter in cases where after the initial approach to individual potential candidates I
    nevertheless did not commit myself to any one composer or any one work.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>The sum amounted to 1,020 Marks, i.e. one third <tei:pb n="4"/> of that legacy. On January
    5 next, the second musician should have his turn, and finally as the third the <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs> composer.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="indent-10">Unfortunately, I could not have done otherwise, as you yourself will
    admit.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">With best wishes, Yours truly, </tei:salute>
    <tei:note type="editorial">unsigned</tei:note>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p>P. S. I should be greatly obliged to you, <tei:add place="interlinear-above">dear Dr.
       <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000902">Türkel</tei:rs></tei:add> if in your letter to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000257">Dr. Friedmann</tei:rs> you would <tei:hi rend="underline">date</tei:hi> my disclaimer <tei:hi rend="underline">to the day</tei:hi>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">June 1, 1917</tei:add> on which I wrote to him for the first
     time – so long as this does not conflict in any way with your interests. <tei:hi rend="underline">A very great deal</tei:hi> for now as well as for later would hang on this
     determination for me.</tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>