<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="95" sdoID="OC-1-B-35-40">OC 1 B/35-40</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>
  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="major">Jeanette Kornfeld/Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="minor">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2009</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2009</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2010</tei:resp>

  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
   <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
   <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-04-30" who="#IB">XML encoding revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002700">Hertzka ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002701">UE ~ H+JSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002702">UE ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   
   
   
   <dc:title>Handwritten draft letter, in Jeanette Kornfeld/Schenker's hand, from Schenker to
    Hertzka (UE), undated [June 10, 1919]</dc:title>
   
   <dcterms:created>1919-06-10T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-05-09</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker promises to send Hans Weisse to see Hertzka. In reacting unfavorably to
    Hertzka's suggestions that the Foreword to Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven ... op. 111 be
    discarded for its second edition, Schenker puts up a stout defense of his use of polemic in his
    writings, contending that art and all manifestations of human life are inextricably
    interconnected. He claims that his pronouncements on politics now will prove correct in the long
    run. His sole concern is with the truth; he is not interested in pandering to his readers. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Vorwort; Foreword; Krieg; war; Polemik; polemics; Wahrheit; truth; Chauvinismus;
    chauvinism; Deutschtum; Germanity; Entente; Zusammenhang; relationship</dc:subject>
   

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000356">Hertzka</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-002408">UE</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:note type="editorial">This transcription gives only the first stage of the draft, i.e. that
    which Heinrich Schenker dictated to Jeanette. His subsequent revisions of Jeanette's long-hand
    copy, many of which are illegible, have not been included. This draft should be compared with
    WSLB 303, the final version of the letter received by UE.</tei:note>
   <tei:lb/>
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:pb n="35"/>
    <tei:note type="editorial">top-left corner, written diagonally:</tei:note>
    <tei:handShift new="#HS"/>
    <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356">Dir. Hertzka</tei:rs>
   </tei:opener>
   <tei:lb/>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>Es<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"> Drafting of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/14, p. 2079, June
     10, 1919 (hence the date proposed here): "An Hertzka (Br.): wegen des Vorwortes (liegt im
     Copierbuch)." ("To Hertzka (letter): concerning the Foreword (is in the copybook).")<!-- XR -->
     Dispatch of the letter in its final form (=WLSB 303) is recorded at OJ 2/14, p. 2080, June
     13.</tei:note> dürfte wohl das Vernünftigste u. Kürzeste sein, wenn ich Ihnen den <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">jungen Dr. mus.</tei:rs> (samt
    opus) zuschicke, was in Bälde geschehen wird.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Weitmehr aber als Ihre Klage über Papiernot u. erhöhte Kosten<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"> in OJ 52/923, June 6, 1919. </tei:note> hat
    mich Ihr mein <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work">op. 111</tei:rs> betreffendes P. S.
    erschreckt. Meinerseits noch zu mehreren Arbeiten bereit, wie z.B. zur „<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001758">Kleinen Bibliothek</tei:rs>“, zum Abschluß der <tei:rs key="entity-001733" type="work">Sonatenserie</tei:rs>, ja sogar zu einer Ausgabe der <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001753">Klaviersonaten von Beethoven</tei:rs>, fühle ich mich nur schon in der
    Bereitschaft wie gelähmt wenn ich befürchten muß, daß auch nur nachträglich meine Gedankengänge
    irgendwelchen Interessen geopfert werden könnten! Ich bin gewohnt so zu denken u. zu schreiben,
    wie der Stoff es fordert; es kann mir also niemals widerfahren, daß ich etwas zu bereuen oder zu
    widerrufen hätte. Auch dort, wo es für oberflächliche Betrachter den Anschein haben könnte, als
    hätte ich ein falsches oder ungerechtes Urteil abgegeben, braucht es eben nur der Zeit, damit
    man sich die Nachwelt von der Sicherheit meines Urteils überzeuge.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich erachte es nicht für des Lesers Sache, zu wissen, ob ich mit Recht oder
    Unrecht auch den Krieg in die Debatte <tei:pb n="36"/> gezogen habe, denn meine Gründe gehen so
    ins Tiefe, daß er weder fürs erste noch fürs tausendste begreifen könnte, weshalb ich es getan.
    Erst bis mein Gesamtwerk in Erscheinung getreten ist, wozu ich natürlich auch alle noch zu
    veröffentlichenden Arbeiten zähle, wird man vielleicht zu beurteilen vermögen, weshalb ich den
    Zusammenhang der Musik mit allen übrigen Lebensäußerungen so hoch veranschlagt habe. Sie
    verstehen, daß mich aus eben diesem Grunde die augenblickliche Empfindung des Lesers gar nicht
    interessiert u. ich am allerwenigsten wohl geneigt wäre, seiner persönlichen oder nationalen
    Eitelkeit Rechnung zu tragen. Es muß der Leser den Autor interessieren, nach dessen Werk er
    langt, um eine Belehrung zu empfangen, die er bis dahin nicht kannte: Bin ich es, der ihn am
    besten belehrt, dann muß er sich darein fügen, wie ich ihn zur Wahrheit führe, u. sei sie ihm
    persönlich noch so unangenehm. Oder aber er - lasse das Werk stehen u. gehe als Esel durch die
    Welt! Selbst die Wahrheit verliert an Wucht, wenn man sie Allen u. Jedern nach ihrer niedern
     <tei:foreign xml:lang="fre">Fasson</tei:foreign> mundgerecht machen will.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="37"/> Ich treibe Wahrheit, aber nicht „Chauvinismus“ u. wenn ich
    dem Deutschtum den höchsten Rang zugewiesen habe, so waren darin bis zum Kriege mit mir sogar
    unsere Feinde einig. Im Laufe des Krieges wurden nur die Feinde um eine Million Grade infamer,
    aber meine Wahrheit nicht um einen Grad „chauvinistischer“. Ich will noch damit gesagt haben zur
    Belehrung, nicht zur Beleidigung wenn ich zu verstehen gegeben habe, daß ein <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> bis ans Ende aller Zeiten niemals, niemals in
     <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002586">England</tei:rs>,
     <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002520">Frankreich</tei:rs>,
     <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002592">Italien</tei:rs>,
     <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002595">Serbien</tei:rs>,
     <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002596">Czechien</tei:rs>,
    geschweige denn in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002510">Amerika</tei:rs>, dem letzten aller Kulturländer je
    verstanden werden könnten. Denn schärfe ich so dem Leser die überhohe Bedeutung des Meisters
    ein, so erwirbt er die Fähigkeit von ihm zu lernen, widrigenfalls er die <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>-Predigt bagatellisiert weil er glaubt, es hätte
    andererswo ähnliche Köpfe wie <tei:persName>Beethoven</tei:persName> schon gegeben oder würde es
    demnächst gehen können. Wie Sie sehen, mache ich es um den Scherz zu wagen mit meinen Arbeiten
    nur dem Verleger billig, aber niemals meinem Leser. Ich dulde es niemals, daß der Leser von
    meinem Tische auf- <tei:pb n="38"/> steht mit dem Gefühl er hätte dies alles schon früher
    gewußt, u. daß er soeben von mir beschenkt, auch mich richte. Ich schreibe, wie gesagt, nicht
    für die Gegenwart, sondern – um es mit vollem Bewußtsein auszusprechen – für Jahrtausende, da
    man mich als allereinzige Quelle für die Blüte-Epoche der Musik zu schätzen wissen wird etwa wie
    z.B. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002527">Aristoteles</tei:rs> als Quelle für griechisches
    Wesen. Daher greife ich ins Volle der Zusammenhänge u. verschmähe es, des Lesers Eitelkeit zu
    ködern. Uebrigens bin ich überzeugt, daß die absolute Rücksicht, die ich wider die Wahrheit übe
    der Weiterverbreitung des Werkes förderlicher ist, als es die Rücksicht gegenüber Lesern. Es hat
    einem <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000524">Lessing</tei:rs> durchaus nicht geschadet, wenn in
    seiner vielgelesenen „Hamburgische Dramaturgie“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"> Gotthold Ephraim Lessing, <tei:title level="m">Hamburgische
      Dramaturgie</tei:title> (1767), a treatise on poetry and drama, which can be seen as a new
     interpretation of Aristotle's theory of drama. </tei:note> bis zum heutigen Tag z.B. der Satz:
    „wie englisch, wie unanständig“ stehen geblieben ist u. die vielen Verspottungen der Franzosen,
    die doch wieder nicht als deutschen Chauvinismus von <tei:persName>Lessing</tei:persName> zu
    betrachten sind, sondern vielmehr als Wahrheit. Und was lesen Sie sonst nicht alles bei allen
    unsern großen Meistern an Kritiken fremder Nationen so scharf als möglich!? Was geht die Meister
    eine Rücksicht an <tei:pb n="39"/> Haben sich je Franzosen ein Blatt vor den Mund genommen, um
    auch nur eine Lüge in die Welt zu schleudern?</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Und was speziell das Vorwort zu <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work">op.
     111</tei:rs> anlangt, so steht doch die Sache so, daß selbst unsere Tagesblätter einen Sieg der
     Entente<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot"> (Triple) Entente: the
     alignment between Great Britain, France, and Russia agreed in 1907 as a counter force to the
     Triple Alliance of Germany, Austria-Hungary, and Italy. </tei:note> nur mit Gänsefüßchen
    anführen, d. h. ihn eben nicht für einen Sieg halten. U. dies ist ja erst eine journalistenhafte
    Betrachtung. Den Sieg aber von dem ich gesprochen, bezog sich ja nicht nur auf die Siege auf den
    Schlachtfeldern, die ja auch nicht wegzuleugnen sind, sondern auch noch auf andere höherer Art.
    Und ob ich nun darin Recht habe, den Sieg der Deutschen prophezeit zu haben, überlasse ich nicht
    dem Leser im Jahre 1920 zu beurteilen, sondern erst dem vom Jahre 2000. Habe ich denn nicht
    bezüglich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000966">Wilson</tei:rs>s Recht behalten, u. bezüglich
    der Engländer? Nun aber genug. Ich bin also durchaus nicht nur nicht einverstanden, sondern
    bitte Sie ausdrücklich, die Ausgabe so stehen zu lassen, wie sie aus meiner Feder gekommen ist:
    ich trage gern u. stolz die Verantwortung für jedes Wort, ja ich habe sogar vor, in den
    künftigen <tei:pb n="40"/> Arbeiten mir Rechte zu nehmen, wie sie sich Menschen herausgenommen
    haben, denen es mit weniger als mir zugekommen ist, wozu ich eben auch die <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000966">Wilson</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000534">Lloyd-George</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000134">Clemenceau</tei:rs>
    rechne, einschließlich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000948">Weingartner</tei:rs> u. wie sie
    alle heißen mögen. Musik ist ja - vergessen Sie es nicht, lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356">Direktor</tei:rs> – keine Angelegenheit eines häuslichen oder
    öffentlichen Konzertes, einer Privatstunde, eines Konservatoriums, sondern eine eminent
    öffentliche Angelegenheit.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Uebrigens freut es mich, daß Sie so weit sind, eine II. Auflage veranstalten
    zu können, da ich mir sonst nicht zu erklären könnte, wie Sie das Vorwort vom Texte loslösen
    wollten.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute>
     <tei:note type="editorial">unsigned, undated</tei:note>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:note type="editorial">This transcription gives only the first stage of the draft, i.e. that
    which Heinrich Schenker dictated to Jeanette. His subsequent revisions of Jeanette's long-hand
    copy, many of which are illegible, have not been included. This draft should be compared with
    WSLB 303, the final version of the letter received by UE.</tei:note>
   <tei:lb/>
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:pb n="35"/>
    <tei:note type="editorial">top-left corner, written diagonally:</tei:note>
    <tei:handShift new="#HS"/>
    <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356">Director Hertzka</tei:rs>
   </tei:opener>
   <tei:lb/>

   <tei:p><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>It <tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> would
    clearly be most sensible and efficacious if I were to send the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">young PhD (Mus.)</tei:rs> to you (together with his opus), and this I shall do
    forthwith.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">However, your P.S. concerning my <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work">
     <tei:title level="m">Op. 111</tei:title>
    </tei:rs> has given me a far bigger fright than your lament about scarcity of paper and
    increased costs.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> Prepared as I remain to
    contribute several works, such as for example the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001758">
     <tei:title level="j">Little Library</tei:title>
    </tei:rs>, the completion of the already begun <tei:rs key="entity-001733" type="work">sonata
     series</tei:rs>, indeed even an edition of the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001753">Beethoven piano sonatas</tei:rs>, I feel as if my legs had already been cut from under me in
    my preparedness on the purely theoretical front if I must fear that even my trains of thought
    could subsequently be sacrificed in the interests of something else. I am accustomed to thinking
    and writing solely as the material itself demands. That way, I should never live to regret or
    have to revoke something. Even where to superficial observers it might appear as if I had
    pronounced a false or incorrect verdict, it will be only a matter of time before posterity will
    be convinced of the rectitude of my viewpoint.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I do not consider it a matter for my reader to know whether or not I am right
    or wrong in having drawn the war into my line of argument, <tei:pb n="36"/> for my reasons run
    so deep that he could not possibly even begin to fathom why I had done it. Only when my entire
    life's work has been completed (among which I of course count all those works yet to be
    published) will people perhaps be in a position to judge why I have rated so highly the
    relationship between music and all other manifestations of human life. You must understand that,
    for this very reason, the feelings of the individual reader at this particular moment do not
    interest me in the slightest, and least of all would I be inclined to take account of his
    personal or national vanity. The reader must interest himself in the author whose work he takes
    up, in order to assimilate a <tei:supplied reason="clarity">body of</tei:supplied> instruction
    of which until then he knew nothing. If I am the only one who can best instruct him, then he
    must just submit to that by which I lead him toward the truth, however uncongenial he may
    personally find it. Otherwise, let him drop the work, and go through life as an ass! Even the
    truth loses weight if after their lower fashion they want to render it palatable to anybody and
    everybody.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="37"/> I pursue truth, but never "chauvinism," and if I have
    accorded the highest status to Germanity, then even our enemies would have agreed with me on
    that up until the war. In the course of the war, our enemies became a million times more
    infamous; but my truth did not become one iota more "chauvinistic." It was to instruct the
    reader and not to insult him that I gave him an understanding that a <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> could never, never, not until the end of time,
    have been understood in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002586">England</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002520">France</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002592">Italy</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002595">Serbia</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002596">Czechoslovakia</tei:rs>, let alone <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002510">America</tei:rs>, the worst of all
    cultural lands. For if I impress upon the reader the supreme importance of the master, he then
    acquires the ability to learn from him, failing which he belittles the
     <tei:persName>Beethoven</tei:persName> sermon because he believes that otherwise figures
    similar to <tei:persName>Beethoven</tei:persName> have already existed somewhere or would be
    able to exist in the near future. As you can see, with my works – if I may venture a joke – I
    make things easy only for the publisher, never for my reader. I never tolerate the reader
    getting up from my table <tei:pb n="38"/> with the feeling that he already knew all of this and
    that albeit it has just been presented by me, he is ahead of even me. As I have said, I do not
    write for the present time, but – to articulate it with full consciousness – for millenia, when
    people will learn to value me as the one and only source for the supreme epoch of music, rather
    like, for example, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002527">Aristotle</tei:rs> as the source for
    the Greek way of life. This is why I delve into the relationships <tei:supplied reason="clarity">between art and life</tei:supplied> in all their fullness, and repudiate all pandering to the
    reader's vanity. Incidentally, I am convinced that the uncompromising approach that I practice
    in respect to the truth is more advantageous to the wide dissemination of my work than the
    approach that privileges readers. It has done a <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000524">Lessing</tei:rs> not the slightest harm that, for example, the phrase "how English, how
    unseemly" has stood the test of time in his widely read <tei:title level="m">Hamburg
     Dramaturgy</tei:title><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> to the present day, and
    the many expressions of derision of the French, which are again not to be considered as German
    chauvinism by <tei:persName>Lessing</tei:persName>, but rather as the truth. And what do you not
    read elsewhere in all our great masters by way of criticism of foreign nations <tei:supplied reason="clarity">that is</tei:supplied> as harsh as could possibly be? So when did the masters
    ever hesitate? Have Frenchmen ever minced matters <tei:pb n="39"/> when spreading even just one
    lie far and wide?</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">And as specifically concerns the Foreword to <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work">
     <tei:title level="m">Op. 111</tei:title>
    </tei:rs>, the situation is such that even our daily papers report a victory of the
     Entente<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> only within quotation-marks, i. e. they
    do not consider it to be a victory. And this is merely the journalist's way of looking at it.
    However, the victory about which I have spoken did not only relate to victories upon
    battlefields (which can certainly not be denied), but to those of an even higher order of
    things. And whether I was right to prophesy the victory of the Germans I leave not to the reader
    in the year 1920 to judge, but to that of the year 2000. Have I not already been proved right
    regarding <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000966">Wilson</tei:rs>? But that's enough of that. So
    I not only completely disagree, but I ask you expressly to leave the edition exactly as it is,
    just as it came from my pen: I stand by every word gladly and proudly, indeed I even intend in
    my future <tei:pb n="40"/> works to take liberties just as other people have taken whom it
    befits even less than it does me, among whom I count even the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000966">Wilson</tei:rs>s, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000534">Lloyd-George</tei:rs>s,
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000134">Clemenceau</tei:rs>s, including <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000948">Weingartner</tei:rs>, and whatever else their names may be. Music is
    truly--and don't you forget it, dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356">Director</tei:rs> –
    not the business of a domestic or public concert, of a the private lesson, of a conservatory,
    but a pre-eminent public business.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">By the way, I am delighted that you have reached the point at which you can
    arrange for a second edition – I could see no other way to interpret the fact that in the very
    case of <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work">
     <tei:title level="m">Op. 111</tei:title>
    </tei:rs> you were wanting to detach its Foreword from its text.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute>
     <tei:note type="editorial">unsigned, undated</tei:note>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>