<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="31" sdoID="OC-1-B-15">OC 1 B/15</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2007, 2019</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2007, 2019</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2019</tei:resp>

  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
   <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
   <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-02-26" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006997">Colbert ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten draft letter from Schenker to Carl Colbert, dated September 15,
    1912</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1912-09-15T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-01-26</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker explains why he deprecates strongly giving a student only one lesson a
    week and positively recommends two or three; he leaves the matter to Colbert, but gives him a
    difficult choice.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Unterricht; instruction; Entscheidung; decision; Altruismus; altruism; Einzelstunde;
    single lesson; Lehrer; teacher; Schüler; Schülerin; pupil; Honorar; honorarium; kosten; to cost;
    Klausel; clause; Geldmangel; financial shortage; Geldgewinn; financial gain; Schade; damage;
    detriment; Opfer; sacrifice; Programm; program of study</dc:subject>




   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000136">ColbertC</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">Drafted and heavily corrected by Heinrich Schenker:
     only the final reading given here:</tei:note><tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-60">
     <tei:date when="1912-09-15">15. 9. 1912</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000136"
      >Kaiserlicher Rat</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">This
      draft, in Heinrich's hand, is preserved in his copybook. It is therefore possible that the
      letter as sent was modified in the final copy. The wording of this letter closely mirrors that
      of the diary entry, OJ 1/10, p. 126, May 30, 1911, in places: "Definitive Absage an Frau
       <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Colbert</tei:hi>. Alle meine Humanität reichte nicht hin, ihr das
      schmutzige Betteln um lumpige paar Gulden auszutreiben : ich dachte ihr ein <tei:hi
       rend="lateinschr">Programm</tei:hi> zu, sorgte für Vermehrung ihrer Kenntnissen schon des
      herannahenden Alters halber, — sie aber starrte unablässig in das Geld, u. lieber, als Alles,
      was ich ihr klug u. human zugedacht, lieber, als alles Interesse für die Kunst, war ihr, eine
      Stunde zu umgehen, nur um sie nicht bezahlen zu müssen! Anders aber freilich lauten (nach
      Frauenart) ihre Briefe an mich : diese glühen von Liebe zur Musik, von Dankbarkeit für meine
      Führung! <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Volenti non fit injuria!</tei:hi> .."<tei:lb/>("Definitive
      rejection given to Mrs. Colbert. All my humanity was not sufficient to cure her of her squalid
      begging for a measly few florins: I intended to prepare a program of study for her that would
      bring about an increase in her awareness of advancing age. ‒ But her mind was forever fixed on
      money, and rather than all that I ingeniously and humanely planned for her, rather than any
      interest in music, she preferred to dodge a lesson merely so as not to have to pay for it! Her
      letters to me on the other hand (typically of a woman) clearly say something else: they glow
      with her love for music, with gratitude for my guidance! <tei:hi rend="italic">Volenti non fit
       injuria!</tei:hi>").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>


   <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Prof. <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
     >Violin</tei:hi></tei:rs> überbrachte mir kürzlich Ihren Wunsch betreffs des Unterrichtes Ihrer
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000137">Frau Gemalin</tei:rs>. Ich will ihm soviel als
    möglich <tei:hi rend="underline">entgegenkommen</tei:hi>, u. lege die <tei:hi rend="underline"
     >Entscheid</tei:hi>ung in <tei:hi rend="underline">Ihre</tei:hi> Hand. Da die Sache ziemliche
    Schwierigkeiten hat, muß ich zu Ihrer Einführung<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
     place="foot">"Einführung": it is unclear to what this refers; perhaps to the opening section of
     a letter from Carl Colbert to Schenker.</tei:note> ausholen bezw. Einiges wiederholen.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich gebe aus <tei:hi rend="underline">Altruismus</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">keine</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">Einzelstunden</tei:hi> obwohl solche ein-träglicher wären. Ich halte es
    für einen Betrug des Lehrers am Schüler u. bei diesen für einen Selbstbetrug, wenn eine
    Einzelstunde gegeben u. genommen wird. Berühmte Lehrer lassen sich für eine solche Stunde 25–50
     <tei:hi rend="underline">fl</tei:hi> (!!) bezahlen, der Schüler nimmt 2–3 Stunden im Jahr(!), –
    u. da er eben <tei:hi rend="underline">noch</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">Schüler</tei:hi> ist (sonst würde er ja des Unterrichtes nicht
    bedürfen), kann er, frage ich, in 2–3 Stunden Nützliches lernen? Sicher nicht! Ich zwinge daher
    meine Schüler zu einem regelmäßigen Unterricht u. <tei:hi rend="underline">ermäßige</tei:hi>
    mein Honorar ebenso entsprechend, daß der Schüler es leisten kann. Am allerwenigsten sind es
    doch die sehr reichen Menschen, die soviel Sinn für Musik u. zugleich soviel Würdigung eines
    seriösen Unterrichtes haben, <tei:pb n="2"/> daß sie sich den letzteren 8 x 25 fl. d.i. 200 fl.
    kosten ließen. Folglich habe ich in Einsicht des Real-Möglichen für je 2 Stunden der Woche 80
    fl. monatlich, für je eine der Woche eben 40 <tei:hi rend="underline">fl.</tei:hi> festgesetzt.
    Außerdem verbinde ich mit dieser Regelmäßigkeit des Unterrichtes eine jetzt schon über Auftrag
    des <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002445">musikpedagogischen Verband</tei:rs>es (dem
    ich natürlich fernstehe) von den letzten Lehrern für „hausbesorgerische“ (Lerchenfeld,<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Lerchenfeld: Alt-Lerchenfeld was one of the
     districts of central Vienna, now incorporated into Josefstadt, the 8th district.</tei:note>
     Ottakring<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Ottakring: the 16th
     district, to the west of Vienna.</tei:note>) <tei:hi rend="underline">gleichmäßig</tei:hi>
    adoptierte Klausel, daß <tei:hi rend="underline">Feiertage</tei:hi> zu Günsten des Lehrers
    fallen, u. ebenso die von Schüler selbst abgesagten Stunden. (Der Lehrer hat die von ihm
    abgesagten Stunden einzutragen). Diese Klausel findet ihre Begründung darin, daß viele Monate 9
    Stunden aufweisen u. es nur gerecht ist, wenn die Ausgleichung eintritt. Außerdem haben von Haus
    aus einige Schüler die Nettigkeit, einen Feiertag auch für den Lehrer gelten lassen zu wollen.
    So meine Praxis.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Nun schrieb ich neulich Ihrer <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000137">Frau
     Gemalin</tei:rs>, daß ich alle, alle Zeit besetzt habe. Und <tei:unclear reason="reading"
     >dem</tei:unclear> ist wirklich so. Immer mehr überzeugen meine Werke das jüngste <tei:rs
     type="place" key="entity-002482"><tei:country>Deutschland</tei:country></tei:rs>, u. von dort
    melden sich unaufhörlich junge Leute, einige sogar mit ganz respektablem Namen, die nach Wien
    (auch mit Familie) kommen, um bei mir zu lernen. Über diesem Erfolg freue ich <tei:pb n="3"/>
    mich sehr u. ich habe <tei:hi rend="underline">im</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">Interesse</tei:hi> der <tei:hi rend="underline">Kunst</tei:hi> alle
    Ursache, die Jugend in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482"
      ><tei:country>Deutschland</tei:country></tei:rs> den falschen Götzen abzuwenden. Außerdem ist
    das Ausland dankbarer. Ist <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Wien</tei:hi> nicht die Stadt, wo man
    bestenfalls – Grünfeld<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Grünfeld:
     presumably Alfred Grünfeld (1852–1924), celebrated Viennese pianist, piano teacher, and
     composer, who settled in Vienna in 1873.</tei:note>
    <tei:foreign xml:lang="fre">souteniert</tei:foreign>, aber Leute meines Schlages laut liegen
    läßt? Wo man, wenns Ernst wird, plötzlich Geldmangel spürt u. an Geldes statt am liebsten einen
    Mittags-, einen Abendtisch servieren möchte ? U. s. w. Sie kennen die Schlampereien ebenso gut,
    wie ich. Und nun komme ich zur Conclusion:</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Da Da ich von den <tei:hi rend="underline">angestammten</tei:hi> Schülern u. Schülerinnen
    (8–9 Jahre)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Tony Colbert applied for
     lessons on December 5, 1906 (OJ 1/5, p. 28). thus by choosing this limit Schenker excludes her;
     "angestammt": lit. "ancestral" or "heritage"; it is unclear which of Schenker's pupils in 1912
     qualified for this epithet: most likely candidates are <tei:rs type="person"
      key="entity-000155">Sonya Davydoff</tei:rs> (first mentioned in the diary on April 4, 1906: OJ
     1/5, p. 12), <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Sofie Deutsch</tei:rs> and <tei:rs
      type="person" key="entity-000107">Robert Brünauer</tei:rs> (both mentioned in the diary as
     having lessons on October 10, 1906: OJ 1/5, p. 21).</tei:note> Keinen opfern darf, auch nicht
    von denen, auf die ich, wie z. B. auf den jungen <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000399"
      ><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Hupka</tei:hi></tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs> im höheren Sinne etwas gebe, den Einen oder anderen
    wegschicken kann, zumal ich schon viel Mühe auf sie wandte, so könnte ich, um Ihrer <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000137">Frau</tei:rs> entgegenzukommen, einen Ausländer jüngsten
    Datums opfern. Es ist mir ein Schmerz, dies zu tun, da ich es als moralische Pflicht empfinde,
    vor Allem der Jugend zu dienen, die selbst Dienst wirken soll. Anbetracht dieses Schadens aber,
    den ich einem Schüler zufüge, werde ich Sie bitten, mich selbst nicht einen weiteren Schaden
    erleiden zu lassen. Lassen Sie nicht mich das Opfer an Ihre Frau bringen, sondern bestimmen Sie
    sie, <tei:pb n="4"/> die zuerst erwähnten Bedingungen einzuhalten! Es wäre verwerflich
    sentimental, wenn ich bei so viel Nachfrage seitens seriöser junger Leute mich anderswo versagen
    wollte, um hier – Schaden zu erleiden. Ihre Frau mag es bestätigen, daß ich in humaner Würdigung
    des herannahenden Alters ihr ein bestimmtes <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Programm</tei:hi>
    vorschlug u. daran mit glühendsten Eifer arbeitete. Aber ich konnte nicht zugeben, daß sie
    diesen verkennt, unterschätzt, einem Andern (doch nicht minder Würdigen) den Platz wegnimmt, –
    mehr als 10 Schüler <tei:hi rend="underline">kann</tei:hi> ich nicht unterrichten! –, ohne
    selbst davon Gebrauch zu machen. Sie darf nicht vergessen, daß ich meine Kraft jungen Leuten –
    schulde, heute dringender denn je, u. sie soll ihr Gewissen nicht mit der Unachtsamkeit
    belasten, selbst nicht zu kommen, dem Anderen nicht kommen zu lassen, u. so geistigen u.
    materiellen Schaden nach 2 Seiten hin zu stoßen, dem ein nur sehr kleiner Geldgewinn auf eigener
    Seite gegenübersteht. Es ist mir angenehm, Ihnen Alles so genau u. seriös gesagt haben zu können
    u. harre Ihre Entscheidung umso drängender, als ich ja eventuell weiter nach <tei:rs
     type="place" key="entity-002286">München</tei:rs> schleunigst schreiben müßte.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Mit besten Grüßen an Sie</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">u. Ihre <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000137">Frau
      Gemalin</tei:rs> verbleibe I<tei:supplied rend="ommission">h</tei:supplied>r</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
       >H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">Drafted and heavily corrected by Heinrich Schenker:
     only the final reading given here:</tei:note><tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-60">
     <tei:date when="1912-09-15">September 15, 1912</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000136">Imperial
      Counselor</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>


   <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Prof. Violin</tei:rs> conveyed to me briefly
    your wish concerning your <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000137">wife</tei:rs>'s program of
    instruction. I wish to <tei:hi rend="underline">accommodate</tei:hi> it as far as possible, and
    I place the <tei:hi rend="underline">decision</tei:hi> in <tei:hi rend="underline">your</tei:hi>
    hands. Since the matter entails considerable difficulties, I must defer to your
     instruction<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> and reiterate one or two
    things.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Out of <tei:hi rend="underline">altruism</tei:hi>, I give <tei:hi rend="underline"
     >no</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">single</tei:hi> lessons, albeit such lessons would be more lucrative. I
    consider it a betrayal by the teacher of the student, and of the latter a self-betrayal, if a
    single lesson is given and taken. Famous teachers demand for such a lesson 25–50 Florins(!!),
    the pupil takes two or three lessons a year(!), – and since he <tei:hi rend="underline">still is
     just a pupil</tei:hi> (otherwise he would have no need of the instruction), can he, I ask,
    learn anything useful in two or three lessons? Surely not! For this reason, I require my pupils
    to take a regular program of instruction and <tei:hi rend="underline">reduce</tei:hi> my fee in
    just such a way that the pupil can afford it. Least of all is it actually the very rich people
    who have so great a feeling for music and at the same time value so highly a serious program of
    instruction <tei:pb n="2"/> that they can pay 8 x 25 Florins = 200 Florins for such a program.
    Consequently, bearing in mind what ordinary people can actually afford to pay, I have fixed 80
    Florins a month <tei:supplied reason="clarity">as the rate</tei:supplied> for two lessons each
    week, and likewise 40 Florins for one per week. In addition, I combine with this regular pattern
    of instruction a clause, now <tei:hi rend="underline">universally</tei:hi> adopted on the orders
    of the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002445">Music-Teachers' Federation</tei:rs> (from
    which, naturally, I distance myself) by the latter teachers as "as what is needed for the
    household" (Lerchenfeld,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> Ottakring<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/>), stating that <tei:hi rend="underline"
     >holidays</tei:hi> fall in favor of the teacher, and likewise those lessons which the pupil
    himself cancels. (The teacher is responsible for the lessons he cancels himself.) This clause
    has as its basis that many months generate nine lessons, and it is only fair that some
    evening-out should occur. Additionally, some of my pupils right from the beginning, out of the
    kindness of their hearts, wish their teacher to have the benefit of a holiday, too. This is my
    practise.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>So I wrote recently telling your <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000137">wife</tei:rs>
    that every single bit of my time is booked up. And that is really the case. Increasingly, my
    work is convincing the most recent generation of Germans, and young people, some even with
    respectable names, are constantly applying to move to Vienna (even bringing their families) to
    study with me. I am delighted at this success, <tei:pb n="3"/> and have every reason, <tei:hi
     rend="underline">in the interests</tei:hi> of the <tei:hi rend="underline">art</tei:hi>, to
    turn the youth of <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482"
     ><tei:country>Germany</tei:country></tei:rs> away from false idols. What's more, people abroad
    are more appreciative. Is Vienna not the city where people at best support Grünfeld,<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> but merely leave men of my ilk to one side?
     <tei:supplied reason="clarity">The city</tei:supplied> where people, when things get difficult
    and they suddenly feel the financial pinch, would instead of <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
     >paying out</tei:supplied> money, prefer to serve a mid-day or evening meal? And so forth. You
    know the slovenliness as well as I do. And now I come to my conclusion:</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Since I could not possibly sacrifice any one of my <tei:hi rend="underline"
     >longest-standing</tei:hi> pupils (8–9 years),<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/>
    nor can I dismiss any of those such as the young <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000399"
     >Hupka</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs>, to whom I give
    something of a higher order, especially since I have already taken great pains with them, so, in
    order to accommodate your <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000137">wife</tei:rs>, I could
    sacrifice a foreigner whom I have taken on most recently. It is painful for me to do this, since
    I take it as a moral duty above all to serve the young, who should themselves give service.
    Considering this damage, however, that I would have to inflict on one student, I must ask you
    not to inflict further damage on me. Do not make me perform the sacrifice for your wife; rather,
    induce her to abide by <tei:pb n="4"/> the conditions already set out! It would be damnably
    maudlin if, given so great a demand on the part of serious-minded young people, I were to deny
    myself in another direction so as to inflict damage here. Your wife can confirm that in humane
    recognition of her approaching age I proposed to her a specific program of study, and worked on
    it ardently. But I could not permit her to underrate, to undervalue this, and take the place
    from some (certainly no less worthy) other person,—I <tei:hi rend="underline">can</tei:hi>not
    teach more that ten pupils! ‒ without herself making use of it. She ought not to forget that I
    owe my strength to young people, more pressingly today than ever, and she ought not to burden
    her conscience with the negligence of failing to turn up herself, not letting the other person
    attend, and inflicting such spiritual and material damage on two sides, which is balanced by
    only a very small monetary gain on my own side. I am glad to be able to say all this in such
    detail and so seriously to you, and await your verdict all the more pressingly since I would
    perhaps have had to write further urgently to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002286"
     >Munich</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">With best wishes to you and your <tei:rs type="person"
      key="entity-000137">wife</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">I remain your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.
     Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
