<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">

 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="1492" sdoID="OC-12-15-17">OC 12/15-17</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="AHa" scope="sole">August Halm's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="LR">
   <tei:persName>Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB-LR">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent and Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Footnotes, 2006, 2013</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2015</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2013-04-15" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">
  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002698">Halm ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker dated April 7, April 14, and May 6,
    1924]</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1924-05-06T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2015-05-07</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Halm again asks Schenker to point out an instance of non-genius in his [Halm's]
    music. — Has long believed that foreground (= corporeality) has been neglected at the expense of
    background (= spirituality) in music. — Defends Kurth against Schenker's critical remarks. —
    Suggests an explanation for the Bruckner classroom incident. — Will send parts of his [A major]
    String Quartet and promises a copy of his "Von Grenzen und Ländern". — Accepts offer of
    assistance with publication costs. — Comments on Reger.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Nichtgenialität; non-genius; Körperlichkeit; corporeality; Geistige; spirituality;
    Phsyiognomie; physiognomy; Gefühl; feeling; Volltaktigkeit; metric fullness; Solidität;
    solidity; Steigerung; escalation; Struktur; structure; Bewusstheit; intention; Musikbild;
    musical image; Beitrag;l contribution; Drucklegung; printing; Verleger; publisher; Maler;
    painter</dc:subject>


   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000326">Halm</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:date when="1924-04-07">7. IV. 24</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Lieber u. verehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
      >Professor</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
      this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/6, p. 2664, May 8, 1924: "Von Halm (Br.):
      lesen vertagt." ("From Halm (letter): reading postponed"); Schenker does not record reading
      the letter later; however, the underlining and sidelining on p. 7 provides evidence that he
      did read it.</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:div>
    <tei:p>So war das mit der Öffentlichkeit von mir nicht gemeint, daß die Leserschaft als Instanz
     gelten soll, sondern so, daß sie sehen soll, wie eine anständig geführte Fehde aussieht, in der
     ein Gegner auch mal gern Unrecht hat, d.h. dankbar ist wenn er bessere Einsicht
      bekennt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Halm is presumably
      responding to Schenker's letter DLA 69.930/12, April 3‒4, 1924. He is in any case matching
      twelve pages for twelve pages.</tei:note> Wenn Sie sich aber die Mühe machen, mir in einem
     Brief diese u. jene Stelle zu zeigen, wo ich ausrutschte, u. die Nichtgenialität meiner Musik
      <tei:pb n="2"/> sich offenbart, so ist mirs auch so recht. Es sind nicht viele Fälle nötig
     aufzuweisen, denn ich vermute von vornherein, daß mir das fehlt was Sie meinen, oder ich halte
     es doch für sehr möglich.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">No
      paragraph-break in the original.</tei:note></tei:p>

    <tei:p>„<tei:term>Vordergrundmusik</tei:term>“ – ein guter Ausdruck, den ich, je nach Befund,
     wohl auch für meine Musik akzeptieren würde mit <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
      >viel</tei:add> Bescheidenheit sowohl als mit<tei:add place="interlinear-above">
      etwas</tei:add> Stolz, d.h.: ich glaube schon lang, daß das
      <tei:term>Vordergründliche</tei:term> oder Oberfläch<tei:subst>
      <tei:del rend="overstrike">lich</tei:del>
      <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ige</tei:add>
     </tei:subst> über dem <tei:pb n="3"/>
     <tei:term>Hinter-</tei:term> u. <tei:term>Untergründliche</tei:term>n, oder die Körperlichkeit
     über dem Geistigen vernachlässigt worden ist.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial"
      place="foot">Neither "vordergründlich" nor "oberflächig" ‒ the latter very deliberately used
      (NB the crossed-out letters "liche" in order to produce "oberflächig") ‒ are proper German.
      Correct would be "vordergründig" and "oberflächlich." Halm rejected the latter because of its
      negative connotation (superficial), and coins "oberflächig" to mean surface detail. Similarly,
      Halm writes "vordergründlich" because "vordergründig" means superficial,
      simplistic.</tei:note> Sie sagen dagegen: alles ist nur ein Körper, u. darin liegt gerade die
     Genialiatät. Zugegeben: aber darum doch noch nicht <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat"><tei:hi
       rend="lateinschr">eo ipso</tei:hi></tei:foreign> die Schönheit – die ist auch Etwas! Unschöne
     Phsyiognomie, Körperteile sind biologisch ebenso ein Wunder wie schöne. Gefühl: werde ich
     keineswegs ausschalten, spreche aber, wie sichs gehört, nur privatim davon. Die Erkenntnis, die
     Tatsachen aufzeigt, wird ja doch auch vom Gefühl geleitet. Die Tatsachen präsentiert man dann
     in der Hoffnung, oder auf gut Glück, daß sie bei dem Leser ins <tei:pb n="4"/> Gefühl
     zurückleiten, dieses speisen. Tatsachen: ich habe stets gesagt: was ich über <tei:rs
      key="entity-000055" type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs>s Musik schreibe, halte ich für
     unwiederlegbar; dagegen bin ich stets gewärtig, daß noch andere Gewichte in die Wagschalen
     geworfen werden; das Steigen u. Sinken dieser ist nicht endgiltig. Was Sie von <tei:rs
      key="entity-000055" type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs> anführen, ist mir, fast alles, wertvoll,
     ich bewundere es, zum Teil beglückt es mich, so z.B. eben die in Ihrem letzten Brief angeführte
     Stelle.</tei:p>

    <tei:p>Religiöses Gefühl gegenüber der Musik: eben aus diesem heraus meine ich die Musik sei an
     sich geistig, u. man müßte sie nicht noch extra vergeistigen. Die unmittelbare Erscheinung, der
      <tei:term>Vordergrund</tei:term>, ist mir deshalb so wichtig. <tei:rs key="entity-000104"
      type="person">Bruckner</tei:rs> hat die Unschuld wiedergewonnen (die Klassiker hatten’s zu
     eilig). Seine Volltaktigkeit, seine Solidität (Anfang mit <tei:term>I</tei:term>,,) rechne ich
      <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ihm</tei:add> gerade zur Größe an. Was Sie erzählen (von
     der Steigerung) <tei:subst>
      <tei:del rend="overstrike">ist gewiß</tei:del>
      <tei:add place="interlinear-above">scheint zuerst</tei:add>
     </tei:subst> tief bedenklich, <tei:pb n="5"/> macht micht aber nicht irre <tei:note
      type="editorial" place="inline">cued from left margin, written top to
     bottom:</tei:note>Einfachste Erklärung: Er schätzte Sie u. wollte Ihnen eine schöne Stelle
     zeigen u. tat dies unter ungeschicktem Vorwand.<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end
      cue</tei:note> – ich sehe zuviel von Struktur u. Bewußtheit, Willen u. Können – ich habe da
     doch wohl einen ordentlich gefüllten Sack voll Tatsachen herbeigeschleppt – u. könnte noch
     manche Bögen füllen. Aber wäre es selbst so, daß es sich nur um „herrliche Musikbilder“
     handelte – das ist <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ja</tei:add> vor allem das, was uns nach
     den Klassikern nottat; Musik der reinen Gegenwart. Aber wie gesagt, ich bestreite, daß es
      <tei:hi rend="underline">bloß</tei:hi> das ist, u. glaube das Gegenteil erwiesen zu
     haben.</tei:p>

    <tei:p rend="first">Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000495" type="person">Kurth</tei:rs>, Ich denke, er
     sagt doch wohl einiges mehr als wie Sie es darstellen, u. dieses Mehr scheint mir wichtig. Der
     „Stoß,“ den Sie führten, hat mir also sein Bild nicht umgeworfen, aber <tei:pb n="6"/> Sie
     dürfen keine Sorge haben, daß ich so was nicht aushielte. Was mir einer umwerfen kann, das mag
     nur umfallen; sowohl meine eigene Musik als ihre Stützen u. Hilfen. Es freut mich immer, wenn
     jemand meine Musik gefällt; beweise man mir, daß er nichts versteht, so ist mirs doch
     willkommen, ihm Freude zu bereiten. <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">cued from left
      margin, written top to bottom:</tei:note>Es ist gewiß <tei:hi rend="underline"
      >möglich</tei:hi>, daß jemand meine Musik gefällt, der wenig von Musik versteht, ja auch
     jemand, der diese meine Musik selbst nicht versteht.<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"
      >end cue</tei:note> Schon lang, schon beim ersten Kennenlernen Ihrer Schriften, merkte ich den
     Unterschied; Sie sind viel mehr esoterisch als ich.</tei:p>

    <tei:p>— Die <tei:term>Quartettstimmen</tei:term><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial"
      place="foot">The parts of Halm's A major String Quartet, as promised in OC 12/10–12, February
      1–6, 1924. Schenker has agreed to receive them, DLA 69.930/12, April 3‒4, 1924, and to comment
      on the work in a forthcoming letter.</tei:note> sende ich demnächst ab. Wenn Sie bei einer
     Probe zuhören, so beeinflussen Sie doch, so gut es geht, die Spieler, daß sie <tei:pb n="7"/>
     nicht hetzen. Im allgemeinen finde ich, daß die Spieler stets schnelleres
      <tei:term>Tempo</tei:term> nehmen als ich es meine (Temperaments-Surrogat!). <tei:title>Von
      Grenzen u. Ländern</tei:title><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot"
        ><tei:bibl><tei:author>Halm</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Von Grenzen und Ländern der
        Musik</tei:title> (Munich: Georg Müller, 1916)</tei:bibl>. Halm mentions it in OC 12/10–12,
      February 1–6, 1924, and in DLA 69.930/12, April 3‒4, 1924, Schenker admits that he does not
      know it, and promises a copy of his elucidatory edition of Beethoven's Op.101 (1920) in return
      if Halm sends it (see below).</tei:note> will ich Ihnen durch den Verlag zusenden lassen. Noch
     nicht geschrieben haben Sie mir, was Sie von meiner <tei:title>Kammermusik</tei:title> nicht
     haben (IV., V. Heft?).<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">"Noch nicht",
      "Kammermusik nicht haben": underlining, also heavy sidelining, by Schenker.</tei:note>
     <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">cued from top margin, inverted:</tei:note>Am liebsten
     ließe ich Ihnen die <tei:term>Stimme</tei:term>n mit den andern Heften zusammen zusenden, also
     bitte schreiben Sie bald darüber.<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end
      cue</tei:note><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot">No paragraph-break
      in the original.</tei:note></tei:p>

    <tei:p>Einen Beitrag für Drucklegungen nehme ich, wenn Sie eine entsprechend<tei:supplied
      reason="syntax">e</tei:supplied> Stiftung, oder ähnl., zur Verfügung haben, gern an<tei:note
      xml:id="r0001-fn09" type="editorial" place="foot">In DLA 69.930/12, April 3‒4, 1924, Schenker
      writes: "It is not impossible that I could be able to send you a payment for your purposes."
      This seems a somewhat ungracious reply. Reference is to the <tei:rs key="entity-000165"
       type="person">Sofie Deutsch</tei:rs> stipends.</tei:note> – ich darf doch aus dem Angebot
     (wenn ein solches mal in betracht kommt) schließen, daß Sie m. Musik veröffentlicht wünschen,
     u. daß Ihnen nicht eine andere bekannt ist, die es nach Ihrem Urteil mehr <tei:pb n="8"/>
     verdient als meine. Immerhin denke ich, Sie sollten in solchem Fall, wo Sie z.B. entschieden
     haben, etwas von <tei:hi rend="underline">Ihren</tei:hi> Schriften veröffentlichen, wo die
     Verleger versagen oder gar hindern (ich habe mit Bedauern u. aufrichtiger Teilnahme von Ihren
     Schwierigkeiten mit dieser <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization"
      >Gesellschaft</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10" type="editorial" place="foot">This must be
      in response to Schenker's remark in DLA 69.903/12, April 3‒4, 1924: "wie schwelgen da die
      Herzen der Juden Hertzka, Kalmus u.Bruder usw!" ("how the hearts of the Jews Hertzka, Kalmus
      and brother, etc. wallow!"): Schenker and his lawyer were threatening to go to the courts at
      this time with charges of breach of contract on the part of Universal Edition: see
        <tei:bibl><tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title>, Eng. transl., vol. II (New York,
       Oxford University Press, 2005), General Preface, pp. v‒xii</tei:bibl>. </tei:note> gelesen u.
     kann mir wohl denken, daß Sie <tei:add place="interlinear-above">da</tei:add> nur eine kleine
     Vorhang-Spalte von einer sehr unsauberen Geschäftsbühne geöffnet haben.). Es kann nicht anders
     sein, als daß Sie Ihre Schriften für die Musik für wichtiger halten als meine Musik, u. danach
     müßten Sie entscheiden u. handeln. Das wäre nun doch wahrhaftig keine Eigensucht.</tei:p>

    <tei:p><tei:pb n="9"/> Sie schreiben, daß Sie mir wohl schon mitgeteilt hätten, „wie <tei:rs
      key="entity-000104" type="person">Bruckner</tei:rs> mühsam die <tei:term>Figur</tei:term>en
     auf den <tei:term>Klang</tei:term> abgestimmt habe.“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11"
      type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker's sentence in DLA 69.930/12 reads: "... darüber, wie
      [Bruckner] seine Figuren auf den Klang mit Mühe abstimmte, glaube ich Ihnen schon einmal
      geschrieben zu haben." ("I believe I have already written to you [describing] with what labor
      [Bruckner] coordinated his figurations to harmony."). </tei:note> Das ist noch nicht
     geschehen, es wird mich sehr interessieren, sehr, u. ich bitte Sie, es mir zu schreiben
      <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">cued from left margin, written bottom to
      top:</tei:note>Oder erwähnen Sie doch einmal Beispiele davon in einem Heft „<tei:rs
      key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title>Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>“.<tei:note
      type="editorial" place="inline">end cue</tei:note> auch wenn Sie nunmehr annehmen werden, daß
     ich mich von meinem Standpunkt dadurch nicht abbringen lasse. Denn schließlich kommts doch auf
     das Resultat der Mühsal an; wie auch bei <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person"
      >Beethoven</tei:rs>, der mir in seinen Skizzen auch <tei:pb n="10"/> (<tei:date
      when="1924-04-14">14.IV.24</tei:date>) manchmal unerwartet ungeschickt erscheint.<tei:note
      xml:id="r0001-fn12" type="editorial" place="foot">No paragraph-break in the
      original.</tei:note></tei:p>

    <tei:p>Zum Anfang zurück: ich halte es nach dem, was ich so beobachte (gelegentlich, denn ich
     studiere meine Sachen nicht so wie die andern), immerhin für <tei:hi rend="underline"
      >möglich</tei:hi>, daß eine schöne <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> in ihnen nachgewiesen werden
     könnte, auch das Gegenteil mag möglich sein. Mein wirkliches bewußtes Arbeiten (so wie der
     Maler Kompositionsstudien,, von dem Bild macht) betrifft hauptsächlich die
      <tei:term>Harmonik</tei:term>, das andere suche ich, bis ich etwas finde was mich
     zufriedenstellt – ohne so eingehende Arbeit wie beim <tei:pb n="11"/>
     <tei:term>Harmonische</tei:term>n. Da ich aber auch hinsichtlich der <tei:term>Linie</tei:term>
     sehr empfindlich <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">cued from bottom of
     page:</tei:note>Sie sagen wohl, ich sei zu wenig empfindlich, zu wenig hellhörig – ich versuche
     nicht, Ihnen meine Meinung hierüber aufzudrängen u. meine das jetzt rein praktisch: ich bin
     tatsächlich empfindlich, ob ich nun falsch oder richtig empfinde.<tei:note type="editorial"
      place="inline">end cue</tei:note> gegen ungenügende Weiterführung bin, so vermute ich, daß
     irgend eine <tei:term>Synthese</tei:term> vorhanden sein muß, vielleicht die
      <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>, vielleicht eine unbekannte.</tei:p>

    <tei:p rend="first">Vorgestern kam <tei:rs key="entity-001737" type="work"><tei:title>op.
       101</tei:title></tei:rs>, nehmen Sie</tei:p>

    <tei:p rend="indent-40"><tei:date when="1924-05-06">6.V.24</tei:date></tei:p>

    <tei:p>Eine Osterreise kam dazwischen: bei einer Jugendtagung in <tei:rs key="entity-005591"
      type="place">Hildesheim</tei:rs>, die Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-005592" type="person"
      >Wyneken</tei:rs> leitete, waren 4 Abende meiner Musik gewidmet; <tei:pb n="12"/> vorher hatte
     ich mancherlei mit Vorbereitungen dazu zu tun. Nun hätte ich ja manches noch zu sagen, aber der
     Brief soll nun endlich fort.</tei:p>

   </tei:div>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute>Ich sage Ihnen herzliche Grüße,</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000326" type="person">A.
     Halm</tei:rs>.</tei:signed><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p><tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person">Reger</tei:rs>:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13"
      type="editorial" place="foot">Max Reger's music has been discussed already in OC 12/10–12,
      February 1–6, 1924, and in DLA 69.930/12, April 3‒4, 1924.</tei:note> Ich meine, gegen ihn ist
     soviel zu sagen (u. <tei:hi rend="underline">für</tei:hi> ihn hat meines Wissens keiner seiner
     Anhänger etwas Greifbares u. Habhaftes gesagt), daß es mir fast unnötig erscheint, daß Sie sich
     damit abgeben. Das <tei:hi rend="underline">Bei<tei:hi rend="overstrike"
      >h</tei:hi>nahe</tei:hi> wäre interessanter, aufschlußreicher ‒ ich verstehe, daß dieses
     Beinahe nach Ihren Einstellung gerade eine <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">cued from
      left margin,written top to bottom:</tei:note>Wesens-Unterschied also Riesen-Distanz bedeuten
      muß.<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end cue</tei:note><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14"
      type="editorial" place="foot">Written "Wesens- also Riesen-Unterschied Distanz bedeuten muß"
      then indicated for inversion. Following this letter, as OC 12/18, is a two-sided sheet on
      which are jotted in Schenker's hand points from Halm's letter ‒ perhaps in preparation for a
      reply.</tei:note></tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:date when="1924-04-07">April 7,
     1924</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Dear and revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
      >Professor</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:div>
    <tei:p>I didn't mean it that way with the <tei:supplied reason="clarity">debate
      in</tei:supplied> public, that the readership should count as a court of appeal, but rather
     that it should see how a respectably conducted dispute looks in which an opponent is sometimes
     gladly in the wrong, i.e., is grateful when he admits better insight.<tei:ptr
      corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> However, If you take the trouble to show me in a
     letter one or another passage where I got off track and the lack of genius in my music <tei:pb
      n="2"/> reveals itself, that's all right with me too. It is not necessary to point out many
     instances, for I suppose from the start that I lack what you mean, or I do consider it very
      possible.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

    <tei:p>"<tei:term>Foreground music</tei:term>" ‒ a good expression which, depending on the
     findings, I would surely also accept for my music with <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
      >much</tei:add> modesty as well as <tei:add place="interlinear-above">some</tei:add> pride.
     That is, I have long since believed that the <tei:term>foreground</tei:term>, or surface, has
     been neglected at the expense of the <tei:pb n="3"/>
     <tei:term>background</tei:term> and <tei:term>foundation</tei:term>, corporeality at the
     expense of spirituality.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> You counter:
     everything is merely a body and therein lies the quality of genius. Granted, but certainly not,
     therefore, on that account beauty. That is something! Unattractive physiognomy, body parts are
     biologically just as much a wonder as beautiful ones. Feeling: I won't dismiss it by any means,
     but I talk about it only in private, as it should be. Knowledge that demonstrates facts is
     surely also guided by feeling. One presents facts in the hope, or relying on luck, that they
     will guide the reader to <tei:pb n="4"/> feelings, to relish them. Regarding facts, I have
     always said: I consider irrefutable what I write about <tei:rs key="entity-000055"
      type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs>'s music. On the other hand, I am constantly aware that yet
     other weights can be tossed on to the scales. Their rise and fall is not definitive. What you
     adduce about <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs> is almost all
     valuable to me. I admire it; in part, it elates me, for example precisely the passage you
     mentioned in your last letter.</tei:p>

    <tei:p>Regarding religious feeling vis-à-vis music: specifically on account of such feeling I
     think music is spiritual in itself, and one doesn't have to spiritualize it yet further. The
     immediate phenomenon, the <tei:term>foreground</tei:term>, is therefore so important to me.
      <tei:rs key="entity-000104" type="person">Bruckner</tei:rs> regained innocence (the
     classicists were too much in a hurry). His downbeat quality, his solidity (opening with
      <tei:term>tonic harmony</tei:term>) I accredit <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
      >him</tei:add> as greatness. What you recount (about escalation) <tei:subst>
      <tei:del rend="overstrike">is certainly</tei:del>
      <tei:add place="interlinear-above">seems at first</tei:add>
     </tei:subst> of deep concern <tei:pb n="5"/> but does not confuse me. <tei:note
      type="editorial" place="inline">cued from left margin, written top to
     bottom:</tei:note>Simplest explanation: he respected you and wanted to show you a nice passage
     and did it under an awkward pretense.<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end
      cue</tei:note> I see too much structure and intention, will and ability. I have hauled out a
     fairly full bag of facts here, and could fill yet quite a few sheets of paper. But even if it
     were just a matter of "wonderful musical images" ‒ that is <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
      >of course</tei:add> above all what was needed after the classicists; music purely of the
     present. But as I said, I dispute that it is <tei:hi rend="underline">merely</tei:hi> that, and
     believe I have proved the opposite.</tei:p>

    <tei:p rend="first">Regarding Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000495" type="person">Kurth</tei:rs>, I
     think he certainly said a bit more than how you present it, and that More seems important to
     me. The "blow" that you struck has thus not overthrown his image for me. But <tei:pb n="6"/>
     you need not worry that I cannot abide such things. What someone can overthrow for me may
     merely fall down, my own music as well as your support and assistance. I am always delighted
     when my music pleases someone. If one were to prove to me that he understands nothing, it is
     for me a pleasure to bring him joy. <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">cued from left
      margin, written top to bottom:</tei:note>It is certainly <tei:hi rend="underline"
      >possible</tei:hi> that my music pleases someone who understands little of music, even someone
     who does not understand my music in particular.<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end
      cue</tei:note> For some time, already at my first acquaintance with your writings, I noticed
     the difference; you are much more esoteric than I am.</tei:p>

    <tei:p>— I will soon be sending you the <tei:term>quartet parts</tei:term>.<tei:ptr
      corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> If you listen in on a rehearsal, do try to influence
     the players, as far as you can, <tei:pb n="7"/> not to rush. In general I find that players
     always take a faster <tei:term>tempo</tei:term> than I intend (surrogate for spiritedness!). I
     will have <tei:title level="m">Of Boundaries and Countries</tei:title><tei:ptr
      corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> sent to you by the publisher. You have still not
     written me what items of my <tei:title level="m">Chamber Music</tei:title> you do not have
     (volume 4, 5?).<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/>
     <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">cued from top margin, inverted:</tei:note>Most
     preferably, I would have the <tei:term>part</tei:term>s sent together with the other volumes,
     so write me soon about it.<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end cue</tei:note><tei:ptr
      corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

    <tei:p>I will gladly accept a contribution toward printing costs if you have an appropriate
     foundation at your disposal.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09" type="footnote"/> I may conclude
     from the offer (if such comes under consideration at some point) that you wish to see my music
     published, and that you are not familiar with other music that in your opinion <tei:pb n="8"/>
     deserves it more than mine. Should you, for example, have decided <tei:supplied
      reason="clarity">on a contribution</tei:supplied>, I still think you should publish something
     from <tei:hi rend="underline">your</tei:hi> writings when publishers don't come through or even
     stand in the way. (I read with regret and sincere sympathy about your difficulties with that
      <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">company</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn10"
      type="footnote"/>, and can readily imagine that you have opened only a small slit in the
     curtain on a very sullied commercial stage.) It can be no other way than for you to consider
     your writings more important for music than my music, and you would have to make decisions and
     act accordingly. In truth, that would truly not be egotism.</tei:p>

    <tei:p><tei:pb n="9"/> You write that you had already told me "how <tei:rs key="entity-000104"
      type="person">Bruckner</tei:rs> laboriously coordinated the <tei:term>figuration</tei:term>s
     with the <tei:term>harmony</tei:term>."<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn11" type="footnote"/> That
     has not yet occurred. It would very much interest me, and I ask that you write me about
      it<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">cued from left margin, written bottom to
      top:</tei:note>, or mention an example of it in a volume of <tei:rs key="entity-001739"
      type="work"><tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>,<tei:note type="editorial"
      place="inline">end cue</tei:note> even if you will then assume that I will not be budged
     thereby from my viewpoint. For ultimately it depends on the outcome of the labor; as with
      <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs>, who also sometimes appears
      <tei:pb n="10"/> (<tei:date when="1924-04-14">April 14, 1924</tei:date>) unexpectedly awkward
     to me in his sketches.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn12" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

    <tei:p>Back to the beginning: After what I have observed (occasionally, for I don't study my
     pieces as I do those of others), I still consider it <tei:hi rend="underline">possible</tei:hi>
     that a beautiful <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> could be demonstrated in them. The opposite may
     also be possible. My actual, conscious work (as the painter makes composition studies of a
     picture) mainly applies to <tei:term>harmony</tei:term>. The remainder I search out until I
     find something that satisfies me ‒ without such intensive work as with the <tei:pb n="11"/>
     <tei:term>harmony</tei:term>. However, with respect to <tei:term>line</tei:term>, since I am
     also very sensitive <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">cued from bottom of the
      page:</tei:note>(You say I am insufficiently sensitive, insufficiently aurally aware ‒ I won't
     try to impose my opinion on you on that point, and mean this now purely from a practical
     viewpoint: I am indeed sensitive, whether I sense incorrectly or correctly.)<tei:note
      type="editorial" place="inline">end cue</tei:note> to unsatisfactory continuation, I suspect,
     accordingly, that some kind of <tei:term>synthesis</tei:term> must exist, perhaps the
      <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>, perhaps an unknown type.</tei:p>

    <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs key="entity-001737" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Op.
       101</tei:title></tei:rs> arrived the day before yesterday. Cordial thanks.</tei:p>

    <tei:p rend="indent-40"><tei:date when="1924-05-06">May 6, 1924</tei:date></tei:p>

    <tei:p>An Easter trip intervened. Four evenings were devoted to my music at a youth convention
     in <tei:rs key="entity-005591" type="place">Hildesheim</tei:rs> that Dr. <tei:rs
      key="entity-005592" type="person">Wyneken</tei:rs> directed; <tei:pb n="12"/> before that, I
     had various things to do with preparations. I do now have other things to say, but the letter
     should finally be off.</tei:p>

   </tei:div>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute>I express to you cordial greetings,</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Yours</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000326" type="person">A.
     Halm</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p><tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person">Reger</tei:rs>:<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn13"
      type="footnote"/> I mean, there is so much to say against him (and to my knowledge none of his
     devotees has said anything tangible or concrete <tei:hi rend="underline">for</tei:hi> him),
     that to me it almost seems unnecessary that you have to deal with it. The <tei:hi
      rend="underline">Nearly</tei:hi> would be more interesting, enlightening. I understand that
     according to your attitude this Nearly must mean a <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"
      >cued left margin, written top to bottom:</tei:note>difference in nature, i.e. a huge
      gap.<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end cue</tei:note><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn14"
      type="footnote"/></tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>

 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
