<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="1888" sdoID="OC-1-A-16-17">OC 1A/16-17</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2007, 2016</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2007, 1016</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2016</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">
  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006215">Newlov ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



   <dc:title>Handwritten letter (carbon copy) from Schenker to Newlov, dated September 16,
    1913</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1913-09-16T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2016-11-04</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker regrets that he is unable to offer Newlov lessons in the coming
    season.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Vertrag; contract; Verlag; publisher; Anmeldung; registration; Kompositionsschüler;
    composition pupil; Schüler;Schülerin; pupil; Stunde; lesson</dc:subject>



   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000628">Fräulein Newlov</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:note type="editorial" place="pre-text">This copy was produced by placing a sheet of carbon
    paper and a second sheet behind the original as it was written by hand.</tei:note>

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Verehrtes Frl. <tei:rs key="entity-000628" type="person">von
      Newlov</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker initially
      wrote a letter (not known to survive), recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 1/13, p. 416:
      "Absage an Frl. v. Newlov." ("Refusal sent to Miss Newlov."). However, his diary records on OJ
      1/13, p. 418, September 16, 1913: "Gegen Abend erhalte ich durch die Hausbesorgerin einen
      Brief von Frl. N., worin sie raffinierterweise so tut, als würde sie meine Absage nicht
      verstanden haben. Noch ist die Tendenz dieses Raffinementes nicht ganz klar. – Ich antworte
      sofort, um auf mein gestriges Schreiben neuerdings zu verweisen!" ("Towards evening the
      caretaker's wife gives me a letter from Miss Newlov, in which she cunningly pretends not to
      have understood the reason for my refusal. The purpose of her cunning is still not entirely
      clear. – I reply immediately in order to refer again to my letter of the previous day!"). —
      The latter is the present letter.</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Da das an Sie als Antwort (auf Ihrem letzten Brief<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
     type="editorial" place="foot">Newlov's request (not known to survive) for a reduction to one
     lesson per week is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 1/13, p. 406, August 20, 1913: "Brief von
     einer Schülerin, Frl. v. Newlov, die ihren Unterricht auf eine Stunde wöchentlich reduzirt
     wünscht. Die unklaren häuslichen Verhältnisse dauern in ihrer Unklarheit fort, sehr zum
     Nachteil des Unterrichts!" ("Letter from a pupil, Miss Newlov, who would like her tuition to be
     reduced to one hour per week. The unclear domestic circumstances will remain unclear, much to
     the disadvantage of my teaching!"). </tei:note> aus Parenzo<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
     type="editorial" place="foot">Parenzo: Poreč, leading seaside resort in the Istria region of
     Croatia. </tei:note>) abgeschickte Schreiben <tei:hi rend="underline">nicht</tei:hi> wieder in
    meine Hände gekommen ist, (was sonst geschieht, wenn Briefe ihre Adressaten nicht erreichen), so
    nehme ich mit Recht an, daß Sie meine <tei:hi rend="underline">Antwort</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">erhalten</tei:hi> haben. Bald darauf wollte ich Ihnen wieder schreiben,
    unterließ es aber, weil ich es bequemer hatte, schon in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place"
      ><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Wien</tei:hi></tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04"
     type="editorial" place="foot">i.e. from his summer vacation in the Tyrol, which began on June
     29 and ended on September 9–11 (OJ 1/12, p. 367, OJ 1/13, pp. 413–15).</tei:note> Ihnen das
    Nötige mitzuteilen. Kaum aber in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place"><tei:hi
      rend="lateinschr">Wien</tei:hi></tei:rs> angelangt, erlitt ich eine kleine <tei:unclear
     reason="reading">Fieberatigin</tei:unclear>, so daß ich vorerst nichts schreiben konnte. Heute
    ist der erste Tag, da der Arzt nicht kommt, u. – ich beeile mich, wie Sie sehen, Ihnen
    mitzuteilen, was ich zu sagen nötig habe.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Es sind nämlich im Laufe der wenigen Tage so viel Veränderungen eingetreten, – neue
    Verträge mit einem Leipziger (Verlags-) Welthaus,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial"
     place="foot">Schenker is most likely alluding to Peters Edition of Leipzig, from whom he
     received a letter on September 11 to which he drafted a reply on September 15 (OJ 1/13, pp.
     415–17).</tei:note> neue Anmeldungen von hochbegabten Kompositionsschülern,<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker's only newly enrolled student in
     October 1913 was <tei:rs key="entity-000098" type="person">Paul Breisach</tei:rs>, but he may
     have been referring retroactively to <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans
      Weisse</tei:rs>, who was studying composition with Schenker and piano with Moriz
     Violin.</tei:note> – daß ich Sie bitten muß, von der <tei:pb n="2"/>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">einen</tei:hi> Stunde, die Sie wünschten, abzusehen. Sie begreifen, daß
    ich den Besitzstand meiner älteren u. ältesten Schüler u. Schülerinnen,<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">Newlov is likely to have been a fairly recent
     addition to Schenker's schedule. Her first recorded lesson occurred on January 15, 1912
     (Lessonbook 1912/13, p. 1).</tei:note> die schon 10 Jahre bei mir sind, <tei:add
     place="interlinear-above">nicht</tei:add> antasten darf. Doch könnte es möglicherweise auch
    dazu kommen, sobald meine Verpflichtungen gegenüber nunmehr 3 Verlagen es erfordern sollten. Ich
    muß überhaupt eine ganz andere Disposition meiner Stunden treffen.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Da ich keine Veranlassung habe, Ihren Worten zu mistrauen, mit denen Sie mir
    so oft für meine Anleitung dankten, so empfinde ich es selbst umso schmerzlicher, mich Ihnen
    nicht auch noch weiterhin zur Verfügung stellen zu können. Hoffentlich sind Sie aber schon
    wohlauf, u. wohl auch Ihre Frau <tei:rs key="entity-000627" type="person">Mama</tei:rs> erfreut
    sich bester Gesundheit. Ich selbst muß mich noch herausmachen, ehe der furchtbare Arbeit
    beginnt.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Mit besten Grüßen an Sie u. Ihre Frau <tei:rs key="entity-000627"
     type="person">Mama</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr ergeb</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60">
     <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">H
      Schenker</tei:rs></tei:hi>
    </tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1913-09-16">16 Sept. 1913</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Revered Miss <tei:rs key="entity-000628" type="person">von Newlov</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
      corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Since the letter that I sent to you by way of reply (to your most recent letter<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> from Parenzo<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
     type="footnote"/>) has <tei:hi rend="underline">not</tei:hi> been returned to me (as otherwise
    happens whenever letters do not reach their addressees), I justifiably infer that you have
     <tei:hi rend="underline">received</tei:hi> my <tei:hi rend="underline">reply</tei:hi>. Soon
    after that, I wanted to write to you again, but refrained from doing so because I felt more
    comfortable saying what I had to communicate once I was in <tei:rs key="entity-002484"
     type="place">Vienna</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> again. Scarcely
    was I back in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>, however, than I went
    down with a slight fever, such that at first I was unable to put pen to paper. Today is the
    first day on which the doctor is not coming, and I hasten, as you see, to inform you of what I
    feel it necessary to say.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Namely, that so many changes have taken place in the course of the last few days ‒ new
    contracts with a world-renowned Leipzig (publishing) company,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05"
     type="footnote"/> new registrations of highly gifted composition pupils<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> ‒ that I have to ask you to abandon the <tei:pb n="2"/>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">single</tei:hi> lesson that you requested. You will appreciate that I
    ought <tei:add place="interlinear-above">not</tei:add> to encroach upon the group of my longer-
    and longest-term students, male and female,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> who
    have been with me already for ten years. It may very well have to come even to that, just as
    soon as my obligations toward henceforth three publishers should demand it. I must anyway devise
    a completely different scheme for my lessons.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Since I have no reason to mistrust the words with which you have so often
    thanked me for my instruction, it comes all the more painfully to me no longer to be able to
    place myself at your disposal. I hope, however, that you are by now well, and that your <tei:rs
     key="entity-000627" type="person">mother</tei:rs> is enjoying the best of health. I must pick
    myself up again before the fearful work begins.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">With best wishes to you and your <tei:rs key="entity-000627" type="person"
     >mother</tei:rs>,</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your devoted</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">H.
     Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1913-09-16">September 16, 1913</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
