<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="1418" sdoID="OC-18-37-38">OC 18/37-38</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="WF" scope="sole">Wilhelm Furtwängler's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="CH">
      <tei:persName>Christoph Hust</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2008</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2015</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-06-28" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002728">Furtwängler ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Furtwängler to Schenker, dated December 10, 1932</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1932-12-10T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2015-01-26</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Furtwängler shares Schenker's assessment of Ludwig Karpath, and has not
        written a letter for publication. — He has been exploring possibilities for Schenker in
        Berlin, particularly taking over a masterclass at the Akademie der Künste, with additional
        lectures at the Stern'sches Conservatory. — He has heard from Hans Weisse. — He encloses a
        review by Herman Roth, and comments on the latter's character.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Besuch; visit; Eindruck; impression; journalistisch; journalistic; Kanal; channel;
        Eitelkeit; vanity; Brief; letter; Veröffentlichung; publication; Erkundigung; exploration;
        Verhältnisse; relations; Meisterklasse; masterclass; Ministerium; Ministry; Hochschule;
        Erfolg; success; Kritik; review; Schüler; pupil; Intellektueller; intellectual</dc:subject>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">
      <tei:opener>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">A photocopy of this letter exists as SBB Nachl.13,
          [5]</tei:note><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:placeName><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Potsdam</tei:hi></tei:placeName>,
            <tei:date when="1932-12-10">10. XII. 32</tei:date>.</tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>Lieber verehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"><tei:hi
              rend="lateinschr">Schenker</tei:hi></tei:rs>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01"
            type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at
            OJ 4/6, p. 3798, December 16, 1932: "Von Furtwängler (Brief u. ein Roth-Aufsatz): denkt
            an eine Meisterklasse für Komposition in Berlin an der Akademie; Gräner begeistert; Roth
            bengelhaft, „falscher Deutscher“!" ("From Furtwängler (letter and a Roth article): is
            thinking of a masterclass in composition at the Academy in Berlin; Gräner is excited;
            Roth uncouth, 'false German'!"). This letter is included in <tei:bibl><tei:title
                level="m">Heinrich Schenker: Selected Correspondence</tei:title>, eds.
                <tei:editor>Ian Bent</tei:editor>, <tei:editor>David Bretherton</tei:editor>, and
                <tei:editor>William Drabkin</tei:editor> (Woodbridge: Boydell Press, 2014), pp.
              213‒14</tei:bibl>.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Erst heute habe ich ein ruhiges Stündchen, um Ihnen zu antworten.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">No item of correspondence from Schenker
          to Furtwängler is recorded in Schenker's diary between his previous meeting with
          Furtwängler on November 16 and this date. The subject at hand is the attempt by Ludwig
          Karpath during 1932‒33 to procure for Schenker ‒ with Furtwängler's support ‒ a
          professorship in Vienna.</tei:note> Zunächst: Was <tei:rs key="entity-000424"
          type="person">Karpath</tei:rs> betrifft, so hatte ich schon bei meinem Besuch bei ihm am
        vorletzten Tage meines <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"><tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place"
            >Wien</tei:rs>er</tei:hi> Aufenthaltes einen ähnlichen Eindruck, wie Sie ihn mir von
        sich aus mitteilen. Nämlich den, daß er nur versucht, die ganze Angelegenheit in seine
        journalistischen Kanäle zu leiten und das ihm viel wichtiger ist als die Sache selbst, zu
        der er offenbar gar kein Verhältnis hat. Außerdem hat mir diesmal seine allzusehr auf
        Schritt und Tritt hervortretende Eitelkeit während des Gesprächs einen etwas unseriösen
        Eindruck gemacht; auch scheint mir, daß <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat"><tei:hi
            rend="lateinschr">de facto</tei:hi></tei:foreign> in letzter Zeit sein Einfluß sehr
        nachgelassen hat. Jedenfalls bin ich darin durchaus Ihrer Meinung, daß ein Brief von mir
        über Sie, an ihn zur Veröffentlichung geschickt, schließlich praktisch gesehen nicht das
        gewünschte Ergebnis <tei:pb n="2"/> haben dürfte. Ich habe einen solchen daher auch nicht
          geschrieben.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">No paragraph-break
          in source.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Hier habe ich inzwischen Erkundigungen einzuziehen versucht. Die
        Verhältnisse sind – oder waren – durch die beständigen Regierungskrisen sehr
          kompliziert.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">1932 was the last
          year of the Weimar Republic; and the rise to power of the National Socialist Party was
          only seven weeks away. </tei:note> Immerhin scheint mir eine Möglichkeit, daß man Ihnen
        eine sog. „Meisterklasse“ für Komposition <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">cued
          from left margin:</tei:note>von der Akademie aus!<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"
          >end cue</tei:note> anbietet, die im September 1933 frei wird.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">The Akademie der Künste in Berlin, which
          had since 1869 included a Hochschule für Musik the Director of which was from 1920 to 1932
          Franz Schreker, and from 1932 Georg Schünemann. The idea came to nothing because of a
          newly applied residential eligibility (diary entry March 2, 1933). </tei:note> Das wäre,
        wenn <tei:rs key="entity-000431" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
          >Kestenberg</tei:hi></tei:rs> noch seine frühere Stellung im <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
          >Ministerium</tei:hi> innehätte, ohne weiteres zu realisieren gewesen; wieweit das unter
        den jetzt veränderten Verhältnissen der Fall ist, weiß ich noch nicht genau, ich werde aber
        versuchen, mir darüber noch vor Weihnachten Klarheit zu verschaffen. Dies würde Ihnen
        materiell eine Existenzgrundlage geben können. Sonstige Vorlesungen – entweder in der
        Hochschule oder bei <tei:rs key="entity-000302" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
            >Gräner</tei:hi></tei:rs> (der sich über Sie begeistert aussprach) <tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">–</tei:supplied> von deren befruchtender Wirkung ich mir unter
        Umständen allerlei verspräche, könnten <tei:pb n="3"/> dann leicht angeschlossen werden. Ich
        werde jedenfalls bald Ihnen mehr sagen können, als ich jetzt weiß; es geht das jedoch
        vielleicht nicht ganz so schnell, einmal wegen der wirklich im Moment sehr unübersichtlichen
        Verhältnisse hier, und dann weil ich auch nicht immer die nötige Zeit habe.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Von <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
            >Weisse</tei:hi></tei:rs> habe ich einen kurzen Brief bekommen. Es geht im gut, und er
        hat offenbar – wenn man die Verhältnisse bedenkt, unter denen er wirkt – viel Erfolg, was
        mich sehr freut. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich schreibe Ihnen bald wieder. Für heute mit den herzlichsten Grüßen wie
        immer – auch an Ihre <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Frau</tei:rs> – </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Wilhelm
            Furtwängler</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p>Anbei eine Kritik Ihres Schülers <tei:rs key="entity-000737" type="person"
            >Roth</tei:rs> aus <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>.<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Perhaps <tei:bibl><tei:author>Herman
                Roth</tei:author>, <tei:title level="a">Bekenntnis zu Schenker,</tei:title>
              <tei:title level="j">Hamburger Nachrichten</tei:title>, September 17, 1931</tei:bibl>,
            a clipping of which appears in Schenker's scrapbook at OC 2/p.84, though one would have
            expected Schenker to have encountered this long before now.</tei:note> Er ist auch einer
          von jenen deutschen Intellektuellen – ohnedies eine von Neid nicht freie, in sich wenig
          wohlwollende Natur – die plötzlich anders zuhören, wenn einer das zweifelhafte Glück hat,
          „berühmt“ zu sein. Die letzte Bemerkung heißt doch geradezu: möge die Welt endlich über
          ihre falsche <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Furtwängler</tei:hi>-Begeisterung aufgeklärt
          werden. Und sowas muß man sich gefallen lassen! Charakteristisch <tei:note
            type="editorial" place="inline">cued from left margin:</tei:note>auch was er lobt: den
          dirigierenden <tei:rs key="entity-000851" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Fritz
              Stein</tei:hi></tei:rs>, den „<tei:rs key="entity-000104" type="person"><tei:hi
              rend="lateinschr">Bruckner</tei:hi></tei:rs>“ <tei:rs key="entity-000613"
            type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Muck</tei:hi></tei:rs>’s!!<tei:note
            type="editorial" place="inline">end cue</tei:note></tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>
    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">
      <tei:opener>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">A photocopy of this letter exists as SBB Nachl.13,
          [5]</tei:note><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:placeName>Potsdam</tei:placeName>, <tei:date when="1932-12-10">December
            10, 1932</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>Dear revered Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Today is the first time I have had a quiet moment in which to answer
          you.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> First: as concerns <tei:rs
          key="entity-000424" type="person">Karpath</tei:rs>, I had a similar impression to that
        which you convey to me, when I visited him on the penultimate day of my stay in <tei:rs
          key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>. Namely that he is only trying to divert
        the whole matter into his journalistic channels, and that that is much more important to him
        than the matter itself, for which he clearly has no affinity. In addition, his overweening
        vanity, which came out at every turn during our conversation, this time gave me the
        impression perhaps of untrustworthiness. It also seems to me that his influence has
          <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat"><tei:hi rend="italic">de facto</tei:hi></tei:foreign> very
        much diminished in recent times. At any rate, I am thoroughly of one mind with you that a
        letter from me about you, sent to him for publication, would not seem ultimately, from a
        practical point of view, to yield the desired outcome. <tei:pb n="2"/> Accordingly, I have
        not written such a letter.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I have meanwhile been trying to do some exploration here. Conditions as a
        result of constant government crises are ‒ or were ‒ very complicated.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> There seems to me to be at least a possibility
        that you may be offered a so-called "masterclass" in composition <tei:note type="editorial"
          place="inline">cued from left margin:</tei:note>emanating from the Academy!<tei:note
          type="editorial" place="inline">end cue</tei:note>, which would fall vacant in September
          1933.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> That could have been achieved
        without more ado, if <tei:rs key="entity-000431" type="person">Kestenberg</tei:rs> still had
        his earlier post at the Ministry; to what extent that is the case under the present, altered
        conditions, I can't exactly say, but I will try and clarify the matter by Christmas. This
        could give you a financial basis for existence. Other lectures ‒ either at the Hochschule or
        with <tei:rs key="entity-000302" type="person">Graener</tei:rs> (who declared himself
        enthusiastic about you) ‒ of the inspiring impact of which I would give sundry assurances
        should the occasion arise, could <tei:pb n="3"/> then easily be added. I will at any rate
        soon be able to tell you more than I know now; things may however perhaps not go as fast as
        we would like, firstly because conditions here are really very unclear at the moment,
        secondly because I may not always myself have the necessary time.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I have had a short letter from <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person"
          >Weisse</tei:rs>. He is doing well, and has clearly ‒ bearing in mind the conditions under
        which he is working ‒ had much success, which pleases me greatly.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I shall write to you again soon. For today, with most cordial greetings as
        ever ‒ and to your <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs>,</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Yours,</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Wilhelm
            Furtwängler</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p>Enclosed <tei:supplied reason="clarity">is</tei:supplied> a review by your pupil
            <tei:rs key="entity-000737" type="person">Roth</tei:rs> from <tei:rs key="entity-002589"
            type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> He is
          also one of those German intellectuals ‒ anyway, a personality in itself not all that
          benevolent, not devoid of envy ‒ who suddenly pay attention differently when one has the
          dubious fortune of being "famous." With this last remark, I really mean to say: may the
          world at long last be enlightened over its false enthusiasm for Furtwängler. And one has
          to put up with that sort of thing! <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">cued from
            left margin:</tei:note>What he praises is characteristic, too: <tei:rs
            key="entity-000851" type="person">Fritz Stein</tei:rs> as a conductor, <tei:supplied
            reason="clarity">and</tei:supplied>
          <tei:rs key="entity-000613" type="person">Muck</tei:rs>'s <tei:rs key="entity-000104"
            type="person">Bruckner</tei:rs>!!<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end
            cue</tei:note></tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
