<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="1781" sdoID="OC-18-52">OC 18/52</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPlk" scope="major">Ludwig Karpath as typist</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="LK" scope="minor">Ludwig Karpath's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="ME">
      <tei:persName>Martin Eybl</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2016</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2016</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2016</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-05-16" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002733">Karpath ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006193">Karpath ~
        Furtwängler</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Typewritten letter (carbon copy) from Karpath to Furtwängler, including a
        typewritten annotation from Karpath to Schenker, dated February 15, 1933</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1933-02-15T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2016-09-28</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Karpath sends the copy of a letter to Furtwängler. He again shows himself
        discontented with the latter's letter. In his letter to the conductor he asks for another
        letter of recommendation.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Unwohlsein; illness; Brief; letter; Elaborat; encomium; spontan; spontaneous;
        Anregung; outpouring; Anfrage; inquiry; Berufung; appointment; hervorragend; eminent;
        Musiker; musician; Leitung; administration; Kundgebung; pronouncement; Zweck; goal;
        Kunstbeirat; Adviser on the Arts; Empfehlung; recommendation; Erfolg; success</dc:subject>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000424">Karpath</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000268">Furtwangler</marcrel:recipient>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:div type="part_1">
        <tei:opener>
          <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#TPlk"
              /><tei:placeName>Wien</tei:placeName>, den <tei:date when="1933-02-10">15. Februar
              1933</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Sehr geehrter Herr Dr. <tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000632">Furtwängler</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01"
              type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary
              at OJ 4/6, p. 3812, February 16, 1933: "Von Karpath (Br.): Durchschlag seiner Antwort
              an Furtwängler; klopft ihm auf die Schulter; wird mich in der nächsten Woche bitten –
              unverbesserlich in seiner Eitelkeit, im Nichtwissen." ("From Karpath (letter): carbon
              copy of his reply to Furtwängler; he pats him on the back; he will summon me next week
              – incorrigible in his vanity, in his ignorance."). — This letter is included in
                  <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Heinrich Schenker: Selected
                  Correspondence</tei:title>, eds. <tei:editor>Ian Bent</tei:editor>,
                  <tei:editor>David Bretherton</tei:editor>, and <tei:editor>William
                  Drabkin</tei:editor> (Woodbridge: Boydell Press, 2014), pp.
              220‒21.</tei:bibl></tei:note></tei:salute>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:p rend="first">Wegen Unwohlseins komme ich erst heute dazu, Ihren Brief vom 6.ds. zu
          beantworten. Leider kann ich Ihr Elaborat über <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"
            >Schenker</tei:rs> nicht brauchen, und zwar wegen des einleitenden Satzes: „Auf Ihre
          Frage über Dr. Schenker möchte ich Ihnen in kurzem folgendes erwidern.“ Das, was ich im
          Interesse Schenkers gewünscht hätte, wäre eine spontane Anregung Ihrerseits gewesen, und
          nicht Antwort auf eine Anfrage. Antwort auf eine Anfrage heisst, dass sich die <tei:rs
            key="entity-002591" type="organization">Akademie</tei:rs> mit einer Erwägung über
          Schenkers Berufung beschäftigt und die Ansicht eines hervorragenden Musikers, wie Sie es
          sind, hätte hören wollen. Das ist aber durchaus nicht der Fall und so würde man mich mit
          Recht fragen, warum ich bei Ihnen angefragt habe, was ja gar nicht der Fall war. Ein
          Anderes ist es, wenn ich der <tei:rs key="entity-002591" type="organization"
            >Akademie</tei:rs>leitung einen Brief aus Ihrer Feder zeige, der sich als eine spontane
          Kundgebung darstellt. Wenn Sie also helfen wollen, den Zweck zu erreichen, so müssten Sie
          einen zweiten Brief an mich schreiben, in dem Sie mich als Kunstbeirat des
          Unterrichtsministeriums auf Schenker aufmerksam machen und mich ersuchen, seine Anstellung
          anzuregen. Auch der Schluss-Satz: „Mehr Verdienste hat als mancher im Moment berühmte
          Komponist“ geht nicht, denn da denkt Jeder an <tei:rs key="entity-000871" type="person"
            >Richard Strauss</tei:rs>, und das vermindert den Grad Ihrer Empfehlungen. Sie dürfen
          mich nicht missverstehen, ich will Ihnen keine Lehren geben, wie man Briefe schreibt, aber
          ich bin gewohnt, nur Dinge zu unternehmen, die irgendwie Aussicht haben, zum Erfolg zu
          führen. Mit Ihrem in meinen Händen befindlichen Brief wäre ein Erfolg nicht zu
          erzielen.</tei:p>


        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Mit den schönsten Grüssen</tei:salute>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Ihr ergebener</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#LK"/><tei:rs key="entity-000424"
              type="person">L. Karpath</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        </tei:closer>
      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="part_2">
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">Typewritten annotation addressed to
          Schenker:</tei:note>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:opener>
          <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#TPlk"/>Lieber Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000632"
              type="person">Schenker</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:p>Dies die Abschrift eines soeben an Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person"
            >Furtwängler</tei:rs> gerichteten Schreibens, über das ich noch mit Ihnen sprechen
          möchte. In einem Begleitschreiben <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person"
            >Furtwängler</tei:rs>s heisst es auch, dass sein Empfehlungsbrief unter gar keinen
          Umständen in die Oeffentlichkeit gelangen dürfe und in- <tei:pb n="2"/> folgedessen ist
          alles, was er gemacht, einfach für die Katz. In der nächsten Woche werde ich Sie bitten,
          einmal zu mir zu kommen, um den weiteren Schlachtenplan zu besprechen. </tei:p>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Inzwischen grüsst herzlichst</tei:salute>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-80">Ihr ergebener</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#LK"/><tei:rs key="entity-000424"
              type="person">L. Karpath</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>

      </tei:div>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:div type="part_1">
        <tei:opener>
          <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#TPlk"
              /><tei:placeName>Vienna</tei:placeName>, <tei:date when="1933-02-10">February 15,
              1933</tei:date></tei:dateline>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Dear Dr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
              >Furtwängler</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:p rend="first">Only today, on account of illness, do I turn to answer your letter of
          the 6th of the month. Unfortunately, I cannot make use of your encomium about <tei:rs
            key="entity-000632" type="person">Schenker</tei:rs>. This is because of your prefatory
          sentence: "In response to your inquiry regarding Dr. Schenker, I should like to reply to
          you briefly as follows." What I would have wished for in the interests of Schenker would
          have been a spontaneous outpouring of appreciation on your part, and not an answer to an
          inquiry. An answer to an inquiry implies that the <tei:rs key="entity-002591"
            type="organization">Academy</tei:rs> is actively considering Schenker's appointment and
          would want to hear the view of an eminent musician such as yourself. But that is
          absolutely not the case, and so people might rightly ask why I had inquired of you, which
          is plainly not at all the case. It is a different matter if I show the <tei:rs
            key="entity-002591" type="organization">Academy</tei:rs> administration a letter from
          your pen that represents a spontaneous pronouncement. Thus, if you wish to help us attain
          our goal, you would have to write me a second letter in which you alert me ‒ as Adviser on
          the Arts to the Ministry of Education ‒ to Schenker and seek to exhort his appointment.
          Also the closing sentence: "has given greater services than many a currently famous
          composer" will not do, for everyone will promptly think of <tei:rs key="entity-000871"
            type="person">Richard Strauss</tei:rs> and that will detract from the force of your
          recommendation. Please do not misunderstand me. I have no wish to give you a lesson in how
          to write a letter; but I am accustomed to undertaking only those things that have some
          prospect of success. With the letter from you that I currently have in my hands, there
          would be no chance of success.</tei:p>


        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-10">With warmest greetings,</tei:salute>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Your devoted</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#LK"/><tei:rs key="entity-000424"
              type="person">L. Karpath</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        </tei:closer>
      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="part_2">
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">Typewritten annotation addressed to
          Schenker:</tei:note>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:opener>
          <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#TPlk"/>Dear Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"
              >Schenker</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:p>This is a copy of a letter that I have just addressed to Dr. <tei:rs
            key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs>, about which I should still like
          to speak to you. In <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs>'s
          covering letter it is made clear that his letter of recommendation may not under any
          circumstance be made public, and <tei:pb n="2"/> as a consequence everything that he says
          is simply worthless. Within the next week I will ask you to come and see me in order to
          discuss our future plan of action.</tei:p>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-20">In the meantime, I send my most cordial
            greetings,</tei:salute>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-80">Your devoted</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#LK"/><tei:rs key="entity-000424"
              type="person">L. Karpath</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>

      </tei:div>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
