<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2655" sdoID="OC-18-23">OC 18/23</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPjm" scope="major">Typist for Josef Marx</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="JM" scope="minor">Joseph Marx's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2011-03-11" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006195">AMdK ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006204">MarxJ ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Typewritten letter from Josef Marx to Schenker, dated February 28, 1933</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1933-02-28T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2022-01-30</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Marx thanks Schenker for hospitality on January 18. He lacks the influence at
        the Vienna Akademie to introduce Schenker's theoretical system, but has advocated for the
        inclusion of Schenker's name on the list of publications to be taken into account in its
        teaching. He has had Violin's name put down for a forthcoming teaching position, but cannot
        say how the Ministry of Education will judge that name.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000577">Joseph Marx</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-002591">Akademie für Musik und darstellende
        Kunst</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>



    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#TPjm"
            /><tei:placeName>Wien</tei:placeName> Dienstag den <tei:date when="1933-02-28">28. Feber
            1933</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Sehr verehrter Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"
            >Doktor</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary for February 28, 1933: “Von Marx (Br.):
            lang, sehr ergeben, verdächtig ergeben ‒ sucht er Stoff, Belehrung für sich u. seine
            Schüler? Will er mit Furtwängler zusammenkommen, um seine Orchestersachen anzubringen?
            Mein Name im „neuen Schulstatut“ vorgemerkt „wenigstens im Amtsbetrieb“ — Violin
            ebenfalls „vorgemerkt“ ‒ will wieder kommen” (“From Marx (letter): long, respectful,
            suspiciously respectful ‒ Is he after material and information for himself and his
            students? Will he get together with Furtwängler in order to have his orchestral works
            heard? My name put down in the ‘new school statute,’ ‘at least in the official business’
            ‒ Violin likewise ‘put down’ ‒ will get back to me!”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Sie werden mich schon für einen "Vergesslichen" oder gar "Ungetreuen"
        halten, weil ich so lange nichts von mir hören liess; es hatte seine Gründe. Ich wollte
        nicht brieflich vor Ihnen erscheinen, ohne nicht wenigstens einiges versucht zu haben, und
        Ihnen darüber Mitteilung zu machen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Vorerst möchte ich Ihnen aber für Ihre liebenswürdige Freundlichkeit
        danken, die ich bei meinem ersten Besuch in angenehmster Weise spüren konnte, und auch für
        die Sympathie, die ich als Echo meiner persönlichen Einstellung zu Ihnen auffasse, und der
        Hoffnung Ausdruck gebe, jene Echowirkung möge sich von Fall zu Fall verstärken! </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">In Angelegenheit Ihres theoretischen Systems ist an der <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002591">Akademie</tei:rs> momentan wohl nicht viel
        durchzusetzen, ausser es wird irgendwas von oben dekretiert. Ich habe nicht die Leitung der
        Anstalt, man hört auch nicht gern auf mich, weil andere am Werk sind, die sich besser
        "verhalten" können als ich, auch (einige!) A-B-C- Schützen, wie Sie sich kürzlich witzig
        äusserten, sind nicht ganz leicht umzustimmen, wenn von der Kurrent-zur Lateinschrift
        übergegangen wird. Man hat so seine liebe Not. Immerhin habe ich die Aufnahme Ihres Namens
        als Autor wertvoller, im Unterricht zu berücksichtigender Werke im neuen Schulstatut
        veranlasst, und er wird sich auch dort finden, wenn er nicht bei der Sanktionierung im
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-005584">Unterrichtsministerium</tei:rs> gestrichen
        wird, was aber kaum zu befürchten ist. So scheinen Sie wenigstens bereits namentlich im
        Amtsbetrieb auf; für unsere Zeit und obendrein Tradition, wo alles am liebsten hundert Jahre
        zu spät kommt, immerhin etwas!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Schenker reported the gist of this paragraph in a letter to Anthony van Hoboken of March
          22, 1933, <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-89-6_4">OJ 89/6, [4]</tei:ref>. In
          translation, it reads: “Court Counselor Marx has written me that my works are "designated"
          to be "teaching materials" in the curriculum of the Academy. He assured me of his
          commitment and again invited himself to visit me. The case is especially difficult: he
          seems to be a nice person, but he is too constantly on the lookout for material for the
            <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002530"><tei:title level="j">Neues Wiener
              Journal</tei:title></tei:rs> – everything he gleaned from the first visit promptly
          came out in the <tei:title level="j">N.W.J.</tei:title>, but dreadfully misunderstood – no
          pupil whether male or female, no visitor has ever stood so helpless at my piano. […] I
          must protect myself against Marx's trespassing on my property. I attach no importance to
          the "reservation": how could it ever be accomplished with a status quo
        ante?”</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> Die Vormerkung <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913"
          >Violin</tei:rs>s für eine freiwerdende Lehrstelle an der <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002591">Akademie</tei:rs> habe ich auch durchsetzen können; leider ist dies
        bisher alles, was erreichbar war . . . Und dabei ist es natürlich noch immer fraglich, wie
        ein diesbezüglicher Antrag im <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-005584"
          >Ministerium</tei:rs> beurteilt wird, <tei:sic>ab</tei:sic> er durch geht oder abgelehnt
        wird. Auch mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005234">Reitler</tei:rs> habe ich
        gesprochen; aber leider hat er sich mit ihm einmal verstritten, und das wirkt sich auch
        jetzt noch irgendwie aus. Schade, dass er nicht nach dem Umsturz in Wien war, da wäre alles
        viel leichter gegangen. <tei:sic>Under</tei:sic> der Vorschlag <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000913">Violin</tei:rs>s, nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-006589"
          >Istanbul</tei:rs> zu gehen, kann mit gutem Gewissen nicht unterstützt werden. Der Mann
        würde dort in der orientalischen Einsamkeit, bei schlechter Bezahlung und den völlig
        geänderten Lebensverhältnissen bestimmt in kürzester Zeit gemütskrank. So kann man nur
        hoffen, es lässt sich in absehbarer Zeit hier was für ihn tun. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">So, nun habe ich Ihre wertvolle Zeit genug in Anspruch genommen. Ich
        begrüsse Sie herzlichst, ebenso bitte ich meine ergebensten Empfehlungen der verehrten
        gnädigen <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Frau</tei:rs> zu vermitteln. Werde mich
        besonders freuen, wenn ich Gelegenheit haben werde, Sie in nächster Zeit wieder aufzusuchen. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Mit dem Ausdruck besonderer Hochschätzung</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">bin ich Ihr ergebenster</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#JM"/><tei:rs key="entity-000577"
            type="person">Marx</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#TPjm"
            /><tei:placeName>Vienna</tei:placeName> Tuesday <tei:date when="1933-02-28">February 28,
            1933</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Much revered Dr. <tei:supplied><tei:rs key="entity-000632"
              type="person">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
            type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">You will by now be taking me for "forgetful" or even "unfaithful," because
        you have heard nothing from me for so long. There were reasons for that. I did not want to
        put anything in writing to you without having at least tried something and informing you
        about it.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">First of all, I should like to thank your gracious kindness, which I
        sensed on my first visit, and also for your understanding, which I take as an echo of my
        personal feeling toward you. It is my hope that this reciprocal effect may grow as time goes
        by!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">In the matter of your theoretical system, there is really not much that
        can be accomplished at the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002591">Academy</tei:rs>,
        unless something is decreed from on high. I do not have control over the institution, nor
        does anybody want to listen to me because others are at work who know how to "behave" better
        than I; also <tei:supplied reason="clarity">there are</tei:supplied> (one or two!)
        A-B-C-sharpshooters, as you recently so wittily put it, who cannot be so easily persuaded if
        one switches from cursive to regular script. One has one's hands full with such people. For
        all that, I have advocated the inclusion of your name in the new school statute as the
        author of valuable works that should be taken account of in teaching, and it will appear
        there if it is not struck out by being sanctioned against in the <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-005584">Ministry of Education</tei:rs> ‒ something that is not really to be
        feared. So you at least already figure by name in the official business. For our time – and,
        moreover, a tradition by which everything at best arrives a hundred years too late –
        something nevertheless!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> I have also succeeded in having <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000913">Violin</tei:rs>'s name put down for a teaching position that is about
        to fall vacant at the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002591">Academy</tei:rs>.
        Sadly, this is the best that could be achieved up to now . . . Of course, it is as always a
        matter for debate how this application will be judged at the <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-005584">Ministry</tei:rs> ‒ whether it will go through or be denied. I have
        also spoken with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005234">Reitler</tei:rs>; but
        unfortunately he once got into a row with him, and that may now work against him in some
        way. It's a pity he wasn't in Vienna after the overthrow ‒ that would have made things a lot
        easier. And <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Violin</tei:rs>'s suggestion of going
        to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-006589">Istanbul</tei:rs> can in good conscience not be
        supported. There, in oriental isolation, badly paid, and with radically changed living
        conditions, the fellow would be sure to become depressed in no time at all. We can only hope
        that in the foreseeable future something will be able to be worked out for him.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ah well! I have taken up enough of your precious time. I send you my most
        heartfelt greetings, and likewise ask you to remember me most cordially to your dear <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000771">wife</tei:rs>. I should be delighted if I were to have
        the opportunity of visiting in the near future.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">In expressing high esteem, </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">I remain your most devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#JM"/><tei:rs key="entity-000577"
            type="person">Marx</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
