<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2565" sdoID="OC-1-B-23">OC 1 B/23</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="JK" scope="major">Jeanette Kornfeld's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="minor">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006, 2021</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2006, 2021</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2021</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2011-03-05" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002704">TürkelS ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002699">DeutschS ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">letter</tei:rs>
      <dc:title>Handwritten draft letter from Schenker to Siegfried Türkel, dated March 17,
        1917</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1917-03-17T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2021-09-24</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker encloses a letter from Dr. Hugo Friedmann and comments on it,
        ridiculing the lack of sophistication of the wealthy, and asserting his own indifference to
        money.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>talmudisch; Talmudic; Jude; Jew; Stipendium; stipend; Reichen; the wealthy; Geld;
        money; Millionäre; millionaire; Milliardeur; billionaire</dc:subject>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">Heinrich Schenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000902">Siegfried Türkel</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address rend="indent-80">
          <tei:addrLine>(<tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000902">Dr.
                Türkel</tei:rs></tei:hi>)</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>
            <tei:date when="1917-03-17">17. III. 17</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>Sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000902"
          >Doktor</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Beiliegend ein heute eingelaufener Brief von Herrn <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000257">D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Friedmann</tei:rs>.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker had drafted a letter five days
          earlier (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-1-B-19-20">OC 1B/19–20</tei:ref>) to Dr.
          Friedmann and another two days after that (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-16-32v"
            >OC 16/32v</tei:ref>). No letter from him to Schenker prior to this date is known to
          have survived, but the letter in question was presumably in response to what resulted from
          those two drafts.</tei:note> Nach dieser talmudistischen Erklärung (ich selbst bin Jude)
        gelangt man zu dem Schlusse, daß <tei:hi rend="underline">ich</tei:hi> das
          Stipendium<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">i.e. the stipend
          left to him by Sofie Deutsch in her will: see <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-10-4_1">OJ 10/4, [1]</tei:ref>, January 26, 1916; <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-12-52_1">OJ 12/52, [1]</tei:ref>, January 12,
          1917.</tei:note> erst nach meinem Tode vergeben sollte. Welche Wandlung nimmt doch die
        Sache seit jenem Brief des Herrn <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000590"
          >Kammerrat</tei:rs>s an mich,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Presumably <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-12-52_1">OJ 12/52, [1]</tei:ref>,
          January 12, 1917, from Fritz Mendl to Schenker.</tei:note> der nichts von diesen
        Haarspaltereien wußte. Und einmal nun wieder in diese Angelegenheit geworfen, will ich,
        lediglich zu Ihrem privaten Gebrauche, in Würdigung gemeinsamer musikalischer Interessen
        nachträglich folgende drastische Erläuterung bieten: Den Herrn <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000590">Kammerrat</tei:rs> schätze ich bis zur Stunde als einen Mann, dem ich
        unter den vielen Industriellen, Bankdirektoren usw, die ich im Leben gesehen, am ehesten das
        Prädikat „genial“ zubillige.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Cf.
          Schenker's first impression of Mendl, at Deutsch's house on December 21, 1906 (diary): "At
          the meal, a brother of the lady of the house, Mr. Fritz Mendl, turns out to be an
          excellent, clever fellow, and equally superb husband and father."</tei:note> Diese Ansicht
        lasse ich mir nicht einmal von ihm selbst <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">rauben</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">nehmen</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>. Stellen Sie dagegen aber folgendes: Eines Tages vor etwa 2–3 Jahren läßt er
        mich durch <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Fr. Deutsch</tei:rs> fragen, ob ich
        nicht ein Mädchen bei einer Musikkapelle unterbringen <tei:pb n="2"/> konnte?! Ich u. eine
        Damenkapelle „<tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">sapiente sat</tei:foreign><tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">“</tei:supplied>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial"
          place="foot"><tei:hi rend="italic">sapiente sat</tei:hi>: Lat.: “a word is enough to the
          wise.”</tei:note> Hier liegt die Wurzel bloß. So sieht der Herr <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000590">Kammerrat</tei:rs> einen Menschen dem nachgewiesenermaßen in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002482">Deutschland</tei:rs> höherer Rang als <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000712">Hugo Riemann</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000484">Hermann Kretzschmar</tei:rs>, als <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000110">Bülow</tei:rs> usw. zugebilligt wird, dem der größte Teil der
        deutschen Jugend huldigt u. folgt, wovon man nur gerade in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002506">Oesterreich</tei:rs> sehr wenig weiß, bloß weil ich einmal dem <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000060">Herrn Benedikt</tei:rs> verraten habe, daß <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000470">Korngold</tei:rs> usw. Herr <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000738">Alfred Rothberger</tei:rs>, Stephansplatz 9, erzählte mir einmal, daß
        er in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002643">London</tei:rs> als Gast eines größten
        Tuchhändlers seinen Gastgeber nach dem Grab des Walther Scott befragte, worauf er die
        Gegenfrage bekam: „Ist das der Cheviothändler Scott? Die Gastgeberin aber flötete: „Aber
        nein, das ist ja der Märchenerzähler.“ Im Hause I, Ehendorferstr. 2, großes, größtes
        Holzhandungshaus verkehrte ich 10–15 Jahre als Freund des Hauses. Rasch habe ich mir für
        mein Teil gemerkt, daß <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006229">Herr Eisler</tei:rs> ein
        großes Holzgeschäft betreibt, aber umgekehrt fragte mich all die vielen Jahre her der
          <tei:pb n="3"/> sonderbare Herr beim Schwarzen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06"
          type="editorial" place="foot">“beim Schwarzen”: uncertain meaning. Literally, “of/in the
          black,” this could be financial, or relate to the black market prevalent in Austria at the
          time, or perhaps it might be an idiom for “on the sly,” or maybe he was a man with a black
          beard or eyebrows! </tei:note> für welche Zeitung ich schreibe. Bis ich endlich das Haus
        aufgab. Ein gewisses Niveau der Betrachtung muß doch da sein.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07"
          type="editorial" place="foot">No paragraph break in the original at this
        point</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>In Ihrer Eigenschaft als Anwalt dürften Sie ebensogut als ich die Natur der Reichen
        kennen. Nun bin ich glücklicherweise so beschaffen, daß ich ihnen nirgend den Vortritt
        lasse, am allerwenigsten, wenn sie auf Geld pochend Ansprüche stellen. (<tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000165">Fr. Deutsch</tei:rs> wußte davon ein Lied zu singen.)
        Ins Gesicht sage ich es den reichen Leuten, daß die wahren Bettler u. Schmarotzer der Welt
        die Reichen sind u. werfen sich Millionäre in die Brust, so <tei:del rend="overstrike"
          >g</tei:del> sage ich: ich bin ein Milliardeur u. <tei:foreign xml:lang="ita"
          >basta</tei:foreign>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot">“ich bin
          ein Milliardeur u. basta“: note Schenker’s toying with other languages, probably to
          achieve an ironic edge: French <tei:hi rend="italic">Milliardeur</tei:hi> (though the
          French word is actually <tei:hi rend="italic">Milliardaire</tei:hi>) and Italian <tei:hi
            rend="italic">basta</tei:hi>. “Milliardeur” is also ambiguous: it could be translated
          “billionaire.”</tei:note> In der Tat krümmten sich vor mir die Reichen, wenn es um ein
        paar Groschen ging, wie die elendesten Straßensammler, während mir ein Leichtes war, auf
        sein Geld u. alles zu verzichten, wenn er nur dieses betonte. Auf diese Weise bitte ich Sie,
        sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000257">Doktor</tei:rs>, meine völlige
        Gleichgiltigkeit <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">puncto</tei:foreign><tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn09" type="editorial" place="foot">Note how Schenker uses Latin words and
          phrases, <tei:hi rend="italic">sapiente sat</tei:hi> earlier, <tei:hi rend="italic"
            >puncto</tei:hi> here; he does this frequently to raise the tone of discourse or to
          overawe his correspondent; in this case, it is more likely to be on the basis of one
          lawyer to another.</tei:note> all der Beträge zu erklären; ich folge Ihrem Rat, nichts
          <tei:pb n="4"/> weiter. Auch habe ich ja im Falle der <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000165">Fr. D.</tei:rs> wirklich ein Recht auf so manches. Vergessen Sie bitte
        nicht, daß ich bei <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002405">Cotta</tei:rs>,
        Stuttgart, meine <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001723"><tei:title>Neuen Theorien u.
            Phantasien</tei:title></tei:rs> im Jahre 1906 u. 1910 publiziert habe, auch ohne
        Akkreditiv u. Zusicherung usw. Es ging, es wird gehen, weil es gehen <tei:note
          type="editorial" place="inline">12 lines in Heinrich Schenker’s hand, inverted, comprising
          a copy with variants of paragraph 1 of <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-10-4_1">OJ
            10/4, [1]</tei:ref> January 26, 1916, from Sofie Deutsch to Schenker</tei:note> muß.
        Ende März erscheine ich über Ihren Wunsch in Ihrer Kanzlei u. grüße Sie bis dahin aufs beste
        als </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Ihr sehr ergebener</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">unsigned</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p>P.S. Gleichzeitig danke ich Herrn <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000590"
            >Kammerrat</tei:rs> für seine Freundlichkeit mit ein paar Zeilen an ihn selbst. </tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>


    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address rend="indent-80">
          <tei:addrLine>(<tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000902">Dr.
                Türkel</tei:rs></tei:hi>)</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>
            <tei:date when="1917-03-17">March 17, 1917</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>Dear Dr. <tei:supplied><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000902"
            >Türkel</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Enclosed is a letter received today from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000257">Dr.
          Friedmann</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> On the basis of this
        Talmudic explanation (I myself am a Jew), one is led to the conclusion that I should be able
        to award the stipend<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> only after my death!
        What a turn the matter has taken since the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000590">Chamber
          Counselor</tei:rs>’s letter to me,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> which
        showed not a trace of this hair-splitting! And now that I have once more been thrust into
        this affair, I will go further and offer you, purely for your own private use, the following
        drastic explanation in appreciation of <tei:supplied reason="clarity">our</tei:supplied>
        common musical interests. I esteem the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000590">Chamber
          Counselor</tei:rs> up to the present moment as a man to whom I would, among the many
        industrialists, bank directors, etc. that I have encountered in the course of my life,
        soonest accord the attribute of “having a touch of genius.”<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
          type="footnote"/> I concede this opinion not solely on the basis of the man himself: One
        day, some two or three years ago, he asked my through <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000165">Mrs. Deutsch</tei:rs> whether I <tei:pb n="2"/> could place a girl in
        a band?! Me and a women’s band: <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat"><tei:hi rend="italic">sapiente
            sat</tei:hi></tei:foreign>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> This is the
        root of the matter. So the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000590">Chamber
          Counselor</tei:rs> sees a man to whom is evidently granted higher status in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002482">Germany</tei:rs> than <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000712">Hugo Riemann</tei:rs> or <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000484"
          >Hermann Kretzschmar</tei:rs>, than <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000110"
          >Bülow</tei:rs>, etc, to whom the majority of the German new generation pays homage and
        whom it emulates, but of whom people in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002506"
          >Austria</tei:rs> itself know very little, all because I once divulged to <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000060">Mr. Benedikt</tei:rs> that <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000470">Korngold</tei:rs> etc., etc. Mr. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000738">Alfred Rothberger</tei:rs>, Stephansplatz 9, once told me that when in
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002643">London</tei:rs> as guest of a major cloth
        merchant he asked his host after the grave of Walter Scott, whereupon the counter-question
        came back: ‘Is that Scott the dealer in cheviot wool?” However, his hostess said in a sugary
        voice: “Oh no, that is surely the fairytale-teller.” For ten to fifteen years I frequented
          <tei:supplied reason="identity">Vienna</tei:supplied> I, Ehendorferstraße 2, the house of
        a great – of the greatest – timber merchant, as a friend of the family. I quickly made a
        mental note to myself that <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006229">Mr. Eisler</tei:rs> ran
        a big timber business, but conversely in all those years the <tei:pb n="3"/> remarkable
        gentleman asked me in the black<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> which
        newspaper I wrote for. In the end, I gave up visiting the house. A certain level of
        consideration has to exist.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>In your capacity as an attorney, you must be as well acquainted as I am with the nature
        of rich people. Now, happily I am constituted such that I do not under any circumstances
        give them precedence, least of all when they insistently make claims on money. (<tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000165">Mrs. Deutsch</tei:rs> knew a thing or two about that.) I
        tell rich people to their faces that the true beggars and spongers of the world are the rich
        people, and when millionaires give themselves airs, I just say: I am a multi-millionaire and
        that’s enough!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/> In actual fact, rich people
        squirmed before me when it was a matter of a couple of measly pennies, like the most
        wretched garbage collectors, whereas it was easy for me to forego his money and everything
        else when this is what he emphasized. I beg you, dear <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000257">Doctor</tei:rs>, to explain my complete indifference in regard
          to<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09" type="footnote"/> all sums of money along these lines. I
        follow your advice, but go no <tei:pb n="4"/> further. Moreover, in the case of <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000165">Mrs. Deutsch</tei:rs> I really do have a right to a
        great deal. Please do not forget that I published my <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001723"
            ><tei:title level="m">New Musical Theories and Fantasies</tei:title></tei:rs> with
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002405">Cotta</tei:rs> of Stuttgart in 1906 and
        1910 without any letter of credit or guarantee, etc. It sufficed, it will suffice, because
        it has to suffice. <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">12 lines in Heinrich Schenker’s
          hand, inverted, comprising a copy with variants of paragraph 1 of <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-10-4_1">OJ 10/4, [1]</tei:ref> January 26, 1916, from
          Sofie Deutsch to Schenker</tei:note> I will appear in your chancellry as you request at
        the end of March, and remain until then with best wishes as</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Your devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">unsigned</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p>P.S. At the same time, I am writing a couple of lines direct to the <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000590">Chamber Counselor </tei:rs> to thank him for his
          kindness.</tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>


    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
