<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2261" sdoID="OC-12-249">OC 12/249</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="major">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS-pencil" scope="minor">Heinrich Schenker's hand, in
        pencil</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>


    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2012-09-26" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-007030">KlenauP ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter (copy) from Schenker to Klenau, dated January 4, 1924</dc:title>
      <dcterms:created>1924-01-04T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-09-02</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker responds to Klenau's remarks on atonal composers and a coming
        Renaissance; invites him to visit on a Wednesday.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Renaissance; afeminine; a-feminine; impotent; Fortschritt; progress; Entwicklung;
        development; Selbstbeschmeichlung; self-conceit; Selbstbetrug; self-deception; Natur;
        Nature; Folgerichtigkeit; consistency; Geschichte; history; Richtung; trend; Bewegung;
        movement; Atonalen; atonal composers; Unfähigkeit; incapacity; Besuch; visit</dc:subject>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000443">Paul von Klenau</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:add><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">top-right
            corner:</tei:note><tei:handShift new="#HS-pencil"/>Fortschritt Renaiss</tei:add><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>Geehrtester Herr <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000443">v. Klenau</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
            place="foot">Writing of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/6, pp.
            2615‒2616, January 2, 1924: "An Klenau (Br.); von <tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000771">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs> kopiert): zu den Atonalen: impotent darf
            nicht afeminin sich nennen – die Natur gibt auch der Unfähigkeit des Atonalen ihre
            Folge: sie müssen atonal sein, sie wollen nicht! Renaissance ein Unding; es gibt kein
            Zusammengehen der Menschheit mit den Großen; stelle Mittwoch zur Verfügung." ("To Klenau
            (letter) ; copied by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs>):
            about the atonalists: the impotent should not be allowed to call themselves unfeminine –
            Nature also exacts the consequences from the atonalists' incompetence: they have to be
            atonal, they do not wish to be! Renaissance an absurdity; there is no association
            between humanity and the great masters; put Wednesday at his disposal."). The letter ‒
            which is preserved in a miscellaneous collection (OC 12) of correspondence, writings,
            and newspaper clippings ‒ is written on two sheets, the second pasted to the bottom of
            the first to make a single sheet written on one side. This letter is presented in
            translation in <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Heinrich Schenker: Selected
                Correspondence</tei:title>, ed. <tei:editor>Ian Bent</tei:editor>, <tei:editor>David
                Bretherton</tei:editor>, and <tei:editor>William Drabkin</tei:editor> (Woodbridge:
              Boydell Press, 2014), p. 245‒46</tei:bibl>.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Herzlich erwidere ich Ihre freundlichen Wünsche, nicht minder herzlich
        danke ich für Ihre freudige Zustimmung zur <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001731"
            ><tei:title>IX</tei:title></tei:rs>. Wegen der übrigen Gedanken über die <tei:hi
          rend="underline">Atonalen</tei:hi> wie die Renaissançe wenn ein impotenter Mann sich für
          <tei:hi rend="underline">afeminin</tei:hi> ausgeben würde mit Anspruch auf eine
        philosophische oder sonst welche Richtung, auf Fortschritt, Entwicklung? Dem unglücklichen
        Manne täte die Selbstbeschmeichlung, der Selbstbetrug in der Seele wohl, aber die Frauen
        würden ihn richtiger beurteilen. Oder von einer andern Seite gesehen: Die Natur ist immer
        folgerichtig, d.h. sie gibt allen Ursachen ihre Folge, aber eben darum wäre es falsch, ihre
        Folgerichtigkeit in Fortschritt, Geschichte, Richtung, Bewegung überhaupt umzubenennen. Ein
        Bückel, ein Mulo Mulatte u. was dergleichen Dinge mehr sind, die die Natur aus gegebenen
        Ursachen hervorzieht, bedeuten gewiß kein Ziel, gar nichts weiter als eine Folgerichtigkeit.
        So stellen auch die Atonalen eine solche Natur-Folgerichtigkeit vor u. nichts mehr als das:
        sie müßten atonal werden, sie müssen atonal bleiben, weil die Natur in gewohnter Weise ihrer
        Unfähigkeit eine Folge gibt, aber von ihnen zu sagen, daß sie atonal sein wollen, wie sie es
        vorgeben, um Entwicklung oder Durchgang, Keim vorzustellen, entspricht nicht dem wahren
        Sachverhalt. Vergessen Sie nicht: Der Zerstörende ‒ u. das ist der Atonale ‒ gefällt sich in
        einer sehr dankbaren Rolle: er glaubt immer von vorn anzufangen, ha, wie fühlt man sich da
        einen Helden!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Eine <tei:hi rend="underline">Renaissançe</tei:hi> gibt es meiner Ansicht
        nach überhaupt nicht: man nimmt von neuem auf, was die Menschen vordem aus Unfähigkeit
        aufgegeben haben, aber nicht mit mehr Verständnis. Ich halte ein Zusammengehen der
        Menschheit mit den Großen nicht für möglich, ja auch nicht für erwünscht. Immer wieder ist
        es der Einzelne, der als Großer hervortritt u. wiederum sind es nur wenige, die sich ein
          <tei:sic>bischen</tei:sic>, sehr sehr wenig nähern: der Rest ist bloß unbescheiden. Doch
        genug davon.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Daß ich mich sehr freuen würde, Sie wieder einmal zu begrüßen, wiederhole
        ich gern. Am Mittwoch empfange ich keine Schüler, vielleicht paßt es Ihnen, an irgend einem
        Mittwoch mir das Vergnügen Ihres Besuches zu machen; aber auch für diesen Fall erbitte ich
        eine Verständigung aus Vorsicht, denn es kommt vor, daß ich ins <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002430">Archiv</tei:rs> gehe usw.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Mit besten Grüßen</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript><tei:lb/>
        <tei:p>P.S. <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001744">Heft 5 des
              <tei:title>Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs> bringt die <tei:rs type="composition"
            key="entity-001265"><tei:title>V. Sinfonie</tei:title></tei:rs> von <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>, vielleicht werfen Sie einen Blick
          darauf </tei:p>
        <tei:p><tei:date when="1924-01-04">4. I. 24</tei:date></tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:add><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">top-right
            corner:</tei:note><tei:handShift new="#HS-pencil"/>Progress Renaissance</tei:add><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>Most revered Mr. <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000443">v. Klenau</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"
          /></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">I reciprocate cordially your kind good wishes, and I thank you no less
        cordially for your ready approval of my <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001731"><tei:title
            level="m">Ninth Symphony</tei:title></tei:rs>
        <tei:supplied reason="clarity">monograph</tei:supplied>. As regards your further remarks on
        the <tei:hi rend="underline">atonal composers</tei:hi> as the Renaissance: If an impotent
        man were to claim to be <tei:hi rend="underline">a-feminine</tei:hi> by reference to a
        philosophical or some other sort of trend ‒ toward progress, development? ‒ the
        self-conceit, self-deception, might please the unfortunate man to the core, but women would
        judge him more accurately. Or from another point of view: Nature is always consistent; that
        is, to every cause she supplies its logical effect; but that is just why it would be wrong
        ever to give her consistency another name: progress, history, trend, movement. A humpback, a
        mule, a mulatto, and all other such things of that sort that Nature has produced from given
        causes, specifically do not signify any purpose ‒ nothing whatsoever more than a logical
        consistency. So the atonal composers represent a consistency in Nature and nothing more than
        that: they had to become atonal, they must remain atonal, because Nature in her usual
        fashion gives to their incapacity a consequence. But to say of them that they want to be
        atonal, as they allege, in order to foster development, transition or germination, does not
        correspond with the true state of affairs. Do not forget: The destroyer ‒ and the atonal
        composer is just that ‒ fancies himself in a rewarding role: he believes always in starting
        from scratch. Ah! what a hero he thinks himself for that!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">To my mind, there is no such thing as a <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >Renaissance</tei:hi>. People take up anew what their predecessors have given up out of
        incapacity, but with no greater understanding. I do not consider possible ‒ or indeed even
        desirable ‒ an association of humanity with the great masters. It is always the individual
        who emerges as a great master, and then again it is only a few who come close, very very
        slightly so, <tei:supplied reason="clarity">to achieving this</tei:supplied>. All the others
        are merely presumptuous. But enough of all that.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I gladly reiterate that I would be delighted to welcome you once again. I
        see no pupils on Wednesdays. Perhaps it would suit you to do me the favor of a visit one
        Wednesday or another. But even in this case I ask for prior notice as a precaution, for it
        could be that I am going to the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002430"
          >Archive</tei:rs>, or something of that sort.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>With best wishes,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript><tei:lb/>
        <tei:p>P.S. <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001744">Issue 5 of <tei:title level="j">Der
              Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs> includes the <tei:rs type="composition"
            key="entity-001265"><tei:title>Fifth Symphony</tei:title></tei:rs> of <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>. You may like to take a look at
          it.</tei:p>
        <tei:p><tei:date when="1924-01-04">January 4, 1924</tei:date></tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>



    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
