<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="3586" sdoID="OC-24-9">OC 24/9</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2025</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">
  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated November 7, 1921</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1921-11-07T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-04-23</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Oppel has not been able to write to Schenker all year because of overwork. He was
    intending to write a theory book that would develop the same concepts as found in the first
    issue of Der Tonwille; but he prioritizes compositional activity during his limited spare time.
    — He comments on the political situation in Germany, and on the success of Schenker’s work
    there.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>



   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002757">Kiel</tei:rs>, <tei:date
      when="1921-11-07">7. XI. 21.</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:address rend="indent-60">
     <tei:addrLine>Feldstr 77<tei:hi rend="supralinear">IV.</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Sehr verehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
       >D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Schenker</tei:rs>![1]</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>entschuldigen Sie bitte mein langes Schweigen! Lediglich Arbeit ist der Grund. 25 Stunden
    im <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002608">Konservatorium</tei:rs> und 15 zu Hause in
    der Woche, daneben Konzerte und die Kontrolle der Schularbeiten meiner beiden älteren Jungen,
    Versammlungen und Betriebsrats(!)lizenzen im Kons. lassen mich wenig zur Ruhe kommen. Ich
    schreibe Ihnen nun bald ein Jahr, und jedesmal gibt’s eine andre Abhaltung von diesem Schritt.
    Zunächst einen heissen Dank für die Übersendung <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001739">des
      „<tei:title>Tonwillen</tei:title>“</tei:rs>. Vortrefflich, ich unterschreibe jedes Wort.
    Übrigens hatte ich in den Sommerferien vor, die gleichen Ideen zu beweisen und zu gewissen
     <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">illegible word</tei:note> ich hatte mir als
    Erläuterungsbeispiele die <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001208"
      ><tei:title>Waldstein</tei:title>-Sonate</tei:rs> (1. Satz) u. von Bach das <tei:rs
     type="composition" key="entity-001130">H-dur Präl. wohltemp. Klavier II No. 23</tei:rs>
    <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">illegible word</tei:note> u. ein paar Melodien von
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003691">Verdi</tei:rs>. Eigne Kompositionen liessen mich aber
    nicht zur Ausführung kommen. Ich werde aber noch einiges dazu schreiben, sobald ich mit meinem
    Streichquintett fertig bin. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>In den nächsten Tagen wird Sie Herr Richard Glas, unser l. Klavierlehrer, aufsuchen. Er
    ist selbst Wiener u. Schüler der Meisterschule u. von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000293"
     >Godowsky</tei:rs>. Er spielt dort in einem eignen Abend auch meine 2. Klaviersonate. Er bringt
    Ihnen auch den Prospect unsrer Anstalt – übrigens wie die meisten Kons. eine Musikfabrik, der
    Director ist ein übler Patron – <tei:sic>in</tei:sic> dem ich, wie Sie sehn werden, in meinem
    Artikel schon von den Urgesetzen der Melodie sprach; <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"
     >illegible word</tei:note> freute ich mich sehr, als ich, nach den Ferien von einer Reise
    zurückgekehrt, Ihre herrliche Arbeit auf meinem Schreibtisch vorfand. Also nochmals herzlichen
    Dank! Glas bringt Ihnen auch noch einige politische Zeitungen mit, die Sie sicher mit Interesse
    durchsehn werden. Wie steht es mit Ihren Umzugsabsichten? Ich bedauere immer wieder, dass mir
    die jeglichen üblen Zustände u. finanziellen Verhältnissen <tei:pb n="2"/> nicht gestatten, noch
    bei Ihnen persönlich zu studieren. Es ist traurig, dass wir jetzt kaum noch die wichtigsten
    Bücher kaufen können. Aber soviel kann ich Ihnen wenigstens sagen, dass die Jugend u. ein
    grosser Teil der Bevölkerung schon wieder anders denken u. aufwärts streben; nur die Arbeiter
    sind noch nach wie vor zu 90% total verblendet. Die werden auch nicht eher vernünftig, als bis
    der Franzose im ganzen Land ist u. jedem Mannsbild die Peitsche morgens u. abends in Gesicht
    baut. Dann sehen sie vielleicht ihre Dummheiten an. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich würde mich sehr freuen, wenn Sie sich meine Sonate anhörten, sie ist 2 Jahre alt u.
    Glas spielt sie sehr gut. – Ich hatte vor, diesen Winter eigentlich ein Analysenbuch zu
    schreiben, in Form einer Kompositionslehre; leider sind die Jungen aber im Gymnasium während des
    Kriegs so schlecht unterrichtet worden, – dazu fehlte die väterliche Zucht u. die Frauen rannten
    stundenlang nach Lebensmittel – dass ich jetzt vieles mitarbeiten u. nachholen muss, um sie an
    Gründlichkeit zu gewöhnen. Und so wird diesen Winter wohl kaum was daraus werden. Plan u. Ideen
    liegen vor und sind von mir auch in der Schule genügend ausprobiert. Ich glaube, dass ich durch
    Ihre Hilfe damit auf dem rechten Wege bin. Wenn ich dann aber den Drang zum Komponieren habe,
    lasse ich natürlich die theoretischen Arbeiten liegen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ihre <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">two words crossed out</tei:note> neuen
    Veröffentlichungen sagen mir, als Zeugen einer ungebrochenen Schaffenskraft, dass es Ihnen
    leidlich geht, soweit das jetzt in Wien der Fall sein kann; ich freue mich auf Glasens
    mündlichen Bericht. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Mit den besten Wünschen für Sie bleibe ich</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">mit den herzlichsten Grüssen</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr sehr ergebener u. dankbarer</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">D<tei:hi
       rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Reinhard Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p>Übrigens freute mich auf meinen Reisen der Erfolg Ihrer Bücher: <tei:rs type="person"
      key="entity-008291">Mendelssohn</tei:rs> in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004486"
      >Darmstadt</tei:rs>, mit dem ich über Sie sprach, erzählte mir, der Komponist
     Vrieslander[entity-000922] nach der Lectüre Ihrer Werke jegliches Komponieren aufgestrebt. Viel
     war auch nicht an <tei:unclear reason="reading">seinen</tei:unclear>
     <tei:unclear reason="reading">Sachen</tei:unclear>, aber diese Einsicht ist immerhin wohltuend.
    </tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002757">Kiel</tei:rs>, <tei:date
      when="1921-11-07">November 7, 1921</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:address rend="indent-60">
     <tei:addrLine>Feldstr 77/4</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Highly revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Dr.
      Schenker</tei:rs>,[1]</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Please excuse my long silence! Work is the only reason for it: twenty-five lessons at the
     <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002608">Conservatory</tei:rs>, and fifteen at home each
    week, also concerts and the supervision of my two older boys’ schoolwork, meetings and licenses
    for work councils(!) leave me little peace. For a year I have wanted to write to you, and each
    time something else prevents me from taking this step. First of all, warm thanks for sending me
     <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001739"><tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>.
    Outstanding, I endorse every word. Moreover, I had hoped to verify the same concepts, and for
    certain <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">illegible word</tei:note>], with the first
    movement of the <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001208"><tei:title level="m"
      >Waldstein</tei:title> Sonata</tei:rs>, of the <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001130"
     >B major prelude from Bach’s Well-Tempered Clavier, Book II</tei:rs>
    <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">illegible word</tei:note>, and a few melodies by
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003691">Verdi</tei:rs>. But I haven’t been able to finish my
    own compositions. I shall still write a few things about it, however, as soon as I have finished
    my string quintet.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>In the next few days, Mr. Richard Glas, our principal piano teacher, will look you up. He
    is himself Viennese, and a pupil of the advanced class and of <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000293">Godowsky</tei:rs>. He will also be playing my Second Piano Sonata in his
    own evening recital. He is also bringing you a prospectus of our institution. Like most
    conservatories, a music factory; the director is a bad patron about whom, as you will se, I have
    already written in my article about the fundamental laws of melody. <tei:note type="editorial"
     place="inline">illegible word</tei:note> I was very glad when, upon returning from a trip, I
    found your splendid work on my desk.Thus my cordial thanks once more! Glas is bringing you also
    a few political newspapers, which you will read with interest. What is the state of your plans
    for moving?[2] I am forever regretting that all the conditions and financial circumstances
    prevent me <tei:pb n="2"/> from studying with you personally. It is sad that we cannot even
    purchase the most important books. But I can tell you at least this much: that the youth and a
    large part of the populace are already thinking differently, and striving upwards; only the
    workers are still – now as before – 90% blinded. And they will not see reason until the
    Frenchman is present in the entire country and brandishes the whip in front of every man,
    morning and evening. Then they will perhaps recognize their stupidity.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>It would please me greatly if you could hear my sonata; I wrote it two years ago and Glas
    plays it very well. – I had actually intended this winter to write a book about analysis, in the
    form of a composition tutor; but the boys were so badly taught at the grammar school during the
    work – they missed their paternal upbringing, and the women ran about for hours in search of
    food – that I must work with them and make up for lost time, to get them accustomed to
    thoroughness. And so hardly anything will come of it this winter. A plan and ideas exist, and
    they have also been tested by me in the school sufficiently. I believe that, with your help, I
    am on the right track. But when I feel compelled to compose music, I naturally leave my
    theoretical work aside.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Your new publications, as witnesses to an unbroken creative power, tell me that things are
    going tolerably well for you, insofar as that can be the case in Vienna; I look forward to
    Glas’s verbal report.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">I remain, with my best wishes for you </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">and most cordial greetings,</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your very devoted and grateful</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">D<tei:hi
       rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Reinhard Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p>Moreover, I was glad to hear of the success of your books during my travels: <tei:rs
      type="person" key="entity-008291">Mendelssohn</tei:rs> in <tei:rs type="place"
      key="entity-004486">Darmstadt</tei:rs>, with whom I spoke about you, told me that the composer
     Vrieslander aspires in all his compositional activity to the content of your work. There was
     also not much in his things; but this insight is nonetheless gratifying. </tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>


  </tei:div>

 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
