<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2549" sdoID="OC-30-40">OC 30/40</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TK" scope="sole">Trude Kaff's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IDB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2021</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2021</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2021</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>


    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2011-03-05" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008061">Kaff ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">letter</tei:rs>
      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Trude Kaff to Schenker, dated December 31, 1932</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1932-12-31T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2021-09-03</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Trude Kaff sends New Year greetings to Heinrich Schenker and thanks him for
        the instruction that he gave her, which has influenced her ever since.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Wünsche; good wishes; Musikunterricht; music instruction; Erinnerung; memory;
        amortisiert; amortized</dc:subject>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000415">Trude Kaff</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute>Geehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Doktor Schenker</tei:rs>
          — Mein Verehrter, ehemaliger Meister,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
            place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary at January 1, 1933:
            “Von Frl. Kaff (Br.): gratuliert” (“From Miss Kaff (letter): sends
            greetings.”</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>das neue Jahr soll mir als Vorwand dienen, Ihnen meine innigsten Wünsche für Ihre
        Gesundheit, Ihr Wohlergehen &amp; Ihr weiteres Schaffen auszusprechen. Und dann möchte ich
        Sie endlich wissen lassen d.h. versuchen Ihnen mitzuteilen, wie dankbar ich Ihnen bin,
          das<tei:supplied reason="omission">s</tei:supplied> ich vor Jahren das Glück hatte Ihre
        Schülerin zu sein, sagten Sie mir einmal: „Dieser Musikunterricht ist das Beste das Eltern
        ihren Kindern für’s Leben mitgeben können.“ Wie recht Sie damit hatten weiss ich schon
        längst. Meine damals so schwer erbettelten &amp; erkämpften Stunden sind nicht nur die
        besten &amp; glücklichsten meines Lebens gewesen die mir immer eine <tei:pb n="2"/>
        unvergessliche Erinnerung sein werden, sie sind sogar – geschäftlich ausgedrückt – überhaupt
        das Einzige in meinem Leben das sich bis dato amortisiert hat. Wenn ich mir so viele Jahre
        lang den Wunsch versagt habe, Sie verehrten Meister aufzusuchen um Sie wieder einmal zu
        sprechen &amp; um Ihnen persönlich zu danken, geschah es nur aus Rücksicht für Sie.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Nehmen Sie die her<tei:supplied reason="omission"
            >z</tei:supplied>lichsten Grüsse entgegen</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">von Ihrer treu ergebenen</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs key="entity-000415" type="person">Trude
          Kaff</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:date>31./12 32</tei:date>
      </tei:closer>
    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute>Dear Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>, my revered former
            Master,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Let me take advantage of the New Year to convey my most heartfelt good wishes for your
        health, your welfare, and your future creative work. And I should also like at last to let
        you know – that is, to try to communicate to you – how grateful I am to you that I had the
        good fortune many years ago to be your pupil. You once said to me: “This music instruction
        is the best legacy that parents can endow their children with for life.” I long since came
        to appreciate just how right you were in that. My lessons, so keenly pleaded and fought for
        at the time, have been not only the best and happiest of my life, which will <tei:pb n="2"/>
        remain an ever unforgettable memory, but they are also – put in commercial terms – the one
        single thing in my life that has continued to amortize to this very day. If I have for so
        many years denied myself the wish to visit you, revered Master, in order once again to speak
        with you and to thank you in person, then it was only out of consideration for you.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Please accept my most cordial best wishes,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">from your truly devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs key="entity-000415" type="person">Trude
          Kaff</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:date>December 31, 1932</tei:date>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
