<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="167" sdoID="OC-52-560">OC 52/560</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>
  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="TPunk" scope="major">unknown typist</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2009</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2009</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding,2010</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-07-10" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-12-20" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">
  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002700">Hertzka ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002701">UE ~ H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002702">UE ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002879">Contract</tei:rs>



   <dc:title>Draft Contract between UE and Schenker for the Kleine Bibliothek, dated March 23,
    1920</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1920-03-23T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-06-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Draft contract for the Kleine Bibliothek.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Vertrag; contract; Abmachung; letter of agreement; Uebersetzungsrecht; translation
    right; Uebersetzung; translation; Bogen; gathering; Heft; issue; Thema; topic; Erörterung;
    discussion; Darstellung; presentation; Inhalt; content; Vortrag; performance; Studie; study;
    Kritisches; criticism; Vermischtes; miscellanea; Auflage; print run; edition; Exemplar; copy;
    Abdruck; reprint; Neuauflage; new edition; Verplichtung; obligation; Frist; deadline;
    Ladenpreis; retail price; Teuerungszuschlag; inflationary increase; Sortimenterzuschlag; retail
    mark-up; Ausgabe; edition; Tonfolge; succession of tones; Tonwerk; musical composition; Aufsatz;
    article; Musikstück; piece of music; Tantieme; royalty; Umfang; extent; Honorar; honorarium;
    Termin; deadline; Veröffentlichung; publication; Publikation; Manuscript; manuscript; Recht;
    right; Meinungsäusserung; expression of opinion; Korrekturen; proofs; Urheberrecht;
    copyright</dc:subject>

   
   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000356">Hertzka</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-002408">UE</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:note type="editorial">This contract was enclosed with OC 52/447 and 547</tei:note>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:note type="editorial">This draft contains numerous interlinear and marginal revisions in
     Heinrich Schenker's hand; these have been disregarded in the present transcription so as to
     convey this recension of the contract drafting process intact. For a later stage of this
     contract incorporating many of these revisions, see OC 52/517, July 10, 1920.)</tei:note>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:note type="editorial">No U-E letterhead</tei:note>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent=50">
     <tei:placeName>Wien</tei:placeName>
     <tei:date when="1920-03-23">23. März 1920</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10">An die Universal-Edition A. G. </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60">
      <tei:hi rend="sperr-underline">Wien</tei:hi>
     </tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
   </tei:opener>


   <tei:p rend="first">Mit<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
     this contract and that for the Beethoven piano sonatas edition (OC 52/447) and covering letter
     (OJ 52/547) is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/1, p. 2222, March 24, 1920: "Von Hertzka
     (recomm. Br.): sendet Verträge u. Brief." ("From Hertzka (registered letter): sends contracts
     and letter."). </tei:note> Vorliegendem bestätige ich, mit Ihnen folgendes Uebereinkommen
    getroffen zu haben: </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">1.) Ich überlasse Ihnen das ausschliessliche und alleinige Verlagsrecht sowie
    das Uebersetzungsrecht der von mir verfassten <tei:quote rend="block">
     <tei:hi rend="sperr">"<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001758"><tei:title>Kleinen
        Bibliothek</tei:title></tei:rs>"</tei:hi>
    </tei:quote> welche als zwanglose Folge von Zweibogen-Heften gedacht ist, von der höchstens 12
    im Jahre erscheinen sollen. Die "<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001758"><tei:title>Kleine
      Bibliothek</tei:title></tei:rs>" wird verschiedene Themen aus dem Gebiete der Musik zur
    Erörterung bringen, z.B. die Darstellung von <tei:term>Symphonie</tei:term>-, <tei:term>Kammermusik</tei:term>, <tei:term>Lied</tei:term>-, <tei:term>Klavierwerk</tei:term>en und zwar sowohl dem Inhalt als auch dem <tei:term>Vortrag</tei:term>, über die Studien, über <tei:term>Vortrag</tei:term> überhaupt, Kritisches und sonst Vermischtes bringen. Es
    wird von vorne herein darauf gesehen werden, dass die Darstellung aus den einzelnen Stoffen ihre
    Abrundung derart erfahre, dass z.B. <tei:term>Symphonie</tei:term>n,
     <tei:term>Sonate</tei:term>n, von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs>, <tei:term>Etüde</tei:term>n von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000129">Chopin</tei:rs> und dgl. auch selbständig und nach Möglichkeit auch vollständig
    herausgegeben werden können. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">2.) Die Auflage der ersten vier Hefte der "<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001758"><tei:title>Kleinen Bibliothek</tei:title></tei:rs>" soll je 2000 Exemplare
    umfassen. Auf Grund der Erfahrungen mit diesen Heften dann die folgenden Auflagen <tei:pb n="2"/> festgesetzt werden. Sobald eine Auflage erschöpt ist, soll sofort eine Neuauflage in Angriff
    genommen werden und im Falle eines unveränderten Abdruckes innerhalb zehn Monate ausgegeben
    werden. Sollte innerhalb dieser Frist die Neuauflage nicht erschienen sein und ich mit einem
    rekommandierten Schreiben auf dieses Versäumnis unter Hinweis auf die vertragsmässige
    Verpflichtung aufmerksam machen, so bin ich innerhalb weiterer drei Monate nach Ablauf der Frist
    berechtigt, das betreffende Heft anderweitig erscheinen zu lassen.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">3.) Der Ladenpreis eines Zweibogen-Heftes der "<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001758"><tei:title>Kleinen Bibliothek</tei:title></tei:rs>" wird einschliesslich
    Teuerungszuschlag mit zwei bis vier Mark festgesetzt. Eine Aenderung dieses Preises soll nur im
    Einverständnis stattfinden. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">4.) Ich erhalte als Honorar vom Ladenpreis einschliesslich des
    Teuerungszuschlages, jedoch ohne Berücksichtigung des Sortimenterzuschlages eine Tantieme von
    20% i. W. zwanzig Prozent eines jeden verkauften und bezahlten Exemplares der gehefteten
    Ausgabe. Falls eine Reihe von Heften gebunden erscheint, so wird von dem Preis des Einbandes
    keine Tantieme zu bezahlen sein.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Im Falle einzelne Aufsätze oder ganze Hefte in eine andere Sprache übersetzt
    werden, so erhalte ich, falls das Uebersetzungsrecht gegen einen Pauschalbetrag überlassen wird,
    die Hälfte des erzielten Pauschalbetrages, im Falle dasselbe jedoch von Ihnen selbst ausgeübt
    wird, 10% i.W. zehn Prozent eines jeden verkauften und bezahlten Exemplares. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">5.) Sie verpflichten sich, die von mir rekonstruierte <tei:term>Tonfolge</tei:term> der von mir herausgegebenen Ausgaben ohne meine
    Zustimmung keiner anderen Ausgabe desselben <tei:term>Tonwerk</tei:term>es zugrunde zu legen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">6.) Sollte einer der in der "<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001758"><tei:title>Kleinen Bibliothek</tei:title></tei:rs>" enthaltenen Aufsätze im späteren Verlaufe
    in Verbindung mit <tei:pb n="3"/> einem oder mehreren Musikstücken, die auf den Aufsatz Bezug
    haben, zur Veröffentlichung gelangen, dann ist für diesen Aufsatz keine höhere Tantieme bezahlt
    worden, als diejenige die dem Umfang des betreffenden Aufsatzes in der "<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001758"><tei:title>Kleinen Bibliothek</tei:title></tei:rs>" entspricht (z.B. für
    einen Aufsatz, der in der "<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001758"><tei:title>Kleinen
      Bibliothek</tei:title></tei:rs>" 8 Seiten umfasst, je nach dem Ladenpreis der "<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001758"><tei:title>Kleinen Bibliothek</tei:title></tei:rs>" 10-20
    Pfennige). </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">7.) Die Abrechnung über die verkauften Exemplare hat halbjährig in den
    Monaten Jänner und Juli zu erfolgen und sind mir die auf mich entfallenden Honorare zu diesen
    Terminen bar auszubezahlen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">8.) Mit Rücksicht darauf, dass mir durch Abschluss des Vertrages die
    selbstverständliche Verpflichtung erwächst, anderen Verlagen musikwissenschaftliche Abhandlungen
    nicht zu übergeben, übernehmen Sie die Verpflichtung, die Ihnen zur Veröffentlichung übergebenen
    Manuskripte unverzüglich zum Druck und zur Publikation zu bringen, schon um zu verhüten, dass
    die Korrekturen mit der Abfassung neuer Hefte kollidieren. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">9.) Sie verpflichten sich, mein Recht auf freie Meinungsäusserung ohne jede
    Einschränkung gelten zu lassen und den Wortlauf der Werke irgendwelchen Rücksichten zuliebe ohne
    meine Zustimmung in keinem Falle zu ändern oder zu kürzen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">10.) Diese Abmachung gilt für die Dauer von 10 Jahren und verlängert sich
    nach diesem Termin automatisch, wenn sie nicht von irgendeinem der beiden Teile halbjärhlich
    aufgekündigt wird und selbstverständlich sind die in der Abmachung vorgesehenen Anteile mir für
    die ganze Dauer des Urheberrechtes zu bezahlen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">11.) Diese Abmachung geht mit allen Rechten und Pflichten auf unsere
    beiderseitigen Rechtsnachfolger über. </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:note type="editorial">unsigned</tei:note>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>



  <tei:div type="translation">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:note type="editorial">This contract was enclosed with OC 52/447 and 547</tei:note>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:note type="editorial">This draft contains numerous interlinear and marginal revisions in
     Heinrich Schenker's hand; these have been disregarded in the present transcription so as to
     convey this recension of the contract drafting process intact. For a later stage of this
     contract incorporating many of these revisions, see OC 52/517, July 10, 1920.)</tei:note>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:note type="editorial">No U-E letterhead</tei:note>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent=50"><tei:placeName>Vienna</tei:placeName>, <tei:date when="1920-03-23">March 23, 1920</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10">To: Universal Edition &amp; Co., </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60">
      <tei:hi rend="sperr-underline">Vienna</tei:hi>
     </tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
   </tei:opener>


   <tei:p rend="first">With<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> the present document, I
    confirm that I have reached the following agreement with you: </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">1.) I relinquish to you the exclusive and sole publishing right as well as
    translation right of the work authored by me, the: <tei:quote rend="block">
     <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001758">
      <tei:title level="j">Little Library</tei:title>
     </tei:rs>
    </tei:quote> which is envisioned as a succession of two-gathering issues appearing from time to
    time, of which a maximum of twelve are to appear per year. The <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001758"><tei:title level="j">Little Library</tei:title></tei:rs> will discuss a
    variety of topics in the realm of music, e.g. the presentation of <tei:term>symphonic</tei:term>
    <tei:supplied reason="clarity">and</tei:supplied>
    <tei:term>chamber music</tei:term>, solo <tei:term>song</tei:term>s, <tei:supplied reason="clarity">and</tei:supplied>
    <tei:term>keyboard work</tei:term>s, as regards not only their
    content but also their <tei:term>performance</tei:term>,
     <tei:supplied reason="clarity">and</tei:supplied> will present critical assessment of secondary
    literature, of <tei:term>performance</tei:term> itself, and other
    miscellanea. It will from the outset take great care that the presentation proceed from the
    separate components through to their fully rounded form, in such a way that for example <tei:term>symphonies</tei:term>
    <tei:supplied reason="clarity">and</tei:supplied>
    <tei:term>sonata</tei:term>s by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>
    <tei:supplied reason="clarity">and</tei:supplied>
    <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs>, <tei:term>etude</tei:term>s by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000129">Chopin</tei:rs> and suchlike, can
    be given not only separately but where possible also in their entirety. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">2.) The edition of the first four issues of the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001758"><tei:title level="j">Little Library</tei:title></tei:rs> shall comprise
    2,000 copies. The editions <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of the</tei:supplied> subsequent
     <tei:supplied reason="clarity">issues</tei:supplied> shall then be determined on the basis of
    experience with these issues. <tei:pb n="2"/> As soon as an edition is exhausted, a new edition
    is to be set in motion, and should in the event of an unaltered reprint be produced within ten
    months. If the new edition has not been published within this time limit and I have drawn
    attention to this omission with a registered letter referring to the contractual obligation,
    then I am entitled to arrange for the publication of the issue in question by some other means
    within the three months subsequent to expiry of the time limit. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">3.) The retail price of a two-gathering issue of the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001758"><tei:title level="j">Little Library</tei:title></tei:rs> inclusive of
    inflationary increase shall be set between two and four Marks. Any increase in this price should
    take place only with consent. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">4.) As honorarium, I am to receive a royalty of 20 (twenty) % of the retail
    price of each copy of the glued-and-stapled edition sold and paid for, inclusive of inflationary
    increase, but without regard for the retail mark-up. In the event of a series of issues being
    published in bound form, no royalty will be payable on the price of the binding. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In the event of individual articles or entire issues being translated into
    another language, I shall receive, in the case of the translation right being surrended against
    a lump-sum payment half of the lump-sum payment arrived at, on the other hand, in the event of
    the said translation being carried by you yourself 10 (ten) % of each copy sold and paid for. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">5.) You undertake not to use the <tei:term>succession of tones</tei:term> reconstructed by me in the editions edited by me as a basis for
    any other edition of the same <tei:term>musical work</tei:term> without my consent. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">6.) Should one of the articles contained in the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001758"><tei:title level="j">Little Library</tei:title></tei:rs> be published at a
    later date in combination with <tei:pb n="3"/> one or more pieces of music that relate to the
    article, then no higher royalty is to be paid for this article than that which corresponds to
    the size of the article in question in the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001758"><tei:title level="j">Little Library</tei:title></tei:rs> (e.g. for an article that in the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001758"><tei:title level="j">Little Library</tei:title></tei:rs>
    comprises eight pages, according to the retail price of the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001758"><tei:title level="j">Little Library</tei:title></tei:rs> 10-20 Pfennigs). </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">7.) The statement of account for copies sold has to be rendered half-yearly
    in the months of January and July, and and the honoraria due to me are to be disbursed to me in
    cash on the same deadlines.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">8.) In view of the fact that by virtue of signing the contract the
    self-evident obligation falls to me not to entrust musicological essays to other publishing
    houses, you undertake the obligation to commit to print and publication immediately the
    manuscripts delivered to you for publication, merely in order to prevent the correction of
    proofs from coinciding with the authoring of new issues.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">9.) You commit yourself to acknowledge my right without any limitation to
    free expression of opinion, and in no event to alter or to curtail the wording of the works for
    the sake of any considerations whatsoever without my consent. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">10.) This letter of agreement is valid for the period of ten years and is
    automatically extended after this time limit if notice of it is not given by either of the two
    parties half-yearly, and naturally the apportionments designated in the letter of agreement are
    to be paid to me for the entire duration of the copyright. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">11.) This letter of agreement devolves with all rights and obligations upon
    our respective legal successors.</tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:note type="editorial">unsigned</tei:note>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>