<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="1119" sdoID="OC-54-91-92">OC 54/91-92</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="major">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="KH">
      <tei:persName>Kirstie Hewlett</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2014</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2011-10-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>


  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-004414">DMV ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Draft of a letter from Schenker to DMV in Schenker’s hand, dated June 24,
        1926</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1926-06-24T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2014-10-03</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>In response to Drei Masken Verlag’s delay in initiating production of the
        second Meisterwerk Yearbook, Schenker points out that the publishers are in breach of
        paragraph 8 of the contract between them for not informing him the previous summer. He
        threatens them with legal action if he has not had a reply within a week, or if they insist
        on delaying production.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>contract; Vertrag; manuscript; Manuskript; deadline; Termin; printing;
        Druck</dc:subject>
    </sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:note type="editorial" place="pre-text">Many words in this hastily written and heavily
        corrected draft are illegible; the following translation is, in places, approximate. The
        transcription and translation presented here are of the last reading of the text.</tei:note>


      <tei:p><tei:handShift new="#HS"/><tei:date when="1926-06-24">24.6</tei:date> Antwort auf Bf.
        vom <tei:date when="1926-06-21">21.6.26</tei:date><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01"
          type="editorial" place="foot">The sending of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary
          at OJ 3/8, p. 2951, June 24, 1926: "An den Verlag (rec. Br.): erkläre dagegen meinen
          Standpunkt, der sich auf § 8 des Vertrages stützt u. befriste die Antwort mit acht Tagen."
          ("To the publisher (registered letter): I explain, by contrast, my position, which is
          based on §8 of the contract and insist on an answer within a week!"); the postal receipt
          is preserved as <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-54-93">OC
          54/93</tei:ref>.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Gestü<tei:supplied reason="syntax">t</tei:supplied>zt auf §8 unseres Vertrags
        betreffend des Jahrb. d. <tei:rs key="entity-001749" type="work"><tei:title>D. M. in d.
            M.</tei:title></tei:rs> war ich bereits daran im Begriffe, die Arbeit am Manusc. f. das
          <tei:rs key="entity-001752" type="work"><tei:title>Jb. III, 1927</tei:title></tei:rs>
        aufzumachen, als mich heute Ihr Brief vom <tei:date when="1926-06-21">21.
          Juni</tei:date><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">= <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OC-54-88">OC 54/88</tei:ref>.</tei:note> überraschte. Daraus
        entnehme ich, daß Ihnen das <tei:title>Jb. III
            1927</tei:title> unter allen <tei:abbr>Umst<tei:ex>ände</tei:ex></tei:abbr> nicht mehr willkommen ist, u. da Sie mir
        davon rechtzeitig Mitteilung machen, so halte ich mich der Vertragspflicht des dritten
        Jahrb. betreffend nun für ledig. Dagegen lasse ich eine Rückbeziehung der Äußerung vom
          <tei:date when="1926-06-21">21. Juni</tei:date> auch des <tei:rs key="entity-001751"
          type="work"><tei:title>Jb. II</tei:title></tei:rs> gewiß <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >nicht</tei:hi> gelten u. halte fest daran, daß Sie das vertragsgemäß abgesandte
            <tei:abbr>M<tei:ex>anuskript</tei:ex></tei:abbr> des <tei:title>II Jahrb.</tei:title> auch <tei:hi rend="underline">zum
          Druck zu befördern</tei:hi> u. zum <tei:hi rend="underline">Nov. des J. 1926 „Termin“
          herauszugeben verpflichtet sind</tei:hi>. Ich habe das Msp. des <tei:rs key="entity-001750" type="work">Jb I</tei:rs> <tei:date
          when="1925-06-15">Mitte Juni 1925</tei:date> abgeliefert, u. es wäre Ihre Pflicht gewesen,
        mir spätestens am <tei:date when="1925-07-01">1. Juli</tei:date> zu sagen, daß Sie auch das
        2. Jahrb. mehr nehmen, oder daß Sie, von §8 Gebrauch machend, eine Änderung des Vertrages
        vorschlagen. Sie ließen mich aber ein Jahr lang ungeachtet arbeiten, ließen mich das Msp.
        Jb. vollenden, u. nun wollen <tei:pb n="2"/> Sie, da Sie das
            <tei:abbr>M<tei:ex>anuskript</tei:ex></tei:abbr> in den Händen haben es erst von
        verschiedenen anderen Umständen, denen der Vertrag nicht errechnet, es abs. <tei:supplied
          reason="editorial">illegible word</tei:supplied> lassen, ob Sie sich auch nur „zur
        Übernahme des <tei:abbr>M<tei:ex>anuskript</tei:ex></tei:abbr> entschließen“ <tei:supplied
          reason="editorial">illegible word</tei:supplied> das alles erkläre ich nun für
          <tei:supplied reason="editorial">two illegible words</tei:supplied>]
        vertragswidrig.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich lasse alle Sentiments beiseite, stelle mich mit Ihnen auf den Standpunkt des
        „Geschäftes“ gemäß Ihrem <tei:supplied reason="editorial">illegible word</tei:supplied> vom
          <tei:supplied reason="editorial">date omitted?</tei:supplied> u. erbitte binnen 8 Tage
        eine Antwort, ob Sie bei Ihrem <tei:abbr>Standp<tei:ex>unkt</tei:ex></tei:abbr> beharren.
        Geschehe das, sei es, daß Sie keine Antwort gegeben, oder doch das <tei:supplied
          reason="editorial">3 illegible words</tei:supplied> so hätte ich mich genötigt, sogleich
        die Hilfe des Richters nachzusuchen zum Schutz einer vereinbarten, vertragsmäßig
          <tei:supplied reason="editorial">illegible word</tei:supplied> von mir.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Alle andere von Ihnen im Bf. <tei:supplied reason="editorial">illegible
          word</tei:supplied> Fragen lasse ich vorläufig bei Seite.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Hochachtungsvoll</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">HSchen</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:p><tei:handShift new="#HS"/><tei:date when="1926-06-24">June 24</tei:date>, reply to the
        letter from <tei:date when="1926-06-21">June 21, 1926</tei:date>.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>On the basis of paragraph 8 of our contract concerning the Yearbook <tei:rs
          key="entity-001749" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Das Meisterwerk in der
            Musik</tei:title></tei:rs>, I was just at the point of starting work on the manuscript
        for <tei:rs key="entity-001752" type="work"><tei:title>Yearbook III</tei:title></tei:rs>,
        for 1927, when your letter of <tei:date when="1926-06-21">June 21</tei:date><tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> surprised me today. From it I infer that Yearbook III for 1927 is in all circumstances no
        longer welcome and as you are informing me of this promptly, I now consider myself free of
        contractual obligation with respect to Yearbook
          III. However, I shall certainly not allow a retroactive arrangement applicable to
          <tei:rs key="entity-001751" type="work">Yearbook II</tei:rs>, according to your statement
        of <tei:date when="1926-06-21">June 21</tei:date>; and I insist upon your obligation to
        prepare the manuscript of Yearbook II, which I sent you, in accordance with the contract,
          <tei:hi rend="underline">for printing and to bring out by the “deadline” of November
          1926</tei:hi>. I delivered the manuscript for <tei:rs key="entity-001750" type="work">Yearbook I</tei:rs> in the middle of <tei:date
          when="1925-06-15">June 1925</tei:date>, and it would have been your responsibility to have
        told me by <tei:date when="1925-07-01">July 1</tei:date> at the latest that you would not
        take Yearbook II or that you, making use of paragraph 8, recommended a change in the
        contract. Notwithstanding you let me, however, work for a year, and only now, <tei:pb n="2"
        /> when you have the manuscript in your hands, you wish for various other circumstances – to
        which the contract does not apply – to leave it to one side as to whether you will “decide
        to accept the manuscript”: I now declare all in breach of contract.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I leave all feelings aside, and deal with you from the standpoint of “business” with
        respect to your letter of <tei:supplied reason="editorial"><tei:date when="1926-06-21">June
            21</tei:date></tei:supplied>, and request an answer within a week as to whether you are
        adhering to your standpoint, which is opposed to the contract, whether you do so by not
        replying, or indeed <tei:supplied reason="editorial">illegible text</tei:supplied>, then I
        would see myself compelled immediately to seek the help of the judiciary to protect an
        agreed, and contractually fulfilled, achievement of mine.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>All other questions in your letter I shall, for the time being, set aside.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">With kind regards,</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">HSchen</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
