<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="165" sdoID="OC-52-223">OC 52/223</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>
  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="major">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="minor">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2009</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2009</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2010</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-07-09" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-12-18" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">
  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002700">Hertzka ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002701">UE ~ H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002702">UE ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002879">Contract</tei:rs>



   <dc:title>Handwritten draft contract, in Jeanette Schenker's hand, between UE and Schenker for
    the Kleine Bibliothek and Beethoven sonatas edition, undated [March 17,?] 1920</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1920-03-17T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-06-12</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Handwritten draft contract jointly for the Kleine Bibliothek and Beethoven
    sonatas edition. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Vertrag; contract; Verlagsrecht; publishing right; Bogen; gathering; Erörterung;
    discussion; Darstellung; presentation; Symphonie; symphony; Kammermusik; chamber music; Lied;
    song; Klaviersonate; piano sonata; Vortrag; performance; Kritisches; criticism; Studie; study;
    Ausgabe; edition; Autograph; autograph manuscript; Skizze; sketch; Erstdruck; first edition;
    Auflage; edition; Neuauflage; new edition; Werk; work; Ladenpreis; retail price; Zweibogenheft;
    two-gathering issue; Tonfolge; succession of tones; Exemplar; copy; Ueberseztung; translation;
    Tonwerk; musical composition; Uebersetzungsrecht; translation right; Kaufsumme; purchase amount;
    Abrechnung; account; Termin; deadline; Honorar; honorarium; Verfasser; author; Thema; topic;
    Publikation; publication; Korrektur; proof; Meisterwerk; masterwork; Rezension;
    review</dc:subject>
   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
  <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000356">Hertzka</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-002408">UE</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:note type="editorial">This draft in Jeanette Schenker's hand contains some interlinear
     revisions in Heinrich Schenker's hand. These have been disregarded in the present transcription
     so as to convey this recension of the contract drafting process intact. For a later stage of
     this contract incorporating many of these revisions, see OC 52/560 and 447, March 23,
     1920.</tei:note>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:note type="editorial">No U-E letterhead</tei:note>
   </tei:opener>
   <tei:p rend="first">Die <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">Universal-Edition</tei:rs> in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Wien</tei:rs> u. Herr
     D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi>
    <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich Schenker</tei:rs>, Tonkünstler in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Wien</tei:rs> sind heute folgenden Vertrag<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">This draft was perhaps the text discussed at
     Schenker's meeting with Hertzka on March 17, 1920, OJ 3/1, p. 2222: "Nach Tisch mit Hertzka:
     einige Korrekturen des Vertrags." ("After lunch with Hertzka: a few corrections to the
     contract.")<!-- XR -->, or was the direct outcome of that discussion. It seems to have been
     this draft which UE split into two separate contracts, as indicated in Hertzka's letter of
     March 22 (OC 52/547). </tei:note> miteinander eingegangen: </tei:p>
   <tei:div n="1">
    <tei:head rend="center">
     <tei:hi rend="underline">§ 1</tei:hi>
    </tei:head>
    <tei:p rend="first">Doktor <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs> übergibt
     der <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">Universal-Edition</tei:rs> in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Wien</tei:rs> das Verlagsrecht nachstehender Arbeiten: </tei:p>

    <tei:p>1. 1. die „<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001758"><tei:title>Kleine
       Bibliothek</tei:title></tei:rs>“, gedacht als zwanglose Folge von Zweibogenheften, höchstens
     zwölf im Jahr, in denen er verschiedene Themen aus dem Gebiete der Musik zur Erörterung bringen
     will, so z.B. die Darstellung von <tei:term>Symphonie</tei:term>-,
      <tei:term>Kammer-Musik</tei:term>, <tei:term>Lied</tei:term>, <tei:term>Klaviersonate</tei:term>n dem Inhalt,
     dem Vortrage nach, Studien über <tei:term>Vortrag</tei:term>
     überhaupt, Kritisches u. sonst Vermischtes. Daher würde er von vornherein auch darauf sehen,
     daß die Darstellung aus den einzelnen Stoffen ihre Abrundung derart erfahre, dass z.B. <tei:term>Sinfonie</tei:term>n von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs>, <tei:term>Etüde</tei:term>n von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000129">Chopin</tei:rs> und dgl. auch selbständig u. nach
     Möglichkeit auch vollständig herausgegeben werden könnten. </tei:p>

    <tei:p>2. die Ausgabe sämtlicher <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001753">Klaviersonaten von
      Beethoven</tei:rs>, revidiert nach den zur Zeit überhaupt erreichbaren Autographen, Skizzen u.
     Erstdrucken u. mit <tei:term>Fingersatz</tei:term> versehen.
    </tei:p>
   </tei:div>
   <tei:div n="2">
    <tei:head rend="center">
     <tei:hi rend="underline">§ 2</tei:hi>
    </tei:head>
    <tei:p rend="first">Die erste u. jede folgende Auflage soll fünftausend (5000) Exemplare
     umfassen. Sobald eine Auflage erschöpt ist, soll eine Neuauflage binnen höchstens sechs Monaten
     ausgegeben werden, widrigenfalls dem Autor das Recht zustünde, das Werk anderswo erscheinen zu
     lassen. </tei:p>
   </tei:div>

   <tei:div n="3">
    <tei:head rend="center">
     <tei:hi rend="underline">§ 3</tei:hi>
    </tei:head>
    <tei:p rend="first">Der Ladenpreis eines Zweibogenheftes bezw. der Ausgabe wird festgesetzt mit
      <tei:handShift new="#HS"/><tei:note type="editorial">added in HS's hand:</tei:note> M 4.-.
      <tei:handShift new="#JS"/>Eine Aenderung dieses Preises hat nur über Vereinbarung
     stattzufinden. </tei:p>

    <tei:p rend="first">D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi>
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs> erhält als Honorar vom Ladenpreis
     des Zwei- <tei:pb n="2"/> bogenheftes 20% u. zwar von jedem verkauften Exemplar. Dasselbe gilt
     von jeder Uebersetzung u. ferner auch von jeder von immer gearteten Ausgabe der von ihm
     revidierten <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001753">Beethoven-Sonaten</tei:rs>. Die <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">Universal-Edition</tei:rs> verpflichtet sich, die vom
     Autor rekonstruirte <tei:term>Tonfolge</tei:term> der von ihm
     herausgegebenen Ausgaben ohne seine Zustimmung keiner anderen Ausgabe derselben <tei:term>Tonwerk</tei:term>e zum Grunde zu legen. </tei:p>
    <tei:p rend="first">Bei Verkauf des Uebersetztungsrechtes teilt der Verlag die Kaufsumme zur
     Hälfte mit dem Verfasser. </tei:p>

    <tei:p>Abrechnung hat alljährlich nach der Buchhändler-Ostermesse, spätestens aber bis 15.
     Oktober eines jeden Jahres zu erfolgen u. das auf Herrn D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi>
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs> entfallende Honorar ist ihm zu
     diesem Termine auszuhändigen. Doch verpflichtet sich der Verlag, die Hälfte der Auflage bei
     Uebergabe des Manuscriptes zu honorieren. Ueber den weiteren Absatz hat Abrechnung wie oben
     erwähnt zu erfolgen. </tei:p>
   </tei:div>

   <tei:div n="4">
    <tei:head rend="center">
     <tei:hi rend="underline">§ 4</tei:hi>
    </tei:head>
    <tei:p rend="first">Mit Rücksicht darauf, daß dem Verfasser der „<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001758"><tei:title>Kleinen Bibliothek</tei:title></tei:rs>“ aus diesem Vertrage
     die selbstverständliche Pflicht erwächst, über die einzelnen Themen keine weiteren Abhandlungen
     an andere Verlage bezw. Stellen zu übergeben, übernimmt dagegen der Verlag seinerseits die
     Verpflichtung, die übernommenen Manuscripte unverzüglich zum Druck u. zur Publikation zu
     bringen, schon um zu verhuten, daß die Korrektur mit der Abfassung neuer Hefte collidieren.
    </tei:p>
   </tei:div>

   <tei:div n="5">
    <tei:head rend="center">
     <tei:hi rend="underline">§ 5</tei:hi>
    </tei:head>
    <tei:p rend="first">Der Verlag verpflichtet sich des Verfassers Recht auf freie
     Meinungsäusserung unter allen Umständen gelten zu lassen u. den Wortlaut der Werke niemals aus
     eigenem, diesen oder jenen Rücksichten zuliebe, zu verändern oder zu kürzen. </tei:p>
   </tei:div>

   <tei:div n="6">
    <tei:head rend="center">
     <tei:hi rend="underline">§ 6</tei:hi>
    </tei:head>
    <tei:p rend="first">Der Verlag verpflichtet sich, der Tendenz des Verfassers, die Werke unserer
     größten Meister von allen im Laufe der Generationen hinzugekommenen, den Inhalt entstellenden
     Veränderungen u. Zitaten zu befreien u. so genau als nur möglich lediglich nach den Wünschen
     der Meister wiederzugeben damit entgegenzukommen, daß er ihm das Vorrecht der Herausgabe der
      <tei:term>Klaviersonaten</tei:term> von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000344">Haydn</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000612">Mozart</tei:rs> einräumt, wodurch die Rettung der ewigen Meisterwerke so voll- <tei:pb n="3"/> ständig als möglich durchgeführt werden kann. Die Uebernahme der Herausgeberarbeit würde
     dann unter denselben Bedingungen wie oben sub § 3 erfolgen. </tei:p>
   </tei:div>

   <tei:div n="7">
    <tei:head rend="center">
     <tei:hi rend="underline">§ 7</tei:hi>
    </tei:head>
    <tei:p rend="first">Dieser Vertrag geht mit allen Rechten u. Pflichten auf die beiderseitigen
     Erben bezw. Geschäftsnachfolger über. </tei:p>
   </tei:div>

   <tei:div n="8">
    <tei:head rend="center">
     <tei:hi rend="underline">§ 8</tei:hi>
    </tei:head>
    <tei:p rend="first">Frei Exemplare? Rezensions-Exemplare - welcher Prozentsatz jeder Auflage?
    </tei:p>
   </tei:div>
   <tei:closer>
    <tei:note type="editorial">unsigned, undated</tei:note>
   </tei:closer>
  </tei:div>
  <tei:div type="translation">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:note type="editorial">This draft in Jeanette Schenker's hand contains some interlinear
     revisions in Heinrich Schenker's hand. These have been disregarded in the present transcription
     so as to convey this recension of the contract drafting process intact. For a later stage of
     this contract incorporating many of these revisions, see OC 52/560 and 447, March 23,
     1920.</tei:note>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:note type="editorial">No U-E letterhead</tei:note>
   </tei:opener>
   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">Universal Edition</tei:rs> in
     <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Vienna</tei:rs> and Dr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich Schenker</tei:rs>, composer in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Vienna</tei:rs> have today mutually concluded the following
     contract:<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:div n="1">
    <tei:head rend="center">
     <tei:hi rend="underline">§ 1</tei:hi>
    </tei:head>
    <tei:p rend="first">Dr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs> assigns to
      <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">Universal Edition</tei:rs> in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Vienna</tei:rs> the publishing right of the following works: </tei:p>

    <tei:p>1. The <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001758"><tei:title level="j">Little
       Library</tei:title></tei:rs>, envisioned as a succession of two-gathering issues appearing
     from time to time, with a maximum of twelve per year, in which he will discuss a variety of
     topics in the realm of music, e.g. the presentation of <tei:term>symphonic</tei:term> and &gt;<tei:term>chamber music</tei:term>,
     solo <tei:term>song</tei:term>, and <tei:term>keyboard sonata</tei:term>s, according to their content and performance,
     studies of <tei:term>performance</tei:term> in its own right, and
     other critical matter, and miscellanea. For this reason, he would from the outset take great
     care that the presentation proceed from the separate components through to their fully rounded
     form, in such a way that for example <tei:term>symphonies</tei:term> by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> and
      <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs>, <tei:term>etude</tei:term>s by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000129">Chopin</tei:rs> and suchlike, could be given not only separately but where possible also in
     their entirety.</tei:p>

    <tei:p>2. the edition of the collected <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001753">Piano Sonatas of
      Beethoven</tei:rs>, revised according to the autograph manuscripts, sketches, and first
     editions insofar as these are accessible at the present time and supplied with <tei:term>fingering</tei:term>.</tei:p>
   </tei:div>

   <tei:div n="2">
    <tei:head rend="center">
     <tei:hi rend="underline">§ 2</tei:hi>
    </tei:head>
    <tei:p rend="first">The first and each succeeding edition shall comprise five thousand (5,000)
     copies. As soon as an edition is exhausted , a new edition is to be produced within at most six
     months, failing which the author would be entitled to arrange for the work to be published by
     some other means. </tei:p>
   </tei:div>

   <tei:div n="3">
    <tei:head rend="center">
     <tei:hi rend="underline">§ 3</tei:hi>
    </tei:head>
    <tei:p rend="first">The retail price of a two-gathering issue or the edition will be set at
      <tei:note type="editorial">added in HS's hand:</tei:note>
     <tei:handShift new="#HS"/>4 Marks. <tei:handShift new="#JS"/>Any increase in this price is to
     take place only by agreement. </tei:p>

    <tei:p rend="first">Dr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs> will receive
     as honorarium 20% of the retail price of each copy sold of the two-gathering <tei:pb n="2"/>
     issue. The same applies to each translation, and moreover also to each edition of the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001753">Beethoven Sonatas</tei:rs> edited him in perpetuity. <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">Universal Edition</tei:rs> undertakes not to use the
      <tei:term>succession of tones</tei:term> reconstructed by the
     author in the editions edited by him as a basis for any other edition of the same <tei:term>musical work</tei:term> without his consent. </tei:p>

    <tei:p rend="first">In the event of the sale of the translation rights the publishing house
     apportions half of the purchase amount to the author. </tei:p>

    <tei:p>Statement of account has to be rendered annually after the book retailers' Easter Fair,
     but at latest by October 15 in any one year, and the honorarium due to Dr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs> is to be handed over to him by this
     deadline. The publishing house commits to paying as honorarium half of the <tei:supplied reason="clarity">honorarium for the</tei:supplied> edition upon the handing over of the
     manuscript. Statement of account of subsequent sales is to be rendered as stated above.
    </tei:p>
   </tei:div>

   <tei:div n="4">
    <tei:head rend="center">
     <tei:hi rend="underline">§ 4</tei:hi>
    </tei:head>
    <tei:p rend="first">In view of the fact that from this contract the self-evident obligation
     falls to the author of the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001758"><tei:title level="j">Little
       Library</tei:title></tei:rs> not to entrust any musicological essays on the individual topics
     to other publishing houses or places, the publishing house on the other hand undertakes for its
     part the obligation to commit to print and publication immediately the manuscripts that it
     receives, merely in order to prevent the correction of proofs from coinciding with the
     authoring of new issues. </tei:p>
   </tei:div>

   <tei:div n="5">
    <tei:head rend="center">
     <tei:hi rend="underline">§ 5</tei:hi>
    </tei:head>
    <tei:p rend="first">The publishing house commits itself to acknowledge the author's right under
     all circumstances to free expression of opinion, and never to alter or to curtail the wording
     of the works for the sake of its own or any other considerations. </tei:p>
   </tei:div>

   <tei:div n="6">
    <tei:head rend="center">
     <tei:hi rend="underline">§ 6</tei:hi>
    </tei:head>
    <tei:p rend="first">The publishing house commits itself to comply with the intention of the
     author to liberate the works of our great composers from all the alterations and quotations
     introduced over the course of the generations to the disfigurement of their content, and to
     give them in such a way that they reflect as precisely as possible the wishes of the composers
     and nothing else; and to according him the privilege of editing the <tei:term>piano sonata</tei:term>s of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000344">Haydn</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000612">Mozart</tei:rs>, whereby the
     rescuing of the eternal masterworks can be carried through as <tei:pb n="3"/> completely as
     possible. The assumption of the work of editing would then occur under the same conditions as
     above under § 3. </tei:p>
   </tei:div>

   <tei:div n="7">
    <tei:head rend="center">
     <tei:hi rend="underline">§ 7</tei:hi>
    </tei:head>
    <tei:p rend="first">This contract devolves with all rights and obligations upon our respective
     heirs and business successors. </tei:p>
   </tei:div>

   <tei:div n="8">
    <tei:head rend="center">
     <tei:hi rend="underline">§ 8</tei:hi>
    </tei:head>
    <tei:p rend="first">Free copies? Review copies – which percentage of each edition? </tei:p>
   </tei:div>
   <tei:closer>
    <tei:note type="editorial">unsigned, undated</tei:note>
   </tei:closer>
  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>