<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="1155" sdoID="OC-54-134">OC 54/134</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPov" scope="major">Typist "Otto Vrieslander"</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="OV" scope="minor">Otto Vrieslander's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>


    <tei:respStmt xml:id="KH">
      <tei:persName>Kirstie Hewlett</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2014</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2011-10-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs key="entity-004915" type="correspondence" role="correspondence">Vrieslander ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


      <dc:title>Typed letter from Otto Vrieslander to Schenker, dated February 20, 1927</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1927-02-20T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2014-03-24</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Vrieslander, at pains to ensure that the music illustrations in the second
        Meisterwerk Yearbook are accurately and elegantly printed, reports that the engravers are
        having difficulty interpreting Schenker’s music examples. He is putting his own work to one
        side in order to work exclusively on creating clear and elegant graphs; he proposes to come
        to Vienna in mid-March to go through all his work with Schenker.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>engraver; Setzer; manuscript; Manuskript; cost; Kosten; original; Original; copy;
        Kopie; stave; System; trip; Reise; graph; Tafel; revise; improve; verbessern; revidieren;
        engraving; Stich; mistake; Fehler; copy; Vorlag; fair copy; Reinschrift; experimental phase;
        Experimentierens; engraver's model; Stichvorlag; proof; proof sheet; Korrektur; number;
        symbol; Ziffer; Zeichen; duplicate; Duplikat</dc:subject>

    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#TPov"/>Sehr verehrter lieber Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Dr. Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at
            OJ 3/9, p. 3039, February 22, 1927: "Von Vrieslander (Br.): wird Mitte März die neuen
            Abschriften bringen u. mit mir durchgehen." ("From Vrieslander (letter): he will bring
            the new copies in the middle of March and go through them with
          me.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:lb/>

      <tei:p>Sie werden vermutlich durch <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Herrn v.
              <tei:abbr>H<tei:ex>oboken</tei:ex></tei:abbr></tei:rs> schon orientiert sein, über den
        neuesten Stand der Dinge. Doch gebe ich Ihnen hiermit nochmals genaueren Aufschluss, um Sie
        für alle Fälle klarsehend zu machen. Der Setzer war bei mir. Er kann nach Ihren Mskpten ganz
        einfach nicht arbeiten, wenn nicht die Gefahr gebannt werden soll, dass Sie 20 Korrekturen
        lesen müssen usw., von unabsehbaren Kosten nicht zu reden. Auch Striche, Hilfslinien &amp;
        was dgl. Setzermodalitäten zwecks Eruierg des Inhaltes sehr schwerer Mskpte anbelangt, nützt
        nicht, versagt vielmehr vollkommen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:hi rend="underline">Dieses sehe ich nach Einsichtnahme in Ihre Originale auch
          vollkommen ein</tei:hi>. Ich habe nun eine neue Art, der Sache noch vollendeter
        beizukommen zur Erziel<tei:supplied reason="clarity">un</tei:supplied>g von allerersten
        tadelsfreien Vorlagen, indem ich mir das Papier selber rastre &amp; zwar ist mir das so
          <tei:hi rend="underline">vollkommen</tei:hi> gelungen, dass ich sagen darf: Keine
          <tei:term>Systemisierung</tei:term> kann so kompliziert sein, dass ich ihrer nicht aufs
        wünschenswerteste Herr würde.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun kommt ein zweiter Punkt. <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Herr v.
              <tei:abbr>H<tei:ex>oboken</tei:ex></tei:abbr></tei:rs> wollte, nachdem ich <tei:hi rend="underline">nicht</tei:hi> sprechen mag, wegen der lächerlichen Beschränkungen
          <tei:add place="margin-left" hand="#OV"><tei:supplied reason="syntax">(</tei:supplied>Beethoven <tei:abbr>Kontrap<tei:ex>unkt</tei:ex></tei:abbr><tei:supplied reason="syntax">)</tei:supplied></tei:add>, meine <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wiener</tei:rs> Reise <tei:date when="1927-04-30">weit in den
          April</tei:date> verlegen. Dieses stimmt leider mit mancherlei meiner Wünsche nicht
        überein, deswegen ich ihm vorschlug, lieber <tei:hi rend="underline">bald</tei:hi> zu
        kommen, nämlich, wenn ich alle für Sie notwendigen <tei:term>Tafel</tei:term>n &amp; Teile
        skizziert habe, welche ich dann mit nach <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> bringe. Sie verbessern, revidieren dieselben <tei:hi rend="underline">unter
          meinem Dabeisein</tei:hi>, und ich arbeite in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> alle Vorlagen drucksetzw. stichvorlagefähig aus, so, wie die beiden
        letzten. Es ist unvergleichlich viel wertvoller für beide Teile, in direktem Konnexe zu
        stehen, als immer erst das <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs>-<tei:rs key="entity-002286" type="place">Münchener</tei:rs> Vacuum dazwische<tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#TPov">n</tei:add> als eigentlich recht hinderlich zu
          empfinden.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">That is, the
          distance between Schenker in Vienna and the Drei-Masken head office in Munich, a gap that
          Vrieslander is willing to bridge by coming to Vienna for a few days to go over graphic
          work.</tei:note>
        <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Herr v.
            <tei:abbr>H<tei:ex>oboken</tei:ex></tei:abbr></tei:rs> gieng gleich telefonisch
          <tei:date when="1927-02-19">gestern</tei:date> vormittag aufs angenehmste auf meinen
        Vorschlag ein, der freilich alles Praktische und Sinnvolle in sich schliesst.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>So arbeite ich denn also an den Vorlagen, welche ich klugerweise allerdings gleich so
        handhabe, dass auch sie <tei:hi rend="underline">allenfalls</tei:hi> als Reinschrift zu
        gelten vermöchten, nämlich in dem Falle, dass nicht viele Fehler drin oder Sie nicht viel zu
        ändern finden würden.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Wir brauchen dann nur <tei:hi rend="underline">ein paar Tage</tei:hi>
        miteinander zu arbeiten, und schon ist alles aufs klarste auseinandergesetzt. Ich habe
          <tei:sic>eigne</tei:sic> Arbeit ruhig auf die Seite getan, denn man kann doch nicht
          <tei:sic>zweierelei</tei:sic> Dinge treiben, welche beide den ganzen Menschen u. sogar
        Künstler verlangen, da die Arbeit über das Mechanische m. E. weit hinausgeht. Somit werden
        Sie mich wohl zwischen dem <tei:date from="1927-03-15" to="1927-03-20">15 &amp; 20,
          III.</tei:date> sehen und ich denke, Ihnen schon jetzt versichern zu können, dass Sie über
        meine neuerlichen Kniffe &amp; Pfiffe erstaunen werden, gegenüber welchen die beiden ersten
        Vorlagen noch im Stadium des Experimentierens waren, welches freilich nichts ausmacht jetzt,
        nachdem Alles Stichvorlagen werden. Dennoch rastriere ich mir jetzt die Dinge bequem und in
        den Platzverhältnissen so loyal, als es nur immer denkbar, wünschenswert und möglich ist.
        Ich lasse mir demnächst nochmals die Mskpte kommen, will sehen was ich selber noch machen
        muss. Hier habe ich <tei:rs key="entity-001751" type="work"><tei:title>g moll
            Sinf.</tei:title></tei:rs> und <tei:rs key="entity-001751" type="work"><tei:title>Chaos</tei:title></tei:rs>. Doch sind noch mehrere schwere Vorlagen bei den
        andern Sachen im <tei:rs key="entity-003129" type="organization">Mandruck</tei:rs>. Die
        schickten mir übrigens auch Ihre Korr. 1–10 des Textes, aber ohne das Mskpt, welches mir
        wenig nütze ist, da ich ja in der Hauptsache wegen <tei:hi rend="underline">Ziffern,
          Zeichen</tei:hi> usw. schwerere Fehler fürchte. Ich ersuchte <tei:sic>diesemnach</tei:sic>
        um Ihr Mskpt, dachte aber nebenbei: Vielleicht haben die mir nur ein Duplikat gesendet u.
        Ihnen die Hauptkorr. nebst <tei:abbr>Originalmspt</tei:abbr>. <tei:date when="1927-02-21">Morgen</tei:date> werde ich’s wissen. Aus Verzweiflung hatten die Setzer
        Identitätsstriche gezogen, aber oh weh, da wurde Ihr Mspt gradezu
        hieroglyphisch-palimpsestisch, es wurde zu einer wahren <tei:rs key="entity-000712" type="person">Riemanniade</tei:rs>. Ich dachte mir gleich, übersah und wusste unmittelbar:
          <tei:hi rend="underline">So</tei:hi> gehts <tei:hi rend="sperr">auf keinen Fall</tei:hi>.
        Und nun erscheint mir meine Lös<tei:supplied reason="clarity">un</tei:supplied>g die einzige
        wahre zu sein, indem durch <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Herrn v.
              <tei:abbr>H<tei:ex>oboken</tei:ex></tei:abbr></tei:rs>’s Entgegenkommen unsere
        Angelegenheit in jenes Fahrwasser geleitet wird, das sichere Fahrt garantiert.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ihnen &amp; Ihrer <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Gattin</tei:rs>
        <tei:sic>miene</tei:sic> allerangelegentlichsten ergebenen Grüsse &amp; hoffentlich auf
        baldige Begegnung zu erspriesslicher Arbeit,</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent=90">Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:handShift new="#OV"/><tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Otto Vrieslander</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#TPov"/>München 38, Walhallastrasse 9,</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1926-02-20">20.II.1927</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>

        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:lb/>

        <tei:p><tei:handShift new="#OV"/>Der <tei:gap reason="editorial" extent="6" unit="chars"/>
          der <tei:title>Sinf.</tei:title>
          ist fertig geworden und einfach vortrefflich ausgefallen, Uebersichtlich, <tei:unclear reason="reading" cert="high">klar</tei:unclear> &amp; s. w.</tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#TPov"/>Most esteemed, dear <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Dr. Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:lb/>

      <tei:p>You have already been informed by <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Mr. van
          Hoboken</tei:rs>, presumably, about the latest state of things. Yet, I shall once again
        give you more precise information, to make things clear to you in any event. The engraver
        came to see me. He quite simply cannot work from your manuscripts, if the danger is not to
        arise that you will have to read twenty sets of proofs, etc, to say nothing of unforeseeable
        costs. Even marks, auxiliary lines, and other engraving features of this sort are of no help
        for the purpose of working out the content of difficult manuscripts; rather, they fail
        completely.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:hi rend="underline">This I can completely understand after studying your
          originals</tei:hi>. I now have a new way of coming to grips with the matter, which is even
        more accomplished, for the purpose of achieving the very best, flawless copies; and I do
        this by drawing the <tei:term>staff line</tei:term>s on the paper myself. And, indeed, I
        have been so <tei:hi rend="underline">completely</tei:hi> successful at this that I can
        safely say that no arrangement of <tei:term>stave</tei:term>s is so complicated that I am
        unable to master it in the most advantageous way.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Now comes a second point. <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Mr. van
          Hoboken</tei:rs> wished – after <tei:supplied reason="clarity">I told him
          that</tei:supplied> I did <tei:hi rend="underline">not</tei:hi> want to speak, on account
        of the ludicrous constraints <tei:add place="margin-left" hand="#OV"><tei:supplied reason="syntax">(</tei:supplied>Beethoven – Counterpoint<tei:supplied reason="syntax">)</tei:supplied></tei:add> – to postpone my trip to <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs> to <tei:date when="1927-04-30">late April</tei:date>. This
        does not, unfortunately, accord with a number of my wishes; for this reason I suggested to
        him that I should instead come <tei:hi rend="underline">soon</tei:hi>, specifically after I
        have sketched all the important <tei:term>graph</tei:term>s and parts for you, which I will
        then bring with me to <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>. You will
        improve and revise these <tei:hi rend="underline">in my presence</tei:hi>, and I shall
        complete all the copies to make them ready for engraving, just like the last two. It is
        incomparably much more valuable for both parts to stand in direct connection with each other
        than always first to feel the <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>-<tei:rs key="entity-002286" type="place">Munich</tei:rs> vacuum
        intervening, as something that is actually quite obstructive.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/>
        <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Mr. van Hoboken</tei:rs> immediately agreed to my
        suggestion over the telephone <tei:date when="1927-02-19">yesterday</tei:date>, in the most
        agreeable way, which of course embraces everything practical and sensible.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Thus I shall work on the copies, which I have sensibly arranged already so that even
        they could <tei:hi rend="underline">in any event</tei:hi> serve as the fair copy, especially
        in the event that there are not many mistakes in them or you do not find much to
        change.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> We then need only <tei:hi rend="underline">a few days</tei:hi> to work
        together, and then everything will be dealt with in the clearest way. I have simply put my
        own work to one side, since one cannot pursue two different things at once, which each
        demand the entire person or even artist, since the work is far more than a mechanical act in
        my view. Thus you will probably see me between the <tei:date from="1927-03-15" to="1927-03-20">15th and 20th of March</tei:date>, and I believe that I can already assure
        you now that you will be astonished by my latest tricks of the trade, compared to the first
        two copies, which represent an experimental phase; this of course does not matter since
        everything will become engraver’s models. Nonetheless, I shall take it upon myself to rule
        the things conveniently, and so faithfully in their spatial relationships, as is only
        conceivable, desirable, and possible. I shall await the arrival of the manuscripts in the
        near future and see what I still have to do. I have the <tei:rs key="entity-001751" type="work"><tei:title>G minor Symphony</tei:title></tei:rs> and "<tei:rs key="entity-001751" type="work"><tei:title>Chaos</tei:title></tei:rs>" here. But there are
        several difficult copies for the other pieces at <tei:rs key="entity-003129" type="organization">Mandruck</tei:rs>’s. They sent me, moreover, your proof-sheets 1–10,
        but without the manuscript, which is of little use to me since I fear that there will be
        serious mistakes mainly on account of <tei:hi rend="underline">numbers and symbols</tei:hi>,
        etc. Accordingly, I asked them for your manuscript, but then thought to myself: perhaps they
        have sent me only a duplicate copy, and the main proofs, together with the original
        manuscript, have gone to you. <tei:date when="1927-02-21">Tomorrow</tei:date> I shall find
        out. In desperation, the engravers draw identity marks, but – oh, dear – your manuscript
        became utterly hierolglyphic-palimpsestic; it became a veritable <tei:rs key="entity-000712" type="person">Riemanniad</tei:rs>. I immediately thought to myself, looked it over, and
        knew immediately: <tei:hi rend="sperr">under no circumstances</tei:hi> will <tei:hi rend="underline">this</tei:hi> do. And now my solution comes to me as the only true one,
        in that by <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Mr. van Hoboken</tei:rs>’s intervention
        our matter will be launched in that channel that will guarantee safe passage.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>To you and your <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs>, my most
        earnest cordial greetings, and in the hope of an early meeting for our fruitful
        collaboration, </tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent=90">your,</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:handShift new="#OV"/><tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Otto Vrieslander</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#TPov"/>Munich 38, Walhallastraße 9,</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1926-02-20">20.II.1927</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>

        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:lb/>

        <tei:p><tei:handShift new="#OV"/>The <tei:gap reason="editorial" extent="6" unit="chars"/>
          of the <tei:title>symphony</tei:title> is finished, and
          has turned out to be simply splendid, neatly arranged, clear, etc.</tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>