<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3672" sdoID="OJ-13-10_24">OJ 13/10, [24]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="TLJ">
      <tei:persName>Timothy L. Jackson</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2010</tei:resp>

    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated September 20, 1924</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1924-09-20T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-07-15</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel has mailed four compositions to Schenker, and comments on each of them,
        in particular his Third Piano Sonata. -- He is doing preparatory stylistic work before
        writing some etudes.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002757"
            >Kiel</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1924-10-20">20. IX. 1924</tei:date>
        </tei:dateline>
        <tei:address rend="indent-60">
          <tei:addrLine>Feldstr 77<tei:hi rend="supralinear">IV</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
              >D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker’s diary for September 20,
            1924 records: “Von Oppel Manuscript von Sonaten, Bläserstück u. Lied – kein Brief.”
            (“From Oppel, manuscript of sonatas, piece for winds and song – no letter.”). The letter
            arrives two days later: “Von Dr. Oppel (Br.): über seine Sonaten.” (“From Dr. Oppel
            (letter): about his sonatas.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Die ganze Woche wollte ich schreiben, aber immer kommen neue Abhaltungen. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-006150">Meiner Frau</tei:rs> gehts besser, sie kann jetzt
        50–100m am Stock und am Arm einer Schwester gehn, u. wir hoffen, dass Sie Ende Oct, Anfang
        Nov. nach dem Süden reisen kann. Den <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801"
          >Jungen</tei:rs> gehts gut, u. ich bin nervös u. abgespannt, aber ich muss ausharren. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Soll ich die Namen der Subscribenten schicken?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot">As sales of <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001739"
              ><tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs> flagged after its launch, and
          the publishers became increasingly unhappy about keeping it going, Schenker asked a number
          of his friends and pupils to take out additional subscriptions and ask their friends and
          pupils to do the same.</tei:note> Legt der <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408"
          >Verlag</tei:rs> keine Listen auf, in die sich die Einzelnen eintragen u. damit sich
        gleich auch zur Abnahme verpflichten? </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Vielen Dank für die Bilder, die mich sehr gefreut haben! </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Die Verleger sind alle Hallunken, <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408"
          >U-E</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002890">Breitkopf u.
          Härtel</tei:rs> sind um kein Haar besser. Ich bekomme doch für meine Klavierstücke <tei:cit>
          <tei:q>keinen Pfennig!</tei:q>
        </tei:cit>
      </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Vorgestern schickte ich als Drucksache 1. u. 2. Klaviersonate,
        Bläserserenade u. das Lied „<tei:title>Früh i. Wagen</tei:title>“ v. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003452">Mörike</tei:rs>. Im letzteren sind die 3 ersten Strophen durch contrap
        Vertausch – entwickelt. Ist es Ihnen nicht zu <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094"
          >brahms</tei:rs>isch? Augenblicklich habe ich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000388"
          >Hölderlin</tei:rs>’s „<tei:title>An die Parzen</tei:title>“ in Arbeit. Auch da ist mir
        manches, gleichfalls zu <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094">br.</tei:rs> In der 1.
        Kl.sonate billige ich heute formell u. kl-technisch nicht mehr den lgs. u. den Schlusssatz,
        in der 2. des lgs. <tei:supplied reason="clarity">Satz</tei:supplied> nicht, der mir zu
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000104">bruckner</tei:rs>isch in der Melodiebildung ist.
        Es genügt, wenn Sie mir die Mscr Mitte Oct. zurückschicken.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot"> Schenker’s reply (non-extant) is recorded at considerable
          length in the diary for September 23: “An Oppel (Br.) über den ersten Eindruck der Sonate;
          ich bleibe dabei, daß er einen eigenen Ton hat, eine glückliche Mischung polyphonen u.
          homophonen Stils, der einzige ist, der solche Sonaten schreiben kann, er verfügt auch über
          den Klaviersatz, doch ist die Haltung nicht gleichwertig; sein Talent erstickt in der
          heutigen Welt! Er braucht von den Meistern nur die <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> abzulernen
          (was möglich ist, siehe die kleine Probe von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
            >Weisse</tei:rs>!); überflüssig ist aber das Stadium der Figurierung an sich.
          Bestellungen sind an <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002456">Gutmann</tei:rs> zu
          richten. Ob eine Verbindung mit der Familie <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000149"
            >Dahms</tei:rs> für die Frau erwünscht ist?” (“To Oppel (letter) about the first
          impression of the sonata; I stick to my opinion that he has his own tone, a successful
          mixture of polyphonic and homophonic style, that he is the only one who can write such
          sonatas, he is also adept at writing for piano, but the general manner is not of equal
          value; his talent is suffocating in today's world! He needs only to learn the
            <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> from the masters (which is possible, see the modest attempt
          by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs>!); but the stage of
          figuration, per se, is superfluous. Orders [for Schenker’s <tei:title level="j">Der
            Tonwille</tei:title>] are to be directed to <tei:rs type="organization"
            key="entity-002456">Gutmann</tei:rs>. Does his wife desire a connection to the <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000149">Dahms</tei:rs> family?”).</tei:note> Können Sie die
        Bläserserenade nicht einer Wiener Vereinigung empfehlen (Ary v. Leuwen) co.?<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Ary van Leeuwen (1875–1953), Dutch
          flautist and composer, was appointed to the Vienna Court Opera orchestra by Mahler in
          1903. During his time in Vienna, he founded a chamber music society for wind instruments.
          By 1924, however, he had emigrated to the United States, where he served as principal
          flautist of the Cincinnati Symphony Orchestra.</tei:note> Sie wird diesen Winter in
        Würzburg u. <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002342">Bern</tei:rs> gemacht. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun zum I. Satz der 3. Sonate:</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Im Wesentlichen teile ich vollkommen Ihre Ansichten und Bedenken. Figuration ist das
        wundeste Kapitel der modernen <tei:pb n="3"/> Komp. Auch <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs>ens Klavierstil ist mir oft zu plump-cyklopenhaft.
        Anderseits genügen mir heute Fig. durch Brechung i. mehreren Oct. durchaus nicht mehr, da
        sie im Grunde doch nur eine überflüssige, weil rein klangliche, aber keine sachlich, resp.
        inhaltlich steigernde Wiederholung bedeuten. So bliebe als letztes Ideal klavierstilistisch
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000129">Chopin</tei:rs>. Ich wälze dieses Problem schon
        lange u. immer wieder hin und her, ohne zu einem anderen Resultat zu kommen. Ähnlich bei der
        Geige, ein <tei:unclear reason="reading">angef<tei:supplied reason="abbreviation"
            >ertiges</tei:supplied></tei:unclear> Kzt liess ich liegen, weil wirklich neue
        Passagentechnik auf der Geige kaum noch möglich. Und was keine neuen Gesichte trägt,
        zerreisse ich selbstverständlich. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000344">Haydn</tei:rs>’s
        lgs Satz im C-dur Quartett op. 54<tei:hi rend="supralinear">2</tei:hi> ist mir immer noch
        ein unerreichtes Vorbild i. s. elementaren Selbstverständlichkeit bei der Intensität des
        Ausdrucks. Wer kann das heute noch? </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Bei dem Sonatensatz habe ich mir auch lange überlegt, ob ich nicht consequent bei der
        3st. Anlage <tei:pb n="4"/> bleiben sollte. Meine Idee war, eine Sonate mit möglichst
        grossen Linien zu schreiben u. alle Teile durch contrap. Umkehrungen der ganzen Linien zu
        bestreiten. Übrigens in der 2. Sonate hatte ich das 2. Thema zunächst durchaus nicht darauf
        angelegt, sondern die contrap Verwendung bei der Reprise ergab sich von selbst. Vorläufig
        lasse ich den <tei:hi rend="supralinear">1.</tei:hi> Sonatensatz der 3. <tei:supplied
          reason="clarity">Sonate</tei:supplied> ruhen, ich werde ihn schon eines Tags wieder
        vornehmen. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Das Wetter ist jetzt herrlich hier, wie fast immer im Herbst und das tägliche Schwimmen
        ist meine einzige Erholung. – Schade, dass <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000287"
          >Glas</tei:rs> Sie noch nicht antraf.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Schenker’s diary for September 5, 1924 records: “... eine Nachricht von Prof.
          Glas aus Kiel, der nur Grüße von Oppel bringen wollte.” (“… a message from Professor Glas
          from Kiel, who merely wanted to extend greetings from Oppel.”).</tei:note> Er hat sich
        sehr gut erholt. Das gleiche hoffe ich von Ihnen beiden. – Ich vergleiche jetzt <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000129">Chopin</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000808">Schumann</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094"
          >Brahms</tei:rs> auf den Klavierstil hin, u. trage mich mit der Absicht einige Etuden zu
        schreiben. </tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Alles Gute u. die herzlichsten Grüsse</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Ihnen beiden, auch von <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-006150">meiner Frau</tei:rs></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Ihr treuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002757"
            >Kiel</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1924-10-20">September 20, 1924</tei:date>
        </tei:dateline>
        <tei:address rend="indent-60">
          <tei:addrLine>Feldstraße 77/4</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Dr.
            Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>I was hoping to write to you all week, but new obstacles constantly intervene. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-006150">My wife</tei:rs> is better, she can now walk between 50
        and 100 meters with a cane and a nurse’s arm; and we hope that she will be able to travel to
        the south by the end of October or the beginning of November. The <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-004801">boys</tei:rs> are well, and I am nervous and exhausted; but I must
        bear up.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Should I send you the names of the subscribers?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> Does the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408"
          >publisher</tei:rs> not issue a list, in which the individuals enter their names and thus
        commit themselves also to purchasing?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Many thanks for the photographs, which delighted me greatly!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>All publishers are scoundrels: <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408"
          >Universal Edition</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002890">Breitkopf
          &amp; Härte</tei:rs>l are not a hair’s breadth better. For my piano pieces I don’t receive <tei:cit>
          <tei:q>a penny!</tei:q>
        </tei:cit>
      </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> The day before yesterday I sent you, as printed papers, my first and
        second piano sonatas, the wind serenade, and the song “<tei:title>Early in the
          Morning</tei:title>” by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003452">Mörike</tei:rs>. In the
        last-named work, the first three verses are developed by contrapuntal (voice) exchange. Is
        that not too <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs>ian for you? At the
        moment I am working on <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000388">Hölderlin</tei:rs>’s
          “<tei:title>To the Fates</tei:title>.” There, too, much seems likewise too <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs>ian. In the first piano sonata, I now no
        longer sanction the formal, the classically technical, in the slow movement and finale. In
        the second sonata, not in the slow movement, which is too <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000104">Bruckner</tei:rs>ian in its melodic construction. It will be fine for
        you to return the manuscripts to me by the middle of October.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
          type="footnote"/> Could you not recommend the wind serenade to a Viennese group (Ary von
          Leeuwen’s<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/>)? It will be performed this
        winter in Würzburg and <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002342">Bern</tei:rs>. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Now to the first movement of the third sonata:</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Essentially, I share your views and concerns completely. Figuration is the toughest
        chapter in modern composition. <tei:pb n="3"/> I often find even <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs>’s piano style too plump–cyclopic. On the other hand,
        figurations by arpeggiation in several octaves no longer satisfy me at all, as they signify
        a purely sonic repetition, but not an objective one that is intensified by its content. Thus
        the ultimate ideal in pianistic style remains <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000129"
          >Chopin</tei:rs>’s. I have wrestled constantly with this problem for a long time, without
        arriving at a different result. It is similarly the case with the violin: I left a
          <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">completed</tei:unclear> concerto aside, because a
        truly new technique of passagework on the violin is hardly possible any longer. And that
        which does not bear new aspects I of course tear up. For me, the slow movement of <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000344">Haydn</tei:rs>’s Quartet in C major, Op. 54, No. 2, is
        still the unreachable model in its elementary naturalness in intensity of expression. Who
        can still do that today?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In my sonata movement, I have for a long time even wondered, whether I should not stick
        to a three-part texture, for sake of consistency. <tei:pb n="4"/> It was my idea to write a
        sonata containing lines that were as long as possible, and to provide all the part with
        contrapuntal inversions of the entire lines. Moreover, in the second sonata I did not at all
        aim at this; rather, the contrapuntal treatment in the recapitulation came naturally of
        itself. For the time being I shall leave the first movement of the third sonata alone and
        take it up again some other day. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>The weather here is splendid now, as is almost always the case in the autumn; and a
        daily swim is my only form of recuperation. – A pity that <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000287">Glas</tei:rs> did not meet up with you.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05"
          type="footnote"/> He has recovered very well. I hope the same thing for you. – At present
        I am comparing the pianistic styles of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000129"
          >Chopin</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000808">Schumann</tei:rs>, and <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs> and am considering writing a few etudes. </tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>All good wishes and the most cordial greetings</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">to the two of you, also from <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-006150">my wife</tei:rs></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Ihr treuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
