<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="1029" sdoID="OC-52-647">OC 52/647</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="MV" scope="sole">Moriz Violin's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
      <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-07-24" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002719">ViolinM ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM+V ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002718">ViolinM+V+F ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Moriz Violin to Schenker, dated February 5, 1925</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1925-02-05T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2013-07-24</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Violin explains why, and how, the number of free copies of Der Tonwille
        distributed to German university music departments was reduced from 10 per university to 7.
        He has seen Paul Bekker's recent book, which includes a survey of recent trends in music
        theory.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

    <!-- This letter was encoded without access to a copy of the original document, 
      thus indents etc. (currently guessed) may subsequently need to be revised. 
    ALSO CHECK GERMAN INVERTED COMMAS ETC. -->

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1925-02-05">5. Februar 25</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Liebster <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in
            the diary at OJ 3/7, p. 2788: "Von Fl. (Brief expreß): erklärt die Zahl 10 x 7, fügt
            aber hinzu, 10 weitere Abonnements dürfe ich als ebenso feststehend annehmen.
            Lie-Liechen meint, dass er mit Temmings Geld 10 weitere Abonnements in seiner Umgebung
            verschenkt habe, um diese 10 sind die Seminare verkürzt worden; er erwähnt schließlich,
            daß Bekker meiner in seinem neuesten Buch gedacht habe, doch verstehe ich die Wendung
            nicht: „. . aber schon gar nicht als Hermeneut.“" (From Floriz (express letter):
            explains the figure 10 x 7, but adds that I can assume that another ten subscriptions
            are equally sure. Lie-Liechen thinks that he has given away ten further subscriptions as
            a present to people around him using Temming's money, the institutes have been reduced
            by these ten; finally, he mentions that Bekker paid tribute to me in his latest book,
            however I do not understand the expression: 'but not in the least as a
            hermeneuticist.'")</tei:note>
        </tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Gestern kam Dein l. Brief<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-6-7_17">=
          OJ 6/7, [17]</tei:ref>. Ich ging abends sofort zu Herrn <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Temming</tei:rs>. Leider ist er auf einer Geschäftsreise u. kommt erst
          <tei:date when="1925-02-08">Sonntag</tei:date> zurück. Das ist für Deine Zwecke nun zu
        lange. Ausserdem ist es nicht dafür absolut nötig. Ich kann Dir ganz genaue Auskunft geben.
        Vorher möchte ich nur Dir die Zahl 7 erklären. Seinerseit gieng ich zu Herrn <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Temming</tei:rs> u. gewann ihn für meinem
        Universtätsspende-Plan. Ich „<tei:soCalled>akkordierte</tei:soCalled>“ 100 Hefte à 1 Mark.
        Inzwischen <tei:del rend="overstrike">kam</tei:del> kam die Preiserhöhung. Da war für mich
        die peinliche Situation, daß <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">T.</tei:rs> leicht
          an<tei:note type="editorial">corr</tei:note> meiner Unwissenheit zweifeln könnte. Ein Buch
        kostet aber über Nacht im allgemeinen nicht um die Hälfte mehr. Das ist ja auch eine Dich
        schädigende Geschäftsgebauung der <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">U.
          E.</tei:rs> (Nicht zu reden von dem 2 Mark Preis!!!).</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich fragte Herrn <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">T.</tei:rs>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">sehr</tei:hi> nebenbei, ob es ihm recht ist, damit ich die alte
        Vereinbarung halten kann, daß ich die Zahl auf 7 reduziere. Er war dafür daß ich es nach
        Gutdünken erledige. Ich behielt die <tei:hi rend="underline">10 Institute</tei:hi> bei
          <tei:note type="editorial">following three words underlined by Schenker, in coloured
          pencil</tei:note>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">à 7 Hefte</tei:hi>. Der Unterschied schien mir so gering, daß ich
        Dich damit weiter nicht aufhalten wollte. Nun war es doch nicht zu vermeiden.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Also: <tei:hi rend="double-underline">Ich</tei:hi> machte die <tei:hi rend="underline">kleine</tei:hi> Bestellung von 7 x 4 Heften für die einzel angeführten
        Seminare.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Von Herrn <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Temming</tei:rs> hätte ich nur
        erfahren können, ob die <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">U. E.</tei:rs> die
        Bestellung auch ordnungsgemäß ausgeführt hat, was durch Einsicht in bezahlte Rechnungen
        möglich gewesen wäre. Sollten die <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">U.
          E.</tei:rs> die Bestellung nicht ordnungsgemäß ausgeführt haben (was ich erst <tei:date when="1925-02-09">Montag</tei:date>, Du vielleicht durch den Anwalt schon früher erfahren
        kannst) so liegt eine ganz gewaltige Sabotage vor. Ich habe Verdacht, kenn<tei:note type="editorial">?</tei:note>
        <tei:note type="editorial">following five words underlined by Schenker, in coloured
          pencil</tei:note>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">die Einzelabonnementssituationen auch nicht gut</tei:hi>. Darüber
        werde ich mich noch vergewissern. Jedenfalls kannst Du auf die Kenntnis der Tatsache, daß
          <tei:note type="editorial">following eleven words underlined by Schenker, in coloured
          pencil</tei:note>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">7 Abonnements für 10 Institute u. in 10 einzelne vollzogen
          wurden</tei:hi>, pochen. Sind sie nicht ausgeführt worden, so ist es Schuld allein der
          <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">U. E</tei:rs>. Ein anständiger Betrieb muß
        in der Lage sein<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> Dir die <tei:note type="editorial">following word underlined by Schenker, in coloured pencil</tei:note>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">80</tei:hi> Abonnements zu verrechnen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:date when="1925-01">Jänner</tei:date> Heft der <tei:rs key="entity-002556" type="journal"><tei:title>Musik</tei:title></tei:rs> habe ich nicht
        gelesen. Hast Du aber das jüngst erschienene Buch von <tei:rs key="entity-000057" type="person">Becker</tei:rs> gelesen? Ich weiß momentan nicht den Titel. Er rubriziert
        darin die einzelnen Richtungen der <tei:term>Theorie</tei:term> u. zählt Dich da aber schon
          <tei:hi rend="underline">gar</tei:hi> nicht zu den <tei:term>Hermeneuten</tei:term>. Er
        scheint für die Ewigkeit vorsichtiger als für die Tagesblätter zu schreiben.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Innigstes von uns an Euch! Und bitte schreibe wenn Du einen Wunsch nach
        weiterer Aufklärung hast.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Dein alter, treuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1925-02-05">February 5, 1925</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dearest <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
        </tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Your lovely letter arrived yesterday<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-6-7_17">= OJ 6/7, [17]</tei:ref>. In the evening, I went to Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Temming</tei:rs> straightaway. Unfortunately he is on a
        business trip and is not returning until <tei:date when="1925-02-08">Sunday</tei:date>. For
        your purposes, that is too long to wait. Moreover, it is not absolutely necessary. I can
        give you very precise information. First of all, let me merely explain the number 7. When I
        approached Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Temming</tei:rs>, and won him over
        to my plan for a grant to the universities, I "<tei:soCalled>consented</tei:soCalled>" to
        100 issues <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs></tei:supplied> at 1 mark each.
        Later on, a price increase was introduced. I was thus faced with the painful situation that
          <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Temming</tei:rs> might be skeptical concerning
        my ignorance: generally speaking, a book should not suddenly cost half again as much
        overnight. That is indeed a business plan of the <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">UE</tei:rs> that would also damage you financially. (To say nothing of
        a price of 2 marks!!!).</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I asked Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Temming</tei:rs>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">very</tei:hi> casually whether it would be all right with him – in
        order that I keep to the original agreement – if I reduced the number <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of copies given to each university</tei:supplied> to 7. He was in favor
        of my doing what I thought best. I retained all <tei:hi rend="underline">10
          departments</tei:hi>, <tei:note type="editorial">following three words underlined by
          Schenker, in coloured pencil</tei:note>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">with 7 copies</tei:hi>. The difference seemed to me so small that I
        did not wish to hold you up further. Now I see that this was, after all,
        unavoidable.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Thus, it was <tei:hi rend="double-underline">I</tei:hi> who made the
          <tei:hi rend="underline">smaller</tei:hi> order of 7 x 4 copies for each of the music
        departments named.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I would have been able to find out from Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Temming</tei:rs> only whether <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">UE</tei:rs>
        also filled this order properly, something that would have been possible by inspecting the
        paid invoices. If <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">UE</tei:rs> has not filled
        the order properly (something that I cannot find out until <tei:date when="1925-02-09">Monday</tei:date>, you perhaps sooner from your lawyer), then a thoroughly monumental
        sabotage has taken place. I have my doubts about this, and also I do not know <tei:note type="editorial">following six words underlined by Schenker, in coloured pencil</tei:note>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">the details of the individual suscriptions</tei:hi>. I shall yet
        ascertain this. In any event, you can reckon on that fact that <tei:note type="editorial">following eleven words underlined by Schenker, in coloured pencil</tei:note>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">7 subscriptions for 10 departments, and 10 individual subscriptions
          were arranged</tei:hi>. If they were not implemented, then only <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">UE</tei:rs> is at fault. A proper company ought to
        be in a position to account for the <tei:note type="editorial">following word underlined by
          Schenker, in coloured pencil</tei:note>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">80</tei:hi> subscriptions.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I have not read the <tei:date when="1925-01">January</tei:date> issue of
          <tei:rs key="entity-002556" type="journal"><tei:title level="j">Die
          Musik</tei:title></tei:rs>. But have you read <tei:rs key="entity-000057" type="person">Bekker</tei:rs>'s most recently published book? At the moment, I do not know its title.
        He categorizes the individual directions taken by <tei:term>music theory</tei:term> and most
        emphatically does <tei:hi rend="underline">not</tei:hi> reckon you among the
          <tei:term>hermeneutists</tei:term>. He seemes to write more carefully for posterity than
        for the daily newspapers.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Most intimate greetings from us to you. And please write if you need
        further explanation.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Your old, faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>