<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2965" sdoID="OC-52-427">OC 52/427</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>
    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPueR" scope="major">UE's typist "R"</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="EH" scope="minor">Emil Hertzka's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS-pencil" scope="minor">Heinrich Schenker's hand, in
        pencil</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="stamp" scope="minor">stamped</tei:handNote>

    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006, 2023</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2006, 2023</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2023</tei:resp>

    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-02-07" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002702">UE ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002701">UE ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002700">Hertzka ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Typewritten letter from Hertzka (UE) to Schenker, dated June 3, 1912</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1912-06-03T14:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2023-01-18</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Hertzka addresses Schenker's request for an honorarium for correcting proofs
        of Beethovens neunte Sinfonie; he counters that the total author corrections have run to 600
        Kronen. He is sending the volume to the printers today. -- He commits in principle to the
        editing of the last five Beethoven piano sonatas [Erläuterungsausgabe], but on the basis of
        the Chromatic Fantasy and Fugue sales he cannot accede to Schenker's demands; he makes a
        counter-proposal.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-002408">Universal Edition</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000356">Emil Hertzka</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>„Universal-Edition“ A.-G.</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>(Jos. Aibl Verlag, G.m.b.H.)</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Leipzig <tei:supplied reason="spacer">/</tei:supplied> Sternwartestrasse
            1520.</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:del rend="overstrike">Wien I., Wipplingerstrasse
            32</tei:del></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#stamp"/>Wien <tei:supplied reason="spacer"
              >/</tei:supplied> I., Reichsratsstrasse 8</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="italic"
                >etc.</tei:hi></tei:note></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:lb/>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:byline><tei:handShift new="#TPueR"/>
          <tei:persName type="typist">R</tei:persName></tei:byline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>
          <tei:placeName>Wien</tei:placeName>, <tei:handShift new="#TPueR"/><tei:date
            when="1912-06-03">3. Juni 1912</tei:date>.</tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="ident-20">Wohlgeboren Herrn Prof. Dr. <tei:persName>Heinrich <tei:hi
                rend="sperr">Schenker</tei:hi></tei:persName></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-70">
            <tei:hi rend="underline sperr">Wien.</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#TPueR"/>Sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000632">Doktor</tei:rs>!</tei:salute><tei:lb/>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ihr Ersuchen eines nachträglichen Honorars von 400 Kronen[1] für Ihre
        Arbeit an Beethovens IX. Symphonie[entity-001731] hätte ich selbstverständlich glatt
        erledigt, wenn nicht die Nachtragsforderungen der Firma Breitkopf &amp;
        Härtel[entity-002890] für sogenannte Autor-Korrekturen, das sind schwere Korrekturen, die
        mit grossen Aenderungen des Manuskriptes zusammenhängen und die ausserhalb jeder Kalkulation
        stehen, bis heute schon zka. 600 Mark betragen würde. So gerne ich im Prinzipe die
        Berechtigung Ihrer Forderung einsehe, so muss ich doch, ehe ich Ihnen endgiltig ja sage,
        irgend eine Basis für diese Ueberschreitung finden und behalte mir vor, in den nächsten
        Tagen auf die Sache zurückzukommen. Ich hoffe, dass es mir möglich sein wird, Ihren über die
        Abmachung hinausgehenden Wünschen entgegenzukommen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in left margin:</tei:note>
        <tei:handShift new="#HS-pencil"/>„<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001733">Erl.
          A.</tei:rs>“<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end</tei:note> Was nun die Frage der
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above"><tei:handShift new="#EH"/>Beethoven</tei:add>
        <tei:handShift new="#TPueR"/>Sonaten betrifft,[2] <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
            ><tei:handShift new="#HS-pencil"/>(nun wieder!)</tei:add>
        <tei:handShift new="#TPueR"/>so habe ich Ihnen ja mehr als einmal gesagt, dass mich die
        Sache interessiert und dass ich sie machen will. <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"
          >in left margin:</tei:note>
        <tei:handShift new="#HS-pencil"/>à 2,000 Kr.<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"
          >end</tei:note> Es hängt nur davon ab, unter wel- <tei:pb n="2"/> chen Bedingungen. Ein
        Herausgabe-Honorar von 2000 Kronen für eine Sonate durchzubringen, ist bei uns derzeit
        vollkommen ausgeschlossen und wenn Sie bei diesem Herausgabe-Honorar beharren müssen, dann
        muss ich, so leid es mir tut, die Sache fallen lassen. Ich bin mir des ausserordentlichen
        Wertes den Ihre Arbeiten haben voll bewusst,[3] und es würde "Eulen nach Athen zu tragen"
        heissen, wenn Sie mich von der Wichtigkeit der Sache noch weiter überzeugen wollten. Ebenso
        aber kenne ich die Grenzen unserer Kraft und ich darf Geschäfte, auch mit den besten
        Zukunfte-Chancen[4] ^[EH:]heute^ nur in begränzter Weise machen. Wenn heute Ihre Ausgab[e]
        der "Chromatischen Fantasie und Fuge von Bach[entity-001730]"[5] [left margin:
        HS-pencil:]War ja falsch angekündigt[end] bereits einen auch nur kleinen materiellen Erfolg
        gehabt hätte, dann wäre ich heute schon sicher zu einem grösseren Engagement berechtigt
        gewesen. Ich bin überzeugt, dass Ihre Chromatische Fantasie-Arbeit im Laufe der Jahre einen
        schönen Absatz haben wird, ebenso wie ihn die Beethoven-Sonaten[entity-001733] haben würden
        und werden und dass also diese Sache im Verlaufe der Jahre auch ‒ wie Sie immer betonen –
        ein gutes Geschäft wird. Und doch bin ich an ein Budget gebunden und bitte Sie, so weit dies
        möglich, das auch zu berücksichtigen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich würde mir eine Abmachung mit Beteiligung am besten vorstellen können
        und zwar dergestalt, dass ich Ihnen für jede Sonate eine Tantième von 20 Hellern bis zum
        Verkauf von zehntausend Exemplaren bezahlen würde und auf die fünf Sonaten einen
        Gesamt-Vorschuss in fünf Jahresraten. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Wenn Sie im Prinzipe einen derartigen Vorschlag akzeptieren können, dann
        müssten wir uns nur noch über den Gesamt-Vor- <tei:pb n="3"/> schuss einigen und von der
        Erfüllbarkeit Ihrer diesbzgl. Wünsche würde dann das Zustandekommen dieser Abmachung
        abhängen. Sollten Sie aber diese Vorschläge ablehnen müssen, dann wäre ich, so aufrichtig
        leid es mir auch täte, nicht in der Lage, diese Sache weiter zu verfolgen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Auf Ihre Anfrage bezüglich Niloff, Instrumentations-Tabelle[entity-001729]
        gibt Ihnen die Buchhaltung gleichzeitig separat Nachricht. Dem Besuch des Herrn
        Weisse[entity-000951] und der Einsendung seiner Manuskripte sehe ich mit grossem Vergnügen
        entgegen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Eben bei Diktat dieses Briefes erhalte ich das gesamte Imprimatur von
        Beethovens "Neunter". Für die überaus pünktliche Erledigung verbindlichsten Dank. Von dem
        Inhaltsverzeichnis ^[EH:] mit den 2 Bogen von Ihnen bezeichneten Bogen^ brauchen wir noch
        Korrektur-Abzug. Ich schicke heute alles an Breitkopf und lasse die Korrekturen und den Satz
        des Inhaltsverzeichnisses aufs Möglichste beschleunigen. Wenn es technisch denkbar ist, so
        werden die ersten Exemplare des Werkes zur Festwoche da sein.[6] </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">In der Angelegenheit Ihrer Organisation[entity-002403] sehe ich mit
        Vergnügen weiteren Mitteilungen entgegen und verbleibe mit besten Grüssen.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Ihr in aufrichtiger Hochschätzung</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">ergebener</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#EH"/><tei:rs key="entity-000356"
            type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>Universal Edition &amp; Co.</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>(Josef Aibl Publishers, &amp; Co.)</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Leipzig <tei:supplied reason="spacer">/</tei:supplied> Sternwartestrasse
            1520</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:del rend="overstrike">Vienna I, Wipplingerstrasse
            32</tei:del></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#stamp"/>Vienna <tei:supplied reason="spacer"
              >/</tei:supplied> I, Reichsratsstrasse 8</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="italic"
                >etc.</tei:hi></tei:note></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:lb/>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:byline><tei:handShift new="#TPueR"/>
          <tei:persName type="typist">R</tei:persName></tei:byline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>
          <tei:placeName>Vienna</tei:placeName>, <tei:handShift new="#TPueR"/><tei:date
            when="1912-06-03">June 3, 1912</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="ident-20">Prof. <tei:persName>Heinrich <tei:hi rend="sperr"
                >Schenker</tei:hi></tei:persName>, Esq.</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-70">
            <tei:hi rend="underline sperr">Vienna</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#TPueR"/>Dear Dr. <tei:supplied><tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,</tei:salute><tei:lb/>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">I would naturally have attended to your petition for a supplementary
        honorarium of 400 Kronen[1] for your work on Beethoven’s Ninth Symphony without more ado,
        had not the firm of Breitkopf &amp; Härtel's supplemental demands for what it calls
        "author's corrections," i.e. heavy corrections relating to major changes of the manuscript,
        and that were not included in any [previous] calculation, amounted, to date, to ca. 600
        Kronen. As much as in principle I understand the justification for your demand, I clearly
        must find some reason for this overrun before I finally say "Yes" to you, so I have resolved
        to come back to the matter in the next few days. I hope it will be possible for me to
        fulfill your wishes, which go beyond the terms of our agreement.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in left margin:</tei:note>
        <tei:handShift new="#HS-pencil"/>"<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001733">Elucidatory
          Edition</tei:rs>"<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end</tei:note> Now, as concerns
        the <tei:add place="interlinear-above"><tei:handShift new="#HS-pencil"/>Beethoven</tei:add>
        <tei:handShift new="#TPueR"/>Sonatas,[2] <tei:add place="interlinear-above"><tei:handShift
            new="#HS-pencil"/>(here we go again!)</tei:add>
        <tei:handShift new="#TPueR"/>I have said to you more than once that the idea interests me,
        and that I will do it. <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in left margin:</tei:note>
        <tei:handShift new="#HS-pencil"/>per 2,000 Kronen<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"
          >end</tei:note>
        <tei:handShift new="#TPueR"/>It just depends under what <tei:pb n="2"/> conditions. To run
        to an editorial honorarium of 2,000 Kronen for a single sonata is completely out of the
        question for us at this time, and if you persist with this editorial honorarium then, as
        much as it grieves me, I am bound let the idea drop. I am fully aware of the exceptional
        value of your works,[3] and it would be "carrying coals to Newcastle" if you were to try to
        convince me still further of the importance of the project. Equally well, however, I know
        the limits of our powers, and can do business ^[EH:]these days^ only on a reduced scale,
        even with the best prospects for the future.[4] If your edition of Bach's Chromatic Fantasy
        and Fugue[5] [left margin: HS-pencil:]It was incorrectly advertised[end] were by now having
        even just some slight financial success today, then I would certainly be entitled to embark
        right away on a larger commitment. I am convinced that your Chromatic Fantasy volume will
        achieve handsome sales over the course of years, just as the Beethoven Sonatas would and
        will, and therefore that this project too will ‒ as you are forever emphasizing ‒ market
        well over the years. And yet I am bound by a budget, and I ask you, insofar as possible, to
        take this into consideration. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">The best way I could envision an agreement with a share for you is
        specifically for me to pay you a royalty of 20 Hellers for each sonata up to sale of the
        first ten thousand copies, and on the Five Sonatas as a whole an advance in five annual
        installments.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">If you are able in principle to accept a proposal of this sort, then all
        that we would have to come to terms on would be the total <tei:pb n="3"/> advance, and then
        making this agreement a reality would depend on the fulfilling of your wishes in this
        respect. If on the other hand you felt compelled to reject these proposals then, genuinely
        sorry though I would be, I would be in no position to pursue this matter any
        further.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">As regards your inquiry re the Niloff Table of Instrumentation, our
        book-keeping department is sending you information simultaneously under separate cover. I
        look forward eagerly to Mr Weisse's visit, and receipt of his manuscripts.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Even as I was dictating this letter, I have received your overall
        imprimatur of Beethoven's Ninth. My most grateful thanks for taking care of this so
        promptly. We still need corrected proof of the Table of Contents ^[EH:] with the two
        gatherings designated by you^. I will send everything to Breitkopf today, and will have the
        corrected proofs and the setting of the Table of Contents rushed as soon as possible. If
        technically feasible, the first copies of the book will be available at the Festival
        Week.[6]</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">On the matter of your Organization, I look forward with pleasure to
        receiving further information, and I remain, with best wishes,</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">And with high regard,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">Your devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#EH"/><tei:rs key="entity-000356"
            type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
