<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="1129" sdoID="OC-54-105-106">OC 54/105-106</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="major">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="KH">
      <tei:persName>Kirstie Hewlett</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2014</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2011-10-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>


  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-004414">DMV ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Draft of a letter from Schenker to Drei Masken Verlag in Jeanette Schenker’s hand,
        dated November 18, 1926</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1926-11-18T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2014-10-04</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker reminds the publishers once again that they owe him a decision about
        starting production of the second Meisterwerk Yearbook; although they have complained about
        poor sales, they have done nothing to publicize the book, which would otherwise be unknown
        to his adherents in foreign countries.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>deadline; Termin; reminder; Erinnerung; contract; Vertrag; correction; Korrektur;
        sales; Absatz; advertisement; Inserat</dc:subject>
    </sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:note type="editorial" place="pre-text">This draft, in Jeanette Schenker’s hand with
        numerous corrections and additions by Heinrich, is crossed through with long vertical lines.
        The following transcription and translation are of the last reading of the text.</tei:note>

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine>An den <tei:rs key="entity-002627" type="organization">Drei Masken
            Verlag</tei:rs>!</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline>geschr. den <tei:date when="1926-11-18">18.XI.26</tei:date><tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Sending of the final version of this
            letter is recorded by the postal receipt <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-54-107"
              >OC 54/107</tei:ref>, and in the diaries at OJ 3/9, p. 3003, November 19, 1926: “rec.
            Br. aufgegeben, s. Mappe.” (“registered letter sent; see the <tei:supplied
              reason="editorial">DMV</tei:supplied> folder.”)</tei:note></tei:dateline>
      </tei:opener>
      
      <tei:lb/>

      <tei:p>Nicht nur haben Sie den Termin überschritten, den Sie selbst für Ihre Aeußerung sich
        gesetzt hatten, Sie antworten auch nicht auf meine Erinnerung. Es ist klar, daß die
        Angelegenheit so nicht stehen bleiben kann. Unhaltbar ist es, daß sie Sie zum Schaden dieser
        u. künftiger Arbeiten – ganz nur in Ihr Belieben stellten u. den Vertrag höchstens nur dazu
        gebrauchten, mir Korrekturen anzurechnen, die zum größeren Teil auf Ihre Schuld zu buchen
        sind, sofern die Form der Klischeés u. <tei:term>Urlinietafeln</tei:term> ohne mich zu
        befragen anders als im <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"
            ><tei:title>Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs> eingerichtet worden sind.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Sie klagen in Ihrem Schreiben auch über den Absatz. Sind die in den
        Abrechnung ausgewiesenen 44 Exemplare gewiß sehr wenig – jedenfalls aber mehr als 6 die von
        gewisser Seite mir vorgehalten wurden – so haben Sie sich das selbst zuzuschreiben, da
        sonderbarerweise bis jetzt kein Inserat publiziert worden ist. Woher sollten Musiker im
        Ausland die mir zugetan sind z.B. in Fin<tei:supplied reason="syntax">n</tei:supplied>land,
        England, Amerika von dem <tei:rs key="entity-001749" type="work">Jahrbuch</tei:rs> erfahren?
        Privat kann sie Ihr Verlag nicht erreichen u. mir obliegt es gewiß nicht, das
        Inseratgeschäft zu besorgen, – das doch nicht erspart werden kann.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich bitte also dringend um die zugesagte Erklärung.</tei:p>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine>To <tei:rs key="entity-002627" type="organization">Drei Masken
          Verlag</tei:rs>!</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline>Written on <tei:date when="1926-11-18">18.XI.26</tei:date><tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:dateline>
      </tei:opener>
      
      <tei:lb/>

      <tei:p>Not only have you passed the deadline that you yourselves had set for your statement,
        you do not even reply to my reminder. It is clear that the matter cannot be left as it is.
        It is untenable that you – to the detriment of this and future pieces of work – looked after
        your own interests entirely, and used the contract at most to charge me for making
        corrections that are largely to be regarded as your responsibility insofar as the form of
        the music examples and <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> graphs has been set up differently than
        in <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Der
          Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>, without your asking me.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> You also complain in your letter about the sales. If the 44 copies
        indicated in your calculations are to be sure very little – though at any rate more than the
        six which were suggested to me from certain quarters – you have yourselves to thank since,
        strangely enough, no advertisement has yet been published. From whence should musicians in
        foreign countries, who are devoted to me, for instance in Finland, England, and America,
        have heard about the <tei:rs key="entity-001749" type="work">Yearbook</tei:rs>? Your
        publishing house cannot reach them personally, and it is certainly not my obligation to take
        care of the advertising business, which of course cannot be dispensed with.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Thus I ask you urgently for the explanation you agreed to provide.</tei:p>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
