<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="1219" sdoID="OC-54-199-200">OC 54/199-200</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="GT" scope="major">Georg Tomay's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="stamp" scope="minor">stamp</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>


    <tei:respStmt xml:id="KH">
      <tei:persName>Kirstie Hewlett</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2014</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2011-10-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs key="entity-005453" type="correspondence" role="correspondence">Tomay ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Georg Tomay to Schenker, dated July 9, 1930</dc:title>
      <dcterms:created>1930-07-09T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2014-04-07</dcterms:dateSubmitted>

      <dc:description>Tomay encloses the imprints of the music examples for the third Meisterwerk
        volume, along with the original manuscripts, and requests clarification on various matters.
        He invites Schenker to send corrections at his earliest convenience, and informs him that
        the printing of the appendix will be undertaken in Leipzig instead of Vienna owing to a
        significant reduction in production costs.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>music example; Figur; manuscript; Manuskript; appendix; Notenbeilagen; blueprint
        process; Lichtpauseverfahren; lithographic process; Litographie; Bogen; gatherings;
        shortcoming; Mangel; printing house; Druckerei; imprint; Abklatsch; large sheet;
        correction; Korrektur; matrix; Matritze; manuscript; Manuskript</dc:subject>

    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000894">Tomay</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#stamp"/>Spezialanstalt für Musikalische
            Arbeiten</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Georg Tomay</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Wien. I., Fichtegasse 1a Tel. R-22-419</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60">
          <tei:placeName><tei:handShift new="#GT"/>Wien</tei:placeName>, <tei:date when="1930-07-09">9. Juli 1930</tei:date>
        </tei:dateline>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>Sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Professor</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt
            of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/3, p. 3494, July 10, 1930: "Von
            Tomay (rec.): Figuren u. B. mit Erläuterung ihrer Behandlung." ("From Tomay (registered
            mail): music examples, and a letter explaining how to deal with them.").</tei:note>
        </tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Übersende Ihnen Abklatsche der Figuren und Manuscripte alles was grün
        angezeichnet ist sind Mängel die ich an Hand der Manuscripte gefunden habe mit lila
        Farbstift angezeichnetes frage ich an ob gemacht wird. Inzwischen ist eine Änderung
        eingetreten und zwar werden die Notenbeilagen doch nicht in
          <tei:placeName>Wien</tei:placeName> gedruckt und zwar in
          <tei:placeName>Leipzig</tei:placeName> bei <tei:rs key="entity-005006" type="organization">Roeder</tei:rs> von den Ihnen <tei:date when="1930-07-09">heute</tei:date> zugehenden Abklatschen wird in
          <tei:placeName>Wien</tei:placeName> ein einziger Abzug und zwar auf transparenten Papier
        gemacht und in <tei:placeName>Leipzig</tei:placeName> neu umgedruckt in Lichtpauseverfahren.
        Angeblich rechnet <tei:rs key="entity-005006" type="organization">Roeder</tei:rs> für die
        ganze Notenbeilage-druckarbeit 200.- Mark und <tei:rs key="entity-005005" type="organization">Piller</tei:rs> hätte nur für die 5 Bögen die Ihnen <tei:date when="1930-07-09">heute</tei:date> zugehen 1400
        Sch. vorangeschlagen mir ist diese Sache recht unglaublich wieso
          <tei:placeName>Leipzig</tei:placeName> die ganze Arbeit die ja gut noch 2½ mal soviel
        ausmachen wird als bereits fertig und dieses soll ¼ alles Wiener preises ausmachen. Die
          <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>n zeichne ich bereits für Lichtpauseverfahren müsste natürlich
        alles wieder umstellen da ja schon auf Litographie eingearbeitet gewesen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Nun bitte ich sehr geehrter <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Herr
          Professor</tei:rs> die Bögen gut und langsam durchsehen zu wollen es können noch beliebige
        Korrekturen vorgenommen werden, alle Änderungen Fehler u. dgl. bitte mit irgend einem
        Farbstift mit Ausnahme <tei:sic>grünn</tei:sic> und lila gütigst anzuzeichnen und den Bogen
        signieren für die Durchführung der Mängel hafte ich vollauf und ebenso hat die <tei:rs key="entity-005006" type="organization">Druckerei</tei:rs> dann keinen Grund
          Kor<tei:supplied reason="clarity">r</tei:supplied>ekturen anzurechnen da die Matritzen
        fehlerfrei in die <tei:pb n="2"/> Hände der <tei:rs key="entity-005006" type="organization">Druckerei</tei:rs> gelangen – jedenfalls muss aber natürlich die <tei:rs key="entity-005006" type="organization">Druckerei</tei:rs> vor dem drucken auch einen
        Abklatsch einsenden damit dieser mit den korrigierten Bögen verglichen werden kann.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Sobald ich Ihnen dann <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>nmatritzen zur
        Durchsicht einsenden werde werde Ihnen sehr geehrter <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Herr Professor</tei:rs> auch Anleitung zur Korrekturanzeichnung mitteilen
        diese Matritzen sind nicht so heikel und können dort <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Herr Professor</tei:rs> alles einzeichnen jedoch nur mit
          <tei:sic>gewöhnlichen</tei:sic> Bleistift keine Tinte keine Farbstifte auch nicht
        Tintenstifte – aber <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Herr Professor</tei:rs> sind
        doch zur Erholung in <tei:placeName>Galtür</tei:placeName> und nicht zur Arbeit ich werde
        Ihnen sehr geehrter <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Herr Professor</tei:rs> jetzt
        auch Ruhe lassen und erst in ca. <tei:date when="1930-07-23">14 Tagen</tei:date> etwas zur Durchsicht einsenden.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Die <tei:date when="1930-07-09">heute</tei:date> eingesendeten Bögen
        müssen auch nicht sofort durchgesehen werden da ich die retouschen selbst mache und <tei:rs key="entity-005005" type="organization">Piller</tei:rs> mit der Arbeit erledigt ist. </tei:p>
      
      <tei:p rend="first">Hochachtungsvollst mit Handküssen der gnädigen <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Frau Gemahlin</tei:rs></tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">ergebenster</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs key="entity-000894" type="person">Georg
          Tomay</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:p><tei:hi rend="underline">N.S. Bitte nur Abklatsche retournieren. Manuscripte benötige
            nicht mehr diese erhöhen das Porto!</tei:hi></tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#stamp"/>Specialist Firm for Musical Works</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Georg Tomay</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Vienna I, Fichtegasse 1a, Tel. 22-419</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60">
          <tei:placeName><tei:handShift new="#GT"/>Vienna</tei:placeName>,
          <tei:date when="1930-07-09">July 9, 1930</tei:date>
        </tei:dateline>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>Dear Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"><tei:supplied reason="identity">Schenker</tei:supplied></tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
        </tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">I am sending you imprints of the music examples and <tei:supplied reason="clarity">original</tei:supplied> manuscripts. Everything indicated in
        green are things that are missing, which I have found when comparing with the manuscripts. With the
        things indicated in purple pencil, I ask you whether this should be printed. In the
        meantime, a change of plan has been introduced: the music appendix will be printed not in
          <tei:placeName>Vienna</tei:placeName>, but by <tei:rs key="entity-005006" type="organization">Roeder</tei:rs> in <tei:placeName>Leipzig</tei:placeName>. Of the
        imprints that are being sent to you <tei:date when="1930-07-09">today</tei:date>, a single
        copy will be made in <tei:placeName>Vienna</tei:placeName> and, in fact, on transparent
        paper; they will be newly printed in <tei:placeName>Leipzig</tei:placeName> using the
        blueprint process. Apparently, <tei:rs key="entity-005006" type="organization">Roeder</tei:rs> reckons that the entire printing of the music appendix will cost 200
        marks, and <tei:rs key="entity-005005" type="organization">Piller</tei:rs> had suggested
        1400 shillings just for the five large sheets that are being sent to you <tei:date when="1930-07-09">today</tei:date>. I find it
        quite unbelievable that <tei:placeName>Leipzig</tei:placeName> can consider the entire work,
        which is a good 2½ times as extensive, as already finished; and all this should come to a
        quarter of the cost in <tei:placeName>Vienna</tei:placeName>. The
          <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>
        <tei:term>graph</tei:term>s, <tei:supplied reason="clarity">which</tei:supplied> I am
        marking up for the blueprint process, must of course be done again, as they have already
        been worked on for the lithographic process.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Now I ask you, dear <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Professor</tei:rs>, to take your time and look through the large sheets carefully; you
        can make any further corrections that you wish. All changes, mistakes, etc., please be so
        kind as to indicate with any colored pencil, except for green and purple, and to sign the
        sheets. I shall take full responsibility for any shortcomings, and likewise the <tei:rs key="entity-005006" type="organization">printing house</tei:rs> will not have any grounds
        for reckoning on mistakes since the matrices will reach the <tei:pb n="2"/> hands of the
          <tei:rs key="entity-005006" type="organization">printers</tei:rs> free of mistakes – at
        any rate, however, the <tei:rs key="entity-005006" type="organization">printing
          house</tei:rs> will, before printing, also have to send an imprint, so that this can be
        compared with the corrected large sheets.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">As soon as I send you <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> matrices for your
        inspection, <tei:supplied reason="clarity">I</tei:supplied> shall, dear <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Professor</tei:rs>, also send you instructions for
        marking the corrections. These matrices are not so awkward, and <tei:supplied reason="clarity">you</tei:supplied>, <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Professor</tei:rs>, can mark up everything, however only with a normal pencil: no ink, no
        colored pencils, and also no indelible pencils – but, <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Professor</tei:rs>, you are after all in
          <tei:placeName>Galtür</tei:placeName> to rest, and not to work; I shall also leave you
        now, dear <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Professor</tei:rs>, in peace and send
        you something for inspection only about <tei:date when="1930-07-23">two weeks from now</tei:date>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">The sheets that I sent you <tei:date when="1930-07-09">today</tei:date>
        also do not have to be studied immediately, since I shall be doing the retouchings myself
        and <tei:rs key="entity-005005" type="organization">Piller</tei:rs> has finished with his
        work.</tei:p>
      
      <tei:p rend="first">Most respectfully, with cordial greetings to your gracious
        <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Yours most faithfully,</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs key="entity-000894" type="person">Georg
          Tomay</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:p><tei:hi rend="underline">p.s. Please return just the imprints. I no longer need the
            original manuscripts; these will increase your postage costs!</tei:hi></tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>