<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="1102" sdoID="OC-54-74">OC 54/74</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="TPgif" scope="major">Typist "Gi./F" (DMV)</tei:handNote>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="AB" scope="minor">Alfred Böhme's hand (DMV)</tei:handNote>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="stamp" scope="minor">stamp</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>


  <tei:respStmt xml:id="KH">
   <tei:persName>Kirstie Hewlett</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2014</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-10-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-004414">DMV ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-004929">BöhmeA ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>




   <dc:title>Typed letter from Alfred Böhme (DMV) to Schenker, dated April 15, 1926</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1926-04-15T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2014-03-14</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Drei Masken Verlag inform Schenker that the proof-copy of Meisterwerk 1 has been
    sent to Dr. Einstein in Munich for final checking. They confirm that the majority of the music
    examples will appear as an unbound supplement at the end of the book, agree to correct two
    errors in the typesetting, and confirm the appearance of the cover.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Imprimatur; imprimatur; publish; Ausdruck; appendix; Notenbeilage; music appendix;
    music example; Notenbeispiel; supplement; Abzug; double-graph; Doppeltafel; printing error;
    Druckfehler; index; Verzeichnis; cover; Einband; linen cloth; Leinenfarbe</dc:subject>




  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-002627">DMV</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-004930">BöhmeA</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>

     <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>DREI MASKEN VERLAG GES. M.B.H.</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>WIEN I.</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>WALLNERSTRASSE 4</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:lb/>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:byline><tei:handShift new="#TPgif"/>Gi./F</tei:byline>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-60">
     <tei:placeName>Wien</tei:placeName>, den <tei:date when="1926-04-15">15.4.1926.</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
    <tei:address>

     <tei:addrLine>Herrn Professor Dr. Heinrich <tei:hi rend="sperr">Schenker</tei:hi>,</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">
      <tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:hi rend="sperr">Wien</tei:hi> III,</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Keilgasse 8.</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address><tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute>Sehr verehrter Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Professor</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
      this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/8, p. 2935, April 16, 1926: "Vom Verlag
      (Br.): die zweite Korrektur zum zweitenmal an Einstein abgegangen; Vorschlag, die beiden
      großen Klischees einzukleben, die Tafeln zu falzen, Einband in Leinen, zwei Stellen lasse sich
      noch korrigieren." ("From the publisher (letter): the second proof sent off for the second
      time to Einstein; suggestion to paste the two large music examples together, to fold the
      graphs, linen binding, two passages are still to be corrected.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">wir bestätigen Ihre <tei:date when="1926-04-14">gestrige</tei:date>
    Unterredung mit unserem <tei:rs key="entity-004930" type="person">Herrn Direktor Böhme</tei:rs>.
    Zu Ihrer Information teilen wir Ihnen noch mit, dass wir das gesamte Imprimatur des <tei:rs key="entity-001750" type="work">Buches</tei:rs> an unser <tei:placeName>Münchner
     Haus</tei:placeName> nochmals einsenden mussten, da vor dem Ausdruck unbedingt <tei:rs key="entity-000195" type="person">Herr Dr. Einstein</tei:rs> in <tei:rs key="entity-002286" type="place">München</tei:rs> das ganze Buch nochmals durchlesen will. Wir haben auch heute
    noch sofort Ihren Wunsch bezüglich der Notenbeilagen nach <tei:rs key="entity-002286" type="place">München</tei:rs> weitergegeben, in dem Sinne, dass die Notenbeispiele auf den 12
    Seiten nicht in das Buch anschliessend an den Text eingeheftet werden, sondern am Schluss des
    Buches beigelegt, sodass sie jederzeit beim Durchlesen des betreffenden Aufsatzes herausgenommen
    und als Vergleich daneben gelegt werden können.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Die beiden <tei:term>Doppeltafeln</tei:term> würden wir jedoch raten,
    unbedingt einzukleben und zwar an den Stellen, die Sie auf dem Abzug vorgeschrieben haben, denn
    das blosse <tei:sic>Beilagen</tei:sic> würde sicherlich bei vielen Besitzern des Buches <tei:pb n="2"/> den Verlust dieser beiden <tei:term>Tafeln</tei:term> nach sich ziehen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">These are the large foldout graphs for the
     analyses of the two movements from Bach’s solo violin works, in each case marked “Fig. 1.” It
     is not clear why the publishers thought that folded graphs measuring 40 x 24 cm were more
     likely to go astray than those measuring 16 x 24 cm. </tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Betreffend der auf dem separaten Verzeichnis von Ihnen zusammengestellten
    Druckfehler teilen wir Ihnen mit, dass wir auch dieses mit nach <tei:rs key="entity-002286" type="place">München</tei:rs> gesandt haben. Die 2 von Ihnen besonders bezeichneten Fehler auf
    Seite 29 und 153 können natürlich noch im Text ausgebessert werden, da es sich nicht um
    gestochene Teile, sondern lediglich um gesetzte handelt.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Bezüglich des Einbandes für das Buch können wir Ihnen zu Ihrer Beruhigung
    mitteilen, dass der Einband, nicht wie beim Mozart-Jahrbuch angefertigt wird, es kommt vielmehr
    ein Ganzleinenband in heller Leinenfarbe mit Aufdruck in einer dazu passenden Farbe, wobei
    ausdrücklich bemerkt wird, dass nur Titelaufdruck angebracht wird, ohne jede Verzierung in Form
    von Linien, Vignetten usw.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">The simple
     gray-green linen-covered boards of the first <tei:title>Meisterwerk</tei:title> Yearbook give
     only the author’s name and the title of the book on the front cover, the same on the spine (the
     name shortened to “H. Schenker”). Not even the publisher’s name is given.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Wir empfehlen uns</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">mit vorzüglicher Hochachtung</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="stamp"/><tei:rs key="entity-002627" type="organization">DREI MASKEN VERLAG Ges. m. B. H.</tei:rs></tei:signed>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#AB"/><tei:rs key="entity-004930" type="person">Böhme</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>



  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>

     <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>DREI MASKEN VERLAG &amp; Co.</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>VIENNA I</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>WALLNERSTRAßE 4</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:lb/>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:byline><tei:handShift new="#TPgif"/>Gi./F</tei:byline>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-60">
     <tei:placeName>Vienna</tei:placeName>, <tei:date when="1926-04-15">15.4.1926.</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
    <tei:address>

     <tei:addrLine>Professor Dr. Heinrich <tei:hi rend="sperr">Schenker</tei:hi>,</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">
      <tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:hi rend="sperr">Vienna</tei:hi> III,</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Keilgasse 8.</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address><tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute>Revered Professor<tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"><tei:supplied reason="identity">Schenker</tei:supplied></tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">We acknowledge your conversation of <tei:date when="1926-04-14">yesterday</tei:date> with our director, <tei:rs key="entity-004930" type="person">Mr.
     Böhme</tei:rs>. In addition, we inform you that we have had to send the entire <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">imprimatur</tei:hi> of the book to our <tei:placeName>Munich
     house</tei:placeName>, as <tei:rs key="entity-000195" type="person">Dr. Einstein</tei:rs> in
     <tei:rs key="entity-002286" type="place">Munich</tei:rs> insists upon reading through the
    entire book once more before it is published. In accordance with your wishes, we have today also
    forwarded the music appendices to <tei:rs key="entity-002286" type="place">Munich</tei:rs>, on
    the understanding that the music examples on the twelve pages will not be bound into the text
    but will appear as a supplement at the end of the book, so that they can be taken out at any
    time during the reading of the article to which they refer and can be placed next to it for
    comparison.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">However, we would recommend that the two <tei:term>double-graph</tei:term>s
    definitely be bound, and indeed at the points that you have indicated in the copy, for their
    simple placement in the supplement would surely result in the eventual loss of these
    <tei:term>graph</tei:term>s <tei:pb n="2"/> by many owners of the book.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Concerning the printing errors you collected in a separate
    index, we inform you that we have also sent this to <tei:rs key="entity-002286" type="place">Munich</tei:rs>. The two mistakes, on p. 29 and p. 153, to which you have called special
    attention, can of course still be corrected in the text, since these occur not in engraved
    sections but merely in typeset ones.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Regarding the cover for the book, we can reassure you that the cover will not
    be made as for the Mozart-Jahrbuch, but rather as a full linen cloth binding in a bright linen
    colour, with printing in a color that will go well with it, whereby it may be expressly noted
    that only the title will be printed, without any adornment of lines, decorations, or the
     like.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">We remain</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">with kind regards,</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="stamp"/><tei:rs key="entity-002627" type="organization">DREI MASKEN VERLAG &amp; Co.</tei:rs></tei:signed>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#AB"/><tei:rs key="entity-004930" type="person">Böhme</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>


  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>