<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2260" sdoID="OC-54-333-336">OC 54/333-336</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="sole">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>


    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2012-09-26" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-007030">KlenauP ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter (copy) from Schenker to Klenau, dated October 9‒10,
        1923</dc:title>
      <dcterms:created>1923-10-10T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-09-01</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker offers further advice on performing the "Eroica"
        Symphony.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Vortrag; performance; metronomisch; metronomic; Bezeichnung; marking;
        Instrumentalist; Stelle; passage; Genie; genius; Held; hero; Fuge; fugue; Korrekturen;
        corrections; Trauermarsch; funeral march; Publikum; public; audience; Musiker; musician;
        Filmschnelligkeit; film speed</dc:subject>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000443">Paul von Klenau</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="recto"/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#JS"/><tei:hi rend="underline">An <tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000443">Paul v. Klenau</tei:rs></tei:hi> (<tei:date when="1923-10-10">10
            &amp; 9. X. 23</tei:date>)</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000443"
            >Kapellmeister</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
            >Writing of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/6, pp. 2579‒2580:
            September 7, 1923: "An Klenau (Br., kopiert): stelle die Tongebung als Voraussetzung für
            das Zeitmaß voran; erkläre die metronomische Bezeichnung des 1. Satzes für zutreffend;
            sie ist durchführbar auch beim 2. Gedanken u. verursacht an sich noch keine Hast.
            Charakterisiere den Satz im Großen, erwähne einige Einzelheiten, wie die sf, einige
            Vl.-Figuren usw. In Bezug auf den 2. Satz gebe ich zu, daß der Anfang eher <tei:note
              type="editorial" place="inline">eighth-note</tei:note> = 60 vertrüge, doch scheint es,
            daß Beethoven weniger einen Trauermarsch habe malen wollen, als eine Trauer empfunden u.
            gelitten zu haben; die unmittelbare Schmerzempfindung drückt sich z. B. in den Keilen
            bei T. 21 in den weiten Bogen aus. Das originale Zeitmaß trifft in den meisten Partien
            zu, nur gerade für den Anfang nicht – usw." <tei:lb/>("To Klenau (letter, copied): put
            intonation forward as a prerequisite for tempo; declare the metronome indication for the
            first movement appropriate; it works for the second theme as well, and does not cause
            any hurry in and of itself. I characterize the movement overall, I mention a few
            details, such as the sf, several violin figures, etc. With regard to the second
            movement, I admit that the beginning could sustain eighth-note = 60 better, but it
            appears that Beethoven wanted less to compose a funeral march than that he was
            experiencing and suffering grief; the immediate experience of pain is expressed, e.g.,
            in the hairpins at measure 21 in the long slurs. The original tempo is applicable in
            most sections, just not specifically for the beginning – etc."). <tei:lb/>This letter
            copy is preserved in OC File 54 among correspondence with the publisher Drei Masken
            Verlag concerning <tei:title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:title> and
            other correspondence relating to the <tei:title level="m">Fünf
              Urlinie-Tafeln</tei:title>. Within that, it is wrapped in a leaf of the magazine
              <tei:title level="j">Radio Wien</tei:title> dated December 21, 1928, together with the
            proof-sheet of an article on the reconstruction of the Beethoven sonatas. It is
            presented in translation in <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Heinrich Schenker: Selected
                Correspondence</tei:title>, ed. <tei:editor>Ian Bent</tei:editor>, <tei:editor>David
                Bretherton</tei:editor>, and <tei:editor>William Drabkin</tei:editor> (Woodbridge:
              Boydell Press, 2014), p. 242‒44</tei:bibl>. </tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="indent-20">Auch mir ergeht es wie Ihnen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot">This letter responds to <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-12-11_4">OJ 12/11, [4]</tei:ref>.</tei:note> Fahren wir indessen fort, in diese
        Sonne zu schauen, ein Sonnenbrand droht uns nicht, nur Genesung winkt . .</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="indent-20">1.) Aller Vortrag hängt mit der <tei:term>Tongebung</tei:term>
        zusammen; eine dicke, schwülstige, aufgeblasene macht verweilen, eine lüftige schlanke
        fließt, eilt usw. Im ersten Satz der <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001263"
            ><tei:title>III.</tei:title></tei:rs> ist die originale metronomische Bezeichnung
          <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">dotted half-note</tei:note> = 60 gar nicht so
        übel, aber wehe wenn das Vlc. sich gleich festsaugt u. sein <tei:term>Motiv</tei:term> so
        genießt, als sie mit <tei:term>Motiv</tei:term>ende auch die Sinfonie zuende. Es ist nicht
        zu viel gesagt, daß nur das Vlc. über das Wohl u. Wehe des Satzes entscheidet. Aber ‒ hier
        liegt die unüberwindliche Schwierigkeit ‒ wie kann man einen Instrumentalisten<tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> ein Orchester <tei:term>weithörig</tei:term> machen?
        Meines Erachtens ist das <tei:term>Tempo</tei:term> durchzuführen möglich, einschließlich
        sogar der von Ihnen zitierten Stelle<tei:del rend="overstrike">n</tei:del> des <tei:term>2.
          Gedanke</tei:term>ns u. es wäre dazu zu raten. Um sich durchaus hineinzuhelfen, könnte man
        sich übungsweise den <tei:term>Hauptgedanke</tei:term>n in drei
          <tei:term>Viertakter</tei:term>n vorstellen ‒ <tei:hi rend="underline">ein</tei:hi> Schlag
        per <tei:choice>
          <tei:sic>Viertel</tei:sic>
          <tei:corr>Takt</tei:corr>
        </tei:choice> ‒ u. man erhält, vorausgesetzt, daß der Cellist (ungefähr angedeutet) so
        spielt: <tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">blank ‒ no music example
        entered</tei:note><tei:lb/> (was für die Folge entscheidend ist), ein fließendes
          <tei:term>Zeit-</tei:term>
        <tei:pb n="334"/>
        <tei:term>maß</tei:term>, das in die Ferne förmlich selbst lockt. Die
          <tei:term>Tongebung</tei:term>, die ich meine, läßt dann den Eindruck einer Hast nicht
        aufkommen. (Hast entsteht nur, wenn dicke Töne, gleichsam Schmerbauche laufen wollen oder
        gejagt werden.) Alles muß in diesem Satz groß sein, die Heiterkeit weitzügig, schwebend auch
        an den <tei:hi rend="bold italic">ff</tei:hi>-Stellen. Pathos, Düsterkeit, Verhängnis hier
        u. dort muß sozusagen aufsaugbar sein. Ueber allen Wechselfällen steht das weithinblickende
        Auge des Genies, des Helden. Ein Schuß Melancholie, Sentimentalität darf nicht fehlen, das
        gehört zum Genie, dennoch bleibt es heiter! Alles geht in jenes fließende
          <tei:term>Zeitmaß</tei:term> hinein. <tei:hi rend="underline">Keine</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">Hast</tei:hi> also (nur bequem,) bei den Figuren in T. 65ff.
          (<tei:hi rend="bold italic">p</tei:hi>-Schatten), ebensowenig in T. 75ff. Die meisten
          <tei:hi rend="bold italic">sf</tei:hi> ungezwungen ausdrucksvoll, warm (nicht stechend),
        so schon in T. 40, 42, besonders aber in der <tei:term>Durchführung</tei:term>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">bei</tei:hi> den <tei:sic>Bassen</tei:sic> im
          <tei:term>Motiv</tei:term> T. 198ff. Der <tei:term>2. Gedanke</tei:term>, T. 83 ff.,
        leidenschaftlich, dem <tei:hi rend="bold italic">sf</tei:hi> zustrebend, ausgleichend die
        Achtelfigur T. 90. Schwebungen des <tei:term>Zeitmaß</tei:term>es sind also erforderlich u.
        der Dirigent tut gut, auch die einzelnen Viertel eines Taktes an manchen Stellen
        nachzumalen, gleich z.B. T. 14.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="indent-20">2.) Die metronomische Bezeichnung des 2. Satzes: <tei:note
          type="editorial" place="inline">quarter-note</tei:note> = 80 stimmt annähernd in den
          <tei:term>Gruppe</tei:term>n T. 17ff., im maggiore, <tei:pb n="335"/> in der Fuge, ja
        sogar in der <tei:term>Wiederholung</tei:term> T. 173ff. Ich sage annähernd, nur der Anfang
        fügt sich nicht, er braucht <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">aber auch</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">etwa</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">quarter-note</tei:note> = 60. In der revidierten
        Abschrift fand ich in T. 20 über den beiden <tei:hi rend="underline">b</tei:hi><tei:hi
          rend="supralinear">1</tei:hi> der Vl. I gewaltige Keile (staccato-Keile): dieses
        Emporschleudern auch des Viertels <tei:hi rend="underline">b</tei:hi> (freilich nicht kalt
        abwerfend sondern <tei:sic>auslautend</tei:sic>) deutet auf einen wühlenden aktiven Schmerz:
        dazu die weiten Bogen, die unsere Partituren gar nicht mehr kennen (!) <tei:note
          type="editorial" place="inline">cued from lower margin:</tei:note> Soeben schicke ich dem
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-003860">Philharmonischen Verlag</tei:rs>
        Korrekturen zu der schon gedruckten <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001265"
            ><tei:title>V. Sinfonie</tei:title></tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot">The Philharmonischer Verlag, founded in 1923, brought out a
          miniature score of Beethoven’s Fifth Symphony as the first publication in their
          Philharmonia series. Having recently completed his essay on the Fifth Symphony for
            <tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title>, which included a close reading of the
          autograph score and first edition, Schenker was sending them – presumably unsolicited ‒
          corrections for a revised imprint. Schenker’s personal copy of the Philharmonia score, OC
          Miniature Scores No. 6, contains textual corrections on most of its pages.</tei:note> zu,
        Sie würden Ihr Antlitz verhüllen.<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end
          cue</tei:note> Es scheint also, daß <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055"
          >Beethoven</tei:rs> nicht etwa einen Trauer<tei:hi rend="underline">marsch</tei:hi> hat
        malen wollen, sondern Trauer dachte, litt, vor unseren Augen gleichsam, nur in seiner Weise
        weit auch in den Trauerwellen. <tei:hi rend="bold italic">pp</tei:hi>, sotto voce zu Anfang
        scheint das zu bestätigen, da <tei:hi rend="underline">sie</tei:hi> das leichte Fortziehen
        der Welle<tei:del rend="overstrike">n</tei:del> fördern. (Wir freilich mochten in jedem
          <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">32nd-note</tei:note> versinken „ . . verweile
        doch, du bist so schön“.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot"
              ><tei:bibl><tei:author>Goethe</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Faust</tei:title>,
            Part II, line 1,700</tei:bibl>, also quoted elsewhere in Schenker's
          correspondence.</tei:note>) Ich glaube aber, daß wir den Anfang so nicht mehr erreichen,
        wie ihn <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> empfunden haben mochte,
        dagegen von T. 17 ab läßt sich die Trauer auch in seinem Sinn be- <tei:pb n="336"/> wegter
        gestalten. Jedenfalls <tei:hi rend="underline">geht</tei:hi> das maggiore.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="indent-20">3.) Das Scherzo ist schnell, die metronomische Anweisung stimmt. Auch
        das Trio. Es hat ein Fernziel, das <tei:hi rend="bold italic">sf</tei:hi> in T. 70 (des
        Trio!). Keine Hast aber, namentlich nicht in den Achteln (T. 9 usw.), auch nicht bei den
        Hörnern im Trio, die freilich darnach blasen müssen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="indent-20">Aber, aber . . . . <tei:lb/>Wehe Ihnen, wenn Sie mit <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> beethoven'sch kommen wollten. Das
        Publikum, die Musiker vertragen seine Maße nicht. Filmschnelligkeiten, ja, die sind
        willkommen, aber Schnelligkeiten des Geistes (ich meine hier nicht auch die Schnelligkeiten
        des <tei:term>Zeitmaß</tei:term>es) sind ihnen quälend, sie können nicht mit. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="indent-20">Nun ja, es ginge endlos, aber trotz Sonntag muß doch schließen </tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Ihr Sie bestens grüßender</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.
          Sch.</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="recto"/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#JS"/><tei:hi rend="underline">To <tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000443">Paul v. Klenau</tei:rs></tei:hi> (<tei:date when="1923-10-10"
            >October 10 &amp; 9, 1923</tei:date>)</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000443"
            >Maestro</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="indent-20">I feel the same way as you.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> In the meantime, let us journey on, to gaze into this sun; sunburn is no
        threat to us, only recovery beckons . .</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="indent-20">1.) All performance is closely linked to <tei:term>sound
          texture</tei:term>: a thick, turgid, overblown texture makes for lingering, an airy, lithe
        texture flows, hurries, etc. In the first movement of the <tei:rs type="composition"
          key="entity-001263"><tei:title>Third <tei:supplied reason="abbreviation"
              >Symphony</tei:supplied></tei:title></tei:rs> the original metronome marking dotted
        half-note = 60 is really not so bad, but woe betide if the cellos immediately slow up and
        savor their <tei:term>motive</tei:term>, as if the symphony finished at the end of the
          <tei:term>motive</tei:term>. It cannot be said too often that the cellos alone decide the
        weal and woe of the movement. But ‒ and here lies the insurmountable difficulty ‒ how can
          <tei:term>long-range hearing</tei:term> be inculcated into an instrumentalist, an
        orchestra? In my opinion it is possible to sustain the <tei:term>tempo</tei:term>
        throughout, including even the passage that you cite from the <tei:term>second
          subject</tei:term>, and moreover one would be advised to do so. In order to help achieve
        this completely, one could for practice imagine the <tei:term>main subject</tei:term> in
        three four-measure <tei:term>group</tei:term>s ‒ <tei:hi rend="underline">one</tei:hi> beat
        per <tei:choice>
          <tei:sic>quarter</tei:sic>
          <tei:corr>measure</tei:corr>
        </tei:choice> ‒ and, provided that the cellos (approximately indicated) play this:<tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">blank ‒ no music example
        entered</tei:note><tei:lb/> (which is crucial for what follows), and one maintains a flowing
          <tei:term>tempo</tei:term>, <tei:pb n="334"/> which itself verily beckons into the
        distance. The <tei:term>sounding texture</tei:term> that I have in mind guards against an
        impression of haste. (Haste arises only when thick tones, like pot-bellied people, try to
        run or are being chased.) Everything in this movement must be on a large scale, the gaiety
        spacious, even hovering at <tei:hi rend="bold italic">ff</tei:hi> passages. Pathos,
        somberness, calamity here and there must, so to speak, be absorbable. Transcending all the
        ups and downs is the far-seeing eye of the genius, the hero. A touch of melancholy, of
        sentimentality there must be ‒ that <tei:supplied reason="clarity">too</tei:supplied>
        belongs to genius, nevertheless it remains cheerful! Everything proceeds at that flowing
          <tei:term>tempo</tei:term>. <tei:hi rend="underline">No haste</tei:hi>, thus (only
        easy-going) at the figures in mm. 65ff (<tei:hi rend="bold italic">p</tei:hi> shadings),
        just as little in mm. 75ff. Most of the <tei:hi rend="bold italic">sf</tei:hi>
        unconstrainedly expressive, warm (not stabbing), already thus at mm. 40 and 42, but
        especially in the <tei:term>development section</tei:term>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">among</tei:hi> the basses in the <tei:term>motive</tei:term> at mm.
        198ff. The second theme, mm. 83ff, passionate, striving toward the <tei:hi
          rend="bold italic">sf</tei:hi>, equalizing the eighth-note figure m. 90. Fluctuations of
        the <tei:term>tempo</tei:term> are thus called for, and the conductor will do well to bring
        out even the individual quarter-notes of a bar in many passages, even as early as m. 14, for
        example. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="indent-20">2.) The metronome marking of the second movement, quarter-note = 80
        works is approximately right in the <tei:term>group</tei:term>s mm. 17ff in the <tei:hi
          rend="italic">Maggiore</tei:hi>, <tei:pb n="335"/> in the fugue, indeed even in the
          <tei:term>reprise</tei:term> at mm. 173ff. I say approximately: only the opening does not
        conform: it <tei:del rend="overstrike">certainly</tei:del> needs to be <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">about</tei:add> quarter-note = 60. In the revised copy at m. 20,
        I found above the two <tei:hi rend="underline">B<tei:g type="flat"/></tei:hi><tei:hi
          rend="supralinear">1</tei:hi>s in violin I strong wedges (<tei:hi rend="italic"
          >staccato</tei:hi> wedges): this flinging upward of the <tei:hi rend="underline">B<tei:g
            type="flat"/></tei:hi> (certainly not to be thrown off coldly, but vehemently sustained)
        conveys an agitated, active pain, together with long slurs, unknown in our scores these days
        (!) <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">cued from lower margin:</tei:note> At this
        very moment I am sending the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-003860"
          >Philharmonischer Verlag</tei:rs> corrections to the <tei:rs type="composition"
          key="entity-001265"><tei:title>Fifth Symphony</tei:title></tei:rs>, which has already been
          published.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> You would cover your
          face.<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end cue</tei:note> So it seems that <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> was not so much aiming to depict a
        funeral march, as that he was contemplating, <tei:hi rend="underline">suffering</tei:hi>
        sorrow, almost before our very eyes, only after his own manner in broad wellings-up of
        sorrow. The <tei:hi rend="bold italic">pp</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="italic">sotto voce</tei:hi> at the opening seems to confirm that, since these
        markings promote the gentle pulling of the wave<tei:del rend="overstrike">s</tei:del>. (We
        might indeed linger on each 32nd-note ". . tarry a while, thou art so beautiful."<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/>) However, I believe that we can no longer
        replicate the beginning as <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> may
        have felt it. By contrast, from m. 17 onward the spirit of the sorrow can be rendered with
        greater movement. <tei:pb n="336"/> At any rate, the major section <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >moves on faster</tei:hi>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="indent-20">3.) The Scherzo is fast, the metronome marking is just right. The
        Trio, too. It has a distant goal, the <tei:hi rend="bold italic">sf</tei:hi> in m. 70 (of
        the Trio!). But <tei:supplied reason="clarity">there should be</tei:supplied> no rushing,
        especially not in the eighth-notes (m. 9 etc), also not in the French horns in the Trio,
        which must of course play accordingly.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="indent-20">But, but . . . . <tei:lb/>woe to you if you try to play <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> as Beethoven intended. The public
          <tei:supplied reason="clarity">and</tei:supplied> musicians cannot match up to his
        measurements. The speeds of film ‒ yes, these are welcome; but the speeds of the spirit (I
        am not also referring here to the speeds of <tei:term>tempo</tei:term>) ‒ those are
        agonizing for them, they cannot abide them.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="indent-20">But now, this could go on for ever, but ‒ even though it is Sunday ‒ I
        must close.</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Yours, with warmest greetings,</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.
          Sch.</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
