<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3675" sdoID="OC-52-637">OC 52/637</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2025</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated February 5, 1925</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1925-02-05T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-07-19</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel sends Schenker some recent compositions for criticism. -- His wife is
        still unwell, and he spends a great deal of time looking after their sons. -- He
        congratulates Schenker on finding a new publisher to keep the Tonwille series
        going.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1925-02-05">5. II 25.</tei:date>
            <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002757">Kiel</tei:rs>, Feldstr 77<tei:hi
              rend="supralinear">IV</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Professor Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
            >Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for February 9, 2025: “Von Dr.
            Oppel (Br. u. Noten, eingeschrieben!): teilt mit, der Tonwille-Verlag habe auf die
            Einsendung einer Abonnenten-Liste gar nicht reagirt. Einige Bemerkungen zur eingesandten
            Suite u. über das Befinden seiner Frau.” (“From Dr. Oppel (letter and music,
            registered!): informs me that the Tonwille-Verlag did not react at all when they were
            sent a list of subscribers. Several comments about the enclosed suite and about how his
            wife is doing.”). — All paragraph-breaks are editorial, based on line-breaks and
            em-dashes in the original.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>endlich komme ich zu einer Sendung an Sie, samt Brief. Aber ich habe soviel zu tun, u.
        die Hauswirtschaft so ganz allein, wächst mir manchmal bedenklich über den Kopf; abends nach
        Konzerten oder Vorlesung noch an Kochtöpfen u. Spültisch hantieren zu müssen ist kein
        Vergnügen. So bleibt mir zu comp. Arbeit meist nur die Zeit von 10–12 nachts. Um 7 muss ich
        die Jungen wieder wecken und ihnen Frühstück machen; ich habe mir keine Hilfe genommen u.
        mache alles allein, auch kochen. Nur 2x die Woche kommt morgens eine Frau zum Reinmachen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006150">Meiner Frau</tei:rs> muss ich monatlich 300 M
        schicken, u. wir brauchen auch manches, da die <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801"
          >Jungen</tei:rs> wachsen u. ganz <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">illegible
          word</tei:note> futtern. Es geht ihnen gut u. mir auch. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-006150">Meine Frau</tei:rs> machte nur sehr langsame Fortschritte, ich
        fürchte, es wird noch Monate dauern. Ostern fahre ich wahrscheinlich nach <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-005343">Lugano</tei:rs>, um mich von dem wahren Stand der Dinge
        zu unterrichten. Denn es hat gar keinen Zweck, wenn sie vor völliger Genesung zurückkommt.
        Ist <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000921">Frau Vrieslander</tei:rs> noch in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-005343">Lugano</tei:rs>? — </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Vielen Dank für <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001748"><tei:title>Tonwille</tei:title>
          10</tei:rs>. Dem Verlag hatte ich <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">word
          deleted</tei:note> die ganze Liste der Abonnenten geschickt, bis jetzt hat der Gauner aber
        noch <tei:hi rend="underline">in keiner Weise</tei:hi> darauf <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >reagiert</tei:hi>!!! Gut, dass Sie wechseln. Übrigens wundert mich <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000195">Einstein</tei:rs>s Entschluss, denn ich weiss, dass er als geistiger
        Verwalter des <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000712">Riemann</tei:rs>’schen Nachlasses
          (<tei:title>Musikgeschichtliches Lexikon</tei:title>)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot">The editing of Hugo Riemann’s <tei:title level="m"
            >Musik-Lexikon</tei:title> (which originally had the subtitle <tei:title level="m"
            >Theorie und Geschichte der Musik, die Tonkünstler alter und neuer Zeit</tei:title>) was
          taken over by Alfred Einstein in the 1920s.</tei:note> Ihnen <tei:pb n="2"/> nicht ganz
        gewogen ist; umso mehr freut mich seine Objectivität. Veranlassen Sie den <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002627">neuen Verlag</tei:rs>, dass ich 25
          Abonn<tei:supplied reason="abbreviation">enten</tei:supplied>-Einladungen bekomme zum
        Vertreiben. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Von den neuen Komp., die ich seit Nov fertiggestellt, schicke ich hier die beiden
        Klaviersuiten, (es sollten urspr. Etuden werden, gab es aber bald auf). Ausserdem habe ich
        ein paar Lieder, ein Cellostück u. kleine Kl.-sachen geschrieben, u. arbeite jetzt an einer
        4händ. Sonate für <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000287">Glas</tei:rs> u. s. Frau. Auch
        an der 3. Kl.-sonate war ich wieder, lasse sie nun aber einige Zeit noch liegen. Ich würde
        viel lieber a. m. Symph. arbeiten, aber unter diesen häuslichen Umständen habe ich an so
        grosse Arbeit wenig Ruhe u. zu wenig Zeit. Für baldige Rückwendung wäre ich Ihnen sehr
        dankbar. Bei der h-moll Suite Seitenzahl beachten! — </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Am <tei:date when="1925-02-02">2.</tei:date> hörte ich hier wieder einmal die <tei:rs
          type="composition" key="entity-001350">1. Symph. v. Brahms</tei:rs> u. war sehr
        niedergeschlagen u. traurig, wie wenig Ahnung Dirigent u. Orchester von dem Ganzen hatten.
        Schlimm! Man könnte da beinahe allen Mut verlieren. Aber ich habe auch beschlossen, nie
        keine mehr von diesem <tei:sic>Dillet.</tei:sic>
        <tei:unclear reason="reading">vorsitzen</tei:unclear> zu lassen. Da studiert man besser
        zuhause seine Partitur. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Sie haben mir noch immer nicht geschrieben, was <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000326">Halm</tei:rs> wollte von mir damals. Ich las wieder einen neuen
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000104">Bruckner</tei:rs>aufsatz von ihm, sehr
          müssig.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Presumably
              <tei:bibl><tei:author>August Halm</tei:author>, <tei:title level="a">Anton
              Bruckner,</tei:title>
            <tei:title level="j">Die grüne Fahne: Die Monatsschrift für jugendliche
              Weltanschauung</tei:title> i/6 (September 1924), 161–65</tei:bibl>, of which a copy is
          preserved in the Jonas Collection, OJ 34/4.</tei:note> Er kommt von diesem seinem
        Tollpunkt doch nicht los. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs> hatte
        schon schwer Recht, wenn er <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000104">Br.</tei:rs> ablehnte.
        – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun kritisieren Sie feste, ich bin immer lernbegierig.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Alles Gute u. die herzlichsten Grüsse</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Ihnen beiden</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">von Ihrem treuen</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1925-02-05">February 5,
              1925</tei:date>, <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002757">Kiel</tei:rs>, Feldstrasse
            77/4</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor
            Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>I have finally got round to sending you something, together with a letter. But I have
        so much to do, and taking care of the household entirely on my own becomes a cause for
        concern. In the evening, after a concert or lecture, to be obliged to busy myself in the
        kitchen or at the games table is no pleasure. And so the time available for compositional
        activity is restricted mainly to between 10 and 12 o’clock at night. At 7 o’clock I must
        wake the boys again and make them breakfast; I have not taken on any help and do everything
        on my own, even cooking. A lady comes to clean, but only twice a week in the
        morning.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I must send <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006150">my wife</tei:rs> 300 marks a
        month; and we also need a lot, as the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801"
          >boys</tei:rs> are growing and consuming food <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"
          >illegible word</tei:note>. They are well, and so am I. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-006150">My wife</tei:rs> is making only very slow progress; I fear that it
        will last months. I shall probably go to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-005343"
          >Lugano</tei:rs> at Easter, to learn the true state of things. For there is no point at
        all in returning until she has recovered completely. Is <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000921">Mrs. Vrieslander</tei:rs> still in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-005343">Lugano</tei:rs>? –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Many thanks for <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001748"><tei:title level="j"
            >Tonwille</tei:title> 10</tei:rs>. I had sent the publisher[entity-002408] the entire
        list of subscribers, but until now the scoundrel has <tei:hi rend="underline">not reacted in
          any way</tei:hi>!!! It is good that you are changing <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
          >publishing houses</tei:supplied>. Moreover, I am surprised by <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000195">Einstein</tei:rs>’s decision; for I know that, as the intellectual
        custodian of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000712">Riemann</tei:rs>’s estate (his
          <tei:title level="m">Music-Historical Lexicon</tei:title>),<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/>
        <tei:pb n="2"/> he is not quite favorably disposed towards you; his objectivity pleases me
        all the more. Please inform the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002627">new
          publisher</tei:rs> that I shall receive twenty-five invitations from subscribers to
        distribute. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Of the new compositions which I have completed since November, I am here sending you
        the two piano suites. (These were originally supposed to be études, but I quickly gave up
        that idea.) In addition, I have written a few songs, a piece for cello, and some small piano
        pieces, and I am currently working on a four-hand sonata for <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000287">Glas</tei:rs> and his wife. I also resumed work on the Third Piano
        Sonata but am leaving it for a while longer. I would much prefer to be working on my
        symphony, but under these domestic circumstances I have little peace and too little time for
        such a large piece of work. I would be most grateful for a quick reply from you. Please note
        the number of pages in the B minor suite! –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>On the <tei:date when="1925-02-02">2nd</tei:date>, I heard <tei:rs type="composition"
          key="entity-001350">Brahms’s First Symphony</tei:rs> once again and was very depressed and
        sad to hear how little the conductor and orchestra understand of the whole work. Bad! One
        could almost lose one’s entire spirit. But I have also decided not to let such dilettantism
        take hold of me; it would be better to study the score at home. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>You have still not told me what <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000326">Halm</tei:rs>
        wanted from me some time ago. I recently read a new article on <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000104">Bruckner</tei:rs> by him, quite pointless.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> He will not get beyond this point of madness.
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs> was, after all, right to reject
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000104">Bruckner</tei:rs>. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Now, criticize me severely, I am always keen to learn.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>All good wishes, and most cordial greetings</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">to the two of you </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">from your faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
