<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="1291" sdoID="OC-50-14">OC 50/14</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPeb" scope="major">Typist (Elsa Bienenfeld)</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="EB" scope="minor">Elsa Bienenfeld's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="ME">
      <tei:persName>Martin Eybl</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="GC">
      <tei:persName>Geoffrey A. Chew</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2014</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2011-03-05" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-005503">BienenfeldE ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
      <dc:title>Typewritten letter from Elsa Bienenfeld to Schenker, dated July 15, 1931</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1931-07-15T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2014-11-03</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Bienenfeld explains her disagreement with Schenker’s acceptance in an article
        of a Mozart letter of questionable authenticity, and inquires whether in the event of a
        negative judgment he still wishes there to be a review. </dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Heft; issue; Brief; letter; Fälschung; forgery; Ueberraschung; surprise; Inhalt;
        content; Tonfall; accent; Psychologisieren; psychologizing; selbstgerechten Bespielgelung;
        narcissism; Stilkopie; pastiche style; Schaffensnatur; creative nature; Kritik; criticism;
        Annahme; acceptance; Autorität; authority; Genie-Verehrung; veneration of genius;
        Besprechung; review</dc:subject>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000072">Elsa Bienenfeld</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">
      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:handShift new="#TPeb"/><tei:date when="1931-07-15">15.
            VII. 31.</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Hochverehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Professor</tei:rs>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt
            of this letter is not recorded in Schenker's diary. Schenker wrote to Bienenfeld as
            recorded at OJ 4/4, p. 3635, July 17, 1931: "An Dr. Bienenfeld (Br.): ganz nach ihrem
            Ermessen ‒ ich wollte nur den Glauben <tei:add place="interlinear-above">auch nicht
              meinen Mitteln</tei:add> stützen (!?). ("To Dr. Bienenfeld (letter): entirely at your
            discretion ‒ I only wanted to uphold my belief <tei:add place="interlinear-above">not
              also my means</tei:add>(!?).").</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p><tei:sic>das</tei:sic>
        <tei:rs key="entity-003014" type="journal"
          ><tei:title>Kunstwart</tei:title></tei:rs>-Heft<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker had evidently sent his article,
              <tei:bibl><tei:title level="a">Ein verschollener Brief von Mozart und das Geheimnis
              seines Schaffens,</tei:title>
            <tei:title level="j">Der Kunstwart</tei:title>, 44 (July 1931), 660–66</tei:bibl>, in
          the hope of a review in the <tei:title level="j">Neues Wiener Journal</tei:title>, of
          which Bienenfeld was the music correspondent. He likewise had a copy of his article sent
          to Felix von Cube: see letter of July 30, 1931, OJ 5/7a, [38]. A short anonymous reaction
          to Schenker’s article appeared in the <tei:title level="j">National-Zeitung</tei:title>,
          July 30, 1931, under the heading <tei:title level="a">Musikalisches</tei:title> (preserved
          in Schenker's scrapbook at OC 2/p. 84).</tei:note> habe ich erhalten, ich danke Ihnen
        dafür und mehr noch für Ihre persönlichen Zeilen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot">The letter from Schenker appears not to survive.</tei:note>
        die ich als hohe Auszeichnung betrachte. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>In der Frage des Briefes<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">The
          letter, dating from 1790, was first published under Mozart's name in the <tei:title
            level="j">Allgemeine Musikalische Zeitung</tei:title> of August 23, 1815. The source is
          regarded today as at least partly spurious: see <tei:bibl><tei:editor>Ulrich
              Konrad</tei:editor>, ed., <tei:title level="m">Mozart: Briefe und Aufzeichnungen,
              Gesamtausgabe</tei:title>, enlarged edition (Kassel: Bärenreiter and Munich: Deutscher
            Taschenbuch Verlag, 2005), IV, pp. 527–31 (text); VI, pp. 673–75
          (commentary</tei:bibl>). Also a letter from Alfred Einstein to Schenker, July 19, 1931, OC
          50/15, confirms the misgivings of the musicological community as to the authenticity of
          the document.</tei:note> kann ich mich nicht anschliessen. Ich kenne gerade diesen Brief
        seit langem und habe, als ich ihn das erstemal las, sofort das sehr bestimmte, ungute Gefühl
        einer Fälschung gehabt. Erst viel später fand ich zu meiner Ueberraschung dies auch von
          Jahn<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Otto
              Jahn</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">W. A. Mozart</tei:title>, 4 vols. (Leipzig:
            Breitkopf &amp; Härtel, 1856–9), vol. 3, pp. 496–505</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> bestätigt.
        Vom Inhalt, (der <tei:rs key="entity-000612" type="person">Mozart</tei:rs>s Art zu
          <tei:term>komponieren</tei:term> sehr voll und mit wahrem Verstand kennzeichnet) <tei:del
          rend="overstrike">abgesehen</tei:del> zunächst abgesehen: es ist nicht der Ton <tei:rs
          key="entity-000612" type="person">Mozart</tei:rs>’s, der aus diesem Briefe klingt. Ich
        meine damit den Tonfall, die Art, die Worte zu setzen und zu wählen. Nirgends finde ich
        unter sämmtlichen Briefen <tei:rs key="entity-000612" type="person">Mozart</tei:rs>s ein
        Gegenstück zu diesem Psychologisieren, zu diesen „Sich-Ueber-sich-selbst-Rechenschaft geben“
        und zu dieser selbstgerechten Bespielgelung<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial"
          place="foot">"Bespielgelung", <tei:hi rend="italic">recte</tei:hi>
          "Bespiegelung".</tei:note>. Der Brief erinnert mich sehr an die kürzlich erschienene
          „<tei:title>Kleine Chronik der <tei:rs key="entity-000023" type="person">Anna Magdalena
            Bach</tei:rs></tei:title>“ und deren gezierte, obschon virtuose Stilkopie<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Esther
              Meynell</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Die kleine Chronik der Anna Magdalena
              Bach</tei:title> (Leipzig: Koehler &amp; Amelang, 1930</tei:bibl>).</tei:note>; nur
        ist es freilich viel merkwürdiger im Falle <tei:rs key="entity-000612" type="person"
          >Mozart</tei:rs>, dass schon um so viel früher von dritter Seite ein Bild seiner
        Schaffensnatur gemalt wurde, wie wir sie heute erkennen. Die feine Kritik und die richtige
        Beleuchtung, die diesem Brief als Zeitzeugnis immerhin Wert gibt, könnte Ihre Annahme
        bekräftigen; dennoch kann ich aus sprachlichen, aus stilistischen, aus psychologischen
        Gründen mich nicht für überzeugt er- <tei:pb n="2"/> klären und muss, selbst gegen eine
        Autorität wie die Ihre, den Vorschlag, ihn für einen echten <tei:rs key="entity-000612"
          type="person">Mozart</tei:rs>-Brief zu halten, ablehnen. Ich halte gerade dieses Dokument
        eher für eine Schädigung, besonders im Hinblick auf Ihre herrliche Theorie der
        Genie-Verehrung. </tei:p>


      <tei:p>Da ich Ihnen, hochverehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
          >Professor</tei:rs>, nicht gerne öffentlich widersprechen möchte und aus diesem Grunde
        lieber von einer Besprechung absehe, frage ich nun zuerst bei Ihnen an, ob Ihnen auch bei
        entgegengesetzter Anschauung mit einer Besprechung gedient wäre. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Stets in grosser Verehrung Ihre sehr ergebene</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs key="entity-000072" type="person">Elsa
            Bienenfeld</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p>Verzeihen Sie, hochverehrter Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"
            >Professor</tei:rs>, dass ich meiner unleserlichen Schrift wegen mit der Maschine
          schreibe! </tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">
      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:handShift new="#TPeb"/><tei:date when="1931-07-15">July
            15, 1931</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Highly revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Professor</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>I have received the issue of <tei:rs key="entity-003014" type="journal"><tei:title
            level="j">Der Kunstwart</tei:title></tei:rs>:<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> thank you for it, and thank you even more for your personal
          note,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> which I regard as a high
        honour.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>As for the letter,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> I cannot agree with
        you. I have been familiar with this very letter for a long time, and had the very definite,
        uneasy impression of a forgery the first time I read it. It was only much later that I
        discovered to my surprise that Jahn<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> had
        expressed the same opinion. If one <tei:del rend="overstrike">ignores</tei:del> first of all
        ignores the content (which characterizes <tei:rs key="entity-000612" type="person"
          >Mozart</tei:rs>'s manner of <tei:term>composing</tei:term> very fully and with genuine
        understanding), it is not <tei:rs key="entity-000612" type="person">Mozart</tei:rs>'s style
        that catches the ear in this letter. By this I mean the "accent"—the way in which the words
        are chosen and assembled. Nowhere in any of <tei:rs key="entity-000612" type="person"
          >Mozart</tei:rs>'s letters do I find a counterpart to this psychologizing, to this
        "objective giving of an account of oneself" and to this self-righteous narcissism.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> The letter reminds me strongly of the
          "<tei:title>Little Chronicle of <tei:rs key="entity-000023" type="person">Anna Magdalena
            Bach</tei:rs></tei:title>" that appeared recently, and its affected (though clever)
        pastiche style;<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> but it is certainly much
        more remarkable in the case of <tei:rs key="entity-000612" type="person">Mozart</tei:rs>,
        that at such an early date the image of his creative nature that we recognize today should
        already be obliquely painted. The penetrating criticism, and the genuine illumination, which
        admittedly confer value on this letter as a contemporary document, could support your
        acceptance of it, but on linguistic, stylistic and psychological grounds I cannot declare
        myself convinced <tei:pb n="2"/> and ‒ even in the face of an authority like yours ‒ must
        disagree with the suggestion that it should be regarded as a genuine <tei:rs
          key="entity-000612" type="person">Mozart</tei:rs> letter. I regard this very document
        rather as prejudicial, particularly in relation to your magnificent theory of the veneration
        of genius. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Since I do not wish, dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor</tei:rs>,
        to contradict you in public, and on these grounds would rather avoid a review, I am first
        asking you whether a review would be of use to you even from a hostile standpoint.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Ever with great admiration, yours very truly,</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs key="entity-000072" type="person">Elsa
            Bienenfeld</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p>Excuse me, dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor</tei:rs>, that I
          am using a typewriter on account of my illegible handwriting.</tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
