<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="8" sdoID="OC-52-205">OC 52/205</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="TPw" scope="minor">typist "W"</tei:handNote>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="EH" scope="minor">Emil Hertzka's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2009</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2009</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
   <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
   <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-02-07" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">
  <!-- 
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2009.
 -->

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <dcterms:isPartOf>Hertzka ~ HSchenker</dcterms:isPartOf>
   <dcterms:isPartOf>UE ~ H+JSchenker</dcterms:isPartOf>
   <dcterms:isPartOf>UE ~ HSchenker</dcterms:isPartOf>
   <dc:title>Typed letter from Hertzka (UE) to Schenker, dated April 10, 1918</dc:title>
   <dc:type>Letter</dc:type>
   <dcterms:created>1918-04-10T12:00:00</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-03-10</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Hertzka returns the Bekker review with thanks, and reflects on Schenker's remarks
    concerning Urtext editions; he encloses the requested copy of the Gazette de Lausanne. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven; The Last Five Sonatas of Beethoven; Op. 111;
    Frankfurter Zeitung; review; Gazette de Lausanne </dc:subject>
   <!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter -->
   <marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">Universal Edition</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">Emil Hertzka</marcrel:correspondent>
   <!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter -->
   <marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">Heinrich Schenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine>
      <tei:supplied reason="format">printed UE letterhead</tei:supplied>
     </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>Wien I, Karlsplatz 6</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:byline>
     <tei:persName type="typist">W</tei:persName>
    </tei:byline>

    <tei:dateline rend="indent-50">
     <tei:placeName>Wien </tei:placeName>
     <tei:handShift new="#TPw"/>
     <tei:date when="1918-04-10">10. April 1918.</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>

    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine>
      <tei:persName rend="indent-20">Wohlgeboren Herrn Prof. Dr. Heinrich <tei:hi rend="sperr">Schenker</tei:hi></tei:persName>
     </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">
      <tei:hi rend="underline sperr">Wien</tei:hi>
     </tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>

    <tei:salute>Sehr geehrter Herr
    <tei:persName>Professor</tei:persName><!-- Heinrich Schenker -->!</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Besten<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
     this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/10, pp. 873–74 : April 12, 1918: "Von
     Hertzka (Br.): dankt für den Hinweis auf Bekkers Notiz, die er schon kannte, fügt hinzu, daß
     die Schwierigkeit bei den <tei:term>Urtextausgaben</tei:term> in Hinblick auf den Durchschnitt
     der Lehrer unüberwindlich sei; legt das Blatt aus Lausanne bei: ein politischer Leitartikel,
     gezeichnet <tei:persName>Maurice Kufferath</tei:persName>, der einige Stellen aus op. 111 zum
     Gegenstand einer symptomatischen Betrachtung macht. Zitiert die Stellen bald in Uebersetzung,
     bald sogar sowohl im Original als in Uebersetzung, damit man ihn ja nicht einer Fälschung
     verdächtige u. dennoch begeht er eine, dort wo er statt von einer schallenden Ohrfeige an
     Amerika von einer „mit Recht verabreichten“ spricht. Schließlich mündet der Artikel in eine
     nachdrückliche Mahnung, vor dem germanischen Sophism, vor dem deutschen Buch auf der Hut zu
     bleiben. Von dem rein musikalischen Teil spricht er nur so weit, als er zugibt, die Ausgabe
     wäre unschätzbar, wenn nicht . . Auf die Erläuterungen geht er nicht weiter sachlich ein.
     ("From Hertzka (letter): thanks for pointing out Bekker's note, which he already knew, adds
     that the problem of Urtext editions with regard to the average teacher cannot be overcome;
     attaches the paper from Lausanne: a political leading article signed by Maurice Kufferath, who
     takes a number of passages from Opus 111 as the subject matter of a symptomatic observation.
     Cites the passages sometimes in translation, sometimes even in both the original and in
     translation so that no one can suspect him of falsification and yet that is precisely what he
     does, where instead of referring to a real slap in the face for America speaks of one "rightly
     doled out." In the end the article turns into an emphatic admonition to be wary of the Germanic
     sophism and the German book. Concerning the purely musical part he only goes so far as to admit
     that the edition would be invaluable if only . . Beyond that he does not go substantively into
     the commentary.").<!-- XR -->
    </tei:note> Dank für die Einsendung der Notiz von
     <tei:persName>Bekker</tei:persName><!-- profile -->,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker had sent Hertzka Bekker's review with WSLB 297 : April
     9, 1918. </tei:note> die ich schon vorher mit Interesse gelesen habe. – Ihre Bemerkung, dass
    mit den <tei:term>Urtextausgaben</tei:term> die französische Lehrer noch weniger als die
    deutschen etwas Rechtes anzufangen wissen werden, erhellt ja die ganze Schwierigkeit der Frage
     auf<tei:add place="inline">'s</tei:add> deutlichste. Bearbeitete<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">"Bearbeitete" (with heavy editorial intervention) underlined by
     Schenker, also "Urtextausgaben" and "derzeit" (at the present time). Literally, the adjective
     "bearbeitet" means "worked on." In the next sentence, Hertzka uses the noun "Bearbeitungen,"
     which in the musical context usually means "arrangements," but here has been translated more
     freely. </tei:note> Ausgaben sind in den meisten Fällen schlecht,
    <tei:term>Urtextausgaben</tei:term> in den meisten Fällen unverkäuflich; derzeit wenigstens. Sie
    glauben doch nicht, dass ein Verleger für Bearbeitungen Geld zahlen würde, wenn er auch die
     <tei:term>Urtextausgabe</tei:term> ebenso gut oder besser verkaufen könnte? Der Weg den Sie
    selbst vorschlagen: Eine ordentliche <tei:term>Originalausgabe</tei:term> mit wenigen
    entscheidenden <tei:term>Erläuterungen</tei:term>*<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">The typist has inserted an asterisk here, which cues to the postscript at the foot
     of the page. The phrase from the beginning of the sentence is quoted direct from WSLB 297.
    </tei:note> wird auch nicht genügen, denn der Durchschnittslehrer und das ist bekanntlich die
    überwältigende Mehrzahl, verlangt unbedingt bei Studienwerken Ausgaben mit
    <tei:term>Fingersatz</tei:term>, reichlichen <tei:term>Vortragszeichen</tei:term>,
     <tei:term>Phrasierungen</tei:term> u. dgl. mehr. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer rend="indent-20">
    <tei:salute>Mit verbindlichen Grüssen</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Ihr in Verehrung ergebener</tei:salute>
    <tei:handShift new="#EH"/>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-20">Hertzka</tei:signed>

   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p><tei:supplied reason="clarity">added, on a different typewriter:</tei:supplied>*
      <tei:handShift new="#TPw"/>P.S. Mitfolgend die <tei:title>Gazette de
      Lausanne</tei:title><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker first
      asked about this on March 3 :WSLB 295, and this is Hertzka's response. No clipping is
      preserved in Schenker's papers, but his diary entry (OJ 2/10, pp. 873–74 : April 12, 1918)
      summarizes it: "a political leading article signed by <tei:persName>Maurice
      Kufferath</tei:persName>, who takes a number of passages from <tei:title level="m">Opus
      111</tei:title> as the subject matter of a symptomatic observation. Cites the passages
      sometimes in translation, sometimes even in both the original and in translation so that no
      one can suspect him of falsification and yet that is precisely what he does, where instead of
      referring to a real slap in the face for America he speaks of one "rightly doled out." In the
      end the article turns into an emphatic admonition to be wary of the Germanic sophism and the
      German book. Concerning the purely musical part he only goes so far as to admit that the
      edition would be invaluable if only . . Beyond that he does not go substantively into the
      commentary." <!-- XR -->
     </tei:note> die wir uns nach Kenntnisnahme zurückerbitten.</tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>
  </tei:div>

  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine>
      <tei:supplied reason="format">printed UE letterhead</tei:supplied>
     </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>Vienna I, Karlsplatz 6</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:byline>
     <tei:persName type="typist">W</tei:persName>
    </tei:byline>

    <tei:dateline rend="indent-50">
     <tei:placeName>Vienna, </tei:placeName>
     <tei:handShift new="#TPw"/>
     <tei:date when="1918-04-10">April 10, 1918</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>

    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-20">
      <tei:persName>Prof. Heinrich Schenker, Esq.,</tei:persName>
     </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">
      <tei:hi rend="underline">Vienna</tei:hi>
     </tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>

    <tei:salute>Greatly honored
    <tei:persName>Professor</tei:persName><!-- Heinrich Schenker -->,</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first"> Many<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1" type="footnote"/> thanks for sending the
    review by <tei:persName>Bekker</tei:persName><!-- profile -->,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2" type="footnote"/> which I had already read with interest. — Your remark that French teachers
    will have even less idea than the German ones how to begin to make sense of the <tei:term>Urtext
     editions</tei:term> casts the clearest possible light on the whole difficulty of the matter.
    Editions with heavy editorial intervention<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3" type="footnote"/> are in
    most cases bad, <tei:term>Urtext editions</tei:term> in most cases unsaleable, least of all at
    the present time. You really do not believe that a publisher would pay money for
     <tei:term>performing editions</tei:term> when he could buy <tei:term>Urtext editions</tei:term>
    every bit as good or better? Nor will the course of action that you yourself suggest, "a
    straighforward original edition with a few decisive <tei:term>elucidations</tei:term>,"*<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4" type="footnote"/> suffice; for, where works for study by pupils are
    concerned, the average teacher—and everybody knows they are the overwhelming majority—insist on
    editions with <tei:term>fingering</tei:term>, lots of <tei:term>performance
    indications</tei:term>, <tei:term>phrase markings</tei:term> and suchlike. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer rend="indent-20">
    <tei:salute>With sincere greetings,</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="intend-10">Yours truly, in admiration,</tei:salute>
    <tei:handShift new="#EH"/>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-20">Hertzka</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p><tei:supplied reason="clarity">added, on a different typewriter:</tei:supplied>*
      <tei:handShift new="#TPw"/>P.S. Enclosed is the <tei:title>
      <tei:hi rend="italic">Gazette de Lausanne</tei:hi>
     </tei:title>;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5" type="footnote"/> which we ask to be returned to us
     after perusal. </tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>


  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>