<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="890" sdoID="OC-54-20-22">OC 54/20-22</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="major">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="minor">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="KH">
      <tei:persName>Kirstie Hewlett</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2012</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2011-10-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>


  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-004414">DMV ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Draft of a letter from Schenker to Drei Masken Verlag, dated February 7,
        1925</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1925-02-07T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2013-09-10</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker agrees to the terms of a contract outlined by Drei Masken Verlag. He
        requests that Fraktur typeface be used in the printing of his Yearbook, and he also needs to
        know the likely dimensions of the book (in words per page) so that he can plan its contents
        accordingly. He ends with a diatribe against Emil Hertzka at Universal
        Edition.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Abrechnung; statement of account; Ablieferung; delivery; Manuscript; Auflage;
        print-run; Format; Aufsatz; article; essay; Vermischtes; Miscellanea; Plan; Satz; setting;
        Fraktur; Absatz; paragraph; Buchhaltung; book-keeping department</dc:subject>
    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-002627">DMV</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:note type="editorial" place="pre-text">This draft, in Jeanette Schenker's hand, bears
        corrections and re-orderings in Heinrich Schenker's hand too numerous and complex to convey;
        in the present transcription and translation, only the final rescension is given, without
        indication of changes of hand.</tei:note>
      <tei:lb/>

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:hi rend="underline">ab <tei:date when="1925-02-07">7.II/25</tei:date></tei:hi><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/7, p. 2781, February 7,
            1925: An den DMV (Br.): erkläre mich mit den Vorschlägen einverstanden, bitte um den
            Vertragsentwurf; nach dem Ausweis der U.-E.-Buchhaltung ist die Zahl 800 überschritten,
            übrigens habe gegenwärtig der Anwalt das Wort in Sachen der Rechnung." ("To Drei Masken
            Verlag (letter): express my agreement with the proposals, ask for the draft contract;
            according to the information provided by the UE book-keeping department, there are more
            than 800, incidentally the attorney currently has the say with regard to the statement
            of account.").</tei:note> als Antwort auf B<tei:supplied reason="abbreviation">rie</tei:supplied>f<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">= OC
            54/19. </tei:note></tei:dateline><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">no salutation</tei:note><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Auch mit den in Ihrem gesch. Schreiben <tei:hi rend="underline">vom
            <tei:date when="1925-02-03">3. II. 25</tei:date></tei:hi> gemachten Vorschlägen erkläre
        ich mich einverstanden. Setzen wir also fest die vierteljährige Abrechnung u. die Hälfte des
        Vorschusses bei Ablieferung des Manuscriptes. Doch bitte ich Sie im Vertrag auch noch die
        Höhe der Auflage zu nennen, damit ich weiß, wohin die Reise geht.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Für meine Arbeit ist jetzt vor allem wichtig, das Format des Buches kennen
        zu lernen, das Verhältnis des Manuscript<tei:supplied reason="syntax">s</tei:supplied> zur
        Druckseite. Wie alle Hefte des „<tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title>Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>“ muß ich auch das <tei:rs key="entity-001749" type="work"><tei:title>Jahrbuch</tei:title></tei:rs> als ein Ganzes halten, das vom ersten
        Aufsatz bis in das Vermischte hinein nach auf einem festen Plan abgestimmt ist. <tei:pb n="2"/> Ich muß also vermeiden, daß ich, in Unkenntnis des Formates, etwas beilege, was
        dann, obwohl zum Ganzen gehörig, den verabredeten Umfang überschreiten würde. Deshalb werde
        ich ein paar Manuscriptblätter einsenden, damit ich aus deren Satz – an der Fraktur will ich
        festhalten – mir ein Bild von diesem Verhältnis machen kann.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Die oben berührte Frage nach der Höhe der Auflage bringt mir den 2. Absatz
        Ihres gesch. Schreibens vom <tei:date when="1925-01-20">20. I. 25</tei:date><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">OC 54/12.</tei:note> in Erinnerung.
          <tei:pb n="3"/> Vielleicht ist auch Ihnen irgendwie dienlich zu erfahren, daß die
        Buchhaltung der <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">U.-E.</tei:rs> in ihren
        letzten Ausweisen die Höhe von 800 Exemplaren per Auflage eines Heftes <tei:hi rend="underline">überschritten</tei:hi> hat. So paradox es klingt, die Unaufrichtigkeit
        der <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">U.-E.</tei:rs> Buchhaltung ist mir hier
        maßgebender als Ihr Gewährsmann. Endlich sei Ihnen mitgeteilt, daß mir der letzter Ausweis
        willkommenen Anlaß gegeben hat, offiziell die Hilfe eines Anwalts in Anspruch zu nehmen.
        Sollte Dir. <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">H.</tei:rs> seine Abrechnung nicht
        richtigstellen wollen (bisher fand er das Richtigstellen noch immer für vernünftiger), so
        würde ich den Richter sprechen lassen, – auch in anderen Fragen des „<tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title>Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>.“</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich bitte also um Zusendung eines Vortragsentwurfes.</tei:p>

      <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:date when="1925-02-07">7. II.
        1925</tei:date></tei:dateline>


      <tei:closer><tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">no valediction or signature</tei:note>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:hi rend="underline">sent <tei:date when="1925-02-07">February 7,
              1925</tei:date></tei:hi><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> in reply to
            letter<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:dateline><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">no salutation</tei:note><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">With the recommendations made in your letter <tei:hi rend="underline">of
            <tei:date when="1925-02-03">February 3, 1925</tei:date></tei:hi>, I am also in
        agreement. Let us then agree: quarterly account, and half of the advance upon despatch of
        the manuscript. But I would ask you to specify the extent of the print-run in the contract,
        so that I know where things are heading.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">For my work, it is now of paramount importance to know the format of the
        book, the relationship between the manuscript and the printed page. As with all issues of
          <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Der
          Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>, I must conceive the <tei:rs key="entity-001749" type="work"><tei:title>Yearbook</tei:title></tei:rs> as a whole, which is worked out according to a
        plan, from the first essay right up to the "Miscellanea." <tei:pb n="2"/> I must avoid
        adding, in ignorance of the format, something that would overstep the agreed size, even
        though it belonged to the whole. For this reason I shall send you a few manuscript leaves,
        from the way in which they are set – I shall insist upon <tei:hi rend="italic">Fraktur</tei:hi> typeface – I can get an idea of this relationship.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">The question I broached above, concerning the size of the print-run,
        reminds me of the second paragraph of your kind letter of <tei:date when="1925-01-20">January 20, 1925</tei:date>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/>
        <tei:pb n="3"/> Perhaps it will be useful in some way to you, too, to learn that the
        book-keeping department of <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">Universal
          Edition</tei:rs>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">exceeded</tei:hi> the level of 800 copies in their most recent
        statements. As paradoxical as it may sound, the insincerity of <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">Universal Edition</tei:rs>'s book-keeping department is more reliable
        than the source of your information. In the end, let me say that the last statement has
        given me the welcome occasion to officially engage the services of an attorney. Should
        Director <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> be unwilling to rectify
        his accounts (up to now, he still found that rectification was always more sensible), then I
        shall let the judge speak – even in other matters concerning <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I ask you, then, to send a draft contract.</tei:p>

      <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:date when="1925-02-07">February 7,
        1925</tei:date><tei:lb/></tei:dateline>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">no valediction or signature</tei:note>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>