<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3128" sdoID="OC-54-315">OC 54/315</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPoed" scope="major">Otto Erich Deutsch typist</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="OED" scope="minor">Otto Erich Deutsch's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2023</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IDB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2015-09-18" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002726">DeutschOE ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002712">DeutschOE ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002727">DeutschOE+H ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Typewritten letter from Deutsch to Schenker, dated July 30, 1930</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1930-07-30T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2023-04-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Deutsch makes further reports on the anticipated costs of the third
        Meisterwerk yearbook. -- He has come across an arrangement of Beethoven’s Op. 74 Quartet as
        a symphony and found some important early editions of the Op. 22 Sonata. -- He would like
        Schenker to meet his friend [Leopold] Liegler, whose theories about literature resonate with
        the concept of Urlinie.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000164">DeutschOE</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>PROF. OTTO ERICH DEUTSCH</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">WIEN II.</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Böcklinstraße 26</tei:addrLine>

        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/><tei:date when="1930-07-30">30.
            Juli 30</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Sehr verehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Doktor</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for August 1, 1930: “von Deutsch (Br.): die
            erste sozusagen halbe Erwiderung auf meinen langen Brief, dazu Beilagen: über Benz’ 2.
            Aufl. u. ein Aufsatz von Benz. D. macht mich auf einen Erstdruck von op. 22 aufmerksam;
            möchte für seinen Bruder einen Lehrer aus meiner Schule.” (“from Deutsch (letter): the
            first half-reply, so to speak, to my long letter, together with two inclosures:
            concerning Benz's second edition, and an article by Benz. Deutsch alerts me to a first
            edition of Op. 22; he would like a teacher from my school, for his
          brother.”)</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ihren schönen und ausführlichen Brief vom 20.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot">= <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="WSLB-Hds-191-565"
            >WSLB-Hds 191.565</tei:ref>, from Schenker to Deutsch, July 20, 1930.</tei:note> werde
        ich leider nur kurz beantworten können. Ich bin doch geplagt hier. Und morgen fahre ich auf
        vier Tage zu den Meinen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Zunächst möchte ich einiges vorausschicken, was mir auf dem Herzen oder
        auf der Zunge liegt. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000894">Tomay</tei:rs> hat, als ich ihm
        nach Ihrer Karte vom <tei:date when="1930-07-23">23.</tei:date><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot">This postcard (not surviving) is recorded in Schenker’s
          diary for July 23, 1930: “An Deutsch (K.): habe das Manuscript schon in der Hand – Piller
          ist bezahlt.” (“to Deutsch (postcard): <tei:supplied reason="clarity">the
            publishers</tei:supplied> have already received the manuscript – Piller has been
          paid.”). Piller’s receipt for payment is preserved as OC 54/220.</tei:note> gleich anrief,
        mir gesagt, dass er eben am <tei:date when="1930-07-24">24.</tei:date> drei Sätze
        abgeschickt hatte. Alle vier würden 50 bis 60 Seiten ausmachen, also wohl mehr, als Sie
        ursprünglich angenommen und ich dem <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002627"
          >DMV</tei:rs> geschrieben hatte. Es hiess 28 doppelseitige <tei:del rend="overstrike"
          >Seiten</tei:del> Urlinientafeln und 7 Seiten (mit 26) Figuren, auch
          doppelseitig.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">In the published
            <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001752">third <tei:title level="j"
              >Meisterwerk</tei:title> yearbook</tei:rs>, two lines of <tei:hi rend="italic"
            >Urlinie</tei:hi> were printed on each page; the entire booklet devoted to these graphs
          took up 35 pages.</tei:note> Dies aber nur wegen <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-005006">Roeder</tei:rs>s Kalkulation. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Dem traurigen Költzsch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial"
          place="foot">A newspaper article by Hans Költzsch on jazz, which was enclosed in
          Schenker’s letter of July 20. </tei:note> (ich liebe den Jungen ein wenig) lege ich zwei
        erfreulichere <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004931">Benze</tei:rs> bei, die ich
        zurückbitte. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ist unter Ihren Schülern in Wien einer, der eventuell für meinen Bruder,
        einen sehr geübten und begabten Pianisten, als Lehrer nach <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003406">Frl. Schab</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005228"
          >Steuermann</tei:rs> etc. in Betracht käme? Er ist ein sehr beschäftigter Kaufmann, im
        Gegensatz also zu <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000107">Brünauer</tei:rs>. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ein Mann namens F. Kummer bearbeitete um 1836 <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000055">B</tei:rs>s. 10. Quartett (op.74 in Es) als „Symphonie“. Die Sache
        wurde bei einer Akademie im Dresdener Hoftheater gespielt, in Wien mit einer Notiz abfällig
        erledigt, ist aber in Stich wohl nie erschienen. Es gab bess’re Zeit … </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Wichtiger für Sie kann aber sein: Die <tei:rs type="composition"
          key="entity-001206">Sonate op. 22</tei:rs> erschien zuerst bei Hoffmeister &amp; Co., wie
        ich festellte, <tei:del rend="overstrike">dabb</tei:del> dann bei Hoffmeister &amp; Kühnel,
        wie <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000636">Nottebohm</tei:rs> sagt, endlich bei Kühnel,
        wie <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003490">Thayer</tei:rs> meint. Das sind wohl
        Titelauflagen der Original-Ausgabe. Die nächste Auflage aber ist eine neue bei deren
        Nachfolger <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002422">Peters</tei:rs>, frühestens 1814
        erschienen. Ich bemerkte das erst jetzt bei <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-00380"
          >Hoboken</tei:rs>, wo wir auch diese Auflage neben der Original von H. &amp; Co. haben.
        Der Titel ist nämlich mit der Platte geblieben. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> Ich kam darauf, als ich eine eben angebotene Ausgabe
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-004304">Jean Cappi</tei:rs>s, die niemand kannte,
        also einen Wiener Druck, mit beiden verglich. Er entspricht der Auflage <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002422">Peters</tei:rs> und nennt sich deshalb auch „2.
        Edition“. Ob die Abweichung beider – wie ich glaube, mehr schreibtechnischer Art – auf
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">B.</tei:rs> zurückgehe und welche (<tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002422">Peters</tei:rs> oder <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-004304">Cappi</tei:rs>) früher erschienen ist, kann ich noch nicht sagen.
        Jedenfalls scheint mir diese 2. Fassung, die sicher bei Lebzeiten <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000055">B</tei:rs>s. erschien, Ihrer Beachtung sehr wert. Ich hoffe, wir
        kaufen auch die Ausgabe <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-004304">Cappi</tei:rs>. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">B.</tei:rs> schrieb im
        Spätherbst 1825 an Schott: „… Soll nichts zu erfinden sein, wenn man auf stereotypische Art
        sogleich seine Worte vervielfältigen könnte, ohne diese Griffel an Kopisten nötig zu haben
          …“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">I have not located this
          obscure passage in Beethoven’s correspondence to Schott; it may have been written to
          another publisher. Beethoven frequently complained about copyists who were unable to read
          his handwriting.</tei:note> Motto für <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452"
          >Archiv</tei:rs> oder <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000894">Tomay</tei:rs>? </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich empfehle Ihnen, sich nächstens einen Offenbach-Vortrag von <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000477">K Kraus</tei:rs> anzuhören. Womöglich zuerst eine
        Operette, die Sie gut kennen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Liegler,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Leopold Liegler (1882–1949), literary historian and critic, author of <tei:title
            level="m">Karl Kraus und die Sprache</tei:title> (1918) and <tei:title level="m">Karl
            Kraus und sein Werk</tei:title> (1920).</tei:note> einst sein, jetzt mein Freund, hat
        für die Lyrik ein System ausgedacht, das mir Ihrer Urlinie, von der er nichts wusste, zu
        entsprechen scheint. Ich möchte Sie zu seinem Nutzen einmal im Herbst mit diesem edlen,
        klugen Menschen (der einen schönen Kopf auf einen Höcker trägt) zusammenführen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Der Brief, wo angeblich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-00380"
          >Hoboken</tei:rs> von seinem Glück auf <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003154"
          >Sylt</tei:rs> schrieb, stammt von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002742">ihr</tei:rs>,
        wie ich nachträglich bemerkte. Ich wunderte mich noch über die herzliche Ansprache … Und
        also fällt alles, was wir daran geknüpft haben, zusammen. Mit der Irre war es – natürlich
        wortwitzig – so gemeint, dass das neue Haus „an der Irre“ heisst, was Sie vielleicht gar
        nicht wussten. Nach dem Wasser dort. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Und nun muss ich richtig abbrechen, bevor ich Ihren Brief eigentlich
        beantworten konnte. ich möchte Ihnen nächste Woche nochmals darüber schreiben. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Leben Sie wohl mit Ihrer werten <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000771">Frau</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/>Ihr ganz ergebener</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000164">O E
          Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>PROF. OTTO ERICH DEUTSCH</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">VIENNA II</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Böcklinstraße 26</tei:addrLine>

        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/><tei:date when="1930-07-30">July
            30, 1930</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear revered Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
            type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">I shall, unfortunately, be able to reply to your lovely and detailed
        letter of the 20th<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> only briefly. I have been
        swamped here. And tomorrow I am travelling to see my family.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">First of all, let me tell you what lies in my heart, or on my
        tongue.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">When, having received your postcard of the <tei:date when="1930-07-23"
          >23rd</tei:date>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> I immediately telephoned
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000894">Tomay</tei:rs>, he told me that he had just sent
        three movements to you on the <tei:date when="1930-07-24">24th</tei:date>. All four would
        come to between 50 and 60 pages, that is somewhat more than you originally expected and what
        I put to <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002627">Drei Masken Verlag</tei:rs> in
        writing. There would be 28 double-sided <tei:hi rend="italic">Urlinie</tei:hi> graphs and
        seven pages of figures (26 music examples), also two-sided.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
          type="footnote"/> But I’m saying this only on account of <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-005006">Roeder</tei:rs>’s calculation.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">To the sad Költzsch<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> (I
        rather like the youngster), I am adding two more cheerful pieces by <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-004931">Benz</tei:rs>, which I should like you to return.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Among your pupils in Vienna, is there one who might possibly consider
        teaching my brother, a very experienced and gifted pianist, apart from <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003406">Miss Schaab</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005228"
          >Steuermann</tei:rs>, etc.? He is a very busy merchant, in contrast to, say, <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000107">Brünauer</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">A man by the name of F. Kummer arranged <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>’s tenth string quartet (Op. 74 in E<tei:g
          type="flat"/>) as a “symphony”. The piece was played at a concert at the Dresden Court
        Theatre and written off in a Viennese newspaper review; but it seems never to have appeared
        in print. Times were better … </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">For you, this may be more important: the <tei:rs type="composition"
          key="entity-001206">Sonata Op. 22</tei:rs> was first published by Hoffmeister, as I
        ascertained, then by Hoffmeister &amp; Kühnel, as <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000636"
          >Nottebohm</tei:rs> says, and finally by Kühnel, as <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003490">Thayer</tei:rs> says. These are probably reprints of the original
        edition. The next printing, however, is a new one, by the firm’s successor, <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002422">Peters</tei:rs>, and appeared in 1814 at the
        earliest. I noticed this only now, at <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-00380"
          >Hoboken</tei:rs>’s library, where we have this edition alongside the original edition of
        Hoffmeister &amp; Co.: the title-page remained with the printing plate.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> I came across it when I compared the two with another
        edition we have just been offered, and which no one knew, by Jean <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-004304">Cappi</tei:rs>, thus a Viennese print. It derives
        from the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002422">Peters</tei:rs> edition and for
        this reason is also designated as “2nd edition.” Whether the differences between the two
        (which I believe to be more of a writing-technical nature) derive from <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>, and which (<tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002422">Peters</tei:rs> or <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-004304"
          >Cappi</tei:rs>) appeared earlier, I cannot yet say. In any event, this second version,
        which surely appeared during <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>’s
        lifetime, is very much worth your while studying. I hope that we shall also buy the <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-004304">Cappi</tei:rs> edition.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">In the late autumn of 1825, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055"
          >Beethoven</tei:rs> wrote to Schott: “… should there be nothing to discover, if his words
        could immediately be duplicated in a stereotypical way, without there being a need for this
        stylus of copyists …”:<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> a motto for the
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archive</tei:rs> or <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000894">Tomay</tei:rs>?</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I recommend that you listen to an Offenbach reading by <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000477">Karl Kraus</tei:rs> in the near future, starting if
        possible with an opera that you know well.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Liegler,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> once his friend
        and now mine, has conceived a system for poetry which seems to correspond to your <tei:hi
          rend="italic">Urlinie</tei:hi>, of which he knew nothing. I should like to introduce you
        sometime this autumn – for his benefit – to this noble, intelligent person, who bears a
        beautiful head on a hunched [back].</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">The letter in which <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-00380"
          >Hoboken</tei:rs> wrote of his happiness on <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003154"
          >Sylt</tei:rs> comes from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002742">his wife</tei:rs>, as
        I subsequently observed. I was still wondering about the cordial [manner of] address … and
        so everything that we had attached to it falls into place. “Irre” – of course a play on
        words – referred to the fact that the new house is called “on the Irre,” after the body of
        water there, something which you did not at all know.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">And now I must interrupt myself, before I am able actually to reply to
        your letter. I should like to write to you about it again next week.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">May you and your dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
            >wife</tei:rs> fare well,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/>Your wholly devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000164">O. E.
            Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
