<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="1096" sdoID="OC-54-68">OC 54/68</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="TPgimo" scope="major">Typist "Gi/Mo" (DMV)</tei:handNote>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="AB" scope="minor">Alfred Böhme's hand (DMV)</tei:handNote>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="stamp" scope="minor">stamp</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>


  <tei:respStmt xml:id="KH">
   <tei:persName>Kirstie Hewlett</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2014</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-10-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-004414">DMV ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-004929">BöhmeA ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>




   <dc:title>Typed letter from Alfred Böhme (DMV) to Schenker, dated March 4, 1926</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1926-03-04T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2014-03-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Drei Masken Verlag reprimands Schenker for introducing so many changes to the
    music examples, and ask him to consider whether he wishes to bear the additional cost of
    reingraving the music example plates.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>page-proof; Umbruch; Umbruchkorrektur; music example; Notenbeispiel; Korrektur;
    correction; galley correction; Fahnenkorrektur; proofs; Abzüge; appendix; Anhang; engraved;
    klischiert; klischieren; engraved plate; page-proof copy; Klischee; Umbruchabzug; Änderung;
    costs; Kosten; revision; Revision; engraved plate; Korrekturabzug; music plate; Notenplatte;
    Druck; pressure</dc:subject>




  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-002627">DMV</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-004930">BöhmeA</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>

     <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>DREI MASKEN VERLAG GES. M.B.H.</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>WIEN I.</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>WALLNERSTRASSE 4</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:lb/>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:byline><tei:handShift new="#TPgimo"/>Gi/Mo</tei:byline>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-60">
     <tei:date when="1926-03-04">4.III.26</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
    <tei:address>

     <tei:addrLine>Herrn Dr. Heinrich Schenker</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">
      <tei:hi rend="sperr">Wien</tei:hi> III.,</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Keilgasse 8.</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address><tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute>Sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Doktor</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this
      letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/8, p. 2925, March 8, 1926: "Vom Verlag (Br.):
      die Klichees müssen jetzt so bleiben." ("From the publisher (letter): the engraved music
      examples must remain as they are.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Wir haben die ersten Umbruchkorrekturen Ihres <tei:rs key="entity-001750" type="work">Musikjahrbuches</tei:rs> zurückerhalten und mussten zu unserem Bedauern
    feststellen, dass Sie in den Notenbeispielen eine ganze Anzahl Korrekturen angebracht haben.
    Beim Vergleichen mit der letzten Fahnenkorrektur bemerkten wir weiter, dass diese Korrekturen in
    den Fahnenabzügen nicht enthalten sind, es handelt sich also in diesem Fall nicht um
    Nachlässigkeiten der Fa <tei:rs key="entity-002402" type="organization">Waldheim</tei:rs>,
    sondern um neue Korrekturen von Ihnen. Auch bei den als Anhang zu drucken den
     <tei:term>Urlinietafeln</tei:term> haben Sie einige Änderungen auf den Seiten I, 6 und 9
    angebracht, die in den vorhergehenden Abzügen nicht vermerkt waren.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Wie Sie ja wissen, sind alle Notenbeispiele einschliesslich der Anhänge schon
    klischiert und in dem ersten Umbruchabzug bereits von den Klischees abgezogen. Die Klischees
    können aber nicht korrigiert werden, wenn Sie darauf bestehen, dass diese Änderungen ausgeführt
     wer<tei:pb n="2"/>den, müssen die Klischees vernichtet und statt dessen neue angefertigt
    werden. Da es sich, wie schon erwähnt, um Änderungen handelt, die Sie jetzt erst nachträglich in
    der Umbruchkorrektur angebracht haben, können wir leider die Kosten, die ziemlich erheblich sein
    werden, nicht tragen und wir bitten, uns umgehend mitzuteilen, ob wir Ihnen die Revision des
     <tei:rs key="entity-001750" type="work">Jahrbuchs</tei:rs> liefern sollen, ohne auf die
    Korrekturen in den Notenbeispielen Rücksicht zu nehmen.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Dass die Abzüge der Klischees nicht so klar und deutlich sind, wie vorher die
    Abzüge von den Notenplatten, hängt mit der Technik des Abziehens zusammen. Die Korrekturabzüge
    von den Notenplatten werden nämlich unter sehr starkem Druck hergestellt, während die Abzüge von
    den Klischees sehr vorsichtig und mit leichtem Druck gemacht werden, um die Klischees nicht zu
    verderben. Beim Reindruck natürlich erscheinen die Klischees zumindest ebenso klar und deutlich
    wie bei den ersten Plattenabzügen. Wenn wir keine Nachrichten von Ihnen bekommen, liefert Ihnen
     <tei:rs key="entity-002402" type="organization">Waldheim</tei:rs> Anfang kommender Woche eine
    Revision des ganzen Textes und zwar nur des Textes ohne Berücksichtigung der Änderungen in den
    Notenbeispielen.</tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Wir empfehlen uns Ihnen</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">mit vorzüglicher Hochachtung</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="stamp"/><tei:rs key="entity-002627" type="organization">DREI MASKEN VERLAG Ges. m. B. H.</tei:rs></tei:signed>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#AB"/><tei:rs key="entity-004930" type="person">Böhme</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>



  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>

     <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>DREI MASKEN VERLAG &amp; Co.</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>VIENNA I</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>WALLNERSTRAßE 4</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:lb/>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:byline><tei:handShift new="#TPgimo"/>Gi/Mo</tei:byline>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-60">
     <tei:date when="1926-03-04">4.III.26</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
    <tei:address>

     <tei:addrLine>Dr. Heinrich Schenker</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">
      <tei:hi rend="sperr">Vienna</tei:hi> III,</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Keilgasse 8.</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address><tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute>Dear Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"><tei:supplied reason="identity">Schenker</tei:supplied></tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">We have received the first page-proofs of your <tei:rs key="entity-001750" type="work">Music Yearbook</tei:rs> and were dismayed to see that you have introduced a large
    number of corrections in the music examples. From a comparison with the last galley corrections,
    we observed further that these are not the result of errors on the part of the <tei:rs key="entity-002402" type="organization">Waldheim</tei:rs> firm, but rather new corrections of
    yours. Also, in the <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> graphs that are to be printed as an appendix,
    you have introduced some changes on pages 1, 6, and 9, which had not been noticed on the
    previous proofs.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">As you must know, all music examples, including those of the appendix, have
    already been engraved and have already been taken from the engraved plates when they appear in
    the page-proof copies. The plates cannot, however, be corrected; if you insist that these
    changes be implemented, <tei:pb n="2"/> the plates will have to be destroyed and new ones made
    to replace them. As these corrections are, as already mentioned, the result of subsequent
    changes made by you, indicated in the page-proofs, we are unable to bear the costs, which will
    be rather considerable; and we ask you to let us know by return of mail whether we should send
    you the revised version of the <tei:rs key="entity-001750" type="work">yearbook</tei:rs> without
    taking into account the corrections to the music examples.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">That the prints made from the engraved plates are not as strong and distinct
    as those made from the music plates is a result of the copying process. The proof copies of the
    music plates were produced with a very firm pressure, whereas the copies from the engraved
    plates were made very carefully and with a light pressure, so as not to damage them. At the
    final impression, of course, the engraved plates will appear just as strongly and distinctly as
    they were when the plates were first copied. If we do not receive further news from you, <tei:rs key="entity-002402" type="organization">Waldheim</tei:rs> will send you a revised version of
    the entire text – and indeed only of the text, without consideration of the changes to the
     music examples.</tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">We remain</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">with kind regards,</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="stamp"/><tei:rs key="entity-002627" type="organization">DREI MASKEN VERLAG &amp; Co.</tei:rs></tei:signed>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#AB"/><tei:rs key="entity-004930" type="person">Böhme</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>


  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>