<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="1134" sdoID="OC-54-111">OC 54/111</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPoed" scope="major">Typist "Otto Erich Deutsch"</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="OED" scope="minor">Otto Erich Deutsch's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>


    <tei:respStmt xml:id="KH">
      <tei:persName>Kirstie Hewlett</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2014</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2011-10-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs key="entity-002712" type="correspondence" role="correspondence">OEDeutsch ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


      <dc:title>Typed letter from Otto Erich Deutsch to Schenker, dated January 8, 1927</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1927-01-08T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2014-03-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Deutsch thanks Schenker for his recent communications, including a copy of the
        contract with Drei Masken Verlag for the Meisterwerk Yearbook, and asks for a copy of
        relevant extracts from the correspondence with the publishers. He reports progress in the
        establishment of a Photogram Archive at the Austrian National Library, with the cooperation
        of Dr Robert Haas and financial support from Anthony van Hoboken; similar plans to
        photographically reproduce autograph manuscripts are underway at the Beethoven House in
        Bonn, and (for manuscripts of Bach and Handel) also in England. He advises Schenker that
        proofs will start arriving from the printing-house Waldheim in a few weeks, and expresses
        his delight in being able to assist Schenker in the promotion of his work.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Vertrag; contract; proposal; Antrag; Photogramm-Archiv; photogram archive;
        administration; Verwaltung; manuscript; Handschrift; positive print; Positiv; Negativ;
        negative print; lecture; Vortrag; Rückkehr; return; proof; Korrektur; Urlinie; printing
        house; Setzerei</dc:subject>

    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000164">DeutschOE</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>OTTO ERICH DEUTSCH</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-50">
          <tei:date when="1927-01-08"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/>8. Jänner 27</tei:date>
          <tei:handShift new="#printed"/>WIEN II., Böcklinstrasse 26 </tei:dateline>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/>Sehr verehrter Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Doktor</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at
            OJ 3/9, p. 3022, January 9, 1927: "Von Deutsch (Br. expr.): erbittet weitere Exzerpte
            aus Briefen des Verlages, spricht von der Stiftung Hoboken! Namentlich werden
            Handschriften von Haydn, Mozart, Schubert in Frage kommen, da sich in England u.
            Frankreich Gelehrte rühren, um Handschriften zu sammeln." ("From Deutsch (express
            letter): asks for further excerpts of letters from the publisher, speaks about Hoboken's
            donation! Specifically, autograph manuscripts of Haydn, Mozart, Schubert come into
            question, since in England and France scholars are keen to collect
            manuscripts.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ihre Begleitbriefe samt der Abschrift des Vertrages (der merkwürdiger
        Weise undatiert ist) habe ich zugleich mit Ihrem Briefe erhalten und danke für
          alles.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Neither letter is known
          to survive.</tei:note> Ihre Mitteilungen über <tei:rs key="entity-000195" type="person">Dr. Einstein</tei:rs> sind mir zur Instruktion von Wert, obzwar ich in diesem Falle nach
        wie vor Ihren Pessimismus nicht teilen kann. Item: der <tei:rs key="entity-002627" type="organization">Dreimaskenverlag</tei:rs> hat <tei:date when="1927-01-07">gestern</tei:date> noch unseren Antrag angenommen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Wenn es für Ihre <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Frau
          Gemahlin</tei:rs> nicht all zu viel Mühe macht, so wäre ich für Exzerpte aus den Briefen
        des <tei:rs key="entity-002627" type="organization">DMV</tei:rs>, soweit sie nach dem
        Vertrag geschrieben sind, sehr verbunden. Es handelte sich um Abschriften der wesentlichen
        Stellen nur.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich habe <tei:date when="1927-01-08">heute</tei:date> mit <tei:rs key="entity-000320" type="person">Dr. Haas</tei:rs> über das Projekt eines <tei:rs key="entity-002452" type="organization">Photogramm-Archives für musikalische
            Meistermanuskripte</tei:rs> gesprochen. Er ist dafür begeistert und glaubt mit mir, dass
        das Archiv wird leicht <tei:pb n="2"/> in der <tei:rs key="entity-002686" type="organization">Nationalbibliothek</tei:rs> untergebracht werden können. Ich möchte es
        als Stiftung <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hoboken</tei:rs> dort bezeichnet
        wissen und denke mir, dass intern Sie und <tei:rs key="entity-000320" type="person">Haas</tei:rs> mit <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Herrn van Hoboken</tei:rs>,
        der das Geschäftliche führen müsste, die sachliche Verwaltung übernehmen sollten. <tei:rs key="entity-000320" type="person">Haas</tei:rs> ist damit sehr einverstanden.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich erfuhr zufällig, dass das <tei:rs key="entity-004558" type="organization">Beethoven-Haus</tei:rs> (die <tei:rs key="entity-002603" type="place">Bonner</tei:rs> Patrizier, die dem <tei:rs key="entity-005329" type="place">Wiener
          Schubert-Museum</tei:rs> durch Schuld der Gemeinde fehlen) eine Sammlung aller
        Handschriften <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person">Bs.</tei:rs> in Photographie
        vorbereitet, was auf dem Kongress – hoffentlich zugleich mit unserem Plane – verlautbart
        werden dürfte. In <tei:rs key="entity-002586" type="place">England</tei:rs> soll ein
        Musikgelehrter die Handschriften <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person">Bach</tei:rs>s so
        sammeln. Vielleicht ist dort auch für <tei:rs key="entity-000329" type="person">Händel</tei:rs> schon der Boden bereitet. Dann beliebe uns vor allem <tei:rs key="entity-000612" type="person">Mozart</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person">Haydn</tei:rs> und <tei:rs key="entity-000803" type="person">Schubert</tei:rs>. Es ist aber in keinem Falle als Konkurrenz anzusehen, wenn andere
          Fakt<tei:del hand="#OED" rend="overstrike">i</tei:del>oren nun endlich in derselben
        Richtung tätig sind. Das erleichtert nur unsere Arbeit, und wir werden hier natürlich
          minde<tei:del hand="#OED" rend="overstrike">s</tei:del>stens die Positive jener Stücke
        haben, die schon anderswo im Negativ ge<tei:pb n="3"/>sammelt werden. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Unser Plan, bei dem ich natürlich nur eine anregende Rolle spiele, soll
        vorläufig geheim bleiben. <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Herr van
          Hoboken</tei:rs>, <tei:subst>
          <tei:del hand="#OED" rend="overstrike">dem</tei:del>
          <tei:add hand="#OED" rend="interlinear-above">für den</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>ich daraus eine wertvolle Bereicherung seines Tun <tei:subst>
          <tei:del hand="#OED" rend="overstrike">verspreche</tei:del>
          <tei:add hand="#OED" rend="interlinear-above">erwarte</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>, wird mit Ihnen wohl noch beim <tei:rs key="entity-000393" type="person">Hubermann</tei:rs>-Konzert darüber sprechen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">See diary entry for <tei:ref type="diaries" cRef="OJ-03-09_1927-01:r0010">January 10, 1927</tei:ref>.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Nach meiner Rückkehr werde ich Ihnen, sehr durch Vorträge bedrängt,
        wenigstens einen kurzen Bescheid über den Verlauf der Münchener Verhandlungen geben.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Bitte, machen Sie sich darauf gefasst, schon in den nächsten Wochen
        Korrekturen von <tei:rs key="entity-002402" type="organization">Waldheim</tei:rs> zu
        bekommen. Ich nehme an, dass Ihr Manuskript so vollkommen ist, dass es wenig nur zu ändern
        geben wird. Sollten Sie wegen der <tei:term>Urlinien</tei:term>
        <tei:add hand="#OED" place="interlinear-above">noch</tei:add> Bedenken habe, so wird es sich
        empfehlen, selbst in die Setzerei zu gehen, um einmal nach dem Rechten zu schauen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich bin glücklich, Ihrer guten Sache praktisch nützlich sein zu
        können.</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="first">Mit besten Empfehlungen von Haus zu Haus</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr sehr ergebener</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/><tei:rs key="entity-000164" type="person">Otto Erich Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>OTTO ERICH DEUTSCH</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-50">
          <tei:date when="1927-01-08"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/>January 8, 1927</tei:date>
          <tei:handShift new="#printed"/>VIENNA II, Böcklinstraße 26 </tei:dateline>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/>Revered Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"><tei:supplied reason="identity">Schenker</tei:supplied></tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">I received your covering letter together with the copy of the contract
        (which, remarkably, is undated) at the same time as your letter, and I thank you for
          everything.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> Your communications about
          <tei:rs key="entity-000195" type="person">Dr. Einstein</tei:rs> are usefully informative
        for me, even though in this case I can share your pessimism no more now than before. In
        addition, <tei:rs key="entity-002627" type="organization">Drei Masken Verlag</tei:rs>
        accepted our proposal <tei:date when="1927-01-07">yesterday</tei:date>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">If it does not create too much work for your <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs>, I would be most grateful for excerpts from the letters from
          <tei:rs key="entity-002627" type="organization">DMV</tei:rs>, insofar as they were written
        after the contract. It is a question merely of copies of the important passages.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I spoke today with <tei:rs key="entity-000320" type="person">Dr.
          Haas</tei:rs> about the project of a <tei:rs key="entity-002452" type="organization">Photogram Archive for Musical Manuscripts of Master Composers</tei:rs>. He is
        enthusiastic about it and believes, with me, that the Archive can easily <tei:pb n="2"/> be
        housed in the <tei:rs key="entity-002686" type="organization">National Library</tei:rs>. I
        should like it to be identified there as the <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hoboken</tei:rs> Endowment, and I suppose that you and <tei:rs key="entity-000320" type="person">Haas</tei:rs>, together with <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Mr
          Hoboken</tei:rs> (who will have to take care of the financial side), ought to assume the
        internal functional administration. <tei:rs key="entity-000320" type="person">Haas</tei:rs>
        very much agrees with this.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I discovered by chance that the <tei:rs key="entity-004286" type="place">Beethoven House</tei:rs> (the patricians of <tei:rs key="entity-002603" type="place">Bonn</tei:rs>, the likes of which are missing from the <tei:rs key="entity-005329" type="place">Schubert Museum</tei:rs> in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs> through the fault of the community) is
        preparing a collection of all of <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs>’s manuscripts in photographic reproduction; something that could be
        announced – together with our plans, I hope – at the <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person"><tei:supplied reason="clarity">Beethoven</tei:supplied></tei:rs> Congress.
        In <tei:rs key="entity-002586" type="place">England</tei:rs>, a musical scholar is
        apparently collecting the autograph manuscripts of <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person">Bach</tei:rs> in this way. Perhaps the ground has already been prepared for <tei:rs key="entity-000329" type="person">Handel</tei:rs>, too. Then there remains for us <tei:rs key="entity-000612" type="person">Mozart</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person">Haydn</tei:rs>, and <tei:rs key="entity-000803" type="person">Schubert</tei:rs> above all. It is, however, in no way to be regarded as competition if
        other parties are, finally, active in the same direction. That will only make our work
        easier, and we shall naturally have here the positive prints of those pieces that elsewhere
        have been collected in negative format.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="3"/> Our plan, in which I shall of course play only an
        encouraging role, should for the moment be kept secret. <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Mr. Hoboken</tei:rs>, from whom I expect a valuable increase in activity as
        a result of this, will probably speak to you about it at the <tei:rs key="entity-000393" type="person">Huberman</tei:rs> concert.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">After my return, though I am hard pressed for time on account of lectures,
        I shall at least give you a short account of the progress of the Munich dealings.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Please be prepared to receive proofs from <tei:rs key="entity-002402" type="organization">Waldheim</tei:rs> in the coming weeks. I gather that your manuscript
        is so complete that there will be little to change. If you still harbor doubts about the
          <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>
        <tei:supplied reason="clarity">pages</tei:supplied>, then you would be well advised to go to
        the printing house yourself, to see that everything is in order.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I am happy to be able to be of practical use to your worthy cause.</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="first">With best wishes from us to you,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">yours very truly,</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/><tei:rs key="entity-000164" type="person">Otto Erich Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>