<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="8" sdoID="OC-52-205">OC 52/205</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="TPw" scope="minor">typist "W"</tei:handNote>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="EH" scope="minor">Emil Hertzka's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2009</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2009</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
   <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
   <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-02-07" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002700">Hertzka ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002701">UE ~ H+JSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002702">UE ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   
   
   
   <dc:title>Typed letter from Hertzka (UE) to Schenker, dated April 10, 1918</dc:title>
   
   <dcterms:created>1918-04-10T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-03-10</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Hertzka returns the Bekker review with thanks, and reflects on Schenker's remarks
    concerning Urtext editions; he encloses the requested copy of the Gazette de Lausanne. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven; The Last Five Sonatas of Beethoven; Op. 111;
    Frankfurter Zeitung; review; Gazette de Lausanne </dc:subject>

   
   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000356">Hertzka</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-002408">UE</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine>
      <tei:supplied reason="format">printed UE letterhead</tei:supplied>
     </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>Wien I, Karlsplatz 6</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:byline>
     <tei:persName type="typist">W</tei:persName>
    </tei:byline>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-50">
     <tei:placeName>Wien </tei:placeName>
     <tei:handShift new="#TPw"/>
     <tei:date when="1918-04-10">10. April 1918.</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine>
      <tei:persName rend="indent-20">Wohlgeboren Herrn Prof. Dr. Heinrich <tei:hi rend="sperr">Schenker</tei:hi></tei:persName>
     </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">
      <tei:hi rend="underline sperr">Wien</tei:hi>
     </tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:salute>Sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Besten<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
     this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/10, pp. 873–74 : April 12, 1918: "Von
     Hertzka (Br.): dankt für den Hinweis auf Bekkers Notiz, die er schon kannte, fügt hinzu, daß
     die Schwierigkeit bei den Urtextausgaben in Hinblick auf den Durchschnitt der Lehrer
     unüberwindlich sei; legt das Blatt aus Lausanne bei: ein politischer Leitartikel, gezeichnet
     Maurice Kufferath, der einige Stellen aus op. 111 zum Gegenstand einer symptomatischen
     Betrachtung macht. Zitiert die Stellen bald in Uebersetzung, bald sogar sowohl im Original als
     in Uebersetzung, damit man ihn ja nicht einer Fälschung verdächtige u. dennoch begeht er eine,
     dort wo er statt von einer schallenden Ohrfeige an Amerika von einer „mit Recht verabreichten“
     spricht. Schließlich mündet der Artikel in eine nachdrückliche Mahnung, vor dem germanischen
     Sophism, vor dem deutschen Buch auf der Hut zu bleiben. Von dem rein musikalischen Teil spricht
     er nur so weit, als er zugibt, die Ausgabe wäre unschätzbar, wenn nicht . . Auf die
     Erläuterungen geht er nicht weiter sachlich ein. ("From Hertzka (letter): thanks for pointing
     out Bekker's note, which he already knew, adds that the problem of Urtext editions with regard
     to the average teacher cannot be overcome; attaches the paper from Lausanne: a political
     leading article signed by Maurice Kufferath, who takes a number of passages from Opus 111 as
     the subject matter of a symptomatic observation. Cites the passages sometimes in translation,
     sometimes even in both the original and in translation so that no one can suspect him of
     falsification and yet that is precisely what he does, where instead of referring to a real slap
     in the face for America speaks of one "rightly doled out." In the end the article turns into an
     emphatic admonition to be wary of the Germanic sophism and the German book. Concerning the
     purely musical part he only goes so far as to admit that the edition would be invaluable if
     only . . Beyond that he does not go substantively into the commentary.").<!-- XR -->
    </tei:note> Dank für die Einsendung der Notiz von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000057">Bekker</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker had
     sent Hertzka Bekker's review with WSLB 297 : April 9, 1918. </tei:note> die ich schon vorher
    mit Interesse gelesen habe. – Ihre Bemerkung, dass mit den <tei:term>Urtextausgabe</tei:term>n die französische Lehrer noch weniger als die deutschen
    etwas Rechtes anzufangen wissen werden, erhellt ja die ganze Schwierigkeit der Frage auf<tei:add place="inline">'s</tei:add> deutlichste. Bearbeitete<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">"Bearbeitete" (with heavy editorial intervention) underlined by
     Schenker, also "Urtextausgaben" and "derzeit" (at the present time). Literally, the adjective
     "bearbeitet" means "worked on." In the next sentence, Hertzka uses the noun "Bearbeitungen,"
     which in the musical context usually means "arrangements," but here has been translated more
     freely. </tei:note> Ausgaben sind in den meisten Fällen schlecht, <tei:term>Urtextausgabe</tei:term>n in den meisten Fällen unverkäuflich; derzeit wenigstens. Sie glauben
    doch nicht, dass ein Verleger für <tei:term>Bearbeitung</tei:term>en
    Geld zahlen würde, wenn er auch die <tei:term>Urtextausgabe</tei:term> ebenso gut oder
    besser verkaufen könnte? Der Weg den Sie selbst vorschlagen: Eine ordentliche
     <tei:term>Originalausgabe</tei:term> mit wenigen entscheidenden <tei:term>Erläuterung</tei:term>en*<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">The typist has inserted an asterisk here, which cues to the postscript at the foot of the
     page. The phrase from the beginning of the sentence is quoted direct from WSLB 297. </tei:note>
    wird auch nicht genügen, denn der Durchschnittslehrer und das ist bekanntlich die überwältigende
    Mehrzahl, verlangt unbedingt bei Studienwerken Ausgaben mit <tei:term>Fingersatz</tei:term>, reichlichen <tei:term>Vortragszeichen</tei:term>, <tei:term>Phrasierung</tei:term>en u.
    dgl. mehr. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer rend="indent-20">
    <tei:salute>Mit verbindlichen Grüssen</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Ihr in Verehrung ergebener</tei:salute>
    <tei:handShift new="#EH"/>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-20">Hertzka</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p><tei:supplied reason="clarity">added, on a different typewriter:</tei:supplied>*
      <tei:handShift new="#TPw"/>P.S. Mitfolgend die <tei:title>Gazette de
      Lausanne</tei:title><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker first
      asked about this on March 3 :WSLB 295, and this is Hertzka's response. No clipping is
      preserved in Schenker's papers, but his diary entry (OJ 2/10, pp. 873–74 : April 12, 1918)
      summarizes it: "a political leading article signed by Maurice
       Kufferath, who takes a number of passages from <tei:title level="m">Opus
       111</tei:title> as the subject matter of a symptomatic observation. Cites the passages
      sometimes in translation, sometimes even in both the original and in translation so that no
      one can suspect him of falsification and yet that is precisely what he does, where instead of
      referring to a real slap in the face for America he speaks of one "rightly doled out." In the
      end the article turns into an emphatic admonition to be wary of the Germanic sophism and the
      German book. Concerning the purely musical part he only goes so far as to admit that the
      edition would be invaluable if only . . Beyond that he does not go substantively into the
      commentary." <!-- XR -->
     </tei:note> die wir uns nach Kenntnisnahme zurückerbitten.</tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>
  </tei:div>

  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine>
      <tei:supplied reason="format">printed UE letterhead</tei:supplied>
     </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>Vienna I, Karlsplatz 6</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:byline>
     <tei:persName type="typist">W</tei:persName>
    </tei:byline>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-50">
     <tei:placeName>Vienna, </tei:placeName>
     <tei:handShift new="#TPw"/>
     <tei:date when="1918-04-10">April 10, 1918</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-20">
      <tei:persName>Prof. Heinrich Schenker, Esq.,</tei:persName>
     </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">
      <tei:hi rend="underline">Vienna</tei:hi>
     </tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:salute>Greatly honored <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first"> Many<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> thanks for sending the
    review by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000057">Bekker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> which I had already read with interest. — Your remark that French teachers
    will have even less idea than the German ones how to begin to make sense of the <tei:term>Urtext edition</tei:term>s casts the clearest possible light on
    the whole difficulty of the matter. Editions with heavy editorial intervention<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> are in most cases bad, <tei:term>Urtext
     edition</tei:term>s in most cases unsaleable, least of all at the present time. You really do not
    believe that a publisher would pay money for <tei:term>performing
     edition</tei:term>s when he could buy <tei:term>Urtext edition</tei:term>s every bit as
    good or better? Nor will the course of action that you yourself suggest, "a straighforward
    original edition with a few decisive <tei:term>elucidation</tei:term>s,"*<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> suffice; for, where
    works for study by pupils are concerned, the average teacher – and everybody knows they are the
    overwhelming majority – insists on editions with <tei:term>fingering</tei:term>, lots of <tei:term>performance
     indication</tei:term>s, <tei:term>phrase marking</tei:term>s and
    suchlike. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer rend="indent-20">
    <tei:salute>With sincere greetings,</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="intend-10">Yours truly, in admiration,</tei:salute>
    <tei:handShift new="#EH"/>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-20">Hertzka</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p><tei:supplied reason="clarity">added, on a different typewriter:</tei:supplied>*
      <tei:handShift new="#TPw"/>P.S. Enclosed is the <tei:title>
      <tei:hi rend="italic">Gazette de Lausanne</tei:hi>
     </tei:title>;<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> which we ask to be returned to us
     after perusal. </tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>


  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>