<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2718" sdoID="OC-B-136-138">OC B/136-138</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="GA" scope="sole">Gerhard Albersheim's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2008</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>


    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2011-06-09" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008170">AlbersheimG ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Gerhard Albersheim to Schenker, dated March 20–21,
        1930</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1930-03-21T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2022-03-22</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>After correction by Schenker, Albersheim has finalized an article on
        Schenker's work, which he will submit to a journal. He will now prepare himself for the
        state examinations.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000007">AlbersheimG</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">
      <tei:div type="part_1">

        <tei:opener>
          <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#GA"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484"
              >Wien</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1930-03-20">20. III. 30.</tei:date></tei:dateline>
          <tei:salute>Verehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>,<tei:note
              xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded
              in Schenker's diary for March 22, 1930: “Von Albersheim eine Reinschrift seines
              Aufsatzes.” (“From Albersheim a fair copy of his article”). Schenker had handed the
              typescript back to Albersheim with annotations on March 12 (diary), requesting its
              return. Schenker's subsequent letter to Albersheim informing him that he had sent the
              article off (to Alfred Einstein) is recorded in the diary for March 23: “An Albersheim
              (K.): sende den Aufsatz ab.” (“To Albersheim (postcard): I send off the article.”; and
              for the same date: “An Einstein (Br.): Empfehle Albersheims Aufsatz; Lie-Liechen
              verpackt Aufsatz u. Brief.” (“To Einstein (letter): I recommend Albersheim's article;
              Lie-Liechen packs the essay and the letter.”), and for March 24: “rec. Briefe an
              Einstein u. Mozio aufgegeben” (“Registered letters to Einstein and Mozio sent”).
            </tei:note></tei:salute>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:p rend="indent-20">Ich habe nun meinen Aufsatz<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
            type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:title level="a">Heinrich Schenker: Grundlagen und
              Bedeutung seines Werkes.</tei:title> This article was submitted to the <tei:title
              level="j">Zeitschrift für Musikwissenschaft</tei:title>, whose editor, Alfred
            Einstein, rejected it on March 28, 1930 (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-B-139"
              >OC B/139</tei:ref>). It was eventually published in the <tei:title level="j"
              >Rheinische Musik- und Theater-Zeitung</tei:title> 15–16 (Cologne, 1931), pp. 1–6. A
            draft version is preserved as OC B/112–134 with emendations by Albersheim and Schenker,
            and a clipping of the final publication in Schenker's scrapbook as OC 2/p.80.
          </tei:note> auf Grund Ihrer Anmerkungen einer nochmaligen Bearbeitung unterzogen und teile
          Ihnen im Folgenden die Gesichtspunkte, die mich dabei leiteten, mit, um Ihnen womöglich
          eine nochmalige Lektüre zu ersparen. </tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="indent-20">Die kleineren stilistischen Umstellungen von Ihrer Hand glaubte ich
          ohne weiteres in den Text übernehmen zu dürfen. Nicht aber ging das für Ihre <tei:rs
            type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title>den freien Satz</tei:title></tei:rs>
          betreffenden Formulierungen an, da ich mich unmöglich mit fremden Federn schmücken kann. <tei:subst>
            <tei:del rend="overstrike">Dort</tei:del>
            <tei:add place="interlinear-above">An diesen 2 Stellen</tei:add>
          </tei:subst> fand ich den einfachen, auch stilistisch gut wirkenden Ausweg, Sie zu
          zitieren. </tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="indent-20">Einige andere Ihrer Anmmerkungen nahm ich zum Anlaß einer eigenen
          Neuformulierung, teils weil Ihr Stil zu unverkennbar war und uns jungeren Menschen nicht
          zukommt, an <tei:pb n="2"/> einer <tei:add place="interlinear-above">anderen</tei:add>
          Stelle, weil ich mich nicht entschließen konnte, einen Gedanken diskussionslos zu opfern,
          der bei der Lektüre auch Ihren Beifall gefunden hatte. </tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="indent-20">Außerdem habe ich die absichtliche Einfachheit des Beispiels noch
          stärker betont und begründet, sowie einen Hinweis auf die Analysen von Ihrer Hand
          eingeschaltet. — </tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="indent-20">Ich betrachte diesen Aufsatz als den Anfang einer Wirksamkeit, in
          deren Ausübung ich mein Lebensziel erblicke, ohne heute schon zu wissen, ob sie sich auf
          ausübendem, (pädagogischem) unterrichtendem oder publizistischem Gebiet abspielen wird.
          Mit dem gewählten Thema habe ich meine Visitenkarte ab<tei:supplied reason="omission"
            >ge</tei:supplied>geben und von Anfang an dokumentieren wollen, <tei:del
            rend="underline">ich</tei:del> in welcher Richtung ich zu wirken gedenke. Außer dem
          Wunsche, dadurch der so nötigen – für die Menschheit nötigen – Verbreitung Ihrer Lehre zu
          dienen, lag mir auch an <tei:pb n="3"/> der Feststellung der Priorität Ihrer Gedanken,
          weil diese mit der Zeit einen immer breiteren Raum in der Publizistik einnehmen werden und
          schon einnehmen. </tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="indent-20">Ich bin der Ansicht, daß eine monographische <tei:hi
            rend="underline">Darstellung</tei:hi> Ihrer Lehre <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">a
            priori</tei:foreign> verfehlt ist, da niemand die Reinheit und Systematik Ihrer eignenen
          Darstellung erreichen könnte. Arbeiten über Ihr Schaffen dürften sich daher meiner Meinung
          nach immer nur auf Spezialgebiete beschränken oder den Charakter von Einführungen in Ihr
          Werk haben. Letzteres habe ich in der vorliegenden Arbeit in der knappsten Form versucht
          und mich dabei bemüht, persönlich ganz hinter die Sache zurückzutreten, wie Sie das auch
          bei meiner Vorlesung empfunden haben. Wenn Sie nun auch nach den letzten Verbesserungen
          noch der Ansicht sind, daß in Einzelheiten <tei:pb n="4"/> die Rechnung zwischen Thema und
          Darstellung nicht ganz aufgegangen ist, dürfte es sich wohl um den Rest der Individualität
          handeln, die bei einer Darstellung ursprünglich ganz persönlicher Gedanken aus fremder
          Feder wohl nie ganz zu vermeiden ist. — </tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="indent-20">Ich bin jetzt intensiv mit den Vorbereitungen auf die
            Staatsprüfung<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">The state
            examination resulting in a teaching qualification, with primary study piano.
            Albersheim's taking of this exam has been under discussion for more than a year, as
            recorded in Schenker's diary. </tei:note> beschäftigt. Meine Frau<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Erna Eder, married 1929. </tei:note>
          war deshalb so lieb, mir den Aufsatz abzuschreiben, wodurch ich viel Zeit sowie die Kosten
          einer nochmaligen Maschinendiktats erspart habe. </tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="indent-20">Das alte Exemplar mit Ihren Anmerkungen geht hiermit wunschgemäß in
          Ihren Besitz über.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">= OC
            B/112–134. </tei:note></tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="indent-20">Ich nehme an, daß sich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000195"
            >Einstein</tei:rs> nach Einsendung des Aufsatzes an mich wenden wird, wobei ich ihm dann
          auch den Wunsch nach einen Anzahl Sonderdrucke eröffnen kann. </tei:p>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Mit besten Grüßen an Sie und Ihre verehrte <tei:rs
              type="person" key="entity-000771">Frau Gemahlin</tei:rs></tei:salute>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Ihr ergebener</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed rend="indent-600"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000007">Gerhard
              Albersheim</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>
      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="part_2">
        <tei:opener/>
        <tei:lb/>

        <tei:p><tei:pb n="5"/> P. S. <tei:date when="1930-03-21">21. III.</tei:date>
        </tei:p>

        <tei:p>Vielen Dank für Ihre w. Karte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial"
            place="foot">This postcard is not known to survive. Its sending is recorded in
            Schenker's diary for March 19, 1930: “An Albersheim (K.): fordere ihn auf die Korrektur
            des Aufsatzes zu beschleunigen, da bald in München ein Aufsatz über mich erscheinen
            dürfte. ” (“To Albersheim (postcard): I ask him to speed up the correction of the
            article, as an article about me is likely to appear soon in Munich.”).</tei:note> In der
          Tat wäre mir eine möglichst rasche Erledigung der Angelegenheit lieb. Da Sie die Arbeit
          schon heute in Händen haben werden, brauchte ich wohl wegen der Aufsatzes Ihre kostbare
          Zeit am nächsten Mittwoch nicht mehr in Anspruch zu nehmen<tei:supplied
            reason="punctuation">.</tei:supplied> Schreiben Sie mir, wenn Sie auch so denken, also
          ganz ungeniert ab! Wenn ich dagegen <tei:hi rend="underline">nichts</tei:hi> mehr von
          Ihnen hören sollte, komme ich um die vereinbarte Zeit. </tei:p>


        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Nochmals beste Grüße</tei:salute>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-65">Ihr ergebener</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000007">Gerhard
              Albersheim</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>
      </tei:div>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:div type="part_1">

        <tei:opener>
          <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#GA"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484"
              >Vienna</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1930-03-20">March 20, 1930</tei:date></tei:dateline>
          <tei:salute>Revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
              corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:p rend="indent-20">On the basis of your annotations, I have now subjected my
            article<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> to a further reworking, and
          should like to tell you in what follows the considerations that guided me in that process
          so as, if possible, to spare your having to read it for a second time.</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="indent-20">I felt able to incorporate into the text without further ado the
          smaller-scale stylistic modifications that you suggested. That was not the case for your
          formulations relating to <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title level="m">Free
              Composition</tei:title></tei:rs>, since I find it impossible to adorn <tei:supplied
            reason="clarity">my own style</tei:supplied> with another person's style. <tei:subst>
            <tei:del rend="overstrike">There,</tei:del>
            <tei:add place="interlinear-above">In these two passages,</tei:add>
          </tei:subst> I arrived at the simple and stylistically workable solution of quoting you
          directly.</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="indent-20">One or two others of your annotations prompted me to devise my own
          new formulation, in part because your style was too unmistakeable and does not befit us
          younger people; in <tei:pb n="2"/>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">another</tei:add> passage, because I could not bring
          myself to offer an idea without discussion, which had actually met with your approval when
          you read it.</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="indent-20">Additionally, I have emphasized and substantiated still more
          strongly the intentional simplicity of the example, while at the same time inserting a
          reference to your own analyses. —</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="indent-20">I consider this article as the beginning of an activity the practice
          of which I look upon as my goal in life – without knowing at this early stage whether it
          will materialize in the realm of performance, (pedagogy) teaching, or journalism. With
          this chosen topic I have presented my visiting card, and I want at the outset to betoken
          the direction in which I see myself working. In addition to my wish to serve the
          dissemination of your theory, which is so necessary – so necessary for mankind –, I have
          set my heart also on <tei:pb n="3"/> establishing the priority of your ideas, because
          these will in time occupy – and are already occupying – an ever greater place in
          journalism.</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="indent-20">I am of the opinion that a monograph <tei:hi rend="underline"
            >presentation</tei:hi> of your theory would be wrong <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat"><tei:hi
              rend="italic">a priori</tei:hi></tei:foreign>, since no one <tei:supplied
            reason="clarity">else</tei:supplied> can attain the purity and systematic nature of the
          way you present it yourself. Publications about the work that you do ought always, in my
          view, to be limited just to specific issues, or to have the character of introductions to
          your work. I have attempted the latter in the most succinct form in the present piece of
          work, and in so doing have been at pains to keep myself entirely out of the matter, as you
          yourself, too, have felt when I read it <tei:supplied reason="clarity">to
            you</tei:supplied>. If even now, after the last set of improvements, you are still of
          the opinion that <tei:pb n="4"/> the balance between subject-matter and presentation has
          not been correctly struck at particular points, then it must surely be a matter of traces
          of a personality that in a presentation by another person of what were originally totally
          personal ideas can ultimately never be completely avoided. —</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="indent-20">I am now intensely occupied with preparations for the state
            examination.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> My wife<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> was so kind as to transcribe the article,
          thereby saving me the loss of much time as well as the costs of dictating it again to a
          typist.</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="indent-20">As you request, I herewith return the old copy to you with your
            annotations.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="indent-20">I assume that <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000195"
            >Einstein</tei:rs> will get back to me after submission of the article, at which point I
          can also put in a plea to him for a number of offprints.</tei:p>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-10">With most cordial greetings to you and your esteemed <tei:rs
              type="person" key="entity-000771">wife</tei:rs></tei:salute>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Your devoted</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed rend="indent-600"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000007">Gerhard
              Albersheim</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>
      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="part_2">
        <tei:opener/>
        <tei:lb/>

        <tei:p><tei:pb n="5"/> P. S. <tei:date when="1930-03-21">March 21</tei:date>
        </tei:p>

        <tei:p>Many thanks for your kind postcard.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/>
          In actual fact, a settlement of the matter as quickly as possible would suit me better.
          Since you will have the work in hand today, I would no longer need to call upon your
          precious time over the article next Wednesday. Write to me canceling the arrangement, if
          you are of the same mind, without ceremony! If on the other hand I hear <tei:hi
            rend="underline">nothing</tei:hi> more from you, I will come at the agreed time. </tei:p>


        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-40">With cordial greetings once again,</tei:salute>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-65">Your devoted</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000007">Gerhard
              Albersheim</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>
      </tei:div>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
