<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="2304" sdoID="OJ-15-16_21">OJ 15/16, [21]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HW" scope="sole">Hans Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2007</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="AH">
   <tei:persName>Alison Hiley</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2008</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-06-25" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated October 7, 1913</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1913-10-07T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-10-18</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Weisse extols the virtues of Schenker's monograph on Beethoven's Piano Sonata Op.
    109.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Studium; study; Satz; movement; Klarheit; clarity; Darstellung; presentation; präzis;
    precise; Sonate; sonata; Gesichtspünkt; aspect; Notenköpfe; noteheads; Monographie; monograph;
    Darlegung; analysis; Wahrheit; truth; Erforschung; research; objektiv; objective</dc:subject>



   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000951">Weisse</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HW"/>Mein geliebter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
      >Meister</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this
      letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 1/12, p. 437; the entry is dated October 6,
      however, whereas the letter is dated October 7, but there is no mistaking the identity of the
      letter from the reported content: "Schöner Brief von Weisse, geschrieben nach der Lektüre von
      op. 109; dazu besonders treffend hervorgehoben der Wert einer Arbeit wie der meinigen, im
      Interesse der Erforschung des Tonmaterials selbst, also eines Elementes, das absolut genommen
      von primärem Werte ist u. sozusagen über Beethoven steht!" ("A nice letter from Weisse,
      written after he had read Op. 109. What he highlights with particular trenchancy is the value
      of a piece of work such as mine for sake of the study of musical material itself, that is, of
      an element which, considered on its own, is of primary value, and stands above Beethoven, so
      to speak!").<tei:lb/>
       
       In a striking change of tone, on October 7 itself, at Weisse's lesson,
      Schenker's diary has a long paragraph beginning "Weisse fragt mich um die Höhe des Honorars
      ..." ("Weisse asks me about the amount of the lesson fee ..."), in which Schenker suspects
      Weisse is seeking a fee reduction since what was previously taught by two teachers (Schenker
      and Violin) is now taught by one! </tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Verzeihen Sie – aber ich kann nicht anders! Denn eben beende ich an Ihrer Hand das Studium
    des 1. Satzes von <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001734"><tei:title>op.
     109</tei:title></tei:rs>! Obgleich ich <tei:del rend="overstrike">doch</tei:del> vieles daraus <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">aus</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">von</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> mündlichen Auseinandersetzungen her kannte bin ich doch ganz hingerissen von der
    wundervollen Klarheit der Darstellung und von der Überwindung aller sprachlichen Hindernisse.
    Wie präzise, wie scharf die Ausführungen, wie sich in der <tei:term>Darstellung</tei:term> einer
    Sonate, sämtliche Gesichtspünkte der <tei:term>zyklischen Form</tei:term> überhaupt offenbaren!
    Wie lächerlich kleinlich alle <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055"
    >Beethoven</tei:rs>-Anekdoten Krämerei neben dieser Rekonstruktion seines Geistes! Wie jene
    gerade durch Ihr Tun das Bewusstsein seines Todes erhöht, so verwandeln sich <tei:add
     place="interlinear-above">mittels <tei:choice>
      <tei:sic>ihrer</tei:sic>
      <tei:corr>Ihrer</tei:corr>
     </tei:choice> kritischen Phantasie</tei:add> die Notenköpfe in kleine transparente
    Homunkulüsse, <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">aus</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">in</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> deren Innern, die Seele des toten Meisters leuchtet. Abgesehen von allen
    technischen Fehlern bilden <tei:add place="interlinear-above">die</tei:add> Monographien etc.
    der andern nichts als pompöse Heiligsprechungen eines Genies<tei:supplied reason="punctuation"
     >.</tei:supplied></tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Sie aber, <tei:hi rend="underline">legen die Gesetze der Unsterblichkeit
     frei</tei:hi>! Sie definieren den Begriff des Künstlers, von dem die anderen <tei:add
     place="interlinear-above">als gegebenen</tei:add> ausgehen!! Und hierin liegt die groteske
    Impotenze aller biographischen Unternehmungen, die sich in ihrer literarischen Ubersicht so
    selbstverständlich entpuppt: Überkommenem <tei:choice>
     <tei:sic>Vertrauend</tei:sic>
     <tei:corr>vertrauend</tei:corr>
    </tei:choice> ist der Name <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">ihm</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ihnen</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> die erste Gewähr zur sogennanten kritischen Tätigkeit: Ihre wundervolle
     <tei:term>Darlegung</tei:term>, lässt im objectivsten Sinne ein namenloses, künstlerisches
    absolutes Empfinden walten, <tei:del rend="overstrike">deren</tei:del> alle Situationen
     prüfen<tei:supplied reason="omission">d,</tei:supplied> bis es zu<tei:del rend="overstrike"
     >r</tei:del> einem vollendeten Gesamteindrucke kommt; dies ist die gleiche Wahrheit, vor der
    einst <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> gestanden hat!! So ist das
    Aufschauen zu <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">Beethoven</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ihm</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> dem blinden Götzendienst nicht gleich, weil in seiner Erforschung die Entdeckung
    eines Höheren mitgegeben ist: Das Eigenleben des Materials! – was nichts andres als die
    Eindeutigkeit, die Notwendig<tei:supplied reason="omission">keit</tei:supplied> und mithin die
    Möglichkeit einer objectiven <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">Kunsttrachtungs</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">Betrachtungs</tei:add>
    </tei:subst><tei:del rend="overstrike">möglichkeit</tei:del> der Musik besagt! </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Ich danke Ihnen im Namen einer noch unmündigen
     Menschheit!</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
     >Hans</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:date when="1913-10-07">7 October 13</tei:date>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HW"/>My beloved <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
      >Master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Apologies ‒ but I cannot help it! For I am just finishing studying the first movement of
     <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001734"><tei:title level="m">Op. 109</tei:title></tei:rs> with
    the help of you<tei:supplied reason="clarity">r interpretation</tei:supplied>! Although I was
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">indeed</tei:del> familiar with much of the content from hearing you
    expound <tei:supplied reason="clarity">it</tei:supplied> in person, I am utterly overcome by the
    wonderful clarity of expression and the manner in which you overcome all linguistic obstacles.
    How precisely and clearly all the aspects of the <tei:term>cyclical form</tei:term> can be
    revealed in the <tei:term>analysis</tei:term> of a sonata! How laughably insignificant all the
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> anecdotes seem, <tei:supplied
     reason="clarity">how</tei:supplied> petty next to this reconstruction of his spirit! In the
    same way that you effect through the latter the heightened awareness of his death, so, <tei:add
     place="interlinear-above">by means of your critical imagination</tei:add>, the heads of the
    notes transform into transparent little homunculi, <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">out of</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">within</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> whose hearts the soul of the dead master shines. Quite apart from all the technical
    errors, <tei:add place="interlinear-above">the</tei:add> monographs etc. of others constitute
    nothing other than pompous adulation of a man of genius.</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> You, however, <tei:hi rend="underline">lay bare the laws of
     immortality</tei:hi>! You <tei:supplied reason="clarity">actually</tei:supplied> define the
    concept of the artist, while the others set out with this <tei:add place="interlinear-above">as
     a given</tei:add>!! And herein lies the grotesque impotence of all those biographical attempts
    ‒ the literary perspective there proves to be so predictable. Relying on convention, the name
     <tei:supplied reason="clarity">alone</tei:supplied> is to them the first guarantee of so called
    critical activity. Your wonderful <tei:term>analysis</tei:term>
    <tei:supplied reason="clarity">on the other hand</tei:supplied> creates, in the most objective
    sense, a nameless, artistically absolute feeling which examines all situations until it reaches
    a perfect overall impression; this is the same truth which once confronted <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>!! Looking up to <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">Beethoven</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">him</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> cannot therefore be equated with blind idolatry because the discovery of a higher
    being is imparted in <tei:supplied reason="clarity">the act of</tei:supplied> researching him ‒
    the material has a life of its own! ‒ which means nothing more than the clearness, the necessity
    and therefore the possibility of an objective <tei:del rend="overstrike">possible</tei:del> view
    of music! </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">I thank you in the name of a humanity which has not yet attained
     its majority!</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
     >Hans</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:date when="1913-10-07">October 7, 1913</tei:date>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
