<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2318" sdoID="OJ-15-16_27">OJ 15/16, [27]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HW" scope="sole">Hans Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:respStmt xml:id="AH">
      <tei:persName>Alison Hiley</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2008</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-06-25" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated August 3, 1916</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1916-08-03T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-10-29</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Weisse hopes to see Kontrapunkt II soon. — He reflects on the state of
        humanity in the light of being in the midst of the war. — He incloses a cutting of an
        article [about sources of Saint-Saëns's music.]</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Ungestörtheit; tranquillity; Natur; Nature; Arbeit; work; mässig; middling;
        Lebensanschauung; view of life; Veränderung; difference; Unveränderte; lack of change;
        Typus; (character-)type; Bazillus; bacillus; Menscheit; humanity; Krieg; war; Aufsatz;
        article; Beschäftigung; occupation; Bild; picture</dc:subject>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000951">Weisse</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HW"/>Liebster, verehrter <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
            place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at p. 366, August 7,
            1916: "Von Hans Weisse Br. mit Beilage: einem Aufsatz Zschorlichs contra Saint-Saëns in
            Fragen der deutschen Ausgaben, die St . S. als inkorrekt bekämpfte. Herr Z. machte sich
            die Sache leicht, indem er lediglich von offenbaren Druckfehlern spricht, u., um
            deutsche Druckfehler zu verteidigen, französische unterstreicht. Also Druckfehler gegen
            Druckfehler ‒ Im übrigen bot Weisses gut geschriebenes Briefchen ein zeitgetreues
            Stimmungsbild." <tei:lb/>("From Hans Weisse, letter with inclosure: an article by
            Zschorlich contra Saint-Saëns on questions of German editions that Saint-Saëns combatted
            as incorrect. Mr. Z. makes the matter easy for himself in that he speaks only of obvious
            printing errors and in order to defend German printing errors he accentuates French
            ones. Thus printing error against printing error. ‒ As for the rest, Weisse's
            well-written little letter presented an atmospheric picture true to its times.")
          </tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>So oft wollte ich noch daransetzen, Ihnen zu schreiben, aber immer und immer wieder kam
        etwas ganz Unwichtiges dazwischen, das mich nichts desto weniger davon abhielt. Was ich
        empfand, als ich hörte, dass <tei:choice>
          <tei:sic>sie ihrer</tei:sic>
          <tei:corr>Sie Ihrer</tei:corr>
        </tei:choice> kostbaren Arbeit erhalten bleiben, können Sie sich ja vorstellen. Nur hoffe
        ich in unser aller Interesse<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> dass wir
          <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001727"><tei:title>II/2</tei:title></tei:rs><tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The publication of the second
          half-volume of <tei:title level="m">Kontrapunkt</tei:title> has yet again been held
          up.</tei:note> bereits im friedlichen Arbeitszimmer werden lesen können und nicht hier, wo
        doch immer der Geist abgelenkt wird. Ich habe jetzt die Überzeugung gewonnen, dass ich,
        zurückgekommen, mit <tei:term>Generalbass</tei:term> nochmals werde anfangen müssen – und
        das wird keiner Wiederholung gleichen!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
          place="foot">No paragraph-break in original at this point.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich beneide Sie <tei:unclear reason="reading">nun</tei:unclear> die Ungestörtheit mit
        der <tei:choice>
          <tei:sic>sie</tei:sic>
          <tei:corr>Sie</tei:corr>
        </tei:choice> in gleicher Weise Natur wie Arbeit geniessen können; mir geht’s obzwar nicht
        schlecht, in dieser Beziehung doch recht mässig, denn der geistige Kontakt vermag hier nur
        sehr spärliche Funken zu erzeugen: der Mensch sammelt alle Überreste der hiesischen Natur,
        die sich in ihm vorfinden gewissermassen auf einem Punkt zusammen, und macht diesen zum
        Standpunkte seiner Lebensanschauung. Rückwärts macht alles anderen Eindruck und man hat die
        Vorstellung einer Veränderung: aber hier<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Weisse was on war service at this time; his precise location is
          unknown.</tei:note> erkennt man das Unveränderte – von jeher Bestehende! Was sollte auch
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above"><tei:choice>
            <tei:sic>einen</tei:sic>
            <tei:corr>einem</tei:corr>
          </tei:choice></tei:add>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000712">Riemann</tei:rs><tei:supplied reason="punctuation"
          >-,</tei:supplied>
        <tei:pb n="2"/>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000838">Specht</tei:rs><tei:supplied reason="punctuation"
          >-</tei:supplied>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000424">Karpath</tei:rs><tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">-</tei:supplied>typus Ursache zur Veränderung bieten?<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Allusion is to the study of character
          features (<tei:hi rend="italic">Charakterkunde</tei:hi>).</tei:note> Es giebt keine
        Hoffnungsberechtigung auf bessere, kommende Zeiten, bevor der Bazillus nicht gefunden ist,
        der jene Charakterköpfe aus dem viel<tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">köp</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">kantigen</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> Profile der Menschheit <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">aust</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">abzehrt</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>! Wenn man hie und da in eines der Rasumofsky Quartette untertaucht, so hat man
        die Empfindung, als gäbe es immer weiter Frieden auf der Welt, und der Krieg und die grosse
          Zeit<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:title level="j">Die
            Grosse Zeit</tei:title>: i.e. the Great War ‒ phrase taken from a contemporary history
          periodical.</tei:note> wären die unwichtigsten Geschehnisse!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Anbei einen Aufsatz aus irgend einer säglichen-kläglichen Rundschau<tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> die hier aufliegt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07"
          type="editorial" place="foot">For Schenker's description of this newspaper cutting, see
          footnote 1. The article was: <tei:bibl><tei:author>Paul Zschorlich</tei:author>,
              <tei:title level="a">Offener Brief an Saint-Saëns,</tei:title>
            <tei:title level="j">Tägliche Runschau</tei:title>, c. June 24, 1916</tei:bibl>; the
          cutting is preserved as OC 38/2‒3.</tei:note> Von meiner Beschäftigung denke ich <tei:del
          rend="overstrike">hier</tei:del> in nächster Zeit Ihnen ein genaueres Bild zu
        geben!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Ich grüsse Sie, wie die liebe gnädige <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000771">Frau</tei:rs> aufs Allerherzlichste</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">und bin ganz Ihr getreuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
          >Hans</tei:rs>.</tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:date when="1916-08-03">3. August. 16</tei:date>.</tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HW"/>Dearest, revered <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000632">Master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"
          /></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>I have wanted to sit down to write to you so often but again and again something
        insignificant came in the way and kept me from doing so. You can well imagine how I felt
        when I heard that you are continuing with your valuable work. I only hope that in all our
        interests we shall soon be able to read <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001727"
            ><tei:title>II/2</tei:title></tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> in
        a peaceful study and not here, where one's mind is always distracted. I am now convinced
        that once I return I shall have to start over again with <tei:term>basso continuo</tei:term>
        ‒ and no revision will be equal to it!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"
        /></tei:p>

      <tei:p>I do envy you the tranquillity in which you can enjoy Nature and work in equal measure,
        although things are not going badly for me, indeed in this respect they are middling, for
        intellectual discourse here is only able to generate very meagre sparks: all that does
        remain of nature here is in some way gathered together in one place within men, and that
        place becomes the source of their view of life. Everything looks different over one's
        shoulder and it seems as if things have changed: but here<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
          type="footnote"/> one sees that which has not changed ‒ that which has existed from time
        immemorial! What can character types such as <tei:add place="interlinear-above">a</tei:add>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000712">Riemann</tei:rs>, <tei:pb n="2"/> a <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000838">Specht</tei:rs> or a <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000424">Karpath</tei:rs> offer us as cause for change?<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> There can be no justification for hoping for
        better times to come until the bacillus is found which <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >causes emaciation</tei:add> in those distinctive features of the many<tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">-sided</tei:add> profile of humanity! If now and then one can
        lose oneself in a Rasumovsky Quartet, one has the feeling that there still is peace in the
        world, and that the War and These Important Times<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06"
          type="footnote"/> are the most insignificant of events!</tei:p>

      <tei:p> I am enclosing an article from some petty-pitiful chronicle which is available
          here.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> I intend to give you a more exact
        idea here of how my time is spent very soon!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Most heartfelt greetings to yourself, and to your good <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000771">lady</tei:rs></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">and I remain your trusty</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
          >Hans</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:date when="1916-08-03">August 3, 1916</tei:date></tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
