<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2051" sdoID="OJ-13-25_5">OJ 13/25, [5]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPhr" scope="major">Hermann Rinn as typist</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed-red" scope="minor">printed (red)</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed-black" scope="minor">printed (black)</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HR" scope="minor">Hermann Rinn's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>


    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2017</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2017</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2018</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2012-09-26" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006727">Kunstwart ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006729">RinnH ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Typewritten letter from Rinn to Schenker, dated March 7, 1929</dc:title>
      <dcterms:created>1929-03-07T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2018-01-31</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Rinn apologizes for the small format in which the autograph of Schubert's
        minuet was reproduced for Schenker's article "Eine Rettung der klassischen Musik-Texte." He
        has publicized the work, and intends to send copies of it to university music departments
        and inform other newspapers and journals of it. He expresses thanks for the efforts that
        Schenker made in contributing to Der Kunstwart, and for his remarks on Bruckner's Ninth
        Symphony.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Verkleinerung; reduction; Format; Querstellung; sideways placement; Lobe; praise;
        Faksimile-Blatt; facsimile page; Seminar; music department; Kosten; costs; Heft; issue;
        Bogen; gathering; Redaktion; editorial office; Aufsatz; article; Zeitung; newspaper;
        Ordinarius; university lecturer; Presse; journalistic community; Beitrag;
        contribution</dc:subject>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-006727">Der Kunstwart</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000717">Hermann Rinn</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-30"><tei:handShift new="#printed-red"/><tei:hi rend="bold">Der
              Kunstwart</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed-black"/>____________________</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-20">Schriftleitung: Dr. Hermann Rinn / Verlag Georg D. W.
            Callwey</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-40">München NW 12, Finkenstr. 2</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#TPhr"/><tei:date when="1929-03-07">7. 3.
          29</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">All corrections in the text are in the hand of
          Hermann Rinn.</tei:note>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Sehr verehrter Herr Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000632"
            type="person">Schenker</tei:rs>:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
            place="foot">Receipt of this letter is not recorded in Schenker's diary.
          </tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Entschuldigen Sie bitte, dass ich Sie seit 14 Tagen ohne Nachricht liess.
        Es hatte sich eine solche Unmenge von dringender <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >Red.-</tei:add>Arbeit angestaut, dass ich nicht dazu kam, ausserdem habe ich seit Wochen
        mit Migräne und Grippenanfällen zu kämpfen. Lassen Sie mich wenigstens jet<tei:add
          place="inline">zt</tei:add> auf das herzlichste danken für die grosse Mühe, der Sie sich
        noch einmal haben unterziehen müssen. Hoffentlich ist jetzt nun auch alles in Ordnung und
        stimmen die Zeichen; diese technische Dingen machen am Ende immer die allergrössten
        Schwierigkeiten. Die Verkleinerung musste des Formats wegen leider sehr weit getrieben
          werden.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The facsimile pages of
          the autograph manuscript of the Minuet from Schubert's Sonata in G major, Op. 78, which
          was the subject of Schenker's article in <tei:title level="j">Der Kunstwart</tei:title>.
          These were reduced to less than a quarter of their original size. </tei:note> Ich hatte
        erst gedacht, dass wir mit der Querstellung auf ein grösseres Format kommen könnten, es
        liess sich aber nicht machen. Inzwischen bin ich schon von <tei:sic>mehereren</tei:sic>
        Seiten angerufen worden und höre überall Worte des Lobes, dass wir uns für diese Sache
        eingesetzt haben. Ich hoffe also, dass Sie sich nicht vergebe<tei:add place="inline"
          >ns</tei:add> bemüht haben.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Gleichzeitig erhalten Sie eine grössere Anzahl des <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overwritten">f</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="superimposed">F</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>aks.-Blattes. Verwenden Sie bitte für die Bogen, die wir Ihnen schickten, was
        Sie brauchen. Für den Rest hat vielleicht das <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002452">Archiv</tei:rs> Verwendung; wenn nicht, können die Blätter ruhig
        vernichtet werden. Möglicherweise ist aber das eine oder andere Seminar froh, einen Abzug zu
        haben.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"> Die Hefte sind an die von Ihnen <tei:pb n="2"/> angegebenen 6 Adressen
        geschickt worden, mit einer Karte, dass es in Ihrem Auftrag geschah. Es versteht sich von
        selbst, dass wir Ihnen dafür keine Kosten aufrechnen. Brauchen Sie übrigens nicht noch
        Hefte? Ich kann Ihnen gerne noch 10-20 Stück schicken. Fordern Sie bitte unbedenklich an!
        Die überschiessenden Bogen steh<tei:supplied reason="omission">e</tei:supplied>n mit den
        Heften nicht im Zusammenhang, sie sind für Sie bestimmt.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich habe von der Redaktion aus an <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003051">Karl
          Holl</tei:rs> von der <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002537"><tei:title>Frankfurter
            Zeitung</tei:title></tei:rs> und an <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000195">Alfred
          Einstein</tei:rs> geschrieben, auf den Aufsatz hingewiesen, Hefte geschickt und gebeten in
        ihren Zeitungen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">At the time,
          Einstein was the editor of the <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002480"><tei:title
              level="j">Zeitschrift für Musikwissenschaft</tei:title></tei:rs>.</tei:note> eine
        Notiz zu bringen. Heute schreibe ich an Herrn von Pander von den <tei:rs type="journal"
          key="entity-002552"><tei:title>Münchner Neuesten</tei:title></tei:rs>. Desgleichen will
        ich an die Ordinarien der Universitäten je ein Heft schicken und der gesamten Presse einen
        kurzen Auszug vorlegen (10-12 Sätze wenigstens), wenn es Ihnen so recht ist.
        Selbstverständlich gehen auch <tei:add place="interlinear-above">an</tei:add> die
        Musikzeitschriften Hefte bezw. Mitteilungen, da wir sowieso mit den meisten in Tausch
        stehen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Für Ihre Mitteilung über <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000104"
          >Bruckner</tei:rs>s <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001386"
            ><tei:title>IX.</tei:title></tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Writing of a letter to Rinn with remarks on Bruckner's symphonies is recorded
          in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/1, p. 3318, March 6, 1928: "An D<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
            >r.</tei:hi> Rinn (Br.): bitte um die Facsimiles; erzähle bei dieser Gelegenheit, was
          ich von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000320">Haas</tei:rs> über die wahre Gestalt der
          Bruckner-Sinfonien erfahren habe." ("To Dr. Rinn (letter): I request the facsimiles; I use
          the occasion to say what I have learned from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000320"
            >Haas</tei:rs> about the true design of Bruckner's symphonies").</tei:note> bin ich
        Ihnen sehr dankbar.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Lassen Sie mich zum Schluss noch einmal herzlich danken für den Beitrag
        und lassen Sie mich versichern, dass es mir eine Ehre und grosse Freude ist, wenn Sie den
          <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-003014"><tei:title>Kunstwart</tei:title></tei:rs>
        bedenken.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr herzlich ergebener</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#HR"/><tei:rs key="entity-000717"
            type="person">R.</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-30"><tei:handShift new="#printed-red"/><tei:hi rend="bold">Der
              Kunstwart</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed-black"/>____________________</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-20">Editorship: Dr. Hermann Rinn / Publisher Georg D. W.
            Callwey</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-40">Munich NW 12, Finkenstraße 2</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#TPhr"/><tei:date when="1929-03-07">March 7,
            1929</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">All corrections in the text are in the hand of
          Hermann Rinn.</tei:note>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Highly revered Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"
            >Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Please excuse me for not sending you any news in the last two weeks. Such
        a large pile of important <tei:add place="interlinear-above">editorial</tei:add> work had
        piled up that I was unable to get to it; in addition I have been battling for weeks with
        migraine headaches and attacks of the flu. At least let me thank you most cordially now for
        the great trouble to which you have had to go. I hope that now everything is in order, and
        the <tei:supplied reason="clarity">performance</tei:supplied> remarks are correct; these
        technical things always cause the greatest difficulties of all in the end. The size
        reduction had, unfortunately, to be carried out very drastically on account of the
          <tei:supplied reason="clarity">page</tei:supplied> format.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> I had initially thought that we could have used a larger format by
        sideways placement, but this was not possible. In the meantime, I have received telephone
        calls from several people and hear words of praise everywhere. I hope, then, that your
        efforts have not been in vain.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">At the same time you will receive a large number of facsimile leaves.
        Please use whatever you need for the gatherings that we sent you. Perhaps the <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archive</tei:rs> will be able to make use of the
        rest; if not, the leaves can be destroyed. Maybe some <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
          >music</tei:supplied> department or other will be happy to have a copy.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">The copies of the issue have been sent to the <tei:pb n="2"/> six
        addresses you provided, with a card to the effect that this was done on your behalf. It goes
        without saying that we shall not charge you for any of this. Do you need any further copies?
        I can gladly send your a further ten to twenty copies. Please do not hesitate to ask! The
        extra gatherings are unrelated to the <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
          >complimentary</tei:supplied> copies of the issue, they are meant for you.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I have, in my capacity as editor, referred <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003051"
          >Karl Holl</tei:rs> at the <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002537"><tei:title level="j"
            >Frankfurter Zeitung</tei:title></tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000195"
          >Alfred Einstein</tei:rs> to your essay, sent them copies of the issue, and requested that
        they put a note in their journals.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> Today I
        shall write to Mr. Pander at the <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002552"><tei:title
            level="j">Münchner Neueste</tei:title></tei:rs>. At the same time I shall send one issue
        each to the chairs of the university <tei:supplied reason="clarity">music
          departments</tei:supplied> and present the entire journalistic community with a short
        extract (at least ten to twelve sentences), if that is agreeable to you. Of course copies or
        communications will also go <tei:add place="interlinear-above">to</tei:add> the music
        periodicals, since in any event we have a reciprocal arrangement with most of them.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">For your communication about <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000104"
          >Bruckner</tei:rs>'s <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001386"
            ><tei:title>Ninth</tei:title></tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/>
        I am very grateful.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">To conclude, let me thank you cordially once more for the essay; and let
        me assure you that it is an honor and a great joy to me if you keep <tei:rs type="journal"
          key="entity-003014"><tei:title level="j">Der Kunstwart</tei:title></tei:rs> in
        mind.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your cordially devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#HR"/><tei:rs key="entity-000717"
            type="person">R.</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
