<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="656" sdoID="OJ-10-1_82">OJ 10/1, [82]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>
    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="WD" scope="sole">Walter Dahms's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="JK">
      <tei:persName>John Koslovsky</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2011</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2011</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2011-12-20" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>

  </sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002725">Dahms ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Dahms to Schenker, dated December 28, 1923</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1923-12-28T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2011-12-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Dahms gratefully acknowledges receipt of a grant from Schenker, reports on his
        book writing, and sends New Year greetings to Heinrich and Jeanette. </dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Summe; sum; money; Betrag; payment; Weihnachten; Christmas; Fixum; fixed payment;
        Wüste; desert </dc:subject>

      
      
    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000149">Dahms</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">Roma</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">via Sardegna 79</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1923-11-20">28. XII. 23.</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Lieber und verehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/5, p. 2615, January 1, 1924: "Von
            Dahms (Br.): dankt für die Liebenswürdigkeit der Zuwendung, erwartet ein besseres Jahr."
            ("From Dahms (letter): thanks for the courtesy of the donation, expects a better
            year."). </tei:note>
        </tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Herzlichsten Dank für Ihren lieben Brief.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter, which is not known to survive, is
          recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/5, p. 2610, December 23, 1923: "An Dahms (Br.):
          erkläre die Herkunft der 1½ Millionen, bitte zu entschuldigen, daß ich ohne zu fragen
          geschickt habe." ("To Dahms (letter): explain the origin of the one-and-a-half million,
          ask him to excuse me for sending without asking."). In this connection, his diary also
          records for December 24: "Von Mozio (Br.): habe an Dahms 487 Lire angewiesen – die
          Angelegenheit sei „beglichen“ [...]" ("From Mozio (letter): has remitted 487 lire to Dahms
          – the matter is "resolved" [...]"). The money is likely to have been one of the stipends
          for "impecunious skilled composers and similarly qualified composition pupils" bequeathed
          in the will of Sofie Deutsch (d. 1917) and left in the gift of Schenker. </tei:note> Es
        ist wirklich zu viel des Guten, dass Sie in dieser Weise meiner gedacht haben. Hätten Sie
        diese Summe nicht besser für Ihre eigenen Arbeiten irgendwie verwenden können? — Doch, ohne
        viel Worte: meinen allerherzlichsten Dank, auch von Seiten meiner <tei:rs key="entity-002817" type="person">Frau</tei:rs>. Wir werden den Betrag bestens verwenden.
        – Die Weihnachtstage vergingen still, wesentlich angenehmer als im vorigen Jahr. Der hiesige
        deutsche Botschafter kaufte zu Weihnachten ein Exemplar der Subskriptions-Ausgabe.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">The de-luxe edition of
              <tei:bibl><tei:author>Dahms</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Musik des
              Südens</tei:title> (Stuttgart: Deutsche Verlags-Anstalt, 1923)</tei:bibl>, of which
          only one hundred copies were printed. Schenker recorded in his diary at OJ 3/5, p. 2604,
          December 7: "Dahms Buch „Musik des Südens“, vom Verlag zugeschickt." ("Dahms's book
            <tei:title level="m">Music of the South</tei:title>, sent by publishing house.").
        </tei:note> 1924 sehen wir mit einiger Hoffnung auf <tei:del rend="overstrike">W</tei:del>
        weitere Besserung und Stabilisierung unserer Verhältnisse entgegen. An Arbeiten muss ich bis
        Mai den <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person">Haydn</tei:rs> abgeliefert haben und den
          <tei:term>Belcanto</tei:term> weiter fördern. Dafür zahlt der <tei:rs key="entity-002985" type="organization">Verleger</tei:rs> nun ein kleines monatliches Fixum. Doch hängt alles
        von der Entwicklung der politischen Lage ab, wie weit die Versprechen reichen u. wie lange
        sie durchführbar sind. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> Ich freue mich, dass Sie die „<tei:title>Musik des
          Südens</tei:title>“ erhalten haben und bin begierig, Ihr Urteil zu hören. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Auf Ihre Mitteilungen über <tei:rs key="entity-003139" type="person">Castiglione</tei:rs> bin ich sehr gespannt. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Hier liegt mit der Musik u. ihrer Ausübung alles im argen; das Wort
        „Wüste“ ist zu schade dafür, denn darunter stellt sich man etwas Grandioses u. Erhabenes
        vor. – Kürzlich lernte ich einen jungen Italiener kennen, der, seit seiner Jugend in
        deutscher Literatur lebend, von <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Deutschland</tei:country></tei:rs> träumend; sich seiner Landsleute
        schämt, die <tei:rs key="entity-000612" type="person">Mozart</tei:rs> nicht lieben; er hat
        sich mir sehr angeschlossen. So trifft man doch dann und wann auf einen wertvollen Menschen.
        — </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich fühle mich zu müde, um einen vernünftigen Brief zustande bringen zu
        können. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Lassen Sie mich <tei:del rend="overstrike">mich</tei:del> Ihnen nochmals
        von Herzen danken. </tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Zum Neuen Jahre von Herzen alles Gute für Sie u. Ihre<tei:del rend="overstrike">r</tei:del> verehrte <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Frau
            Gemahlin</tei:rs>
        </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">– auch von meiner <tei:rs key="entity-002817" type="person">Frau</tei:rs> – </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr stets dankbarer </tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000149">Walter
          Dahms</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">Rome</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">via Sardegna 79</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1923-11-20">December 28, 1923</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dear and revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
        </tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Many thanks for your kind letter.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> It is really just too good of you to have thought of me in this way.
        Could you not have used this money better for your own work in some way? – All the same,
        without many words: my sincerest thanks to you, also on behalf of my <tei:rs key="entity-002817" type="person">wife</tei:rs>. We will make the best possible use of the
        money. – The Christmas days go by quietly, essentially more pleasant than in the previous
        year. The local German ambassador bought a copy of the subscription edition<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> for Christmas. For 1924 we look forward with hope
        to further improvement and stability of our relations. For my work I have to have the
          <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person">Haydn</tei:rs> book delivered by May and I have
        to make further headway with the <tei:term><tei:hi rend="italic">bel
          canto</tei:hi></tei:term> book. For this the <tei:rs key="entity-002985" type="organization">publisher</tei:rs> now pays a small monthly fixed sum. But everything
        depends on how political conditions develop, how far the financial assurances will last and
        how long they are viable. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> I am happy that you have received <tei:title level="m">Music of the South</tei:title> and I am eager to hear your opinion. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I am looking forward very keenly to your report on <tei:rs key="entity-003139" type="person">Castiglioni</tei:rs>. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Here music and the way it is practiced is in total disorder; the word
        "desert" is too good a word, since underneath it one imagines something grandiose and
        sublime. – Recently I met a young Italian who having been immersed in German literature
        since his youth and dreamed of <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Germany</tei:country></tei:rs> was embarrassed by his own countrymen, who
        did not like <tei:rs key="entity-000612" type="person">Mozart</tei:rs>. He has really become
        attached to me. Every now and again one meets such a worthwhile person. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I feel too tired to be able to write an intelligible letter. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Let me thank you once again from the bottom of my heart. </tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">For the New Year all the best to you and your revered <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs>
        </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">– also from my <tei:rs key="entity-002817" type="person">wife</tei:rs> – </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your ever thankful </tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000149">Walter
          Dahms</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>