<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2884" sdoID="OJ-15-6_8">OJ 15/6, [8]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="FW" scope="sole">Fritz Wahle's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2022</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2011-09-23" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008359">WahleF ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Fritz Wahle to Schenker, dated October 7, ?1910</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1910-10-07T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2022-10-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Fritz Wahle thanks Schenker for sending him his latest book -- almost
        certainly the first half-volume of Kontrapunkt; he has looked through the table of contents
        and read the introduction. He hopes that the two of them could get together
        sometime.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000925">WahleF</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address rend="indent-60">
          <tei:addrLine>Wien <tei:date when="1910-10-07">7. 10</tei:date> nachts</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>nicht im Wirtshause</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Als mir heute nachmittag Dein Buch gebracht wurde<tei:supplied reason="punctuation"
          >,</tei:supplied>
        <tei:del rend="overstrike">ruch</tei:del> rief ich meiner Köchen zu „also ist es schon da“.
        Ich tat das nicht, weil ich etwa <tei:add place="interlinear-above">mit</tei:add> dieser
          kontrapunctiere,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Wahle’s joke
          about being “in counterpoint” with his cook suggests that this book is the first
          half-volume of <tei:bibl><tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001726"><tei:title level="m"
                >Kontrapunkt</tei:title></tei:rs> (Stuttgart: J. G. Cotta, 1910)</tei:bibl>,
          released on October 4, 1910. If Schenker sent Wahle a copy on or soon after that date,
          then this letter of acknowledgement – in which the year of writing is not specified – can
          safely be dated to the year 1910. The implication of a substantial table of contents, on
          the second page of the letter, confirms that this is detailed theoretical work. A month
          later, in a letter dated November 10, 1910, Wahle mentions a book of Schenker’s that will
          take him a long time to finish reading; this is probably the same work.</tei:note> sondern
        mir war ähnlich zu Mute, wie etwa bei einer Geburtstagüberraschung. Dass Dein Muss-Fleiß
        Dich dem Ziele nah gebracht – du hast des ja eigentlich schon erreicht – hat mich wirklich
        gefreut, und dass du auch gleich an mich gedacht hast ist für mich ehrend und hat mir
        aufrichtige Freude bereitet. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun habe ich das Vorwort gelesen: Der kühne entschlossene Ton desselben zeugt für
        deinen heiligen Ernst, für die sichere Ueberzeugung, für die große Arbeit wahr, richtig zu
        sein, und nur das zu sagen<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> was Du
        vorantreiben kannst kraft deiner tiefen Studien und der strengsten Ehrlichkeit gegen die
        Sache, gegen Dich und gegen die, zu denen Du sprechen willst. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Ich habe mich seit den Ferien auch theoretisch beschäftigt und erlaube
        mir mich zu denen zu zählen, die Dein Buch mit Fleiß lesen werden, ich bin dir nach
        Durchlesung des Inhaltsverzeichnisses und einen Blick in die Einleitung <tei:del
          rend="overstrike">si</tei:del> im vorhinein dankbar für Belehrung und
          Anregung<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> die ich mir sicher aus Deinem
        Werke ver<tei:del rend="overstrike">f</tei:del>greifen kann. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Also nun meinen wärmsten Dank für die freundschaftliche Sendung Deines Buches und die
        besten Wünsche für sein Wirken. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Könnten wir auch am Abend einmal treffen. Ich bin jetzt abends viel zuhause – komme
        aber gerne in eine beliebigeres Wirtshaus. Uebrigens kannst du auch, wenn es dir
          passt<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> bei mir nachtmalen. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Die besten Grüße</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Dein</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000925"
          >Fritz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000926">Richard</tei:rs> grüßt dich wol auch
          bestens; ich kann ihm dein Buch erst morgen zeigen. </tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address rend="indent-60">
          <tei:addrLine>Vienna, <tei:date when="1910-10-07">October 7</tei:date>,
            evening</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>not in the tavern</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>When your book was brought to me this afternoon, I cried out to my cook: “Well, it is
        already there.” I did that not because I wanted perhaps to be in counterpoint <tei:add
          rend="overstrike">with</tei:add> her,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> but
        rather because I was feeling in a mood similar to one resulting from, say, a birthday
        surprise. That your compulsive industry has brought you close to your goal – you have, in
        fact, already reached it – has truly pleased me; and that you also thought of me at the same
        time is an honor for me, and has furnished me with heartfelt joy.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I have now read the Foreword: its bold, decisive tone bears true witness to your holy
        seriousness, to your secure conviction, and to your great work being correct, and to your
        saying only what you are able to promote on the strength of your deep learning and most
        rigorous honesty concerning the subject, concerning yourself, and concerning those to whom
        you wish to speak.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Since the holidays I, too, have occupied myself with theoretical
        matters and allow myself to be reckoned among those who will read your book assiduously.
        Having read through the table of contents and looked at the introduction, I am grateful to
        you in advance for the teaching and stimulation that I shall surely be able to derive from
        your work. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>And so my warmest thanks for having kindly sent me your book, and the best wishes for
        its success.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Could we also get together some evening? Nowadays I am often at home in the evening,
        but I would be happy to get to any tavern. Moreover you could also have supper with me, if
        that is convenient for you.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">With best greetings, </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000925"
          >Fritz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000926">Richard</tei:rs> also sends you his best
          greetings; I cannot show him your book until tomorrow.</tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
