<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3087" sdoID="OJ-10-3_104">OJ 10/3, [104]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPoed" scope="major">Otto Erich Deutsch typist</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="OED" scope="minor">Otto Erich Deutsch's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2023</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IDB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2015-09-18" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002726">DeutschOE ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002712">DeutschOE ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002727">DeutschOE+H ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Typewritten letter from Deutsch to Schenker, dated July 28, 1929</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1929-07-28T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2023-03-16</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>In a long letter, Deutsch thanks Schenker for encouraging him to apply for the
        post of Head Archivist at the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde following the death of the
        previous postholder, Eusebius Mandyczewski, on July 13. He comments on the present state of
        play at the Archive, above all on its insecure position. — He also expresses his regret that
        Austrian Radio is no longer interested in his “Chamber Ensemble” broadcasts with professors
        from the Vienna Academy, and that some of the players are no longer enthusiastic about them;
        he hopes to start a new initiative of that sort in the autumn. — He is in good standing with
        Hoboken, but the work on his private library is not bringing him rewards. — He enjoyed his
        recent trip to Italy, and thinks that he might have become an art historian had he gotten to
        know the country earlier.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000164">DeutschOE</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>PROF. OTTO ERICH DEUTSCH</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">WIEN II. </tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Böcklinstraße 26</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/><tei:date when="1929-07-28">28.
            Juli 1929</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber verehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Doktor</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for July 30, 1929: “Von Deutsch (Br.):
            Mandyczewski habe 200 S. monatlich gehabt! Beklagt sich über Launen bei v. Hoboken”
            (“From Deutsch (letter): Mandyczewski earned 200 shillings per month! He complains about
            Hoboken’s mood”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>


      <tei:p rend="first">Es war sehr lieb, dass Sie sich aus diesem – sehr traurigen – Anlass
        meiner erinnerten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker’s
          diary for July 20, 1929 records the writing of a letter to Deutsch which is summarized as
          follows: “An Deutsch (Br.): möchte glauben, daß Mandyczewski’s Stelle für ihn passend
          wäre” (“To Deutsch (letter): I should like to think that Mandyczewski’s post would suit
          him”). </tei:note> Auch mein Freund Otto Stoessl hat mich mit solcher Aufmunterung
        überfallen. Aber ich glaube, es geht nicht. Im Vertrauen sage ich Ihnen, dass <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000498">Präsident Kux</tei:rs> (Vorstandsmitglied der <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002430">Gesellschaft</tei:rs>) schon vor Jahr und Tag, und
        nicht etwa gegen <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000562">Mandyczewski</tei:rs>, einen
        Schritt in dieser Sache ohne mein Vorwissen gemacht hat. Er bekam den Bescheid, dass ja
        schon Anwärter da sind, vor allen <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003061">Frau Dr.
          Kraus</tei:rs>, der ich wirklich nichts zuleid tun möchte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Hedwig Kraus succeeded Eusebius Mandyczewski in 1930 as the
          head archivist at the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde. Her father had been Vice-President of
          the Society from 1908 to 1912.</tei:note> Sie ist eine subalterne Natur von begrenztem
        Geiste, aber brav und verlässlich. Solange das <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002430">Archiv</tei:rs> nicht mit neuem Statut und neuen Mitteln gehoben wird,
        womöglich aber verstaatslicht und am besten mit der MS der <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002686">Nationalbibliothek</tei:rs> vereint, ist auch für mich – wenn man die
        Einseitigkeit meiner wirklichen Begabung als Archivar ganz ausseracht lässt – dort wenig
        Ruhm und Frucht zu holen. Dazu kommt noch die ganz miserable Bezahlung, die diese
        irrationelle <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002430">Gesellschaft</tei:rs> den
        Archivsbeamten zuteil werden lässt. Ich glaube, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000562"
          >Mandyczewski</tei:rs> bekam S200 monatlich, da man weit von einer Valorisierung der immer
        bescheidenen Bezüge entfernt war. Er konnte das durch seine Pension als Staatsbeamter und
        durch seine Arbeiten für <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002890">Breitkopf</tei:rs>
        ertragen, war auch sehr anspruchslos. Sachlich gesprochen, könnte ich als Ratgeber natürlich
        niemals <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000562">Mandyczewski</tei:rs> ersetzen. Als
        Verwalter der Handschriften und vor allem der Druckwerke könnte ich Besseres leisten, bei
        den Noten sogar das Beste. Nun interessiert sich auch <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000435">Kinsky</tei:rs> für die Stelle, der mich vertraulich befragt hat. Ich
        hatte ihn längst im Sinne dafür, da ich an mich gar nicht dachte (vor <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000498">Kux</tei:rs>), aber ich glaube, er kann auf keinen Fall zu den
        Bedingungen, die der <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002430">Ges.</tei:rs> möglich
        wären, nach Wien übersiedeln. So steht die Sache. Ich werde im September mit <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000498">Kux</tei:rs> und einem Herrn des
        Unterricht-Ministeriums, vielleicht auch noch im Juli, sprechen. Aber ich glaube nicht
        daran. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003510">Gal</tei:rs>, der besser ist (menschlich) als die
        anderen jungen Adler,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">"die
          anderen jungen Adler": a pun on the name of the Professor of Music at the University of
          Vienna, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000003">Guido Adler</tei:rs>, who supervised the
          doctoral work of most Austrian musicologists in the early 20th century, including Gal’s on
          Beethoven’s early style (1913).</tei:note> sprach sehr gut, aber nicht sympathisch nach
        Kraus und Breitner am Grabe. Ich glaube nicht, dass er sich für die Nachfolge interessiert
        oder in Betracht käme. Er war <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000562">Mand.</tei:rs> nur
        also Schüler verbunden. Und – das betone ich ausdrücklich – <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000562">Mandyczewski</tei:rs> war immer sehr gut zu mir!<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Deutsch may be emphasizing this because
          he was aware that Schenker had not trusted Mandyczewski entirely; see Schenker’s letters
          to Moriz Violin, October 6 and November 8, 1924 (<tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-6-7_10">OJ 6/7, [10]</tei:ref> and <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-6-7_12">OJ 6/7, [12]</tei:ref>).</tei:note> Es ist noch ein junger Dr.
          Luithlen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Viktor Luithlen
          (1901–1987) received his doctorate at the University of Vienna in 1927 and began working
          that year as a librarian at the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde.</tei:note> dort, als
        Hilfskraft vorläufig, sehr strebsam. Und der alte Dabrowa, den er im Notendienst wohl
        ablösen soll, vor allem bei dem gefährlichen Verleihamt. Er (Luithlen) ist sehr empfänglich
        für meine Ratschläge, die er öfters erbat. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Es hat mir leid getan, dass ich Sie im Juni nicht mehr aufsuchen könnte.
        Ihr Maibrief<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot"> For this letter
          from Schenker to Deutsch, May 10, 1929 (which does not survive), see Deutsch’s reply,
            <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-10-3_102">OJ 10/3, [102]</tei:ref> of May 13,
          footnote 2.</tei:note> über die <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-004436"
          >Ravag</tei:rs> hat mir sehr wohl getan. Obzwar ich <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003530">Ast</tei:rs> noch einmal, als Antwort, meine Meinung schrieb – in
        einer bestimmten, aber höflichen Form – hat sich nichts mehr gerührt. Ob die Abende<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot">The evening broadcasts of music
          performed by a “chamber ensemble” of professors from the <tei:rs type="organization"
            key="entity-002591">Vienna Academy</tei:rs>, which Deutsch coordinated and with whom he
          collaborated.</tei:note> im Herbst wieder aufleben werden, weiss ich nicht. Ich bin matt
        gesetzt im Handeln, weil mich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003513"
          >Wunderer</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09" type="editorial" place="foot">Alexander
          Wunderer, Professor of oboe at the Vienna Academy and the leader of Deutsch’s
          “Kammerensemble.”</tei:note> im Stich gelassen hat, wohl auch Romagnoli,<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn10" type="editorial" place="foot">Karl Romagnoli, the second horn player
          in Deutsch’s “Kammerensemble.” </tei:note> mit dem ich bei den Serenaden wieder
        zusammentraf, ohne dass er die Kammermusiken erwähnte. Ein oder zwei andere sprachen nett
        davon und hofften auf Fortseztung. Leider bin ich auch an <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-004819">Richtera</tei:rs> irre geworden, das heisst: ich glaube, mich in ihm
        geirrt zu haben. Er ist ein kluger, in seinem Fach wohl tüchtiger, aber als
          <tei:sic>Oeberster</tei:sic> wohl zu glatter Mann, der mehr verspricht, als er hält. Ob es
        der Mühe wert ist, noch andere Kanonen spielen zu lassen, weiss ich nicht. Ich werde jetzt
        keine Zeit dazuhaben, weil die Fortsetzung meines <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000803"
          >Schubert</tei:rs>werkes mir enge Termine auferlegt für das nächste Jahr. <tei:handShift
          new="#OED"/>Die Sozialdemokraten, die sich im letzten Herbst für mich einsetzten, haben
        nichts mehr getan. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/>Uebrigens will ich der Stadt Wien die Idee
        suggerieren, eine Stadtkapelle als Ersatz für die Burgmusik etc. aufzustellen, nach
        italienischen Mustern, aber womöglich besser. Die Uniform, wenigstens die militärisch
        aussehende, wird aber vermieden werden müssen. Ich hörte in Rom, Florenz und Venedig die
        Abendmusiken der Stadtkapellen immer andächtig an. Das Programm war immer schlechter als bei
        den Serenaden, die ich hier angeregt und durchgesetzt habe. Das letzte Mal hat mir {3}
        allerdings Johann Strauss, der nicht dazu passt und den man – der „lästige Witwe“<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn11" type="editorial" place="foot"> A pun on the title of Franz Lehár’s
          operetta <tei:title level="m">Die lustige Witwe</tei:title> (The Merry Widow).</tei:note>
        wegen – verlangt hatte, die Suppe versalzen. Dafür will ich mit <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">Benno</tei:add>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">Lies</tei:hi> Gunst, die ich merkwürdigerweise besitze, schon im
        Herbst wieder eine richtige Serenade machen, wo u. a. von <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000612">Mozart</tei:rs> ein Stück für vier kleine Orchester<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn12" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:title level="m"
            >Notturno</tei:title> in D major, K. 286.</tei:note> gespielt werden soll, auf dem
        Podium und den drei Balkonen der <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002686"
          >Nationalbibliothek</tei:rs> (Josefplatz, wie immer). <tei:handShift new="#OED"/><tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-003815">Nilius</tei:rs> kommt nicht mehr in Frage, wohl aber
        neben Hager <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002999">Clemens Kraus</tei:rs>. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/>Mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380"
          >Hoboken</tei:rs> stehe ich gut, aber die Bibliothek ist mir eine ständige Sorge, besser
        ein Kummer. Nicht nur wegen des Eigensinns, mit dem er oft ohne mich handelt und meine
        Erfahrung aus Laune in den Wind schlägt, sondern vor allem: wegen der Zukunft. Ich denke
        dabei wirklich zuletzt an meine Bezahlung, eher an die Früchte meiner Arbeit, vor allem aber
        an den schrecklichen Zustand des Zufalls, dem solche Sammlungen in Privatbesitz ausgesetzt
        sind. Vielleicht finden Sie einmal eine Lösung. Mein Vortrag ist gut von Stapel gegangen. Er
        wird aber erst im Druck wirken können. Der Plan, Bibliographien der Erstdrucke von den
        Meistern herauszugeben, ist noch nicht gesichert, aber ich habe Hoffnungen bekommen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002592">Italien</tei:rs> war mir ein
        grosser Genuss. Wenn mein Vater mich früher hingeschickt hätte (ich kam 1913 erst nach
        Unteritalien, ebenso 1924), so wäre ich vielleicht doch Kunsthistoriker geblieben. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Im Herbst werden wir uns hoffentlich wieder einmal aussprechen können. Ich
        gehe am 2. August auf einen Monat nach Seewalchen am <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-006738">Attersee</tei:rs>, Eschenhaus, wo es den Meinen sehr wohl ergeht. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Bitte, empfehlen Sie mich bestens Ihrer <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000771">Frau</tei:rs>, und seien Sie herzlich gegrüsst von Ihrem </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">treu ergebener</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/><tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000164">O E Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p>NB. Der DMV[] schickte <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs>
          eine Abrechnung für 2 Monate jetzt (2 Exemplare). </tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>PROF. OTTO ERICH DEUTSCH</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">VIENNA II </tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Böcklinstraße 26</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/><tei:date when="1929-07-28">July
            28, 1929</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear revered Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
            type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>


      <tei:p rend="first">It was very kind of you to think of me on this – very sad –
          occasion.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> My friend Otto Stoessl also
        bombarded me with such encouragement. But I believe that it will not work. In confidence, I
        can tell you that <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000498">President Kux</tei:rs> (a member
        of the Board of Directors of the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002430"
          >Society</tei:rs>) has already taken a step in this matter, without my prior knowledge of
        it, and not really in opposition to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000562"
          >Mandyczewski</tei:rs>. He had heard that there were already contenders <tei:supplied
          reason="clarity">for the post</tei:supplied>, above all <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003061">Dr. Kraus</tei:rs>, a lady to whom I really do not wish any
          harm.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> She is by nature a subservient
        figure, of limited intellect, but dutiful and trustworthy. So long as the <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002430">Archive</tei:rs> is not raised by a new statute
        and new financial means, best of all made into a state institution and joined with the music
        division of the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002686">National Library</tei:rs>,
        then even for me there is little fame and fortune to be gotten there – even if I disregard
        the onesidedness of my true gift as an archivist. To this is also added the thoroughly
        miserable payment which this irrational <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002430"
          >Society</tei:rs> confers on its archival officers. I believe that <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000562">Mandyczewski</tei:rs> received 200 shillings per month, one was far
        from being able to make a value adjustment to the emoluments, which were always modest. He
        could survive this from his pension as a state official, and from his work for <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002890">Breitkopf</tei:rs>; and he was also very
        undemanding. Objectively speaking, I could of course never replace <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000562">Mandyczewski</tei:rs> as an advisor. As custodian of the manuscripts
        and, above all, the printed materials, I could accomplish better things, with the printed
        music even the best. Now <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000435">Kinsky</tei:rs>, too, is
        interested in the post; he questioned me about it, in confidence. I had him in mind for it
        for a long time, as I was not thinking at all about myself (in the face of <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000498">Kux</tei:rs>); but I believe that on no account could he
        relocate to Vienna under conditions that would be acceptable to the <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002430">Society</tei:rs>. That is how the matter now
        stands. In September I shall speak with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000498"
          >Kux</tei:rs> and a gentleman at the Ministry of Education, perhaps I shall do so even in
        July. But I am not optimistic.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003510">Gal</tei:rs>, who is better (from a human point of
        view) than the other young eagles,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> spoke
        very well at the graveside, but not in a sympathetic way after Kraus and Breitner. I do not
        believe that he would be interested in the post or even consider it. He was connected to
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000562">Mandyczewski</tei:rs> only as a pupil. And – I
        emphasize this expressly – <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000562">Mandyczewski</tei:rs>
        was always very good to me!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> There is another
        youth there, Dr. Luithlen,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> at present an
        assistant, very assiduous. And old Dabrowa, whom he ought probably to replace in the musical
        scores department, above all in the dangerous office of the lending of scores. He (Luithlen)
        is very receptive to my advice, which he has often sought.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"> I was sorry that I was no longer able to look you up in June. Your letter
        of May<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> about <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-004436">Austrian Radio</tei:rs> did me a power of good. Although I gave my
        opinion again to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003530">Ast</tei:rs>, in reply – in a
        forthright way, but politely – nothing more has changed. Whether the evenings<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/> will be revived in the autumn, I don’t know. I
        have been checkmated in my dealing, as <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003513"
          >Wunderer</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09" type="footnote"/> abandoned me, and
        probably also Romagnoli,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn10" type="footnote"/> whom I met again at
        the outdoor evening concerts, without his mentioning the chamber music programs. One or two
        others spoke nicely about them and hoped that they would continue. Unfortunately I have also
        lost faith in <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004819">Richtera</tei:rs>; that is, I
        believe that I was mistaken about him. He is intelligent, and probably proficient in his
        discipline, but as the chief he is perhaps too slippery a person, who promises more than he
        can make good. Whether it is worth firing other cannons, I do not know. I will not now have
        any time for that, as the continuation of my work on <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000803">Schubert</tei:rs> has set me strict deadlines for the coming year.
          <tei:handShift new="#OED"/>The Social Democrats, who supported my cause last autumn, have
        done nothing more.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/>In addition, I want to suggest that the city
        of Vienna forms a town ensemble as a replacement for the <tei:hi rend="italic"
          >Burgmusik</tei:hi>, on Italian models, but better if possible. Uniforms however,
        especially those that have a military appearance, will have to be avoided. In Rome, Florence
        and Venice I always listened attentively to the evening concerts of the town ensembles. The
        programs were always worse than the serenades that I proposed and mounted. The last time, at
        any rate, Johann Strauss, who does not belong there and whom I was asked to include – on
        account of the “tiresome widow”<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn11" type="footnote"/> – spoiled
        things for me. To make up for this I shall use <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >Benno</tei:add>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">Lies</tei:hi>’s favor which, remarkably, I possess, to make a
        proper serenade as early as this autumn where, among other things, a piece by <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000612">Mozart</tei:rs> for four small orchestras<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn12" type="footnote"/> is to be played, on the podium and the three
        balconies of the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002686">National Library</tei:rs>
        (Josefplatz, as always). <tei:handShift new="#OED"/><tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003815">Nilius</tei:rs> is no longer eligible, but <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-002999">Clemens Kraus</tei:rs> is a possibility, alongside Hager.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/>I am on good terms with <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs>, but his library is a constant source of concern or,
        better, anguish. Not only because of the stubbornness with which he often deals, without
        consulting me and in cavalier disregard of my experience, but above all: on account of the
        future. I am thinking least of all about my payment, but more about the fruits of my work,
        and above all on the frightful state of fortuity to which such collections in private
        ownership are exposed. Perhaps you will find a solution at some point. My lecture went off
        well, but its true effect will come only when it is published. The plan to publish
        bibliographies of the first editions of the masters has not yet been secured, but I have
        been given grounds for hope.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002592">Italy</tei:rs> was a great
        pleasure for me. Had my father sent me there earlier (I first went to Lower Italy in 1913,
        and again in 1924), I would probably have remained an art historian after all.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">In the autumn we shall, I hope, be able to have a good long chat. I am
        leaving on August 2 to spend a month in Seewalchen on the <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-006738">Attersee</tei:rs>, at the Eschenhaus, where my family are very
        happy.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Please give my best regards to your <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000771">wife</tei:rs>, and receive cordial greetings from your</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">true devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/><tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000164">O. E. Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p>NB: Drei Masken Verlag have just sent <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380"
            >Hoboken</tei:rs> an invoice for two months (2 copies <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of
            the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001752">third <tei:title level="j"
                >Meisterwerk</tei:title> yearbook</tei:rs> sold</tei:supplied>.</tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>
    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
