<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3927" sdoID="OJ-13-10_142">OJ 13/10, [142]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="TLJ">
      <tei:persName>Timothy L. Jackson</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2026</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2026</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2026</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated December 10, 1931</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1931-12-10T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2026-02-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel speaks of corruption at the Leipzig Conservatory. – He gives a lengthy
        account of the errant behavior of one of his pupils. – His new Oboe Quartet has been
        performed, and a performance of his Wind Serenade has been broadcast on Swiss
        Radio.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:placeName>Leipzig</tei:placeName>, <tei:date
              when="1931-12-10">10. XII. 1931</tei:date>. Könneritzstr 58<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
              >III l</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Professor Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
            >Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for December 12, 1931: “Von
            Oppel (Br.): Goos ist ganz unreif, 20 Jahre alt u. Neurotiker!; über Aufführungen seiner
            Werke u. allerlei Häusliches.” (“From Oppel (letter): Goos is totally immature, twenty
            years old and a neurotic!; concerning performances of his works and various domestic
            matters.”). — Goos had approached Schenker in early December, and on December 7,
            Schenker had written to Oppel inquiring about Goos.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Längst wollte ich schreiben, aber ich sass Abend für Abend an einem
          Oboenquartett,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The manuscript
          score of Oppel’s Oboe Quartet is preserved in the Reinhard Oppel Collection, University of
          North Texas, Denton. A recording of one movement is available online.</tei:note> das jetzt
        fertig ist und das ich heute mit meiner Kammermusikklasse probiert habe. Deshalb habe ich
        auch noch die Walzer zurückbehalten, weil ich das angefangene Streichquartett liegen liess.
        Die Walzer kommen aber noch vor Weihnachten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
          place="foot">The waltzes were Oppel’s own, of which there were two sets, one of nine
          waltzes written in 1929 and dedicated to Jeanette Schenker, preserved as OJ 32/10 (See
            <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-13-10_85">OJ 13/10, [85]</tei:ref>, September 3,
          1929), and three waltzes written in 1931 in Galtür, also dedicated to Jeanette Schenker,
          preserved as OJ 32/11. Oppel was making an arrangement of the waltzes for string
          quartet.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Dass <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title>der „fr.
          S.</tei:title></tei:rs>“ soweit ist, dazu gratuliere ich. Sie haben also schwer
        gearbeitet. – Hier ist alles wohl, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008523">Bepo</tei:rs>
        bekommt Zähne u. ist daher jetzt manchmal etwas ungnädig. Weihn. kommen auch <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003957">Walter</tei:rs>. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Das Oboenq. wird Ende Januar in Gera<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Gera, in Thuringia, is the town in which Oppel spent much of his childhood,
          having been born in Grünberg, Oberhessen.</tei:note> gespielt. Die <tei:foreign
          xml:lang="ita">a capella</tei:foreign> Messe wahrscheinlich in Insterburg u. <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-006675">Königsberg</tei:rs> im Februar. Am <tei:date
          when="1931-11-12">12. Nov.</tei:date> brachte der Schweizer Rundfunk (<tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002342">Bern</tei:rs>-<tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002693">Basel</tei:rs>)
        meine Bläserserenade, ich wusste aber selbst nichts davon u. habe es erst durch Schüler
        erfahren, die sie angehört haben. Sonst hätte ich Ihnen natürlich rechtzeitig Mitteilung
        davon gemacht. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Im <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002872">Konservatorium</tei:rs> bei uns gärt
        es gewältig. Der Finanzdirector hat mit den Geldern eine starke Misswirtschaft getrieben u.
          <tei:pb n="2"/> seine Günstlinge unglaublich bevorzugt aus andern Lehrern gegenüber.
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000659">Pauer</tei:rs> hat neben s. Gehalt von 15000 M
        noch 15000 M für Überstunden bezogen u. 4000 M Wohnungszuschuss extra! <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000866">Straube</tei:rs> hat für s. Umzug von einer Strasse zur andern 16000
        M!!! erhalten. Und Ähnliches mehr. Nun wehren wir uns kräftig und bringen, wenn keine
        gründliche Änderung dieser Zustände eintritt, diese Corruption in der Presse zur Sprache;
        den Behörden ist schon Mitteilung darüber geworden. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun zu dem Fall <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000299">Goos</tei:rs>. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000299">Goos</tei:rs> ist ein braver Junge von 20 Jahren, noch
        blutiger Anfänger, nur Volksschulbildung. Er arbeitet aber sehr an s. Lücken. Aber für seine
        Kleinkinderschule sind Ihre Grundsätze viel zu schwer. Er hat noch kein Examen gemacht u.
        ist durch ein Nervenleiden bei der praktischen Ausübung (Klavier) sehr behindert. Natürlich
        jagen diese jungen Herrn immer nach den „neuesten“ Methoden u. schielen dauernd nach dem
        „actuellen“! Ich habe ihm gleich geschrieben, dass er erst einmal 10 Jahre Schenker
        studieren soll, langsam u. gründlich u. dass man als blutiger Anfänger auch verstehen muss,
        von geistigen Grössen die nötige Distanz zu halten; aber Bescheidenheit u. Geduld sind
        wahrlich nicht die Tugenden der heutigen politisch verseuchten Generation, die natürlich
        alle Sterne nur für ihr lächerliches Ich geschaffen währt. Ich habe ihm auch gesagt, dass
        Sie wichtigeres zu tun haben jetzt <tei:pb n="3"/> beim Abschluss Ihres Lebens- u.
        Rettungswerkes, als bei Ihren geschwächten Augen die Anfragen kleiner Musiklehrer zu
        beantworten. Schreiben Sie ihm also ruhig, dass, wenn er Ihre sämtlichen Werke studiert hat,
        ihm sich die Beantwortung der gestellten Fragen von selber böte. Ich habe ihm <tei:rs
          type="work" key="entity-001724">Bd I</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001725"
          >II</tei:rs> empfohlen zum gründlichen Durcharbeiten u. <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001739"><tei:title>den Tonwillen</tei:title></tei:rs>, allein die jungen
        Herren lesen das alles nur zu flüchtig u. glauben, mit blosser Lectüre sei dann allein
        Genüge geschehen. – Er beherrscht ja kaum die nötigen Anfänge, u. wagt dann schon, selbst zu
        unterrichten, wo er selbst noch nicht sicher ist. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Der Grundfehler beim theor. Unterricht in d. Instituten heute liegt in den staatlichen
        Prüfungsordnungen zum Unterrichten zu erwerben. Natürlich kann man den Riesenstoff in 2
        Jahren nicht bewältigen u. so bleibt am Ende alles Oberfläche. Der mechanische, „virtuose“
        Drill erstickt jede tiefere geistige Anlage u. Betätigung. Kontrapunkt wird nicht einmal
        mehr von den Klavierspielern verlangt, es ist schon ein Trauerspiel. – Ich freue mich schon
        heute darauf, wenn ich mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008523">Bepo</tei:rs> anfange,
        musikalisch zu arbeiten, der soll mir keine Umwege machen, wie ich sie tun musste, bis ich
        an Ihr Werk geriet. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Was hören Sie von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>?
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">V. Hobocken</tei:rs>? <tei:pb n="4"/> Die neue
        Notverordnung <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005819">Brüning</tei:rs>s wird ein Schlag
        ins Wasser werden.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Heinrich
          Brüning (1885–1970), the Chancellor of Germany in the last three years of the Weimar
          Republic, was responsible for enacting emergency economic measures decreed by President
          Paul von Hindenburg, though these were opposed by the Reichstag.</tei:note> Die Wirtschaft
        kommt so nicht in Ordnung, Gleichzeitige Senkung der Ausgaben u. Einnahmen erzeugen keine
        Sparkonten. Die Versenkung ist ein Trugschluss. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Angelica ist ja nun in den Hafen der Ehe eingelaufen, hoffentlich ist der Mann ein
        ordentlicher Kerl. – Der Hartmann hat Zeit.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Oppel had lent Schenker <tei:bibl><tei:author>Eduard von
              Hartmann</tei:author>‘s <tei:title level="m">Gedanken über Staat, Politik und
              Sozialismus</tei:title> (Leipzig: Alfred Kröner, 1923)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> – </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Alles Gute u. die herzlichsten Grüsse</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Ihnen beiden von uns allen!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr treuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1931-12-10">December 10,
              1931</tei:date>. <tei:placeName>Leipzig</tei:placeName>, Könneritzstr 58<tei:hi
              rend="supralinear">III left side</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor
            Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>I've long wanted to write, but have been working evening after evening on an Oboe
          Quartet,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> which is now finished and which I
        rehearsed today with my chamber music class. That is also why I held back the waltzes,
        because I put the string quartet I had started aside. The waltzes will arrive before
        Christmas, though.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>I congratulate you on <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title level="m">Free
            Composition</tei:title></tei:rs> being so far along. You've certainly worked hard. –
        Everything is fine here, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008523">Bepo</tei:rs> is teething
        and is therefore a bit grumpy sometimes. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000644"
          >Ulrich</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003957">Walter</tei:rs> are also
        coming for Christmas. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>My Oboe Quartet will be performed in Gera<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"
        /> at the end of January, my <tei:hi rend="italic">a cappella</tei:hi> Mass probably in
        Insterburg and <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-006675">Königsberg</tei:rs> in February. On
          <tei:date when="1931-11-12">November 12</tei:date>, Swiss Radio (<tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002342">Bern</tei:rs>–<tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002693">Basel</tei:rs>)
        broadcast my Wind Serenade, but I didn't even know about it myself and only found out
        through students who had listened to it. Otherwise, I would of course have informed you in
        good time. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>At our <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002872">Conservatory</tei:rs>, things
        are in an awful mess. The financial director has mismanaged the funds terribly and <tei:pb
          n="2"/> shown incredible favoritism towards his protégés compared to other teachers.
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000659">Pauer</tei:rs> received, in addition to his
        salary of 15,000 marks, another 15,000 marks for overtime and 4,000 marks extra for housing
        allowance! <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000866">Straube</tei:rs> received 16,000
        marks!!! for moving from one street to another. And more of the same. Now we are fighting
        back vigorously and, if there is no fundamental change in these conditions, we will bring
        this corruption to the attention of the press; the authorities have already been informed.
        –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Now to the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000299">Goos</tei:rs> case. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000299">Goos</tei:rs> is a good boy, 20 years old, still a
        complete beginner, with only elementary school education. However, he is working very hard
        to fill in his gaps. But your principles are far too difficult for his kindergarten
        students. He hasn't taken any exams yet and is severely hampered in his practical work
        (piano) by a nervous disorder. Of course, these young men are always chasing after the
        "latest" methods and constantly looking for what's "current"! I immediately wrote to him
        that he should first study Schenker for ten years, slowly and thoroughly, and that as a
        complete beginner he must also understand how to maintain the necessary distance from
        intellectual giants; but modesty and patience are truly not the virtues of today's
        politically corrupted generation which, of course, believes that all the stars were created
        only for their ridiculous selves. I also told him that you have more important things to do
        now, <tei:pb n="3"/> with the completion of your life's work and your work of salvation,
        than to answer the inquiries of minor music teachers with your weakened eyesight. So please
        write to him that once he has studied all your works, the answers to his questions will
        present themselves to him. I recommended <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724">volumes
          I</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001725">II</tei:rs> to him for thorough
        study, as well as <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001739"><tei:title level="j">Der
            Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>; but these young men read everything far too superficially
        and believe that with mere reading alone they will get all that they need. – He hardly
        masters the necessary fundamentals, and yet he already dares to teach, even though he
        himself is not yet fully competent. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>The fundamental flaw in theoretical instruction in today's institutions lies in the
        state examination regulations for obtaining teaching qualifications. Of course, it is
        impossible to master the vast amount of material in two years, and so in the end everything
        remains superficial. The mechanical, "virtuoso" drill stifles any deeper intellectual
        aptitude and development. Counterpoint is not even required of the pianists anymore; it's a
        real tragedy. – I'm already looking forward to when I start working musically with <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-008523">Bepo</tei:rs>; he shouldn't have to take the detours I
        had to take before I came across your work. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>What do you hear from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>?
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs>? <tei:pb n="4"/>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005819">Brüning</tei:rs>'s new emergency decree will be a
        complete failure.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> The economy won't recover
        this way; simultaneous reduction of expenditures and income doesn't create savings accounts.
        The deflation is a fallacy. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Angelica has now entered the harbor of marriage; hopefully, the man is a decent fellow.
        – The Hartmann can wait.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> –</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">All good wishes and the most cordial greetings</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">to both of you from all of us!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
