<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="2880" sdoID="OJ-15-6_4">OJ 15/6, [4]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="FW" scope="sole">Fritz Wahle's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2022</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2022</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2022</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-09-23" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008359">WahleF ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">letter</tei:rs>



   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Fritz Wahle to Schenker, dated August 20, 1903</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1903-08-20T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2022-10-18</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Fritz Wahle thanks Schenker for receipt of Eine Beitrag zur Ornamentik; he
    praises its serious intent, but there may be some things about which he would
    disagree.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>

   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000925">WahleF</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#FW"/>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
      >Schenker</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Mit der Bestätigung Deiner überaus freundlichen Sendung und mit dem Danke für dieselbe
    habe ich gewartet<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> um gleichzeitig mit diesen
    von deinem Werke<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
       ><tei:bibl><tei:author>Heinrich Schenker</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Ein Beitrag zur
       Ornamentik</tei:title> (Vienna: Universal Edition, [1903])</tei:bibl>; this is confirmed by
     Wahle’s mention of C. P. E. Bach, and it in turn confirms the date of the letter, which has not
     been clearly written. Schenker also had a copy of the revised edition (1908) sent to Wahle
      (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="WSLB-43">WSLB 43</tei:ref>, October 2, 1909).</tei:note>
    selbst zu schreiben. Seite 8–20<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"
     >Sections III to VI, which in the 1908 revised edition are entitled: “Über die Form bei Bach,“
     “Über das Mißverständnis dieser Form …,“ “Einige Anmerkungen zu den spezielleren Vorzügern in
     den Bach’schen Klavierwerken,“ “Vom Vortrag der Bachschen Werke.“</tei:note> waren mir
    natürlich das Interessanteste. Was mich am meisten gefreut, war der Umstand, dass die mit
    heiligem Ernste die Grenzen der Musik bewachte, ich mußte fortwährend an den Gedanken
    festhalten, dass die wirklichen Musiker in gleicher Weise, wie Du denken. Nur in Deinem Sinne
    ist eine wirkliche Begeisterung für <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000025">Bach</tei:rs>,
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000344">Haydn</tei:rs> (ich nenne den Beiden gegenüber mit
    Vorliebe nur diese zwei, weil sie von <tei:unclear reason="reading">ihnen</tei:unclear> nur als
    rythmische <tei:add place="interlinear-above">Begleitung</tei:add> zu <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000612">Mozart</tei:rs><tei:add place="interlinear-above">, <tei:rs type="person"
      key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs></tei:add>, oder besser gesagt <tei:add
     place="interlinear-above">nur</tei:add> zu <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055"
     >Beethoven</tei:rs> genommen werden) möglich. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000612"
     >Mozart</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> aber müßten mit
    den Augen <tei:unclear reason="reading">jener</tei:unclear> anderen gesehen immer geringer
    werden, da sie der Gefühlsgeilheit des modernen Orchesters ja nicht mehr zu entsprechen
    schienen. Ich habe sehr unklar geschrieben weil ich nicht wiederholen wollte, was wir ja schon
    oft untereinander <tei:pb n="2"/> gesprochen, schnell fertig werden wollte. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Der andere Teil der Arbeit, die Ausarbeitung der Manieren<tei:supplied
     reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> könnte von mir vielleicht einige etwas ungünstigere
    Kritik erfahren, doch wäre das überhaupt nur äusserlich, schon deshalb <tei:unclear
     reason="reading">nämlich</tei:unclear>, weil ja Alles bereits gedrückt ist, für denjenigen, der
    diesbezügliches <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">two illeg. words</tei:note> eine
    belehrende Unterstützung bittet. Auch in diesem Sinne danke ich dir Anregung, denn ich möchte
    nun die theoretische Schrift <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000025">E.
     Bach</tei:rs>s<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"
       ><tei:bibl><tei:author>C. P. E. Bach</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Essay on the True Art
       of Playing Keyboard Instruments</tei:title> (1753–62)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> gerne ansehen,
    obwol ich aus der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000611">Mozart</tei:rs>’schen
     Schule<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Leopold
       Mozart</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Treatise on the Fundamentals of Violin
       Playing</tei:title> (1756)</tei:bibl>. </tei:note> noch viel Erinnerung habe. Gestatte, dass
    ich <tei:del rend="overstrike">nochmals</tei:del> mit bestem Danke sowol für deine Bemühung der
    Sendung als für die Arbeiten selbst den schriftlichen Bericht schließe, und auf manche zu
    erwartende mündliche oder gar musicierende Unterhaltung hinweise. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Von mir ist nicht viel zu berichten. Ich bin fleißig, gehe spazieren. Du wirst es
     <tei:unclear reason="reading">wol</tei:unclear> ähnlich treiben.[?] </tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> Nun grüße ich Dich bestens – auch <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000926">Richard</tei:rs>
    <tei:supplied reason="punctuation">–</tei:supplied> und bitte nochmals um Entschuldigung für die
    Unklarheit des Briefes. – Es wäre mehr als ein Brief, würde ich mit meinem Gedanken kommen über
    Kunst. Für Dich sehr belästigend, für mich eine Schreibearbeit, deren Mühe ich scheue </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Servus</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Dein</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000925"
     >Fritz</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">Velden<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial"
       place="foot">Velden on the Wörthersee, in Carinthia, where the Villa Martha once
       stood.</tei:note> Villa Martha.</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80"><tei:date when="1903-08-20">20/8
      1903</tei:date>.</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#FW"/>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
      >Schenker</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>I have waited with the confirmation of the receipt of your thoroughly kind package, and
    with my thanks for the same, in order to write simultaneously about your work<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> itself. Pages 8–20<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
     type="footnote"/> were, naturally the most interesting for me. What I enjoyed most was the
    circumstance that guarded the boundaries of music with a holy solemnity; I had constantly to
    adhere to the idea that true musicians think in the same way as you. Only in the way in which
    you understand things is it possible to gain a genuine enthusiasm for <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000025">Bach</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000344">Haydn</tei:rs>.
    (I prefer to name only these two, since they are to be taken only as rhythmic <tei:add
     place="interlinear-above">accompaniment</tei:add> to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000612"
     >Mozart</tei:rs>
    <tei:add place="interlinear-above">and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055"
      >Beethoven</tei:rs></tei:add> – or rather <tei:add place="interlinear-above">only</tei:add> to
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>). <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000612">Mozart</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055"
     >Beethoven</tei:rs>, however, must be viewed, through the eyes of those others, in an ever more
    limited way, as they seem no longer to correspond to the emotional lustfulness of the modern
    orchestra. I have written very unclearly because I did not want to repeat what we had already
    spoken to each other about very often, <tei:pb n="2"/> <tei:supplied reason="clarity">and</tei:supplied> I
    wanted to finish quickly.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>The other part of your work, the realization of ornaments, could perhaps attract some less
    favorable criticism; but that would be, at any rate, only superficial – already on account of
    the fact that everything has already been printed, for someone who asks for educative support in
    this respect. In this sense, too, I thank you for the incentive – for I should now like to look
    at <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000025">C. P. E. Bach</tei:rs>’s writing,<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> even though I still recall much from the <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000611">Mozart</tei:rs> school.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
     type="footnote"/> Permit me <tei:del rend="overstrike">once again</tei:del> to conclude this
    written report with my best thanks to you both for the work itself and for the trouble you have
    taken to send it, and to refer to many a face-to-face or even music-making conversation.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>About myself, there’s not much to say. I am conscientious, I go for walks. You are
    probably engaged in a similar way.[?]</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> And now I send you my best greetings, as does <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000926">Richard</tei:rs>, and beg your forgiveness once again for the lack of
    clarity in this letter. It would require more than a letter if I were to express my ideas about
    art: For you it would be a great burden, for me a piece of writing, over which I dread to
    trouble myself.</tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">With greetings,</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000925"
     >Fritz</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">Velden<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> Villa
      Martha</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80"><tei:date when="1903-08-20">August 20,
      1903</tei:date>.</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
   </tei:closer>
  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
