<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="1772" sdoID="OJ-12-9_28">OJ 12/9, [28]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPlk" scope="major">Ludwig Karpath as typist</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="LK" scope="minor">Ludwig Karpath's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="ME">
      <tei:persName>Martin Eybl</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2016</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2016</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-05-16" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002733">Karpath ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002719">ViolinM ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Typewritten letter and envelope from Karpath to Schenker, dated October 23,
        1931</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1931-10-03T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2016-06-17</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>To Schenker's inquiry regarding Moriz Violin, Karpath gives information as to
        how in the era of Perger and Bopp at the Vienna Conservatory professors and teachers were
        addressed.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Musikreferat; music review; Zeitung; newspaper; Kunstbeirat; Adviser on the Arts;
        Unterrichtsminister; Minister for Education; Klageruf; complaint; Lehrer; teacher;
        Professorstitel; title of professor; Uebung; practice; Schüler; pupil; student; Anstalt;
        institution</dc:subject>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000424">Karpath</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold">envelope</tei:hi></tei:note><tei:lb/>
        <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="recto"/>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>HOFRAT LUDWIG KARPATH</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>WIEN IV., PRINZ EUGENSTRASSE 16</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied reason="clarity">An: </tei:supplied><tei:handShift new="#TPlk"
            />Dr. Heinrich Schenker</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-20">Wien III.,</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-20">Keilgasse 8.</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:lb/>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#LK"/>bzw. <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person"
              >Violin</tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:lb/>
          <tei:fw type="postmark">|| 4 WIEN 50 | 23.X.31 13 | *4g * || </tei:fw>
          <tei:lb/>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold">letter</tei:hi></tei:note><tei:lb/>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>HOFRAT LUDWIG KARPATH</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>WIEN, IV., PRINZ EUGENSTRASSE 16</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>TELEPHON: U-49-0-61</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#TPlk"
            /><tei:placeName>Wien</tei:placeName>, den <tei:date when="1931-10-23">23. Oktober
            1931</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Lieber Freund <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Schenker</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt
            of this letter and other occurrences are recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/5, p.
            3672, October 23, 1931: "Telephongespräch mit Karpath, [...] — Von Karpath (Br.):
            treffend, wirksam? — An Violin (Br.): schicke ihm K.s Brief" ("Telephone conversation
            with Karpath, [...] — From Karpath (letter): to the point, effective? — To Violin
            (letter): I send him Karpath's letter.")</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Wo leben Sie?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >The letter to which this responds is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/5, p. 3671,
          October 21, 1931: "Von <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Floriz</tei:rs> (Brief
          expreß): vielleicht eine Bestätigung des „Usus“ zu haben? — An Karpath (Br. expreß):
          pflichte <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Floriz</tei:rs> bei: es ist ein
          Unterschied zwischen Kellnern u. Dirnen u. Menschen aus unseren Kreisen, wenn sie den
          Titel „Professor“ beilegen! Warum eine „Gewerbeordnung“ nur in der Musik, nicht in der
          Dichtkunst? Und ich? Mein Titel „Professor“ ist doch korrekt, ich habe mich selbst schwer
          genug „geprüft“ (Höchstens Ehrendoktor!); vielleicht schreibt <tei:rs key="entity-000961"
            type="person">Wiener</tei:rs> ein Wort über den „Usus“. ("From <tei:rs
            key="entity-000913" type="person">Floriz</tei:rs> (express letter): perhaps he could
          have a confirmation of what is 'common practice'? — To Karpath (express letter): I concur
          with <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Floriz</tei:rs>: there is a difference
          between waiters and prostitutes on the one hand, and people from our circles on the other,
          when they attach the title 'Professor'! Why is there a 'professional ordering' only in
          music, and not in poetry? And myself? My title 'Professor' is surely correct: I have
          'proved' myself sufficiently. (At most, 'honorary doctor'!); perhaps <tei:rs
            key="entity-000961" type="person">Wiener</tei:rs> would write a word [of clarification]
          about the 'common practice.'").</tei:note> Es scheint, dass Sie so sehr in Ihre Arbeiten
        eingesponnen sind, (recht haben Sie!) dass Sie nicht einmal wissen, dass ich seit vielen
        Jahren keine Musikreferate mehr schreibe. Wahrscheinlich lesen Sie keine Zeitungen, was
        ebenfalls sehr vernünftig ist. Ich lebe nunmehr als freier Schriftsteller, muss aber leider
        Zeitungen doch noch lesen, weil ich seit neun Jahren als Kunstbeirat des
        Unterrichtsministers tätig bin. Das scheint Ihnen nun doch bekannt zu sein, denn sonst
        würden Sie sich wohl kaum in der Angelegenheit unseres gemeinsamen Freundes <tei:rs
          key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs>, von dem ich seit tausend Jahren nichts
        gehört habe, an mich gewendet haben. Das, was da beanständet wird, was Sie mir über <tei:rs
          key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs>s Klageruf schreiben, ist barer Unsinn.
        Natürlich wurde jeder, der am <tei:rs key="entity-002591" type="organization">Konservatorium
          der Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde</tei:rs> (an der heutigen Staatsakademie) wirkte, mit
        „Herr Professor“ angesprochen. Es <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">hab</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above"><tei:handShift new="#LK"/>gab</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>
        <tei:handShift new="#TPlk"/>auch keinen einzigen Lehrer, der dagegen protestiert hätte, weil
        er sich sonst eine Tafel hätte umhängen müssen mit der Aufschrift: „Ich bin noch nicht
        Professor, sondern nur Lehrer“. Ich weiss aus Erfahrung, dass selbst die verstorbenen
        Konservatoriumsdirektoren <tei:rs key="entity-000667" type="person">Perger</tei:rs> und
          <tei:rs key="entity-000089" type="person">Bopp</tei:rs> jede einzelne Lehrkraft mit „Herr
        Professor“ titulierten, obwohl sie doch selber <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
            ><tei:handShift new="#LK"/>am besten</tei:add>
        <tei:handShift new="#TPlk"/>wissen mussten, dass mit dem Professorstitel nicht
        ausgestatteten Lehrkräften der Professorstitel nicht gebührte. Diese Tatsache erklärt sich
        eben aus einer allgemein befolgten Uebung, die bei niemandem Anstoss erregte, da ja endlich
        und schliesslich jeder Lehrer nach einigen Jahren der Tätigkeit, fast möchte ich sagen,
        automatisch zum Professor ernannt wurde. Nun erst die Anrede von Seite der Schüler! Es wäre
        fast komisch gewesen, wenn die Schüler anstatt „Herr Professor“ „Herr Lehrer“ gesagt hätten.
        Auch bin ich überzeugt, dass den Schülern <tei:pb n="2"/> der einfache Tatbestand, dass es
        an der Anstalt ernannte Professoren und dann auch nur Lehrer gab, gar nicht bekannt war.
        Wenn Sie also der Meinung sind, dass es zu jener Zeit allgemein üblich war, jeden am <tei:rs
          key="entity-002591" type="organization">Konservatorium</tei:rs> oder an der späteren
        Akademie unterrichtenden Lehrer mit „Herr Professor“ anzusprechen, so pflichte ich dieser
        Meinung vollständig bei.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Violin,
          to whom Schenker sent Karpath's letter, responded by referring to 'the stupidity over
          titles' as 'incomprehensibly tragic' (letter of November 4, 1931).</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Sollte ich im Unterrichtsministerium darüber befragt werden, (die Sektion
        ist ja heute mit ganz neuen Leuten besetzt), so würde ich selbstverständlich dieselbe
        Auskunft geben, die ich Ihnen hiermit erteile. Ich habe nichts dagegen, dass Sie diese meine
        Ausführungen in zweckentsprechender Weise verwenden, bloss in Zeitungen möchte ich nicht
        gerne genannt sein, weil ich hiezu erst die Erlaubnis meines Ministers einholen
          müsste.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">The self-declared
          anti-Semite Emmerich Czermak (1885‒1965), a member of the Christian Social Party, was
          Minister of Education in three Christian-Social-led governments between September 1930 and
          May 1932.</tei:note></tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Mit den schönsten Grüssen</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr in alter Freundschaft ergebener</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000424" type="person">Ludwig
            Karpath</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>
    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">


      <tei:opener>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold">envelope</tei:hi></tei:note><tei:lb/>
        <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="recto"/>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>COURT COUNSELOR LUDWIG KARPATH</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>VIENNA IV, PRINZ EUGENSTRASSE 16</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied reason="clarity">To: </tei:supplied><tei:handShift new="#TPlk"
            />Dr. Heinrich Schenker</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-20">Vienna III,</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-20">Keilgasse 8</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:lb/>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#LK"/>re: <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person"
              >Violin</tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:lb/>
          <tei:fw type="postmark">|| 4 VIENNA 50 | 23.X.31 13 | *4g * || </tei:fw>
          <tei:lb/>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold">letter</tei:hi></tei:note><tei:lb/>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>COURT COUNSELOR LUDWIG KARPATH</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>VIENNA IV, PRINZ EUGENSTRASSE 16</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>TELEPHONE: U-49-0-61</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#TPlk"
            /><tei:placeName>Vienna</tei:placeName>, <tei:date when="1931-10-23">October 23,
            1931</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Dear friend <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Are you so out of touch with the world?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> It seems you are so wrapped up in your own works (and you are right to
        be!) that you are not even aware that I gave up writing music reviews many years ago. In all
        probability you don't read any newspapers, which is very sensible. Nowadays I make my living
        as a freelance writer; but alas I still have to read newspapers, because for the past nine
        years I have served as Adviser on the Arts to the Minister for Education. Evidently you do
        already know that, for otherwise you would surely hardly have turned to me on the matter of
        our mutual friend <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs>, from whom I
        have not heard in a million years. What <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person"
          >Violin</tei:rs> is complaining about, in his cry of anguish about which you write to me,
        is sheer nonsense. Naturally, anyone who worked at the <tei:rs key="entity-002591"
          type="organization">Conservatory of the Society of the Friends of Music</tei:rs> (at what
        is today the State Academy) would be referred to as "Herr Professor." There was not a single
        teacher who would have protested against it, because he would have had to hang a placard
        around his neck saying "I am not yet a professor, just a teacher." I know from experience
        that even the deceased conservatory Directors <tei:rs key="entity-000667" type="person"
          >Perger</tei:rs> and <tei:rs key="entity-000089" type="person">Bopp</tei:rs> addressed
        every individual teacher as "Herr Professor," though they themselves must have known
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above"><tei:handShift new="#LK"/>better than anyone
          else</tei:add>
        <tei:handShift new="#TPlk"/>that teachers to whom the title "Professor" had not been
        formally granted were not as of right accorded the professorial title. This can be accounted
        for as a generally observed practice, to which no one took exception, since in fact
        ultimately every teacher after a few years' service was, I might almost say automatically,
        nominated as a professor. Then there is the mode of address on the part of the students! It
        would have been almost comical if the students, instead of saying "Herr Professor," had said
        "Herr Lehrer"! Indeed, I am pretty sure that <tei:pb n="2"/> the simple fact that there
        existed both professors appointed to that rank and also mere teachers was completely unknown
        to the students. Thus if you are of the opinion that at that time it was the general
        practice to address all teachers giving instruction at the <tei:rs key="entity-002591"
          type="organization">Conservatory</tei:rs> or the later Academy as "Herr Professor," then I
        would entirely go along with that view.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"
        /></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Were I to be asked this in the Ministry of Education (the section is today
        entirely filled with new people), I would automatically give the answer that I have given
        here. I would have no objection to your using these remarks of mine in a suitable fashion; I
        would just prefer not to be cited in newspapers because I would first have to obtain the
        permission of my Minister.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">With most cordial greetings,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Yours truly in old friendship,</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000424" type="person">Ludwig
            Karpath</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
