<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="277" sdoID="OJ-15-16_45">OJ 15/16, [45]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HW" scope="sole">Hans Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="AH">
   <tei:persName>Alison Hiley</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2008</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-01-13" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~ H+JSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   
   

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated July 20, 1921 </dc:title>
   
   <dcterms:created>1921-07-20T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-03-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Weisse has completed a string quartet, the parts of which are being copied out,
    after which the score will be sent to the leader of the Rosé Quartet. He has been recommended as
    a music teacher in a school being set up in India by Rabindranath Tagore, but cannot accept
    because his knowledge of English is insufficient. He enquires about the progress of Schenker's
    current projects. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Klavierauszug; piano reduction; Klarinettensonate; clarinet sonata; Streichquartett;
    string quartet; Stimme; part; Partitur; score; Unterricht; lessons; instruction;
    Musikhochschule; music highschool; Notenhandlung; music store</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000951">Weisse</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Lieber verehter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Besten<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter
     is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/2, p. 2368, July 24, 1921: "Von Weisse (Br.): neue
     Arbeit unter der Hand; Adler wollte ihn an die indische Musik-Hochschule schikken; bittet Ende
     August uns besuchen zu dürfen; Frau Pairamall nimmt Stunden, 500 Kronen." ("From Weisse
     (letter): new work in hand; Adler wanted to send him to the Indian music highschool; asks if
     they may visit us at the end of August; Mrs. Pairamall is taking lessons, 500 Kronen.").
    </tei:note> Dank für Ihre beiden lieben Karten;<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">These postcards are not known to survive. The writing of a postcard is recorded in
     Schenker's diary at OJ 3/2, p. 2362, July 7, 1921: "An Weisse (K.): empfehle vierhandigen Satz
     zu den Variationen." ("To Weisse (postcard): recommend four-handed arrangement of the
     Variations.")</tei:note> an den 4 händigen Klavierauszug<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Clearly a response to Schenker's recommendation in his postcard
     on July 7, 1921. </tei:note> habe ich schon selbst gedacht, ja ihn sogar schon im Frühling
    angefangen, nur ist er dann im Hochzeitsrummel<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Weisse married Hertha [maiden name?] earlier that year. </tei:note> liegen
    geblieben. Ich will ihn im Herbst machen. Denn jetzt ist die Zeit der neuen Produktion. 2 Sätze
    einer Klavier-Klarinettensonate sind schon fertig. Ich arbeite fast den ganzen Tag – dabei geht
    es mir, wie Sie Sich vorstellen können<tei:supplied reason="syntax">,</tei:supplied>
    ausgezeichnet. Daß Sie das Streichquartett nochmals sehen wollen ist hoffentlich nur das
    Interesse für die Sätze, die Sie nicht kennen, und nicht auf eine Korrektur Ihres ersten
    Eindrucks <tei:pb n="2"/> zurückzuführen! Augenblicklich werden die Stimmen aus der Partitur
    reingeschrieben (Preis 2000K!!) und dann wandert sie zu Ihrem <tei:unclear reason="reading">assyrischen</tei:unclear> Freunde <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000727">Rosé</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">The reference
     to an "Assyrian friend" is probably a light-hearted comment on Rosé's origin, as a Jew from
     Jassy on the eastern fringe of the Austrian empire (now Romania). </tei:note> nach
     <tei:placeName>Weissenbach</tei:placeName> am <tei:placeName>Attersee</tei:placeName>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Weissenbach: small town on the southern tip
     of the Attersee in the Salzkammergut (Upper Austria). </tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000655">Frau Pairamall</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">It appears that Weisse took over her tuition
     from Schenker in the summer of 1921. </tei:note> hat gestern die erste Stunde genommen,
    natürlich zum Preise von 500 K. Sie hat mir zwar gleich eröffnet, sie wisse nicht, ob sie den
    Sommer nicht doch verreise, ich habe den Unterricht jedoch nur unter der Bedingung begonnen, daß
    Sie sich verpflichtet, ihn, falls sie jetzt unterbricht, im Herbst oder Winter zu Ende zu
    führen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Vorige Woche bevorderte <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000003">Adler</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot">Adler was Weisse's doctoral supervisor.
    </tei:note> mich zu sich und eröffnete mir unter ehrwürdiger Liebkosung seines Prophetenbartes,
    daß <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002511">Rabindranath Tagore</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09" type="editorial" place="foot">Rabindranath Tagore (1861-1941), Indian poet,
     winner of the Nobel Prize for Literature in 1913. With Leonard Elmhirst, he founded in 1921 the
     Institute for Rural Reconstruction – later renamed Shriniketan (Abode of Peace) – in the
     village of Surul, to which he recruited a large number of Western teachers. The music school to
     which Adler refers was probably a part of this Institute. </tei:note> in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002512">Indien</tei:rs> eine Musikhochschule
    errichte, und daß <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000003">Adler</tei:rs> mich als Lehrkraft für
    ihn vorschlagen möchte. <tei:pb n="3"/> Das Projekt scheiterte für ihn am Mangel meiner
    englischen Sprachkenntnisse, wäre natürlich von mir nie angenommen worden! Geht doch die Musik
    in die europäischen Köpfe schwer ein, geschweige erst in die indischen! - </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Nun bitte ich Sie um etwas! Wir werden Sie gerne<tei:supplied reason="syntax">,</tei:supplied> verehrter Meister<tei:supplied reason="syntax">,</tei:supplied> Ende August
    auf 2-3 Tage besuchen. Können Sie mir sagen, wie lange zeitlich für die Reise bis <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs> in Anschlag bringen muß? Wieviel eventuell ein Wagon
    kosten würde – und vor allem, ob wir Sie nicht stören? Wir würden freilich Ihre Arbeit in allen
    Ehren halten, Sie brauchen nicht zu fürchten, daß wir uns allzu klettenmässig benehmen würden! </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Was ist mit <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001737"><tei:title>op.
     101</tei:title></tei:rs>. Zu haben ist sie noch in keiner Notenhandlung! Auch den <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001739"><tei:title>Tonwillen</tei:title></tei:rs> habe <tei:pb n="4"/>
    ich von der <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">U. E.</tei:rs> noch nicht zugeschickt
    bekommen. Ist die <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001754"><tei:title>Mondscheinsonate</tei:title></tei:rs> in der Liebhaberausgabe schon
     draussen?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10" type="editorial" place="foot">These three works of
     Schenker's were all published by UE in the same year: the fourth and final volume of the
      <tei:title level="m">Erläuterungausgabe</tei:title> of Beethoven's late piano sonatas; the
     first issue of <tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title>; and the facsimile edition of
     Beethoven's "Moonlight" Sonata, Op. 27, No. 2, the first in the series of "Musikalische
     Seltenheiten: Wiener Liebhaberdrucke" under the general editorship of Otto Erich Deutsch.
    </tei:note>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich wünsche Ihnen und Ihrer lieben <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Frau
     Lie-Lie</tei:rs> auch weiterhin die beste Erholung und sende Ihnen beiden von uns beiden
    die allerherzlichsten Grüsse. </tei:p>




   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Ihr getreuer und dankbarer</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Hans</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1921-07-20">20. Juli 21.</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Dear revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Master</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Many<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> thanks for both your kind
     postcards;<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> I too have already thought about the
    piano reduction for four hands,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> indeed I even
    started on it in the spring, but it then got set aside in the wedding turmoil.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> I want to do it in the autumn. For just now is a time
    of fresh production. Two movements of my clarinet sonata are already finished. I am working
    almost all day – as you can imagine, I am therefore in the best of spirits. The fact that you
    wish to see the string quartet once more has been motivated, I hope, out of interest for the
    movements which you do not know, and not in order to correct your first impressions! <tei:pb n="2"/> At the moment the parts of the score are being copied out (at a cost of 2,000 Kronen!)
    and then it will find its way to your <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">Assyrian</tei:unclear> friend <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000727">Rosé</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> in <tei:placeName>Weissenbach</tei:placeName> on the
     <tei:placeName>Attersee</tei:placeName>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000655">Frau Pairamall</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> had her first lesson yesterday, for a fee of 500 Kronen
    of course. She revealed to me right away, however, that she did not know whether she might be
    away for the summer after all; I only started the lessons on the condition that she should
    commit herself to complete them in the autumn or winter if she was going to be take a break now. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Last week <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000003">Adler</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/> summoned me to him and, whilst venerably stroking his
    prophet's beard, revealed to me that <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002511">Rabindranath
     Tagore</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09" type="footnote"/> was building a music
    academy in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002512">India</tei:rs>
    and that <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000003">Adler</tei:rs> would like to recommend me to
    him for a teaching post. <tei:pb n="3"/> As far as he was concerned, my lack of English language
    skills put paid to the project, but of course I would never have accepted the post! It's hard
    enough to imbue European heads with music, let alone Indian ones! </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Now I have a request! We will happily visit you, honored master, for two to three days at
    the end of August. Can you tell me how long one should allow for the journey to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>? How much would the coach fare be – and above all,
    will we really not disturb you? We would of course respect your need to work; you do not need to
    fear that we would behave too much like limpets! </tei:p>

   <tei:p>How do things stand with <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001737"><tei:title level="m">Op.
      101</tei:title></tei:rs>? It is not to be had in any music store! <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">UE</tei:rs> has not sent me the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001739"><tei:title level="j">Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs> either. <tei:pb n="4"/>
    Has the connoisseur edition of the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001754"><tei:title>"Moonlight" Sonata</tei:title></tei:rs> come out yet?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn10" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>I wish you and your dear wife <tei:persName>Lie-Lie</tei:persName> a most relaxing
    vacation, and send you both most heartfelt greetings from us both. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Your faithful and grateful</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Hans</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1921-07-20">July 20, 1921</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>