<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3471" sdoID="OJ-14-10_4">OJ 14/10, [4]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RW" scope="major">Rosa Weil's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="AW" scope="minor">Arnold Weil's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008456">WeilR ~
        JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008455">WeilR ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Rosa Weil to Heinrich &amp; Jeanette Schenker, dated January
        9, 1933</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1933-01-09T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-07-22</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Rosa Weil reports that Klara approached Arnold to declare herself insane and
        ask to be placed in an institution, since when she has become delusional and asks for poison
        to end her life. — Rosa reports on her daughter Lene's training in
        medicine.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>
      
      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000944">Rosa Weil</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000943">Arnold Weil</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:div type="part_1">
        <tei:opener>
          <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RW"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002248"
              >Aussig</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1933-01-09">9. Jänner 1933</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
          <tei:salute>Meine Lieben<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
              >Receipt of this letter is recorded in Heinrich’s diary for January 11, 1933: “Von
              Rosl Weil (Br.): über Klaras Befinden.” (“From Rosl Weil (letter): concerning Klara’s
              condition.”). — Heinrich’s diary for February 10, 1933 records a reply: “An Rosl
              (Br.): wegen Klara u. vom <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002455"
                >Schenker-Institut</tei:rs>.” (“To Rosl (letter): concerning Klara, and about the
                <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002455">Schenker
              Institute</tei:rs>.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:p>ich will Euch gerne über die arme <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003244"
            >Klara</tei:rs> berichten, leider kann von einer Besserung nicht die Rede sein. – Sie
          hat eine Melancholie <tei:add place="interlinear-above"><tei:handShift new="#AW"/>(wovon
              <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000339">Oscar</tei:rs> nichts weiß.)</tei:add>
          <tei:handShift new="#RW"/><tei:hi rend="underline">mit hysterischen Einschlag</tei:hi>.
          Ich hab‘ das von allem Anfang an kommen sehen, es war schwer, den l. <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs> darauf zu bringen; er sah es wohl auch, schob das
          schreckliche aber solange als möglich von sich, umsomehr als <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-003244">Klara</tei:rs> es bei ihrer geistigen Einstellung verstand, ihren
          Zustand bis zum letzten Augenblick <tei:add place="interlinear-above">vor ihm</tei:add> zu
          verbergen. </tei:p>

        <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Dann freilich kam der Zusammenbruch; an einem Freitag Abend kam sie
          meinem <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">Mann</tei:rs>, auf den sie immer gebaut
          hat mit den Worten entgegen: „Denk‘ Dir nur <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943"
            >Arnold</tei:rs> jetzt bin ich wahnsinnig geworden und jetzt muß ich fort!“ <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs>, der jeder Situation ruhig und gefaßt
          gegenübersteht, nahm sie gleich beim Wort, am nächsten Tag brachten wir sie fort, <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-008447">Trude</tei:rs>, (<tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-006733">Louis</tei:rs>‘ Tochter) die sehr, sehr brav ist; fuhr mit, man hat
          sie mit vieler Mühe in das Zimmer gebracht. Anfangs hat sie immer die Angst gehabt,
            <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs> wird sich das Leben nehmen und
          so musste er ihr täglich schreiben. Von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008428"
            >Helmut</tei:rs> spricht sie nun garnichtsmehr, von <tei:pb n="3"/>
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs> nur wenn der Brief kommt, aber
          sie hat eine neue, schreckliche Wahnidee; sie leidet an Paralyse und Tabes und bittet auf
          den Knien um Gift, um nicht weiter leben zu müssen. Das hat sie auch hier schon immer
          getan und begonnen hat die Sache damit, daß sie sich die Schuld gab und sich den Kopf
          darüber zerbrach, wie sie die Sache hätte verhüten können. Sie war entsetzlich abgemagert
          und hätte sich zuhause völlig erschöpft und aufgerieben; wohl stellen die Ärzte, vor allem
          Prof. Fischer eine günstige Prognose, aber es wird lange dauern, man wird viel Geduld
          haben müssen. </tei:p>

        <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> Vorläufig geht der Haushalt noch weiter, weil ein eingearbeitetes,
          tüchtiges Mädchen da ist, von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008447">Trude</tei:rs> und
          mir ein bißl kontrolliert; Die Abende verbringt er <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs
              type="person" key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs></tei:supplied> meist bei uns, bei
            <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008447">Trude</tei:rs>, oder mit Freunden und es ist
          bewunderungswürdig, wie sich der arme Mensch beherrscht, sich ganz ruhig und harmlos mit
          uns unterhält und sein Leid vor uns zu verbergen sucht. Man kann nicht alles so schreiben,
          wie ich Euch erzählen könnte, von den furchtbar traurigen Wochen, so unsagbar traurig, daß
          man sich am liebsten selbst zum Sterben hingelegt hätte. </tei:p>

        <tei:p>Nun noch herzlichsten Dank für Euere guten Wünsche, die wir aufrichtig erwidern.
            <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005248">Lene</tei:rs> arbeitet in <tei:rs type="place"
            key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs> am Westend-Krankenheim bei Prof. Umber als
          Medicinalpraktikantin, selbstverständlich unbezahlt. <tei:pb n="5"/> Ein Vierteljahr hat
          sie hier gearbeitet, aber es hat ihr so garnicht gefallen und sie durchaus nicht
          befriedigt, sodaß wir sie schweren Herzens ziehen lassen müssten. Sie ging garnicht gerne
          fort, denn wir haben jetzt ein wirklich schönes Heim und so Gut wie bei Muttern hat sie‘s
          ja draußen weiß Gott nicht. Aber sie will viel lernen und da ist sie an der richtigen
          Quelle. </tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">Ich vergaß Euch noch zu sagen, daß <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-003244">Klara</tei:rs> um zu beweisen, daß sie Tabes hat, sich eines Nachts
          nach vorn fallen ließ, auf die Tischkante auffiel und sich an der Stirn eine Verletzung
          zuzog, die genäht werden mußte; damals war sie mit dem Verband eine Woche zu Bett, jetzt
          ist das wieder ganz gut. Man darf sie nicht besuchen, auch <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs> hat sie noch nicht gesehen. </tei:p>

        <tei:p><tei:pb n="6"/> Ich hoffe (was sollten wir Menschen heute anfangen, wenn wir nicht
          noch ein bißchen Hoffnung hätten?), daß ich Euch bald besseres berichten kann, und</tei:p>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute>bin mit den herzlichsten Grüßen von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943"
              >Arnold</tei:rs> und mir </tei:salute>
          <tei:salute>Eure</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000944">Rosa</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>
      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="part_2">
        <tei:opener/>

        <tei:p/>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#AW"/>Herzliche Grüße</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>

      </tei:div>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:div type="part_1">
        <tei:opener>
          <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RW"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002248"
              >Aussig</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1933-01-09">January 9,
            1933</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
          <tei:salute>My dear ones,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:p>I will gladly report to you on poor <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003244"
            >Klara</tei:rs>. Sadly there is no longer any question of improvement. – She suffers
          from melancholy <tei:add place="interlinear-above"><tei:handShift new="#AW"/>(of which
              <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000339">Oscar</tei:rs> is completely
            oblivious.)</tei:add>
          <tei:handShift new="#RW"/><tei:hi rend="underline">with elements of hysteria</tei:hi>. I
          saw it coming right from the beginning. It was hard to get <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs> to acknowledge it. In truth, he saw it, too; but
          turned a blind eye to it as long as possible, all the more so as <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-003244">Klara</tei:rs>, with her innate intelligence, knew to conceal her
          condition <tei:add place="interlinear-above">from him</tei:add> until the last
          moment.</tei:p>

        <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Then came the decisive break: one Friday evening she came to my
            <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">husband</tei:rs>, on whom she has always
          relied, saying: “Just think, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs>, I
          have now become insane and must go away!” <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943"
            >Arnold</tei:rs>, who handled the situation coolly and calmly, took her at her word, and
          the next day we took her away, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008447">Trude</tei:rs>
            (<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006733">Louis</tei:rs>‘ daughter), who is very, very
          good, went with us; with great difficulty she was taken into her room. Initially she was
          constantly afraid that <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs> would
          commit suicide, so he had to write to her every day. She no longer speaks of <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-008428">Helmut</tei:rs>, or of <tei:pb n="3"/>
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs>, except when she receives a
          letter from him. But she has come up with a new delusional idea; she suffers from
          paralysis and ataxia, and goes down on her knees begging for poison so as not to have to
          live a moment longer. She had already been doing that even when she was here, and it all
          began with her saying that she blamed herself, and that she was agonizing over how she
          could have prevented what happened. She was horribly emaciated, and at home she would have
          exhausted herself and worn herself down. But the doctors, above all Prof. Fischer, offer a
          favorable prognosis, although it will be long-drawn-out process, and we must all have
          great patience.</tei:p>

        <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> For now, the house continues to be looked after, thanks to a
          fully-trained and skilled maid, on whom <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008447"
            >Trude</tei:rs> and I keep an eye. <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs></tei:supplied> spends most of his evenings with us,
          or with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008447">Trude</tei:rs> or friends, and it’s
          remarkable how the poor man keeps himself under control, chats with us quite calmly and
          innocently, and tries to hide his sorrow from us. It’s not possible to write as if I were
          talking to you face to face about these fearfully sad weeks, so unspeakably sad that one
          would like to just lie down and die.</tei:p>

        <tei:p>Most heartfelt thanks, again, for your good wishes, which I reciprocate. <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-005248">Lene</tei:rs> is working in <tei:rs type="place"
            key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>, with Prof. Umber at the West End Hospital, as a
          medical trainee – needless to say, unpaid. <tei:pb n="5"/> She has worked there for three
          months, but she is so dissatisfied with it, and so thoroughly discontented, that with a
          heavy heart we have had to let her withdraw. She absolutely did not want to continue, for
          we now have a really nice home and out there she doesn’t have it so good as with her
          mother – God knows! But she will learn a lot, and she is on the right path.</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">I also forgot to tell you that <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003244"
            >Klara</tei:rs>, in order to prove that she has ataxia, one night let herself fall
          forward and hit the edge of the table, wounding her forehead, which had to be stitched.
          She was in bed for a week, bandaged up; now it is completely healed. We are not permitted
          to see her; even <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs> has not seen
          her.</tei:p>

        <tei:p><tei:pb n="6"/> I hope (what would we folk do today if we didn’t still have just tiny
          bit of hope left?) that I can give you a better report soon, and</tei:p>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute>send most heartfelt greetings from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943"
              >Arnold</tei:rs> and myself</tei:salute>
          <tei:salute>Your</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000944">Rosa</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>
      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="part_2">
        <tei:opener/>

        <tei:p/>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#AW"/>Cordial greetings</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>

      </tei:div>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
