<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="546" sdoID="OJ-14-45_26">OJ 14/45, [26]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="MV" scope="major">Moriz Violin's hand</tei:handNote>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2011</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-09-12" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002719">ViolinM ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM+V ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002718">ViolinM+V+F ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002845">Lettercard</tei:rs>



   <dc:title>Handwritten lettercard from Moriz Violin to Heinrich Schenker, dated October 9, 1923 </dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1923-10-09T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2011-09-12</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>In response to Schenker’s recent postcard, Violin reports that his family are
    mainly well, but that the political situation in Germany is so depressing that it is almost
    impossible to write. He would be glad to have some news from Schenker. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Zustand; conditions; Zukunftslosigkeit; lack of future; Geldwahnsinn; money madness;
    Milliardeneinnahmen; earn billions; prices; cost of living; Eier; eggs; Butter; butter; Gas;
    gas; Genies; genius; Politik; politics; Rechtsleute; right-wingers; Agitation; agitation;
    Zerfall; downfall; Gefahr; danger; Mord; murder; Kultur; culture; Lehrgegenstand; subject of
    instruction; Chaos; chaos</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="recto"/>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:fw type="envelope">
     <tei:address>
      <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="printed"/>Absender <tei:handShift new="MV"/>Violin </tei:addrLine>
      <tei:addrLine>Hamburg </tei:addrLine>
      <tei:addrLine>Woldsenweg 3 ptr. </tei:addrLine>
     </tei:address>
     <tei:address>
      <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="printed"/>An <tei:handShift new="MV"/>D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi> Heinrich Schenker </tei:addrLine>
      <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10">Wien III. </tei:addrLine>
      <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10"><tei:hi rend="overstrike">Reisnerstrasse</tei:hi>
      </tei:addrLine>
      <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10">Keilgasse 8</tei:addrLine>
     </tei:address>
     <tei:lb/>
     <tei:fw type="postmark">|| HAMBURG | 9.10 <tei:gap reason="illegible"/> || </tei:fw>
     <tei:lb/>
     <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="verso"/>
     <tei:lb/>
    </tei:fw>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-40">Hamburg, <tei:date when="1923-10-09">9. Oktober
     23</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Liebster <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this
      lettercard is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/6, p. 2583, October 12, 1923: "Von Fl.
      (Kartenbr.): sieht deutlich den Untergang der Kultur, wie reif zum Unterrichtsgegenstand an
      Mittelschulen; bittet mich um ein ausführliches Schreiben." ("From Floriz (lettercard): sees
      clearly the demise of culture, how ripe for the discipline of teaching in secondary schools;
      asks me for a detailed letter."). </tei:note>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Vielen, vielen Dank für deine liebe, besorgte Karte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">= OJ 8/4, [25]. </tei:note> Es ist mir
    wahrhaftig seelisch unmöglich dir zu schreiben. Ich weiß daß Du zu den wenigen, an den Fingern
    zu zählenden Menschen gehörst, die im Stande sind kombinativ den Zustand in <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Deutschland</tei:country></tei:rs> u. seine
    Zukunftslosigkeit zu beurteilen. Wie soll ich Dir nun durch die Schilderung der allen Sinn
    spottenden Begebenheiten vielleicht noch die letzte Hoffnung rauben? </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich selbst kann dem Geldwahnsinn einigermaßen nachhumpeln, trotzdem die
    Bedingung dafür Milliardeneinnahmen ist. <tei:hi rend="double-underline">Heute</tei:hi> kostet
    ein Ei 25 Millionen, Butter ein Pfund 300 Millionen, ein cbm. Gas 30 Millionen u. s. w. Morgen ?
    ? ? Das Furchtbare ist, daß Du hier das Gefühl haben wirst, daß die Deutschen mehr an diesen
    Wirkungen als ihren Ursachen leiden. Hilflos, blöde Politik, aktive Politik im Inneren nur in
    feindseliger Weise, Bürger gegen Bürger. Natürlich machen die Rechtsleute aus der inneren
    Konfliktsituation <tei:pb n="2"/> heraus, über's Ziel schießende Agitation u. dennoch, man mag
    noch so viel hohlen Patriotismus hinter ihren Phrasen vermuten, sind sie die Einzigen, die
    wenigstens gegen den wirklichen Feind gehen wollen. Der Zerfall <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Deutschland</tei:country></tei:rs>s wird mehr besprochen als
    befürchtet – – – von den Profithyänen! </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich habe <tei:hi rend="underline">keinen</tei:hi> Menschen hier getroffen der wirklich
    daran leidet, woran nur zu leiden ist: an der furchtbaren Gefahr, daß der Geist der deutschen
    Genies für alle Ewigkeit um's Leben gebracht werden soll. Ich habe das Gefühl daß der Mord
    bereits vollzogen ist u. daß deutsche Kultur bereits reif ist, in der quarta als Lehrgegenstand
    neben griechischer u. römischer, vorgetragen zu werden. Man fühlt sich tot unter Lebenden, man
    lebt unter Toten. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Heinrich wie schrecklich fließt mir von Lippe u. Herzen der Gedanke, daß das
    Deutsche Chaos das edle Ziel deines Lebenswerkes krönt! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="3"/> Wenn Du mir schreibst, machst Du mich nur glücklich.
    Umgekehrt kann es nur Störung bedeuten. Deshalb schreibe ich so wenig. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Bubi</tei:rs> geht es sehr gut. Er
    ist zwar noch schwach. Aber langsam wird er jetzt dem Leben zugeführt. Alle sind sonst vollkomen
    gesund. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Innigstes von Uns an Euch </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Dein </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">getreuer</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs>
    </tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="recto"/>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:fw type="envelope">
     <tei:address>
      <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="printed"/>From <tei:handShift new="MV"/>Violin, </tei:addrLine>
      <tei:addrLine>Hamburg, </tei:addrLine>
      <tei:addrLine>Woldsenweg 3 ground floor </tei:addrLine>
     </tei:address>
     <tei:address>
      <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="printed"/>To <tei:handShift new="MV"/>Dr. Heinrich Schenker, </tei:addrLine>
      <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10">Vienna III, </tei:addrLine>
      <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10"><tei:hi rend="overstrike">Reisnerstrasse</tei:hi>
      </tei:addrLine>
      <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10">Keilgasse 8</tei:addrLine>
     </tei:address>
     <tei:lb/>
     <tei:fw type="postmark">|| HAMBURG | 9.10 <tei:gap reason="illegible"/> || </tei:fw>
     <tei:lb/>
     <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="verso"/>
     <tei:lb/>
    </tei:fw>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-40">Hamburg, <tei:date when="1923-10-09">October 9,
     1923</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dearest <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Many, many thanks for your kind, concerned postcard.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> It is really and truly impossible, from a psychological
    point of view, for me to write to you. I know that you belong among the few people I can count
    on my fingertips who are in a position to judge <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Germany</tei:country></tei:rs>'s present condition and its lack of future
    comprehensively. Why should I perhaps rob you of the last remaining vestige of hope by
    describing the events that beggar all belief. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I myself can stumble through this money madness to some degree, despite the
    condition for this being to earn billions. <tei:hi rend="double-underline">Nowadays</tei:hi>, an
    egg costs 2.5 million, a pound of butter 300 million, a cubic meter of gas 30 million, etc. What
    will they cost tomorrow? The terrible thing is that you will get the impression here that the
    Germans suffer more from these symptoms than from their causes. Helplessly half-witted politics,
    internal political activism only of a hostile fashion, setting citizen against citizen. Of
    course the right-wingers, taking advantage of the internal conflict, <tei:pb n="2"/> agitate in
    a way that oversteps the mark; and yet although one can detect so much hollow patriotism behind
    their rhetoric, they are the only ones who at least want to go after the real enemy. The
    downfall of <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Germany</tei:country></tei:rs>
    is more spoken of than feared – – – by the hyenas of profit! </tei:p>

   <tei:p>I have met <tei:hi rend="underline">nobody</tei:hi> here who genuinely suffers from the
    only thing about which one is to be sorrowful: from the terrifying danger that the spirit of
    German genius is to be robbed of its life for all eternity. I have the feeling that the murder
    has already been carried out, and that German culture is now ripe to be put forward as a subject
    of instruction in high school, alongside that of the ancient Greeks and Romans. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Heinrich, how dreadful it is that the thought flows from my lips and my heart
    that German chaos will trump the noble goal of your life's work! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="3"/> Whenever you write to me, you make me so happy. The opposite
    serves only to upset me: that is why I write so rarely. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">The <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">little lad</tei:rs> is getting
    on very well. True, he is still weak. But he is now slowly returning to life. The rest of us are
    entirely well. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Most hearfelt feelings from us to you, </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Your </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">faithful</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs>
    </tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>

 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>