<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="666" sdoID="OJ-11-25_2">OJ 11/25, [2]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="MG" scope="sole">Max Graf's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="ME">
   <tei:persName>Martin Eybl</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="GC">
   <tei:persName>Geoffrey Chew</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2012</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2012-02-26" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-003183">GrafM ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Graf to Schenker, dated May 17, 1910</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1910-05-17T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2012-02-26</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Graf justifies his request for a discussion, refused by Schenker, about some
    details in Beethoven's "Leonora" overtures. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Mißverständnis; misunderstanding; Gespräch; conversation; Erfahrungen; experiences;
    Denkergebnissen; conclusions; Aesthetik; aesthetics; esthetics; Schaffen; creativity; Künstler;
    artist; Styl; style; Gedankengängen; trains of thoughts; Einfluß; influence; Kunsterfahrungen;
    experiences of art; Theoretisieren; theorizing</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000303">GrafM</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in unknown hand, top right corner: "17. V.
     1910"</tei:note><tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-15">Verehrtester Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Doctor</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this
      letter seems not to be recorded in Schenker's diary. </tei:note>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">ich glaube, daß hier ein Mißverständnis vorliegt. Es war meine Absicht mir
    durch ein Gespräch mit Ihnen die Sicherheit zu holen, ob meine Auffassung einiger Details in den
    L.-Ouvertüren richtig ist oder nicht. Es hätte durchaus von Ihnen abgehangen, ob und wieweit Sie
    bei diesem Anlasse mir etwas von Ihren Erfahrungen und Denkergebnissen mitgetheilt hätten. Ihre
     Bedenken<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The precise context of this
     letter is unknown. In a letter, now lost, Schenker refused a meeting with Graf, possibly on
     account of misgivings in case Graf published Schenker's opinions as his own ideas. A few years
     later, Arnold Schoenberg also expressed similar fears, in connection with Graf's negative
     criticism of Schoenberg's continuo realization in volume 39 of the <tei:title level="s">Denkmäler der Tonkunst in Österreich</tei:title> (Monn). In a letter to Guido Adler written
     on April 14, 1913 he suspected Schenker and Moriz Violin of being the experts orchestrating
     this attack: "At first I intended to respond, but I shall not do so because I do not intend to
     have anything more to do with people of Graf's type. Furthermore, it is obvious to me that Graf
     has 'behind the scenes' collaborators (I suspect Schenker and Violin, who have always had the
     honorable role of inciting critics against artists and of supplying them with their
     'material'), since Graf is unable to distinguish between a continuo and a market report
     [footnote: "or, as Kraus would say: a counterpoint from a freckle"]. This I have been aware of
     since that time in the coffee-house when he stole my views on musical questions in order to
     claim them as his own in mutilated form in the newspaper." (Quoted from Egbert M. Ennulat, ed.,
      <tei:title level="m">Arnold Schoenberg Correspondence: A Collection of Translated and
      Annotated Letters exchanged with Guido Adler, Pablo Casals, Emanuel Feuermann and Olin
      Downes</tei:title> (Metuchen/London: Scarecrow Press 1991), in Ennulat's translation, pp.
     104-05.) The article appeared on April 2, 1913. This, together with Adler's answer on April 16,
     yields a date of April 14, not March 14, 1913 as in the edition (see Ennulat, pp. 110–13,
     282–86). </tei:note> will ich natürlich gerne respektieren, bemerke jedoch noch folgendes: Es
    scheint Ihre Annahme zu sein, daß ich die Publikation einer Arbeit über die beiden
    Leonoren-Ouvertüren beabsichtige. Das ist nicht der Fall. Ich hoffe Sie werden im Herbste im
    Besitz meiner Arbeit<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl>Max
      Graf, <tei:title level="m">Die innere Werkstatt des Musikers</tei:title> (Stuttgart: Ferdinand
      Enke, 1910)</tei:bibl>. When he examined this work, Schenker commented in his diary on
     November 26, 1910: "Dr. Max Graf's latest book, <tei:title level="m">The Inner
      Workplace</tei:title> etc., cites my <tei:title level="m">Theory of Harmony</tei:title> ‒
     although in journalistic fashion, needless to say, not at one of the more important passages,
     where the theft of the main points occurs and would be bound to discredit the thief, but at a
     point in the material that is fundamentally entirely irrelevant, namely local modulation. As a
     result, the theft itself is very effectively masked, and the reader assumes that the central
     issue belongs to the author himself, the subordinate issue to another author who is merely
     cited. In actual fact, however, the analysis belongs to me, draws attention to both Brahms's
     editions of Op. 8 [and] Beethoven's "Leonora" overtures, about which I spoke with Dr. Graf for
     years in Café Frohner, and several other topics." (OJ 1/11, p. 119a). </tei:note> sein, die
    sich mit der <tei:sic>Aehsthetik</tei:sic> des musikalischen Schaffens beschäftigt und wo ich in
    einem Capitel neben anderen Beispielen die Leonorenouvertüren als ein Exempel dafür benütze, wie
    ein Künstler zum Stil kommt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Chap.
     XVI, "The High Style," pp. 228–46, discusses the modifications in Beethoven's "Leonora"
     Overture No. 2 compared with the "Leonora" Overture No. 1. Schenker is mentioned neither here
     nor in the Foreword. But there is indirect reference to him on p. 38, and at the corresponding
     point in the "Quellennachweis" ["Sources"] (p. 252) his <tei:title level="m">Harmonielehre</tei:title> p. 441 (Eng. transl., p. 332) (on the classical use of
     enharmonicism) is cited. </tei:note> Alles, was ich über die Leonorenouvertüren zu sagen habe,
    ist mit allen anderen Gedankengängen so verknüpft, daß es nur durch diese Verbindung Werth hat.
    So sehr es mich interes- <tei:pb n="2"/> sieren wird die Arbeit ihres Schülers<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">It is unclear what planned publication, and
     which pupil, are being referred to here by Graf. </tei:note> zu lesen, wenn Sie publiziert sein
    wird, so wenig Einfluß wird sie auf meine Gedankengänge nehmen können, weil es sich hier um
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">allgemeine</tei:add> Auffassungen und Überzeugungen handelt,
    die das Resultat langjähriger Kunsterfahrungen sind. Doch das Theoretisieren führt hier zu
    nichts. Sie werden selbst Gelegenheit haben, die Sachen zu sehen und zu prüfen. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Mit den herzlichsten Grüßen </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr stets ergebener </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000303">Max
     Graf</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in unknown hand, top right corner: "17. V.
     1910"</tei:note><tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-15">Most revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Dr.
       <tei:supplied reason="identity">Schenker</tei:supplied></tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">I think there is a misunderstanding here. I intended, by means of a
    conversation with you, to establish securely whether my understanding of certain details in the
    "Leonora" overtures is correct or not. Throughout it would have depended on you, whether, and to
    what extent, you would have communicated to me some of your experiences and conclusions on this
    occasion. Naturally I shall gladly respect your scruples,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> but would add the following remarks: You seem to assume that I intend to
    publish an article on the two "Leonora" overtures. That is not the case. I hope that by the
    autumn you will have at your disposal my work,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/>
    which is concerned with the aesthetics of musical creativity, and in it I use the "Leonora"
    overtures in one of the chapters, together with other examples, as an illustration of the way in
    which an artist achieves style.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> All I have to
    say about the "Leonora" overtures is so interconnected with other trains of thought that it is
    only in that context that it has value. As highly as the work of your student<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> will interest me, <tei:pb n="2"/> when it comes to be
    published, it will be able to exert equally little influence on my trains of thought, since it
    is <tei:add place="interlinear-above">general</tei:add> concepts and opinions that are dealt
    with here, which are the fruit of many years' experience of art. But theorizing is pointless
    here. You will have occasion to see matters for yourself and to test them. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">With my most cordial greetings, </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">yours very faithfully, </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000303">Max
     Graf</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>