<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2218" sdoID="OJ-12-17_1">OJ 12/17, [1]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="MK" scope="sole">Maria Komorn's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="MS">
      <tei:persName>Michaela Searfoorce</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008, 2019</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2008, 2019</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2011-03-05" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-007009">Komorn ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">letter</tei:rs>
      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Komorn to Heinrich Schenker, dated September 20,
        1923</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1923-09-20T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-02-10</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Miss Komorn is transferring her studies from Hans Weisse to Schenker. She asks
        for suggested pieces to prepare, and for the day and time of her first
        lesson.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Vereinbarung; agreement; Aufnahme; take-up; Krise; crisis; Stunde; lesson time;
        Stück; piece; Literatur; repertory; Bereitwilligkeit; willingness</dc:subject>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000460">Maria Komorn</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute>Hochverehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Doktor</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/4, p. 2571, September 21, 1923: "Von
            Frau Komorn (Br.): hat die Angelegenheit mit Weisse leicht geordnet; bittet nun um
            Angabe des Stückes u. der Stunde." ("From Mrs. Komorn (letter): she has easily
            straightened out the situation with Weisse; now asks for information about the piece and
            the lesson time.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>unserer Vereinbarung gemäß teile ich Ihnen mit, dass ich mit D<tei:hi
          rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs> gesprochen habe. Ich sagte ihm
        ganz gleicherweise wie Ihnen, dass der Grund, der mich bestimmte, Sie um Aufnahme zu bitten,
          <tei:hi rend="underline">nicht</tei:hi> der wäre, dass <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >er</tei:hi> mir nicht gut genug ist, sondern dass ich die Überzeugung hätte, nur Sie
        könnten mir aus der rein klavieristisch-technischen Krise, in der ich mich gegenwärtig
        befinde, heraushelfen. Er freute sich sehr, dass mir die Möglichkeit gegeben ist, <tei:del
          rend="overstrike">nun</tei:del> bei Ihnen zu arbeiten<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker reports a conversation with Weisse in his diary for
          September 25 (OJ 3/4, p. 2574): "er ist über den Abgang der Frau Komorn beleidigt, fühlt
          sich „erlöst”, obgleich weder er noch seine Frau vor hatten, sie wegzuschicken, bis 100000
          Kronen Honorar war er sie trotz Abneigung zu behalten entschlossen. Das allein ist
          richtig. Er fragt micht, warum ich sie annehme? Ich gab zur Antwort, daß ich keinen Grund
          hatte, gerade ihr den Unterricht zu verweigern, sofern sie nur die Angelegenheit mit ihm
          in Ordnung gebracht hat [...])" ("he is offended at Mrs. Komorn's departure, feels
          'relieved,' although neither he nor his wife planned to turn her away; until 100,000
          Kronen in fees <tei:supplied reason="clarity">were paid</tei:supplied>, he had decided,
          despite disinclination, to keep her on. That at least is true. He asks me why I am taking
          her on. I answer that I had no <tei:hi rend="italic">prima facie</tei:hi> reason to deny
          her instruction just so long as she squared the matter with him […]."). — In her opening
          lessons she played Schubert, <tei:title>Impromptu in G major, D899</tei:title>, and
          Beethoven, "<tei:title>Rage over a Lost Penny,</tei:title>" Op. 129, after which she moved
          on to the Schumann<tei:title> Piano Quintet, Op. 44</tei:title>, J. S. Bach, <tei:title
            level="m">St Matthew Passion</tei:title>, Beethoven, <tei:title>Violin and Piano Sonata,
            op. 47 ("Kreutzer")</tei:title>, and D. Scarlatti, <tei:title>Sonata in E
            major</tei:title> (lessonbook 1923/24, p. 10).</tei:note> und ich bitte Sie nun recht
        sehr um die Güte, mir die Stunde bekannt zu geben, wann ich das erste Mal zu kommen habe.
        Alles Nähere werde ich Ihnen auf Ihr Befragen jederzeit mündlich sagen.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker's reply is summarized in
          Schenker's diary at OJ 3/4, p. 2573, September 21, 1923: "An Frau Komorn (K.): schlage
          einige Stücke vor; die Stunde werde ich später ansagen." ("To Mrs. Komorn (postcard):
          I suggest a few pieces; I will inform her of the lesson time later."). He further wrote to
          her, OJ 3/4, p. 2575, September 27, 1923: "An Frau Komorn (K.): bitte sie für Montag zur
          ersten Stunde, teile auch das Programm mit u. ersuche sie, <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000416">Frl. Kahn</tei:rs> zu verständigen." ("To Mrs. Komorn (postcard): I
          ask her to come for her first lesson on Monday, I also let her know the program and ask
          her to inform <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000416">Miss
        Kahn</tei:rs>.").</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Sehr dankbar wäre ich, wenn Sie die Liebenswürdigkeit hätten, mir 2 oder 3
        nicht zu große Stücke zu nennen, die ich mir <tei:pb n="2"/> unterdessen besorgen, ein wenig
        ansehen und eines davon auswählen und mitbringen könnte. Mir wäre am liebsten etwas, was
        inhaltlich schön und gleichzeitig für mich technisch günstig <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">wäre</tei:add>, etwa <tei:add place="interlinear-above">in der
          Art</tei:add> des Rondos über den velorenen Groschen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Beethoven: <tei:title>Rondo <tei:hi rend="italic">a
              capriccio</tei:hi> "Rage over a Lost Penny,"</tei:title> Op. 129. Komorn plays it in
          her early lesson(s) in October 1923, and again at the lesson on November 3,
          1924.</tei:note> der Gavotte mit Variationen von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002972"
          >Rameau</tei:rs> oder derlei. Aber das überlasse ich natürlich vollkommen Ihrer
        Bestimmung, da ich ja viel zu wenig an Literatur kenne.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Indem ich Ihnen, sehr verehrter Herr Doktor<tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> meinen aufrichtigen Dank für Ihre Bereitwilligkeit,
        mich zu unterrichten, ausspreche, bin ich mit den besten Empfehlungen an Sie und die
        verehrte gnädige <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Frau</tei:rs></tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Ihre wahrhaft ergebene</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs key="entity-000460" type="person">Maria
          Komorn</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1923-09-20">20. 9. 23</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60">IX Bleichergasse 15</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Telefon 5014/VIII</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute>Highly revered Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
            type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>I wish to inform you in accordance with our agreement that I have spoken with Dr.
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs>. I told him, exactly as you did,
        that the reason why I decided to ask you to take me on was <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >not</tei:hi> that <tei:hi rend="underline">he</tei:hi> is not good enough, but rather
        that I was convinced that you alone were able to help me out of the purely
        pianistic-technical crisis in which I currently find myself. He was delighted that I had
        been given the opportunity to work with you.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/>
        Please now be so very kind as to notify me of the hour at which I have to come for the first
        time. I will tell you all the details that you wish to know in person then.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I should be very grateful if you would be so kind as to identify two or
        three not too large pieces to me that I <tei:pb n="2"/> could procure for myself in the
        meantime, look at a little, and select one of them and bring along. Preferable to me would
        be something beautiful in content and at the same time technically favorable for me, for
        instance <tei:add place="interlinear-above">of the sort</tei:add> of the rondo over the lost
          penny,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> the gavotte with variations by
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002972">Rameau</tei:rs>, or the like. But naturally I
        leave this completely up to you, since I after all know much too little about
        repertory.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">In expressing to you, dear Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity"
          >Schenker</tei:supplied>, my sincere thanks for your willingness to teach me, I am, with
        the best regards to you and your revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
          >wife</tei:rs>,</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Your truly devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs key="entity-000460" type="person">Maria
          Komorn</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1923-09-20">September 20, 1923</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60"><tei:supplied reason="identity">Vienna</tei:supplied> IX,
            Bleichergasse 15</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">telephone 5014/VIII</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
      </tei:closer>



    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
