<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3808" sdoID="OJ-13-10_200">OJ 13/10, [200]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2025</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008522">Oppel ~
        JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Jeanette Schenker, dated June 17, 1939</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1939-06-17T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-09-26</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel wishes Jeanette a pleasant summer. – He expresses his dismay about a
        paper at a recent Bach conference which argued that Bach’s counterpoint was indebted to that
        of the “old Netherlandish” composers.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1939-06-17">17. VI. 39</tei:date>.</tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Meine liebe, hochverehrte <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000771">Frau D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi>
            Schenker</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">This is
            the last surviving communication from Oppel to Jeanette Schenker. Unfortunately, the
            photographs available for transcription were defective, resulting in incomplete or
            missing words at the margin. These are limited to page 3, and will be rectified in due
            course.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Sie wissen, wie ich am Geburtstag des geliebten Meisters seiner und Ihrer denke. Umso
        mehr hat mich betrübt, was Sie mir im letzten Brief vom <tei:date when="1939-05-09">9.
          V.</tei:date> über sein Werk schrieben. Aber geistig hohe und wahre Ideen gehn nicht
        unter. Ich muss dabei an die bitteren Lebensschicksale Rousseau’s denken, für den seine Zeit
        auch nicht reif war. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Und grade las ich dass der College David<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Possibly Johann Nepomuk David (1895–1977), who was a professor of composition
          and music theory at the Leipzig Conservatory from 1934 to 1945 and thus a colleague of
          Oppel’s in 1939.</tei:note> auf d. Bachfest in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-006612"
          >Bremen</tei:rs> diese Pfingsten einen Vortrag über das Wesen des Kontrapunktes gehalten
        hat, – den genauen Wortlaut kenne ich noch nicht – mehr <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">pro
          domo</tei:foreign> u. mehr um seine retrospective Art alt-niederländischen Kontrapunkts zu
        rechtfertigen. Dass <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000027">Bach</tei:rs>’s historische
        Mission u. die der <tei:pb n="2"/> Klassiker gegen diesen altniederl. Modus gerichtet war u.
        noch ist, übersieht er in seiner Kurzsichtigkeit. Und so hat Meister Schenker noch immer
        Recht und behält es auch: dass ihn die Welt noch gar nicht begriffen hat. Seine Saat wird
        erst in der Zukunft voll und ganz aufgehn; ein Trost und ein Licht- und Leitgedanke für uns.
        – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> habe ich lange
        nichts gehört. Ich selbst kam vor Schule und Arbeit zu nichts Eigenem, u. jetzt beginnen die
        mündl. Prüfungen bis zum Schluss am <tei:date when="1939-07-08">8. VII.</tei:date></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wahrscheinlich bleibt es für den <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801"
          >Jungen</tei:rs> u. mich bei <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002334">Tirol</tei:rs> in d.
        Ferien. Andrerseits plant die hiesige Dantegesellschaft eine sehr billige Reise nach <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002592">Italien</tei:rs> bis Neapel, – 4 Tage in Italien
          <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">gratis</tei:foreign> mit allen dabei in It., Übernachten,
        Fahrten u. Verpflegung. <tei:pb n="3"/> Sie findet aber erst Ende August / 18. Sept. statt;
        und ich weiss noch nicht ob nach dem Aufenthalt <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005266"
          >meiner Frau</tei:rs>
        <tei:supplied reason="clarity">und</tei:supplied>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006151">Brigitte</tei:rs> a. d. See meine Kasse diese it.
        Belastung aushalten wird. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Kürzlich las ich die Biographie des Ko<tei:unclear reason="cutoff"
          >mponisten</tei:unclear> Schoeck, den die Schweizer ihren „Sch<tei:unclear reason="cutoff"
          >ubert</tei:unclear>“ nennen: aber wie traurig ist das <tei:unclear reason="cutoff"
          >Ende</tei:unclear> der Entwickelung nach schönen An<tei:unclear reason="cutoff"
          >fang</tei:unclear> es fehlt doch am Charakter, dem <tei:supplied reason="cutoff"
          >guten</tei:supplied> Alten die Stange zu halten und der „Fortschritts“-teufel führt die
        Herren <tei:unclear reason="cutoff">in</tei:unclear> Irrlichtersümpfe. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich freue mich, dass Sie verhältnismässig gut in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-003337">Küb</tei:rs> getroffen <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">word
          cut off</tei:note> man wird immer bescheidener <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"
          >word cut off</tei:note> Schliesslich kommt es ja auch mehr auf die innere Ruhe an. Das
        Äussere können wir nicht bestimmen. Bleiben Sie die ganze Zeit bis zum Herbst dort?<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Küb: a village in Lower Austria, about
          35 miles southwest of Vienna. – Jeanette Schenker was in Küb am Semmering from at least
          April to early July 1939, but was back in Vienna soon after that, at the Sanatorium
          Perchtoldsdorf, and by August at Sankt Veitgasse 7, Vienna XIII, then back in Küb again by
          October. </tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> Hoffentlich gibt es nun einen ordentlichen warmen Sommer, denn wir
        haben es noch immer kühl u. viel Regen bisher. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wie sind die Pensionspreise in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003337">Küb</tei:rs>?
        Es scheint auch in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002334">Tirol</tei:rs> nach d. Zeitungen
        eine Preissteigerung gegen früher eingetreten zu sein. Wie schön war es doch immer in
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>! Mit Freuden denke ich der
        herrlichen Tage, die ich mit Ihnen und dem Meister dort verbringen durfte. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun wünsche ich Ihnen Ruhe, viel Sonne und Erholung und bleibe mit den herzlichsten
        Grüssen von uns allen in treustem Gedenken </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Ihr sehr ergebener</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1939-06-17">June 17, 1939</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">My dear, highly revered <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000771">Mrs. Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
            type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>You know how much I think about our beloved Master, and you, on his birthday. I am all
        the more saddened by what you write to me about his work in your last letter of <tei:date
          when="1939-05-09">May 9</tei:date>. But intellectually lofty and true ideas do not perish.
        In this regard I think of the bitter personal fate of Rousseau, for whom his time was also
        not ready.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>And I just read that my colleague David,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"
        /> who gave a paper on the meaning of counterpoint at the Bach festival in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-006612">Bremen</tei:rs> this Pentecost – the exact title I do not
        yet know –more on his own behalf, and more to justify his retrospective style of
        old-Netherlandish counterpoint. That <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000027"
        >Bach</tei:rs>’s historical mission, and those of the <tei:pb n="2"/> Classical composers,
        was and still is directed against this old-Netherlandish mode is something that he overlooks
        in his shortsightedness. And so Master Schenker is still always right and has been proved
        right: that the world has not by any means yet understood him. His seed will germinate
        fully, entirely, only in the future; this is a comfort for us, and a thought that will lead
        us and light our way. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I have heard nothing from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922"
          >Vrieslander</tei:rs> for a long time. I myself did not get to any of my own things –
        school and work took precedence – and now the oral tests have begun; they will finish on
          <tei:date when="1939-07-08">July 8</tei:date>. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>It is probable that the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801">boys</tei:rs> and I
        will again go to the <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002334">Tyrol</tei:rs> in the
        holidays. On the other hand, the local Dante Society is planning a very cheap trip to
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002592">Italy</tei:rs>, as far as Naples – four days in
        Italy free of charge, everything in Italy included: accommodation, transport and
        subsistence. <tei:pb n="3"/> But it doesn’t take place until from the end of August to
        September 18; and I still do not know whether my cash box can cover this Italian burden
        after <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005266">my wife</tei:rs>
        <tei:supplied reason="clarity">and</tei:supplied>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006151">Brigitte</tei:rs>’s residence at the sea.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Recently I read the biography of the co<tei:unclear reason="cutoff"
          >mposer</tei:unclear> Schoeck, whom the Swiss call their “Sch<tei:unclear reason="cutoff"
          >ubert</tei:unclear>”: but how sad is the <tei:unclear reason="cutoff">end</tei:unclear>
        of development after beautiful <tei:unclear reason="cutoff">beginnings</tei:unclear>: there
        is a lack in the character of being loyal to the <tei:supplied reason="cutoff"
          >good</tei:supplied> old masters, and the Devil of “progress” is leading the gentlemen
        into morasses of eerie lights.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I am glad to hear that you got along relatively well in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-003337">Küb</tei:rs>. <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">word cut
          off</tei:note> one becomes ever more modest <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">word
          cut off</tei:note>. In the end, it is indeed more a matter of inner peace. What lies
        outside us is something we cannot determine. Will you stay there the entire time, until the
          autumn?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> I hope that there will now be a decent, warm summer, as it has
        always been cool here, with much rain, even until now. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>How much does a guesthouse in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003337">Küb</tei:rs>
        cost? It seems that in the <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002334">Tyrol</tei:rs>, too,
        there has been an increase in prices compared to previous years, according to the
        newspapers. How lovely it always used to be in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292"
          >Galtür</tei:rs>! I recall with joy those splendid days which I was permitted to spend
        there with you and the Master.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Now, I wish you peace, much sunshine, and recovery, and with the most cordial greetings
        from us all, in most faithful remembrance,</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Your very devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
