<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2265" sdoID="OJ-12-11_10">OJ 12/11, [10]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="PvK" scope="sole">Paul von Klenau's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>


    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2012-09-26" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-007030">KlenauP ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Klenau to Schenker, dated September 23, 1924</dc:title>
      <dcterms:created>1924-09-23T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-09-03</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Klenau sends a letter he has received from Felix Weingartner and his own
        response.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Bemerkungen; remarks; Erwiderung; response; Artikel; article; Karten;
        tickets</dc:subject>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000443">Paul von Klenau</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>

    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#PvK"/>Hoch verehrter Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000632"
            type="person">Professor</tei:rs>!‒<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
            place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/6, p.
            2728‒2729, September 23, 1924: "Von Klenau Brief u. Abzug von Weingartners Erwiderung:
            dazu wieder Klenaus Erwiderung." ("Letter and a copy of Weingartner's response from
            Klenau: in addition, Klenau's response to that."). This letter is presented in
            translation in <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Heinrich Schenker: Selected
                Correspondence</tei:title>, ed. <tei:editor>Ian Bent</tei:editor>, <tei:editor>David
                Bretherton</tei:editor>, and <tei:editor>William Drabkin</tei:editor> (Woodbridge:
              Boydell Press, 2014), p. 249</tei:bibl>.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Anbei erlaube ich mir Ihnen die Bemerkungen <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000948"
          >Felix Weingartner</tei:rs>s zu meinem Artikel<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Paul von Klenau</tei:author>,
              <tei:title level="a">Die 'Klassische' Neunte,</tei:title>
            <tei:title level="j">Pult und Taktstock</tei:title> iv (July 4, 1924)</tei:bibl>, a copy
          of which is preserved in OJ 41/6.</tei:note> zu <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">legen</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">schicken</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> ‒ und meine Erwiderung darauf. Ich danke Ihnen herzlich für Ihren
          Brief<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">This letter is not known
          to survive, but its writing is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/6, p. 2727, September
          20, 1924: "An Klenau (Br.): zurück Brief von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006849"
            >Rickert</tei:rs>; im Facsimile die betreffende Stelle nachgesehen, eine Anweisung an
          den Kopisten gefunden, war aber durch den Ladenschluss zu sehr bedrängt; empfehle das
          Vermischte zum 8. Heft nachzulesen; danke für den Rickert-Brief; Kapellmeister Lorenz muß
          mit den übergreifenden Zusammenhängen irregehen, da bloß willkürlich herausgezupfte Punkte
          ohne Stimmführungsbeleg keinen Zusammenhang bedeuten." ("To Klenau (letter): I return
          letter from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006849">Rickert</tei:rs>; looked at the
          passage in question in the facsimile, found an instruction to the copyist, but was too
          hurried because the store was closing; recommend reading through the "Miscellanea" for the
          eighth issue; I thank him for the Rickert letter; music director Lorenz must be mistaken
          about the overarching connections, since just arbitrarily selected points without evidence
          of voice-leading do not constitute a connection.")</tei:note> ‒ Heute werde ich in die
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">U-E</tei:rs> gehen und bitten, dass man
        mir das <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001747">Heft 8 der
          <tei:title>TW</tei:title></tei:rs> zeigt. Dürfte ich Sie bitten die grosse
        Lierbenswürdigkeit zu haben mir das Einliegende zurückzuschicken ‒ Ich möchte nicht gern in
        Anschluss an diesen Artikel etwas in Druck geben ‒ ohne mit Ihnen conferiert zu
          haben.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker's response is
          recorded in his diary at OJ 3/6, p. 2729, September 24, 1924: "An Klenau (Br. u. Beilagen
          zurück): das Wichtigste ist, im Scherzo das Tempo durch den ersten Teil u. durch das Trio
          beizubehalten; verweise auf den von mir S. 177 dargestellten motivischen Grund, mache
          aufmerksam, daß im Trio zwei statt drei Viertel auf einen Schlag von selbst den Eindruck
          einer Verlangsamung bewirken, weshalb nicht nötig ist, noch langsamer zu spielen, als es
          sich von selbst ergibt. An Weingartners Adresse gerichtet: eine echte
          Kapellmeister-Bosheit ist es, die andern als Musiker hinzustellen, die nur buchstabentreu
          sind, sich selbst für denjenigen auszugeben, der sinngemäß dirigirt. Ich sage: würde er
          den Sinn kennen, so fände er ihn vor allem schon im Buchstaben; erbitte für Samstag zwei
          Karten (Den Brief selbst der Hausbesorgerin übergeben)." <tei:lb/><tei:lb/>("To Klenau
          (letter and enclosures returned): the most important thing is to maintain the tempo in the
          Scherzo throughout the first section and throughout the Trio; refer him to the motivic
          reason described by me on p. 177, draw to his attention that in the Trio, the fact that
          there are two instead of three quarter-notes to a beat itself gives the impression of a
          retardation, which is why it is not necessary to play even more slowly than what the
          notation itself indicates. Aimed in Weingartner's direction: it is a true act of meanness
          for a music director to make the others out to be musicians who only follow <tei:supplied
            reason="clarity">the notation</tei:supplied> literally, while making oneself out to be
          the one who conducts according to the meaning. I say: if he knew the meaning, he would
          above all find it especially already present in the literal notation; ask for two tickets
          for Saturday (the letter handed over to the concierge myself)."). </tei:note></tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mit der höflichsten Empfehlung</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">und herzlichsten Grüssen</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr ergebener</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs key="entity-000443" type="person"><tei:hi
              rend="lateinschr">Paul v. Klenau</tei:hi></tei:rs>.</tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine>d. <tei:date when="1924-09-23">23/Spt 24</tei:date>.</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Jacquingasse 15 Parterre</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-20">III</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:p>P.S. Am <tei:date when="1924-09-27">Samstag</tei:date> und <tei:date
            when="1924-09-28">Sonntag</tei:date> dirigiere ich wi<tei:supplied reason="spelling"
            >e</tei:supplied>der die <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001269"
              ><tei:title>IX</tei:title></tei:rs> im <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003998"
            >Konzerthaus</tei:rs> ‒ Falls Sie Karten haben wollen ‒ bitte ich Sie dieses nur zu
            äussern.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Klenau delivered
            tickets for three loge seats to the Schenkers in person on September 2 (OJ 3/6, p.
            2730), and Schenker records the concert in his diary at OJ 3/6, p. 2731, September 27,
            1924: "Im Konzert: Fest-Feier aus Anlaß des 20-jährigen Bestehens der Arbeiter-Konzerte!
            Eine infame Rede von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003384">D<tei:hi
                rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Bach</tei:rs> aus der man deutlich entnehmen konnte,
            daß er nicht wisse, ob er vor sich ein schon gebildetes oder erst zu bildendes Publikum
            habe! Den Anfang machen zwei Choralvorspiele von <tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000027">Bach</tei:rs>, von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798"
              >Schönberg</tei:rs> instrumentirt: zu kurz das erste, das zweite zur Instrumentierung
            sehr geeignet; eine Sinfonische Dichtung von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006054"
              >Salmhofer</tei:rs>: ein überlanges Nichts mit dem üblichen Schwung einer talentlosen
            Jugend vorgebracht; zum Schluss die „<tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001269"
                ><tei:title>IX.</tei:title></tei:rs>“; der 1. Satz zeigt noch die meisten Mängel,
            das Scherzo im 1. Teil zu schnell, dann besser. Im Trio noch immer eine kleine Neigung
            zum schleppen, das Adagio vorzüglich, einschließlich der langen Bogen der Geiger. Der
            letzte Satz sehr gut." <tei:lb/><tei:lb/>("In the concert: celebration to mark the 20th
            anniversary of the Concerts for Workers! A disgraceful speech by <tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-003384">Dr. Bach</tei:rs> from which one could clearly deduce that he does
            not know whether he is facing an already educated audience or one that first needs to be
            educated! It begins with two chorale preludes by <tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000027">Bach</tei:rs> arranged for instruments by <tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000798">Schoenberg</tei:rs>: the first too short, the second very well
            suited for instrumental arrangement; a symphonic poem by <tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-006054">Salmhofer</tei:rs>: an overly long nothing played with the typical
            vigor of an untalented youth; at the end the <tei:rs type="composition"
              key="entity-001269"><tei:title>Ninth</tei:title></tei:rs>; the first movement still
            shows the most flaws, the Scherzo in the first section is too fast, then better. In the
            Trio, still a slight tendency to drag, the Adagio is superb, including the long bowings
            by the violins. The last movement is very good."). </tei:note></tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#PvK"/>Highly revered Professor <tei:supplied
            reason="identity"><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"
            >Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"
          /></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>I take the liberty of enclosing herewith <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000948"
          >Felix Weingartner</tei:rs>'s remarks concerning my article,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> and my response to them. My cordial thanks for your letter.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> I shall go to <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002408">UE</tei:rs> today and ask them to show me <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001747">issue 8 of <tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>. May
        I ask you to be so kind as to return the enclosed to me? I should not like to say anything
        in connection with this article in print without having conferred with you.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">With warmest compliments</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">and most cordial greetings,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs key="entity-000443" type="person">Paul v.
            Klenau</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:date when="1924-09-23">September 23, 1924</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Jacquingasse 15, 1st <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">=
              ground</tei:note> floor</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-20"><tei:supplied reason="location">Vienna</tei:supplied>
            III</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:p>P.S. On <tei:date when="1924-09-27">Saturday</tei:date> and <tei:date
            when="1924-09-28">Sunday</tei:date> I am again conducting the <tei:rs type="composition"
            key="entity-001269"><tei:title>Ninth</tei:title></tei:rs> in the <tei:rs type="place"
            key="entity-003998">Konzerthaus</tei:rs>. If you should wish to have tickets, please
          just let me know.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/></tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>



    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
