<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3683" sdoID="OJ-13-10_32">OJ 13/10, [32]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="TLJ">
      <tei:persName>Timothy L. Jackson</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2010</tei:resp>

    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated November 29, 1925</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1925-11-29T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-07-21</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel thanks Schenker for his condolences, describes his domestic situation,
        sends him a Chopinesque étude with the promise of more compositions, and says that his
        Fourth String Quartet will be performed in a few days' time.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002757"
              >Kiel</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1925-11-29">29. XI 25.</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Feldstr 77<tei:hi rend="supralinear">IV</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt
            of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for December 1, 1925: “Von Oppel (Br.):
            schickt auch zwei Notenhefte, eine Suite u. Etüden.” (“From Oppel (letter): he also
            sends two music manuscript books, a suite and etudes.”). — All paragraph-breaks are
            editorial.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Sie wundern sich gewiss über mein langes Schweigen, aber in mir ist noch alles
        zerissen, Nacht und Chaos. Herzlichen Dank für Ihre herzlichen Beileidsbezeugungen!<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker‘s message of sympathy is
          recorded in his diary for August 16, 1925: “An Oppel (Br.): Beileid – verrate einiges aus
          dem <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001751">II. Jahrbuch</tei:rs>.” (“To Oppel (letter):
          condolences – I reveal a few things from <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001751">Yearbook
            II</tei:rs>.”).</tei:note> Den <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801">Jungen</tei:rs>
        gehts gut, ich hause mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> und
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003957">Walter</tei:rs> wieder allein, <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-008510">Hans Reinhard</tei:rs> hat meine Schwägerin mit nach
        Münster genommen, sehr gegen meinen Willen, aber der <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-008510">Junge</tei:rs> braucht eine mütterliche Hand und würde bei uns rauhen
        Kriegern seelisch verkümmern. 2 Mädchen habe ich schon entlassen müssen, wegen
        Unselbstständigkeit u. w herrscht vorläufig einmal wieder mein männl. Kücheninterregnum u.
        nur Donnerstags und Montags kommt eine alte Aufwartefrau, um mir die Stuben zu reinigen.
        Witwernöte. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich hätte Ihnen so viel zu schreiben, verschiebe es aber bis zu den Weihnachtsferien,
        wo ich hoffentlich etwas zur Ruhe komme. Am <tei:date when="1925-12-13">1<tei:subst>
            <tei:del rend="overwritten">2</tei:del>
            <tei:add place="superimposed">3</tei:add>
          </tei:subst>. Dec</tei:date> wird hier mein 4. Streichquartett aufgeführt zum ersten
        Male, langsam fange ich wieder an zu komponieren. Hier die gedruckten Stücke! Etude Des ist
        zwar etwas <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000149">Chopin</tei:rs>, aber erst soll mans
        können u. es dann überwinden. Mehr schicke ich Weihn. An der Suite habe ich nichts geändert,
        obwohl ich Ihre Ausstellungen durchaus anerkenne. Nur mit der Füllung der Pause – ich habe
        es öfters versucht – kann ich mich bei der Suite nicht befreunden. Mein Instinct ist
        dagegen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wie geht es Ihnen? Was machen Sie? Hoffentlich sind Sie beide gesundlich auf der Höhe.
          <tei:pb n="2"/> Mir geht es nicht besonders, ich schlafe kaum. Und m. einzige Erholung ist
        noch das Baden, vorgestern bei -1 Luft und +3 Wasser. Ich werde es aber jetzt weniger wegen
        der Temperatur als aus Zeitmangel aufgeben müssen. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich habe verschiedenes Neue bei <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000027">Bach</tei:rs>
        entdeckt, u. bei <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beeth.</tei:rs>, darüber dann
        ausführlicher Weihn. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Lassen Sie sichs gut gehn u. gelegentlich was hören!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mit herzlichem Gruss Ihnen beiden</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Ihr treuer dankbarer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002757"
              >Kiel</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1925-11-29">November 29,
            1925</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Feldstraße 77/4</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">My dear Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>You must be wondering about my long silence; but in me everything is still torn apart,
        night, and chaos. Heartfelt thanks for your heartfelt expressions of sympathy.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> The <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801"
          >boys</tei:rs> are well, I am living alone again with <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003957"
          >Walter</tei:rs>; my sister-in-law took <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008510">Hans
          Reinhard</tei:rs> with her to Münster, much against my will, but the <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-008510">boy</tei:rs> needs a maternal hand and would have been emotionally
        impoverished among us coarse warriors. I have already had to dismiss two maids, because they
        could not work independently, and my masculine culinary interregnum is again in charge for
        the time being. Only on Thursdays and Mondays does an old cleaning lady come, to clean the
        rooms for me. The hardships of being a widower!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I would have had so much to write to you about, but will postpone this until the
        Christmas holidays when, I hope, I shall get some peace. On <tei:date when="1925-12-13"
          >December 13</tei:date>, my Fourth String Quartet will be performed here for the first
        time; I am slowly getting back to composing. Enclosed are the printed pieces! The étude in
          D<tei:g type="flat"/> is, to be sure, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000149"
          >Chopin</tei:rs>esque; but first one should learn how, and then overcome <tei:supplied
          reason="clarity">the stylistic dependence</tei:supplied>. I shall send you more at
        Christmas. I have changed nothing in the Suite, although I am entirely aware of your
        objections. It is only with the filling-in of the rest – I have made several attempts at
        this – that I cannot come to terms. My instinct opposes it.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>How are you? What are you doing? I hope that both of you are in the peak of health.
          <tei:pb n="2"/> I’m not particularly well, I hardly sleep. And my only form of recovery is
        still bathing: air -1 deg., water +3 deg. I shall have to give this up now, less on account of the
        temperature than lack of time. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I have discovered various new things in <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000027"
          >Bach</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>; more
        about this at Christmas.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I hope that you are doing well, and that I shall hear from you from time to
        time!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">With cordial greetings to you both, </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Your faithful and grateful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
