<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3800" sdoID="OJ-13-10_192">OJ 13/10, [192]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2025</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008522">Oppel ~
        JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Jeanette Schenker, dated March 9, 1935</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1935-03-09T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-09-22</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel assures Jeanette that she has done all the right things in her devotion
        to her late husband’s work, and gives some news of his family.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1935-03-09">9. III 35</tei:date>.
          </tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Hochverehrte liebe <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
            >Frau Professor Schenker</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>am <tei:date when="1935-03-08">8.</tei:date> kam Ihr Brief erst an, so dass ich leider
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000164">Deutsch</tei:rs>’s Rundfunkvortrag nicht gehört
          habe<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">No broadcast talk by Otto
          Erich Deutsch seems to have been recorded in the house magazine of <tei:rs
            type="organization" key="entity-002755">Radio-Wien</tei:rs> between mid-January and
          mid-February 1935. If Deutsch had delivered a talk about Schenker and his work, it may
          have been scheduled after the relevant issue had gone to press.</tei:note> Ich hatte schon
        vorige Woche vor, Ihnen zu antworten, immer kam neue Arbeit dazwischen. Selbstverständlich
        halte ich Ihnen ebenso die Treue wie dem geliebten Meister. Wir alle haben doch nur dankbar
        zu sein, dass Sie mit Ihrer unendlichen Fürsorge für ihn ihm die Vollendung seines grossen
        Reformwerkes ermöglicht haben. Wenn ich einmal etwas später antworte, so ist nur der Andrang
        des täglichen kleinen Lebens daran schuld; meine innere Verbindung zu Ihnen und zu dem
        Lebenswerk unsres teuren Toten kann niemand und nichts stören oder gar lösen. Im Gegenteil,
        unsre Arbeit beginnt jetzt erst recht, die Ideen Heinrich Schenkers überall zu verbreiten
        und durchzusetzen. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Dass Sie, trotz Grippe u. Fieber, so emsig am „<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"
            ><tei:title level="m">fr. S</tei:title></tei:rs>“ arbeiten, war mir eine Freude zu
        hören. Es ist tragisch, dass der Meister nicht die Vollendung selbst erlebte; um so grösser
        wird die Wirkung des <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728">Schlussband</tei:rs>es auf uns
        alle sein, und die Klarheit und Logik des Verfassers wird uns allen wieder die Wunder der
        Geniewerke offenbaren, wie wir sie noch nicht gehört u. erlebt haben. Und diese Freude muss
        u. wird uns auch alle trösten. Sein Geist bleibt in uns lebendig. Diese Widmung an Sie als
        seine treuste Mitarbeiterin habe ich erwartet als selbstverständlich. Wie oft hat mir
        Meister Schenker geschrieben, dass Sie sich mit Aufopferung <tei:pb n="2"/> Ihrer gesamten
        Kräfte eingesetzt haben! Die Inschrift der Gruftplatte drückt in ihrer lapidaren Kürze u.
        Wahrheit die Summe seines Lebens aus. – Die Verkleinerung des Haushaltes wird der Pflege des
        geistigen Nachlasses zu gute kommen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
          place="foot">In June 1935 Jeanette Schenker closed up the Keilgasse house in which she and
          Heinrich had lived since 1921 and moved temporarily to a spa in Hofgastein.</tei:note>
        –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich bedaure nur, dass ich bei den augenblicklichen Verhältnissen nicht einmal nach Wien
        kann, hoffe aber, dass es mir noch vergönnt sein wird, Sie und des Meisters Ruhestätte zu
          sehn.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Heinrich Schenker’s grave
          is in the Zentralfriedhof in Vienna.</tei:note> Denn mir war es auch schmerzlich, sehr
        schmerzlich, die letzten Sommer Sie beide nicht sehn zu können. Ich hatte mir auch ein
        Grenzübertritt bei Nacht u. Nebel wohl überlegt, aber so etwas kann man nur mit einem
        gesunden Herzen vollbringen, und meinem traue ich nicht mehr ganz. Sonst hätte ich den Weg
        nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002359">Böckstein</tei:rs> gemacht. – Sobald ich kann,
        schreibe ich wieder. Heute nur noch so viel: Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000754"
          >Salzer</tei:rs> hat mir sein Buch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial"
          place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Felix Salzer</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Sinn
              und Wesen der abendländlischen Mehrstimmigkeit</tei:title> (Vienna: Saturn-Verlag,
            1935)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> geschickt, es ist sehr gut, vielleicht nur etwas zu breit. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Den Kindern geht’s gut, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008523">Bepo</tei:rs> u.
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008524">Brigitte</tei:rs> entwickeln sich ausgezeichnet,
        sie sind meine ganze Freude in dem täglichen Lebenskampfe. Am <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002872">Institut</tei:rs> sind 150 junge Leute zum Arbeitsdienst eingezogen
        für ½ Jahr, den pecuniären Ausfall müssen natürlich wieder wir Lehrer tragen. – <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-008525">Ingeborg</tei:rs> ist als Hülfsarbeiterin im
        Justizministerium verpflichtet, zur Ausarbeitung beim neuen Jugendrecht. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-008526">Wolf</tei:rs> ist in Berlin<tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002501"/> kommandiert. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003957"
          >Walter</tei:rs> klagt sehr über die Ausnützung im Geschäft, er muss bis abends 9
        arbeiten. Bei mir wird es meistens nachts 1 und 2 Uhr. – </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Mit den herzlichsten Grüssen, auch von <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-005266">meiner Frau</tei:rs></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">bleibe ich, wie immer,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr sehr ergebener und treuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1935-03-09">March 9,
              1935</tei:date>
          </tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Highly revered, dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
            >Mrs. Schenker</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Your letter did not arrive until the <tei:date when="1935-03-08">8th</tei:date>, and so
        I did not hear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000164">Deutsch</tei:rs>’s radio
          broadcast.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> I was already intending last
        week to answer your letter, but fresh work got in the way. Of course, I shall be just as
        faithful to you as I was to the dear Master. We can all only be grateful that you, with your
        incessant care for him, have made the completion of his great reform work possible. If I
        should be somewhat late in replying to you, it is only the pressures of the daily, petty
        things in my life that are to blame; no one, and nothing, can interrupt or even sever my
        inner connection to you and to the life’s work of our dearly departed. On the contrary, our
        work – to disseminate and establish the ideas of Heinrich Schenker everywhere – is beginning
        only now. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>To hear that you, in spite of the ‘flu and a fever, are working so assiduously on
          <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title level="m">Free
          Composition</tei:title></tei:rs>, was a joy to me. It is a tragedy that the Master did not
        experience the completion himself; the effect of this <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001728">final volume</tei:rs> on us all will be all the greater, and the
        author’s clarity and logic will reveal to all of us again the wonders of works of genius in
        a way in which we have not yet heard or experienced them. And this joy must, and will, also
        be a comfort to all of us. His spirit remains alive in all of us. This dedication to you, as
        his most faithful collaborator, is something I had of course expected. How often did Master
        Schenker write to me that you supported him <tei:pb n="2"/> with all your devotion. The
        inscription on his gravestone expresses, in its succinct brevity and truth, the totality of
        his life. – The reduction in your household will be of benefit to the care of his
        intellectual estate.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I am just sorry that the present conditions prevent me from coming to Vienna; I hope,
        however, that I shall still be granted the opportunity to visit you and the Master’s final
        resting place.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> For it was also painful –
        very painful – to me not to be able to see the two of you last summer. I had certainly even
        considered crossing the border in the dead of night; one can achieve something of that sort
        only with a healthy heart, and I no longer trust mine entirely. Otherwise I would have made
        my way to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002359">Böckstein</tei:rs>. – As soon as I can, I
        shall write again. For now, I will just say that Mr. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000754">Salzer</tei:rs> has sent me his book;<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
          type="footnote"/> it is very good, perhaps only a bit too broad.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>The children are well. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008523">Bepo</tei:rs> and
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008524">Brigitte</tei:rs> are developing magnificently;
        they are my entire joy in the daily struggles of life. At the <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002872">Institute</tei:rs>, 150 young people have been withdrawn from work for
        six months; we teachers must of course again bear the burden of the financial deficiency. –
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008525">Ingeborg</tei:rs> has been obliged to serve as
        an assistant in the Ministry of Justice, for the development of the new juvenile law.
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008526">Wolf</tei:rs> has been transferred to <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003957">Walter</tei:rs> complains a good deal about being exploited in his
        business; he must work until 9 o’clock in the evening. I am usually up working until 1 or 2
        o’clock in the night.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">With the most cordial greetings, also from <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-005266">my wife</tei:rs></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">I remain as ever </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your very devoted and faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
