<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3482" sdoID="OJ-14-10_15">OJ 14/10, [15]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RW" scope="major">Rosa Weil's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="AW" scope="minor">Arnold Weil's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="unk" scope="minor">unknown hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>


    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008456">WeilR ~
        JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Rosa Weil to Jeanette Schenker, dated November 24–28,
        1934</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1934-11-28T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-07-25</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>12-page letter written over four days: Arnold has, Rosa Weil agrees with
        Jeanette, taken on a paternal role over the Schiff siblings. She comments at length on
        Victor: admirable in what he has achieved, as a free man in [South] America he shows no
        concern for the troubles of his siblings in Europe, responding only by preaching Zionist
        rhetoric. Arnold, on the other hand, cares selflessly for all who are in need, while working
        from morning to night. — Jeanette is given news of her sons [whom she has not seen since
        1910], their wives and children. — Rosa reflects on her own life and responsibilities, and
        her wishes before she dies. — She proudly describes her home and the plants that she
        cultivates in it.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000944">Rosa Weil</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:fw type="envelope">
          <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold">envelope</tei:hi></tei:note><tei:lb/>
          <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="recto"/><tei:lb/>
          <tei:address>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied reason="clarity">An:</tei:supplied>
              <tei:handShift new="#RW"/>Herrn u. Frau D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi>
              Heinrich Schenker</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine>Wien III. <tei:handShift new="#unk"/>12</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RW"/>Keilgasse 8.</tei:addrLine>
          </tei:address>
          <tei:fw type="postmark">|| [ÚSTI NAD] LABEN 2 | 28.XI.34–15 | 3e | * AUSSIG 2 *
            ||</tei:fw><tei:lb/>
          <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="verso"/><tei:lb/>
          <tei:address>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied>Absender:</tei:supplied> R. Weil, Westphalenstr.
              25.</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine>Aussig a/Elbe.</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine>C. S. R.</tei:addrLine>
          </tei:address>
        </tei:fw>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold">letter</tei:hi></tei:note><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline>
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002248">Aussig</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1934-11-24">24.
            Nov. 1934</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Meine liebe <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Jenny</tei:rs>,<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in
            Heinrich‘s diary for November 29, 1934: “Von Rosl (Br.): hartes, aber richtiges Urteil
            über Victor! Meldet eigene Sorgen, haben viel auf sich genommen: Klara, Hella, Paul.”
            (“From Rosl (letter): a severe but correct judgment about Victor! She reports her own
            troubles, has taken a great many of them upon her shoulders: Klara, Hella, Paul.”). —
            With the exception of the last two, all paragraph-breaks are editorial.
          </tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>spät, aber doch, wirst Du Dir denken und mir gewiß zürnen, aber es ging beim besten
        Willen nicht und jetzt muß ich mir einen gewaltsamen <tei:unclear reason="reading"
          >Stoß</tei:unclear> geben, sonst wächst mir meine Briefschuld nach allen Seiten hin über
        den Kopf zusammen. Dringende Herbstarbeiten, ganz großer Hausputz vom Dach bis zum
        Kohlenraum hinunter, ich atme auf, daß das nun vorüber ist. Auch sonst war nicht alles
        rosig, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs> besonders hatte große
        Unannehmlichkeiten geschäftlicher Art über sich ergeben zu lassen. Man kann über diese Dinge
        nicht schreiben; schade, daß wir Schwestern nicht einmal alle beisammen sein und über alles
        plaudern können. Da wären <tei:pb n="2"/> allerdings zwei sehr schmerzliche Lücken. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Und da muß ich Dir gleich sagen, daß in <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003244"
          >Klara</tei:rs>’s Befinden leider keine Änderung zu verzeichnen ist. Die Ärmste lebt
        leider nach wie vor in ihrer Flucht aus der Wirklichkeit, negiert alles geschehene und
        bestehende und ist zeitweise so aufgeregt und lärmend, daß man garnicht daran denken kann,
        sie nachhausezunehmen. Die Ärzte geben noch immer nicht die Hoffnung auf, da man Fälle
        kennt, in denen die Krankheit nach 4–5 Jahren wenn auch nicht ganz geheilt, so noch
        bedeutend gebessert wurde, also ein kleines Fünkchen Hoffnung bleibt uns noch. Auch hier
        hört man viel seufzen und stöhnen und ich glaube, auf jeden drückt irgendwie mehr oder
        weniger unsere große und <tei:pb n="3"/> ach für viele so bitter schwere Zeit. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Und da muß ich Dir wieder sagen, daß Du sehr recht hattest mit Deiner seinerzeitigen
        Bemerkung, daß <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs> wohl in unserer
        Familie die Rolle unseres guten <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008431">Vater</tei:rs>s
        übernommen hat. Was in anderen Familien ein liebevoller Bruder tut, hat er als Schwager
        freiwillig auf seine Schultern genommen da von unseren Brüdern keiner dazu imstande oder
        willens ist. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Unser lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000783">Victor</tei:rs>! Ich freue mich
        und gönne es ihm von ganzem Herzen, daß er sich nach all den schweren, mühevollen Jahren zu
        einer schönen Höhe emporgeschwungen hat. Er hat viel durchgemacht schwer gearbeitet und
        große Kenntnisse gesammelt. Er baut Reben und Orangen, pflanzt Rosen, lebt sorglos und in
        Ruhe mit seiner neuen Gattin, hat ein großes Vermögen ge- <tei:pb n="4"/> sammelt und –
        zitiert große Geister! Alles recht schön und gut, aber, wenn man so glücklich in Ruhe und
        Sicherheit lebt nach seinen Geschwistern und seiner Heimat ein bißchen Sehnsucht hat, meidet
        man das Land aus egoistischer Angst um seine eigene Person? Und muß sich zwingen, den
        Geschwistern einen deutschen Brief zu schreiben, ein deutsches Buch zu lesen? Was hat das
        alles mit seiner zionistischen Einstellung zu tun? Niemand wird ihm seine Überzeugung
        nehmen, aber er muß andern die ihrige lassen; Chauvinismus war wir von jeher in tiefster
        Seele verhaßt<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">.</tei:supplied> Als amerikanischer
        Staatsbürger kann er überallhin kommen, wenn er nicht lästert, kann ihn nirgends ein Haar
        gekrümmt werden. Auf Reisen kann man Menschen <tei:pb n="5"/> aus aller <tei:unclear
          reason="reading">Herren</tei:unclear> Ländern begegnen und keiner der ein reines Gewissen
        hat, und sich fürchten. Und wenn man soviele Geschwister in Europa hat und die Lage kennt,
        fragt man nie, ob es auch allen gut geht, oder ob der eine oder andere von ihnen vielleicht
        Sorgen hat? Doch, einmal vor Jahren, da hat er gefragt und <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs> hat ihm getreulich über alle und alles berichtet. Aber
        da schrieb er in biblischem Stil: Ich bin kein Joseph und will kein Joseph sein; und wer
        sein Leben nicht selbst lenken und sein Schicksal fest in die Hand nehmen kann, der ist
        lebensuntüchtig und nicht wert, daß ihn der Erdboden trägt! Weiß er wirklich nicht, daß
        heute auf der ganzen Welt Millionen Menschen leben, die Kenntnisse, Wissen, Arbeitswillen
        besitzen und doch kein <tei:pb n="6"/> Unterkommen finden können? Was aber nützen dem
        Darbenden Zitate aus Dante und Jesaias? </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Seither liest <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs> nie wieder
        einen Brief von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000783">Victor</tei:rs>, will nicht von
        seinen Phrasen hören, aber – er ist da; ist da wenn <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs> von den Verpflichtungen für sein krankes <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-003244">Weib</tei:rs> beinahe erdrückt wird, ist da, wenn sich
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000782">Paul</tei:rs> mit <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000781">Weib</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008429">Kind</tei:rs>
        und Schwiegermutter kaum behaupten kann, ist da, wenn unsere arme, kleine <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-003920">Hella</tei:rs> morgen vis à vis de riens stünde, weil
        ihr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008436">Mann</tei:rs> ein Lump ist. Ist immer und für
        jeden auch außerhalb der Familie mit Rat und Hilfe zur Stelle, bis zur Selbstverleugnung.
        Verlangt für seine Person nichts als ein gepflegtes, ruhiges Heim als Buen Retria,<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:hi rend="italic">Buen
            retria</tei:hi>: perhaps <tei:hi rend="italic">Buen retiro</tei:hi>: Spanish for
          “resting place” or “retreat.” Possibly the name of the house that Victor had built for
          himself and his local wife in South America.</tei:note>
        <tei:pb n="7"/> wo er wenigstens ungestört nach intensiver verantwortungsvoller Arbeit
        (ungestört) die <tei:unclear reason="reading">div.</tei:unclear> Zeitungen lesen kann, da er
        tagsüber auch dazu nicht kommt. Verläßt früh um 7<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> das
        Haus in das er, eine kurze Mittagspause abgerechnet, um 7<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
          >h</tei:hi> abends zurückkehrt, arbeitet Jahr aus, Jahr ein auch Samstag nachm. und
        Sonntag vorm. und ist doch leider nicht mehr ganz gesund. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Du siehst, meine l. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Jenny</tei:rs>, was Du
        Lücken in meiner Familienkurzgeschichte nanntest sind so traurige unerquickliche Dinge mit
        denen ich Dich lieber hätte verschonen sollen, obgleich ich Dir das alles ja nur so
        andeutungsweise sagen kann, sei froh, daß Du diese Dinge nicht so wie wir aus nächster Nähe
        kennst und Dich nicht mit ihnen belasten mußt; denn es hat ja jeder seine eigenen Sorgen,
        von denen wir garnicht reden wollen. Soll ich sagen leider oder G.S.D. haben wir sogarkein
        Talent, die Wäsch’ wegzuhängen, wenn Komödianten kommen <tei:pb n="8"/> und so kommt man aus
        den Sorgen überhaupt nichtmehr heraus. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Von den Geschwistern unserer lieben <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008432"
          >Mutter</tei:rs> lebt nur noch <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008434">Tante
          Lotti</tei:rs>, die ich in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004561">Karlsbad</tei:rs>
        besuchte und die im kommenden Jahre 80 wird. Sie wohnt bei Regenstreifs, denen es nicht gut
        geht, ist körperlich und geistig ganz frisch. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Deine Söhne haben beide sehr hübsche, nette Frauen, (Nichtjüdinnen,) beide haben je
        einen prächtigen Buben, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity_000467">Erich</tei:rs> einen
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity_008435">Peter</tei:rs>,<tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity_000468">Felix</tei:rs> einen <tei:rs type="person" key="entity_000469"
          >Tommy</tei:rs>. Die Frau von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity_000467">Erich</tei:rs> ist
        eine Öttl<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Erich’s wife was
          Elisabeth Vobornik (born Aussig, 1906); Felix’s wife was Marianna Öttl (born Aussig, 1906;
          died ibid., 1985), their son being Thomas Karl Kornfeld (born Aussig, 1932; died ibid.,
          2015), whose correspondence with Heribert Esser survives as <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-71-21a_1">OJ 71/21a, [1]</tei:ref>, May 5, 1988 and <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-71-21a_2">OJ 71/21a, [2]</tei:ref> June 7, 1988, the
          latter revelatory of Jeanette and relationship to her first family</tei:note> früher
        einmal mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005248">Lene</tei:rs> in die Schule gegangen;
        von einer Freundschaft kann man nicht reden, weil ja <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-005248">Lene</tei:rs> leider seit Jahren fast nicht in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002248">Aussig</tei:rs> ist. Mein „ominöser Fünfziger“ ist bereits verjährt,
        seither übergehe ich diesen Tag am liebsten stillschweigend. Von mir spreche ich nicht
        gerne; man hat Fehler gemacht und macht sie noch, ich bin nicht immer so ganz mit mir
        zufrieden. Zwei Wünsche habe ich; mein <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005248"
          >Kind</tei:rs> froh und glücklich zu sehen, <tei:supplied reason="omission"
          >(</tei:supplied>bei diesen Zeiten beinahe ein anmaßender Wunsch) und meinen <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000943">Mann</tei:rs> ohne <tei:unclear reason="reading"
          >Frohn</tei:unclear> und Plage, sodaß er noch ein bißchen seinen Interessen leben könnte,
        die er doch <tei:pb n="9"/> all’sein Lebtag zurückstellen mußte. Er lastet eine große
        Verantwortung auf seinen Schultern, dazu außer den eigenen, die Sorgen so vieler anderer.
        Und noch einen dritten, ganz leisen Wunsch habe ich, den ich aber noch eine kleines bißchen
        hinausschieben möchte, ich möchte so gerne ein Ende meiner Tage mit reinem Gewissen sagen
        können. Ich war auf meinem Posten und konnte wenigstens 2 Menschen auf der Welt etwas sein.
        Auch beinahe ein anmaßender Wunsch, denn kein Mensch ist unentbehrlich oder gar unersetzlich
        und jede Lücke schließt sich automatisch. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Mein Brief ist heute zu lang und ein bißchen bitter geworden; leider habe ich in meinem
        ganzen Leben alles viel zu tragisch genommen. Woher hätte ich auch Heiterkeit nehmen sollen,
        bei den Erfahrungen meiner Jugendjahre? <tei:pb n="10"/> Trotzdem kann ich mich im tiefsten
        Innern ganz stark mit allem wirklich schönen und guten freuen; auch ich habe viele Pflanzen,
        die trotz Centralheizung hier im Hause prächtig gedeihen; ein Riesen-Gummibaum, Palmen,
        Araukarien, Zimmerlinde, <tei:unclear reason="reading">Assander</tei:unclear> Tracene, 2
        exotische Warmhauspflanzen und auch meine Kamelie hat mich heuer mit 7 herrlichen Blüten
        beschenkt. Nur etwas verfrüht und sie sind leider schon abgefallen. Dann ist noch eine
        kleine, seidige, tiefschwarze Griffon-Hündin unser Hausgenosse<tei:del rend="overstrike"
          >n</tei:del>, bereits das siebente Jahr, ist aber <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-005248">Lene</tei:rs>ns Eigentum. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wie gesagt, meine liebe Schwester, wenn Dir der Brief zu lang ist und er Dir nicht
        gefällt, wirf ihn ins Feuer. <tei:pb n="11"/> Ich wollte Dir nur einmal ganz gründlich Deine
        Fragen beantworten. Du mußt also entschuldigen, wenn ich da etwas unerquickliche Bilder vor
        Deinen Augen entrollt habe; vergiß sie wieder und wie gesagt, freue Dich, daß Du Dich nicht
        mit diesen Dingen belasten mußt. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Für <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs> habe ich eine Abschrift
        des Freiherrn v. Pappuschen Testamentes<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Freiherrn von Pappuschen Testament: unknown; the entire circumstance is
          unclear.</tei:note> in Verwahrung genommen; (er hat alle Sachen von <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-008428">Hellmuth</tei:rs>, alles was ihn erinnern könnte zu mir gegeben;) wenn
        es Dich interessiert und <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs>
        einwilligt, könnte ich es Dir einmal leihweise schicken, nur weiß ich nicht, wie, da es doch
        nicht unterwegs verloren geben dürfte. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="12"/> Nun will ich schließen und tue es mit der Bitte, mir etwaige
        Bitterkeiten in diesem Briefe nicht übelzunehmen. Es besteht bei mir niemals die Absicht,
        jemand zu kränken. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wieviele Jahre haben wir uns eigentlich nichtmehr gesehen? </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich wünsche Dir und dem lieben <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
          >Heinrich</tei:rs> alles gute und Schöne, allerbeste Gesundheit und Zufriedenheit und
        bleibe </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>mit den herzlichsten Grüßen von mir und den Meinen</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Euere Schwester</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000944"
          >Rosa</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p><tei:handShift new="#AW"/>Beim Briefschreiben werde ich immer gestört und so kann
          auch dieser erst am <tei:date when="1934-11-28">28. d.</tei:date> weggehen. </tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:fw type="envelope">
          <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold">envelope</tei:hi></tei:note><tei:lb/>
          <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="recto"/><tei:lb/>
          <tei:address>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied reason="clarity">To:</tei:supplied>
              <tei:handShift new="#RW"/>Dr. and Mrs. Heinrich Schenker</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine>Vienna III <tei:handShift new="#unk"/>12</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RW"/>Keilgasse 8</tei:addrLine>
          </tei:address>
          <tei:fw type="postmark">|| [ÚSTI NAD] LABEN 2 | 28.XI.34–15 | 3e | * AUSSIG 2 *
            ||</tei:fw><tei:lb/>
          <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="verso"/><tei:lb/>
          <tei:address>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied reason="clarity">From:</tei:supplied> R. Weil,
              Westphalenstraße 25</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine>Aussig on the Elbe</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine>Czechoslovakia</tei:addrLine>
          </tei:address>
        </tei:fw>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold">letter</tei:hi></tei:note><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline>
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002248">Aussig</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1934-11-24"
            >November 24, 1934</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Jenny</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>


      <tei:p rend="first">Better late than never, you will surely be thinking, and you will
        certainly be vexed with me; but with the best will in the world it didn’t happen, and now I
        must give myself a hefty slap, otherwise my guilt over letter-writing will grow on all sides
        and engulf me. Urgent autumn chores, a complete house clean from top to bottom, I heave a
        sigh of relief that it is all now done. In other respects as well, not everything was rosy.
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs> in particular couldn’t stop big
        unpleasantnesses on the business front from overwhelming him. One can’t write about these
        matters; it’s a pity that we sisters are never all together and able to chat about it all.
        There would, <tei:pb n="2"/> however, be two very painful lacunae.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>And now I must tell you right away that, alas, no change is to be discerned in <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-003244">Klara</tei:rs>’s condition. The poor dearest one lives,
        sadly, now as ever in an escape from reality, denies all that has gone before, and
        occasionally gets so agitated and shrill that the very idea of taking her home is utterly
        unthinkable. The doctors still never give up hope, since they know of cases in which after
        four or five years the illness, if not completely cured, improves so significantly, and that
        we are left still with a tiny glimmer of hope. Here, too, one hears much moaning and
        sighing, and it’s my belief that, to a great or lesser extent, everyone feels weighed down
        by such bitter and harsh times as <tei:pb n="3"/> we are experiencing.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>And now I must say to you again that you were absolutely right in your remark of a
        while ago that <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs> has assumed the
        role that our good <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008431">father</tei:rs> played in the
        family. What in other families a responsibly-minded brother takes on he, as a
        brother-in-law, has willingly taken on his shoulders, since none of our brothers is in a
        position, or is willing, to do.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Our dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000783">Victor</tei:rs>! I rejoice and
        wholeheartedly give him credit for having under all those arduous and painstaking years
        risen considerably in standing. He has accomplished a lot, worked hard, and accumulated
        great knowledge. He cultivates vines and oranges, plants roses, lives a carefree and
        tranquil life with his new wife, has <tei:pb n="4"/> acquired a large fortune and – cites
          <tei:supplied reason="clarity">the words of</tei:supplied> great minds! All well and good,
        but if one lives so happily in contentment and security, and harbors a little longing for
        his siblings and his homeland, is it right to shun one’s country out of egotistical fear for
        one’s own person? And has to force himself to write a letter in German to his siblings or to
        read a book in German? What has all of that to do with his Zionist allegiance? No one will
        take his convictions <tei:supplied reason="clarity">from him</tei:supplied>, but he must
        allow others theirs; all our lives we detested chauvinism with all our might. As an American
        citizen, he can go wherever he likes; so long as he doesn’t commit slander, no one anywhere
        can lay a finger on him. When travelling, one can meet people <tei:pb n="5"/> from all lands
        not one of whom has a clear conscience, and be afraid. And when one has so many siblings in
        Europe and knows the situation they are in, does one never inquire whether all is well with
        them, or whether one or other of them perhaps has any worries? Once years ago, he inquired,
        and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs> reported faithfully on
        everyone and everything. But he wrote back in biblical style: I am no Joseph and do not want
        to be a Joseph; and whoever does not govern the course of his own life and have his fate
        firmly in his own hand, he is unfit for life and unworthy of being borne up by the earth!
        Does he really not know that today, throughout the world, there live millions of people who
        possess skills, knowledge, and the will to work, but cannot find <tei:pb n="6"/> a job? Of
        what use are quotations from Dante and Jesus to starving people?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Since then, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs> will never again
        read a letter from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000783">Victor</tei:rs>, refuses to
        listen to his claptrap, but – he is there: is there when <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs> is well-nigh overwhelmed by his duties toward his sick
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003244">wife</tei:rs>; is there when <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000782">Paul</tei:rs> can barely cope with <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000781">wife</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008429"
          >child</tei:rs> and mother-in-law; is there if our poor little <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003920">Hella</tei:rs> were to wake up tomorrow with nothing, because her
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008436">husband</tei:rs> is an idiot. He is always
          <tei:supplied reason="clarity">there</tei:supplied> and for each one, even outside the
        family on the scene with advice and help to the point of self-renunciation. He demands
        nothing for his person other than a well cared-for, peaceful home as <tei:hi rend="italic"
          >Buen Retria</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/>
        <tei:pb n="7"/> where he can read the various newspapers leastways undisturbed after
        intensive, responsible work (undisturbed), since he can’t do so during the daytime. He
        leaves the house at 7 o’clock in the morning and, with the exception of a short midday
        break, returns at 7 o’clock in the evening, works year in year out, even on Saturday
        afternoon and Sunday morning, and is, sad to say, no longer in good health.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>You see, my dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Jenny</tei:rs>, what you
        called lacunae in my short family history are sad, unedifying matters that I would have
        preferred to spare you, albeit I can speak to you of them all only very sketchily. Be glad
        that you don’t know these things at first hand, as we do, and don’t have to burden yourself
        with them; for, after all, everyone has his own troubles of which we know absolutely
        nothing. I could say, sadly – or thankfully – we have so little talent at putting the
        laundry out of sight when comedians arrive; <tei:pb n="8"/> and so we can no longer find any
        means of escaping from our troubles.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Of the sisters of our dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008432">mother</tei:rs>,
        the only one still alive is <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008434">Aunt Lotti</tei:rs>,
        whom I visited in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004561">Karlsbad</tei:rs>, and she will
        be 80 next year. She lives with the Regenstreifs, (who are not at all well) and is full of
        life in body and mind.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Your sons both have pretty, likeable wives (non-Jews), and each has one splendid child:
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity_000467">Erich</tei:rs> has <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity_008435">Peter</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity_000468"
          >Felix</tei:rs> has <tei:rs type="person" key="entity_000469">Tommy</tei:rs>. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity_000467">Erich</tei:rs>’s wife is an Öttl,<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> who was at one time in school with <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-005248">Lene</tei:rs> – not that they are friends, since <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-005248">Lene</tei:rs> has, alas, scarcely been in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002248">Aussig</tei:rs> for years. My “dreaded 50th" is already
        behind me, since when I pass over this day preferably in silence. I don’t like talking about
        myself; mistakes have been made and still are; I’m not always so very pleased with myself. I
        have two wishes: to see my <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005248">child</tei:rs> happy
        and contented (these days a somewhat presumptuous wish), and to see my <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000943">husband</tei:rs> without <tei:unclear reason="clarity"
          >vexation</tei:unclear> and worry so that he might enjoy a little of the interests that he
          <tei:pb n="9"/> has wanted to get back to all his life. He carries a great sense of
        responsibility on his shoulders, not only his own but the troubles of many others. I have a
        third wish, too, an unspoken one, but one that I still should like to put off a little
        longer: I should so very much like to be able to say at end my days that I have a clear
        conscience. I stayed at the helm, and was able to be something for at least two people in
        the world. Also a somewhat presumptuous wish, for no man is indispensable or even
        irreplaceable, and every lacuna is automatically filled.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Today’s letter is too long and has acquired a rather bitter tone. Unfortunately, I have
        taken everything much too tragically throughout my life. Where, from among the experiences
        of my youth, should I ever have acquired merriment? <tei:pb n="10"/> Nonetheless, in my
        innermost being I can take keen pleasure in all that is truly beautiful and good. In
        addition, I have many plants that, despite central heating, thrive splendidly here in the
        house: a giant gum tree, palms, araucarias, an African hemp, <tei:unclear
          reason="original_unclear">assander</tei:unclear> tracene, two exotic hothouse plants; in
        addition, my camelia has presented me this year with seven magnificent blooms. Only somewhat
        early arriving, and that have sadly already fallen. Also, our house companion is a small,
        silky, jet-black miniature griffon dog, already in its seventh year, but it belongs to
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005248">Lene</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>As I’ve already said, my dear sister, if this letter is too long and displeases you,
        throw it into the fire. {<tei:pb n="11"/> I only wanted for once to answer your questions in
        real detail. You must therefore excuse me if I have paraded any unedifying images before
        your eyes. Forgive them and, as said, be thankful that you do not have to suffer these
        things.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>For <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs>, I have taken a copy for
        safe keeping of the Baron von Pappusch testament<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
          type="footnote"/> (he got all these items from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008428"
          >Hellmuth</tei:rs>; all that he could remember to give to me). If it interests you and
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs> agrees, I could send it to you
        sometime on loan, only I don’t know how since it must not get lost in transit.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="12"/> It’s time for me to close, and in doing so to beg you not to think the
        worse of me for possible displays of bitterness. It is never my intention to cause offense
        to anyone.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>How many years is it since we actually saw another?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I wish you and dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs> the
        very best, good health and contentment, and remain </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>with the most cordial greetings from me and my family</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your sister</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000944"
          >Rosa</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p><tei:handShift new="#AW"/>I an always be utterly exhausted by letter-writing, so even
          this one cannot go off before the <tei:date when="1934-11-28">28th</tei:date>.</tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
