<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3279" sdoID="OJ-10-3_205">OJ 10/3, [205]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPoed" scope="major">Otto Erich Deutsch typist</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="OED" scope="minor">Otto Erich Deutsch's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2023</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IDB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2015-09-18" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002726">DeutschOE ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002712">DeutschOE ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002727">DeutschOE+H ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Typewritten letter from Deutsch to Schenker, dated January 6, 1934</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1934-01-06T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2023-09-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Deutsch sounds out Schenker on various performance projects he has in mind,
        including performances of Schubert part-songs in their original setting for four soloists
        (for which the radio would be an ideal medium) and choruses and arias from his operas that
        have never been performed.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000164">DeutschOE</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>PROF. OTTO ERICH DEUTSCH</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Tel. R 45–6–72</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">WIEN II.</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Böcklinstraße 26</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/><tei:date when="1934-01-06">6.
            Januar 34</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Verehrter</tei:rs>!<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in
            Schenker’s diary for January 8, 1934: “Von Deutsch (Br.): Pläne.” (“From Deutsch
            (letter): plans.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008405">Architekt
            <tei:sic>Schmidt</tei:sic></tei:rs> erfuhr ich heute vertraulich, dass <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000380">H.</tei:rs> wieder gesund <tei:del rend="overstrike"
          >ist</tei:del>, dass die Ehe nach wie vor unfriedlich ist, dass er aber nach Wien strebt
        und hier heuer bauen will. Gott erhalt’ ihn bei dieser Absicht! Uebrigens will er allein
        Anfang Februar herkommen. Ein Brief dürfte Sie bald von den Plänen verständigen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich schreibe Ihnen heute aber <tei:del rend="overstrike">mehr</tei:del>,
        um Sie zu befragen, was Sie zu diesen Gedanken meinen: </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000803">Schubert</tei:rs>s „Männerchöre“
        sind als Solquartette geschrieben, er hat sie auch nie anders gehört und gedacht. Ich meine,
        dass man die Erfindung des Radios <tei:del rend="overstrike">auch</tei:del> dazu benützen
        müsste, das Original hier wieder herzustellen, die Quartette von vier guten, vielleicht
        sogar hervorragenden Solostimmen singen zu lassen. Ich fürchte nur, das Berufssänger nicht
        dazu zu haben sein werden, derlei für eine, wenn auch gut bezahlte Aufführung zu studieren.
        Gerne möchte ich alle Quartette in einem Zyklus aufführen lassen, aber es wird, wenn
        überhaupt nur mit einem Soloquartett eines der drei guten Vereine möglich sein. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Neulich ist mir auch die Barbarei deutlich bewusst geworden, die darin
        liegt, solche Quartette oder gemischte als Chöre von 100 bis 300 Sängern mit Begleitung
        eines <tei:hi rend="underline">Klaviers</tei:hi> vorzutragen. Viele sind ja glücklicherweise
        ohne Begleitung, und da stört die Aenderung weniger. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">(Dabei gibt es gewiss ebenso viel Chöre, wirkliche Chöre, aus <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000803">Schubert</tei:rs>s totgeborenen Opern zu heben, meist
        mit Orchesterbegleitung.) </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Darüber erbitte ich mir sehr Ihre Meinung, es hat aber auch Zeit, bis wir
        uns wieder sehen, damit Sie nicht viel schreiben müssen, oder sonst nur, was auf eine Karte
        geht.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich bringe nächstens bei der <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-004436">Ravag</tei:rs> (Literarische Abteilung!) eine sehr geschmackvolle
        Einrichtung von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000610">Mottl</tei:rs> zur Aufführung, die
        ich in einzelnen Punkten noch verbessern konnte: Raimunds „<tei:title>Gefesselte
          Phantasie</tei:title>“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"
            ><tei:title level="m">Die gefesselte Phantasie</tei:title> (The Imagination Bound), a
          magical play first performed in January 1828, written by the Austrian actor and playwright
          Ferdinand Raimund (1794–1836).</tei:note> mit der Musik der verschollenen
          „<tei:title>Zauberharfe</tei:title>“, die <tei:pb n="2"/> nur von der Ouvertüre aus
        bekannt ist (die sog. <tei:title>Rosamunden-Ouvertüre</tei:title>). </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ein weiterer Plan ist für die ziemlich unzugängliche musikalische
        Abteilung: Arien und Duette aus <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000803">Schubert</tei:rs>s
        unbekannten Opern, mit Klavier- oder mit Orchester-Begleitung. Ich habe zwei Dutzend
        zusammengestellt, ausgewählte, für Männer- und für Frauenstimmen. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">4:2!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Herzlichst ergeben Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/><tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000164">O E Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>PROF. OTTO ERICH DEUTSCH</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Tel. R 45–6–72</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">VIENNA II</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Böcklinstraße 26</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/><tei:date when="1934-01-06"
            >January 6, 1934</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">friend</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Today I learned from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008405">architect
          Schmid</tei:rs>, in confidence, that <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380"
          >Hoboken</tei:rs> is back in good health, that the marriage is as unpeaceful as it was
        before, but that he is striving to come to Vienna and build here this year. May God protect
        him in his intentions! Moreover, he expects to come here on his own at the beginning of
        February. A letter is supposed to inform you of these plans. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">But I am writing to you today to ask you what you think of the following
        ideas:</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000803">Schubert</tei:rs>’s “male
        choruses” were written as solo quartets; he never heard or conceived of them in any other
        way. I think that one would have to take advantage of the invention of the radio to restore
        the original here, by having the quartets sung by four good, perhaps even outstanding, solo
        voices. I fear only that there will not be professional singers of the sort who would want
        to learn them for a performance, even for a well-paid performance. I would dearly like to
        have all the quartets performed as a cycle; but that would be possible, if at all, only with
        a solo quartet from one of the three good <tei:supplied reason="clarity">male
          choral</tei:supplied> societies.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Recently I have become distinctly aware of the barbarity of the
        performance of such quartets, or mixed-voice ensembles, by choruses for 100 to 300 singers
        with the accompaniment of a <tei:hi rend="underline">piano</tei:hi>. Many are, fortunately,
        performed without accompaniment, and then the change is less intrusive.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">(At the same time there are certainly just as many choruses, true
        choruses, to be lifted from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000803">Schubert</tei:rs>’s
        stillborn operas, most of which are with orchestral accompaniment.)</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">On this I would very much like your opinion, but it can wait until we see
        each other again, so that you don’t have to write a lot, or indeed no more than what can be
        got on to a postcard.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I shall shortly be arranging for a performance on <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-004436">Austrian Radio</tei:rs> (literary department!) of
        a very tasteful adaptation by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000610">Mottl</tei:rs>,
        which I have also been able to improve in a few details: Raimund’s <tei:title level="m">Die
          gefesselte Phantasie</tei:title>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> with
        music from the lost <tei:title level="m">Zauberharfe</tei:title>, <tei:pb n="2"/> which is
        well known only from its overture, the so-called <tei:title>“Rosamunde”
        Overture</tei:title>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">A further plan is intended for the rather unapproachable music department:
        arias and duets from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000803">Schubert</tei:rs>’s unknown
        operas, with piano or orchestral accompaniment. I have chosen and put together two dozen of
        these, for male and female voices.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Best wishes from the four of us to the two of you!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Your most cordially devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/><tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000164">O. E. Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>



    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
