<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="991" sdoID="OJ-14-45_55">OJ 14/45, [55]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="MV" scope="sole">Moriz Violin's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
      <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-07-11" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002719">ViolinM ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM+V ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002718">ViolinM+V+F ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Moriz Violin to Schenker, dated September 5, 1926</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1926-09-05T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2013-07-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Violin reports that he had to cut short his holiday in Bad Gastein because his
        son Karl was again seriously ill. The costs of treatment amounted to nearly 4000 Marks, and
        this sum must be paid by the end of the year.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>


    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-35"><tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>,
            <tei:date when="1926-09-05">5. September 26</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Liebster <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt
            of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/8, p. 2974 (September 7, 1926):
            "Von Floriz (Br.): über die schwere Krankheit Karlis, die den Aufenthalt in Gastein
            abzubrechen nötigte. Prof. Braun wurde nach Bistrai gerufen, in einem Krankenwagen der
            Bahn mußte der Junge heimreisen! Floriz beziffert die Kosten bis heute auf 4000 Mark!"
            ("From Floriz (letter): about the serious illness of his son Karl, which necessitated
            the termination of his stay in Gastein. Prof. Braun was called to Bistrai, and the boy
            had to travel home in a railway ambulance-car! Floriz reckons that the costs until now
            have reached 4000 marks!") <tei:lb/>Violin's letter begins by mentioning his receipt of
            the first <tei:title level="m">Meisterwerk</tei:title> Yearbook (according to <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-45_54">OJ 14/45, [54]</tei:ref>, this arrived in Bad
            Gastein on July 12) but fails to acknowledge Schenker's letter of reply of 23 July. The
            writing of this reply is recorded in his diary at OJ 3/8, p. 2958: "An Fl. (Br.): Dank
            für seine Mitteilung, entwickle mein Arbeitsprogramm." ("To Floriz (letter): thanks for
            his communication; I outline my programme of work.") As Violin's departure from Bad
            Gastein was unexpected and sudden, it is possible that the letter was never forwarded to
            Hamburg, and it must therefore be presumed lost.</tei:note>
        </tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">In den ersten Tagen meines <tei:rs key="entity-003099" type="place">Gastein</tei:rs>er Aufenthalts, schrieb ich<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-45_54">= OJ 14/45, [54]</tei:ref> Dir u. auch vom freudigen Empfang Deines
          <tei:rs key="entity-001750" type="work">letzten Werkes</tei:rs>. Nach neuntägigem (oder
        12tägigem) Aufenthalt, wurde ich telegraphisch von <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">Vally</tei:rs> berufen, weil <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Karli</tei:rs>
        doch furchtbar u. hoffnungslos an Herzbeutelentzündung erkrankte. Da begannen die
        dornenvollsten Tage meines Lebens. Ich fand meinen armen <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Karl</tei:rs> hoffnungslos vor. Ich brachte jedes Opfer u. berief Prof.
          <tei:rs key="entity-004886" type="person">Braun</tei:rs> aus <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs>. Der erklärte den Fall für einen, bei dem man nicht einmal mit
        Glück mehr rechnen kann. Und <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Karli</tei:rs>? – – –
        Er schlug allen Pessimisten das Schnippchen u. sein unerschütterlicher Lebenswille half
        viel. Aber wenige Menschenkinder dürften das an Schmerzen u. Elend erlitten haben, was er so
        voll Güte durchmachte. Vor 14 Tagen brachte ich ihn mit dem Krankenwagen <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">der Eisenbahn</tei:add> nach <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>. Jetzt wird es Monate noch dauern,
        vorausgesagt es verläuft alles ohne Zwischenfälle u. erst nach diesem Krankenlager wird sich
        sein Lebensschicksal beurteilen lassen. Ich hoffe das Beste!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Nun muß ich sehen, wie ich meine finanziellen Wunden heilen werde. 4000
        Mark kostet <tei:hi rend="underline">mich</tei:hi> bis jetzt die Krankheit. Das <tei:hi rend="underline">muß</tei:hi> alles heuer bezahlt werden. Wie? Und wie das weitere
        bestreiten? Wahrlich eine <tei:pb n="2"/> Börsenaufgabe, wert von 10 Menschen, nicht von
        einem, gelöst zu werden. Ich halte mich physisch natürlich nur durch die ständige Erregung
        u. Verpflichtung. Aber <tei:hi rend="underline">alles</tei:hi> wird u. <tei:hi rend="underline">muss</tei:hi> gehen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Verstehe nun gütigst mein Schweigen. Es war nicht zu geringestem Teile
        Rücksicht mit Deinem Sommer.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Hoffentlich seid Ihr recht gestärkt?!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-35">Sei in unwandelbarer Treue gegrüßt. Ebenso Frau <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Lie</tei:rs></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">von <tei:lb/>Uns <tei:lb/>und besonders <tei:lb/>noch von
            <tei:del rend="overstrike">D</tei:del>Eueren</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-35"><tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>,
            <tei:date when="1926-09-05">September 5, 1926</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dearest <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
        </tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">In the first day of my stay in <tei:rs key="entity-003099" type="place">Gastein</tei:rs>, I wrote<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-45_54">= OJ 14/45,
          [54]</tei:ref> to you, and also about the delightful receipt of your most <tei:rs key="entity-001750" type="work">recent work</tei:rs>. After a stay of nine (or twelve)
        days, I was summoned by a telegram from <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">Vally</tei:rs>, because little <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Karl</tei:rs>
        was frightfully, and hopelessly, suffering from pericarditis. Thus began the most painful
        days of my life. I discovered my poor, helpless <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Karl</tei:rs>. I made every sacrifice and summoned Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-004886" type="person">Braun</tei:rs> from <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>. He explained that the case was one for which one could not count on a
        happy outcome. And little <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Karl</tei:rs>? – – – He
        outwitted all the pessimists and his indestructible will to live helped a great deal. But
        few children could have suffered the pain and sorrow that he bore with such graciousness.
        Two weeks ago, I took him back to <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>
        in the <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">railway</tei:add> ambulance. Now he
        will spend months on his sickbed, assuming that everything proceeds without relapses; and
        only after that will it be possible to judge the fate of his life. I hope for the
        best!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Now I must find a way to heal my financial wounds. So far his illness has
        cost <tei:hi rend="underline">me</tei:hi> 4000 marks. All that <tei:hi rend="underline">must</tei:hi> be paid this year. And how to deal with what follows? A veritably <tei:pb n="2"/> monumental problem to solve, amounting to the wealth of ten people, not one. I
        shall of course hold up physically only through constant attention and responsibility. But
          <tei:hi rend="underline">all</tei:hi> will and <tei:hi rend="underline">must</tei:hi> be
        done.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Please be so kind now to understand my silence, not least because I did
        not wish to spoil your summer: I hope that the two of you have gained new strength!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-35">Accept our greetings in unconditional faith; likewise <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Lie</tei:rs>.</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">From <tei:lb/>us, <tei:lb/>and especially <tei:lb/>from
          your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>