<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2141" sdoID="OJ-15-16_87">OJ 15/16, [87]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HW" scope="sole">Hans Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2008</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2018</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-10-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Hans Weisse to Schenker, dated September 14, 1932</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1932-09-14T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2018-10-16</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>After a long silence, for which he apologizes, Weisse congratulates Schenker
        on the completion of Der freie Satz and reports that he has composed a violin sonata, which
        retains the neo-Bachian style of his three-voiced piano pieces of 1931. He gives Schenker
        the dates of his sailing to America and his address in New York.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Glückwünsche; congratulations; Fertigstellung; completion; Werk; work; Pass;
        passport; Arbeit; work; Beitrag; contribution; Sonata; Reise; journey; Stil; style;
        Setzweise; texture; Missverhältnis; mismatch; Unding; annoyance; Gesamtklangwirkung; overall
        sonorous effect; Aufführungsmöglichkeiten; performance possibilities; Studium; study;
        Erfolg; success; Verbreitung; dissemination; Beruhigung; assurance; Adresse; address;
        Vorarbeit; preliminary work; Endarbeit; concluding work</dc:subject>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:lb/><tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#HW"
            /><tei:placeName>Grundlsee</tei:placeName>, <tei:date when="1932-09-14">14. Sept.
            32</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Meister</tei:rs>,<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in
            Schenker's diay at OJ 4/5, p. 3772, September 15, 1932: "Von Weisse (Br.): Glückwünsche
            zur Fertigstellung <tei:title>des freien Satzes</tei:title>; hat eine
              <tei:title>Klavier-Violin Sonate</tei:title> komponirt (gegen Brahms! was für eine
            Originalitätssucht!); entschuldigt sein langes Schweigen, erbittet eine Nachricht auf
            sein Schiff – neue Adresse." ("From Weisse (letter): best wishes for the completion of
              <tei:title level="m">Free Composition</tei:title>; he has composed a sonata for piano
            and violin (contra Brahms! what a craving for originality!); he apologizes for his long
            silence, asks for news to be sent to his ship – new address.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>vor allem meine herzlichsten Glückwünsche und den Ausdruck aufrichtiger Freude über die
        Fertigstellung des <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title>Freien
            Satz</tei:title></tei:rs>es.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >From Weisse's previous letters, one can infer that Schenker had expected to complete
            <tei:title level="m">Der freie Satz</tei:title> by the spring of 1931. Even so, a
          further two years were to elapse before he was able to correct the proofs, and the work
          was not published until 1935.</tei:note> Wie sehr ich auf dieses alles krönende Werk
        gespannt bin, brauch ich wohl nicht erst zu betonen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Infolge der Ihnen bekannten Passunannehmlichkeiten war mir sehr wenig Zeit übrig
        geblieben für meine eigene Arbeit. Ich musste mich von Anfang August an ganz auf mich selbst
        konzentrieren und darunter litt mein Verkehr mit der Aussenwelt. Oft bedrückte mich der
        Gedanke, dass Sie mein Schweigen als Zeichen von Teilnahmslosigkeit auslegen könnte und ich
        bin mir bewusst, dass ich<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> dem äussern
        Schein nach wenigstens, Ihnen diesen Sommer über manches schuldig blieb.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">No paragraph-break at this point in the
          original.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich habe nun doch auch wieder meinen persönlichen Beitrag zur gemeinsamen Sache liefern
        dürfen und bin sehr froh, Ihnen mitteilen zu können, das ich vergangenen Sonntag eine
        Klavier-Violin Sonate fertiggestellt habe, von der ich getrost sagen darf, dass sie der
        Sache, die wir vertreten<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> bestimmt nur
        alle Ehre machen wird. Es war nicht leicht angesichts der durch die Mitnahme von <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-003100">Frau und Kinder</tei:rs>n bedeutend komplizierten Reise
        die innere Sammlung und Ausgeglichenheit zu bewahren, die zur schöpferischen <tei:pb n="2"/>
        Arbeit nötig ist und so bedeutet mir die Vollendung des Werkes nicht blos einen
        künstlerischen sondern auch einen moralischen Erfolg. Die Sonate ist im Stil meiner Ihnen
        gewidmeten Stücke<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">A set of
          three-voice piano pieces, which Weisse dedicated to Schenker as a farewell
          present.</tei:note> gehalten, neigt also mehr zur <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000027">Bach</tei:rs>ischen Setzweise. Mir persönlich war das klangliche
        Missverhältnis zwischen Klavier und Violine besonders in den <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs> Sonaten immer ein Unding und so habe ich mich denn
        bemüht, bei Beibehaltung von Ausdruck und Lebendigkeit, die Setzweise so viel als möglich
        zum Vorteile der Gesamtklangwirkung zu verdünnen. Wie weit mir das gelungen ist, werde ich
        in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002873">New York</tei:rs><tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> wo mir die verschiedensten Aufführungsmöglichkeiten
        zu Gebote stehen, festzustellen bald Gelegenheit finden.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Zum Studium der so schönen <tei:term>Tafeln</tei:term><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05"
          type="editorial" place="foot">i.e. the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001755"><tei:title
              level="m">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln / Five Analyses in Sketchform</tei:title></tei:rs>.
          Schenker's Foreword in the published edition is dated August 1932; and Weisse is probably
          looking at a proof copy.</tei:note> werde ich also erst in der nächsten Zeit die nötige
        Sammlung finden. Über deren Erfolg und Verbreitung werde ich Sie immer im Laufenden
        erhalten. Das Materielle hoffe ich in Bälde vollkommen zu Ihrer Zufriedenheit erledigen zu
        können.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wollten Sie mir noch ein Wort an die Hamburg-Amerika Linie, <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002589">Hamburg</tei:rs>, als Passagier der „<tei:title>Milwaukee</tei:title>“
        schicken, um mir die Beruhigung zu geben dass Sie mein sommerliches „Passivschein“ nicht
        missverstanden oder zumindest jetzt verstanden haben, damit würden Sie mich besonders
        erfreuen. Wir fahren von <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002589">Hamburg</tei:rs> am
          <tei:date when="1932-09-18">18. Sept.</tei:date> ab und treffen am <tei:date
          when="1932-09-28">28. Sept.</tei:date> in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002873">New
          York</tei:rs> ein. Meine neue Adresse läutet: 1 W 64th Street, <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002873">New York</tei:rs>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial"
          place="foot">This address has been boxed, in pencil, probably by
        Schenker.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ihnen beiden von uns die besten Wünsche für den Winter und erfolgreichstes
        Gelingen aller Vor- und Endarbeiten am <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"
            ><tei:title>Freien Satz</tei:title></tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Herzlichst Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person"
          >Hans</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:lb/><tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#HW"
            /><tei:placeName>Grundlsee</tei:placeName>, <tei:date when="1932-09-14">September 14,
            1932</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>First of all, my most heartfealt congratulations and the expression of my sincere joy
        on your completion of <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title level="m">Free
            Composition</tei:title></tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> How
        eager I am to see this all-crowning work is something I probably don't need to
        stress.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>On account of the troubles with my passport, of which you are aware, there was very
        little time left over for my own work. From the beginning of August onwards, I had to
        concentrate entirely on myself, and my relationship to the outside world suffered as a
        result. I was often afflicted by the thought that you might interpret my silence as a sign
        of indifference, and I am conscious that, at least with regard to outward appearances, I
        owed you much this summer.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>But I have now been permitted to present my personal contribution to our common cause,
        and it gives me great pleasure to be able to inform you that, last Sunday, I completed a
        sonata for violin and piano which, I can honestly say, will surely bring nothing but honor
        to that cause. It was not easy, as the trip was significantly more complicated by my having
        to bring <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003100">wife and children</tei:rs> with me, for
        me to preserve the inner composure and sense of balance that is necessary for creative
          <tei:pb n="2"/> work. Thus the completion of this piece is not merely an artistic success
        but a moral triumph as well. The sonata remains in the style of the pieces I dedicated to
          you,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> thus it inclines more towards <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000027">Bach</tei:rs>ian textures. Personally, I thought that
        the sonorous mismatch between violin and piano, especially in the <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs> sonatas, a constant annoyance, and so I have taken
        considerable trouble to thin the texture as much as possible, to the advantage of the
        overall sonorous effect, without compromising expression or animation. How far I have
        succeeded is something that I will soon have occasion to determine in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002873">New York</tei:rs>, where a variety of possibilities for performance
        are at my disposal.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I shall therefore be able to find the necessary composure to study the very beautiful
          <tei:term>analytical graphs</tei:term><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/>
        only in the coming days. I shall keep you constantly informed about their success and
        transmission. I hope I shall soon be able to sort out financial matters to your complete
        satisfaction.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Were you to send me another line, care of the Hamburg-America Line in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002589">Hamburg</tei:rs>, as a passenger on the <tei:title
          level="m">Milwaukee</tei:title>, to assure me that you have not misunderstood my
        "passivity" this summer, or that you have at least understood it, you would give me special
        pleasure. We are leaving <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002589">Hamburg</tei:rs> on
          <tei:date when="1932-09-18">September 18</tei:date> and arriving in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002873">New York</tei:rs> on <tei:date when="1932-09-28">September
          28</tei:date>. My new address is as follows: 1 West 64th Street, <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002873">New York</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"
        /></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">To the two of you, best wishes from us for the winter and for the most
        triumphant success in all preliminary and concluding work on <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001728"><tei:title level="m">Free Composition</tei:title></tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Most cordially, your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person"
          >Hans</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>
    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
