<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="2284" sdoID="OJ-15-16_8">OJ 15/16, [8]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HW" scope="sole">Hans Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB-WD">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent and William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2007</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2007</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-06-25" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated August 10, 1912</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1912-08-10T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-10-09</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Weisse speaks of Schenker's monograph on Beethoven's Ninth Symphony and progress
    with his own string quintet; — reiterates his desire to transfer from Violin to Schenker for
    piano lessons; — refers to lectures that he is about to give, and quotes from Florence May's
    biography of Brahms. — He will write to Lorle Meissner; — gives his address in
    Pontresina.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Lesen; reading; Arbeit; work; Reise; travel; Besuch; visit; Partitur; score;
    Klavierspiel; piano playing; Harmonielehrevorlesungen; lectures on harmonic theory; Biographie;
    biography; Handmechanismus; hand mechanics; Etüde; study; Finger; Arpeggien; arpeggios;
    Trillern; trills; Doppelgriffen; two notes per hand; Oktaven; octaves; Lieder; Pension; boarding
    house</dc:subject>



   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000951">Weisse</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Geliebter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
     >Meister</tei:rs>![1]</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>


   <tei:p>Für Ihren langen lieben Brief[2] unendlichen Dank und für alles Lehrreiche darin! Ihre IX.
    wird mit solchem Fleiss und Eifer studiert[,] dass von einem „Lesen“ wohl die Rede nicht sein
    kann – taktweise und infolgedessen sehr langsam. Immer mehr und mehr staune ich über die feinen,
    subtilen Zusammenhänge die Sie aufdecken, und die am Kunstwerke das begründen, was unbekannt und
    unbenannt die Überzeugung des Grossen erweckt, die der Laie aus seinen „Gefühl“ bezieht!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Nachdem die ersten 2 ^Quintett^ Sätze fertig waren beschloss ich ein wenig auszuruhen,
    konnte mich aber doch eines Scherzos nicht erwehren, das in mir rumort und dessen Trio einzig
    und allein noch fehlt, während das andere[3] schon ein wenig skizziert aus dem Halbdunkel tritt.
    Nun wird die Arbeit doch durch eine Reise unterbrochen, die mich auf Besuch zu meinem einzigen,
    lieben Freunde Spiegler[entity-000840] nach Pontresina[entity-003072] in die Schweiz führt. Am
    16. August werde ich dort anlangen um eine Woche daselbst und eine zweite Woche auf einer
    kleinen Rundtour in fröhlicher Stimmung zu verleben. Hernach wieder Ischl und neuerdings
    Ringkampf mit dem Quintett – so hoffe ich Ende September bei Ihnen mit der reinen Partitur
    erscheinen zu dürfen!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich habe jetzt mehr denn je das Verlangen nach jenem Klavierspiel das ich an Ihnen und
    Ihrer Schülerin bewunderte, und hoffe dass Professor Violin[4] von mir genug hat! Wahrlich nicht
    aus Undankbarkeit, das wissen Sie, Liebster, so gut wie ich ^er^ selbst begreifen würde! Könnten
    Sie nicht doch schonungsvoll ihn bedeuten?</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Was die Harmonielehrevorlesungen[5] betrifft zweifeln Sie doch gewiss!
    Denken Sie an meine dummen Gesichter der ersten Stunden! Und nun erst eine Masse! Sind nicht
    doch Perlen vor die Säue geworfen?</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Lese jetzt die Brahmsbiographie einer Engländerin Florence May die in einem einleitenden
    Kapitel Interessantes über Äusserungen Brahms zu sagen weiss. Klara Schumann übergab sie als
    Schülerin für kurze Zeit dem Meister[Brahms]; ich zitiere einiges:</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Sie erzählte B. von den Schwierigkeiten des Handmechanismus beim Klavierspielen: Er
    antwortete: „Ja das muss zuerst kommen“ und nachdem er eine Etüde aus Clementis Gradus ad
    Parnassum[6] von mir angehört hatte, begann er sofort meine Finger zu lockern und auszugleichen.
    Denselben Tag fing er an[,] mich allmählich durch den ganzen Kursus technischer Ausbildungen zu
    führen indem er mir zeigte[,] wie ich am besten zur Erreichung meines Zieles an Arpeggien,
    Trillern[,] Doppelgriffen und Oktaven arbeiten sollte. — Er glaubte nicht, dass es nützlich für
    mich sei, die gewöhnlichen Fünffingerübungen zu machen, sondern zog es vor aus den Stücken oder
    Etüden, mit denen ich mich grade beschäftigte, Übungen zu bilden. Eine schwierige Stelle
    bearbeitete er häufig indem er mich dieselbe nicht so wie sie geschrieben war, überliess sondern
    mit andern Akzenten und verschiedenen Figuren . . . . — oder:</tei:p>

   <tei:p>„Am Schlusse der ersten dieser beiden Mozartstunden sagte ich ihm: „Alles was Sie heute
    gesagt haben, ist mir ganz neu.[“] (!) „Es steht alles da“ erwiderte er, [„]auf die Noten
    deutend![“]</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> Schade, das dieses Werk nicht mehr sachliche Äusserungen bringt.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Frau Lorle Meissner werde ich ba also wegen der Lieder schreiben und danke ich Ihnen im
    Vorhinein dafür!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Vielleicht könnten Sie mir nach Pontresina Pontresina Pension Collina ein paar Zeilen
    schreiben! Ich bin vom 16. August bis 22. incl. dort. Es würde riesig freuen Ihren Sie innigst
    verehrenden und liebenden</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
     >Hans</tei:rs>.</tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:date when="1912-06-01">10. August 1912</tei:date>.</tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Beloved <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Master</tei:rs>,[1]</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>


   <tei:p>Endless thanks for your long and precious letter[2] and for all the instructive things it
    contains! Your Ninth Symphony will be studied with such diligence and eagerness that "reading"
    won't be the word for it ‒ measure-by-measure, hence very slowly. I am more and more astonished
    at the refined and subtle relationships that you uncover, and that establish for the artwork
    that which awakes, unknown and unnamed, the conviction of greatness that the layman gets from
    his "gut feeling"!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Once the first two movements ^of my Quintet^ were finished, I resolved to take a short
    break. However, I simply could not keep at bay a Scherzo that was rumbling around in my mind,
    only the Trio of which was still lacking, while the other movement,[3] already partway sketched,
    was beginning to emerge from the shadows. Now the work will have to be interrupted for a journey
    that will take me to visit my one and only dear friend Spiegler[entity-000840] in Pontresina in
    Switzerland. I shall arrive there on August 16 and spend one week there and a second week in
    cheerful spirits on a short tour. After that, back to Ischl to wrestle anew with the Quintet. So
    I hope to be able to appear at your place at the end of September with a fair copy of the
    score!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>More than ever now I yearn for the piano playing that I admired in you and your lady
    pupil, and hope that Professor Violin[4] has had enough of me! Genuinely not out of ingratitude
    ‒ you know that, most beloved [Master], as well as I ^he^ himself would appreciate. So could you
    not be merciful [to me] and take his place?</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> As concerns the harmonic theory lectures,[5] you may well have misgivings!
    Think of my stupid faces during the initial lessons! And now for the first time, a crowd! Are
    not pearls cast before swine?</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Am currently reading a Brahms biography by an English woman, Florence May, who has
    interesting things to say in an introductory chapter about remarks that Brahms made. Clara
    Schumann passed her on as a pupil to the master[Brahms] for a short time. Let me quote a few
    things:</tei:p>

   <tei:p>She told Brahms of the difficulties she had with the mechanics of her hand while playing
    the piano. He replied: "Yes, that has to take priority" and after he had listened to me playing
    an etude from Clementi's Gradus ad Parnassum[7] he immediately began to relax and equalize my
    fingers. The same day, he began taking me gradually through the whole course of technical
    training, while showing me how best I should work to attain my goal by means of arpeggios,
    trills, two notes in each hand, and octaves. — He did not believe it profitable for me to play
    the customary five-finger exercises, but instead favored devising exercises direct from the
    pieces or etudes on which I was actually working. He frequently rearranged a difficult passage
    by giving it to me not as it was written but with altered accentuation and different figurations
    . . .–or:</tei:p>

   <tei:p>At the end of the first of these two Mozart lessons, I said to him: "Everything that you
    have said today is totally new to me."(!) "It is all there," he responded, "in the notes
    themselves!"</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> What a pity that this work does not pass on remarks that are more
    substantial.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>So I will write to Mrs Lorle Meissner regarding the songs: thank you in advance for
    that!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Perhaps you could drop me a line to Pontresina, Pension Collina. I shall be there August
    16 to 22 inclusive. It would give me enormous pleasure to yours with deepest respect and
    love,</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
     >Hans</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:date when="1912-06-01">August 10, 1912</tei:date></tei:closer>


  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
