<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="1024" sdoID="OJ-14-45_86">OJ 14/45, [86]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="MV" scope="sole">Moriz Violin's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
      <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-07-19" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002719">ViolinM ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM+V ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002718">ViolinM+V+F ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Moriz Violin to Schenker, dated July 23, 1930</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1930-07-23T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2013-07-19</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Violin despairs of the future for his son, who has just turned 17, and about
        life in general. He has faith only in Schenker, whom he sees as truly a product of his time,
        because of his intimate attachment to the great achievements of bygone eras. He thinks that
        the rest of the world will recognize in half a century what he knows now; he has no interest
        in Furtwängler, who may appear to be modest in Schenker's company, but is no less arrogant
        than any other idiot when left to his own devices. He is concerned about things that might
        interfere with the completion of Schenker's last works.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-30"><tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>,
            <tei:date when="1930-07-23">23. Juli 30</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-15">Geliebtester <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this
            letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/3, p. 3497 (July 25, 1930): "Von Floriz
            (Br.): Bericht über den hoffnungslosen Stand Karlis, den er seinem Schicksal überlassen
            müsse, er selbst sei sehr übermüdet. Er erkundigt sich nach meinem „aber“." ("From
            Floriz (letter): report about poor Karl's hopeless situation, which he must leave to its
            fate; he himself is over-tired. He enquires about my 'but.'")</tei:note>
        </tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Du kannst Dir sicher das meiste denken! Ich zerreibe mein<tei:note type="editorial">corr</tei:note> Leben, im Bestreben <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Karli</tei:rs> auf Lebensbeine zu stellen. Es ist zu kompliziert Dir von
        seinen in ihm entstehenden Minderwertigkeitsgefühlen zu berichten, von dem trostlosen
        Abseits jeder Lebendisziplin. Ich musste einen Arzt zu Rate ziehen. Der hatte den <tei:hi rend="underline">besten</tei:hi> Eindruck von dem armen Jungen u. gab mir einen Rat, der
        sicher der richtigste u. Einzigste war, aber der auch 300 M. monatlich kosten würde. Ich bin
        gezwungen das Zukunftsleben meines <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Karl</tei:rs>s
        seinem Schicksal zu überlassen. Es wäre eine Sünde <tei:sic>den</tei:sic> Ärmsten Vorwürfe
        zu machen oder ihn mißverständlich in den Augen anderer herunterzusetzen.<tei:note type="editorial">corr</tei:note> Alles muss man bei ihm verstehen; die Tatsachen aber
        dennoch nicht <tei:sic>läugnen</tei:sic>. Wie er sein Leben gestalten kann, ist mein größtes
        Lebensrätsel! Er wurde gestern 17 Jahre!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Kaum <tei:note type="editorial">two characters deleted</tei:note> rapple ich mich aus
        einer Finanzmisère heraus, haut mir das Schicksal eine neue auf. Momentan ist es sehr arg.
        Wie ich <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">Vally</tei:rs> letzhin schrieb: Auch
        Maschinen können nur bis zu einer gewissen Grenze leisten. Auch sie kennen
        Ermüdungserscheinungen! Wie Gott will!!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Nun habe ich Dich doch anständig angejammert? Dazu musste mir die Liebe
        Deiner Zeilen<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-6-7_49">=OJ 6/7, [49]</tei:ref>
        verführen. In Wirklichkeit war mein Egoismus der verführerischeste! Dieser will Deine
        „Revanche“ erzwingen! Schrecklicher als <tei:hi rend="underline">alles</tei:hi> ist mir das
        „Aber“ von <tei:hi rend="underline">Deinem</tei:hi> Leben, daß Du versprachst mir nicht
        vorzuenthalten!!! Dein Werk mit zu erleben, ist doch mein einziges Verbindungsfädchen zur
        Kunst. <tei:pb n="2"/> Die „<tei:soCalled>modernen</tei:soCalled>“ geistesgeschichtlich
        eingestellten Musikwissenschaftler, produzieren denselben verruchten Blödsinn wie der
        preußische Kulturminister es tat. Es giebt nur „<tei:soCalled>Exponenten der
          Masse</tei:soCalled>“, das Genie ist das Resultat seiner Zeit. So gewiß man in Gestein
        nicht Getreide anpflanzen kann, so gewiß kann es heute keinen Künstler geben. Humus muss
        vorhanden sein. Da <tei:hi rend="underline">bestimmte</tei:hi> das Genie auch das
        Ideal-Zeitbild. Geschichtlich wird unsere Zeit eben als Zerfallszeit registriert werden.
        Deshalb halte ich Dein Werk ursächlich im Zusammenhang mit der Zeit stehend. Du fandest den
        Ausweg aus ihr, ertobst als Erster die <tei:term>Theorie</tei:term> zur Kunst. Das wird
        Deine Ausnahmsstellung sein, das konntest Du auch nur machen, weil Du in Deiner ersten
        Entwicklung noch der reichen Vergangenheit angehörtest. Was ich heute von Dir weiß, werden
        die Menschen warscheinlich in 50 Jahren sagen. Was soll mich da ein Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs> interessieren? Die Leute sind alle
        sachlich von Dir befangen u. <tei:hi rend="underline">scheinen</tei:hi> bescheiden. Sich
        überlassen, sind sie hochfahrend wie alle heutigen Dummköpfe! Ich kann <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">F.</tei:rs> nicht schmecken. Ich habe anders ihn zu
        sehen Gelegenheit, als Du. Morgen kommt <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">Vally</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs key="entity-000911" type="person">Evi</tei:rs> vom
        Urlaub!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich höre doch <tei:hi rend="double-underline">bald</tei:hi> Dein
        „Aber“??!!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-35">Seid innigst begrüßt</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">in Treue</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-75"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-30"><tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>,
            <tei:date when="1930-07-23">July 23, 1930</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-15">My dearest <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
        </tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">You can certainly imagine most of it! I am destroying my life in my effort
        to keep little <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Karl</tei:rs> alive and on his
        feet. It is too complied to give an account of the feelings of inferiority that have taken
        hold of him, of his dismal aloofness from any of life's functions. I had to take advice from
        a doctor. He had the <tei:hi rend="underline">best</tei:hi> impression of the poor boy and
        gave me a piece of advice which was surely the most correct and only possible one, but one
        which would also cost 300 marks each month. I am forced to leave the future of my <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Karl</tei:rs> to his fate. It would be a sin to make
        criticisms of this poorest creature, or to mistakenly undervalue him in the eyes of others.
        One must be understandable about him in all respects without, however, denying the facts.
        How he will be able put his life together is the greatest puzzle of my life! Yesterday he
        turned seventeen!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Hardly have I wriggled out of one financial misery than Fate clobbers me with a new
        one. At the moment, things are very difficult. As I recently wrote to <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">Vally</tei:rs>: even machines can be productive only up
        to a certain point. They, too, show signs of being tired! As it is God's will!!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Have I now, after all, complained to you properly? My love for your
          lines<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-6-7_49">=OJ 6/7, [49]</tei:ref> are what lead
        me astray. In reality, my egoism was what most led me astray! This will bring about your
        "revenge match." More terrible than <tei:hi rend="underline">anything</tei:hi> is the "but"
        in <tei:hi rend="underline">your</tei:hi> life, which you promised to not to withhold from
        me!!! To be a witness to your work is, after all, the only thread that binds me to my art.
          <tei:pb n="2"/> The "<tei:soCalled>modern</tei:soCalled>" musicologists, bent on
        intellectual history, produce the same loathsome nonsense that the Prussian Minister of
        Culture used to. There is now only "<tei:soCalled>Exponents of the Masses,</tei:soCalled>"
        genius is the product of its time. As certain as one cannot plant grain in solid rock, just
        as certainly there cannot today be any artists. Humus is required. Genius <tei:hi rend="underline">determined</tei:hi> also the ideal conception of its time. Historically,
        our time will be registered precisely as a time of decay. For this reason I regard your work
        as standing in a causal relationship with our time. You found the way out of it, the first
        to proclaim a <tei:term>theory</tei:term> for the art <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of
          music</tei:supplied>. That will be your exceptional position, that was also something that
        only you were able to do, since in your first maturity you belonged to the great riches of
        the past. What I today know from you, people will probably be saying fifty years from now.
        Why should a Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs> interest me?
        The people are all objectively occupied by you and <tei:hi rend="underline">only
          appear</tei:hi> to be modest. Left to their own devices, they are as arrogant as all
        today's blockheads! I cannot abide <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs>; I have had occasion to observe him in a different light than you.
        Tomorrow <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">Vally</tei:rs> and little <tei:rs key="entity-000911" type="person">Eva</tei:rs> are returning from holiday!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">But may I hear about your "But" <tei:hi rend="double-underline">soon</tei:hi>??!!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-35">With affectionate greetings</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">in faithfulness</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-75"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>