<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3165" sdoID="OJ-11-36_23">OJ 11/36, [23]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="VH" scope="sole">Viktor Hammer's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="HS-SP">
      <tei:persName>Hedi Siegel &amp; Stephanie Probst</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2023</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2011-02-12" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006186">HammerV ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Hammer to Schenker, dated October 6, 1925</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1925-10-06T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2023-07-19</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Hammer encloses as a gift two prints of his mezzotint of Schenker; Weisse will
        convey to Schenker a print from which the printing block of the mezzotint can be made for
        Die Musik's purposes. -- The Albertina has just purchased one of the
        proofs.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000327">Viktor Hammer</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#VH"/><tei:date when="1925-10-06">6. X.
            25</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber Herr Doktor <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Schenker</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt
            of this letter is not recorded in the diary; it was most likely handed to Schenker by
            Weisse along with the items he gave him during the visit described in the entry for
            October 9, 1925: “Um 10<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> bringt Weisse die Blätter
            u. noch zwei Kupferdrucke für uns, dann die Rolle für die
            ‘<tei:title>Musik</tei:title>’. Weisse erzählt, daß die Vorzugsdrucke vergriffen sein,
            daß die Albertina einen Vorzugsdruck gekauft habe u. nur noch die 35 Schilling-Blätter
            zu haben seien.” (“At 10 o’clock Weisse brings the prints and, in addition, two copper
            engravings for us, also the roll for <tei:title level="j">Die Musik</tei:title>. Weisse
            says that the artist’s proofs are sold out, that the Albertina purchased an artist’s
            proof and that only the 35-shilling prints are available.”). – Prints had been made
            available for sale at the art shop of <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002413"
              >Artaria &amp; Co</tei:rs>. Regarding the planned publication of the mezzotint
            portrait in <tei:title level="j">Die Musik</tei:title> see <tei:ref
              type="correspondence" cRef="JOB-94-3_15">JOB 94-3, [15]</tei:ref>.<tei:lb/> Before
            this visit Schenker had sent Weisse, who was serving as a liaison for Hammer, a note of
            inquiry (diary, October 7, 1925): “An Weisse (K.): auf welche Art die bestellten Bilder
            zu den Bestellern gelangen werden? – was hat Hammer in bezug auf <tei:title>die
              ‘Musik’</tei:title> beschlossen?” (“To Weisse (postcard): how will the pictures that
            have been ordered reach those who have ordered them? – what has Hammer decided with
            regard to <tei:title level="j">Die Musik</tei:title>?”). Weisse, in a letter written on
            the same day (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-15-15_19">OJ 15/15,
            [19]</tei:ref>), told Schenker of the arrangements he had made shortly before Hammer’s
            departure for Florence: “Hammer habe ich Ihren Brief [<tei:ref type="correspondence"
              cRef="JOB-94-3_19">JOB 94-3, [15</tei:ref>]] übergeben und ihn noch gesprochen: Er hat
            wegen Photographen etc. alles veranlaßt und an meine Adresse wissen lassen. Ich komme
            dann mit Allem zu Ihnen.” (“I have given Hammer your letter [<tei:ref
              type="correspondence" cRef="JOB-94-3_15">JOB 94-3, [15]</tei:ref>] and also spoken to
            him. He has arranged everything regarding a photographer, etc., and will send things to
            my address. I will then bring everything to your place.”) Schenker received the letter
            on the next day (diary, October 8): “Von Weisse (Br.): wird die bestellten Bilder selbst
            bringen, außerdem die Fotografie für <tei:title>die Musik</tei:title>.” (“From Weisse
            (letter): he will be bringing the prints that were ordered, and in addition the
            photograph for <tei:title level="j">Die Musik</tei:title>.”). </tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Beifolgen noch 2 Drucke der Platte auf gewöhnlichem Kupferdruckpapier, die ich Sie
        bitte von mir anzunehmen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">These
          two prints were a further gift from Hammer to Schenker, adding to those Weisse had brought
          on October 5; see <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="JOB-94-3_15">JOB 94-3,
            [15]</tei:ref>. </tei:note> Die <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-003987"
          >Albertina</tei:rs> hat gestern einen von den Vorzugsdrucken angekauft, hat den <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">sogenannten</tei:add> spätern Druck vorgezogen da er heller war
        als <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">illegible word or words</tei:note> den ich
        auch angeboten habe. Von den Vorzugsdrucken hab ich Ihnen 2 hellere und 2 dunklere
          ausgesucht<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">These artists proofs
          were for Schenker to sell or give away. Among the first pupils to buy them from him were
            <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000107">Robert Brünauer</tei:rs> (diary, October 5, 9,
          and November 2, 1925) and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000201">Angi Elias</tei:rs>
          (diary, October 6 and 13). The diary and correspondence document the many recipients of
          the portrait, e.g., <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Moriz Violin</tei:rs>, who
          wrote (March 13, 1926, <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-45_111">OJ 14/45,
            [111]</tei:ref>): “Heute kam Dein Bild! Ich finde es meisterhaft in Ähnlichkeit u. als
          Kunstwerk. Diese Karte soll Dir nur meine Freude darüber sagen. Alle finden das Werk an
          sich so außerordentlich. Ich freue mich extra mit der Wahrheit des Ausdrucks.” (“Today
          your portrait arrived! I find it masterly, as a likeness and as a work of art. This
          postcard will only communicate my joy about it. Everyone finds the work extraordinary in
          itself. I am especially pleased with the truthfulness of the expression.”). <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000149">Walter Dahms</tei:rs>, however, had reservations
          (December 1, 1925, <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-10-1_91">OJ 10/1,
            [91]</tei:ref>): “Gestern traf Ihr Bild ein! . . . und wird nun den schönsten Schmuck
          meines Zimmers bilden. Wir danken Ihnen beide von Herzen für die Gabe! Das Blatt ist eine
          bedeutende künstlerische Leistung, ohne Zweifel. Trotzdem habe ich zunächst einen gewissen
          inneren Widerspruch und Widerstand in mir überwinden müssen, um mich ganz damit zu
          befreunden. . . . Ich hätte es zunächst weniger symbolisch, sondern lebendiger, – um
          Gotteswillen nicht ‘gefälliger,’ – aber expansiver, blutvoller gewünscht.” (“Yesterday
          your portrait arrived! . . . and it will now make the most beautiful decoration to my
          room. We both thank you from the bottom of our hearts for the gift! The mezzotint is a
          significant artistic accomplishment, without a doubt. However I have to overcome a certain
          inner contradiction and resistance in me in order to grow accustomed to it. . . . I would
          have preferred something less symbolic and more lively, – God forbid not more ‘pleasing,’
          – but more expansive, more warm-blooded.”).</tei:note> und sie als 13. 14. 15. 16.
        nummeriert, denn unter uns gesagt, nummeriert sind sie willkürlich, da ich nicht weiß
        welchen Druck der Drucker zuerst und welchen er zuletzt gemacht hat, was bei 16 Drucken auch
        gar nicht ins Gewicht fällt. — <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs>
        wird Ihnen auch eine verschlossene Rolle übergeben. In der Rolle ist ein Druck nach welchem
        das Clichée für <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002556"><tei:title>die
            „Musik“</tei:title></tei:rs> gemacht werden kann. Wenn es also dazu kommt so bitte ich
        Sie nur auf die Rolle die Adresse für den <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-000362"
          >Verlag</tei:rs> zu schrei- <tei:pb n="2"/> ben und hin zuschicken, die machen dann das
        Clichée direkt nach dem Bild. Für den Inseraten oder Mitteilungsteil wäre folgendes in die
        Nummer wo das Bild erscheint zu setzen. Ich lege den Zettel dafür bei.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun nochmals alles Gute lieber Herr Doktor empfehlen Sie mich bitte Ihre<tei:supplied
          reason="aggrement">r</tei:supplied>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Gattin</tei:rs></tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Ich bin Ihr stets ergebener</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000327" type="person">Victor
            Hammer</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:address rend="indent-25">
          <tei:addrLine>4. Via di Corbignano – Settignano, Firenze</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#VH"/><tei:date when="1925-10-06">October
            6, 1925</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear Doctor <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Enclosed are two more prints of the plate on ordinary copperplate printing paper, which
        I ask you to please accept from me.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/>
        Yesterday the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-003987">Albertina</tei:rs> bought one
        of the artist’s proofs, preferring the <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >so-called</tei:add> later print because it was lighter than <tei:unclear
          reason="original_unclear">that</tei:unclear> which I also offered them. I selected two
        lighter and two darker artist’s proofs for you<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"
        /> and numbered them 13, 14, 15, and 16, between ourselves they are numbered arbitrarily,
        since I don’t know which print the printer made first and which he made last, though this
        really isn’t important when dealing with sixteen prints.— <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs> will also give you a sealed roll. The roll contains a
        print from which the printing block for <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002556"
            ><tei:title level="j">Die Musik</tei:title></tei:rs> can be made. When the time comes,
        please just write the address of the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-000362"
          >publishing house</tei:rs> on the roll <tei:pb n="2"/> and send it off, they will then
        create the printing block directly from the picture. For the advertisement or information
        section the following could be placed in the issue in which the portrait appears. I enclose
        the note for it.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Now once again, all the best, dear Doctor, please give my regards to your <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000771">wife</tei:rs></tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">I am your ever devoted </tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000327" type="person">Victor
            Hammer</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:address rend="indent-25">
          <tei:addrLine>4. Via di Corbignano – Settignano, Florence</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
