<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="1796" sdoID="OJ-11-36_5">OJ 11/36, [5]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="VH" scope="sole">Viktor Hammer's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="HS-SP">
   <tei:persName>Hedi Siegel &amp; Stephanie Probst</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2016</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2016</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2016</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-02-12" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006186">HammerV ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Hammer to Schenker dated March 23, 1922</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1922-03-23T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2016-08-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Hammer praises Schenker's edition of Bach's Chromatic Fantasy &amp; Fugue,
    raising an issue about fingering on the clavichord.— He inquires after Tonwille 2, and hopes to
    visit Schenker in Vienna soon.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Verständnis; comprehension; Verkleidung; disguise; Gesetz; law; Kunst; art;
    rätselhaft; puzzling; Malerei; painting; Zweiteilung; binary division; Stück; piece;
    Mannigfaltigkeit; diversity; Buch; book; Klarheit; clarity; Beispiel; example; bildende Kunst;
    visual art; Clavichord; Töne; tones; Taste; key; Finger; Clavier; keyboard; piano; Unterschied;
    difference; Klavierwerk; keyboard work; Zuhörer; listener; Schrift; monograph</dc:subject>



   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000327">Viktor Hammer</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>



  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Sehr verehrter und lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
      >Professor</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
      this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/3, p. 2422, March 24, 1922: "Von Victor
      Hammer (Br.): über einen Fingersatz meiner Ausgabe der Chromatischen Phantasie." ("From Victor
      Hammer (letter): about a fingering in my edition of the <tei:title level="m">Chromatic
       Fantasy</tei:title>.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Zögernd zwar tut sich mir das Verständnis auf für die schöne Welt die Sie uns zeigen aber
    jeder Schritt führt auf sichern Boden. So manches tritt mir als Verkleidung längst bekannter
    Gesetze meiner Kunst entgegen, manches Rätselhafte in der Malerei wird mir <tei:add
     place="interlinear-above">erst</tei:add> durch <tei:hi rend="underline">Sie</tei:hi> klar. Ich
    versuche mich in der „<tei:rs key="entity-001730" type="work"
      ><tei:title>Chromatischen</tei:title></tei:rs>“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
     place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:editor>Schenker</tei:editor>, <tei:title level="m">Chromatische
       Fantasie und Fuge D moll von Johann Sebastian Bach: Kritische Ausgabe mit Anhang</tei:title>
      (Vienna: Universal Edition, 1910; 2nd rev. edn Oswald Jonas, 1969)</tei:bibl>; Eng. transl.
       <tei:bibl><tei:editor>Hedi Siegel</tei:editor>, <tei:title level="m">J. S. Bach's Chromatic
       Fantasy and Fugue: Critical Edition with Commentary</tei:title> (New York: Longman,
      1984)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> zurechtzufinden. Schon die klare Zweiteilung in der Fantasie die
    Sie uns zeigen, die <tei:term>Tonalität</tei:term> des Stücks <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
     >die Sie aufweisen</tei:add><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"
       ><tei:bibl><tei:editor>Schenker</tei:editor>, <tei:title level="m">Chromatische Fantasie und
       Fuge</tei:title> (1910 and 1969), p. 19; Eng. transl., pp. 23–24</tei:bibl>.</tei:note>
    versetzen uns in eine so reine klare Luft. Wers nie begriffen hat dass Mannigfaltigkeit erst aus
    dem Gesetz fließt, hier <tei:hi rend="underline">muß</tei:hi> ers doch sehn. Trotzdem: solange
    ich mich schon plage um das Gesetzmäßige in der Farbe genau zu erfassen, jetzt erst, nach so
    vielen Jahren hab ich wieder einen Schritt vorwärts getan u.z. mit Hilfe eines Buchs von einem
    gewissen Brand: <tei:title>Akkord und Quintenzirkel in Tönen und Farben</tei:title>.<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Hans Bartolo
       Brand</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Der Akkord- und Quintenzirkel in Farben und Tönen.
       Ein einfaches Gesetz der Farbenharmonie</tei:title> (München: Lindauer,
     1914)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note>
    <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">cued from bottom margin:</tei:note> und wie muß ich
    mich erst am Klavier plagen um ein wenig verstehen zu lernen<tei:supplied reason="punctuation"
     >.</tei:supplied><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end cue</tei:note> Ich werde es
     <tei:pb n="2"/> Ihnen einmal bringen. Es enthält auch sonst für Sie sehr
     Interessantes.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Hammer inserts an
     emdash at this point, then continues writing without paragraph-break.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Aber die schöne Klarheit die Sie uns durch Beispiele im einzelnen geben, sie muß für uns
    verfliessen, die wir allein nicht imstande sind die <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> so wie in
    Werken der bildenden Kunst, auch in denen der <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">Musik</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">Tonkunst</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> zu sehen. So anregend und klar Ihre <tei:rs key="entity-001724" type="work"
      ><tei:title>Harmonielehre</tei:title></tei:rs> ist, für uns ist sie doch sehr schwer fassbar.
    Und meine <tei:rs key="entity-003571" type="person">Frau</tei:rs>, die „<tei:title>Ihr
     Bild</tei:title>“ von <tei:rs key="entity-000803" type="person">Schubert</tei:rs> einfach und
    klar empfindet durch Ihre Er„klär“ung,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial"
     place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Schenker</tei:author>, <tei:title level="a">Franz Schubert:
       'Ihr Bild' (Heine),</tei:title>
      <tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title> I (1920), pp. 46–49; Eng. transl., vol. I, pp.
      41‒43</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> sie „schwimmt“ halt doch wenn sie versucht von <tei:rs
     key="entity-000589" type="person">Mendelssohn</tei:rs> das „<tei:title>Altdeutsche
     Lied</tei:title><tei:supplied reason="punctuation">“</tei:supplied>, oder das
     <tei:title>Frühlingslied</tei:title> (mit dem Text von U. v. Lichtenstein) zu singen.<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl>Mendelssohn,
       "<tei:title>Altdeutsches Lied</tei:title>," Op. 57, No. 1;
       "<tei:title>Frühlinglslied</tei:title>" (set to a poem by Ulrich von Lichtenstein, beginning
      "In dem Walde süße Töne"), Op. 19, No. 1</tei:bibl>. — At this point, Hammer inserts an emdash
     and continues without paragraph-break.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Wann kommt denn der <tei:rs key="entity-001741" type="work">zweite
      <tei:title>Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs> heraus, wir sind alle schon sehr gespannt. Sicherlich
    ist es nicht richtig sich nur auf die Hilfe eines Menschen zu verlassen und ich verzweifle nicht
    daran auch selbst einmal sehend zu werden, aber doch <tei:pb n="3"/> ist es begreiflich dass wir
    uns so sehr auf Sie verlassen denn nur durch Sie sind wir überhaupt soweit gekommen.<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot">At this point, Hammer inserts an emdash and
     continues without paragraph-break.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Etwas ist mir an der „<tei:rs key="entity-001730" type="work"
      ><tei:title>Chromatischen</tei:title></tei:rs>“ schon aufgefallen: Takt 5, 2. Hälfte geben
     <tei:hi rend="underline">Sie</tei:hi> in der rechten Hand die <tei:term>Fingersätze</tei:term>
    1 2 5, 1 2 5, während ich auf meinem Clavichord fast gezwungen bin 2 1 5, 2 3 5 zu nehmen. Dies
    kommt daher weil am Clavichord die Töne am schönsten klingen wenn man die Tasten so weit als
    möglich vorne anschlägt. Durch den <tei:term>Fingersatz</tei:term>, an diesen Stellen <tei:add
     place="interlinear-above">1.2.5</tei:add> komme ich aber mit dem 2. Finger am <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">cis</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">d<tei:hi rend="supralinear">2</tei:hi></tei:add>
    </tei:subst> sehr weit nach rückwärts <tei:add place="interlinear-above">auf der
    Taste</tei:add>, ebenso am cis<tei:hi rend="supralinear">2</tei:hi>, bei <tei:hi
     rend="underline">meinem</tei:hi>
    <tei:term>Fingersatz</tei:term> aber hab ich überall die Finger so weit als möglich vorne auf
    der Taste. Beim Clavichord ist diese Art die Finger zu halten die einzig mögliche und
    möglicherweise sind auch davon manche frühere Fingersätze abhängig gemacht worden. <tei:note
     type="editorial" place="inline">cued from bottom margin:</tei:note> denn beim Clavier kommt
    noch immer ein Ton wo man ihn auch anschlägt, beim Clavichord aber muß man die richtige Stelle
    treffen, sonst ist es fast nicht mehr als ein Geräusch.<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"
     >end cue</tei:note> Spricht denn <tei:rs key="entity-000025" type="person">Ph. E.
     Bach</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09" type="editorial" place="foot"
       ><tei:bibl><tei:author>Carl Philipp Emanuel Bach</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Versuch
       über die wahre Art das Clavier zu spielen</tei:title> (Berlin, 1753–62); Eng. transl.
       <tei:editor>William J. Mitchell</tei:editor>, <tei:title level="m">Essay on the True Art of
       Playing Keyboard Instruments</tei:title> (New York: Norton, 1949)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note>
    niemals von <tei:pb n="4"/> dieser Art die Finger so weit als möglich am vordern Ende der Taste
    zu halten? Beim Clavier machts ja nichts aus, obwohl <tei:rs key="entity-006187" type="person"
     >Helmholtz</tei:rs> auf die verschiedene Länge der Claves den charakteristische<tei:supplied
     reason="syntax">n</tei:supplied> Unterschied der Tonarten zurückführt, letzten Endes also auf
    den Anschlagspunkt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10" type="editorial" place="foot"
       ><tei:bibl><tei:author>Hermann Helmholtz</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Die Lehre von den
       Tonempfindungen als physiologische Grundlage für die Theorie der Musik</tei:title>
      (Braunschwieg: Friedrich Vieweg, 1863); 4th edn (1877) Eng. transl. <tei:editor>Alexander
       Ellis</tei:editor>, <tei:title level="m">On the Sensations of Tone as a Physiological Basis
       for the Theory of Music</tei:title> (2nd edn, London: Longman Green, 1885; repr. edn New
      York: Dover, 1954)</tei:bibl>. Hammer may be referring to the following passage (in Part III,
     chapter 16): "Dagegen ist auf dem Clavieren und bei den Streichinstrumenten entschieden ein
     verschiedener Charakter der Tonarten vorhanden. . . . Man kann hier kaum an etwas anderes
     denken, als dass der Anschlag der kürzeren und schmalen Obertasten des Claviers eine etwas
     andere Klangfarbe giebt als der Anschlag der Untertasten, und je nachdem der kräftigere oder
     weichere Klang sich auf die verschiedenen Stufen der Tonart vertheilt, ein anderer Charakter
     eintritt." (1st edn, p. 476) ("On the other hand, there is a decidedly different character in
     different keys on pianoforte and bowed instruments. . . . It is scarcely possible to think of
     any other reason than that the method of striking the short narrow black digitals [keys] of the
     piano must produce a somewhat different quality of tone, and that difference of character
     arises from the different distribution of the stronger and gentler quality of tone among the
     different degrees of the scale." (p. 311). — At this point, Hammer inserts an emdash and
     continues without paragraph-break.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Es ist übrigens sehr lehrreich zu sehn wie die wirklich großartigen Klavierwerke <tei:rs
     key="entity-000027" type="person">Bach</tei:rs>s auf dem Clavichord wirken während schon
     <tei:rs key="entity-000612" type="person">Mozart</tei:rs>
    <tei:add place="interlinear-above">fast</tei:add> unmöglich drauf zu spielen ist. <tei:add
     place="interlinear-above">Für</tei:add> Zuhörer kann man <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike"><tei:unclear reason="reading">ins</tei:unclear></tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">am</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> Clavichord allerdings nicht recht spielen, vielleicht für 2 oder 3 und diese Musik
    ist am Ende auch nicht für Zuhörer gemacht, sondern zur höhern Ehre Gottes.<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn11" type="editorial" place="foot">At this point, Hammer inserts an emdash and
     continues without paragraph-break.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Meine Schrift<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12" type="editorial" place="foot">Hammer's
     monograph, referred to as his "Schrift," is mentioned frequently in his correspondence with
     Schenker; its relation to any of Hammer's published writings is unknown.</tei:note> ist jetzt
    fertig, Probedrucke kommen in 14 Tagen, sobald ich nach <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place"
     >Wien</tei:rs> komme suche ich Sie auf, einstweilen alles Gute und vielen Dank von Ihrem
    aufrichtigen</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Verehrer</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs key="entity-000327" type="person">V.
     Hammer</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1922-03-23">23. III. 1922</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine>St. Martin im Innkreis.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13" type="editorial"
       place="foot">Hammer was writing from his residence on the estate of a patron in the village
       of Sankt Martin im Innkreis in Upper Austria.</tei:note></tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>



  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Highly revered and dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
      >Professor</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>My comprehension of the beautiful world you show us advances gradually indeed, but every
    step is taken on a more secure foundation. I recognize some things as long familiar laws of my
    own art in disguise, and there are some puzzling aspects of visual art that <tei:add
     place="interlinear-above">first</tei:add> became clear to me through <tei:hi rend="underline"
     >you</tei:hi>. I am attempting to make my way through the <tei:rs key="entity-001730"
     type="work"><tei:title level="m">Chromatic Fantasy</tei:title></tei:rs>.<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> Even just the clear binary division of the Fantasy you
    show us and the <tei:term>tonality</tei:term> of the piece <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
     >you point out</tei:add><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> transport us to such
    pure, clear air. Those who have never understood that diversity in fact emanates from law
     <tei:hi rend="underline">must</tei:hi> finally perceive it here. And yet: though I have labored
    long and hard to gain a precise understanding of the laws governing color, only now, after so
    many years, have I taken another step forward, namely with the help of a book by certain person
    named Brand: <tei:title level="m">Akkord und Quintenzirkel in Tönen und
     Farben</tei:title>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/>
    <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">cued from bottom margin:</tei:note> And how very hard
    did I have to struggle at the piano to make some sense of it.<tei:note type="editorial"
     place="inline">end cue</tei:note> I will <tei:pb n="2"/> bring it to you one day. It also
    contains other things of great interest to you.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"
    /></tei:p>

   <tei:p>But the beautiful clarity you offer us by means of detailed examples must remain opaque to
    us, for on our own we are incapable of seeing the <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> in <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">music</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">musical works of art</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> as we see it in visual works of art. As stimulating and clear as your <tei:rs
     key="entity-001724" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Theory of Harmony</tei:title></tei:rs> is,
    for us it is really very difficult to grasp. And my <tei:rs key="entity-003571" type="person"
     >wife</tei:rs>, who understands <tei:rs key="entity-000803" type="person">Schubert</tei:rs>'s
     "<tei:title>Ihr Bild</tei:title>" simply and clearly from your "clear"ification,<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> she literally "flounders around" when she attempts to
    sing <tei:rs key="entity-000589" type="person">Mendelssohn</tei:rs>'s "<tei:title>Altdeutsches
     Lied</tei:title>" or the "<tei:title>Frühlingslied</tei:title>" (with Ulrich von Lichtenstein's
     text).<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>When will the <tei:rs key="entity-001741" type="work">second issue of <tei:title level="j"
      >Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs> appear, we are all already very eager. Surely it isn't right to
    be dependent on the help of just one person and I have no doubt that someday I will be able to
    see things for myself, yet <tei:pb n="3"/> it is understandable that we depend on you so much
    since only through you could we have ever come this far.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08"
     type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Something has already occurred to me concerning <tei:supplied reason="clarity">your
     edition of</tei:supplied> the <tei:rs key="entity-001730" type="work"><tei:title level="m"
      >Chromatic Fantasy</tei:title></tei:rs>. In the second half of bar 5 <tei:hi rend="underline"
     >you</tei:hi> indicate the right-hand <tei:term>fingering</tei:term> as 1 2 5, 1 2 5, while on
    my clavichord I am practically forced to use 2 1 5, 2 3 5. This is because on the clavichord
    tones sound best when one strikes the keys as far forward as possible. Because of the
     <tei:term>fingering</tei:term>
    <tei:add place="interlinear-above">1 2 5</tei:add> in these places my second finger arrives on <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">c<tei:g type="sharp"/></tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">d<tei:hi rend="supralinear">2</tei:hi></tei:add>
    </tei:subst> very far back <tei:add place="interlinear-above">on the key</tei:add>, likewise on
     c<tei:g type="sharp"/><tei:hi rend="supralinear">2</tei:hi>, but with <tei:hi rend="underline"
     >my</tei:hi> fingering the fingers are always as close to the front of the key as possible. On
    the clavichord this kind of finger placement is the only possibility and it is possible that
    this may have also affected some earlier fingerings. <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"
     >cued from bottom margin:</tei:note> For on the piano a tone is produced no matter where one
    depresses <tei:supplied reason="clarity">the key</tei:supplied>, but on the clavichord one has
    to find just the right place, or what results is hardly more than noise.<tei:note
     type="editorial" place="inline">end cue</tei:note> Doesn't <tei:rs key="entity-000025"
     type="person">C. P. E. Bach</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09" type="footnote"/> ever speak
    of <tei:pb n="4"/> this technique of placing the finger as close as possible to the front end of
    the key? It certainly makes no difference on the piano, though <tei:rs key="entity-006187"
     type="person">Helmholtz</tei:rs> traces the characteristic differentiation of tonalities back
    to the different lengths of the piano keys, and ultimately to the point at which a key is
     struck.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn10" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>By the way, it is very instructive to see how effective the truly magnificent keyboard
    works of <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person">Bach</tei:rs> are on the clavichord, while it
    is <tei:add place="interlinear-above">nearly</tei:add> impossible to play even <tei:rs
     key="entity-000612" type="person">Mozart</tei:rs> on it. Indeed one cannot rightly play on the
    clavichord <tei:add place="interlinear-above">for</tei:add> listeners, perhaps just for two or
    three, and after all this music is not intended for listeners, rather for the higher glory of
     God.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn11" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>My monograph<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn12" type="footnote"/> is now finished; proofs will
    arrive in two weeks. As soon as I get to <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place"
     >Vienna</tei:rs> I will call on you, in the meantime all the best and many thanks from your
    sincere </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">admirer</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs key="entity-000327" type="person">V.
     Hammer</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1922-03-23">March 23, 1922</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine>St. Martin im Innkreis<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn13" type="footnote"
      /></tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
