<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3670" sdoID="OJ-13-10_22">OJ 13/10, [22]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2025</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated May 20, 1924</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1924-05-20T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-07-14</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel thanks Schenker for a copy of Tonwille 6, and reports on his wife's
        serious illness. -- He sends the first movement of his Third Piano Sonata and asks
        Schenker's opinion of it from the formal perspective. -- He wishes the Schenkers a happy
        Pentecost!</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002757"
            >Kiel</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1924-05-20">20. V. 24. </tei:date>
        </tei:dateline>
        <tei:address rend="indent-60">
          <tei:addrLine>Feldstr 77<tei:hi rend="supralinear">IV.</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Mein Lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Professor Schenker</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
            >Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for June 2, 1924: “Von Oppel
            Brief u. Sonate, 1. Satz; auch liegt das Bild seiner drei Buben bei; erzählt von der
            Krankheit seiner Frau.” (“From Oppel letter and sonata, first movement; also a picture
            of his three boys enclosed; tells of his wife's illness.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Leider komme ich erst heute zum Schreiben Ich hoffe, es geht Ihnen u. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000771">Ihrer lieben Frau</tei:rs> gut. Vielen Dank für den
          <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001745"><tei:title>Tonwillen VI</tei:title></tei:rs>! </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Hier ein Bild von den <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801">Jungen</tei:rs>, das
        ich m. Frau z. Geburtstage in Mai machen liess. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008510"
          >Hans Reinhard</tei:rs> macht etwas blöde Augen, da er beim Photogr. vor Müdigkeit u.
        Hitze beinahe im Stehen einschlief. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006150">Meiner Frau</tei:rs> geht’s gottseidank
        besser. Sie ist ungefähr seit 10 Tagen fieberfrei, darf etwas im Bett sitzen, lesen u.
        handarbeiten. In 4 Wochen, meinen die Ärzte, dürfte sie zum 1. Male aufstehn. Im rechten
        Bein ist immer noch Trombose, u. die Leber noch geschwollen. Ob diese überhaupt wieder ganz
        zurück geht, können die Herren nicht sagen. Das ganze nennen sie jetzt Koli-sepsis. Und
        durch den Chirurgen hörte ich hinterher an, dass wahrscheinlich doch voriges Jahr bei der
        Fehlgeburt irgend etwas <tei:pb n="2"/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">line missing</tei:note> [geschehen ist bei der]
        Operation. Vor <tei:date when="1924-10-01">1. Oct.</tei:date> werde ich sie wohl nicht nach
        Hause bekommen, ich bin heilfroh, dass sie soweit ist. Den Fingern geht’s gut. Ich bin etwas
        müde u. abgespannt, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-003957">Walter</tei:rs> habe ich wieder zu mir genommen seit
        Ostern, damit ich sie unter Aufsicht habe. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008510">H.
          R.</tei:rs> ist noch bei m. Freunden. Aber die Versorgung der beiden ältesten morgens u.
        abends, ohne Mädchen, u. die täglichen 2maligen Besuche <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-006150">m. Frau</tei:rs> i. d. Klinik kosten mich jeden Tag 4 Stunden
        mindestens. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich komme daher nur zum wichtigsten u. kaum zu meinen eignen Arbeiten. Hier schicke ich
        Ihnen aber den 1. Satz der 3. Klsonate. Genehmigen Sie das formell? Die blaue Stellen i. d.
        Dchführung passen mir noch nicht. Wenn Sie ihn mir sobald wie möglich zurücksändten, wäre
        ich Ihnen sehr dankbar.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Schenker’s diary records his (non-extant) reply on June 14: “An D<tei:hi
            rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Oppel (K.): sende vorläufig die Sonate zurück, Brief
          darüber aus Galtür.” (“To Dr. Oppel (postcard): return the sonata in the interim, letter
          about it from Galtür.” — Schenker does write (letter non-extant) from Galtür, on July 18,
          but is a detailed commentary on Oppel’s C<tei:g type="sharp"/> minor Sonata.).</tei:note> Die drei
        übrigen Sätze sollen a. d. gleichen Motiv entwickelt werden. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun wünsche ich fröhliche Pfingsten u. alles Gute! </tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Mit den herzlichsten Grüssen </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Ihnen beiden</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Ihr treuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002757"
            >Kiel</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1924-05-20">May 20, 1924 </tei:date>
        </tei:dateline>
        <tei:address rend="indent-60">
          <tei:addrLine>Feldstraße 77/4</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor
            Schenker</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Unfortunately, I am only getting around to writing today. I hope that you and <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000771">your dear wife</tei:rs> are well. Many thanks for
          <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001745"><tei:title level="j">Tonwille
          6</tei:title></tei:rs>!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Enclosed is a picture of the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801">boys</tei:rs>
        which I had taken for my wife’s birthday in May. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008510"
          >Hans Reinhard</tei:rs> is making somewhat stupid-looking eyes, as he nearly fell asleep
        at the photographer’s on account of tiredness and the heat.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006150">My wife</tei:rs> is, thankfully, getting
        better. She has had no fever for ten days, can sit up in bed a bit, reading and doing
        handiwork. In four weeks, say the doctors, she will be able to stand up for the first time.
        She still suffers from thrombosis in her right leg, and her liver remains swollen. Whether
        these will recover completely is something that the gentlemen are unable to say. The whole
        thing is now called colisepsis. And I heard from the surgeons subsequently that it was
        probably something that happened when she had a miscarriage the previous year. <tei:pb n="2"/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">line missing</tei:note> operation. She will
        probably not be able to come home before <tei:date when="1924-10-01">October 1</tei:date>; I
        am delighted that she has gotten so far. My fingers are good. I am somewhat tired and
        stressed out. I have had <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> and
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003957">Walter</tei:rs> with me again since Easter, so
        that I have them under my supervision. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008510"
          >Hans-Reinhard</tei:rs> is still with my friends. But looking after the two elder ones,
        morning and evening, without a maid, and the twice-daily visits to <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-006150">my wife</tei:rs> in the clinic cost me at least four hours a
        day.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I can thus get only to the most important things, and hardly ever to my own work. But I
        am sending you here the first movement of my Third Piano Sonata. Do you approve it from a
        formal point of view? I am not satisfied with the passages in the development section marked
        in blue. If you could return it as early as possible, I would be most grateful.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> The other three movements will be developed from
        the same motif.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Now, I send you all good wishes for a happy Pentecost! </tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>With most cordial greetings </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">to you both,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Your faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
