<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3763" sdoID="OJ-13-10_90">OJ 13/10, [90]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2025</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated October 6, 1929</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1929-10-06T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-08-25</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel praises Hammer’s portrait of Schenker effusively. – In Leipzig he is
        learning Italian. – He hopes that Hoboken and Vrieslander have patched up their differences.
        – He is pessimistic about the political and financial situation in Germany, where
        “Americanism” is working its way into all aspects of society; support for culture has been
        curtailed; the universities have been affected too; he blames the decline on
        socialism.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1929-10-09">6. X. 29</tei:date>.
            <tei:placeName>Kiel</tei:placeName></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Professor Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
            >Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for October 8, 1929: “Von Oppel
            (Br.): dankt fast überschwänglich für das Bild” (“From Oppel (letter): he thanks me
            almost gushingly for the portrait”). — Several paragraph-breaks are editorial, guided by
            emdashes in the original text.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>das Bild<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The mezzotint
          portrait of Schenker made by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000327">Viktor
            Hammer</tei:rs> in 1925.</tei:note> lag auf meinem Schreibtisch, als ich Donnerstag
        nacht hier ankam. Es machte mir eine Riesenfreude, und <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003957"
          >Walter</tei:rs> finden es ebenso lebendig und ausdrucksvoll und wahr und charakteristisch
        wie ich. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000327">Hammer</tei:rs> hat entschieden damit ein
        Meisterstück geliefert. Besonders vortrefflich ist ihm Ihre sinnig-beschauliche, abwartende
        Haltung gelungen, ganz Natur. Und diese treff<tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">liche</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ende</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> Ausdruck der Augen, die den Dingen bis in die dunkelsten Tiefen schauen bei
        aller <tei:del rend="overstrike">S</tei:del> Ruhe des sicher abwägenden Geistes. Jeder
        Strich an seinem Platze, fabelhaft die Verteilung von Licht u. Schatten, die ganze
        Komposition in der Form schön, unbeschreiblich schön, alle Details glänzend gelöst. Ich
        danke ihm und Ihnen <tei:pb n="2"/> allerherzlichst für diese herrliche Gabe, das Bild kommt
        morgen zum Rahmen, u. dann kommt es über meinen Schreibtisch. Eine grössere Freude könnten
        Sie mir gar nicht machen. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Den <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801">Jungen</tei:rs> geht’s gut, sie haben
        grade Herbstferien, u. bis auf <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003957">Walter</tei:rs>,
        leidliche Zeugnisse. Wir schwimmen noch, aber morgen ist leider Schluss damit, da die
        Badeanstalt wegen Strassenbau abgebrochen wird. Das Wetter ist noch sehr milde, doch
        herbstelt es schon stark. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>In <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002479">Leipzig</tei:rs> feierten wir Klengels 70.
          Geburtstag,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Julius Klengel
          (1859–1933), German cellist, born in Leipzig, principal cellist of the Gewandhaus
          Orchestra and member of the Gewandhaus Quartet, also concert soloist, professor at the
          Leipzig Conservatory, and composer of many works involving the cello.</tei:note> er ist
        ein prachtvoller Mensch u. Kollege und versteht sein Cello. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich lerne jetzt in einem Kurs bei uns italienisch mit, bei einem Kollegen Smigelski,
        der früher in Italien Mönch war, dann aus dem Kloster ging u. Musikant wurde.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Ernst Richard Edmund Smigelski
          (1881–1950), born in Silesia (southern Poland), took holy orders in Rome in 1895 and spent
          some time in India before giving up monastic life to study theory and composition at the
          Leipzig Conservatory. He served as conductor at the opera house in Vilnius and was a
          critic for Leipzig newspapers before taking up a post at the Conservatory, which included
          the teaching of Italian.</tei:note> – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Was ist nun mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>? Hat er
        eine Tätigkeit? Und wie hat sich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">A. v. H</tei:rs>
        zu den Dingen gestellt? Hoffentlich findet letzterer den guten <tei:pb n="3"/> Weg eines
        vernünftigen Einklanges zurück. Denn was nutzt ihm sein vieles Geld, wo seine Seele leer
        ausgeht? – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wir stehen in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482">Deutschland</tei:rs> vor einem
        schlimmen Winter: überall drohen Arbeiterentlassungen aus Mangel an Aufträgen. Dazu diese
        ewigen Finanzskandale, Frankfurter Versicherungskonzern,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05"
          type="editorial" place="foot">The Frankfurter Allgemeine Versicherung was a huge insurance
          corporation which assumed control of several smaller insurance companies that had fallen
          victim to the hyperinflation of the 1920s. In 1929 it was investigated on account of
          reports of irregular business practices, which were found to be true; the company was
          dissolved and subsequently taken over by other insurance concerns.</tei:note>
        Raiffeisenbank, Berlin-Sklarek.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >In the “Sklarek Scandal,” the city of Berlin was defrauded of an estimated 11 million
          marks by three Jewish brothers, Leo, Max, and Willy Sklarek, who also attempted to bribe
          municipal officials to cover up their illicit activities; they were arrested in 1929. The
          legal action against them spanned more than two years and is documented in over 2,000
          pages of court records. The National Socialists used the case to discredit the Weimar
          Republic, and Jewish people more generally. Willi died in 1938; Leo and Max were murdered
          in Nazi concentration camps in 1942 and 1944, respectively.</tei:note> Der Amerikanismus
        macht leider auf der ganzen Linie böse Fortschritte. Unsern Industrieherren fehlt es auch
        durchaus an dem guten Willen, die wirklich vorhanden sozialen Härten auszugleichen,
        verärgert darüber, dass der Staat durch seine falsche Steuerpolitik jede Neubildung von
        Kapital verhindert. Man muss tatsächlich froh sein, wenn man jetzt Arbeit hat und sich
        geradeso durchschlägt. Schlimm ist geradezu der Abbau i. d. geistigen Betrieben, wie Sie aus
        d. beilieg. Artikel aus d. <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002992"
            ><tei:title>DAZ</tei:title></tei:rs>: Kulturabbau entnehmen können. – Auch bei den
        Universitäten wird stark gestrichen! </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> Das sind die Folgen dieses verbohrten Socialismus, der die blöde Masse
        zum Götzen erhob. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Übrigens noch eine erfreuliche Nachricht: ich hörte dieser Tage, dass so ziemlich
        alles, auch s. direkten Anbringer, von Herrn <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000405"
          >Jöde</tei:rs> abrückt, langsam kommt die Jugend hinter die Hohlheit dieser Scheingrössen.
        – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Und nun nochmals herzlichen Dank .. </tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">u. herzliche Grüsse Ihnen beiden von uns allen!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Ihr treuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1929-10-06">October 6,
            1929</tei:date>. <tei:placeName>Kiel</tei:placeName></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor
            Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Your portrait<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> was lying on my desk when
        I returned here on Thursday night. It gave me a great deal of joy, and <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003957"
          >Walter</tei:rs> find it just as animated and expressive, and true and characteristic, as
        I do. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000327">Hammer</tei:rs> has decisively delivered a
        masterpiece. He has succeeded in a specially admirable way in conveying your thoughtfully
        contemplative, expectant bearing. And this trenchant expression of your eyes, which observes
        things to their darkest depths with all the quiet of a confidently appraising intellect.
        Every stroke is in place, the distribution of light and shade is fabulous, the entire
        composition beautiful – indescribably beautiful – in its form, all details radiantly
        resolved. I thank him and you <tei:pb n="2"/> in the most heartfelt way for this splendid
        gift; the portrait will go to be framed tomorrow, and then it will sit above my desk. You
        could not possibly have given me a greater pleasure.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>The <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801">boys</tei:rs> are well; their autumn
        holiday has just begun and, apart from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003957"
          >Walter</tei:rs>, their school grades are passable. We have been swimming until now; but
        tomorrow that will unfortunately come to an end, as the pool is closed on account of road
        works. The weather is still very mild but it is already turning quite autumnal.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002479">Leipzig</tei:rs> we celebrated Klengel’s
        70th birthday.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> He is a splendid person and
        colleague, and he understands the cello.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I am studying Italian in a course here, with a colleague named Smigelski, who was
        previously a monk in Italy and then left the convent and became a musician.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>What’s the news with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>?
        Does he have a position? And how did <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Anthony van
          Hoboken</tei:rs> respond to those things? I hope that the latter will find the <tei:pb
          n="3"/> path back to a sensible harmoniousness. For of what use is his vast amount of
        money if his soul comes away empty-handed?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482">Germany</tei:rs>, we are about to face a
        bad winter: workers are threatened with layoff everywhere, on account of a shortage of
        contracts. Added to which these eternal financial scandals, the Frankfurt Insurance
          Concern,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> the Raiffeisenbank,
          Berlin-Sklarek.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> The American Way is,
        unfortunately, taking evil strides everywhere. Our captains of industry are utterly lacking
        in the goodwill needed to compensate for the social hardships that are really at hand; this,
        compounded by the state on account of the wrong taxation policies, thwarts every attempt at
        regenerating capital. One must be truly glad if one has work now and can just about manage
        things. The near-disassembly in the intellectual fields is bad, as you can gather from
        reading the enclosed article from the <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002992"><tei:title
            level="j">Deutsche Allgemeine Zeitung</tei:title></tei:rs>: “The Dismantling of
        Culture.” In the universities, too, there have been severe cutbacks!</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> These are the consequences of this pig-headed socialism, which the
        stupid masses raised to a false god.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Incidentally, a piece of good news. I have heard these days that pretty much everyone,
        even his closest adherents, is turning away from Mr. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000405">Jöde</tei:rs>; the youth are gradually discovering the hollowness of
        this sham bigwig. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>And now, once again, heartfelt thanks ...</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">and cordial greetings to the two of you</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Your faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
