<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="126" sdoID="OJ-10-1_49">OJ 10/1, [49]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>
  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="WDa" scope="sole">Walter Dahms's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="JK">
   <tei:persName>John Koslovsky</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2009</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2009</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2010</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

 </sdo:collectionDesc>
 <sdo:record ID="r0001">
  <sdo:itemDesc><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002725">Dahms ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   
   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Dahms to Schenker, dated December 27, 1919</dc:title>
   
   <dcterms:created>1919-12-27T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2010-06-12</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Thanking Schenker for his kindness, he agrees that Schenker should delay the
    payment of a sum of money to him, and asks if he might stay near Schenker for a few weeks during
    the summer of 1920. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Güte; kindness; Gebender; giver; Übersendung; transfer; Betrag; sum of money; Sommer;
    summer; Stunden; lessons; Ferien; holidays; Unterweisung; instruction; Lektionen;
    readings</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000149">Dahms</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address rend="indent-60">
     <tei:addrLine>Wasserburg a/ Inn <tei:date when="1919-12-27" rend="indent-70">27. XII.
       19</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-05">Lieber verehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>! </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Meinen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
     this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/1, p. 2200, January 3, 1920: "Von Dahms
     (Br.): dankt für den zugedachten Betrag, schlägt vor, daß ich ihn zurückhalte u. eventuell für
     seinen Unterricht im Sommer annehme." ("From Dahms (letter): thanks [me] for the sum of money
     intended for him, suggests that I hold on to it and possibly accept it for his instruction
     during the summer.").<!-- XR -->
    </tei:note> allerherzlichsten Dank für Ihren Brief vom 21. XII.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">This letter is not known to survive, but its writing is recorded
     in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/1, p. 2195: "An Dahms (Br.): ob ich das Geld senden soll." (To
     Dahms (letter): whether I should send the money.").<!-- XR -->
    </tei:note> Ihre Güte beschämt mich, denn ich muss noch sehr viel leisten, um sie zu verdienen.
    Sie sind stets der Gebende. Ich kann also nichts anderes tun, als versprechen, mich Ihres
    Wohlwollens würdig zu erweisen. Das ist der einzige Dank, den ich Ihnen, verehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>, darbieten kann. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Vor allem nehme ich Ihr freundliches Anerbieten an, die Übersendung des
     Betrages<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">One of the stipends from a
     Sofie Deutsch bequest for "impecunious skilled composers and similarly qualified composition
     pupils," of which Schenker was appointed the sole life-long arbiter. There is further reference
     to this in Schenker's diary for the following summer. </tei:note> bis auf weiteres zu vertagen.
    Und ich knüpfte hieran – wie unbescheiden, werden Sie sagen – gleich eine Frage, den kommenden
    Sommer 1920 betreffend, die ich Sie bitte, im weiteren Verlauf der Zeit einmal in Erwägung zu
    ziehen und mir später ganz rückhaltlos, wie Sie es vor allem sich selbst schuldig sind, einige
    Worte darüber zu schreiben. Wäre es möglich, dass ich im kommenden Sommer einige Wochen Ihrer
    Ferien in Ihrer Nähe weilen könnte, weit genug entfernt, um Sie nicht zu stören (und um selbst
    intensivst arbeiten zu können) und doch nahe genug, um wenigsten<tei:add place="interlinear-above"> für</tei:add> einige Stunden Ihre Unterweisung geniessen zu können;
    aber natürlich nur soweit und sooft wie es Ihnen Ihre Zeit, Ihre Stimmung und Ihre
    Erholungsbedürftigkeit erlaubt. Dies wäre die einzig mögliche Anwendung, die ich mir von dem mir
    durch Ihre Güte in Aussicht stehenden Betrag denken kann. Es sollte mir dazu dienen, bei Ihnen
    zu lernen. Und wie wertvoll jede einzelne Stunde für mich wäre, das brauche ich Ihnen ja
    garnicht <tei:add place="interlinear-above">erst</tei:add> zu schildern. Und es sollte sich um
    nichts weiter als um streng abgemessene Lektionen handeln, ausserhalb deren ich Ihnen keine
    Stunde Ihrer Sommerzeit rauben <tei:pb n="2"/> möchte. Sie müssen mir hierüber ganz offen Ihre
    Meinung schreiben; ich nehme im voraus jede Ihrer Antworten mit Dank entgegen. Denn ich weiss
    natürlich, dass notwendiger als alles andere Ihre Erholung und eigene Arbeit ist. Es ist ja auch
    einzig und allein <tei:add place="interlinear-above">nur</tei:add> die Not unsere Zeit, die mich
    zu meiner Frage drängt. </tei:p>
   <tei:p rend="first">Nochmals allerherzlichsten Dank! </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Für Ihre und die Weihnachtsgrüsse Ihrer verehrten Frau
      <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Gemahlin</tei:rs> danke ich, auch im Namen meiner
      <tei:persName>Frau</tei:persName> und schliesse </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">mit den besten Wünschen für ein glückliches, schaffensfrohes und
     gesegnetes Neues Jahr</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">als Ihr stets dankbarer und ergebener</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50">Walter Dahms</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>
  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address rend="indent-60">
     <tei:addrLine>Wasserburg on the Inn, <tei:date when="1919-12-27" rend="indent-70">December 27,
       1919</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-05">Dear revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Master</tei:rs>, </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">My<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> warmest thanks for your
    letter of December 21.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> Your kindness puts me to
    shame, for I still have much to fulfill in order to earn such kindness. You are ever the giving
    one. I can do nothing other than promise to show myself worthy of your good will. That is the
    only thanks, most revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">master</tei:rs>, that I can
    offer you. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">First of all, I accept your kind offer to postpone the transfer of the sum of
     money<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> until further notice. I would also like
    to ask (how immodest, you will surely say) a question concerning the summer of 1920. I ask you
    please to take as much time as you need to consider this question, and then write to me later
    without reserve, however much time you feel is necessary. Would it be possible for me to stay
    near you during your vacation in the coming summer for a few weeks? Far enough away so that I do
    not bother you (and so you can work as intensely as you wish yourself), but close enough so
    that, at least, I can benefit from some hours of study with you. Of course, only as far and as
    often as your time, mood, and your need for recovery permits. This is the only possible way I
    can think of of using the sum of money you have in mind for me, out of the kindness of your
    heart. It should serve me well to study with you. And how worthwhile every session would be for
    me, this I hardly need tell you. And it should not be more than strictly timed lessons, outside
    which I would not like to rob you of a single hour of your vacation. <tei:pb n="2"/> You must
    write me your honest opinion on this; I look forward with thanks to whatever answer you give.
    Naturally, I know that your recovery and your work are the most important things. It is <tei:add place="interlinear-above">simply</tei:add> the necessity of our times that impels me to ask
    such a thing. </tei:p>
   <tei:p rend="first">Once again, most heartfelt thanks! </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">For your and your <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">wife</tei:rs>'s Christmas greetings, my <tei:persName>wife</tei:persName> and I thank
     you, </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">and I close in wishing you all the best for a happy, joyfully
     productive, and blessed New Year.</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your ever-thankful and respectful</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50">Walter Dahms</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>
  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>