<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2157" sdoID="OJ-15-16_93">OJ 15/16, [93]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HW" scope="sole">Hans Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2008</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2018</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-10-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Hans Weisse to Schenker, dated July 27, 1933</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1933-07-27T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2018-11-01</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Weisse thanks Schenker for a copy of an (unidentified) essay; he is
        preoccupied by news of his father's death, and reports that the year ahead will be a
        difficult one for America, in spite of the more optimistic mood that has come about since
        Roosevelt became President. He has completed a Variations and Fugue on a Popular American
        Song, for two pianos, and is now at work on a new string quartet.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Aufsatz; essay; Abgeschiedenheit; solitude; Zeitung, newspaper; Artikel; article;
        Übersetzung; translation; Variationenwerk; set of variations; Ableben; death; Arbeit; work;
        Reaktion; reaction</dc:subject>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:lb/><tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:handShift new="#HW"/><tei:date
            when="1933-07-27">27. Juli 33</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber, verehrter <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"
            >Meister</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/6, p. 3857, August 10, 1933: "Von
            Hans Weisse (Br.): geschrieben einen Tag nach Empfang der Todesnachricht; würde
            empfehlen, den Aufsatz zu übersetzten; komponirt W Variationen u. ein Streichquartett,
            im übrigen „nicht mitteilungsbedürftig“ (!!)." ("From Hans Weisse (letter): written one
            day after the news of the death <tei:supplied reason="identity">of his
              father</tei:supplied>; he would recommend translating the article; is composing
            variations and a string quartet, otherwise is feeling "not up to communicating"
            (!!).").</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>was Ihren sehr interssanten Aufsatz,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Schenker recorded in his diary OJ 4/6, p. 3842, June 20, 1933: "An Weisse
          (Br. u. <tei:title>National Ztg.</tei:title>): ob ein Abdruck in N. Y. möglich ist? Ueber
          Bambergers u. Jonas‘ Fortschritte." ("To Weisse (letter, and <tei:title level="j"
            >National-Zeitung</tei:title>): would a reprint in New York be possible? Concerning
            <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000034">Bamberger</tei:rs>'s and <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000412">Jonas</tei:rs>'s progress."). He subsequently wrote (p. 3855) on
          August 4: "An Hans Weisse (Br.): Beileid; charakterisiere die Lage in Deutschland; bedaure
          Furtwänglers Rückschritt." ("To Hans Weisse (letter): condolences; I portray the situation
          in Germany, regret Furtwängler’s step backwards."). Neither letter is known to survive.
          Adolf Weisse had died in Vienna on July 17.</tei:note> für dessen Übersendung ich
        herzlichst danke, anlangt, so bin ich in der Abgeschiedenheit von <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-006964">Lake Placid</tei:rs> sehr arg in Verlegenheit<tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> was damit zu tun sei, an Ihrem Wunsche zu
        entsprechen. Wohl wird es besser sein zu warten bis ich nach <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002873">New York</tei:rs> zurückkehre, obgleich meines Wissens in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002873">N.Y.</tei:rs> nur eine deutsche Zeitung, die
          <tei:title>Staats-Zeitung</tei:title><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
          place="foot">The <tei:title level="j">New Yorker Staats-Zeitung</tei:title>, founded in
          1834, was the major German newspaper in New York for most of the 19th century and, for a
          time, the third-largest selling daily paper in the city. It declined in the 20th century
          because of American prejudice against the Germans during the First World War and, more
          steeply, with Hitler's accession to power and the establishment of the Third
          Reich.</tei:note> existiert, die aber einen eher üblen Ruf geniesst. Ihr Artikel
        übersteigt gewiss das Niveau der Leser dieser Zeitung zu sehr. Bliebe nur die Frage der
        Übersetzung des Artikels zu erwägen, und ich wäre Ihnen dankbar, wollten Sie mich wissen
        lassen, wie Sie sich dazu stellen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich habe in der Einsamkeit ein grosser <tei:term>Variation</tei:term>enwerk und
          <tei:term>Fuge</tei:term> für zwei Klaviere über ein: “popular American Song” fertig
        gestellt und wende mich nun der Arbeit eines Streichquartetts zu.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wie Sie den Zeitungen entnommen haben dürften, ist mein <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000949">Vater</tei:rs>
        <tei:pb n="2"/> nach namenlosem Leiden, bedingt durch Verkalkung und Erweichung des Gehirns,
        gestorben und es war schwer für mich, meine Mutter die Pflege und Sorgen allein tragen zu
        wissen. Ich habe mich um so mehr meiner eigenen Arbeit gewidmet und gefühlt, wie sehr
        konzentrierte Tätigkeit die einzig menschenwürdige Reaktion gegen die unvermeidlichen
        Schicksalsschläge des Lebens ist.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wir haben auch hier nichts zu lachen, und ich bin mir bewusst<tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> dass das Jahr<tei:supplied reason="punctuation"
          >,</tei:supplied> das vor mir liegt, wohl das Schwierigste ist, durch das
          <tei:country>Amerika</tei:country> wird hindurchmüssen. Freilich hat man hier das Gefühl,
        dass <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006965">Roosevelt</tei:rs> in ganz ungewöhnlich
        energischer und zielbewusster Weise die Führung in die Hand genommen hat und die allgemeine
        Athmosphäre ist die gläubigen Vertrauens.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Verzeihen Sie, when ich mich heute so kurz fasse, aber die erst gestern erhaltene
        Nachricht vom Ableben meines <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000949">Vater</tei:rs>s macht
        mich begreiflicherweise wenig mitteilungsbedürftig.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Seien Sie von uns beiden herzlichst gegrüsst. Ich wünsche Ihnen einen guten und
        erfolgreichen Sommer</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">und bin, wie stets,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr getreuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person"><tei:hi
              rend="lateinschr">H</tei:hi></tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:lb/><tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:handShift new="#HW"/><tei:date
            when="1933-07-27">July 27, 1933</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear, revered <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Most cordial thanks for your very interesting essay.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> Cut off as I am at <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-006964">Lake
          Placid</tei:rs>, I am utterly at a loss to do anything about responding to your request.
        It will probably be better to wait until I return to <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002873">New York</tei:rs>; although I know of only one German newspaper in
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002873">New York</tei:rs>, the <tei:title level="j"
          >Staatszeitung</tei:title>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/>, and it has a
        bad reputation. Your article is certainly on a far higher plane than the readership of this
        newspaper. There remains only to consider the possibility of translating the article, and I
        would be grateful if you let me know what you think about that.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I have, in the solitude, completed a large-scale set of <tei:term>variation</tei:term>s
        with <tei:term>fugue</tei:term> for two pianos on a "popular American Song" and am now
        turning toward work on a string quartet.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>As you have probably seen in the newspapers, my <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000949">father</tei:rs>
        <tei:pb n="2"/> has died, after unspeakable suffering caused by the calcification and
        softening of the brain, and it was difficult for me to know that my mother had to look after
        him and bear these sorrows on her own. I devoted myself all the more intensively to my work
        and felt that a very concentrated activity was the only possible humane reaction to the
        unavoidable strokes of fate one encounters in life.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Here, too, there is nothing to laugh about, and I am aware that the coming year will
        probably be the most difficult that <tei:country>America</tei:country> has to get through.
        Admittedly, there is the feeling that <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006965"
          >Roosevelt</tei:rs> has taken control of things in an entirely exceptionally energetic,
        goal-oriented manner, and the general atmosphere is one of faith and trust.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Forgive me if I write so briefly today, but the news of my <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000949">father</tei:rs>'s death, which reached me only yesterday, has
        naturally put me out of the mood for communicating.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Most cordial greetings from us; I wish you a good and successful summer</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">and remain, as ever,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">your devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person"
          >H</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
