<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3780" sdoID="OJ-13-10_103">OJ 13/10, [103]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="TLJ">
      <tei:persName>Timothy L. Jackson</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2010</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated May 15, 1930</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1930-05-15T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-09-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel apologises for delay in writing, on account of a heavy teaching
        schedule. — He enjoyed Schenker’s letter in the Zeitschrift für Musikwissenschaft and has
        read Riezler’s article about the Urlinie. — He has had a dispute with two followers of Hugo
        Riemann.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1930-05-15">15. Mai
              1930</tei:date>. Leipzig</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Professor Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
            >Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for May 16, 1930: “Von Oppel
            (Br.): Disput mit einem Riemann-Anhänger, vergeblich! Die Kinder sind versorgt” (“From
            Oppel (letter): dispute with a follower of Riemann, in vain! The children have been
            taken care of”). — Paragraph-breaks are editorial, based mainly on emdashes in the
            original text.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>längst wollte ich Ihnen auf Ihren lieben Brief vom <tei:date when="1930-04-28">28.
          4.</tei:date> antworten,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Writing of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for April 28, 1930: “An Oppel
          (Br.): Erwiderung der Osterwünsche, Lösung seines Notenbeispiels als Vermeidung von
          5–5-Folgen” (“To Oppel (letter): return of the Easter greetings; solution to his music
          example as a way of avoiding consecutive fifths”).</tei:note> für den ich herzlich danke;
        aber der Anfang des neuen Semesters bringt immer viel Arbeit mit Schüler- u.
        Stundeneinteilung, so dass man zu nichts kommt. Ich habe wieder hier in den 4 Tagen 32
        Stunden zu geben. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ihre Entgegnung in d. <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002480"><tei:title>Z. f.
            M.</tei:title></tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Eduard Beninger, <tei:title level="a">Pianistische Herausgebertechnik,</tei:title>
          published in the February 1930 issue of <tei:title level="j">Zeitschrift für
            Musikwissenschaft</tei:title>; a citation to this article appears in Schenker’s
          scrapbook OC 2/page 80. Schenker’s reply to Beninger was published in the same issue.
        </tei:note> hatte ich schon gelesen. Sie hat mich diebisch gefreut. Den Artikel von <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000714"><tei:sic>Rietzler</tei:sic></tei:rs><tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Walter
              Riezler</tei:author>, <tei:title level="a">Über die Urlinie,</tei:title>
            <tei:title level="j">Die Musik</tei:title> (April 1930), 502–10</tei:bibl>; a copy is
          preserved in Schenker’s scrapbook OC 2/page 80.</tei:note> las ich auch gleich, den Leuten
        ist eben nicht zu helfen. Schon rein äusserlich müsste Mann, wenn er je ein Skizzenbuch von
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> mit wirklichem Verständnis
        studiert hätte, eine Ahnung haben von dem ungeheuern Wege von der
          <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> bis zum fertigen Kunstwerk. Heute aber glaube ich, dass
        dieser Art Gelehrter weder den Willen noch die Fähigkeit zur wahren Erkenntnis hat; wie
        bescheiden sind daneben doch die Mathematiker; da schrieb dieser Tage einer über eine neue
        Zahlen-Theorie: "ich habe 2 Jahre daran studiert u. gewacht, bis ich wagte diese Besprechung
        zu schreiben." <tei:pb n="2"/> Und wenn ein <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055"
          >Beethoven</tei:rs> Jahre lang ein Stück in seinem Hirn wälzt, so glauben diese
        Affenleute, sie lösten sein Probleme in ein paar Abendstunden nach ihrer eigentlichen
        Berufsarbeit, deshalb lohnt es eigentlich gar nicht, diesen Maulwürfen irgend etwas zu
        entgegnen: es wäre Zeitverschwendung.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Auch ich hatte mit 2 Kollegen hier Ihretwegen ein sehr scharfen Disput, man kann aber
        von Riemännern<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Riemännern:
          Oppel’s playful use of the music theorist Hugo Riemann’s surname in the dative
          plural.</tei:note> keine Logik verlangen. – Wir haben schlechtes Wetter, sehr viel Regen
        u. Kühle, alles heizt noch. Hoffentlich haben Sie mehr Sonne. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003957">Walter</tei:rs> geht mit Begeisterung auf die
        Handelsschule, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> fängt an, auf der
        Werft zu arbeiten; er hat sich gut erholt, allerdings noch immer nicht sein früheres
        Körpergewicht erreicht. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Das neue Schülermaterial ist denkbar schlecht. –</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Alles Gute u. die herzlichsten </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>Grüsse Ihnen beiden</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr treuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1930-05-15">May 15,
              1930</tei:date>. Leipzig</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor
            Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>I have long wanted to reply to your kind letter of <tei:date when="1930-04-28">April
          28</tei:date>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> for which I thank you
        cordially, but the beginning of the new semester always brings a lot of work sorting pupils
        and their lesson times, so that one can get nothing done. I must again give 32 lessons in
        the space of four days. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>I had already read your reply in the <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002480"
            ><tei:title level="j">Zeitschrift für Musikwissenschaft</tei:title></tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> which I gloated over. I also read the article by
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000714">Riezler</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
          type="footnote"/> immediately; such people simply cannot be helped. Even from a
        superficial perspective, the man, if he had ever studied a <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> sketchbook with true understanding, would have had
        to have an inkling of the immense distance from the <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> to the
        finished work of art. Today, however, I believe that this type of scholar has neither the
        will nor the capability of true understanding; and how modest, by comparison, are the
        mathematicians; recently one of them wrote about a new theory of numbers: “I have spent two
        years studying keeping watch over this before daring to write this paper.” <tei:pb n="2"/>
        And if a <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> lets a piece toss
        about in his head for years, these ape-men think that they could solve his problem in a
        couple of hours in the evening, after finishing their own professional work; for this reason
        it is actually not worth the trouble to make any sort of reply to these moles, as it would
        be a waste of time.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I, too, had a sharp dispute with two of my colleagues here on your account; but one
        cannot expect any logic from Riemann-men.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> –
        We are having bad weather, a great deal of rain and cool temperatures; the heating is still
        on. I hope that you have more sunshine.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003957">Walter</tei:rs> is attending the commercial
        school with enthusiasm. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> is
        beginning to work at the harbor; he has recovered well but has still not reached his earlier
        bodyweight.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>My new crop of pupils is very bad. –</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>All good wishes, and the most cordial</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>greetings to the two of you</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
