<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="1537" sdoID="OJ-12-6_10">OJ 12/6, [10]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPoj" scope="major">Typing of Oswald Jonas</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="OJ" scope="minor">Hand of Oswald Jonas</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="JR">
      <tei:persName>John Rothgeb</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006, 2011</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2006, 2011</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2015</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002714">Jonas ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002713">Jonas ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


      <dc:title>Typewritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated March 3, 1932</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1932-03-03T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2015-07-26</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Jonas reports on his course on Schenker's theory at the Stern Conservatorium,
        two forthcoming lectures, an article intended for publication, two radio talks and a radio
        recital; includes reference to his later textbook Das Wesen des musikalischen
        Kunstwerks.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Kampf; struggle; battle; Kurs; course; Sonderkurs; special course; Einführung;
        introduction; Lehre; theory; Schüler; pupil; Schulgeld; school fees; Ostern; Easter;
        Verehrung; respect; Vortrag; lecture; Lehrer; teacher; faculty; Aufsatz; essay; Beurteilung;
        appraisal; Herausgeber; editor; Empehlung; recommendation; Umarbeitung; revision; Fassung;
        version; Leserschaft; readership; Zeitschrift; periodical; journal; Rundfunk; radio;
        Todestag; death; Stunde; lesson; Zögling; pupil</dc:subject>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000412">Jonas</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="ident-80"><tei:handShift new="#TPoj"
            /><tei:placeName>Berlin</tei:placeName>, den <tei:date when="1932-03-03">3. März
            1932</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Sehr verehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Doktor</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/5, p. 3710, March 5, 1932: "Von Dr.
            Jonas (Br. rec.): Aufsatz „Heinrich Schenker“ für Schwers; ‒ von Gräner Grüße „in
            tiefster Verehrung“; Furtwängler hat den Aufsatz empfohlen. Jonas kündigt ein Lehrbuch
            an." ("From Dr. Jonas (registered letter): essay "Heinrich Schenker" for Schwers; ‒
            greetings from Graener "in deepest respect"; Furtwängler has recommended the essay.
            Jonas announces textbook."). — Writing of Schenker's reply, not known to survive, is
            recorded at ibid, p. 3711, March 8, 1932: "An Jonas (Br., Aufsatz zurück): billige den
            Aufsatz, taste ihn nicht an; er gehörte eigentlich zu Einstein, hoffentlich nimmt ihn
            Schwers. Furtwängler hat alle Ursache die Geschicklichkeit zu loben. Etwas über die
            Seminaristen." ("To Jonas (letter, essay returned): I approve of the essay, I don't make
            any changes to it; it really belongs to Einstein; let us hope Schwers accepts it.
            Furtwängler has every reason to praise its skilfulness. A few words about the seminar
            members.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Mit großer Freude habe ich gehört, welchen Anteil Sie an meinen
        Bestrebungen hier in <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs> nehmen. Wenn
        ich Ihnen nicht schon längst ausführlich geschrieben habe, so hängt das vor allem damit
        zusammen, daß das Resultat meiner Bemühungen größtenteils durch die katastrophale Mißgunst
        der Zeit in keinerlei Verhältnis zu diesen steht und daß der tägliche Kampf trotz des guten
        Willens Gutgesinnter einen in ständigem Atem hält. Auch sind die Menschen selbst hier nicht
        mehr von jener absoluten Verläßlichkeit, wie man es früher gewohnt war - die Not hat sie
        eben auch schon ein wenig zermürbt.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Von meiner Tätigkeit haben Sie wahrscheinlich durch Herrn van <tei:rs
          key="entity-000380" type="person">Hoboken</tei:rs> gehört. Das Schwierige an meinem Kurs
          „<tei:title>Einführung in die Lehre H. Schs.</tei:title>” ist der Umstand, daß er als
        Sonderkurs geht, d.h. von den Schülern des <tei:rs key="entity-005671" type="organization"
          >Konservatorium</tei:rs>s extra bezahlt werden muß, eine fast unmögliche Sache in einer
        Zeit, wo die meisten um eine Ermäßigung des normalen Schulgeldes ansuchen müssen. Möglich
        daß nach Ostern hier eine Änderung geschaffen wird, jedenfalls bemühe ich mich in dieser
        Richtung.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Direktor <tei:rs key="entity-000302" type="person">Graener</tei:rs>, ein rührend guter
        Mensch, bemüht sich sehr für mich, aber es ist eben nicht alles von ihm abhängig. Im übrigen
        hat er mir aufgetragen, Ihnen seine tiefste Verehrung auszudrücken. Am 9. und 16. werde ich
        übrigens zwei Vorträge für die Lehrer halten. (Den ersten: allgemeine Einführung in die
        Lehre vom <tei:term>Ursatz</tei:term> an Hand der Beiden ‚<tei:title>kleinen
          Präludien</tei:title><tei:supplied reason="punctuation">’</tei:supplied> in C; den zweiten
        unter dem Titel: „<tei:title>Geist der Form; Fuge und Sonate</tei:title>“). Beiliegenden
        Aufsatz, den ich Ihnen zur gütigen Beurteilung ein- <tei:pb n="2"/> sende, habe ich für die
          <tei:rs key="entity-005670" type="journal"><tei:title>Allgemeine
          Musikzeitung</tei:title></tei:rs> bestimmt, an dessen Herausgeber, <tei:rs
          key="entity-000815" type="person">Paul Schwers</tei:rs>, Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000268"
          type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs> mir eine glänzende Empfehlung gegeben hat. Es ist
        übrigens schon eine Umarbeitung, die erste Fassung war für die Leserschaft angeblich zu
        „schwer“! Ja, der Inhalt der „führenden“ Zeitschriften, das ist ein trauriges Kapitel. Im
        Dezember habe ich im Rundfunk einen Vortrag über die „<tei:title>Wiederholung in der
          Musik</tei:title>“ gehalten, ein weiterer über „<tei:title>Phantasien für
          Klavier</tei:title>“ (<tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person">Bach</tei:rs>, <tei:rs
          key="entity-000344" type="person">Haydn</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000055"
          type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs>) wird hoffentlich bald folgen. (Übrigens spiele ich am
        10. zum 100. Todestag <tei:rs key="entity-000135" type="person">Clementi</tei:rs>s am
        Rundfunk.) Dies von mir für heute.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich hoffe, daß Sie sich voller Gesundheit erfreuen und sich rüstig und wohl fühlen. Wie
        geht es Ihrer werten Frau <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Gemahlin</tei:rs>? Macht
        Ihnen übrigens die Stunde mit den <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person"
          >Weisse</tei:rs>zöglingen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">This
          group of Weisse pupils, elsewhere called the "seminar" by both Schenker and Jonas,
          included <tei:rs key="entity-000473" type="person">Trude Kral</tei:rs>, <tei:rs
            key="entity-002498" type="person">Greta Kraus</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000754"
            type="person">Felix Salzer</tei:rs>, and <tei:rs key="entity-000964" type="person"
            >Manfred Willfort</tei:rs>; the published result of their studies was
              <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln</tei:title> (New York: David Mannes
            Music School; Vienna: Universal Edition, 1932)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> Freude? Wenn es
        Ihre kostbare Zeit einmal erlaubt und Sie auch nur wenige Zeilen an mich richten würden,
        bedeutete es für mich eine innige Freude! Indes verbleibe ich mit den besten Empfehlungen an
        Ihre werte Frau <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Gemahlin</tei:rs></tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Ihr stets dankbarer und ergebenster</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:handShift new="#OJ"/><tei:rs key="entity-000412"
            type="person">Oswald Jonas</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p rend="first"><tei:handShift new="#TPoj"/>Augenblicklich versuche ich mich an einem
            „Lehrbuch“,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">This is the first
            mention in the Jonas‒Schenker correspondence of the work that would lead to Jonas's
                <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks: Eine
                Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers</tei:title> (Vienna: Saturn-Verlag,
              1934)</tei:bibl>, the subtitle of which duplicates the title of the course about which
            Jonas speaks in paragraph 2.</tei:note> dessen Plan ich Ihnen gelegentlich vorlegen
          möchte. <tei:cit>
            <tei:q>Anbei 1 Aufsatz.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">The
                essay, entitled (according to Schenker's diary) "Heinrich Schenker," was returned to
                Jonas on March 8.</tei:note></tei:q>
          </tei:cit>
        </tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="ident-80"><tei:handShift new="#TPoj"
            /><tei:placeName>Berlin</tei:placeName>
          <tei:date when="1932-03-03">March 3, 1932</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Greatly revered Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
            type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">I have heard with great pleasure of your interest in my endeavors here in
          <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs>. If I have not written you in
        detail long before now, the reason is above all that, through the catastrophic malaise of
        the time, my efforts have for the most part produced no commensurate result, and the daily
        struggle, despite the good will of well-meaning people, keeps one on the move. And people
        here are themselves no longer so absolutely reliable as they used to be ‒ privation has
        already worn them down somewhat.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>You have probably heard of my activities through Mr. van <tei:rs key="entity-000380"
          type="person">Hoboken</tei:rs>. The difficulty with my course "<tei:title>Introduction to
          the Theory of Heinrich Schenker</tei:title>" is that it is held as a special course ‒
        i.e., one for which the students at the <tei:rs key="entity-005671" type="organization"
          >Conservatory</tei:rs> must pay extra, almost an impossibility at a time when most have to
        seek a reduction of the normal school fees. Possibly a change will be made here after Easter
        ‒ at least I am working in that direction.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Director <tei:rs key="entity-000302" type="person">Graener</tei:rs>, an affectingly
        good man, tries hard for me, but he does not have absolute say-so. For the rest, he
        instructs me to convey his deepest respect to you. On the 9th and 16th, incidentally, I will
        give two lectures for the faculty. (The first: general introduction to the theory of the
          <tei:term>Ursatz</tei:term> with reference to the two "<tei:title>small
          preludes</tei:title>" in C; the second under the title: "<tei:title>Spirit of Form; Fugue
          and Sonata</tei:title>"). The accompanying essay, which I <tei:pb n="2"/> send for your
        kind appraisal, is intended for the <tei:rs key="entity-005670" type="journal"><tei:title
            level="j">Allgemeine Musikzeitung</tei:title></tei:rs>, to whose editor, <tei:rs
          key="entity-000815" type="person">Paul Schwers</tei:rs>, Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000268"
          type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs> provided me with a glowing recommendation. It is,
        incidentally, already a revision; the first version was allegedly too "difficult" for the
        readership! Ah, the contents of the "leading" periodicals ‒ that's a sad chapter. In
        December I gave a radio lecture on "<tei:title>Repetition in Music</tei:title>," and another
        on "<tei:title>Phantasies for Keyboard</tei:title>" (<tei:rs key="entity-000027"
          type="person">Bach</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person">Haydn</tei:rs>,
          <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs>) will, I hope, follow soon.
        (I play on the 10th, incidentally, on the radio for the 100th anniversary of <tei:rs
          key="entity-000135" type="person">Clementi</tei:rs>'s death.) So much for today.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I hope that you enjoy perfect health and feel vigorous and good. How is your esteemed
          <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs>? Did you, by the way, enjoy the
        lesson with the <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs> pupils?<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> If your precious time permits and you would send
        me only a few lines, it would give me great pleasure! Meanwhile I remain with best greetings
        to your good <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs>,</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Your ever grateful and devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:handShift new="#OJ"/><tei:rs key="entity-000412"
            type="person">Oswald Jonas</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p rend="first"><tei:handShift new="#TPoj"/>At the moment I am working on a
            "textbook,"<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> the outline of which I would
          like to show you at some point. <tei:cit>
            <tei:q>Enclosed: one essay<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:q>
          </tei:cit>
        </tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
