<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="295" sdoID="OJ-11-54_4">OJ 11/54, [4]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="AvH" scope="major">Anthony van Hoboken's hand</tei:handNote>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="JR-HE">
   <tei:persName>John Rothgeb &amp; Heribert Esser</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008, 2010</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2008, 2010</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-02-14" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002730">Hoboken ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002731">Hoboken ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Hoboken to Schenker, dated September 28, 1925 </dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1925-09-28T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-01-07</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Van Hoboken reports on his recent travels, describing the house that he has
    rented for a year in Vienna; he is to register in Vienna for nine months for study purposes; he
    thanks Schenker for the plan of work he has sent, and will start lessons with Schenker on
    October 13, 1925; encloses $60 in advance monthly payment. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Stunden; lessons</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000380">Hoboken</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>



  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:note type="editorial">printed letterhead: </tei:note>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>ANTON VAN HOBOKEN</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>MÜNCHEN, WALHALLASTRASSE 1</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-75"><tei:handShift new="#AvH"/><tei:date>28. IX.
     '25</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Dr.</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>



   <tei:p rend="first">Vor<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
     this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/7, p. 2872, September 30, 1925: "Von
     Hoboken (Geldbrief): 60 Dollar u. fünf Seiten Bericht über den Weg zu Dr. Liebenschein, die
     Wohnung im Heiligenkreuzerhof, sonst über Pläne; kommt am 13. X." ("From Hoboken (money order):
     60 dollars and a five-page report about the trip to see Dr. Liebenschein's, the apartment in
     Heiligenkreuzerhof, otherwise about [his] plans; he is coming on October 13.").</tei:note>
    einigen Wochen, vom 31 August bis zum 5<tei:hi rend="supralinear">ten</tei:hi> September war ich
    mit meiner <tei:persName>Frau</tei:persName> in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Wien</tei:rs>, und möchte ich Ihnen doch einen kleinen Bericht über diesen Besuch
    erstatten. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Wir sind nicht im Auto hingefahren sondern mit dem Schnellzug, der um 10
    Abends eintreffen sollte, jedoch, infolge eines Machinendefektes kurz vor <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002340">St. Pölten</tei:rs>, erst kurz vor 12 eintraf. Am nächsten Tage
    begaben wir uns sofort zu dem Architekten <tei:persName>Hans Goldschmid</tei:persName>, der die
    Wohnung vermittelt und mit ihm dann sogleich dorthin. Wir waren einfach berauscht von der
    Wohnung und haben ihn sogleich auf die Dauer von einem Jahr gemietet. Sie liegt am
    Heiligenkreuzerhof, direkt in der Nähe vom Fleischmarkt. Man betritt sie durch ein kleines,
    etwas verwittertes Barock-steintor welches in einen kleinen von Bäumen und Wein bewachsenen
    Vorplatz führt. Dann führt eine grosse und breite Stiege zum ersten Stock und zu der hölzernen,
    eingelegten Eingangstür der Wohnung. Diese, sowie <tei:hi rend="underline">alle</tei:hi> übrigen
    Türen, sind alt, aus der Barockzeit, und zum Teil noch mit den alten <tei:pb n="2"/>
    Türschlössen versehen. Überhaupt ist die ganze Wohnung und alle Möbel darin Barock. Die Etage
    heisst „das Prälatenstöckl“ und soll früher die Abt-Wohnung eines Stiftes gewesen sein. Jetzt
    wird sie bewohnt vom Prinzen <tei:persName>Hohenlohe</tei:persName> von dem wir wiederum
    möbliert gemietet haben. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Die Wohnung ist riesig gross. Ausser dem unermesslichen Esssaal gibt es
     ein<tei:supplied reason="syntax">en</tei:supplied> noch grösseren Saal wo ich mich mit meinen
    Instrumenten häuslich niederlassen werde. Ausserdem gibt es dann noch 4 Zimmer, ein Boudoir und
    ein Vorzimmer während Küche und Dienerschaftzimmer sich darunter im Parterre befinden. <tei:del rend="overstrike">Sie lieg</tei:del> Die ganze Wohnung liegt sehr ruhig, da man den
    Heiligenkreuzerhof mit Fahrzeugen nur von einer Seite einfahren kann und es infolgedessen keinen
    Durchgangsverkehr dort gibt. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Wir freuen uns sehr darauf, die Wohnung zu bewohnen und hoffen, dass sich
    keine unüberwindliche<tei:supplied reason="syntax">n</tei:supplied> Beschwerden dabei einstellen
    werden, da man doch bei einer Besichtigung nicht alles übersehen kann, obwohl wir 3 bis 4 Mal
    dort waren. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="3"/> Die uns übrigbleibende Zeit haben wir in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Wien</tei:rs> verbracht wie das so für Fremden üblich ist. Wir sind
    spazierengegangen an den Läden vorbei und waren Abends meistens zusammen mit einer Freundin
    meiner <tei:persName>Frau</tei:persName>. Wir waren im Museum, im Theater, u.s.w. Auch haben wir
    bei <tei:orgName>Gräf und Stift</tei:orgName><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Gräf and Stift: automobile manufacturer, founded 1904, Franz, Heinrich, and Carl
     Gräf, and Wilhelm Stift; the Gräf brothers had built the first front-wheel drive car in 1898
     and patented it in 1900. Its main factory was located in Liesing, a district of Vienna. The
     company also built buses and trucks. (<tei:title level="m">Wikipedia</tei:title></tei:note> ein
    kleines Auto für meine Frau bestellt und dazu die nötigen Vorbesprechungen sowie auch eine
    Probefahrt auf dem <tei:placeName>Cobenzl</tei:placeName><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Cobenzl: perhaps Schloss Cobenzl, northwest of Vienna, between
     Grinzing and Klosterneuburg. </tei:note> und der <tei:placeName>Sophienhöhe</tei:placeName> (so
    hiess es, glaub' ich) gehabt. Das war sehr schön. Wir lernen jetzt beide Chauffieren und hoffen
    als gelernte Fahrer unser Eintritt in <tei:placeName>Wien</tei:placeName> zu machen. (Vielleicht
    würde es sich empfehlen, dass die Wiener ihre Lebensversicherungen etwas erhöhen! Doch so
    schlimm wird's wohl nicht werden). </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Am 5<tei:hi rend="supralinear">ten</tei:hi> sind wir nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002477">Paris</tei:rs> gefahren. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Doch habe ich noch etwas vergessen zu erwähnen<tei:supplied reason="syntax">,</tei:supplied> nähmlich meinen Besuch bei Dr. <tei:persName>Siebenschein</tei:persName>
    bezw. sein Vertreter, Hofrat <tei:persName>Stein</tei:persName>. Das Resultat dieser Besprechung
    ist, dass ich mich in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Wien</tei:rs> wie für einen
    vorübergehenden Aufenthalt von 9 Monaten anmelde zu Studienzwecke und mir wieter
    Entschliessungen bis später vorbehalte. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">
    <tei:pb n="4"/>
    <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002477">Paris</tei:rs> haben wir wieder genossen wie immer.
    Nur war noch gar kein Saison, und auf musikalischem wie auf theatralischem Gebiet noch nichts
    von Bedeutung los. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Seit dem 23<tei:hi rend="supralinear">ten</tei:hi> sind wir nun wieder hier,
    und ich hatte diesen Brief schon soweit zusammengestellt als letzten Samstag Ihr Schreiben vom
     25<tei:hi rend="supralinear">ten</tei:hi><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">This letter is not known to survive, but its writing is recorded in Schenker's
     diary at OJ 3/7, p. 2870, September 25, 1925: "An Hoboken (Br.): teile ihm den Stundenplan
     mit." ("To Hoboken (letter): tell him the lesson schedule").</tei:note> eintraf. Ich danke
    Ihnen für die Einteilung, welche ja für mich ganz besonders bequem ist. Nur kann <tei:supplied reason="clarity">ich</tei:supplied> nicht schon am 3. X. in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Wien</tei:rs> sein. Ich sprach diese Befürchtung bereits in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galltür</tei:rs> aus und sie hat sich
    bewahrheitet. Ich habe hier noch allerhand zu erledigen. So die Verpachtung meines Gartens, die
    noch nicht abgeschlossen ist und wobei die Hauptschwierigkeit darin besteht, dass mein
    verflossenen Gärtner die Wohnung nicht räumen will. Dann die Veräusserung eines Geschäftes
    dessen Inhaber ich bin, u.s.w. Nun kann ich natürlich wohl einfach abreisen, doch müsste ich
    dann alle diese Sachen von <tei:placeName>Wien</tei:placeName> aus schriftlich erledigen oder
    doch am Ende noch einmal nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002286">München</tei:rs> zurück
    fahren. Es scheint mir daher vorteilhafter, alles jetzt zu erledigen wenn auch mein Eintreffen
    in <tei:placeName>Wien</tei:placeName> sich dadurch verspätet. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="5"/> Immerhin hoffe ich um den 10<tei:hi rend="supralinear">ten</tei:hi> herum fertig zu sein und am Dienstag den 13<tei:hi rend="supralinear">ten</tei:hi> nachmittags halb 3 zu Ihnen zu kommen. Allerdings werde ich dann noch kein
    Klavier haben. <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002442">Kohn</tei:rs> konnte mir auf einen Steinway
    keine Hoffnung geben und so habe ich mich entschlossen, einen von hier mitzunehmen und bei der
    Gelegenheit auch mein <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000027">Bach</tei:rs>-Klavier nach
     <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Wien</tei:rs> zu schaffen. Wie <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">lange</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">viel Zeit</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> die Reise dieser Instrumente in Anspruch nehmen wird ist mir noch nicht bekannt. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich erlaube mir, Ihnen einschliessend $60.- zukommen <tei:supplied reason="clarity">zu lassen</tei:supplied> als erste Zahlung, für den Monat October <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">praenumerando</tei:foreign>, wie ausgemacht. Ich leiste diese Zahlung in
    Amerikanischen Noten ohne zu wissen, ob Ihnen diese Form angenehm ist. Sollten Sie eine andere
    Zahlungsform vorziehen, so bitte ich Sie, mir dieses gelegentlich mitzuteilen. Ich kann mich
    nach jedem Ihrer Wünsche richten. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich bitte Sie, mich Ihrer Frau <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Gemahlin</tei:rs> empfehlen zu wollen wobei sich meine
     <tei:persName>Gattin</tei:persName> gerne anschliesst. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Mit freundlichem Gruss bin ich</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr sehr ergebener</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70">AvHoboken.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>



  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:note type="editorial">printed letterhead: </tei:note>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>ANTON VAN HOBOKEN</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>MUNICH, WALHALLASTRASSE 1</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-75"><tei:handShift new="#AvH"/><tei:date>September 28,
      1925</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Dr. Schenker</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>



   <tei:p rend="first">A<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> few weeks ago, from August
    31 to September 5, I was in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Vienna</tei:rs> with my
     <tei:persName>wife</tei:persName>, and would just like to give you a brief report on this
    visit. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">We traveled not by car but on the express train, which was supposed to arrive
    at 10 p.m., but because of a mechanical failure shortly before <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002340">St. Pölten</tei:rs>, we did not arrive until shortly before 12. The
    next day we immediately proceeded to the architect <tei:persName>Hans Goldschmid</tei:persName>,
    who served as agent for the house, and from there, with him, directly to the latter. We were
    simply enchanted with the place and immediately rented it for a term of one year. It lies on the
    Heiligenkreuzerhof, quite close to the Fleischmarkt. You enter it through a small, somewhat
    weathered Baroque stone gate, which leads into a small forecourt covered with trees and vines.
    Then a large and broad stairway to the first level and to the wooden, inlaid entry-door to the
    residence. This, like <tei:hi rend="underline">all</tei:hi> other doors, is old, from the
    Baroque period, and in part still fitted with the old <tei:pb n="2"/> locks. The whole dwelling
    in general, and all the furniture in it, is Baroque. This level is called "the prelate's floor,"
    and is said to have been previously the quarters of the abbot of a cloister. Now it is occupied
    by Prince <tei:persName>Hohenlohe</tei:persName>, from whom we in turn have rented it
    furnished.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">The place is enormous. Aside from the huge dining room there is a still
    larger room where I shall settle in with my instruments. Then there are four more rooms, a
    boudoir and an anteroom, while the kitchen and servant quarters are below on the ground floor.
    The whole place is very quiet, as one can enter the Heiligenkreuzerhof with vehicles only from
    one side, and consequently there is no through traffic. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">We look forward to moving into the place and hope that no insuperable
    difficulties will arise, since not everything can be checked at a viewing, although we were
    there three or four times. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="3"/> The time we had left over in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Vienna</tei:rs> we passed in the way usual for foreigners. We went
    walking past the shops, and evenings were spent mostly in the company of a girlfriend of my
     <tei:persName>wife</tei:persName>. We went to museums, to theater, etc. And we ordered from
    Gräf and Stift<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> a small auto for my wife, and had
    the necessary preliminary conference as well as a demonstration drive to the
     <tei:placeName>Cobenzl</tei:placeName><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> and the
     <tei:placeName>Sophienhöhe</tei:placeName> (so it is called, I believe). That was very
    beautiful. We are now both learning to drive, and hope to make our entrance into
     <tei:placeName>Vienna</tei:placeName> as skilled motorists. (Perhaps it would be advisable for
    the Viennese to increase their life insurance somewhat! But it probably won't be that bad.) </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">On the 5th we traveled to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002477">Paris</tei:rs>. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">But I forgot to mention something, namely my visit to Dr.
     <tei:persName>Siebenschein</tei:persName>, or his agent, Hofrat
     <tei:persName>Stein</tei:persName>. The result of that conversation is that I'm to register in
     <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Vienna</tei:rs> as though for a temporary stay of
    nine months for study purposes, and leave the way open to make further plans later. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="4"/> We enjoyed <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002477">Paris</tei:rs> as always. Except that it was completely off-season, and on both musical
    and theatrical fronts nothing of importance was happening yet. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">We have been back here since the 23d, and I had this letter finished to this
    point when your mail of the 25th<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> arrived. I
    thank you for the work-schedule, which is indeed very convenient for me. Except that I cannot be
    in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Vienna</tei:rs> as early as October 3. I already
    expressed this misgiving in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>, and it
    has proven true. I have all manner of things to take care of here. Such as the lease of my
    garden, which is not yet definite, and in which the main difficulty consists in the fact that my
    previous gardner refuses to vacate the residence. Then the disposal of a business of which I am
    the proprietor, etc. Naturally, I could simply leave; but then I would have to attend to these
    matters in writing from <tei:placeName>Vienna</tei:placeName>, or, in the end, return once more
    to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002286">Munich</tei:rs>. It thus appears to me more
    advantageous to see to everything now, even though my arrival in
     <tei:placeName>Vienna</tei:placeName> is thereby delayed. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="5"/> Anyway, I hope to be ready on the 10th and to come to you on
    the afternoon of Tuesday the 13th at 2:30. Then, to be sure, I will still have no piano.
     <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002442">Kohn</tei:rs> could not hold out hope for a Steinway, and
    thus I have decided to take one with me from here, and use the occasion to send my <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000027">Bach</tei:rs> keyboard to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Vienna</tei:rs> as well. How much time the journey of these instruments will take is as
    yet unknown to me. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I take the liberty of enclosing $60 for you, as first payment in advance for
    the month of October, according to agreement. I make this payment in American notes without
    knowing whether this form is acceptable to you. Should you prefer a different form of payment,
    please notify me. I can proceed in any way you wish. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Please be so kind as to convey my best wishes to your <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">wife</tei:rs>, a request in which my
     <tei:persName>wife</tei:persName> joins me. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">With cordial greetings, I remain</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Yours very truly,</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70">A. v. Hoboken</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>