<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3888" sdoID="OJ-13-10_176">OJ 13/10, [176]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2025</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated November 26, 1933</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1933-11-26T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-12-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel describes a concert given in memory of Julius Klengel. – He has been
        studying the music of Hugo Wolf. – His income will be reduced as a result of the closure of
        the Society of German Composers. </dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1933-11-26">26. XI.
          33</tei:date>.</tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Professor Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
            >Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for November 28, 1933: “Von
            Oppel (Br.): schickt eine neue Deutschland-Hymne von Knettel, ein Bildchen von Beppo u.
            eine Einladung der Goos-Schule zu einer Schenker-Vorlesung; im Brief eine gute
            Musikkritik, über die Verhältnisse. Das Nebeneinander von Hitler, Goebels u. Schenker
            wirkt sehr erheiternd” (“From Oppel (letter): sends a new hymn to Germany by Knettel, a
            snapshot of Beppo, and an invitation from Goos’s school to a lecture on Schenker; in the
            letter, a good music review; concerning the conditions [in Germany]. The juxtaposition
            of the names Hitler, Goebbels, and Schenker has a very amusing
          effect”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>schon wieder ist ein Monat vorüber seit Ihrer letzten Nachricht.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker’s diary records the writing of
          a postcard to Oppel on October 26, 1933: “An Oppel (K.): wie das Befinden?” (“To Oppel
          (postcard): how is his health?”). </tei:note> Wie geht’s mit den Augen? Hoffentlich hat
        die vom Artzte verordnete Schonung Linderung gebracht. Mir geht es leidlich, eine
        Muskelzerrung beim Turnen mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008523">Bepo</tei:rs> zwang
        mich, 2 Tage still im Bett zu liegen, jetzt geht es wieder. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-008523">Bepo</tei:rs> ist gestern 3 Jahre geworden, ich schicke hier ein Bild
        von ihm, das Ende Sept. vor einem Schaufenster gemacht wurde. Er u. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-008524">Brigitte</tei:rs> machen körperlich u. geistig gute Fortschritte. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Leider hat unsre Genossenschaft Deutscher Tonsetzer liquidiert, u. wir armen
        Kompositionshasen sollen nun <tei:unclear reason="reading">Jahre</tei:unclear>
          resp<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">.</tei:supplied> in Zukunft an unsren Einnahmen
        gekürzt werden. Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000871">Rich. Strauss</tei:rs> kann
        das ganz gut vertragen! Ausgerechnet an dem Tage, da Goebbels den Kulturrat eröffnete,
        erhielten wir diese üble Nachricht, gleichsam als kleinen Schicksalsdämpfer u. Mahnung,
        nicht zu hoch auf die Bäume zu klettern. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Heute war Feier bei uns für den verstorb. Julius Klengel, nur Werke von ihm: eine
        Konzertouverture op 35, formal zu mechanisch u. weitschweifig, ohne Konzentration, Serenade
        op. 24 F-dur f. Streichorchester, ebenso, u. Konzert für Violoncell No. 4, op 37, h-moll.
        Alles unpersönlich, meist Tschaikowsky-Fahrwasser, gelegentlich eine Anleihe bei <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000808">Schumann</tei:rs>. In d. Cellokonzert die Technik für ds
        Soloinstr. übersteigert, bei dem vollen Orchester klingt diese Akrobatic oben beim Steg
        nicht. Das Cello entmannt sich selbst in diesen hohen Lagen. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000027">Bach</tei:rs> hat es den Cellisten ja gezeigt, wie weit man zu gehen
        hat u. selbst Boccherini bleibt i. den natürlichen Grenzen. Ich kampfe immer gegen diese
          <tei:pb n="2"/> Auswüchse, (<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003093">Paganini</tei:rs>’s
          <tei:title>perpetuum mobile</tei:title> in <tei:del rend="overstrike">V</tei:del>
        originale Violinlage auf d. Cello, u. selbst Violinkonzerte, auf dem Cello kastriert). Im
        übrigen ist alle Klengel-musik rein harmonisch empfunden u. construiert, mit jedem Takt
        rückt die Harmonie einen Schritt weiter, u. die Holzwollepuppen tanzen oben drüber. Von
        Bassmelodisierung keine Rede, kurz u. gut, die Stücke trotz sorgfältiger Vorbereitung höchst
        unerfreulich. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Neulich las ich drei Stunden über <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-00974"
          >Wolf</tei:rs> u. liess den Schülern sehr viele Lieder vorsingen in den parallelen
        Vertonungen von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000803">Schubert</tei:rs>, <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000808">Schumann</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005104"
          >Jensen</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-00974">Wolf</tei:rs>. Auch <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-00974">Wolf</tei:rs>s Art rückt mir immer ferner, sie ist
        ebenfalls zu harmonisch u. das beste bei ihm sind noch die Lieder, bei denen er sich streng
        an <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000803">Schubert</tei:rs>s Weise hält. Merkwürdig, dass
        er nach <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000803">Schubert</tei:rs>’s „<tei:title>Ihr
          Bild</tei:title>“ (<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000348">Heine</tei:rs>) den Text
        nochmals vertont hat; er hatte also doch <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000803"
          >Schubert</tei:rs>s geniale Lösung offenbar gar nicht begriffen. Psychologisch ist auch
        interessant, wie sehr sich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000695">Reger</tei:rs> zu
        seinem Nachteil mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-00974">Wolf</tei:rs> beschäftigt hat.
        – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Als Drucksache schicke ich Ihnen eine neue Deutschlandhymne meines Freundes <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-006121">Knettel</tei:rs> in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-004583">Bingen</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Josef Knettel is first mentioned in the Oppel–Schenker correspondence in
          October 1926; he arranged to have Oppel’s <tei:hi rend="italic">a cappella</tei:hi> Mass
          performed in the Rhineland the following year.</tei:note> schlicht u. vornehm empfunden u.
        leicht eingänglich. Mein Schüler <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000299">Goos</tei:rs> hat
        am <tei:date when="1933-11-01">1. Nov</tei:date> in Neumünster einen Vortrag gehalten, um
        für Sie zu wirken. Er wird Ihnen darüber noch selbst schreiben. Er gibt sich alle Mühe, wenn
        er auch noch zu unselbständig ist. Übrigens hat er die Absicht, in einem oder 2 Jahren noch
        selbst bei Ihnen in Wien etwas zu studieren. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Meine Anzeige beim Staatsanwalt wegen der unglaublichen Wirtschaft unsres <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002872">Landeskonservatorium</tei:rs>s <tei:del
          rend="overstrike">ist</tei:del> hat nichts gefruchtet, alle Missstände werden ohne
        weiteres zugegeben, aber die <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">illegible
          word</tei:note> ehemalige Vorstand des Kuratoriums ist leider staatrechtlich nicht zu
        fassen. Ich lasse aber jetzt das Material an das Kultus- u. Justizministerium u. die
        Kreishauptmannschaft weiter gehen. Damit diese Herrn v Kuratorium, die uns in eine so üble
        pecuniäre Lage gebracht haben, wenigstens öffentlich moralisch gebrandmarkt werden. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003109">Hitler</tei:rs>s Bündnisvorschlag an <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002520">Frankreich</tei:rs> will mir in keiner Weise in den
        Kopf!!! </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Alles Gute u. <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in left margin,
            sideways</tei:note> die herzlichsten Grüsse </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>Ihnen beiden von uns allen!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>Ihr treuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1933-11-26">November 26,
            1933</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor
            Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Yet another month has passed since I last heard from you.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> How are your eyes? I hope that the rest that the doctor prescribed has
        brought relief. I am tolerably well; a muscle strain, while doing exercises with <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-008523">Bepo</tei:rs>, compelled me to lie still in bed for two
        days, and now things are again fine. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008523">Bepo</tei:rs>
        was three years old yesterday; I am sending you a snapshot of him here, which was taken at
        the end of September in front of a shop window. He and <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-008524">Brigitte</tei:rs> are making good physical and intellectual progress.
        –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Unfortunately, our Society of German Composers has been liquidated, and we poor
        composing rabbits must now have our incomes reduced for <tei:unclear
          reason="original_unclear">years</tei:unclear>, or for the future. Mr. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000871">Richard Strauss</tei:rs> can survive that very well! On
        the very day on which Goebbels opened the Council of Culture, we received this bad news, as
        a little damper of fate and a warning not to climb too high in the trees.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Today we had a celebration of the late Julius Klengel, with works only by him: a
        concert overture, Op. 35: too mechanical and discursive, without concentration; likewise,
        the Serenade in F major for string orchestra Op. 24; and the Cello Concerto No. 4 in B
        minor, Op. 37. Everything impersonal, mainly along the lines of Tchaikovsky, occasionally an
        indebtedness to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000808">Schumann</tei:rs>. In the Cello
        Concerto, the technique for the solo instrument was overdone; against a full orchestra,
        these acrobatics high up by the bridge don’t sound well. The cello emasculates itself in
        these high registers. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000027">Bach</tei:rs> showed
        cellists just how far one can go; and even Boccherini remains within the natural boundaries.
        I struggle against these <tei:pb n="2"/> excrescences (<tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003093">Paganini</tei:rs>’s <tei:title level="m">Perpetuum mobile</tei:title>
        on the cello, in its original violin register; and even violin concertos, castrated on the
        cello). Moreover, all of Klengel’s music is felt and constructed on a purely harmonic basis;
        with every bar, the harmony takes one step further and the wood-shaving puppets dance above.
        There is no trace of the bass becoming melodic; in short, the pieces were highly displeasing
        despite being prepared carefully. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Recently I lectured for three hours on <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-00974"
          >Wolf</tei:rs> and had my pupils sing many songs in the parallel setting of <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000803">Schubert</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000808">Schumann</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094"
          >Brahms</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005104">Jensen</tei:rs>, and <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-00974">Wolf</tei:rs>. Even <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-00974">Wolf</tei:rs>’s style seems remote to me, it is likewise too harmonic,
        and the best of his works are still those songs that adhere strictly to <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000803">Schubert</tei:rs>’s manner. It is strange that, after
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000803">Schubert</tei:rs>’s <tei:title level="m">Ihr
          Bild</tei:title>, he set the text of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000348"
          >Heine</tei:rs>’s poem once again; he evidently had not understood Schubert’s
        genius-imbued solution at all. It is interesting, from a psychological point of view, to see
        how much <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000695">Reger</tei:rs> studied <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-00974">Wolf</tei:rs>, to his disadvantage.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I am sending you as printed papers a new hymn to Germany by my friend <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-006121">Knettel</tei:rs> in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-004583">Bingen</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/>
        simply and elegantly felt, and easily accessible. My pupil <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000299">Goos</tei:rs> gave a lecture in Neumünster on <tei:date
          when="1933-11-01">November 1</tei:date>, to plead your cause. He will write to you about
        it himself. He spares himself no effort, even though he is not sufficiently independent. In
        addition, he intends to study a bit with you in Vienna in a year or two.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>My complaint to the district attorney about the unbelievable situation at our <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002872">State Conservatory</tei:rs> bore no fruit; all the
        grievances were acknowledged without further ado; but the previous <tei:note
          type="editorial" place="inline">illegible word</tei:note> of the Board of Trustees is,
        unfortunately, not to be comprehended. I am now having the materials forwarded to the
        Ministry of Culture and Justice and the local captaincy. These gentleman on the Board of
        Trustees, who have brought us into such a bad financial state, will thus at least publicly
        be branded as immoral. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003109">Hitler</tei:rs>'s suggested alliance with
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002520">France</tei:rs> is nothing that I can possibly
        contemplate!!!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>All good wishes and <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in left margin,
            sideways</tei:note> the most cordial greetings </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>to the two of you from all of us!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>Your faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
