<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="2313" sdoID="OJ-15-16_23">OJ 15/16, [23]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HW" scope="sole">Hans Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2007</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="AH">
   <tei:persName>Alison Hiley</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2008</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-06-25" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated July 16, 1914</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1914-07-16T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-10-23</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Weisse thanks Schenker for clippings of two articles from the Münchener Zeitung.
    Returning them, he critiques Alexander Berrsche's references there to the theory of the trill as
    expounded in Schenker's Beitrag zur Ornamentik.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Zeitungsausschnitt; newspaper clipping; Auseinandersetzung; analysis; misverstehen;
    to misunderstand; Triller; trill; Hervorhebung; giving prominence; Stellungnahme;
    opinion</dc:subject>



   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000951">Weisse</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HW"/>Geliebter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
      >Meister</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker’s diary
      records at OJ 1/15, p. 611, July 14, 1914: "Sendungen: [...] an Weisse die
       „<tei:title>Münchener Ztg</tei:title>“. ("Mailings: [. . .] to Weisse, the <tei:title
       level="j">Münchener Zeitung</tei:title>").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Anbei sende ich Ihnen die beiden Zeitungsausschnitte zurück, die ich natürlich sofort
    gelesen und deren Auseinandersetzungen mich wenig erbaut haben.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
     type="editorial" place="foot">The two articles, copies of which are preserved in Schenker's
     scrapbook (OC 2/p. 44), are from issues of the <tei:title level="j">Münchener
      Zeitung</tei:title> dated May 29 and June 9, 1914. The first, entitled <tei:title level="a"
      >Der Triller bei den Klassikern</tei:title> (concerning Schenker's theory of trill as
     expounded in his <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001721"><tei:title level="m">Beitrag zur
       Ornamentik</tei:title></tei:rs> (1903; 2/1908)), is an open letter from Alexander Berrsche, a
     regular columnist for the newspaper, that replies to an earlier article on the subject (not
     preserved in the scrapbook). The second (printed under the same title) is a reply by Eduard
     Bach ‒ presumably the author of the original piece ‒ together with a further response from
     Berrsche. There is a more extended discussion of this material in Schenker's letter to <tei:rs
      type="person" key="entity-000356">Emil Hertzka</tei:rs> of June 30, 1914 (WSLB
     222).</tei:note> Es macht mir den Eindruck, als ob <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000067"
     >Berrsche</tei:rs> Sie absichtlich missverstehen wollte, um überhaupt schreiben zu können.
    Indem <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">Ihr</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">er</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> Ihnen Unverständlichkeit unterschiebt, gewinnt er für sich die Möglichkeit erklären
    – breiter ausführen zu können – was im Grunde nichts andres zu sagen – als Sie selbst! Nur dass
    die beiden Pünkte, die ihn zur „Ausführlichkeit“ bestimmen, unter seiner Hand einen viel
    unsichereren Profil bekommen – als sie es in Ihrer Darstellung nach seiner Angabe ja haben
    konnten. Schon sein Satz: „Dieser innere Grund ist – wie Sch. richtig erkannt hat – die
     <tei:term>Vorhalt</tei:term>snatur <tei:hi rend="double-underline">des</tei:hi> Trillers“
    (während Sie so klar sagen: „<tei:hi rend="double-underline">im</tei:hi> Triller“) verwirrt. –
    (Kann doch die <tei:term>Hauptnote</tei:term> des Trillers selbst harmonisch genommen ein
     <tei:term>Vorhalt</tei:term> sein!) Seine Folgerung aus obigem Satze ergibt jedoch, dass ihm
     <tei:del rend="overstrike3">der</tei:del> Ihr <tei:term>Gedanke</tei:term> unverständlich
    geblieben ist: wenn Sie sagen, dass auch der Triller, wenn er auf der
     <tei:term>Hauptnote</tei:term> beginnt, <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">seinen</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">den</tei:add>
    </tei:subst>
    <tei:term>Vorhalt</tei:term>scharacter der <tei:term>Hilfsnote</tei:term> durch ihre
    Wiederholung und besonders durch die Charakterisierung <tei:pb n="2"/> der harmonischen
    Situation beibehalten könne! Ich bitte Sie nun ein Wort über Ihre Stellung dazu! Im übrigen –
    will es mich sicher bedünken – dass sie alle beide . . . . . (der eine wegen <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000695">Reger</tei:rs>, der andere, wegen Hervorhebung <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000150">d’Albert</tei:rs>s <tei:choice>
     <tei:sic>Angaben</tei:sic>
     <tei:corr>angaben</tei:corr>
    </tei:choice>).<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">In his earlier piece,
     Berrsche singles out Eugen d'Albert for his excellent interpretation of Beethoven's trills; in
     the second, he mentions Max Reger's, probably in connection with Bach's original (lost)
     newspaper article. — No paragraph-break in original at this point.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich schicke Ihnen zugleich, liebster Meister<tei:supplied reason="punctuation"
     >,</tei:supplied> ein Exemplar <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002546"><tei:title>der
      Fackel</tei:title></tei:rs>, (das ich weiter nicht benötige) weil ich denke, dass Sie es dort
    oben nicht bekommen werden! Ich bitte Sie besonders das Zitat Theodor Häckers<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Theodor Häcker, German writer. Outspoken
     representative of Catholic existentialism; radical critic of fascism's "renewal of culture"
     during the Weimar Republic and the Third Reich (<tei:title level="m"
     >wikipedia</tei:title>).</tei:note> auf Seite 57 daselbst zu lesen mit dem guten Schlusssatze:
    wo die <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overwritten">Toten</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="superimposed">Lebenden</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> tot sind, haben auch die Toten, die lebendig sind Ihr Recht verloren!<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Weisse is probably including this because of
     its direct relation to the final sentence in Berrsche's first piece: <tei:lb/><tei:cit>
      <tei:q>Aber wenn man schon dem lebenden grossen Meister nicht glauben will, so soll man
       wenigstens den alten Ph. Em. Bach nicht mit dem Beckmesserwort abtun: „Ein guter Meister,
       doch lange schon tot“ (Wie lehrte wohl der uns des Trillers Gebot?) <tei:lb/>(But if one
       refuses to believe even the great living master, one should at the very least not dismiss old
       C. P. E. Bach with the Beckmesser words: "a good master, but long since dead." (How, then,
       did he teach us the rule of the trill?))</tei:q>
     </tei:cit>
    </tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich bin ganz gesund, doch aber noch faul und wenig arbeitsarm! Falls Sie einen Augenblick
    Zeit haben, Liebster, so schreiben Sie doch ein Wort Ihrer Stellungnahme zu <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000067">Berrsche</tei:rs>s Ausfsatz. Ihrem Sie herzlichst umarmenden
    und zur letzten Korrektur beglückwünschenden</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">getreuen</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
     >Hans</tei:rs>.</tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002339">Bad Ischl</tei:rs>. <tei:date
       when="1914-07-16">16/VII 14</tei:date>.</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript><tei:lb/>
    <tei:p>Die Vorschule der Ästhetik<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot"
      >Jean Paul Richter's <tei:title level="m">Vorschule der Ästhetik</tei:title>, first published
      in 1804.</tei:note> ist vollständig vergriffen und leider nicht mehr aufzutreiben!</tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>


  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HW"/>Beloved <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
      >Master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>I am returning to you the two newspaper articles which I of course read at once ‒ I found
    little delight in their analyses, however.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> I get
    the impression that <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000067">Berrsche</tei:rs> deliberately set
    out to misunderstand you, in order that he might have something to write about. In accusing you
    of being incomprehensible he grants himself the freedom to explain ‒ to be able to expound at
    greater length ‒ that which, when all is said and done, is nothing other than your own words!
    Except that the two points which he feels bound to expand on take on a far less certain profile
    in his hands than they could have according to his assessment of your representation. The
    following sentence alone is confusing: "This inner foundation lies ‒ as Schenker has rightly
    recognized ‒ in the <tei:term>retardation</tei:term>
    <tei:hi rend="double-underline">of</tei:hi> the trill" (whereas you say so clearly "<tei:hi
     rend="double-underline">in</tei:hi> the trill"). (Harmonically speaking, indeed, the
     <tei:term>main note</tei:term> of the trill can itself be a <tei:term>retardation</tei:term>!)
    However, the conclusion he draws from the above sentence shows that he has not understood your
    thinking, when you say that the trill, if it begins on the <tei:term>main note</tei:term>, can
    still retain <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">its</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">the</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> retarding character of the <tei:term>auxiliary note</tei:term>, through repetition
    and especially through the characterization <tei:pb n="2"/> of the harmonic situation! Please
    give me a word of your own on the subject! Otherwise ‒ so it seems to me ‒ both of them … (the
    one regarding <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000695">Reger</tei:rs>, the other on account of
    giving prominence to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000150">d’Albert</tei:rs>, were showing
     off).<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>I'm also sending you, dearest Master, a copy of <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002546"
      ><tei:title level="j">Die Fackel</tei:title></tei:rs> (which I no longer need) because I don't
    think that you'll be able to get it up there! Do have a look in particular at the quotation from
    Theodor Häcker<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> on p.57, with its fine
    conclusion: "where the <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overwritten">dead</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="superimposed">living</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> are dead, so, too, have the living dead lost their rights!"<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>I am quite well but still lazy and unproductive! Should you have a moment, dearest
     <tei:supplied reason="clarity">Master</tei:supplied>, please let me know your opinion of
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000067">Berrsche</tei:rs>'s article. Embracing you most
    cordially, wishing you all the best for the final corrections, I am your</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">trusty</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
     >Hans</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002339">Bad Ischl</tei:rs>. <tei:date
       when="1914-07-16">July 16, 1914 </tei:date></tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript><tei:lb/>
    <tei:p><tei:title level="m">Die Vorschule der Ästhetik</tei:title><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06"
      type="footnote"/> is completely out of print and unfortunately no longer to be had!</tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>


  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
