<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2762" sdoID="OJ-13-35_3">OJ 13/35, [3]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HRu" scope="sole">Hilde Rubinraut's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2022</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2022</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>


    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2011-06-09" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008187">RubinrautH ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Hilde Rubinraut to Schenker, dated September 7,
        1922</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1922-09-07T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2022-06-06</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Hilde Rubinraut asks Schenker to name a gilt-edged currency in which to pay
        him, and decides to opt for two piano lessons per 3-weekly visit.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000719">HRubinraut</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#HRu"/><tei:date when="1922-09-07">7.
            September 1922</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Doktor</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for September 9, 1922: “Von Frau Rubinraut
            (Br.): nimmt die Bedingungen an, bittet in einer anderen Währung zahlen zu dürfen;
            wünscht Mittwoch u. Donnerstag.” (“From Mrs. Rubinraut (letter): accepts the conditions,
            asks for permission to pay in a different currency; prefers Wednesday and
            Thursday.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Für Ihre Bereitwilligkeit mich als Schülerin wieder aufzunehmen, braucht es keiner
        Versicherung meinerseits, wie sehr ich mich zu Dank verpflichtet fühle. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Was Ihre Honoraransprüche betreffen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot">In response to Mrs Rubinraut’s inquiry in <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-13-35_2">OJ 13/35, [2]</tei:ref>, September 1, 1922,
          Schenker answered, according to his diary summary, September 4: “20 Goldkronen.” (“20
          Goldkronen.”). Schenker’s diary for September 10 records his reply: “An Frau Rubinraut
          (Br.): schlage Dollar vor.” (“To Mrs Rubinraut (letter): propose the dollar.”).</tei:note>
        erkläre ich mich bereit die Basis der 20 Goldkronen anzuerkennen, jedoch wäre es mir aus
          technisch<tei:supplied reason="agreement">en</tei:supplied> und praktischen Gründen sehr
        wünschenswert wenn Sie als Equivalent eine stabilisierte, sogenannte Edelvalute wählen
        würden, wie zum Beispiel Dollar, schweizer Franc, oder englischer Pfund. In der von Ihnen
        bestimmten Währung würde ich dann bei Entgegennahme meiner Stunden jede 3te Woche den von
        Ihnen auf Grund der 20 Goldkronen fest- <tei:pb n="2"/> gesetzten Betrag, in einer von
        obigen Valuten, in bar überreichen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Dies würde mir Zeit (die für mich in Wien sehr kostbar ist) und jeweilige
        Umwechslung ersparen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich erkläre mich mit <tei:choice>
          <tei:sic>jeden</tei:sic>
          <tei:corr>jedem</tei:corr>
        </tei:choice> von Ihnen bestimmten Tag einverstanden und da Sie einstweilen den
          <tei:sic>Mitwoch</tei:sic> vorziehen, gedenke ich die erste Stunde am <tei:date
          when="1922-10-04">4. Oktober</tei:date> zwischen 5–6 Uhr Abend zu nehmen, die zweite am
          <tei:date when="1922-10-05">5. Oktober</tei:date> von 10–11 Uhr Vormittag.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Entries for October 4 and 5 of
          Schenker’s diary record: “Frau Rubinraut zur ersten Stunde. […] Frau Rubinraut 2. Stunde.”
          (“Mrs Rubinraut to her first lesson. […] Mrs Rubinraut second lesson.”). That for October
          7 records: “Zu <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000655">Frau Pairamall</tei:rs> in Frau
          Rubinraut Passangelegenheit: verspricht, sich zu erkundigen” (“At <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000655">Mrs. Pairamall</tei:rs>'s place regarding Rubinraut's passport
          issue: she promises to inquire.”), and the next day: “11–12½<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
            >h</tei:hi> Herr u. Frau Rubinraut denen wir die Auskunft der Fr. Pairamall mitteilen;
          vereinbaren, in Prag ein Conto anzulegen, Dollar; werden in 3 Wochen wiederkommen. Geben
          ihr das <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001742">3. Heft des
              <tei:title>Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>n als Geschenk.” (“11:00–12:30 Mr and Mrs
          Rubinraut, to whom we pass on the information from Mrs Pairamall; they agree to open an
          account in Prague, in dollars; will come again in three weeks' time. We give her the
            <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001742">third issue of <tei:title level="j">Der
              Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs> as a present.”). The story continues on October 14:
          “Frau Pairamall 5–6¼<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi>: […] in der Angelegenheit
          Rubinraut meint sie, das Dauervisum werde viel kosten.” (“Mrs Pairamall 5:00–6:15: […]
          regarding the Rubinraut situation, she says the long-term visa will cost a lot.”). Further
          entries can be followed from the Rubinraut profile.</tei:note> Ich möchte Sie, sehr
        geehrter Herr Doktor sehr bitten sich an diese Stunden zu halten, da die Ankunft und Abfahrt
        von und nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002892">Prag</tei:rs> mich zwingen, selbst,
        und diese Stunden zu bestimmen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich danke für den Rat und fühle es auch notwendig vorderhand <tei:pb n="3"
        /> die Klavierstunden den Theoriestund<tei:supplied reason="agreement">en</tei:supplied>
        vorzuziehen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich bitte um Ihr Einverständnis bezüglich meines heutigen Vorschlages und
        ersuche gleichzeitig um Andeutung in der Wahl (betreffs erster Stunde) bezüglich meines
        Notenmaterials. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich freue mich meinen langgehegten Wunsch endlich in Erfüllung gehen zu
        sehen und bin </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihre immer dankbare</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000719">Hilde
            Rubinraut</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine>Prag Weinberge</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10">Manesová 16.</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#HRu"/><tei:date when="1922-09-07"
            >September 7, 1922</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dear Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
            type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>I scarcely need tell you how deeply grateful I feel for your willingness to take me on
        again as your pupil.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">As concerns the fee that you demand,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> I confirm that I am ready to honor the intrinsic value of 20 Goldkronen,
        but I would for technical and practical reasons greatly prefer you to nominate the
        equivalent in a stable, so-called gilt-edged foreign currency, for instance the dollar,
        Swiss franc, or English pound. I would then, in receipt of my lessons, pay you in cash every
        third week in the currency specified by you, <tei:pb n="2"/> the amount set by you on the
        basis of 20 Goldkronen, in one of the above foreign currencies.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">This would save me time (which in Vienna is very expensive for me) and
        prevailing currency rate.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I can confirm my concurrence with each of the days that you propose, and
        since you for the time being prefer Wednesday, I have in mind <tei:date when="1922-10-04"
          >October 4</tei:date> between 5 and 6 p.m. for the first lesson, and <tei:date
          when="1922-10-05">October 5</tei:date> from 10 to 11 a.m. for the second.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> I should be very grateful, dear Dr. <tei:supplied
          reason="identity">Schenker</tei:supplied>, if you could adhere to these times, since it is
        the arrival and departure from and to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002892"
          >Prague</tei:rs> that compels me to specify these, and only these times.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I am grateful for your advice, and feel it also necessary for the time
        being <tei:pb n="3"/> to opt for piano lessons over theory lessons.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I ask for your assent to my proposal of today, and at the same time
        request your suggestion as to the selection (for the first lesson) of sheet music
          <tei:supplied reason="clarity">to bring with me</tei:supplied>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I am thrilled to see my long-harbored wish finally about to be fulfilled,
        and remain</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your ever grateful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000719">Hilde
            Rubinraut</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine>Prag Weinberge</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10">Mánesova 16</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
