<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3102" sdoID="OJ-10-3_119">OJ 10/3, [119]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPoed" scope="major">Otto Erich Deutsch typist</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="OED" scope="minor">Otto Erich Deutsch's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2023</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IDB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2015-09-18" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002726">DeutschOE ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002712">DeutschOE ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002727">DeutschOE+H ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Typewritten letter from Deutsch to Schenker, dated February 26, 1930</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1930-02-26T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2023-03-23</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>In contrast to the uprightness of Schenker’s other pupils, Hans Weisse and
        Felix Salzer, Hoboken is described by Deutsch as an unsteady, unfocussed person who may yet
        be able to do some good but whose restlessness gives him grounds to fear for the future of
        his library, and his own future.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000164">DeutschOE</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>PROF. OTTO ERICH DEUTSCH</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">WIEN II.</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Böcklinstraße 26</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Tel. R 45–6–72</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/><tei:date when="1930-02-26">26.
            Februar 30</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber verehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Doktor</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for February 27, 1930: “Von Deutsch (Br.):
            sehe van H. nun etwas klarer.” (“From Deutsch (letter): he now sees Hoboken in a
            somewhat clearer light.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>


      <tei:p rend="first">Dank für Brief und Karten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
          place="foot">This correspondence is summarized in the diary as follows:<tei:lb/> February
          16: “An Deutsch (Br.): Offerte von <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002402"
            >Waldheim</tei:rs>; erkundige mich nach einem Kommisionsverlag; erkläre es für eine
          Schande, daß mir in einem solchen Augenblick keine andere Möglichkeit bequem geboten wird”
          (“To Deutsch (letter): quotation from <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002402"
            >Waldheim</tei:rs>; I enquire about a publisher who will take on my work on a commission
          basis; I say that it is a scandal that, at such a moment, no other possibility is
          reasonably offered to me”).<tei:lb/> February 21: “An Deutsch (K.): Dank für seine Mühe;
          mache ihm Gedanken über Salzer–Weisse, Hobokens Betragen daran gemessen?,” (“To Deutsch
          (postcard): thanks for his efforts; I offer him my thoughts on Salzer-Weisse, Hoboken’s
          behavior measured against it?,”). :<tei:lb/> February 23: “An Deutsch (K.): wie v. H. die
          Missa solemnis bestellt hat” (“To Deutsch (postcard): <tei:supplied reason="clarity">I ask
            him</tei:supplied> how Hoboken booked the <tei:title level="m">Missa
            solemnis</tei:title>”). </tei:note> Es war auch für mich sehr erhebend, wie schön
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs> und <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000754">Salzer</tei:rs> sich benahmen, letzterer ein würdiger Spross der
          Wit<tei:supplied reason="omission">t</tei:supplied>genstein-Tradition, in die sich auch
        ein Ausländer (Stonborough)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Probably Thomas Stonborough (1906–86), the nephew of the philosopher Ludwig Wittgenstein
          and a cousin of Felix Salzer.</tei:note> als Rabe eingeschlichen hat … Ich war sehr
        dankbar für den allseitigen Genuss. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Unser Freund<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >“Unser Freund”: from the context, Anthony van Hoboken</tei:note> ist anders, aber man
        darf ihm – abgesehen von seinem quartalsweisen Fleiss – doch nicht Leistungen absprechen,
        die er, aus welchen Gründen immer, für die Allgemeinheit geleistet hat und jetzt halt noch
        launischer leistet. Dass er sich als Schüler nicht viel besser benimmt wie als Brotgeber
        (Bibliotheks-Inhaber), glaube ich freilich. Aber was tun? Wir können ihn doch nicht mehr in
        die Schule schicken. Nur durch Beispiel und durch Noblesse kann er gebessert werden. Wie Sie
        sagen, durch seine Mäzene hier. Die <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002742">Frau</tei:rs>
        beurteilen wir noch immer anders als Sie, und wir glauben, sie besser zu kennen, näher
        wenigstens. Sie lässt zwar seinen Launen meist freien Lauf, wie den harmloseren eigenen,
        aber <tei:choice>
          <tei:sic>Sie</tei:sic>
          <tei:corr>sie</tei:corr>
        </tei:choice> hindert ihn doch nicht, Vernünftiges zu tun und zu leisten (<tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archiv</tei:rs>). Die Zukunft wird entscheiden,
        wer richtiger hier sieht. Jedenfalls ist der neu Ausflug, wenn er nicht durch die kranke
        Hand eingegeben ist, ein neuer Beweis der Unstetheit. Die <tei:rs type="composition"
          key="entity-001188"><tei:title>Missa</tei:title></tei:rs> hat er doch hier eben unter
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs> gehört, und von den <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-003235">Philharmonik</tei:rs>ern. Wenn in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs> wirklich, wie es scheint, das Werk
        innerhalb von 2 oder 3 Wochen von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">F.</tei:rs> und
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000442">Klemperer</tei:rs> dirigiert wird, so ist das
        für einen normalen Menschen gewiss kein Grund, dorthin zu fahren und dort drei Wochen zu
        bleiben. Aber er fühlt sich vielleicht auch einsam hier, und ein fliegender Holländer kann
        ebenso unstet sein wie ein ewiger Jude. Auch Gschaftlhuberei spielt natürlich mit. Es ist
        traurig, dass er damit auch die Arbeit bei Ihnen, die er doch ernst zu nehmen scheint,
        spielerisch macht. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> Die Jahrbuch-Sitzung,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05"
          type="editorial" place="foot">A yearbook recording the activities of the <tei:rs
            type="organization" key="entity-002452">Photogram Archive</tei:rs> and publishing
          articles on textual criticism.</tei:note> an der ich eventuell teilnehmen sollte, ist also
        neuerlich verschoben durch diesen Abstecher. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich möchte Ihnen noch aufrichtig sagen, dass ich mich über <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-002742">Frau v. H.</tei:rs>, mit der ich sonst ganz gut
        auskomme, wiederholt geärgert habe, wenn Sie [recte: sie] die Bibliothek als eine launige
        Beschäftigung auffasste, die man nicht zu ernst und konsequent betreiben dürfe. Dabei schien
        aber nie das Geld entscheidend zu sein, das sie kostet, und meine Honorierung wurde als
        selbstverständlich, meine Stellung als nicht subaltern bezeichnet. Aber ich fürchte, da das
        Thema dieser Arbeit noch keineswegs populär ist bei Verlegern, Sammlern, Lesern – dass ich
        die Früchte nicht ernten werde, bevor <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">H.</tei:rs>
        seine Zelte abbricht und, wie manche fürchten einem Nebehay<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Gustav Nebehay (1881–1935), a famous and highly respected
          art dealer in Vienna.</tei:note> in den Rachen wirft, was ich zusammengetragen habe. Nicht
        einmal einen neuen Beethoven-Katalog (<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000636"
          >Nottebohm</tei:rs>, 3. Auflage) dürfte ich herausbringen, der mir sehr am Herzen läge. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Wenn Sie in der Sache der <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001752"
            ><tei:title>Eroica</tei:title></tei:rs> noch einen Rat brauchen (verlegerisch), so stehe
        ich gerne zur Verfügung. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">2:2!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-80">Ihr sehr ergebener</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-90"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/><tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000164">O E Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>PROF. OTTO ERICH DEUTSCH</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">VIENNA II</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Böcklinstraße 26</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Tel. R 45–6–72</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/><tei:date when="1930-02-26"
            >February 26, 1930</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear revered Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
            type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>


      <tei:p rend="first">Thank you for your letter and postcards.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> For me, too, it was very uplifting to see how beautifully <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs> und <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000754">Salzer</tei:rs> behaved, the latter being a worthy scion of the
        Wittgenstein tradition, in which even a foreigner (Stonborough)<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> sneaked in, like a raven … I was very grateful for
        the pleasure from all sides.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Our friend<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> is something
        else; but, in spite of his diligence every three months, one should not deny what he has
        achieved – whatever the reasons – and what he is failing to achieve in an even more erratic
        way. That he does not behave much better as a pupil than as an employer (library
        proprietor), is something that I believe. But what should be done about it? We can no longer
        send him to school. Only by being set a good example can he be improved. As you say, by his
        philanthropists here. We still judge his <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002742"
          >wife</tei:rs> differently than you do; and we believe that we are better acquainted with
        her, at least more closely. She allows his caprices free reign, as she does her own, more
        benign ones; but she nonetheless does not prevent him from acting sensibly and accomplishing
        things (the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archive</tei:rs>). The future
        will decide which of us is the better observer. In any event the new excursion, if it is not
        inspired by the bad hand, is new evidence of his unsteadiness. He actually heard the <tei:rs
          type="composition" key="entity-001188"><tei:title level="m">Missa
          solemnis</tei:title></tei:rs> here, under <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268"
          >Furtwängler</tei:rs> with the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-003235"
          >Philharmonic</tei:rs>. If the work is really to be performed twice in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs> within two or three weeks, by <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000442">Klemperer</tei:rs>, that is still no reason at all for a normal person
        to travel there and stay there for three weeks. But perhaps he also feels lonely here, and a
        Flying Dutchman can be as restless as a Wandering Jew. Being a busybody is naturally a
        contributing factor. It is sad that he also toys around with his work with you, although he
        does seem to take it seriously.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> The meeting to discuss the yearbook,<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> which I might possibly have attended, has also
        just been postponed on account of this side trip.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I should also like to tell you frankly that I have repeatedly been annoyed
        with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002742">Mrs. Hoboken</tei:rs>, with whom I am
        otherwise on entirely good terms, when she views the library as a capricious occupation
        which one ought not pursue too seriously or systematically. But in this matter, money that
        it costs is not a decisive issue, and the payment that I receive is taken for granted and my
        position is not regarded as subordinate. But I fear that the theme of this work is by no
        means popular among publishers, collectors and readers, and that I shall not harvest its
        fruits before <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs> breaks camp and, as
        many fear, throws what I have amassed into the throat of a Nebehay.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> I would not even be able to bring out a new
        Beethoven catalog (a third edition of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000636"
          >Nottebohm</tei:rs>), which I would dearly like to do.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">If you need any further advice (from a publishing perspective) on your
          <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001752"><tei:title>Eroica</tei:title> project</tei:rs>, I
        shall be glad to be of service.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">From the two of us to the two of you,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-80">Your very devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-90"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/><tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000164">O E Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
