<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3480" sdoID="OJ-14-10_13">OJ 14/10, [13]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RW" scope="sole">Rosa Weil's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>


    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008456">WeilR ~
        JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Rosa Weil to Jeanette Schenker, dated May 28,
        1934</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1934-05-28T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-07-24</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Rosa Weil reports that her sister Hella is recovering from surgery and will
        return home. — She regrets she is unable to accept Jeanette’s invitation, but she has to
        care for her husband, Arnold, who is ill. — She reports on Klara and Oskar Hatschek; Oskar
        sends advice on choice of vacation place for the Schenkers.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000944">Rosa Weil</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RW"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002248"
            >Aussig</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1934-05-28">28. Mai 1934</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Meine liebe <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Jenny</tei:rs><tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter was recorded in
            Heinrich’s diary for May 30, 1934: “Von Rosl Weil (Br.): sehr lieb gehalten, meldet ein
            besseres Befinden; Oskar rät von Mallnitz ab.” (“From Rosl Weil (letter): expressed very
            tenderly; she reports improved health; Oskar advises against Mallnitz.”). — Heinrich’s
            diary for May 25 records: “Frau Pairamall sagt sich für ¼4<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
              >h</tei:hi> an – kommt, empfiehlt eine von Dr. Münz empfohlene Villa in Mallnitz.”
            (“Mrs. Pairamall agrees to come at 3:15 – she comes, and suggests a villa in Mallnitz
            recommended by Dr. Münz.”). — Paragraphs 2, 4, and 5 are written continuously, and
            paragraph-breaks have been introduced editorially for easier
          readability.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">vor allem vielen Dank für Deine so prompte Antwort betreffs <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-003920">Hella</tei:rs>;<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot">The last letter from Jeanette recorded in Heinrich’s diary
          is on May 22, 1934: “Lie-Liechen an Rosl (Br.): Auskunft über Hella (bei Frau Suschytzki
          geholt, tel.), Einladung zu einem Rendezvous, ich lade mit! ” (“Lie-Liechen to Rosl
          (letter): information about Hella (collected from Mrs. Suschytzki, by telephone).
          Invitation to a get-together; I second the invitation!”). However, Jeanette must have
          written again on or after May 25 inquiring as to the suitability of Mallnitz for their
          purposes.</tei:note> inzwischen erhielt ich auch von <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003920">ihr selbst</tei:rs> einen sehr netten Brief, sie fühlt sich wohl noch
        recht schwach und erholungsbedürftig, will aber trotzdem schon diese Woche mit <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-005060">Lotte</tei:rs> nachhause fahren. Gott sei Dank ist die
        Sache gut abgelaufen, sie hätte es nicht solange anstehen lassen sollen, dann wäre sie gewiß
        nicht bis auf 47 kg. heruntergekommen. Nun, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005060"
          >Lotte</tei:rs> wird sie wohl jetzt ein bißl pflegen und päppeln; so gerne wäre ich
        wenigstens für eine Woche zu ihr gefahren, hätte geschaut, daß sie vor allem das Richtige
        richtig ißt und die Pflege hat die <tei:pb n="2"/> sie gewiß noch sehr braucht. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Leider muß sich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs> am Freitag
        wieder einer gründlichen Röntgen-Untersuchung des ganzen Verdauungsapparates unterziehen und
        braucht daher wieder 2 Tage früher eine ganz strenge und sorgfältige Diät. Eine ganz
        ansehnliche Sammlung von Steinen wurden ja in seiner Gallenblase entdeckt und werden wir
        wohl voraussichtlich am <tei:date when="1934-07-01">1. Juli</tei:date> selbander nach
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004561">Karlsbad</tei:rs> ziehen. Es wäre für mich sehr
        verlockend, Dich, l. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Jenny</tei:rs>, widerzusehen
        und endlich einmal den lieben <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs>
        kennenzulernen; aber, ich will <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs>
        nicht allein lassen, denn in seiner übergroßen Be- <tei:pb n="3"/> scheidenheit nimmt er
        leicht mit dem schlechtesten vorlieb und ich möchte, daß er von dem Aufenthalt auch ein
        bißchen Freude hat wenn er schon die unangenehme Kur auf sich nehmen nimmt. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Meiner Ansicht nach muß sich jeder Mensch selbst auf den <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">Posten</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">Platz</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> stellen der ihm gebührt, die lieben, guten Nebenmenschen sind schon sehr gerne
        und jederzeit bereit einen soviel als möglich zu drücken und zu ducken. Die Zeiten haben
        sich gewaltig geändert, Feinheit und Bescheidenheit stehen fast ganz tief im Curse. Heute
        muß man Ellenbogen haben und ein stark ausgeprägtes Selbstbewußtsein. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs> ist eigentlich bei all seinem
        Un- <tei:pb n="4"/> glück ziemlich ruhig und gefaßt, auch geben die Ärzte nicht alle
        Hoffnung auf, da ihr körperliches Befinden ganz zufriedenstellend ist; <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003244">sie</tei:rs> wiegt jetzt wieder 50 kg. Auch ist <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003244">sie</tei:rs> viel ruhiger und die Anfälle sind viel seltener. So
        bleibt immernoch ein Hoffnungsstrahl. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs> läßt Euch sagen, daß seiner
        Meinung nach Mallnitz für Euch nicht das richtige wäre; sehr laut, da es Durchgangsstation
        für sehr viele Touristen ist. Das einzige, große Hotel, das Eueren Ansprüchen voll und ganz
        gerecht werden könnte, liegt an der Hauptstraße, kann also nicht ruhig sein. Ich kenne
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003099">Badgastein</tei:rs> nur von meinen wiederhalten
        Fahrten mit der Tauernbahn; da lag es immer wie ein Juwel zu unseren Füßen und ich glaube
        nach allem, was ich bisher davongehört habe, daß Ihr dort finden müsset, was Ihr
          suchet.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">One of Schenker’s
          pupils, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000655">Evelina Pairamall</tei:rs>, had
          suggested a certain villa in Mallnitz for the Schenkers’ summer vacation (cf. footnote 1);
          Heinrich and Jeanette spent the summer in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002359"
            >Böckstein</tei:rs>.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Vielen Dank noch für Euere so liebe Aufforderung und alles Gute und Schöne für den
        Sommer. <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">left margin, sideways:</tei:note>
        Vielleicht kommen wir doch bald einmal zusammen! Allen meinen Patienten<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Rosa is, of course, referring to sick
          family members for whom she is currently caring, directly and indirectly.</tei:note> auch
        mir geht es G.s.D. wieder ganz gut. Wir wünschen Euch eine vollkommene Erholung, danken für
        Euere guten Wünsche und bleiben </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>mit den allerherzlichsten Grüßen</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>Euere</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed>Weils</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RW"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002248"
            >Aussig</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1934-05-28">May 28, 1934</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Jenny</tei:rs><tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">First and foremost, many thanks for your prompt answer concerning <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-003920">Hella</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> In the meantime, I also received a very nice letter from <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-003920">Hella herself</tei:rs>: she is still feeling very weak
        and in need of recuperation, but will travel home with <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-005060">Lotte</tei:rs> this week, despite that. Thank God the thing has gone
        well. She ought not to have let it drag on for so long, then she would surely not have lost
        weight down to 47 kilos. Now <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005060">Lotte</tei:rs> will
        take care of her a little and feed her up. I would have been glad to go to her for at least
        a week and see to it that she eats the right things in the correct way, and that the care is
          <tei:pb n="2"/> really what she still very much needs.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Sadly, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs> has to undergo another
        intensive X-ray investigation of the entire digestive system on Friday, and needs to go on a
        very strict and careful diet again for two days beforehand. A sizeable collection of stones
        was discovered in his gall bladder, and we will probably go to <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-004561">Karlsbad</tei:rs> together on <tei:date when="1934-07-01">July
          1</tei:date>. It will be very tempting for me to see you again, dear <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000771">Jenny</tei:rs>, and at long last to get to know dear <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs>; but I don’t want to leave <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs> on his own, because with his
        overwhelming <tei:pb n="3"/> shyness he is prepared to settle for the minimum whereas I
        would like him to get a little enjoyment from his stay even though he has to submit to the
        unpleasant cure. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>To my mind, every person needs to stand up for themselves as they deserve; the dear,
        good fellow-men are all too keen and are at any moment ready to put you down and humiliate
        you as much as possible. Times have changed mightily: courtesy and modesty are in steep
        decline. These days one has to have elbows and a strongly pronounced degree of
        self-assurance.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs> is, amid all his misfortune,
          <tei:pb n="4"/> quite calm and composed; moreover, the doctors don’t give up all hope
        since her physical condition is entirely satisfactory. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003244">She</tei:rs> is now back up to 50 kilos. What’s more, <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-003244">she</tei:rs> is a lot calmer, and the attacks are far
        less frequent. So there still remains a ray of hope.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs> asks me to tell you that in
        his opinion Mallnitz would not be right for you; <tei:supplied reason="clarity">it
          is</tei:supplied> very loud, because it is a transit station for a great many tourists.
        The only large hotel that could satisfactorily meet your requirements is on the main street,
        so cannot offer peace and quiet. I know <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003099"
          >Badgastein</tei:rs> only from my frequent journeys with the Tauern railway. It lies
        always at our feet like a jewel, and I believe from all that I have heard that you would be
        sure to find there what you are looking for.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"
        /></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Many thanks for your very kind invitation. All the very best for the summer. <tei:note
          type="editorial" place="inline">left margin, sideways:</tei:note> Maybe we can get
        together one of these days soon! All my patients<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
          type="footnote"/> and I are well again, thank God. We wish you a full recuperation, thank
        you for your good wishes, and remain, </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>with most cordial greetings, </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed>Weils</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
