<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3725" sdoID="OJ-13-10_52">OJ 13/10, [52]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2025</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated March 17, 1928</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1928-03-17T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-08-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Writing from Kiel (while the Leipzig Conservatory is closed), Oppel describes
        some of the contemporary music he has heard recently.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1928-03-17">17. III.
              28.</tei:date> Feldstr 77<tei:hi rend="supralinear">IV</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt
            of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for March 17, 1928: “Von Oppel (Br.):
            kann den Besuch in Wien nicht ausführen, wegen Schwierigkeiten, die ihm die Kinder in
            Kiel bereiten; er will nach Galtür kommen.” (“From Oppel (letter): he is unable to make
            the trip to Vienna on account of the difficulties his children in Kiel are making; he
            would like to come to Galtür.”). — Some paragraph-breaks are editorial, based on
            emdashes in the original text.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>seit drei Wochen bin ich hier, morgen fahre ich wieder nach <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002479">Leipzig</tei:rs>. Das <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002872"
          >Konserv</tei:rs>gebäude war während der Zeit für Messezwecke vermietet. Ursprünglich
        wollte ich solange nach Wien, aber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003957">Walter</tei:rs>
        steht sehr schwach in der Klasse, und ich möchte nicht, dass er noch ein weiteres Jahr
        verliert, nach dem er schon durch die Krankheit und den Tod s. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-006150">Mutter</tei:rs> eins eingebüsst hat. So habe ich die ganze Zeit mit
        den <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801">Jungen</tei:rs> gebüffelt und kaum musikalisch
        gearbeitet, ausser etwas <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000344">Haydn</tei:rs>, Symph. u.
          <tei:title>Theresie</tei:title>nmesse. Wenigstens eine reine Freude. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Den <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801">Jungen</tei:rs> geht es
        körperlich gut. Aber seelisch taugt meine Abwesenheit ihnen doch nichts, junge Menschen
        brauchen in der Entwicklung dauernd Aufsicht, Führung und Fürsorge. Dabei ist noch gar keine
        Aussicht auf eine Wohnung in <tei:rs key="entity-002479">L.</tei:rs> Das Ganze lastet schwer
        auf mir. Aber es muss durchgefochten werden. – An <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268"
          >Furtw.</tei:rs> hatte ich geschrieben, wann ich einmal zu ihm kommen dürfte; keine
        Antwort. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>In der „<tei:title>Deutschen Musiker-Zeitung</tei:title>“ N<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
          >o</tei:hi> 10 von <tei:date when="1928-03-10">10. III 28</tei:date> stand eine famose
        Kritik über Keussler’s Volkslied-Oratorium,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
          place="foot">“<tei:title>In jungen Tagen</tei:title>”: a “folk oratorio” by Gerhard von
          Keussler, first performed in 1928.</tei:note> das ich mir gerade ein paar Tage zuvor
        angesehen hatte. Von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000089">Wilhelm Bopp</tei:rs>, 1.
        Aufführung im Heidelberger Bachverein. Endlich hat einer den Mut, die Wahrheit zu sagen. Und
        diesem impotenten Herrn von Keussler hat man den halben Beethovenstaatpreis gegeben! – Am
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002872">Konserv</tei:rs>. selbst ist auch nicht
          <tei:pb n="3"/> alles Gold, was glänzt. Neid u. Intrigen, Himmel, wie klein sind doch die
        meisten Menschen. Hier <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000659">Pauer</tei:rs>, da
        Teichmüller, letzterer ein infamer <tei:sic>Intrig.</tei:sic> Ich habe so etwas in dieser
        künstl. Atmosphäre nicht für möglich gehalten. Im theoret. Betrieb herrscht ein furchtbarer
        Wirrwarr. Die Herren kennen dort nur eine harm. Analyse! Traurig. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Mein Urteil über <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000866">Straube</tei:rs> wird leider
        auch immer härter: neulich brachte er ein Requiem von Wetz (lebt in Erfurt u.
          Weimar),<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">The <tei:title>Requiem
            in B minor</tei:title>, Op. 50, by Richard Wetz (1875–1935), dates from the
          mid-1920s.</tei:note> so was von zähem, ledernem Brei, wie halbkalten Asphalt, – <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000695">Reger</tei:rs> ist ein Lichtgott dagegen –, nein, dann
        hört es für mich auf.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">“Dann hört
          es für mich auf”: Oppel probably means that there is little hope for him if the music of
          Richard Wetz can attract such attention.</tei:note> Und vorige Woche sah ich mir <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000373">Hindemith</tei:rs>’s op 32 an, das Streichtrio, so was
        wird gedruckt u. aufgeführt! Was hat das noch mit Musik zu tun? Da wird es mir schwer, noch
        an das deutsche Volk zu glauben. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> Die philos. Fakultät von <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501"
          >Berlin</tei:rs> liess neulich einen Warnungsballon hoch, ich glaube er nützt nicht viel.
        Dazu der Grössenwahn der heutigen Volksschule! Sie reden alle von Kunst, aber ihnen fehlt
        das erste u. letzte dazu: die Ehrfurcht davor. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wie geht es Ihnen u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000881">Ihrer lieben
          Frau</tei:rs>? Wie hatte ich mich auf Sie beide gefreut, aber ich sah ein, dass die
        Vaterpflichten allem anderen vorgehn u. eigne Wünsche schlafen gelegt werden müssen. Um so
        mehr freue ich mich auf den Sommer in Heiterwang u. die paar Tage in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtw.</tei:rs> hatte übrigens die <tei:rs
          type="composition" key="entity-001654">g-moll Symph. v. Mozart</tei:rs> angesetzt, dann
        aber wieder gestrichen; ich war schon sehr gespannt darauf nach dem Studium des <tei:rs
          type="work" key="entity-001751">Jahrbuch</tei:rs>s.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05"
          type="editorial" place="foot">The second <tei:title level="j">Meisterwerk</tei:title>
          yearbook, which appeared in 1927, contains an extensive study of Mozart’s Symphony in G
          minor, K. 550.</tei:note> – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wir hatten es die 3 Wochen bei eisigem Nord- u. Ostwind ziemlich kalt. Jedenfalls war
        an lange Spaziergänge dabei nicht zu denken. Alles Gute und die herzlichsten Grüsse von uns
        Allen! </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr treuer </tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1928-03-17">March 17,
              1928</tei:date>, Feldstraße 77/4</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">My dear Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>I have been here for three weeks; tomorrow I return to <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002479">Leipzig</tei:rs>. The <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002872"
          >Conservatory</tei:rs> building was rented out during the time for purposes of the trade
        fair. I had originally wanted to go to Vienna for such a long time, but <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-003957">Walter</tei:rs> is doing very badly in school and I do
        not wish him to lose yet another year after he had to forfeit one on account of his <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-006150">mother</tei:rs>’s illness and death. And so I spent the
        whole time cramming with the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801">boys</tei:rs> and
        hardly worked on musical matters – apart from some things by <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000344">Haydn</tei:rs> (symphonies and the “<tei:title>Maria
          Theresa</tei:title>” Mass). At least it was a pure joy.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Physically, the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801">boys</tei:rs>
        are well. But from a spiritual point of view, my absence does nothing for them; young
        people, as they develop, need constant supervision, leadership, and care. Moreover, there is
        no prospect whatever of an apartment in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002479"
          >Leipzig</tei:rs>. The entire matter weighs heavily upon me. But it must be fought
        through. – I had written to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs>,
        asking him when I might be able to come to him: no reply. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>In the <tei:title level="j">Deutsche Musiker-Zeitung</tei:title>, No. 10 (<tei:date
          when="1928-03-10">March 10, 1928</tei:date>) there appeared a terrific review of
        Keussler’s Folksong Oratorio,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> a performance
        of which I had attended just a few days before. By <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000089"
          >Wilhelm Bopp</tei:rs>: first performance at the Heidelberg Bach Society. Finally, someone
        has the courage to speak the truth. And this impotent Mr. Keussler was given half of the
        Beethoven state prize! – At the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002872"
          >Conservatory</tei:rs> itself, not all that glitters is gold. <tei:pb n="3"/> Envy and
        intrigue: my goodness, how small-minded are most people! First <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000659">Pauer</tei:rs>, then Teichmüller, the latter <tei:supplied
          reason="clarity">the perpetrator of</tei:supplied> a despicable intrigue. I thought that
        something like that would not have been possible in this artistic atmosphere. A frightful
        confusion reigns on the theoretical front: the only analysis that the gentleman understand
        is harmonic analysis! Sad. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>My judgment of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000866">Straube</tei:rs>,
        unfortunately, is becoming ever harsher. Recently he performed a Requiem by Wetz (who lives
        in Erfurt and Weimar),<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> something like a
        tough, leathery paste, like half-set asphalt – <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000695"
          >Reger</tei:rs> is a god of light by comparison – no, then things finish for me.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> And the previous week I attended a performance of
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000373">Hindemith</tei:rs>’s String Trio, Op. 32;
        something like that is published, and performed! What indeed does that have to do with
        music? In such cases it is difficult for me to maintain faith in the German people.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> The philosophical faculty in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501"
          >Berlin</tei:rs> recently sent up a warning balloon; I don’t believe it will do much good.
        In addition, the delusions of today’s elementary school! Everyone talks about art, but they
        are missing the first and last things it requires: veneration.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>How are you and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000881">your dear wife</tei:rs>? I
        was so looking forward to seeing the two of you, but I recognized that paternal duties take
        precedence and one’s own desires must be put aside. I am looking forward all the more to
        summer in Heiterwang and a few days in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292"
          >Galtür</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs>, moreover, had scheduled
          <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001654">Mozart’s G minor Symphony</tei:rs>, but
        then cancelled it again; I was already excited about it after studying the <tei:rs
          type="work" key="entity-001751">second Yearbook</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05"
          type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>These three weeks have been rather cold, with an icy wind from the north and east. In
        any event, long walks were out of the question in such conditions. All good wishes, and most
        cordial greetings from all of us!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your faithful </tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
