<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3204" sdoID="OJ-10-3_173">OJ 10/3, [173]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPoed" scope="major">Otto Erich Deutsch typist</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="OED" scope="minor">Otto Erich Deutsch's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2023</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IDB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2015-09-18" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002726">DeutschOE ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002712">DeutschOE ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002727">DeutschOE+H ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Typewritten letter from Deutsch to Schenker, dated July 12, 1932</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1932-07-12T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2023-08-06</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Deutsch portrays Hoboken’s current situation and state of mind. Hoboken has
        made an amicable settlement with his first wife and will probably move to Munich with his
        bride; his [disposable] income has been substantially reduced. He will give up the second
        floor of his villa in Vienna but keep his library, on which he works occasionally but
        without true dedication.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000164">DeutschOE</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>PROF. OTTO ERICH DEUTSCH</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">WIEN II.</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Böcklinstraße 26</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/><tei:date when="1932-07-12">12.
            Juli 32</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Verehrter</tei:rs>!<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in
            Schenker’s diary for July 14, 1932: “Von Deutsch (Br.): über v. H.<tei:hi
              rend="supralinear">s</tei:hi> Pläne u. Stimmung.” (“From Deutsch (letter): concerning
            Hoboken’s plans and mood.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ihr letzter Brief,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Schenker’s diary entry for July 8 records the dictation of a letter (not
          surviving) to Deutsch, which Jeanette wrote out in the evening; but it does not provide a
          summary of its contents.</tei:note> durch die Hand Ihrer <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000771">Frau</tei:rs> auch äusserlich so schön geraten, hat mir wieder wohl
        getan; ich danke Ihnen herzlich dafür. Leider kann ich ihn nicht gebührend beantworten,
        vorläufig wenigstens, denn es sind doch letzte Tage, mit denen ich ringe. Die nächste Woche
        verbringe ich schon in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004103">Reichenau</tei:rs> und
        Trofaiach (genügt als Adresse), dann bin ich wieder etwa eine Woche in Wien, vom 1. bis 11.
        August in Trofaiach, vom 11. bis 21. in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002578"
          >Salzburg</tei:rs> (Berichterstatten), dann wieder in Wien und fallweise in Trofaiach,
        aber nur mehr zu Besuch der Meinen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich will heute nur kurz berichten was ich von <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000380">H.</tei:rs> weiss. Es sind Fetzen von Eindrücken, die ich gesammelt
        habe, aus Volkes- und Freundesmund. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Er weiss selbst noch nicht genau, was er tut. Die Ehe ist geschieden. Wann
        wieder geheiratet wird, ist unbestimmt oder geheim. Vielleicht überlegt er es sich doch
        noch. Aber die Braut ist nicht anders zu haben. In Wien wird wohl ein Stockwerk,
        wahrscheinlich das obere, aufgegeben. Das untere ist aber nicht kom- <tei:pb n="2"/>
        fortabel genug für Beide. So dürfte also die <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002286"
          >München</tei:rs>er Villa wieder in Stand gesetzt werden. Dort wird wohl das Hauptquartier
        bleiben, wenn er heiratet. Die Bibliothek scheint vorläufig in Wien zu bleiben. Verkauf
        werden höchstens Dubletten, aber auch Bilder nach wie vor. Das Einkommen ist wirklich sehr
        verringert. Der Ausgleich mit der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002742">Frau</tei:rs>
        war aber schliesslich ein friedlicher. Ueber das <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002452">Archiv</tei:rs> verlautet nichts Bestimmtes. Jedenfalls ist es
        möglich, dass er sich ihm zu entziehen sucht, nicht gleich, aber allmählich. Die Stimmung
        ist beim Heurigen ganz heiter und bescheiden. Man fährt sogar ostentativ Trambahn und isst
        Mitgebrachtes, das nicht von Stalzer ist.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
          place="foot">The up-market delicatessen Mathias Stalzer, based at Lichtensteg 5 in the
          first district of Vienna and with two other branches in the city. Deutsch mentions it to
          show that Hoboken is not being extravagant.</tei:note> Mit Arch. und <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-005306">Dr. Schmid</tei:rs> (nicht verwandt) besteht gutes Einvernehmen. Aber
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002687">Rochlitzer</tei:rs>, der Advokatus diaboli,
        weiss wohl manchmal mehr. Keiner weiss alles, am wenigstens der Herr selber. Er ist im
        Grunde zerrissener, als er es vor dem Fund der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005826"
          >Braut</tei:rs> war. Arbeit fallweise, anfallweise, mehr tiftlerisch als hingebungsvoll. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Leben Sie wohl! Allbeide. </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">Herzlichst Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/><tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000164">O E Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>PROF. OTTO ERICH DEUTSCH</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">VIENNA II</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Böcklinstraße 26</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/><tei:date when="1932-07-12">July
            12, 1932</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">friend</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Your last letter,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> which
        turned out so beautifully in your <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">wife</tei:rs>’s
        hand, did me a great deal of good again; I thank you for it most cordially. I cannot,
        unfortunately, do it justice in my reply, at least not at present, as these are in fact the
        last days with which I am struggling. I shall spend the next week in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-004103">Reichenau</tei:rs> and Trofaiach (which is sufficient as an address),
        then I shall be back in Vienna for about a week, from the 1st to the 11th in Trofaiach, from
        the 11th to the 21st in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002578">Salzburg</tei:rs>
        (preparing reports), then again in Vienna and occasionally in Trofaiach – but only to visit
        my family.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Today I shall only report briefly what I know about <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs>. These are scraps of impressions which I have
        collected – from what I hear generally and from friends.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">He himself still does not know what he will do. The marriage has been
        dissolved. When he will remarry is either not fixed or being kept secret. Perhaps he is
        still considering it. But the bride is not to be won by other means. In Vienna, one floor –
        probably the upper one – will be given up. But the lower one is not sufficiently comfortable
        for the two of them. <tei:pb n="2"/> Thus the <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002286"
          >Munich</tei:rs> villa is likely to be made habitable again. That will probably serve as
        their principal residence, if he marries. It seems that the library will remain in Vienna
        for the time being. At most, duplicate copies will be sold, but also pictures now as before.
        His income has indeed been greatly diminished. The settlement with his <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-002742">wife</tei:rs>, however, was a peaceful one in the end. Nothing
        definite is known about the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452"
        >Archive</tei:rs>. In any event it is possible that he is seeking to cut his ties with it –
        not immediately, but gradually. The mood at the wine festival is thoroughly cheerful and
        modest. He is making a point of taking the tram there, and eating food that he has brought
        with him (and not bought at Stalzer’s).<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> He
        is on good terms with his architect Schmid and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005306">Dr.
          Schmid</tei:rs> (not related). But <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002687"
          >Rochlitzer</tei:rs>, the devil’s advocate, probably knows a bit more. No one knows
        everything, least of all the gentleman himself. He is basically more at odds with himself
        than he was before he discovered his <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005826"
          >bride</tei:rs>. He works occasionally, sporadically, more in a fiddly way than with real
        engagement.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">May you fare well! Both of you.</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">Most cordially, your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/><tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000164">O. E. Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
