<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3355" sdoID="OJ-10-13_6">OJ 10/13, [6]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="JPD" scope="major">John Petrie Dunn's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="CH">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2007</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2007</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-23" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008413">DunnJP ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Dunn to Schenker, dated November 14, 1927</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1927-11-14T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-01-30</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Dunn thanks Schenker for the copy of Meisterwerk 2 sent to him, and comments
        on the clarity with which Bach’s C minor Fugue (WTC I) is revealed; his musical instincts
        found confirmation in Schenker’s theories, and after the war he obtained all of Schenker’s
        books; he proposes that they meet some time, perhaps by making a side-trip from to Austria
        from Leipzig, where his wife grew up.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000178">DunnJP</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">
      <tei:opener>
        <tei:fw type="header" rend="inline">
          <tei:handShift new="#printed"/><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">University of
            Edinburgh crest</tei:note></tei:fw>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-30"><tei:handShift new="#JPD"/>42, Murrayfield
            Avenue,</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-40">Edinburgh, den <tei:date when="1927-11-14">14. November,
              1927</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>Hochverehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Schenker</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt
            of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for November 17, 1927: “Von Dunn (Br.):
            dankt für das Jahrbuch, hat, um mir schreiben zu können, eigens die Cm-Fuge Zeile um
            Zeile gelesen u. große Freude davon gehabt; er will uns im Spätsommer besuchen.” (“From
            Dunn (letter): he thanks me for the Yearbook; in order to be able to write to me, he has
            read the <tei:supplied>essay on the</tei:supplied> C-minor Fugue line by line and took
            great pleasure from that. He would like to visit us in late summer.”). — This letter was
            published in English in <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Heinrich Schenker: Selected
                Correspondence</tei:title>, ed. <tei:editor>Ian Bent</tei:editor>, <tei:editor>David
                Bretherton</tei:editor>, and <tei:editor>William Drabkin</tei:editor> (Woodbridge,
              UK: The Boydell Press, 2014), pp. 446–47</tei:bibl>.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Für die Zusendung des <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001751">zweiten
          Jahrbuches</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker’s
          diary for November 1, 1927 records: “An Dunn u. an Baumgarten recomm. das <tei:rs
            type="work" key="entity-001751">Jhb. II</tei:rs>.” (“To Dunn and to Baumgarten by
          registered post <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001751">Yearbook II</tei:rs>.”).
            <tei:title level="m">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:title>, vol. II (Munich: Drei
          Masken Verlag, 1926) was released in August/September 1927. Dunn is not on the list of
          review copies to be sent (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-54-193">OC
            54/193</tei:ref>, undated), and it is evident that Schenker sent out the volume
          personally by registered mail to Dunn and Baumgarten. — A letter from Hoboken to Schenker,
            <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-11-54_15">OJ 11/54, [15]</tei:ref>, dated August
          28, 1927, remarked “There <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">Edinburgh</tei:note> I
          will be in touch with Prof. Dunn. I would very much have liked to take him the new
          Yearbook. Is there a chance that Drei Masken (one mask would really be enough for this
          publisher) could have the book ready by then?”</tei:note> kann ich Ihnen nicht genug
        danken; Sie haben mir damit eine grosse Ehre erwiesen. Erst heute komme ich dazu, Ihnen
        darüber zu schreiben, denn ich hatte mir vorgenommen, mich nicht eher für Ihr unschätzbares
        Geschenk zu bedanken, als bis ich wenigstens <tei:hi rend="underline">ein</tei:hi>
        abgeschlossenes Kapitel des Jahrbuches sorgfältig durchgearbeitet hätte. Das ist denn auch
        heute (Sonntag) Vormittag geschehen; ich habe Ihre Analyse der C-moll Fuge von Bach<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:title level="a">Das
              Organische der Fuge</tei:title> (<tei:title level="a">The Organic Nature of
              Fugue</tei:title>), <tei:title level="m">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:title>,
            vol. II (Munich: Drei Masken Verlag, 1926), pp. 55–95 (Eng. transl. Hedi Siegel, pp.
            31–54)</tei:bibl>. </tei:note> Wort für Wort, Zeile für Zeile durchgelesen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Der Eindruck, den ich dabei empfangen habe, war eben der, dass <tei:del
          rend="overstrike">ich</tei:del> mir das “Organische” an einer <tei:pb n="2"/> Bach’schen
        Fuge noch nie so überzeugend, so einleuchtend klar vor die Augen trat. Nicht minder wertvoll
        war die Erkenntnis, dass eine jede Fuge von Bach ihre eigenen Gesetze hat, denen der
        Komponist – im Sinne Ihres <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000294">Goethe</tei:rs>’schen
          Zitats<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Dunn is referring to the
          distinction Goethe makes, in an aphorism in <tei:title level="m">Über Kunst und
            Altertum</tei:title>, between treating the specific case on the one hand merely as an
          instance of a general principle and, on the other, seeking to understand the general
          principle by “vividly grasp<tei:supplied>ing</tei:supplied> the specific,” which he takes
          to be the essence of poetry. Schenker quotes this toward the end of his essay, where he
          ponders the question of whether Bach himself was aware of the things that Schenker has
          been discussing (<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001751"><tei:title level="m"
              >Meisterwerk</tei:title> 2</tei:rs>, p. 92; Eng. transl., p. 52).</tei:note> – zu
        gehorchen hat, ungeachtet dessen, was er in einer anderen Fuge und bei anderer Gestaltung
        der <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>, der <tei:term>Stufe</tei:term>n, u.s.w. zu tun sich
        veranlasst sehen mag. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Meine Schreibfaulheit mögen Sie mir aus besonderen Gründen zugute halten.
        Ich habe hier in meiner Heimatstadt eine ganz enorme Praxis, denn alle möglichen Menschen
        aus Nah und Fern’, die mit verkrüppelten Fingern oder sonstigen körperlichen oder geistigen
        Fehlern behaftet sind, betrachten mich gewissermassen als ihren Hart. So kommt es denn, dass
        ich heute das “Jahrbuch” lese, morgen über “<tei:term>Tonicalization</tei:term>” (das
          <tei:hi rend="underline">ganz</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">neue</tei:hi> englische Wort) rede und übermorgen eine
        Clementi-Sonatine einpauke! Meine <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000177">Frau</tei:rs>
        klagt fortwährend darüber, dass ich so unaufhörlich unterrichten muss und meinen eigenen
        Studien <tei:pb n="3"/> so wenig Zeit widmen kann, allein es liegt nun einmal in den
        schwierigen heutigen Verhältnissen begründet, dass man das Eisen schmieden muss, dieweil es
        warm ist. Nun, wir hoffen alle beide auf bessere Zeiten; ausserdem gelingt es mir ja, in
        grossen ganzen auf den Laufenden zu bleiben. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Was mir an Ihren Schriften <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >persönlich</tei:add> so ausserordentlich wohltuend berührt, ist dass <tei:del
          rend="overstrike">ich</tei:del> sie mit meinem instinktiven Gefühl so vollständig
        übereinstimmen. Ich hatte ja immer gefühlt: <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000712"
          >Riemann</tei:rs> ist nicht überzeugend, Debussy und Ravel sind Geklimper, <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000695">Reger</tei:rs> ist teils gut, teils schlecht, u.s.w.
        u.s.w. Nun kommen <tei:hi rend="underline">Sie</tei:hi> und <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >beweisen</tei:hi> das alles. Aus diesen Gefühl heraus liess ich mir gleich nach
        Kriegsschluss Ihre Bücher kommen. Da fand ich gerade das, was ich erwartet hatte und ich bin
        auf meine <tei:pb n="4"/> gute Witterung nicht wenig stolz. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Nun aber Schluss. Mir steht morgen ein sehr anstrengender Tag bevor. Ich
        möchte nur noch sagen, dass ich und meine <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000177"
          >Frau</tei:rs> so nach und nach auf dem Standpunkt angelangt sind, dass das viele
        Geschreibe nichts nützt und man sich persönlich kennen lernen muss. Da meine <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000177">Frau</tei:rs> in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002479">Leipzig</tei:rs> zu Hause ist, so würde ein noch viel geringerer
        Anlass ausreichen, um sie (und mich) zu einem kleinen Abstecher nach <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002506">Oesterreich</tei:rs> zu bewegen! (Im Spätsommer natürlich.) </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Mit herzlichsten Grüssen, auch an Ihre <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000771">Frau Gemahlin</tei:rs>, und mit innigsten Dank, </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Ihr ganz ergebener,</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000178">John Petrie
            Dunn</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:fw type="header" rend="inline">
          <tei:handShift new="#printed"/><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">University of
            Edinburgh crest</tei:note></tei:fw>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-30"><tei:handShift new="#JPD"/>42, Murrayfield
            Avenue</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-40">Edinburgh, <tei:date when="1927-11-14">November 14,
              1927</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>Highly esteemed Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">I cannot thank you enough for sending me the <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001751">second Yearbook</tei:rs>;<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> you have thereby conferred a great honor upon me. I have only just got
        round to writing to you today, as I had not wanted to thank you for your priceless gift
        until I had carefully gone through at least <tei:hi rend="underline">one</tei:hi> complete
        chapter of the yearbook. This I have done this morning (Sunday); I have read through, word
        for word, line for line, your analysis of the C minor fugue by Bach.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>The impression that I gathered from it was precisely this: that never has the “organic”
        quality of a <tei:pb n="2"/> Bach fugue appeared before my eyes so convincingly, and with
        such clarity. No less valuable was the recognition that each fugue by Bach has its own laws
        which the composer must obey – along the lines of the <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000294">Goethe</tei:rs> quotation<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
          type="footnote"/> – not withstanding that which he is required to do in another fugue and
        in a different construction of the <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>, the <tei:term>harmonic
          degree</tei:term>s, etc.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I hope you will make allowances for my laziness as a correspondent on
        particular grounds: here in my home town I have an enormous practice, for all sorts of
        people, from near and far, who are afflicted with crippled fingers or some other bodily or
        intellectual shortcomings, and regard me to a certain extent as their rock. As things turn
        out, I am reading the Yearbook today, tomorrow I shall speak about
          “<tei:term>tonicalization</tei:term>” (an <tei:hi rend="underline">entirely new</tei:hi>
        English word), and the day after tomorrow I shall be drumming a Clementi sonatina
          <tei:supplied reason="clarity">into someone’s head</tei:supplied>! My <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000177">wife</tei:rs> constantly complains that I must teach
        unceasingly and can devote so little time to my own studies <tei:pb n="3"/> but this can be
        attributed simply to the difficult circumstances of today: one must forge the iron while it
        is hot. Well, the two of us are hoping for better times; moreover, I do actually succeed, by
        and large, in making ends meet.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">What it is about your writings that touches me <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">personally</tei:add>, to such beneficial effect, is that they
        agree so completely with my instinctive feeling. I had always felt that <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000712">Riemann</tei:rs> was not convincing, that Debussy and
        Ravel are shallow, that <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000695">Reger</tei:rs> is partly
        good, partly bad, etc. etc. Now <tei:hi rend="underline">you</tei:hi> come along and <tei:hi
          rend="underline">prove</tei:hi> all this. Having received this impression, I got hold of
        your books as soon as the war ended. There I found precisely that which I had expected, and
        I am not a little proud of my <tei:pb n="4"/> good instinct.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">It is time to close. I have a very strenuous day ahead of me tomorrow. I
        would only like to say further that my <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000177"
          >wife</tei:rs> and I have gradually arrived at the point at which we believe that all this
        writing is of no use, and that one should get to know each other personally. As my <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000177">wife</tei:rs> comes from <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002479">Leipzig</tei:rs>, then a much less significant occasion would suffice
        for her (and me) to make a slight detour to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002506"
          >Austria</tei:rs>! (In the late summer, of course.)</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">With most cordial greetings, also to your <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000771">wife</tei:rs>, and with my deepest thanks,</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Your entirely devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000178">John Petrie
            Dunn</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
