<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2161" sdoID="OJ-15-16_96">OJ 15/16, [96]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HeW" scope="sole">Hertha Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2008</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-10-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-003069">WeisseHe ~
        JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Hertha Weisse to Jeanette Schenker, dated February 21,
        1935</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1935-02-21T11:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-01-04</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>In this letter of condolence, sent together with one by Hans, Hertha Weisse
        explains that the obituary of Schenker in the New York Times by Olin Downes, though based
        partly on information supplied by Hans, was hastily written and contains many errors. A
        pupil of Hans [Adele Katz] has prepared an article on Schenker's theory, which will soon be
        published in an American music journal. </dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Tod; death; Einsamkeit; loneliness; schöpferisch; creative; Hineingehen;
        penetration; Artikel; article; Journalist; Druckfehler; printing error; Probedruck; proof;
        Information; Musikerhandbuch; music handbook; Musikzeitschrift; music journal; Herz; heart;
        Einheit; unity; Unterbewußtsein; subconscious mind</dc:subject>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000952">Hertha Weisse</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">Jeanette Schenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute>Liebe, verehrte <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Frau
          Lie-Lie</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich fragte mich seit dem Tode Ihres teueren <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000632">Mann</tei:rs>es<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Schenker died on January 14, 1935.</tei:note> schon oft, wie Sie wohl Ihre
        Einsamkeit ertragen können? Als heute früh Ihr ergreifender Brief kam, habe ich mich in
        Gedanken zu Ihnen gesellt u. mit Ihnen gelitten. Was könnten wir nur für Sie tun, um Ihnen
        Ihr Leben tragen zu helfen? <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Hans</tei:rs> weiß,
        was für ein gottvoller Mensch Ihr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Mann</tei:rs>
        war u. daß dieses schöpferische Hineingehen in die Werke der großen Meister einzig allein
        nur ihm gegeben war. Seine Saat wird aufgehen, wenn es auch länger brauchen wird. Es gibt
        jetzt schon eine Menge junger u. älterer Leute, die fühlen oder ahnen, welche Grösse in
        seinem Werk verborgen liegt.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Am <tei:date when="1935-02-03">3. Februar</tei:date> erschien in der
          <tei:title>New-York-Times</tei:title> durch <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006968">Olin
          Downes</tei:rs> ein Artikel, den ich bei- <tei:pb n="2"/> -lege.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:title level="a">The Late Heinrich
            Schenker</tei:title>; this was pasted into the Schenker Scrapbook at OC 2/p.
          89.</tei:note>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Hans</tei:rs> hatte schon mehrere Mal Gelegenheit
        über das große Werk Ihres teueren <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Mann</tei:rs>es
        mit ihm zu sprechen u <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006968">Olin Downes</tei:rs> wüßte
        es vielleicht ganz zu würdigen, wenn er nicht ein gehetzter Journalist wäre u daher keine
        Zeit zur Vertiefung hat. Die Druckfehler in diesem Artikel sind leider darin geblieben, da
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Hans</tei:rs> nicht Gelegenheit hatte, den
        Probedruck zu sehen. Der Artikel wurde von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006968">Olin
          Downes</tei:rs> auf grund einer langen Information seitens <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000951">Hans</tei:rs>
        <tei:del rend="overstrike">selbst</tei:del> geschrieben u. manches ist nicht ganz im Sinne
        dieser Information, ausserdem hat sich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006968">Olin
          Downes</tei:rs> des Musikerhandbuches<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Possibly the 1929 edition of Riemann's <tei:title level="m"
            >Musiklexikon</tei:title>, which contained a <tei:ref type="other" cRef="OC-2-79_4"
            >short entry on Schenker</tei:ref>.</tei:note> bedient u wie anders sieht dieser Artikel
        aus, als ihn <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Hans</tei:rs> gewünscht u. gedacht
        hat. Es wird übrigens im ersten Halbjahr zu einer Musikzeitschrift ein Artikel über <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000632">Dr. Schenker</tei:rs> erscheinen, dass eine <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-006967">Schülerin</tei:rs> von <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000951">Hans</tei:rs> seit längerer Zeit vorbereitet hat.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Adele T.
              Katz</tei:author>, <tei:title level="a">Heinrich Schenker's Method of
              Analysis,</tei:title>
            <tei:title level="j">Musical Quarterly</tei:title> 21 (1935), pp. 311–29</tei:bibl>.
          Katz was later to write a book, <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Challenge to Musical
              Tradition: A New Concept of Tonality</tei:title> (New York: Alfred Knopf,
            1945)</tei:bibl>, the first in which Schenkerian theory was applied positively to
          20th-century music, including works by Debussy, Stravinsky and
        Schoenberg.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wie bitter ist der Tod! Geliebe Frau Lie-Lie schütten Sie uns Ihr Herz aus, so oft
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">Sie Be</tei:del>
        <tei:pb n="3"/> es <tei:choice>
          <tei:sic>sie</tei:sic>
          <tei:corr>Sie</tei:corr>
        </tei:choice> zu erleichtern scheint, zu jemand zu sprechen, der Sie beide als eine Einheit
        gesehen u. verstanden hat. Wir wünschen uns beide, wir könnten dort in der Keilgasse die
        Gegenwart Ihres teueren <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Mann</tei:rs>es noch
        fühlen, aber dann würden wir an der Tatsache, daß er wirklich nicht mehr da ist, noch mehr
        leiden als jetzt, wo wir wahrscheinlich im Unterbewußtsein nicht daran glauben
        wollen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In tiefer Verehrung für Sie Frau Lie-Lie u in aufrichtiger Freundschaft bin ich</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihre</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000952">Hertha
          W.</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1935-02-21">21. Februar <tei:choice>
              <tei:sic>1934</tei:sic>
              <tei:corr>1935</tei:corr>
            </tei:choice></tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine>New-York</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute>Dear, revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Mrs.
          Lie-Lie</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">I have been asking myself, ever since I heard that your dear <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000632">husband</tei:rs> had died:<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
          type="footnote"/> How are you able to bear your loneliness? When your moving letter
        arrived this morning, my thoughts turned to you, and I grieved with you. Is there anything
        we could possibly do for you, in order to help make your life more bearable? <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000951">Hans</tei:rs> knows what a divine person your <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000632">husband</tei:rs> was, and that this creative penetration
        of the works of the great masters was given to him and him alone. His seeds will germinate,
        even if it takes a while longer. There is already a large group of people, young and old,
        who feel or sense the greatness that lies hidden within his work.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">On <tei:date when="1935-02-03">February 3</tei:date>, an article by
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006968">Olin Downes</tei:rs> appeared in the <tei:title
          level="j">New York Times</tei:title>, which I am enclosing.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/>
        <tei:pb n="2"/>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Hans</tei:rs> had already had several occasions on
        which to speak to him about the great work of your dear <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000632">husband</tei:rs>, and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006968">Olin
          Downes</tei:rs> would have probably been able to appreciate fully were he not such a busy
        journalist, with no time to study it more deeply. The printing mistakes have, unfortunately,
        remained in this article, as <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Hans</tei:rs> was not
        given the occasion to look at a proof copy. The article was written by <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-006968">Olin Downes</tei:rs> on the basis of some lengthy information provided
        by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Hans</tei:rs>
        <tei:del rend="overstrike">himself</tei:del>, and much of it does not accurately reflect
        that information; in addition, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006968">Olin
          Downes</tei:rs> made use of the handbook on music,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
          type="footnote"/> and this article says rather different things from that which <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000951">Hans</tei:rs> would have wished, or said himself.
        Moreover, in the first semestral issue of a journal of music, there will appear an article
        about <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Dr. Schenker</tei:rs> that a <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-006967">female pupil</tei:rs> of <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000951">Hans</tei:rs>'s has been working on for a long time.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>How bitter death is! Dear Mrs. Lie-Lie, open your heart to us, whenever <tei:pb n="3"/>
        it would seem to make things easier if you could talk to someone who saw and understood the
        two of you as a unity. We both wish that we could still feel the presence of your dear
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">husband</tei:rs> there, at your Keilgasse home;
        but then we would suffer even more than we do now from the fact that he is really no longer
        with us, though in our subconscious minds we probably do not want to believe it.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In deep reverence for you, Mrs. Lie-Lie, and in true friendship, I am</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000952">Hertha
          W.</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1935-02-21">February 21, <tei:choice>
              <tei:sic>1934</tei:sic>
              <tei:corr>1935</tei:corr>
            </tei:choice></tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine>New York</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
