<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3467" sdoID="OJ-14-9_3">OJ 14/9, [3]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="vS" scope="sole">Victor Schiff's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008454">SchiffV ~
        JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Victor Schiff to Jeanette Schenker, dated March 21,
        1926</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1926-03-21T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Victor Schiff thanks Jeanette for the invitation to stay with her and
        Heinrich; he uses nautical imagery to liken this contact to two ships on different courses,
        whose courses happen to cross in mid-ocean. — Victor encloses a photograph of himself. — He
        is touched that Jeanette has kept all the letters from him; he himself kept all of hers but
        lost them while travelling,</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>
      
      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000783">Victor Schiff</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-0000771">Jeanette Schenker</marcrel:recipient>
      
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:note type="editorial" place="pre-text">This is the only surviving letter in Victor’s
        hand, unlike OJ 14/9, [1] and [2], which were copies in Anna’s hand.</tei:note>
      <tei:lb/>


      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003627"><tei:hi
              rend="lateinschr">Valparaiso</tei:hi></tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1926-03-21">21 de
            Marzo de 1926</tei:date>.</tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>Meine liebe unvergessliche <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
            >Schwester</tei:rs>:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt
            of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for April 23, 1926: “Von Victor (Br. aus
            Valparaiso): noch immer sehr schwelgerisch in Freiheit u. Abenteuer, die Urlinie geht
            also fort. Sonst etwas befangen.” (“From Victor (letter from Valparaiso): he is still,
            as always, very indulgent in freedom and adventure, the Urlinie thus continues.
            Otherwise, somewhat self-conscious.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Vor allem danke ich Dir viele tausend male für Deinen Brief,<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Presumably the letter recorded in
          Schenker’s diary for February 7, 1926: “An Victor (längerer Br. v. Lie-Liechen): voll
          schwesterlicher Liebe; dieser Brief dürfte, wenn er ihn erreicht, besten Eindruck machen,
          Trost u. Labsal werden für trübe Stunden des Bruders.” (“To Victor (longish letter from
          Lie-Liechen): full of sisterly love, this letter ought, if it reaches him, to make the
          best impression, [offering] consolation and refreshment for her brother's gloomy hours.”).
          — From the fifth paragraph of the current letter, we know that this letter reached Victor
          on March 8, thus taking a month to reach its destination.</tei:note> welcher mir so grosse
        Überraschungen und so aufrichtige Freude bereitet hat. Wusste ich doch gar nicht einmal ob
        Du noch am Leben warst, denn auf meine Anfragen bei <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003244">Klara</tei:rs> erhielt ich nur eine ausweichende Antwort. Ich danke
        Dir von ganzem Herzen für Deine so gütige und liebevolle Einladung mit Dir eine Weile zu
        verleben, an <tei:choice>
          <tei:sic>Deinen</tei:sic>
          <tei:corr>Deinem</tei:corr>
        </tei:choice> Herzen auszuruhen, sei es nur für Augenblicke und danke Dir für das Interesse
        mit <tei:choice>
          <tei:sic>welches</tei:sic>
          <tei:corr>welchem</tei:corr>
        </tei:choice> Du für mich an den Tag legst. Liebe <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
          >Schwester</tei:rs>, mir fällt es sehr schwer deutsch zu schreiben, nie weiss ich recht
        ob’s richtig ist oder nicht u. diese Tatsache allein schon legt einen Menschen gewisse
        Zurückhaltung auf. Ich hoffe, dass Du mir das alles entschuldigen wirst. Wie zwei Schiffe,
        auf einer Werft erbaut, begegnen wir uns auf der hohen See des Lebens. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Nach so vielen Jahren der Entfremdung, nach all den Stürmen durchlebt in
        den sieben Seen des Lebens, nach so langer und gefährlicher Fahrt durch Riffe und Klippen,
        kreuzen sich wieder einmal unsere Pfade. Wir trugen nicht dieselbe Ladung, wir sind nicht
        bestimmt für den selben Port und die Wimpel die von unseren Masten weh’n sind nicht von
        gleicher Farbe. Alles dies sind Kleinigkeiten. Ein alter, zeitgeheiligter Brauch derer die
        auf lange Fahrten gehen schreibt es vor, und sie sehnen sich danach, nach Wochen, Monaten,
        Jahren des sich-nicht-gesehen-habens, die Ceremonie des Grusses ganz auszukosten. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wer ihn kennt, den Abschied, seine letzte schmerzvolle Stunde, der, nur der wird das
        Wiedersehen zu schätzen wissen. Durch Gefahren zehntausend, den sicheren Tode wohl hundert
        mal zieht der Kiel meines Schiffes wieder einmal durch altbekannte Gewässer und unsere
        Course kreuzen sich. Mit allen Segeln, unter günstigen Winde, mit wehenden Wimpeln, vom Bug
        bis zum Heck noch „ganz“ <tei:pb n="2"/> sei Dir mein Flaggengruss und über die Wellen, den
        Schaum gekrönten Wellen der salzigen Tiefe tönt mein “homeward-bound, all is
          well.<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">"</tei:supplied></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Entschuldige<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> liebe
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Schwester</tei:rs>, dass ich Dir erst heute
        antworte. Dein Brief kam am <tei:date when="1926-03-08">8. ds. Ms.</tei:date> hier an, aber
        ich wollte Dir eine kleine Überraschung bereiten und habe ein Bild anfertigen
          lassen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">This postcard-size,
          head-and-shoulders photographic portrait of Victor was found with the current letter, and
          is now preserved as OJ 72/21. (At the time of writing, the folder was mislaid.) The
          photographer was Navarro-Martinez, and the inscription: “Frühling 1926 (hier Herbst) in
          Liebe gewidmet” (“Spring (here Fall) 1926, with devoted love”).</tei:note> Es ist nicht
        gut ausgefallen, Du wirst die hiesigen Verhältnisse entschuldigen müssen, da es jedoch das
        Bild eines Mensch<tei:supplied reason="syntax">en</tei:supplied> ist<tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> der keine Eitelkeit besitzt<tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> so ist es am Ende ohne Bedeutung ob Flecke drauf
        sind oder nicht. Jedenfalls hat’s nicht gefehlt am guten Willen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Du hast Briefe von mir die ich vor zwanzig Jahren schrieb, das hat mich
        sehr interessiert und es ist sehr lieb von Dir, dass Du sie aufbewahrt hast. Auch ich hatte
        die Deinen lange aufbewahrt mit einem Bilde welches Dich mit aufgespannten Sonnenschirm
        zeigt, es war aus den Jahre 1903.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >No letters between Victor and Jeanette are recorded in Heinrich’s diary before the
          current letter, there being no reference to Victor in the diary before 1920. Nine letters
          to and from Victor are recorded and briefly summarized in Heinrich’s diary (see profile
          for <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000783">Victor</tei:rs> for list.</tei:note> Alle
        diese Dinge und viele andere mehr, die mir lieb und teuer waren, sind mir auf einer Reise
        abhanden gekommen. Ich hab‘ sie lang betrauert, denn es waren Briefe dabei welche mir,
        unsere gute <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008432">Mutter</tei:rs> nach <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-008430">Chemnitz</tei:rs> geschrieben hatte. Aber ich hab‘ mich
        getröstet, denn unsere wahre Werte, die tragen wir in uns, die werden uns nicht verloren
        gehen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich hoffe meine liebe <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
          >Schwester</tei:rs>, das Du bei bester Gesundheit bist <tei:del rend="overstrike"
          >,so</tei:del> und es Dir in Wien recht gut gefällt. Es ist eine grosse Stadt und dort
        wird es wohl alles geben um jeden Geschmack zufrieden zu stellen. Ich schreibe Dir wenig,
        denn ich glaube, dass „dicke“ Briefe hier Aufsehen erregen und unterschlagen werden. Ich
        schrieb am <tei:date when="1925-12-20">20. XII. 25.</tei:date> einen solchen Brief an unser
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000782">Paulchen</tei:rs>, bis heute habe ich keine
        Antwort bekommen, vielleicht bist Du so gütig und frägst bei ihm an<tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> ob er diesen Brief empfangen hat?<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">There is no record of Jeanette writing
          to Paul in April or May 1926 with such an inquiry. — Schenker’s diary for July 8, 1926
          records: “An Victor (Br.): Lie-Liechen entwirft eine breite Darstellung unseres Lebens,
          ich füge einige Zeilen bei. — An Paul (Br.): Lie-Liechen über den Inhalt des Briefes an
          Victor.” (“To Victor (letter): Lie-Liechen sketches a broad-ranging picture of our life; I
          add a few lines to it. — To Paul (letter): Lie-Liechen on the content of her letter to
          Victor.”).</tei:note> Schreibt bitte keine recom<tei:supplied reason="omission"
          >m</tei:supplied>andierten (eingeschriebenen) Briefe diese werden alle geöffnet. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000782">Paul</tei:rs> schrieb mir er hätte ein Büchlein seinen
        Brief begelegt, aber ich hab‘ keines drin gefunden. Die Beamten in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-005845">Chile</tei:rs> sind sehr unehrlich, und in <tei:choice>
          <tei:sic>ganzen</tei:sic>
          <tei:corr>ganzem</tei:corr>
        </tei:choice> Lande herrschen keine guten <tei:hi rend="underline">Sitten</tei:hi> und
        Gebräuche. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ich umarme und küsse Dich mit Liebe</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-90">Dein alter treuer Bruder</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000783">Victor
          Schiff</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in left margin of p. 1,
            sideways:</tei:note>
          <tei:handShift new="#VS"/>Herzliche Grüße an Herrn <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000632">Dr. Schenker</tei:rs>!</tei:p>

        <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in left margin of p. 2,
            sideways:</tei:note> Heute zieht der Lenz bei euch ein und ich hoffe, dass eure Herzen
          ihm offen stehen und ihr ein <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">bottom margin, p.
            2:</tei:note> fröhliches und angenehmes <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">Hebrew
            script:</tei:note>
          <tei:hi rend="italic">Pesach</tei:hi>
          <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">Latin script:</tei:note> fest verlebt, und
            <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">Hebrew script:</tei:note>
          <tei:hi rend="italic">matzos</tei:hi>
          <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">Latin script:</tei:note> essen wird.<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">In 1926, the eight days of Passover
            ran from March 30 to April 6, Lent ran from February 17 to April 3, and Easter Sunday
            fell on April 4.</tei:note></tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003627">Valparaiso</tei:rs>,
            <tei:date when="1926-03-21">March 21, 1926</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>My dear, unforgettable <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
            >Sister</tei:rs>:<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Above all, I thank you many thousand times over for your letter,<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> which has afforded me such big surprises and such
        unalloyed joy. I did not for a moment know whether you were even still in the land of the
        living, for in response to my inquiries <tei:supplied reason="clarity">about
          you</tei:supplied> to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003244">Klara</tei:rs> I received
        only an evasive answer. From the bottom of my heart, I thank you for your so kind and
        affectionate invitation to spend a while with you, and to relax in your company, be it only
        for a little while; and I thank you for the interest that you show in me. Dear <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000771">sister</tei:rs>, it is very hard for me to write in
        German. I never know whether I have got it right or not, and this fact alone gives a person
        a cause for a certain reticence. I hope that you will forgive me everything. Like two ships
        built in the same shipyard, we meet on the high seas of life.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">After so many years of estrangement, after all the storms outlived in the
        seven seas of life, after so long and perilous a journey past reefs and cliffs, our paths
        cross once again. We did not carry the same cargo, we are not bound for the same port, and
        the pennants that billow from our masts are not of the same hue. All these matters are
        trivia. An old, time-hallowed custom of those who make long journeys dictates it – and they
        yearn after it – that after weeks, months, or years of not seeing one another, they savor
        fully the ceremony of greeting.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Only anyone familiar with the last painful moments of parting will know how to treasure
        the reunion. Through ten thousand dangers, through certain death a hundred times over, the
        keel of my ship guides me once again into well-known waters, and our courses cross one
        another. With sails all hoist, <tei:supplied reason="clarity">running</tei:supplied> before
        a favorable wind with flags a-waving, from prow to stern still “in one piece,” <tei:pb n="2"
        /> may my flag-greeting <tei:supplied reason="clarity">reach you</tei:supplied>, and over
        the waves and whitecaps of the salty depths my <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in
          English:</tei:note> “homeward-bound, all is well” <tei:note type="editorial"
          place="inline">in German:</tei:note> ring out.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Please forgive me, dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
          >sister</tei:rs>, for not replying to you until today. Your letter arrived here on the
          <tei:date when="1926-03-08">8th of the month</tei:date>, but I wanted to prepare a little
        surprise for you, so have had a portrait made.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"
        /> It has not worked out too well. You will have to excuse the local conditions, for it is
        the picture of a person who possesses no vanity, so it is in the end without significance
        whether or not it has stains on it. In any case, it is not short of good intentions.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">You have letters from me that I wrote twenty years ago. This caught my
        interest keenly, and it is very sweet of you to have kept them. I, too, had long kept yours,
        together with a photograph that shows you with an open parasol – that was from 1903.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> All of these things, and many others besides,
        which were precious to me, went missing on a journey. I have long mourned them, for there
        were letters with them that our good <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008432"
          >Mother</tei:rs> had written to me in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-008430"
          >Chemnitz</tei:rs>. However, I have comforted myself with the thought that our true
        values, which we carry within ourselves – <tei:hi rend="italic">they</tei:hi> will not be
        lost to us.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I hope, my dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">sister</tei:rs>,
        that you are in the best of health, and that you are truly happy in Vienna. It is a big
        city, and there will no doubt be everything to satisfy every taste. I am keeping this letter
        brief because I believe that “thick” letters attract attention and get misappropriated. I
        wrote such a letter on <tei:date when="1925-12-20">December 20, 1925</tei:date> to our dear
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000782">little Paul</tei:rs>, to which I have so far had
        no reply. Perhaps you would be so kind as to ask him whether he received that
          letter?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> Please do not write registered
        letters as these all get opened. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000782">Paul</tei:rs>
        wrote to me that he had enclosed a little book with his letter, but I did not find one
        included. The officials in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-005845">Chile</tei:rs> are very
        dishonest, and throughout the country no good <tei:hi rend="underline">customs</tei:hi> and
        practices prevail</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">I embrace and kiss you with love,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-90">Your faithful brother</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000783">Victor
          Schiff</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in left margin of p. 1,
            sideways:</tei:note>
          <tei:handShift new="#VS"/>Cordial greetings to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Dr. Schenker</tei:rs>!</tei:p>

        <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in left margin of p. 2,
            sideways:</tei:note> Today spring is setting in where you live, and I hope that your
          hearts will be open to it, and that you all <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"
            >bottom margin, p. 2:</tei:note> will have a happy and pleasant <tei:note
            type="editorial" place="inline">Hebrew script:</tei:note>
          <tei:hi rend="italic">Passover</tei:hi>
          <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">Latin script:</tei:note> and will be eating
            <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">Hebrew script:</tei:note>
          <tei:hi rend="italic">matzos</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"
          /></tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
