<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2746" sdoID="OJ-12-59_2">OJ 12/59, [2]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="SFM" scope="sole">Siegfried Fritz Müller's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2022</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2022</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>


    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2011-06-09" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008182">MüllerSF ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Siegfried Fritz Müller to Schenker, dated July 12,
        1923</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1923-07-12T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2022-05-08</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Siegfried Fritz Müller asks for a testimonial for a piano teaching
        position.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000618">SFMüller</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:handShift new="#SFM"/><tei:rs type="place"
            key="entity-004164">St. Gallen</tei:rs>, d. <tei:date when="1923-07-12">12. Juli
            23</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Sehr verehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Professor</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt
            of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary at July 17, 1923: “Von Müller (Br.):
            erbittet ein Zeugnis, da er sich um eine Anstellung bewirbt; hofft hierher kommen zu
            können.” (“From Müller (letter): asks for a letter of recommendation, since he is
            applying for a position; hopes to be able to come here.”). Schenker’s response is
            recorded the next day: “An Müller (Br. eingeschr.): Zeugnis u. Grüße.” (“To Müller
            (letter registered): letter of recommendation and greetings.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="indent-20">Sie werden sich gewiß wundern, so bald schon von mir zu
          hören.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">No communication from
          Müller to Schenker is known to survive from the previous ten months.</tei:note> Ein ganz
        besonderer Anlaß nötigt mich aber, Ihre Ferienruhe zu stören.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot">The Schenkers were on vacation in <tei:rs type="place"
            key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs> in the <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004160"
            >South Tyrol</tei:rs> at this time.</tei:note> Es ist hier nämlich in einer kantonalen
        Anstalt eine Klavierlehrerstelle frei geworden, welche so große Vorteile bringt, daß ich
        nicht um sie kann, mich um sie zu bewerben. Als Schweizer habe ich ja wohl auch innige
        Aussichten, sie zu bekommen. Die Stelle wird jetzt schon ausgeschrieben und ich brauche zur
        Bewerbung nur noch ein Zeugnis, um welches ich Sie, sehr verehrter Herr Professor, höflichst
        bitten möchte. Der Inhalt sollte ungefähr sein, <tei:pb n="2"/> daß ich zur Vervollkommnung
        meines Könnens die allgemeinen Fächer der Musik, im speziellen und besonders aber Klavier
        bei Ihnen studiert habe. Wenn Sie die Güte hätten, mir darin zu bestätigen, daß Sie mich für
        einen guten Musiker und begabten Pianisten halten, so würde das meine Aussichten wohl
        bedeutend vermehren. Ich bitte Sie sehr, mir nicht böse zu sein, daß ich Sie belästige. Was
        mich besonders an dieser Stelle reizt, ist, daß ich neben guter Bezahlung und
        Pensionsberechtigung, die Möglichkeit hätte, mehrmals im Jahr zu Ihnen zu reisen, um Ihnen
        vorzuspielen, da mir genügend Zeit bliebe, für mich weiterzustudieren und zu arbeiten, was
        an einer Theaterstelle neben der schlechten Bezahlung wohl fast ausgeschlossen ist. Dürfte
        ich Sie vielleicht noch bitten, die Sache so bald als möglich zu erledigen, da das Termin
        für die Einreichung des Gesuches nur etwa vierzehn Tage läuft. Als Ausstellungsort bitte ich
          <tei:pb n="3"/> Sie, nicht <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>
        sondern Wien angeben zu wollen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="indent-20">Ich hoffe, daß es Ihnen und Ihrer verehrten <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000771">Frau Gemahlin</tei:rs> gut geht. Es ist sehr leicht möglich, daß ich
        Sie einmal besuchen komme, da ich die Absicht habe, eine Tour ins Silvrettagebiet zu
        machen.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Bis dahin grüßt Sie mit dem</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">besten Danke zum Voraus</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">Ihr sehr ergebener</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000618">Siegfried
            Müller</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004164">St. Gallen</tei:rs>, Notkerstrß.
              73<tei:hi rend="supralinear">II</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:p rend="first">Nb. Ihre Unkosten werde ich natürlich umgehendst begleichen.</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">Beste Empfehlungen von meinen Eltern, die finden, daß ich bei Ihnen
          riesig gelernt habe. </tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:handShift new="#SFM"/><tei:rs type="place"
            key="entity-004164">St. Gallen</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1923-07-12">July 12,
            1923</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Greatly revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Professor</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="indent-20">You will surely be wondering why you are hearing <tei:supplied
          reason="clarity">again</tei:supplied> from me so soon.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> A quite exceptional circumstance necessitates my disturbing the peace of
        your vacation.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> A position for a piano
        teacher has become vacant in a cantonal institute here – one that would afford me such great
        advantages that I cannot do other than apply for it. As a Swiss citizen I have really
        favorable prospects of getting it. The position will by now have been advertized, and all
        that I need to complete the application is a testimonial, for which I should respectfully
        like to ask you, most revered Professor. The content should roughly be <tei:pb n="2"/> that
        for the improvement of my ability I have studied with you the general fields of music, but
        as a speciality in particular the piano. If you would be so kind as to confirm in it that
        you consider me a good musician and talented pianist, my prospects would doubtless be
        significantly enhanced. Please do not think ill of me for burdening you with this. What
        especially attracts my in this position is that, in addition to a good salary and pension
        entitlement, it would have the possibility of my travelling to you several times a year in
        order to play to you, since there would be adequate time for me to engage in further study
        and to do my own work – advantages that in a theater job would surely be out of the
        question, quite apart from the poor remuneration. May I perhaps also beg you to deal with
        the matter as soon as possible, since the deadline to submit the application is in only
        about two weeks’ time? As the sender address, I ask you <tei:pb n="3"/> to give Vienna, not
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="indent-20">I hope that you are your esteemed <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000771">wife</tei:rs> are both well. It is highly possible that I may come and
        visit you sometime, since I have a plan to make a tour of the Silvretta Region.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Until then, I send you my greetings and</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">sincerest thanks in advance,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">your very devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000618">Siegfried
            Müller</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004164">St. Gallen</tei:rs>, Notkerstraße
              73<tei:hi rend="supralinear">II</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:p rend="first">NB I will of course defray your expenses most promptly.</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">Best regards from my parents, who find that I have learned a huge amount
          with you.</tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
