<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3472" sdoID="OJ-14-10_5">OJ 14/10, [5]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RW" scope="major">Rosa Weil's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="AW" scope="minor">Arnold Weil's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008456">WeilR ~
        JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008458">WeilA ~
        JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Rosa Weil to Jeanette Schenker, dated April 19,
        1933</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1933-04-19T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-07-22</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Rosa Weill reports that she has heard nothing of her brother Victor, assuming
        that he will move to Palestine. —She comments sadly on the death of her sister, Frieda
        (Glässner), for whose cremation she, Arnold, and Trude travelled to Berlin, and describes in
        detail Frieda’s deteriorating condition and death. — Lene has moved from Berlin to Prague to
        continue her medical training — Klara is somewhat improved.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>
      
      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000944">Rosa Weil</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000943">Arnold Weil</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:div type="part_1">
        <tei:opener>
          <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RW"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002248"
              >Aussig</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1933-04-19">19. April,
            1933</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
          <tei:salute>Liebe <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Jenny</tei:rs><tei:note
              xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded
              in Heinrich’s diary for April 25, 1933: “Von Rosl (Br.): Schicksal der armen Frieda u.
              der Kinder; Klara besser!” (“From Rosl (letter): the fate of poor Frieda and her
              children; Klara is better!”). — Heinrich’s diary for April 20 and 24, 1933 records:
              “Lie-Liechen verpackt für Rinn u. für die Schwester Rosa.” — “Postweg: Brahms für […]
              Rosl.” (“Lie-Liechen packs [copies of <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-003331"
                  ><tei:title level="m">Oktaven und Quinten</tei:title></tei:rs>] [...] and for her
              sister Rosa.” – “Trip to the post office: Brahms for [...]
            Rosl.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:p>gleich zu Beginn will ich Dir <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000782"
          >Paul</tei:rs>s Adresse schreiben, sonst vergesse ich wieder. P. S. Praha VIII Na Rokytec
          1081. </tei:p>

        <tei:p>Von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000783">Victor</tei:rs> hören wir leider
          garnichts; wir nehmen an, daß er seine Absicht ausgeführt und sich in <tei:rs type="place"
            key="entity-004528">Palästina</tei:rs> angekauft hat.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
            type="editorial" place="foot">Victor Schiff migrated from Chile to Palestine sometime in
            mid- or late-1930, and was back in Chile by August 1933.</tei:note></tei:p>

        <tei:p>Daß die arme <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003245">Frieda</tei:rs> nur wirklich
          tot sein soll, will mir garnicht in den Sinn,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
            type="editorial" place="foot">Frieda Glässner (<tei:hi rend="italic">née</tei:hi>
            Schiff) died sometime early in 1933.</tei:note> ich kann es nie einfach überhaupt nicht
          vorstellen und weil sie doch seit Jahren von <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002248"
            >Aussig</tei:rs> weg war, denke ich mir immer, sie muß doch einmal wieder zu uns
          zurückkommen. Es geht nur damit so, wie <tei:pb n="2"/> den einfältigsten Kinderseelen. </tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">Wir, d.h. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs>,
            <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008447">Trude</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs> und ich waren von Mittwoch, an dem wir die <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-003245">Arme</tei:rs> engeäschert haben, bis Montag in <tei:rs
            type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>; <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs> fuhr am nächsten Morgen, <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs> am Freitag, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008447"
            >Trude</tei:rs> und ich mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008445">Hedl</tei:rs>, die
          ganz zusammengebrochen <tei:add place="interlinear-above">am Montag</tei:add> war, nach
            <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002248">Aussig</tei:rs> zurück. Wir wollten die <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-008445">Arme</tei:rs> aus dem traurigen Milieu heraus und ein
          bißchen auf andere Gedanken bringen und so war sie na 1½ Wochen unser lieber Gast. Leider
          mußte sie die Hälfte der Zeit wegen einer fieberhaften Erkältung im Bett verbringen. Ein
          großer Teil ihrer Nervosität hängt auch mit den Ereignissen der letzten Zeit zusammen,
          weshalb sie auch seit <tei:date when="1933-04-01">1. April</tei:date> mit beiden Buben
          wieder hier ist.</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="3"/> Seit 1½ Wochen ist auch ihr <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-003921">Mann</tei:rs> hier und die Armen stehen vor einer ganz ernsten und
          schweren Lebenswende. Ihr kennst ja wohl all‘ die Sachen aus den Zeitungen. </tei:p>

        <tei:p>**Seit ihrer Übersiedlung von <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002589"
            >Hamburg</tei:rs> nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs> hat die
          Arme <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003245">Schwester</tei:rs> gekränkelt; erst war es
          ein leichter Mumps, (von den Kindern angesteckt,) dann eine Grippe mit leichter
          Lungenzündung, welchen Umstand der Arzt verschwieg, wohl um die Angehörigen nicht
          allzusehr zu ängstigen. Vielleicht ging sie bei nicht ganz gutem Wetter zu früh aus und es
          stellte sich eine eitrige Mittelohrentzündung ein; erst floß der Eiter von selbst ab, dann
          müßte doch operiert werden. Das ging alles ganz glatt und sie ging schon allein zum
          Verband- <tei:pb n="4"/> wechsel. Nach einiger Zeit stellten sich Schmerzen, Suchen nach
          Worten Verwechslung von Worten und Sehstörungen, <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
              ><tei:unclear reason="reading">u.</tei:unclear></tei:add> die Ärzte konstatierten
          einen Abszess im Gehirn; bei der ersten Operation fand man nichts, die
          Lähmungserscheinungen schritten fort, beim zweiten Öffnen entnahm man 13 cm<tei:add
            place="interlinear-above">3</tei:add><tei:del rend="overstrike">m<tei:add
              place="interlinear-above">3</tei:add></tei:del> Eiter, doch hielt das Herz nichtmehr
          stand und es war wohl noch besser so, denn sie wäre geistig nie wieder in Ordnung
          gekommen. Sie war noch zu jung und hat so gerne bei ihren Kindern gelebt, aber ich denke,
          der Tod ist einem jahrelangen Siechtum vorzuziehen. </tei:p>

        <tei:p>**<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005248">Lene</tei:rs> mußte fort von <tei:rs
            type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>, wo sie sogerne im Westend-Krankenheim
          bei Prof. Umber gearbeitet und viel gelernt hat. Nun ist sie in <tei:rs type="place"
            key="entity-002892">Prag</tei:rs> an der Klinik Schmidt, und ist ein bißchen
          unglücklich. </tei:p>

        <tei:p>Alles soll gesund bleiben und die Zukunft soll besseres bringen. </tei:p>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute>Alles Gute und herzlichste Grüße</tei:salute>
          <tei:salute>Euere</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000944">Rosa</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>

        <tei:postscript>
          <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">right margin, sideways:</tei:note> Clara
            geht es G. L. anhaltend besser wir hoffen sie bald wieder hier zu haben.</tei:p>
        </tei:postscript>
      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="part_2">
        <tei:opener/>

        <tei:p/>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#AW"/>Herzlichste Grüße</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>
      </tei:div>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:div type="part_1">
        <tei:opener>
          <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RW"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002248"
              >Aussig</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1933-04-19">April 19, 1933</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
          <tei:salute>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Jenny</tei:rs><tei:ptr
              corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:p>To start with, let me give you <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000782">Paul
            Schiff</tei:rs>"s address right away, or I’ll forget it again: Paul Schiff, Na Rokytec
          1081, Prague VIII.</tei:p>

        <tei:p>Sadly, we have heard nothing at all from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000783"
            >Victor</tei:rs>; we infer that he has made up his mind and has bought himself some land
          in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004528">Palestine</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

        <tei:p>I simply can’t get it into my head that poor <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-003245">Frieda</tei:rs> could now really be dead.<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> I just can’t imagine it at all; and because she
          was away from <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002248">Aussig</tei:rs> for a good many
          years, I constantly imagine that she must return to us again some day. It can only happen
          to <tei:pb n="2"/> the most simple-minded children.</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">We – that is, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs>,
            <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008447">Trude</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs> and I – were in <tei:rs type="place"
            key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs> from the Wednesday on which we cremated the <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-003245">poor thing</tei:rs> to <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
            >the following</tei:supplied> Monday. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943"
            >Arnold</tei:rs> departed the next day, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000339"
            >Oskar</tei:rs> on Friday, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008447">Trude</tei:rs> and
          I with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008445">Hedl</tei:rs>, who was totally distraught
            <tei:add place="interlinear-above">on the Monday</tei:add>, returned to <tei:rs
            type="place" key="entity-002248">Aussig</tei:rs>. We wanted to get the <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-008445">poor girl</tei:rs> away from the gloomy surroundings
          to take her mind off things a bit, so she was our dear guest for a week and a half.
          Unfortunately, she had to spend half that time in bed with a feverish cold. A large part
          of her nervousness arose out of the events of recent days, which is why she has been back
          here with both little children since <tei:date when="1933-04-01">April
          1</tei:date>.</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="3"/> For the last week and a half her <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-003921">husband</tei:rs> has also been here, and the poor souls are faced
          with a serious and difficult turning point in their lives. You know all of this from the
          newspapers.</tei:p>

        <tei:p>Our poor <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003245">sister</tei:rs> has been sick ever
          since her move from <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002589">Hamburg</tei:rs> to <tei:rs
            type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>. First it was a slight case of the
          mumps (caught from the children), then influenza with mild inflammation of the lungs, a
          fact the doctor didn’t disclose, doubtless so as not to alarm the patient too much.
          Perhaps because she went out too soon in not very good weather, a suppurating middle-ear
          inflammation flared up; at first the pus drained of its own accord, then even so it had to
          be operated on. Everything progressed smoothly and she went on her own to have the bandage
            <tei:pb n="4"/> changed. A short time later, she had pains, was searching for her words
          and mixing words up, with impaired vision, <tei:add place="interlinear-above"><tei:unclear
              reason="original_unclear">and</tei:unclear></tei:add> the doctors suspected an abscess
          on the brain. In the first operation, they found nothing; the signs of paralysis advanced
          and with the second operation they took out 13 cubic centimeters of pus, but her heart
          could not withstand anything more, and it was really better so, for she would never have
          recovered mentally. She was still young, and loved life with her children so much, but I
          think death is preferable to a years-long lingering illness.</tei:p>

        <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005248">Lene</tei:rs> had to leave <tei:rs
            type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>, where she had so much enjoyed working
          in the West End hospital under Prof. Umber, and learned a great deal. Now she is in
            <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002892">Prague</tei:rs>, at the Schmidt Clinic, and is
          somewhat unhappy.</tei:p>

        <tei:p>Let’s hope we all remain healthy, and that the future brings us something
          better.</tei:p>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute>Most cordially wishing you all the best,</tei:salute>
          <tei:salute>Your</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000944">Rosa</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>

        <tei:postscript>
          <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">right margin, sideways:</tei:note> Klara
            has been better for some time now, and we are hoping, God willing, to have her here
            again soon. </tei:p>
        </tei:postscript>
      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="part_2">
        <tei:opener/>

        <tei:p/>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#AW"/>Most cordial greetings</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>
      </tei:div>


    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
