<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="2295" sdoID="OJ-15-16_14">OJ 15/16, [14]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HW" scope="sole">Hans Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2007</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="AH">
   <tei:persName>Alison Hiley</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2007</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-06-25" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated March 29, 1913</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1913-03-29T17:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-10-16</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Weisse apologizes for having interrupted Robert Brünauer's lesson, and declares
    his allegiance to Schenker effusively. He asks to call on March 31 (his
    birthday).</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Stören-Fried; disturbance of the peace; Entschuldigung; excuse; Freude; joy;
    Wahrheit; truth; Anhänger; hanger-on; follower; Kunstbetrachtung; artistic sense; Analyse;
    analysis; Dankgefühl; gratitude; Geburtstag; birthday; Walzer; waltz</dc:subject>



   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000951">Weisse</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HW"/>Liebster <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
      >Meister</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this
      letter is not recorded in Schenker's diary.</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>


   <tei:p>Nachträglich noch muss Sie der Stören-Fried der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000107"
     >Brünauer</tei:rs>schen Stunde<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"
     >Weisse is apologizing for having interrupted a lesson given to Robert Brünauer. Brünauer's
     previous lesson took place on March 28; there is no mention of an interruption either in the
     diary for that date or in the 1912/1913 lessonbook.</tei:note> um Entschuldigung bitten, und
    sich vor allem <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">vor</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">gegen</tei:add>
    </tei:subst>
    <tei:choice>
     <tei:sic>dem</tei:sic>
     <tei:corr>den</tei:corr>
    </tei:choice> Vorwurf<tei:del rend="overstrike">e</tei:del> verwahren, er sei zudringlich. Grade
    aus dem gestrigen keineswegs lyrischen Intermezzo,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
     place="foot">Heinrich Heine's collection of 65 poems was given the title <tei:title level="m"
      >Lyrisches Intermezzo</tei:title> because it was originally published in 1823 between two
     tragedies, <tei:title level="m">William Ratcliff</tei:title> and <tei:title level="m"
      >Almansor</tei:title>; it was later incorporated into his <tei:title level="m">Buch der
      Lieder</tei:title> (1827). The most famous musical setting of these poems is Schumann's
      <tei:title level="m">Dichterliebe</tei:title>, composed in 1840, a cycle of sixteen of these
     poems.</tei:note> können Sie im Gegensatze zu dem Unbeteiligten, tief in mein Inneres schauen,
    das sich vor Ihnen nie verschlossen hat und nie verschliessen wird! Was mich trieb<tei:supplied
     reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> war nur in gewissem Sinne mein Feuer, im tiefern aber
    doch das Ihre!! Es war – so komisch es auch klingen mag, nicht meine Freude an dem kleinen
    Stücke, sondern meine Freude an der Ihren! Sie müssen also, Liebster, verstehen, dass ich, dem
    die Wahrheit noch wie ein grosser Sturm durch Tür und Fenster zieht, aufgehört habe, zu Ihnen
    als Herrn D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Heinrich Schenker zu kommen, sondern dass ich
    Sie mit jener identifiziert habe, und sobald <tei:pb n="2"/> ich Ihre Schwelle betreten habe,
    bei der Wahrheit selbst zu sein vermeine. Ich schmeichle mir sagen zu dürfen, dass ich mehr wie
    so mancher Ihrer Anhänger, wie man das so treffend zu nennen pflegt, von dem Segen und der
    tiefen Klarheit Ihrer Kunstbetrachtung, ihrer regenerierenden Analyse verstehe, weil ich auf
    jeden Fall Ihre Tragweite richtig erkannt habe.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Lassen Sie also, Sie innig verehrten, mein tiefes Dankgefühl so weit zu Ihrem Herzen
    dringen, wie tief es eben aus dem meinen, strömt. Sie haben einen Menschen in herrlichstem Sinne
    für <tei:sic>seinen</tei:sic> Leben glücklich gemacht, so glücklich, dass wenn ich heute stürbe,
    das Bild meines Denkens innerhalb der letzten 3 Jahre so einheitlich und zielbewusst wäre, wie
    selten bei einem Greise!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Dank ist viel zu wenig!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Wenn es mir aber je nach gesunder ruhiger Arbeit gelingen sollte<tei:supplied
     reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> etwas nicht ganz Unrühmliches zu schreiben, so werde ich
    mich nicht vermessen<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> meine Person
    davorzustellen, <tei:pb n="3"/> sondern werde den Geist von Ihrem Geiste, das Feuer von Ihrem
    Feuer, die Ausdauer von Ihrer Ausdauer darin zu finden wissen!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04"
     type="editorial" place="foot">These four paragraphs, albeit effusive, have some
     posthumous justification in that Weisse, by moving to New York and teaching Schenker's ideas at
     the Mannes School, proved to be the principal vehicle of Schenker's ideas and the bridge to
     subsequent Schenker pedagogy in America and the rest of the world.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Nun aber bitte ich, mich nicht misszuverstehen, wenn ich Sie bitte, ob ich Montag<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">i.e. March 31; the lessonbook 1912/1913
     records after the last lesson: "Weisse brings the manuscript of the small waltz."</tei:note> an
    meinem Geburtstage gegen ¾ 6 auf einen Augenblick zu Ihnen kommen könnte, um den gestern
    missglückten Walzer,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">The lessonbook
     for Weisse's lesson on March 28 read: "Exercises good; Chopin mazuka studies; new waltz of his
     own."</tei:note> sicher und ohne Fehler Ihnen vorzuspielen, weil ich ihn dennoch für einen
    meiner besten halte.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">In inniger Verehrung, ganz Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
     >Hans</tei:rs>.</tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1913-03-29">29./III. 1913</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">


   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HW"/>Most beloved <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
      >Master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>


   <tei:p>The disturber of the peace must belatedly apologize for interrupting <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000107">Brünauer</tei:rs>'s lesson<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/>
    and above all plead <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">before</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">against</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> any reproach for obtrusiveness. Yesterday’s intermezzo ‒ which was in no way
     lyrical<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> ‒ enables you, in contrast to one who
    is indifferent, to look deep into my inner self ‒ a place which has never been hidden from you,
    and never shall be! That which drove me on was only in a certain sense my fire ‒ in a deeper
    sense it was yours!! However comical it may sound, it was not my delight in the little piece,
    but my delight in your <tei:supplied reason="clarity">delight</tei:supplied>! Thus, dearest
     <tei:supplied reason="clarity">Master</tei:supplied>, you must understand that I, for whom the
    truth is as a draught from a big storm at door and window, have ceased to come to you as Dr.
    Heinrich Schenker, but rather that I have identified you with <tei:supplied reason="clarity">the
     truth</tei:supplied>, and that the moment <tei:pb n="2"/> I cross your threshold believe myself
    to be in the presence of truth <tei:supplied reason="clarity">itself</tei:supplied>. I flatter
    myself that I may say that, more than most of your <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
     >followers</tei:supplied> (or 'hangers-on', as people so aptly like to put it), I have an
    understanding of the grace and deep clarity of your artistic sense, of your regenerative
    analysis, because I at least have recognized your significance for what it truly is.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>You, whom I hold in such affectionate reverence, must allow my deep-felt gratitude to
    penetrate your heart as fully as it gushes forth from my own. You have made a man most
    gloriously content with his life, so content <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
     >indeed</tei:supplied>, that if I were to die today, the representation of my thinking over the
    past three years would have a uniformity and purpose seldom to be found <tei:supplied
     reason="clarity">even</tei:supplied> in an old man!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Thanks cannot in any way suffice!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>If, however, after some sound and composed labour, I should ever succeed in writing
    something not altogether inglorious, I will not be so bold as to judge my own person as the
    source <tei:pb n="3"/> but will recognize that the spirit will come from your spirit, the fire
    from your fire, the endurance from your endurance!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"
    /></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Please do not take it amiss if I now request that I might come to see you for a moment on
     Monday,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> on my birthday, around 5:45. I should
    like to play you the waltz which I performed so poorly yesterday,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06"
     type="footnote"/>
    <tei:supplied reason="clarity">only</tei:supplied> this time accurately and without mistakes,
    for I still consider it to be one of my best.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">With heartfelt respect, entirely your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
     >Hans</tei:rs>.</tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1913-03-29">March 29, 1913</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
