<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2758" sdoID="OJ-12-50_6">OJ 12/50, [6]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="BM" scope="sole">Bernhard Martin's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2022</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2022</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>


    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2011-06-09" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008186">MartinB ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Bernhard Martin to Schenker, undated [?July c.10,
        1930]</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1930-07-10T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2022-05-27</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Bernhard Martin reports using Schenker's analysis of the Haydn E-flat major
        piano sonata [Tonwille 3] with his secondary school class. -- As a violinist he is working
        on the Brahms Op. 78 violin sonata. -- He inquires after the "Eroica monograph." --
        Universal Edition has still not rectified his defective copy of Schenker's Harmonielehre. --
        He asks about Furtwängler's studies with Schenker.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000574">BMartin</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#BM"/>Sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000632">Doktor</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
            place="foot">Receipt of this letter – which comprises two cards written on both sides
            and presumably mailed in an envelope that is not preserved – is recorded in Schenker’s
            diary for July 14, 1930: “Von Martin (Br.): fragt nach meinen Arbeiten.” (“From Martin
            (letter): inquires about my publications.”), and Schenker‘s reply in that for July 22,
            1930: “An Martin (Br.): beantworte Frage um Frage, zuletzt auch die in wie fern ich
            Furtwängler zu meinen Schülern zähle.” (“To Martin (letter): I answer each of his
            questions in turn, at the end even the one about the extent to which I reckon
            Furtwängler among my pupils.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Nachdem ich vor längerer Zeit Ihre <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001737">Ausgabe von
          Beethovens <tei:title>op. 101</tei:title></tei:rs> studiert habe, müßte ich die Arbeiten
        eine Zeitlang einstellen. Trotz oder besser wegen Ihrer gründlichen Einführung stellen Sie
        an die Arbeitskraft doch einige Ansprüche. <tei:del rend="overstrike">Dort</tei:del> Da ich
        im Nebenberuf auch noch Schwerkriegsbeschädigter bin, muß ich mich augenblicklich ein wenig
        schonen. In den Herbstferien werde ich vielleicht noch eine Sonate von <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> vornehmen. In der Unter- <tei:pb n="2"/> sekunda
        unserer Anstalt habe ich heute das Studium der <tei:rs type="composition"
          key="entity-001554"><tei:title>E<tei:hi rend="supralinear">s</tei:hi> dur
            Sonate</tei:title> von Haydn</tei:rs> begonnen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Cf. <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-12-50_3">OJ
            12/50, [3]</tei:ref>, July 3, 1929, for his first reference to use of this
          analysis.</tei:note> Mein Geigenspiel wird augenblicklich mit dem Studium der <tei:rs
          type="composition" key="entity-001359"><tei:title>G dur Sonate</tei:title> von
          Brahms</tei:rs> ausgefüllt. Die Aufdeckung der Zusammenhänge verursacht mit manche
          Kopfschmerzen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Martin writes
          continuously at this point without paragraph-break.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Planen Sie wohl noch eine Herausgabe eines neuen <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001749">Jahrbuch</tei:rs>es? Dürfte man auf eine solche Möglichkeit hin die
          <tei:unclear reason="reading">Bitterauf</tei:unclear> Berücksichtigung von <tei:rs
          type="composition" key="entity-001359">Brahms <tei:title>op. 78</tei:title></tei:rs>
        aussprechen? Schande nur, daß <tei:pb n="3"/> bei <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002448">Simrock</tei:rs> alles bearbeitet wird. So ist z.B. bei <tei:rs
          type="composition" key="entity-001354">Brahms
          <tei:title>Händelvariationen</tei:title></tei:rs>, bearbeitet von Mayer-Mahr,<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Moritz Mayer-Mahr (1869–1947),
          German-Jewish pianist and teacher, pupil of Woldemar Bargiel and Ernst Rudorff. Based in
          Berlin, he wrote two manuals on piano playing, and published editions of piano pieces by
          Brahms and études by Czerny. (<tei:title level="m">wikipedia</tei:title>)</tei:note> der
        Urtext garnicht herauszulesen. Wieweit Ossip Schnirlin<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Ossip Schnirlin (1869–1939), Russian-Jewish violinist,
          played the “Apollo” Stradivarius. He published <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Der Neue Weg
              zur Beherrschung des gesamten Violinliteratur</tei:title> (Mainz: Schott,
            1923)</tei:bibl> and edited a volume of chamber music without piano, then one of classic
          transcriptions for violin and piano. (<tei:title level="m">wikipedia</tei:title>) As a
          pupil of Joseph Joachim he had some claim to authenticity when editing music of
          Brahms.</tei:note> bei den Geigenwerken das echte Bild beibehält ist auch nicht immer
        ersichtlich. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Trotz Ihrer liebenswürdigen Vermittlung habe ich wohl wegen der Unausführbarkeit vom
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">Universalverlag</tei:rs> die fehlenden
        Bogen in Ihrer <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724"
          ><tei:title>Harmonielehre</tei:title></tei:rs> nicht ersetzt bekommen.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Since Schenker’s <tei:title level="m"
            >Harmonielehre</tei:title> was first published by J. G. Cotta of Stuttgart in 1906 and
          the remaining stocks were taken over by Universal Edition in 1920, it would perhaps be
          understandable if UE did not feel responsible for the collation and binding of those
          surviving stocks. – Schenker had complained to UE in detail about Martin’s copy (WSLB
          418/1, c. December 18, 1929), concluding “Would it not be possible to make amends for
          this,” and had received the reply from Emil Hertzka “Regarding the missing gatherings of
            <tei:title level="m">Harmonielehre</tei:title>, I will look into the matter with my
          publishing department” (OC 52/857 = WSLB 418/2, December 20, 1929).</tei:note> Viel-
          <tei:pb n="4"/> leicht kann aber der Fehlende im Grundzug aus Ihren anderen Werken bei den
          Einze<tei:supplied reason="omission">l</tei:supplied>fällen entnommen <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">werden</tei:add>, wie es mir nach den Titeln des
        Inhaltsverzeichnisses scheint. Wie steht es nun mit dem Erscheinen der
          <tei:title>Eroica-Monographie</tei:title><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Reference is to <tei:bibl><tei:author>Schenker</tei:author>‘s <tei:title
              level="a">Beethovens Dritte Sinfonie zum erstenmal in ihrem wahren Inhalt
              dargestellt,</tei:title>
            <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001752"><tei:title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der
                Musik</tei:title>, vol. III</tei:rs>, pp. 25–121 and four foreground graphs (<tei:hi
              rend="italic">Bilder</tei:hi>) and 49 music examples (<tei:hi rend="italic"
              >Figuren</tei:hi>)</tei:bibl>. This was not produced separately as a monograph, as
          originally intended by Schenker. It was published in mid-December 1930.</tei:note> und des
          <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728">„<tei:title>freien Satzes</tei:title>“</tei:rs>? </tei:p>

      <tei:p>In gespannter Erwartung freue ich mich darauf. Ist meine Vermutung wohl richtig, daß
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs> bei Ihnen Studien
        absolviert hat? In der Hoffnung, daß dieser Brief Sie in bester Gesundheit erreicht </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>grüßt Sie herzlichst</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr ergebenster</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000574">B
          Martin</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#BM"/>Dear Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs
              type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>After I had some time ago studied your <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001737">edition
          of Beethoven’s <tei:title>Op. 101</tei:title></tei:rs>, I was obliged to set my work aside
        for a while. Despite, or better on account of, your exhaustive introduction, you place some
        demands on one’s capacity for work. Since in my secondary occupation I am also still a
        severely disabled ex-serviceman, I have currently to go a little easy on myself. In the Fall
        holidays I will perhaps tackle another <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055"
          >Beethoven</tei:rs> sonata. With the sixth-year secondary school class <tei:pb n="2"/> at
        our institution I have today begun the study of the <tei:rs type="composition"
          key="entity-001554">Haydn <tei:title>E<tei:g type="flat"/> major
          Sonata</tei:title></tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> My violin
        playing is currently occupied by studying the <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001359"
          >Brahms <tei:title>G major Sonata</tei:title></tei:rs>. The discovery of the <tei:supplied
          reason="clarity">internal</tei:supplied> coherences is causing me many headaches.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Are you by any chance planning publication of a new <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001749">Yearbook</tei:rs>? Might it be possible to announce the possibility of
        this in the <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">Bitterauf</tei:unclear>
        <tei:unclear reason="translation">consideration</tei:unclear> of <tei:rs type="composition"
          key="entity-001359">Brahms <tei:title>Op. 78</tei:title></tei:rs>? It’s such a shame that
          <tei:pb n="3"/> everything is handled by <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002448"
          >Simrock</tei:rs>. So, for instance, in the <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001354"
          >Brahms <tei:title>Handel Variations</tei:title></tei:rs> edited by Mayer-Mahr<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> it is impossible to tell what is original notation
        and what not. To what extent Ossip Schnirlin<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/>
        has been faithful to the original notation is also not always evident.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Because of the incompetence of <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408"
          >Universal Edition</tei:rs>, I have not had the missing gatherings of your <tei:rs
          type="work" key="entity-001724"><tei:title level="m">Theory of
          Harmony</tei:title></tei:rs> replaced despite your kind intervention.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> But perhaps <tei:pb n="4"/> the missing materials
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">can be</tei:add> inferred from your other works item by
        item, as seems to me the case from the titles in the table of contents. Where do things
        stand now on the “Eroica” monograph<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> and
          <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title level="m">Free
          Composition</tei:title></tei:rs>?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I look forward to those with eager anticipation. Am I right in thinking that <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs> has completed his studies with you?
        In hopes that this letter finds you in the best of health,</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Your most devoted <tei:supplied reason="identity"
          >pupil</tei:supplied></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">sends most cordial greetings</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000574">B.
          Martin</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
