<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2115" sdoID="OJ-15-16_74">OJ 15/16, [74]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HW" scope="major">Hans Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2008</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2018</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-10-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated April 15, 1931</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1931-04-15T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2018-10-04</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Weisse thanks Schenker for a letter of reference [for his teaching post at the
        Mannes School of Music], and asks for some modifications. — He has not heard from
        Furtwängler, whom he has also asked for a reference, and urges Schenker to be patient with
        Furtwängler, too. — He is completing a set of three-voice piano pieces and wishes to
        dedicate them to Schenker on the occasion of his leaving Vienna.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Begriff; concept; term; Propagierung; support; advocacy; Schüler; pupil;
        hypertroph; hypertrophic; Passus; passage; Komposition; composition; Unterricht;
        instruction; Dokument; document; Zaghaftigkeit; timidity; Abgang; departure; Klavierstücke;
        piano pieces; widmen; to dedicate; Lob; praise</dc:subject>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000951">Weisse</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:lb/><tei:note type="editorial">printed letterhead:</tei:note>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10"><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>WIEN</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>XIII., WATTMANNGASSE 5</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:lb/><tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:handShift new="#HW"/><tei:date
            when="1932-04-15">15. IV. 31</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber verehrter <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"
            >Meister</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">(Weisse
            has asked Schenker for a letter of reference for the Mannes School of Music in New York,
            where he has been provisionally offered a post, and has received the text of <tei:ref
              type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-45_6">OJ 5/45, [6]</tei:ref>.) Receipt of this letter
            and Schenker's reply are recorded in his diary at OJ 4/4, pp. 3606‒3607, April 15, 1931:
            "Von Weisse (expreß Br.): bittet um eine Korrektur: „. . ein bekannter“ statt
            „berühmter“ . . bleibt bezüglich Furtwänglers optimistisch, widmet mir neue
            Klavierstücke. [...] An Weisse (expreß Br.): korrigiere nach Wünsch, danke für die
            Widmung; erinnere wieder an verschiedene Möglichkeiten, Furtwängler u. seinen Freunden
            beizukommen." ("From Weisse (express letter): requests a correction: 'a well-known…'
            instead of 'a famous…'; he remains optimistic with regard to Furtwängler, is dedicating
            new piano pieces to me. [...] To Weisse (express letter): I make the correction
            according to his wishes, thank him for the dedication, remind him again about various
            possibilities for winning over Furtwängler and his friends.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>ich danke Ihnen herzlichst für die Zeilen und bitte Sie um Entschuldigung wenn ich mit
        der lästigen Angelegenheit nochmals komme. Aber ein mir innewohnendes Gefühl der
        Bescheidenheit will und kann sich dabei nicht beruhigen, dass Zeilen die von Ihnen für die
        Öffentlichkeit (wenn auch nur <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002510"
            ><tei:country>Amerika</tei:country></tei:rs>’s) geschrieben sind von einem „berühmten
        Wiener Meister der Musik“ sprechen und dabei mich meinen. Sie haben in Ihrem Werk zu
        deutlich gezeigt, was die Wiener Meister zustandebrachten; <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">dass</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">deshalb möchte</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> ich diesen Begriff, der<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> wenn
        Sie ihn aussprechen, etwas ganz Bestimmtes aussagt, in seiner <tei:pb n="2"/> völligen
        Reinheit erhalten <tei:del rend="overstrike">möchte</tei:del> und auch nicht den Schatten
        eines Verdachtes gegen Sie aufkommen lassen <tei:del rend="overstrike">möchte</tei:del>, als
        Seien Sie dort, wo es sich um Propagierung eines Schülers handle, nachsichtiger als in
        anderen Fällen. Feinde würden dies bestimmt so auslegen können.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Darf ich Sie also bitten<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> diesen
        etwas gar zu hypertroph ausgefallenen Passus auszulassen und zu ersetzen durch: “unter der
        Leitung des bekannten Wiener Musikers Dr. H. W. ihre Studien wird machen können“. Wollten
        Sie hier noch eine Bemerkung einschalten, dass meine Kompositionen
          (<tei:title>Oktett</tei:title>) mich zum Unterricht von Komposition besonders berechtigen,
        so würden Sie damit nicht mehr aussagen, als <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >was</tei:add> Sie ja vor jedem aufrecht erhalten können. Alles Weitere ist sehr schön und
        das bitte ich Sie dann auch beizubehalten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Schenker changed his reference to accommodate Weisse's comments. For a
          revised draft, see <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-45_7">OJ 5/45, [7]</tei:ref>,
          dated April 15, 1931.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs>, den ich auch um ein solches
        Dokument bat, schweigt hartnäckig.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Furtwängler’s silence refers mainly to the promise he had made to ask friends
          of his to help subvent the printing costs of Schenker’s published work; the next letter
          from Weisse to Schenker brings news of this, and of Furtwängler’s reference for
          Weisse.</tei:note> Ich werde mich bald gezwungen sehn, ihn telegrafisch aus seiner Ruhe
        aufzustöbern.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Dennoch sehe ich noch immer nicht pessimistisch und bitte Sie<tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> das gleiche zu tun: Man muss <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000268">F.</tei:rs> kennen, um zu wissen, dass er bei seiner Zaghaftigkeit
        erst <tei:choice>
          <tei:sic>denn</tei:sic>
          <tei:corr>den</tei:corr>
        </tei:choice> richtigen Moment erlauern will.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich glaube meinen Abgang von Wien nicht besser beschliessen zu können, als mit der
        Bitte, Ihnen, vorausgesetzt dass <tei:del rend="overstrike">S</tei:del> sie Ihre Billigung
        erfahren, meine nun bald fertig gestellten 3 stimmigen Klavierstücke, an denen ich im Laufe
        der letzten zwei Monate gearbeitet habe, widmen zu dürfen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> Vielleicht erzeige ich mich in diesem Werke ein wenig des Lobes wert,
        das Sie <tei:add place="interlinear-above">mir</tei:add> in so verschwenderischer Weise
        erteilen.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Mit den allerherzlichsten Grüssen und vielem, vielem
          Dank</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Ihr getreuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person"><tei:hi
              rend="lateinschr">H</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:lb/><tei:note type="editorial">printed letterhead:</tei:note>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10"><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>VIENNA</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>XIII, WATTMANNGASSE 5</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:lb/><tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:handShift new="#HW"/><tei:date
            when="1932-04-15">April 15, 1931</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear, revered <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>I thank you most cordially for your lines, and beg your forgiveness if I return yet
        again to this burdensome matter. But a feeling of modesty within me can and will not leave
        me in peace on account of the fact that lines written by you for public consumption (even if
        only for <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002510"
          ><tei:country>America</tei:country></tei:rs>'s) speak about a "famous Viennese master of
        music" and refer to me. You have shown in your work only too clearly what the Viennese
        masters accomplished; <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">that</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">for this reason</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> I <tei:add place="interlinear-above">would like</tei:add> this concept ‒ which
        has a quite precise meaning when uttered by you ‒ to <tei:pb n="2"/> retain it complete
        purity, and not allow even the shadow of suspicion to fall upon you, as though you would be
        more lenient where it concerns support for one of your pupils than in other cases. Your
        enemies would certainly be able to use this against you.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Might I ask you therefore to omit this rather overly hypertrophic passage, and replace
        it with "will be able to undertake their studies under the supervision of the well-known
        Viennese musician, Dr. Hans Weisse." If you were to add a further remark, to the effect that
        my compositions (e.g. the <tei:title>Octet</tei:title>) qualify me in particular for the
        teaching of composition, you would thereby be saying no more than <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">what</tei:add> you would be justified in being able to say to
        anyone. Everything else that you have written is very beautiful, and I would ask you to
        retain that.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs>, to whom I also asked for
        such a document, is being stubbornly silent.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/>
        I shall see myself soon compelled to rouse him telegraphically from his slumbers.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nonetheless, I still do not see cause for pessimism, and I ask you to do the same: you
        have to know <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">F.</tei:rs> to understand that, in
        spite of his timidity, he is waiting to seize the right moment at which to act.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I believe I can conclude my departure from Vienna no better than with the request ‒
        assuming they meet with your approval ‒ to dedicate to you my three-voice piano pieces,
        which I have been working on during the past two months and which will soon be
        finished.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> Perhaps I will show myself, in this work, to be deserving of a little
        of the praise that you have granted <tei:add place="interlinear-above">me</tei:add> in such
        an overly generous way.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">With my most cordial greetings, and many, many
          thanks,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Your faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person"
          >H.</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
