<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="85" sdoID="OJ-13-10_5">OJ 13/10, [5]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="TLJ">
   <tei:persName>Timothy L. Jackson</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2010</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2010</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">
  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated August 26, 1918</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1918-08-26T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-04-21</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Oppel is stationed in Lille, where he has been able to devote some of his time to
    music. He asks Schenker if he knows Arnold Mendelssohn’s recent works and Kurth’s book on Bach’s
    linear counterpoint.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>



   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002757">Kiel</tei:rs>, Feldstr 77<tei:hi
       rend="supralinear">IV.</tei:hi>
     </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine><tei:date when="1918-08-26">26. VIII 18</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Sehr verehrter Herr D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi>
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01"
      type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for
      September 3, 1918: “Von Oppel (Br.): über seine neue Verwendung im Felde, die
       <tei:sic>im</tei:sic> aus Rücksicht auf seine fünf Kinder zugebilligt worden; freue sich auf
      seinen Besuch in Wien” (“From Oppel (letter): about his new-found employment on the
      battlefield, which has been granted him in view of his five children; he is looking forward to
      his visit to Vienna.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Über Ihren lieben Brief vom <tei:date when="1918-02-27">27. II.</tei:date><tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is recorded in
     Schenker’s diary for February 27, 1918: “An Oppel (Br.): Dank für sein freundliches Gedenken;
     „von Anfang im Westen“: eine Dichtung für sich. Doch auch ich habe ein Schützengrabenleben
     geführt, einen Kampf wider eine gesinnungslose Umgebung, Kaiser, Minister u. Einzelne
     ausgenommen; in <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001736">op. 111</tei:rs> u. in der Vorrede zu
      <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001727">II<tei:hi rend="supralinear">2</tei:hi></tei:rs>
     spielt der Krieg in die ohnehin kriegerisch gehaltenen Arbeiten hinein” (“To Oppel (letter):
     thanks for his convivial dedication; "von Anfang im Westen" [From the beginning in the West], a
     poem apart. But I too have led a life in the trenches, fighting against an environment without
     ethos, with the exception of the Kaiser, his ministers and certain individuals; in <tei:rs
      type="work" key="entity-001736">Op. 111</tei:rs> in the preface to the <tei:rs type="work"
      key="entity-001727">second volume of <tei:title level="m">Counterpoint</tei:title></tei:rs>,
     the War infuses this already quite martially conceived work”).</tei:note> habe ich mich sehr
    gefreut, und besonders darüber, dass Sie trotz der innern Zustände <tei:rs type="place"
     key="entity-002506">Österreich</tei:rs>s ruhig weiterarbeiten. Bis Mitte Juli war ich noch an
    der Front, zuletzt drei Monate bei Montdidier; auch die Offensive hier haben wir mit sehr
    geringen Verlusten überstanden. Dann wurde ich zu einer andern Truppe versetzt, die in Lille
    stationiert ist. Ein Art Druckposten mit Rücksicht auf meine 5 Kinder. Hier komme ich wenigstens
    zum Musicieren und Arbeiten, ein paar mir befreundete Violinvirtuosen wirken dort auch am
    Theater, und wir spielen nun häufig in Lazaretten u.s.w. Streichquartett. Dienst habe ich nur
    morgens und zeitweilig nachts Wachen-Revision.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich habe eine Sonatine geschrieben für Violine und Klavier u. Variat. für Orgel über einen
    Choral. Aber, da ich <tei:unclear reason="reading">dauernd</tei:unclear> k<tei:supplied
     reason="abbreviation">riegs</tei:supplied>v<tei:supplied>erwendungsfähig</tei:supplied> bin,
    fürchte ich, die Herrlichkeit dauert nicht allzulange. – Auf den Besuch in Wien bei Ihnen nach
    dem Frieden freue ich mich schon jetzt. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Der Geist in Wien wird sich nach dem Frieden wol auch ändern, wenn eine feste,
    zielbewusste deutsche Politik <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">illegible
     word</tei:note> wird. <tei:pb n="2"/> Bei uns in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482"
     >Deutschland</tei:rs> wünschen wir auch manches besser, allein das sind Friedensaufgaben, über
    die zu streiten ich jetzt für müssig halte. Erst gilts, den äusseren Feind mürbe zu machen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Kennen Sie <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008291">Arnold Mendelssohn</tei:rs>? Was
    halten Sie von seinen letzten Sachen (Klaviersonate, Streichquartett bei <tei:rs
     type="organization" key="entity-002422">Peters–Leipzig</tei:rs>)?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
     type="editorial" place="foot">Arnold Mendelssohn’s String Quartet in D major, Op. 67, was
     published by C. F. Peters in 1916, his Piano Sonata in E minor, Op. 66, in the following
     year.</tei:note> Haben Sie den <tei:title>linearen Kontrapunkt bei Bach</tei:title> von <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000495"><tei:hi rend="underline"
     >Kurth</tei:hi></tei:rs>–Bern<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot"
       ><tei:bibl><tei:author>Ernst Kurth</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Grundlagen des linearen
       Kontrapunkts: Einführung in Stil und Technik von Bachs melodischer Polyphonie</tei:title>
      (Bern: Max Drechsel, 1917)</tei:bibl></tei:note> gelesen? Ich konnte das Buch leider nicht
    bekommen hier. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>In der Hoffnung dass Sie gesund und frisch bei der Arbeit sind, </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute>bleibe ich mit den herzlichsten Grüssen</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr sehr ergebener</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">D<tei:hi
       rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Reinhard Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002757">Kiel</tei:rs>, Feldstraße 77/4 </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine><tei:date when="1918-08-26">August 26, 1918</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Highly revered Dr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
      >Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>I was delighted to receive your kind letter of <tei:date when="1918-02-27">February
     27</tei:date>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> especially because you have been
    able to continue your work in peace in spite of the internal conditions in <tei:rs type="place"
     key="entity-002506">Austria</tei:rs>. I was still at the front until the middle of July, most
    recently at Montdidier for three months; we even survived the offensive here with very few
    casualties. Then I was transferred to another troop, which is stationed in Lille: a sort of
    “pressure posting,” in view of my five children. Here I am at least able to make music and to
    work; a few of the violin virtuosos with whom I am on friendly terms also work here at the
    theater, and we often play string quartets in military hospitals and elsewhere. I am on duty
    only in the morning; occasionally I keep night watch.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>I have written a sonatina for violin and piano, and variations on a chorale for organ. But
    since I am permanently fit for war service, I fear that this splendid arrangement will not last
    very long. – I am already looking forward to visiting you in Vienna.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>The mood in Vienna will probably also change after the war if a firm and purposeful German
    politics <tei:supplied reason="illegible_word">is established</tei:supplied>. <tei:pb n="2"/>
    Here in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482">Germany</tei:rs> we would also like things to
    improve; there are just obligations for peace which I now think it is useless to quarrel about.
    The first task is to wear down the external enemy.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Do you know <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008291">Arnold Mendelssohn</tei:rs>? What do
    you think of his most recent works (a piano sonata and a string quartet, published by <tei:rs
     type="organization" key="entity-002422">Peters in Leipzig</tei:rs>)?<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> Have you read the book by <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000495"><tei:hi rend="underline">Kurth</tei:hi></tei:rs> (Bern) on
     <tei:title>Bach’s linear counterpoint</tei:title>?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
     type="footnote"/> Unfortunately, I could not obtain the book here.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>In the hope that you are healthy and eagerly at work, </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute>I remain, with my most cordial greetings</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your very devoted</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Dr. Reinhard
      Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>


  </tei:div>

 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
