<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2163" sdoID="OJ-15-16_98">OJ 15/16, [98]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HW" scope="major">Hans Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="minor">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2008</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-10-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006969">WeisseHa ~
        JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Hans Weisse to Jeanette Schenker, dated May 26,
        1935</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1935-05-26T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-01-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Weisse outlines a plan to give Jeanette financial support in the form of a
        collection from his most dedicated pupils, equivalent to 200 Austrian shillings per month,
        for a year, and encloses the first of three planned annual payments. — He inquires whether
        Schenker's notes on C. P. E. Bach’s Essay on the True Art of Playing Keyboard Instruments
        might be included in an Afterword to a projected English translation. — He plans an
        exposition of Schenkerian theory for use in schools, for which he needs to receive a copy of
        Der freie Satz. — He thanks Jeanette for mementos of her husband, and says a few words about
        his family and their summer plans.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>finanziell; financial; Lage; situation; Schüler; pupil; Beitrag; contribution;
        Betrag; sum; Kollekte; collection; Subskribent; subscriber; Inflation; Monatszahlung;
        monthly payment; Check; Sendung; money sent; Kommentar; commentary; Abschrift; copy;
        Übersetzung; translation; Exemplar; copy; Plan; Lehre; theory; theoretisch; theoretical;
        Fassung; formulation; Grundgedanke; basic principles; Tintenfass; inkwell; Blatt; sheet;
        Wortspiel; play on words; Schafblattern; chickenpox; Spital; hospital; Sommeradresse; summer
        address; Verlust; loss</dc:subject>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:fw type="envelope">
          <tei:note type="editorial"><tei:hi rend="bold">Envelope:</tei:hi>
          </tei:note><tei:lb/>
          <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="recto"/><tei:lb/>
          <tei:address>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#HW"/><tei:hi rend="underline">S. S.
              Bremen</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
          </tei:address>
          <tei:address>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied reason="clarity">An:</tei:supplied> Frau D<tei:hi
                rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi>. Heinrich Schenker</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine rend="indent-20">Keilgasse 8</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine rend="indent-40">Wien III.</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:hi rend="underline">Austria</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
          </tei:address>
          <tei:fw type="postmark">|| 1 WIEN 7 | 5.VI.35.11 | * 4a* ||</tei:fw><tei:lb/>
          <tei:add resp="JS"><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>beantw. 9. <tei:choice>
              <tei:sic>V.</tei:sic>
              <tei:corr>VI.</tei:corr>
            </tei:choice> 35</tei:add><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
          <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="verso"/><tei:lb/>
          <tei:address>
            <tei:addrLine rend="indent-30"><tei:supplied reason="clarity">Absender:</tei:supplied>
              <tei:handShift new="#HW"/>D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi>. Hans Weisse. 1 West
                64<tei:hi rend="supralinear">th</tei:hi>
              <tei:supplied reason="location">Street</tei:supplied> New York</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine>U.S.A.</tei:addrLine>

            <tei:fw type="postmark">|| New York (Rockefeller Center Sta.) N.Y. | MAY 28 1935 |
              REGISTERED ||</tei:fw>
            <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">x 2</tei:note>
            <tei:lb/>
            <tei:fw type="postmark">|| NEW YORK U.S.A. | 5 – 28 1935 | FOREIGN ||</tei:fw>
          </tei:address>
        </tei:fw><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold">Letter:</tei:hi>
        </tei:note><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:date when="1935-05-26">26. Mai,
          1935</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Liebe, verehrte, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Frau
          Lie-Lie</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p resp="first">Ihr Brief<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">This
          letter, a reply to Weisse's letter of February 21, <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-15-16_97">OJ 15/16, [97]</tei:ref>, is not known to survive. Evidently, in it
          Jeanette spoke of her financial difficulties, referred to Schenker's unpublished
          commentary on C. P. E. Bach's <tei:title level="m">Versuch</tei:title> (cf. footnote 2),
          perhaps indicated the likely date of publication of <tei:title level="m">Der freie
            Satz</tei:title>, and offered Schenker's inkwell and enclosed a sheet of paper with
          Schenker's handwriting, both in response to Weisse's request for a memento.</tei:note>
        stimmte mich sehr traurig, da er die Gedanken über Ihre finanzielle Lage, da ich mir schon
        öfters gemacht hatte, bestätigte. Ihre Äusserung, dass es heute keinen Verleger gebe, der
        Ihnen monatlich S. 200 geben wollte – rief nun in mir einen Gedanken wach, den ich sofort in
        Wirklichkeit umsetzte, und von dessen Resultat Ihnen dieser Brief Mitteilung machen
        soll.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Mein Gedanke war der: warum sollte es nicht mir unter Mithilfe meiner hiesigen Schüler
        möglich sein, Ihnen fürs erste, für <tei:hi rend="underline">ein Jahr</tei:hi> den Betrag
        von 2400 S. – (also monatlich 200 S.) sicherzustellen? Zum Prinzipe machte ich mir, nur an
        diejenigen meiner Schüler heranzutreten, die sich ganz des Wertes unseres geliebten,
        unersetzlichen <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>s bewusst sind.
        Meine Gedanken trügte mich nicht. Jeder einzelne folgte dem von mir gegebenen Beispiele,
        sich schriftlich zu einem monatlichen Beitrage zu verpflichten, und betrachtete die Tatsache
        meiner Aufforderung als eine Auszeichnung meinerseits. Die Kollekte von 22 Subskribenten
          <tei:pb n="2"/> ergab den gewünschten Betrag von 489 Dollar, die nach dem heutigen Stande
        den Betrag von 2400 Schillingen etwas übersteigen. — Die Gerüchte über eine etwaige
        Inflation veranlassten mich meinen Schüler<tei:supplied reason="syntax">n</tei:supplied>
        <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">zu veranlassen</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">nahezulegen</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>, gleich 4 Monatszahlungen auf einmal zu leisten. Manche zahlten den vollen
        Betrag, manche konnten fürs erste nur 2 Monate im Voraus bezahlen, die meisten aber <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">folgten</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">leisteten</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> meiner Bitte <tei:add place="interlinear-above">folgen</tei:add>. Ich habe nun
        einen Betrag von 182$ beisammen, dessen Gegenwert ich in Schillingen <tei:del
          rend="overstrike">ich</tei:del> von meiner Bank mittels Checks <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">Ihnen</tei:add> anweisen lasse und <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">den ich</tei:add> diesem Briefe beilege. Wenn der Betrag etwas
        mehr ausmacht als 4 x 200 Sch. so rührt das daher, dass eine Schülerin alles auf einmal,
        eine andere die Hälfte des gezeichneten Betrages erlegt haben. Meine Sendungen werden also
        nicht alle gleichmässig sein können. Ich werde es mir natürlich angelegen sein lassen, die
        Oktobersendung wieder für 2‒3 Monate durchzuführen, wenn es irgend geht, um Sie für den
        etwaigen Fall einer Inflation und einer weiteren Senkung des Dollars, nicht zu viel
        einbüssen zu lassen. Doch habe ich mir auf für diesen Fall noch 2 Schüler freigelassen, an
        die ich gegenwärtig <tei:add place="interlinear-above">noch</tei:add> nicht herangetreten
        bin, um durch deren etwaigen Beitrag den durch Inflation gekürzten Betrag wieder aufs
        Gleiche zu bringen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> Die Kollekte gilt von Juni 35 – Juni 36. Was nachher sein wird, kann
        ich im gegenwärtigen Augenblick <tei:add place="interlinear-above">nicht</tei:add>
        voraussagen. Auch werden Sie verstehen, dass es bei der Unsicherheit der Verhältnisse hier
        im Lande ein psychologischer Fehlgriff gewesen wäre, die Leute über die Dauer eines Jahres
        hinaus zu binden. — Doch hoffe ich, dass Sie Sich auf meine getreue Gesinnung und meinen
        guten Willen verlassen werden: ich werde auch dann zu tun trachten, was in meiner Macht
        steht.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich bin froh, den geschäftlichen Teil dieses Briefes hiemit erledigt zu haben. Ich bin
        sicherlich ein wenig schwerfällig gewesen und hoffe, dass Sie mir das nicht übel
        nehmen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Was den Kommentar zu <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000025">Ph. Em. Bach</tei:rs>’s
          <tei:term>Generalbass</tei:term> anlangt, wäre ich sehr interessiert ihn zu sehen und
        wüsste gerne ob Ihnen eine Abschrift davon zu viele Mühe machen würde.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">OJ 19/18 contains a "<tei:title
            level="m">Generalbasslehre</tei:title>. Prepared by Felix Salzer from a manuscript work
          by Schenker." One part of Salzer's work is described as a typewritten "Kommentar zum
          'Versuch.'" Presumably Jeanette, in a letter not now known to survive, has suggested this
          work in response to the request by Weisse in the penultimate paragraph of <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-15-16_97">OJ 15/16, [97]</tei:ref>.</tei:note> Ich sprach
        unlängst mit einem Musiker (Kirkpatrick),<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Possibly the American harpsichordist and Scarlatti scholar Ralph Kirkpatrick
          (1911‒83), who had recently returned from periods of study in Europe that included a
          year's tuition in harpsichord playing with Wanda Landowska and theory with Nadia
          Boulanger.</tei:note> der eine Übersetzung des „<tei:title>Versuch</tei:title>s“ ins
        Englische plant<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">An English
          translation of Bach's <tei:title level="m">Versuch</tei:title> seems to have been a
          priority for Schenker's adherents in America, though it was not realized until after World
          War II. William J. Mitchell's translation was published in New York by W. W. Norton in
          1949.</tei:note> und es fragt sich, ob nicht ein Kommentar des <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>s einen ganz besonders erwünschten Anhang hiezu
        (freilich auch in englischer Sprache) ergäbe. Der Mangel einer Übersetzung von <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs>s Büchern ins Englische wird hier schon
        in weiteren Kreisen bedauert. Es wird sicher dazu kommen müssen. — Ich hoffe Sie haben mich
        nach dem Erscheinen <tei:pb n="4"/> des „<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"
            ><tei:title>freien Satzes</tei:title></tei:rs>“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Whether by coincidence of not, the first print-run of
            <tei:title level="m">Der freie Satz</tei:title>, 505 copies, was released by Universal
          Edition on May 25, the day before this letter was written.</tei:note> nicht vergessen und
        den <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">Verlag</tei:rs> beauftragt mir eine
        Exemplar schicken zu lassen. Nicht nur brenne ich darauf, das Werk endlich zu sehen – ich
        kann meinen Plan eine Darstellung der Schenkerschen Lehre für den <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >Schul</tei:hi>gebrauch in englischer Sprache zu verfassen, nicht vornehmen und
        durchführen, ehe ich nicht die entscheidende theoretische Fassung der Grundgedanken in
        seiner eigenen Sprache gesehen und studiert habe.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Was Ihre gütige Absicht, mir des <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
          >Meister</tei:rs>s Tintenfass<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >In his letter of February 21, <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-15-16_97">OJ 15/16,
            [97]</tei:ref>, Weisse had asked for some object of Schenker's as a memento, and this is
          clearly what Jeanette has suggested in her reply.</tei:note> zuzudenken anlangt, so danke
        ich Ihnen aufs Innigste dafür – ebenso wie für das eingesandte Blatt <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above"><tei:del rend="overstrike">in</tei:del></tei:add> dessen
        Wortspiel — „erlauben – erleben“ – ich nur erfühlen konnte, ohne <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">dessen</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">jedoch den</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> letzten Sinn genau zu verstehn. Frau Jella Pessl Lobotka wird Sie <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">in meinem Auftrage</tei:add> aufsuchen und falls das Tintenfass
        nicht zu voluminös ist, es mir nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002873">New
          York</tei:rs> bringen. Wollen Sie es ihr also gütigst ausfolgen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wir haben mit unsern Kindern fürchterliches mitgemacht. Beide wurden operiert: <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-004676">Moni</tei:rs> am Mittelohr – <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-004675">Susi</tei:rs> an einem schweren Abzess – als Folge von Schafblattern.
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004676">Moni</tei:rs> ist noch nicht genesen. Sie liegt
        nun (zum 2. Mal) im Spital schon seit drei Wochen – und das Ärgste steht uns jetzt bevor:
        Wir werden aufs Land abreisen und sie hier im Spital lassen <tei:pb n="5"/> müssen. Wie
        lange – das wissen wir nicht. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000952">Hertha</tei:rs> wird
        sie erst von <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002873">New York</tei:rs> holen können, bis
        sie vollkommen hergestellt ist. Unser Sommeradresse wird die gleiche, wie im Vorjahr sein:
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003102">TENANTS-HARBOR</tei:rs>, MAINE. U.S.A. Wir
        beabsichtigen am <tei:date when="1935-05-29">29.<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
          >ten</tei:hi></tei:date> abzureisen. Ihre nächste Nachricht wird mich also dort
        erreichen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000952">Hertha</tei:rs> lässt sie aufs
        Innigste grüssen. Sie wissen liebste Frau, wie <tei:hi rend="underline">sehr</tei:hi> wir
        Ihrer gedenken, und wie sehr wir Ihren Verlust ermessen. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000952">Hertha</tei:rs> ist jetzt so sehr in Anspruch genommen, das sie im
        Augenblick nicht schreiben kann, doch wird sie Ihnen später sicherlich schreiben.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Nehmen Sie unser beider herzlichste Grüsse entgegen. Ich hoffe bald von
        Ihnen zu hören.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Ihr aufrichtiger</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person"><tei:hi
              rend="lateinschr">D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi> Hans
            Weisse</tei:hi>.</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:fw type="envelope">
          <tei:note type="editorial"><tei:hi rend="bold">Envelope:</tei:hi>
          </tei:note><tei:lb/>
          <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="recto"/><tei:lb/>
          <tei:address>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#HW"/><tei:hi rend="underline">S. S.
              Bremen</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
          </tei:address>
          <tei:address>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied reason="clarity">To:</tei:supplied> Mrs. Heinrich
              Schenker</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine rend="indent-20">Keilgasse 8</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine rend="indent-40">Vienna III</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:hi rend="underline">Austria</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
          </tei:address>
          <tei:fw type="postmark">|| 1 VIENNA 7 | 5.VI.35.11 | * 4a* ||</tei:fw><tei:lb/>
          <tei:add resp="JS"><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>answered <tei:choice>
              <tei:sic>May</tei:sic>
              <tei:corr>June</tei:corr>
            </tei:choice> 9, 1935</tei:add><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
          <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="verso"/><tei:lb/>
          <tei:address>
            <tei:addrLine rend="indent-30"><tei:supplied reason="clarity">From:</tei:supplied>
              <tei:handShift new="#HW"/>Dr. Hans Weisse. 1 West 64th <tei:supplied reason="location"
                >Street</tei:supplied> New York</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine>U.S.A.</tei:addrLine>

            <tei:fw type="postmark">|| New York (Rockefeller Center Sta.) N.Y. | MAY 28 1935 |
              REGISTERED ||</tei:fw>
            <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">x 2</tei:note>
            <tei:lb/>
            <tei:fw type="postmark">|| NEW YORK U.S.A. | 5 – 28 1935 | FOREIGN ||</tei:fw>
          </tei:address>
        </tei:fw><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold">Letter:</tei:hi>
        </tei:note><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:date when="1935-05-26">May 26,
          1935</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear, revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Mrs.
          Lie-Lie</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p resp="first">Your letter<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> made me feel
        very sad, since it confirmed the thoughts that had already occurred to me frequently about
        your financial situation. Your comment, that there is no publisher today who would give you
        200 shillings per month, soon awakened in me an idea that I immediately turned into a
        reality. This letter will communicate the result of it.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>My idea was the following: why should it not be possible, with the assistance of my
        pupils here, to secure for you, for <tei:hi rend="underline">one year</tei:hi> in the first
        instance, the sum of 2,400 shillings, i.e. 200 shillings per month? As a matter of
        principle, I approached only those pupils of mine who were thoroughly conscious of the worth
        of our beloved, irreplaceable <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">master</tei:rs>. My
        thoughts did not deceive me: every one of them followed the example I set, committing
        themselves in writing to a monthly contribution, and considered the fact of my proposal as a
        commendation of me. The collection from the twenty-two subscribers <tei:pb n="2"/> resulted
        in the desired sum of 489 dollars, which at the current exchange rate is somewhat higher
        than 2,400 shillings. — Murmurs about a possible inflation led me to suggest to my pupils
        that they come up with four months' payment immediately. Some paid the full amount; some
        could only pay the first two months initially; but most <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >were able to agree</tei:add> to my request. I now have a sum of $182 set aside, whose
        value in shillings I have had my bank make out <tei:add place="interlinear-above">to
          you</tei:add> in the form of checks and <tei:add place="interlinear-above">which
          I</tei:add> am enclosing with this letter. If the sum is somewhat more than 4 times 200
        shillings, that is because one female pupil paid the full amount at once, another paid half
        the sum indicated. The money that I send you will not, therefore, always be exactly the
        same. I will, of course, arrange to send you the next two or three months’ worth in October,
        if possible, so that you do not lose too much in the event of a further fall in the value of
        the dollar. But I have not <tei:add place="interlinear-above">so far</tei:add> approached
        two of my pupils; they have been excused from this round, so that their possible
        contribution <tei:supplied reason="clarity">at a later date</tei:supplied> might restore
        balance to the full in the event that inflation results in a shortfall.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> The collection will cover the period from June 1935 to June 1936. What
        happens after that is something I can<tei:add place="interlinear-above">not</tei:add> say at
        the present moment. You too will understand that, given the uncertainty of the financial
        situation here in this country, it would have been a psychological mistake to bind the
        people beyond the duration of one year. — And yet I hope that you will have faith in my
        conviction and goodwill: I will then strive once again to do what is in my power.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I am glad thus to have dispatched the business part of this letter. I have of course
        been a bit ponderous and hope that you do not take that amiss. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Concerning the commentary to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000025">C. P. E.
          Bach</tei:rs>'s <tei:term>thoroughbass</tei:term> theory, I would be very interested to
        see it and would like to know whether making a copy of it would give you too much
          trouble.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> I spoke recently with a musician
        by the name of Kirkpatrick,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> who is planning
        a translation of the <tei:title level="m">Versuch</tei:title> in English,<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> and I wondered whether a commentary from the
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">master</tei:rs> might not make a particularly
        desirable appendix to it (in English, of course). The lack of English translations of
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs>'s books is already being
        lamented in wider circles; something will surely have to be done about this. — I hope that,
        when <tei:pb n="4"/>
        <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title level="m">Free
          Composition</tei:title></tei:rs> appears,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/>
        you will not have forgotten to instruct the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408"
          >publishers</tei:rs> to have a copy sent to me. Not only am I burning to see the work at
        last, but I cannot carry out and realize my plan of writing an account of Schenkerian theory
        in the English language, for <tei:hi rend="underline">schools</tei:hi> use, until I have
        seen and studied the definitive theoretical formulation of the basic principles in the
        original language.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Regarding your kind intention of passing on to me the <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000632">master</tei:rs>'s inkwell,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06"
          type="footnote"/> I thank you from the bottom of my heart ‒ likewise the sheet of paper
        you sent me in which I could only sense the play on words "erlauben–erleben" without
        actually understanding its ultimate meaning. Mrs. Jella Pessl Lobotka will look you up
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">on my behalf</tei:add> and, in the event that the
        inkwell is not too large, bring it back to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002873">New
          York</tei:rs> for me. Please be so good as to entrust it to her. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>We have experienced the most frightening things concerning our children. Both were
        operated: <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004676">Moni</tei:rs> on her middle ear, <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-004675">Susi</tei:rs> on a difficult abcess resulting from
        chicken pox. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004676">Moni</tei:rs> has not yet recovered;
        she has been in the hospital (for the second time) for three weeks now, and the worst is now
        to come: we will be leaving for the country and will have to leave her in the hospital.
          <tei:pb n="5"/> For how long is something we do not know. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000952">Hertha</tei:rs> will not be able to collect her from <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002873">New York</tei:rs> until she is completely recovered. Our
        summer address remains the same: <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003102">TENANTS
          HARBOR</tei:rs>, MAINE, U. S. A. We plan to leave on the <tei:date when="1935-05-29"
          >29th</tei:date>, so your next communication will reach me there.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000952">Hertha</tei:rs> sends her most
        heartfelt greetings. You know, dearest lady, how <tei:hi rend="underline">very much</tei:hi>
        we think of you and how very much we imagine your loss. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000952">Hertha</tei:rs> is currently so occupied that, at this moment, she
        cannot write; but she will certainly write to you later.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Please accept the most cordial greetings from the two of us. I hope to
        hear from you soon</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Your faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Dr. Hans
            Weisse</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
