<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="547" sdoID="OJ-14-45_27">OJ 14/45, [27]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="MV" scope="sole">Moriz Violin's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2011</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-09-12" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002719">ViolinM ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM+V ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002718">ViolinM+V+F ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Moriz Violin to Heinrich Schenker, dated December 11, 1923 </dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1923-12-11T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2011-09-12</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Violin reports the conversion to a new, stable currency in Germany; Hamburg has
    been among the first cities to benefit from this, as a result of which he is somewhat better off
    and the prospects for the future appear brighter. He plans to come to Vienna for Christmas, if
    only for a few days; this will give him an opportunity to discuss arrangements for the
    distribution of copies of Der Tonwille to libraries and schools. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Umstellung; conversion; Goldmark; Kaufmannschaft; merchants; Plan; plan; Musiker;
    musician; Komponist; composer; </dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-40">Hamburg, <tei:date when="1923-12-11">11. Dez.
     23</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Liebster <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this
      letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/6, p. 2607, December 15, 1923: "Von Fl. (Br.):
      komme zu Weihnachten; befindet sich in besseren Verhältnissen; Herr X. wolle Wort halten;
      Müller-Hartmann komme mit." ("From Floriz (letter): will come at Christmas time; his situation
      is better; Mr. X. wants to keep to his word; Müller-Hartmann is coming along."). </tei:note>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Die Umstellung auf „Goldmark“ hat uns alle auf den Kopf gestellt. <tei:hi rend="underline">Heute</tei:hi> ist <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>
    bereits Oase in der Wüste <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Deutschland</tei:country></tei:rs>s. Ein Gefilde der Seligen, die da nur mit
    Pfennigen zu nehmen brauchen. Es dürfte teurer als in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> sein, billiger aber als im übrigen <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Deutschland</tei:country></tei:rs>. Die Kaufmannschaft hatte es verhältnismäßig,
    mit der beliebten Formel „Angebot u. Nachfrage“, leicht, dagegen die „freien“ Berufe in den
    letzten Wochen einen schweren Goldumstellungskampf. Ich habe ihn mit Erfolg bestanden u.
    verdiene mehr als sonst u. wertbeständig.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">In the fall of 1923, the Weimar Republic made a special effort to put an end to
     spiraling inflation. On November 16 it introduced a new currency, the "Rentenmark," to replace
     the virtually worthless currency that had been previously issued by the Reichsbank; this
     resulted in the stabilization of prices. Though not redeemable in gold, the value of the
     Rentenmark was pegged to that of gold bonds, which may explain why Violin refers to the new
     currency as "Goldmark." </tei:note>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich wollte Dir nicht früher schreiben, als bis ich Herrn <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Themming</tei:rs> gesprochen habe. Der ist natürlich bei
    seinem Versprechen geblieben. Nun handelt es sich Form u. Inhalt dem Plane zu geben u. er
    erwartet meine Vorschläge. Die habe ich ihm nur im <tei:hi rend="underline">Principe</tei:hi>
    vorgelegt u. mir vorbehalten mit Dir, Deinen Intentionen gemäß, alles zu fixieren.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Violin had secured the agreement of Max
     Temming to provide free copies of <tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title> to research
     libraries and university and conservatory music departments. Presumably Violin was intending to
     draw up, with Schenker's assistance and approval, a list of recipient institutions. </tei:note>
    Dazu bietet sich nicht besser Gelegenheit als mein Abstecher zu Weihnachten nach <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs>. Ich komme knapp zum „heiligen Abend“ nach
     <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> u. möchte gleich am ersten
    Weihnachtsfeiertag früh bei Euch erscheinen. Wie innig freue ich mich darauf. Da wollen wir
    alles bereden, will Dir nochmals dann sagen, daß ich nichts von <tei:rs key="entity-001753" type="work">Beethoven-Sonaten</tei:rs> erhielt, wie verhältnismäßig gut es uns geht u. s. w. u.
    s. w. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> Mich begleitet unser Nachbar u. Freund Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000619" type="person">Müller-Hartmann</tei:rs>, ein braver Musiker u. Komponist,
    als irgend einer in <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> u. vielleicht auch
    in manchen anderen Städten <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Deutschland</tei:country></tei:rs>s. Er will <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> kennen lernen. Im gewissen Sinne für mich keine angenehme Belastung,
    die ich mit Anstand auf ein Mindestmaß reduzieren werde. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Wir sind alle gesund, <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Bubi</tei:rs>
    u. <tei:rs key="entity-000911" type="person">Mädi</tei:rs> fleißige Schüler, <tei:rs key="entity-000911" type="person">Mädi</tei:rs> außerdem Klaviervirtuosin u. Lebenskünstlerin. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Wir grüßen Alle Euch inngest! </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Frohes, schönes Wiedersehen!!! </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Euer getreuer </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-40">Hamburg, <tei:date when="1923-12-11">December 11,
     1923</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dearest <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">The conversion to the "Goldmark" has turned everything for us upside down.
     <tei:hi rend="underline">This very day</tei:hi>
    <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> has become an oasis in the German
    desert. An Elysium in which the blessed need only to take pennies with them. Things may be more
    expensive than in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>, but they are cheaper
    than in the rest of <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Germany</tei:country></tei:rs>. The merchants with their popular expression
    "supply and demand" had a relatively easy <tei:supplied reason="clarity">transition</tei:supplied>; by contrast, the "free" professions had a difficult struggle with
    the currency conversion. I survived it successfully, and am earning more than usual, and money
    that will keep its value.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I did not want to write to you until I had spoken with Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Temming</tei:rs>. He has of course kept his promise. It is
    now a question of giving the plan form and content, and he awaits my suggestions. I have set
    these out only in <tei:hi rend="underline">principle</tei:hi>, and have left it to myself to fix
    everything with you, in accordance with your intentions.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> For this there will be no better opportunity than my short trip to <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs> at Christmas. I shall be coming to <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs> right on Christmas Eve, and I should like to
    appear at your place in the morning of the first Christmas holiday. How deeply I look forward to
    this. Then we can talk over everything; and I can tell you again that I didn't receive any of
    the <tei:rs key="entity-001753" type="work">Beethoven sonata volumes</tei:rs>, that we are
    relatively well off, and so on and so forth. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> I shall be accompanied by our neighbour and friend Mr <tei:rs key="entity-000619" type="person">Müller-Hartmann</tei:rs>, as fine a musician and composer as
    there is in <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> and probably in many other
    cities in <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Germany</tei:country></tei:rs>.
    He wants to get to know <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>. In a certain
    sense this will be no agreeable burden; but I shall reduce it to a minimum with decency. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">We are all well. My <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">little
     boy</tei:rs> and <tei:rs key="entity-000911" type="person">girl</tei:rs> are industrious
    pupils, the <tei:rs key="entity-000911" type="person">girl</tei:rs> in addition a piano virtuoso
    and someone who knows how to make the best of things. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">We send you all our most heartfelt greetings! </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Looking forward to a happy, beautiful reunion!!! </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your faithful </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>

 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>