<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3795" sdoID="OJ-13-10_118">OJ 13/10, [118]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2025</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated December 15, 1930</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1930-12-15T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-09-16</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel reports on the success of Hans Weisse’s lectures at the Prussian
        Ministry of Culture in Berlin, where he also met Moriz Violin and Anthony van Hoboken; the
        latter told him he did not want to bear the full cost of a new edition of the music of C. P.
        E. Bach. — Oppel will be giving a series of lectures on Schenker’s theory to a ladies’ club
        in Leipzig in the new year.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1930-12-15">15. XII.
            30</tei:date>. Leipzig</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Professor Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
            >Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for December 16, 1930: “Von
            Oppel (Br.): über Weisses Vortrag; macht ein + über v. H.; über seinen eigenen Vortrag
            im Conservatorium, in dem er auch mich zu propagiren gedenkt!” (“From Oppel (letter):
            concerning Weisse's lecture; he puts a cross above Hoboken; concerning his own lecture
            at the Conservatory, in which he also plans to propagandize for
          me!”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs>’s beide Vorträge<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">At the invitation of <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000431">Leo Kestenberg</tei:rs>, and on the recommendation of
          Wilhelm Furtwängler, Hans Weisse delivered two lectures on Schenker’s theory at the
          Prussian Ministry of Education in early December 1930.</tei:note> waren ausgezeichnet,
        inhaltlich u. formell klar. Die Beispiele waren sehr gut gewählt. Ich hatte grosse Freude
        und wirkliche Befriedigung. Schade war nur, dass beim 1. Vortrag so wenig Menschen da waren,
        die ganze musik. Facultät der Universität Berlin glänzte durch Abwesenheit. Aber das hatte
        ich von den Herren nicht anders erwartet<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">.</tei:supplied>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs> spielte mir am andern Tage noch
        die Bagatellen vor u. die 2st. Psalmen. Seine Kompositionsweise ist mir sehr sympathisch. –
        Leider konnte <tei:pb n="2"/> ich zur Discussion über den Contrapunktvortrag nicht
        dableiben, da ich Donnerstag früh schon wieder hier unterrichten musste. Es kommt ja bei
        solchen Disc. auch nie viel heraus, da die Gegner ja keine Ahnung vom Umfang u. Art des
        Stoffes haben. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Prof Violin</tei:rs> bestellte mir Ihre
        lieben Grüsse. Ich werde ihn in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002589">Hamburg</tei:rs>
        einmal aufsuchen. Van <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380"
          ><tei:sic>Hobocken</tei:sic></tei:rs> sprach von der <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000025">Ph. E. Bach</tei:rs>-Ausgabe:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot">A collected edition of the works of Carl Philipp Emanuel
          Bach, which was discussed intensively in 1930 by the committee overseeing the <tei:rs
            type="organization" key="entity-002452">Photogram Archive</tei:rs> at the <tei:rs
            type="organization" key="entity-002686">Austrian National Library</tei:rs>; it was
          eventually abandoned, in part because Schenker did not want to be saddled with heavy
          editorial responsibilities, in part because Hoboken was unwilling to finance the project
          fully.</tei:note> er allein könne die Kosten nicht tragen. Er hat gut reden und leben. Ein
        wirkliches Verantwortungsgefühl aus seinem Reichtum heraus der Kunst gegenüber <tei:pb n="3"
        /> hat er noch immer nicht, und wird es auch nie bekommen. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Jedenfalls aber ist <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs>s
        Schritt eine weitere Etappe zur Verbreitung Ihrer Lehre, und <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs> der berufener Vertreter, der seine Aufgabe glänzend
        gelöst hat.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Hans Weisse was to
          move to New York City the following year, where he taught at the Mannes Music School and
          Columbia University until his death in 1940, so transmitting Schenker’s theory to North
          America, and ultimately realizing Oppel’s prediction on an international scale.</tei:note>
        Langsam aber sicher wird die Wahrheit durchdringen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Im Januar und Februar halte ich hier 6 Vorlesungen, in denen ich Sie ordentlich
        propagieren werde. Es geschieht in einem Zirkel von Damen, die sonst nur
        Universitätsprofessoren über Litteratur, Malerei etc. reden lassen. <tei:del
          rend="overstrike">Allenfalls</tei:del> Höchstens einmal über <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000924">Wagner</tei:rs> sonst. Ich habe aber bei der Vorstandsdame
        durchgesetzt, dass auch einmal musiktheoretische Dinge behandelt werden. <tei:pb n="4"/>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000866">Straube</tei:rs>’s Frau wird auch teilnehmen, die
        wird sich dann ja manchmal wundern u. <tei:del rend="overstrike">I</tei:del> ihrem Mann
          berichten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Oppel gave his
          lectures between mid-January and February 17, 1931: see <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-13-10_121">OJ 13/10, [121]</tei:ref>, January 17, <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-13-10_122">[122]</tei:ref>, January 23, <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-13-10_123">[123]</tei:ref>, February 3, and <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-13-10_124">[124]</tei:ref>, February 19, 1931.</tei:note>
        – </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Mit herzl. Gruss Ihnen beiden !</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Ihr treuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-30"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1930-12-15">December 15,
              1930</tei:date>, Leipzig</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor
            Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs>’s two lectures<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> were outstanding, clear both in content and form.
        The examples were very well chosen; I took great pleasure and genuine satisfaction
          <tei:supplied reason="clarity">from them</tei:supplied>. It was just a pity that so few
        people attended the first lecture; the entire music faculty of the University of Berlin was
        conspicuous in its absence. But I had not expected otherwise of the gentlemen. The next day
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs> also played me his bagatelles
        and two-voice psalm settings. I find his compositional style very agreeable. –
        Unfortunately, <tei:pb n="2"/> I could not stay for the discussion of the lecture on
        counterpoint, since I had to teach here already on Thursday morning. But such discussions
        never produce much, since the opponents have no idea whatever of the nature and scope of the
        materials. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Prof Violin</tei:rs> conveyed your kind
        greetings to me. I shall look him up in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002589"
          >Hamburg</tei:rs> some time. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs>
        spoke about the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000025">C. P. E. Bach</tei:rs>
          edition:<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> he cannot bear the costs of it on
        his own. He speaks and lives well. A true sense of responsibility with respect to art, in
        consideration of his wealth, <tei:pb n="3"/> is something he still does not have, nor will
        he ever acquire it. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In any event, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs>’s effort
        represents a further stage in the dissemination of your theory, and <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs> is its desigated advocate, who has fulfilled his
        mission splendidly.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> Slowly but surely the
        truth will prevail.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In January and February, I shall give six lectures here in which I shall promote your
        work thoroughly. It will take place in a circle of ladies, who are usually addressed only by
        university professors about literature, painting, and the like. Or, in other instances,
        about <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000924">Wagner</tei:rs> at most. But I managed to
        persuade the chairlady that even matters of music theory should be discussed for once.
          <tei:pb n="4"/>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000866">Straube</tei:rs>’s wife will also be attending;
        she will then be in for a surprise and can report to her husband.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">With a cordial greeting to the two of you,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Your faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-30"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
