<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3091" sdoID="OJ-10-3_108">OJ 10/3, [108]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPoed" scope="major">Otto Erich Deutsch typist</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="OED" scope="minor">Otto Erich Deutsch's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2023</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IDB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2015-09-18" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002726">DeutschOE ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002712">DeutschOE ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002727">DeutschOE+H ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Typewritten letter from Deutsch to Schenker, dated October 7, 1929</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1929-10-07T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2023-03-17</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Deutsch gives a comprehensive analysis of the prospect of a publication
        devoted to the Photogram Archive: its content, its editorship, the frequency of its
        appearance, and the publishing houses who might be interested in taking it on. </dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000164">DeutschOE</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>PROF. OTTO ERICH DEUTSCH</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">WIEN II.</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Böcklinstraße 26</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Tel. R 45–6–72</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/><tei:date when="1929-10-07">7.
            Oktober 29</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber verehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Doktor</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for October 7, 1929: “Von Deutsch (Br.
            expreß): habe mit Haas einen neuen Vorschlag ausgeheckt: mehr
              <tei:sic>archivalisches</tei:sic>, bibliographisches Material – auch über Schenker
            theoretisierend einschränken!” (“From Deutsch (express letter): he has hatched a new
            plan with Haas: more archival, bibliographic material – also curtailing Schenkerian
            theorizing!”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>


      <tei:p rend="first">Verzeihen Sie, dass ich ihre beiden Briefe<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker’s diary records the sending of two letters to
          Deutsch (neither surviving), the first on October 2: “An Deutsch (Br.): Dank für die
          Zeichnung; vielleicht ein Ausweg möglich: einen Vorrat an den gewissen Aufsätzen sammeln
          u. dann erst die Mitteilungen herausgeben” (“To Deutsch (letter): thanks for the drawing;
          perhaps an expedient is possible: collect a supply of the essays that are certain, and
          only then publish the Communications <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of the Photogram
            Archive</tei:supplied>”). For the second, sent on October 4, Schenker indicates that he
          is essentially repeating what he had written to Vrieslander earlier that day: “An
          Vrieslander (Br.): empfehle die Revisionen etwas in den Hintergrund treten zu lassen, um
          anderen einfacheren Aufsätze Platz zu machen – nur fragt sich, wie Hoboken u. Nagel sich
          dazu stellen. An Deutsch (Br.): das selbe” (“To Vrieslander (letter): I recommend letting
          the <tei:supplied reason="clarity">textual</tei:supplied> revisions recede somewhat into
          the background, in order to make room for other, simpler essays – it is only a question of
          how Hoboken and Nagel feel about this. To Deutsch (letter): the same”).</tei:note>
        zusammen und erst heute beantworte; es geschieht noch rechtzeitig. Ich war vorige Woche sehr
        für <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs> beschäftigt und wollte auch
        noch einmal mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000320">Haas</tei:rs> sprechen, was erst
        heute möglich war. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ihr erster Brief: Ich glaube freilich, dass man noch warten könnte, bis
        Sie mehr Arbeiten dieser Art beisammen hätten. Aber ich glaube nicht, dass es für ein
          Jahrbuch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">That is, a “yearbook”
          associated with the Photogram Archive.</tei:note> nötig ist zu warten. Denn darin kann
        jeder Autor nur mit einer Arbeit vertreten sein. Fünf grosse Beiträge genügen, und davon
        werden noch nur zwei <tei:del rend="overstrike">Analysen</tei:del> Textrevisionen Ihrer Art
        sein können. Ich meine, dass daneben jetzt oder später einfach philologische Arbeiten (auch
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">als</tei:del> Textrevisionen) erscheinen könnten. Sie werden
        nicht so vollkommen sein, wie Ihre Arbeiten oder die von Ihnen verbesserten Leistung Ihrer
        Schüler, aber doch im Sinne des <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452"
          >Archiv</tei:rs>s wirken können. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> Dazu kämen, wie ich schon erwähnte, am besten ein
        Rechenschaftsbericht des <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archiv</tei:rs>s
        (nicht nur Listen seiner Arbeit), Verzeichnisse aus Handschriften-Sammlungen,
        Handschriften-Verzeichnisse nach Meistern geordnet (etwa: Die <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000612">Mozart</tei:rs>-Autographe), Nachlass-Verzeichnisse (aus dem Besitz
        der Meister), vielleicht auch Ergebnisse aus der Bibliothek <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000380">v. H.</tei:rs> (Drucke). Das Jahrbuch – oder die Zeitschrift, wohl nur
        ein Vierteljahrsschrift – wird nach dem ersten Erscheinen viel Angebote erhalten, die von
        der Redaktion (Kuratorium) gesiebt werden müssten. Aber es wird auch darunter Brauchbares
        sein und das <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archiv</tei:rs> wird für junge
        Kräfte eine grössere Anziehung haben, wenn sie Aussicht haben, ihre Arbeiten darüber zu
        veröffentlichen. Ich meine, dass die Publikation nicht von Ihren Schülern allein bestritten
        werden soll, auch bei den Textrevisionen. Durch die Qualität der Arbeiten aus Ihrer Schule
        aber wird sie von selbst eine Propagandaschrift für Schenker werden. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="3"/> Damit habe ich auch schon ausgesprochen, dass ich es nicht
        für gut, ja nicht für möglich halte, das objektive und halbstaatliche Unternehmen des
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archiv</tei:rs>s mit einer Zeitschrift in
        Verbindung zu bringen, wie Sie Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
          >Weisse</tei:rs> vor zwei Jahren im Sinne hatte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04"
          type="editorial" place="foot">In 1927 Hans Weisse proposed the establishment of a
          periodical devoted to the pursuit of Schenker’s methods of analysis, edited by his pupils
          and with contributions largely drawn from their work. This came to nothing; but after
          Schenker’s death two of his pupils, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000754">Felix
            Salzer</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000412">Oswald Jonas</tei:rs>,
          collaborated on such a publication, <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-006065"><tei:title
              level="j">Der Dreiklang</tei:title></tei:rs>. </tei:note> In einer Publikation des
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archiv</tei:rs>s kann keine Arbeit über
        Sie erscheinen. Aber auch kein Aufsatz allgemeiner Art, wie Sie <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">ihn</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">solche</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> vorbehalten wollten. Ich
        halte es auch für ausgeschlossen, dass Vrieslander die Redaktion führt. Nicht nur wegen der
        Schwierigkeiten aus seinem jetzigen Verhältnis zu <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380"
          >H.</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">The relationship
          between the two men was strained; Hoboken accused Vrieslander of swindling him in the
          purchase of material from the antiquarian music dealer Walter Höckner in Zwenkau
          (Leipzig).</tei:note> sondern weil der Redakteur in Wien sitzen muss, wenn schon der
        Verlag nicht hier ist. Als solcher käme <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005090"
          >Filser</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Benno Oskar
          Alfred Filser (1887–1939) owned and ran a music publishing house in Augsburg, with
          branches in Cologne and Vienna.</tei:note>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">cued from lower margin:</tei:note>
        <tei:handShift new="#OED"/>oder Strache (Wien–Warnsdorf, mit eigener Druckerei)<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">Robert Strache (1875–1943), music
          publisher in Warnsdorf (now Varnsdorf in the Czech Republic) and Vienna. He inherited the
          business from his father Eduard Strache, who was a member of the Austrian Parliament
          (1885–86) and the mayor of Warnsdorf (1901–05).</tei:note>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end cue</tei:note>
        <tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/>eher als der junge Nagel in Betracht, dessen Sammlung vorläufig
        eigentlich nichts mit dem <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archiv</tei:rs> zu
        tun hat und also keinen besonderen Anreiz für <tei:del rend="overstrike">die</tei:del> seine
        Publikation bietet. Die Redaktion könnte <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000320"
          >Haas</tei:rs> etwa führen, der m. E. dafür besonders honoriert werden müsste. Er ist aber
        nicht darauf erpicht. Natürlich wäre es, wenn ein Herr des Kuratoriums die Redaktion führte,
        und er ist am besten dazu geeignet. Die Arbeit wird wegen des zu erwartenden {<tei:pb n="4"/> Einlaufs
        nicht gering sein. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Persönlich möchte ich noch bemerken, dass mir jede Möglichkeit, <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> zu helfen, willkommen wäre, dass
        ich aber in diesem Rahmen keine sehe. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000320">Haas</tei:rs> glaubt, dass ein
        Jahrbuch die beste und würdigste Form der <tei:sic>Piblikation</tei:sic> wäre. Mir wäre eine
          <tei:sic>Viertelsjahrschrift</tei:sic> auch gut erschienen, die ja öfters an das <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archiv</tei:rs> erinnerte. Aber sie dürfte etwa
        doppelt so viel kosten in der Herstellung. Das erste Jahrbuch könnte m. E. in zwei Monaten
        druckreif gemacht werden können. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Bitte, nehmen Sie es mir nicht übel, dass ich an die Möglichkeit denke,
        auch von dritten Leuten Textrevisionen zu bringen. Ihre Leistung und die nur mit Ihrer Hilfe
        von den Schülern zu bewältigenden Arbeiten können bei der Fülle des Materials <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/>im <tei:rs type="organization"
            key="entity-002452">Archiv</tei:rs></tei:add>
        <tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/>nicht zur Bestreitung der Publikation ausreichen. Und in jedem
        Sammelwerke sind Arbeiten verschiedenen Rangs enthalten. Das dabei kein Unsinn unterläuft,
        wird Sache des Redakteurs sein. Dies meine offene und uneigennützige Meinung. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Mit schönen Grüssen von Haus zu Haus</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr ganz ergebener</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/><tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000164">O E Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>PROF. OTTO ERICH DEUTSCH</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">VIENNA II</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Böcklinstraße 26</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>tel. R 45–6–72</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/><tei:date when="1929-10-07"
            >October 7, 1929</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear revered Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
            type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>


      <tei:p rend="first">Forgive me for answering your two letters<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> together, and only today; I am still doing so in good time. Last week I
        was very occupied with things for <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs>
        and also wanted to speak once more with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000320"
          >Haas</tei:rs>, which was not possible until today.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Your first letter: Of course I believe that we can wait until you would
        have more pieces of work of this sort. But I do not believe that, for a yearbook,<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> it is necessary to wait. Five substantial
        contributions are sufficient, and of these only two have to be textual revisions of your
        kind. What I mean is that, alongside these, now or later, simply philological studies (also
        textual revisions) could appear. They will not be as thorough as your studies, or your
        pupils’ achievements with your emendations; but they could nonetheless be effective, in the
        spirit of the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archive</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> To this would ideally come, as I already mentioned, a full
        report about the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archive</tei:rs> (not
        merely lists of its work), catalogs from manuscript collections, catalogs of manuscripts
        arranged by composer (for example, the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000612"
          >Mozart</tei:rs> autographs), inventory catalogs (of items in possession of the masters),
        perhaps even results from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs>’s
        library (printed editions). The yearbook – or perhaps just a quarterly journal – will
        receive many offers after its first issue appears, which will have to be sieved by the
        editorial committee (the Board of Directors). But there will be useful things among them,
        and the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archive</tei:rs> will have a greater
        attraction to younger forces if they have the prospect of publishing their studies about it.
        What I am saying is that the publication will not be provided by your pupils alone, even
        those concerned with textual revisions. But from the quality of the studies from your
        circle, it will automatically become an organ of propaganda for Schenker.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="3"/> In addition, I have already thus declared that I do not
        regard it as a good thing, or even a possibility, to bring the objective and partly
        state-sponsored undertaking of the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452"
          >Archive</tei:rs> into a relationship with a journal of the sort that Mr. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs> suggested to you two years ago.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> In a publication of the <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archive</tei:rs>, there is no place for a study
        about yourself. But also no essay of a general nature, of the sort that you wished to
        reserve for <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>. I also regard it
        as out of the question for <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> to
        lead the editing. Not only because of the difficulties of his current relationship to
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05"
          type="footnote"/> but because the editor must reside in Vienna, even if the publishers are
        not located here. As such, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005090">Filser</tei:rs><tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">cued from lower margin:</tei:note>
        <tei:handShift new="#OED"/>or Strache (in Vienna and Warnsdorf, with its own
          printing-house<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end cue</tei:note>
        <tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/>should be considered in preference to the young Nagel, whose
        collection at present actually has nothing to do with the <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002452">Archive</tei:rs> and thus offers no special incentive for its
        publication. The editing could perhaps be led by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000320"
          >Haas</tei:rs>, who, in my opinion, would have to be given a special fee for it. But he is
        not keen to take it on. It would be natural for a member of the Board of Trustees to lead
        the editing, and he is best suited for the task. On account of the intake that may be
        expected, <tei:pb n="4"/> the work will not be inconsiderable.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">On a personal note, I would also like to remark that I would welcome any
        possibility of helping Vrieslander, but that I do not see any in this framework.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000320">Haas</tei:rs> believes that a
        yearbook would be the best, most dignified form of publication. For me, a quarterly
        publication would also look well, as it would indeed remind one of the <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archive</tei:rs> often. But that might cost about
        twice as much in the production. The first yearbook could, in my view, be ready to go to
        press in two months. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Please do not take it amiss that I am thinking of the possibility of
        including textual revisions from third parties. Considering the richness of the material
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/>in the <tei:rs
            type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archive</tei:rs></tei:add>, <tei:handShift
          new="#TPoed"/>your achievement and those of your pupils, which can be managed only with
        your help, will not suffice to fill the publication. And every collective publication will
        contain studies of varying quality. That no nonsense should creep in will be a matter for
        the editor. This is my candid, unselfish opinion.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">With best greetings from our house to yours,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your wholly devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/><tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000164">O. E. Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
