<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3776" sdoID="OJ-13-10_101">OJ 13/10, [101]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="TLJ">
      <tei:persName>Timothy L. Jackson</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2010</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2010</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated March 17, 1930</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1930-03-17T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-09-04</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel sends Schenker a book by Ricarda Huch, in gratitude for Schenker’s
        corrections of his arrangements of two Handel cantatas.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/>Leipzig. <tei:date when="1930-03-17">17. III.
              1930</tei:date>.</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Professor Schenker</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
            >Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenkers diary for March 19, 1930: “Von Oppel:
            Ricarda Huch „<tei:title>Der Sinn der heiligen Schrift</tei:title>“ als Geschenk für
            meine Mühe um seine Kantaten; Brief privaten Inhalts, auch über den Young-Plan usw.”
            (“From Oppel: Ricarda Huch's <tei:title level="m">Der Sinn der heiligen
              Schrift</tei:title> as a gift for the trouble I took over his cantatas; letter with
            personal content, also concerning the Young Plan, etc.”) — Paragraph-breaks are
            editorial, guided by emdashes in the original text.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>heute schicke ich als Drucksache das Buch von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005245"
          >Ricarda Huch</tei:rs>: „<tei:title>der Sinn der Heiligen Schrift</tei:title>“
          ab.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"
              ><tei:bibl><tei:author>Ricarda Huch</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Der Sinn der
              Heiligen Schrift</tei:title> (Leipzig: Insel-Verlag, 1919)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note>
        Bitte, nehmen Sie es als kleines äusseres Zeichen meiner Dankbarkeit hin für die viele
        Mühewaltung und liebevolle Korrectur der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000329"
          >Händel</tei:rs>kantaten. Es wird Ihnen Freude bereiten, u. hat den Vorzug, dass man es
        auch in einzelnen Kapiteln geniessen kann. Manche Gedankenreihen decken sich durchaus mit
        den Ihren. Und <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Ihre liebe Frau</tei:rs> liest
        Ihnen sicher gern manches <tei:pb n="2"/> daraus vor. Ich lese den <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-004801">Jungen</tei:rs> manchmal einzelne Kapitel vor, sie sollten so was in
        den Oberklassen im Religionsunterricht lesen. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich hoffe, es geht Ihnen beiden gut. Hier wird es langsam Frühling aussen, innen drückt
        die Annahme des Youngplans die ernsten Gemüter.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot">A plan devised by the American industrialist Owen D. Young
          (1874–1962) which cut Germany’s war reparations debt by two thirds and extended the
          country’s time to repay it.</tei:note> Unser Leidensweg in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002482">Deutschland</tei:rs> wird damit noch schärfer. Aber sie kriegen uns
        doch nicht unter. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> wird am Donnerstag fertig.
        Ich freue mich für ihn, und er freut sich auf die Arbeit in der Werft. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich lese gerade eine Arbeit über etruskische Kunst, sehr interessant, <tei:pb n="3"/>
        obgleich sie mir keine Aufschlüsse über die Sprache der Etrusker gab, ein dunkles Kapitel.
        Ferner ein Buch von Feldhaus über Leonardo da Vinci als Techniker,<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Franz Maria
              Feldhaus</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Leonardo, der Techniker und
              Erfinder</tei:title> (Jena: E. Diederichs, 1913)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> er ist doch
        der grösste Geist der Renaissance gewesen. Es gibt kaum ein technisches Problem, das er
        nicht schon angefasst hätte. Leider sind die in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002586"
          >England</tei:rs> befindlichen Teile seines Nachlasses noch immer nicht veröffentlicht. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Heute abend hörte ich im <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002479">Leipz.</tei:rs>
        Tonkünstler-Verein einen Vortrag über naturreine Stimmung mit Vorführung an dem Harmonium
        aus Oettingers Nachlass, mit 53 Zwischenstufen i. d. Octave!!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Also known as the Orthonophonium. The division of the octave
          into 53 equal parts, which accommodates both Pythagorian tuning (by fifths) and just
          intonation (based on the overtone series), had been known about since antiquity; it was
          developed further in the 17th century by the German mathematician Nicholas Mercator and
          the English music theorist William Holder.</tei:note> Ob <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000027">Bach</tei:rs> nicht doch die besseren Ohren hatte, als er zum
          temp<tei:supplied reason="abbreviation">erierten</tei:supplied> System überging?! <tei:pb
          n="4"/> Ich betrachte das nur als einen Rückfall. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun lassen Sie die Frühlingssonne ordentlich auf sich wirken und machen Sie wirklich
        Osterferien, die Sie nach der strengen Winterarbeit ehrlich verdient haben! </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="entity-10">Mit den herzlichsten Grüssen </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">an Sie beide</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Ihr dankbarer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-30"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/>Leipzig. <tei:date when="1930-03-17">March 17,
              1930</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor
            Schenker</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Today I send you as printed matter the book by <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-005245">Ricarda Huch</tei:rs>, <tei:title level="m">The Meaning of the Holy
          Scripture</tei:title>;<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> please accept it as a
        small outward sign of my gratitude for the laborious and loving correction of the <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000329">Handel</tei:rs> cantatas. It will give you pleasure and
        has the advantage that one can enjoy it also in individual chapters. Many of the modes of
        thinking throughout harmonize with yours. And <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">your
          dear wife</tei:rs> will surely gladly read much from it to you. <tei:pb n="2"/> I often
        read individual chapters to the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801">boys</tei:rs>;
        they should read something like this in the upper classes in religious education. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I hope that you are both doing well. Here, outside, it is slowly becoming spring; on
        the inside, the adoption of the Young Plan<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/>
        oppresses us. On its account, our painful path in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482"
          >Germany</tei:rs> will become yet more difficult. But through it, they will not drive us
        under. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000644">Ulrich will be finished on Thursday. I am
          happy for him, and he is happy with the work at the shipyard. –</tei:rs>
      </tei:p>

      <tei:p>I am now reading a work about Etruscan art, very interesting, <tei:pb n="3"/> although
        it gives me no insight into the language of the Etruscans, a mysterious subject. Further, a
        book by Feldhaus about Leonardo da Vinci as technician;<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
          type="footnote"/> he was, after all, the greatest spirit of the Renaissance. There is
        hardly a technical problem that had not already engaged him. Unfortunately, those parts of
        his legacy that survive in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002586">England</tei:rs> are
        still not yet published.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>This evening in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002479">Leipzig</tei:rs> at the
        Society of Composers, I heard a lecture about natural pure tuning, demonstrated on a
        harmonium from Oettinger's collection, with 53 tones to the octave!!<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> Did not <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000027"
          >Bach</tei:rs> still have the better ears when he switched to the tempered system?!
          <tei:pb n="4"/> I considered this just as a relapse. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Now, let the spring sun truly shine upon you and take the real Easter vacation that you
        have honorably earned after hard work through the winter!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="entity-10">With the most cordial greetings </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">to you both, </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Your grateful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-30"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
