<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2886" sdoID="OJ-15-6_10">OJ 15/6, [10]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="FW" scope="sole">Fritz Wahle's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2022</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2011-09-23" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008359">WahleF ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Fritz Wahle to Schenker, dated July 26, 1912</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1912-07-26T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2022-10-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Fritz Wahle thanks Schenker profusely for sending him his book on Beethoven’s
        Ninth Symphony, which he will read through quickly. He has acquired a copy of the score of
        the work.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000925">WahleF</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address rend="indent-60">
          <tei:addrLine><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002339">Ischl</tei:rs> Concordiastr.
            1</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:date when="1912-07-26">26./7 1912</tei:date>.</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Deine <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001731"
          ><tei:title>9.</tei:title></tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
          place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Heinrich Schenker</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m"
              >Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie</tei:title> (Vienna: Universal Edition, 1912)</tei:bibl>,
          released on July 2, 1912.</tei:note> habe ich erhalten und danke Dir vielmals für Deine
        Aufmerksamkeit. Es erfüllt mich jedesmal mit Stolz und Freude, wenn Du mir Deine Arbeiten
          widmest,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">widmest: presumably
          Schenker has penned an inscription to Wahle at the front of the volume.</tei:note> indem
        ich dies für die Ausdruck Deiner Gesinnung nehme, die mich würdig und fähig hält, Deine
        ernsten Wege zu gehen, die Ziele, Resultate zu verstehen, schließlich bei mir ein dem Deinen
        ähnliches Streben <tei:sic>vorraussetzt</tei:sic>, die heilige Wahrheit der Kunst ganz zu
        verstehen und hoch zu halten. Ich habe mich auch sehr über Dich gefreut, über den
        großartigen Fleiß <tei:sic>nemlich</tei:sic>, mit dem Du Dein Werk bis zu diesem Umfange
        ausgearbeitet hast, dies Alles mitten im Kampfe ums liebe Brod, die Dir begreiflicher Weise
        verdrießlicher ist als dem gewöhnlichen Stundengeber. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Dass Du durch das <tei:del rend="overstrike">eigene</tei:del>
        Bewusstsein, ein würdiges, Deinen idealen Anschauungen der Kunst entsprechendes Werk zu
        vollbringen in Deiner Arbeit gestärkt, gekräftigt wagst ist selbstverständlich, der erste
        Künstler kann eben kein anderes Ziel als für die Kunst zu leben. Du wirst mich nicht
          <tei:sic>verächtigen</tei:sic>, dass ich Dir einen „schönen Brief“ schreiben wollte. Ich
        habe Dir meine aufrichtigste Ueberzeugung mitteilen wollen; dass diese ausgefallen ist,
        liegt in der Schwierigkeit des Ausdruckes. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Sachlich kann ich nicht sein. Ich habe die Einleitung gelesen<tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> in der der heilige Eifer vor Allem überzeugend
        wirkt, wie in Deinen anderen Schriften. Nun habe ich auch die Partitur aus Wien bekommen,
        werde Dein Werk <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">auf</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">in</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> einem <tei:pb n="3"/> Zuge durchlesen in der Ueberzeugung zu lernen, soweit zu
        werden durch den Hinweis auf das Schöne, durch Deine Kraft, Tüchtigkeit mit der Du diese
        edle Arbeit vollbracht hast. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Also nochmals besten Dank, Grüße von mir, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000926"
          >Richard</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Dein</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000925">Fritz
          Wahle</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address rend="indent-60">
          <tei:addrLine><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002339">Ischl</tei:rs> Concordiastrasse
            1</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:date when="1912-07-26">July 26, 1912</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>I received your <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001731"><tei:title level="m"
            >Ninth</tei:title></tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> and offer
        you many thanks for your kindness. I am filled with pride and joy every time you
          dedicate<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> your works to me, as I regard
        this as the expression of your sentiment that regards me as worthy and capable of going
        along your serious paths, of understanding the goals and results, which in the end
        presupposes in me a pursuit, similar to yours, of understanding completely and holding aloft
        the sacred truth of art. I have also been greatly cheered for your sake, namely for the
        magnificent industry with which you have developed your work to this magnitude, all this in
        the midst of the struggle for one’s daily bread, which for you is understandably more vexing
        than for the usual giver of lessons.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> That you dare, through the consciousness of having been strengthened in
        your work by bringing to fruition a work that corresponds to your ideal perspective of art,
        is something that does not need to be mentioned; the foremost artist can have no other goal
        but to live for the sake of art. You will not despise me for wanting to write you a
        “beautiful letter.” I wanted to communicate my sincerest convictions to you; that I have
        been unsuccessful is a result of the difficulty of expression.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I am unable to be objective. I have read the introduction in which the sacred zeal
        stands out above everything, as in your other writings. I have now received the score from
        Vienna, too, and will read through your work at a stroke, <tei:pb n="3"/> convinced that I
        shall learn, at least to become <tei:supplied reason="clarity">educated</tei:supplied> by
        being pointed towards what is beautiful by the strength and virtue with which you have
        accomplished this noble work.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>And so, once more, my best thanks, greetings from me, and from <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000926">Richard</tei:rs>. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000925">Fritz
          Wahle</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
