<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3940" sdoID="OJ-13-10_152">OJ 13/10, [152]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="TLJ">
      <tei:persName>Timothy L. Jackson</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2026</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2026</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2026</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated July 20, 1932</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1932-07-20T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2026-02-23</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel comments on an article by Chrysander about Handel’s Messiah and Jephtha.
        – His students will be performing Hans Weisse’s Octet, and he reports on performance
        prospects for his own compositions. – He has been reading all of Schenker’s articles in Die
        Zukunft between 1892 and 1897 and observing their clarity of thought and language, admiring
        particularly the articles on Smetana and Bruckner.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:placeName>Leipzig</tei:placeName>, <tei:date
              when="1932-07-20">20. 7. 32</tei:date>. Könneritzstr 58<tei:hi rend="supralinear">III
              l</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Professor Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
            >Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for July 22, 1932: “Von Oppel
            (Br.): über meine Aufsätze in der „Zukunft[“]; noch einmal zu Händel, Fuge Gmoll; hofft
            im nächsten Jahr auf ein Wiedersehen; bestellt Vrieslanders Lieder!!!” (“From Oppel
            (letter): concerning my articles in <tei:title level="j">Die Zukunft</tei:title>; once
            again, mentions Handel’s Fugue in G minor; hopes to see me again next year; orders
            Vrieslander’s songs!!!”). — Schenker’s most recent articles had been <tei:title
              level="a">Gedanken über Kultur, Kunst und Musik,</tei:title>
            <tei:title level="j">Der Kunstwart</tei:title>, 44 (January 1931), 222–30, and
              <tei:title level="a">Ein verschollener Brief von Mozart und das Geheimnis seines
              Schaffens,</tei:title>
            <tei:title level="j">Der Kunstwart</tei:title>, 44 (July 1931), 660–66. – Schenker
            published eighteen articles in <tei:title level="j">Der Kunstwart</tei:title> between
            1892 and 1897.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005266">Meine Frau</tei:rs> und ich danken herzlich
        für die Gluckwünsche zu <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008535">Bepos
          Schwesterchen</tei:rs>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing
          of these congratulations is not recorded in Schenker’s diary.</tei:note> Es ist an <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000644"><tei:hi rend="underline">Ulrich</tei:hi></tei:rs>’s
        Geburtstag erschienen, Sie haben das verwechselt. Es geht allen gut. Nur meine älteste
        Tochter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008525">Ingeborg</tei:rs> hat eine periodische
        Lebersache, die nach Aussage des Artztes 7 Jahre dauert. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> ist gestern in die See gestochen nach Schweden und
        Finnland. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003957">Walter</tei:rs> plagt sich im Geschäft,
        wie es einem brasen Lehrling geziemt. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008523"
          >Bepo</tei:rs> entwickelt sich prächtig. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Vielen Dank für den Hinweis auf <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000130"
          >Chrysander</tei:rs>’s Aufsatz i.<tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002566"><tei:title>d.
            Zukunft</tei:title></tei:rs>; er bezieht sich auf <tei:rs type="composition"
          key="entity-005626"><tei:title>Messias</tei:title></tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="composition"
          key="entity-004889"><tei:title>Jephta</tei:title></tei:rs>; aber Sie haben recht, seine
        Beweisführungen sind nicht stichhaltig. Zu dem Thema <tei:add place="interlinear-above">in
          g-moll</tei:add> (siehe Notenbeilage)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
          place="foot">The page with the music examples does not survive.</tei:note> glaube ich
        jetzt, dass <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000329">Händel</tei:rs> durch die Flötensonate
        darauf gekommen ist, die ursprüngliche <tei:term>Bassauswickelung</tei:term> des
          <tei:term>Quartzug</tei:term>s als Oberstimme zu nehmen. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002334">Tirol</tei:rs> werde ich teuer sehr vermissen, aber die Finanzen
        verlangen Achtung. Ich hoffe, dass Sie in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002380"
          >Igls</tei:rs> eine gründliche Erholung finden von den Winterstrapazen. Im nächsten Jahre
        werde ich bei Zeiten sparen, um <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002334">Tirol</tei:rs> und
        ein Wiedersehn zu ermöglichen. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Auf das Oktett v. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs> bin ich
        sehr gespannt. Im letzten Vortragsabend des <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002872"
          >Konserv.</tei:rs> stieg noch mein neues Oboenquartett, der eingeladene Specialverleger
        erschien aber nicht, dankte bis heute nicht einmal für meine persönliche Einladung. Mit der
        Messe in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002495">Frankfurt</tei:rs> habe ich auch wieder
        Pech: dem Dirigenten u. dem Vorsitzenden des Vereins gefiel sie sehr; aber der Graf
        Hardenberg, der das Konzert finanziert <tei:pb n="2"/> bewilligte dem <tei:hi
          rend="underline">Schweizer</tei:hi> Komponisten Kelterborn, der eine Dichtung des Grafen
          „<tei:title>Vater unser</tei:title>“ vertont hat, den ganzen Abend den dieser
          verlangte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Das grosse
            <tei:title level="m">Vater Unser</tei:title> (The Great Lord’s Prayer), cantata for
          soloists, choir, organ, eleven wind instruments, and percussion; a setting of a text of
          Kuno von Hardenberg by the Swiss composer Louis Kelterborn (1891–1933). A piano-vocal
          reduction was published around 1920.</tei:note> So müssen wir Deutsche zurückstehn, damit
        ein deutscher Graf mit s. Gelde Ausländer unterstützt! – </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>s neue Sachen habe ich
        mir bestellt. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Die Politik wird immer trostloser: heute abend Ausnahmezustand für <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>; es wird bis zur Reichstagswahl am <tei:date
          when="1932-07-31">31.</tei:date> noch einige Tote geben. Die kommunistische Gesindel
        bekommt von <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002568">Russland</tei:rs> zu viel materielle
        und moralische Unterstützung! Da hilft nur eisernes Zugreifen, zu dem die Regierung nun
        endlich entschlossen scheint. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Am <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002872">Konserv.</tei:rs> ist noch immer
        unentschieden, ob <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000659">Pauer</tei:rs> wiederkommt. Im
        Grunde fehlt auch da ein eiserner Besen, denn das geistige Niveau der Anstalt ist auf einem
        Tiefpunkt angelangt, der bald nicht mehr zu überbieten ist. Alles ist nur auf
        Virtuosenbetrieb- u. – Ausbildung eingestellt, jeder lächerlichen Mode wird gehuldigt
        anstatt in jahrlanger, stiller Arbeit gesunde, kräftige Fruchte heranreifen zu lassen. Mich
        ekeln der Betrieb und die Intriguen schon lange an, aber als Familienvater darf man sich
        heute keine Experimente leisten. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Eine wahre Freude waren mir jetzt die beiden letzten Tage, da ich auf der Bibliothek
        Ihre Aufsätze in <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002566"><tei:title>der
            „Zukunft“</tei:title></tei:rs> las. Die müssten eigentlich als <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >Muster</tei:hi>kritiken neu herausgegeben werden. Welche Kritiker, ausser Ihnen, hat
        jemals seine Urteile durch sein nachfolgendes Lebenswerk so fundiert? Ich wusste keinen. Wie
        treffend haben Sie 1897 <tei:pb n="3"/>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs> charakterisiert in 19<tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">261</tei:add>; dazu den warmen Grüssen <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs> zu s. 60. Geburtstag 7. V. 93! Die Aufsätze über
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000833">Smetana</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000104">Bruckner</tei:rs>, die Konzertdirigenten sind grossartig. Ebenso der
        über <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006067">Rubinstein</tei:rs>. Eine Klarheit der
        Gedanken und der Sprache, die den damaligen Zeitgenossen wohl kaum ganz aufgegangen ist.
        Sigfried Wagner 14 <tei:hi rend="supralinear">281</tei:hi> konnte wohl zufrieden sein mit
        Ihrem objectiven Urteil. Nur im Falle <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000150"
          >d’Albert</tei:rs> 9 <tei:hi rend="supralinear">33</tei:hi> kann ich mich nicht enthalten,
        zu sagen, dass er zu sehr der Mode geopfert hat, besonders i. s. letzten Zeit, und sein
        eigentliches Vestalenamt an der Kunst nicht seiner Würde entsprechend verwaltet hat. Ich
        denke noch mit Schrecken an seine Oper: „<tei:title>die schwarze Orchidee</tei:title>“, die
        ich hier hörte. Wie kann ein Mann, der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055"
          >Beethoven</tei:rs> so gut interpretieren konnte, einen solchen Fehlschritt begehn. Das
        ist mir unverständlich. Neben Ihren Aufsätzen verblasst alles andre, was ich noch dazwischen
        las, wie z.B. ein Aufsatz von Jodl-Prag „<tei:title>Musik und Metaphysik</tei:title>“. Der
        Titel reizte mich, wie das verschleierte Bild von Saïs, aber bei der Entschleierung kam
        nichts heraus. Die Kontroverse <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000150"
          >d’Albert</tei:rs>–<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006320">Stavenhagen</tei:rs> war mir
        unbekannt ebenso wie die Tatsache, dass <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000150"
          >d’Albert</tei:rs> in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002886">Weimar</tei:rs> ¼ Jahr
        Hofkapm. war. Nach dem Aufsatz von Peter Gast „<tei:title>Nietzsche u. Brahms</tei:title>“
        will ich mich doch einmal <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000631">N</tei:rs>’s Hymnus
        ansehn. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Also heissen Dank sage ich Ihnen für dieses Geschenk! Ich werde versuchen, mir all
        diese Hafte antiquarisch zu verschaffen. Wird sie <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000412"
          >Jonas</tei:rs> eigentlich herausgeben? <tei:pb n="4"/> Wollen Sich nicht eine Würdigung
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000181">Dvořák</tei:rs>’s schreiben, die fehlt uns doch!
        – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ist das neue <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001755">Urlinieheft</tei:rs> schon
        erschienen? –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wie gehts mit den Augen?</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Alles Gute und die herzlichsten Grüsse</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Ihnen beiden von uns allen!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr treuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:placeName>Leipzig</tei:placeName>, <tei:date
              when="1932-07-20">July 20, 1932</tei:date>. Könneritzstrasse 58<tei:hi
              rend="supralinear">III left side</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor
            Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005266">My wife</tei:rs> and I thank you sincerely
        for the congratulations on the birth of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008535">Bepo's
          little sister</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> She was born on
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000644"><tei:hi rend="underline"
          >Ulrich</tei:hi></tei:rs>'s birthday; you must have confused the dates. Everyone is well.
        Only my eldest daughter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008525">Ingeborg</tei:rs> has a
        recurring liver condition, which, according to the doctor, will last seven years. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> sailed yesterday for Sweden and Finland.
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003957">Walter</tei:rs> is working hard at the business,
        as befits a diligent apprentice. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008523">Bepo</tei:rs> is
        developing splendidly. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Many thanks for the reference to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000130"
          >Chrysander</tei:rs>'s article in <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002566"><tei:title
            level="j">Die Zukunft</tei:title></tei:rs>; it refers to <tei:rs type="composition"
          key="entity-005626"><tei:title level="m">Messiah</tei:title></tei:rs> and <tei:rs
          type="composition" key="entity-004889"><tei:title level="m">Jephtha</tei:title></tei:rs>;
        but you are right, his arguments are unconvincing. Regarding the theme <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">in G minor</tei:add> (see musical supplement),<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> I now believe that <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000329">Handel</tei:rs> arrived at it via the flute sonata, taking the
        original <tei:term>bass elaboration</tei:term> of the
          <tei:term>fourth-progression</tei:term> as the upper voice. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I will dearly miss <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs> and the
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002334">Tyrol</tei:rs>, but finances demand prudence. I
        hope that you will find thorough rest in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002380"
          >Igls</tei:rs> after the rigors of the winter. Next year I will save diligently to make a
        trip to the <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002334">Tyrol</tei:rs> and a reunion possible.
        – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>I'm very much looking forward to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
          >Weisse</tei:rs>'s Octet. At the last concert evening at the <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002872">Conservatory</tei:rs>, my new Oboe Quartet was performed, but the
        invited special publisher didn't show up and hasn't even thanked me for my personal
        invitation to the event. I've also had bad luck again with the <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002495">Frankfurt</tei:rs> concert: the conductor and the chairman of the
        association liked it very much, but Count Hardenberg, who is financing the concert, <tei:pb
          n="2"/> granted the <tei:hi rend="underline">Swiss</tei:hi> composer Kelterborn, who set
        one of the Count's poems, "<tei:title>Our Father</tei:title>," to music, the entire
          evening.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> So we Germans have to take a back
        seat so that a German count can support foreigners with his money! –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I've ordered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>'s new
        works. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>The political situation is becoming increasingly bleak: a state of emergency was
        declared for <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs> this evening; there
        will be several more deaths before the Reichstag elections on the <tei:date
          when="1932-07-31">31st</tei:date>. The communist rabble is receiving far too much material
        and moral support from <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002568">Russia</tei:rs>! Only an
        iron fist will help, which the government finally seems determined to use. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>At the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002872">Conservatory</tei:rs>, it's
        still undecided whether <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000659">Pauer</tei:rs> will
        return. Basically, an iron broom is needed there too, because the intellectual level of the
        institution has reached a low point that will soon be impossible to surpass. Everything is
        geared toward virtuoso performance and training; every ridiculous fashion is embraced
        instead of allowing healthy, strong fruits to ripen through years of quiet work. The whole
        operation and the intrigues have disgusted me for a long time, but as a family man, one
        can't afford to take any risks these days. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>The last two days were a real joy for me, as I read your essays in <tei:rs
          type="journal" key="entity-002566"><tei:title level="j">Die Zukunft</tei:title></tei:rs>
        at the library. They should really be republished as <tei:hi rend="underline">model</tei:hi>
        critiques. Which critic, besides yourself, has ever substantiated his judgments so
        thoroughly through his subsequent life's work? I couldn't think of any. How aptly you
        characterized <tei:pb n="3"/>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs> in 1897 (vol. 19, <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">pp. 261–</tei:add>); also, the warm greetings to <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs> on his 60th birthday, May 7, 1893! The
        essays on <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000833">Smetana</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000104">Bruckner</tei:rs>, and the concert conductors are magnificent.
        Likewise, the one on <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006067">Rubinstein</tei:rs>. A
        clarity of thought and language that probably wasn't fully appreciated by his
        contemporaries. Siegfried Wagner (vol. 14, pp. 281–) could certainly be satisfied with your
        objective judgment. Only in the case of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000150"
          >d'Albert</tei:rs> (vol. 9, pp. 33–) can I not refrain from saying that he sacrificed too
        much to fashion, especially in recent times, and did not manage his actual office of purity
        in art in a manner befitting his dignity. I still shudder at the thought of his opera:
          <tei:title level="m">The Black Orchid</tei:title>, which I heard here. How could a man who
        could interpret <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> so well make
        such a misstep? That is incomprehensible to me. Next to your essays, everything else I read
        in between pales in comparison, such as an essay by Jodl-Prague <tei:title level="a">Music
          and Metaphysics</tei:title>. The title intrigued me, like the veiled image of Sais, but
        nothing came of the unveiling. The <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000150"
          >d'Albert</tei:rs>–<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006320">Stavenhagen</tei:rs>
        controversy was unknown to me, as was the fact that <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000150">d'Albert</tei:rs> was court Kapellmeister in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002886">Weimar</tei:rs> for a quarter of a year. After reading Peter Gast's
        essay <tei:title level="a">Nietzsche and Brahms</tei:title>, I want to take a look at
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000631">Nietzsche</tei:rs>'s hymn. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>So, I thank you very much for this gift! I will try to obtain all these issues from an
        antiquarian bookseller. Will <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000412">Jonas</tei:rs>
        actually publish them? <tei:pb n="4"/> Wouldn't you like to write an appreciation of <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000181">Dvořák</tei:rs>? We are lacking one! –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Has the new <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001755"><tei:hi rend="italic"
            >Urlinie</tei:hi> issue</tei:rs> already been published? –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>How are your eyes?</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">All the best and the most cordial regards</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">to both of you from all of us!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr treuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
