<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="266" sdoID="OJ-11-35-15">OJ 11/35, 15</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="AHa" scope="sole">August Halm's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="LR">
   <tei:persName>Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2010</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>


  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-12-07" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">
  <sdo:itemDesc><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002698">Halm ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   
   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated January 11, 1920</dc:title>
   
   <dcterms:created>1920-01-11T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-03-21</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Halm expresses reservations about Kleine Bibliothek plan; wishes Schenker might
    write history of music. —PS: Advises Sschenker to insure a regular income before moving to
    Germany. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Verleger; publisher; geschäftlich; business; Analyse; analysis; Kunstwerk; work of
    art; Musikgeschichte; music history; Surrogate; Kadenz; cadence; Sequenz; sequence; Geld; money;
    Währung; currency</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000326">Halm</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:date when="1920-01-11" rend="indent-80">11. I. 20.</tei:date>
    <tei:salute>Verehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Zu<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is
     recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/1, p. 2208, January 17, 1920: "Von Halm (Br.): möchte den
     Wunsch äußern, daß ich der „Kleinen Bibliothek[“] von Analysen absehe u. destomehr die
     Musikgeschichte bedenke, an der es ganz u. gar fehlt." ("From Halm (letter): would like to
     express the desire that I leave analyses out of the <tei:title level="j">Little
      Library</tei:title> and consider all the more strongly music history, which is lacking
     completely."). Federhofer transcribes all of this letter except for the opening and the
     postscript in <tei:title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern und Briefen
      ...</tei:title>, p. 140. </tei:note> Ihrem Brief<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">This letter is not known to survive. </tei:note> könnte ich zunächst in Beziehung
    auf die geschäftliche Frage mich äußern. Daß Ihr <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">Verleger</tei:rs> nun einsieht, daß Sie zu Wort kommen müssen, oder daß er auch gut dabei
    fährt, wenn er Wichtiges u. Nachhaltiges bringt, freut mich sehr. Der Gedanke der <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001758"><tei:title>Kleinen Bibliothek</tei:title></tei:rs> aber nicht
     <tei:unclear reason="reading">gleichermaßen</tei:unclear>, d.h. nicht unbedingt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">The publisher is UE. Hellmut Federhofer
     transcribes a large section of Schenker’s reply of January 18, 1920 to Halm’s letter of January
     11 in <tei:title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern und Briefen ...</tei:title>, pp.
     141–142. </tei:note> Ich meine, die typischen <tei:term>Analyse</tei:term>n sollten genügen; eine ganze zweite Existenz der Kunstwerke in Analysen
    stelle ich immer ungern vor.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">In the
     essay <tei:title level="a">Musik und Volk,</tei:title>
     <tei:title level="j">Von schwäbischer Scholle. Kalendar für schwäbische Literatur und
      Kunst</tei:title> (Heilbronn: Eugen Salzer, 1922), p. 70, Halm spoke disparagingly – and with
     unwitting accuracy! – of a “proliferation of such analyses” that would “gradually form a large
     literature, so that at some point opposite the bookcase with masterworks another would stand
     with analyses of them.” </tei:note> Von meinem Bedürfnis aus müßte ich wünschen, Sie schrieben
    die Musikgeschichte, für die wir bis jetzt kaum kümmerliche Surrogate haben, u. wenn das nicht
    möglich, da nach meinem Wissen oder Vermuten Wichtiges noch ganz unaufgeklärt ist (wer hat
    zuerst mit klarem Bewußtsein ihrer funktionellen Wirkung <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">eine</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">die</tei:add>
    </tei:subst>
    <tei:term>Kadenz</tei:term>, <tei:pb n="2"/> die
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002489">Sequenz</tei:rs> gebraucht? Das kümmerte ja die
    Musikgeschichtenvefasser gar nicht!) einzelne Abschnitte von Musikgeschichte; was ich in Ihren
    Büchern nach dieser Richtung fand, erweckte mir sehr stark diesen Wunsch, den ich Ihnen hiemit
    vortragen will. Der Verleger wird, denke ich, auch an das mit Mut hingehen. (Ich selbst weiß
    viel zu wenig u. kann an dergleichen nicht denken, u. wer außer Ihnen sollte das können?) </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mit besten Grüßen u. Wünschen </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70">A. Halm</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p>Es fiel mir noch ein, daß Sie schon um die Möglichkeit in ein anderes Land, sei es auch
     nur <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482">Deutschland</tei:rs>,
     zu ziehen, sich zu wahren, sich anstatt einmaliger Abfindung mit österreich. Geld regelmäßige
     Einkünfte sichern sollten, u. zwar eben auch Prozent daraus, anderen Ländern fließenden
     Einnahmen in der betreffenden Währung u. mit Einberechnung des Verleger- (u. womöglich (?)
      Buchhändleraufschlags.<tei:supplied reason="syntax">)</tei:supplied>
    </tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:date when="1920-01-11" rend="indent-80">January 11, 1920</tei:date>
    <tei:salute>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>In<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> response to your letter,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> I could for the moment give my opinion regarding the
    business matter. I am very happy that your <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">publisher</tei:rs> now accepts that you must have a say, or that he will do well if he
    provides something important and lasting. However, the idea of the “<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001758"><tei:title level="j">Little Library</tei:title></tei:rs>” <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">likewise</tei:unclear> no, that is, not necessarily."<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> I mean typical <tei:term>analyses</tei:term> should suffice; only reluctantly do I imagine an entire
    second existence of works of art in analyses.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/>
    Based on my needs, I would have to wish that you might write history of music, for which up to
    now we barely have paltry surrogates; and if that is not possible, individual sections of music
    history, since things of importance are yet wholly unclarified according to my knowledge or
    supposition (who first employed a the <tei:term>cadence</tei:term>, <tei:pb n="2"/> the <tei:term>sequence</tei:term>, with clear awareness of its functional effect? That <tei:supplied reason="clarity">question</tei:supplied> does not occupy authors on music history at all!).
    What I found in that direction in your books stirred in me very strongly the wish that I want to
    present to you here. The publisher will approach it eagerly, I think. (I know far too little and
    cannot consider something of that sort, and who other than you should be able to do it?) </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">With warm greetings and best wishes, </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70">A. Halm </tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p>It occurs to me additionally, that if you follow through on the possibility of moving to
     another country, even if it is only <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482">Germany</tei:rs>, you should assure yourself of regular
     proceeds instead of a one-time settlement in Austrian currency, and moreover also a percentage
     of earnings going to other countries, in the relevant currency, including publishers’ (and
     where possible (?)) the retailers’ mark-up. </tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>

 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>