<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3893" sdoID="OJ-13-10_181">OJ 13/10, [181]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2025</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated February 19, 1934</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1934-02-19T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-12-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel has been looking at some compositions by his friend Josef Knettel. He is
        generally despondent about the state of affairs at the Leipzig Conservatory, and in
        Germany.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:placeName>Leipzig</tei:placeName>, <tei:date
            when="1934-02-19">19. II 34</tei:date>.</tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Professor Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
            >Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for February 22, 1934: “Von
            Oppel (Br.): unzufrieden mit den Zuständen.” (“From Oppel (letter): dissatisfied with
            the conditions.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>leider komme ich erst heute zum Schreiben: mein Freund <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-006121">Knettel</tei:rs> hatte mir eine Reihe neuer Kompositionen zur
        Durchsicht geschickt mit der Bitte sofortiger Rückgabe. Darunter eine für den Wettebewerb
        der deutschen Arbeitsfront,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The
            <tei:hi rend="italic">Deutsche Arbeitsfront</tei:hi> was created in May 1933 as a
          replacement for all the independent trade unions in Germany, which were broken up by the
          National Socialists. Its establishment ensured that wages were kept low throughout the
          period of Nazi rule.</tei:note> die am <tei:date when="1934-03-01">1. März</tei:date>
        eingeliefert sein muss. So büffelte ich Sonnabend und Sonntag alles genau durch u. machte
        ihm eine Reihe von Vorschlägen zur Änderung. Daher die Verzögerung. Nun muss ich Ihnen aber
        zuerst sagen, wie heilfroh ich war, als Ihr Brief kam; denn die ganze Zeit der Wiener
          Unruhen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">The Austrian Civil War,
          or “February Uprising,” took place February 12–15, 1934, between the Republican Protection
          League (the paramilitary force of the Social Democrats) and the repressive government of
          Chancellor Engelbert Dollfuss. There was fighting in the city, imposition of martial law,
          the banning of the Social Democratic Workers’ Party, arrests, and executions.</tei:note>
        war ich natürlich in schwerer Sorge um Sie beide. Ich war grade im Begriff, eine Anfrage an
        Sie zu richten, da wurde ich durch Ihren l. Brief beruhigt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of a letter to Oppel is recorded in Schenker’s diary
          for February 14, but its summary there does not mention the unrest in Vienna.
        </tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Der <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002873">New York</tei:rs>er Artikel freut
          mich,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Probably
              <tei:bibl><tei:author>Israel Citkowitz</tei:author>, <tei:title level="a">The Role of
              Heinrich Schenker,</tei:title>
            <tei:title level="j">Modern Music</tei:title> 11/1, published in the last quarterly
            issue of 1933</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> hat ihn <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
          >Weisse</tei:rs> inspiriert?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Uns geht es allen soweit gut. Was die Kunst macht? Die Studenten u. Schüler werden
        durch den politischen Dienst und die sogen. politische Schulung (SA u. SS Dienst, Vorträge,
        Versammlungen) viel zu viel in Anspruch genommen, so dass die wirkliche Fachausbildung zu
        kurz kommt. Und vieles, das ich sehe u. erlebe, erfreut mich durchaus nicht. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>In der Musik hat sich nicht viel geändert; grade brachte der <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-005889">Gewandhaus</tei:rs>chor unter Ramin Reutter’s: „<tei:title>der grosse
          Kalender</tei:title>“,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot"
            ><tei:title level="m">Der große Kalender</tei:title> (1933), secular oratorio in four
          parts, by the German composer and pianist Hermann Reutter (1900–85).</tei:note> ein
        furchtbares Machwerk, unmusikalisch; es ist ein Verbrechen, dass für solches unfruchtbar
        Zeug Geld, Zeit u. Kräfte geopfert werden. Modetorheit u. Fortschrittsfimmel! Obwohl wir
        kaum Geld haben für lebende Kunst u. Künstler, wird hier eine Art Nationaldenkmal für
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000924">Richard Wagner</tei:rs> gebaut, Bauperiode
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">1934</tei:add> bis 1936! vorgesehn!! Wohnungen wären,
        weiss Gott, nötiger. Aber es gibt hier Leute, die mit der Ausführung dieser Idee sich bei
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003109">Hitler</tei:rs> liebkind machen wollen! <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000631">Nietzsche</tei:rs> hat in N<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
          >o</tei:hi> 179 der <tei:title>Morgenröte</tei:title> diese politische <tei:pb n="2"/> Art
        schon im voraus prophetisch gebrandmarkt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial"
          place="foot">In this aphorism, headed “As Little State as Possible!”, Nietzsche asserts
          that the brightest intellects have more important things to do than to get involved in
          state politics and economics.</tei:note> – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Zum komp. komme ich wenig; diese verdammten Vorlesungen über Musikgeschichte nehmen mir
        zu viel Zeit weg. Selbst <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006339">Ambros</tei:rs>
        schwefelt, es bleibt das meiste äusserlich und musikalisch unzulänglich. – Vielleicht
        beteilige ich mich auch noch an dem Wettbewerb, obwohl ich innerlich ganz auf dem
        Standpunkte stehe, den <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000306">Grillparzer</tei:rs> i. d.
        Vierzeiler: „<tei:title>Tendenzpoesie</tei:title>“ so schön präcisiert hat.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:title level="m"
            >Tendenzpoesie</tei:title>: An epigrammatic quatrain composed by Franz Grillparzer in
          1844.</tei:note> Motto: „Ehrung der Arbeit“. Ja, wie wenige Dichter haben die Arbeit
        besungen! – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Gern würde ich einen Artikel a. d. <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002537"
            ><tei:title>Frankfurter Zeitung</tei:title></tei:rs> beilegen, in dem sie das Resultat
        aus den Wiener Unruhen zieht, aber ich wage es nicht. Er war sehr gut u. treffend. Ich habe
        das unsichere Gefühl, dass die Briefe controlliert werden amtlich. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Gestern war der erste deutsche Komponistentag in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>, leider konnte ich aus Geldmangel nicht hin. Es wäre
        aber durchaus nötig, dass die <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>er
        führenden Zeitungen etwas mehr überprüft würden in Zukunft durch die Provinzler. Möglich ja,
        dass man jetzt aus den Fehlern der Gema u. SD. T.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09"
          type="editorial" place="foot">These may be abbreviation of institutions associated with
          music composition and performance. The “Gesellschaft für musikalische Aufführungs- und
          mechanische Vervielfältigungsrechte,” or GEMA, was the successor to the STAGMA (see
            <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-13-10_180">OJ 13/10, [180]</tei:ref>, February
          15), but it was not so named until 1945.</tei:note> gelernt hat. Bei den hiesigen
        Sitzungen hatte ich den Eindruck, dass die Verleger wie immer ihre Rechte wahren werden,
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000871">Strauss</tei:rs> als Führer war ihnen wenig
        sympathisch. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000866">Straube</tei:rs> „schiebt“ hier noch immer im
        Geheimen; wieder ist einer seiner Schüler Professor geworden, während dessen Lehrer noch
        ohne Titel ihren Dienst tun. Allgemeine Erbitterung; ich lache darüber; äussere
        Auszeichnungen verleihen keinen inneren Wert und decken inneren Unwert auch nicht zu. Herr
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000866">Straube</tei:rs> braucht aber Stützen für seine
        eigne Unsicherheit. – Nun muss der Brief zur Post. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Alles Gute u. die herzlichsten Grüsse</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>Ihnen beiden</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">von Ihrem treuen</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:placeName>Leipzig</tei:placeName>, <tei:date
            when="1934-02-19">February 19, 1934</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor
            Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>I regret that I have not got round to writing to you until today. My friend <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-006121">Knettel</tei:rs> had sent me a series of compositions
        for me to look through, with a request to return them immediately. Among them was one for a
        competition for the German Labor Front,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/>
        which must be submitted by <tei:date when="1934-03-01">March 1</tei:date>. So, I slogged
        through everything carefully on Saturday and Sunday and gave him a series of recommended
        changes. Hence the delay. Now I must first tell you, however, how overjoyed I was when your
        letter arrived, for I was naturally most deeply concerned about the two of you during the
        entire period of unrest in Vienna.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> I was at
        the very point of making an inquiry to you when your kind letter put my mind at
          rest.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>The article published in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002873">New York</tei:rs>
        pleases me;<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> did <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs> inspire it?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Things are reasonably well with us. What is happening with our art? My students and
        pupils have been called upon far too much by the political services and the so-called
        political education (service in the SA and SS, lectures, gatherings), so they have too
        little time for true development in their profession. And much that I see and experience
        cheers me not at all.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In the field of music, not much has changed; the <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-005889">Gewandhaus</tei:rs> Chorus recently performed Reutter’s <tei:title
          level="m">The Great Calendar</tei:title>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/>
        conducted by Ramin: a frightful concoction, unmusical. It is a crime to sacrifice money,
        time, and energy to such unfruitful material. The folly of fashion, and the craze for
        progress! Although we hardly have money for living art and artists, a sort of national
        monument for <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000924">Richard Wagner</tei:rs> is being
        built, building works expected to extend <tei:add place="interlinear-above">from
          1934</tei:add> until 1936! Places to live would, God knows, be more necessary. But there
        are people here who, in bringing this idea to fruition, would like to ingratiate themselves
        with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003109">Hitler</tei:rs>! <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000631">Nietzsche</tei:rs>, in No. 179 of his <tei:title level="m">Dawn of the
          Day</tei:title>, had prophetically denounced this <tei:pb n="2"/> sort of political
          behavior.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>I get little composing done; these damned lectures on music history occupy too much of
        my time. Even <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006339">Ambros</tei:rs> sulfurates; most of
        what he writes is superficial and musically unsatisfactory. – Perhaps I shall also take part
        in the competition, although inwardly I take the standpoint that <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000306">Grillparzer</tei:rs> has expressed with such beautiful precision in
        his quatrain “<tei:title>Tendency Poetry</tei:title>.”<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08"
          type="footnote"/> Motto: “Honor one’s work.” Indeed, how few poets have sung the praises
        of their work! –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I would gladly enclose an article from the <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002537"
            ><tei:title level="j">Frankfurter Zeitung</tei:title></tei:rs>, in which they assess the
        result of the Viennese unrest, but I dare not do so. I have the uneasy feeling that the
        letters are being inspected officially. It was very good and hit the mark.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Yesterday was the first German Composers’ Day in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>; unfortunately, I could not afford to go. But it would
        be quite important for the leading <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>
        newspapers to be reassessed in the future by the provincials. It is indeed possible that one
        has now learned from the mistakes of the Gema and the SD. T.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09"
          type="footnote"/> At this year’s conferences, I had the impression that the publishers, as
        always, want to protect their rights; as their leader, <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000871">Strauss</tei:rs> was less friendly to them. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000866">Straube</tei:rs> continues to poke around
        here as ever; another of his pupils has been made professor, while his teachers continue to
        perform their services without title. General embitterment: I laugh at it; outward
        distinctions confer no inner worth, and they are also unable to conceal their inner
        worthlessness. But Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000866">Straube</tei:rs> needs
        supports for his own insecurity. – Now I must get this letter to the Post Office. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>All good wishes and the most cordial greetings</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>to the two of you</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">from your faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
