<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="686" sdoID="OJ-10-1_89">OJ 10/1, [89]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>
    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="WD" scope="sole">Walter Dahms's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="JK">
      <tei:persName>John Koslovsky</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2012</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2012</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2012</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2012-03-18" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>

  </sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002725">Dahms ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Dahms to Schenker, undated [c. April 29, 1925]</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1925-04-29T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2012-03-18</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Dahms has found a rental cottage in rural Pallanza, and invites the Schenkers
        to visit. — Hindenburg's election as German President has given a "jolt" to Europe and
        pleased Mussolini; it should produce shrewd politics, but he doubts whether Hindenburg will
        be able to lift Germany out of mediocrity.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Ruhe; peace; See; lake; Gebirge; mountains; Vögel; birds; Wahl; election; choice;
        Volk; people; nation; Politik; politics; Mittelmässigkeit; Mediokrität; mediocrity;
        Ungeistigkeit; spiritlessness; Kultur; culture; Richter; judge; Gauner; scrounger; Geschäft;
        business </dc:subject>

      
      
    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000149">Dahms</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60">Milano (2)</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60">Stenopost No. 67.</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Lieber und verehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/7, p. 2819, May 11, 1925: "Von Dahms
            (Br.): ladet uns ein; mengt auch politische, etwas hoffnungsvollere Betrachtungen ein."
            ("From Dahms (letter): invites us; also ties in political, somewhat more hopeful
            observations."). </tei:note>
        </tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ihre freundlichen Wünsche zu unserem Wechsel<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The postcard, not known to survive, of which writing is
          recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/7, p. 2813, April 27, 1925: "An Dahms (K.): wünsche
          Glück zur neuen Wohnung." ("To Dahms (postcard): I congratulate him on the new
          dwelling."). The proposed date for this document is based in part on this entry.
        </tei:note> werden sich hoffentlich erfüllen. Wir sind am Lago Maggiore und zwar in <tei:rs key="entity-003196" type="place">Pallanza</tei:rs> gelandet – jedoch bleibt meine Adresse
        für jedermann die obige. Auf diese Weise hoffe ich, hier Ruhe zu haben, die mir in <tei:rs key="entity-003073" type="place">Venedig</tei:rs> so unangenehm gestört worden ist. Ich
        bitte Sie sehr, niemandem gegenüber meinen Aufenthalt am Lago Maggiore zu erwähnen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Nach langem Suchen habe ich hier auf halbe Höhe des Monterosso über
          <tei:rs key="entity-003196" type="place">Pallanza</tei:rs> ein Landhaus zur Miete
        gefunden, dass im grossen ganzen meinen Wünschen entspricht, wenngleich es eigentlich viel
        zu gross für uns und dementsprechend viel zu teuer ist. Aber da begründete Aussicht besteht,
        hier in Ruhe arbeiten zu können, lässt sich das Mehr an Ausgaben leicht einholen. Wir atmen
        auf, dem entsetzlichen Lärm und der Roh<tei:supplied reason="spelling">h</tei:supplied>eit
          <tei:rs key="entity-003195" type="place">Mailand</tei:rs>s entronnen zu sein. Von unserem
        Haus aus, das ganz im Grünen liegt, überblicken wir See und Gebirge – die Vögel singen, kurz
        es ist ein idÿllischer Platz. <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs>
        wird uns wahrscheinlich bald besuchen. Dürfen wir die Hoffnung hegen Sie und Ihre verehrte
          <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Gattin</tei:rs> in diesem Sommer einmal für ein
        paar Tage bei uns zu sehen? Wir haben so schönen Platz – es ist alles da, was Sie wünschen,
        in erster Linie zwei Menschen, die sich unendlich freuen würden. Vielleicht wäre es Ihnen
        eine Erfrischung nach Beendigung der grossen Arbeit am <tei:rs key="entity-001750" type="work"><tei:title>Jahrbuch</tei:title></tei:rs>, hier angesichts einer ebenso
        lieblichen wie erhabenen Natur auszuruhen. Ich weiss, dass es Sie eine <tei:pb n="2"/>
        starke Überwindung kostet, nach <tei:rs key="entity-002592" type="place"><tei:country>Italien</tei:country></tei:rs> zu kommen. Aber einmal hier, werden Sie von
        dem Fremden nichts verspüren, sondern auf deutschem Boden sein. Möglicherweise können Sie,
        wenn Sie wieder nach <tei:rs key="entity-002334" type="place"><tei:region>Tirol</tei:region></tei:rs> gehen, den Weg hierher – anstatt über <tei:rs key="entity-002822" type="place">Brenner</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-003074" type="place">Verona</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-003195" type="place">Mailand</tei:rs> –
        über die <tei:rs key="entity-002507" type="place"><tei:country>Schweiz</tei:country></tei:rs> nehmen, wo sie nur mit dem Dampfer von
          <tei:rs key="entity-002619" type="place">Locarno</tei:rs> eine kurze Strecke durch
        italienisches Gebiet fahren, um in <tei:rs key="entity-003196" type="place">Pallanza</tei:rs> von mir in Empfang genommen, auf einen Wagen gesetzt und in unsere Burg
        gefahren zu werden. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Die Wahl <tei:rs key="entity-000374" type="person">Hindenburg</tei:rs>s
        zum Reichspräsidenten hat mit einem Schlage die Stellung <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Deutschland</tei:country></tei:rs>s verändert. Man fühlt hier
        ganz deutlich, dass ganz <tei:rs key="entity-003147" type="place"><tei:region>Europa</tei:region></tei:rs> einen Stoss bekommen hat, der zu einer
        Neuordnung der Moleküle führt. In <tei:rs key="entity-002592" type="place"><tei:country>Italien</tei:country></tei:rs> hat der Entschluss des deutschen Volkes
        grossen und vorteilhaften Eindruck gemacht. <tei:rs key="entity-002988" type="person">Mussolini</tei:rs> ist sehr zufrieden damit, da <tei:rs key="entity-002592" type="place"><tei:country>Italien</tei:country></tei:rs> von dem drohenden französischen Druck
        erleichtert und befreit wird. Jetzt eine kluge Politik <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Deutschland</tei:country></tei:rs>s, und in 10 Jahren steht es
        mächtiger da denn je, ein Reich, in dem alle Bedingungen des <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Deutschland</tei:country></tei:rs>liedes erfüllt sind. Der
        Beweis ist wieder einmal erbracht, dass es nur die Macht der Persönlichkeit, der Einzelnen
        ist, die über die Geschicke der Völker entscheidet. Wenn <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Deutschland</tei:country></tei:rs> nun noch aus der
        Mittelmässigkeit und Ungeistigkeit der Flugzeugfabrikanten und Industriellen in eine höhere
        Sphäre gelangt, wo wieder Kulturmenschen den Ton angeben, dann können wir wieder hoffen.
        Aber ob dies sein wird? Ich vermag es nicht zu glauben. Denn vorläufig haben die Richter und
        die Gauner es noch zu sehr in der Hand, die produktiven <tei:pb n="3"/> Kräfte zu schädigen
        und lahmzulegen. Und es werden all die unsauberen Elemente, die mit <tei:rs key="entity-000183" type="person">Ebert</tei:rs> zusammen das Geschäft gemacht haben, auch
        jetzt nicht rücksichtslos eliminiert werden. Ich sprach einmal mit einem hohen
        Botschaftsbeamten in <tei:rs key="entity-002638" type="place">Rom</tei:rs> über den Begriff
        „Gesinnung“ und sagte ihm, dass ein Mann, wie <tei:rs key="entity-000873" type="person">Stresemann</tei:rs>, der heute monarchistisch und morgen republikanisch, heute für rechts
        und morgen zusammen mit Marx<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Dahms is referring not to Karl Marx but to Wilhelm Marx (1863‒1946), a social democrat
          who served as chancellor of Germany from 1923 to 1925 and again from 1926 to 1928.
        </tei:note> für links sei, auf gut deutsch charakterlos genannt werden müsse, da man ja an
        jeden einfachen Staatsbürger die hohe Anforderung stelle, eine Überzeugung zu haben und für
        diese Überzeugung einzustehen. Worauf man mir erklärte,<tei:gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" extent="3"/> Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000873" type="person">Stresemann</tei:rs> tue nur seine Pflicht. Nach meiner Replik, dass es für mich ein
        trauriges Zeichen von Pflichtauffassung sei, wenn gerade die hohen Beamten ihre Gesinnung
        nach der Gehaltszahlung einstellten, hatte das Gespräch ein Ende. Die Grabschrift, die ich
        dem ganzen Gesindel von <tei:rs key="entity-000765" type="person">Scheidemann</tei:rs> bis
          <tei:rs key="entity-000873" type="person">Stresemann</tei:rs> entworfen habe, lautet: <tei:cit>
          <tei:q>Er lebte nur <tei:hi rend="underline">von</tei:hi> der Allgemeinheit und erwarb
            sich grosse Verdienste <tei:hi rend="underline">vom</tei:hi> Vaterland.</tei:q>
        </tei:cit>
      </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Aber man muss sich wohl damit abfinden, dass die Schurken immer obenauf sind. Wenn man
        liest, dass <tei:rs key="entity-000340" type="person">Gerhart Hauptmann</tei:rs> und <tei:rs key="entity-000563" type="person">Thomas Mann</tei:rs>
        <tei:del rend="overstrike">auf</tei:del> bei der Eröffnung der Deutschen Akademie in <tei:rs key="entity-002286" type="place">München</tei:rs> den heutigen deutschen Geist
        repräsentiert haben, dann ist man wirklich froh, in <tei:rs key="entity-003196" type="place">Pallanza</tei:rs> zu sitzen und eine solche Mediokrität nicht täglich vor Augen zu haben.
        – Kommen Sie! hier ist es schön! </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Mit den herzlichsten Grüssen an Sie und Ihre verehrte Frau <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Gemahlin</tei:rs>, von uns beiden </tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr treuergebener </tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000149">Walter
          Dahms</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60">Milan (2)</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60">Stenopost No. 67.</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dear and revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
        </tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Your kind good wishes for our exchange<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> will hopefully be fulfilled. We have landed at Lake Maggiore and indeed
        in <tei:rs key="entity-003196" type="place">Pallanza</tei:rs> – however my address for
        everyone remains the one above. This way I hope to have some quiet here, which was for me so
        unpleasantly disturbed in <tei:rs key="entity-003073" type="place">Venice</tei:rs>. I beg
        you not to mention my residence at Lake Maggiore to anyone. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">After a lengthy search I have found a cottage for rent half way up the
        Monterosso over <tei:rs key="entity-003196" type="place">Pallanza</tei:rs>, which for the
        most part fulfills my wishes, even if it is actually far too big for us and far too
        expensive. But here the real prospect remains to be able to work here in quiet, and that
        easily makes up for the excess of expenses. We breathe a sigh of relief to have escaped from
        the awful noise and the crudeness of <tei:rs key="entity-003195" type="place">Milan</tei:rs>. From our house, which is completely surrounded by nature, we overlook the
        sea and the mountains – the birds sing, in short it is an idyllic place. <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs> will probably visit us soon. May we
        cherish the hope of seeing you and your dear <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs> this summer for a couple of days here? We have such a beautiful place –
        everything you could wish for is here, first and foremost two people who would be endlessly
        delighted to have you. Perhaps after the enormous work on the <tei:rs key="entity-001750" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Yearbook</tei:title></tei:rs> it would be refreshing for
        you to take a rest by coming face-to-face with such lovely and sublime nature. I know it
        would be <tei:pb n="2"/> a great effort to come to <tei:rs key="entity-002592" type="place"><tei:country>Italy</tei:country></tei:rs>. But once here you will not at all feel like
        a foreigner, rather you will be on German soil. Perhaps when you come again to the <tei:rs key="entity-002334" type="place"><tei:region>Tyrol</tei:region></tei:rs> you could come
        through <tei:rs key="entity-002507" type="place"><tei:country>Switzerland</tei:country></tei:rs> – instead of through <tei:rs key="entity-002822" type="place">Brenner</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-003074" type="place">Verona</tei:rs>, and <tei:rs key="entity-003195" type="place">Milan</tei:rs>
        – where by steamboat from <tei:rs key="entity-002619" type="place">Locarno</tei:rs> you
        travel only a short stretch through Italian waters, and then will be received by me in
          <tei:rs key="entity-003196" type="place">Pallanza</tei:rs> and brought by car to our
        lodge. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">The election of <tei:rs key="entity-000374" type="person">Hindenburg</tei:rs> to the presidency has changed the position of <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Germany</tei:country></tei:rs> with a single
        blow. One clearly feels here that the whole of <tei:rs key="entity-003147" type="place"><tei:region>Europe</tei:region></tei:rs> has received a jolt that will bring about a
        new arrangement of molecules. In <tei:rs key="entity-002592" type="place"><tei:country>Italy</tei:country></tei:rs> the decision of the German people has made a
        largely favorable impression. <tei:rs key="entity-002988" type="person">Mussolini</tei:rs>
        is very pleased by it, since <tei:rs key="entity-002592" type="place"><tei:country>Italy</tei:country></tei:rs> will be relieved and freed from the menacing
        pressure of the French. Now there will be some shrewd politics in <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Germany</tei:country></tei:rs>, and in ten
        years it will be more powerful than ever, a state in which all the conditions of the song of
          <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Germany</tei:country></tei:rs> are
        fulfilled. The proof is provided once again that it only takes the power of a single person
        to decide the fate of the people. If <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Germany</tei:country></tei:rs> were still able to reach above mediocrity
        and the spiritlessness of the airplane factories and industries, where people of culture
        once again set the tone, then we have something again to hope for. But whether this will
        actually come about? I am incapable of believing such a thing. Because temporarily the
        judges and the crooks still have too much at their disposal <tei:pb n="3"/> to damage and
        paralyze productive energies. And all the impure elements, which together did business with
          <tei:rs key="entity-000183" type="person">Ebert</tei:rs>, will now be eliminated
        indiscriminately. I once spoke to a high-ranking official at the embassy in <tei:rs key="entity-002638" type="place">Rome</tei:rs> about the idea of "basic conviction" and
        told him that a man like <tei:rs key="entity-000873" type="person">Stresemann</tei:rs> – who
        today is a monarchist and tomorrow a republican, today for the right and tomorrow with
          Marx<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> for the left – would have to be
        called characterless in plain German, since people there place a high demand on every
        citizen to have a conviction and to stand by this conviction. It was then explained to me
        that Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000873" type="person">Stresemann</tei:rs> is simply doing his
        duty. After replying that for me it is a woeful indication of one's sense of duty if even
        high officials sacrifice their basic conviction for a salary, the discussion came to an end.
        The epitaph that I have drafted for the whole riffraff from <tei:rs key="entity-000765" type="person">Scheidemann</tei:rs> to <tei:rs key="entity-000873" type="person">Stresemann</tei:rs> reads: <tei:cit>
          <tei:q>He only lived <tei:hi rend="underline">off of</tei:hi> the general public and
            earned tremendous profit <tei:hi rend="underline">from</tei:hi> the fatherland.</tei:q>
        </tei:cit>
      </tei:p>

      <tei:p>But one has to come to terms completely with the fact that the scoundrels are always
        sitting on top. When one reads that <tei:rs key="entity-000340" type="person">Gerhart
          Hauptmann</tei:rs> and <tei:rs key="entity-000563" type="person">Thomas Mann</tei:rs> were
        the representatives of the present-day German spirit at the opening of the German Academy in
          <tei:rs key="entity-002286" type="place">Munich</tei:rs>, then one is truly happy to be in
          <tei:rs key="entity-003196" type="place">Pallanza</tei:rs> and not to have such mediocrity
        in front of one's eyes on a daily basis. – Come! It is beautiful here! </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">With the warmest greetings to you and your dear <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs>, from the two of us </tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your truly devoted, </tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000149">Walter
          Dahms</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>