<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2152" sdoID="OJ-15-16_88">OJ 15/16, [88]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HeW" scope="sole">Hertha Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2008</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2018</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-10-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006960">WeisseHe ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Hertha Weisse to Schenker, dated February 15,
        1933</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1933-02-15T11:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2018-10-24</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Hertha Weisse reports that, through Hans's teaching at Columbia University and
        the Mannes School, Schenker's work has gained a footing in New York (where people seem more
        receptive to new ideas), and she expresses her gratitude to Schenker for breathing life into
        the spirit that has given such joy to her husband's pupils. The children are growing up
        speaking German, and she has begun to restudy the piano.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Dankbarkeit; gratitude; Zuhörer; listener; Aufmerksamkeit; alertness; Musiker;
        musician; Lehrer; teacher; Virtuose; virtuoso; concert artist; Vortrag; lecture; Werk; work;
        Klavier; piano</dc:subject>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000952">Hertha_Weisse</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute>Verehrter lieber Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"
            >Doktor</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
            this letter and its companion is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/6, p. 3814,
            February 24, 1933: "Von Weisse u. Frau (zwei Briefe u. eine Ankündigung): eine sehr
            erfreuliche Bewegung sei im Zuge, einträglich – für ihn!!" ("From Weisse and his wife
            (two letters, and an announcement): a very gratifying movement is in progress, which is
            profitable – for him!!"). Schenker sent both letters to Ludwig Karpath, and reported
            their contents to Oppel, Kalmus and others in the next few days. This letter and
              <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-15-16_89">OJ 15/16, [89]</tei:ref> were
            written, sent, and delivered on the same day.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">So oft ich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Hans</tei:rs> über
        Ihr Werk sprechen höre, entweder an der <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-005886"
          >Columbia-University</tei:rs> alle Montag oder an der<tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002454"> Mannes School</tei:rs> alle Mittwoch, dann schwillt mir mein Herz vor
        Dankbarkeit u. Seligkeit. Wie erquickend, wie tröstend ist der Geist, den Sie lebendig
        gemacht haben in dieser Zeit u. ich glaub für Alle. Es kann sich keiner diesem Geist
        entziehen, ich sehe das an den Zuhörern. Es herrscht eine Aufmerksamkeit, eine feierliche
        Stille u. die Gesichter buchten vor Freude u. alle haben nachher das Bedürfnis zu danken. Es
        sind lauter reifer Leute, Musiker, Lehrer<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied>
        Virtuosen sogar <tei:pb n="2"/> in den Vorträgen, auch an der <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-005886">Columbia</tei:rs>. Sie sind wirklich alle tief interessiert u. wollen
        damit auch was anfangen, nicht nur das Neue aufnehmen als etwas Interessantes. Ich bin
        selig, daß Ihr Werk auch hier Boden fasst.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In dem Sinn, daß hier nichts feste Formen hat u. daß alles Gute noch Platz gewinnen
        kann, liebe ich <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002873">New York</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Die <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003100">zwei Kleinen</tei:rs> entwickeln sich
        hier auch gut, sie haben den ganzen Tag Freude<tei:del rend="overstrike">n</tei:del> u.
        Spass. Dieses Jahr kommen sie noch als ganz deutsche Kinder nach <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-003147"><tei:region>Europa</tei:region></tei:rs> zurück. Bei uns im Haus wird
        nur deutsch gesprochen. Wir haben eine Schweizerin u. die Kinder haben eher Schwitzerisch
        gelernt.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich denke oft mit Freude an die paar Mal, wo ich letztes Jahr zu Ihnen kommen durfte.
        Obzwar <tei:pb n="3"/> ich nicht Musikerin bin, ich bin begeistert für Ihr Werk, weil es den
        Geist darstellt, der das ganze Leben durchdringen sollte. Ich habe sogar wieder Klavier zu
        lernen begonnen oder fortgesetzt, nur um mit der Zeit Ihrem Werk näher kommen zu
          können<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">.</tei:supplied></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ein Teil dieses Briefes ist auch an <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Frau
          Lie-Lie</tei:rs> gerichtet, die ich herzlichst grüße. Es geht hoffentlich ihr und Ihnen
        gesundheitlich sehr gut.</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">In tiefer Verehrung</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60">Ihre <tei:rs key="entity-000952" type="person">Hertha
            Weisse</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1933-02-15">15. Februar 1933</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute>Dear revered Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs key="entity-000632"
              type="person">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
            type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Whenever I hear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Hans</tei:rs>
        speak about your work, either at <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-005886">Columbia
          University</tei:rs> every Monday or at the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002454"
          >Mannes School</tei:rs> every Wednesday, my heart swells with gratitude and contentment.
        How restorative, how comforting is the spirit that you have brought to life in these times
        and, I believe, for all times. Surely no one can lose his hold of this spirit: I see this in
        the listeners. There reigns an alertness, a solemn peace, and the faces light up with joy
        and everyone has the need to express thanks afterwards. There are nothing but mature people
        ‒ musicians, teachers, even concert artists ‒ <tei:pb n="2"/> at the lectures, also at
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-005886">Columbia</tei:rs>. They are all deeply
        interested and want to make a start with it: not merely because it is new but because it is
        something interesting. I am delighted that your work has found a footing here, too.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Knowing that nothing here has a permanent shape, and that all that is good can
        eventually gain a place, I love <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002873">New
        York</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Our <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003100">two little ones</tei:rs> are also
        developing well here; they have joy and fun the whole day long. This year they will return
        to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003147"><tei:region>Europe</tei:region></tei:rs>, still
        as thoroughly German children. At home we speak only German. We employ a Swiss girl, and the
        children have learned rather more Swiss-German.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I often think with joy of the few occasions that I was invited to your place last year.
        Although <tei:pb n="3"/> I am not a musician, I am eager to know about your work, because it
        represents the spirit that should penetrate our whole life. I have even begun to learn, or
        restudy, the piano, so that I might in time be able to get nearer to your work.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>A part of this letter is also addressed to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
          >Lie-Lie</tei:rs>, whom I greet most cordially. I hope that she, and you, are in very good
        health.</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">With deep respect,</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60">Your <tei:rs key="entity-000952" type="person">Hertha
            Weisse</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1933-02-15">February 15, 1933</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
