<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="121" sdoID="OJ-10-1_44">OJ 10/1, [44]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="WDa" scope="sole">Walter Dahms's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="JK">
   <tei:persName>John Koslovsky</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2009</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2009</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2010</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002725">Dahms ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   
   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Dahms to Schenker, dated September 10, 1919</dc:title>
   
   <dcterms:created>1919-09-10T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2010-06-08</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Dahms thanks the Schenker's for his time with them, and reports what he is doing
    currently; he endorses Nietzsche's view of Germany and the Germans, and speaks of the
    unprincipledness that its legal system and officialdom fosters.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Korrekturen; proofs; Register; index; Kontrapunkt; counterpoint</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000149">Dahms</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address rend="indent-70">
     <tei:addrLine>Wasserburg a/ Inn 340</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:date when="1919-09-10" rend="indent-80">10.9.19</tei:date>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-05">Lieber verehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>! </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Meiner<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
     this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/14, p. 2144, September 15, 1919: "Von Dahms
     (Br.): Illustrationen; erhebt in gewohnter Weise die schreisten Anklagen gegen seine Brüder!"
     ("From Dahms (letter): illustrations; in his usual fashion, voices the shrillest accusations
     against his brothers!").<!-- XR --> "Brüder" (meaning fellow-Germans) is not used in this
     letter by Schenker, but is by Schenker in his reply, and in Dahms's letter of September 26 (OJ
     10/1, [45]), and this suggests that Schenker did not dictate this diary entry until at least
     after he had replied to it on September 16. </tei:note> Karte<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">= OJ 10/1, [43], August 31, 1919. </tei:note> muss ich nun
    endlich ein paar Zeilen folgen lassen, Zeilen des Dankes vor allem für all das Schöne, was ich
    bei Ihnen genossen habe, sowohl von Ihnen als von Ihrer verehrten Frau <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Gemahlin</tei:rs>. Ich habe viel nachzudenken und von der Erinnerung
    zu zehren. Inzwischen hatte ich noch schnell Korrekturen zu erledigen und Register
     anzufertigen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Presumably of his
      <tei:title level="m">Mendelssohn</tei:title> (Berlin &amp; Leipzig: Schuster &amp; Loeffler,
     1919).</tei:note>, will nun noch ein paar Tage in die Berge und dann an die Arbeit gehen, um
    den <tei:term>Kontrapunkt</tei:term> zu bewältigen. Wenn nur nicht
    das Äussere so deprimierend wäre und durch seine Unentrinnbarkeit auf das Innere abfärbte. Man
    darf in<tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482">
     Deutschland</tei:rs> von staatswegen nicht mehr zurückgezogen
    und einsam leben. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> Ich habe viel über alles nachgedacht, was Sie gesagt haben.
    Aber ich kann mir nicht helfen: ich unterschreibe Wort für Wort von dem, was <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000631">Nietzsche</tei:rs> im „<tei:title>Willen zur
     Macht</tei:title>“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Friedrich
     Nietzsche, <tei:title level="m">Will to Power</tei:title>, transl. Walter Kaufmann and R.J.
     Hollingdale (New York: Vintage Books, 1968). </tei:note> und „<tei:title>Ecce
     homo</tei:title>“,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Friedrich
     Nietzsche, <tei:title level="m">Ecce Homo</tei:title>, transl. R.J. Hollingdale (New York:
     Penguin, 1979). </tei:note> hierin ganz besonders, über <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482">Deutschland</tei:rs> und die Deutschen gesagt hat. Ich
    verstehe es, wenn er in einem Brief an <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000650">Overbeck</tei:rs>
    schreibt, dass ihm <tei:country>Deutschland</tei:country> phÿsischen Ekel verursache und dass er
    erst gesund werde, wenn er die Grenze überschritten habe. Sie können sich die Summe von Roheit,
    Niedrigkeit, Gesinnungslosigkeit, Gemeinheit und B<tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overwritten">ö</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="superimposed">o</tei:add>
    </tei:subst>sheit nicht vorstellen, die das heutige <tei:country>Deutschland</tei:country>, vor
    allem die gänzlich korrumpierte und dabei bis ins Masslose selbstsgefällige Rechts, pflege und
    Beamtenschaft beherrscht. Es ist unmöglich in <tei:country>Deutschland</tei:country> zu leben,
    wenn man geistige Ziele hat. Man wird mit allen Mitteln verhindert, Ruhe zur Arbeit zu finden. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="3"/> In der nächsten Woche komme ich zu <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>, der schon gespannt ist auf alles, was ich
    erzählen werde. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Wahrscheinlich haben Sie jetzt noch schönes sonniges Wetter gehabt, wie wir
    hier. Umso schwerer wird Ihnen das Scheiden von dort werden. Nur gut, dass Sie es noch so lange
    ausnutzen konnten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">i.e. Schenker was
     given an extension of his stay there by Mr. Klammerth (snr). </tei:note>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Indem ich Ihnen und Ihrer verehrten Frau <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Gemahlin</tei:rs> die ergebensten Grüsse meiner
      <tei:persName>Frau</tei:persName> übermittle</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Begrüsse ich Sie herzlichst</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">als Ihr stets ergebener</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60">Walter Dahms</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address rend="indent-70">
     <tei:addrLine>Wasserburg on the Inn 340</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:date when="1919-09-10" rend="indent-80">September 10, 1919</tei:date>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-05">Dear, revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Master</tei:rs>, </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">I<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> finally must follow up on
    my previous postcard,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> and express my thanks for
    the many things I enjoyed with you as well as with your good lady <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">wife</tei:rs>. I have so much to think about and to reflect on. In
    the meantime, I had proofs to deal with and an index to create.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> I want to spend a few days in the mountains and then set to work to master
     <tei:term>counterpoint</tei:term>. If only the outside world (so
    inescapable as it is) were not so depressing and did not rub off on the inner world. For
    political reasons one is no longer allowed to retreat from life and live alone. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> I have thought a lot about what you said to me. But I can't
    help myself: I endorse word for word what <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000631">Nietzsche</tei:rs> in his <tei:title level="m">Will to Power</tei:title><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> and <tei:title level="m">Ecce Homo</tei:title><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> (especially the latter) said about <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482">Germany</tei:rs> and the Germans. I
    understand him when he writes in a letter to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000650">Overbeck</tei:rs>, for instance, that <tei:country>Germany</tei:country> causes him a
    physical disgust, and that he felt healthy for the first time only when he crossed the border
    out of the country. You can't imagine the amount of brutality, scurrilousness, lack of
    principle, nastiness, and malice that today's <tei:country>Germany</tei:country> (above all the
    whole corrupt and excessive law) cultivates and its officialdom commands. It is impossible to
    live in <tei:country>Germany</tei:country> if one has worthy goals. One is hindered in every
    possible way from finding peace for one's work. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="3"/> In the next week I will visit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>, who is already excited about everything I will
    tell him. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Perhaps you have by now some nice sunny weather, just as we have had here.
    All the harder will it be for you to part from there. The only good thing is that you were able
    to take advantage of it for so long.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">In sending you and your <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">wife</tei:rs> my <tei:persName>wife</tei:persName>'s most respectful greetings, </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">I send you my own most cordial greetings, </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your ever-devoted </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60">Walter Dahms</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>