<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3731" sdoID="OJ-13-10_58">OJ 13/10, [58]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="TLJ-KO">
      <tei:persName>Timothy L. Jackson, ed. Kurt Oppel</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2010</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated June 22, 1928</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1928-06-22T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-08-14</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel congratulates Schenker again on his 60th birthday. He is despondent
        about the direction the Leipzig Conservatory is taking, aiming at the training of virtuoso
        musicians and with poor theoretical teaching. He is critical of Halm’s
        Beethoven.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1928-06-22">22. VI
            1928</tei:date>. Kiel, Feldstr 77<tei:hi rend="supralinear">IV</tei:hi>.</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Professor Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
            >Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for June 25, 1928: “Von Oppel
            (Br.): noch einmal Gratulation.” (“From Oppel (letter): congratulations once again.”).
            This letter was promised by Oppel in <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-13-10_56"
              >OJ 13/10, [56]</tei:ref>, June 18, 1928.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>vielen Dank für die Karte aus Wien v. <tei:date when="1928-06-12">12.</tei:date>
          noch,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker’s diary for June
          12, 1928 records an immediate (non-extant) reply to Oppel’s previous postcard: “An ihn
          (Ansichtsk.): auf Wiedersehen in Galtür” (“To him (picture postcard): until we see each
          other in Galtür”). The Schenkers arrived in Galtür on June 20.</tei:note> die leider erst
        kam, als ich Depesche u. Brief schon losgelassen hatte. Sie haben sich also der
        Glückwünschattaque durch die Flucht ins Fluchthorn entzogen! Dort können Sie auch in Ruhe u.
        Distanz alles geniessen. Hoffentlich haben Sie viel Sonne. Bei uns in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002482">Deutschland</tei:rs> ist es kalt u. windig, viel Regen u. kaum Sonne;
        man hockt abends i. d. Zimmern u. friert. Sonntag fahre ich wieder n. <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002479">Leipzig</tei:rs>, mein Hals ist zwar noch nicht ganz in Ordnung. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs> hat nichts mehr von sich
        hören lassen, allerdings war er, nach den Zeitungsnachrichten, meist auf Reisen. – Der
        Betrieb im <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002872">Konservatorium</tei:rs> macht mir
        vorläufig noch wenig Freude: alles ist auf virtuose Erziehung und Erfolge eingestellt.
        Kammermusik wird viel zu wenig gepflegt. Der theor. Unterricht ist höchst mangelhaft
        organisiert. Aber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000659">Pauer</tei:rs> ist viel zu
        bequem, um irgendwo energisch einzugreifen. Und wohl auch zu sehr einseitig Pianist. Der
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000659">Director</tei:rs> eines solchen <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002872">Kons.</tei:rs> muss nicht <tei:pb n="2"/> nur
        Virtuose sein. Das Kircheninstitut ist etwas besser aufgezogen. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun geniessen Sie die Ruhe der Berge u. die Herrlichkeiten der Natur mit <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000771">Ihrer lieben Frau</tei:rs>, – ich hoffe, Sie haben keine
        Arbeit mitgenommen – an solch einem Markstein wie dem 60. Geburtstage soll man ruhig die
        wohlverdiente Fermate machen u. auch aushalten. Wenn wir dann nach <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs> kommen, wollen wir ihn ordentlich feiern! Ich brauche
        Ihnen nicht zu sagen, was ich Ihnen alles danke; und dass andererseits ich den Rest meiner
        Lebensaufgabe nur darin sehe, Ihre Ideen an die Jugend weiterzugeben. Also in diesem Sinne
        Heil und Sieg! – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Gerade las ich gestern <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000326">Halm</tei:rs>’s
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beeth</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>August Halm</tei:author>, <tei:title
              level="m">Beethoven</tei:title> (Berlin: Max Hesse, 1927)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note>
        einfach furchtbar, abgesehen v. d. Tatsachen: dieser verwaschene, unkonzentrierte Stil!
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000104">Bruckner</tei:rs> über <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000612">Mozart</tei:rs> etc. Nein, einen solchen geistigen Rückschritt habe
        ich von ihm nicht erwartet. Alles was ich in letzter Zeit über <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000055">Beeth</tei:rs> las, beweist nur, wie wenig ihn die Menschen v. d. rein
        musikalischen Seite erfasst haben, dass sie Gott weiss was alles erst herbeiholen müssen von
          <tei:hi rend="underline">aussen</tei:hi>, um ihn angeblich zu verstehen. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Also alles Gute u. auf frohes Wiedersehen!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Mit den herzlichsten Grüssen </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>Ihnen beiden von uns allen</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr treuer </tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1928-06-22">June 22,
              1928</tei:date>, Kiel, Feldstraße 77/4</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor
            Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Many thanks for your postcard of the <tei:date when="1928-06-12"
          >12th</tei:date>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> sent while you were
        still in Vienna but which did not reach me before I had already sent a package and letter.
        So, you have escaped the barrage of congratulatory messages by fleeing to the Fluchthorn!
        There you can enjoy everything, even in peace and away from it all. With luck, you are
        having much sunshine. Here in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482">Germany</tei:rs> it
        is cold and windy, a lot of rain and hardly any sun; in the evening one crouches in one’s
        room and freezes. On Sunday I am travelling again to <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002479">Leipzig</tei:rs>; my throat is, in fact, not entirely healed.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs> has not been in touch
        further; at any rate he was mainly touring, according to newspaper reports. – The activities
        at the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002872">Conservatory</tei:rs> give me little
        joy at present: everything is aimed at training virtuosos and achieving successes. Chamber
        music is cultivated far too little. The theoretical tuition is poorly organized. But <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000659">Pauer</tei:rs> is much too easygoing to take energetic
        action anywhere. And he is probably too much a pianist with a single point of view. A
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000659">director</tei:rs> of such a <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002872">Conservatory</tei:rs> ought not to be <tei:pb
          n="2"/> merely a virtuoso. The church music institute is somewhat better organized. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Now, enjoy the peace of the mountains and the splendors of nature with <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000771">your dear wife</tei:rs> – I hope that you have not
        brought any work with you – for such a milestone as one’s 60th birthday, one should simply
        make a well-deserved fermata and also resist <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
          >working</tei:supplied>. And when we come to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292"
          >Galtür</tei:rs>, we shall celebrate properly! I do not need to tell you all that I have
        you to thank for, or that I see my life’s mission as only the dissemination of your ideas to
        the younger generation. And so in this sense, hail and victory!</tei:p>

      <tei:p> Just yesterday I read <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000326">Halm</tei:rs>’s book
        on <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>:<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> simply frightful, apart from the facts: such a
        wishy-washy, unconcentrated style! <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000104"
          >Bruckner</tei:rs> above <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000612">Mozart</tei:rs>, etc.
        No, such an intellectual regression is something I did not expect from him. Everything that
        I recently read about <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> merely
        proves how little people have understood him in purely musical terms: that they must fetch
        God-knows-what entirely from <tei:hi rend="underline">outside</tei:hi>
        <tei:supplied reason="clarity">the music</tei:supplied> if they are to pretend to understand
        him. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>All good wishes, then; and here’s to a happy reunion!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>With most cordial greetings</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>to the two of you, from all of us,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
