<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="653" sdoID="OJ-10-1_79">OJ 10/1, [79]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>
    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="WD" scope="sole">Walter Dahms's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="JK">
      <tei:persName>John Koslovsky</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2011</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2011</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2011-12-20" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>

  </sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002725">Dahms ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Dahms to Schenker, dated November 1, 1923</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1923-11-01T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2011-12-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Dahms has devoted a chapter of his Musik des Südens to "genius" in which he
        asserts its absoluteness and the gulf between genius and mediocrity. — He concurs with
        Hertzka's judgement of Furtwängler as a "coward"; In his quest for success, the latter has
        compromised his belief in genius by pandering to Schoenberg. The Korngolds are coming to
        Rome in August.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Erfolg; success; Spürnase; nose; Konjunktur; business opportunity; Tribüne;
        platform; Schüler; pupils; Lehrer; teachers; Genie; genius; Genieglauben; belief in genius;
        Durchschnitt; mediocrity; Religion; Feigling; coward; Kompromissen; compromises; Schmierer;
        scribbler; protistuieren; to prostitute; politics; Kohle; coal; Eisen; iron; </dc:subject>

      
      
    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000149">Dahms</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">Rom</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">via Sardegna 79</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1923-11-01">1. November 1923.</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/5, p. 2594, November 5, 1923: "Von
            Dahms (Br.): Freude über den steigenden Erfolg meiner Arbeiten; Hertzkas Stichwort:
            Furtwängler ein Feigling ist ihm aus der Seele gesprochen; für einen unbeirrbaren
            Charakter halte er ihn nicht! er ginge mit mir durch Dick u. Dünn, wenn er mit
            Sicherheit wüßte, daß mir die Zukunft zufällt." ("From Dahms (letter): happiness over
            the growing success of my publications; Hertzka's statement that Furtwängler is a coward
            expresses his thoughts exactly; he does not consider him an unwavering character! He
            would go through thick and thin with me, if he knew for sure that the future would be in
            my favor."). </tei:note>
        </tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Es war eine grosse Freude für mich, zu hören,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">This communication is not known to survive, nor is it
          recorded in Schenker's diary. </tei:note> dass Ihre Sache sicher von Erfolg zu Erfolg
        schreitet. Dass <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Herzka</tei:rs>s Spürnase eine
        „Konjunktur“ darin wittert, dass er Ihre Tribüne erweitert und vergrössert, das ist ein
        sicheres Zeichen für die wachsende „Nachfrage.“ Und da diese Nachfrage kaum auf müssige
        Neugier, sondern wohl mehr auf das langsame aber unaufhaltsame Durchdringen Ihrer Gedanken
        zurückzuführen ist, in einer Zeit, wo das Suchen kein Ende ist, wo die Verzweiflung die
        Schüler von den schlechten Lehrern forttreibt, wo so Unzählige eine Rechtfertigung Ihres
        Daseins als Musiker und darum zunächst einen Halt suchen — darum, meine ich, kann nun der
        Erfolg nur noch eine Sache von geringer Zeit sein. Teilangriffe, Überraschungs-Manöver
        führen schneller zu gewissen Zielen. Aber ein Frontalangriff, wie der Ihre, musste sich
        allmählig auswirken. Dann ist aber der Durchbruch auch gleichbedeutend mit dem Sieg. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich bin Ihnen von Herzen dankbar, dass Sie mir so freundliche Worte
        geschrieben haben. Einmal zu der Erkenntnis und Überzeugung gekommen, dass das
          <tei:term>Genie</tei:term> der Kernpunkt alles Werdens, aller Taten und Werke <tei:pb n="2"/> von Dauer ist, bleibt nichts anderes übrig, als mit den besten Kräften für diesen
          <tei:term>Genie</tei:term>glauben zu werben. In der „<tei:title>Musik des
          Südens</tei:title>“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Dahms</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Musik des
              Südens</tei:title> (Stuttgart and Berlin: Deutsche Verlags-Anstalt, 1923), chap. 8
              <tei:title level="a">Der Genius,</tei:title> pp. 227‒71</tei:bibl>. </tei:note> steht
        im Mittelpunkt ein Kapitel „Der Genius,“ in welchem ich diesen Glauben so ausführlich wie
        nur möglich ausgesprochen habe. Leider muss man oft verzweifeln, wenn man den Durchschnitt,
        die grosse Masse der Menschen um sich betrachtet, dass dieser Glaube viele Anhänger finden
        kann. Auch die Religion hat ja heute ‒ vielleicht dank der versagenden Organisationen der
        sichtbaren Kirchen ‒ keine Anhänger mehr. Überall derselbe Kompromiss des Etwas-Glaubens,
        Etwas-Wollens, Etwas-Könnens. Ein Wort der Unbedingtheit – und man steht sofort allein, man
        fühlt sofort die einige Atmosphäre völliger Verständnislosigkeit, ja Feindseligkeit der
        Anderen. O, ich verstehe ganz Ihren Stolz, durchgehalten zu haben gegen alle Not, alle
        Demütigungen. Es war dies der Weg aller Grossen. Es gibt denen, die ihn siegreich gegangen
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">d</tei:del> sind, die wunderbare Gewissheit, dass sie „diese
        Welt“ überwunden haben und dass es ihnen erspart ist, ewig und ewig von neuem durch den
        Schlamm waten zu müssen. - - - - </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="3"/> Waren Sie verwundert darüber, dass <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Herzka</tei:rs>
        <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs> einen Feigling nannte?
          <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">H.</tei:rs> ist ein Menschenkenner! und er hat
        in diesem Falle ins Schwarze getroffen. <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtw.</tei:rs> glaubt gewiss an das <tei:term>Genie</tei:term>; aber nicht ganz. Er
        glaubt auch an den „Erfolg,“ fast noch mehr als an das <tei:term>Genie</tei:term>. Da er
        unter allen Umständen immer Erfolg haben will, muss er Kompromissen schliessen, ist er
        schliesslich abhängig von jedem Zeitungsschmierer. Ihn drücken die Sorgen, was irgend ein
          <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs>er <tei:rs key="entity-003146" type="organization">Ullstein</tei:rs>-Schmierer etwa gegen ihn sagen könne. Und, ich weiss
        es, er weicht zurück, weil er sich fürchtet, etwa an der Seite <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs>s oder <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person">Haÿdn</tei:rs>s von dieser Meute zur Strecke gebracht zu werden. Lieber <tei:del rend="overstrike">wirft er ihnen</tei:del> prostituiert er sich auf dem Podium vor aller
        Öffentlichkeit mit <tei:rs key="entity-000798" type="person">Schönberg</tei:rs>, um die
        Meute zu beschwichtigen. Dass er schreiben will, wundert mich nicht; ich habe in dem letzten
        kleinen Aufsatz (er steht in der <tei:rs key="entity-003086" type="journal"><tei:title>Allgemeinen Musik-Zeitung</tei:title></tei:rs>
        <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs>-Schöneberg, Innsbruckerstr. 24/2
        —ich habe ihn leider nicht zu Gesicht bekommen!) einige Worte, und zwar absichtlich,
        geschrieben, die ihn reizen sollten. <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs> würde, davon bin ich überzeugt, sofort schreiben <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">sodann</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">und</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> bekennen, wenn er bestimmt, ganz bestimmt, mit absoluter Sicherheit wüsste,
        dass Ihre Sache die Sache der Zukunft ist. Sein Gefühl sagt wohl ja, aber er hat nicht die
        Gewissheit, weil ihm der letzte, tiefste Glaube fehlt. Das ist es. So sehr ich <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">F.</tei:rs> als Künstler schätze — ein unbeirrbarer
        Charakter ist er nicht. Er ist eben, um mit <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs> zu reden, nur ein Kapellmeister. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="4"/> Die Dinge, die in <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Deutschland</tei:country></tei:rs> vorgehen, kann man nur mit einem Gefühl
        des Schauderns und Grauens betrachten. Gänzlich entblösst von einer bindenden, religiösen
        Idee, taumelt das von Partei zu Partei, von einer Geistlerigkeit zur anderen. Die Vorkriegs-
        u. Krieges Zeit trägt ihre üblen Früchte. Trotz alledem kommt aus diesem Ozean von Schmutz
        und Leiden einmal ein neuer Gedanke, der uralte Gedanke in neuer Fassung. Ein barmherziger
        Himmel schicke über <tei:rs key="entity-003147" type="place"><tei:region>Europa</tei:region></tei:rs> u. <tei:rs key="entity-002510" type="place"><tei:country>Amerika</tei:country></tei:rs> ein erlösendes Erdbeben, das die Kohle u.
        das Eisen verschlucke, damit der Mensch wieder als Mensch leben könne; das würde die
        Erlösung beschleunigen. Denn ehe wir nicht die verfluchte Maschine vernichten, eher haben
        wir keine Ruhe, keinen Frieden vor dem Industrievolk. Das ist mein Morgen- u. Abendgebet. -
        - - - - - </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Demnächst erscheint <tei:rs key="entity-000470" type="person">Korngold</tei:rs> hier, um im Augustes zu dirigieren. Der <tei:rs key="entity-000471" type="person">Vater</tei:rs> wird mitkommen, wie ich hörte, um das römische Musikleben zu
        studieren!! </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Aber vorläufig scheint noch leuchtend und wärmend die Sonne, sodass wir vorgestern noch
        im Meer baden konnten. </tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Herzlichste Grüsse, lieber Meister, an Sie und Ihre <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Frau Gemahlin</tei:rs>
        </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">von uns beiden </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr ergebenster </tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000149">Walter
          Dahms</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">Rome</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">via Sardegna 79</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1923-11-01">November 1, 1923</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
        </tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">It was a great joy for me to hear<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> that your cause moves ahead one success after another. That <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs>'s good nose scents a "business
        opportunity" in it, that he is expanding and enlarging your platform, that is a definite
        sign for the growing "demand." And since this demand is hardly attributed to leisurely
        curiosity but much more to the slow but unstoppable penetration of your ideas, at a time
        when the search is at no end, where doubt drives away students from bad teachers, where
        countless individuals search for a vindication of your existence as a musician and therefore
        an initial foothold – for that reason, I mean, success can now only be a matter of time.
        Military sorties and surprise maneuvers lead faster to specific targets. But a frontal
        assault like yours must work itself out gradually. Only then is the breakthrough also
        synonymous with victory. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I am deeply thankful to you that you wrote such kind words to me. Once the
        knowledge and conviction comes that <tei:term>genius</tei:term> is the quintessence of all
        becoming, all facts and works <tei:pb n="2"/> of permanence, nothing else remains, other
        than to promote this belief in <tei:term>genius</tei:term> with the most vigor. Midway
        through <tei:title level="m">Music of the South</tei:title><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> there is a chapter "The Genius," where I have spoken out for this belief
        as elaborately as possible. Unfortunately one must often doubt whether this belief can find
        many adherents when one gazes upon the commoner, the great mass of people. Even religion
        today finds no more adherents – perhaps thanks to the collapsing organization of the visible
        churches. Everywhere the same compromise for those who believe in little, who desire little,
        and who are capable of little. One word about the absolute – and one stands immediately
        alone, one feels immediately an atmosphere full of misunderstanding and even hostility from
        others. Oh, I understand completely your pride, upheld despite all affliction, all
        humiliation. This was the way of all the greats. There are those who have become victorious,
        the wonderful certainty that they have conquered "this world" and that it has saved them
        from having to wade forever and ever through the slime anew - - - - </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="3"/> Were you surprised that <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> called <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs> a coward? <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs>
        knows people! and has hit the mark in this case. <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs> certainly believes in <tei:term>genius</tei:term>; but not entirely.
        He also believes in "success," perhaps even more than in <tei:term>genius</tei:term>.
        Because he wants to have success under all circumstances he has to make compromises, and he
        is exclusively dependent upon every scribbler from the newspaper. He is worried what some
          <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs>
        <tei:rs key="entity-003146" type="organization">Ullstein</tei:rs> scribbler could say
        against him. And I know it, he backs away because he is afraid to take the side of <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs> or <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person">Haydn</tei:rs> against this pack. He prefers to prostitute himself on the
        podium in full public view with <tei:rs key="entity-000798" type="person">Schoenberg</tei:rs>, in order to appease the pack. That he wants to write I am not
        surprised; in my last small article (he is in the <tei:rs key="entity-003086" type="journal"><tei:title level="j">Allgemeine Musik-Zeitung</tei:title></tei:rs> under the address
          <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs>-Schöneberg, Innsbruckerstraße
        24/2 – unfortunately I did not see him in person!) I wrote a few words, indeed expressly,
        that should anger him. <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs> would,
        I am convinced, write immediately <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">then</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">and</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> admit, if he decides, really decides that he wanted to with absolute certainty,
        that your cause is the cause of the future. His feelings tell him yes, but he does not have
        the certitude, because the last, deepest beliefs fail him. That is it. I esteem <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs> very much as an artist – but an
        unflinching character he is not. He is, in the words of <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs>, just a Capellmeister. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="4"/> The things that are happening in <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Germany</tei:country></tei:rs> one can only
        observe with a feeling of shivering and terror. Entirely divested of a binding, religious
        idea, it staggers from party to party and from one empty spirit to another. The period
        before and during the war bear their evil fruit. Despite all of this a new idea at once
        comes out of this ocean of filth and suffering, the age-old idea in a new form. A merciful
        heaven sends to <tei:rs key="entity-003147" type="place"><tei:region>Europe</tei:region></tei:rs> and <tei:rs key="entity-002510" type="place"><tei:country>America</tei:country></tei:rs> a redemptive tremor, that the coal and
        steel swallow up, so that man can once again live as man; that would hasten the solution.
        Because until we defeat the cursed machines we will not have any peace from the people of
        industry. That is my morning and evening prayer. - - - - - - </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Soon <tei:rs key="entity-000470" type="person">Korngold</tei:rs> will be
        here, to conduct in August. His <tei:rs key="entity-000471" type="person">father</tei:rs>
        will come with him, as I heard, in order to study Roman musical life!! </tei:p>

      <tei:p>But for the present the sun still shines luminously and warm, two days ago we could
        still bath in the sea. </tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Most cordial greetings, dear master, to you and your <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs>, </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">from the two of us, </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your most devoted </tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000149">Walter
          Dahms</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>