<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3258" sdoID="OJ-10-3_198">OJ 10/3, [198]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPoed" scope="major">Otto Erich Deutsch typist</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="OED" scope="minor">Otto Erich Deutsch's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2023</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IDB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2015-09-18" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002726">DeutschOE ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002712">DeutschOE ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002727">DeutschOE+H ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Typewritten letter from Deutsch to Schenker, dated October 2, 1933</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1933-10-02T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2023-08-25</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Deutsch quotes at length from a letter from Hoboken to his wife Hanna, in
        which it is reported that his current honorarium has been raised but the rest of Hoboken’s
        commitment to his library [and to him] will be decided only after he returns from the
        Netherlands later in the autumn.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000164">DeutschOE</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>PROF. OTTO ERICH DEUTSCH</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Tel. R 45–6–72</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">WIEN II.</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Böcklinstraße 26</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/><tei:date when="1933-01-05">2.
            Okt. 33</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Verehrter</tei:rs>!<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in
            Schenker’s diary for October 3, 1933: “Von Deutsch (Br.): die Frau hat an v. Hoboken
            geschrieben, erhöht auf S. 300, Senkung der Bezüge überall – Aufstellung der Bibliothek
            noch unverbindlich – <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000320">Haas</tei:rs> noch nichts
            sagen. Na, die Zeche werde vermutlich, wie immer, ich bezahlen. Offenbar war die Not bei
            Deutsch auf das Aeußerste gestiegen, sonst hätte er einsehen müssen, daß von allen Wegen
            der des Bettlers bei v. H. der bedenklichste ist u. ihn erst recht kopfscheu macht; auch
            hätte er den Schaden bedenken müssen, den er mit dem Schritt Anderen zufügt. Ich glaube
            nicht, daß v. H. herzlich gern eine ‘Rente’ von S. 300 monatlich für nichts bezahlt! An
            sich ist D.s Forderung eine Anmaßung u. Selbstüberschätzung, die erklärt, weshalb er
            mich hinter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000562">Mandyzewsky</tei:rs>
            <tei:foreign xml:lang="ita">e tutti quanti</tei:foreign> stellt, er weiß es nicht
            besser.” <tei:lb/>(“From Deutsch (letter): his wife has written to Hoboken,
              <tei:supplied reason="clarity">requesting that her husband’s monthly stipend
              be</tei:supplied> raised to 300 shillings; decline in payments everywhere – the
            establishment of his library is still not fixed – <tei:supplied reason="clarity">I
              should</tei:supplied> say nothing yet to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000320"
              >Haas</tei:rs>. Well, I shall probably end up paying the bill, as usual. Evidently,
            Deutsch’s hardship had reached its limit, otherwise he would have surely realized that,
            of all the paths leading to Hoboken, that of the beggar is the most risky and the one
            most likely to make him resistant; he would also have had to consider the damage his
            move would have inflicted on others. I do not believe that Hoboken would, in all
            honesty, have been happy to pay a monthly ‘pension’ of 300 shillings in return for
            nothing! Considered in itself, Deutsch’s demand is a form of arrogance and an
            exaggerated opinion of himself, which explains why he places me lower than <tei:rs
              type="person" key="entity-000562">Mandyczewski</tei:rs> and everyone else; he knows no
            better”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Indem ich Ihnen für Ihre gütigen Glückwünsche<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Cf. <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="WSLB-Hds-191-576"
            >WSLB-Hds 191.576</tei:ref>, September 29, 1933, from Schenker to Deutsch.</tei:note>
        herzlichst danke, beeile ich mich, Ihnen heute einen Brief <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs>s mitzuteilen, den er an meine <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000163">Frau</tei:rs> gerichtet hat. Sie schrieb ihm vor einer Woche „ohne
        mein Wissen“,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Cf. Schenker’s
          diary for September 27, 1932, reporting a meeting at which the Deutsches, Schenkers and
          Kurt Thomasberger were present, when afterwards: “[…] Frau D. ist empört über das cynische
          Zerstören einer wichtigen Arbeit, die Eigentum ihres Gatten ist […]” (“[…] Mrs. Deutsch is
          incensed over the cynical destruction of an important work <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
            >i.e. Hoboken’s library and her husband’s role as librarian</tei:supplied>, which is the
          property of her husband […] ”).</tei:note> wie es um uns steht, denn das Wasser lief uns
        zum Munde. Also: die Uebersiedlung der Bibliothek ist in Vorbereitung, die Wiederherstellung
        meines alten Honorares wird erhofft, und nun wird sie schon ab <tei:date when="1933-10-01"
          >1. Oktober</tei:date> erbeten. Darauf er: <tei:cit>
          <tei:q>„…Ich verstehe Ihre brenzlige Lage sehr gut. Es werden aber allerwege Kräfte
            abgebaut und ich muss auch dafür Sorge tragen, dass meine <tei:del rend="overstrike"
              >Kräfte</tei:del> festen Verpflichtungen nicht zu hoch werden. Ich will aber
            einstweilen dem <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000164">OE</tei:rs> 300 Sch. im Monat
            zugehen lassen statt 200, wie bisher. – Ueber die Bibliothek kann ich noch nichts
            Bindendes bestimmen. Ich habe auch nur ganz unverbindlich über eine eventuelle
            Wiederaufstellung derselben mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000164">OE</tei:rs>
            gesprochen. Alles Weitere kann ich erst in Wien mit Euch bereden. – Wir werden wohl
            später dorthin kommen, als wie vorgesehen, da <tei:pb n="2"/> wir von hier (Sanary)
            zuerst nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002508">Holland</tei:rs> fahren wollen. Es
            ist für mich dringend notwendig, einmal dort gewesen zu sein, um mich über die Lage zu
            orientieren …“</tei:q>
        </tei:cit></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich bitte Sie deshalb, zunächst nichts bei <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000380">H.</tei:rs> zu unternehmen, auch wenn Ihre Sache inzwischen geklärt
        ist oder wird.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">i.e. Hoboken’s fee
          for lessons with Schenker: Schenker’s diary October 6 records: “Von Hoboken (Br.):
          Ausschnitte u. Ankündigung des Honorars.” (“From Hoboken (letter): clippings, and
          announcement of the lesson fee.”); and that for October 7: “Von Hoboken durch die
          Rotterdamer Bank S. 1560.” (“From Hoboken, via the Rotterdam Bank, 1,560
          shillings.”).</tei:note></tei:p>




      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">In Eile Ihr herzlichst ergebener</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-90"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/><tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000164">O E Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>PROF. OTTO ERICH DEUTSCH</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Tel. R 45–6–72</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">VIENNA II</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Böcklinstraße 26</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/><tei:date when="1933-01-05"
            >October 2, 1933</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">friend</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">While thanking you for your kind wishes,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> I hasten to communicate the contents of a letter that <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs> has sent to my <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000163">wife</tei:rs>. She had written to him a week before, “without my
        knowledge”, explaining how things stood with us,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
          type="footnote"/> as we were in water up to our neck. The relocation of the library is in
        preparation, the restoration of my old salary is hoped for, and now it is being requested as
        of <tei:date when="1933-10-01">October 1</tei:date>. Of this he writes: <tei:cit>
          <tei:q>“… I understand your precarious situation very well. But everywhere my resources
            are dwindling, and I must also ensure that my fixed commitments are not too great. For
            the time being, however, I shall send <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000164">Otto
              Erich</tei:rs> 300 shillings per month instead of 200, as before. – With regard to the
            library, I cannot yet determine anything firm. I have spoken with <tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000164">Otto Erich</tei:rs>, again entirely without commitment, about
            possibly reestablishing it. I cannot discuss anything else with you until I am in
            Vienna. – We shall probably come there later than we expected, <tei:pb n="2"/> as we
            first have to go from here (Sanary) to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002508"
              >Holland</tei:rs>. It is of urgent importance for me, once I am there, to orient
            myself to the situation …”</tei:q>
        </tei:cit></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">For this reason, I ask you not to undertake anything with <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs> at first, even if, in the meantime,
        your own matter has been or is about to be clarified.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
          type="footnote"/></tei:p>




      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">In haste, Your most cordially devoted </tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-90"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/><tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000164">O. E. Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
