<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="115" sdoID="OJ-10-1_37">OJ 10/1, [37]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="WDa" scope="sole">Walter Dahms's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="JK">
   <tei:persName>John Koslovsky</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2009</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2009</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2010</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002725">Dahms ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   
   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Dahms to Schenker, dated June 11, 1919</dc:title>
   
   <dcterms:created>1919-06-11T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-01-30</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Dahms sends greetings on Schenker's birthday, finds solace in Nietzsche and
    Kierkegaard, and is studying counterpoint with Vrieslander. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Glückwünsche; best wishes; Geburtstag; birthday; Kontrapunkt; counterpoint; Opfer;
    sacrifice; Krieg; war</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000149">Dahms</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address rend="indent-60">
     <tei:addrLine>Wasserburg a/Inn 340</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-75">
     <tei:date when="1919-03-15">den 11. 6. 19.</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Hochverehrter, lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>! </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Wenn<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
     this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/14, pp. 2080-2081, June 16, 1919: "Von
     Dahms (Br.): gratuliert zum Geburtstag, bezeichnet sich als Opfer des Krieges früher, der Masse
     gegenwärtig, äußert überhaupt ernste Besorgnisse wegen der Zukunft; schöpfe Trost aus Nietzsche
     Kierkegard; erzählt auch von Vrieslanders Resignation." ("From Dahms (letter): sends
     congratulations on my birthday, calls himself a sacrifice to the war earlier, to the masses
     now, expresses serious anxieties about the future, draws consolation from Nietzsche and
     Kierkegaard; tells of Vrieslander's resignation."). </tei:note> ich heute an Sie schreibe, dann
    kommt der Brief hoffentlich bis zum 19. Juni in Ihre Hände, um Ihnen zu diesem Tage<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">June 19, 1919 was Schenker's 51st birthday.
    </tei:note> die herzlichsten Glückwünsche von mir und ausschliessend von meiner
     <tei:persName>Frau</tei:persName> zu überbringen. Was ich wünsche, wissen Sie – es ist ja nicht
    nur das Glück des Schaffens und Wirkens für Sie selbst, sondern auch unser Stolz und Glück, die
    wir an Sie glauben. <tei:supplied reason="illegible">Solche</tei:supplied> Betrachtungen haben
    heute keinen Wert mehr. Ich rette mich aus dem deutschen Elend in die reine Welt des <tei:term>Kontrapunkt</tei:term>es und erhebe Feststunden in <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000631">Nietzsche</tei:rs> und <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002577">Kierkegaard</tei:rs> und sehe wiederum mit Entsetzen, wie ungeheuer recht diese
    erlauchten Geister im Verein mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000799">Schopenhauer</tei:rs>
    und anderen Grossen gehabt haben in ihrem Urteil über die Menschheit. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> Wie sehr wünsche ich,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">"ich": asterisk above. </tei:note> dass es Ihnen in diesem Sommer
    vergönnt sein möge, in den Bergen neue Kraft zu finden. Ich hatte mich sehr darauf gefreut, Sie
    dann einmal für ein paar Stunden aufzusuchen. Aber die Hoffnungen sind wohl leider sehr geringe. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>, bei dem ich
    jetzt kontrapunktiere, ist voller Resignation. Ich muss ihm in so vielem Recht geben und doch
    stimmt es mich jedesmal wieder herunter. Wir sprechen oft von Ihnen und wie Sie sich wohl mit
    der neuen Zeit der „goldenen Freiheit“ abfinden mögen. Ich selbst bin auch oft nahe daran, die
    Flinte ins Korn zu werfen: die besten Jahren, die zweite Hälfte der Zwanziger, hat mir der
    glorreiche Krieg geraubt und der Rest fällt der „Masse“ zum Opfer. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">herzlichst grüssender</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">treuergebener</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-75">Walter Dahms</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address rend="indent-60">
     <tei:addrLine>Wasserburg on the Inn 340</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-75">
     <tei:date when="1919-03-15">June 11, 1919</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Revered, dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Master</tei:rs>, </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">If<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> I write today, then I hope
    this letter will reach you by June 19 so as to bring you on that day<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> the most cordial best wishes of my
     <tei:persName>wife</tei:persName> and myself. What I wish, you know well – it is not just a
    wish for good fortune in your creative work and activities, but also for the pride and happiness
    that we take in you. <tei:supplied reason="illegible">Such</tei:supplied> reflections have no
    more worth today. I escape from German misery in the pure world of <tei:term>counterpoint</tei:term>, and bury myself for hours in <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000631">Nietzsche</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002577">Kierkegaard</tei:rs>. At the same time, I see with horror just how awfully accurate
    these two illustrious souls were (in addition to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000799">Schopenhauer</tei:rs> and other great writers) in their judgment of mankind. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> How greatly I<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/>
    wish that it be granted to you this summer to find renewed strength in the mountains. I had
    truly looked forward to visiting you for a couple of hours, but such hopes are unfortunately
    slender. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>, with whom I now
    study counterpoint, is full of resignation. I am forced to agree with him every time, but deep
    down I concur. We speak often of you and how you are able to come to terms with this new time of
    "golden freedom." Personally, I often come close to throwing in the towel: the best years of my
    life, the second half of my twenties, were robbed from me by the glorious War, and the rest
     <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of those years</tei:supplied> fall victim to the "masses." </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">If you ever have the desire and the good spirits to drop me a line or two, I
    would be very grateful to hear from you. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Yours, </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">with warmest greetings, </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">ever-faithfully, </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-75">Walter Dahms</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>