<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="1297" sdoID="OJ-11-2_3">OJ 11/2, [3]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="EF" scope="sole">Emma Fischer's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB-ME">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent and Martin Eybl</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2009</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2009</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2014</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2011-03-05" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-005506">FischerE ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">letter</tei:rs>
      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Emma Fischer to Schenker, dated May 26, 1932</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1932-05-26T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2014-11-10</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Baroness Fischer sends her commiserations to Schenker on the death of Alfred
        Rothberger, and comments on the latter's(?) children. -- She will be playing movements 2 and
        3 of her piano concerto on the radio, and asks Schenker to listen. -- She has broken her
        left ankle.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Verewigter; Dahingeschiedener; deceased; Anteilnahme; sympathy; Knöchelbruch;
        ankle break; Aufführung; performance </dc:subject>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000227">Emma Fischer</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">
      <tei:opener>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">music notational monogram: treble clef with notes
          E – F (dotted halfnotes)</tei:note><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="authorial" place="inline">Das Briefpapier ein Geschenk d. l. kl. <tei:rs
            key="entity-003712" type="person">Agathe R</tei:rs> Monogramm von ihr
          verfertigt</tei:note><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:date when="1932-05-26">26/V 32</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Hochgeehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Doctor</tei:rs>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/5, p. 3733, May 27, 1932: "Von
            Baronesse Fischer (Br.): Beileid; bittet ihren Rundfunk-Vortrag anzuhören; hat sich
            einen Knöchelbruch zugezogen." (From Baroness Fischer (letter): commiserations; asks me
            to listen to her radio performance; has broken her ankle.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Da ich durch <tei:rs key="entity-002937" type="person">Familie
          Rothberger</tei:rs> weiß, daß Sie in dem nun Verewigten<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Alfred Rothberger, whose death is reported in Schenker's
          diary on May 24, 1932, OJ 4/5, p. 3732: "Mittags meldet der junge Rothberger das Ableben
          seines Vaters. Aus Freude an uns u. an sich gab er immer Freude, wenn er kam oder schrieb
          – es sei ihm herzlichst gedankt." ("At mid day the young Rothberger communicates the death
          of his father. Whenever he came or wrote, he forever conveyed joy, out of sheer joy toward
          us and in himself. He deserves heartfelt thanks.") — ibid, May 25: "An Frau Rothberger
          (Br. espress): ich drücke mein Beileid aus." ("To Mrs. Rothberger (express letter): I
          convey my commiserations."). </tei:note> einen nahestehenden wertvollen Freund verloren,
        erlaube ich mir, auch Ihnen meine aufrichtige Anteilnahme auszudrücken. Ich fühle innig mit
        den mir persönlich<tei:del rend="overstrike">en</tei:del> so lieb gewordenen, nicht
        zumindest in ihrem Familienleben hochgeschätzten Menschen und werde dem <tei:pb n="2"/>
        Dahingeschiedenen, der auch gegen mich immer voll Liebenswürdigkeit war, ein herzlich treues
        Gedenken bewahren! </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Das brave Mädi<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >little girl: presumably the daughter of Alfred and Hilda Rothberger.</tei:note> machte
        recht schöne Fortschritte, keine besonders raschen, aber ehrliche, spielt nett und
        musikalisch, sogar mit selbstverständlichem <tei:term><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
            >Rhythmus</tei:hi></tei:term> kleine <tei:term>Triomusik</tei:term> u. das ist doch
        gewiß f. ein 10 jähriges Kind viel. – Auch <tei:unclear reason="reading">Dal
          Becharf</tei:unclear>, die ungemeine Intelligenz besitzt, macht mir, wieder in anderer Art
        viel Freude. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Dieser Brief war Ihnen, hochgeehrter Herr Professor <tei:pb n="3"/> seit
        Sonntag zugedacht, – wohl hatte ich, da <tei:rs key="entity-000740" type="person"
          >Karl</tei:rs> meinte, sein guter <tei:rs key="entity-000738" type="person">Vater</tei:rs>
        sei außer Gefahr, noch keine Ahnung, daß ich ihn mit so traurigen Worten beginnen würde. —
          <tei:rs key="entity-000042" type="person">Dolfy Baudrexel</tei:rs> meinte nämlich, es wäre
        keine zu arge Kühnheit, Sie aufmerksam zu machen, daß ich nächsten Montag (<tei:date
          when="1932-05-30">30<tei:hi rend="supralinear">t</tei:hi></tei:date>) zwischen 5 u. 6 Uhr
        d. 2. u. 3. Satz meines eigenen <tei:term>Klavierkonzert</tei:term>s im Radio mit Orchester
        spiele u. Sie zu bitten, falls Zeit, Befinden, Stimmung es zulassen, die Sache
          anzuhören.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker's diary has
          no record of his listening to the concert on May 30 (OJ 4/5, p. 3733). However, for June
          1, 1932 (p. 3734) it records: "An Baronesse Fischer (Br.): Dank für ihr Beileid – Bravo
          zum Konzert." ("To Baroness Fischer (letter): thanks for her commiseration; 'Bravo' for
          the concert.").</tei:note> Vor 2 Jahren spielte ich d. 1. Satz, das wohl vertiefter ist. –
        Nun ist aber eine recht unliebsamen <tei:pb n="4"/> Wendung f. mich eingetreten: ich zog mir
        Sonntag nachmittag einen Knöchelbruch am linken Fuß zu, was für mich ein in den Folgen sehr
        trauriges Ereignis ist, – die Ärzte hoffen, daß ich Samstag 3. Probe und Montag z.
        Aufführung gebracht werden kann, was jedenfalls eine äußerst umständliche enervierende
        Expedition ist. Wie werde ich da spielen? – Mein ohnedies so armer Sommer ist nun noch
        betrüblicher geworden. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Mögen Sie, hochgeehrter Herr Professor, wie Ihre geehrte Frau <tei:rs
          key="entity-000771" type="person">Gemahlin</tei:rs><tei:supplied reason="syntax"
          >,</tei:supplied> ein<tei:sic>en</tei:sic> recht erholungsreich<tei:sic>en</tei:sic>
          befriedigend<tei:sic>en</tei:sic> Ferienzeit<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Corpus Christi, May 26, 1932, the day of writing, was a public holiday in
          Austria.</tei:note> entgegengehen: </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">dies wünscht, – mit innigen Grüßen –</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihre stets dankbare</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000227" type="person">Emma
          Fischer</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">
      <tei:opener>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">music notational monogram: treble clef with notes
          E – F (dotted halfnotes)</tei:note><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="authorial" place="inline">The notepaper <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
            >is</tei:supplied> a gift from the dear little <tei:rs key="entity-003712" type="person"
            >Agathe R</tei:rs>; monogram created by her.</tei:note><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:date when="1932-05-26">26/V 32</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Greatly revered Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
            type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Having learned through the <tei:rs key="entity-002937" type="person"
          >Rothberger family</tei:rs> that you have lost a close and valued friend in the recently
          deceased,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> permit me to express to you,
        too, my sincere sympathies. I feel keenly for those highly esteemed people who have become
        personally so dear to me, not least in their family life, and shall treasure a faithful
        memory of the <tei:pb n="2"/> deceased, who himself unfailingly showed great kindness even
        to me. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">The splendid little girl<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/>
        made really delightful progress, not particularly rapid, but forthright, plays
          <tei:term>trio music</tei:term> neatly and musically, not to mention with sturdy
          <tei:term>rhythm</tei:term> ‒ and that is saying a lot for a ten-year-old child. Also
          <tei:unclear reason="original unclear">Dal Becharf</tei:unclear>, who possesses uncommon
        intelligence, afforded me, albeit in a different way, much pleasure. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">This letter has been intended for you, dear Professor, <tei:pb n="3"/>
        ever since Sunday. As <tei:rs key="entity-000740" type="person">Karl</tei:rs> expressed the
        opinion that his good <tei:rs key="entity-000738" type="person">father</tei:rs> was out of
        danger, I never dreamt that I would be beginning it with such sorrowful words. — You see,
          <tei:rs key="entity-000042" type="person">Dolfi Baudrexel</tei:rs> assured me that it
        would be no undue presumption if I were to alert you to the fact that next Monday (the
          <tei:date when="1932-05-30">30th</tei:date>) between 5 and 6 I will be playing the second
        and third movements of my own <tei:term>piano concerto</tei:term> with orchestra on the
        radio, and to ask you, if time, health, and inclination permit, to listen to it.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> Two years ago, I played the first movement, which
        is a lot more deeply-felt. — Now, however, there has been a most unwelcome <tei:pb n="4"/>
        turn of events: on Sunday, I broke the ankle of my left foot, and this, with all its
        consequences, is a very distressing thing to have happened. The doctors hope that I can be
        got to the third rehearsal, on Saturday, and the performance on Monday, which will in any
        event be an extremely complicated and enervating expedition. How shall I play when I get
        there? My summer, which without this was already wretched, has now become an even sorrier
        affair. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">May you, highly revered Professor, and your dear lady <tei:rs
          key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs>, enjoy a truly relaxing and pleasant
          holiday.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">This wish comes with cordial greetings from</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your ever grateful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000227" type="person">Emma
          Fischer</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
