<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3379" sdoID="OJ-14-5_29">OJ 14/5, [29]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="MS" scope="sole">Moriz Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>


    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2023</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2023</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-21" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence">Schenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-004924">SchenkerM ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Moriz Schenker to Heinrich Schenker, dated January 14,
        1930</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1930-01-14T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-02-15</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Obtaining a mortgage on the Arzberg [investment property] is delayed; Moriz
        Schenker is exploring alternative possibilities of selling. -- He inquires as to the
        whereabouts of Hoboken. -- He reports that the [economic] situation in Germany is even worse
        than in Austria, because of the war reparations.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000774">Moriz Schenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
      
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#MS"/>Baden, <tei:date when="1930-01-14">14. Jänner
            1930</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Meine Lieben!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
            place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for January 16,
            1930: “Von Mozio (Br.): kann doch nicht sein Wort einlösen, führt mehrere Gründe an;
            fühlt sich gekränkt, nur um an meiner Lage vorbeigehen zu können.” (“From Mozio
            (letter): he is unable, after all, to keep his promise, citing various reasons; feels
            aggrieved, only so as to be able to ignore my situation.”). — In places where Moriz has
            inserted an emdash or endash and then embarked upon a new subject, a paragraph-break has
            here been editorially inserted.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Leider kann ich auch <tei:date when="1930-01-15">morgen</tei:date> zu Euch
        nicht kommen, weil ich telegrafisch nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004104"
          >Reichraming</tei:rs> gerufen werde. Ich hoffe am <tei:date when="1930-01-18"
          >Samstag</tei:date> wieder daheim zu sein. Es wäre mir sehr daran gelegen gewesen, Dich
        gerade morgen zu sehen, weil ich Dir die Restzahlung Deines Guthabens für Mitte Jänner in
        Aussicht gestellt habe.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >“Restzahlung Deines” (“the balance of your”) and “Mitte … habe” (“have the prospect ...
          January”): underlined in crayon by Heinrich, with “Mitte Jänner!” ("mid-January") written
          near the right top corner with arrow down to “Mitte” in the text.</tei:note> Leider muss
        ich Dich noch um etwas Geduld bitten, weil durch die furchtbaren Geldverhältnisse die
        Hypothekarinstitute sehr sehr langsam funktionieren. Zum Beweis führe ich folgendes an, was
        sehr leicht zu überprüfen ist. Die Oberoest. <tei:hi rend="underline"
        >Landes</tei:hi>hypotheken-Anstalt, welche mir eine Hypothek von S. 80000.– bereits früher
        zugesagt hat, kann vorläufig nichts machen, weil sie ihre Pfandbriefe jetzt nicht verwerten
        kann, und „momentan über deine flüssigen Mittel verfügt“. Ich werde vom Direktor D<tei:hi
          rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Pessel auf „baldmöglichst“ vertröstet. – Zweiter Fall. Herr
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005241">Direktor Blitz</tei:rs> von der
        Bodencredit-Anstalt (Hypothekar-Abtlg.) hat mir eine <tei:pb n="2"/> Hypothek unter noch
        günstigeren Bedingungen als bei der Landeshyp-Anstalt in Aussicht gestellt, kann aber
        momentan nicht „in’s meritorische“ übergehen, weil die Übertragungsformalitäten auf die
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-004959">Kredit-Anstalt</tei:rs> noch nicht ganz
        durchgeführt sind. Ich habe gerade heute früh mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005241"
          >Blitz</tei:rs> wieder gesprochen, und sagt er, dass es nicht mehr lange dauern wird. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ausserdem scheint das Erzbistum Wien (Monsignore D<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
          >r.</tei:hi> Wagner durch Vermittlung des Baumeisters Julius Stadler, Wien, I Akademiestr
        2) ernstliches Interesse für den Ankauf des Gutes als Erholungsheim für Priester zu haben.
        Es werden höchstwahrscheinlich in der zweiten Hälfte dieses Monates 2 Patres den <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-008410">Arzberg</tei:rs> besichtigen. Aber auch ein
        anderer Reflektant aus Deutschböhmen zeigt sich, denn er wird nächste Woche einen Experten
        zu mir schicken. Ich führe diese Tatsachen aus dem Grunde detailliert an, damit Du siehst,
        dass ich <tei:del rend="overstrike">mich</tei:del> mit allen Kräften trotz dieser kritischen
        Zeiten bemüht bin, meiner Verpflichtung nachzukommen, und damit Du die Beruhigung hast, dass
        ich noch für den in Frage kommenden Betrag gut bin, u. auch nicht die Absicht habe, mit dem
        Gute <tei:pb n="3"/> am Buckel jemandem durchzugehen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot">“nicht die Absicht ... durchzusehen” (“not have …
          property”): underlined in crayon by Heinrich.</tei:note> Heute sind die Zeiten solche,
        dass die reichen Leute alles besitzen, nur keine flüssigen Mittel. Ich bitte Dich also um
        etwas Geduld, und wirst Du sicher Dein Geld mit Zinsen so bald als es nur halbwegs möglich
        ist bekommen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">“wirst Du ...
          bekommen.” (“will be ... possible”): underlined in crayon by Heinrich. — Schenker’s diary
          for January 17, 1930 records Heinrich‘s reply: “An Mozio (Br.): ich habe kein Mißtrauen,
          ich brauche das Geld zum Eroica-Stich u. Druck; erwähne des Zinsenverlustes von 60 S. u.
          des Zinsenverlustes wegen des im Schranke behaltenen Hoboken-Honorars, – um nicht von
          einem Todesfall zu sprechen.” (“To Mozio (letter): I do not distrust him; I need the money
          for the engraving and publication of the "Eroica"; I mention the loss of interest of 60
          shillings and the loss of interest on account of Hoboken's fee, which is kept in a drawer,
          – to say nothing of the possibility of [my] death.”).</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich war vorige Woche in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs> wo die
        Situation noch schlechter ist, als bei uns. In einer gemeinsamen Sitzung der Deutschen Bank,
        Dresdner Bank u. Reichskreditges. habe ich von den maßgebenden Herren Ansichten gehört, die
        einem die Haare zu Berge stehen machen. Das deutsche Volk wird diese enormen Kriegsschulden
        nicht leisten können, ohne dass es zu inneren Umwälzungen politischer Art kommt, und dann
        werden die Herren Sieger bereuen, dass sie so weit gegangen sind.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Reference is to the reparations that the
          allied nations imposed on Germany through the 1919 Versailles Treaty for costs incurred by
          World War I.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ingenieur Kraft hat seinerzeit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hob.</tei:rs>
        telefonisch angerufen, u. sagte ihm ein Secretär, dass Herr <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000380">Hob.</tei:rs> verreist wäre. Nach einiger Zeit schrieb Kraft einen
        Brief, in welchem er unter Berufung auf Minister Resch u. noch einen Herrn (Namen mir
        entfallen) den <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hob.</tei:rs> frug, ob er Interesse
        für das bewusste Palais <tei:pb n="4"/> habe. Darauf ist Kraft ohne Antwort geblieben. Ist
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hob.</tei:rs> wirklich von Wien abwesend? Soll
        Kraft noch die Sache verfolgen? <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003139">Cast<tei:supplied
            reason="abbreviation">iglioni</tei:supplied></tei:rs> möchte gerne verkaufen, u. könnte
        man sich mit ihm leicht wegen des Preises und bequemer Zahlungsmodalitäten
        verständigen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich hoffe Euch nächste Woche zu sehen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial"
          place="foot"> The next visit by Moriz recorded in Heinrich’s diary is for February 12,
          1930: “Mozio erscheint um die Jausezeit, spricht kein Wort über seine Verpflichtung,
          möchte mir aber bei <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002402">Waldheim</tei:rs>
          beistehen!!” (“Mozio appears at teatime, says not a word about his obligations, but would
          like to offer assistance to me with <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002402"
            >Waldheim</tei:rs>!!”).</tei:note> wenn mich nicht die rumänischen Leute wieder nach
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs> verschicken. Inzwischen </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10"> verbleibe ich mit herzlichen Küssen</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">eur</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774"
          >Moriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>



    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#MS"/>Baden, <tei:date when="1930-01-14">January 14,
            1930</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">My dears,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"
          /></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Sadly I can’t come to you <tei:date when="1930-01-15">tomorrow</tei:date>
        after all, because I have been called by telegraph to go to <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-004104">Reichraming</tei:rs>. I hope to be back home again on <tei:date
          when="1930-01-18">Saturday</tei:date>. It would have been very opportune for me to see you
        right away tomorrow, because I have the prospect of paying you the balance of your asset
        holding in the middle of January.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> Alas, I
        must ask you to be patient a little longer, because the mortgage societies are, on account
        of the dreadful monetary conditions, functioning very, very slowly. As proof I cite the
        following, which is very easy to verify. The Upper Austrian <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >Agricultural</tei:hi> Mortgage Association, which earlier promised me a mortgage on
        80,000 shillings, can temporarily do nothing, because it cannot now realize its mortgage
        bonds, and “at the moment has your liquid funds at their command.” I am kept waiting “as
        little as possible” by Director Dr. Pessel. – Second case: <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-005241">Director Blitz</tei:rs> of the Boden Creditanstalt (mortgage division)
        holds out the prospect for me of a <tei:pb n="2"/> mortgage at still more favorable terms
        than those of the Agricultural Mortgage Association, but cannot move on to the approval
        stage because the transfer formalities to the <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-004959">Creditanstalt</tei:rs> are still not fully implemented. I have spoken
        directly with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005241">Blitz</tei:rs> this morning, and he
        says that it will not take much longer.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Furthermore, the Archdiocese of Vienna (Monsignor Dr. Wagner by the agency of master
        builder Julius Stadler, Vienna I, Akademiestrasse 2) appears to have a serious interest in
        the acquisition of the property for a convalescent home for priests. It is highly likely
        that two priests will inspect the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-008410"
          >Arzberg</tei:rs>
        <tei:supplied reason="definition">house</tei:supplied> in the second half of this month.
        However another prospective purchaser, from German Bohemia, has surfaced, for he will send
        me an expert next week. I am laying out these facts in such a detailed manner so that you
        can see that I am endeavoring with all my strength despite these critical times to fulfil my
        obligations, and so that you can have peace of mind that I am still good for the sum of
        money in question, and also that I do have no the <tei:pb n="3"/> intention of <tei:unclear
          reason="translation">going behind anyone's back</tei:unclear> with your property.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> Today’s times are such that rich people possess
        all, only no liquid funds. I therefore beg you to show a little patience, and you will be
        sure to get your money with interest as soon as remotely possible.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>The week before last, I was in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501"
        >Berlin</tei:rs>, where the situation is even worse than with us. In a joint meeting with
        the Deutsche Bank, Dresdner Band, and the Central German Credit Association, I heard views
        from men in authority that would make your hair stand on end. The German people will not be
        able to make these enormous war reparations without there being internal upheavals of a
        political nature, and then the victors will rue that they have gone so far.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Engineer Kraft telephoned <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs>
        recently and a secretary informed him that Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380"
          >Hoboken</tei:rs> was away. After a while, Kraft wrote a letter in which he asked <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs>, with reference to Minister Resch and
        another gentleman (whose name escapes me), whether he has any interest in the palace in
        question. <tei:pb n="4"/> Kraft has had no response. Is <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs> really away from Vienna? Should Kraft continue to
        pursue the matter? <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003139">Castiglioni</tei:rs> would like
        to sell, and it would be easy to come to an agreement with him over price and convenient
        payment terms.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I hope to see you next week,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> so long as
        the Rumanian people don’t send me back to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501"
          >Berlin</tei:rs>. In the meantime,</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">I remain, with heartfelt kisses</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774"
          >Moriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
