<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3903" sdoID="OJ-13-10_166a">OJ 13/10, [166a]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2025</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008551">Schmitt ~
        ROppel</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Dr. Schmitt, dated May 3, 1933</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1933-05-03T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2026-01-07</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel lists some of his compositions by category, including publishers' names,
        performers and performances. -- He offers to send copies of reviews. -- He mentions his work
        as chair of a cell of the Nazi Party investigating the history of the Leipzig
        Conservatory.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-008552">Schmitt, Dr.</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/>Leipzig, <tei:date when="1933-05-03">3. V
              33</tei:date>. W31, Könneritzstr 58<tei:hi rend="supralinear">III
            l</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008552">Dr.
            Schmitt</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Dr.
            Schmitt: this person has not been identified.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>wie mir mein Freund <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006121">Knettel</tei:rs> aus
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004583">Bingen</tei:rs> schreibt, wünschen Sie Auskunft
        über meine Kompositionen, deren Aufführungen und Erfolge. Hier ist ein Teil der Liste. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Männerchöre bei Kistner erschienen, meist von Lehrergesangvereinen aufgeführt (<tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002495">Frankfurt</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002589">Hamburg</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002840"
          >Düsseldorf</tei:rs>). </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Kirchenmusikalisches bei Vandenhoeck u Ruprecht in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-003046">Göttingen</tei:rs>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht: scholarly publishing house founded in Göttingen
          in 1735, not known as a major music publisher.</tei:note> Von Violinsonaten ist nur
        gedruckt Solosonate op 12 in d-moll bei Tischer u. Jagenberg,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot">There is also a Suite for solo violin in E minor, Op. 19, a
          Duet for two violins in A minor, Op. 22, and a Sonata for violin and piano in G minor, Op.
          7, and a Sonatina for violin and piano in D major, Op. 24. — Tischer &amp; Jagenberg:
          Cologne-based publishing house, which brought out several works by Frederick Delius and
          Arnold Schoenberg’s <tei:title level="m">Friede auf Erden</tei:title> Op. 13, as well as
          much music by Ewald Straesser (1867–1933), who taught at the Hochschule für Musik in
          Cologne.</tei:note> ein Werk, das von Hans Bassermann,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Hans Bassermann (1888–1978), German violinist, who held
          various teaching positions in Germany until 1933, when he was dismissed from his post at
          the Weimar Conservatory because he was Jewish. Oppel probably met him at the Leipzig
          Conservatory, where he taught for two years in the late 1920s.</tei:note> Walter
          Schulze-Prisca<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Walter
          Schulze-Prisca (1879–1957), German violinist, founder and leader of the Prisca
          Quartet.</tei:note> u. andern Geigern viel gespielt wurde u. noch gespielt wird.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Von den 4 Streichquartetten<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >String Quartets No. 2 in D minor, No. 3 in C minor, No. 4 in F minor (the key of No. 1 is
          not known). There is also a set of Variations and Fugue on a Theme by Bach for string
          quartet.</tei:note> ist nur das 4. in f-moll op 33 gedruckt, sehr viel gespielt. Ein
        Streichquintett ist Manuscript. Meine Bläserserenade für Flöte, Oboe, Klar. Fagott u. Horn
        ist ein von den Bläsern sehr begehrtes Stück; ein Quartett für Oboe, Violine, Viola u. Cello
        von 1932 ist erst zweimal aufgeführt, hier u. in Gera; es steigt demnächst im Rundfunk
        Mannheim. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Von Klaviersachen liegen op. 21, 26, 27 u 28<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Five Pieces for piano, Op. 21; Little Suite for piano, Op.
          26; Four Preludes for piano, Op. 27; Chaconne in B<tei:g type="flat"/> major for piano,
          Op. 28. There are also Three Preludes, in F minor, G<tei:g type="flat"/> major, and
            F<tei:g type="sharp"/> minor, and a Scherzo in D major and <tei:title level="m"
            >Tanzweise</tei:title> in G major, all for solo piano.</tei:note> gedruckt bei <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002890">Breitkopf u. Härtel</tei:rs> vor, op. 30 u 31 bei
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-008512">Mühlau</tei:rs> – <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002757">Kiel</tei:rs>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Suite in E major for piano, Op. 30; Two Etudes for piano, Op. 31. — Mühlau:
          the publisher and principal bookseller of the University of Kiel, founded in 1902 by
          Walter G. Mühlau.</tei:note> Die Klaviersonaten (3) sind Manuscript. Die <tei:foreign
          xml:lang="ita">a cap.</tei:foreign> Messe hat <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006121"
          >Knettel</tei:rs>
        <tei:pb n="2"/>
        <tei:sic><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006121">Knettel</tei:rs></tei:sic> in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-005401">Kreuznach</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-004583">Bingen</tei:rs> gebracht. Von Orchestersachen (Suiten) ist noch nichts
        aufgeführt. Deutsche Musik war ja seither nichts, dagegen <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-002793">Stravinsky</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000373"
          >Hindemith</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000156">Debussy</tei:rs>, <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-003707">Ravel</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000798">Schönberg</tei:rs>, Ausland u. Juden (<tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-003155">Schott-Verlag</tei:rs>!!) beherrschen das Feld. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich habe in letzter Zeit mich wenig bemüht, meine Sachen anzubringen, da ich bei der
        Genoss. deutscher Tonsetzer Mitglied bin u. die Virtuosen keine Tantiemen zahlen konnten bei
        den heutigen Geldlagen. Vielleicht bitten Sie einmal Kopatschka<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Cyrill Kopatschka (1909–76), German violinist, active in
          Darmstadt in the 1930s.</tei:note> – <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004486"
          >Darmstadt</tei:rs>, dass er Ihnen die Solosonate op 12 vorspielt u. Präludium u. Var für
        Kl u. Violine. Er wird es gern tun für mich u. wohnt <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-004486">Darmstadt</tei:rs>, Kasinostr 20<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
        >II</tei:hi>. Den besten Begriff von meiner Art erhalten Sie, wenn Sie sich das Quartett op
        33 in f-moll ansehn. Kleine Partitur bei <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002422"
          >Peters</tei:rs>. Leider kann ich Ihnen kein Ex. davon schicken, da ich selbst nur 2
        bekam, die ich längst gebraucht habe. Wenn Sie noch Kritiken wünschen, so stehn solche gern
        zu Ihrer Verfügung. Ich suche sie dann Ende der Woche heraus. Augenblicklich habe ich als
          Zellenobmann<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:hi
            rend="italic">Zellenobmann</tei:hi>: a term used by the National Socialist party for the
          chairman of a “cell,” or unit, in which a group of party members worked.</tei:note> des
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002872">Landeskonservatorium</tei:rs>s sehr viel
        zu tun, Sitzungen mit der Direction, dem Staatscommissar u. den Schülern, so dass ich vor
        Freitag nicht dazu komme. Wenn sie also noch Wert darauf legen, bitte ich um eine kurze
        Kartennachricht. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Hochachtungsvoll u. ergebenst</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Dr Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/>Leipzig, <tei:date when="1933-05-03">May 3,
              1933</tei:date>. W31, Könneritzstrasse 58<tei:hi rend="supralinear">III left
              side</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008552">Dr.
            Schmitt</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>My friend <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006121">Knettel</tei:rs> of <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-004583">Bingen</tei:rs> writes to me to say that you would like
        information about my compositions, their performances and successes. Here is a partial
        list.</tei:p>

      <tei:p> Male choruses, published by Kistner, performed mainly by teachers’ choral societies
          (<tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002495">Frankfurt</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002589">Hamburg</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002840"
          >Düsseldorf</tei:rs>).</tei:p>

      <tei:p> Sacred musical works, published by Vandenhoeck &amp; Ruprecht, <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-003046">Göttingen</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> Of
        my violin sonatas, only the unaccompanied Sonata in D minor, Op. 12, is published by Tischer
        &amp; Jagenberg,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> a work that has been
        performed many times by Hans Bassermann,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/>
        Walter Schulze-Prisca,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> and other violinists,
        and which is still performed.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Of my four string quartets,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> only No. 4
        in F minor is published, and very often performed. A String Quintet is in manuscript. My
        Wind Serenade, for flute, oboe, clarinet, bassoon and horn is a piece in great demand from
        wind players; a Quartet from 1932 for oboe, violin, viola and cello has only been performed
        twice, here and in Gera; it will soon be broadcast on Mannheim Radio.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Among my works for piano, Opp. 21, 26, 27, and 28<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07"
          type="footnote"/> are published by <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002890"
          >Breitkopf &amp; Härtel</tei:rs>, Opp. 30 and 31 by <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-008512">Mühlau</tei:rs> in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002757"
          >Kiel</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/> My piano sonatas, of which
        there are three, are in manuscript. My <tei:foreign xml:lang="ita"><tei:hi rend="italic">a
            cappella</tei:hi></tei:foreign> Mass <tei:pb n="2"/> was performed by <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-006121">Knettel</tei:rs> in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-005401">Kreuznach</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004583"
          >Bingen</tei:rs>. None of my orchestral works (suites) has yet been performed. Since then,
        German music has come to nought; the field is governed by <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-002793">Stravinsky</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000373"
          >Hindemith</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000156">Debussy</tei:rs>,
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003707">Ravel</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000798">Schoenberg</tei:rs>, foreigners and Jews (<tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-003155">Schott’s publishing house</tei:rs>!!).</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Recently I have made little effort to get my works played, as I am a member of the
        Society of German Composers and the virtuosos cannot pay royalties under the present-day
        financial circumstances. Perhaps you could ask Kopatschka<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09"
          type="footnote"/> in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004486">Darmstadt</tei:rs> to play
        my unaccompanied Sonata Op. 12 to you, and the Prelude and Variations for violin and piano.
        He would gladly do this for me; his address is Kasinostraße 20/II, <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-004486">Darmstadt</tei:rs>. You will understand the nature of my music best by
        looking at the <tei:supplied reason="clarity">String</tei:supplied> Quartet in F minor, Op.
        33; the miniature score is published by <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002422"
          >Peters</tei:rs>. Unfortunately, I cannot send you a copy of it as I myself received only
        two, which I have been using for a long time. If you would also like reviews, I shall gladly
        make them available to you; I shall then look for them at the end of the week. At the moment
        I have a great deal to do as the chair of the unit<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn10"
          type="footnote"/> at the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002872">State
          Conservatory</tei:rs>: meetings with the directorship, the state commissioner and the
        pupils, so I cannot get to this before Friday. If you are still interested in it, please
        send a short reply on a postcard.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Yours respectfully and most sincerely, </tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Dr. Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
