<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="36" sdoID="OJ-10-1_34">OJ 10/1, [34]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="WDa" scope="sole">Walter Dahms's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="JK">
   <tei:persName>John Koslovsky</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2009</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2009</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
   <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
   <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-02-07" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002725">Dahms ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   
   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Dahms to Schenker, dated July 29, 1918</dc:title>
   
   <dcterms:created>1918-07-29T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-01-30</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Dahms thanks Schenker for his long letter; reports on his vacation in Munich and
    visit with Vrieslander; he is looking forward to studying with Schenker in Vienna. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Munich; war; soldier; study; Tirol</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000149">Dahms</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Hochverehrter lieber
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>! </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Herzlichen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this
     letter is recorded at OJ 2/11, p. 927, August 2, 1918: "Von Dahms (Br.): erneuert die
     Anhänglichkeit, teilt von seiner neuen Mission mit u. erzählt vom Besuch bei Vrieslander."
     ("From Dahms (letter): re-affirms his devotion, intimating his newfound mission and recounting
     his visit to Vrieslander."). <!-- XR -->
    </tei:note> Dank für Ihren langen Brief,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker's letter is not known to survive. There is another entry recorded at OJ
     2/11, pp. 905-906, June 20, 1918: "Von Dahms (Br.): Glückwunsch, herzlich, innig." ("From Dahms
     (letter): best wishes, heartfelt, sincere."). Schenker's letter is recorded at OJ 2/11, p. 921,
     July 19, 1918: "An Dahms (Br.): Gründe der Verzögerung, Dank insbesondere für die
     Uebereinstimmung betreffs der Notwendigkeit einer Disziplin gegenüber dem Genie." ("To Dahms
     (letter): reasons for delay, thanks especially for his agreement over the necessity for a
     discipline with respect to genius."). <!-- XR -->
    </tei:note>
    <tei:unclear reason="reading">der</tei:unclear> mich sehr beglückt hat. Ich hätte Ihnen zum 50.
    Geburtstag so gern etwas Würdigeres geschrieben,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">See OJ 10/2, [33]. </tei:note> aber die Kraft reicht jetzt einfach nicht dazu.
    Wenn man fast 4 Jahre lang Soldat ist, dann kann man gerade noch Schmock markieren; mehr nicht.
    Es freut mich aber doch von Herzen, dass Sie wenigstens die Gesinnung herausgehört haben. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Mein Brief aus <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002286">München</tei:rs> fiel <tei:pb n="2"/> in meinen 14 tägigen Urlaub, von dem ich 10 Tage in
     <tei:placeName>München</tei:placeName> und Umgebung zubrachte. Ich hatte dort das Vergnügen (in
    jeder Beziehung) der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000447">Friedrich Klose</tei:rs>-Woche
    beiwohnen zu können. Jedoch fand ich das nötiger Purgator bei <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>, in dessen Behausung ich zwei prächtige unvergessliche Tage
    verlebte. Dort konnte ich endlich einmal mit jemandem sprechen, der von Ihnen erfüllt ist. Wenn
    mein „Wille zu Schenker“ (Wille zur Wahrheit) überhaupt noch stärker werden konnte, dann ist er
    es bei <tei:persName>Vrieslander</tei:persName> geworden.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Aber wie fern liegt die Zeit, wo ich endlich meine Pilgerfahrt nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Wien</tei:rs>
    <tei:pb n="3"/> antreten kann! An ein Ende des Krieges ist ja vorläufig garnicht zu denken. Aber
    nun besteht gute Aussicht, worüber Sie sich jedenfalls mit mir freuen werden, dass ich doch zum
    Herbst zur eigenen Arbeit kommen kann und zwar, wenn mir das Glück günstig ist, in
     <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002516">Kopenhagen</tei:rs>, woselbst ich die Zeitung einer
    Propagandazeitschrift übernehmen soll. Vorläufig schwebt die Angelegenheit noch; aber ich hoffe
    bestimmt, dass alles gut gehen wird. Für den Fall habe ich nun mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> einen brieflichen Austausch von theoretischen
    Arbeiten verabredet, der mich dann aus beste für Ihre eigene Unterweisung <tei:pb n="4"/>
    vorbereiten wird. Ich lebe jetzt in Hangen und Bangen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">"Hangen und Bangen" is the title of a poem by the German poet
     Theodore Fontane (1819-1898), to which Dahms is possibly alluding. </tei:note> Im Falle einer
    baldigen Entscheidung gebe ich Ihnen sogleich Nachricht. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich wünsche von Herzen, dass Sie doch noch nach
    <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002334">Tirol</tei:rs> gekommen sind. Was die Berge bedeuten, das habe
    ich jetzt wieder in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002338">Schliersee</tei:rs> pp. gesehen, d.h.
    ich bin ganz krank geworden vor Sehnsucht. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mit den herzlichsten Grüssen</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-25">Ihr stets dankbar ergebener</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-30">Walter Dahms</tei:signed>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine>Charlottenburg <tei:date when="1918-07-29">29./7.18.</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>Neue Kantstr. 1.</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dear, revered
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Master</tei:rs>, </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Thank<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> you very much for your long
     letter,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> which made me very happy indeed. I
    would have written something worthier for your fiftieth birthday,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> but I simply did not possess the strength to do so. When one has been a
    soldier for nearly four years, one can barely even write like a hack; but no more of that. It
    nevertheless makes me happy that at least you have heard my disposition.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>My letter from <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002286">Munich</tei:rs> came during
     <tei:pb n="2"/> my two-week vacation, of which I spent ten days in
     <tei:placeName>Munich</tei:placeName> and its surroundings. I had the pleasure (in every
    respect) of being present at the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000447">Friedrich
     Klose</tei:rs> week. However, I found the more necessary purgatory with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>, in whose house I spent two splendid and
    unforgettable days. There I could finally speak with someone who is up to your standards. If my
    "Will to Schenker" (that is, Will to the truth) could ever become stronger, then it does so when
    I am with <tei:persName>Vrieslander</tei:persName>.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>But how far away is the time when I can finally make my pilgrimage to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Vienna</tei:rs>! <tei:pb n="2"/> An end to the war is still not in
    sight. But my chances look good, something that you will feel happy about with me: I can finally
    get down to my own work in the fall. Indeed, if luck comes my way in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002516">Copenhagen</tei:rs>, I alone should take over the newspaper of a
    publicity journal. For the present the matter still remains up in the air, but I seriously hope
    that all will go well. For one thing, I have arranged for a regular exchange with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> on theoretical matters that will best <tei:pb n="2"/> prepare me for your own instruction. I now live in fear and trembling.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> In case I make a quick decision to come I will tell you
    straight away.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>I nevertheless truly wish that you are still off in the
    <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002334">Tyrol</tei:rs>. What the mountains signify I have
    discovered in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002338">Schliersee</tei:rs> by proxy; namely, I have
    become sick with longing.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">With the most cordial greetings, </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-25">Your ever thankful devotee, </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-30">Walter Dahms</tei:signed>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine>Charlottenburg <tei:date when="1918-07-29">July 29,
      1918</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>Neue Kantstraße 1</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>