<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="2278" sdoID="OJ-15-16_4">OJ 15/16, [4]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HW" scope="sole">Hans Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB-WD">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent and William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2007</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2007</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-06-25" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated June 1, 1912</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1912-06-01T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-10-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Weisse is concerned that Schenker will turn his attention from himself to Felix
    Hupka, whom Schenker has just taken on as a pupil.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Fortschritt; progress; Genius; Lehrer; teacher; Meister; master; Freund; friend;
    Interesse; interest; wenden; to turn</dc:subject>



   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000951">Weisse</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Geliebter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>!<tei:note
      xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is not recorded in
      Schenker's diary.</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>


   <tei:p>Wenn ich Ihnen jetzt schreibe, so geschieht es aus dem Empfinden heraus, dass zwischen
    zwei sich nahestehenden Menschen alles deutlich und klar sein muss, alles das zur Verhütung
    eines Missverständnisses, das an sich wieder eine Trübung mit sich bringen könnte. Und dass ich
    Ihnen nahestehe werden Sie wohl selbst wissen, liebster Doktor, dass ich in Ihnen gleichsam
    meinen „geistigen Erzeuger“ sehe, wohl verstehen! Was also mein Begehren, was die Ursache einer
    so langen Einleitung sei? Bevor ich Ihnen die Antwort auf diese Frage gebe, muss ich Sie bitten,
    das folgende als Äusserung eines sehr empfindsamen Seele anzusehen und darin nur das Bedürfnis
    eines völligen Ehrlichkeitsgefühls Ihnen gegenüber zu erkennen. Ich habe also tatsächlich von
    Woche zu Woche im Verkehre mit Ihnen meinen Fortschritten folgen können und habe Sie als meinen
    guten Genius zu nennen mir angewöhnt. Ging ich auf der Gasse, war ich inmitten der Arbeit – kurz
    bei jeder geistigen Tätigkeit habe ich Zwiesprache mit Ihnen gehalten, indem ich in Ihnen die
    höchste Instanz, den Zensor meiner Arbeit empfand und stets mit fragenden Blicken zu Ihnen
    aufsah! Könnte es Sie also wundern, wenn ich bei einem solch regen Verkehr bald
     aufhörte<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> den Lehrer und Meister in Ihnen zu
    erblicken, sondern auch das Bedürfnis fand, Sie wie einen Freund zu lieben, und dies so edel und
    schön als es einer Menschenseele nur gegeben ist!?</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Sei’s mit Recht oder Unrecht, hat nun mein wachsendes Gefühl auch bei
    Ihnen <tei:sic>einen</tei:sic> sich mehrendes Interesse zu vernehmen ge<tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">freut</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">meint</tei:add>
    </tei:subst>, das nur die grösste Freude <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">ab</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">bereitete</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> und als schönste Erwerbung, als Verdienst meines bisherigen Strebens schien. Nun
    hat sich die Sonne verdüstert und an ihr freilich liegt es mich wieder froh und arbeitslustig zu
    machen. Ich habe <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">nun</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">nämlich</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> ein wenig befürchtet, dass wenn der kleine <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000399">Hupka</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"
     >Schenker's diary for June 30 (which seems to review the entire month), p. 204, records:
     "Aufnahme eines neuen Schülers, Felix Hupka, der sich zuerst an d’Albert wendete u. erst über
     dessen Empfehlung zu mir kam (Theorie u. Klavierspiel)[.]" ("Acceptance of a new pupil, Felix
     Hupka, who first turned to d'Albert, and only came to me (for theory and piano playing) after
     his recommendation.").</tei:note> begabter wäre, <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">wie</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">als</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> ich, sich Ihr Interesse doch, was sehr leicht begreiflich wäre, von mir langsam zu
    ihm wenden würde, und ich tatsächlich hier einen doppelter Verlust<tei:supplied
     reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> den des Lehrers und den des Freundes <tei:supplied
     reason="punctuation">–</tei:supplied> zu erleiden hätte!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Dies die Sorge, die mich nun ganz traurig und arbeitsmüde gemacht hat! Nehmen Sie’s nur
     <tei:hi rend="underline">nicht</tei:hi> übel!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Nehmen Sie’s infantil, stult,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"
     >Possibly from Latin <tei:hi rend="italic">stultus</tei:hi>, vain, silly, foolish. </tei:note>
    feminin, liebster Doktor<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> es war die Äusserung
    eines ehrlichen Gefühls</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute>von Ihrem</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
     >Hans</tei:rs>.</tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:date when="1912-06-01">1. Juni, 1912</tei:date>. </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Beloved <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Master</tei:rs><tei:ptr
      corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>


   <tei:p>If I am writing to you now, it is from the feeling that, between two persons who are close
    to one another, everything must be clear and open, to guard against any misunderstanding that
    might result in a further clouding of their relationship. And that I stand in a close relation
    to you is something, dearest Doctor, that you yourself know; that I see in you my "spiritual
    creator," so to speak, is something you understand well. What, then, is my request, what might
    be the cause of such a long introduction? Before I give you the answer to this question, I must
    ask you to regard the following as the expression of a very sensitive soul and to recognize
    therein the need for a complete sense of honesty on your part. I have indeed been able to follow
    my progress from week to week in my work with you and have grown accustomed to calling you my
    good genius. If I was walking down the street, or in the midst of work ‒ in short, during any
    spiritual activity ‒ I held a dialogue with you, since I saw in you the highest authority, the
    censor of my work, and I always looked up to you with questioning glances! Could you be
    surprised, then, if after such a close association I were soon to cease merely to regard you as
    my teacher and master, but also found the need to love you as a friend, and to do so as nobly
    and beautifully as a human soul possibly can!?</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Rightly or wrongly, my growing feelings led me to <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">be glad</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">believe</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> that I could perceive an increasing interest on your part, that brought only the
    greatest joy and seemed to be the most beautiful acquisition, as the earnings of my previous
    efforts. Now the sun has cast a shadow, and it is up to her to make me happy and keen to work
    once more. I have <tei:add place="interlinear-above">in fact</tei:add> feared that, if the
    little <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000399">Hupka</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
     type="footnote"/> were more gifted than I, your interest would after all ‒something that would
    be easily understandable ‒ turn aside from me toward him, and I would have to suffer a double
    loss, that of a teacher and that of a friend!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>This is the concern that has made me so sad and work-weary now! But please do <tei:hi
     rend="underline">not</tei:hi> think badly of me on account of it!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>You may regard it as infantile, foolish,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/>
    feminine, dearest Doctor: it was the expression of an honest feeling</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute>from your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
     >Hans</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:date when="1912-06-01">June 1, 1912</tei:date>
   </tei:closer>


  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
