<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3806" sdoID="OJ-13-10_198">OJ 13/10, [198]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2025</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008522">Oppel ~
        JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Jeanette Schenker, dated April 3, 1938</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1938-04-03T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-09-24</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel hopes that, following the annexation of Austria to Germany, it will be
        easier for him to visit Jeanette. – He has completed his work on the revised edition of
        Schenker’s Harmonielehre and makes some suggestions regarding its publication. – He was not
        pleased to read that Furtwängler championed Walter Riezler’s recently published book on
        Beethoven.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1938-04-03">3. IV 38</tei:date>.
          </tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Meine liebe sehr verehrte <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000771">Frau D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi>
          Schenker</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Durch die Correcturen der Beispiele für <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922"
          >Vrieslander</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Oppel had
          offered to help Otto Vrieslander with the identification of the music examples from
          original edition of Schenker’s <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724"><tei:title
              level="m">Harmonielehre</tei:title></tei:rs> (1906) that were to be included in the
          planned revised edition.</tei:note> bin ich nicht so frühe zur Antwort an Sie gekommen,
        als ich wollte. Inzwischen habe ich alles erledigt, was er wissen wollte, bis auf das Citat
        von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000025">Ph. E. Bach</tei:rs>’s Klavierkot, das ich
        hier nirgends erreichen konnte. Wahrscheinlich hat es der Meister selbst abgeschrieben auf
        einer der Wiener Bibliotheken. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun sind Sie schon wieder 6 Wochen im sonnigen Süden,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot">On April 2, 1938 Jeanette Schenker was staying at the
          Pension Regina in Gries-Bolzano. The length of her stay there is unclear.</tei:note>
        inmitten der Berge. Dieses Jahr hoffe ich Sie auch zu sehn; vielleicht gehe ich mit einem
        Collegen 18 Tage nach Italien und anschliessend nach <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002506">Österreich</tei:rs>, wenn nichts dazwischen kommt. Nun, nachdem wir
        ein <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482">Deutschland</tei:rs> sind, gibt es ja keine
        Schwierigkeiten mehr zu überwinden. Ich glaube, über die Lösung, wie sie <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-003109">Hitler</tei:rs> so unblutig vollzogen, hätte sich auch
        unser geliebter Toter gefreut.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">By
          these remarks, Oppel indicates that he welcomed the annexation of Austria to Germany (the
            <tei:hi rend="italic">Anschluss</tei:hi>) three weeks earlier, on March 12.</tei:note> – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun zunächst einmal zu dem Neudruck:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial"
          place="foot">i.e. the planned new edition of Schenker’s <tei:rs type="work"
            key="entity-001724"><tei:title level="m">Harmonielehre</tei:title></tei:rs>, vol. I of
          the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001723"><tei:title level="m">Neue Musikalische
              Theorien und Phantasien</tei:title></tei:rs>.</tei:note> ich habe auch schon <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000922">Vr.</tei:rs> geschrieben, ob es nicht billiger wäre, den
        Text allein zu drucken, u. die Beispiele alle in einem Notenband im gleichen Format mit den
        laufenden Ziffern; die Unterbrechung des Textes durch Noten ist immer teurer. Und wer genau
        studiert, sieht die Beispiele doch auch im Zusammenhang des Stückes an. Das ist also eine
        Arbeit. Wie wird sich denn nun die <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408"
          >U-E</tei:rs> unter den neuen Verhältnissen zu dem Neudruck verhalten? <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000320">Haas</tei:rs> hat gar nicht so Unrecht, aber ich würde
        an <tei:pb n="2"/> die ganze Sachlage besprechen. Ohne Kenntnis des alten und neuen Vertrags
        kann ich von hier aus ja nicht urteilen. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs> ist ein merkwürdiger
        Mensch, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000714">Riezler</tei:rs>, den Meister Schenker ja
        ablehnte, förderte er, wie Sie aus beil. Bücherbesprechung sehn, die ich mir zurückerbitte.
        Ich habe das Buch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot"
              ><tei:bibl><tei:author>Walter Riezler</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m"
              >Beethoven</tei:title> (Zurich: Hug, 1936)</tei:bibl>. The book went through many
          editions and was translated into several languages; Furtwängler provided a foreword to the
          second edition. Riezler was first trained in the study of archaeology and art history by
          Adolf Furtwängler, the conductor’s father. He gave Wilhelm piano lessons and also
          instructed him in classical languages. </tei:note> noch nicht gelesen, aus Zeit- u.
        Geldmangel. Gespannt bin ich aber doch auf die „genaue“ Analyse des 1. <tei:rs
          type="composition" key="entity-001263"><tei:title>Eroica</tei:title></tei:rs>satzes von
        diesem Herrn <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000714">R</tei:rs>! Der Schweizer Verlag Hug
        ist auch ein zweischneidiges Schwert, nimmt lieber, als er gibt. Darin gleichen sich alle. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich mache schon gar keinen Versuch mehr, irgend ein Stück unterzubringen, zumal bei der
        heutigen Entwickelung der Musik und des Geschmacks nach der motorischen und negroiden Seite
        her. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p> Innerhalb der Familie geht alles gut, bis auf den jüngsten Bruder von <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-003957">Walter</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial"
          place="foot">That is, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008510">Hans Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:note> der zwar jetzt seiner Militärpflicht in Darmstadt genügt, der
        mir aber dauernd schwereren Ärger u. pecuniäre Sorgen bereitet. Er ist leider von seiner
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006150">verstorbenen Mutter</tei:rs> u. s. Tante
        gründlich verzogen worden, und ich muss nun dafür büssen, damit die Bäume nicht in den
        Himmel wachsen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07nzer" type="editorial" place="foot">Cf.
          Nietzsche’s aphorism “No tree can grow in Heaven without sending its roots down to
          Hell.”</tei:note> – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun haben wir noch eine Woche Schule mit vielen Prüfungen, und ich bin froh, wenn
        dieser lange, anstrengende Winter vorüber. Ich gehe mit <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-008523">Bepo</tei:rs> am <tei:date when="1938-04-11">11.</tei:date> für 14
        Tage in die Thüringer Heimat, um meine Archivstudien fortzusetzen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ihnen wünsche ich Sonne und einen gesegneten Aufenthalt in den Bergen und verbleibe mit
        den herzlichsten Grüssen an Sie von uns allen </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Ihr treuer u. dankbarer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1938-04-03">April 3,
              1938</tei:date>
          </tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">My dear, very revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
            >Mrs. Schenker</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Because I was proof-reading the music examples for <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
        I was not able to get round to replying to you as quickly as I had hoped. In the meantime, I
        have dealt with everything that he wanted to know, except for the quotation from <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000025">C. P. E. Bach</tei:rs>’s Piano Concerto, which I cannot
        get hold of anywhere here. Probably the Master copied it out himself in one of the Vienna
        libraries.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Now you are again in the sunny south for six weeks, in the midst of the
          mountains.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> This year, I am also hoping to
        see you; I may go to Italy with a colleague for eighteen days, and subsequently to <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002506">Austria</tei:rs> if nothing intervenes. Now that we have
        become a single <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482">Germany</tei:rs>, there are surely
        no more obstacles to overcome. I believe that our beloved deceased would also have been
        delighted by the solution, as <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003109">Hitler</tei:rs> has
        achieved it, without bloodshed.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>First of all, concerning the new edition:<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"
        /> I have also written to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>
        already, to say that it might be cheaper to print the text on its own and all the examples
        in a volume of music which has the same format, and the examples with consecutive numbering;
        interrupting the text with music examples is always more expensive. And anyone who studies
        the work carefully will of course see each example also in connection with the piece
          <tei:supplied reason="clarity">to which it refers</tei:supplied>. That will be a job. How
        will <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">Universal Edition</tei:rs> act with
        regard to the revised edition under the new circumstances? <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000320">Haas</tei:rs> may actually have a point, but I would <tei:pb n="2"/>
        discuss the entire state of affairs. Without knowledge of the old and new contract, I am
        unable to make a judgment from where I stand. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs> is a strange person; he
        is supporting <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000714">Riezler</tei:rs>, whom Master
        Schenker clearly rejected; you can see this from the enclosed book review, which I ask you
        to return. I have not yet read the book,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> on
        account of lack of time and money. But I am indeed eager to see the “precise” analysis of
        the first movement of <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001263"><tei:title level="m"
            >Eroica</tei:title></tei:rs> by this Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000714"
          >R.</tei:rs>! The Swiss publishing house Hug is also a two-edged sword, which takes more
        than it gives. In that respect, they are all the same. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>I no longer make any attempt to get any of my works performed, all the more so given
        the present development in music and taste towards the motoric and Negroid side.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Within the family everything is going well, except for the youngest brother of <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-003957">Walter</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> who
        is now indeed fulfilling his military obligation in Darmstadt but is constantly giving me
        great trouble and financial worries. He was, unfortunately, thoroughly spoiled by his
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006150">late mother</tei:rs> and his aunt, and I must
        now pay the price for this, lest the trees grow in Heaven.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07"
          type="footnote"/> –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>We now have a further week of school, with many examinations; and I shall be glad when
        this long, strenuous winter is over. I shall go with <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-008523">Bepo</tei:rs> on the <tei:date when="1938-04-11">11th</tei:date> for
        two weeks in my Thuringian homeland, to continue my archival studies.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I wish you sun and a blessed stay in the mountains and, with the most cordial greetings
        to you from all of us, I remain</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Your faithful and grateful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
