<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="1874" sdoID="OJ-11-54_40">OJ 11/54, [40]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPavh" scope="major">Anthony van Hoboken as typist</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="AvH" scope="minor">Anthony van Hoboken's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="JR-HE">
      <tei:persName>John Rothgeb and Heribert Esser</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2016</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2016</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2016</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2013-02-16" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002730">Hoboken ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002731">Hoboken ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Typewritten letter from Hoboken to Schenker, dated July 29, 1932</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1932-07-29T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2016-11-07</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Hoboken comments on some contemporary music; — he comments adversely on the
        new edition by Edouard Ganche of Chopin's works; — he may visit the Schenkers and bring Eva
        Boy with him.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Programmheft; program book; Konzert; concert; Publikum; public; Beifall; applause;
        Ausgabe; edition; Original-Ausgabe; original edition; Archiv; archive; Bemerkung; comment;
        Verbesserung; improvement; Text; Aenderung; alteration; Fehler; mistake; Photogramm;
        photogram</dc:subject>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000380">Hoboken</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">Heinrich Schenker</marcrel:recipient>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">Jeanette Schenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#TPavh"/>Partenkirchen, bei Dr. W.
            Grahl</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:date when="1932-07-29">29 Juli
          1932</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Lieber und verehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000643">Dr.</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
            place="foot">Receipt of this letter (in Igls, Tyrol) is recorded in Schenker's diary at
            OJ 4/5, p. 3754, July 30, 1932: "Von v. Hoboken (Br.): Dank für die Programme; über die
            französische Chopin-Ausgabe; kommt „vielleicht“ mit Frl. Boy, wann, fragt er?" ("From
            Hoboken (letter): thanks for the programs; concerning the French edition of Chopin; he
            will "perhaps" come with Miss Boy; when, he asks?").</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Vielen Dank für Ihre freundliche Karte vom <tei:date when="1932-07-15">15
          Juli</tei:date> und für die Sendung Programmhefte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot">No postcard of this date from Hoboken is known to
          survive.</tei:note> Davon kannt<tei:supplied reason="syntax">e</tei:supplied> ich
        allerdings schon einige, denn ich habe <tei:add place="interlinear-above"><tei:handShift
            new="#AvH"/>mir</tei:add>
        <tei:handShift new="#TPavh"/>ein Paar Konzerte dieses Katzenmusikfestes angehört. Ich muss
        zu meiner Freude bekennen, dass das Publikum sich derartige Musik doch nicht mehr
        widerspruchslos gefallen lässt. Nur an dem Abend, wo die "<tei:title>Musik zu einer
          Lichtspielszene</tei:title>" von <tei:rs key="entity-000798" type="person"
          >Schönberg</tei:rs> und "<tei:title>Der Wein</tei:title>" von <tei:rs key="entity-000061"
          type="person">Alban Berg</tei:rs> aufgeführt wurde, spendete es, besonder nach dem zweiten
        Stück, frenetischen Beifall. Worauf das zurückzuführen ist, ist mir allerdings ein Rätsel,
        denn, wenn man auch immer wieder behauptet<tei:supplied reason="punctuation"
          >,</tei:supplied> dass <tei:rs key="entity-000061" type="person">Berg</tei:rs> "ernster"
        Streber sei (wohl im Gegensatz zu den anderen Musikern von heute, die dann nicht "ernst" zu
        sein scheinen)<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> so kommt das Stück doch
        nicht über dem Niveau eines Zeilenprogrammstückes hinaus. Ich meine damit, dass jede Zeile
        des schönen Gedichtes von Baudelaire, welches in der Uebersetzung von <tei:rs
          key="entity-003810" type="person">Stefan George</tei:rs> zunächst seiner Hauptbuchstaben
        und Interpunktionszeichen beraubt worden ist, irgendwie getonmalt worden ist, der Sinn des
        ganzen aber nicht erfasst wurde. Leider fehlte gerade von diesem Konzert das Programmheft,
        weil <tei:rs key="entity-000164" type="person">Deutsch</tei:rs> nicht darin war; ich habe
        meines auch nicht aufgehoben, sonst hätte ich es Ihnen noch gerne geschickt.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Die neue <tei:rs key="entity-000129" type="person">Chopin</tei:rs>-Ausgabe
        von <tei:rs key="entity-003553" type="person">Edouard Ganch</tei:rs><tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">The
              Oxford Original Edition of Frédéric Chopin</tei:title>, edited from the original
            edition and the manuscripts by <tei:editor>Edouard Ganche</tei:editor>, vols 1–3
            (London: Oxford University Press, 1932)</tei:bibl>. The dated notes on Hoboken's lessons
          with Schenker end at February 23, 1932 (OC 3/4, lessonbook 1931/32). There is a set of
          undated notes at OC 30/52‒63 devoted to Hoboken's lessons, and p. 56r reads: "van Hoboken
          / Ganche, <tei:hi rend="double-underline">Manuscript</tei:hi> (Archive) / <tei:hi
            rend="underline">Eschevich</tei:hi>, / <tei:hi rend="underline">Kobenheyer</tei:hi>,
            <tei:hi rend="underline">Faulhaber</tei:hi> / <tei:title level="j">Die
          Musik</tei:title>, 2 issues / <tei:title level="j">Zeitschrift für
            Musikwissenschaft</tei:title>, 2 issues / Schlesinger / Breitkopf &amp; Härtel prints
          [...]" Whether these have anything to do with the present letter is unclear (July was of
          course outside the season).</tei:note> enthält auf den ersten Blick manche gute Sachen,
        die andere Ausgaben nicht haben. Leider geht aus nichts hervor, welche Stücke nach dem
          <tei:term>Autograph</tei:term> und welche nach der <tei:term>Original-Ausgabe</tei:term>
        redigiert worden sind. An den Mazurken Op. 24 habe ich jedoch schon feststellen können, dass
        sie nach der <tei:sic>Schlesinger!schen</tei:sic>
        <tei:term>Originalausgabe</tei:term> redigiert worden sind. Sie enthalten alle Fehler
        derselben, und noch ein Paar. Das <tei:term>Autograph</tei:term>, welches ja im <tei:rs
          key="entity-002890" type="organization">Breitkopf</tei:rs>'schen
          <tei:sic>Archive</tei:sic> ruht, scheint <tei:rs key="entity-003553" type="person"
          >Ganche</tei:rs> nicht gesehen zu haben<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied>
        und ein oberflächlicher Ueberblick lässt mich vermuten, dass er aus jenem Archiv überhaupt
        keine <tei:term>Autograph</tei:term>en eingesehen hat. Ob er sie nicht bekommen hat? Er
        weiss jedenfalls ganz genau, welche sich dort befinden.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> Interessant ist aber, dass er die französische
          <tei:term>Originalausgabe</tei:term>n aus dem Besitz der Miss Stirling hat einsehen
        können, in welchen <tei:rs key="entity-000129" type="person">Chopin</tei:rs> während des
        Unterrichts Bemerkungen und Verbesserungen eingetragen hat. So in dem <tei:title>c-moll
          Praeludium</tei:title> ein Bé vor dem e' im vierten <tei:term>Viertel</tei:term> von Takt
        3, wo man, dem gedruckten Text nach eigentlich e' spielen sollte (während ich dort immer
        schon es' gespielt habe) und ferner eine sehr merkwürdige <tei:subst>
          <tei:del><tei:gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" extent="12"/></tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">Aenderung</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> in der <tei:rs key="entity-001418" type="composition"><tei:title>gis-moll Etude
            aus Op. 25</tei:title></tei:rs>, wo er in Takt 42 die beiden cis' bei der l.H. im 6ten
        und 7ten<tei:term> Achtel</tei:term> in c, also eigentlich in his, verwandelt haben soll. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Das Vorwort ist leider sehr arrogant; besonders die Bemerkung, dass die
          französische<tei:supplied reason="syntax">n</tei:supplied>
        <tei:term>Original-Ausgabe</tei:term>n, trotz ihrer Fehler, immer noch besser seien als die
        deutschen, ist nicht zutreffend. Ich hoffe, wenn ich Sie einmal besuchen sollte, Ihnen einen
        Band mitbringen zu können; ich bin jetzt dabei, die Ergebnisse, die wir in den Stunden aus
        dem Vergleich der Photogrammen mit den <tei:term>Or.<tei:supplied reason="abbreviation"
            >iginal</tei:supplied>-Ausgabe</tei:term>n herausbekommen haben, mit der neuen Ausgabe
        zu vergleichen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Wie geht es Ihnen in <tei:rs key="entity-002380" type="place"
          >Igls</tei:rs>? Ist es Ihnen dort nicht zu <tei:choice>
          <tei:sic><tei:foreign xml:lang="fre">mondain</tei:foreign></tei:sic>
          <tei:corr>mondän</tei:corr>
        </tei:choice>? Sie werden wohl das gleiche Wetter haben, wie wir hier, also meistens Regen
        und wenig Sonnenschein. Vielleicht komme ich, mit <tei:rs key="entity-000093" type="person"
          >Frl. Boy</tei:rs>, doch einmal zu Ihnen herüber; es ist ja nicht sehr weit. Um welche
        Tageszeit sind Sie meistens zu Hause? </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Mit den besten Grüssen, ebenfalls an Ihre <tei:rs key="entity-000771"
          type="person">Gattin</tei:rs>, bin ich, wie immer</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">Ihr sehr ergebener</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#AvH"/><tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000380">AvHoboken</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#TPavh"/>Partenkirchen, c/o Dr. W.
            Grahl</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:date when="1932-07-29">July 29,
          1932</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dear and revered Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs
              type="person" key="entity-000643">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Many thanks for your friendly card of <tei:date when="1932-07-15">July
          15</tei:date> and for sending program-books.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"
        /> I already knew some of them, to be sure, since I have heard a few concerts of this
        musical-rubbish festival. I must attest, to my satisfaction, that the public no longer
        accepts such music without reservation. Only on the evening when the <tei:title level="m"
          >Music for a Film Scene</tei:title> by <tei:rs key="entity-000798" type="person"
          >Schoenberg</tei:rs> and <tei:title level="m">Der Wein</tei:title> by <tei:rs
          key="entity-000061" type="person">Alban Berg</tei:rs> was performed did it bestow ‒
        especially after the second piece ‒ frenetic applause. Where the explanation for that might
        lie is, to be sure, a riddle to me; for if people constantly repeat that <tei:rs
          key="entity-000061" type="person">Berg</tei:rs> is a "serious" aspirant in his work (no
        doubt in contrast to the other musicians of today, who thus do not appear to be "serious"),
        the piece still fails to rise above the level of a line-by-line programmatic work. By that I
        mean that each line in the beautiful poem by Baudelaire – which, in the translation by
          <tei:rs key="entity-003810" type="person">Stefan George</tei:rs>, first of all is stripped
        of its capitalization and punctuation – has been somehow tone-painted, but the meaning of
        the whole has not been grasped. Unfortunately the program-book of precisely this concert is
        missing, since <tei:rs key="entity-000164" type="person">Deutsch</tei:rs> was not present; I
        didn't save mine either, else I would have been glad to send it to you.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">The new <tei:rs key="entity-000129" type="person">Chopin</tei:rs> edition
        by <tei:rs key="entity-003553" type="person">Edouard Ganche</tei:rs><tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> contains at first glance many good things that
        other editions lack. Unfortunately it is nowhere made clear which pieces have been revised
        according to the <tei:term>autograph manuscript</tei:term> and which according to the
          <tei:term>original edition</tei:term>. Regarding the Mazurkas Op. 24, however, I was
        already able to discover that they are revised according to the Schlesinger (!)
          <tei:term>original edition</tei:term>. They include all of its errors and a few more. The
        manuscript, which of course resides in the <tei:rs key="entity-002890" type="organization"
          >Breitkopf</tei:rs> archive, <tei:rs key="entity-003553" type="person">Ganche</tei:rs>
        appears not to have seen, and a superficial inspection supports my assumption that he has
        examined none of the manuscripts from that archive. Did he not receive them? In any case, he
        knows perfectly well which of them are there.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> It is interesting, though, that he was able to examine the
        French <tei:term>original edition</tei:term> from the collection of Miss Stirling, in which
          <tei:rs key="entity-000129" type="person">Chopin</tei:rs> entered comments and
        improvements in the course of teaching. Thus in the <tei:title>C minor Prelude</tei:title>,
        a flat sign before the e’ in the fourth <tei:term>quarter</tei:term> of bar 3, where
        according to the printed text one is actually supposed to play e’ (while I have always
        played e<tei:g type="flat"/>’ at that point), and also a very noteworthy <tei:subst>
          <tei:del><tei:gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" extent="12"/></tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">alteration</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> in the <tei:rs key="entity-001418" type="composition"><tei:title>G<tei:g
              type="sharp"/> minor Etude from Op. 25</tei:title></tei:rs>, where in bar 42 he is
        supposed to have changed the two occurrences of c<tei:g type="sharp"/>’ in the left hand in
        the sixth and seventh <tei:term>eighths</tei:term> to c, thus really to b<tei:g type="sharp"
        />.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">The Foreword is unfortunately very arrogant; especially the comment that
        the French <tei:term>original edition</tei:term>s, despite their errors, are always better
        than the German, is not accurate. I hope, when I should visit you some time, to be able to
        bring along a volume to you; I am just now in process of comparing with the new edition the
        information that we gained in the lesson from comparison of the photostats with the
          <tei:term>original edition</tei:term>s.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">How are you faring in <tei:rs key="entity-002380" type="place"
          >Igls</tei:rs>? Is it not too fashionable there for you? You will probably have the same
        weather as we here, thus mostly rain and little sunshine. Perhaps I shall after all come,
        with <tei:rs key="entity-000093" type="person">Miss Boy</tei:rs>, to see you sometime; it is
        really not very far. What time of day are you usually in?</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">With best greetings, also to your <tei:rs key="entity-000771"
          type="person">wife</tei:rs>, I am, as always,</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">Your very devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#AvH"/><tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000380">A. v. Hoboken</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
