<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="3589" sdoID="OJ-13-10_12">OJ 13/10, [12]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2010</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">
  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated November 21, 1922</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1922-11-21T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-04-24</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Oppel reports the imminent publication of an article by him in the Zeitschrift
    für Musikwissenschaft. -- He makes clear that his discussion of Beethoven Op. 2, No. 1 in that
    article was written before Schenker's own study of the sonata in Tonwille 2 was published. -- He
    has been asked to review the first two issues of Der Tonwille, but plans to defer doing so until
    Der freie Satz is available to be reviewed with them; but he seeks Schenker's advice on
    this.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>



   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002757">Kiel</tei:rs>, <tei:date
      when="1922-11-21">21. XI 22.</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:address rend="indent-60">
     <tei:addrLine>Feldstr 77<tei:hi rend="supralinear">IV.</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Sehr verehrter Herr Professor <tei:rs type="person"
      key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
      place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for November 25, 1922:
      “Von Dr. Oppel: Separatabdruck aus Einstein mit Zitat; teilt mit, Einstein habe einen Aufsatz
      über mich erbeten, Arbeit u. Plage seien im Wege” (“From Dr. Oppel: “Separate offprint from
      Einstein with quotation; he tells me that Einstein has asked for an article about me; work and
      difficulties get in the way”). — Schenker’s reply is recorded on November 26: “An Oppel (Br.):
      gebe ihm den Rat, aufzutrumpfen, wie ich es tue; über die Intellektuellen in Deutschland, die
      das Unglück angerichtet haben! über Halms unbegreifliche Objektivität; lobe die Richtung des
      Aufsatzes (die Ergebnisse freilich sind nicht durchweg richtig!) u. erkundige mich, ob ein
      Zusammenschluß von Gleichgesinnten möglich wäre? Verspreche Bildchen von mir.” (“To Oppel
      (letter): advise him to demonstrate how good he is, as I do; about the intellectuals in
      Germany who caused the misery! about Halms's incomprehensible objectivity; praise the
      article's thrust (the results are of course not altogether correct!) and ask, whether a union
      between like-minded people would be possible? Promise small picture of
     myself.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>endlich schickte mir <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000195">Einstein</tei:rs> die
    Correctur meines ihm bereits am <tei:date when="1922-06-18"><tei:hi rend="underline">18.
      April</tei:hi></tei:date> gesandten Aufsatzes, also bevor Ihr <tei:rs type="work"
     key="entity-001741">2. Heft <tei:title>des Tonwillens</tei:title></tei:rs> erschien.<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Reinhard
       Oppel</tei:author>, <tei:title level="a">Über Beziehungen Beethovens zu Mozart und zu Ph. Em.
       Bach,</tei:title>
      <tei:title level="j">Zeitschrift für Musikwissenschaft</tei:title> 5 (1922–23),
      30–39</tei:bibl>. The article includes a reduction of the bass line of the development section
     of Beethoven’s Piano Sonata in F minor, Op. 2 No. 1, first movement. Schenker’s own analysis of
     that sonata was published in the second issue of <tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title>,
     released on June 10, 1922.</tei:note> Ich hoffe, dass Sie mit der Arbeit zufrieden sind.
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000195">Einstein</tei:rs> forderte mir jetzt wieder auf, Ihre
    beiden Hefte <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001739"><tei:title>des
     Tonwillen</tei:title></tei:rs>s zu besprechen, da ich Ihr Anhänger zu sein scheine. Allerdings.
    Trotzdem werde ich es ihm abschlagen, da ich Ihren Schlussband<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
     type="editorial" place="foot">The final volume of Schenker’s <tei:rs type="work"
      key="entity-001721"><tei:title level="m">New Musical Theories and
      Fantasies</tei:title></tei:rs>, i.e. <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title
       level="m">Der freie Satz</tei:title></tei:rs> (published only posthumously in
     1935).</tei:note> abwerten will, um über Ihr ganzes System zu schreiben. Wenn Ihnen aber daran
    gelegen ist, dass ich die beiden Hefte eben jetzt <tei:pb n="2"/> bespreche in der Zeitschrift,
    so will ich es gerne tun. Aber bei 65 Stunden Arbeit i. der Woche habe ich jetzt keine rechte
    Ruhe zu so geschlossenen Arbeiten. Ich komme nicht einmal mehr zu meinen Kompositionen,
    Streichquintett, Klaviertrio u. Suite f. Streichorchester harren noch immer der Vollendung.
    Zudem plagen mich Gedanken über die Gesetze der Melodiebildung, eine Arbeit, die mich schon
    lange beschäftigt. Höchstens dass ich abends einmal <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006339"
     >Ambros</tei:rs> u. Muther (<tei:title>Geschichte d. Malerei</tei:title>) lese.<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Richard
       Muther</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Geschichte der Malerei</tei:title> (5 vols,
      1899–1900)</tei:bibl>. “Ambros” probably refers to August Wilhelm Ambros’s similarly
     monumental <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Geschichte der Musik</tei:title> (5 vols,
      1862–82)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Über Ihre Abfertigung der Herren <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005298">Wyzewa</tei:rs>
    u. Saint-Foix habe ich mit ausserordentlich gefreut.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05"
     type="editorial" place="foot">Wyzewa’s and Saint-Foix’s comments on Mozart’s Sonata in A minor,
     K. 310, are critiqued in issue 2 of <tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title>, 22–24 (Eng.
     transl, vol. 1, pp. 69–71).</tei:note> Dieses französ. Gelichter! Leider hat der letztere
     <tei:pb n="3"/> im internationalen „<tei:title>Bulletin</tei:title>“ wieder so einen
    Oberflächen <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">illegible word</tei:note> über <tei:rs
     type="composition" key="entity-007792">Mozarts Es-dur Violinkonzert</tei:rs>
     losgelassen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">This article has not
     been traced. The publication in question is probably the <tei:title level="j">Bulletin de la Société “Union
     Musicologique”</tei:title>, vol. 2, No. 1 (1922).</tei:note> Und solches Zeug wird gedruckt.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Das <tei:title>Bachjahrbuch</tei:title> u. meine Klaviersachen sind noch nicht heraus, ich
    schicke sie Ihnen aber sofort nach Eingang.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>In der Hoffnung, dass es Ihnen u. Ihrer l. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000701"
     >Frau</tei:rs> gut geht,</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">bleibe ich mit den herzlichsten Grüssen</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr sehr ergebener u. dankbarer</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
     Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002757">Kiel</tei:rs>, <tei:date
      when="1922-11-21">November 21, 1922</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:address rend="indent-60">
     <tei:addrLine>Feldstraße 77/4</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Highly revered Professor <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
      >Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Finally, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000195">Einstein</tei:rs> sent me the proofs my
    article, which I had sent him as long ago as <tei:date when="1922-06-18"><tei:hi
      rend="underline">April 18</tei:hi></tei:date> – that is, before the <tei:rs type="work"
     key="entity-001741">second issue of your <tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>
     appeared.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> I hope that you will be pleased with
    my work. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000195">Einstein</tei:rs> then asked me again to
    review the first two issues of <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001739"><tei:title level="j">Der
      Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>, as I appear to be an adherent of yours. At any rate! In spite
    of this I shall turn him down, as I want to await the final volume<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
     type="footnote"/> so that I can write about your entire system. But if you are anxious that I
    review the two issues in the journal immediately, <tei:pb n="2"/> then I would be happy to do
    so. But with 65 hours of work each week, I do not have the true peace in which to take on such
    intense work. I can no longer even get to my compositions: a string quintet, a piano trio, and a
    suite for string orchestra all await completion. In addition, I am troubled by thoughts about
    the laws of melodic formation, a work with which I have been engaged for a long time. At most, I
    occasionally read from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006339">Ambros</tei:rs> or Muther
     (<tei:title level="m">History of Painting</tei:title>).<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
     type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>I was extremely delighted to read your snub of Messrs. <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-005298">Wyzewa</tei:rs> and Saint-Foix.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05"
     type="footnote"/> This French riff-raff! Unfortunately, the latter has <tei:pb n="3"/> again
    let loose such a superficial <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">illegible word</tei:note>
    about <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-007792">Mozart’s Violin Concerto in E<tei:g
      type="flat"/> major</tei:rs> in the <tei:title level="j">Bulletin</tei:title>.<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> And this sort of stuff gets published.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>The <tei:title level="j">Bach-Jahrbuc</tei:title>h and my piano pieces have not yet been
    published; I shall send them to you as soon as they arrive.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Hoping that you and your dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000701">wife</tei:rs> are
    well,</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">I remain with most cordial greetings</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">your very devoted and grateful</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
     Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>


  </tei:div>

 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
