<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3466" sdoID="OJ-14-9_2">OJ 14/9, [2]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="AS" scope="sole">Anna Schiff's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008453">SchiffV ~
        PSchiff</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Victor Schiff to Paul Schiff, dated December 19,
        [1925]</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1925-12-19T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-07-19</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>After lightly sketching the history of the Jews from farming to trade, Victor
        Schiff describes in detail his trading life in Bolivia, his settling in Chile, the
        promptings of his three sons, and his resolve to settle in Palestine (“the land of Israel”).
        The original letter was preceded and concluded by material in Hebrew not provided in Anna
        Schiff’s transcription.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000783">Victor Schiff</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-0000782">Paul Schiff</marcrel:recipient>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-0000771">Jeanette Schenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:note type="editorial" place="pre-text">Upon receipt by Paul Schiff of this letter from
        his older brother Victor, Paul’s wife Anna transcribed it, and that transcription was later
        sent to Jeanette. It is thus in Anna’s hand, and may have undergone changes, intentional or
        unintentional, in the copying process.</tei:note>
      <tei:lb/>

      <tei:p><tei:handShift new="#AS"/>Brief <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000783"
          >Viktor</tei:rs>s an <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000782">Paul</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>(Nach seinem Bekenntnis zum Judentum, welches schon in dem Brief an <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-003244">Klara</tei:rs> enthalten ist, schrieb er
          folgendes<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">:</tei:supplied>)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01"
          type="editorial" place="foot">A letter from Paul Schiff to Jeanette, dated February 1
            (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-8_10">OJ 14/8, [10]</tei:ref>), 1926,
          states: “Mit diesem Briefe folgt eine Abschrift eines Schreibens, das Viktor an Klara
          geschickt hat u. gleichzeitig den Schlussabsatz eines Briefes von V. an mich.“ (“With this
          letter follows a transcript of a letter that Viktor sent to Klara, and with it the final
          paragraph of a letter from Viktor to myself”). — Heinrich’s diary for February 4, 1926
          reports: “Von Paul: Victors Brief, von Anna abgeschrieben, Paul schreibt auch selbst.
          Viktors Brief ist überaus warm, man versteht seine wiederholte Rückkehr zu den
          Geschwistern, wie auch die Rückkehr zum Volk – die Quelle ist die gleiche! Um so
          unangebrachter betragen sich die jüngeren Geschwister Klara, die ihn förmlich abkanzelt
          mit dem grobe Wort „enttäuscht“! (Ja, würde Victor den Dollarbetrag nennen, den er seiner
          Schwester vermacht, das wäre ein „Erfolg“.). Paul wirft Victor den Handel vor usw. In
          seiner Selbständigkeit, seinem Wagemut u. insbesondere seiner Herzenswärme scheint Victor
          seine Geschwister Paul u. Clara zu übertreffen.”<tei:lb/> (“From Paul: Viktor's letter,
          copied by Anna, Paul himself writes, too. Viktor's letter is thoroughly warm, one can
          understand his repeated return to his siblings, as also the return to his people – the
          source is the same! All the more inappropriate is the behavior of the younger siblings[,
          e.g.] Clara, who verily reprimands him with the crude word "disappointed"! (Indeed, if
          Victor would name the amount in dollars that he made over to his sister, that would be a
          "success." Paul criticizes Victor for his business dealings, etc. In his independence, his
          daring and above all his warm-heartedness, Viktor appears to exceed his siblings Paul and
          Clara.”).</tei:note>
      </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Es wäre ungerecht, mein lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000782"
          >Paul</tei:rs>, wollte ich hier meinen Brief schließen, ohne vom Handel gesprochen zu
        haben. Unsere Stammväter beschäftigten sich fast ausschließlich mit Ackerbau und Viehzucht.
        Das Leben unseres Volkes aber war ein sehr gezwungenes in den letzten 2000 Jahren u. es
        entwickelte sich in unserer Rasse eine ganz hervorragende merkantile Eigenschaft. Der Handel
        u. der Handel allein trägt unbegrenzte Möglichkeiten in sich. Nur der Wille ist nötig u. die
        Ausdauer.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Als ich in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-008451">Bolivien</tei:rs>
        lebte, während des Krieges, ließ ich meine seel. Frau auf dem Gute, welches ich gepachtet
        hatte. Sie führte die Wirtschaft allein. Ich packte meine Maulesel u. mit Ware beladen
        betrat ich die langen Pfade. Durch Sumpf u. Urwald, über Steppe u. Hochland drang ich in
        noch unerforschtes Gebiet vor, wo die Eingeborenen noch kein Geld kennen. Für Dinge von
        geringem Werte tauschten sie mit mir Goldstaub u. edle Steine. Die Kälte im Hochland, in
        brennender Sonnenglut, ich hab’s alles mitgemacht ich hab’s kennen gelernt der Handel
        vergütet alle Opfer. Wenn ein Mensch eine gewisse Altersgrenze erreicht hat, wird er
        naturgemäß nach einem sehr aktiven Leben sich umsehen nach einem Orte, wo er sein spätes
        Alter verleben kann.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">In December
          1925 Victor had turned 40. He moved to Palestine in c. 1930, but was back in South America
          by 1933. His place and date of death are unknown.</tei:note> Er wird sich dann einen Ort
        aussuchen, wo er seiner Ansicht nach zu Hause ist. Wo man ihn versteht u. wo Menschen leben,
        die ihm sympatisch sind.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Als ich nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-005845">Chile</tei:rs> kam,
        glaubte ich, daß dieses Land für mich geeignet wäre. Ich baute mir ein Häuschen, ich baute
        es selbst; nahm mir einige Arbeiter u. leitete den Bau. Als es fertig war, wurde mir ein
        Angebot gemacht u. da ich es günstig verkaufen konnte, willigte ich gerne ein. Dann baute
        ich verschiedene Häuschen, kleine, größere. Es war ganz einträglich. Aber <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-005845">Chile</tei:rs> gefällt mir nicht. <tei:pb n="2"/> Ich
        will hier nicht leben. Philip schreibt mir aus <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-007990">Erez
          Israel</tei:rs>, er fuhr von San Antonio, Texas. Auch David ist dort von Californien. Nur
          Marcos<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Philip, David, Marcos:
          presumably Victor’s sons.</tei:note> ist noch im Norden, er schreibt mir immer von
        Iquique, er will absolut, ich solle mit ihm dem Norden geschäftlich bereisen, Handel. Ich
        selbst werde mich definitive in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-007990">Erez
          Israel</tei:rs> ansiedeln. Dort u. nur dort will ich mein Alter verleben. Dort werde ich
        mir eine Farm kaufen u. den Abend meines Lebens verbringen. Im Lande unserer Ahnen, die
        historische Heimat meines Volkes. Und so hoffe ich, daß mein Brief Dich nicht allzusehr
        überrascht, Dir am Ende eine Enttäuschung bereitet.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Dir liegt an der Caracterisierung des Menschen u. ich schrieb Dir mit viel
        Offenheit. Was ich vom Leben denke? Hier werden wir wohl kaum verschiedene Ansichten haben.
        Der Sinn desselben — <tei:foreign xml:lang="fre">au fond, un seul: l’ideal de bonté et
          l’amour désintéressé</tei:foreign>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial"
          place="foot">“fundamentally a solitary person, the ideal of goodness [and] disinterested
          love.” (source unknown).</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich aber trage in meiner Brust eine Hoffnung, eine große, eine
        unsterbliche Hoffnung. Es ist die ewige Hoffnung meines Volkes.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>(folgen 5 Zeilen in hebräischer Schrift, die <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000782"
          >Paul</tei:rs> – nicht übersetzten kann. Auch die Einleitung des Briefes begann mit
        einigen hebräischen Sätzen.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">Euer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000783">Victor
          Schiff</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:address rend="indent-60">
          <tei:addrLine><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003629">Valparaiso</tei:rs>, <tei:rs
              type="place" key="entity-005845">Chile</tei:rs>, Han<tei:add place="interlinear-above"
              >u</tei:add>kah 5686</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>(<tei:date when="1925-12-19">19. Dezember</tei:date>)<tei:note
              xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">In 1925, the last day of Hanukah
              fell on December 19.</tei:note></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p><tei:handShift new="#AS"/>Diesen Brief <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
            >x)</tei:add> habe ich vom Original abgeschrieben, während die Abschrift des Briefes <tei:subst>
            <tei:del rend="overstrike">von</tei:del>
            <tei:add place="interlinear-above">an</tei:add>
          </tei:subst>
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003244">Klara</tei:rs> nur von einer Abschrift gemacht
          ist.</tei:p>

        <tei:p><tei:add place="interlinear-above">x)</tei:add> Er ist die Antwort auf <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000782">Paul</tei:rs>s <tei:hi rend="underline"
            >ersten</tei:hi> Brief. Ein zweiter, in welchem <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000782">Paul</tei:rs> dringend rät, <tei:hi rend="underline">nicht</tei:hi>
          nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004528">Palästina</tei:rs> zu fahren u. auch Gründe
          dafür angibt, ist noch unbeantwortet.</tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:p><tei:handShift new="#AS"/><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000783">Viktor</tei:rs>'s
        letter to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000782">Paul</tei:rs>.</tei:p>
      <tei:p>(After his confession of the Jewish faith, which is contained in his letter to <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-003244">Klara</tei:rs>, he wrote the following:)<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">It would be incorrect, my dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000782"
          >Paul</tei:rs>, were I to end my letter at this point without having spoken about trade.
        Our <tei:supplied reason="clarity">Jewish</tei:supplied> ancestors worked almost exclusively
        in agriculture and cattle breeding. The life of our people was, however, a very constrained
        one during the past 2,000 years, and there developed among our race a wholly preeminent
        mercantile nature. Trade, and trade alone, offered unlimited possibilities. All that is
        necessary is the will, and perseverance.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">When I lived in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-008451">Bolivia</tei:rs>,
        during the war, I left my spiritual wife on the property that I had rented. She managed the
        household on her own. I packed my mule and, laden with my wares, set out on the trail.
        Through swamp, virgin forest, over steppes and highland, I trekked into uncharted territory
        where the natives were still unacquainted with money. For items of low value they exchanged
        gold dust and precious stones. The cold in the highland, in the glare of the sun – I
        persevered through it all; I learned that trade repays all sacrifice. When a man has reached
        a certain age barrier he will, by the very nature of things, after a highly active life look
        around for a place where he can live out his final years.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> He will then seek out for himself a place where, in his estimation, he
        will feel at home, where others understand him, where people live who are sympathetic toward
        him.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">When I moved to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-005845">Chile</tei:rs> I
        thought this country was going to be well-suited to me. I built myself a small house; I
        built it on my own, found myself some workers and oversaw the building. When it was
        finished, an offer was made me, and since I could sell it at a profit I acceded. Then I
        built several different houses, small ones and larger ones. It was entirely advantageous.
        But <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-005845">Chile</tei:rs> doesn’t please me. <tei:pb n="2"
        /> I don’t want to live here. Philip writes to me from the <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-007990">land of Israel</tei:rs> that he <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
          >had</tei:supplied> moved from San Antonio, Texas. Likewise David is there, <tei:supplied
          reason="clarity">having moved</tei:supplied> from California. Only Marcos<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> is still in the North. He writes to me always from
        Iquique <tei:supplied reason="clarity">in Northern Chile</tei:supplied>; he really wants me
        to join him in traversing the North on business – trade. I myself will definitely resettle
        in the <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-007990">land of Israel</tei:rs>. There and there
        alone will I live out my old age. I will buy myself a farm and spend the evening of my life
        there, in the land of our forefathers, the historical homeland of my people. And so I hope
        that my letter does not surprise you too very much – does not end by causing you a
        disappointment.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">It is for you to engage in the characterisation of man, and I have written
        to you with much openness. What do I think of life? It is here that we are hardly likely to
        have different opinions. The sense of self: “<tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:foreign
            xml:lang="fre">au fond, un seul: l’idéal de bonté et l’amour
          désinterressé</tei:foreign></tei:hi>.”<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"
        /></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I however cherish in my breast a hope, a big, an immortal hope. It is the
        eternal hope of my people.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>(There follow five pages in Hebrew script that <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000782">Paul</tei:rs> can’t translate. Also, the introduction to the letter
        began with several sentences in Hebrew.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000783">Victor
          Schiff</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:address rend="indent-60">
          <tei:addrLine><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003629">Valparaiso</tei:rs>, <tei:rs
              type="place" key="entity-005845">Chile</tei:rs>, Hanukah 5686</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>(<tei:date when="1925-12-19">December 19</tei:date>)<tei:ptr
              corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p><tei:handShift new="#AS"/>I have transcribed this letter <tei:add
            place="interlinear-above">x)</tei:add> from the original, whereas the copy of the letter <tei:subst>
            <tei:del rend="overstrike">from</tei:del>
            <tei:add place="interlinear-above">to</tei:add>
          </tei:subst>
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003244">Klara</tei:rs> has been made only from a copy. </tei:p>

        <tei:p><tei:add place="interlinear-above">x)</tei:add> is the answer to <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000782">Paul</tei:rs>‘s <tei:hi rend="underline"
            >first</tei:hi> letter. A second, in which <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000782"
            >Paul</tei:rs> advises him urgently <tei:hi rend="underline">not</tei:hi> to travel to
            <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004528">Palestine</tei:rs> and gives reasons, is still
          unanswered.</tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
