<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2201" sdoID="OJ-10-18_9">OJ 10/18, [9]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="AE" scope="sole">Angi Elias's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="MR-S">
      <tei:persName>Michaela Rejack-Searforce</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006, 2019</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2006, 2019</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2011-03-05" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-007002">EliasA ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Elias to Schenker dated August 23, 1934</dc:title>
      <dcterms:created>1934-08-23T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-02-04</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Miss Elias thanks Schenker for his words of condolence. She has decided to
        remain in Vienna to be with her brother.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Trostesworte; words of sympathy; Vereinsamung; isolation; Bedauern;
        regret</dc:subject>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000201">Angi Elias</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">with black border</tei:note><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:placeName>Wien</tei:placeName>, <tei:date
            when="1934-08-16">23/VIII-34</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Doktor</tei:rs>!<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in
            Schenker's diary at OJ 4/7, p. 3937, August 24, 1934: "Von Frl. Elias (Br.): Dank für
            das Beileidschreiben." ("From Miss Elias (letter): thanks for the letter of
            condolence.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Herzlichsten Dank Ihnen und Ihrer lieben <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
          >Frau</tei:rs> für Ihre so überaus lieben Trostesworte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of Schenker's letter of condolence is recorded in
          Schenker's diary at OJ 4/7, p. 3935, August 18, 1934: "Beileidschreiben an Frl. Elias, Dr.
          Elias u. Frau Albrecht." ("Messages of condolence to Miss Elias, Dr. Elias, and Mrs.
          Albrecht.").</tei:note> Zu kummervollen Tagen ist die Teilnahme wahrer Freunde doppelt
        wohltuend. Gewiß muß ich es als besonderes Glück schätzen, daß <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000202">Mama</tei:rs> ein so hohes Alter <tei:pb n="2"/> bei vollkommener
        körperlicher und geistiger Frische erreichte, daß sie, abgesehen von den unvermeidlichen
        Ermüdungserscheinungen, die wirklichen Altersbeschwerden nicht kannte und nach so kurzer
        Krankheit ganz schmerzlos einschlief! Aber Abschied nehmen ist immer gleich schwer!</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> Ich bleibe nun doch endgiltig in Wien. Es gibt noch vielerlei zu
        erledigen, dann möchte ich auch nicht <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000203"
          >Manolo</tei:rs> in seiner jetzigen Vereinsamung allein lassen. Ich denke ab und zu
        tagsüber in die nächste Umgebung zu fahren und will nun auch vieles zu arbeiten beginnen.
        Das wird meine Nerven am <tei:pb n="4"/> ehesten beruhigen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Für Ihre liebe Karte,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">This
          postcard is not known to survive.</tei:note> die mir aus Vent<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Vent: ski village in the foothills of the Wildspitze
          mountain, near to Obergurgl and Sölden, in the Ötztal region. Evidently, Elias was in Vent
          when she received the news that her mother was ill, and rushed home to Vienna, writing to
          the Schenkers en route, from Innsbruck (see <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-10-18_8">OJ 10/18, [8]</tei:ref>, August 16, 1934).</tei:note> nachgesandt
        wurde, danke ich auch noch vielmals. Es tut mir unendlich leid, daß Sie fortlaufend so
        schlechtes Wetter hatten. Hoffentlich werden Ihnen nun wenigstens zum Abschluß noch einige
        schöne Tage beschieden sein, wie ich es Ihnen herzlichst wünsche.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="5"/> Wie lange blieb das <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000093"
          >Ehepaar</tei:rs>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs> bei Ihnen? Hatten Sie auch sonst
        noch Besuch?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Daß der Besitz Ihres Bruders<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Presumably Moriz Schenker, who had risen to become director of a bank, at one point
          apparently a millionaire, and had taken care of Schenker’s financial affairs, but who lost
          his fortune.</tei:note> nun doch versteigert wird, habe ich mit Bedauern vernommen.
        Hoffentlich kommen Sie dabei doch nicht zu Schaden?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Es wurde mich freuen bald <tei:pb n="6"/> wieder zu hören, wie es Ihnen geht, ob Sie
        sich auch wirklich gut erholt haben.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Viele herzliche Grüsse Ihnen und Ihrer lieben <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000771">Frau</tei:rs></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">von Ihrer dankbaren</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000201" type="person">Angi
          Elias</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">with black border</tei:note><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:placeName>Vienna</tei:placeName>, <tei:date
            when="1934-08-16">August 23, 1934</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear Dr. <tei:supplied><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
              >Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"
          /></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Most heartfelt thanks to you and your dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
          >wife</tei:rs> for your exceptionally precious words of consolation.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> On sorrowful days, the condolence of true friends
        is doubly soothing. Certainly I must count it as specially fortunate that <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000202">Mama</tei:rs> reached such an advanced age <tei:pb n="2"
        /> in complete physical and intellectual vigor, so that, apart from the unavoidable signs of
        fatigue, she did not experience the real discomforts of old age and passed away completely
        free from pain after so short an illness! But to say goodbye is always hard!</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> I am definitely going to remain in Vienna. There is still so much to
        take care of, and I also do not want to leave <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000203"
          >Manolo</tei:rs> alone in his present isolation. During the day, I think now and then
        about taking a ride into the surrounding area, and now also want to begin work on many
        things. That will calm my nerves <tei:pb n="4"/> the best.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I thank you very much for your lovely postcard,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
          type="footnote"/> which was forwarded to me from Vent.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
          type="footnote"/> I am immensely sorry that you had such continuously bad weather. I hope
        you will still now be granted at least a few nice days at the conclusion <tei:supplied
          reason="clarity">of your trip</tei:supplied>, as I most sincerely wish. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="5"/> How long did <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Mr.</tei:rs> and
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000093">Mrs.</tei:rs>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs> stay with you? Did you also have
        company apart from that?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I was sorry to hear that your brother's<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/>
        property will be auctioned off. Nothing bad will come of it for you, I hope?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I would be glad <tei:pb n="6"/> to hear from you again soon how you are doing, and
        whether you have had a restful time.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Many cordial greetings to you and your dear <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000771">wife</tei:rs></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">from your grateful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000201" type="person">Angi
          Elias</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
