<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3773" sdoID="OJ-13-10_99">OJ 13/10, [99]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="TLJ">
      <tei:persName>Timothy L. Jackson</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2010</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="TLJ-IDB">
      <tei:persName>Timothy L. Jackson and Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2010, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated February 22, 1930</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1930-02-22T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-09-04</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel expresses his deep gratitude for Schenker’s return of his work, with
        comments; he will bring revisions of the works by Handel to Galtür. — His Fourth String
        Quartet is being performed in Berlin. — He urges Schenker not to kowtow to Athony van
        Hoboken. — He offers to help with correcting Schenker’s Eroica study, and reports further on
        photography of the Brahms study of parallel fifths and octaves..</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1930-01-31">22. II.
              1930</tei:date>. Kiel, Feldstr. 77<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
            >IV</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Professor Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
            >Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for February 24, 1930: “Von
            Oppel (Br.): Dank, wird noch einiges nach Galtür bringen (!!!); bietet sich zu
            Korrekturen an” (“From Oppel (letter): thanks; he will bring a few more things to Galtür
            (!!!); he offers to help with corrections”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>als ich gestern nach hier kam, fand ich Ihre liebe Sendung.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Sending of a package to Oppel is
          recorded in Schenker’s diary for February 15, 1930: “An Oppel seine 15 Stücke zurück; 11
          Seiten langer Brief, Korrekturen; recomm. abgeschickt” (“To Oppel, his fifteen pieces
          returned; an eleven-page letter, corrections; sent by registered mail”).</tei:note>
        Herzlichen Dank für alles! Was für Mühe haben Sie wieder darauf gewandt, und ich starre
        immer von neuem! In allen Punkten haben Sie recht, jetzt, wo ich wieder Abstand von den
        Dingen habe, ist mir das alles klar, u. bei manchem frage ich mich, warum sieht man das
        nicht gleich und hört es nicht gleich? Weil unsre Lehrer selbst nichts wussten von all
        diesen Einfachheiten; immer wieder frage ich das Schicksal: warum durfte ich Ihnen als dem
        einzig richtigen Führer nicht 30 Jahre früher begegnen? Wieviel Umwege hätte ich gespart!!
        Aber auch so bin ich froh u. dankbar, dass ich das jetzt noch nachholen kann. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Sie haben ganz recht: <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000329">Händel</tei:rs>s
        Stimmführung ist verschleiert einfach. Natürlich dürfen Sie mir alles sagen; von Ihnen
        acceptiere ich jede Correctur, das ist doch selbstverständlich. Gegen so unbedingte Logik,
        wie es die Ihre ist, gibt es kein Schranken und keine Widerrede. Ich habe allerdings leider
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000329">Händel</tei:rs> immer wenig gepflegt, mein Vater
        besass nichts von ihm, auf dem Konservatorium in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002495"
          >Frankfurt</tei:rs> spielte man lediglich ein paar Violinsonaten und ein oder höchsten 2
        Orgelkonzerte. Heute weiss ich, dass er uns allen ein höchst notwendiges Stahlbad ist, um
        den ganzen modernen <tei:pb n="2"/> Wust von der Seele u. den Ohren herunterzuwaschen. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Das Benedictus ist ein sehr frühes Stück, aus einer Messe für Chor, Soli u. Orchester,
        das mir jedes Mal durch Militärverpflichtungen unterbrochen wurde. Mit dem Choralvorspiel
        bin ich auch heute noch nicht zufrieden. Und dann lasse ich die Sachen meistens liegen. Ich
        ändere also jetzt die <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000329">Händel</tei:rs> um u. bringe
        sie nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs> mit. Also nochmals heissen
        Dank! – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Das Quartett wird am Montag im <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501"
        >Berlin</tei:rs>er Tonkünstler-Verein gespielt, vielleicht fahre ich dazu hin, obwohl es für
        mich eine Hetzjagd wird, denn Dienstags habe ich dann 10 Stunden zu halten. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Den <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801">Jungen</tei:rs> geht’s gut. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> hat gestern die letzte schriftliche
        Examensarbeit gemacht, in einem Monat ist das mündliche. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Was Sie von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hob.</tei:rs> etc. schreiben, hat
        mich sehr betrübt, obwohl ich nicht viel von ihm erwarte. Aber Sie dürfen Ihre eignen
        Arbeiten u. Ihre Gesundheit u. die <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Ihrer lieben
          Frau</tei:rs> nicht seiner Eitelkeit opfern; ich verstehe nicht, dass <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000320">Haas</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000164">Deutsch</tei:rs> ihm nicht beibringen können, zu was ihn sein Geld
        verpflichtet. Ich würde ihm gar nicht mehr helfen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot">e.g. on February 17 Schenker wrote in his diary: “An Roth
          No. 17, 18, 19 für v. Hoboken.” (“Work on Roth, Nos. 17, 18, and 19 for Hoboken.”); on
          February 21 he was required to spend two hours taking Hoboken through the score of the
            <tei:title level="m">Missa solemnis</tei:title> at the piano prior to Hoboken’s
          attending a performance.</tei:note> oder ihm jede Stunde ordnungsmässig anrechnen. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Kann ich bei der Korrectur der <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001752"
            ><tei:title>Eroica</tei:title></tei:rs> nicht irgendwie helfen? Ich tue es sehr gerne!
        Verfügen Sie nur über mich! </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000320">Prof Haas</tei:rs> schrieb mir, dass Brahms‘
        Studie über die Oct u. Q-par.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Brahms’s study of parallel fifths and octaves in music from the 16th to 19th centuries,
          of which Schenker, with Oppel’s help, produced a facsimile edition, <tei:rs type="work"
            key="entity-003331"><tei:title level="m">Johannes Brahms, Oktaven und Quinten
              u.a.</tei:title></tei:rs> (Vienna: UE, 1933).</tei:note> mir zur Verfügung steht, aber
        nur durch die Universitätsbibliothek in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002757"
          >Kiel</tei:rs> oder <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002479">Leipzig</tei:rs> (da es sich
        um öffentlichen Bibliotheksbesitz handle). Ich werde sie jetzt in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002479">Leipzig</tei:rs> bestellen u. anfangen, alle Stellen zu kontrollieren.
        Sobald ich damit fertig bin, schicke ich Ihnen das Material. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Und nun ärgern Sie sich nicht weiter über <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380"
          >Hob.</tei:rs>, im Grunde ist er trotz seines Reichtums doch ein armer Mensch. – </tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Mit den herzlichsten Grüssen an Sie beide </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>von uns allen bleibe ich </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>Ihr treuer und dankbarer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1930-01-31">February 22,
              1930</tei:date>. Kiel, Feldstrasse 77/4</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor
            Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>As I arrived here yesterday, I found your wonderful package.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> The most heartfelt thanks for everything! With
        what great care you have devoted to it I am always newly amazed! In every point you are
        right. Now that I have some distance from the thing, it is clear to me, and concerning many
        points I ask myself why one doesn't see it immediately and also hear it immediately?
        Probably because our teachers themselves did not know anything of all of these simplicities:
        always I ask myself about Destiny: why did I not encounter you thirty years earlier as the
        one correct teacher? How many detours I would have saved myself!! But nevertheless I am of
        good cheer and thankful that I can make up for it now.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>You are quite right: <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000329">Handel</tei:rs>'s
        voice-leading is deceptively simple. Naturally you can say anything to me; from you I will
        accept every critique, that goes without saying. Against such unbending logic as yours,
        there are no defensive barriers and no objection. Unfortunately I never performed <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000329">Handel</tei:rs> very much. My father owned none of his
        works, and at the Conservatory in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002495"
          >Frankfurt</tei:rs>, only a few violin sonatas were performed and at most two organ
        concertos. Today I recognize that he is a desperately needed restorative spa, in which one
        can wash away the moderns' waste of the soul and the ear. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>The Benedictus is a very early work, from a Mass for chorus, soloists, and orchestra,
        that I had been interrupted each time <tei:supplied reason="clarity">from
          completing</tei:supplied> by military obligations. About the chorale prelude, I am not
        happy with it even today. And then I usually put these things aside. I shall make
        alterations to the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000329">Handel</tei:rs> pieces and
        bring them with me to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>. Once more,
        the most profound thanks!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>My <tei:supplied reason="identity">Fourth</tei:supplied> String Quartet will be played
        at the <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs> Society of Composers on
        Monday. I may perhaps travel there, although it will be a mad rush for me, as I have ten
        lessons to give on Tuesday. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>The <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801">boys</tei:rs> are well. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> took his last written examination
        yesterday; he will have his oral exam in a month’s time. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>What you write about <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs> etc.
        saddens me greatly, although I do not expect much from him. But you must not sacrifice your
        own work and your health, and that of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">your dear
          wife</tei:rs>, to his vanity. I do not understand why <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000320">Haas</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000164"
          >Deutsch</tei:rs> are unable to get him to do what his wealth compels him. I would not
        offer him any more help,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> or duly credit him
        with any lessons.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>May I offer you any help with the correction of the proofs to your <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001752"><tei:title level="m">Eroica</tei:title> study</tei:rs>? I would be
        happy to do so! You only have to ask me!</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000320">Professor Haas</tei:rs> wrote to say that
        Brahms’s study of parallel octaves and fifths<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"
        /> is ready for me, but only via the University library in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002757">Kiel</tei:rs> or <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002479"
          >Leipzig</tei:rs> (since it is official library property). I shall now order it in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002479">Leipzig</tei:rs>, and begin to check all passages. As
        soon as I have finished, I shall send you the material.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>So now, do not be troubled any further by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380"
          >Hoboken</tei:rs> who, in spite of his wealth, is in fact a poor man. –</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>With the most cordial greetings to the two of you </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>from us all, I remain </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>Your faithful and grateful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>
    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
