<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="439" sdoID="OJ-14-45_13">OJ 14/45, [13]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="MV" scope="sole">Moriz Violin's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>


  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2011</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-06-17" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002719">ViolinM ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM+V ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002718">ViolinM+V+F ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>




   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Moriz Violin to Schenker, dated February 2, 1922 </dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1922-02-02T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2011-06-17</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>In this direct reply to Schenker's previous letter, OJ 6/7, [2], Violin expresses
    his dismay that some of the performing material for keyboard concertos by C. P. E. Bach,
    including original cadenzas by Schenker, appear to have gone missing. — He reports on his
    growing number of pupils, on the acquisition of a piano for his apartment, and on Hamburg's
    extremely conservative musical tastes.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Konzert; concerto; Kadenz; cadenza; Vortrag; lecture; Mäcene; patron;
    Klavierunterricht; piano instruction; Existenzgründungsarbeit; work-sustaining existence;
    Privatstunden; private lessons; Conservatorium; conservatory; Flügel; piano; Publikum; public;
    Moderne; moderns; Musiker; musician; Kritik; criticism; </dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-40"><tei:placeName>Hamburg</tei:placeName>, <tei:date when="1922-02-02">2. Februar 1922</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Liebster <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in
      Schenker's diary at OJ 3/3, p. 2415, February 11, 1922: "Von Floriz (Br.): wegen der Kadenz,
      die er bei sich nicht findet, wegen des Konzertes überhaupt." ("From Floriz (letter):
      regarding the cadenza, which he cannot find at home, regarding the concert in general").
     </tei:note>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Vor allem vielen Dank für die Sendung!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">= OJ 6/7, [2]. </tei:note> Gestern kam sie, und ich kehrte noch
    abends meine gesamten Noten. Hab u. Gut um u. fand – – nichts!! Ich erinnere mich nur, daß Du
    einmal das <tei:title>a moll Konzert</tei:title> bei mir reklamiert hast u. ich es Dir auch
     gab.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">All that Schenker had reported
     missing were two cadenzas to the A-minor concerto. </tei:note> Jetzt, nachdem ich suchte, ist
    es mir ein Rätsel, wie es nur verloren gehen konnte? Ist also nur noch mit einem Wunder zu
    rechnen? Die Stimmen des <tei:title>Doppel-Konzert</tei:title>s, sind immerhin ein mißlicher
    Verlust, aber mit Geld ist er gut zu machen. Entsetzlich ist mir der Gedanke, daß die Kadenzen
    verloren sein sollten! Sie waren mir, als wahre Musterstücke so an’s <tei:del rend="overstrike">Hez</tei:del> Herz gewachsen, daß es mir schwer gelingen würde welche neu zu setzen. Dazu
    erinnere ich mich noch zu genau an sie. Ich konnte Dir genau den Bau der ersten aus dem
    Gedächtnis aufzeichnen. Konntest Du sie dann rekonstruieren? Die Andante Kadenz war ein Juwel.
    Sie habe ich leider nicht mehr in guter Erinnerung. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans Weisse</tei:rs> hat mir
     <tei:hi rend="underline">durchaus</tei:hi> nicht abgesagt. Er schrieb mir nur, daß er die
    Vorträge nicht gerne im scheinbaren Zusammenhang mit der Aufführung seiner Werke, aus Dir
    bekannten Gründen, <tei:del rend="overstrike">nicht</tei:del> halten will. Ich antwortete ihm,
    daß ich seine Argumente diesbezüglich anerkennen will, daß ich ihm nur auch die Freude bereiten
    wollte, seine Sachen hören zu können u. daß wir deshalb die Vorträge verschieben wollen u.
    fragte <tei:hi rend="underline">nochmals</tei:hi> an, wie viel er gezahlt bekommen muß. Sollte
    seine Bescheidenheit eine verkappte Feigheit sein, so wäre das nicht gerade
     erbaulich<tei:supplied reason="syntax">.</tei:supplied> Ich werde mir da völlige Klarheit
    verschaffen! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Sehr peinlich war mir der dumme Zufall der <tei:rs key="entity-002868" type="person">Landesmann</tei:rs>schen Plauscherei. Seine Kentnisse muß er schon aus vierter
    Hand haben. Denn 1.) habe ich <tei:rs key="entity-002868" type="person">Landesmann</tei:rs>s
    überhaupt noch nicht geschrieben u. 2.) habe ich kein Wunderkind außer meinen zwei Eigenen.
    Offenbar hat <tei:rs key="entity-000909" type="person">Fanny</tei:rs> ihnen erzählt, daß hiesige
    Mäcene einen 13 j. Knaben ausbilden lassen u. ich den Klavierunterricht besorge. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich habe Dir bis nun nichts schreiben wollen, denn all meine Arbeit ist
    Existenzgründungsarbeit. <tei:pb n="2"/> Zufällig hat diese in den letzten 14 Tagen beträchtige
    Fortschritte gemacht. Ich habe jetzt 7 Privatstunden wöchentlich. In nächster Zeit kommen noch
    3–4 dazu. Ich bekomme 50 M.<tei:supplied reason="syntax">,</tei:supplied> von einer sogar 70 M.
    p. Stunde. Ich werde also ausser dem geringen Verdienst im Conservatorium noch 2000 M. monatlich
    verdienen. Das reicht nicht. Aber es wird im Laufe des Jahres alles beträchtlich wachsen.
     <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">Vally</tei:rs> verdiente durch Verkauf von
    gehäckelten Hüten schon ein par tausend Mark. Vielleicht wird sie auch ein Geschäft einrichten.
    Ich schreibe Dir heute das alles, weil ich viel mutiger bin u. die sichere Überzeugung habe, das
    wir mit vereinbarten Kräften bald, zwar bescheiden aber gesichert haben werden können. Viel
    Kampf kostete mich die Beschaffung eines Flügels. <tei:hi rend="underline">Heute</tei:hi> bekam
    ich von <tei:rs key="entity-002880" type="organization">Steinway</tei:rs> die Zusage, daß sie
    mir ein Instrument in der neuen Wohnung zur Verfügung stellen. Denke nun noch an meine spielen,
    noch unausgeführten Pläne u. Du wirst verstehen, daß ich dich nicht gerne an meinen <tei:hi rend="underline">Krämpfen</tei:hi> teilnehmen lassen wollte. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Das Publikum in <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>
    ist, glaube ich, <tei:hi rend="underline">durchwegs</tei:hi> konservativ, bis auf die Kritik,
    die aber noch in der „Modernen“ ganz ungeübt ist u. teilweise noch <tei:unclear reason="reading">erscheißt</tei:unclear>, weil das Publikum in <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> bei Exzessen noch aus dem Saal geht, teilweise mutig tut, weil in <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs> die „Moderne“ das „Jeschäft“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Violin writes "Geschäft" in the way in which
     it is pronounced by Berliners. </tei:note> ist. Die Musiker hier sind ebenso unbedeutend u.
    schwebend wie die Kritik. Ein außerordentlicher Organist, <tei:rs key="entity-002836" type="person">Sittard</tei:rs>, ist hier. Es ist schwer für <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> eine Prognose zu stellen. Es ist in <tei:hi rend="underline">jeder</tei:hi> Hinsicht im guten <tei:hi rend="underline">u.</tei:hi> schlechten Sinne
    konservativ u. fortschrittlich. Starker Rheedereinschlag. <tei:hi rend="underline">Positiv</tei:hi> ist nur der unangekränkelte <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">contined in left margin written sideways:</tei:note> Geschmack des Publikums Bis <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs> inklusive wird geliebt. Ansonsten schaut es
    hier aus wie in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> vor 30 Jahren. Bis
    einiges meiner Absichten sich verwirklichen wird, will ich Dir Klügeres u Wertvolleres
    schreiben. <tei:unclear reason="reading">Das</tei:unclear>
    <tei:unclear reason="reading">spielt</tei:unclear> bei allen meinen Gedanken die größte u.
    bedeutendste Rolle.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">The edge of the
     paper is crumpled, or torn, and one or two words at the beginning of the sentence are virtually
     illegible. </tei:note>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">valediction and signature in right margin:</tei:note><tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Inniges von</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Uns an Euch</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60">Dein <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>


  </tei:div>

  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-40"><tei:placeName>Hamburg</tei:placeName>, <tei:date when="1922-02-02">February 2, 1922</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Dearest <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">First of all, many thanks for the communication!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> It arrived yesterday, and in the evening I combed my
    entire collection of scores. I looked high and low and found – nothing!! I remember only that
    you once asked at my place for the return of the <tei:title>Concerto in A minor</tei:title>, and
    that I gave it back to you. Now, having looked, it is a mystery as to how it could have gone
     missing.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> The parts to the <tei:title>Double
     Concerto</tei:title> are in any event an unfortunate loss, but with money they can be regained.
    For me, it is dreadful to think that your cadenzas could have gone missing. They had, so to
    speak, become attached to my heart, as true models of such pieces, that it would be difficult
    for me to succeed in composing new ones. In addition, I still remember them quite precisely. I
    could indicate to you the construction of the first cadenza from memory; could you then
    reconstruct it? The cadenza to the Andante was a gem: unfortunately, I cannot remember it well. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans Weisse</tei:rs> did not,
     <tei:hi rend="underline">most certainly</tei:hi>, cancel <tei:supplied reason="clarity">the
     lectures</tei:supplied> that I arranged. He merely wrote to me to say that he would not like to
    give the lectures in apparent connection with the performance of his music, for reasons known to
    you. I replied to him, saying that I accepted his arguments, that I only wanted to give him the
    pleasure of being able hear his pieces and that was the reason we wanted to postpone the
    lectures; and I asked him <tei:hi rend="underline">again</tei:hi> how much he would want to be
    paid <tei:supplied reason="clarity">for giving the lectures</tei:supplied>. If this modesty
    conceals a certain cowardice, this was not immediately discernible. I shall uncover the complete
    truth in the matter! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">The silly case of the <tei:rs key="entity-002868" type="person">Landesmann</tei:rs>s' chit-chat was very painful to me. His information must have come
    fourth-hand. For, firstly, I have not written to the <tei:rs key="entity-002868" type="person">Landesmann</tei:rs>s at all and, secondly, I do not have any child prodigies, other than my
    own two. Apparently <tei:rs key="entity-000909" type="person">Fanny</tei:rs> told them that
    current patrons have arranged for the education of a thirteen-year-old boy, and that I am
    providing the piano tuition. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Until now I did not want to write anything to you, since all my work is
    devoted to sustaining my existence. <tei:pb n="2"/> By chance, this has made considerable
    progress in the last two weeks. I now have seven private lessons a week; in the near future
    there will be three or four more. I receive 50 Marks per lesson, from one pupil as much as 70
    Marks per lesson. Apart from my marginal earnings at the Conservatory, I shall thus be earning
    2,000 marks per month. That is not enough; but in the course of the year it will increase
    significantly. <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">Vally</tei:rs> is already earning a few
    thousand Marks from selling crocheted hats; perhaps she will even be able to start up a
    business. I am writing all this to you today because I am in much better spirits and I have the
    secure conviction that, by the uniting of our powers, we will be able to have a modest but
    secure existence. The acquisition of a piano cost me a lot of effort. <tei:hi rend="underline">Today</tei:hi> I received confirmation from <tei:rs key="entity-002880" type="organization">Steinway</tei:rs> that they will furnish me with an instrument in the new apartment. Think,
    then, about my goals, my as yet unrealized plans, and you will understand that I was not happy
    to have you share in my <tei:hi rend="underline">fruitless efforts</tei:hi>. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">The musical public in <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> is, I believe, <tei:hi rend="underline">thoroughly</tei:hi> conservative,
    apart from the newspaper criticism, which is, however, still entirely inexperienced with respect
    to "modern" music. In part, it could not care less, because the <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> public will walk out of the concert hall when an excessively
     <tei:supplied reason="clarity">modern</tei:supplied> work is performed; in part it behaves
    audaciously, because in <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs> "modern music"
    is where the "action"<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> is. We have an outstanding
    organist here, by the name of <tei:rs key="entity-002836" type="person">Sittard</tei:rs>. It is
    difficult to offer a prognosis for <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>: In
     <tei:hi rend="underline">every</tei:hi> respect it is conservative and progressive in the good
     <tei:hi rend="underline">and</tei:hi> bad senses of the terms. There is a strong <tei:hi rend="italic">Rheeder</tei:hi> element. The only <tei:hi rend="underline">positive</tei:hi>
    feature is the <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">contined in left margin written
     sideways:</tei:note> public's uncorrupted taste. They love everything up to and including
     <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs>. Otherwise, things here look like
    they did in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs> thirty years ago. As soon
    as one of my intentions is realized, I shall write you something cleverer and more valuable.
    That is what counts the most with respect to all my thoughts.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">valediction and signature in right margin:</tei:note><tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Heartfelt greetings </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">from us to you, </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60">Your <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>