<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2761" sdoID="OJ-13-35_2">OJ 13/35, [2]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HRu" scope="sole">Hilde Rubinraut's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2022</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2022</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>


    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2011-06-09" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008187">RubinrautH ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Hilde Rubinraut to Schenker, dated September 1,
        1922</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1922-09-01T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2022-06-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Hilde Rubinraut explains her difficulties as a resident of Prague visiting
        Vienna under current conditions; she asks Schenker in which currency she should pay his fee;
        and seeks advice as to whether she should continue taking one piano and one theory lesson,
        or opt, for a time, for two piano lessons.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000719">HRubinraut</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#HRu"/><tei:rs type="place"
            key="entity-002892">Prag</tei:rs>, am <tei:date when="1922-09-01">1. September
            1922</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Sehr geehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Herr</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for September 2, 1922: “Von Frau Rubinraut
            (Br. aus Prag): bittet um Stunden.” (“From Mrs. Rubinraut (letter from Prague): asks for
            lessons.”), and for September 4: “An Frau Rubinraut (Br.): 20 Goldkronen.” (“An Frau
            Rubinraut (Br.): 20 Goldkronen.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Da es die wirtschaftlichen Verhältnisse meinem Manne als Kaufmann bisher und
        voraussichtlich noch längere Zeit nicht gestatten sich in Wien ansässig zu machen und ich
        nicht noch länger auf eine Besserung in der Beziehung warten will, habe ich mich
        entschlossen von <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002892">Prag</tei:rs> aus meine Stunden,
        allerdings in viel begrenzterer Anzahl als früher, mit Ihrer gütigen Zustimmung wieder
        aufzunehmen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Selbstredend bringt mein Aufenthalt in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002892">Prag</tei:rs> und der Umstand, daß ich mich nach einem anderen Staate
        begeben muß, viele Momente mit sich, die bedacht sein müssen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Was die Zahlung betrifft, könnte sie in <tei:pb n="2"/> jeder von Ihnen
        beliebigen Währung bestimmt werden. Ich bin absolute nicht informiert, welches, sehr
        geschätzter Herr Doktor derzeit Ihre Ansprüche sind und müßte mir die Anzahl meiner Stunden
        in Anbetracht dieser, und der Reisekosten bemessen. Ich würde bitten, bei so ungewöhnlicher
        Situation, mir bei Bestimmung der Stundenanzahl mit Rat zu Hilfe zu kommen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Da ich in sehr argem Rückstand betreffs Spiel und noch mehr in Theorie
        bin, weiß ich nicht ob eine Reise jede 3te Woche nach Wien da genügen dürfte. Ich muß auch
        meinen Pflichten als Frau Rechnung tragen, respektive dem Wunsche meines Mannes, dem
          <tei:sic>vorleufig</tei:sic> eine öftere Fahrt als <tei:pb n="3"/> einmal in 3 Wochen
        nicht erwünscht ist. Soll ich nun die Theoriestunde fallen lassen und lieber 2
        Klavierstunden auf einmal nehmen, oder genügt eine Klavierstunde und eine Theoriestunde
        3wöchentlich um mich wenigstens in einiger Zeit dahin zu bringen wo ich war, um von da aus
        weiter arbeiten zu können. Ich wäre Herrn Doktor für Rat sehr und sehr dankbar. Ich bringe
        gerne das Opfer der <tei:hi rend="italic">Strapac</tei:hi><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:hi rend="italic">Strapac</tei:hi>: German term, <tei:hi
            rend="italic">Strapaze</tei:hi>, “exertion,” “strain,” written with Czech
          orthography.</tei:note> und vielleicht noch andere, um nur den Unterricht bei Ihnen wieder
        aufnehmen zu können. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Man müßte auch die Frage in Erwägung ziehen, ob man in Anbetracht der
        möglich eintretenden politischen Wirren (Bahnstreick,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker himself speaks in his diary on September 5 of a
          strike of typesetters.</tei:note> Revolution <tei:sic>ect. ect.</tei:sic>) einen bindenden
        Abschluß <tei:pb n="4"/> für die ganze Saison, oder die Angelegenheit in einen kürzeren
        Zeitraum begrenzen soll. Auch Feiertage dürften mir den ohnedies großen Zeitabschnitt nicht
        noch mehr verlängern. In derartigem Eventualitätsfall könnte man vielleicht die Stunden um 1
        oder 2 Tage (nach Möglichkeit Ihrerseits) verlegen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich bitte nun sehr geehrter Herr Doktor um Ihre Meinung und Ansprüche und
        will hoffen, daß mir keine abschlägige Antwort beschieden ist. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Mit altgewohnter Hochachtung</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">und Grüßen</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000719">Hilde
            Rubinraut</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:add rend="indent-80">früher Frl. König.</tei:add><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine>Prag-Weinberge</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10">Manesová N<tei:hi rend="supralinear">o</tei:hi>
            16.</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#HRu"/><tei:rs type="place"
            key="entity-002892">Prague</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1922-09-01">September 1,
            1922</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Sir</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Since financial conditions preclude my husband, as a merchant, up to now and for the
        foreseeable future, from claiming residence in Vienna, and I do not anticipate any
        improvement in the situation, I have decided, with your kind consent, to resume my lessons
        from <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002892">Prague</tei:rs>, albeit in much reduced
        numbers than previously.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Needless to say, my status as a resident of <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002892">Prague</tei:rs>, and the fact that I must travel to another country,
        raises many aspects that need to be taken into consideration.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">As concerns payment, this could be arranged in <tei:pb n="2"/> any
        currency that you designate. I have no idea what your charges, highly esteemed Dr.
          <tei:supplied reason="identity">Schenker</tei:supplied>, currently are, and would have to
        calculate the number of lessons that I take against the latter and the costs of travel. In
        so unorthodox a situation, I would appreciate it if you could advise me on how many lessons
        I should take.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Since I am terribly out of practice, even more so in theory, I don’t know
        whether a trip to Vienna every third week would be sufficient. I must also take into account
        my duties as a wife, and the wishes of my husband to whom <tei:hi rend="underline">for
          now</tei:hi> travel more frequently than <tei:pb n="3"/> once every three weeks would be
        unwelcome. Ought I for now to let the theory lesson go and instead take two piano lessons
        per visit, or will one piano lesson and one theory lesson every third week be sufficient to
        bring me, at least in reasonable time, back up to where I used to be, in order then to
        progress further. I would be very, very grateful for your advice, Dr. <tei:supplied
          reason="identity">Schenker</tei:supplied>. I am prepared to make sacrifices, to put in
        much effort,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> and perhaps other things, so as
        to be able to resume my instruction with you.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">It may be necessary also to factor in whether the looming political
        turmoil (rail strike,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> revolution, etc, etc)
        might possibly put an unavoidable end <tei:pb n="4"/> to the whole season, or restrict the
        amount of time we have at our disposal. Also, might not holidays prolong the already long
        period still further? In any such eventuality could the lessons perhaps be <tei:unclear
          reason="meaning">rescheduled</tei:unclear> by one or two days (if convenient for
        you)?</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Please, dear Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity">Schenker</tei:supplied>,
        let me know your opinion and requirements; I hope not to receive a negative response.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">With long-accustomed regards </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">and greetings,</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000719">Hilde
            Rubinraut</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:add rend="indent-80">formerly Miss König.</tei:add><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine>Prag-Weinberge</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10">Mánesova 16</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
