<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3812" sdoID="OJ-13-27_2">OJ 13/27, [2]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="JR" scope="sole">Julius Röntgen's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="KK">
      <tei:persName>Kevin Karnes</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IDB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2011-09-15" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008521">RoentgenJ ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Julius Röntgen to Schenker, dated April 22, 1901</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1901-04-22T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-10-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Röntgen comments favorably on two compositions by Schenker; he plans to play
        through the songs when in the coming days Johannes Messchaert visits him. -- He is working
        on one of his editorial commitments for Universal Edition.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000724">JRoentgen</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-30"><tei:handShift new="#JR"/>Amsterdam, <tei:date
            when="1901-04-22">22 April 1901</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>Verehrtester Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Doctor</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">This letter
            is published in English in <tei:bibl><tei:editor>Bent, Ian</tei:editor>,
                <tei:editor>David Bretherton</tei:editor> and <tei:editor>William
                Drabkin</tei:editor>, eds, <tei:title level="a">Heinrich Schenker: Selected
                Correspondence</tei:title> (Woodbridge: Boydell Press, 2014), pp.
            65–66</tei:bibl>.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Endlich ein Wort des Dankes auf Ihre inhaltsreiche Sendung! Halten Sie die Verzögerung
        nicht für Gleichgültigkeit! Im Gegentheil: Ihre Lieder und vor Allem die
          <tei:title>Inventionen</tei:title> beschäftigen mich sehr, ich wollte Ihnen aber nicht
        eher schreiben, ehe ich in ein etwas intimerer Verhältniß zu den Sachen getreten war und das
        ist mir nicht sogleich gelungen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Sie gehen in den <tei:title>Inventionen</tei:title> auf ziemlich verschlungenen Pfaden,
        auf denen Ihnen zu folgen nicht immer leicht fällt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Heinrich Schenker</tei:author>,
              <tei:title level="a">Zweistimmige Inventionen</tei:title>, Op. 5 (Leipzig: Breitkopf
            &amp; Härtel, 1901)</tei:bibl>. The item in F<tei:g type="sharp"/> minor is Op. 5, No.
          2.</tei:note> Besonders liegt die rein <tei:hi rend="underline">musikalische</tei:hi>
        Essenz nicht immer <tei:pb n="2"/> vor der Hand, während das Technische ja sogleich
        intereßirt und imponirt. Am Meisten in dieser Beziehung zieht mich das Fismoll Stück an –
        bisjetzt aber mehr beim Lesen, als beim Spielen. Klanglich scheint mir Vieles gewagt,
        obgleich Alles vollkommen logisch ist. Sie können getrost darauf schreiben: “eine deutliche
        Art darneben einen starken Vorschmack von der Komposition zu überkommen” – wie es <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000027">Bach</tei:rs> bei den Inventionen gethan hat.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"> Röntgen quotes, apparently to signal
          his approval of Schenker’s adherence to expectations associated with the genre, and
          without syntactic coherence, from Bach’s inscription on the title page of the fair copy of
          his <tei:title level="m">Inventions and Sinfonias</tei:title>, BWV 772-801 (1723). Bach’s
          inscription reads: “Upright Instruction wherein the lovers of the clavier, and especially
          those desirous of learning, are shown a clear way not alone to learn to play clearly in
          two voices but also, after further progress, to deal correctly and well with three <tei:hi
            rend="italic">obbligato</tei:hi> parts; furthermore, at the same time not alone to have
          good <tei:hi rend="italic">inventiones</tei:hi> [ideas] but to develop the same well and,
          above all, to arrive at a singing style in playing and at the same time to acquire a
          strong foretaste of composition.” (“Auffrichtige Anleitung, Wormit denen Liebhabern des
            <tei:hi rend="italic">Clavires</tei:hi>, besonders aber denen Lehrbegierigen, eine
          deütliche Art gezeiget wird, nicht alleine mit 2 Stimmen reine spielen zu lernen, sondern
          auch bey weiteren <tei:hi rend="italic">progreßen</tei:hi> mit dreyen <tei:hi
            rend="italic">obligaten Partien</tei:hi> richtig und wohl zu verfahren, anbey auch
          zugleich gute <tei:hi rend="italic">inventiones</tei:hi> nicht alleine zu bekommen,
          sondern auch selbige wohl durchzuführen, am allermeisten aber eine <tei:hi rend="italic"
            >cantable</tei:hi> Art im Spielen zu erlangen, und darneben einen starcken Vorschmack
          von der Composition zu überkommen.”) (<tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Bach-Dokumente.
              Supplement zu Johann Sebastian Bach: Neue Ausgabe sämtlicher Werke</tei:title>, ed.
              <tei:editor>Werner Neumann</tei:editor> and <tei:editor>Hans-Joachim
              Schulze</tei:editor>, vol. 1, <tei:title level="m">Schriftstücke von der Hand Johann
              Sebastian Bachs</tei:title> (Kassel: Bärenreiter, 1963), 220-21</tei:bibl>; facs. and
          transl. in <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">The New Bach Reader: A Life of Johann Sebastian
              Bach in Letters and Documents</tei:title>, ed. <tei:editor>Hans T. David
            </tei:editor>and <tei:editor>Arthur Mendel</tei:editor>, revised and enlarged by
              <tei:editor>Christoph Wolff</tei:editor> (New York: W. W. Norton, 1998),
            97–98</tei:bibl>.) My thanks to Stephen Crist for his help in identifying the source of
          Röntgen’s quotation.</tei:note> Dagegen scheint mir die “Gemüths-Ergötzung” etwas
          zurückzutreten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">
          “Gemüths-Ergötzung”: This term appears on the title-pages of the first editions of Bach’s
          four volumes of <tei:title level="m">Clavier-Übungen</tei:title> (I: BWV 825–830 [1731];
          II: BWV 831, 971 [1735]; III: BWV 552/1, 669–689, 802–805, 552/2 [1739]; IV: BWV 988 [c.
          1742]). The spelling used by Röntgen, however, is found only in Bach’s second volume,
          containing the <tei:title level="m">Italian Concerto</tei:title> (BWV 971) that Röntgen
          was then editing for Universal Edition. The title pages reads: “Second part of the
          Keyboard Practice, consisting of a Concerto after the Italian Taste and an Overture after
          the French Manner, for a harpsichord with two manuals. Composed for music lovers, to
          refresh their spirits, by Johann Sebastian Bach, Capellmeister to His Highness the Prince
          of Saxe-Weissenfels and <tei:hi rend="italic">Directore Chori Musici Lipsiensis</tei:hi>.
          Published by Christoph Weigel, Junior.” (“<tei:title>Zweyter Theil der Clavier Ubung
            bestehend in einem Concerto nach Italiœnischen Gusto und einer Overture nach
            Französischer Art, vor ein Clavicÿmbel mit zweÿen Manualen. Denen Liebhabern zur
            Gemüths-Ergötzung verfertiget. von Johann Sebastian Bach</tei:title>. Hochfürstl:
          Sœchßl: Weißenfelßl: Capellmeistern und Directore Chori Musici Lipsiensis. in Verlegung
          Christoph Weigel Junioris.”) (<tei:title level="m">Bach-Dokumente</tei:title>, vol. I,
          235; facs. and transl. in <tei:title level="m">The New Bach Reader</tei:title>, 167–68.)
          My thanks to Stephen Crist for his help in identifying the source of Röntgen’s
          quotation.</tei:note>
      </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Soweit bin ich <tei:hi rend="underline">bisjetzt</tei:hi> mit den
          <tei:title>Inventionen</tei:title> gekommen, vielleicht ändert sich mein Urtheil aber
        noch. Ich werde jedenfalls oft zu den Stücken zurückkehren und ich freue <tei:pb n="3"/>
        mich darauf später mehr mit Ihnen darüber zu reden! </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Mit den Liedern habe ich mich noch nicht viel beschäftigen können, da ich gerade in den
        letzten Wochen sehr viel Anderes zu thun hatte. Die <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000027">Bach</tei:rs>-Ausgabe, die ich übernommen habe,<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">The identity of the edition to which
          Röntgen refers is unclear. During this period, Röntgen’s editorial work for Universal
          Edition was extensive. His editions of Bach’s Little Preludes and Fugues, Two- and
          Three-Part Inventions, French Suites, English Suites, Partitas, Italian Concerto, D minor
          Concerto, and <tei:title level="m">Chromatic Fantasy &amp; Fugue</tei:title> all appeared
          in 1902.</tei:note> beschäftigt mich in freien Stunden ganz und gar (zu dieser Thätigkeit
        paßten nun Ihre <tei:title>Inventionen</tei:title>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">sehr</tei:hi> gut<tei:supplied reason="cutoff">)</tei:supplied> und
        Alles Andere mußte deßhalb zurücktreten. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>“<tei:title>Ausklang</tei:title>” steht mir unter den Liedern obenan.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot"
              ><tei:bibl><tei:author>Schenker</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Sechs Lieder für
              eine Singstimme mit Begleitung des Pianoforte</tei:title>, Op. 3 (Leipzig: Breitkopf
            &amp; Härtel, [c. 1898]), No. 4</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> Der herrliche Text hat einen
        unmittelbaren Ausdruck in der Musik gefunden und das Lied muß eine tiefe Wirkung machen. Die
        anderen Lieder kommen mir zum Theil nicht so natürlich vor (das reizende
          <tei:title>Wiegenlied</tei:title> ausgenommen!)<tei:supplied reason="omission"
          >.</tei:supplied><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker,
            <tei:title level="m">Sechs Lieder</tei:title>, Op. 3, No. 2.</tei:note>
        <tei:pb n="4"/> Die Texte sind ja aber auch mehr geistreicher Art und interessant haben Sie
          <tei:hi rend="underline">Alles</tei:hi> illustrirt! Am Wenigsten sagt mir das letzte Lied
        zu – mir kommt’s hie und da etwas zu schwer für den leichtfertigen Text vor (gis-moll
          <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Episode</tei:hi>)<tei:supplied reason="omission"
          >.</tei:supplied> Doch, wie gesagt, ich muß noch besser eindringen und bitte Sie diese
        paar Worte nur als vorläufig anzusehen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000592">Messchaert</tei:rs> kommt dieser Tage nach
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-005779">Amsterdam</tei:rs>. Ich freue mich darauf die
        Lieder mit ihm durchzumachen und besonders auf den “<tei:title>Ausklang</tei:title>”. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Und nun nehmen Sie heute mit dieser zu kurzen Antwort auf Ihren so Vieles anregenden
        Brief vorlieb und nochmals für Alles herzlichen Dank<tei:supplied reason="omission"
          >.</tei:supplied>
      </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihren Sie verehrenden</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000724">Julius
            Röntgen</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-30"><tei:handShift new="#JR"/>Amsterdam, <tei:date
            when="1901-04-22">Apri 22, 1901</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>Most revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Dr. <tei:supplied
              reason="identity">Schenker</tei:supplied></tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
            type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>At last a word of thanks for your letter, which was so rich in content! Don’t mistake
        the delay for indifference! To the contrary: your songs and, above all,
          <tei:title>Inventions</tei:title> have occupied me intensely; but I did not want to write
        until I had developed a somewhat more intimate relationship with the material at hand, and
        that did not come immediately to me.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In your <tei:title>Inventions</tei:title> you tread upon fairly twisted paths, and it
        is not always easy to follow you.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> In
        particular, the purely <tei:hi rend="underline">musical</tei:hi> essence is not always
          <tei:pb n="2"/> readily apparent, even though the technical aspect is immediately
        interesting and impressive. In this respect, I’m drawn most strongly to the piece in F<tei:g
          type="sharp"/> minor – but more, thus far, through reading it than through playing it.
        There is much that sounds quite daring to me, even though everything is entirely logical. On
        it, you can safely write, as <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000027">Bach</tei:rs> did on
        his inventions: “a clear way at the same time to acquire a strong foretaste of
          composition.”<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> In contrast, “refreshing of
        the spirit” seems to take somewhat of a back seat.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
          type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Considering how well I have become acquainted with your
          <tei:title>Inventions</tei:title>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">thus far</tei:hi>, it is possible that my opinion will change. In
        any case, I will return to the works frequently, and I look forward <tei:pb n="3"/> to
        discussing them with you further in the future!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I have not yet spent a great deal of time with the Lieder, since I’ve had many other
        things to do in recent weeks. The <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000027">Bach</tei:rs>
        edition I took on<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> has occupied me during
        every free hour (for the latter purpose, your <tei:title>Inventions</tei:title> are very
        well suited!), and everything else had therefore to be pushed back.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>To me, “<tei:title>Ausklang</tei:title>” stands out among the Lieder.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> The marvelous text has found immediate expression
        in the music, and the Lied must make a profound impression. The other Lieder seem a bit less
        natural to me (with the exception of the delightful
          “<tei:title>Wiegenlied</tei:title>”!).<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/>
        <tei:pb n="4"/> But the texts are of a wittier sort, and you have illustrated <tei:hi
          rend="underline">everything</tei:hi> interestingly! The last Lied is least to my liking –
        it seems, to me, to be too heavy for the frivolous text in places (the G<tei:g type="sharp"
        /> minor episode). As I said, however, I must probe them further and ask that you consider
        these few words as merely provisional.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000592">Messchaert</tei:rs> is coming to <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-005779">Amsterdam</tei:rs> in a day or so. I’m looking forward to
        playing through the Lieder with him, especially “<tei:title>Ausklang</tei:title>.” </tei:p>

      <tei:p>And now you must make do, for today, with this overly brief reply to your highly
        stimulating letter, and once again many thanks for everything,</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Yours, in great admiration,</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000724">Julius
            Röntgen</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
