<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3215" sdoID="OJ-10-3_184">OJ 10/3, [184]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPoed" scope="major">Otto Erich Deutsch typist</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="OED" scope="minor">Otto Erich Deutsch's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2023</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IDB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2015-09-18" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002726">DeutschOE ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002712">DeutschOE ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002727">DeutschOE+H ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Typewritten letter from Deutsch to Schenker, dated September 30, 1932</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1932-09-30T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2023-08-08</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Deutsch would like to arrange a meeting with Kurt Thomasberger and Anthony van
        Hoboken to discuss the latter’s plans, possibly including Schenker. He is pessimistic about
        a future without Hoboken’s support and, consequently, about his future worth as a scholar;
        he is contemplating moving to the southern part of Europe, possibly the Balearic
        Islands.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000164">DeutschOE</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>PROF. OTTO ERICH DEUTSCH</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Tel. R 45–6–72</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">WIEN II.</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Böcklinstraße 26</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/><tei:date when="1932-09-30">30.
            Sept. 32</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Verehrter</tei:rs>!<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in
            Schenker’s diary for October 1, 1932: “Von Deutsch (Br.): äußerste Verzweiflung!
            Thomasberger scheint schon auf Widerstand gestoßen zu sein, möchte den Hauptweg
            vermeiden.” (“From Deutsch (letter): extreme despair! Thomasberger appears to have
            already encountered opposition and would like to avoid taking <tei:supplied
              reason="clarity">Deutsch’s</tei:supplied> chosen path.”). Schenker responded
            immediately with a seven-page letter (not surviving), suggesting that Thomasberger speak
            directly with Hoboken; Jeanette wrote out the letter that evening, and Schenker added a
            postscript the following day.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005784">Thomasberger</tei:rs> habe
        ich noch nicht mündlich wieder gesprochen, nur kurz telephonisch. Deshalb kann ich Ihnen
        auch die Drucksache noch nicht dankend zurückgeben. Dafür lege ich heute eine bei, die ich
        von einem Unbekannten zugeschickt bekam. Es würde mich interessieren, was Sie – mit einem
        Satze – dazu sagen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Die Balearen sind jetzt der billigste Fleck in Europa. Ich erfuhr es, als
        ich mich danach erkundigte, wo jetzt im Süden ein Zufluchtsort für einen armen Familienvater
        zu finden wäre: Capris Gegend, Südfrankreich und vor allem die Balearen! </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Was meinen Sie: soll <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005784"
          >Thomasberger</tei:rs>, er das möchte, mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380"
          >Hoboken</tei:rs>, den er kennt, über alle Sachen sprechen: <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002452">Archiv</tei:rs>, Bibliothek etc.? Allein oder in Ihrer Gegenwart? Bei
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs> oder an einem anderen Orte? Und
        wann? </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ueber Emil Ludwig van Beethoven haben wir leider nicht gesprochen. Und
        Ihren Hinweis auf das <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000034">Bamberger</tei:rs>-Konzert
        habe ich also wirklich übersehen, weil ich jetzt so ganz verwirrt bin.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker’s diary for September 20, 1932
          speaks of a forthcoming radio concert by Bamberger on September 25th, with the Vienna
          Symphony Orchestra in a program of works by Bach and Telemann. Schenker does not record
          having heard the concert, but the next day he writes of meeting Bamberger and expressing
          his approval of the performance.</tei:note> Sie ahnen gar nicht, wie es bei uns steht:
        alles auf dem Spiele. Und dabei rechne ich wirklich mit <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000380">H.</tei:rs> gar nicht mehr. Eine neue Stellung, Vorträge in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002510">Amerika</tei:rs> oder Auswanderung nach dem billigen
        Süden, wobei die Balearen mit <tei:sic>Malorka</tei:sic> für diesen Winter wenigstens
        auszuschliessen wären, wenn <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">H.</tei:rs> dorthin
        geht. Aber so schnell wird sich mein Schicksal wohl nicht entscheiden. Meine Arbeit hängt
        jedenfalls bald in der Luft. Ich klage nicht, aber ich erkläre Ihnen damit, dass ich nicht
        mehr viel wert bin. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Herzlichst ergeben Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-90"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/><tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000164">O E Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>PROF. OTTO ERICH DEUTSCH</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Tel. R 45–6–72</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">VIENNA II</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Böcklinstraße 26</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/><tei:date when="1932-09-30"
            >September 30, 1932</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">friend</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">I have not yet spoken face-to-face with <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-005784">Thomasberger</tei:rs>, only on the telephone briefly. For this reason
        I cannot yet return the printed material to you, with thanks. Instead I am enclosing one
        which was sent to me by an unknown person. It would interest me to know what you have to say
        about it – in one sentence.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">The Balearic Islands are now the cheapest spot in Europe. I learned this
        when I inquired about where a place of refuge in the south could be found for a poor head of
        a family: the area around Capri, the south of France, and above all the Balearic
        Islands!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">What do you think: Should <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005784"
          >Thomasberger</tei:rs>, if he wishes, speak with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380"
          >Hoboken</tei:rs>, whom he knows, about all the matters: the <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002452">Archive</tei:rs>, his library, etc.? Alone, or in your presence? At
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs>’s, or at some other place? And
        when?</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">We did not, unfortunately, speak about Emil Ludwig van Beethoven. And I
        quite overlooked your tip about <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000034"
        >Bamberger</tei:rs>’s concert, as I am now so confused.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> You have no idea how things are with us: everything hangs in the
        balance. And in this respect I really am not reckoning on <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs>: a new position, lectures in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002510">America</tei:rs>, or emigration to the south, which is cheap – though
        the Balearic Islands with Mallorca would have to be ruled out, for this winter at any rate,
        if <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs> goes there. But my fate will
        probably not be decided so quickly. In any event, my work is in limbo. I am not complaining,
        but I thereby declare to you that I am no longer worth very much.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Most cordially, your devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-90"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/><tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000164">O. E. Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
