<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="2288" sdoID="OJ-15-16_12">OJ 15/16, [12]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HW" scope="sole">Hans Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB-WD">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent and William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2007</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2007</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-06-25" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated December 18, 1912</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1912-12-18T17:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-10-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Diatribe by Weisse against Otto Vrieslander's plan to produce a simplified
    version of Schenker's Harmonielehre, impugning Vrieslander's motives.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Exzerptenbuch; book of excerpts; Herausgabe; edition; verdeutlichen; to explicate;
    Erklärung; explanation; Vereinfachung; simplification; Verbreitung; dissemination; Handbuch;
    handbook; Schmarotzengesicht; parasitism; Egoist; </dc:subject>



   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000951">Weisse</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Liebster <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Doktor</tei:rs>!<tei:note
      xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is not recorded in
      Schenker's diary. It is perhaps surprising that Schenker would not record so outspoken a
      letter (but he has not recorded any of the letters from Weisse received in 1912). Nor is
      anything of Vrieslander's proposals for Schenker's <tei:title level="m"
       >Harmonielehre</tei:title> recorded in Schenker's diary at this time, although a significant
      paragraph headed "Vrieslander's psychology" appears in the first entry for September 30, 1912.
      For fullest information on the post-publication plans for <tei:title level="m"
       >Harmonielehre</tei:title>, see <tei:bibl><tei:editor>Robert Wason </tei:editor>and
        <tei:editor>Matthew Brown</tei:editor>, eds, <tei:title level="m">Heinrich Schenker's
        Conception of Harmony</tei:title> (Rochester: Rochester University Press,
       forthcoming)</tei:bibl>. <tei:lb/>—On December 24, Schenker recorded: "Weisse bringt
      vormittags ein Geschenk u. sagt für Nachmittag ab." ("Weisse brings a present in the morning,
      and cancels for the afternoon.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>


   <tei:p>Sie kennen mich gut genug, um zu wissen, dass ich mich nie in Dinge menge, die mich nichts
    angehn. Aber was den Fall des Herrn <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922"
     >Vrieslander</tei:rs> anbelangt, von dem Sie unlängst Erwähnung getan haben,<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Evidently Schenker had spoken to Weisse of
     the Vrieslander matter in the previous day's lesson. Weisse had lessons with Schenker at this
     time on Tuesdays and Fridays (the letter is written on Wednesday): the absence of any reference
     to the matter in the notes to that lesson is not surprising, since these notes were restricted
     to instructional and technical topics. Records of Vrieslander's lessons with Schenker survive
     only between January 5 and March 5, 1912: it is not known how long before that period he had
     been taking lessons, though they may well have extended back at least to October 1911; the
     first reference to Vrieslander in the diary is on January 19, 1912 (OJ 1/11, p. 198). Of the
     diary entries prior to this letter, the pertinent one is probably a long entry dated September
     30, 1912 (OJ 1/11, pp. 243–44) that begins "Vrieslander's psychology." There is no record in
     the diary of any letter from Schenker to Weisse around this time (nor of receipt of the present
     letter).</tei:note> so möchte ich Ihnen hiedoch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
     place="foot"><tei:hi rend="italic">hiedoch</tei:hi>: perhaps <tei:hi rend="italic"
      >hiedurch</tei:hi>, "by this means," is intended.</tei:note> einige Worte <tei:del
     rend="overstrike">geben</tei:del> sagen, und zwar berechtigte, weil ich, wenn schon nicht an <tei:choice>
     <tei:sic>Ihrem</tei:sic>
     <tei:corr>Ihrer</tei:corr>
    </tei:choice> Person, so doch an Ihrem Werke Interessent sein darf! Die Tatsache die Sie mir
    berichteten, das<tei:supplied reason="syntax">s</tei:supplied>
    <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> einen Auszug – eine
     „<tei:sic>Populariesierung</tei:sic>“ – aus Ihrem Werke vorbereitet,<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">According to Robert Wason, Vrieslander
     produced three "lengthy commentaries" (72pp, 468pp, and 472pp, respectively) on Schenker's
      <tei:title level="m">Harmonielehre</tei:title> between 1910 and 1925, and on October 11, 1915
     wrote to Schenker suggesting that a second edition of the work should be produced including
     "practical exercises and assignments" (which Schenker resisted): <tei:bibl><tei:title level="a"
       >From <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> to <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmony</tei:hi>:
       Schenker's Theory of Harmony and its Americanization,</tei:title> in <tei:title level="m"
       >Schenker-Traditionen: Eine Wiener Schule der Musiktheorie und ihre internationale
       Verbreitung</tei:title>, ed. <tei:editor>Martin Eybl</tei:editor> &amp; <tei:editor>Evelyn
       Fink-Mennel</tei:editor> (Vienna: Böhlau Verlag, 2006), pp. 171–201, esp.
     181–82</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> hat erst nach meinem Scheiden von Ihnen grosse Bedenken erregt,
    die ich Ihnen auch hier mitteilen möchte.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Vor allem muss man sich über das Vorgehen <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922"
      ><tei:hi rend="underline">Vr.</tei:hi></tei:rs> klar sein, der, wenngleich er auch ein Jahr im
    Verkehre mit Ihnen einiges gewann,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot"
     >This may be the only evidence as to the extent of the prior association of Vrieslander with
     Schenker, at least until the bulk of the large Vrieslander‒Schenker correspondence, currently
     in private hands, is made accessible.</tei:note> den Menschen <tei:pb n="2"/> in sich durch
    Erkenntnis seiner Umgebung und der Verhältnisse, in die er hineingeboren ist nicht besser<tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">n</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">te</tei:add>
    </tei:subst>
    <tei:del rend="overstrike">konnte</tei:del>, weil er sonst an sich bemerken könnte, was das Um-
    und Auf des heutigen, armseligen sterilen Geistesleben geworden ist: Die Ausbeutung fremden
    Kapitals – oder treffender gesagt die Ausbeutung des Zinsen eines Kapitals. Denn was heute
    geschrieben wird ist leider Gottes das Erfordernis einer Zeit, die dem Schaffenden wie dem
    Medium gleich wenig Fähigkeiten zu geben <tei:choice>
     <tei:sic>wusste</tei:sic>
     <tei:corr>weiss</tei:corr>
    </tei:choice>: Zwischen den Kunstwerken, die beschrieben werden und dem Publikum, das diese
     Beschreibungen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Weisse no doubt has
     in mind <tei:bibl><tei:author><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000484">Hermann
        Kretzschmar</tei:rs></tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Führer durch den
       Konzertsaal</tei:title> (Leipzig: Liebeskind, 1888–90, numerous later editions by Breitkopf
      &amp; Härtel)</tei:bibl>, of which Schenker owned the first, two-volume edition; also
        <tei:bibl><tei:author><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003312">George
       Grove</tei:rs></tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Beethoven and his Nine
       Symphonies</tei:title> (London: Novello, [1896])</tei:bibl>, of which Schenker owned the
     German translation, <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Beethoven und seine Neun
       Symphonien</tei:title> (London: Hehemann, 1906)</tei:bibl>; the program books written by
     Schenker's friend <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000378">Robert Hirschfeld</tei:rs> for the
     Vienna Philharmonic Society's concerts, 1893–1913; and other popular guides for concert- and
     opera-goers.</tei:note> verschlingt<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> liegt
    eine ungeheure Kluft: Der Tod des Künstlers! Er hat in seinem Werke eben eine Summe gehäuft, die
    er <tei:del rend="overstrike">eben</tei:del> als Kapital fest umrissen der Welt uberliess; –
    aber das Fehlen der Erben hat es den Würmern ermöglicht aus blühendem Leben einen Kadaver zu
    machen, an dem jeder einzelne nagt, und <tei:subst>
     <tei:del>das</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">die Nährung</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> findet<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> die er sucht. <tei:pb
     n="3"/> Die Würme<tei:supplied reason="syntax">r</tei:supplied> aber zu verscheuchen geht
    ebensowenig an – als den Kadaver zum Leben zu erwecken. Die geistige Luft, in der wir leben ist
    verseucht, von dem Pestgestanke nicht versorgter Leichen, die sich freilich gegen ihre Zernager
    nicht wehren konnten!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Was <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>s Arbeit – sei sie gut
    oder schlecht – betrifft – so ist sie die Ausbeutung – und das ist es worauf ich hinaus will –
    einer Summe, die zum Kapitale noch nicht abgeschlossen wurde. Sie haben – Gott sei Dank <tei:choice>
     <tei:sic>ihr</tei:sic>
     <tei:corr>Ihr</tei:corr>
    </tei:choice> letztes Wort noch nicht gesprochen – und hiemit die Konsequenzen, die sich aus <tei:choice>
     <tei:sic>ihren</tei:sic>
     <tei:corr>Ihren</tei:corr>
    </tei:choice> Prämissen und Schlüssen ergeben, selbst zu ziehen!! (wie <tei:choice>
     <tei:sic>sie</tei:sic>
     <tei:corr>Sie</tei:corr>
    </tei:choice> es ja auch vorhaben!) Was sollte dieses Exzerptenbuch<tei:del rend="overstrike"
     >e</tei:del> – und wem anders stünde es zu, wenn es sich darum handelte, eines zu machen – als
    wieder Ihnen selbst??</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Der Prophet der einen Mittler duldet wird sich von der Menge, der er offenbart, durch
    diesen eher entfernen, abnähern.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Abgesehen von allem ist es notwendig und hat es je gute Früchte getragen, von der Quelle
    der <tei:pb n="4"/> Weisheit – Wasser in Abzugsflaschen zu exportieren<tei:hi rend="infralinear"
     >?</tei:hi> Ist, der den Weg zur Quelle scheut, <tei:choice>
     <tei:sic>ihrer</tei:sic>
     <tei:corr>Ihrer</tei:corr>
    </tei:choice> überhaupt wert?</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Und zugegeben – dass das Entgegenkommen gegenüber all diesen geistigen Krückenträgern von
    Vorteil wäre, und zur Verbreitung beitrüge – so steht doch die Verdeutlichung eines scheinbar
    „zu schwierigen und komplizierten“ <tei:add place="interlinear-above">nur und nur</tei:add> dem
     <tei:hi rend="underline">Autor</tei:hi> zu. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000421"><tei:hi
      rend="underline">Kant</tei:hi></tei:rs> selbst nur könnte und dürfte in den Prolegomenon die
    Erklärung und Vereinfachung der <tei:title>Kritik der reinen Vernunft</tei:title> geben. Aus dem
    Munde eines andern hätte es gegen ihn eingenommen.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Wer könnte es dem Durchschnitte verargen, ja sogar we<tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">gen</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">r</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> könnte etwas anders von ihm erwarten als, dass dieser, nach dem man ihm in den Mund
    legte: Schenkers <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724"><tei:title level="m"
      >Harmonielehre</tei:title></tei:rs> ist zu schwierig, vor dessen <tei:rs type="work"
     key="entity-001726"><tei:title level="m">Kontrapunkt</tei:title></tei:rs>,<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">This appears to refer to Schenker's <tei:rs
      type="work" key="entity-001724"><tei:title level="m">Harmonielehre</tei:title></tei:rs> having
     been produced as volume I of the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001723"><tei:title level="m"
       >Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:title></tei:rs>, and <tei:rs type="work"
      key="entity-001725"><tei:title level="m">Kontrapunkt</tei:title></tei:rs> as volume II, a
     matter which is taken up by Schenker in his correspondence with Vrieslander of October
     1915.</tei:note> (<tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">vor</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">dem gegen</tei:add>
    </tei:subst>über er ja <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">a priori</tei:foreign> Angst hatte),
    zurückschrecken würde und auch auf dessen Verdeutlichung warten würde!</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="5"/> Wenn aber auch dessen Verdeutlichung ihm in Aussicht gestellt <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">würde</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">wäre</tei:add>
    </tei:subst>, würde hier nicht in aller Stille einbekannt<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08"
     type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:hi rend="italic">einbekennen</tei:hi>: Austrian usage for
      <tei:hi rend="italic">eingestehen</tei:hi>, to confess, admit, acknowledge.</tei:note> werden,
    dass Ihre Schreibweise, Ihre Ausdrucksweise, tatsächlich nicht geklärt <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">ist</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">sei</tei:add>
    </tei:subst>: und <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ist</tei:add> nicht das Gegenteil der
    Fall?? Die Verbreitung Ihres geistigen Eigentumes ist bereits vor sich gegangen – wahrscheinlich
    zumeist auf unehrliche Weise. Aber Sie sind Idealist genug, <tei:del rend="overstrike"
     >mit</tei:del> auf die Verbreitung überhaupt, und auch auf die Art, wie sie vor sich geht, zu
    schauen. Wenn hiemit Ihre „Gegner“ in Anbetracht jeglichen Fehlens einer Moral und eines
    Gewissens Ihren Namen zu verschweigen übersich<tei:del rend="overstrike">te</tei:del> brachten,
    so wäre im Falle eines Excerptenbuches dieses Vorgehen, sogar <tei:hi rend="double-underline"
     >mit</tei:hi> gutem Gewissen verbunden! Denn es hätte sich vor Ihrem eigenen Namen ein Zweiter
    gestellt, den zu verheimlichen kleine Gefahr und Notwendigkeit vorhanden wäre.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Jede Wahrheit aus zweiter Hand ist um einen Grad trüber – und kann umso leichter
    missverstanden und missdeutet werden! Und hiemit <tei:pb n="6"/> wären an dieses Unglücksbuch
    unfruchtbare und von unbefugter Seite geführte Kontroversen <tei:del rend="overstrike"
     >wird</tei:del> geknüpt!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Wie gesagt nicht gegen die Idee eines „Handbuches“ habe ich Einwendungen sondern nur gegen
    die zweite Hand. Denn <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>s geistiges
    Schmarotzengesicht hat wie das aller seiner Kollegen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09"
     type="editorial" place="foot"> It is unclear what is implied by Vrieslander's "colleagues,"
     here.</tei:note> einen Januskopf: Er <tei:hi rend="underline">scheint</tei:hi> zu geben,
     <tei:hi rend="underline">nur</tei:hi> in Wahrheit selbst nur zu nehmen, und zu
    profitieren.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Lässt einer, aber der seine beiden Hände frei hat, sich unter dem Vorwande, man gäbe ihm
    etwas hinein, in seine Tasche greifen?</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Die Psychologie allein könnte Ihr Urteil in diesem Falle sofort <tei:del rend="overstrike"
     >v</tei:del>erklären: Sie haben an <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vr.</tei:rs>
    Ehrlichkeit schon lange gezweifelt, haben ihn als Egoisten erkannt, und werden doch nicht
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">plötzlich</tei:add> eine altruistische Regung in ihm
    vermuten, die ihn derlei Dinge machen liesse, ohne selbst davon einen Vorteil zu haben?<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn10" type="editorial" place="foot">Weisse places a question-mark at the end of
     this paragraph, but there is no question to mark. </tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="7"/> Wenn es überhaupt so weit kommen sollte, dass er Ihnen sein
    „verdeutlichtes Handbuch“ vorlegen sollte, so bitte ich Sie, diesen Brief, der wahrlich ehrlich
    und im Interesse der Sache gemeint war, vorzunehmen und <tei:choice>
     <tei:sic>ihre</tei:sic>
     <tei:corr>Ihre</tei:corr>
    </tei:choice> Billigung zur Herausgabe jenes erst zu geben, nachdem die treffende Widerlegungen
    meiner Einwände gefunden haben.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Herzlichst Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"><tei:hi rend="underline"
       >Hans</tei:hi></tei:rs>.</tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1912-12-18">18. Dez. 1912</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Dearest Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs type="person"
       key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
      type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>


   <tei:p>You are well enough acquainted with me to know that I never meddle with things that do not
    concern me. But when it comes to the matter of Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922"
     >Vrieslander</tei:rs>, of whom you recently made mention,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
     type="footnote"/> I should like to say a few words to you here,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
     type="footnote"/>
    <tei:supplied reason="clarity">words that are</tei:supplied> justified, moreover, because I
    should be <tei:supplied reason="clarity">seen as</tei:supplied> someone having a vested interest
    not in your person but in your work. That, as you reported to me, <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> is preparing an abridgment ‒ a
     "popularization"<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> ‒ of your work has given me
    much pause for thought since left you, and I should like to convey those thoughts to you
    here.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>First and foremost, we must be clear about the actions of <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000922"><tei:hi rend="underline">Vrieslander</tei:hi></tei:rs>, who, even though he
    gained something by a year's association with you,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/>
    <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">did</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">could</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> not improve the man himself <tei:pb n="2"/> through cognizance of his environs and
    the circumstances into which he was born, because he could otherwise see for himself what the
    full extent of today's impoverished, sterile spiritual life has become. The exploitation of
    someone else's capital ‒ or better put, the exploitation of the interest on that capital. For
    that which is written today is unfortunately the condition of an age that is able to confer as
    little competence on the creative artist as on the medium <tei:supplied reason="clarity">in
     which he works</tei:supplied>: between works of art that are described and the public that
    devour these descriptions<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> there lies an enormous
    gulf: the death of the artist! What he has done in his work is precisely to heap up a sum that
    he entrusts to the world as well defined capital. But the failings of his inheritors have made
    it possible for the worms to make out of blossoming life a cadaver at which each individual one
    of them gnaws and finds the <tei:add place="interlinear-above">nourishment</tei:add> that it
    seeks. <tei:pb n="3"/> But to get rid of the worms is just as difficult as bringing the cadaver
    back to life. The spiritual air in which we live is contaminated by the pestilential stench of
    unattended corpses, who admittedly cannot defend themselves against those who gnaw at
    them!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>As concerns <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>'s work ‒ be it
    good or bad ‒ the exploitation ‒ and that is what it amounts to ‒ of a sum which has not yet
    been added into the capital. You have ‒ thanks be to God! ‒ not yet spoken your final word, and
    therefore you have not yourself drawn the consequences that arise from your premisses and
    conclusions. (As you indeed plan to do!) What is this book of excerpts supposed to be, and who
    else should have a claim on writing it ‒ if one is to be written at all ‒ than, again, you
    yourself??</tei:p>

   <tei:p>The prophet who tolerates a mediator will in so doing distance himself, sever himself from
    the crowd to which he makes his revelations.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Apart from everything <tei:supplied reason="clarity">else</tei:supplied>, is it necessary,
    and has it ever been fruitful to draw liquid from the fountain of <tei:pb n="4"/> wisdom and
    export it as bottled water<tei:hi rend="infralinear">?</tei:hi> Is he who shuns the path to the
    source at all worthy of you?</tei:p>

   <tei:p>And granted, to make concession to all these intellectual cripples would be of advantage
    and might contribute to the dissemination <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of the
     word</tei:supplied>; however, the <tei:hi rend="underline">author</tei:hi>
    <tei:add place="interlinear-above">and he alone</tei:add> has sole claim on the explication of
    something allegedly "too difficult and complicated." Only <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000421"><tei:hi rend="underline">Kant</tei:hi></tei:rs> himself could and was
    entitled to give in his Prolegomenon the explanation and simplification of his <tei:title
     level="m">Critique of Pure Reason</tei:title>. From the mouth of anybody else it would have
    been to his detriment.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Who could blame the mediocre man ‒ what's more, who could expect anything else of him
    other than, after the idea had been put into his head, that Schenker's <tei:rs type="work"
     key="entity-001724"><tei:title level="m">Theory of Harmony</tei:title></tei:rs> was too
    difficult, more so than his <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001726"><tei:title level="m"
      >Counterpoint</tei:title></tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> (which he
    already dreaded), he would be scared off and would wait for the explication of it!</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="5"/> However, even if the prospect of an explication of <tei:supplied
     reason="clarity">the <tei:title level="m">Theory of Harmony</tei:title></tei:supplied> were to
    be held out to him, nobody would admit<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/> to him
    covertly that it lacked any explanation of your style of writing <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
     >or</tei:supplied> manner of expression: and is not the contrary the case? The dissemination of
    your intellectual property has already taken place ‒ probably mostly in a disgraceful fashion.
    But you are idealist enough to take care of the dissemination as a whole, and also of the way in
    which it is carried out. If in this connection your "adversaries" were, out of a sheer lack of
    any ethics or conscience, to go so far as to suppress your name, they would do so in the case of
    a book of excerpts, even one made <tei:hi rend="double-underline">in</tei:hi> good faith! For in
    place of your own name would have been put that of another, the concealment of which would
    present little danger, nor <tei:supplied reason="clarity">would there be any</tei:supplied>
    necessity <tei:supplied reason="clarity">to include it</tei:supplied>.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Any truth conveyed at second hand loses a degree in clarity and can all the more easily be
    misunderstood and misinterpreted! And coupled to this <tei:pb n="6"/> would be unfruitful
    controversies led by unauthorized sources that would overtake this ill-fated book.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>As I have already said, I have no objections to the idea of a "handbook," only to its
    second-hand nature. For <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>'s
    intellectual parasitism has, like that of all his colleagues,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09"
     type="footnote"/> a janus face: He <tei:hi rend="underline">appears</tei:hi> to give, <tei:hi
     rend="underline">only</tei:hi> in fact to take away and to profiteer.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>But does someone who has his two hands free reach into his pocket under the pretext that
    someone else had put something in it?</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Only psychology could give an instantaneous explanation of your verdict in this case: you
    have long doubted <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>'s honesty, you
    have recognized him for an egotist, and will certainly not <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
     >suddenly</tei:add> expect to find a streak of altruism in him that causes him to do such
    things unless there is some advantage to be had from it.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn10"
     type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="7"/> If it should ever come to such a pass that he presents you with his
    "explicated handbook," I beg you to take up this letter, which is intended sincerely and
    honestly, and in the interests of the cause, and give your approval to the edition only after
    the relevant refutations have been given to my objections.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Most cordially your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"><tei:hi rend="underline"
       >Hans</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1912-12-18">December 18, 1912</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>


  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
