<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3275" sdoID="OJ-15-8_5">OJ 15/8, [5]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPwe" scope="major">Typist Waldheim-Eberle</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="minor">Josef Stritzko's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="stamp" scope="minor">stamp</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2007, 2023</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2007, 2023</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2011-10-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:rs type="correspondence" role="correspondence" key="entity-005439">Waldheim-Eberle ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Typewritten letter from Waldheim–Eberle to Schenker, dated September 24,
        1906</dc:title>
      <dcterms:created>1906-09-24T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2023-09-02</dcterms:dateSubmitted>

      <dc:description>Josef Stritzko asserts the honesty of Bernhard Herzmansky [of Doblinger], and
        explains Herzmansky's pricing [of Schenker's Instrumentations-Tabelle]; Stritzko resents
        having had to renege on his agreement, and is consequently unwilling to help Schenker any
        further with finding a publisher.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-002402">Waldheim-Eberle</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000875">Josef Stritzko</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>Telefon No. 133</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Stein- / Buch- / Kunst- / und / Musikalien- / Druckerei</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">decorative engraved
              image</tei:note></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>R. v. WALDHEIM <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">shield</tei:note>
            JOS. EBERLE &amp; Co.</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>ERSTE WIENER ZEITUNGS-GESELLSCHAFT</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60"><tei:placeName>Wien</tei:placeName>, <tei:handShift
              new="#TPwe"/><tei:date when="1906-09-24">24. September, 06</tei:date>.</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>VII/1. SEIDENGASSE
            3—9</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10"><tei:handShift new="#TPwe"/>Hochwohlgeboren Herrn Dr.
            Heinrich Schenker,</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80"><tei:placeName>Wien.</tei:placeName></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:lb/>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Jhr gesch. Schreiben vom <tei:date when="1906-09-22">22.
          ds.</tei:date><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker’s diary
          for September 24, 1906 records: “von Doktor Stritzko Antwort erhalten, Auflösung des
          Vertr.” (“Answer received from Dr. Stritzko: cancellation of the contract.”). — This
          follows an entry of September 22: “Antwort von Str.: Ablehnung des Vertrages mit Dbl.”
          (“Answer from Stritzko: rejection of the contract with Doblinger.”).</tei:note> bringt
        mich tatsächlich in Verlegenheit. Wie ich Jhnen bereits mitgeteilt habe, habe ich auf Grund
        Jhrer mündlichen Zusage <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Schenker’s diary for September 13, 1906 records: “Bei Director Stritzko: mündliche
          Vorabledigung des Vertrages betreffs der <tei:title>Tabelle</tei:title>. (auf 5 Jahre, mit
          Doblinger, 33⅓ von einer 1.20 Kr. = 20 <tei:sic>Kr</tei:sic> per Exempl. Ausbedingen als
          Nebengeschenk Partiturren von Bruckner, Mahler, (der Erweiterung der Bibliothek halber.) –
          Um Ergänzung der <tei:title>Tabelle</tei:title> in Hinsicht möglicher u. unmöglicher
          “Triller” von Str. angegangen.” (“At Director Stritzko’s: preliminary word-of-mouth
          dealings over the contract re: the <tei:title level="m">Tabelle</tei:title>. (over[?] five
          years, with Doblinger, 33⅓ of a 1.20 Kronen = 20 <tei:choice>
            <tei:sic>Kronen</tei:sic>
            <tei:corr>Pfennigs</tei:corr>
          </tei:choice> per copy) on condition of gratis scores by Bruckner and Mahler (for the
          expansion of my library.) – Approached by Stritzko for extension of the <tei:title
            level="m">Tabelle</tei:title> with respect to possible and impossible “Trills.”). — The
          diary for September 15 records: “An Dir. Str. das Resultat abgeschickt.” (“The result sent
          to Director Stritzko.”).</tei:note> den Vertrag mit der Firma <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-004002">Doblinger</tei:rs> geschlossen, und bin ich daher heute gezwungen
        dahin zu wirken, dass mich Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000359"
          >Herzmansky</tei:rs> meiner Verpflichtungen wieder entbindet. Jch thue dies aus dem Grunde
        ungern, weil man eine Zusage überhaupt nicht gerne rückgängig macht, umsomehr in diesem
        Falle, als Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000359">v. Herzmansky</tei:rs> zu meinen
        liebsten Kunden zählt. Auch finde ich das mit Herrn <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000359">Herzmansky</tei:rs> geschlossene Uebereinkommen durchaus nicht für Sie
        ungünstig, und glaube ich kaum, dass Sie ein besseres Uebereinkommen treffen werden. <tei:pb
          n="2"/> Sie sind sehr im Jrrtum, wenn Sie Herrn <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000359"
          >v. Herzmansky</tei:rs> für fähig halten, die Exemplare zu höherem Preise zu verkaufen wie
        dies vereinbart wurde. Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000359">Herzmansky</tei:rs>
        ist ein streng reeler Geschäftsmann mit dem wir 25 Jahre in angenehmster Verbindung stehen,
        und dessen ehrenwerter Character uns zur Genüge bekannt ist. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000359">Herzmansky</tei:rs> hat den Verkaufspreis an das Publikum mit K. 2.40
        bestimmt, und muss den übrigen Musikalienhändlern von diesen K. 2.40 25% Rabatt einräumen,
        und auf 10 Expl. 1 Freiexemplar bewilligen. Ausserdem hat derselbe die Kosten der üblichen
        Reklame zu tragen, und bei grösseren Abgaben sogar den Rabatt auf 33 1/3 und Freiexemplare
        erhöhen, so zwar, dass der Verdienst pro Exemplar ein durchaus bürgerlicher genannt werden
        muss. Sie vergessen ganz, dass <tei:hi rend="underline">Sie</tei:hi> in diesem Falle <tei:hi
          rend="underline">keinerlei</tei:hi> Risiko tragen, indem die Kosten der Herstellung,
        welche ziemlich bedeutend sind, wir übernommen haben, und dass Sie daher an der Sache
        unbedingt Geld verdienen müssen, während es bei uns zweifelhaft ist, ob wir aus dem Erlös
        des Bändchens auf unsere Kosten kommen werden. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Jch habe gewiss alles getan, um Jhnen mein Entgegekommen zu erweisen, ich
        werde nun auch die Angelegenheit mit <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-004002"
          >Doblinger</tei:rs> ordnen, und bin überzeugt, dass Herr <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000359">v. Herzmansky</tei:rs> über mein Ansuchen, welches ich auf Grund Jhrer
        Entschliessung an denselben richten muss, mich meiner Vertragsverbindlichkeiten entbinden
          <tei:pb n="3"/> wird, aber ich bedauere auch gleichzeitig mitteilen zu müssen, dass ich
        nicht in der Lage bin, einen anderen Verleger für Sie aufzutreiben, und muss ich es Jhnen
        daher überlassen, diesbezüglich selbst Jhre Schritte zu gehen. Es soll mich recht sehr
        freuen, wenn Sie eine Verlagsfirma finden, welche das Werk auf eigene Rechnung übernimmt, in
        welchem Falle Sie wohl die Güte haben werden, dafür Sorge zu tragen, dass uns seitens dieser
        Firma die Kosten der Herstellung bezahlt werden.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker’s diary for November 4, 1906 records: “Verleger
          Herzmansky ( Doblinger ) gesteht unumwunden den Gedankengang Drt. Stritzko’s, wie auch den
          eigenen ein, der in seiner nackten Borniertheit u. Unzweckmäßigkeit die gemeinsamen
          Herausgabe1 der <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001729"
              ><tei:title>Instrumententabelle</tei:title></tei:rs> vereitelt hat. So behielt mein
          Instinkt, selbst in der angeblich praktischeren Welt des Kaufmannes, vollauf Recht!”
          (“Publisher Herzmansky (of Doblinger) openly admits Director Stritzko's line of thought
          (and his own, too), which in its unvarnished narrowmindedness and inappropriateness has
          thwarted the joint edition of the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001729"><tei:title
              level="m">Instrumentation Table</tei:title></tei:rs>. So my instinct was absolutely
          right, even in the allegedly practical world of the businessman.”).</tei:note></tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Mit vorzüglicher Hochachtung</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:handShift new="#stamp"/><tei:rs key="entity-002402"
            type="organization">R. v. Waldheim-Jos. Eberle &amp; Co.</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:handShift new="#stamp"/> Erste Wiener
          Zeitungs-Gesellschaft</tei:signed>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>mpa <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000875">Josef Stritzko</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>Telephone No. 133</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Lithographic, book, art, and music printer</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">decorative engraved
              image</tei:note></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>R. v. WALDHEIM <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">shield</tei:note>
            JOS. EBERLE &amp; Co.</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>FIRST VIENNESE NEWSPAPER SOCIETY</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60"><tei:placeName>Vienna</tei:placeName>, <tei:handShift
              new="#TPwe"/><tei:date when="1906-09-24">September 24, 1906</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>VII/1, SEIDENGASSE
            3—9</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10"><tei:handShift new="#TPwe"/>Dr. Heinrich Schenker,
            Esq.</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80"><tei:placeName>Vienna</tei:placeName></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:lb/>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Your esteemed letter of the <tei:date when="1906-09-22">22nd of this
          month</tei:date><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> in fact places me in an
        embarrassing position. As I have already informed you, I made the contract with the firm of
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-004002">Doblinger</tei:rs> on the basis of your
        verbal agreement,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> and today I am therefore
        compelled to see to it that the Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000359"
          >Herzmansky</tei:rs> will release me from my commitments. I do this unwillingly, because
        one does not ever gladly go back on a promise, all the more so in this case since I count
        Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000359">Herzmansky</tei:rs> among my dearest
        customers. Moreover, I consider the agreement formed with Mr. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000359">Herzmansky</tei:rs> in no way unfavorable to you, and I find it hard
        to believe that you will find a better agreement <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
          >elsewhere</tei:supplied>. <tei:pb n="2"/> You are very much in error in considering Mr.
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000359">Herzmansky</tei:rs> capable of selling the
        copies at a higher price than that settled upon. Mr. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000359">Herzmansky</tei:rs> is a strictly honest businessman with whom we have
        been most agreeably associated for twenty-five years, for whose honorable character we can
        thoroughly vouch. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000359">Herzmansky</tei:rs> set the
        purchase price to the public as 2.40 Kroner, and has to grant the other music retailers a
        discount of 25% from this 2.40 Kroner and allow for one free copy per every ten copies. In
        addition, he has to bear the cost of the usual advertisements, and on larger orders he even
        has to raise the discount to 33⅓% and <tei:supplied reason="clarity">increase the number
          of</tei:supplied> free copies, hence the profit per copy can only be described as
        thoroughly modest. You are completely forgetting that <tei:hi rend="underline">you</tei:hi>
        bear <tei:hi rend="underline">no</tei:hi> risk <tei:hi rend="underline">whatsoever</tei:hi>
        in this matter, whereas we have undertaken the costs of production, which are fairly
        significant, and that accordingly you are bound inevitably to earn money, whilst for us it
        is doubtful whether we will cover our costs out of the proceeds from the little
        volume.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I have certainly done all that I can to demonstrate to you my good will. I
        will even clear up the business with <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-004002"
          >Doblinger</tei:rs> now, convinced as I am that Mr. Herzkmansky will release me from my
        contractual obligations at my request, which I must put to him in consequence of your
        decision. <tei:pb n="3"/> However, I regret that I am obliged at the same time to inform you
        that I am not in a position to get hold of another publisher for you, and must accordingly
        leave it to you to go your own way in this regard. I shall be truly delighted if you are
        able to find a publishing firm that will take over the work on its own account, in which
        case please be so good as to insure that the costs of production will be paid to us on the
        part of this firm.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">With kind regards,</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:handShift new="#stamp"/><tei:rs key="entity-002402"
            type="organization">R. v. Waldheim-Jos. Eberle &amp; Co.</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:handShift new="#stamp"/>First Viennese Newspaper
          Society</tei:signed>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>mpa <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000875">Josef Stritzko</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
