<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3883" sdoID="OJ-13-10_171">OJ 13/10, [171]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2025</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated July 6 and 10, 1933</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1933-07-10T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-12-10</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel is continuing his opposition to Karl Straube and the “Reger clique” at
        the Leipzig Conservatory. – He is uneasy about the current youth movement. – He praises
        Adolf Hitler’s achievements but is critical of the lower administrative authorities in
        Germany.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/>Leipzig, <tei:date when="1933-07-06">6. VII
              33</tei:date>. Könneritzstr 58<tei:hi rend="supralinear">III</tei:hi>.</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Professor Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
            >Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for July 13, 1933: “Von Oppel
            (Aufsatz zum 65. Geburtstag von Goos): Spuren einer Verstimmung gegenüber dem neuen
            Regime. Der kleine Aufsatz von Goos ist rührend – daß der Rundfunk abgelehnt hat, ist
            ein Widerspruch” (“From Oppel (essay for my 65th birthday by Goos): traces of
            displeasure regarding the new regime. The short article by Goos is touching – that the
            radio station declined to broadcast it is a contradiction.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>herzlichen Dank für Ihren lieben Brief,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Writing of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for July 4, 1933: “An
          Oppel (Br.): Dank für den Geburtstagswunsch; knüpfe an den leise pessimistischen Ton an u.
          deute die trostlose Lage des Nachwuchses. Gäbe es eine Gleichschaltung der Genies –, so
          aber . . !! Um <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs> ist mir
          bange. Die Bildchen der Brigitte behalte ich bis auf Widerruf” (“To Oppel (letter): thanks
          for the birthday wishes; I draw on the gently pessimistic tone [of his message] and
          portend the grim prospects for the next generation. If [only] there were an enforced
          uniformity applied to geniuses – but as things stand …!! I am apprehensive for <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs>. I shall keep the photographs of
          Brigitte until requested to return it.”).</tei:note> den ich gleich erwidere. Die
        Prüfungen sind vorbei und ich habe mehr Zeit, zumal ich mich auch bei der Partei beurlauben
        lasse. Mein Kampf gegen <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000866">Straube</tei:rs> hat
        nämlich sehr böses Blut gesetzt, und da soll eine Ruhepause eintreten. Der Herr hat eben
        überall seine Fäden Kreisstörung wie eine Spinne gezogen. Aber er wird sich schon noch in
        seinem eignen Netz verstricken. Nach den Ferien geht der Kampf wieder. Denn letzten Endes
        geht es für mich contra <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000695">Reger</tei:rs> und
        Konsorten u. für Ihre Ideen. – Die Bilder sind selbstverständlich für Sie bestimmt, wir
        haben Duplikate. – Mein kleiner Schüler <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000299"
          >Goos</tei:rs> hat ein paar Zeilen für Sie verfasst, die Ihnen sicher Freude machen. Er
        wollte sogar ursprünglich im Sender über Ihr Werk sprechen, was aber abgelehnt wurde. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich habe auch hier ein paar Leute wieder dafür gewonnen. Aber bei die <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000712">Riemann</tei:rs>seuche u. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000695">Reger</tei:rs>inzucht hier habe ich damit keinen leichten Stand. –
        Mich freut, dass Sie es in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-006028">Reigersberg</tei:rs> so
        gut getroffen haben in allen Punkten. Wir haben fast täglich Regen. Hoffentlich ist die
        Sonne da unten beständiger bei ihrer wirklichen Ferienaufgabe<tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">.</tei:supplied>
      </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Leider gewährt man der Jugend etwas zu viel Spielraum, ich fürchte sehr, dass bei der
        frühen politischen Erziehung nur Mittelmässigkeit und mehr oder weniger kindische
        Altklugheit herauskommt u. die wirklichen geistigen Werte ins Hintertreffen <tei:del
          rend="overstrike">kommen</tei:del> geraten. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Die neuen (Tendenz) Schauspiele u. Filme habe ich mir noch nicht
          angesehn.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">The term “tendency
          film” is used to describe a film with a specific cultural and especially political goal,
          in effect a propaganda film. It was first applied to left-wing cinema in 1920s and ‘30s
          Japan.</tei:note> Ich warte noch, aus dem Gefühl heraus, dass ich nicht auf meine Kosten
        komme. Die Parteien sind ja nun alle verschwunden, auch das Centrum. Gott sei Dank! Das
        Schielen <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">ultra montes</tei:foreign> ist uns nie gut bekommen.
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002643">London</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002590">Genf</tei:rs> sind zwei völlig gleiche Nieten.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Reference is to the London Monetary and
          Economic Conference, June 12 to July 27, 1933, aimed at fighting the Great Depression and
          its effects, and Geneva conferences that took place in 1927 and 1932.</tei:note> Arbeit
        und die altpreussische Sparsamkeit müssen uns nun helfen. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Was ich in den Ferien beginne, ist noch unklar, vorläufig habe ich gar kein Geld und
        Schulden möchte ich nicht machen. Ich bin zwar wieder in den Hunsrück u. an den Rhein
        eingeladen. Aber an <tei:choice>
          <tei:sic>Nahenverdienst</tei:sic>
          <tei:corr>Nebenverdienst?</tei:corr>
        </tei:choice> ist jetzt gar nicht zu denken und der Gehalt schmal, dabei wachsen die
        Ausgaben für <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008523">Bepo</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-008524">Brigitte</tei:rs> auch langsam. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:date when="1933-07-10">10. 7. 33</tei:date>. Nach 3 herrlichen Sommertagen mit
        fast Tropenhitze die durch längere Spaziergänge mit <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-008523">Bepo</tei:rs> teilweise ausgefüllt wurden, schreibe ich den Rest des
        Briefes. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003109">Hitler</tei:rs>s Erfolge sind wundervoll.
        Aber die unteren Organe <tei:supplied reason="omission">sind</tei:supplied> nicht immer den
        Situationen gewachsen. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich lese mit Begeisterung: Theodor Birt: <tei:title>von Homer bis Sokrates, ein Buch
          über die alten Griechen</tei:title>, das ich gleich nochmals lesen werde. Eine
        ausgezeichnete Darstellung<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">.</tei:supplied> Verlag Quelle
        u. Meyer, Leipzig 1921.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot"
              ><tei:bibl><tei:author>Theo Birt</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Von Homer bis
              Sokrates: ein Buch über die alten Griechen</tei:title> (Leipzig: Quelle und Meyer,
            1921)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> – </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Alles Gute und die herzlichsten Grüsse </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Ihnen beiden von uns allen!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr treuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/>Leipzig, <tei:date when="1933-07-06">July 6,
              1933</tei:date>. Könneritzstrasse 58<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
            >III</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor
            Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Heartfelt thanks for your kind letter,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/>
        to which I am replying immediately. The examinations are over, and I have more time,
        especially as I am also taking a leave of absence from the Party. My struggle against
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000866">Straube</tei:rs> has, in particular, spilt very
        bad blood, and a period of calm should now intervene. The gentleman has indeed everywhere
        spun his threads of circular disorder, like a spider. But he will end up entangling himself
        in his own web. After the holidays, the struggle will continue. For in the end, I am
        standing against <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000695">Reger</tei:rs> and his clan and
        for your idea. – The pictures are of course intended for you; we have duplicates. – My young
        pupil <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000299">Goos</tei:rs> has written a few lines for
        you, which will surely delight you. He even wanted originally to speak about your work on
        the radio, but that was turned down.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I have gained a few people in support <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of
          you</tei:supplied>. But given the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000712"
          >Riemann</tei:rs> plague and the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000695">Reger</tei:rs>
        inbreeding, I am not having an easy time of it. – I am delighted that you have found <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-006028">Reigersberg</tei:rs> to your liking in every respect. I
        hope that the sun down there is more reliable during your actual holiday assignment.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Unfortunately, the youth have been given somewhat too much room for maneuvering; I am
        very much fearful that, with an early political upbringing, only mediocrity and a rather
        juvenile precociousness will come of it and the real spiritual values will fall
        behind</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> I have not yet seen any of the new (“tendency”) plays or films. I am
        still waiting, out of a feeling that I will not get my money’s worth.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> All the parties have now disappeared, even the
        Centre. Thank God! This squinting beyond the mountains has never done us any good. <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002643">London</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002590">Geneva</tei:rs> are two completely identical failures.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> Work, and the old Prussian frugality, must help us
        now. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>It is still unclear when I shall begin my holiday; at the moment I have no money, and I
        do not want to run up debts. I have in fact been invited back to the Hunsrück, and to the
        Rhine. But at the moment I cannot think at all about <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear"
          >supplementary</tei:unclear> earnings, and the pay would be slender; all the while, the
        expenses for <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008523">Bepo</tei:rs> and <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-008524">Brigitte</tei:rs> are gradually increasing.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:date when="1933-07-10">July 10, 1933</tei:date>. After three splendid summer’s
        days with almost tropical heat, which were filled in part by long walks with <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-008523">Bepo</tei:rs>, I am writing the rest of this letter.
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003109">Hitler</tei:rs>’s successes are wonderful. But
        the lower authorities are not always equal to their situations.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I’m reading with inspiration Theodor Birt’s <tei:title level="m">From Homer to
        Socrates: a Book about the Ancient Greeks</tei:title>, which I shall reread immediately.
        An outstanding account. Published by Quelle and Meyer, Leipzig, 1921.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">All good wishes, and the most cordial greetings</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">to the two of you from all of us!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
