<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3760" sdoID="OJ-13-10_87">OJ 13/10, [87]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2025</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated September 18, 1929</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1929-09-18T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-08-24</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel thanks the Schenkers for their kind words [about his waltzes for
        Jeanette]. -- He says, in relation to a professorship in Heidelberg, that Schenker is doing
        the right thing by staying away from university circles. . – He asks Schenker to exhort
        Furtwängler over performing Oppel’s Mass. – He has not yet received the photograms of
        Brahms’s Oktaven u. Quinten.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:placeName>Leipzig</tei:placeName>, <tei:date
              when="1929-09-18">18. 9. 29</tei:date>. Landeskonservatorium, Grassistr
            8.</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Professor Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
            >Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for September 19, 1929: “Von
            Oppel (Br.): freut sich unseres Dankes. Orchester-Variationen seien begonnen. Er würde
            es gern sehen, wenn ich Furtwängler erinnerte” (“From Oppel (letter): he is delighted by
            our gratitude; his variations for orchestra have been begun; he would be pleased if I
            could send Furtwängler a reminder.”). — Paragraph-breaks are editorial, guided by
            emdashes in the original text.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>haben Sie beide herzlichen Dank für Ihre liebe Zeilen vom <tei:date when="1929-09-08"
          >8. IX</tei:date>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">In the first
          of two letters to Oppel, written on September 8, the Schenkers thanked Oppel for the
          waltzes he wrote for Jeanette. In the second of these, written the following day, Heinrich
          urged Oppel to be discreet when speaking to Anthony van Hoboken about Otto Vrieslander, as
          the two men have fallen out over personal matters.</tei:note> Gern hätte ich gleich
        geantwortet, aber die Aufnahmeprüfungen und Neueinteilung der Stunden hier kosten immer eine
        lästige Menge Zeit. Ich habe jetzt Montags 9, Dienstags 12, Mittwochs 5 u. Donnerstags 3
        Stunden zu geben. Das reicht. Die Notwendigkeit, Geld verdienen zu müssen in dem Maasse,
        hindert mich auch stark bei meinen compos. Arbeiten. Die Var. für Orchester <tei:hi
          rend="underline">sind</tei:hi> angefangen, ruhen aber, wie so vieles andre, unvollendet u.
        unberührt auf meinem Flügel, denn jetzt komme ich bei der Fahrerei zwischen <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002757">Kiel</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002479"
          >Leipzig</tei:rs> doch zu keiner konzentrierten Arbeit. Aber gelegentlich schicke ich
        Ihnen doch ein paar Kostproben. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005147">Curtius</tei:rs> u. die <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-005353">Heidelberg</tei:rs>er Ordinariatsfrage!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker’s diary for August 15, 1929 records: “In the
          entrance hall [in Galtür], Prof. Curtius speaks to us, saying that, at the time, on the
          strength of Furtwängler's recommendation, he recommended me for the professorship at
          Heidelberg; but the adviser in the Ministry could not agree to this, since he had grounds
          for disregarding an Austrian candidate.” Furtwängler’s letter to Schenker, <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-11-16_7">OJ 11/16, [7]</tei:ref>, August 30, 1929,
          comments on this situation; and more is explained in Schenker’s letter to Hoboken,
            <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-89-3_10">OJ 89/3, [10]</tei:ref>, the same day
          as the present letter, concluding: “It is very, very nice that they considered me in
          Leipzig and Heidelberg ‒ since I have not come up from the ranks preparing myself for a
          university professorship ‒ but more correctly: a university and I do not belong
          together.”</tei:note> Ja, Sie sind viel zu gut für diese letzten Endes doch kleinlichen,
        engherzigen u. nur zu sehr an <tei:del rend="overstrike">die</tei:del> ihre eigne, allein
        seligmachende Kraft glaubenden Universitätskreise; es ist wirklich schon besser, Sie bleiben
        unabhängig <tei:pb n="2"/> in jedem Sinne u. in jeder Richtung, wenn auch das Dasein
        äusserlich nicht mit den pecuniären Äquivalenten abläuft, die die Nation eigentlich Ihrer
        Kraft schuldet. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs>? Ja es stimmt schon,
        dass er vor 2 Jahren die Messe hören wollte von mir, aber dann ging er auf Reisen, u. es
        blieb bei seinem guten Vorsatz u. ich habe nie wieder etwas von ihm gehört. Aber vielleicht
        stossen Sie ihn doch noch einmal darauf: vielleicht kann er die Messe in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs> mit einem Chor bringen. – <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000320">Prof. Haas</tei:rs> hat mir die Photogr von Brahms op
        117 geschickt, dagegen nicht die <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-003331"><tei:title>Q- u.
            Octaven</tei:title></tei:rs>, ich habe daher ihn heute noch einmal darum gebeten. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>An <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">v. Hoboken</tei:rs> habe ich vorhin auch
        geschrieben, dass mich sein Besuch sehr freuen würde. Selbstverständlich bekommt er von mir
        über <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vr.</tei:rs> nichts zu hören, ausser Ihrer
        Weisung gemäss. Ich werde ihn schon mit der äussersten Diplomatie anfassen. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wir haben hier noch immer das herrlichste Wetter, u. die tägliche Fronarbeit schmeckt
        noch gar nicht. Morgen fahre ich nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002757">Kiel</tei:rs>
        u. freue mich auf meine <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-0004801">Jungen</tei:rs>, vorige
        Woche blieb ich nämlich hier, um zu sparen, – die Universität beginnt erst wieder am
          <tei:date when="1929-11-01">1. November</tei:date>. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Alles Gute u. die </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>herzlichsten Grüsse Ihnen beiden!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr treuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">sideways in left margin:</tei:note> An die
            <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">Universaledition</tei:rs> schreibe ich
          gleichzeitig wegen des <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724">I.
            Band</tei:rs>es.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">In a
            previous exchange, Oppel was surprised to hear that Schenker’s <tei:title level="m"
              >Harmonielehre</tei:title> had been out of print and not yet reissued.</tei:note>
        </tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:placeName>Leipzig</tei:placeName>, <tei:date
              when="1929-09-18">September 18, 1929</tei:date>. State Conservatory, Grassistraße
            8</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor
            Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>To both of you, my heartfelt thanks for your kind words of <tei:date when="1929-09-08"
          >September 8</tei:date>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> I would have
        liked to answer them immediately, but the admissions tests and the new distribution of the
        lessons here always cost a great deal of time. I now have nine lessons to give on Monday,
        twelve on Tuesday, five on Wednesday and three on Thursday. That is enough. The need to earn
        money in that measure also severely hinders my compositional work. The Variations for
        Orchestra <tei:hi rend="underline">have been</tei:hi> begun but remain incomplete and
        untouched on my piano, like so much else; for now I am unable to do any concentrated work
        when travelling between <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002757">Kiel</tei:rs> and <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002479">Leipzig</tei:rs>. But from time to time I shall still
        send you a few samples. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005147">Curtius</tei:rs> and the matter of the
        tenured professorship in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-005353"
          >Heidelberg</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> Yes, you are much
        too good for these university circles which, when all is said and done, are petty-minded and
        mean-spirited, believing in their own self-sanctifying power; it is really much better for
        you to remain independent <tei:pb n="2"/> in every respect and in every direction, even your
        existence is not in step outwardly with the pecuniary equivalences that the nation actually
        owes your powers. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs>? Yes, it is certainly
        correct that he wanted to hear my Mass two years ago; but then he went on tours and only his
        good intention remained, and I never heard anything from him further. But perhaps you can
        prod him: perhaps he can perform the Mass in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501"
          >Berlin</tei:rs> with a choir. – <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000320">Professor
          Haas</tei:rs> sent me the photograms of <tei:supplied reason="clarity">the autograph
          of</tei:supplied> Brahms’s Op. 117, but not the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-003331"
          >study of parallel fifths and octaves</tei:rs>; and so today I asked him once again for
        it. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>I have also written just now to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">v.
          Hoboken</tei:rs> to say that his visit would please me greatly. Of course he shall hear
        nothing about <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> from me, except
        in accordance with your instructions. I shall certainly deal with him with the utmost
        diplomacy. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>We are still enjoying the most splendid weather here, and the daily drudgery still
        doesn’t agree at all with me. Tomorrow I travel to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002757"
          >Kiel</tei:rs> and I look forward to being with my <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-0004801">sons</tei:rs>; last week I actually stayed here, to economize: the
        University does not begin until <tei:date when="1929-11-01">November 1</tei:date>.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>All good wishes, and the most </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>cordial greetings to the two of you!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">sideways in left margin:</tei:note> I shall
          write at the same time to <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408"
            >Universal Edition</tei:rs> about your <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724">volume
            I</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
