<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3381" sdoID="OJ-14-5_31">OJ 14/5, [31]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="MS" scope="major">Moriz Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="minor">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>


    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2023</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2023</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-21" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence">Schenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-004924">SchenkerM ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Moriz Schenker to Heinrich Schenker, dated March 5,
        1930</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1930-03-05T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-02-16</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Moriz Schenker again assures Heinrich that his money is safe and will be
        returned to him, but the collapse of the building society concerned and its transfer to the
        Vienna Creditanstalt is delaying the securing of a mortgage [on the Arzberg property]. --
        Moriz is launching, and will be the director of, a finance house for automobiles. -- He
        asserts that he is highly regarded [in the finance industry]. -- This letter is heavily
        annotated by Heinrich.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000774">Moriz Schenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
      
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#MS"/>Mittwoch Abend Baden <tei:date when="1930-03-05">5/3
            1930</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Meine Lieben!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
            place="foot">Receipt of this letter and Heinrich’s response are recorded in his diary
            for March 7, 1930: “Von Mozio (Br.): Blitz werde . . usw. –, er spricht nichts von
            Zinsen, auch nichts davon, was zu geschehen hat, wenn Blitz nicht eingreift. — An Mozio
            (Br. expreß Judenplatz 6): gleich die Zinsen schicken u. meine Fragen beantworten, das
            Gut hinhauen, wenn es anders nicht geht.” (“From Mozio (letter): Blitz will … etc.; he
            does not say anything about the interest; nor anything about what will happen if Blitz
            does not intercede. — To Mozio (express letter Judenplatz 6): Send the interest and
            answer my questions immediately; deal with the property if there is no alternative.”). —
            The diary for March 9 – the deadline for payment of the balance of the costs on the
              <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001752">third <tei:title level="j"
                >Meisterwerk</tei:title> yearbook</tei:rs> being due on March 15 – records: “An
            Mozio Telegramm: bis Dienstag Zinsen erlegen.” (“To Mozio, telegraph: Pay the interest
            by Tuesday.”), and for March 14 records: “Ich hole die ersten Zinsen: 397.40 S.” (“I
            collect the first interest payment, 397.40 shillings.”), for which payment is confirmed
            by the Creditanstalt the next day. — Moriz had canceled earlier in the day on March 5
            for a visit arranged a week previously, see <tei:ref type="correspondence"
              cRef="OJ-14-5_30">OJ 14/5, [30]</tei:ref>, February 27, 1930.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Leider war es mir wieder nicht möglich Euch heute zu besuchen. Ich hätte
        dies schon aus dem Grunde getan, um Euch in der leidigen Geldangelegenheit alle Aufklärungen
        und Beruhigung zu geben. Wie Dir bereits früher erzählt <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
          >wurde</tei:supplied>, habe ich Schritte unternommen, um eine Hypothek auf das Gut im
        Betrage von S. 80000.–<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">“Gut ...
          80.000” (“property ... 80,000”): underlined in crayon by Heinrich, who also writes in the
          top right corner “Zinsen” (“interest”).</tei:note> aufzunehmen. Wenn die
        Bodencredit-Anstalt nicht eingefallen wäre, hätte ich das Geld schon längst bekommen und
        selbstverständlich Dir den Rest samt 8½% Zinsen ausgezahlt. Dadurch, dass obige Bank nicht
        mehr existiert, und die Credit-Anstalt deren Geschäfte übernimmt, müssen die Privilegien für
        Hypothekargeschäfte (Emissionsrecht von Pfandbriefen) auf die <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-004959">Credit-Anstalt</tei:rs> übertragen werden. Diese Formalitäten
        erfordern eine gewisse Zeit trotz den <tei:pb n="2"/> eifrigsten Bemühungen der Bank, welche
        doch das Geschäft fortsetzen will. Der Direktor dieser Abteilung namens <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-005241">Blitz</tei:rs> hat mir versprochen, dass das <tei:hi
          rend="underline">erste Geschäft</tei:hi>, welches die neue Abteilung machen wird, die
        Hypothek für mich sein wird. Bitte, glaube mir doch, dass ich nicht einen Moment versäume,
        um meine Pflicht zu erfüllen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">The
          two paragraph-breaks in this letter are editorially introduced.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Dies umsomehr, als ich gerade jetzt genug andere Aufregungen mitmache, weil ich im
        Begriffe <tei:add place="interlinear-above">bin</tei:add> eine Finanzierungsgesellschaft für
        Kraftwagen in‘s Leben zu rufen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >“Finanzierungsgesellschaft … rufen” (“bringing … automobiles”): underlined in crayon by
          Heinrich.</tei:note> deren Leitung ich übernehmen soll </tei:p>

      <tei:p> Gott sei Dank genieße ich das Vertrauen der Leute, die mir bis heute von den hiezu
        erforderlichen S. 5000000.– den Betrag von S. 300,000.– subscribiert haben. Dabei schlafe
        ich keine Nacht wegen der Restzahlung an Dich, weil ich fühle, dass Ihr ungeduldig seid, und
        lieber auf eine höhere Verzinsung meinerseits verzichtet, um nur so rasch als
          möglich<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">“ich fühle … möglich”
          (“I feel ... possible”): underlined in crayon and double-sidelined in the left margin by
          Heinrich. In addition, Heinrich has written: “*)? Schülernot,– abgebrochen, andere
            <tei:unclear reason="reading">Lage</tei:unclear>” (*)? Need of pupils – broken off,
            <tei:unclear reason="meaning">another situation</tei:unclear>”) to the right of the
          passage, beneath the valediction and signature on p. 3.</tei:note>
        <tei:pb n="3"/> das Geld wiederzusehen. Eure Angst<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06"
          type="editorial" place="foot">“Angst” (“anxiety”): underlined in crayon by Heinrich; and
          above “ist” (“is”) Heinrich has written “?*)”.</tei:note> ist wirklich unberechtigt, weil
        ich Euch bestimmt werde bezahlen können. Anders stünde die Sache, wenn ich nichts besässe
        oder nicht den guten Willen hätte, meine Pflicht zu erfüllen. Der Mensch, welcher mir aber
        nachsagen kann, dass ich meine Pflicht nicht erfülle, hat nicht existiert und wird nicht
        existieren. Wenn <tei:del rend="overstrike">aber</tei:del> nicht so dreckige Zeiten wären,
        hätte ich es ja nicht einmal nötig auf eine Hypothek zu warten, aber kein Mensch hat
        flüssiges Geld. Also ich bitte Euch nochmals keine Angst zu haben und überzeugt zu sein, das
        Ihr Euer Geld mit Zinseszinsen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >“Ihr ... Zinseszinsen” (“you ... interest”): underlined in crayon by Heinrich.</tei:note>
        und Ordnung bekommen werdet in dem Momente, in welchen ich die Formalitäten
          durchmachen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot">“die Formalitäten
          durchmachen” (“get … formalities”): underlined in crayon by Heinrich.</tei:note>
        kann.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Herzliche Grüße und Küsse von</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Euerem</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774"
          >Moriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>



    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#MS"/>Wednesday evening, Baden, <tei:date
            when="1930-03-05">March 5, 1930</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">My dears,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"
          /></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Unfortunately it was again not possible for me to call on you today. I
        would have done so in order, in the midst of wretched financial matter, to give you full
        explanations and reassurance. As has already been recounted to you, I have taken steps to
        take out a mortgage on the property in the amount of 80,000 shillings.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> If the Boden Creditanstalt had not collapsed, I
        would long ago have received the money and naturally paid you the balance with 8½% interest.
        By virtue of the bank no longer existing, and the <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-004959">Creditanstalt</tei:rs> taking over its business, the privileges for
        mortgage business (emissions law of mortgage bonds) were conferred. These formalities
        necessitate a certain time despite the <tei:pb n="2"/> most assiduous efforts of the bank,
        which will certainly carry on the business. The director of the division, by the name of
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005241">Blitz</tei:rs>, has promised me that the <tei:hi
          rend="underline">first piece of business</tei:hi> that the new division will conduct with
        be the mortgage for me. Please believe me that I shall not fail for one single moment to
        fulfil my obligation.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>This, moreover, <tei:supplied reason="syntax">comes</tei:supplied> when I am right now
        participating in other commotions, because I <tei:add place="interlinear-above">am</tei:add>
        in the process of bringing into existence a finance house for automobiles,<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> the directorship of which I am to take on. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Thank God, I enjoy the trust of the people who have up to today subscribed 300,000
        shillings of the 5,000,000 shillings required for this. What’s more, I don’t sleep at night
        on account of the payment balance to you, because I feel you are impatient and prefer to
        forgo a higher interest rate on my part merely in order as soon as possible<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/>
        <tei:pb n="3"/> to see your money. Your anxiety<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06"
          type="footnote"/> is really unwarranted because I will definitely be able to pay you.
        Matters would be different if I possessed no means, or did not have the goodwill, to fulfil
        my obligation. The person who can speak ill of me, saying that I will not fulfil my
        obligation, has not existed and will not exist. If these were not such squalid times, I
        would not for a moment have needed to resort to a mortgage, but nobody has liquid money. So
        I implore you yet again to have no fear, and to be convinced that you will get your money
        with compound interest<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn7" type="footnote"/> and orderliness the
        moment I can get through the formalities.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"
        /></tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Cordial greetings and kisses from</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774"
          >Moriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
