<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="418" sdoID="OJ-14-45_12">OJ 14/45, [12]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="MV" scope="sole">Moriz Violin's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>


  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2011</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-06-02" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002719">ViolinM ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM+V ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002718">ViolinM+V+F ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>




   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Moriz Violin to Schenker, dated October 30, 1921 </dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1921-10-30T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2011-06-02</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Violin reports on his work, and on musicians in Hamburg, and congratulates
    Schenker on his (publication) successes.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Wohnung; apartment; Existenz; existence; hurly-burly; Schule; school; Schülerinnen;
    pupils; Fundament; foundation; Zukunft; future; Privatschüler; private pupils; Arbeit; work;
    Valuta; currency; Steigerung; increase; Erfolg; success; Entdeckung; discovery; Besprechung;
    review; Honorar; honorarium; Aussprache; accent</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-30"><tei:placeName>Hamburg</tei:placeName>, <tei:date when="1921-10-30">30 Okt. 1921.</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Liebster, bester <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in
      Schenker's diary at OJ 3/3, p. 2398, November 2, 1921: "Von Fl. (Br.): über seine Schülerzahl
      u. anderes." ("From Floriz (letter): about the number of his pupils and other [matters].").
     </tei:note>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Deinen so schön berichtenden Brief<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The only letter from Schenker to Violin recorded in the diary
     prior to October 30 appears at OJ 3/3, p. 2395: "An Fl. (Br.): über den Verlauf der letzten
     Monate u. Arbeit." ("To Floriz (letter): about the course [of developments] in recent months
     and work."). </tei:note> kann ich leider erst heute mit Ruhe beantworten. Nicht daß <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ich</tei:add> sie jetzt schon gefunden hätte; nur ein Atempauschen im
    Wohnungs u. Existenzrummel! Hoffentlich kann ich diesen Winter bis nächsten Herbst aushalten,
    dann wird alles gut werden. Ich habe in der Schule bereits zehn Schülerinnen. Das trägt zwar
    nicht viel, aber ist ein gutes Fundament für die Zukunft. Günstig ist es auch, daß mein erster
    Privatschüler, den<tei:add place="interlinear-above">en</tei:add> ich gestern definitiv bekam,
    ein 13jähriger Knabe ist (er komponiert u. spielt von „allein“), bei dem <tei:choice>
     <tei:sic>einen</tei:sic>
     <tei:corr>ein</tei:corr>
    </tei:choice> Lehrerfolg auch Zinsen tragen kann. Mäcene zahlen für ihn. 2 mal wöchentlich 50 M.
    pro Stunde. Im November u. Jänner spiele ich in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002589">Hamburg</tei:rs>. <tei:unclear reason="reading">S<tei:supplied reason="spelling">o</tei:supplied>iree</tei:unclear> Engagements. Nicht sehr gut bezahlt, aber günstig für
    meine Pläne. Du siehst: meine Arbeit ist ganz dem zeitigen Leben gewidmet, also höchst
    uninteressant für Dich in künstlerischer Hinsicht. Ich habe heute einmal Pflichten, da giebt es
    eben nichts; vielleicht erringe ich mir nach, nur für mich wenigstens, ein Stückchen Kunstglüte
    auf Erden. Denn Geld allein – – – – – – – u. s. w. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Das Steigen Deiner Lebens-Börse<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Violin presumably means the teaching and royalty income, on which Schenker
     depends. </tei:note> habe ich aufmerksam überprüft. Ich wüsste nichts, was du hättest anders
    machen können u. sollen, bis auf den einen tschecho-slovakischen Fall. Das war kaufmännisch
    nicht richtig durchdacht, denn die Valuta, die dich eben nötigen deine Wiener Schüler zu
    erhöhen, besorgt dies ja automatich beim tsch. slov. Fall. Wenn du gar nicht gesteigert hättest,
    würden 100 tsch. Kr. ein Vielfaches deiner jetzigen Steigerung bedeuten. Geschehen ist
    geschehen. Ein trauriger Wahrspruch! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/>
    <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs> war in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002589">Hamburg</tei:rs>. Natürlich großer Erfolg. Er sprach wieder viel über die –
    – <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>: Wenn er auch Deine „Entdeckung“ zugiebt (sein Wort!), so
    vermuthe ich es <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike"><tei:gap reason="illegible"/>noch</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">dennoch</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> daß er die Meinung hat, es wäre die „<tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>“ in seiner
    Begabung mit ihm schon auf die Welt geraten. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich habe <tei:hi rend="underline">gar</tei:hi> keine Besprechung über dich zu
    Gesicht bekommen. Ich komme heuer sicher nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Wien</tei:rs> spielen, da freue ich mich schon Dir alle <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002849">Spengler</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000619">Müller-Hartmann</tei:rs>gespräche etc. etc. in einheitlicher Weise erzählen zu können. Was ich
    dir mit einigen Worten erzählen werden, geht brieflich nicht auf 20 Seiten. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Von Deiner <tei:rs key="entity-001753" type="work"><tei:title>Beethoven-Ausgabe</tei:title></tei:rs> besitze ich nur die großen Bearbeitungen
     <tei:rs key="entity-001737" type="work"><tei:title>op. 101</tei:title></tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-001734" type="work"><tei:title>109</tei:title></tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-001735" type="work"><tei:title>110</tei:title></tei:rs> u. <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title>111</tei:title></tei:rs>. — Wann sind die übrigen
    erschienen? Tausend Dank, daß ich sie bekommen werde! Bei <tei:rs key="entity-001738" type="work"><tei:title>op. 106</tei:title></tei:rs> würde ich dir folgenden Zahlenschlüssel
     empfehlen<tei:supplied reason="syntax">.</tei:supplied> Z. B.: für <tei:rs key="entity-001737" type="work"><tei:title>op. 101</tei:title></tei:rs> machte das Honorar nach Seiten berechnet x
    aus. Jetzt berechne das Plus der Seitenzahl bei <tei:rs key="entity-001738" type="work"><tei:title>106</tei:title></tei:rs>. Damit bekommst du dasselbe Honorar wie bei <tei:rs key="entity-001737" type="work"><tei:title>101</tei:title></tei:rs> heraus. Dann berechne die
    Geltentwertung, etwa als Maßstab Deine Stundensteigerungen. Deine Forderung müßte also
    beispielsweise lauten: Für 100 Seiten bei <tei:rs key="entity-001737" type="work"><tei:title>op.
      101</tei:title></tei:rs> bekam ich 1000 Kr. Für 200 Seiten bei <tei:rs key="entity-001738" type="work"><tei:title>op. 106</tei:title></tei:rs> demnach 2000 Kr. Das Honorar ist aber für
    mich entwertet u. ich bekomme daher, ebenso wie ich von meinen Schülern inzwischen das Doppelte
    bekomme, 4000 K. Verstehst Du mich? Hoffentlich? </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000912">Bubi</tei:rs> geht hier zur Schule,
    gilt als begabt, aber noch nicht reif genug für die „nordische Gunst“. Er kommt <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">continued in left margin, written sideways, including
     valediction and signature:</tei:note> aber gut mit u. hat leider von nordischen am meisten bei
    seiner Aussprache profitiert. Er spricht <tei:sic>eckelhaft</tei:sic> „<tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002589">hamburg</tei:rs>’sch“. In 14 Tagen sind wir in unsere Wohnung u. ich in
    meiner Ordnung! Lasse gütigst bald etwas hören! Wir sind alle gesund u. grüßen viel tausend mal
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Tante Lie-Lie</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Onkel Heinrich</tei:rs>! </tei:p>

   <tei:closer><tei:salute rend="indent-40">Dein treuer</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>


  </tei:div>

  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-30"><tei:placeName>Hamburg,</tei:placeName>, <tei:date when="1921-10-30">October 30, 1921</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Dearest, best <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Alas, only today can I get down in peace and quiet to answering your
    wonderfully informative letter.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> Not that
     <tei:supplied reason="clafrity">I</tei:supplied> have really found any <tei:supplied reason="clarity">peace and quiet</tei:supplied> now: merely a short pause for breath in the
    hurly-burly of apartment and existence! I hope I can survive this winter and through to next
    Fall; <tei:supplied reason="clarity">if so,</tei:supplied> then all will be well. At school, I
    already have ten pupils (all female). Admittedly, that does not amount to much, but it is a good
    basis for the future. It is also auspicious that my first private pupil, whom I acquired for
    sure yesterday, is a thirteen-year-old boy (he composes and plays "on his own"), and if I make a
    success of teaching him, this could pay dividends. Patrons pay for him: two lessons a week at 50
    Marks a lesson. In November and January I will be playing in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002589">Hamburg</tei:rs>: <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">soirée</tei:unclear> engagements. Not very well paid, but providential for my plans. As you
    can see, my work is entirely dedicated to material living, and thus extremely uninteresting for
    you from the artistic point of view. These days, I have obligations; before, I didn't have any;
    maybe I will achieve, just for myself, a little piece of artistic glory on earth. After all,
    money alone – – – etc. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I have carefully checked the increase in value of your life
     securities.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> I cannot think of anything you
    might or should have done differently, with the exception of the one Czechoslovak case. That was
    not properly considered from a commercial point of view; for the exchange rate, which recently
    compelled you to <tei:supplied reason="clarity">raise the lesson fees of</tei:supplied> your
    Viennese pupils, would have taken care of this automatically in the Czechoslovak case. If, in
    fact, you had not raised <tei:supplied reason="clarity">those fees</tei:supplied> at all, 100
    Czech Kronen would have represented many times your current increase. What is done is done: a
    sad verdict! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/>
    <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs> was in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002589">Hamburg</tei:rs>. A great success, needless to say. He again spoke much of
    the – – <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>: even though he conceded that it was your "discovery" (his
    word!), I sense nevertheless that he believes that the "<tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>" had
    already come into the world with him, as part of his giftedness. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I have seen no sign <tei:hi rend="underline">whatsoever</tei:hi> of any
    review of your work. I am coming to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Vienna</tei:rs> for
    sure this year to play, and am already looking forward to being able to recount to you in great
    detail all my conversations with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs>,
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002849">Spengler</tei:rs>, and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000619">Müller-Hartmann</tei:rs>, etc., etc. What I will tell you in a few words
    would not fit into a twenty-page letter. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Of your <tei:rs key="entity-001753" type="work"><tei:title>Beethoven
      edition</tei:title></tei:rs>, I possess only your large-scale treatments of Opp. <tei:rs key="entity-001737" type="work"><tei:title>101</tei:title></tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-001734" type="work"><tei:title>109</tei:title></tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-001735" type="work"><tei:title>110</tei:title></tei:rs>, and <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title>111</tei:title></tei:rs>. — When did the others
    appear? A thousand thanks that I will be receiving them! For Op. <tei:rs key="entity-001738" type="work"><tei:title>106</tei:title></tei:rs>, I would recommend to you the following
    formula. Suppose, for example, that the honorarium for <tei:rs key="entity-001737" type="work"><tei:title>Op. 101</tei:title></tei:rs> amounted to x, calculated by the page. Now calculate
    the increase in page-count for <tei:rs key="entity-001738" type="work"><tei:title>106</tei:title></tei:rs>. From that you derive the same honorarium as for <tei:rs key="entity-001737" type="work"><tei:title>101</tei:title></tei:rs>. Then calculate the
    monetary depreciation, perhaps using your increases in lesson fees as a measure. What you demand
    ought thus, for example, to go as follows: for 100 pages of <tei:rs key="entity-001737" type="work"><tei:title>Op. 101</tei:title></tei:rs> I got 1,000 Kronen; for 200 pages of
     <tei:rs key="entity-001738" type="work"><tei:title>Op. 106</tei:title></tei:rs> in the same
    terms 2,000 Kronen. The honorarium has however for me become devalued and I <tei:supplied reason="clarity">shall</tei:supplied> therefore get, just as I have been getting double the
    amount from my pupils in the meantime, 4,000 Kronen. Does that make any sense? I hope so! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">My <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000912">little boy</tei:rs> is going to
    school here. He is considered gifted, though not mature enough yet for the "Nordic taste."
     <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">continued in left margin, written sideways, including
     valediction and signature:</tei:note> However, he is coming along nicely, and unfortunately his
    accent has for the most part profited from the Nordic one. He speaks an ugly <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002589">Hamburg</tei:rs> dialect. In two weeks' time, we will be in
    our apartment and I will be in good form! Do let us have news of you soon! We are all in good
    health and send many thousandfold greetings to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Auntie
     Lie-Lie</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Uncle Heinrich</tei:rs>! </tei:p>

   <tei:closer><tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your faithful</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>