<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="2277" sdoID="OJ-15-16_3">OJ 15/16, [3]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HW" scope="sole">Hans Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB-WD">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent and William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2007</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2007</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-06-25" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated January 13, 1912</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1912-01-13T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-10-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Weisse thanks Schenker for having taught him to make fine adjustments in his
    compositions, and for imbuing him with greater clarity; he marvels at the subtlety of Schenker's
    musical sensibility, and speaks of his joy at being Schenker's pupil.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Kleingkeit; trifle; Dank; thanks; Neuigkeit; new thing; Feilen; adjustment; Klarheit;
    clarity; Schüler; pupil; Feinheit; subtlety; Empfindung; sensibility; Lobe; praise; Lieder;
    songs</dc:subject>



   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000951">Weisse</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Verehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>!<tei:note
      xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is not recorded in
      Schenker's diary.</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>


   <tei:p>Nun Sie sich mit meinen Kleinigkeiten<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
     place="foot">Evidently Weisse had sent (or perhaps handed over at his previous lesson, January
     10) to Schenker some recent compositions. <tei:hi rend="italic">Kleinigkeiten</tei:hi> are
     short pieces ("bagatelles"), usually for solo piano; but in the course of the letter Weisse
     uses the term, disparagingly, to mean music of short duration, which lacks the depth of vision
     needed to write in the larger forms. Some or all of these pieces were performed on February 22,
     1912: diary: "Violin’s Konzert: schöner Erfolg des Trio u. der Klavierstücke Weisse’s; die
     Lieder des letzteren litten unter den Mangel an Proben ..." ("Violin's concert: a nice success
     of the trio, and of Weisse's piano pieces; the latter's songs suffered from lack of rehearsal
     ...") (diary, p. 200, February 22, 1912).</tei:note> so viel Mühe gaben, und ihnen Ihren ganzen
    Feuereifer zugute kommen liessen, fühle ich mich genötigt, Ihnen aus tiefster Seele Dank zu
    sagen für all Ihre Plage und Mühe! Und auch für jene Neuigkeiten, die ich dabei zu hören bekam,
    die mir unsre Kunst von einer ganz andren Seite her erschlossen; ich habe vielleicht genau so
    stark wie Sie den Reiz des Feilens verspürt, die Freude an der Entdeckung kleiner und grosser
    Mangel und die Beseelung durch die <tei:term>Artikulierung</tei:term>! Wie ich besonders früher
    das Wesen der <tei:term>Bögen</tei:term> unterschätzt habe, <tei:del rend="overstrike"
     >die</tei:del> ihrer <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">ferne</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">weithin</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> reichenden Wirkung, und <tei:term>motivisch</tei:term>er Wichtigkeit <tei:pb n="2"
    /> nicht achtend! Nun ist’s mir auf einmal klar geworden, dass ich meinen eigenen
     <tei:term>Themengebilden</tei:term> eigentlich doch immerhin mehr oder minder fremd war, ja sie
    sogar wie es meine <tei:term>Bogenführung</tei:term> ja bewies trotzdem sie mir nahestanden,
    verkannte! Die richtige Erkenntnis und Wertung der <tei:term>Artikulierung</tei:term> nun hat
    mich in einen wahren Freudestaumel versetzt; freilich, wenn dies allein noch lange nicht genügt,
    so habe ich doch die Empfindung<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> dass jetzt
    zwischen mir und dem was ich schreibe mehr Klarheit herrschen wird. Naturgemäss knüpft sich an
    die Freude die Frage, woher mir Aufklärung über dieses <tei:term>Thema</tei:term> kam?</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Und da muss ich Ihnen, liebster Meister<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied>
    danken, ohne den ich früher ganz verkehrte und sinnlose Wege gegangen wäre. Aber ich bin mir des
    Glückes, Ihr Schüler zu sein, <tei:hi rend="underline">vollständig bewusst</tei:hi>, und so
     <tei:pb n="3"/> doch nicht mehr ganz wertlos! Je mehr ich über die Feinheit Ihrer musikalischen
     Empfindung<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> über die Klarheit Ihres alles
    durchdringenden kritischen Auges staune, umso mehr fühle ich, dass ich in der Erreichung meines
    mir gesetzten Zieles nämlich alles mit solcher vornehmen Ruhe und Tiefe zu durchprüfen wie Sie,
    die höchste Befriedigung erreichen werde! Aber diese Ungeduld, liebster Meister<tei:supplied
     reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> diese jugendliche Ungeduld, die mich jeden Augenblick vor
    fremden Schweren entmutigt!! Ganz konnte ich die Freude Ihres Lobes nicht auskosten, weil ich,
    wie von einem fixen Gedanken beherrscht, mir immer einbildete, dass mir nunmehr nichts mehr
    gelingen werde, und dass ich bei einem armseligen op. 2. stehen bleiben müsse und werde!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Vielleicht <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">ist</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">trägt</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> die Ungleichheit meines <tei:pb n="4"/> Wollens und Könnens Schuld an solchem
     Versagen<tei:del rend="overstrike">s</tei:del>! Aber wenn sich meine kühnen Gedanken auf die
    Höhe von Trios, Quartetten und <tei:sic>Symphonieen</tei:sic>, schwingen, so habe ich das
    Gefühl: Diese Trauben werden <tei:add place="interlinear-above">mir</tei:add>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">immer</tei:hi> zu hoch häufen! Als ob ich dieser Höhenluft nicht
    gewachsen, in die dumpfe Atmosphäre von allerhand Kleinigkeiten wieder hinab müsste! Wieder
    Lieder und wieder Kleinigkeiten! Offen gestanden! Sie wachsen mir schon <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">beim</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">zum</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> Hals heraus!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Um ein tröstendes Wort will Sie also Ihr Schüler bitten, der sich einbildet<tei:supplied
     reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> alles was Ihnen nahegeht und steht mit dem gleichen
    Interesse und der gleichen Liebe des Freundes zu betrachten und zu fühlen!</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
     >Hans</tei:rs>.</tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:date when="1912-01-13">13. Jänner, 1912</tei:date>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
      corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>


   <tei:p>As you have taken so much trouble over my trifles,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
     type="footnote"/> and brought the fullness of your fiery zeal to bear upon them, I feel obliged
    to thank you from the bottom of my heart for all your trouble and toil! And also for those new
    things that I gathered along the way, which showed me our art in an entirely new light; perhaps
    I have felt, just as keenly as you, the excitement of making fine adjustments <tei:supplied
     reason="clarity">to my work</tei:supplied>, the joy in discovering shortcomings small and
    large, and the spiritedness that comes from marking the <tei:term>articulation</tei:term>! How,
    in particular, I undervalued the meaning of the <tei:term>slur</tei:term>s at an earlier time,
    failing to attend to their far-reaching effect and <tei:term>motivic</tei:term> importance!
     <tei:pb n="2"/> Now it has suddenly become clear to me that I was always more or less a
    stranger to my very own <tei:term>thematic construction</tei:term>s, indeed that I even did not
    recognize them, as my placement of <tei:term>slur</tei:term>s actually proved! The correct
    understanding and appreciation of <tei:term>articulation</tei:term> has now transported me into
    a true frenzy of joy; of course, even if this alone is far from satisfactory, I nonetheless have
    the feeling that greater clarity will prevail between myself and what I write. Naturally, with
    my joy comes the question: From whence came my enlightenment about this theme?</tei:p>

   <tei:p>And there I must thank you, dear master, without whom I would certainly have taken
    entirely wrong and meaningless paths. But I am <tei:hi rend="underline">completely
     conscious</tei:hi> of the joy of being your pupil, and thus <tei:pb n="3"/> indeed no longer
    entirely worthless! The more I marvel at the subtlety of your musical sensibility, at the
    clarity of your all-penetrating, critical eye, the more I feel that, in attaining the goal I
    have set myself, namely, the ability to check through everything with such admirable tranquility
    and profundity as you have, I shall achieve the greatest satisfaction. But this impatience,
    dearest master, this youthful impatience, which at every turn discourages me in the face of
    unknown difficulties!! I could not savor the joy of your praise to the full, because I always
    imagine, as if ruled by an <tei:hi rend="italic">idée fixe</tei:hi>, that now I shall no longer
    be successful at anything, and that I must and shall remain stuck at the level of a wretched
    opus 2!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Perhaps the inequality between <tei:pb n="4"/> what I want to do and what I am able to do
    is to be blamed on such a failing! But if my keen ideas soar to the level of trios, quartets and
    symphonies, I have the feeling: these grapes will <tei:hi rend="underline">always</tei:hi> pile
    up beyond <tei:add place="interlinear-above">my</tei:add> reach! As if I have not grown
    sufficiently to breathe this rarified air, and must sink once more into the gloomy atmosphere of
    all sorts of trivial things! More songs, and more trivial pieces. I admit it: they are already
    growing around my neck!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Thus your pupil begs for a word of comfort from you; he imagines himself contemplating and
    feeling everything that is dear to you with the same interest, the same friendly love.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
     >Hans</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:date when="1912-01-13">January 13, 1912</tei:date>
   </tei:closer>


  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
