<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3519" sdoID="OJ-14-6_1">OJ 14/6, [1]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="WS" scope="sole">Wilhelm Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="LR">
      <tei:persName>Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008423">SchenkerW ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Wilhelm to Heinrich Schenker, dated April 17,
        1930</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1930-04-17T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-10-08</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Wilhelm encloses a letter he has received from younger brother Moriz, in which
        the latter tries to explain his financial circumstances and prospects. Wilhelm has urged
        Moriz to return Heinrich’s money to him.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000775">Wilhelm Schenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>

    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">St. Bernhard bei Horn. Post: Horn</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">N.O. <tei:date when="1930-04-17">17/4
            1930</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>Mein lieber <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:supplied>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01"
            type="editorial" place="foot"> Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary
            for April 19, 1930: “Von Wilhelm (Br.): ein überlanger Brief von Mozio liegt bei, darin
            wimmelt es von unvernünftigem Zeug, namentlich nimmt sich der Gedanke wunderlich aus, M.
            halte krampfhaft das Gut fest, um mir für spätere Zeiten einen Platz zu sichern!!!”
            (“From Wilhelm (letter): an overly long letter from Mozio is enclosed; it is filled with
            irrational nonsense; in particular, the strange idea emerges that Mozio is desperately
            holding on to his property in order to secure a place for me at a later
            time!!!”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Auf meinen Brief an unseren Bruder <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774"
          >Moschki</tei:rs> erhalte ich heute seinen beiliegenden Brief resp. Antwort. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich habe ihm in Güte aufmerksam gemacht, dass Du lieber Heinrich das Geld benötigst –
        dass Du auch in den Jahren bist – wo <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">Dich</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">Dir</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> jede Aufregung schadet – und du auch nicht wie früher arbeitsfähig bist.
        Ausserdem hast Du auch dringend stets eine Erholung notwendig. Ich bat Ihn – Er möge die
        Geldangelegenheit ordnen. Ich glaube Ihm sehr gerne – dass jetzt so ein Gut nicht
        anzubringen ist. Seine Pläne – eine Sommerfrische dort zu errichten – ist mir unklar. Auf
        meine Anfrage aber – was Er jetzt macht – ob er arbeitslos sei – erhalte ich keine Antwort. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich erwarte nun von Dir jetzt eine Antwort u. z. was für Bedingungen Du für gut findest
        – nur zu Deinem Gelde zu kommen – damit ich in dieser Gelegenheit in beiderseitiger
        Zufriedenheit erledigen kann. Dass Du in Rechte bist – wenn Du Dein eigenes Geld verlangst –
        ist ja richtig. Auch muss ja vor Allem auch auf Deine liebe <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000771">Lili</tei:rs> Rücksicht genommen werden – damit Sie im<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">“damit ich … Sie im” (“so that I ...
          that in”): sidelined right by Heinrich.</tei:note>
        <tei:pb n="2"/> Notfalle nicht von Gnade und Ungnade abhängt </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Bei Antwort – lasse – aber die liebe <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
          >Lili</tei:rs> schreiben – da ich zu Deiner Schrift einige Tage benötige, um Alles zu
        entziffern – dass Du Dich dabei nicht aufregen sollst. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich hoffe Alles günstig zu erledigen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="indent-20">Sende mir daher Deine Idee – und beiliegenden Brief retour – damit
        Alles geschehen soll. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Stets</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Euer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775"
          >Wilhelm</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">St. Bernhard near Horn. Post: Horn</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Lower Austria, <tei:date when="1930-04-17">April 17,
              1930</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>My dear <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
            type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>In response to my letter to our brother <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774"
          >Moschki</tei:rs> I have today received his enclosed letter, i.e. answer.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In good will, I alerted him that you, dear Heinrich, need the money – that you are also
        in the years when every agitation is harmful to you – and that you are no longer capable of
        work as previously. Besides, you also urgently always need recuperation time. I requested
        that he put the money matter in order. I gladly believe him that such a property cannot be
        offered up right now. His plans – of building a summer retreat there – are unclear to me. In
        response to my query, however – what he is going to do now, whether he is out of work – I
        get no answer.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I am now waiting for an answer from you, namely what conditions you find acceptable –
        just to get at your money – so that I can wrap up this matter to mutual satisfaction. That
        you are within your rights – in demanding your own money – is certainly correct. Above all,
        your dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Lili</tei:rs> must also be considered –
        so that in<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> an <tei:pb n="2"/> emergency she
        is not dependent on mercy and lack thereof.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>For an answer, let <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Lili</tei:rs> write,
        because for your handwriting I need some days to decipher everything – so that you shouldn’t
        get agitated.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I hope to get everything favorably taken care of.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="indent-20">So, send me your idea – and the enclosed letter by return – so that
        everything can proceed.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">As always,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775"
          >Wilhelm</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
