<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="540" sdoID="OJ-14-45_20">OJ 14/45, [20]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="MV" scope="sole">Moriz Violin's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>


  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2011</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-09-05" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002719">ViolinM ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM+V ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002718">ViolinM+V+F ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>




   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Moriz Violin to Heinrich Schenker, dated February 6, 1923 </dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1923-02-06T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2011-09-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Violin thanks Schenker for Tonwille 3 and reports on growing social unrest and
    anti-French feeling in Germany. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>hardship; Abwehrkampf; defensive fight; finanziell; financial; Gabe; gift;
    Verläßlichkeit; feeble powers; Lebensmitteln; food; Stunden; lessons; Börsensorgen; worries;
    stocks; shares; Lehrauftrag; teaching post; lectureship</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-40">Hamburg, <tei:date when="1923-02-06">6. Februar
     23</tei:date>.</tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute>Mein liebster u. bester <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this
      letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/4, p. 2494, February 8, 1923: "Von Fl. (Br.):
      habe viele Stunden, muß aber auch Geschäfte machen." ("From Floriz (letter): he has many
      lessons, but must do business."). </tei:note>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Deine Gabe<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">A copy
     of <tei:title level="j">Tonwille</tei:title> 3; see OJ 8/4, [20]. </tei:note> kam vom Himmel in
    unserer schwersten Zeit. Denke daß wir uns (ich meine uns alle Unbegüterten in <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>, in <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Deutschland</tei:country></tei:rs>) auf die kommenden Zeiten des Abwehrkampfes,
    finanziell vorbereiten müssen. Mir ist es gut gelungen. Verstehst Du solch prosaischen Zustand,
    in dem man es nicht wagt die Würde vorzuschieben, die dazu gehört, Deine Gabe zu quittieren?
    Jetzt habe ich wenigstens recht u. schlecht den „<tei:rs key="entity-001742" type="work"><tei:title>Tonwille</tei:title> N<tei:hi rend="supralinear">o</tei:hi> 3</tei:rs>“
    durchgemacht. Ich schäme mich nur, meine Begeisterung auf's Papi<tei:supplied reason="spelling">e</tei:supplied>r zu bringen. Die Hauptsache: Es steht alles felsenlfest da; ärgern werden sie
    sich immer weil <tei:add place="interlinear-above">Du</tei:add> sagst: nur so u. nicht anders
    ist es! Wer nicht hören u. sehen lernt, dem wird nicht zu helfen sein! Deine Absicht mit dem
    folgenden Heft is so richtig u. meine schwachen Kräfte werden sich bemühen, sie vollstrecken zu
    helfen. Wenn Du mir gelegentlich, in bequemer, freier Minute einige Personalkenntnis verraten
    würdest, wäre ich sehr dankbar. Ich meine damit, Du mögest mir schreiben, was Du vom
    persönlichen künstlerischen Mut, von der Verläßlichkeit, dem Mitgehen mit einer Sache, bei einem
     <tei:rs key="entity-000326" type="person">Halm</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000149" type="person">Dahms</tei:rs>
    etc. etc. (hast Du mir nicht auch jemanden in <tei:rs key="entity-002757" type="place">Kiel</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Reinhard Oppel, who
     taught in Kiel from 1911 to 1924; he later obtained a post at the University of Leipzig.
    </tei:note> genannt) hältst?!?! Ich wäre Dir <tei:hi rend="underline">sehr</tei:hi> dankbar! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Oben deutele ich Dir <tei:hi rend="underline">unseren</tei:hi> Abwehrkampf
    an. Es ist nichts anderes als Vorsorge mit Lebensmitteln, Kleidern u. Heizmaterialen. Dazu waren
     100.000<tei:hi rend="supralinear">de</tei:hi> nötig. Ich habe enorm viel Stunden. (27–30
    Privatstunden in der Woche) spielte u. spiele gegen Honorar in <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> u. Umgebung. Habe Papiere gekauft. Kurz: Ich bin heute aus dem
    äußern Dreck. Dafür desto intensiver stecke ich im inneren Dreck! Täglich fünf Stunden, üben
    für's öffentlich Spielen, <tei:hi rend="underline">eigenste</tei:hi> Börsensorgen (ich mache
    alles allein) stets Sorge mit <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Bubi</tei:rs> – – –
    alles in allem das unkünstlerischeste <tei:sic>Vegitieren</tei:sic>. Wo bleibe ich? </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Aber auch das werde ich finden müssen, denn sonst lebe ich wirklich <tei:pb n="2"/> nur
    aus Pflichtgefühl! Ich habe nicht weniger als 3 Ideen angeschnitten. Ich schreibe sie Dir nicht.
    Sie werden ja wieder an den <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overwritten">t</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="superimposed">an</tei:add>
    </tei:subst>deren zerschellen. Gelingt eine, kann ich's Dir noch immer sagen. Dieser Tage wurde
    an der <tei:rs key="entity-003002" type="organization">Hamburger Universität</tei:rs>
    Musik-Lehrauftrag erteilt. Seinerzeit dachte ich an <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans Weisse</tei:rs>! <tei:rs key="entity-000619" type="person">Müller-Hartmann</tei:rs> hat
    ihn bekommen. Wenigstens der Einzige, der sich immerhin in <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> Musiker nennen darf. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Hier steht alles Kopf. Zwischen Kriegsbegehren u. Ohnmachtsgefühl schwankt
    die ganze deutsche Welt. Wenn man darin auch eine höhere Gerechtigkeit erblicken will – – –
    schrecklich ist es zu erleben! Jetzt finden die Zeitungen das Wort vom Franzosenpeltz, Gesindel,
    Einbrecher, Schänder u.s.w. Ob <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Deutschland</tei:country></tei:rs> zu Grunde geht oder nicht – – – – seinen
     Leidensweg<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">"Leidensweg": i. e. the
     path taken by Christ to the Cross. </tei:note> muss <tei:add place="interlinear-above">es</tei:add> abdienen. In seiner Verkommenheit ist es mir noch lieber als alles andere. Ich
    lebe gerne hier, weil ich den Segen dieser Strafe verspüre. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Bleibt recht gesund,</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">von Uns innigst begrüßt! </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Dein </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70">getreuer <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Fl.</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p><tei:rs key="entity-000798" type="person">Schönberg</tei:rs>s „epochale“
      <tei:title>Harmonielehre</tei:title>, als Reklame im <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title>Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>n geht über die Hutschnur.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:title level="j">Tonwille</tei:title> 3
      carries a full-page advertisement on the inside back page (opposite Schenker's Urlinie-Tafeln)
      for Schoenberg's <tei:title level="m">Harmonielehre</tei:title> (1911), now newly revised,
      which speaks of the first edition as having "been epoch-making ten years ago." This must
      surely have irked Schenker. </tei:note> Umgekehrt macht es Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> nicht? </tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>


  </tei:div>

  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-40">Hamburg, <tei:date when="1923-02-06">February 6,
     1923</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute>My dearest and best <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Your gift<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> came from heaven in
    our darkest hour. I think we (by which I mean all of us in <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>, in <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Germany</tei:country></tei:rs>, who are not affluent) have to prepare ourselves
    financially for the defensive fight that is to come. I have succeeded. Can you understand so
    prosaic a state of affairs as this, in which one does not dare to flaunt the dignity that comes
    with accepting your gift. I have at least somehow or another managed to get through <tei:rs key="entity-001742" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Tonwille</tei:title> 3</tei:rs>. Only I am
    ashamed to put my enthusiasm down on paper. The chief thing is: it is all out there, rock-like;
    they will all be annoyed because it is <tei:add place="interlinear-above">you</tei:add> who are
    saying it: that is how it is and always will be! Anyone who does not know how to hear and see
    cannot be helped! Your intentions for the next issue are so right, and my feeble powers will
    exert themselves to assist you. I should be very grateful if you could sometime find a quiet
    moment in which to divulge some personal information to me. What I mean by that is that you
    might write and tell me what you think of, say, <tei:rs key="entity-000326" type="person">Halm</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000149" type="person">Dahms</tei:rs>, etc, etc (did you not mention to me someone
    in <tei:rs key="entity-002757" type="place">Kiel</tei:rs>?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/>) in terms of personal artistic courage, of dependability, of readiness to
    stick with a cause?!?! I should be <tei:hi rend="underline">really</tei:hi> grateful! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In the above, I hint at <tei:hi rend="underline">our</tei:hi> defensive
    fight. It is nothing other than preoccupation with providing food, clothing, and fuel. I have
    had to pay several hundred thousand for that. I have to give a huge number of lessons (27–30
    private lessons a week), have been playing (still am) on a fee basis in <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> and the surrounding area. I have bought
    financial securities. In short: today I have freed myself from the outer mire. Instead, I am
    stuck all the deeper in the inner mire! Five lessons a day, practice for public performances,
    the <tei:hi rend="underline">most particular</tei:hi> worries over stocks and shares (I have to
    do it all on my own), constant worry with my darling <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">son</tei:rs> — all in all, the most inartistic vegetative existence. What will become of me? </tei:p>

   <tei:p>But then, I must find that out, since otherwise my life will be driven <tei:pb n="2"/>
    only by a sense of obligation! I have embarked on no fewer than three ideas. I will not write to
    you about them. They will be destroyed by my other <tei:supplied reason="clarity">work</tei:supplied>. I can always tell you if one of them succeeds. The other day a music
    teaching post at the <tei:rs key="entity-003002" type="organization">University of
     Hamburg</tei:rs> was filled. At the time, I had thought of <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans Weisse</tei:rs>! <tei:rs key="entity-000619" type="person">Müller-Hartmann</tei:rs> was appointed. He is, at least, the only person in <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> who can call himself a musician. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Here everything is topsy-turvy. The entire German world vacillates between a
    yearning for war and a feeling of powerlessness. Even if one wants to see in it a higher justice
    – it is dreadful to experience! Now the newspapers are speaking about French swindlers,
    riff-raff, thieves, violaters, and suchlike. Whether or not <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Germany</tei:country></tei:rs> will go to wrack and ruin — <tei:add place="interlinear-above">it</tei:add> must endure its long ordeal<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> Even in its depravity, it is, in my view, preferable to
    all else. I am glad to be living here, because I feel the blessing of this punishment. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Do keep healthy,</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">warmest greetings from us all, </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Your </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70">true <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Fl.</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p><tei:rs key="entity-000798" type="person">Schoenberg</tei:rs>'s "epoch-making" <tei:title level="m">Theory of Harmony</tei:title> advertised in <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>: that is going too far!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> On the other hand, how could Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> do otherwise!</tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>