<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="544" sdoID="OJ-14-45_24">OJ 14/45, [24]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="MV" scope="sole">Moriz Violin's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2011</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-09-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002719">ViolinM ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM+V ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002718">ViolinM+V+F ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Moriz Violin to Heinrich Schenker, dated July 14, 1923 </dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1923-07-14T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2011-09-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Violin has met an industrialist by the name of Max Temming who would be willing
    to help make Schenker’s work more widely accessible. Violin will probably not visit the
    Schenkers in Galtür this summer, as prices have gone up in Germany. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>edieren; publish; kontraktlich; contractual; Kontrakt; contract; Schädigung;
    detriment; harm; Kavalier; cavalier; Bedingungen; conditions; Kampf; struggle; fight;
    Musikenthusiast; music enthusiast; finanziell; financial; Vorteil; advantage; Sicherstellung;
    secure foundation; Universität; university; Hochschule; highschool; conservatory; Bibliothek;
    library; Abonnement; subscription; Honorar; honorarium; fee; Arbeitsplan; work plan;
    Privatstunden; private lessons; Preis; price; Herbst; Fall; autumn; Vortrag; lecture;
    patron</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-40">Hamburg, <tei:date when="1923-07-14">14. Juli
     23</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Mein liebster guter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this
      letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/4, p. 2535, July 17, 1923: "Von Fl. (Br.): ein
      Musik-Enthusiast wäre bereit, den Tonwillen für alle Universitäten u. Bibliotheken zu
      stiften!" ("From Floriz (letter): a music enthusiast is willing to donate a copy of Der
      Tonwille to every university and research library!"). </tei:note>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Du sollst nun rasch meine Meinung u. – – den Anfang meiner Tätigkeit zur
    Kenntnis bekommen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich frage Dich: Ist <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> kontraktlich verpflichtet 4 Hefte „<tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title>TW</tei:title></tei:rs>“ jährlich zu edieren? Wenn ja, so bist Du, aus Gründen
    Deiner künstlerischen u. finanziellen Schädigung, in der Lage, den Kontrakt zu lösen, was ich
    für das <tei:hi rend="underline">Beste</tei:hi> halten würde. Denn alle Lockmittel werden diesen
    Kavalier nicht zur Treue bekehren. Er wird sich ferner in <tei:choice>
     <tei:sic>ihrem</tei:sic>
     <tei:corr>Ihrem</tei:corr>
    </tei:choice> Genuß setzen, im Bewußtsein, daß er im Stande ist auch die neuen Bedingungen zu
    umgehen. Ich bin von der Tatsache, daß Dich der Kampf mit <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> entnerven muß u. Dein Werk bedroht wird, ganz u. gar im
    Innersten erbost. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich habe gestern mit einem Herrn <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Temming</tei:rs>, einem reichen Musikenthusiasten, gesprochen. Ich entwickelte ihm Deine ganze
    Situation u. sagte ihm, daß es gilt, durchaus Dir nicht finanziellen Vorteile zu schaffen,
    sondern Dein Werk an Sicherstellung sicher zu stellen. Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Temming</tei:rs> ist bereit eine solche Zahl von Heften jährlich zu abonnieren,
    die nötig wäre, um die deutschen Universitäten u. Hochschulen mit je einem Stiftungsexemplar zu
    versehen. (Bibliotheken vielleicht in erster Linie!) Du müßtest diesbezüglich Deine Anordnungen
    u. Wünsche geben. In privaten Kreisen werde ich noch so <tei:pb n="2"/> manches Abonnement
    plazieren können. Käme dazu noch eine tüchtige Tätigkeit in <tei:rs key="entity-002286" type="place">München</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs>, –
    warum sollte da nicht ein Grundstock geschaffen sein, der es <tei:hi rend="underline">Dir</tei:hi> ermöglicht zu schaffen wie <tei:hi rend="underline">Du</tei:hi> willst? </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Die <tei:rs key="entity-000798" type="person">Schönberg</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs key="entity-000373" type="person">Hindemith</tei:rs> etc. etc. -Nummern, – sieh, wie wichtig
    sind die!!! Schreibe mir sofort Deine Meinung über meine Idee. Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Temming</tei:rs> verreist am 1. August auf 3–4 Wochen. <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans Weisse</tei:rs> hat mir seinerzeit einen großen Strich
    durch die Rechnung gemacht.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">This
     remark probably refers to Weisse’s decision not to give any lectures on Schenker’s theory at
     the Vogt Conservatory in Hamburg, where Violin was teaching. </tei:note>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">Du</tei:hi> – – könntest hier Vorträge halten so viel Du willst u.
    bekämst Honorar, was Du wolltest. Das passt leider nicht in Deinem Arbeitsplan! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Hier ist's viel schlimmer mit den Steigerungen wie in <tei:rs key="entity-002506" type="place"><tei:country>Österreich</tei:country></tei:rs> u. – –
    Verdienst noch schwerer. Wenn <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">Vally</tei:rs> nicht
    auch tüchtig verdienen würde, könnten wir's überhaupt nicht schaffen, trotzdem ich im Winter 4–5
    Privatstunden täglich gebe. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Wenn also der <tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs>er
    Preis nicht sehr verlockend ist, werde ich wahrscheinlich nicht kommen können, umso mehr im
    Herbst sicher für <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Bubi</tei:rs> etwas gesehen muß. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs key="entity-000909" type="person">Fanny</tei:rs> kommt morgen. </tei:p>



   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Für heute innigstes von uns an Euch! </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Dein <tei:supplied reason="reading">g</tei:supplied>etreuer</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>
   <tei:lb/>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-40">Hamburg, <tei:date when="1923-07-14">July 14,
     1923</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">My dearest, good <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">You shall now quickly become acquainted with my intentions, and the start of
    my activity <tei:supplied reason="clarity">on your behalf</tei:supplied>.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Let me ask you: Is <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs>
    contractually obliged to publish four issues a year of <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>? If so, then, on grounds of it being
    to your artistic and financial detriment, you are in a position to dissolve the contract, which
    I consider would be for the <tei:hi rend="underline">best</tei:hi>. For no manner of inducements
    will return this cavalier to good faith. He will happily put himself in your good favor by
    knowing that he is in a position to circumvent even these new conditions. I am utterly and
    entirely enraged by the fact that your struggle with <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> has gotten the better of your nerves and threatened your work. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Yesterday, I spoke with a Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Temming</tei:rs>,
    a wealthy music enthusiast. I laid out for him your whole plight, and told him that it is not in
    the least a matter of creating financial advantages for you, but of putting your work on a
    secure and firm foundation. Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Temming</tei:rs> is
    willing to take out as many annual subscriptions as would be necessary to supply every German
    university and conservatory with a free copy. (<tei:supplied reason="clarity">Research</tei:supplied> libraries probably first and foremost!) All you would have to do in
    this regard is to explain your preferences and wishes. In private circles, I shall still <tei:pb n="2"/> arrange as many subscriptions as possible. If there were, in addition, an efficient
    practice <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of this sort</tei:supplied> in <tei:rs key="entity-002286" type="place">Munich</tei:rs> or <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>, – why should it not be possible to a create a firm base that would enable
     <tei:hi rend="underline">you</tei:hi> exactly as <tei:hi rend="underline">you</tei:hi> wish? </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">The <tei:rs key="entity-000798" type="person">Schoenberg</tei:rs> and <tei:rs key="entity-000373" type="person">Hindemith</tei:rs> etc., etc. journal issues – see how
    important they are!!! Write to tell me immediately your opinion of my idea. Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Temming</tei:rs> leaves on August 1 for three to four weeks.
     <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans Weisse</tei:rs> messed up my plans a while
     ago.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">You</tei:hi> – – could give as many lectures as you want here and would
    get whatever honorarium you wanted. Unfortunately, that <tei:supplied reason="clarity">probably</tei:supplied> does not fit into your work plan! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Things are much worse with price rises here than in <tei:rs key="entity-002506" type="place"><tei:country>Austria</tei:country></tei:rs> and – – earning a
    living is even more difficult. If <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">Vally</tei:rs> were
    not also capable of earning a good income, we could not cope at all, despite my giving four or
    five private lessons daily during the season. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">If, as it seems, the cost of a vacation in <tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs> is unattractive, I shall probably not be able to come, especially
    as something must surely be done about my <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">little
     boy</tei:rs> next fall. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs key="entity-000909" type="person">Fanny</tei:rs> arrives tomorrow. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">For today, most heartfelt greetings from us to the two of you! </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your true </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>

 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>