<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3493" sdoID="OJ-14-10_26">OJ 14/10, [26]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RW" scope="major">Rosa Weil's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="AW" scope="minor">Arnold Weil's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="minor">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008456">WeilR ~
        JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008458">WeilA ~
        JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter with envelope from Rosa Weil to Jeanette Schenker, dated August
        11, 1935</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1935-08-11T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-07-31</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Acknowledging Jeanette’s letter, Rosa describes the travel that she and Arnold
        have done (reminiscing on their time in Hofgastein with Jeanette), and their short stay in
        Vienna, where they met daughter Lene and packed her off for leave from her [clinical] work.
        Lene is now more responsible and mature. — Sister Hella is separated from husband Emil. </dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000944">Rosa Weil</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000943">Arnold Weil</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:div type="part_1">
        <tei:opener>
          <tei:fw type="envelope">
            <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold"
              >envelope</tei:hi></tei:note><tei:lb/>
            <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="recto"/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:address>
              <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied reason="clarity">An:</tei:supplied>
                <tei:handShift new="#RW"/>Frau D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Heinrich
                Schenker</tei:addrLine>
              <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-006026"
                  >Hofgastein</tei:rs> 34/5,</tei:addrLine>
              <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002578"
                  >Salzburg</tei:rs>.</tei:addrLine>
            </tei:address>
            <tei:fw type="postmark">|| [ÚSTÍ NAD LABE]M 2 | <tei:gap reason="illegible"/>VIII. 35–10
              | 3f | * AUSSIG 2 * ||</tei:fw><tei:lb/>
            <tei:address>
              <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>Antwort</tei:addrLine>
              <tei:addrLine><tei:date when="1935-08-30">30. VIII. 35</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
            </tei:address>
            <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="verso"/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:address>
              <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied>Absender:</tei:supplied>
                <tei:handShift new="#RW"/>R. Weil, Westphalenstr. 25.</tei:addrLine>
              <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">Aussig <tei:hi rend="supralinear"
                >a</tei:hi>/E.</tei:addrLine>
              <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">C. S. R.</tei:addrLine>
            </tei:address>
          </tei:fw>
          <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold">letter</tei:hi></tei:note><tei:lb/>
          <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RW"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002248"
              >Aussig</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1935-08-11">11. Aug. 1935</tei:date>.</tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
          <tei:salute>Meine liebe <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
              >Schwester</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">All
              paragraph-breaks except the first and last are editorial and based on endashes by
              Rosa.</tei:note></tei:salute>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:p rend="first">auch ohne Deinen so lieben herzlichen Brief, für den ich Dir vielmals
          danke, hätte ich Dir heute geschrieben. Diese erste Woche war sehr mit Arbeit angefüllt
          und es ist mir noch nie so schwer geworden, mich in den Alltag zurückzufinden. Diese Reise
          war so wunderschön und überreich an Eindrücken, daß es noch einige Zeit braucht, alles zu
          verarbeiten und zu den früheren, schönen Erinnerungen zu legen. Es ist wie ein Geschenk
          vom Himmel, daß man in diesen Zeiten noch schöne Erinnerungen sammeln kann und man sollte
          es ausnützen, solange es möglich ist. – </tei:p>

        <tei:p>Die Rückreise von Wien, wo wir zwei herrliche Tage verbrachten, verlief in angenehmer
          Gesellschaft sehr rasch und angenehm und die Wiedersehensfreude mit <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-005248">Lene</tei:rs> war groß. Leider war die Zeit des <tei:pb n="2"/>
          Beisammenseins ganz kurz, auspacken und mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005248"
            >Lene</tei:rs> wieder einpacken, noch am selben Abend; das mußte sehr rasch gehen, weil
          sie am nächsten Morgen wegfahren mußte, sonst hätte sie ihren Urlaub nicht voll ausnützen
          können; außerdem hatte sie für Montag abends schon das Schlafwagenbillet. Sie hatte uns
          eigentlich zwei Tage früher erwartet, weil wir diesmal ausnahmsweise und da zwei Feiertage
          vor dem Sonntag fielen, statt Samstag schon Freitag weggefahren sind. Nun in drei Wochen
          sehen wir uns wieder; da ihr die Arbeit im Lungenheim sehr gut gefallen und sie sehr viel
          gesehen und zugelernt hat, wird sie vielleicht auch noch den Monat September hier
          verbringen. Sie hat in meiner Abwesenheit, trotzdem sie doch fast den ganzen Tag außer
          Haus war, alles wunderschön geleitet und <tei:pb n="3"/> angeordnet auch wiederholt Gäste
          bewirtet und mir damit den Beweis erbracht, daß ein intelligenter Mensch mit festem Willen
          jede ihm gestellte Aufgabe irgendwie zu lösen vermag.</tei:p>

        <tei:p>Das alles wird Dich kaum sehr interessieren, aber aus allen Deinen Äußerungen
          entnehme ich immer mehr und mehr, daß Dir das Ehepaar O. H.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
            type="editorial" place="foot">“O. H. couple”: presumably <tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-003244">Klara</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000339"
              >Oskar</tei:rs> Hatschek (there is no other “O. H.” among Heinrich’s close
            acquaintances), though this seems an unlikely slur.</tei:note> ein ganz falsches Bild
          von meinem Kind und unserem Verhältnis zueinander entworfen hat. Es mag sein, daß ich in
          früheren Jahren oft recht nervös war, da ich fast zehn Jahre mit dem Wechsel und seinen
          recht üblen Begleiterscheinungen zu tun hatte; das war recht hart für mich und meine
          Lieben; daß ein junges Mädl mit hohen Interessen und geistigen Bestrebungen viel härter an
          den Flegeljahren und der ersten Sturm-und<tei:supplied>-</tei:supplied>Drangperiode zu
          kauen hat, als ein Gänschen, <tei:pb n="4"/> das an Mutter‘s Schürzenband hängt, – und daß
          sie deshalb fortstrebt aus einer Kleinstadt mit so engbegrenzten Möglichkeiten, kann eine
          Mutter, die keine Tochter hat, nicht verstehen und die seelischen Konflikte aus der
          eigenen Jugendzeit hat sie längst vergessen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
            place="foot">Is there a suggestion here (with “Wechsel” and “die keine Tochter hat”)
            that Lene was adopted, or that she was Arnold’s daughter by another
          mother?</tei:note></tei:p>

        <tei:p>Verzeih‘ wenn ich Dich mit Sachen belästigen, die kein großes Interesse für Dich
          bedeuten können. </tei:p>

        <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005248">Lene</tei:rs> telegrafierte aus <tei:rs
            type="place" key="entity-003980">Brüssel</tei:rs>, wollte weiter in das belgische Seebad
            Knocke,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Knokke: the most
            north-easterly seaside resort in Belgium, adjacent to the border with Holland
              (<tei:title level="j">Wikipedia</tei:title>). Earlier in the letter we were told that
            Lene would be away for three weeks. Evidently the telegraph has come in during the
            writing of this letter.</tei:note> dann in die Normandie. Wir erwarten morgen
          ausführlichen Bericht. </tei:p>

        <tei:p>Deine Befürchtung wegen <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003920">Hella</tei:rs> ist
          schon deshalb hinfällig, weil der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008436"
            >Mann</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Emil Hatschek,
            Hella’s husband, who Rosa in an earlier letter spoke of as a “Lump” (“idiot”) (<tei:ref
              type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-10_15">OJ 14/10, [15]</tei:ref>, November 24–28,
            1934).</tei:note> seit Monaten im Hotel lebt und <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-003920">Hella</tei:rs> mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005060"
            >Lotte</tei:rs>, die jetzt Ferien hat, eine neue 2 Zimmer-Wohnung bewohnt. </tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">Ich werde noch oft an die schönen Stunden in <tei:rs type="place"
            key="entity-006026">Gastein</tei:rs> denken und danke Dir, daß Du uns für würdig
          befunden hast, einen Blick in Dein Heiligtum zu werfen. Ich habe mich auch mit Deinem
          besseren Aussehen sehr gefreut! </tei:p>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute><tei:note>left margin, sideways:</tei:note> Noch den allerherzlichsten Grüßen </tei:salute>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Deine Schwester</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000944"
            >Rosa</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>

      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="part_2">
        <tei:opener/>

        <tei:p>
          <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in top margin, p. 3:</tei:note><tei:lb/>
          <tei:table rows="2" cols="2">
            <tei:row role="data">
              <tei:cell role="data"><tei:handShift new="#AW"/>Hellas Adresse:</tei:cell>
              <tei:cell role="data">Prostějov (Morava)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial"
                  place="foot">. Prostějov: town 60 km (38 miles) north-east of
                Brno.</tei:note></tei:cell>
            </tei:row>

            <tei:row role="data">
              <tei:cell role="data"/>
              <tei:cell role="data">Pod Nošitěm 71.</tei:cell>
            </tei:row>
          </tei:table>
        </tei:p>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute>Herzlichste Grüße</tei:salute>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Dein</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943"
            >Arnold</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>

      </tei:div>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:div type="part_1">
        <tei:opener>
          <tei:fw type="envelope">
            <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold"
              >envelope</tei:hi></tei:note><tei:lb/>
            <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="recto"/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:address>
              <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied reason="clarity">To:</tei:supplied>
                <tei:handShift new="#RW"/>Mrs. Heinrich Schenker</tei:addrLine>
              <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-006026"
                  >Hofgastein</tei:rs> 34/5</tei:addrLine>
              <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002578"
                  >Salzburg</tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
            </tei:address>
            <tei:fw type="postmark">|| [ÚSTÍ NAD LABE]M 2 | <tei:gap reason="illegible"/>VIII. 35–10
              | 3f | * AUSSIG 2 * ||</tei:fw><tei:lb/>
            <tei:address>
              <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>Answer<tei:supplied reason="clarity"
                  >ed</tei:supplied></tei:addrLine>
              <tei:addrLine><tei:date when="1935-08-30">August 30, 1935</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
            </tei:address>
            <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="verso"/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:address>
              <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied>From:</tei:supplied>
                <tei:handShift new="#RW"/>R. Weil, Westphalenstraße 25</tei:addrLine>
              <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">Aussig on the Elbe</tei:addrLine>
              <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">Czechoslovakia</tei:addrLine>
            </tei:address>
          </tei:fw>
          <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold">letter</tei:hi></tei:note><tei:lb/>
          <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RW"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002248"
              >Aussig</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1935-08-11">August 11,
            1935</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
          <tei:salute>My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">sister</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
              corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:p rend="first">Even without your dear, warm letter, for which I thank you from the
          bottom of my heart, I would have written to you today. This first week was packed with
          jobs to do, and never before has it become so difficult for me get back into the daily
          routine. The journey this time was so glorious and profuse with impressions that it still
          requires some time to absorb it all, and to consolidate with our earlier beautiful
          memories. It is like a gift from heaven that in these times one can still accumulate
          delightful memories, and one should take advantage of it for as long as is
          possible.</tei:p>

        <tei:p>The journey back from Vienna, where we spent two magnificent days, passed by in
          congenial company very quickly and pleasantly, and our joy at seeing <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-005248">Lene</tei:rs> again was great. It’s a pity our <tei:pb n="2"/> time
          together was so short, unpacking and repacking together with <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-005248">Lene</tei:rs> all on the same evening. It had to be done very fast
          since we needed to depart the next morning, otherwise she would not have been able to make
          full use of her leave, added to which she already had her sleeping car ticket for the
          Monday evening. She had been expecting us two days earlier, because unusually this time,
          and since two national holidays fell before the Sunday, we set off on the Friday instead
          of the Saturday. In three weeks’ time we will see each other again. As she has enjoyed her
          work in Lungenheim very much, and has seen and learned a great deal, she may perhaps spend
          the month of September here. In my absence, and despite her having been out of the house
          the whole day, she has managed and <tei:pb n="3"/> regulated everything magnificently and
          hosted several guests, and in so doing has shown me proof that an intelligent person with
          a strong will can dispatch any tasks assigned to them.</tei:p>

        <tei:p>All of this will hardly be of interest to you, but from all that you say I gather
          more and more that the O. H. couple<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> has
          created a totally false impression for you of my child and our relationship to one
          another. It may be that in earlier years I was often highly nervous, since for nearly ten
          years I had to deal with the change and its insidious accompanying symptoms. That was
          really hard for me and those close to me. A mother who has no daughter cannot understand
          that a young lass with keen interests and intellectual aspirations had to try out the
          first sturm-und-drang period, as a gosling <tei:pb n="4"/> that clings to its mother’s
          apron strings, and consequently strained at the leash to get away from a small town with
          such restricted possibilities, and <tei:supplied reason="clarity">that that
            mother</tei:supplied> has long since forgotten the mental conflicts of her own youthful
            years.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

        <tei:p>Forgive me if I am burdening you with matters that can be of no great interest for
          you.</tei:p>

        <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005248">Lene</tei:rs> telegraphed from <tei:rs
            type="place" key="entity-003980">Brussels</tei:rs> wanting to extend her travels, to the
          Belgian seaside resort of Knokke and then on to Normandy.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
            type="footnote"/> We are expecting a detailed report tomorrow. </tei:p>

        <tei:p>Your anxiety concerning <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003920">Hella</tei:rs> is
          by now out-of-date because her <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008436"
            >husband</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> has been living for
          some months in a hotel, and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003920">Hella</tei:rs> and
            <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005060">Lotte</tei:rs> (who is now on holiday) are
          living in a two-room apartment.</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">I still think often of those happy hours we spent in <tei:rs
            type="place" key="entity-006026">Gastein</tei:rs>, and thank you for considering us
          worthy of having a glimpse into your sanctuary. I was also greatly cheered by your
          improved appearance.</tei:p>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute><tei:note>left margin, sideways:</tei:note>Once again, most heartfelt
            greetings </tei:salute>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your sister</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000944"
            >Rosa</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>

      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="part_2">
        <tei:opener/>

        <tei:p>
          <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in top margin, p. 3:</tei:note><tei:lb/>
          <tei:table rows="2" cols="2">
            <tei:row role="data">
              <tei:cell role="data"><tei:handShift new="#AW"/>Hella's Address:</tei:cell>
              <tei:cell role="data">Prostějov (Moravia)<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06"
                  type="footnote"/></tei:cell>
            </tei:row>

            <tei:row role="data">
              <tei:cell role="data"/>
              <tei:cell role="data">Pod Nošitěm 71</tei:cell>
            </tei:row>
          </tei:table>
        </tei:p>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute>Most cordial greetings,</tei:salute>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943"
            >Arnold</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>

      </tei:div>
    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
