<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="578" sdoID="OJ-14-45_30">OJ 14/45, [30]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="MV" scope="sole">Moriz Violin's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2011</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-09-19" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002719">ViolinM ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM+V ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002718">ViolinM+V+F ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Moriz Violin to Schenker, dated February 5, 1924 </dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1924-02-05T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2011-09-19</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Violin reports that Max Temming is keen to support his plan to promote Schenker's
    work. Following discussions with Schenker in Vienna, he makes some provisional calculations on
    how the gift of money would give Schenker more time to devote to his writings. He also thinks
    about the happy prospect of Schenker coming to Hamburg. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>patronage; subscriptions; Bübrigkeit; Bübigkeit; childish actions; Stunden; lessons;
    Arbeit; work; Goldmark; gold mark; Dollar; Musiker; musician; Abreise; departure; </dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-40">Hamburg, <tei:date when="1924-02-05">5. Februar
     24</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Liebster <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this
      letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/6, p. 2631, February 7, 1924: "Von Fl. (Br.):
      Themming ist von der „Idee“ entzückt; nun soll ich unter dem Titel von so u. so viel Verlusten
      die Summe den Betrag von 2000 Goldmark nennen." ("From Floriz (letter): Themming is enamored
      of the "idea"; now, under the heading of so and so many losses, I am supposed to name the
      figure of 2,000 goldmarks.") </tei:note>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Erst heute kann ich, was wir in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> besprochen, fortsetzen. Denn erstens kam Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Themming</tei:rs> vor 4 Tagen von einer <tei:rs key="entity-003029" type="place"><tei:country>Schweden</tei:country></tei:rs>reise zurück, zweitens hatte ich hier
    Lebenssorgen auszufechten (bei 5 Stunden täglich Unterricht!). Es geht aber alles in schönster
    Ordnung u. da lässt es sich leicht vergessen u. verschweigen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Themmings</tei:rs> sind sehr
    begeistert von meiner Idee. Als solche hatte ich sie vorgetragen, nachdem ich sagen konnte, daß
    unser <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title>Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>-Vorhaben,
    durch die <tei:choice>
     <tei:sic>Bübrigkeit</tei:sic>
     <tei:corr>Bübigkeit</tei:corr>
    </tei:choice> des <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">Verlag</tei:rs>s nicht mehr
    zur Diskussion steht. Da ich vor Allem bedacht bin, Deine Würde zu wahren, so gelang es mir
    leicht bei <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Themmings</tei:rs> den Vorschlag zu
    provozieren, ich möge bei Dir anfragen, ob Du geneigt wärst, die neueste „Idee“ zu
    verwirklichen. Das ist nun die schickliche Gelegenheit, bei der Du nur schreiben kannst, daß sie
    Dich an sich interessiert, aber daß die Schwierigkeit darin bestünde, daß Du 1.) so u. so viel
    Stunden 2.) Arbeit versäumst u. 3.) Arbeit auch von der Ausführung der Idee hättest u. daß somit
    Du mit einem Betrag von so u. so Goldmark rechnen müsstest. 4.20 G. M. = 1 Dollar, also schreibe
    genau was Du willst. Wir sprachen in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> von
    2000 G. M.) Ich würde es nicht billiger raten, wenn es auch das Usuelle ein wenig übersteigt.
     <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs> soll kommen; wann, entscheidet
    sich in nächster Zeit. Um diese Zeit möchten <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Themmings</tei:rs> es machen. Ich hatte <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs>s Anwesenheit nach wie vor für nützlich. Durch <tei:pb n="2"/> sie wird es
    den Musikern schwer werden zu kneifen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Wie geht es Euch? Innen u. Außen? </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Vor meiner Abreise sah ich <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">word
     crossed out</tei:note>
    <tei:persName>Artur</tei:persName>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Artur: probably an old friend or relative of Violin's, known also to Schenker, whose death had
     recently been announced. </tei:note> Ich glaube es war ihm noch eine Freude. Ein armer,
    gequälter, übermüder Mensch würde erlöst. Doch war mir die nachgesandte Mitteilung überraschend!
    Danach sah es nicht aus! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Die Forderungen des Lebens werden immer größer. Ich versumpfe in der Arbeit,
    durch welche ich es bestreiten kann. Ein ewiges <tei:unclear reason="reading">Weckungsleben</tei:unclear>! Wie sollte ich da nicht allein in den Gedanken an die Festtage
    aufgehen, die mir Deine <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>er Anwesenheit
    spenden würde<tei:supplied reason="syntax">n</tei:supplied>? Ich kann nur berichten daß wir alle
    gesund sind, trotzdem ich mich nicht sehr wo<tei:supplied reason="spelling">h</tei:supplied>l
    fühle. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Wir grüßen Euch innigst! </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Dein getreuer </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-40">Hamburg, <tei:date when="1923-12-11">February 5,
     1924</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dearest <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Only now can I continue what we first spoke about in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>. For, in the first place, Mr <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Temming</tei:rs> returned from his trip to <tei:rs key="entity-003029" type="place"><tei:country>Sweden</tei:country></tei:rs> four days ago and,
    secondly, I had some personal problems to sort out (in addition to five hours of teaching each
    day!). Everything, however, is in perfectly good order, and it can easily be forgotten and not
    spoken about. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Temming</tei:rs> is very much
    excited by my idea. I presented it to him after I was able to say that the childish actions of
    the <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">publisher</tei:rs> make our concerns about
     <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>
    no longer open to discussion. That I am above all determined to preserve your dignity, so it was
    easy for me to put to <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Temming</tei:rs> the suggestion
    that I might ask you whether you would be inclined to put the latest "idea" into practice. This
    is now the proper occasion on which you alone can write to me that the idea itself is of
    interest to you, but that the difficulty with it resides in the fact that (1) you would lose so
    many hours (2) of work, and (3) you would have to undertake some work in order to realize the
    idea, and that therefore you would have to expect a payment of so many goldmarks. 4.20 goldmarks
    = 1 <tei:supplied reason="clarity">US</tei:supplied> Dollar; thus write to us precisely what you
    need. We spoke in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs> of a sum of 2000 gold
    marks. I would not advise you to ask for any less, even if this is a little more than what one
    would usually expect. <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs> is expected
    here; he will decide when in the next few days. <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Temming</tei:rs> would want to make the arrangements around this time. I regarded <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs>'s presence as useful, then and now.
    Through <tei:pb n="2"/> it, it will be difficult for musicians to back out of the arrangement. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">How are the two of you? Personally and professionally? </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Before I left, I saw <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">word crossed
     out</tei:note>
    <tei:persName>Artur</tei:persName>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> I believe
    that it was still a joy for him. A poor, tortured, over-tired human being was set free. And yet
    the news that followed came as a surprise! Things did not look so serious! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">The demands of life become ever greater. I am mired in the work that enables
    me to meet them. An unceasing <tei:unclear reason="original_reading">life on the
     go</tei:unclear>! How can I avoid being absorbed only in the thoughts that your presence in
     <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> would bestow upon me? I can only
    report that we are all healthy, despite the fact that I do not feel very well. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">We send you our most intimate greetings, </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your faithful </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>
  </tei:div>

 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>