<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3879" sdoID="OJ-13-10_167">OJ 13/10, [167]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2025</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated May 21, 1933</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1933-05-21T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-12-09</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel is working in a [National-Socialist] “cell” to introduce reforms at the
        Leipzig Conservatory. — He is hopeful that music will return to a simpler, more natural
        state but expresses his distaste for the melody of the “Horst Wessel Lied” and says that
        many administrative mistakes have been made, especially the appointment of Fritz Stein to
        the directorship of the Berlin Conservatory. </dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1933-05-21">21. V 33</tei:date>.
            Lpzig, Könneritzstr 58<tei:hi rend="supralinear">III</tei:hi> l.</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Professor Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
            >This letter was initially misaddressed and returned to Oppel, so its receipt was not
            recorded in Schenker’s diary until Oppel resent it, together with a subsequent letter,
            on June 14. The diary for June 23, 1933 records: “ Von Oppel (K.): der Brief zum 19. sei
            zurückgekommen, bittet um die genaue Adresse.“ […] “An Oppel (Ansichtsk.): die Adresse;
            bitte um den Brief.” (“From Oppel (postcard): his letter of the 19th was returned,
            requests the precise address” [...] “From Oppel (postcard): his letter of the 19th was
            returned, requests the precise address.”) The letter was finally received on June 27,
            when the Schenkers were in Ilz, Styria: “Von Oppel (Br. zum 19.)” (“From Oppel (letter
            of the 19th)”), but the contents that he records are those of <tei:ref
              type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-13-10_168">OJ 13/10, [168]</tei:ref>, June 14,
            1933.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> schickte mir den Aufsatz a.
        der <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002992"><tei:title>D. A. Z.</tei:title></tei:rs> Er
        hat mich sehr gefreut, geärgert habe ich mich nur über die Vorbemerkung der Redaction; diese
        Quadratesel! <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-003014"><tei:title>Den
          Kunstwart</tei:title></tei:rs> muss ich i. d. Universitätsbibliothek lesen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Schade, dass Sie Ihre Augen so bei der <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-003331">Br 5–8
          Studie</tei:rs> überangestrengt haben, ich hatte alles bereits fertig gemacht; wenn wir
        diesen Sommer uns sehen, was ich stark hoffe, zeige ichs Ihnen. – In der Musik hoffe ich vom
        Nationalsocialismus eine Rückkehr zur Einfachheit. Das Volk muss erst wieder zu den
        Klassikern erzogen werden. Melodien wie die zum <tei:title>Horst Wessel-Lied</tei:title>
        sind musikalisch unmöglich. Ich singe es deshalb nie mit. Die Leute, die wie <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000344">Haydn</tei:rs> Nationalhymnen schreiben können, sind
        doch jahrhundertdünn gesät! – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Leider habe ich in der Zelle sehr viel tun, um unsern Augiasstall, genannt <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002872">Landeskonservatorium</tei:rs>,
          auszuräumen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Cf. <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-13-10_166">OJ 13/10, [166]</tei:ref>, April 27, 1933.
          Here Oppel refers specifically to the National Socialists, hence the “cell” may have been
          a sub-unit of the NS Party. Oppel is evidently a member of a group tasked with writing –
          or rewriting? – the history of the Leipzig Conservatory, which had been founded in 1843 by
            <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008291">Felix Mendelssohn</tei:rs>, who was Jewish by
          birth. The oldest conservatory in Germany, it was granted the title Royal Conservatory of
          Music in Leipzig in 1876, and then renamed Landeskonservatorium (State Conservatory) in
          1924.</tei:note> Manches ist direct reif für den Staatsanwalt. Aber ich greife jetzt
        rücksichtslos durch. Im übrigen werden natürlich viele Fehler gemacht: dass eine solche Null
        wie <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000851">Prof. Stein</tei:rs> aus <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002757">Kiel</tei:rs> an die <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002888"
          >Berliner Hochschule</tei:rs> kommt, ist eine Schiebung u. ein Witz.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Fritz Stein: he was Professor of Music
          at the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002968">University of Kiel</tei:rs> from
          1919 to 1933, in which year, supported by a recommendation from <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000268">Wilhelm Furtwängler</tei:rs>, he became the Director of the Berlin
          Hochschule für Musik. Stein was also a leading figure in the Kampfbund für deutsche Kultur
          (Militant League for German Culture), a right-wing antisemitic association founded by
          Alfred Rosenberg.</tei:note> Seither konnte er sich nicht modern genug gebärden,: <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000373">Hindemith</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000798">Schönberg</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000482"
          >Křenek</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002793">Stravinsky</tei:rs> etc! Und
        jetzt soll <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000851">der Mann</tei:rs> am 1. Musikinstitut
        des Reiches die Jugend zu nationaler Musik erziehen! Lachhaft. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Wie wird es mit Ihren Ferien? Gehn Sie wieder nach <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>? Die Verhältnisse in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002506">Östreich</tei:rs> spitzen sich ja auch immer mehr zu u. ich hoffe,
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006085">Dollfuss</tei:rs> verschwindet. Man wirbt zwar
        hier in den Zeitungen schon, den Sommer in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482"
          >Deutschland</tei:rs> selbst zu verbringen. Aber ich brauche Bergluft u. Fusstouren, nach
        diesem anstrengenden Winter. Leider komme ich zu keiner eigenen Arbeit mehr vor den
        politischen Aufgaben. Diese gehn nun aber vor. – Das geistige Niveau der Provinzblätter ist
        noch sehr mässig u. Sonntags hole ich nur meist die <tei:rs type="journal"
          key="entity-002992"><tei:title>D. A. Z.</tei:title></tei:rs> zur Ergänzung. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wird <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs> im Sommer nach Wien
        kommen?</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801">Den Kindern</tei:rs> geht’s gut. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> büffelt fleissig. Die Kleinen entwickeln
        sich weiter gut. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008523">Bepo</tei:rs> beobachtet jetzt im
        Park alles Getier sehr gut. – <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000287">Glas</tei:rs> in
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002757">Kiel</tei:rs> hat natürlich unter den neuen
        Verhältnissen keinen leichten Stand, doch scheint er nach seinem letzten Brief sich halten
        zu können.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">This is the first
          letter in which Oppel hints that Richard Glas, a friend and colleague from his days at the
            <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002608">Kiel Conservatory</tei:rs>, is
          Jewish</tei:note> Ich vertraue seiner Zähigkeit, sich durchzubeissen. Die ganze Jugend ist
        mir etwas zu selbständig geworden, ohne jede eigne Leitung stellt sie vorläufig nur
        Ansprüche, das ist natürlich ein Unsinn u. führt auf die Dauer zu nichts Gutem. Man wird sie
        langsam wieder in die für sie nötigen Schranken zurückweisen müssen, wenn die Entwickelung
        gesund vor sich gehn will u. soll. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Alles Gute u. die herzlichsten Grüssen</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Ihnen beiden von uns allen!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr treuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1933-05-21">May 21,
              1933</tei:date>. Leipzig, Könneritzstrasse 58<tei:hi rend="supralinear">III</tei:hi>
            left</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor
            Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> sent me the article from the
          <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002992"><tei:title level="j">Deutsche Allgemeine
            Zeitung</tei:title></tei:rs>. It greatly delighted me, I was only annoyed by the
        editors’ preliminary note: these square asses! I can read <tei:rs type="journal"
          key="entity-003014"><tei:title level="j">Der Kunstwart</tei:title></tei:rs> only in the
        University Library. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>A pity that you have overstrained your eyes working on the <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-003331">Brahms study of parallel fifths and octaves</tei:rs>; I had finished
        preparing everything. If we see each other this summer, as I sincerely hope, I shall show it
        to you. – Under National Socialism, I hope that there will be a return to simplicity in
        music. The people must once again be educated in the classics. Melodies like that of the
          <tei:title level="m">Horst Wessel-Lied</tei:title> are musically impossible; for that
        reason, I never join in singing it. The people who can compose national anthems like <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000344">Haydn</tei:rs> have been thin on the ground for
        centuries! –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Unfortunately, I have a great deal to do in my cell to clean out our Augean Stables,
        also known as the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002872">State
          Conservatory</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> But I will take
        vigorous action ruthlessly. Moreover, many mistakes are of course being made; that such a
        nonentity as <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000851">Professor Stein</tei:rs> from <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002757">Kiel</tei:rs> has been appointed to the <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002888">Conservatory in Berlin</tei:rs> is a piece of foul
        play, and a joke.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> Since then, he has been
        unable to deport himself with sufficient modernity: <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000373">Hindemith</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798"
          >Schoenberg</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000482">Křenek</tei:rs>, <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-002793">Stravinsky</tei:rs>, and so on! And now <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000851">the man</tei:rs> is supposed to educate the youth in
        national music in the premier musical institution of the state! Ludicrous.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> What will you do about the summer holidays? Will you go to <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs> again? The conditions in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002506">Austria</tei:rs> are becoming ever more acute, and I hope
        that <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006085">Dollfuss</tei:rs> will disappear. One is
        already advertising in the newspapers here for people to spend the summer in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002482">Germany</tei:rs> itself. But I need mountain air, and
        walking tours, after this strenuous winter. Unfortunately, I don’t get any of my own work
        done, on account of political obligations. But these must take precedence. – The
        intellectual level of the provincial newspapers is still very mediocre, and on Sundays I
        usually take only the <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002992"><tei:title level="j"
            >Deutsche Allgemeine Zeitung</tei:title></tei:rs>, as a supplement.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Will <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs> come to Vienna this
        summer?</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801">The children</tei:rs> are well. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> is studying conscientiously. The little
        ones are developing well. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008523">Bepo</tei:rs> is now
        very adept in observing all the animal life in the park. – <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000287">Glas</tei:rs> in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002757"
          >Kiel</tei:rs> does not, of course, have an easy time under the new circumstances but
        seems to be able to survive, according to his last letter.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
          type="footnote"/> I trust his tenacity to stay afloat. The entire youth have become too
        independent, in my view; with no leadership of their own, they only make demands at present.
        That is naturally nonsensical and will in the long run lead to nothing good. One will have
        to return them to their necessary confines if they are to develop in a healthy
        manner.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">All good wishes and the most cordial greetings</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">to the two of you from all of us!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
