<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="87" sdoID="OJ-13-10_7">OJ 13/10, [7]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>


  <tei:respStmt xml:id="TJa">
   <tei:persName>Timothy L. Jackson</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2010</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2010</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2010</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   
   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated September 7, 1919</dc:title>
   
   <dcterms:created>1919-09-07T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2010-04-22</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Oppel expresses his pessimism in the aftermath of the war and the prospects for
    his generation. He sends a chaconne for Schenker's comment, and reports his appointment as a
    teacher in theory and composition at the Kiel Conservatory. Alfred Einstein asked him for a
    review of the Erläuterungsausgabe, but he declined. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Krieg; war; Front; battle front; Entente; Heimat; homeland; Nation; nation; Egoismus;
    egoism; Charakter; character; Generation; generation; Schmach; disgrace; Musik; music; Chaconne;
    Theorie; theory; Komposition; composition; Besprechung; review</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline>Kiel, <tei:date when="1919-09-07">7. IX. 19.</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:address rend="indent-60">
     <tei:addrLine>Feldstr 77<tei:hi rend="supralinear">IV.</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Sehr geehrter Herr D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi>
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Endlich<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter
     is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/14, pp. 2142–2143, September 13, 1919: "von Oppel
     (Brief mit beigelegter Chaconne): erzählt unter anderem, wie er vom Herausgeber einer
     Musik-Zeitschrift aufgefordert über mich zu schreiben, dies mit der Begründung ablehnte, selbst
     noch nicht so weit zu sein, um dies fertig zu bringen;" ("from Oppel (letter with enclosed
     chaconne): among other things, tells how he was asked by the publisher of a music magazine to
     write about me, which he refused on grounds that he is himself not yet advanced enough to do
     that; "). </tei:note> komme ich dazu, Ihnen für Ihre liebe Karte vom 31. III.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The writing of this postcard, which is not
     known to survive, is not recorded in Schenker's diary. </tei:note> zu danken. Sie war mir eine
    kleine Aufmunterung in den pessimistischen Gedanken, die uns Frontkrieger bei der Rückkehr in
    die Heimat anwandelten. Gesiegt hat die Entente keineswegs. Aber man hat doch ein sehr bitteres
    Gefühl, dass wir für diese Narrenzustände jetzt in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482">Deutschland</tei:rs> 4½ Jahre draussen im Dreck gelegen und <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">seine</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">unsre</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> besten Mannesjahre vom 36. bis zum 40! geopfert haben. Das schlimmste ist, dass ich
    vorläufig den Glauben an die Nation verloren habe: überall nur der krassste Egoismus, der nakte,
    brutale englische Geschäftssinn; für ein Pfund Butter verkäufen heute 99% der Menschheit ihre
    Seele. Von Charakter keine Spur mehr! Ein trauriges Geschlecht. Von unsrer Generation erhoffe
    ich nichts mehr. Unsre Kinder werden die Schmach, <tei:pb n="2"/> die uns diese aufgeblasenen
    eitlen Affen von Franzosen jetzt täglich antun, hoffentlich einst rächen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">This indignation at Clemenceau's plans for
     vengeance through the dictates of the Versailles Treaty was widely felt by Germans. [Kurt
     Oppel] </tei:note> Das ist mein glühender Wunsch. – </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Was mich angeht, so soll meine Kraft der Rettung der Musik gehören, und ich hoffe, dass
    die äussere Not die innere Sammlung von selbst erzeugen wird. Wie gerne hätte ich bei Ihnen noch
    studiert, aber bei diesen Verhältnissen ist das unmöglich. Als Drucksache schicke ich Ihnen eine
     <tei:term>Chaconne</tei:term> für Klavier, die ich nach der
    Rückkehr aus dem Felde gemacht habe. Manuscripte wage ich bei der Unsicherheit der Verhältnisse
    jetzt nicht zu schicken. Und die Herren Verleger nehmen ja nichts. Ich habe manches auf Lager,
    aber ich wage gar nicht mehr, die Verleger anzugehn. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Seit 1. Sept. bin ich hier wieder 1. Lehrer für <tei:term>Theorie</tei:term> und <tei:term>Komposition</tei:term> am
     <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002608">Konservatorium</tei:rs>. Wenn nur die Konserv.-directoren
    mehr Musiker wären als Geschäftsmacher, die Kunst kommt bei den meisten erst in allerletzter
    Linie. – </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Bleiben Sie nun in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Wien</tei:rs> oder denken Sie
    noch daran, nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482">Deutschland</tei:rs> übersiedeln? </tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> Ich glaube Ihnen gern, dass es heute für Sie nicht ganz einfach ist, eine
    neue Zukunft aufzunehmen. Aber man ist ja bei uns auch mit Blindheit geschlagen, dass man Leute
    wie Sie nicht an die richtige Stelle setzt. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich wurde neulich von D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi>
    <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000195">Einstein</tei:rs> aufgefordet, Ihre <tei:rs key="entity-001733" type="work">letzten Beethovenausgaben</tei:rs> zu besprechen i. d. <tei:rs key="entity-002480" type="journal">Zeitschrift für Musikwissenschaft</tei:rs> (Deutsche
    Musikgesellschaft). Ich habe aber abgelehnt, weil ich mich noch nicht reif dafür fühle und es
     mi<tei:del rend="overwritten">r</tei:del>
    <tei:add place="superimposed">ch</tei:add> eine Vermessenheit dünkt, Ihre gewaltige Arbeit und
    Ihr ungeheueres Wissen unter meine kritische Lupe zu nehmen. Ich habe auch
     <tei:persName>Einstein</tei:persName> geantwortet, in 4–5 Jahren würde ich das sehr gern tun.
    Jetzt nach 4½ Kriegsjahren heisst es, sich wieder gründlich in alles einarbeiten und die
    inzwischen erschienen Dinge zu verdauen. Später hoffe ich Ihnen und Ihren Werke besser dienen zu
    können, wenn ich mich dazu voll<tei:supplied reason="abbreviation">ständig</tei:supplied>
    gerüstet fühle. Halbe Dinge sind nicht mein Fall. Ich hoffe, dass Sie diesen meinen Schritt und
    seine Gründe billigen und bleibe mit besten Gruss </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute>Ihr dankbarer und sehr ergebener </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50">Dr. Reinhard Oppel.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline>Kiel, <tei:date when="1919-09-07">September 7, 1919</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:address rend="indent-60">
     <tei:addrLine>Feldstrasse 77<tei:hi rend="supralinear">IV.</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dear, highly esteemed Dr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Finally<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> I am able to thank you for your
    kind postcard of March 31.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> To me it proffered a
    small encouragement in view of the pessimistic thoughts that overcame us battle-front soldiers
    upon our return to the homeland. In no wise did the Allies win. But one still has a very bitter
    feeling that we spent four-and-a-half years out there in the mud and sacrificed the best years
    of our manhood from 36 to 40 for this craziness now in Germany! The worst thing is that I have
    for the time being lost my faith in the nation: everywhere only the most base egotism, the
    naked, brutal English business practices; for a pound of butter, 99% of humanity will sell their
    soul. Of character, not a trace is left! A sad race. From our generation I expect nothing
    further. Hopefully, at some point our children will have the opportunity <tei:pb n="2"/> to
    avenge the disgrace that these inflated, arrogant apes of Frenchmen daily heap upon us.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> That is my ardent wish. – </tei:p>

   <tei:p>For myself, I wish to put my energy into the salvation of music, and I hope that external
    deprivation will bring forth of itself inner composure. How gladly I still would have studied
    with you, but under present circumstances that is impossible. As printed matter I am sending you
    a <tei:term>chaconne</tei:term> for piano that I composed after my
    return from the field. Under present uncertain circumstances I do not dare to send manuscripts.
    And the publishers take nothing. I have many things in storage but I hardly consider approaching
    publishers any more. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Since September 1, I am the principal teacher for <tei:term>theory</tei:term> and <tei:term>composition</tei:term> at the
     <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002608">Conservatory</tei:rs>. If only the Conservatory directors
    were more musicians than business types; for most of them art comes at the very end. – </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Will you remain in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Vienna</tei:rs> or are you
    considering moving to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482">Germany</tei:rs>? </tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> I can well understand that it certainly is not easy to believe in a new
    future. But in our case, people are so blighted with blindness that they cannot properly value
    people like yourself. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Lately, I was encouraged by Dr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000195">Einstein</tei:rs>
    to review your recent <tei:rs key="entity-001733" type="work">Beethoven editions</tei:rs> in the
     <tei:rs key="entity-002480" type="journal">
     <tei:title level="j">Zeitschrift für Musikwissenschaft</tei:title>
    </tei:rs> (Deutsche Musikgesellschaft). But I turned it down since I do not yet consider myself
    sufficiently mature and think it presumptuous for me to place your impressive work and enormous
    learning beneath my critical lens. I answered <tei:persName>Einstein</tei:persName> that in four
    to five years I would gladly do it. Now after four-and-a-half years of war the task is to work
    through everything thoroughly and to digest the things that have appeared in the meantime. Later
    I hope to be better able to serve you and your work, especially once I feel myself fully armed
    for the task. Half-way measures are not my thing. I hope that you will approve of my decision
    and the reasons for it, and remain with best greetings </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute>Your grateful and very faithful </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50">Dr. Reinhard Oppel</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>



  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>