<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="752" sdoID="OJ-10-1_6">OJ 10/1, [6]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="WDa" scope="sole">Walter Dahms's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="JK">
   <tei:persName>John Koslovsky</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2012</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2012</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2012</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
   <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
   <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2012-08-09" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002725">Dahms ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Dahms to Schenker, dated July 15, 1914</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1914-07-15T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2012-08-09</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Dahms communicates from the Black Forest, commiserating over Schenker's
    experiences with the Vienna Konzerthausgesellschaft.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Einsiedelei; hermitage; Gesundung; recovery; Nerven; nerves; Fortschritt; progress;
    Schlecht; wicked people; Minderwertigen; less worth people; Kunst-Verderbern; art degenerates;
    Gralsritterschaft; knighthood of the Grail; Zaubergärten; enchanted gardens; Grossen; great
    masters</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000149">Dahms</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-40">Muggenbrunn</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-60">d. <tei:date when="1914-07-15">15. 7.
     14</tei:date>.</tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute>Sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Doktor</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this
      letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 1/15, p. 617, July 17, 1914: "Briefe: ... von
      Dahms, wie immer herzlich ergeben u. ausführlich." ("Letters: ... from Dahms, as ever,
      heartily devoted and detailed.").</tei:note>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ihr freundlicher Brief<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 1/15, p. 613, July
     12, 1914: "Brief an Dahms u. Frl. Fanny." ("Letter[s] to Dahms and Miss Fanny
     [Violin].").</tei:note> hat mich in meiner Einsiedelei herzlich erquickt. Die Gesundung von
    Herz und Nerven macht täglich Fortschritte und nichts ist schöner als dieses Kraftgefühl, mit
    dem man dem Kommenden entgegensehen kann, und gerade dem Schwierigsten und Widrigsten mit der
    grössten Kämpfer wonne. Jede Zeile von Ihnen schärft das Bild unserer Zeit mir noch um einige
     <tei:foreign xml:lang="fre">Nuancen</tei:foreign>. Aber das Herzlichste ist das Bewusstsein und
    die Lust, zu dem Damm gegen die Schlammflut des Schlechten und Minderwertigen (vor allem: des
    Unehrlichen) ein kleines Steinchen beitragen zu können. Nun haben Sie selbst die selige
    Gewissheit, dass Ihr Werk wächst, dass langsam aber unaufhaltsam die Wirkung sich ausbreitet,
    dass Freunde von allen Seiten kommen mit heissem Herzen und dem Verlangen mitzuhelfen und dass
    Ihr Wirken <tei:pb n="2"/> den Unredlichen, diesen verruchten Kunst-Verderbern, immer schärfer
    in die Augen sticht. Auch <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> wird zur
    Erkenntnis reifen. Sind es erst einige, die aus Ihren Born schöpfen, so werden es immer mehr und
    eine Gralsritterschaft (aber keine mitleidsvolle tränenselige, sondern eine kühne, kämpferische)
    wird da erstehen, die die modernen Zaubergärten ausrodet. Triumph! – </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ihr Erlebnis mit der <tei:rs key="entity-003270" type="organization">Wiener
     Konzerthausgesellschaft</tei:rs> spricht wieder einmal Bände. Was für ein erbärmliches, dummes
    Volk. Das Schönste aber ist Ihr Standpunkt, mit dem Sie allem Kleinlichen, aller Verbitterung so
    sehr überlegen sind. Wie wird man später einmal jammern! Uns bleibt allen das tröstende
    Bewusstsein, dass die <tei:rs key="entity-000871" type="person">Strauß</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person">Reger</tei:rs> und <tei:rs key="entity-000556" type="person">Mahler</tei:rs> trotz aller erdenklichen „Förderungen“, trotz aller krampfhaften Lobpreisungen
    und Denkmäler und Titel und Goldstücke doch den kürzeren ziehen werden. Die Geschichte ist hart
    und <tei:pb n="3"/> unbestechlich. Die Wahrheit wird für die späteren Generationen lehrreich
    sein; aber sie werden ihren Grossen ebenso blind zunächst gegenüberstehen wie es bei uns ist und
    wie es immer war. Ich habe gerade <tei:rs key="entity-000799" type="person">Schopenhauer</tei:rs> über „<tei:title>Ruhm, Kritik etc.</tei:title>“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Arthur
       Schopenhauer</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Parerga und Paralipomena</tei:title> (1851),
      Part II, chapter 15, section 20, <tei:title level="a">Über Urteil, Kritik, Beifall und
       Ruhm</tei:title> (On Judgment, Criticism, Applause, and Fame)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> gelesen
    und alles so klar und nötig gefunden, dass das Grosse eben Zeit haben muss und das Kartenhaus
    des Tagesruhms in sich zusammenfällt, wenn der Wind kommt. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Hier rauschen die Bäche in das Briefschreiben hinein und alles ist in so
    unendliche Schönheit getaucht, dass einem ganz liebevoll und mildversöhnlich ums Herz wird. Aber
    wir können <tei:add place="interlinear-above">eben</tei:add> nur mit dem Schönen und Guten
    Freundschaft schliessen; darum geht der Kampf an, wenn wir wieder dort sind, wo unsere Gegner
    hausen und wüsten. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ihnen die beste Erholung und Kräftigung wünschend verbleibe ich mit den
    herzlichsten Grüssen </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">und Dank</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50">Ihr <tei:rs key="entity-000149" type="person">Walter
     Dahms</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-40">Muggenbrunn</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:date when="1914-07-15">July 15,
     1914</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute>Dear Dr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Your kind letter<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> has
    thoroughly revitalized me in my hermitage. The recovery of heart and nerves progresses daily,
    and nothing is more beautiful than this feeling of strength with which one can await what is to
    come and take delight in the greatest difficulties and adversities with the greatest fighter.
    Every line of yours continues to sharpen the picture of our time to me a few shades. But most
    splendid of all is the awareness and joy of being able to contribute a little stone to the dam
    against the flow of mud of wicked and less worthy people (above all: the disingenuous). Now you
    yourself have the blessed certainty that your work is spreading, that slowly but inexorably the
    effects are disseminating, that friends from all parts come with fiery hearts and the desire to
    help, and that your work <tei:pb n="2"/> pierces ever more sharply the eyes of the dishonest,
    these demented art degenerates. Even <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>
    will come to this realization. If there are at first some who spring from your well then it will
    continue to grow, and a knighthood of the holy grail (but not a pitiful or teary-eyed, rather a
    bold and fierce one) will arise, which will uproot the modern magic garden. Triumph! –</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Your experience with the <tei:rs key="entity-003270" type="organization">Vienna Concert Hall Society</tei:rs> yet again speaks volumes. What a pitiful, stupid bunch of
    people. The best part of it though is your position, with which you outmatched all the pettiness
    and bitterness. How one will later lament! To all of us the consoling awareness remains, that
    the <tei:rs key="entity-000871" type="person">Strauss</tei:rs>es, <tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person">Reger</tei:rs>s and <tei:rs key="entity-000556" type="person">Mahler</tei:rs>s,
    despite all the imaginable "advances," despite all the desperate praise and monuments and titles
    and gold pieces, will shortly be pulled aside. History is hard and <tei:pb n="3"/> unerring. The
    truth will be instructive for later generations; but they will stand by their great masters just
    as blindly as they do today and as they always have. I have just read <tei:rs key="entity-000799" type="person">Schopenhauer</tei:rs> on "<tei:title>Fame, Criticism,
     etc.</tei:title>"<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> and found everything so clear
    and necessary, that greatness even requires time and that the house of cards of quotidian fame
    collapses on itself when the winds blows in.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Here the streams flow into the writing of this letter and everything is so
    endlessly immersed in beauty, that something wholly wonderful and mildly conciliatory gathers
    around the heart. But we can <tei:add place="interlinear-above">really</tei:add> only ally
    ourselves with beauty and good friendship, therefore the fight goes on if we are there again,
    where our foes live and dissipate.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Wishing you the best recovery and renewal of vigor, I remain with the warmest
    greetings </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">and thanks,</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50">Ihr <tei:rs key="entity-000149" type="person">Walter
     Dahms</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>