<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3499" sdoID="OJ-14-10_32">OJ 14/10, [32]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RW" scope="sole">Rosa Weil's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008456">WeilR ~
        JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Rosa Weil to Jeanette Schenker, dated February 11,
        1938</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1938-02-11T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-08-01</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Rosa and Arnold Weil are planning to holiday again imminently in Hofgastein. –
        Jeanette’s last letter was melancholic and complained of eye trouble. – Rosa alludes to
        their “fears” without enlarging, and later to “troubles." – She reports Lene’s uncertainty
        as to whether to enter medical practice, and also on a further death in the family and its
        impact.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000944">Rosa Weil</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RW"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002248"
            >Aussig</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1938-02-11">11. Feber 1938</tei:date>.</tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>Meine liebe <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
          >Schwester</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs>s kurze
          Nachricht<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-10_31">OJ 14/10, [31]</tei:ref>, postcard of February
          2, 1938. — All paragraph-breaks in this edition are editorial, usually prompted by an
          endash in the original followed by continuation.</tei:note> wirst Du wohl erhalten haben
        und ich bekenne mich ohneweiteres schuldig; obwohl ich einen in jeder Hinsicht recht
        schlechten Winter hatte, wäre es wiederholt möglich gewesen, Dir eine ausführlichere
        Nachricht gekommen zu lassen! Nur, und dies wäre meine einzige Rechtfertigung, ich mag es
        nun einmal nicht und trachte nach Thunlichkeit zu vermeiden, daß sich meine gedrückte
        Stimmung in meinen Briefen bemerkbar macht, mit anderen Worten, es darf niemand eingejammert
        werden. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Deinen großen Brief<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Jeanette
          annotated the postcard <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-10_31">OJ 14/10,
            [31]</tei:ref>, February 2, 1938, from Arnold, to indicate that she had answered it, but
          instead of the date she inserted some indecipherable shorthand.</tei:note> haben wir
        selbstverständlich erhalten und gut aufbewahrt; nur <tei:pb n="2"/> darfst Du nicht darauf
        bestehen, daß Dir das frühere Schreiben so umgebend zürückgeschickt wird.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Arnold’s postcard <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-10_31">OJ 14/10, [31]</tei:ref> refers to Jeanette’s
          previous letter as having two inclosures, one of which must have been an earlier letter
          from Rosa.</tei:note> Die Sachen sind alle in sicherer Verwahrung, ich gehe <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs> niemals über diese Mappen und er selbst
        ist gerade zur Zeit des Jahresschlusses und Beginnes derart in Anspruch genommen, daß ihm
        kaum Zeit zum aufatmen bleibt. Am Abend ist er rechtschaffen müde und ein bißl Zeit braucht
        der Mensch auch für sich selbst. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Gesundheitlich war auch bei ihm meist immer alles in schönster Ordnung und so bin ich
        froh und glücklich, daß er sich endlich überreden ließ, kommenden Samstag einen Urlaub für
        drei Wochen anzutreten. Wir wollen wieder nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-006026"
          >Hofgastein</tei:rs>, erwarten Antwort vom Hause Moser, wo wir um szt. so wohlgefühlt
        waren. Eine weitere Reise wäre zu ermüdend, <tei:pb n="3"/> wir suchen schöne Landschaft,
        (hoffentlich Winterlandsch<tei:supplied reason="abbreviation">aft</tei:supplied>) gute,
        reine Luft, Ruhe, Ruhe und noch einmal Ruhe und guten, gesunden Schlaf. Hoffen wir, daß wir
        nicht gerade in eine Regenperiode geraten, so ein Schneesturm wie heute, wäre gerade auch
        nicht angenehm, doch die Hauptsache bleibt für <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943"
          >Arnold</tei:rs> das Ausspannen. – Der Winter kehrt noch einmal zurück und Du willst jetzt
        schon nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-008462">Gries</tei:rs>, wo doch gerade in Wien
        der Frühling so wunderschön ist? –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Aus Deinem Brief klingt sehr viel wehmühige Stimmung sodaß ich Dich fragen muß, ob Du
        gesundheitlich nicht ganz zufrieden bist? – Das mit dem Auge muß Dich nicht allzu sehr
        beunruhigen; seit Jahren hat <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs>
        dasselbe mit dem linken Auge, ist damit unter ständiger ärztlicher Kontrolle. Der Zustand
        hat sich nicht verschlimmert und er muß doch weiß Gott seine armen Augen sehr
        anstrengen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> Wie das Leben jetzt ist und wie und was man von einem Tag zum anderen
        fürchtet, muß ich Dir nicht erzählen:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial"
          place="foot">We must recall that the German annexation of Austria was precisely one month
          away, with the seizure of Vienna only four days beyond that, while annexation of
          Czechoslovakia was still a year away.</tei:note> – Meinen Kindern geht es G. <tei:unclear
          reason="uncertain">L.</tei:unclear> gut leider haben sie einen <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">N</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">n</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>ervenzermürbenden Beruf.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial"
          place="foot">“Meinen Kindern”: presumably Lene and her husband Max, both of whom were in
          the medical profession.</tei:note> Im Frühjahr richten wir endlich eine schöne moderne,
        ganz comfortable Wohnung ein; ob sich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005248"
          >Lene</tei:rs> je für Praxis entschließen wird? Wir fragen und drängen nicht, das haben
        wir nie getan; noch arb<tei:supplied>eitet</tei:supplied> sie an der Klinik, ihre Liebe galt
        immer nur der Wissenchaft, nicht der Praxis. – Nimm vielen Dank für Deine gute Absicht,
        immer der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005248">Lene</tei:rs> eine Freude machen zu
        wollen, wie kommt sie wohl dazu?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >“wie … dazu“: perhaps she is questioning whether Lene will be able similarly to thank
          Jeanette.</tei:note> Wie Du weißt, laufen bei uns die Fäden der ganzen Familienereigniße
        zusammen; die arme <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003920">Hella</tei:rs> lebt ja jetzt in
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-005333">Teplitz</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07"
          type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-10_34">OJ 14/10,
            [34]</tei:ref> gives her address as: Teplitz-Schönau, Königstraße 19. </tei:note> wo
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005060">Lotte</tei:rs> ihre Stellung hat und neulich
        gerade am <tei:date when="1938-02-01">1. Feber</tei:date> kam die Nachricht von ihres Mannes
        plötzlichem Ableben im Eisenbahnabteil infolge Herzschlages. Das gab viel Aufregung, <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-003920">Hella</tei:rs> lag gerade mit Angina, <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-005060">Lotte</tei:rs> fuhr allein nach <tei:unclear
          reason="reading">Pravintz</tei:unclear>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Possibly Pravenec, now in Slovakia. </tei:note> sie hat den Vater dennoch
        heiß geliebt. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs> kann ihr in manchem
        behilflich sein. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000782">Paul</tei:rs> lebt mit der
        Familie wieder in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002892">Prag</tei:rs> man hat ihm seine
        Einkünfte reduziert, weit unter das Minimum.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">p. 4, in right margin, sideways:</tei:note>
        Wo man hinschaut, gibt es Sorgen und alle<tei:supplied reason="omission">i</tei:supplied>n
        kann man nicht alle Sorgen abnehmen, man ist älter geworden es kann nur noch bergab
        gehen!</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">p. 2, in right margin, sideways:</tei:note>
        Recht gute Reise, gutes Wetter, angenehmen Aufenthalt und sehr gute Erholung!</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">p. 4, in left margin, sideways:</tei:note>
        Ich hoffe, der Brief erreicht Dich noch,</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>sei recht herzlich gegrüßt von uns allen! </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>Deine</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000944">Rosa</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RW"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002248"
            >Aussig</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1938-02-11">February 11,
          1938</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">sister</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">You will probably have received <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943"
          >Arnold</tei:rs>‘s brief communication,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
        and without more ado, I acknowledge my guilt. Although I had in every respect a really bad
        winter, it would have been repeatedly possible to have sent you more detailed news! Only –
        and this would be my sole justification – I simply couldn’t do it, and I strove after
        expediency to avoid my depressed voice coming through in my letters; in other words, no one
        should be subjected to whinging. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>We have of course received and greatly treasured your long letter.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> But <tei:pb n="2"/> you did not need to insist on
        returning our earlier letter to you so promptly.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
          type="footnote"/> The items are all in secure safekeeping, I never go to Arnold over these
        folders, and at the end and beginning of the year he himself is so occupied that he scarcely
        has time to draw a breath. In the evening he is downright tired and the man needs a little
        time for himself. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>He was almost always in the best of shape as regards his health, and so I am happy and
        fortunate that he is finally allowing himself to be persuaded to embark on a holiday this
        coming Saturday for three weeks. We want <tei:supplied reason="clarity">to go</tei:supplied>
        again to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-006026">Hofgastein</tei:rs>, and are awaiting an
        answer from the Moser House, where we were previously so warmly welcomed. Any further travel
        would be too tiring, <tei:pb n="3"/> we are seeking beautiful landscape (hopefully winter
        landscape), good, pure air, rest, rest, and still more rest, and good, healthy sleep. We are
        hoping it will not turn out to be right in a rainy period, nor would a snow storm like today
        be pleasant, but the main thing remains for Arnold to spread his wings. With winter
        returning yet again, you want now, so soon, <tei:supplied reason="clarity">to be
          heading</tei:supplied> to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-008462">Gries</tei:rs>,
        precisely when in Vienna spring is so wonderful? –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Your letter is so steeped in melancholy that I feel compelled to ask you: Are you
        entirely happy with your health? – The trouble with your eye can’t be troubling you all that
        much. For years Arnold had the same with the left eye and is therefore under constant
        medical observation. The condition has not worsened and he must, God knows, put his poor
        eyes under very severe strain.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> I must not regale you with what life is, and what and how much we have
        to fear from one day to the next:<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> – My
        children are, thank God, well, though they unfortunately have an nerve-racking
          vocation.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> Early this year, we will finally
        be making ready an elegant, modern, amply comfortable dwelling. Will <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-005248">Lene</tei:rs> ever decide for <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
          >medical</tei:supplied> practice? We don’t ask or press <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
          >her</tei:supplied>; we’ve never done that; she is still working at the Clinic; her heart
        is always in the science alone, not the practice. – Thank you very much for your good
        intention always to aim at giving pleasure to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005248"
          >Lene</tei:rs>
        <tei:supplied>–</tei:supplied> how will she ever get round to that?<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> As you know, with us the threads of our entire
        family events run together; poor <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003920">Hella</tei:rs>
        now lives in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-005333">Teplitz</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> where <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005060"
          >Lotte</tei:rs> has her place, and recently the news came precisely on <tei:date
          when="1938-02-01">February 1</tei:date> of her husband’s sudden death by a heart attack in
        a railway compartment. That caused much agitation: <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003920"
          >Hella</tei:rs> was struck down by angina, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005060"
          >Lotte</tei:rs> went off alone to <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear"
          >Pravintz</tei:unclear>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/> she nevertheless
        loved her father passionately. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs> can
        help her in many ways. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000782">Paul</tei:rs> is again
        living with his family in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002892">Prague</tei:rs>; his
        earnings have been reduced to well below the minimum.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">p. 4, in right margin, sideways:</tei:note>
        Wherever you look – there are troubles, and one cannot remove all troubles on one’s own –
        one has become older, and things can only go downhill!</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">p. 2, in right margin, sideways:</tei:note>
        <tei:supplied>We wish you</tei:supplied> a very good journey, good weather, a pleasant
        sojourn, and full recuperation!</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">p. 4, in left margin, sideways:</tei:note> I
        hope this letter will reach you.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Sincerely heartfelt greetings from us all!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000944">Rosa</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>
    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
