<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"
  xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker"
  xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="1568" sdoID="OJ-10-3_42">OJ 10/3, [42]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPunk" scope="major">unknown typist</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="OED" scope="minor">Otto Erich Deutsch's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
      <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2015</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2015</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2015</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2015-09-18" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002726">DeutschOE ~ H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002712">DeutschOE ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002727">DeutschOE+H ~ H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Typewritten letter from Deutsch to Schenker, dated November 6, 1925</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1925-11-06T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2015-09-18</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Deutsch informs Schenker that due to space constraints the editors have (without Deutsch's prior
        knowledge) cut the first four paragraphs of Schenker's article, leaving only the last two paragraphs, which
        refer particularly to Schubert. He asks Schenker to agree to this cut, but also offers him the option of
        removing his article so that it can be used in full elsewhere. Deutsch asks Schenker to look at a Beethoven
        manuscript at Heck's.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000164">DeutschOE</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000163">DeutschH</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:fw type="header" rend="inline">
          <tei:note type="editorial">printed letterhead:</tei:note>
          <tei:handShift new="#printed"/>OTTO ERICH DEUTSCH</tei:fw>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-75">WIEN II.</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-75">Böcklinstrasse 26</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#TPunk"/><tei:date when="1925-11-06">6. Nov.
          25</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor</tei:rs>!<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at
            OJ 3/8, p. 2887 (November 7, 1925): "Von O. E. Deutsch (Br.): die Redaktion habe ihm die peinliche
            Ueberraschung bereitet, den Aufsatz bis auf die letzten beiden Absätze zu kürzen. Er macht auf ein
            Beethoven-Manuscript bei Heck aufmerksam." ("From O. E. Deutsch (letter): the editors have given him the
            painful surprise of having abbreviated my essay to the two final paragraphs. He alerts <tei:supplied
              reason="clarity">me</tei:supplied> to a Beethoven manuscript at Heck's.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Für die Korrektur Ihres Beitrages sage ich Ihnen besten Dank. Ich hatte doch einen Druckfehler
        übersehen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Nun erfuhr ich heute zu meiner peinlichen Ueberra<tei:add place="inline" hand="#OED"
          >s</tei:add>chung, dass man in der Redaktion von Ihrem Beitrag die ersten vier Absätze gestrichen habe, so
        dass nur die letzten zwei übrig bleiben, die sich auf <tei:rs key="entity-000803" type="person"
          >Schubert</tei:rs> besonders beziehen. Ich bin darüber sehr traurig, kann aber keinen Einspruch erheben,da es
        technisch notwendig war. Wir haben für diese Abteilung nur 1 Seite Raum, die trotz eines, mir erlaubten,
        Striches im Zitat <tei:rs key="entity-000563" type="person">Thomas Mann</tei:rs>s (auf die Hälfte) <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above" hand="#OED">endlich</tei:add> durch einen kleinen Beitrag von <tei:rs
          key="entity-000732" type="person">Moritz Rosenthal</tei:rs>, der noch in letzter Stunde eintraf, so stark in
        Anspruch genommen ist, dass für Ihren Artikel eben nicht mehr Platz als etwa für die beiden anderen
        Musiker-Bekenntnisse bleibt. Ausser <tei:rs key="entity-000563" type="person">Thomas Mann</tei:rs>, der noch
        immer die halbe Seite fast einnimmt, ist für die anderen Beiträger: Sie, <tei:rs key="entity-000722"
          type="person">Rolland</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furt-</tei:rs>
        <tei:pb n="2"/>
        <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">wängler</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000732" type="person"
          >Rosenthal</tei:rs> nur ein Platz von je 10 Zeilen cca. geblieben.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich bitte Sie daher um Ihre nachträgliche Zustimmung zu dieser Kürzung, die Ihren Gedankengang
        zwar verstümmelt, aber nicht unverständlich macht. Sollten Sie aber <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          hand="#OED">jedoch</tei:add> keineswegs zu dieser Streichung Ja und Amen sagen wollen, so werde ich den
        Beitrag natürlich nicht bringen und er stünde Ihnen zu anderweitigen Benützung frei, wobei ich Sie nur zu bitten
        hätte, die etwa unn<tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overwritten" hand="#OED">ü</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#OED">ö</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>tige oder überflüssige Bemühung gütigst zu entschuldigen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Das Manuskript sende ich Ihnen jedenfalls anbei mit Dank zurück.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:hi rend="underline">NB.</tei:hi> Wenn Sie bei <tei:rs key="entity-000345" type="person"
          >Heck</tei:rs> am Kärnt<tei:supplied reason="spelling">n</tei:supplied>erring vorbeikommen, sehen Sie sich,
        bitte, ein interessantes Jugend-Manuskript von <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs> an,
        mit Berufung auf mich. Es ist eine kleine kirchliche Komposition, die wahrscheinlich während seiner Studienzeit
        in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> schon gemacht worden ist. Die Handschrift ist aufs
        Erste befremdend, ich glaube aber doch, sie ist nicht zweifelhaft.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-15">Mit schönen Grüssen von Haus zu Haus</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr sehr ergebener</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000164">Otto Erich
            Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:fw type="header" rend="inline">
          <tei:note type="editorial">printed letterhead:</tei:note>
          <tei:handShift new="#printed"/>OTTO ERICH DEUTSCH</tei:fw>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-75">VIENNA II</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-75">Böcklinstrasse 26</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#TPunk"/><tei:date when="1925-11-06">November 6,
            1925</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
              >Schenker</tei:supplied></tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">I thank you very much for proofreading your article. I had still overlooked one
        misprint.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Now I learned today, to my painful surprise, that one of the editors has cut the first four
        paragraphs of your article, so that only the last two remain, which refer in particular to <tei:rs
          key="entity-000803" type="person">Schubert</tei:rs>. I am very sad about this, but cannot raise an objection,
        as it was technically necessary. For this section we have only one page of space, and despite me <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above" hand="#OED">finally</tei:add> being allowed to cut the <tei:rs key="entity-000563"
          type="person">Thomas Mann</tei:rs> quotation (by half), due to a small article by <tei:rs key="entity-000732"
          type="person">Moritz Rosenthal</tei:rs>, which arrived at the eleventh hour, as much is claimed; and so there
        remains no more room for your article than there is for the other two musicians' statements. With the exception
        of <tei:rs key="entity-000563" type="person">Thomas Mann</tei:rs>, who still takes up almost half the page,
          <tei:pb n="2"/> only about ten lines each remain for the other contributors (yourself, <tei:rs
          key="entity-000722" type="person">Rolland</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person"
          >Furtwängler</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000732" type="person">Rosenthal</tei:rs>). </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I therefore ask for your retrospective agreement to this abbreviation, which mutilates your
        line of argument but does not obscure it. Should you in no way want to say "Yes, and Amen" to this cut, I will
        naturally not publish your contribution and you would be free to use it elsewhere, in which case I would only
        ask you to kindly accept my apologies for the unnecessary or superfluous effort.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I am sending the manuscript back to you in any case, with gratitude.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:hi rend="underline">NB.</tei:hi> If you pass <tei:rs key="entity-000345" type="person"
          >Heck</tei:rs> on the Kärntner Ring, please have a look at an interesting manuscript of the young <tei:rs
          key="entity-000055" type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs>, saying that I asked you to do so. It is a short sacred
        composition, which was probably dates from as early as the time of his studies in <tei:rs key="entity-002484"
          type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>. The handwriting seems at first sight to be strange, but I believe its
        authenticity is not in doubt.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-15">With best greetings from house to house,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Yours very truly,</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000164">Otto Erich
            Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
