<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2769" sdoID="OJ-11-36_19">OJ 11/36, [19]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="VH" scope="sole">Viktor Hammer's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="HS-SP">
      <tei:persName>Hedi Siegel &amp; Stephanie Probst</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2022</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2011-02-12" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006186">HammerV ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Hammer to Schenker, dated September 1, 1925</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1925-09-01T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2022-06-16</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Hammer explains why he can't just take the test print of his Schenker
        mezzotint as the final product. -- He speaks of money difficulties.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000327">Viktor Hammer</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#VH"/><tei:date when="1925-09-01">1. IX.
            25</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Lieber Doktor <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Schenker</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for September 2, 1925: “Von Hammer (Br.):
            brauche Geld – wie verwerten?” (“From Hammer (letter): says he needs money – how to turn
              <tei:supplied reason="clarity">it</tei:supplied> to
          account?”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Sehr schönen Dank für Ihren lieben Brief.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
          place="foot">= <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="JOB-94-3_12">JOB 94-3, [12]</tei:ref>,
          August 23, 1925.</tei:note> Dass Sie den Versucher spielen und mir die Worte des Schöpfers
        in den Mund legen wie die Schlange im Paradiese, das ist ein ungewöhnliches Schauspiel. Doch
        nett und verständlich von Ihnen. Aber es dreht sich da um Dinge die rein technisch sauberer
        und noch besser gemacht werden können und da ich die erste Platte nicht zerstöre sondern
        eine zweite, neue mache so ist das wieder eine von der Arbeiten von mir, wo ich mir in
        meiner Sachlichkeit wieder einmal nicht genug tun kann und lieber 3 Wochen Zeit mehr an die
        Arbeit wende nur damit ich mir nicht sagen muß ich <tei:hi rend="underline">hätte</tei:hi>
        es besser machen können.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Hammer
          writes continuously at this point, without paragraph-break.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Damit rühr ich an einen <tei:pb n="2"/> Zustand den ich Ihnen doch einmal und gerade
        jetzt klarlegen möchte, da Sie mir vielleicht in etwas helfen können. Er ist freilich so
        uralt und bekannt und trotzdem falsch, übel und ungerecht. Nämlich mir gehts so scheußlich
        jetzt wiedereinmal mit dem Geld zusammen wie seit vielen Jahren nicht – na Sie haben ja auch
        Kenntnis von den Dingen. Bei mir sind’s halt immer grad <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >die</tei:hi> Gaben und Kräfte in mir welche meiner Arbeit als solcher zu gut kommen aber
        mir diese stets unrentabel machen. Sie sehn’s ja selber ich kann mir selten genug thun ich
        kann einfach nicht sagen, da habt’s jetzt die Platte vom D<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
          >r.</tei:hi> Schenker sie ist gut und so wie sie ist müsst ihr sie pressen. Sondern ich
        selber weiß und muß wissen wann ich sagen darf: besser kann ich es nicht machen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> Dass es mir nicht gut geht find ich selbstverständlich, aber dass mich
        der Geldmangel an einer consequenten Arbeit hindert das thut mir doch leid und wollte ich
        gerne abstellen. Ich komme mir vor wie ein Kaufmann der mit zu wenig Kapital arbeitet und
        stets in Schwierigkeiten ist deswegen so ein Geschäft kann nicht rentabel sein. Um aber aus
        dieser abstrakten Sphäre des Jammern zu kommen: Was glauben Sie wie könnt ich das Blatt am
        besten verwerten? Soll ich es zu <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002413"
          >Artaria</tei:rs> geben oder in einen Verlag wie <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002890">Breitkopf</tei:rs> oder ganz privat verhandeln? Unter Ihren Freunden
          z.B.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Hammer writes continuously
          at this point, without paragraph-break.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Dann noch was. Wissen Sie jemand der die Zeichnung welche ich für den Schabstich
        gemacht habe, kaufen würde?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Hammer originally told Schenker he wanted to keep the drawing for himself; he outlined
          his plans for the drawing, plate, and prints during the last sitting for the portrait on
          June 26, 1924. See the diary entry on that date, quoted in footnote 1 to Hammer’s postcard
          of June 17, 1924 (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-11-36_16">OJ 11/36,
            [16]</tei:ref>).</tei:note> Ich verlange 600 öst. Schillinge dafür. Als
        Originalzeichnung ist es nicht so viel denk ich und behält doch ihren Wert. — ich komme <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">mitte</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="inline">2te Hälfte</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>
        <tei:date rend="underline">Septem-</tei:date>
        <tei:pb n="4"/>
        <tei:date rend="underline">ber</tei:date> nach Wien, wir können dann über diese Sachen
        reden. Nicht?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker’s reply is
            <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="JOB-94-3_13">JOB 94-3, [13]</tei:ref>, September 8,
          1925.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002586">England</tei:rs> war künstlerisch
        ein großer Erfolg, habe sehr schöne ungewöhnlich gute Kritiken, doch gar keinen Auftrag. 3
        Monate nichts getan, Geld ausgegeben und nichts nach Haus bringen, bringt einem leicht um.
        Doch geh ich wieder zurück im Frühjahr. </tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">1000 Grüße verehrter Meister </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">stets Ihr treuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs key="entity-000327" type="person"
          >Hammer</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-30"><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-008188">St. Martin im
              Innkr.</tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#VH"/><tei:date when="1925-09-01"
            >September 1, 1925</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dear Dr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Schenker</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Very many thanks for your kind letter.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/>
        Your playing the role of the tempter and putting the words of the Creator in my mouth like
        the serpent in paradise – that’s an unusual spectacle. Yet how nice and understanding of
        you. But what I’m talking about are things that from a purely technical point of view could
        be cleaner and could be done even better. Since I am not destroying the first plate but am
        making a second new one, this turns out to be another one of my works for which I can’t do
        enough, in a substantive sense. I would rather work on it for three more weeks, if only to
        avoid telling myself I <tei:hi rend="underline">could have</tei:hi> improved it.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>With that I touch on a <tei:pb n="2"/> situation I would like to tell you about at this
        point, and especially now, since you could perhaps help me with something. To be sure, it’s
        an age-old and common situation and yet it is false, evil, and unjust. Namely, I am once
        again having dreadful money troubles, worse than for many years – well, you surely also have
        some experience with such things. In my case it is always precisely <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >those</tei:hi> of my gifts and strengths that, as such, benefit my work but always make
        it unprofitable. You can see for yourself that I can seldom satisfy myself, I can’t simply
        say: There’s the plate for Dr. Schenker’s portrait, it’s good enough and you must print it
        just as it is. Rather, I myself know and must know when I can say: I can’t do any better
        than that.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> It goes without saying that I don’t do well financially but I hate to
        feel that lack of money hampers me in doing important work, and it’s something I would like
        to avoid. I feel like a merchant who works with insufficient capital and is in constant
        difficulties; consequently, such a business can’t be profitable. But now let’s leave this
        abstract realm of whining behind: What do you think would be the best way for me to profit
        from the print? Should I give it to <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002413"
          >Artaria</tei:rs> or to a publisher like <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002890"
          >Breitkopf</tei:rs>, or should I only negotiate privately? Among your friends, for
          instance.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Then there’s something else. Do you know someone who would like to buy the drawing that
        I made for the mezzotint?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> I would ask 600
        Austrian shillings for it. I think that’s not so much for an original drawing, which after
        all would retain its value. I will come to Vienna in <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">mid-</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="inline">the second half of</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>
        <tei:date when="1925-09">September</tei:date>; <tei:pb n="4"/> we can talk about these
        things then, can’t we?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002586">England</tei:rs> was a great
        success artistically, I had very nice and unusually good reviews, but not a single
        commission. Doing nothing for three months, spending money and not bringing anything home,
        can easily become deadly. Yet I am going back again in the Spring.</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">A thousand greetings, revered master,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">your ever faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs key="entity-000327" type="person"
          >Hammer</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-30"><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-008188">St. Martin im
              Innkreis</tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
