<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="260" sdoID="OJ-15-16_41">OJ 15/16, [41]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HW" scope="sole">Hans Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="AH">
   <tei:persName>Alison Hiley</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2008</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML encoding, 2010</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-12-02" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~ H+JSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   
   

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated "end of June, 1920"</dc:title>
   
   <dcterms:created>1920-06-24T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-03-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Taking his leave of Schenker as a pupil, Weisse expresses his gratitude for all
    that Schenker has done for his artistic and human development, and declares himself ready to
    continue in the service of his teacher's highest ideals. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Dankbarkeit; gratitude; Abschied; farewell; Künstler; artist; Meister; Master;
    Führerschaft; leadership; Meisterschaft; mastery; Schüler; pupil; Entwicklung; development;
    Ziel; goal; Lehrer; teacher; Lehre; teaching; Verehrung; admiration</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000951">Weisse</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Lieber, verehter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>


   <tei:p>Wenn<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is
     recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/1, p. 2246, June 25, 1920 [thus the letter can
     provisionally be dated June 24]: "Dr. Weisse bringt ein Facsimile von „Messias", darin
     Abschiedsbrief; vertraut mir an, daß er zu einem Mädchen eine ernste Beziehung unterhalte,
     hierbei leider auf Schwierigkeiten in seinem Elternhause stoße; will meinen Rat hören, sich
     zugleich auf mein Vorbild berufen." ("Dr. Weisse brings a facsimile of <tei:title level="m">Messiah</tei:title>; in it a farewell letter; confides to me that he is maintaining a serious
     relationship with a girl, in this connection is unfortunately meeting with difficulties with
     his parents; wants to hear my advice, drawn as he always is to me as a model."). Then on June
     28 (ibid, p. 2247) is recorded: "Weisse nimmt Abschied u. kündigt Pläne an, so Vorlesungen in
     der Urania über Einführung in die Schenker-Theorie, Veröffentlichung von Schriften: gegen
     Busoni, über Brahms op. 8 u. Volkslieder." ("Weisse takes his farewell and talks about plans to
     give lectures at the Urania on introduction to the Schenker theory, [and] publication of
     writings: against Busoni, about Brahms Op. 8 and folksongs."). Thereafter, they lunch together
     on July 1 (ibid, 2249). </tei:note> ich heute zur Feder greife, um von Ihnen, als meinem
    persönlichen Lehrer Abschied zu nehmen, so weiß ich im Vorhinein, daß es insoferne ein
    vergebliches Unternehmen darstellt, als der Fassungsraum der Sprache meiner unbegrenzten
    Empfindung der Dankbarkeit nicht zu genügen vermag. Aber doch drängt mich alles dazu, diesem
    entscheidenden Einschnitt in meinem persönlichen und künstlerischen Leben, einen wenn auch noch
     <tei:pb n="2"/> so bescheidenen Ausdruck zu verleihen. Sind Sie es doch, verehrter
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>, gewesen, der in mir den Menschen
     sowohl<tei:sic>,</tei:sic> als den Künstler geweckt und somit die Bausteine zu einer Lebensform
    gelegt hat, deren Früchtbarkeit und Segen ich von Tag zu Tag gesteigerter in mir wirksam fühle. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Mit der Erfassung Ihrer Lehre bin ich erst Mensch geworden; im täglichen Umgange mit
    Ihnen, Ihrer so hinreissenden, zielsicheren und konsequenten Individualität habe ich erst die
    Möglichkeit gewonnen, Ihr Werk in mich aufzunehmen und Ihre auf künstlerischem Gebiete noch
    nicht <tei:pb n="3"/> dagewesene Leistung bis ins Letzte zu <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">erfassen</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">würdigen</tei:add>
    </tei:subst>. Von Natur aus dem Brand'schen Motto: „Alles oder Nichts"<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Brand: reference is to the missionary zeal of
     the eponymous hero in Ibsen's verse drama – the obsessive priest who is prepared to sacrifice
     his own life and those of his wife and child for the sake of his perceived mission. </tei:note>
    zugeneigt habe ich durch Sie den Boden gefunden, einem solchen Prinzipe getreu leben zu können.
    Denn Vorsätze bleiben immer unfruchtbar im Leben, so lange die Materie des Lebens <tei:del rend="overstrike">d</tei:del> ihnen nicht adäquat ist; deshalb schätze ich den Tag, der mich
    Ihnen als Schüler zuführte, als den bestimmendsten und beglückendsten meiner Entwicklung. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Führer- und Meisterschaft ist immer geistige Vaterschaft und so sind Sie mir ein Vater ge-
     <tei:pb n="4"/> worden, dessen Person ich mit uneigennützigster, tiefster Liebe im Herz
    geschlossen habe und dessen Wirken, Wissen und Denken ich die unbegrenzteste demütigste
    Verehrung entgegenbringe. Wollten Sie nun, wo ich den unmittelbaren Verkehr mit Ihnen als
    Schüler einbüsse, auch weiterhin an meiner geistigen und künstlerischen Entwicklung teilnehmen,
    so würde ich mit Stolz darin ein Zeugnis erblicken dafür, daß Sie mich dessen nicht unwert
    halten. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Was mich selbst anbelangt, so kenne ich nur das eine Ziel, mich uneingeschränkt und gleich
     <tei:pb n="5"/> Ihnen mit Hintansetzung jedes persönlichen Interesses, in den Dienst jener
    großen Aufgabe zu stellen, die durch Sie Eingang in die Welt gefunden hat. Auf meinen
    bescheidenen Wissen und Können hoffe ich dafür beizutragen, in Ihrem Sinne Wahrheit zu
    verbreiten - und seien Sie versichert, daß ich an jedem Erfolge, der mir beschieden sein sollte,
    mit vollstem Bewußtsein erkennen werde, wie sehr ich ihn nur Ihnen zu verdanken habe. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Außerdem bitte ich Sie noch, verehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>, <tei:pb n="6"/> bei jeder Arbeit, die ich Ihnen irgendwie abnehmen
    könnte, völlig über mich zu verfügen. Ich umarme Sie mit jener Treue, Hingebung und Verehrung,
    die der Mensch nur dem Höchsten und Größten entgegenbzubringen vermag! </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Hans</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline><tei:placeName>Wien</tei:placeName>, <tei:date when="1920-06-24">Ende Juni
      20.</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Dear, revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Master</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>


   <tei:p>Today,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> as I reach for my pen in order to
    take my leave of you as my personal teacher, I know from the outset that it will be a vain
    undertaking, insofar as the range of my linguistic expression will not suffice to enable me to
    convey my boundless sense of gratitude. And yet everything compels me to lend expression,
     <tei:pb n="2"/> however modestly, to this decisive chapter in my personal and artistic life.
    You, rerevered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Master</tei:rs>, are the one who has
    awakened both the man and the artist in me, and thereby laid the building blocks for a way of
    life whose fruitfulness and blessing I feel to be increasing in effectiveness daily within me. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>It was only on grasping the import of your teaching that I found my identity as a man; and
    in my daily dealings with you and your captivating, unerring and consistent individuality, that
    I gained the possibility of absorbing your work and of <tei:pb n="3"/>
    <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">grasping</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">appreciating</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> to the full what your artistry would effect within me. Since I lean by nature
    towards Brand's motto, "all or nothing",<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> it was
    through you that I found the basis needed to remain true to such a principle. For intentions
    always remain unfulfilled in life, as long as the conditions of one's life cannot meet them; I
    therefore value the day which led me to you as your pupil as the most defining and gladdening of
    my development. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Spiritual fatherhood always comes from mastery and leadership, and it was thus that you
    became a father to me, <tei:pb n="4"/> one whom I took to my heart with the deepest and most
    selfless love and one whose influence, knowledge and thinking I approach with utmost boundless
    and humble admiration. Should you wish to continue to contribute towards my spiritual and
    artistic development, now that I am forfeiting the immediate contact with you as a pupil, I
    would proudly take that as a sign that you would not consider me unworthy of this. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>As for me, I am aware of only one goal, to place myself, unfettered <tei:pb n="5"/> and,
    like you, with disregard for all things personal, in the service of that one great task which
    has found its way into the world through you. With my modest knowledge and ability I hope to be
    able to contribute towards spreading the truth as you have revealed it--and you may be certain
    that with every bit of success that may be granted to me, I shall be fully aware how very much I
    owe it to you and only you. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Otherwise please accept, honored <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Master</tei:rs>,
     <tei:pb n="6"/> that I am fully at your disposal for any task of which I could possibly relieve
    you. I embrace you with that loyalty, devotion and admiration which a man can only show the
    greatest and best! </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Hans</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline><tei:placeName>Vienna</tei:placeName>, <tei:date when="1920-06-24">End of June
       <tei:supplied reason="clarity">19</tei:supplied>20</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>