<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2166" sdoID="OJ-15-16_101">OJ 15/16, [101]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HW" scope="major">Hans Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="minor">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2008</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-10-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006969">WeisseHa ~
        JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Hans Weisse to Jeanette Schenker, dated October 22,
        1935</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1935-10-22T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-01-09</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Weisse thanks Jeanette for the photographs of her husband, and will distribute
        them to his pupils soon, when he sends the next payment of financial support that he has
        collected from them on her behalf. — He is actively engaged in bringing Schenker's ideas to
        an English-speaking audience, and urges her to consider agreeing to a suitably shortened
        version of Harmonielehre, rather than a word-for-word translation. — For Der freie Satz, an
        English translation would do more harm to Schenker's cause than not to have it translated at
        all, and it would be necessary to reconceive the presentation of the theory entirely,
        especially with respect to terminology. — He suggests that there may be a market for
        Schenker's library in American universities and libraries.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Bild; photograph; Sendung; [financial] payment; Unterricht; teaching; Neuauflage;
        new edition; gekürzt; abridged; abbreviated; Fassung; version; Kürzung; abbreviation;
        Handexemplar; working copy; Übersetzung; translation; Leserschaft; readership; Sprachgeist;
        language; eindeutig; unambiguous; Übertragung; transmission; präzis; precise; Malerei;
        painting; hörbar; audible; Verbreitung; dissemination; Lehre; theory; Namengebung; naming;
        Philosophie; philosophy; Geologie; geology; Hörwelt; auditory world; Mataphysik;
        metaphysics; vag; vague; Notenbeilage; appendix of music examples; Darstellung;
        presentation; Kommentar; commentary; Publikation; publication; Chaos; Widerspruch;
        contradiction; Bibliothek; library</dc:subject>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:fw type="envelope">
          <tei:note type="editorial"><tei:hi rend="bold">Envelope:</tei:hi>
          </tei:note><tei:lb/>
          <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="recto"/><tei:lb/>
          <tei:address>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#HW"/><tei:hi rend="underline">S. S.
                Normandie</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
          </tei:address>
          <tei:address>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied reason="clarity">An:</tei:supplied> Frau D<tei:hi
                rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi>. Heinrich Schenker</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine rend="indent-20">Hasenauerstrasse 12</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine rend="indent-40">Wien XIX.</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:hi rend="underline">Austria</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
          </tei:address>
          <tei:add resp="JS"><tei:handShift new="#JS"/><tei:supplied reason="clarity"
              >received?:</tei:supplied>
            <tei:date when="1935-10-30">30. X. 35</tei:date></tei:add><tei:lb/>
          <tei:add resp="JS">beantw. <tei:date when="1935-11-08">8. XI. 35</tei:date></tei:add><tei:lb/>
          <tei:fw type="postmark">|| NEW YORK N.Y. | OCT 23 9‒AM | 1935 ||</tei:fw><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
          <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="verso"/>
          <tei:address>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied reason="clarity">Absender:</tei:supplied>
              <tei:handShift new="#HW"/>D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi> H. Weisse, 1
                64<tei:hi rend="supralinear">th</tei:hi>
              <tei:supplied reason="identity">Street</tei:supplied> New York City </tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine>U. S. A.</tei:addrLine>
          </tei:address><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        </tei:fw>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold">Letter:</tei:hi>
        </tei:note><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002873">New York</tei:rs>,
            <tei:date when="1935-10-22">22. Oktober 35</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Liebe <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Frau Lie-Lie</tei:rs>,<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">This is Weisse's last surviving letter
            to Jeanette Schenker. Her reply, dated November 8, is not known to survive. The only
            subsequent items of Weisse correspondence are: OJ 70/46, [12], December 21, 1935 (Weisse
            to Moriz Violin), OJ 36/73, [1], June 18, 1938 (Jonas to Weisse), OJ 36/246, [6], July
            17, 1938 (Weisse to Jonas), and OJ 36/73, [2], August 15, 1938 (Jonas to
            Weisse).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Ich bestätige dankend den Empfang der Bilder, die von meinen Schülern mit Rührung
        empfangen werden.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">A photograph of
          Heinrich Schenker, which Jeanette had reproduced for each of Weisse's pupils who had
          contributed a sum of money toward an annuity for her for the year 1935/36.</tei:note>
        Noch hatte ich nicht Gelegenheit alle zu verteilen, weil der Unterricht erst kürzlich
        begonnen hat. Dies ist auch der Grund, weshalb ich die zweite Sendung,<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Weisse had made a first "quarterly"
          payment at the end of May; see Weisse's letter <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-15-16_98">OJ 15/16, [98]</tei:ref> of May 26, 1935, in which he describes how
          he conceived and set up the fund.</tei:note> die bis zum Jahresende für die Monate
        Oktober–Dezember gelten soll, nicht schicken konnte. Doch werde ich das in Bälde in Angriff
        nehmen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich habe, so weit ich mich erinnere in meinem letzten Brief an Sie<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">= <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-15-16_100">OJ 15/16, [100]</tei:ref>, September 18, 1935.</tei:note> die Frage
        der Neuauflage der <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724"
            ><tei:title>Harmonielehre</tei:title></tei:rs> nicht berührt, möchte mich aber dazu
        jetzt kurz äussern. Ich glaube, das Buch müsste erscheinen. Die Frage einer gekürzten
        Fassung ist freilich eine delikate Angelegenheit und ich verstehe Ihren Standpunkt durchaus,
        der Sie zuerst kurzerhand nein dazu hat sagen lassen. <tei:del rend="overstrike"
          >Bei</tei:del> Nach reiflicher Überlegung jedoch glaube ich, dass eine Kürzung vielleicht
        doch taktvoll zu machen wäre und dass es vielleicht möglich wäre, die im Handexemplar des
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>s hinzugekommenen Bemerkungen
        der neuen Ausgabe einzuverleiben und die Kürzung trotzdem sich <tei:pb n="2"/> auswirken zu
        lassen. Die Frage ist, ob das völlige, dauernde Verschwinden des Buches vom Markte <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">der Sache</tei:add> nicht schädlicher ist, als etwaige
        Kürzungen, die doch selbstverständlich nur Unwesentliches betreffen dürften. Ich lese Ihren
        diesbezüglichen Brief jetzt grade noch einmal durch,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05"
          type="editorial" place="foot">No letters from Jeanette to Weisse at this period are known
          to survive. We know only, from her annotations to Weisse's envelopes, that she wrote to
          him on June 9 and August 10, and replied to the previous and current letters on November
          8, 1935. — For a full account of initiatives to republish and to translate <tei:title
            level="m">Harmonielehre</tei:title>, see <tei:bibl><tei:author>Robert
            Wason</tei:author>, <tei:title level="a">From <tei:hi rend="italic"
                >Harmonielehre</tei:hi> to <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmony</tei:hi>: Schenker's Theory
              of Harmony and its Americanization,</tei:title> in <tei:title level="m">Essays from
              the Fourth International Schenker Symposium</tei:title>, vol. I, ed. <tei:editor>Allen
              Cadwallader</tei:editor> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms Verlag, 2008), pp. 213‒58, esp. pp.
            231‒33</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> kann aber daraus nicht entnehmen, worauf sich die <tei:del
          rend="overstrike">Ab</tei:del>Kürzung beziehen sollte?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wenn die <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">U. E.</tei:rs> verlangte, dass
        das Buch gleich um die Hälfte kürzer sein soll, dann hatten Sie gewiss Recht. Im Prinzip
        aber meine ich sollte man sich nur von rein sachlichen Argumenten leiten lassen und nicht
        allzu sklavisch an dem Buchstaben hängen. Vielleicht hatte ich früher nie so gedacht – aber
        die Tatsache, dass ich mich ernstlich mit dem Unternehmen beschäftige, das Werk Schenkers
        dem englischen Sprachgeist einzuverleiben, hat mich dazu geführt. Nach monatelanger
        intensivster Beschäftigung mit <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title>dem freien
            Satz</tei:title></tei:rs> ist mir durchaus klar geworden, dass eine wörtliche
        Übersetzung des Buches unmöglich ist und dass der, der diesen Versuch unternehmen würde, das
        Buch <tei:add place="interlinear-above">einer englischen Leserschaft</tei:add> noch mehr
        unzugänglich machen würde, als wenn er es gar nicht übersetzt hatte. Kein einziger der
        Termini (soweit es überhaupt englische Worte dafür gibt) <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">sagt</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">könnte</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>
        <tei:del rend="overstrike">etwas</tei:del> im englischen Sprachgeist Aufgewachsenen <tei:pb
          n="3"/> etwas Eindeutiges, etwas Vorstellbares bedeuten. Mir ist klar geworden, dass um
        der Idee zu liebe, die für die Menschheit von grösster Bedeutung ist, eine Übertragung in’s
        Englische nur möglich ist, wenn die Lehre aus dem englischen Sprachgeist neu wiedergeboren
        wird. Das bedeutet ein völliges Abwenden vom Buchstaben, vom Einzelwort – und Ausdruck und
        verlangt als Ersatz für jeden Terminus ein Wort oder eine Wortgruppe, die die Sache, als das
        was sie wirklich ist, treffend kennzeichnet. Die englische Sprache ist zu präzis, als dass
        die bildliche Ausdrücke im übertragenen Sinne als Mittel der Verständigung zulassen würde.
          <tei:term>Hinter</tei:term>, <tei:term>Mittel</tei:term> und
          <tei:term>Vordergrund</tei:term>
        <tei:add place="interlinear-above">zum Beispiel</tei:add> bedeuten dem Engländer nur solange
        etwas, wenn sie auf die Malerei angewandt werden. Zur Charakterisierung von Hörbarem taugen
        sie einfach nicht und wären, so angewandt, nur Worte, die verschleiern, verdunkeln, statt
        eindeutig das Gedachte und Vorgestellte blitzartig dem Lesenden oder Hörenden
        aufzuzwingen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich halte es übrigens <tei:add place="interlinear-above">für</tei:add> ein Verhängnis,
        das der Verbreitung der Lehre mehr als man zuerst anzunehmen gewillt ist im Wege steht, dass
        die „Namengebung” von der Schenker selbst sagt, sie sei eines der wichtigsten Geschäfte des
        Geistes, im „<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title>freien
          Satz</tei:title></tei:rs>“ einem so billigen und <tei:sic>verschleierndem</tei:sic>
        Prinzip huldigt, wie das des Gleichnisses es ist. Mit wenigen Ausnahmen sind alle Termini
        erborgt von andern Disziplinen, sei es Philosophie, Ma- <tei:pb n="4"/> lerei, Geologie … .
        Dies verbreitet über Schenkers Hörwelt, die sich nur auf Wirkliches, Wirksames,
        Tatsächliches bezieht, einen fast undurchsichtigen Schleier von Mystischem und nur daher
        rührt es, dass diejenigen, die durch sein geschriebenes Wort zu seiner Hörwelt hingeleitet
        werden sollen den Verdacht <tei:add place="interlinear-above">er</tei:add>heben, es betreibe
        Metaphysik und vom kritischen Zweifel abgeschreckt werden. Ich werde das an den <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overwritten">e</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="superimposed">E</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>inzelnen Fachausdrücken in meinen „freien Sätzen“ zu Schenkers <tei:rs
          type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title>freiem Satz</tei:title></tei:rs><tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Weisse used the same play on words in
          his previous letter to Jeanette; the body of the letter is, in effect, a varied repetition
          of <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-15-16_100">OJ 15/16, [100]</tei:ref>, with
          Schenker receiving more severe criticism for lack of clarity when defining technical
          terms.</tei:note> Punkt für Punkt beweisen. Ich erwähne das hier blos, um zu erklären, wie
        ich <tei:add place="interlinear-above">zu</tei:add>
        <tei:choice>
          <tei:sic>einen</tei:sic>
          <tei:corr>einem</tei:corr>
        </tei:choice> neuen Standpunkt gekommen bin, der zwar die Idee über alles hochhält, ihre
        sprachliche Fassung jedoch daraufhin zu prüfen den Mut findet, ob in ihr das Gedachte
        endgültigen und eindeutigen Ausdruck gefunden hat. Es war gewiss keine leichte Aufgabe der
        vollkommen präzisen Hörweise einen entsprechend präzisen sprachlichen Ausdruck zur Seite zu
        stellen, doch darf die Bewunderung für die erstere einen nicht so blind machen, dass man
        sich der Tatsache verschliessen will, wie viele verhängnisvolle Fehler Schenker<tei:supplied
          reason="syntax">s</tei:supplied> bei dem Prozess der sprachlichen Fassung unterlaufen
        sind. Das ist es, was einen beim Lesen <tei:title>des freien Satzes</tei:title> so sehr
        bedrückt: man ahnt, fühlt die Wahrheit, sobald sie in der musikalischen Skizze dargestellt
        ist und man wird um das Meiste wieder beraubt, wenn man das Daraufbezügliche liest und einen
        die unpräzis geprägten Begriffe und noch unpräziser angewandten <tei:del rend="overstrike"
          >Begriffe</tei:del> in der Schwebe des Unent- <tei:pb n="5"/> schiedenen und Vagen
        halten.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich brauche nach Allem bisher Gesagten nicht noch einmal zu betonen, dass ich es als
        eine meiner Hauptaufgaben ansehe, der Lehre zur Verbreitung zu verhelfen, doch habe ich
        Ihnen mit dem vor<tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">aus</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">her</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>gesagten die Richtung angedeutet, in der ich es einzig für möglich halte. Eine
        Übersetzung halte ich nicht blos, so weit ich selbst in Betracht komme, sondern für
        jedermann, für unmöglich. Eine gänzlich<tei:del rend="overstrike">e</tei:del> neue
        sprachliche Umformung ist notwendig, soweit <tei:add place="interlinear-above">es</tei:add>
        das Englische anbetrifft. Unverändert könnte die Notenbeilage belassen werden. Dass ich mich
        bei der Abfassung des englischen Textes von dem Gedanken leiten lassen würde, die Lehre für
        den praktischen Gebrauch des Schulbetriebes darzustellen, versteht sich von selbst.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich bitte Sie nun, mir zu sagen, wie Sie sich dazu stellen und auch Ihre Fühler nach
        der <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">U. E.</tei:rs> auszustrecken, und mir
        deren Standpunkt bekannt zu geben. Sie können sich wohl denken, dass ich eine solche immense
        Arbeit nicht gerne in Angriff nehme, bevor ich nicht weiss, dass <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">man</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">mir</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> weder von Ihnen noch von Seiten des <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002408">Verlag</tei:rs>es Schwierigkeiten in den Weg gelegt werden. Ich habe
        die Arbeit bereits in Angriff genommen: wie langsam so etwas auch im Anfange vor sich geh<tei:subst>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">t</tei:add>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">en würde</tei:del>
        </tei:subst>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Was die deutsche Fassung <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title>des freien
            Satzes</tei:title></tei:rs> anlangt, so bin ich zu der, für mich unwiderlegbaren
        Überzeugung gekommen, dass er sich <tei:unclear reason="reading">da</tei:unclear> um die
        nicht zu Ende gedachte sprachliche Darstellung einer in sich völlig gerun- <tei:pb n="6"/>
        deten, ausgereiften Hörweise handelt, die eines Kommentars bedarf. In welchen Bahnen sich
        ein solcher Kommentar bewegen müsste, werden Ihnen meine Bemerkungen zum <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001728"><tei:title>freien Satz</tei:title></tei:rs> deutlich zeigen, deren
        Niederschrift ich dieser Tage in Angriff nehmen werde. Diese Bemerkungen sind, ich
        wiederhole es, nicht zur Publikation bestimmt und nur an die Eingeweihten gerichtet. Es
        liegt mir ferne „Kritik“ zu üben, die nicht zu Positivem führt. Doch muss der <tei:hi
          rend="underline">Lehrende</tei:hi> aus dem Chaos von Widersprüchen und Ungereimtheiten
        heraus, in das ihn <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title>der freie
            Satz</tei:title></tei:rs> von Seite zu Seite verstrickt.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Hier noch eine Anfrage: wären Sie willens des <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
          >Meister</tei:rs>s Bibliothek als Ganzes zu verkaufen und besitzen Sie ein Verzeichnis der
        Bücher und Noten? Ich könnte in dieser Richtung vielleicht etwas unternehmen. Universitäten
        und Bibliotheken, sind hier im Wachstum begriffen und es könnte sich vielleicht die eine
        oder andere finden, die interessiert wäre.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wir sind alle wohl und müssen und recht und schlecht mit der Stadt, und allem Lärm und
        Hässlichkeit abfinden.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Mit herzlichsten Grüssen von <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000952">Hertha</tei:rs> und mir</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr aufrichtiger Freund</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person"><tei:hi
              rend="lateinschr">Hans</tei:hi></tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:fw type="envelope">
          <tei:note type="editorial"><tei:hi rend="bold">Envelope:</tei:hi>
          </tei:note><tei:lb/>
          <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="recto"/><tei:lb/>
          <tei:address>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#HW"/><tei:hi rend="underline">S. S.
                Normandie</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
          </tei:address>
          <tei:address>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied reason="clarity">To:</tei:supplied> Mrs. Heinrich
              Schenker</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine rend="indent-20">Hasenauerstrasse 12</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine rend="indent-40">Vienna XIX</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:hi rend="underline">Austria</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
          </tei:address>
          <tei:add resp="JS"><tei:handShift new="#JS"/><tei:supplied reason="clarity"
              >received?:</tei:supplied>
            <tei:date when="1935-10-30">30. X. 35</tei:date></tei:add><tei:lb/>
          <tei:add resp="JS">answered <tei:date when="1935-11-08">8. XI. 35</tei:date></tei:add><tei:lb/>
          <tei:fw type="postmark">|| NEW YORK N.Y. | OCT 23 9‒AM | 1935 ||</tei:fw><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
          <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="verso"/>
          <tei:address>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied reason="clarity">From:</tei:supplied>
              <tei:handShift new="#HW"/>Dr. H. Weisse, 1 64th <tei:supplied reason="identity"
                >Street</tei:supplied> New York City </tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine>U. S. A.</tei:addrLine>
          </tei:address><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        </tei:fw>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold">Letter:</tei:hi>
        </tei:note><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002873">New York</tei:rs>,
            <tei:date when="1935-10-22">October 22, 1935</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Mrs. Lie-Lie</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>I confirm, with my thanks, the arrival of the pictures, which my pupils will be touched
        to receive.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> I have not yet had the
        opportunity to distribute all of them, since teaching has only just recently begun. This is
        also the reason why I could not send you the second payment,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
          type="footnote"/> which applies to the months October–December. But I will take care of
        that soon.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>So far as I recall, in my last letter to you<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
          type="footnote"/> I did not raise the matter of a new edition of <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001724"><tei:title level="m">Theory of Harmony</tei:title></tei:rs>; but I
        should like to say a few words about it now. I believe that the book ought to be published.
        The question of an abbreviated version is, of course, a delicate matter, and I thoroughly
        understand your viewpoint, which led you to dismiss it on the spot. After thinking the
        matter well over, however, I believe that making a shortened version would perhaps be
        judicious, and that it would perhaps be possible to incorporate the remarks added to the
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">master</tei:rs>'s working copy and still effect
        an abbreviated version. <tei:pb n="2"/> One has to consider whether the complete and
        long-term absence of the book from the market will be more damaging <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">to the cause</tei:add> than a few cuts ‒ which would, of course,
        concern only non-essential matters. I am reading through your letter about this again right
          now,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> but cannot tell where the cuts should
        be applied.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>If <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">Universal Edition</tei:rs> insisted
        that the book should be shortened to half its length, then you were of course in the right
          <tei:supplied reason="clarity">to say no</tei:supplied>. In principle, however, I believe
        that one should be guided only by purely objective arguments and not follow the letter too
        slavishly. Perhaps I would not have thought so earlier, but the fact that I am working
        seriously on the project of incorporating Schenker's work into the spirit of the English
        language has led me in this direction. After months of intensive study of <tei:rs
          type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title level="m">Free
        Composition</tei:title></tei:rs>, it has become perfectly clear to me that a word-for-word
        translation of the work is impossible, and that anyone who would attempt this would make the
        work even more inaccessible <tei:add place="interlinear-above">to an English
          readership</tei:add> than if he had not translated it at all. Not one of the technical
        terms (insofar as one can come up with English words for them at all) could <tei:pb n="3"/>
        mean something unambiguous, something imaginable, to a reader who was mentally brought up in
        the English language. It has become clear to me that, for the sake of the idea, which is of
        the greatest importance for humanity, an English translation is possible only if the theory
        is born again, in the spirit of the English language. This means a complete turning away
        from the letter, from the individual word and individual expression, and demands that every
        technical term be replaced by a word or group of words that indicates convincingly the point
        that it really conveys. The English language is too precise for us to use conceptual
        expressions in translation as a means of clarification: "<tei:term>background</tei:term>,"
          "<tei:term>middleground</tei:term>" and "<tei:term>foreground</tei:term>," <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">for example,</tei:add> will mean something to the English
        speaker only if they are applied to painting. For the purpose of characterizing something
        that is audible, they are simply unsuitable; they would only be words that veiled and
        obscured, instead instilling in the reader (or listener) a clear idea of what was thought or
        imagined as if by a stroke of lightning.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I regard it, moreover, as a tragedy that the dissemination of the theory will be
        impeded, more than one is prepared to admit, by the fact that the "naming of things," which
        Schenker himself claimed to be one of the most important intellectual activities, pays
        homage to such an easy and obscuring principle as that of the allegory. With very few
        exceptions, all the technical terms have been borrowed from other disciplines, whether
        philosophy, painting, <tei:pb n="4"/> geology …. This spreads over Schenker's auditory world,
        which is concerned only with what is real, effective and objective, an almost impenetrable
        veil of mysticism; and only for this reason will it come about that those who are supposed
        to be led from his written word to his auditory world will become suspicious that he is
        practising metaphysics, and their critical doubts will scare them off. I shall demonstrate
        this, point for point, in each of the technical terms, in my "free sentences" on Schenker's
          <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title level="m">Free
          Composition</tei:title></tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> I
        mention this here merely to explain how I arrived at a new point of view, which holds the
          <tei:supplied reason="clarity">Schenkerian</tei:supplied> idea above all else, but finds
        the courage to test its verbal formulation as to whether what was thought has found a
        definitive and unambiguous expression. It was, for sure, no easy task to find for a
        thoroughly precise manner of hearing a corresponding precise verbal expression; yet one's
        admiration for the former should not make one so blind as to ignore the fact that so many
        disastrous mistakes on Schenker's part have been commited in the process of verbal
        formulation. This is what depressed me so much when I read <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001728"><tei:title level="m">Free Composition</tei:title></tei:rs>: I can
        sense and feel the truth so long as it is presented as a musical illustration, and I am then
        robbed of most of its meaning when I read what is said about it, and the imprecisely
        formulated ‒ and the even more imprecisely applied ‒ terminology holds me in the air, in a
        state of uncertainty <tei:pb n="5"/> and vagueness.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>After all I have said until now, I need not stress yet again that I regard it as one of
        my principal assignments to assist in the dissemination of the theory; yet I have indicated
        to you, by what I have previously said, the only possible direction I could possibly take. I
        regard a translation of it, not merely as concerns myself but for anyone, as an
        impossibility. A completely new verbal formulation is necessary, as far as the English
        language is concerned. The appendix of musical illustrations could be left unchanged. It
        goes without saying that, in preparing an English text, I would be led by the idea of
        presenting the theory for practical use in the education system.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I ask you now to tell me what you think of this, and also to put out your feelers to
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">Universal Edition</tei:rs>, and to let me
        know where they stand. You can probably imagine that I would not wish to undertake such an
        immense piece of work before I knew that difficulties would be placed in my way neither by
        you nor by the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">publishing house</tei:rs>,
        however slowly things would have to proceed at the outset.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Regarding the German version of <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title
            level="m">Free Composition</tei:title></tei:rs>, I have come to the inescapable
        conclusion that a fully rounded, fully matured method of hearing <tei:pb n="6"/> requires a
        commentary to compensate for a verbal presentation that has not been fully thought out.
        Along what paths such a commentary must move is something that my forthcoming observations
        on <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title level="m">Free
          Composition</tei:title></tei:rs> will indicate clearly; I shall make a point of writing
        these down in the coming days. These observations are, I repeat, not intended for
        publication, and only intended for those who are initiated. Far be it from me to practise
        "criticism" that does not lead to positive results. And yet, the <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >teacher</tei:hi> must free himself from the chaos of contradictions and inconsistencies
        into which he has become entangled by <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title
            level="m">Free Composition</tei:title></tei:rs>, page after page. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>I have one further question: would you be willing to sell the <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000632">master</tei:rs>'s library as an entirety, and do you posess an index
        of the books and scores? I could perhaps undertake something in this direction. Universities
        and libraries here are in the process of growing, and one might find one or another of them
        that would be interested.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>We are all well, and must put up with the hustle and bustle of the city, with all its
        noise and unpleasantness.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">With most cordial greetings from <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000952">Hertha</tei:rs> and me,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your faithful friend</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person"
          >Hans</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
