<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="2043" sdoID="OJ-11-36_10">OJ 11/36, [10]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="VH" scope="sole">Viktor Hammer's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="HS-SP">
   <tei:persName>Hedi Siegel &amp; Stephanie Probst</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2017</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2017</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2017</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-02-12" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006186">HammerV ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Hammer to Schenker dated November 25, 1923</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1923-11-25T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2018-01-26</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Hammer thanks Schenker for hospitality on November 7, and recommends Eugen
    Steinhof for lessons.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Musiker; musician; Talent; Kunstgewerbeschule; School of Industrial Art; Empfehlung;
    recommendation; Begabung; gift; Musikalität; musicality; Stunden; lessons</dc:subject>



   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000327">Viktor Hammer</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Verehrtester Herr Doktor <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
      >Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this
      letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/6, p. 2602, November 28, 1923: "Von Hammer
      (Br.): Halm sage ihm zu wenig, bleibe aber sympathisch; empfiehlt mir Prof. Steinhof der
      angeblich seit 15 Jahren den Wunsch habe, mein Schüler zu werden." ("From Hammer (letter):
      Halm says too little to him, but stays agreeable; recommends Professor Steinhof to me, who
      purportedly has wished to become a student of mine for the past fifteen
     years.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Lassen Sie sich noch <tei:add place="interlinear-above">einmal</tei:add> recht von Herzen
    danksagen für den schönen Nachmittag bei Ihnen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
     place="foot">The Hammers' visit on November 7, 1923 is described in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/6,
     pp. 2595‒96:<tei:lb/> "Hammer um 5<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi>, Frau Hammer um
      ½6<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi>; sein Eintreten für Kokoschka Kubismus will er nur so
     aufgefaßt wissen, wie etwa meine Würdigung von Bruckner, nicht mehr. In der Frage der Polemik
     faßt er, was er sagen will in die Worte zusammen: ich täte ihm leid wenn es so ist, daß ich es
     machen muß! Ich habe auf beide Themen wenig Gewicht gelegt; die Verschiedenheit unserer Künste,
     unserer Tätigkeit u. Missionen läßt keine Analogie aufkommen, weshalb seine Ratschläge als
     unzuständig abgelehnt werden müssen. Spiele Bach u. Haydn-Trios, bedrängt von Hitze innen u.
     außen: die üppige Jause, die üppige Ofenwärme hat mich etwas unfrei gemacht. Leihe ihm Halms
      ‘<tei:title>Zwischen zwei Kulturen</tei:title>.’ Er will mir sein Clavichord für paar Monate
     zur Verfügung stellen, spricht aber noch lieber davon, wie schön es wäre, wenn einer meiner
     Schüler oder einige mir ein solches Instrument schenkten! Die vielen Stunden haben uns beide
     erschöpft – sie, die Gäste bleiben bis 9h!"<tei:lb/> ("Hammer at 5:00, Mrs. Hammer at 5:30; he
     wants his advocacy of Kokoschka's cubism to be understood as rather like my appreciation of
     Bruckner, no more. In the question of polemic, he summarizes what he wants to say with the
     words: he would be disappointed if it is the case that I have to do it! I attach little
     importance to both topics; the differences between our art, our activities, and <tei:supplied
      reason="clarity">our</tei:supplied> missions leave no room for analogy, which is why his
     advice must be rejected as inappropriate. I play Bach and Haydn trios, oppressed by internal
     and external heat: the sumptuous teatime <tei:supplied reason="clarity">and</tei:supplied> the
     sumptuous heat of the stove made me somewhat self-conscious. I lend him Halms's <tei:title
      level="m">Between Two Cultures</tei:title>. He wants to let me use his clavichord for a few
     months, but likes even more to talk about how nice it would be if one of my students, or
     several of them, would give me an instrument like that as a present! The many hours exhausted
     us both – they, the guests, stay until 9 p.m.!"). </tei:note> darnach ist man nicht leicht mehr
    mit etwas zufrieden. So selten dass gute Musiker die Musik der Meister machen und nicht die
    ihrige allein. – <tei:rs key="entity-000326" type="person">Halm</tei:rs> versteht sehr gut zu
    schreiben, viel Talent dafür, etwas weniger Selbstgefälligkeit täte gut, doch ist er durchaus
    sympathisch. – In <tei:hi rend="underline">Ihren</tei:hi> Schriften – soweit Sie sich nicht
    einlassen müssen mit der Bestie zu streiten zur höhern Ehre Gottes zwar – kommt aber doch viel
    mehr die Sache zu Wort als bei Halm und das ist so wohltuend, <tei:rs key="entity-000326"
     type="person">Halm</tei:rs>s große Begabung für das Wort entschädigt dafür nicht. Dies ist bloß
    meine Ansicht. – Doch habe ich den <tei:title>Lehrgang des Klavierspiels</tei:title> gemeint als
    ich Sie bat mir das Buch von <tei:rs key="entity-000326" type="person">Halm</tei:rs> zu
     leihen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">The book Hammer had wanted
     to borrow was <tei:bibl><tei:author>Halm</tei:author>'s <tei:title level="m">Klavierübung ‒ Ein
       Lehrgang des Klavierspiels nach neuen Grundsätzen, zugleich erste Einführung in die
       Musik</tei:title> (Stuttgart: G. A. Zumsteeg, 1918–19)</tei:bibl>, but Schenker had
     mistakenly lent him <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Von zwei Kulturen der Musik</tei:title>
      (Munich: G. Müller, 1913</tei:bibl>), on which Hammer is commenting in this letter.</tei:note>
    –</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> 2 Tage bevor ich von Wien weg bin traf ich einen alten Bekannten, einen
    Maler, Professor an der Kunstgewerbeschule in Wien, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006726"
     >Eugen Steinhof</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Eugen
     Steinhof (b. 1880 in Vienna, d. 1952 in Los Angeles) is mentioned in Anthony van Hoboken's
     letter to Schenker of March 21, 1928 ( <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-11-54_23">OJ
      11/54, [23]</tei:ref>): ". . . ist nämlich Wiener obwohl er fast sein ganzes Leben hier
     verbracht hat. Seit drei Jahren kommt er wieder regelmässig nach Wien und unterrichtet an der
     Kunstgewerbeschule. Er ist Architekt. Er erzählte mir, dass er einmal beinahe Ihr Schüler
     geworden wäre. Das war in 1905 aber durch einen Zufall ist nichts daraus geworden." (". . . is
     in fact a Viennese, although he has spent almost his whole life here <tei:supplied
      reason="placew">in Paris</tei:supplied>. For three years he has again come regularly to Vienna
     and taught at the School of Industrial Art. He is an architect. He told me that he once almost
     became your pupil. That was in 1905, but because of a coincidence, nothing came of it.") In his
     reply to Hoboken of March 26, 1928 (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-89-2_5">OJ 89/2,
      [5]</tei:ref>) Schenker writes: "Von Prof. Steinhof hörte ich öfter durch Hammer, zu Gesicht
     bekam ich ihn aber nie." ("I have heard of Prof. Steinhof often through Hammer, but have never
     met him.") Schenker's diary for 1905 does not record any contact between Steinhof and Schenker,
     nor does his name appear in the index of Schenker's diaries to 1911.</tei:note> der mich sehr
    lebhaft um eine Empfehlung für Sie bat. Er spielt gut Klavier, jedenfalls ist seine grosse
    koloristische Begabung und seine Musikalität sehr verwandt. Er wollte schon vor 15–20 Jahren
    Stunden bei Ihnen nehmen. – Bei allen Einschränkungen die vielleicht nötig sind habe ich doch
    das Gefühl, dass Sie Freude an ihm haben werden oder haben könnten. – Er wohnt erst seit kurzem
    in Wien (IX Währingerstrasse 2) und ich werde ihm schreiben, dass er sich brieflich an Sie
    wenden soll wann Sie ihn empfangen wollen, ich habe ihm zugesagt dass ich seinetwegen an Sie
    schreiben werde.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Nun verehrtester Doktor Schenker vielen Dank von uns Beiden bitte empfehlen Sie sich Ihrer
     <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Gattin</tei:rs>,</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">ich bin in treuer Verehrung Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs key="entity-000327" type="person">V.
     Hammer</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:p><tei:date when="1923-11-25">25. XI. 23</tei:date>, Firenze, Via San Carlo 15. Villa dei
     Cipressi</tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Most highly revered Dr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
      >Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Let me <tei:add place="interlinear-above">once</tei:add> again express my heartfelt thanks
    for the lovely afternoon at your place,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> after
    which one is no longer easily satisfied with anything else. It is so seldom that good musicians
    perform the music of the masters and not just their own music. – <tei:rs key="entity-000326"
     type="person">Halm</tei:rs> writes very well, has much talent for it, a little less
    self-importance would be nice, yet he is quite likeable. But in <tei:hi rend="underline"
     >your</tei:hi> writings ‒ provided you don't have to do battle with the beast for the greater
    glory of God ‒ you express the issues much more effectively than <tei:rs key="entity-000326"
     type="person">Halm</tei:rs>, and the result is so pleasing that it cannot be outdone by Halm's
    great gift for words. That's just my opinion. – But I meant the <tei:title level="m">Piano
     Method</tei:title> when I asked you to lend me the book by <tei:rs key="entity-000326"
     type="person">Halm</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> –</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Two days before I left Vienna I met an old acquaintance, a painter,
    professor at the School of Industrial Art in Vienna, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006726"
     >Eugen Steinhof</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> who fervently
    requested that I recommend him to you. He plays the piano well; at any rate his keen sensitivity
    for color and his musicality are closely related. He wanted to take lessons with you as long as
    fifteen or twenty years ago. – In spite of all the restrictions you might need to impose, I have
    the feeling that you will or could be pleased with him. He just recently took up residence in
    Vienna (IX, Währingerstrasse 2) and I will write to him suggesting that he send you a letter
    asking when you would like to receive him; I have assured him I will write to you about
    him.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Now most revered Dr. Schenker many thanks from both of us; please give regards to your
     <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs>,</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">I am your truly devoted</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs key="entity-000327" type="person">V.
     Hammer</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:p><tei:date when="1923-11-25">November 25, 1923</tei:date>, Florence, via San Carlo 15.
     Villa dei Cipressi</tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>


  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
