<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3259" sdoID="OJ-10-3_199">OJ 10/3, [199]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPoed" scope="major">Otto Erich Deutsch typist</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="OED" scope="minor">Otto Erich Deutsch's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2023</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IDB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2015-09-18" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002726">DeutschOE ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002712">DeutschOE ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002727">DeutschOE+H ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Typewritten letter from Deutsch to Schenker, dated November 4, 1933</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1933-11-04T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2023-08-25</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Deutsch has heard that Eva van Hoboken is trying to persuade her husband that
        Deutsch is exploiting him. He fears that the letter his wife has written to Hoboken will
        have done more harm than good, and that it will hardly be possible for a family of four to
        live on 600 shillings a month. He fears that Eva will persuade him not to buy the villa in
        Vienna in which his library is to be housed.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000164">DeutschOE</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>PROF. OTTO ERICH DEUTSCH</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Tel. R 45–6–72</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">WIEN II.</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Böcklinstraße 26</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/><tei:date when="1933-11-04">4.
            Nov. 33</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Verehrter</tei:rs>!<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is not recorded
            in Schenker’s diary. On Monday, November 6, the day on which it presumably arrived,
            Schenker wrote a postcard to Deutsch in which he quotes “excerpts from Hoboken’s letter”
            received earlier in the day.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Bevor wir uns wieder sehen, möchte ich Ihnen zu Ihrer Orientierung für
        morgen etwas schreiben, was sich telefonisch nicht gut sagen liesse. Ich habe erfahren, dass
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005826">Frau Eva</tei:rs>, dieser böse Geist <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000380">H</tei:rs>s., ihm auch einzureden versucht hat, dass ich
        ihn ausnütze. Im Wortlaut weiss ich das freilich nicht. Ich brauche mich Ihnen gegenüber
        nicht zu salvieren, Ihnen nicht zu versichern, dass ich mich, wo es mir immer möglich war,
        eher kavaliersmässig gegen <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">H.</tei:rs> betragen
        habe, ihm womöglich noch etwas geschenkt habe, ihn durch Ersparnisse meinen Gehalt bezahlt
        habe etc. Jedenfalls habe ich es nie darauf angelegt, ihn auszunützen, weil mir die Sache –
        die Bibliothek – viel zu teuer war, um sie durch Enttäuschung oder auch nur Misstrauen zu
        gefährden. Der Brief meiner <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000163">Frau</tei:rs> an
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">H</tei:rs>, der auf Rat von Freunden in Not
        geschrieben war,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Cf. Deutsch’s
          letter to Schenker, <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-10-3_198">OJ 10/3,
            [198]</tei:ref>, October 2, 1933.</tei:note> scheint mir jedenfalls geschadet zu haben,
        vielleicht nicht direkt bei ihm, aber wohl-gesehen durch die scheelen Augen der <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-005826">Frau Eva</tei:rs>. Ich wollte, ich könnte den Brief
        ungeschehen machen, denn die 7 mal 100 Schilling Plus <tei:pb n="2"/> vom Oktober bis April
        können uns nicht so viel helfen, dass sie einen Verlust für die Zukunft aufwiegen: <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000380">H.</tei:rs> hat ja erklärt, dass er mir auch, wenn die
        Bibliothek hier wieder aufgestellt würde, nicht mehr den alten Betrag (S 500), sondern nur
        300 zahlen könnte, sonst aber noch zwei Jahre nur 200. Ich fürchte, dass Sie jetzt daran
        auch nichts ändern könnten, wenn Sie Ihre Absicht, mit ihm über meine Bezüge zu sprechen,
        ausführen wollten. Ich sage Ihnen das alles nur, damit Sie im Bilde sind, auch noch das
        Eine, dass wir jetzt ab <tei:date when="1933-12-01">1. Dezember</tei:date> wirklich in die
        Lage gekommen sind, mit 600 S monatlich zu Viert leben zu müssen, einschliesslich der
        unsicheren Summe <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">H</tei:rs>s. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Dass <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">H.</tei:rs> den Grund nicht
        gekauft <tei:del rend="overstrike">hat</tei:del>, sondern nur eine Option bis <tei:date
          when="1933-12-31">31. Dezember</tei:date> darauf erworben hat, wissen Sie jetzt wohl
        schon. Bis dahin dürfte ihn <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005826">Frau Eva</tei:rs> in
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-005700">Garmisch</tei:rs> ja überzeugt haben, dass er den
        Grund nicht kaufen darf. Wir müssen also wohl warten, bis er die Ohrenbläserin los ist.
        Gestern waren beide bei uns, wir vermieden aber verfängliche Gespräche. Im Einkauf hat sich
        H. so zögernd benommen, dass meine grosse Aktion in Oed (Sammlung Hauer-Rosthorn)
        wahrscheinlich vergeblich gewesen ist. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/>Herzlichst ergeben Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000164">O E
          Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>PROF. OTTO ERICH DEUTSCH</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Tel. R 45–6–72</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">VIENNA II</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Böcklinstraße 26</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/><tei:date when="1933-11-04"
            >November 4, 1933</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">friend</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Before we see each other, I should like to write something to you that
        cannot easily be said over the telephone, to put you in the picture for tomorrow. I have
        learned that <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005826">Eva</tei:rs>, this evil spirit of
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs>’s, has tried to talk him into
        thinking that I am exploiting him. Of course, I don’t know the exact words she has used. I
        don’t have to defend myself in front of you, to assure you that, on the contrary, I have
        behaved chivalrously towards <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs>
        whenever it was possible for me to do so, and that I have paid for my remuneration by giving
        him still more, by making savings, etc. In any event I have never intended to take advantage
        of him because the matter – the library – was too dear to me for me to endanger it through
        disappointment or even just through distrust. My <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000163"
          >wife</tei:rs>’s letter to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs>,
        which was written in desperation on the advice of friends,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> seems in any event to have done damage to me – perhaps not directly with
        him, but clearly through the disapproving eyes of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005826"
          >Eva</tei:rs>. I wish I could undo the writing of that letter, since an advantage of 7
        times 100 shillings, <tei:pb n="2"/> from October to April, is not sufficient to offset a
        loss for the future: <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs> has indeed
        said that, even if his library were to be set up again, he could no longer pay me the old
        fee (500 shillings) but only 300, but otherwise only 200 for a further two years. I fear
        that you cannot do anything to change this if you wished to carry out your intention to
        discuss my emoluments with him. I am telling you all of this only so that you are still
        aware even of the one thing: that now, as of <tei:date when="1933-12-01">December
          1</tei:date>, we have actually reached the point of having to live as a family of four on
        600 shillings per month, including <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380"
          >Hoboken</tei:rs>’s uncertain sum.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">You probably know that <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380"
          >Hoboken</tei:rs> has not bought the land but merely taken out an option on it until
          <tei:date when="1933-12-31">December 31</tei:date>. By then <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-005826">Eva</tei:rs> will probably have convinced him in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-005700">Garmisch</tei:rs> that he is not permitted to buy the land. We must
        therefore wait until he is rid of this spreader of rumors. The two of them were at our place
        yesterday, but we avoided awkward conversations. In his purchases, Hoboken has behaved so
        hesitantly that my great initiative in Oed (the Hauer-Rosthorn collection) has probably been
        in vain.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/>Your most cordially
          devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000164">O. E.
            Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
