<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3804" sdoID="OJ-13-10_196">OJ 13/10, [196]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2025</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008522">Oppel ~
        JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Jeanette Schenker, dated December 9,
        1935</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1935-12-09T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-09-23</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel urges Jeanette Schenker to publish her husband’s correspondence with
        August Halm. – He thinks that Hans Weisse, a mere disciple, does not understand Schenker’s
        theories well enough to find fault with their expression in Free
        Composition.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1935-03-09">9. XII 35</tei:date>.
          </tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Sehr verehrte liebe <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
            >Frau Professor Schenker</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Gegen Ende November war ich mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008523"
        >Bepo</tei:rs>, um einmal auszuspannen, ein paar Tage in der Nähe von <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-004513">Meiningen</tei:rs>, in der Heimat meiner Mutter. Daher komme ich erst
        heute zur Beantwortung Ihres l. Briefes vom <tei:date when="1935-11-27">27. XI.</tei:date>
        Ob die Witwe von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000326">August Halm</tei:rs> noch lebt,
        weiss ich nicht, ich werde aber jetzt nachforschen. Man erfährt das wohl am einfachsten
        durch seinen Verleger <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002410">Georg Müller</tei:rs>
        in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002286">München</tei:rs>. Falls die Dame nicht mehr
        lebt, steht Ihrer Absicht, den Briefwechsel zu veröffentlichen, nichts mehr im
          Wege.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">The complete surviving
          correspondence between August Halm and Heinrich Schenker is available on this
          site.</tei:note> Im Gegenteil, bei der heutigen Vorliebe für <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000104">Bruckner</tei:rs> wird ein solcher Beitrag allen willkommen sein. Ich
        erinnere mich, dass Meister Schenker damals eine <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >öffentliche</tei:add> Discussion mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000326"
          >Halm</tei:rs> mit Recht abgelehnt hat. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000326"
          >Halm</tei:rs>’s Standpunkt war zu beschränkt. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Es freut mich, dass Sie nun, nach dem recht unnötigen 2. Umzug, einen warmen, guten
        Hafen gefunden haben.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">In
          September or October 1935 Jeanette had moved to a guesthouse in Hasenauerstraße, Vienna
          XVIII, then in November she moved to Cottagegasse in the same district, where she remained
          for at least a year. This is probably the move referred to.</tei:note> Jetzt können Sie
        mit Ruhe an die Ordnung des Nachlass gehn. Natürlich bitte ich Sie herzlich um die Zusendung
        der N-aufnahme; selbstverständlich habe ich für das Werk unseres lieben Entschlafenen immer
        Zeit. Ich werde sofort alles lesen und es Ihnen <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"
          >word or line missing</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs>’s Verhalten ist mir ein
          Rätsel.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">In his letter to
          Jeanette of September 18 (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-15-16_100">OJ 15/16,
            [100]</tei:ref>), Hans Weisse (in New York City) had written an extended critique of
            <tei:title level="m">Free Composition</tei:title>, noting among other things that the
          subtitle of the book was misleading and its terminology was poorly defined. Jeanette
          presumably communicated his misgivings to Oppel in her letter of November 27 but may have
          already hinted at them previously. In his letter of November 1 (<tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-13-10_195">OJ 13/10, [195]</tei:ref>), Oppel had already
          expressed surprise about “criticism from America.”</tei:note> So gut, wie man in jeder
        Sprache, auch i. d. englischen die einfachsten und die höchsten Probleme der Mathematik
        darstellen kann, so gut geht das auch mit den letzten Fragen i. d. Musik. Und gab es u. gibt
        es für die letzten u. tiefsten Probleme der Musik, insbesondere ihrer
          <tei:term>Synthese</tei:term> eine klarere Sprache und Ausdrucksweise als die Meister
        Schenker? Ich wüsste keine. Alles vom kleinsten bis ins grösste ist von einer
        unbestechlichen und überzeugenden u. unwiderstehlichen <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000524">Lessing</tei:rs>’schen Klarheit. Man sieht hier aber wieder einmal,
        dass von den Jüngern bis zum Schöpfer noch ein ungeheuer weiter Weg ist. Ihre Ablehnung war
        auf sein törichtes Ansinnen die einzig richtige Antwort. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wie geht es denn <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>? Wenn
        Sie ihm wieder schreiben, bitte ich ihn herzlich von mir zu grüssen. Hoffentlich kommt er
        pecuniär einigermassen aus in der <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002507">Schweiz</tei:rs>.
        Die allgemeine Lage wird ja überall immer complizierter. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Weihnachten kommen <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> und
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003957">Walter</tei:rs>, der sich beim Militär sehr wohl
        fühlt. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005266">Meine Frau</tei:rs> wird viel Arbeit haben.
        – – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun wünsche ich Ihnen alles Gute und bleibe mit den herzlichsten Grüssen von uns
        allen</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Ihr sehr ergebener und treuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">
      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1935-03-09">December 9,
              1935</tei:date>
          </tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Very revered, dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
            >Mrs. Schenker</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Toward the end of November, I went with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008523"
          >Bepo</tei:rs> to relax for a few days near <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004513"
          >Meiningen</tei:rs>, in the homeland of my mother. Thus it is only now that I am getting
        around to answering your kind letter of <tei:date when="1935-11-27">November 27</tei:date>.
        I do not know whether <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000326">August Halm</tei:rs>’s widow
        is still alive; I shall now make inquiries. One could most easily find out from his
        publisher, <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002410">Georg Müller</tei:rs> of <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002286">Munich</tei:rs>. If the lady is no longer alive then
        there is no longer anything to prevent you from publishing the correspondence.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> On the contrary, given today’s fondness for
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000104">Bruckner</tei:rs>, such a contribution will be
        welcome to all. I recall that Master Schenker previously declined a <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">public</tei:add> discussion with <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000326">Halm</tei:rs>, and rightly so. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000326">Halm</tei:rs>’s point of view was too limited.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I am glad to hear that, after a second move which was entirely unnecessary, you have
        now found a warm harbor.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> Now you can
        peacefully work on ordering the unpublished papers. Of course, I cordially request that you
        send me a photograph of it; I always have time, of course, for the work of our dearly
        departed. I shall read everything immediately and <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"
          >word or line missing</tei:note> it to you.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs>’s attitude
        puzzles me.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> Granted that one can explain the
        simplest and most difficult problems of mathematics in any language, even in English, that
        is also true for the ultimate problems in music. But has there been – is there – a clearer
        language and mode of expression for the ultimate, deepest problems of music, especially its
          <tei:term>synthesis</tei:term>, than that of Master Schenker’s? I would not know of any.
        Every idea, from the smallest to the largest, is explained with an unerring, convincing, and
        irrefutable <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000524">Lessing</tei:rs>-like clarity. One
        sees again that there is still an immensely large gulf between the disciples and the
        creator. Your rejection was the only correct reply to his foolish imposition. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>And how is <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>? If you write
        to him again, please give him my cordial greetings. I hope that he will manage financially
        in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002507">Switzerland</tei:rs>. The general situation is
        indeed getting more complicated everywhere. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>At Christmas I shall have <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> and
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003957">Walter</tei:rs>, who is very happy in the
        military. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005266">My wife</tei:rs> will have a lot of
        work. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Now, I send you all good wishes and, with the most cordial greetings from all of us,
        remain</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Your very devoted and faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>
    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
