<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3180" sdoID="OJ-10-3_151">OJ 10/3, [151]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPoed" scope="major">Otto Erich Deutsch typist</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="OED" scope="minor">Otto Erich Deutsch's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2023</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IDB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2015-09-18" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002726">DeutschOE ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002712">DeutschOE ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002727">DeutschOE+H ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Typewritten letter from Deutsch to Schenker, dated July 29, 1931</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1931-07-29T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2023-07-27</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Deutsch reports illness in his family over the summer. -- He is glad to see
        Schenker’s article on the lost Mozart letter in print, and mentions other places in which it
        was reproduced. He has made some discoveries about Lord Horatio Nelson and Haydn, which
        have, however, been misrepresented in the press.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000164">DeutschOE</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>PROF. OTTO ERICH DEUTSCH</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">WIEN II.</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Böcklinstraße 26</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/><tei:rs type="place"
              key="entity-004540">Nauders</tei:rs> (Tirol), Pension Grete</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Verehrter</tei:rs>!<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in
            Schenker’s diary for July 30, 1931: “Von Deutsch (Br. aus Nauders): Krankheit der Frau;
            hofft v. H.<tei:hi rend="supralinear">s</tei:hi> Bibliothek in Wien halten zu können;
            über meinen <tei:title>Kunstwart</tei:title>-Aufsatz; über eigene Artikel zum
            Urheberrecht.” (“From Deutsch (letter from Nauders): his wife’s illness; he hopes to be
            able to keep Hoboken’s library in Vienna; concerning my article in <tei:title level="j"
              >Der Kunstwart</tei:title>; concerning his own articles on copyright
            law.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Wenn ich diesmal Ihre freundlichen Sendungen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot"> In his diary entry of July 3, 1931, Schenker recorded
          dictating a reply to Deutsch’s postcard of July 1, which Jeanette then wrote
          out.</tei:note> nicht rascher beantwortete, so hat das einen traurigen Grund. Meine
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000163">Frau</tei:rs> war lebensgefährlich krank und die
        Juliwochen waren fast ganz der Sorge um sie gewidmet. Sie bekam, ohnehin schon übermüdet,
        nach der Pflege eines gastrischen Fiebers beider Kinder, eine heftige Angina, die sich bald
        als Streptokokken-Angina enthüllte und eine Sepsis zur Folge hatte. Gesunde Organe und die
        Klinik Neumann haben das Wunder ihrer Genesung vollbracht. Inzwischen war aber auch der Bub
        und die Köchin erkrankt, nur leicht, wie sich ergab. Dann schickte ich die Kinder mit der
        Schwester meiner <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000163">Frau</tei:rs> zur Schwiegermutter
        in den Schwarzwald, wohin mein <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000163">Frau</tei:rs>
        Anfang August nachfahren soll, nachdem sie sich bei meiner Schwester in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-004103">Reichenau</tei:rs> erholt haben wird. Ich hatte in dem Wirbel fünf
        fremde Personen zuhause. Aber wir haben gesiegt, obzwar meine <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000163">Frau</tei:rs>, die zu viel wusste, sehr pessimistisch war und vielen
        Zuspruchs bedurfte, um alle Kräfte und Säfte gegen die Bazillen unbekannter Herkunft
        aufzubieten. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Nun bin ich seit Sonntag hier und recht zufrieden. Ihr <tei:rs
          type="journal" key="entity-003014"
          ><tei:title>Kunstwart</tei:title></tei:rs>-Artikel<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:title level="a">Ein verschollener Brief von
            Mozart,</tei:title> which appeared in the July 1931 edition of <tei:title level="j">Der
            Kunstwart</tei:title>. Schenker has underlined “Kunstwart-Artikel” and sidelined the
          entire paragraph in pencil.</tei:note> hat mich sehr erfreut, besonders weil nichts
        versäumt war, was ich später zum Thema erfuhr oder im Wirbel erst erfahren zu haben glaubte.
        Ausser in dem Goethe-Buch von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005799">Carus</tei:rs> ist
        der Brief auch ein einem Werk über Shelley von A. C.
          Clutton-<tei:sic>Broch</tei:sic><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial"
          place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>A. Clutton-Brock</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m"
              >Shelley: the Man and the Poet</tei:title> (1909)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> und in einem
        über Plotin von W. R. Inge<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot"
              ><tei:bibl><tei:author>William Ralph Inge</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">The
              Religious Philosophies of Plotinus and Some Modern Philosophies of
              Religion</tei:title> (1914)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> erwähnt. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003455">Jahn</tei:rs> schreibt in der ersten Auflage auch S. 423ff. davon und
        nennt einmal den Empfänger: Baron v. P., was aber wohl Versehen ist, da der Name nicht
        einmal angedeutet war. Einige andere Zitate, die mir Mr. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-006246">Oldman</tei:rs> gab, muss ich noch nachsehen oder überprüfen, den er
        sprach davon aus dem Gedächtnisse (<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000780"
          >Schiedermaier</tei:rs>s Vorwort, Mozart von Holmes<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06"
          type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Edward Holmes</tei:author>, <tei:title
              level="m">The Life of Mozart</tei:title> (1845)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> – nach Nissen
        –, Mozart von <tei:sic>Schlossar</tei:sic> 1828).<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07"
          type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Johann Aloys Schlosser</tei:author>,
              <tei:title level="m">Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart</tei:title> (Prague: Buchler, Stephani
            &amp; Schlosser, 1828)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> Jedenfalls haben Sie das Dokument ins
        gehörige Licht gerückt! </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="indent-60"><tei:pb n="2"/>
        <tei:date when="1931-07-29">29. VII. 31</tei:date></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Mein Artikel über das Urheberrecht, der in den <tei:title>Juristischen
          Blättern</tei:title> noch ein praktisches Nachwort von mir bekommt, hatte die beiden
        anderen Punkte: <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archiv</tei:rs> und Schutz
        gegen Verballhornung nur gestreift. Dieser scheint in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002590">Genf</tei:rs> nicht neu gewesen zu sein, jener aber soll wie der
        Hauptpunkt dort und in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002477">Paris</tei:rs> (Sektion und
        Institut für internationale geistige Zusammenarbeit) verfolgt werden, wie mir <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-005284">Hofrat Strzygowski</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Probably the Polish-Austrian art historian Josef Strzygowski
          (1862–1941).</tei:note> berichtete. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002963"
          >Bartok</tei:rs> und Capek,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Karel Čapek (1890–1938), Czech writer and critic, best known for his science
          fiction.</tei:note> die in <tei:rs key="entity-002590">Genf</tei:rs> verwandte Fragen
        vorbrachten, bekamen den Prospekt des <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452"
          >Archiv</tei:rs>s, von dem sie nichts wussten, zugeschickt. Ich hoffe nun wirklich auf
        einigen praktischen Erfolg. Dass der Staat die Texte nicht herausgeben soll, habe ich
        bedacht; aber dass die Autographe gesetzlich geschützt werden, ist wohl die Voraussetzung
        für Ihre und <tei:add place="interlinear-above">etwa</tei:add> anderer Kenner Leistung.
        Deshalb scheint mir meine Aktion nicht überflüssig. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Was <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs>s Abgang betrifft, so
        hoffe ich noch immer, die Bibliothek in Wien erhalten zu können. Vielleicht können Sie im
        Herbst dabei raten. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Dass Ihre Kosten für das <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001752">Jahrbuch III</tei:rs>
        ersetzt wurden, freut mich aufrichtig und mit Genugtuung.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Through the efforts of <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000268">Wilhelm Furtwängler</tei:rs>, Schenker obtained 3,000 marks to help
          defray the production costs of the third <tei:title level="m">Meisterwerk</tei:title>
          yearbook.</tei:note> Dem <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002627">DMV</tei:rs>
        wollen wir schon beikommen; er ist auch mir für <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380"
          >Hoboken</tei:rs> noch eine Antwort schuldig. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003823"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003823"
            >Smekal</tei:rs>s Geschwätz ist heiter, aber ich habe es nicht gelesen. Ebenso leider
          nicht die Rezension des <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001752">Jb. III</tei:rs> in
            <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002556"><tei:title>der
            „Musik“</tei:title></tei:rs>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11" type="editorial" place="foot"
            >Carl Johann Perl’s review appeared in the June 1931 issue of <tei:title level="j">Die
              Musik</tei:title>. (A clipping of this is preserved in Schenker’s scrapbook (OC File
            2), on page 83.</tei:note></tei:rs>
      </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Mit meinem Nelson-Fund<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Deutsch’s <tei:title level="m">Admiral Nelson und Joseph Haydn: ein
            britisch-österreichisches Gipfeltreffen</tei:title> was published posthumously in
          1982.</tei:note> hat es eine andere Bedeutung, als jetzt in vielen Zeitungen steht. Frau
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000072">Dr. Bienenfeld</tei:rs> hatte eine Vornotiz
        meiner grossen Arbeit über „Nelson in Oesterreich“ missverstanden, den Abdruck des von mir
        wieder gefundenen Gedichtes auf Nelson, das <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000344"
          >Haydn</tei:rs> für seine noch ungedruckte Publikation benützt hat. Und der Unsinn, den
        sie darüber schrieb, ging gekürzt durch viele Zeitungen. Da ich aber Gazetten nicht mehr
        berichtige, in solchen Tatsachen nämlich, muss ich auch zu meinem neuen Ruhme schweigen, der
        sich wie immer nur an kleine Leistungen heftet. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Der beiliegende Ausschnitt diene zur Vernichtung.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Mit schönen Grüssen an Ihre</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Frau
            Gemahlin</tei:rs> bleibe ich </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Ihr ganz ergebener</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/><tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000164">O E Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p><tei:handShift new="#OED"/>Zur 2. Mozart-Tagung in Salzburg (2.–5. VIII.) habe ich
          abgesagt. </tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>PROF. OTTO ERICH DEUTSCH</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">VIENNA II</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Böcklinstraße 26</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/><tei:rs type="place"
              key="entity-004540">Nauders</tei:rs> (Tyrol), Pension Grete</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Verehrter</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">If I did not reply more quickly to your kind mailings<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> this time, there is an unhappy reason for it. My
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000163">wife</tei:rs> was gravely ill, and the weeks in
        July were dedicated almost entirely to her care. Already exhausted after both children were
        ill with gastric fever, she contracted a severe case of angina, which quickly turned out to
        be streptococcal angina, which led to septicemia. Healthy organs and the Neumann Clinic have
        brought about the miracle of her recovery. In the meantime my son and our cook fell ill, but
        only mildly as it turned out. I then took the children to my wife’s sister in the Black
        Forest, where my <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000163">wife</tei:rs> is supposed to go
        at the beginning of August, after she has recovered at my sister’s place in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-004103">Reichenau</tei:rs>. In the whirlwind, I had five
        unfamiliar people at my house. But we have been victorious, although my <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000163">wife</tei:rs>, who knew too much <tei:supplied
          reason="clarity">about her illness</tei:supplied>, was very pessimistic and needed much
        encouragement to summon all her strength and energy against the germs of unknown
        origin.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I have now been here since Sunday, and am thoroughly content. I greatly
        enjoyed your article in <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-003014"><tei:title level="j">Der
            Kunstwart</tei:title></tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/>
        especially as nothing was missed out of what I later discovered about the topic – or
        believed to have discovered in the confusion of events. Besides <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-005799">Carus</tei:rs>’s book on Goethe, the letter is also mentioned in a
        study of Shelley by A. C. Clutton-Brock,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> and
        in one about Plotinus by W. R. Inge.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003455">Jahn</tei:rs> also writes about it in the first
        edition <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of his biography of Mozart</tei:supplied>, pp.
        423ff., and names the recipient as “Baron v. P,” which is probably an oversight, as the full
        name is never given. A few other quotations, which Mr. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-006246">Oldman</tei:rs> gave me, must still be looked up or checked, for he
        spoke about them from memory (<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000780"
          >Schiedermair</tei:rs>’s foreword, Holmes’s book on Mozart<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06"
          type="footnote"/> – based on Nissen, Schlosser’s 1828 book on Mozart).<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> In any event, you have presented the document in
        the light that it deserves!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="indent-60"><tei:pb n="2"/>
        <tei:date when="1931-07-29">July 29, 1931</tei:date></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">My article on copyright law, which still needs a practical afterword from
        me before it is published in the <tei:title level="j">Juristische Blätter</tei:title>, only
        touches on the two other points: the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452"
          >Archive</tei:rs>, and protection against misrepresentation. The latter seems to have been
        nothing new in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002590">Geneva</tei:rs>, but the former is
        expected to be pursued there and in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002477">Paris</tei:rs>
        (Department and Institute for International Intellectual Collaboration), as <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-005284">Court Councillor Strzygowski</tei:rs><tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/> reported. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-002963">Bartók</tei:rs> and Čapek,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09"
          type="footnote"/> who introduced related questions in <tei:rs key="entity-002590"
          >Geneva</tei:rs>, received the prospectus from the <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002452">Archive</tei:rs>, of which they knew nothing. I am now really hoping
        for a few practical successes. That the state should not publish the texts is something I
        have considered; but that the autograph manuscript should be protected by law is perhaps a
        precondition for your achievement, and that of other experts. Thus my action seems to me not
        to have been unnecessary.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>As concerns <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs>’s departure, I
        still keep hoping to be able to keep his library in Vienna. Perhaps you can advise me about
        this in the autumn.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I am thoroughly delighted, and satisfied, that your costs for the production of the
          <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001752">third yearbook</tei:rs> have been
          defrayed.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn10" type="footnote"/> We ought already to be
        negotiating with <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002627">Drei Masken
        Verlag</tei:rs>; it still owes me a reply on behalf of <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003823"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003823"
            >Smekal</tei:rs>’s gossip is amusing, but I have not read it. Likewise, I haven’t read
          the review of <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001752">Yearbook III</tei:rs> in <tei:rs
            type="journal" key="entity-002556"><tei:title level="j">Die
            Musik</tei:title></tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn11" type="footnote"/></tei:rs>
      </tei:p>

      <tei:p>My collection of Nelson discoveries<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn12" type="footnote"/>
        means something different from that which is reported in many newspapers. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000072">Dr. Bienenfeld</tei:rs> misunderstood an advance notice
        of my large-scale work about “Nelson in Austria,” the print of a poem about Nelson,
        rediscovered by me, which <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000344">Haydn</tei:rs> use for
        an as yet unpublished composition. And the nonsense that she wrote about it recently made
        the rounds of many newspapers. But since I no longer correct newspapers in such incidents, I
        must also be silent about my new fame which, as always, is attached only to small
        achievements.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>The enclosed clipping may be safely discarded.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">With best greetings to your</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">wife</tei:rs> I
          remain</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Your wholly devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/><tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000164">O. E. Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p><tei:handShift new="#OED"/>I have turned down an invitation to the second Mozart
          conference in Salzburg (August 2–5).</tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>



    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
