<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2123" sdoID="OJ-15-16_82">OJ 15/16, [82]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HW" scope="sole">Hans Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2008</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2018</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-10-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated October 15, 1931</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1931-10-15T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2018-10-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Weisse describes his new life in America; — is touched by the spirit that
        pervades the Mannes Music School; — has given a lecture to the faculty on the role of a
        theorist in a music school. — He reports that he has 22 pupils, and is about to meet George
        A. Wedge, Dean of the Institute of Musical Art. — He asks whether Schenker has had any news
        from Hamburg.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Wirkungskreis; working environment; Geist; spirit; Leiter; Director; Schule;
        School; Versammlung; gathering; Lehrerschaft; faculty; Debut; Theorielehrer; theory teacher;
        Vortrag; lecture; Musikschule; music school; Erfolg; success; Unterricht; instruction;
        Nebenfach; subsidiary subject; Klasse; class; Schuler; pupils; Kompositionsklasse;
        composition class; Privatstunden; private lessons; Grundsteinlegung; laying of the
        foundations; Begriff; concept; Umgebung; surroundings; Strassenlärm; street noise;
        Freundschaft; friendship; europäisch; European; Zusammenarbeit; collaboration</dc:subject>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000951">Weisse</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address rend="indent-60">
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#HW"/>New York, <tei:date when="1931-10-15">15. Oct.
              31</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>170 E 79 Str. c/o Mrs. Freeman.</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>Lieber, verehrter <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"
            >Meister</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/5, p. 3673, October 27, 1931: "Von
            Weisse (Br. vom 15. X.): Bericht über überraschende Erfolge für mich u. ihn u. über den
            Schülerstand." ("From Weisse (letter of October 15): report on astonishing successes for
            me and him, and on the number of pupils."). — Two days later, Schenker forward it to
            Moriz Violin. (The diary for October 13 poignantly records: "An Frau Hertha Weisse (Br.
            Lie-Liechen): ladet zum „Herz ausschütten“ ein." ("To Mrs. Hertha Weisse (letter from
            Lie-Liechen): she invites her to 'pour her heart out.')".)</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Nun bin ich schon so sehr eingewöhnt, dass ich glaube, Ihnen berichten zu dürfen, ohne
        dass meine Urteile allzu schief ausfallen. Im übrigen ist ja für’s erste mir von der Sache
        selbst, meinem Wirkungskreis zu berichten und da glaube ich jetzt schon sagen zu können,
        dass ich es nicht besser hätte treffen können. Der Geist<tei:supplied reason="punctuation"
          >,</tei:supplied> der durch die beiden Leiter der <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002454">Schule</tei:rs>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004633">Mr.</tei:rs> und <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-004634">Mrs. Mannes</tei:rs> in die Lehrerschaft verpflanzt wurde<tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> war die beste Vorbereitung für das, was ich ihnen zu
        bringen hatte.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Vorige Woche wurde mir zu Ehren, ehe die <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002454">Schule</tei:rs> eröffnet <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >wurde</tei:add><tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> eine Versammlung der
        Lehrerschaft abgehalten und ich hielt mein Debut mit einem 25-30 Minuten lang währenden
        Vortrag über das Verhältnis des Theorielehrers zu den andern Lehrern einer Musikschule in
        englischer Sprache. Der Erfolg, abgesehen vom persönlichen, <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">war</tei:add> der, dass sich 15 Lehrer und Lehrerinnen meldeten, <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overwritten">mir</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="superimposed">um</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> mit mir zu arbeiten, und 1 mal in der Woche regelmässig zusammen<tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">zu</tei:add>kommen, um die neuen Begriffe kennen zu lernen.
        Ferner: der zweite Theorielehrer<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> ein um
        etwa 15 Jahre älterer Mann als ich, nimmt regelmässig bei mir Unterricht, um allmählich
        alle, die obligat Theorie als Neben- <tei:pb n="2"/> fach zu lernen haben in der gleichen
        Weise und Anschauung anzuleiten, wie ich es tue. Ich selbst habe zwei verschiedene Klassen
        zu je 6 Schülern, eine Kompositionsklasse mit 3 Schülern, und noch 5–6 Privat<tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">stunden</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">schüler à 2 Stunden</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> alles in allem daweil gegen 22 Schüler. Die Gesichter von allen leuchten, schon
        bei der ersten Grundsteinlegung der Begriffe: <tei:term>Kpt</tei:term> und
          <tei:term>Harmonie</tei:term> – und ich bin überzeugt, dass sich <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">der</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">die Nachricht vom</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> Einzug der neuen Lehre wie ein Lauffeuer verbreiten wird.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Morgen treffe ich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000939">Mr. Wedge</tei:rs>, der
        obersten Leiter des <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002437">Institute of Musical
          Art</tei:rs>, der schon längere Zeit nach Ihren Büchern unterrichtet und schon darauf
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">brennt<tei:supplied reason="punctuation"
            >,</tei:supplied></tei:add> mich kennenzulernen um mehr zu erfahren.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Alles übrige versteht sich eigentlich von selbst: wer stark nach innen lebt, dem
        erscheint die äussere Umgebung nicht so verwirrend. Jedesfalls fühlte ich mich vom ersten
        Tag an zu Hause hier, das einzige woran ich mich gewöhnen musste, war der
        Strassenlärm.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Alles andere ist aber zu ertragen und vor allem erfreue ich mich der Freundschaft von
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004633">Mr.</tei:rs> und <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-004634">Mrs. Mannes</tei:rs>, die für mich wie Eltern sorgen, in deren Heim
        ein durchaus europäische Athmosphäre herrscht und mit denen das Zusammenarbeiten ein
        direktes Vergnügen ist.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Soviel für heute, aus <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002589"
          >Hamburg</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">At the
          invitation of Moriz Violin, head of the newly founded Schenker-Institut in Hamburg, Weisse
          gave a lecture there the day before setting sail for America: see <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-15-16_81">OJ 15/16, [81]</tei:ref>.</tei:note> haben Sie
        jedesfalls mehr erfahren als ich, denn ich habe gar nichts gehört. Schreiben Sie bitte
        bald.</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Ihnen und Ihrer <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
            >Frau</tei:rs> alles Liebe von Ihrem</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person"><tei:hi
              rend="lateinschr">H</tei:hi></tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address rend="indent-60">
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#HW"/>170 East 79th Street, New York</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine> c/o Mrs. Freeman, <tei:date when="1931-10-15">October 15,
            1931</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>Dear, revered <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Master</tei:rs><tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>I am now so well settled in that I believe I may be allowed to report to you without my
        judgments going too far astray. Moreover, I must report first of all about my work and my
        working environment; and here I believe I am able to say that things could not have gone
        better. The spirit that has been instilled in the teaching staff by the two directors of the
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002454">School</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-004633">Mr.</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004634">Mrs.
          Mannes</tei:rs>, was the best preparation for that which I had to offer them.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Last week, before the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002454">School</tei:rs>
        was in session, a gathering of the faculty was arranged in my honor, and I gave my debut
        with a presentation, of 25 to 30 minutes' duration, about the relationship of the theory
        teacher to the other teachers in a music school ‒ in English. The effect, apart from the
        personal success, <tei:add place="interlinear-above">was</tei:add> that fifteen teachers,
        male and female, applied to work with me, and to get together once a week in order to learn
        the new concepts. Further: the second theory teacher, a man about fifteen years older than
        myself, receives regular tuition from me so that he can eventually teach everyone who must
        study theory as a subsidiary subject <tei:pb n="2"/> in the same way and from the same point
        of view as I do. I myself have two different classes with six pupils in each, a composition
        class with three pupils, and a further five or six private <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">lessons</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">pupils for two hours each</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>: all in all about twenty-two pupils at present. Their faces all light up, even
        when I lay the foundation stones of the concepts "<tei:term>counterpoint</tei:term>" and
          "<tei:term>harmony</tei:term>"; and I am convinced that the <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">news of the</tei:add> introduction of the new theory will spread
        like a brush fire.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Tomorrow I am meeting <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000939">Mr. Wedge</tei:rs>, the
        Dean of the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002437">Institute of Musical
          Art</tei:rs>, who has already been teaching from your books for a considerable time and
        who <tei:add place="interlinear-above">is keenly</tei:add> looking forward to meeting me, in
        order to find out more.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Everything else actually fits into place: anyone who lives strongly within himself will
        find that his external surroundings are not so bewildering. In any event, I felt at home
        from the first day; the only thing that I had to get used to was the street noise.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Everything else, however, I can bear; and above all I take joy from the friendship of
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004633">Mr.</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-004634">Mrs. Mannes</tei:rs>, who look after me as parents, in whose home a
        thoroughly European atmosphere reigns, and with whom collaboration is an unalloyed
        pleasure.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>So much for today. About <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002589"
          >Hamburg</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> you will have learned
        more than I, for I have not heard a thing. Please write soon.</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">To you and your <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
            >wife</tei:rs>, all good wishes from your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person"
          >H</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
