<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3376" sdoID="OJ-14-5_26">OJ 14/5, [26]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="MS" scope="sole">Moriz Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>


    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2023</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2023</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-21" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence">Schenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-004924">SchenkerM ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Moriz Schenker to Heinrich Schenker, dated May 18,
        1929</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1929-05-18T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-02-14</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Having made an investment in a property (Arzberg) purchased by Moriz Schenker,
        Heinrich has got cold feet and has asked to withdraw his share of the asset. Moriz explains
        the situation and tries to reassure Heinrich, while at the same time outlining steps whereby
        he could eventually pay Heinrich back. He questions Heinrich's pessimism, and points out
        that Heinrich is at the peak of his creative powers.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000774">Moriz Schenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
      
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#MS"/>Wien, Bureau Samstag früh <tei:date
            when="1929-05-18">18/5 1929</tei:date><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
            place="foot">Date underlined in crayon by Heinrich.</tei:note></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Meine Lieben!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
            place="foot">Receipt of this letter and Heinrich’s reply are recorded in Heinrich’s
            diary for May 20, 1929: “Von Mozio (Br.): bittet um Geduld bis zum Herbst, er müßte
            sonst eine Hypothek aufnehmen. — An Mozio (Br.): keine Nervosität bei mir, sondern
            billige Erwägung dessen, was nach meinem oder seinem Tode geschehen müßte, also eine
            Vorbeugung.” (“From Mozio (letter): he asks us to be patient until the autumn, otherwise
            he would have to take out a mortgage. — To Mozio (letter): no nervousness on my part,
            but rather a simple consideration of what must come to pass after my death or his; thus
            a precautionary measure.”). — Where Moriz has inserted dashes, paragraph-breaks have
            been editorially introduced</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Deine l. Zeilen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Heinrich’s diary for May 15, 1929 records: “im Graben-Café treffen wir mit Mozio
          zusammen, er empfiehlt Schatzscheine; lügt wie immer.” (“in the Café Graben we meet up
          with Mozio; he recommends treasury notes, lies as always.”), and that for May 16: “An
          Mozio (Br. 6 Seiten): laut Abschrift qualvoll genug.” (“To Mozio (letter, 6 pages):
          according to the transcript, painful enough!”). The latter is not known to
          survive.</tei:note> von vorgestern habe ich gestern Abend in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002349">Baden</tei:rs> vorgefunden u. beeile ich mich dieselben umgehend zu
        beantworten. Aus Deinen Ausführungen ersehe ich, dass Ihr wegen Eures Guthabens bei mir
        etwas nervös geworden seid, wozu wahrhaftig gar kein Grund vorliegt. Ich habe angesichts
        Deiner Kündigung,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">“Deine
          Kündigung” (“your notice to withdraw”): underlined in crayon by Heinrich. — In his diary
          for June 4, Heinrich writes to his elder brother Wilhelm “about giving notice (<tei:hi
            rend="italic">Kündigung</tei:hi>) concerning my account with Mozio (<tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-38_56">OJ 5/38, [56]</tei:ref>).</tei:note> die Du nur
        aus Vorsicht u. Befürchtung, dass in einigen Jahren politische internationale Verrichtungen
        entstehen könnten, das Bargeld nicht vorrätig, um es Dir sofort auszufolgen.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">“das Bargeld … auszu-” (“the cash ...
          instantly”): underlined in crayon by Heinrich.</tei:note> Anderseits ist der Zustand für
        uns, dass mein <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003438">Liserl</tei:rs> in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-005929">Oberoesterreich</tei:rs> sitzen muss, um das Gut zu
        behüten, welches eine sehr bescheidene Verzinsung bietet, unerträglich, und da habe ich
        Deine Kündigung auch zum Anlass genommen, um den <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-008410">Arzberg</tei:rs> zu verkaufen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06"
          type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-008410"
            >Gutsverwaltung Arzberg (Property Management Arzberg)</tei:rs> was a company in <tei:rs
            type="place" key="entity-004104">Reichraming</tei:rs>; Moriz may be the initiator of the
          company, or just the owner of a property; whichever it is, it forms the basis of his
          family investment. — “Deine … verkaufen” (“your withdrawal … Arzberg”): underlined in
          crayon by Heinrich.</tei:note> Ich stehe jetzt in diesbezüglichen Verhandlungen, will aber
        das Gut, in welches wir nachgewiesenermaßen im Jahre 1918 fünfhunderttausend Goldkronen u.
        später an 3.8 Milliarden hineingesteckt haben, nicht um jeden Preis verkaufen, denn das wäre
        ja eine Sünde. Ich stehe daher mit mehreren Interessenten in Verbindung, u. ziehen sich die
        Verhandlungen hin. Sollten diese Verhandlungen nicht so ausfallen, wie wir es wünschen,
        werde ich im Herbst eine Hypothek bei der Oberoesterr. Landeshypotheken-Anstalt auf 42½
        Jahre aufnehmen u. Dir sofort das ganze Guthaben in Dollars mit Zinsen ausfolgen.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">“Dir sofort … ausfolgen” (“issue ...
          interest”): underlined in crayon and sidelined in the left margin by Heinrich.</tei:note>
        Ich habe nur aus dem Grunde Deine Kündigung als nicht so brennend angesehen, weil ich
        dachte, dass Ihr wegen des Geldes, welchem doch Grund und Boden gegenübersteht, nicht
        beunruhigt seid. Im Gegenteil, ich wollte Dir demnächst sagen, dass ich angesichts der
        jetzigen Verhandlungen Euch <tei:del rend="overstrike">umsoferne</tei:del> um einen Aufschub
        des Termines<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot">“Terminus”
          (“deadline”): which was apparently June 15, 1929. See in this respect <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-5_25">OJ 14/5, [25]</tei:ref>, December 9,
          1928.</tei:note> bitten muss, um spätestens im Herbst den ganzen Betrag flüssig zu machen.
        Das Gut, das unbedingt einen Wert von 4½ Milliarden hat, welchen Betrag man bei den heutigen
          <tei:pb n="2"/> Verhältnissen gewiss nicht erzielen kann, habe ich mir seinerzeit auch als
        Ruhesitz für die älteren Tage gedacht. Wenn aber die Bewirtschaftung mit solchen Opfern
        verbunden ist, dass eine Familie zerrissen wird, ich auch mit flüssigem Geld etwas
        unternehmen könnte, so hat die Sache für uns keinen Sinn. Ich habe ja das für unser Leben
        notwendige Fixum als Vertreter einer rumänischen Bank bei der hiesigen
          Bodencredit-Anstalt,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09" type="editorial" place="foot">“Ich habe
          … Anstalt” (“I have .. Credit Bank”): lightly sidelined in the left margin by Heinrich.
          Boden-Creditanstalt was an all-Austrian bank located in Vienna Leinfaltstrasse 8, founded
          in 1863 and in 1929 absorbed into the larger Creditanstalt.</tei:note> bin aber, wie Du
        siehst, nicht in der Lage grössere Beträge sofort flüssig zu machen. Um solchen
        Eventualitäten auszuweichen, denken wir daran, das Gut zu verkaufen, u. wenn dies nicht
        halbwegs günstig geht, zu hypotezieren. Ich habe ja ausser dem Gut ein grosses Depot bei der
        Rumänischen Kreditbank <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002526">Bucharest</tei:rs>,<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn10" type="editorial" place="foot">. “grosses … Bucharest” (“larger deposit
          ... Bucharest”): underlined in crayon by Heinrich.</tei:note> deren Generaldirektor ich
        war, dieses Depot ist als oesterr. Guthaben unter Sequester.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11"
          type="editorial" place="foot">“Ich habe … Sequester” (“I have ... under sequester”):
          sidelined in left margin by Heinrich.</tei:note> Es ist zu hoffen, dass den
        oesterreichischen Guthabungen in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-005391">Rumänien</tei:rs>
        endlich bald freigegeben sein werden. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Wie Ihr seht, bin ich noch solvent<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12"
          type="editorial" place="foot">“noch solvent” (“still solvent”): underlined in crayon by
          Heinrich.</tei:note> u. Gott sei Dank gesund. Ich werde in den nächsten Monaten noch
        hoffentlich am Leben bleiben und Euch Euer Guthaben liquidieren.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn13" type="editorial" place="foot">“und Euch ... liqidieren” (“and will ...
          asset”): underlined in crayon by Heinrich.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Warum bist Du in Deinem Schreiben so pessimistisch und sprichst von
        Krankheit, Not und Tot?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14" type="editorial" place="foot">“von ...
          Tot?” (of illness ... death?”): underlined in crayon by Heinrich.</tei:note> Wenn ich nach
        den grossen Aufregungen in der <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-004196"
          >Treuga</tei:rs> und der Entwertung von 900000 Goldkronen Kriegsanleihe, welche heute
        keine 10 Schillinge wert sind, nicht den Hut sinken lasse, sondern noch hoffe, wieder zu
        schaffen, um viel, viel später einmal meiner Familie doch etwas schöner zuwie hinterlassen,
        so dürfst Ihr zwei Menschen wegen eines Schülers, der vielleicht im Herbst ausbleiben wird,
        nicht sofort verzweifeln!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15" type="editorial" place="foot">“dürfst
          ... verzweifeln?” (“ought not ... despair”): underlined in crayon by Heinrich. It is
          unclear who the school child referred to might be.</tei:note> Ich bin viel jünger als Du,
        aber Du bist Gott sei Dank gesund und auf der Höhe der Schaffenskraft. Ich bin davon
        überzeugt, dass in kürzer Zeit die Menschen, welche auf der Höhe der Kultur stehen, Deine
        Autorität, u. deine Werke so einschätzen werden, dass Ihr noch viele Freuden in Gesundheit
        u. Wohlhabenheit erleben werdet. Dass Ihr das Geld von nur nicht gestern, sondern in den
        nächsten Monaten bekommen werdet, ist gewiss kein Unglück. Sollte ich aber bis zum <tei:date
          when="1929-06-15">15. Juni</tei:date><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn16" type="editorial"
          place="foot">In his diary for June 6, Heinrich writes: “An Mozio (Br.): recomm. Mahnung –
          wir kommen am 15. d. um 10<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> u. holen das Geld” (“To
          Mozio (registered letter): notice – we are coming on the 15th of the month at 10 o'clock
          to collect the money.”), and on June 14 her writes: “An Wilhelm (Br.): melde die
          Rückzahlung der Hälfte unseres Guthabens bei Mozio; kündige unseren Besuch an.” (“To
          Wilhelm (letter): I report the repayment of half of our asset holdings at Mozio's; I
          announce our next visit.”).</tei:note> vielleicht schon so weit <tei:pb n="3"/> kommen,
        dass etwas perfekt wird, so werde ich Euch sofort den ganzen Betrag und nicht die Hälfte
        ausfolgen. Am liebsten hätte ich Euch auf Deinem Brief besucht, ich wusste aber nicht, wann
        ich nicht störe. Vielleicht geht es, dass wir uns die nächste Woche sehen? Bis dahin
        verbleibe ich mit herzlichen Küssen </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Eur</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774"
          >Moriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p>Da ich täglich <tei:subst>
            <tei:del rend="overstrike">um</tei:del>
            <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ab</tei:add>
          </tei:subst> ½9<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> früh bis ½6<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
            >h</tei:hi> Abends in Wien bin, gebe ich Euch auch meine Wiener Adresse auf: I
          Wächtergasse N<tei:hi rend="supralinear">o</tei:hi> 1 Telefon U 24420 </tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>



    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#MS"/>Vienna office, Saturday morning <tei:date
            when="1929-05-18">May 18, 1929</tei:date><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"
          /></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">My dears,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"
          /></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">I came upon your letter of two days ago<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
          type="footnote"/> in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002349">Baden</tei:rs> yesterday
        evening, and hasten to reply to it by return post. From your remarks, I see that you have
        become nervous about the asset holding you have deposited with me – for which in truth there
        is no basis. Faced with your notice of withdrawal<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
          type="footnote"/> – which you <tei:supplied reason="clarity">give</tei:supplied> only out
        of caution and apprehension that adverse international political events might occur in a few
        years’ time – I do not have the cash available to issue it to you instantly.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> By comparison, the situation for us is that my
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003438">Liserl</tei:rs> has, unbearably, to remain in
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-005929">Upper Austria</tei:rs> in order to protect the
        property that yields a very meager rent, and now I have taken notice of your withdrawal also
        as an opportunity to sell <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-008410"
          >Arzberg</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> I am now in the throes
        of negotiations, but will not sell the property – in which, in the year 1918, we
        demonstrably invested 500,000 Gold Kronen and later 3.8 billion – at that price, for that
        would be a sin. Accordingly, I am in touch with several interested parties, and negotiations
        are proceeding. Should these negotiations not work out as we wish, I will take out a
        mortgage in the autumn with the Upper Austrian Agricultural Mortgage Bank for 42½ years and
        promptly issue you with the entire asset holding in dollars with interest.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> I had no idea how serious you were about your
        notice of withdrawal, because I thought you were not anxious about the money, since it is
        linked to real estate. On the contrary, in the near future I was going to say to you that in
        view of the current negotiations you must ask for a deferment of the deadline<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/> in order at the latest in the autumn to liquidize
        the entire sum. The property, which absolutely has a value of 4½ billion, which figure no
        one under today’s <tei:pb n="2"/> conditions can achieve, I had thought of at the time as a
        place of retirement for our later life. But if managing it is tied to such sacrifices that a
        family is torn apart, the matter makes no sense for us when I could undertake something even
        with liquid money. I have a fixed income necessary for our life, as representative of a
        Rumanian bank through the Land Credit Bank;<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09" type="footnote"/>
        but I am, as you see, not in a position the make larger sums of money liquid immediately. In
        order to avoid such eventualities, we are thinking of selling the property, and if this
        doesn’t go half as well as we hoped, to resort to mortgaging. Apart from the asset, I have a
        large deposit in the Rumanian Credit Bank of <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002526"
          >Bucharest</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn10" type="footnote"/> of which I was the
        general director; this deposit is, as an Austrian asset, under sequester.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn11" type="footnote"/> We can only hope that the Austrian asset holding
        in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-005391">Rumania</tei:rs> will at last soon be
        unfrozen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>As you can see, I am still solvent<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn12" type="footnote"/> and,
        thank God, in good health. In the coming months I will, I hope, still be in the land of the
        living, and will liquidate your asset.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn13" type="footnote"
        /></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Why in your letter are you so pessimistic and speak of illness, hardship, and
          death?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn14" type="footnote"/> If after the big upheavals at the
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-004196">Treuga Bank</tei:rs> and the devaluation
        from <tei:supplied reason="clarity">a</tei:supplied> 900,000 Gold Kronen war bond that is
        today worth not even 10 shillings, I am not letting the ship sink, but rather am still
        hoping to accomplish things again, <tei:supplied reason="clarity">and</tei:supplied> much,
        much later to leave my family something rather more elegant, then you two people ought not,
        on account of a school child who will perhaps withdraw in the autumn, so soon to
          despair.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn15" type="footnote"/> I am much younger than you, but
        thank God you are in good health and at the height of your creative powers. I am convinced
        that in no time at all people in the higher echelons of culture will value your authority
        and your publications to such an extent that you will have many joys in health and
        prosperity still to experience. That you will get the money not only from time gone by but
        also in the coming months is truly no misfortune. But if by any chance I have, come
          <tei:date when="1929-06-15">June 15</tei:date>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn16"
          type="footnote"/>
        <tei:pb n="3"/> made so much headway that something perfect will come about, then I will
        issue you immediately the whole sum and not the half <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of
          it</tei:supplied>. I would greatly have preferred to come and seen you about your letter,
        but I did not know when I could avoid disturbing you. Perhaps it might be possible for us to
        see each other next week? Until then, I remain with heartfelt kisses</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774"
          >Moriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p>Since every day I am in Vienna from 8.30 a.m. to 5.30 p.m., let me give you my Vienna
          address: I Wächtergasse 1, telephone U 24420. </tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>



    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
