<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="70" sdoID="OJ-11-17_3">OJ 11/17, [3]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="sole">printed</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2010</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2010</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML encoding</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-23" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002729">GärtnerP ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002749">Announcement</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Printed funeral notice for Eduard Gärtner to Schenker, dated July 2, 1918</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1918-07-02T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2010-03-23</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Announces death and date and time of funeral of Eduard Gärtner. </dc:description>
      <dc:subject>death; Leichenbegängnis; funeral; Aufbahrungshalle; funeral parlor;
        mortuary</dc:subject>




      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000274">GärtnerE</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:note type="editorial">centered emblem: cross</tei:note>

      <tei:p rend="first">Allen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">While
          receipt of this notice is not itself recorded in Schenker's diary, there is an extensive
          entry at OJ 2/11, p. 913, July 3, 1918, of how the Heinrich and Jeanette learned of his
          death: " Zu Gärtners: erfahre auf der Straße vom Briefträger, daß Gärtner schon
          verschieden sei. Die Familie zuhause angetroffen, bis ¾11h geblieben; erfahre die näheren
          Umstände der letzten Tage, von den schweren Operationen, die der Aermste zu bestehen
          hatte, aber auch, daß er glücklicherweise sanft u. ohne Bewußtsein eingeschlafen.
          Beantrage, in der Parte seine werktätige Anteilnahme an den Mitmenschen hervorzuheben, die
          in der Tat zueigen war; fasse aus Eigenem den Entschluss, den ich auch der Familie
          mitteile, an Karpath einen Expreßbrief zu richten, um ihm Anhaltspunkte für eine halbwegs
          gerechte Würdigung des Dahingegangenen zu ermöglichen, wie ich mich auch bereit erkläre,
          Herrn Dr. Müller zur Verfügung zu stehen, der, wie der Sohn Hans mitteilt, die Aufgabe
          übernommen hat, eine ausführliche Würdigung in der „N. Fr. Pr.“ zu bringen. In der Tat
          empfinde ich es nicht erst unter dem schmerzlichen Drucke seines Todes, daß er vielfache
          Verdienste um das Musikleben, freilich an dem Berufe eines Sängers gemessen, sich erworben
          u. noch mehr sich hätte erwerben können, wenn er klüger, neidloser, freundschaftlicher den
          Weg auch weiterhin mit mir fortgesetzt hätte, wie er ihn jahrelang gegangen. Doch soll ihm
          trotz allem nicht vergessen werden, daß er vielen Liederkomponisten die erste Gelegenheit
          gegeben, hervorzutreten, sowohl als Komponisten als auch begleitend, daß er sich die
          würdigsten Kunstaufgaben (zum größten Teil wohl über meine Anregung) sich vorsetzte u.
          löste, daß er zur Musik in einem viel breiteren Verhältnis als andere Sänger stand usw."
          ("To Gärtner's: on the way, I hear from the postman that Gärtner has already died.
          Arriving at their home, I meet the family, staying until 10:45; I am told about the
          circumstances of the last few days, about the severe operations which the poor man had to
          endure, but also that fortunately he had died peacefully in his sleep without regaining
          consciousness. I propose that in the death notice his efficacious sympathy for the needs
          of others, which in fact was quite innate in him, should be stressed. Of my own accord I
          resolve to send an express letter to Karpath, a decision I also communicate to the family,
          in order to give him advice about how to facilitate a halfway fitting tribute to the
          deceased, as I also declare my preparedness to be available for Dr. Müller, who, as his
          son Hans informs us, is to undertake the task of providing a detailed obituary for the
          Neue Freie Presse. In fact, the painful experience of his death is not the first occasion
          that sets me thinking how copious his services to music have been, naturally measured
          within the context of a singer's profession, but also that they could have been even
          greater had he continued to accompany me on my path [through life] with more acumen, with
          less envy, with more affability, as he did for so many years. But it should never be
          forgotten of him that he gave many Lieder composers their first opportunity to come to the
          fore, not just as composers but also as accompanists, and that he undertook and performed
          the worthiest of musical tasks (to be sure most of them at my instigation), and that his
          attitude to music was much broader than that of other singers, and so forth"). Their
          decision as to the service is recorded ibid, July 4, 1918: "An Frau Gärtner (Br.): bitte
          in meinem wie Lie-Liechens Name um Entschuldigung wegen unseres Entschlusses, morgen an
          der Leichenfeier nicht teilzunehmen." ("To Mrs. Gärtner (letter): asking her in my name as
          well as in Lie-Liechen's for forgiveness for our decision not to participate in the burial
          service tomorrow."). See also correspondence with Ludwig Karpath, OJ 12/9, [22] and [23],
          July 18 abd 28, 1918. </tei:note> unseren Freunden die tieftraurige Kunde, daß mein
        innigstgeliebter Mann, unser fürsorglicher, für das Wohl der Familie allzeitbereiter Vater,
        Bruder und Onke <tei:list type="simple">
          <tei:item><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000274"> Eduard Gärtner </tei:rs>
            <tei:lb/>Musiker,</tei:item>
        </tei:list> am 2. Juli d. J. um 6 Uhr abends nach langem, schweren Leiden im 56. Lebensjahre
        sanft verschieden ist. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Das unerbittlich wirkende Schicksal hat ein Leben voll rastloser Arbeit,
        voll hingebungsvoller, werktätiger Anteilnahme an jedem seiner Mitmenschen allzufrüh
        beendet. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Das Leichenbegängnis findet Freitag, den 5. Juli d. J. nachmittags 3½ Uhr
        von der Aufbahrungshalle des Zentralfriedhofes (Haupttor) aus statt. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Wien</tei:rs>, den <tei:date
          when="1918-07-02">2. Juli 1918</tei:date>. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>
        <tei:list type="simple">
          <tei:note type="editorial">list in two columns:</tei:note>

          <tei:item><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000277"> Poldi Gärtner </tei:rs>
            <tei:lb/>als Gattin</tei:item>
          <tei:item><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002517"> Ernst Gärtner </tei:rs><tei:lb/>k. u.
            k. Leutnant i. d. R.</tei:item>
          <tei:item><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-000276"> Hans Gärtner </tei:rs><tei:lb/>k. u.
            k. Leutnant i. d. R.<tei:lb/>als Söhne</tei:item>
          <tei:item><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002518"> Ing. Emil Gaertner
            </tei:rs><tei:lb/>Oberstaatsbahnrat<tei:lb/>als Bruder</tei:item>
          <tei:item><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002519"> Xenia Dolores Gaertner
            </tei:rs><tei:lb/>als Nichte </tei:item>
        </tei:list>
      </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>Gemeinde Wien. — Stadt. Leichenbestattung, III., Borromäuspl. 1, Tel. 9688. Druck:
        Krempel, III., Rochusg. 2.</tei:closer>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:p rend="first">To<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> all our friends, the
        very sad news that my deeply-beloved husband, our solicitous father, brother, and uncle,
        always attentive to the well-being of his family <tei:list type="simple">
          <tei:item><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000274"> Eduard Gärtner </tei:rs>
            <tei:lb/>musician,</tei:item>
        </tei:list> passed away peacefully on July 2 of this year at 6 p.m., after long and hard
        suffering in his 56th year. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">The inexorable working of fate has ended all too soon a life full of
        ceaseless work, full of devoted, unfailing sympathy for every one of his fellow human
        beings. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">The funeral rite will take place on Friday July 5 of this year, at 3.30
        p.m. setting out from the funeral parlor of the Central Cemetery (main door). </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Vienna</tei:rs>, <tei:date
          when="1918-07-02">2. July 2,1918</tei:date>. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>
        <tei:list type="simple">
          <tei:note type="editorial">list in two columns:</tei:note>

          <tei:item><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000277"> Poldi Gärtner </tei:rs>
            <tei:lb/>as wife</tei:item>
          <tei:item><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002517"> Ernst Gärtner
            </tei:rs><tei:lb/>Imp-Royal 2nd Lieutenant</tei:item>
          <tei:item>
            <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000276">Hans Gärtner</tei:rs><tei:lb/>Imp-Royal 2nd
            Lieutenant<tei:lb/>as sons</tei:item>
          <tei:item><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002518"> Emil Gaertner, engineer
            </tei:rs><tei:lb/>General Superindendant of the State Railways<tei:lb/>as
            brother</tei:item>
          <tei:item><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002519"> Xenia Dolores Gaertner
            </tei:rs><tei:lb/>as niece </tei:item>
        </tei:list>
      </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>Municipality of Vienna. — City Funeral Services, III, Borromäusplatz 1, Tel. 9688.
        Printer: Krempel, III, Rochusgasse 2.</tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
