<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="268" sdoID="OJ-11-35-17">OJ 11/35, 17</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="AHa" scope="sole">August Halm's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="LR">
   <tei:persName>Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2010</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>


  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-12-07" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">
  <sdo:itemDesc><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002698">Halm ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   
   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated April 13, 1920</dc:title>
   
   <dcterms:created>1920-04-13T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-03-21</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Halm acknowledges receipt of DLA 69.930/9; voices misgivings about publishing
    with UE and discusses publishers' unscrupulous tactics and the difficulty of legal redress. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Taktik; tactics; Manöver; maneuvers; Verleger; publisher; Gericht; judge; Abrechnung;
    settlement </dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000326">Halm</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:date when="1920-04-13" rend="indent-80">13. IV. 20.</tei:date>
    <tei:salute>Lieber u. verehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Ich<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is
     recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/1, p. 2227, April 17, 1920: "Von Halm (Br.): möchte unter
     solchen Umständen mit der U.-E. lieber nichts zu tun haben, – habe gegen seinen Verleger zwei
     Prozesse geführt u. stehe jetzt vor der 2. Auflage. " ("From Halm (letter): under those
     conditions, he would rather having nothing to do with UE, – he has brought two lawsuits against
     his publisher and is now awaiting the second edition."). </tei:note> danke Ihnen für Ihren
    ausführlichen Brief.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">= DLA 69.930/9,
     January 18, 1920. </tei:note> Demnach möchte ich mit der <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">Universal-Edit.</tei:rs> lieber gar nicht anknüpfen. Man muß sich freilich vielleicht
    einmal entscheiden, ob man nicht doch lieber auch unter <tei:hi rend="underline">ganz
     schlechten</tei:hi> Bedingungen etwas veröffentlicht, was man eben für das Ergehen der Musik
    für wichtig hält. Und die großen Herrn u. Räuber vertreiben die Sachen (in allgemeinen) doch
    noch am besten, so daß der Zweck eher erfüllt wird. Aber was Sie mir von dem Herrn schreiben,
    geht über das Maß, u. man sollte (wenn man dazu eben irgendwie in der Lage ist) diese
     <tei:unclear reason="reading">Geschäftsmänner</tei:unclear> kaltstellen anstatt sie durch
    Erfolg zu krönen. Das ist ja alles bewußte Taktik, Ermüdungs- u. Aufreibungstaktik. Die Verleger
    haben Zeit u. Kraft dazu, es ist ihr Metier, ihre Lebensgabe, u. <tei:pb n="2"/> sie wissen, daß
    wir keine Zeit dazu haben u. irgendwann einmal nachgeben werden, so daß sie trotz ihrer dümmsten
    u. plümpsten Manöver immer noch uns überlegen sind. Ich meine, wir müßten ihren gerade diesen
    Trumpf vorweg aus der Hand schlagen; in diesem Fall: Sie sollten sich solche Mißachtung Ihrer
    Zeit durch des Verlegers Unzuverläßigkeit bzw. Zurückziehen verabredeter Dinge ein für allemal
    verbitten, u. erklären, daß Sie dergleichen als Abbrechen der möglichen Beziehungen seinerseits
    verstehen. Und dann, im Fall der <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001729"><tei:title>Instrumentationslehre</tei:title></tei:rs> einfach klagen, vorausgesetzt, daß Sie
    Beweise oder so gegründeten Verdacht haben, daß das Gericht seine Bücher nachsehen lassen muß.
    Das kann natürl. nur ein guter Rechtsanwalt beurteilen. Ich habe den <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002410">Gg. Müllerverlag</tei:rs> schon 2 mal wegen säumiger Abrechnung
    verklagt, u. stehe immer noch ganz gut zu ihm. Er macht eben eine 2. Auflage meines
     <tei:title>Kulturbuchs</tei:title>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:title level="m">Von zwei Kulturen der Musik</tei:title> (Munich: George Müller Verlag,
     1913); the second edition appeared in 1920, by the same publisher. </tei:note>
   </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:note type="editorial">valediction and signature written vertically in right margin: </tei:note>
    <tei:salute>Herzlich grüße ich Sie. </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute>Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed>A. Halm</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:date when="1920-04-13" rend="indent-80">April 13, 1920</tei:date>
    <tei:salute>Dear and revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Thank<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> you for your detailed
     letter.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> According to its content, I would
    prefer not to hook up with <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">Universal Edition</tei:rs> at
    all. One must naturally decide whether one prefers to publish, even under <tei:hi rend="underline">very unfavorable</tei:hi> conditions, something that one considers important
    for the welfare of music. And the high profile gentlemen and crooks market things best (in
    general) so that the objective is sooner achieved. However, what you write me about the
    gentleman goes beyond the measure, and one should neutralize these <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">businessmen</tei:unclear> (if one is somehow in a position to do it)
    instead of crowning them with success. That is all intentional tactics, to wear down and
    annihilate. Publishers have the time and power for it. It is their element, their life’s knack,
    and <tei:pb n="2"/> they know that we have no time for it and at some point will give in, so
    that they still have the upper hand over us despite their dumbest and crudest maneuvers. I mean,
    we would have to eliminate that trump card from their hand up front. In that case, you should
    refuse once and for all to tolerate such disrespect of your time by the publisher’s
    unreliability or, as the case may be, retracting agreed upon items. And then, in case of the
    <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001729"><tei:title>manual of orchestration</tei:title></tei:rs> simply complain,
    provided that you have evidence or sufficiently substantiated suspicion that the court has to
    have their books audited. Of course only a good lawyer can judge that. I have already brought
    legal action against the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002410">Georg Müller publishing
     house</tei:rs> two times because of delinquent settlements, and still get along with him
    quite well. He is presently doing the second edition of my <tei:title level="m">Two
     Cultures</tei:title> book.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/>
   </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:note type="editorial">valediction and signature written vertically in right margin: </tei:note>
    <tei:salute>With warm greetings, </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute>Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed>A. Halm</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>

 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>