<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="1659" sdoID="OJ-15-22_2">OJ 15/22, [2]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="MW" scope="sole">Manfred Willfort's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>


  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2016</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2016</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Encoding, 2016</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-09-05" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006170">WillfortM ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>




   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Willfort to Schenker, dated June 7, 1932</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1932-06-07T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2016-02-08</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Willfort and Greta Kraus are still uncertain as to whether they will be able to
    participate in Schenker's seminar next academic year.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Veröffentlichung; publication; Entscheidung; decision; Teilnahme; participation;
    Schüler; pupils</dc:subject>



   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000964">Manfred Willfort</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60">Wien, III., Jacquing. 37</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:date when="1932-06-07">7. Juni
     1932</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"
      >Doktor</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this
      letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/5, p. 3736, June 7, 1932: "Von Wilfort (Br.
      durch Boten): Vorbehalt für die nächste Saison auch im Namen des Frl. Kraus." ("From Wilfort
      (letter via messenger): reservations about next season, also on behalf of Miss
      Kraus.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Der Umstand, daß die geplante Veröffentlichung erst zum Ziel geschehen
     ist,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The product of the first year
     of <tei:rs key="entity-002499" type="organization">Schenker's seminar</tei:rs>, intended as the
     first volume of <tei:title level="m">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln/Five Analyses in
      Sketch-Form</tei:title>, was received from the printers by Universal Edition on July 25, 1932
     (UE 10.385 Verlagsdruckbuch ‒ Schenker's Preface is dated August 30, but there can be no doubt
     publication occurred before that date). Most likely, Willfort is referring to news that the
     David Mannes Music School was to make a second payment to cover the printing costs (diary, OJ
     4/5, p. 3735, June 4 and 6). — Schenker's diary contains evidence of Willfort's involvement in
     the publication: OJ 4/5, p. 3695, January 7, 1932: "An Korrekturen eines Blattes von Wilfort
     bis ¼11h." ("Work on corrections to a page of Wilfort's until 10:15."); ibid, p. 3700, January
     24, 1932: "An den letzten Korrekturen für Wilfort." ("Work on the final corrections for
     Wilfort."); ibid, p. 3711, March 9, 1932: "Das Wilfort Blatt zu Tomay gebracht." ("Wilfort’s
     page [of Urlinie analysis] brought to [the autographer] Tomay.").</tei:note> erlaubt mir zu
    hoffen, ‒ was gelegentliche Bemerkungen Ihrerseits zu bestätigen schienen ‒ daß Sie die Absicht
    haben, die begonnene Arbeit<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"
     >Presumably the planned but never published second volume of the <tei:title level="m">Fünf
      Ulinie-Tafeln/Five Analyses in Sketch-Form</tei:title>. We know that Willfort graphed the
     third movement of Beethoven's <tei:rs key="entity-001212" type="composition">Piano Sonata in C
      sharp minor, Op. 27, No. 2 ("Moonlight")</tei:rs> ‒ see <tei:ref type="correspondence"
      cRef="OJ-15-22_7">OJ 15/22, [7]</tei:ref>, June 14, 1934; and this work was included in the
     plans for the second volume ‒ see <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Five Graphic Music
       Analyses</tei:title>, ed. <tei:editor>Felix Salzer</tei:editor> (New York: Dover
      Publications, 1969), pp. 18‒19</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> mit uns zu Ende zu führen.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> Ich brauche nicht ausdrücklich zu versichern, mit welcher
    Freude mich dieser Gedanke erfüllt und wie viel mir daran gelegen ist, nächstes Jahr das
    Begonnene fortzusetzen oder überhaupt in irgend einer Form unter Ihrer Führung zu arbeiten. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Anderseits fühle ich mich verpflichtet Ihnen, sehr geehrter Herr Doktor, zu
    sagen, daß ich, ungeachtet meines aufrichtigen Wunsches, im gegenwärtigen Zeitpunkt <tei:pb
     n="3"/> nicht im Stande bin, eine endgültige Entscheidung für den Herbst zu treffen.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Vielmehr muß ich meine weitere Teilnahme schweren Herzens vorderhand als
    ungewiß bezeichnen: Sie hängt nämlich davon ab, ob ich selbst nächstes Jahr genügend Schüler
    (und somit Verdienst) finden werde, worüber ich aber naturgemäß erst im Herbst einen Überblick
    gewinnen kann. (Frl. <tei:rs key="entity-002498" type="person">Kraus</tei:rs> befindet sich in
    derselben Situation: Diese Zeilen sind auch in ihrem Namen geschrieben.)</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> Wenn es also keine allzu große Zumutung bedeutet, ginge unsere Bitte
    dahin, Sie möchten uns gestatten, solcherart vor Abgabe einer bindenden Erklärung die
    Entwicklung der Dinge abzuwarten, von denen leider die Ausführung unserer Absichten abhängt. Es
    versteht sich, daß wir Ihnen hierüber, sobald sich etwas entscheidet ‒ und ich hoffe doch noch:
    im günstigem Sinne ‒ sogleich Nachricht geben werden.</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="5"/> Verzeihen Sie bitte, daß ich Ihnen mit diesem Briefe beschwerlich falle,
    eine Gelegenheit mündlich davon zu sprechen schien sich weniger leicht zu finden.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mit den ergebensten Grüßen</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr dankbarer</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000964">Manfred
     Willfort</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>

  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60">Vienna III, Jacquingasse 37</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:date when="1932-06-07">June 7,
     1932</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dear Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs
       key="entity-000632" type="person">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,<tei:ptr
      corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">The fact that the planned publication has just reached its goal<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> gives me reason to hope ‒ as occasional remarks on your
    part seemed to confirm ‒ that you intend to bring to fruition the work<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> begun with us.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> I don't need spell out what joy this thought fills me with,
    and how very important it is to me to continue next year what has been begun, or at any rate to
    work in some form or another under your direction.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">On the other hand, I feel in duty bound to tell you, dear Dr. [Schenker],
    that, irrespective of my earnest desire, I am not at the present moment <tei:pb n="3"/> in a
    position to reach a final decision as regards the fall.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">On the contrary, I must for the time being with a heavy heart indicate that
    my further participation is uncertain. It depends on whether I myself will find enough pupils
    (and hence income) next year; but this is something of which I naturally cannot get an idea
    until the fall. (Miss <tei:rs key="entity-002498" type="person">Kraus</tei:rs> finds herself in
    the same position: these words are written also on her behalf.)</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> So if it is not too great an imposition we would beg you to permit us
    before making a binding commitment to wait and see how things unfold ‒ things on which, alas,
    the determination of our plans depends. It goes without saying that as soon as something is
    decided ‒ and I still hope that it will be favorable ‒ we will immediately inform you.</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="5"/> Please forgive me that I am making these difficulties for you
    communicating this by letter. It seemed less easy to find an opportunity to speak with you in
    person.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">With the most devoted greetings,</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your grateful</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000964">Manfred
     Willfort</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
