<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3469" sdoID="OJ-14-10_2">OJ 14/10, [2]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RW" scope="sole">Rosa Weil's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008456">WeilR ~
        JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008455">WeilR ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Rosa Weil to Heinrich &amp; Jeanette Schenker, dated
        November 1, 1932</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1932-11-01T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-07-22</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Rosa Weil reports how the news of Hellmut Hatschek’s death had to be broken to
        his parents, and the traumatisation of the entire family. — Klara, always so strong a
        character, reproaches herself for not having prevented the accident; her life’s work is
        extinguished. — Rosa implies that she fears suicide.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>
      
      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000944">Rosa Weil</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RW"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002248"
            >Aussig</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1932-11-01">1. November 32</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>Meine Lieben,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt
            of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for November 2, 1932: “Von Rosl (Br.):
            unsagbar traurig!” (“From Rosl (letter): unspeakably sad!”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>für Euere lieben Worte<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Schenker’s diary records for October 13 and 15, 1932: “Lie-Liechen schreibt an Klara u.
          an Arnold Weil.” – “Ich schreibe an Klara u. Arnold an!” (“Lie-Liechen writes to Klara and
          to Arnold Weil.” – “I add a few lines to [Lie-Liechen’s letters to] Klara and Arnold!”). —
          These were preceded by a message recorded on October 12: “Von Arnold Weil (K.): Sonntag,
          den 9. ist Helmut Hatschek abgestürzt – tot!!! — An Hatscheks, von Lie-Liechen
          aufgesetzt.” (“From Arnold Weil (postcard): on Sunday the 9th, Helmut Hatschek collapsed –
          dead!!! — To the Hatscheks, drafted by Lie-Liechen.”). Arnold’s postcard survives as
            <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-10_1">OJ 14/10, [1]</tei:ref>, October 10,
          1932.</tei:note> herzlichen Dank; Euerer Einladung will ich gerne Folge leisten, sollte
        mich mein Weg nach Wien führen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich hätte Euch sofort geschrieben, allein die Erinnerung an dieses
        traurige Ereignis<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">i.e. the sudden
          death of Helmut Hatschek, the son of Oscar and Klara Hatschek: see footnote 2
          above.</tei:note> verläßt mich Tag und Nacht nicht, ich bin an Leib und Seele wie
        zerschlagen, wir gehen alle wie in einem bösen Traum herum. Die Schreckensnachricht kam
        zuerst zu uns, da <tei:rs type="person" key="entity- 003244">Klara</tei:rs> und <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs> nicht zuhause waren. <tei:pb n="2"/>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs> und <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-005248">Lene</tei:rs> mußten die Nachricht überbringen, es war das traurigste
        Amt, das ein Mensch übernehmen kann. Ich selbst bin wie eine Irre im Haus herumgerannt, als
        musste ich den Jungen in einem Winkel finden und der armen Mutter zurückbringen. 10 Minuten
        nachdem ich die Lichter angezündet hatte, am Vorabend des Versöhnungstages.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Day of Atonement: Yom Kippur, which in
          1932 fell on October 9–10.</tei:note> Was soll ich Dir, liebe <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000771">Jenny</tei:rs>, von der armen, kleinen <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity- 003244">Schwester</tei:rs> sagen? Ich habe sie immer bewundert, ihre geistige
        und körperliche Regsamkeit, ihren Lebensmut und festen Willen, mit dem sie auf ein Ziel
        losgesteuert ist, <tei:pb n="3"/> und vor allem ihre strenge Selbstbeobachtung und
        Selbstzucht, mit der sie ihr bestes in ihr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008428"
          >Kind</tei:rs> gelegt hat. Er war so prächtig und vor allem so lebensfroh und bereit, die
        ganze Welt zu umarmen; ihr ganzes Glück, ihr größter Reichtum war ihr <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-008428">Helmut</tei:rs>. Nun ist ihr Lebenswerk vernicht<tei:supplied
          reason="syntax">et</tei:supplied> – und sie selbst im Häufchen Unglück.Wenn Du sie sehen
        würdest Du müßtest weinen; man kann ja auch nichts anderes tun, als mit ihr weinen. Die
        Nachmittage verbringe ich bei ihr und versuche mit meinen schwachen Kräften, sie abzulenken;
        es gelingt natürlich nicht. <tei:pb n="4"/> Sie ist jetzt im Stadium der Selbstanklagen und
        macht sich die bittersten Vorwürfe, daß sie als Mutter unbedingt das Unglück hätte verhüten
        müssen. Sie kann nicht schlafen und will nicht essen, man muss ihr immer vor Augen halten,
        daß sie sich unbedingt für den <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000339">Mann</tei:rs>
        erkalten muß; ich fürchte, wenn sie diese Rücksicht nicht nehmen müßte, sie wäre zum
        aüßersten bereit. Es ist so unsagbar traurig, ein einziges Kind zu haben, ist doch wirklich
        ein va-banque-Spiel. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Seid mir, bitte nicht böse, daß ich das ganze, traurige Bild so vor Euch
        entrollt habe, Gott helfe der armen, schwer geprüften! Wie hab‘ ich es so bedauert, daß ich
        keine Millionen besitze, ich würde mit ihr eine weite, weite Reise machen! </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">left margin, sideways:</tei:note>
          Allerherzlichste Grüße von mir und den Deinen</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>Eure</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000944">Rosa</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RW"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002248"
            >Aussig</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1932-11-01">November 1, 1932</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>My dear ones,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Heartfelt thanks for you dear words:<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> I
        will gladly accept your invitation should my path take me to Vienna.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I would have written to you immediately but I can’t shake off the memory
        of this sad misfortune<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> night and day, I am
        utterly devastated, all of us are going around as if in a dream. The shocking news came
        first to us, since <tei:rs type="person" key="entity- 003244">Klara</tei:rs> and <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs> were not at home. <tei:pb n="2"/>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-005248">Lene</tei:rs> had to take the news over; it was the saddest mission
        that a person could undertake. I myself am dashing around the house aimlessly, as if I were
        having to find the boy in a corner and bring him back to his mother. Ten minutes after I had
        lit the candles on the evening before the Day of Atonement.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
          type="footnote"/> What am I to say to you, dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
          >Jenny</tei:rs>, of our poor little <tei:rs type="person" key="entity- 003244"
          >sister</tei:rs>? I have always marvelled at her, her mental and physical vigor, her
        zest for life and strong will, with which she steered toward a goal, <tei:pb n="3"/> and
        above all her sturdy self-examination and self-castigation, the best of which she has passed
        on to her <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008428">child</tei:rs>. He was so splendid and
        above all so full of the joy of life and ready to embrace the world. Her <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-008428">Hellmuth</tei:rs> was her whole happiness, her greatest
        treasure. Now her life’s work is extinguished – and she herself a picture of misery. If you
        were to see her, you would have to weep; truly, there is nothing one can do but weep with
        her. I spend the afternoons with her and try my poor best to take her mind off it. Needless
        to say, it doesn’t work. <tei:pb n="4"/> She is in a phase of self-recrimination, and
        reproaches herself, as his mother, most bitterly for not having prevented the accident. She
        can’t sleep and has no desire to eat; one has to keep one’s eye constantly on her lest
        without provocation she becomes cold toward her <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000339"
          >husband</tei:rs>; I fear that, if she were not to have to take this into account, she
        would be capable of the very worst. It is so unspeakably sad to have an only child – it’s a
        gamble.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Don’t be hard on me for having spilled the whole sad story out to you in
        this way. God help the poor sorely afflicted one! How sorry I am that I don’t possess
        millions; I would go on a long, long journey with her!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">left margin, sideways:</tei:note> Most
          heartfelt greetings from me and yours,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000944">Rosa</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
