<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="1070" sdoID="OJ-15-16_58">OJ 15/16, [58]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HW" scope="major">Hans Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
   <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2013</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2013-09-30" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated October 27, 1927</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1927-10-27T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2013-09-30</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Weisse congratulates Schenker on the publication of the second Meisterwerk
    Yearbook, of which has expresses mainly admiration. But he is unhappy with Schenker's dismissal
    of the fugue from Reger's Variations and Fugue on a theme of Bach, and with his reading of the
    Urlinie in Schubert's Waltz Op. 9 (D. 365), No. 5, and Beethoven's Sonata Op. 10, No.
    2.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>



  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000951">Weisse</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:note type="editorial">printed letterhead:</tei:note>
    <tei:handShift new="#printed"/> D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">R</tei:hi> HANS WEISSE <tei:dateline rend="indent-65"><tei:handShift new="#HW"/><tei:date when="1927-10-27">27. Oktober
      27</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Lieber verehrter <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Meister</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this
      letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/1, p. 3127 (October 27, 1927): "Von Weisse
      (Br.): über das Jhrb. II. Denke sich manches anders – bedauert am meisten, daß ich die Fuge
      von Reger nicht ebenso gründlich zurückgewiesen habe, wie die Variationen. Die ständige Angst,
      die ihn kennzeichnet, hindert den sonst so gebildeten Menschen die nötige Erklärung aus
      Eigenem herbeizuschaffen. Sie lag ja hier so nahe: erstens habe ich durch so u. soviele
      Variationen den Satz Regers bloßgestellt, so daß eine weitere Bloßstellung sich erübrigt hat;
      zweitens: hätte ich diese Fuge zum Gegenstand einer besondern Abhandlung gemacht, etwa im
      Vergleich mit einer Bachschen Fuge, dann hätte ich jede Einzelheit zu prüfen gehabt. Das hätte
      Weisse sich wohl selbst sagen können." ("From Weisse (letter): concerning Yearbook II. He has
      different views about several things – regrets most of all that I did not contest Reger's
      fugue as thoroughly as the variations. The constant fear, which marks him out, prevents this
      otherwise so educated person to work out the necessary explanation on his own. It was indeed
      so obvious: first of all, I exposed the weaknesses of Reger's counterpoint in so many
      variations that a further exposition was unnecessary; secondly, had I made this fugue the
      object of a special study, for instance in comparison with a fugue by Bach, then I would have
      had to check every detail in it. Weisse could have said so himself.")</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>lassen Sie mich Ihnen, wenn auch in Eile, mit wenigen Worten sagen, mit welchem Genuss ich
     „<tei:rs key="entity-001751" type="work">Meisterwerk II</tei:rs>“ gelesen habe und noch lese.
     „<tei:title>Das Organische der Fuge</tei:title>“ ist prachtvoll – nicht minder das
     „<tei:title>Organische der <tei:term>Sonatenform</tei:term></tei:title>“. Welchen Reichtum
    enthalten aber auch die <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> Betrachtungen, bei denen Sie ja dem Leser
    ganze <tei:term>Urlinien</tei:term> stillschweigend überlassen. Die Auseinandersetzung mit
     <tei:rs key="entity-000798" type="person">Schönberg</tei:rs> finde ich ausserordentlich, nur
    fürchte <tei:pb n="2"/> ich, werden die meisten Leser nicht den
     <tei:term>Durchgangsbegriff</tei:term> in Ihrem Sinne, und <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="HW">daher</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="HW">deshalb</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> auch das Resultat der Polemik <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="HW">nicht</tei:add> verstehen können. Das Urteil über <tei:rs key="entity-002793" type="person">Strawinsky</tei:rs> halte ich gradezu für „<tei:soCalled>klassisch</tei:soCalled>.“ Die Sätze
    von: „<tei:quote>Meine Beweisführung gibt mir das Recht</tei:quote>“ auf Seite 39 finde ich in
    ihrer Einfachheit und Vollkraft wirklich erhebend. Mir persönlich erscheint die Abfertigung des
     <tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person">Reger</tei:rs>schen Werkes genügend, doch fürchte
    ich, wird Ihnen das Odium der Voreingenommenheit bei der Kürze, mit der Sie die Fuge blos
    streifen, nicht erspart bleiben. Auch muß ich gestehn, dass in einem Werke, worin das
     <tei:term>Organische</tei:term> der <tei:pb n="3"/> Fugenform so meisterhaft dargestellt ist,
    das Gegenbeispiel: das <tei:term>Unorganische</tei:term>, dessen diese Form, wo sie
    misverstanden wird, fähig ist, von Ihnen hätte vielleicht wirklich auch meisterhaft dargestellt
    werden müssen, schon aus rein künstlerischen Gründen der Darstellung. Diese Versäumnis ist für
    mich der einzige dunkle Punkt an diesem Werke. Besonders glücklich ist Ihnen die optische
    Darstellung der <tei:rs key="entity-001488" type="composition">Nocturne op 15 No 2</tei:rs>
    gelungen! Dazu ist wirklich schon jedes Wort überflüssig geworden. Ihrem Absatz zum
      „<tei:quote><tei:term>ersten Urlinieton</tei:term> durch Anstieg</tei:quote>“ würde ich einen:
     „<tei:quote>zum <tei:term>ersten Urlinieton</tei:term> durch Abstieg</tei:quote>“ <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HW">gerne</tei:add> gegenüber <tei:pb n="4"/> gestellt sehen,
    dorthin gehörten meiner Meinung nach Beispiel fig 6,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">This figure shows a voice-leading analysis of <tei:rs key="entity-000803" type="person">Schubert</tei:rs>'s Waltz, <tei:rs key="entity-002942" type="composition">Op. 9 (D. 365)</tei:rs>, no. 5.</tei:note> mit deren Lesart von <tei:g type="cap5"/> aus ich mich über einer Stufe nicht befreunden kann. Die
     <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> hiesse konsequenter Weise <tei:g type="cap3"/>
    <tei:g type="cap2"/>
    <tei:g type="cap1"/>, wobei die <tei:g type="cap3"/> von der <tei:g type="cap5"/> aus im
    gleichen Klange durch Abstieg als <tei:term>Kopfton</tei:term> herbeigeführt wird! —<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">No paragraph-break in
    source.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>(Das einzig Unverständliche und Willkürliche scheint mir die Art wie Sie in <tei:rs key="entity-001223" type="composition">op. 10 N<tei:hi rend="supralinear">o</tei:hi> 2</tei:rs>
    den ersten Gedanken in einem einzigen f untergehen lassen: doch darüber mündlich mehr – und
    hoffentlich bald!) Ich hatte so sehr das Bedürfnis mich Ihnen mitzuteilen, entschuldigen Sie
    bitte die Eile <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#HW">mit</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HW">in</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> der ich es tue. Ich beglückwünsche Sie aus vollstem Herzen und danke Ihnen
    gleichzeitig vielmals.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr dankbarer</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-75"><tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:note type="editorial">printed letterhead:</tei:note>
    <tei:handShift new="#printed"/> D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">R</tei:hi> HANS WEISSE <tei:dateline rend="indent-65"><tei:handShift new="#HW"/><tei:date when="1927-10-27">October, 27,
      1927</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Dear revered <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Permit me to tell you, albeit in haste and in a few words, with what pleasure with which I
    have read and continue to read <tei:rs key="entity-001751" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Meisterwerk 2</tei:title></tei:rs>. "<tei:title>The Organic Nature of Fugue</tei:title>" is
    magnificent – no less so is the "<tei:title>Organic Nature of <tei:term>Sonata
     Form</tei:term>.</tei:title>" But what riches are also contained in the
     "<tei:title>Considerations of the <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>,</tei:title>" in which you
    tacitly provide the reader with full and complete <tei:term>Urlinie graphs</tei:term>. The
    confrontation with <tei:rs key="entity-000798" type="person">Schoenberg</tei:rs> I find
    extraordinary, but I fear <tei:pb n="2"/> that most readers will be unable to understand the
    concept of "<tei:term>passing tone</tei:term>" as you intend it, and therefore the result of the
    polemic. The judgment of <tei:rs key="entity-002793" type="person">Stravinsky</tei:rs> I regard
    as a real "<tei:soCalled>classic</tei:soCalled>." The sentences on p. 39 beginning with
     "<tei:quote>My line of reasoning gives me the right ...</tei:quote>" I find truly uplifting in
    their simplicity and full vigor. For me, personally, your dispatch of <tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person">Reger</tei:rs>'s work is sufficient; yet I fear that you will
    not be spared the odium for the bias you show by the brevity with which you merely in merely
    touch on the Fugue. I must also admit that, in a work in which the <tei:term>organic</tei:term>
    nature of <tei:pb n="3"/> fugal form is represented so masterfully, the counterexample – the
     <tei:term>unorganic</tei:term> nature, of which this form is capable when it it is misundertood
    – should perhaps also ought to have been demonstrated in a truly masterful way, merely out of
    purely artistic reasons of presentation. This omission is, for me, the only black mark in the
    work. You succeed especially well in the optic representation of the <tei:rs key="entity-001488" type="composition">Nocturne Op. 15, No. 2</tei:rs>! For this, words are indeed superfluous.
    Instead of your phrase about the "<tei:quote><tei:term>first tone of the Urlinie</tei:term>, by
     means of ascent,</tei:quote>" I would have <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HW">rather</tei:add> seen "<tei:quote>to the <tei:term>first tone of the Urlinie</tei:term>, by
     means of descent</tei:quote>"; <tei:pb n="4"/> to that place also belongs, in my opinion, the
    example given in Fig. 6,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> with whose reading from
     <tei:g type="cap5"/> I cannot bring myself to agree. The <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> would
    logically be <tei:g type="cap3"/>
    <tei:g type="cap2"/>
    <tei:g type="cap1"/>, whereby the <tei:g type="cap3"/>, proceeding from the <tei:g type="cap5"/>
    by means of a leap under a single harmony, is made to become the <tei:term>primary
     tone</tei:term>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>(The only incomprehensible and arbitrary thing, in my view, seems to be the way in which
    you allow a single f to stand for the first subject of <tei:rs key="entity-001223" type="composition">Op. 10, No. 2</tei:rs>; but more about that in person – and, I hope, soon!)
    I had such a great urge to communicate this to you; please excuse the haste with which I do so.
    I congratulate you with all my heart and at the same time send you many thanks.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your grateful</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-75"><tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>

 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>