<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3488" sdoID="OJ-14-10_21">OJ 14/10, [21]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RW" scope="major">Rosa Weil's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="minor">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>

    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008456">WeilR ~
        JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter with envelope from Rosa Weil to Jeanette Schenker, dated May 27,
        1935</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1935-05-27T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-07-30</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Rosa Weill admits to suffering bouts of mild depression. She regrets being
        unable to visit Jeanette because committed to taking Arnold away for health reasons. — She
        asks whether Jeanette had yet made any decisions [on her own future]. Jeanette has evidently
        told her of the mass of Heinrich’s papers that she will dedicate herself to [organizing and
        preserving]. — Hedda and Hans [Delmonte] have been staying; he is building a fish canning
        factory there. — Hella has forwarded a letter from Victor with photographs: he “shuts us
        out” more and more.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000944">Rosa Weil</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">


      <tei:opener>
        <tei:fw type="envelope">
          <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold">envelope</tei:hi></tei:note><tei:lb/>
          <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="recto"/><tei:lb/>
          <tei:address>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied reason="clarity">An:</tei:supplied>
              <tei:handShift new="#RW"/>Frau D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Heinrich
              Schenker</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">Wien III.</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">Keilgasse 8.</tei:addrLine>
          </tei:address>
          <tei:fw type="postmark">|| <tei:gap reason="illegible"/> | <tei:gap reason="illegible"/> |
            [*] AUSSIG 2 [*] ||</tei:fw><tei:lb/>
          <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="verso"/><tei:lb/>
          <tei:address>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied>Absender:</tei:supplied> R. Weil, Westphalenstr.
              25.</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">Aussig <tei:hi rend="supralinear"
              >a</tei:hi>E.</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">C. S. R.</tei:addrLine>
          </tei:address>
          <tei:fw type="postmark">|| WIEN 40 | [2]7. VI. 35. 11 | * 5a * |</tei:fw><tei:lb/>
          <tei:address>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#JS"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-006026"
                >Hofgastein</tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:date when="1935-06-02">2.<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"
                  >or23?</tei:note>. VI. 1935</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
          </tei:address>
        </tei:fw>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold">letter</tei:hi></tei:note><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#RW"/><tei:rs type="place"
            key="entity-002248">Aussig</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1935-05-27">27. Mai,
            1935</tei:date>.</tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>Meine liebe <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
          >Schwester</tei:rs></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Es ist nicht Faulheit und auch nicht Interesselosigkeit, wenn ich einmal längere Zeit
        nicht schreibe; aber <tei:unclear reason="reading">oh</tei:unclear> finde ich wirklich
        tagsüber nicht die nötige Ruhe dazu und am Abend sind wir oft nicht allein, oder bin ich
        recht müde, denn bei uns beginnt der Tag um 6<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi>, also muß
        man doch abends spätestens um 11<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> das Licht löschen. Auf
        eine regelmäßige Correspondenz kann ich mich schon deshalb nicht einlassen, weil ich leider
        noch hie und da mal kleine Depressionen habe und in so einer Stimmung nicht schreiben kann
        noch will, weil es da leicht zu Mißverständnissen kommt, wie es mir einmal mit <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-006478">Emma</tei:rs> gegangen ist. Wenn ich nicht irre, hab‘
        ich auch Dir mal in so einer Stimmung beschrieben und das tut mir dann nachher immerschreck-
          <tei:pb n="2"/> liche leid; ich finde, daß durch Briefe überhaupt leicht Mißverständnisse
        entstehen. So schrieb ich Dir letzthin: Vielleicht komme ich doch noch einmal.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Cf. <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-14-10_20">OJ 14/10, [20]</tei:ref>, April 19, 1935.</tei:note> Hatte dabei aber
        keinen festen Termin im Auge, und Du hast es als feste Zusage aufgefaßt. Das tut mir wieder
        schrecklich leid. Denn, liebe Schwester, sogerne ich zu Dir käme, ich kann jetzt hier nicht
        weg. Wir haben beide ein bißchen Ausspannen recht nötig; der Arzt verlangt, daß <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs> 3–4 mal im Jahr, wenn auch nur für
        einige Tage, eine Pause einschiebt. Das war längst fällig. Nun hat er sich doch
        entschlossen, Ende dieser Woche zu fahren und über Pfingsten zu bleiben, doch wünscht er daß
        ich ihn begleite. Im Juli muß er wahrscheinlich wieder nach <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-004561">Karlsbad</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Karlsbad (Karlovy Vary): i.e. to take the cure in its hot springs, as Arnold
          regularly did.</tei:note> da fährt er aber diesmal allein und ich benütze die Zeit um das
        Haus von oben bis unten malen und herrichten zu lassen. <tei:pb n="3"/> Das wird keine
        kleine, noch weniger eine angenehme Arbeit werden; doch auch solche Unannehmlichkeiten
        geben, wie alles, vorüber. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Wie stehen Deine Angelegenheiten? Schade daß Du unsere Einladung nicht
        ernst genommen hast; vielleicht hätte Dir <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943"
          >Arnold</tei:rs> doch irgendwie behilflich sein können. Oder ist alles schon erledigt? Ich
        dachte nicht, daß Du so bald Deinen Haushalt auflösen würdest doch hast Du ganz recht mit
        Deiner Behauptung, daß es bessere Dinge gebe, als Teppiche zu pflegen.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">The last known communication to Jeanette
          addressed to the Keilgasse was <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-10-18_11">OJ 10/18,
            11]</tei:ref>, notecard dated June 19, 1935 (what would have been Heinrich’s 68th
          birthday).</tei:note> Wenn du so einen großen Nachlaß befunden hast, ich meine, an
        Schriften, kannst Du ja eine Dir lieb gewordene Arbeit fortsetzen und damit der Welt viel
        wertvolles erhalten. In diesen Dingen habe ich Dich immer bewundert. Ich hoffe daß Du
        körperlich ganz auf der Höhe bist und daß Du <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-006026"
          >Gastein</tei:rs> wohl zur Erholung, nicht aber zur Kur nötig hast. Gesundheit ist und
        bleibt unser größtes Kapital, sie hilft uns über manches leichter hinweg. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008445">Hedl</tei:rs> war mit ihrem <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003921">Mann</tei:rs> fast 14 Tage hier, seit heute ist <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003921">Hans</tei:rs> wieder da. Erzählte ich Dir, daß er hier eine
        Fischconserven-Fabrik eingerichtet hat? Ich glaube, diese oder nächste Woche werden sie mit
        der Arbeit beginnen. Hoffentlich wird sich die Sache auch rentieren. –<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">This paragraph-break is editorial: Rosa
          inserts an en-dash at this point and writes continuously.</tei:note>
      </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006478">Emma</tei:rs> geht es G.s.D. wieder ganz gut,
        ich muß annehmen daß sie wieder zuhause ist. Eduard und Anne Palme<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Anne Palme: daughter of Emma and Eduard
          (1904-88). Her husband was Elias Franz Palme (1898–1958).</tei:note> mit ihrem Mann waren
        vorigen Sonntag hier. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003244">Klara</tei:rs> scheint es
        etwas besser zu gehen, seit <tei:unclear reason="reading">etw</tei:unclear> 14 Tagen ist sie
        in einer anderen Anstalt. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs> fährt
        Mittwoch nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004561">Karlsbad</tei:rs>. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003920">Hella</tei:rs> schrieb mir, legt einen Brief
        von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000783">Victor</tei:rs> mit einigen Photos aus dem
        Seebad bei; wo die Phrasen aufhören, fängt die Mauer an, mit der er sich gegen uns
        abschließt und die immer dicker und dicker wird. Mehr als ein Menschenalter ein <tei:unclear
          reason="reading">Ozean</tei:unclear> dazwischen, das muß sich irgendwie auswirken.
          –<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">This paragraph-break is
          editorial: Rosa inserts an en-dash at this point and writes continuously</tei:note>
      </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun wünsche ich Dir einen recht angenehmen Aufenthalt, gutes Wetter für <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-006026">Gastein</tei:rs> und auch sonst alles Gute und Schöne! </tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Mit den herzlichsten Grüßen von uns allen</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">von Deine</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000944"
          >Rosl</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:fw type="envelope">
          <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold">envelope</tei:hi></tei:note><tei:lb/>
          <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="recto"/><tei:lb/>
          <tei:address>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied reason="clarity">To:</tei:supplied>
              <tei:handShift new="#RW"/>Mrs. Heinrich Schenker</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">Keilgasse 8</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">Vienna III</tei:addrLine>
          </tei:address>
          <tei:fw type="postmark">|| <tei:gap reason="illegible"/> | <tei:gap reason="illegible"/> |
            [*] AUSSIG 2 [*] ||</tei:fw><tei:lb/>
          <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="verso"/><tei:lb/>
          <tei:address>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied>From:</tei:supplied> R. Weil, Westphalenstraße
              25</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">Aussig on the Elbe</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">Czechoslovakia</tei:addrLine>
          </tei:address>
          <tei:fw type="postmark">|| VIENNA 40 | [2]7. VI. 35. 11 | * 5a * |</tei:fw><tei:lb/>
          <tei:address>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#JS"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-006026"
                >Hofgastein</tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:date when="1935-06-02">June 2<tei:note type="editorial"
                  place="inline">or23?</tei:note>, 1935</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
          </tei:address>
        </tei:fw>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold">letter</tei:hi></tei:note><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#RW"/><tei:rs type="place"
            key="entity-002248">Aussig</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1935-05-27">May 27,
          1935</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">sister</tei:rs></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>It’s not through laziness, or even lack of interest, that I’ve not written for a long
        time, but during the day I don’t find the necessary peace and quiet for it, and in the
        evening we are often not alone, or I am dead tired – for in our household the day begins at
        6 a.m. and we really do need to put the light out around 11 o’clock at night. I can’t give
        myself over to a regular correspondence also because, unfortunately, I suffer from minor
        depression now and then, and in such a state of mind I neither can nor want to write, when
        it can easily lead to misunderstanding, as happened to me once with <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-006478">Emma</tei:rs>. If I’m not mistaken, I also once wrote to you in such a
        state, and that then makes me infinitely <tei:pb n="2"/> sad. I find misunderstandings arise
        all too easily through letters. I wrote to you just recently “Perhaps I may come to visit
        you some day!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> By that I had no fixed
        deadline in mind, and you took it to be a firm commitment. That makes me terribly sorry.
        For, dear sister, however much I would like to come and visit you, I can’t get away from
        here. We are both in real need of a short respite. The doctor requires <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs> to take a break three or four times a year, if only
        for a few days. That remained the case for a long time. Now however he has decided at the
        end of this week to travel and stay away over Pentecost, and he wants me to accompany him.
        In July he must apparently to go again to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004561"
          >Karlsbad</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> but this time he will
        travel alone, and I will use the time to paint the house from top to bottom and put
        everything in order. <tei:pb n="3"/> That will be no small task, still less a pleasant one;
        but then, even such disagreeable jobs, as with all things, it will pass.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">How are your affairs going? It was such a pity you didn’t take our
        invitation seriously – <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs> might
        perhaps have been of some help to you. Or has everything by now been settled? I never
        imagined you would disband your household so soon, but you are certainly right in your
        assertion that there are better things to do than clean carpets.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> Now that you are left with so large a legacy of
        personal effects – by that I mean papers – you can pursue a task that is close to your
        heart, and thereby preserve for posterity much that is of great value. In these matters I
        have always admired you. I hope that you are feeling physically on top of the world and that
        your need of <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-006026">Gastein</tei:rs> is for refreshment
        rather than for the cure. Good health is now and ever our greatest capital; it helps us to
        cope more easily with many things.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008445">Hedl</tei:rs> was here with her <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-003921">husband</tei:rs> for almost two weeks. Today, <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-003921">Hans</tei:rs> is again here. Did I tell you that he has
        built a canned fish factory here? I have an idea that it will start operation this week or
        next. Let’s hope it will be profitable. –<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"
        /></tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006478">Emma</tei:rs>, thank God, is well again; I
        should think that by now she is back home. Eduard and Anne Palme<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> with her husband were here the previous Sunday.
        Things seem to be a little better with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003244"
          >Klara</tei:rs>. Since <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">about</tei:unclear> two
        weeks ago she has been in a different establishment. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs> goes to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004561"
          >Karlsbad</tei:rs> on Wednesday. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003920">Hella</tei:rs> wrote me enclosing a letter
        from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000783">Victor</tei:rs> with some photographs from
        the seaside resort. Where the florid language ceases the wall begins, the wall with which he
        shuts us out, and which gets ever thicker and thicker. More than a generation, an
          <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">ocean</tei:unclear> separates us; it must work
        itself out. –<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Now I wish you a really pleasant stay, good weather for <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-006026">Gastein</tei:rs>, and otherwise all the very best!</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>With most heartfelt greetings from us all,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000944"
          >Rosl</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>
    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
