<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="584" sdoID="OJ-14-45_36">OJ 14/45, [36]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="MV" scope="sole">Moriz Violin's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2011</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-09-20" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002719">ViolinM ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM+V ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002718">ViolinM+V+F ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Moriz Violin to Schenker, dated October 22, 1924 </dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1924-10-22T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2011-09-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>In the process of arranging for copies of Der Tonwille to be distributed, Violin
    discovers that a pupil of his paid twice as much for one issue as the marked price in Austria.
    He has made some inquiries into this matter, and asks Schenker what an issue currently costs in
    Austria. There are no respectable music institutions in Hamburg, so Violin will distribute
    copies there personally. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Militärrock; military uniform; Geldschweinerei; Irrtum; error; Preis; price; Summe;
    sum; Dollar; Schülerin; pupil; Heft; issue; Rechnung; account; invoice </dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-50">Hamburg, <tei:date when="1924-10-22">22. Oktober
     24</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Liebster <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this
      letter is not recorded in Schenker's diary. </tei:note>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich bin in der seelischen Lage eines jungen Mädchens, das sein schlechtes
    aber recht gemeintes <tei:add place="interlinear-above">Liebes-</tei:add>Gedicht<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Violin is referring to the essay he wrote in
     1918, on the occasion of Schenker's fiftieth birthday. He still finds it embarrassing, although
     Schenker was himself touched by it. </tei:note> verirrt findet. Na, Du wirst am besten
    beurteilen, warum ich es verurteile. Im Militärrock geschrieben, der Herausgerissene plötzlich
    in sein schönstes Leben versetzt, verschönert gedenkend, andererseits für das große Material zu
    unsolide gerüstet u. s. w. – u. s. w. –– </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Dein Wort von „Nichtüberwindenmüssen“ war zu wahr u. schön u. ich selbst fühle es mit
    Stolz. Deine Nachricht u. Güte ließ aber meinen Unglückspunkt unberührt, der stark durch meine
    Art enstand u. vielleicht <tei:hi rend="underline">noch</tei:hi> stärker durch das Leben: Daß
    ich auf dem Wege so zurückgeblieben, nicht mit Schritt hielt. Schließlich: bin ich verwundeter
    Krieger, so doch Krieger. In Gesellschaft mit Dir rede ich nicht gerne von mir u. als „Doch
    Krieger“ <tei:add place="interlinear-above">will ich</tei:add> den Rest meines Lebens nützlichst
    im Kleinen verwenden. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Bevor ich Deine Fragen beantworte, will ich Dir erst ein besonderes
    berichten. Ich konnte die Lieferung <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Themming</tei:rs>
    noch nicht liquidieren, weil ungeahnt durch den Versand der <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">U. E.</tei:rs> eine kleine Geldschweinerei entstand. Ich liefere Dir das
    Material u. bitte um Rücksendung desselben u. Deine Auskunft hiezu. Ein kleiner Irrtum kann bei
    mir in der Erinnerung an <tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galthür</tei:rs> sein, hat
    aber wesentlich nichts mit der später folgenden Tatsache zu tun. Ich frug Dich in <tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galthür</tei:rs> um den Preis eines Heftes u. Du nanntest mir
    16.000 Kronen. (Ich glaube so!) Ich rechnete um u. kam zum deutschen 1 Mark Preis. So berechnete
    ich auch für <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Themming</tei:rs>, was Du aus der mit 100
    Dollar gennante Summe in meinem letzten Brief ersehen kannst. Inzwischen sagt mir meine
    Schülerin <tei:rs key="entity-000049" type="person">Frl. Bekker</tei:rs>, das sie 2 M. pro Heft
    bezahlte. Ich sagte daß das nicht möglich sei u. bat sie, sich unter anderen Namen in <tei:rs key="entity-002479" type="place">Leipzig</tei:rs>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">u.</tei:hi>
    <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> zu erkundigen. Auf einmal kommt aus
     <tei:rs key="entity-002479" type="place">Leipzig</tei:rs> Antwort: Preis 1 M. 50 Pf. ???? Aus
     <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> kam nichts. </tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Was kostet ein Heft in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs>? Bitte darüber sofortigen Bescheid. Ich lege hier die Rechnung für <tei:rs key="entity-000049" type="person">Frl. B.</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">This receipt does not seem to have survived. Two subsequent
     receipts from Universal Edition (in Leipzig) to Agnes Becker, for <tei:title level="j">Tonwille</tei:title> 7-9 and 10, respectively, are filed in the correspondence with the
     publisher (OC 52/645-66). </tei:note> u. die Antwort vom Verlag. Andere Mehrberechnungen sammle
    ich noch. Behalte das Wissen von all dem bei Dir! Sollen die Leute gegen den <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">Verlag</tei:rs> vorgehen? Ich muß erst in’s Reine
    kommen um Herrn <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Themming</tei:rs> die Rechnung stellen
    zu können. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Beiliegt auch die Antwort von <tei:rs key="entity-000013" type="person">Altmann</tei:rs>. Wie verhältst Du Dich dazu? </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Du <tei:hi rend="underline">mußt</tei:hi> Herrn <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Themming</tei:rs> nicht danken. Aber ein gescheuter Dankbrief von Dir scheint mir
    doch schmeichelhaft für ihn u. von Nützen für Zukünftiges. Also wie Du willst! </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Für <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> weiß ich Dir weder gute noch
    ansehnliche Hände, in die Dein <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title>Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs> gelegt werden kann. Es gibt hier auch keine
    ernsthafte Institution. Ich wirke da persönlich am besten. Letzthin borgte ich z. B.
    Kapellmeister <tei:rs key="entity-003032" type="person">Pollak</tei:rs> einen Haufen Hefte. Und
    so rede ich immer davon u. verbreite es. Bestellung u. Auftrag für Versand werde ich natürlich
    besorgen. Also ich warte auf Deine Auskünfte u. Weisungen. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Alles Schöne von Uns an Euch! </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">In Treue Dein </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-50">Hamburg, <tei:date when="1924-10-22">October 22,
     1924</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dearest <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">I am in the emotional state of a young girl, who finds that her poorly
    composed but well intended <tei:add place="interlinear-above">love</tei:add> poem<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> has misfired. You will be able to best judge why I
    condemn it. Written while I was in uniform, the one who had been torn away suddenly found
    himself in the happiest time of his life, brightly recollecting but at the same time
    insufficiently well armed for the difficult material, etc. etc. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Your expression of "not having to overcome" was only too true and beautiful, and I feel it
    myself with pride. Your report and your kindness, however, left my point of weakness untouched,
    an innate condition that has perhaps intensified <tei:hi rend="underline">even</tei:hi> more as
    a result of my life: that I have been left behind on the path, that I could not keep up. In
    short: if I am a wounded warrior, I am nonetheless a warrior. In your company, I do not enjoy
    talking about myself, and as "nonetheless a warrior" <tei:add place="interlinear-above">I
     intend</tei:add> to spend the rest of my life being as useful as possible in small matters. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Before I answer your questions, I should like first to report something in
    particular to you. I could not complete the <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Temming</tei:rs> dispatch because, unsuspectedly, <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">UE</tei:rs> played a nasty little monetary trick. I am returning the
    material to you and ask you for its return with a piece of information. My memory may have
    played a trick on me in <tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs>, but this has
    nothing of significance to do with the following event. I asked you in <tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs> about the price of an issue <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of <tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title></tei:supplied> and you said
    it was 16,000 Kronen. (Or so I believe!) I calculated that this came to a German price of 1
    Mark. So I reckoned also for <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Temming</tei:rs>, as you
    can see from the agreed sum of 100 dollars in my last letter. In the meantime, my pupil <tei:rs key="entity-000049" type="person">Miss Becker</tei:rs> tells me that she paid 2 Marks per
    issue. I said that this could not be possible and asked her to inquire about the price in
     <tei:rs key="entity-002479" type="place">Leipzig</tei:rs>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">and</tei:hi>
    <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs> under a pseudonym. Immediately, the
    reply from <tei:rs key="entity-002479" type="place">Leipzig</tei:rs> was: 1 Mark 50 Pfennig!
    (There was no reply from <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>.) </tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> What does an issue cost in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>? Please let me know immediately. I am enclosing the receipt for <tei:rs key="entity-000049" type="person">Miss Becker</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> and the reply from the publisher. Other further calculations I am continuing
    to collect. Keep the knowledge of all this to yourself! Should these people complain to the
    publisher? I must know the correct answer before I can present Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Temming</tei:rs> with the invoice. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Also enclosed is the reply from <tei:rs key="entity-000013" type="person">Altmann</tei:rs>. What do you think of it? </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">It is not <tei:hi rend="underline">necessary</tei:hi> to thank Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Temming</tei:rs>, but a modest letter of thanks from you
    would seem to me to flatter him, and could be useful in future. As you see fit! </tei:p>

   <tei:p>For <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>, I know of neither good nor
    useful hands into which your <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs> could be placed. Moreover, there are no serious institutions.
    It would be best for me to distribute it personally. Recently, I lent conductor <tei:rs key="entity-003032" type="person">Pollak</tei:rs>, for instance, a pile of issues. And thus I
    always talk about it and broaden <tei:supplied reason="clarity">interest in</tei:supplied> it. I
    shall of course take care of ordering and arranging for the copies to be sent. And so I await
    you information and instructions. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">All good wishes from us to you! </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your faithful </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>
  </tei:div>

 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>