<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="74" sdoID="OJ-14-33_5">OJ 14/33, [5]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="Rs" scope="sole">Rudolf Steglich's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2010</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2010</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML encoding, 2010</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-03-26" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002736">Steglich ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   
   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Steglich to Schenker, dated July 22, 1918</dc:title>
   
   <dcterms:created>1918-07-22T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2010-03-26</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Steglich has studied the Op. 111 Erläuterungsausgabe. Rejecting the polemic as
    redundant, he makes detailed suggestions concerning the relationship of the Arietta to the coda
    of the first movement.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>analysis; Studium; study; Polemic; polemic; Arietta; Satz; movement; Koda; coda;
    Motiv; motive; Anfangsmotiv; opening motive; Idee; idea; Gedanke; Skizze; sketch; Skizzenbuch;
    sketchbook; Vorhalt; suspension; Hauptmotiv; principal motive; Grundmotiv; basic motive;
    Harmonik; Harmonie; harmony; Entwurf; sketch; Fassung; version; form; Gestaltung; shaping;
    Brücke; bridge; Entwicklung; development; Thema; theme; Variation; variation</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000849">Steglich</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline>Lhakoro[?], <tei:date when="1918-07-22">22. 7. 18.</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Doktor</tei:rs>!
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Nach<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
     this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/11, p. 927, July 31, 1918: "Von Steglich
     (Br.): gegen die Polemik; fragt, ob die Arietta nicht von den letzten Takten des 1. Satzes
     abzuleiten wäre?" ("From Steglich (letter): against the polemic; asks whether the Arietta is
     not in part derived from the last bars of the first movement?").<!-- XR -->
    </tei:note> dem Studium Ihres <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work">Beethoven op. 111</tei:rs>
    muß ich Ihnen nochmals für die Übersendung des Werkes danken. Ich meine, Ihre Ausführungen zur
    Sache sind derart musikalisch tiefgegründet und klar, daß sie für sich allein mehr wirken als
    alle Polemik, so begründet diese auch sein mag. Auf diejenigen, die sie treffen soll, wirkt sie
    ja erfahrungsgemäß am wenigsten. So hat sie schließlich nur die Wirkung eines Blitzableiters,
    der die Gemütsspannung des Autors zwar wohltuend entlastet, ihr aber gleichzeitig die gewünschte
    Wirkung nach außen versagt. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich möchte noch ein paar Worte zur Arietta sagen. Mir scheint, daß zwischen
    ihr und dem ersten <tei:term>Satz</tei:term> Zusammenhänge
    bestehen, auf die Sie nicht hindeuten, die aber vielleicht einiges in noch anderem Sichte
    erscheinen lassen. Dem zunächst nur unbestimmtes Gefühl, daß die Arietta irgendwie mit dem 1.
    Satz verwandt, aus ihm herausgemachten sei, versuchte ich auf den Grund zu kommen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> Zunächst scheint mir das <tei:term>Anfangsmotiv</tei:term>
    <tei:note type="editorial">mus. ex.: first three notes of Arietta melody</tei:note>
    zurückzugreifen auf die Takte 152 und 154 der <tei:term>Koda</tei:term>, ja ihre fortzeugende Kraft (Steigerung <tei:hi rend="double-underline">e"</tei:hi> c" c", <tei:hi rend="double-underline">g"</tei:hi> c" c", <tei:hi rend="double-underline">c'"</tei:hi> – ? ) scheint erst hier erfüllt, gleichzeitig aber in
    genialer Weise zu einem Anfang neuen musikalischen Geschehens umgedeutet. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Das Herauswachsen der Arietta aus der Koda bestätigt noch mehr die erste
    Fassung im Skizzenbuch:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Artaria 201,
     comprising sixty-one pages of sketches for Op. 111. Schenker gives the relevant passages as
     music examples on p. 50, col. 2. </tei:note> der Inhalt des ersten Taktes ist nichts anderes
    als – jene Halben der Takte 150 ff. sogar mit der Spaltung der dritten (Takt 153 der Koda = Takt
    3 des Entwurfs!) So bleibt es trotz der geänderten 2. Fassung „zuletzt,“ bestehen. Hier erst
    findet also die <tei:term>Idee</tei:term> jener <tei:term>Halbe</tei:term>n – die ihrerseits wieder auf das <tei:rs key="entity-001906" rend="musical-term">Grundmotiv</tei:rs> des ersten Satzes zurückgeht, wie
    Sie darlegen – ihre Erfüllung (S. 51, 1. Spalte, Zeile 8).<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Steglich is picking up Schenker's own words at this point, in the
     latter's advice to the performer: "Man lasse daher auch noch in den T. 150 ff. eine Stimmung
     der Sammlung nicht aufkommen, sondern treibe – zumal von der gespensterhaften Begleitung der l.
     H. getragen – in gleicher Leidenschaft bis zu T. 156 fort, wo sich endlich der Rhythmus der
     Halben bricht, weil nun auch deren Idee zugleich ihre letzte Erfüllung gefunden."
     ("Accordingly, one should also not allow a sense of finality to arise yet in mm. 150 ff., but
     should drive forward – especially born by the ghostly accompaniment in the left hand – with
     similar passion right through to m. 156, where finally the rhythm of the half-notes breaks
     forth, because now their idea has at the same time found its final fulfillment."). </tei:note>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Auch die <tei:term>Harmonik</tei:term>
    der 1. wie der 2. Fassung entspricht den betreffenden Kodatakten: T | D | T | D |. In der
    Arietta wird freilich durch die <tei:term>Achtel</tei:term>bewegung der übrigen <tei:term>Stimme</tei:term>n auch andre Deutung möglich: die ersten <tei:term>Achtel</tei:term> des 1. und 2. Taktes als <tei:term>Vorhalt</tei:term>e, wie Sie es nehmen und wie <tei:del rend="overstrike">wie</tei:del> es schon für die 1. <tei:term>Variation</tei:term> ohne Zweifel feststeht. Ob nicht aber <tei:pb n="3"/> in der Arietta selbst
    trotzdem die Beziehung auf das Vorhergegangene, die Anknüpfung an die Koda des 1. Satzes
    ausschlaggebend ist? Ich möchte im ersten Takt nicht e' <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overwritten">
      <tei:gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" extent="3"/>
     </tei:del>
     <tei:add place="superimposed">als</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> Vorhalt, sondern f' d' als <tei:term>Auftakt</tei:term> nehmen – wobei in der <tei:term>Mittelstimme</tei:term> und im <tei:term>Baß</tei:term> das
    der <tei:term>Koda</tei:term> entstammende <tei:term>Motiv</tei:term> auftaucht, das die führende Stimme
    angeschlagen hat; die Vorausnahme der <tei:term>Harmonie</tei:term> des folgenden Taktes ist ja bei <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> nichts Ungewöhnliches. Im 2. Takt ist das mittlere Achtel dann
     <tei:term>Durchgang</tei:term>. Übrigens wird jetzt auch
    neben der Analogie der Takte 3–4 die harmonische Analogie der Takte 1–4 mit 9–12 fühlbar. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Auch im übrigen scheinen mir <tei:term>Gedanke</tei:term>n des 1. Satzes in der Arietta anzuklingen. Das <tei:term>Hauptmotiv</tei:term> und seine Vorbereitung (Figur 1<tei:hi rend="supralinear">a</tei:hi><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">i. e.
     the three-note figure, staccato eight-notes b–c–d, in m. 1 of the first movement, designated
     "Fig. 1 a)" by Schenker on p. 32, col. 1. </tei:note>) miteinander verschmolzen
     <tei:sic>der</tei:sic> Takt 7–8: h' (c") d" | g'; das Hauptmotiv allein in ausgeprägtester
    Form, wie triumphierend, in 15–16: d" g" | e". Daß Beethoven bewußt um die Auswirkung dieses
    Motivs in der Arietta gerungen hat, möchte ich aus dem 2. Entwurf schließen, der dieses
    dreitönige Motiv, mit Vorhalt vor der dritten <tei:pb n="4"/> Note, in den ersten 8 Takten
    viermal hintereinander bringt. Die endgültige Fassung ist eine Verschmelzung der beiden ersten,
    sie behält die in der 1. gegebene Anknüpfung an die Koda bei, füllt aber den dort noch offen
    gelassenen 4. Takt im Sinne der 2. und gelangt anschließend auch zu reicherer Gestaltung des 5.
    und 6. Taktes. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Zusammenfassend möchte ich also behaupten: die <tei:term>Koda</tei:term> des 1. Satzes nicht nur Ausklang dieses ersten, sondern auch
     <tei:rs key="entity-001813" rend="musical-term">Brücke</tei:rs> zum 2. Satze; und andrerseits:
    die Arietta nichts durchaus Neues, sondern aus dem 1. Satz, besser vielleicht aus der <tei:term>Entwicklung</tei:term> des ersten Satzes heraus <tei:hi rend="underline">geworden</tei:hi>; beide Sätze also eine lebendige Einheit – nicht nur als
    musikalischer Glaubensartikel sondern als musikalisch beweisbare Tatsache. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Übrigens bestreite ich durchaus nicht, daß auch <tei:term>Thema</tei:term> und Variationen in ihrer <tei:term>Entwicklung</tei:term> sich gegenseitig gefördert haben, wie Sie S. 55 behaupten;<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">"Zunächst entnimmt man nun den Skizzen, daß
     das Thema in seiner endgültigen Fassung keinswegs schon von vornherein feststand, vielmehr erst
     im Laufe der Arbeit seine gegenwärtige Gestalt angenommen hat. Und damit im Zusammenhang steht
     es ferner, daß ebenfalls nun auch die Variationen erst allmählich, und zwar in Wechselwirkung,
     mit der fortschreitenden Gestaltung des Themas der definitiven Fassung sich näherten. Mußten
     schließlich Thema und Variationen gleichsam eine Seele werden, so kam es nur folgerichtig, daß
     beide einander zur Entwicklung beitrugen." ("From the sketches can be concluded first that, far
     from adopting its definitive form at the very outset, the theme acquired its present shape only
     in the course of the process of composition. And furthermore, in relation to this, that even
     the variations themselves likewise approached their definitive form only gradually, and more to
     the point in reciprocal action with the progessive shaping of the theme. If the theme and
     variations were so to speak to become of one mind, then it is only logical that the two
     contributed to one another's development.") </tei:note> – ich will nur sagen, daß sich das
    Thema in erster Linie entwickelt hat als Frucht des 1. Satzes. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Wenn Sie Zeit fänden, mir mitzuteilen, ob Sie mir beistimmen können, würde
    ich mich sehr freuen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker's
     diary does not record the writing of a reply. </tei:note>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:closer rend="indent-20">
    <tei:salute>Bestens grüßend bin ich </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Ihr ergebenster </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-20">Rudolf Steglich</tei:signed>. </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:note type="editorial">in left margin, written sideways:</tei:note>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:p>Ich wurde geboten, bei Ihnen anzutragen, wann Ihre <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001756">„Formenlehre“</tei:rs> erscheint. Der Betreffende schreibt dazu: „Ich
     erwarte sie mit großer Ungeduld“. Hoffentlich kann ich ihm günstigen Bescheid geben? </tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>


  </tei:div>



  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline>Lhakoro[?], <tei:date when="1918-07-22">22. 7. 18.</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Dr. Schenker</tei:rs>! </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Now<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> that I have studied your
     <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work">Beethoven Op. 111</tei:rs>, I must thank you once again
    for sending the work. In my opinion, your exposition of the object under discussion is so
    well-founded and clear in musical terms that it carries greater weight in its own right than any
    polemic, no matter how justified the latter may be. For those on whom the latter is going to
    make its mark, it will at least do so through their own experience. Therefore, it will
    ultimately act only as a lightening rod, releasing the author's inner tension with soothing
    effect, true, but at the same time denying it the desired impact on others. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I should like to go on to say a few words about the Arietta. It seems to me
    that connections exist between it and the first <tei:term>movement</tei:term> to which you do not draw attention, but which perhaps show up some things
    from yet another angle. I tried to get to the bottom of the feeling, at first only inchoate,
    that the Arietta is in some way related to, <tei:supplied reason="clarity">indeed</tei:supplied>
    develops out of, the first movement </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> First of all, it seems to me that the <tei:term>opening motive</tei:term>
    <tei:note type="editorial">mus. ex.: first three notes of Arietta melody</tei:note> can be
    related back to mm. 152 and 154 of the <tei:term>coda</tei:term>, indeed their generative force (intensification <tei:hi rend="double-underline">e"</tei:hi> c" c", <tei:hi rend="double-underline">g"</tei:hi> c" c", <tei:hi rend="double-underline">c'"</tei:hi> – ?) appears fulfilled here for the first time whilst
    simultaneously being reinterpreted by the hand of genius as the beginning of a new musical
    event. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">The growth of the Arietta out of the <tei:term>coda</tei:term> is confirmed still further by the first version in the
     sketchbook:<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> the content of the first measure is
    nothing other than those <tei:term>half-note</tei:term>s of
    measures 150ff even with the subdivision of the third (m. 153 of the coda = m. 3 of the
    sketch!). Thus does it remain, despite the altered second version "finally." It is here that for
    the first time the <tei:term>idea</tei:term> of those
    half-notes – which for their part again relate back to the <tei:term>basic motive</tei:term> of the first movement, as you expound – finds its
    fulfillment (p. 51, col. 1, line 8).<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Also the <tei:term>harmony</tei:term> of
    the first as well as the second version corresponds to the relevant measures of the coda: T | D
    | T | D |. Admittedly, in the Arietta the <tei:supplied reason="clarity">dotted</tei:supplied>
    <tei:term>eighth-note</tei:term> motion in the other <tei:term>voice</tei:term>s admits of another possible
    interpretation: <tei:supplied reason="clarity">reading</tei:supplied> the first <tei:supplied reason="clarity">dotted</tei:supplied>
    <tei:term>eighth-note</tei:term>s of mm. 1 and 2 as <tei:term>suspension</tei:term>s (as you read them), and as is
    already undoubtedly established for <tei:term>Variation</tei:term> 1. But <tei:supplied reason="clarity">the question remains</tei:supplied>
    whether <tei:pb n="3"/> in the Arietta itself, despite its relationship to what has gone before
    it, the linking to the <tei:term>coda</tei:term> of the
    first movement is decisive. In m. 1, I should prefer to read not e' as a suspension, but rather
    f' d' as an <tei:term>upbeat</tei:term> – as a result of
    which in the <tei:term>middle</tei:term> and <tei:term>bass</tei:term> voices the <tei:term>motive</tei:term> arising from the coda makes its appearance, which the
    melody voice has announced. The anticipation of the <tei:term>harmony</tei:term> of the subsequent bar is certainly nothing unusual in
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>. In m. 2 the middle <tei:supplied reason="clarity">dotted</tei:supplied> eighth-note is then a <tei:term>passing tone</tei:term>. In addition, alongside the analogy of mm. 3–4, the
    harmonic analogy of mm. 1–4 with mm. 9–12 is now perceptible. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Moreover, <tei:supplied reason="clarity">thematic</tei:supplied>
    <tei:term>idea</tei:term>s from the first movement also seem
    to me to have resonance in the Arietta: the <tei:term>principal motive</tei:term> and its preparation (Fig. 1a<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/>) fused together as mm. 7–8: b<tei:hi rend="supralinear">1</tei:hi> (c<tei:hi rend="supralinear">2</tei:hi>) d<tei:hi rend="supralinear">2</tei:hi> | g<tei:hi rend="supralinear">2</tei:hi>; the principal motive <tei:supplied reason="clarity">appearing</tei:supplied> alone in its most pronounced form, triumphant, in mm. 15–16: d<tei:hi rend="supralinear">2</tei:hi> g<tei:hi rend="supralinear">2</tei:hi> | e<tei:hi rend="supralinear">2</tei:hi>. That Beethoven has consciously striven to perpetuate this motive
    in the Arietta, I should like to infer from the second sketch, which introduces this three-note
    motive with suspension before the third <tei:pb n="4"/> note four times, one after another, in
    the first eight measures. The finalized version is a fusing together of the first two; it
    retains the linking to the coda of the first <tei:supplied reason="clarity">sketch</tei:supplied>, but fills m. 4, which is there left open, in the manner of the second
     <tei:supplied reason="clarity">sketch</tei:supplied>, and also subsequently achieves a richer
    configuration of mm. 5 and 6. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In summary I should like thus to assert: the coda of the first movement as
    not only conclusion of this latter but also <tei:term>bridge</tei:term> to the second movement; and on the other hand, the Arietta as not something
    entirely new but as having <tei:hi rend="underline">arisen</tei:hi> from the first movement, or
    perhaps better, from the <tei:term>development</tei:term> of
    the first movement; both movements thus as a living unity – not merely as musical article of
    faith, but as musically demonstrable fact. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I do not, however, for a moment dispute that also <tei:term> theme</tei:term> and variations have assisted one another mutually in the
    course of their development, as you assert on p. 55.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> I will merely say that in the first place the theme has developed itself as
    the fruit of the first movement. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I should be delighted if you could find time to let me know whether you are
    able to concur with me.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:closer rend="indent-20">
    <tei:salute>With best greetings, I am </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Yours most truly, </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-20">Rudolf Steglich</tei:signed>. </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:note type="editorial">in left margin, written sideways:</tei:note>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:p>I have been asked to inquire of you when your "<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001756">Theory of Form</tei:rs>" will appear. The person concerned writes in this regard: "I await it
     with great impatience." Can I give him an encouraging answer – I hope so?</tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>


  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>