<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="1077" sdoID="OJ-15-16_65">OJ 15/16, [65]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HW" scope="major">Hans Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
      <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-10-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated November 27, 1930</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1930-11-27T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2013-10-01</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Weisse thanks Schenker for the essay "Rameau oder Beethoven?". He is surprised
        to hear that Jonas has sought Schenker's help in finding employment, and urges Schenker not
        to write a letter of recommendation until a concrete piece of work materializes. He is about
        to go to Berlin to deliver two lectures on Schenker's theories, and has heard that Moriz
        Violin and Reinhard Oppel will be there; he would like to give one of these lectures at
        Schenker's home before a small audience of his most dedicated pupils, and suggests a date
        and time for this.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000951">Weisse</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:lb/><tei:note type="editorial">printed letterhead:</tei:note>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10"><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>WIEN</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>XIII., WATTMANNGASSE 5</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:lb/><tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#HW"/><tei:date when="1930-11-27">27 XI. 30</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber verehrter <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Meister</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary a day earlier than the date given, at OJ
            4/4, p. 3547 (November 26, 1930): "Von Weisse (Br.): billigt mein Vorgehen Jonas
            gegenüber. Möchte Freitag, den 5. XII. um ½7h mir u. meinem Schülern den Vortrag über
            mich vorlesen." ("From Weisse (letter): he applauds my objections to Jonas; he would
            like to read his lecture on my work to me and my pupils on Friday, December 5, at
            6:30.")</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>vor allem vielen Dank für die Übersendung des <tei:rs key="entity-002972" type="person">Rameau</tei:rs>–<tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs>
          Aufsatzes.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:title level="a">Rameau or Beethoven?,</tei:title> the opening essay of the third <tei:title level="m">Meisterwerk</tei:title> Yearbook. This was a proof copy, as the Yearbook was not
          published until the second week of December. Writing of a covering letter, to which Weisse
          responds here, is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/4, p. 3545 (November 23, 1930): "An
          Weisse (Br.): Begleitbrief zur Drucksache: Rameau-Aufsatz (2. Korrektur); führe Klage über
          Jonas im obigen Sinne." ("To Weisse (letter): covering letter for the printed papers: the
          essay on Rameau (second proof-corrections); I lodge a complaint against Jonas, in the
          above terms <tei:supplied reason="clarity">i.e. as in the previous diary
            entry</tei:supplied>.")</tei:note> Kann ich ihn noch einige Tage behalten?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Was Sie mir von D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi>. <tei:rs key="entity-000412" type="person">Jonas</tei:rs> schrieben, hat mich selbst aufs Sonderbarste berührt. Dass er
        sich an Sie wendet, ist mir unbegreiflich. Ich kann mir nur vorstellen, dass er jetzt um
        jeden Preis sich eine Existenz begründen will und dabei auf Mittel verfällt, die er bei
        ruhiger Besinning niemals in Erwägung ziehen würde. Ich selbst habe D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi>. <tei:rs key="entity-000412" type="person">Jonas</tei:rs>
        vor zwei Jahren mit Unterstützung einiger Schüler einen monatliche Rente <tei:pb n="2"/>
        durch ein ganzes Jahr hindurch gegeben, um ihm die Möglichkeit zu geben, Arbeit zu leisten –
        und ihm die Ausrede zu nehmen, dass ihn die Not daran hindere. Er hat eine gross angelegte
        Arbeit über den Choral begonnen, was draus geworden ist habe ich nie erfahren. Es mag wohl
        darin der Grund liegen, dass D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi>. <tei:rs key="entity-000412" type="person">Jonas</tei:rs> sich nicht an mich wendet, weil er
        irgendwie fühlt dass ich ihm eine Empfehlung abschlagen müsste. Ich sagte ihm immer: zuerst
        die Leistung, und dann die Empfehlung! Da er die Leistung ausweisen kann, vermeidet er die
        Empfehlung von mir zu verlangen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">No item in the catalogue of the Oswald Jonas Memorial Library corresponds to a project on
          the chorale, or on plainsong. Weisse did, however, write a letter of recommendation for
          Jonas in 1930; it is preserved as OJ 69/16.</tei:note> Sie haben selbstverständlich
        vollkommen recht, wenn auch Sie sie ihm abschlagen. —</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs key="entity-000643" type="person">Oppel</tei:rs> hat mir erfreulicherweise für
        beide Vorträge<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Weisse's lecture
          at the Central Institute for Musical Education and Teaching in Berlin on December 9, 1930,
          and a follow-up lecture at a music college the following day.</tei:note> zugesagt. Auch
          <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs> wird kommen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich würde sehr gerne, falls Sie mit der Idee einverstanden <tei:pb n="3"/> sind, meinen
        Vortrag über Sie, bei Ihnen, für Sie und jene Schüler von Ihnen auf diese Sie Wert legen
          (<tei:rs key="entity-000201" type="person">Elias</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hoboken</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000107" type="person">Brünauer</tei:rs>) eventuell auch Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000164" type="person">Deutsch</tei:rs> vorlesen. Ich könnte allerdings nur <tei:date when="1930-12-05">Freitag
          abends <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HW">(nächste Woche!)</tei:add></tei:date>
        (von ½7 – ½9 etwa, wenn es Ihnen recht ist) weil <tei:date when="1930-12-04">Donnerstag</tei:date> mein <tei:rs key="entity-004627" type="composition">Sextett</tei:rs> aufgeführt wird, bis dahin Proben sind – und weil ich <tei:date when="1930-12-06">Samstag</tei:date> nach <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs> fahre.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Halten Sie diesen meinen Vorschlag für keine Zudringlichkeit, doch möchte ich Ihnen
        gern das Lesen ersparen und gleichzeitig auch Ihre Schüler <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HW">daran</tei:add> teilnehmen lassen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wenn Sie den <tei:rs key="entity-000178" type="person">Dunn</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl>John Petrie Dunn, <tei:title level="m">A Student's Guide to Orchestration</tei:title> (London: Novello,
            [1928])</tei:bibl>. This is the first book in the English language to quote from
          Schenker's writings.</tei:note> sofort brauchen, schicke ich <tei:sic>Ihn</tei:sic> durch
        Herrn <tei:rs key="entity-000964" type="person">Willfort</tei:rs>, der in Ihrer
        unmittelbarsten Nähe wohnt. Sonst bringe ich ihn. Denn sehen muss ich Sie auf jeden Fall,
        bevor ich fahre. Könnte ich also auf jeden Fall <tei:date when="1930-12-05">Fraitag <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HW">den 5. Dezember</tei:add></tei:date> ½7 kommen,
        entweder um vorzulesen, oder blos um Ihnen die beiden Vor- <tei:pb n="4"/> träge zu
        übergeben?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Der Zufall führte mich in Angelegenheiten der Vervielfältigung meiner Vorlagen zu Herrn
          <tei:rs key="entity-000894" type="person">Tomay</tei:rs> – und ich erstaunte nicht wenig –
        als ich dort <tei:term>Urlinienskizzen</tei:term> liegen sah!</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs> schrieb sehr lieb, wie
        sehr er sich auf mein Kommen freue, ich soll ihn gleich anrufen.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Bitte um eine Zeile!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-15">Allerherzlichstes von uns beiden Ihnen beiden!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-75"><tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:lb/><tei:note type="editorial">printed letterhead:</tei:note>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10"><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>VIENNA</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>XIII, WATTMANNGASSE 5</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:lb/><tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#HW"/><tei:date when="1930-11-27">November 27, 1930</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear revered <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>First of all, many thanks for sending me the essay on <tei:rs key="entity-002972" type="person">Rameau</tei:rs> and <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> May I keep it for a
        few more days?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>What you wrote to me about Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000412" type="person">Jonas</tei:rs>
        touched me personally in a most particular way. That he turns to you is inconceivable to me:
        I can only imagine that he would now do anything possible to earn a living, and thus grabs
        at measures that he would never consider taking if he were to think things out calmly. Two
        years ago, I myself gave Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000412" type="person">Jonas</tei:rs> a
        monthly salary <tei:pb n="2"/> for a whole year, with the help of a few of my pupils, in
        order to give him the opportunity to complete some work, and deprived him of the excuse that
        necessity was preventing him from doing it. He had begun a monumental work on the chorale;
        what came of it I have never learned. This may explain why Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000412" type="person">Jonas</tei:rs> is not approaching me, since he feels somehow that I would
        have to refuse him a recommendation! Since he cannot produce the finished product, he avoids
        asking me for the recommendation.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> You are of
        course entirely in the right if you, too, refuse him.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs key="entity-000643" type="person">Oppel</tei:rs> has, to my delight, accepted
        my invitations for both lectures.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/>
        <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs> will be coming, too.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I would be very grateful if you were to agree to the idea of <tei:pb n="3"/> my reading
        my lecture about you at your place, for you and those pupils of yours whom you hold in high
        regard (<tei:rs key="entity-000201" type="person">Elias</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hoboken</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000107" type="person">Brünauer</tei:rs>), perhaps also Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000164" type="person">Deutsch</tei:rs>. At any rate, I could do this only on <tei:date when="1930-12-05">Friday <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HW">of next
            week</tei:add></tei:date> – from about 6:30 to 8:30 pm, if that is okay with you – as my
          <tei:rs key="entity-004627" type="composition">Sextet</tei:rs> will be performed on
          <tei:date when="1930-12-04">Thursday</tei:date> and there are rehearsals until then, and
        as I shall be travelling to <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs> on
          <tei:date when="1930-12-06">Saturday</tei:date>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Do not take my suggestion as a sign of my pushiness; I just wanted to spare you having
        to read it and, at the same time, let your pupils, too, take part in it.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>If you need <tei:rs key="entity-000178" type="person">Dunn</tei:rs>'s book<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> straightaway, I shall send it to you by way of Mr.
          <tei:rs key="entity-000964" type="person">Willfort</tei:rs>, who lives very near you.
        Otherwise I shall bring it personally. For I must see you in any event before I leave. Can I
        see you in any case on <tei:date when="1930-12-05">Friday, <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HW">December 5,</tei:add></tei:date> at half past six
        in the evening, either to read out my two lectures or merely to leave them for you?</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> Concerning the reproduction of my handout in multiple copies, chance
        took me to Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000894" type="person">Tomay</tei:rs>, and I was not a
        little surprised to see <tei:term>Urlinie graphs</tei:term> lying there!</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs> wrote a very kind letter
        to me, saying how much he was looking forward to my coming, and that I should ring him
        immediately after I arrive.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Please, write me a line!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-15">Most cordial wishes from the two of us to the two of
          you!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Yours,</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-75"><tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>