<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="1628" sdoID="OJ-12-6_39">OJ 12/6, [39]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPoj" scope="sole">Oswald Jonas as typist</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="JR">
      <tei:persName>John Rothgeb</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2015</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002714">Jonas ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002713">Jonas ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


      <dc:title>Typewritten letter (carbon copy) from Jonas to Schenker, dated November 28,
        1934</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1934-11-28T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2015-12-02</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Jonas has agreed to let his publisher proceed with a lawsuit against Willi
        Reich; he has written up the documentary evidence of the case and asks Schenker to circulate
        it among his circle. — He reports his activities in Berlin. — He reports his dispute with
        the Jüdischer Verlag.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Klage; lawsuit; Verhandlung; hearing; Richter; judge; Dreh; trick; Anwalt; lawyer;
        Materialuntergrundlage; material foundations; Schwindler; swindler; Aufführung; performance;
        Kreis; circle; Exemplar; copy; Flugblatt; pamphlet; Vortrag; lecture; Korrekturen; proofs;
        Affäre; affair; Revisionsabzug; revised proof; Hymnusabschnitt; adulatory section;
        Briefwechsel; correspondence; Laufen; visit</dc:subject>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000412">Jonas</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="ident-80"><tei:handShift new="#TPoj"
            /><tei:placeName>Berlin</tei:placeName>, den <tei:date when="1934-11-28">28. XI.
            1934</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Sehr verehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Doktor</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/8, p. 3962: November 29, 1934: "Von
            Jonas (Br.): wird klagen; 2 Exemplare der Unterlage." ("From Jonas (letter): he will
            take legal action: two copies of the document."). This letter appears to be a carbon
            copy of a missing original, hence it is unsigned. — On November 9, Schenker had written
            to Jonas: "An Jonas (Br.): erwäge die Chançen einer Klage." ("To Jonas (letter): I
            assess the prospects of legal action.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Nach mancherlei Überlegung habe ich dem Drängen des <tei:rs
          key="entity-000906" type="person">Verleger</tei:rs>s nachgegeben und ihm die Vollmacht zur
        Klage eingesandt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">i.e. lawsuit
          against Willi Reich and/or the journal <tei:title level="j">23— eine Wiener
            Musikzeitschrift</tei:title> : see <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-44-9">OC
            44/9</tei:ref>, October 27, 1934.</tei:note> Mein Zaudern kam aus der Erwägung, daß ich
        nicht in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> und bei der Verhandlung
        nicht anwesend sein kann. Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000697" type="person">Reich</tei:rs>
        könnte aber dem Richter einen „Dreh“ vormachen, dem der Anwalt aus Sachunkenntnis einfach
        nicht gewachsen wäre. So habe ich mich entschlossen, beiliegendes „Opus“<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Undoubtedly Oswald Jonas, "<tei:title
            level="u">Vorläufer und Nachläufer. (Ein Dokumentarischer Nachweis)</tei:title>"
          (unpubd. manuscript, carbon copies preserved as OC 30/91‒98 and OJ 38/52). For the
          circumstances, see <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-44-9">OC 44/9</tei:ref>,
          October 27, 1934.</tei:note> zu verfassen, erstens um die Nötige Materialuntergrundlage
        für den Anwalt zu bieten, dann aber um die Herren so zu erledigen, wie es für Schwindler
        paßt: satirisch und sie zu entlarven. Ob es Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000815" type="person"
          >Schwers</tei:rs>, den ich darum ersucht habe, bringen wird, weiß ich noch nicht. Ich
        zweifle noch daran, wiewohl es ihm willkommen sein könnte in Anbetracht der
          <tei:sic>der</tei:sic> bevorstehenden Aufführung der „<tei:title>Lulusuite</tei:title>“
        von <tei:rs key="entity-000061" type="person">Alban Berg</tei:rs>!<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Berg's <tei:title level="m">Symphonische
            Stücke aus der Oper „Lulu“</tei:title> was given its première in Berlin on November 30,
          1934 under Erich Kleiber ‒ the latter's last concert before resigning from his post at the
          Berlin Staatsoper on December 4 in protest against the Nazis' embargo on works such as
            <tei:title level="m">Lulu</tei:title>. </tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Jedenfalls bitte ich Sie, verehrter Herr Doktor, die Blätter indes unter
        Ihren Kreis zirkulieren zu lassen, ein Exemplar auch <tei:rs key="entity-000973"
          type="person">Hans Wolf</tei:rs> (dessen Adresse ich verlegt habe) zu geben. Er soll es
        aber nicht gleich Herrn <tei:rs key="entity-000697" type="person">Reich</tei:rs> unter die
        Nase halten – mindestens nicht vor der Verhandlung. Vielleicht gibt der <tei:rs
          key="entity-000906" type="person">Verleger</tei:rs> ein kleines Flugblatt heraus! Halten
        Sie das für richtig. Sonst werden die Herren ja immer frecher.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Neulich habe ich in <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place"
          >Hamburg</tei:rs> bei Frau Fromm<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Apparently a Hamburg-based pianist. <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-12-6_30">OJ 12/6, [30]</tei:ref>, March 16, 1934, mentions a “Frau Michaels”
          for whom (or for whose class) Jonas might give a "course"; <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OC-44-9">OC 44/9</tei:ref>, October 27, 1934, refers to a "Fromm-Michaels" for
          whom he is to give a lecture "next time." Probably Michaels, Fromm-Michaels, and the "Frau
          Fromm" cited here are the same persion.</tei:note> einen Vortrag gehalten – zunächst über
        die „Wiederholung“, das die Leute sich aber beschwert haben daß sie daraus noch zu wenig
        über den eigentlichen „Schenker“ erfahren <tei:pb n="2"/> haben, wird nun jedesmal bei
        meinem Aufenthalt dort fortgesetzt werden. Die Gemeinde wächst!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Wie geht es Ihnen gesundheitlich? Sind Sie auch mit dem Fortschritt der
          Korrekturen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Proofs for <tei:rs
            key="entity-001728" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Der freie
          Satz</tei:title></tei:rs>.</tei:note> zufrieden?</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich hatte und habe hier leider eine böse Affäre mit dem Jüd.
          Verlag.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">Jüdischer Verlag: a
          publishing house founded in 1902 by Martin Buber and others to serve as a "central agency
          for the promotion of Jewish literature, art and scholarship." Its publications included
          the <tei:title level="m">Jüdisches Lexicon</tei:title> (1927–30), for which Alfred
          Einstein had provided the musical component, including an article on Schenker (quoted
          derisively in OJ 12/6, [27], December 18, 1933), the <tei:title level="m">Babylonischer
            Talmud</tei:title>, transl. L. Goldschmidt (1930–36), the <tei:title level="m"
            >Weltgeschichte des Jüdischen Volkes</tei:title> by Simon Dobnow (1925–29), and works by
          Theodor Herzl, including <tei:title level="m">Der Judenstaat</tei:title> (1920). The press
          was prohibited in 1938.</tei:note> Aus dem mir zugesandten Revisionsabzug entnahm ich, daß
        ohne mein Wissen und ohne meine Einwilligung von fremder Hand (ich kenne sie) ein
        Hymnusabschnitt über <tei:rs key="entity-000798" type="person">Schönberg</tei:rs> nebst
        anderen Veränderungen (auch in den Zeilen über Schenker) eingestreut worden war – unter
        meinem Namen. Sie können sich meinen Schreck und meine Empörung vorstellen. Zeitraubender
        Briefwechsel und Laufen zum Anwalt war die Folge. Und das gerade in diesem Moment der
          „<tei:title>23</tei:title>“ Geschichte! Die Sache ist noch nicht zu Ende! Aus einer
        Bemerkung im letzten Brief von <tei:rs key="entity-000973" type="person">Wolf</tei:rs> an
        mich schloß ich, daß Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000697" type="person">Reich</tei:rs> darüber
        bereits vom Täter, Herrn Rudolf Kastner,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Perhaps reference is to Rudolf Kastner (1906–57), lawyer; during World War II
          he was head of the Jewish Rescue and Relief Committee in Budapest, and served as a conduit
          between the Nazis and the Hungarian Jewish community. Found guilty of Nazi collaboration
          in his trial in 1954–58, he was assassinated by a Holocaust survivor in Israel in
          1957.</tei:note> der jetzt in Wien weilt, „informiert“ worden ist. Eine saubere
        Welt!!!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mit ergebensten Grüßen an Sie sowie Ihre werte Frau <tei:rs
            key="entity-000771" type="person">Gemahlin</tei:rs></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">stets Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">unsigned</tei:note>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="ident-80"><tei:handShift new="#TPoj"
            /><tei:placeName>Berlin</tei:placeName>, <tei:date when="1934-11-28">November 28,
            1934</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Greatly revered Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
            type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">After much consideration I have yielded to the urging of the <tei:rs
          key="entity-000906" type="person">publisher</tei:rs> and have authorized him to conduct
        the lawsuit.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> My hesitation came from the
        reflection that I cannot be in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs> and
        be present at the hearing. Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000697" type="person">Reich</tei:rs>,
        however, could pull a "trick" on the judge, which the lawyer, through lack of technical
        understanding, simply wouldn't be able to handle. So I have decided to write up the enclosed
          "Opus"<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> in order first to provide necessary
        material foundations for the lawyer, but then also to deal with the gentlemen in a way
        fitting for swindlers: satirically, and to expose them. Whether Mr. <tei:rs
          key="entity-000815" type="person">Schwers</tei:rs>, whom I have asked about it, will use
        the text I don’t yet know. I have doubts about how welcome it will be to him in light of the
        forthcoming performance of the <tei:title>"Lulu" Suite</tei:title> by <tei:rs
          key="entity-000061" type="person">Alban Berg</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
          type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">In any event, Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity">Schenker</tei:supplied>,
        I ask you please to circulate the pages among your circle, and also to give a copy to
          <tei:rs key="entity-000973" type="person">Hans Wolf</tei:rs> (whose address I have
        misplaced). But he shouldn't immediately hold it under Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000697"
          type="person">Reich</tei:rs>'s nose ‒ at least not before the hearing. Perhaps the <tei:rs
          key="entity-000906" type="person">publisher</tei:rs> will bring out a small pamphlet! Do
        you think that would be appropriate<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">?</tei:supplied>
        Otherwise the gentlemen will become ever more impudent.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Recently at Mrs. Fromm's<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/>
        in <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> I gave a lecture on
        "Repetition," about which people complained that they learned from it too little about the
        real "Schenker"” <tei:pb n="2"/> It will be continued each time I stay over there. The
        circle grows!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">How is your health? Are you satisfied too with the progress of the
          proofreading?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I unfortunately had and still have here an unpleasant affair with the
        Jewish Press.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> I learned from the proof copy
        sent me that, without my knowledge and permission, a section adulating <tei:rs
          key="entity-000798" type="person">Schoenberg</tei:rs> was inserted in a foreign hand (I
        recognize it), as well as other alterations (even in the lines on Schenker) ‒ under my name.
        You can imagine my horror and outrage. Time-consuming correspondence and trips to the lawyer
        were the result. And this precisely at the moment of the <tei:title level="j">23</tei:title>
        episode! The matter is not over yet! From a comment in the last letter to me from <tei:rs
          key="entity-000973" type="person">Wolf</tei:rs> I gathered that Mr. <tei:rs
          key="entity-000697" type="person">Reich</tei:rs> has already been "informed" about it by
        the culprit, Mr. Rudolf Kastner,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/> who is now
        staying in Vienna. A sanitary world!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">With most devoted greetings to you and to your good <tei:rs
            key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">ever your</tei:salute>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">unsigned</tei:note>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
