<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3205" sdoID="OJ-10-3_174">OJ 10/3, [174]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="OED" scope="sole">Otto Erich Deutsch's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2023</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IDB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2015-09-18" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002726">DeutschOE ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002712">DeutschOE ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002727">DeutschOE+H ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Deutsch to Schenker, dated July 21, 1932</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1932-07-21T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2023-08-07</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Deutsch advises Schenker on the wording and placement of an advertisement for
        a private seminar in music theory, to be inaugurated in the autumn of 1932. He notes that
        Tomay’s invoice for the autography of the Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln was considerably lower than
        what was originally estimated. He regrets having to decline an invitation to visit Schenker
        during the summer.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000164">DeutschOE</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/>Trofaiach, <tei:date
            when="1932-07-21">21. VII. 32</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Verehrter</tei:rs>!<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">. Receipt of this letter is recorded
            in Schenker’s diary for July 23, 1932: “Von Deutsch (Br.): könnte als Schülerwerbung
            ausgelegt werden; empfiehlt im Ernstfall eher die Schweiz und England.”) (“From Deutsch
            (letter): it could be construed as an advertisement for pupils; in case of serious
            difficulties, he would suggest Switzerland and England in the first instance.”).
          </tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Erst heute morgens kam Ihr schöner Brief<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Dictation of a letter to Deutsch is recorded in Schenker’s
          diary for July 16, 1932: “Diktire einen Brief an Deutsch: ziehe die Summe: das 1. Heft ist
          – quod erat demonstrandum – ein Ergebnis von Seminar u. S. 1250, also ist künstlerisch u.
          wirtschaftlich begründet, wenn ich den Anspruch auf eine Klasse (= Seminar) u. den so
          niedrigen Betrag erhebe, um mehr Hefte herausbringen zu können. Da es aber zu einer Klasse
          nicht kommt, wie wäre es, wenn ich eine Annonçe einrückte? Wo? Ich lade ihn nach Igls
          ein.” (“I dictate a letter to Deutsch: I sum things up: the first volume of the
            <tei:supplied reason="clarity"><tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001755"><tei:title
                level="m">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln</tei:title></tei:rs></tei:supplied> is – <tei:hi
            rend="italic">quod erat demonstrandum</tei:hi> – an achievement of the seminar and
            <tei:supplied reason="clarity">brings in</tei:supplied> 1,250 shillings; thus it is
          artistically and financially justified, if I can avail myself of a class (= seminar) and
          raise the sum <tei:supplied reason="clarity">received from my pupils</tei:supplied>, which
          is so low, in order to be able to publish more volumes. But since there will be no class,
          how would it be if I placed an advertisement? Where? I invite him to <tei:rs type="place"
            key="entity-002380">Igls</tei:rs>.”).</tei:note> in meine Hände. Ich beeile mich, die
        Hauptfrage zu beantworten. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Wenn solches Angebot von Ihnen gemacht wird, müßte der Anschein einer
        Stundenwerbung vermieden werden, das Seminarhafte betont, weil man nur so das Geschenk
        andeuten kann. Den entworfenen Text finde ich nicht gemeinverständlich, er müßte auch
        prägnanter sein. Sind vier Kategorien nicht zu viel für ein Seminar? Das Augustheft <tei:rs
          type="journal" key="entity-002556"><tei:title>der „Musik“</tei:title></tei:rs> dürfte
        schon abgeschlossen sein. Bei den Devisen-Schwierigkeiten verspreche ich mir wenig Zuzug aus
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482">Deutschland</tei:rs>. Wenn <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002506">Österreich</tei:rs> als Reservoir nicht genügt, wäre vielleicht eher
        an die <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002507">Schweiz</tei:rs> oder <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002586">England</tei:rs> zu denken. Die <tei:rs type="journal"
          key="entity-002559"><tei:title>N. Fr. Presse</tei:title></tei:rs> bringt nichts umsonst,
        auch von Liebkindern nicht, aus Blattgefühl. In der <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002507"
          >Schweiz</tei:rs> käme die „<tei:title>Schweizerische Musikzeitung</tei:title>“ – Verlag
        Hugh in Zürich – in Betracht; in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002586">England</tei:rs>
        der „<tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-003178"><tei:title>Musikal
          Courier</tei:title></tei:rs>“ etwa, dessen Adresse ich nächste Woche in Wien feststellen
        könnte. Wenn Sie also Ernst machen wollen, so würde ich ungefähr folgenden Text empfehlen: </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:hi rend="underline">Dr. Heinrich Schenker</tei:hi>
        <tei:lb/>beabsichtigt, im kommenden Wintersemester (Oktober bis März) ein <tei:del
          rend="overstrike">ein</tei:del>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">Privatseminar</tei:hi> für <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> und
          <tei:term>Generalbaß</tei:term>, Handschriftenkunde und <tei:term>Vortrag</tei:term>
        abzuhalten. Anmeldungen bis 15. September: Wien III. Keilgasse 8. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Soll man <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000027">J. S. Bach</tei:rs>s
        Generalbaß-Büchlein nennen, so würde ich überhaupt nur sagen: Privatseminar über <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000027">J. S. B</tei:rs>s. G.–B. Das andere wäre Draufgabe.
        Stundenzahl, Zeitangabe, Preis nur brieflich. Darüber könnten wir ja dann in Wien noch
        reden. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Wegen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker
          put an X in the left margin of this paragraph and the one following.</tei:note> der
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002591">Akademie</tei:rs> sprach ich neulich, nach
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008161">Prüger</tei:rs>s Hinscheiden, wieder mit einem
        Eingeweihten: das Ministerium scheint nach wie vor machtlos zu sein, <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000961">Wiener</tei:rs> ganz autokratisch. Zu ihm aber habe ich keinen Weg. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000894">Tomay</tei:rs>s Kosten, die
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000420">Kalmus</tei:rs> höher einschätzte als <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002402">Waldheim</tei:rs>s Rechnung!, werden hoffentlich
        nach und nach durch den europäischen Absatz hereingebracht werden. Daß das <tei:rs
          type="work" key="entity-001755">Heft</tei:rs> so billig ist – trotz des teuren <tei:pb
          n="2"/> und verschwenderisch großen Papiers, ist sehr erfreulich. Es ist so ein doppeltes
        Geschenk geworden. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Wenn Ihre Zeit es erlaubt, schreiben Sie mir – bitte – noch, wie Sie sich
        die Ausgabe des Generalbaß-Büchleins denken. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich fürchte, daß ich aus notwendiger Sparsamkeit Ihrer freundlichen
        Einladung, der ich so gerne vor oder nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002578"
          >Salzburg</tei:rs> folgen möchte, entsagen muß. Bei dieser Gelegenheit möchte ich Ihnen
        andeuten, daß <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs>s Gehaltszahlung für
        mich bedeutsam werden kann, weil meine Haupteinnahme durch <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002506">Österreich</tei:rs>s Unglück gefährdet ist. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000320">Haas</tei:rs>, den ich vorige Woche wieder sprach, zweifelt mir auch
        an <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">H</tei:rs>s. Bleiben in Wien; er weiß aber
        nichts Näheres. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Über die Kosten der Annoncen weiß ich nichts. Man müßte anfragen, was
        eventuell durch ein Wiener Zentralbüro (Hasenstein &amp; Vogler<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04"
          type="editorial" place="foot">The first European agency for the distribution of
          advertisements (Annoncen-Expedition), founded by the Altona bookseller Ferdinand
          Haasenstein (1828–1901) and Adolf Vogler.</tei:note> etwa) geschehen könnte. Eine deutsche
        Tageszeitung wäre wohl am ehesten die <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002537"
            ><tei:title>Frankfurter</tei:title></tei:rs>. Ich glaube aber, man sollte nur an
        Fachblätter denken (<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000195">Einstein</tei:rs>?)<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">As the music editor for <tei:rs
            type="organization" key="entity-002627">Drei Masken Verlag</tei:rs> and, subsequently,
          editor-in-chief of the <tei:title level="j">Zeitschrift für Musikwissenschaft</tei:title>,
          Alfred Einstein had frequent dealings with both Schenker and Deutsch.</tei:note> und
        ergänzend bloß an die <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002559"><tei:title>N. Fr.
            Presse</tei:title></tei:rs>.</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Leben Sie wohl! 2:2!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Ihr treue ergebener</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000164">O E
          Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/>Trofaiach, <tei:date
            when="1932-07-21">July 21, 1932</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">friend</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Your lovely letter<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> did not
        reach me until this morning. I hasten to reply to the main question.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">If such an offer is to be made by you, then you should avoid the
        appearance of an advertisement for lessons and emphasize the seminar-like quality, as it is
        only in this way that the gift can be indicated. I do not find the draft text generally
        comprehensible; it must also be more incisive. Aren’t four categories too many for a
        seminar? The August issue of <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002556"><tei:title level="j"
            >Die Musik</tei:title></tei:rs> is probably already in press. Given the currency
        problems, I would imagine that there would be little influx from <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002482">Germany</tei:rs>. If <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002506"
          >Austria</tei:rs> is not sufficient as a reservoir, then one should rather be thinking of
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002507">Switzerland</tei:rs> or <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002586">England</tei:rs>. The <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002559"
            ><tei:title level="j">Neue Freie Presse</tei:title></tei:rs> will not publish anything
        for free, not even from their favorite children, out of journalistic pride. In <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002507">Switzerland</tei:rs>, the <tei:title level="j"
          >Schweizerische Musikzeitung</tei:title> is worth considering; in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002586">England</tei:rs> perhaps the <tei:rs type="journal"
          key="entity-003178"><tei:title level="j">Musical Courier</tei:title></tei:rs>, the address
        of which I can find next week when I am in Vienna. If you are going to take this seriously,
        I would recommend the following text, approximately:</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:hi rend="underline">Dr. Heinrich Schenker</tei:hi>
        <tei:lb/>intends to hold a <tei:hi rend="underline">private seminar</tei:hi> on
          <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> and <tei:term>thoroughbass</tei:term>, manuscript study, and
          <tei:term>performance</tei:term> in the winter semester (October to March). Apply to
        Keilgasse 8, Vienna III, by September 15. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">If you are going to mention <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000027">J.
          S. Bach</tei:rs>’s handbook on thoroughbass by name, then I would say nothing more than:
        Private seminar on <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000027">J. S. Bach</tei:rs>’s
        thoroughbass handbook. Everything else would be in addition. Number of lessons, time, price
        only by mail. We can then still speak about this in Vienna next week.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Regarding<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn31" type="footnote"/> the <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002591">Academy</tei:rs>, following <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-008161">Prüger</tei:rs>’s resignation I spoke again with someone who is in the
        know: the Ministry seems to be as powerless as ever, <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000961">Wiener</tei:rs> is thoroughly autocratic. I have, however, no access
        to him.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000894">Tomay</tei:rs>’s costs, which
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000420">Kalmus</tei:rs> estimated as being higher than
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002402">Waldheim</tei:rs>’s calculation (!), will
        I hope be gradually recovered by the European sales. It is gratifying that the <tei:rs
          type="work" key="entity-001755">volume</tei:rs> is so inexpensive, in spite of the
        costly <tei:pb n="2"/> and wastefully large paper. The result is a twofold gift.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">When time permits, write to me – please – about how you conceive the
        edition of the booklet on thoroughbass. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I am afraid that, on account of having to make necessary economies, I
        shall have to turn down your kind invitation, which I would have so liked to take up either
        before or after my trip to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002578">Salzburg</tei:rs>. On
        this occasion, I would like to indicate to you that <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs>’s salary can be significant for me, as my principal
        income is jeopardized by <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002506">Austria</tei:rs>’s
        misfortune. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000320">Haas</tei:rs>, with whom I spoke again
        last week, expressed his doubt to me about <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380"
          >Hoboken</tei:rs>’s staying in Vienna; but he does not know anything more
        specific.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I do not know anything about the price of newspaper advertisements. One
        would have to ask, which is something that could be done by a central bureau in Vienna (such
        as Haasenstein &amp; Vogler<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/>). Among the
        German dailies, the <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002537"><tei:title level="j"
            >Frankfurter Zeitung</tei:title></tei:rs> comes to mind first. But I think that one
        should be thinking only of specialist publications (<tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000195">Einstein</tei:rs>?)<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/>
        and, in addition, only on the <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002559"><tei:title
            level="j">Neue Freie Presse</tei:title></tei:rs>.</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">May you fare well! From the two of us to the two of
          you!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Your faithfully devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000164">O. E.
            Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
