<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="267" sdoID="OJ-11-35-16">OJ 11/35, 16</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="AHa" scope="sole">August Halm's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="LR">
   <tei:persName>Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2010</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>


  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-12-07" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">
  <sdo:itemDesc><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002698">Halm ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   
   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated February 10, 1920</dc:title>
   
   <dcterms:created>1920-02-20T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-03-21</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Halm acknowledges 69.930/9 and return of contracts. H is looking for a new
    publisher for his compositions, and wonders whether Schenker would put in a good word to UE on
    his behalf, or whether Schenker knows of a small press that might be suitable. Wishes
    Furtwängler would perform something of his. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Kontrakt; contract; Verlags-Kontrakt; publisher's contract; Verlag; Verleger;
    publisher; Kompositionen; compositions; Autor; author; </dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000326">Halm</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:date when="1920-02-10" rend="indent-80">10. II. 20.</tei:date>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine>Wickersdorf bei Saalfeld/Saale (in Thüringen)</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:salute>Sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Ich<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is
     recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/1, p. 2215, February 19, 1920: "Von Halm (Br.): bittet um
     Intervention bei Hertzka." ("From Halm (letter): ask for intervention with Hertzka").
    </tei:note> bin auf etwa 7 Wochen (auch jetzt noch etwa 6) hier, wo ich mich noch immer in der
    Heimat fühle.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Halm returned at the
     end of December 1919 to teach at the Free School Community (Freie Schulgemeinde) at
     Wickersdorf, which he co-founded in 1906 with Paul Geheeb and close friend, colleague and,
     later, brother-in-law Gustav Wyneken (Halm married Wyneken’s younger sister, Hilda, in 1913).
     Halm left his Wickersdorf post as music teacher when Wyneken was forced to resign as director
     of the school in spring of 1910 for various reasons, among them charges of homosexual activity
     with students. </tei:note> Ihre Sendung mit meinen Verlags-Kontrakten habe ich richtig erhalten
    u. danke Ihnen auch für Ihren eingehenden Brief,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Presumably DLA 69.930/9, January 18, 1920. </tei:note> den ich beherzige u. öfters
    gelesen habe. Erlauben Sie mir für jetzt eine geschäftliche Frage. Von der gegenwärtig starken
    Unternehmungslust der <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">Universaledition</tei:rs> hörte ich
    kürzlich auch von anderer Seite. Nun gehen manche meiner Kompositionen, d.h die Auflage, auf die
    Neige, z.B. meine Klaviersachen, u. ich suche auch für neues einen Verlag. Das eigene Risiko u.
    das eigene geschäftliche Drum u. Dran habe ich beschlossen, nicht mehr auf mich zu nehmen u. ich
    möchte Sie fragen, ob Sie glauben, daß die Universaled. meine Sachen nimmt, u. ob Sie bereit
    wären, ihr dazu zu raten. (u. mir). Sie sollen <tei:hi rend="triple-underline">wirklich nicht
     mal Zeit damit verlieren</tei:hi>; aber <tei:pb n="2"/> vielleicht bedarf es Ihrerseits nicht
    vieler Worte, um ihn dafür zu interessieren. Näheres schreibe ich dann, wenn ich Ihre
    grundsätzliche Stellung zu der Frage kenne, die natürlich auch von der Ihnen einstweilen
    gewordenen Antwort des Verlags abhängt (wenn auch einer Neigung, dem Verlag m. Sachen
     anzuvertrauen).<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Halm writes
     continuously at this point, without paragraph-break. </tei:note>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich suche auch in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482">Deutschland</tei:rs>, aber wahrscheinl. nicht mit Erfolg.
    Wissen Sie nicht einen kleinen, <tei:hi rend="underline">aufstrebenden</tei:hi> Verlag <tei:add place="interlinear-above">dort</tei:add>, der noch eher mit den berechtigten Wünschen des
    Autors rechnet?—Ja: das noch: die Buchstabentypen der <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">Univ.
     Ed.</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">UE made use of
     Jugendstil fonts and layout, cultivating a modern appearance. These must have been unwelcome to
     S, as well. </tei:note> sind mir sehr unerwünscht u. fast ein Abhaltungsgrund. Hoffentlich
    besteht sie nicht auf ihnen.—Wenn nur <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furthwängler</tei:rs> einmal was von mir aufführte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Beginning with this sentence (“Wenn Fürthwängler...”), Federhofer
     transcribes this letter in <tei:title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern und Briefen
      ...</tei:title>, p. 141. </tei:note> Ich war eigentlich überrascht, als Sie mir davon
    schrieben, daß er sich Ihnen gegenüber günstig über meine Sachen geäußert habe. Als ich einmal
    bei ihm war, sprach er, zwar dies u. jenes anerkennend, im ganzen in einer für mich wenig
    hoffnungsvoller Weise. Ich habe auch schlecht gespielt, wie es mir leicht passiert, wenn ich
    Widerstand spüre. Meine Stellung zu den Verlegern wird natürlich durch die Zurückhaltung der
    Dirigenten auch nicht leichter. </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Mit herzlichem Gruß </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70">A. Halm</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:date when="1920-02-10" rend="indent-80">February 10, 1920</tei:date>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine>Wickersdorf near Saalfeld/Saale (in Thuringia)</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:salute>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>I<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> have been here going on seven weeks (now
    still around six), where I still feel at home.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> I
    received your mailing with my publisher’s contracts and thank you for your detailed
     letter,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn013" type="footnote"/> which I take to heart and have
    frequently read. Allow me a business question for the moment. I recently heard from another
    quarter about the currently strong enterprising spirit of <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">Universal Edition</tei:rs>. Some of my compositions, that is the edition, are beginning
    to decline, for example my piano pieces, and I am also looking for a publisher for new things. I
    have resolved no longer to take upon myself the personal risk and all the personal odds and
    ends, and would like to ask you whether you believe Universal Edition would take on my pieces,
    and whether you would be prepared to advise them to do that (and to so <tei:supplied reason="clarity">advise</tei:supplied> me). You <tei:hi rend="triple-underline">really should
     not spend too much time on this</tei:hi>; but <tei:pb n="2"/> perhaps it would not require too
    many words from you in order to get him interested. I will write further once I know your basic
    attitude on the matter, which of course also depends on the answer to you from the publisher (if
    also my inclination to entrust the publisher with my pieces).<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p>I am looking in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482">Germany</tei:rs> but probably without success. Do you not
    know a small, <tei:hi rend="underline">up-and-coming</tei:hi> publisher <tei:add place="interlinear-above">there</tei:add> which might sooner reckon with the justified wishes
    of the author?—Yes, this too: the fonts of <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">Universal
     Edition</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> are very undesirable to
    me and almost a reason to deter. Hopefully, it will not insist on them.—If only <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs> would once perform something of mine.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> I was actually surprised when you wrote me that he
    spoke favorably to you about my pieces. When I was once with him, he spoke, acknowledging this
    and that, on the whole in, for me, a less than hopeful manner. I also played badly, as easily
    happens to me when I sense resistance. Because of the reluctance of conductors, my position with
    publishers is of course not made any easier. </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">With cordial greetings, </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70">A. Halm</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>

 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>