<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3783" sdoID="OJ-13-10_106">OJ 13/10, [106]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="TLJ">
      <tei:persName>Timothy L. Jackson</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2010</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated July 21, 1930</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1930-07-21T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-09-10</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel apologizes for not being in touch. – Examinations and meetings at the
        Leipzig Conservatory have consumed his time; in particular, his music theory colleagues have
        been at odds with Sigfrid Karg-Elert, their representative in the Conservatory’s
        Senate.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/>Kiel, <tei:date when="1930-07-21">21. 7.
              30</tei:date>. Feldstr. 77.<tei:hi rend="supralinear">IV</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Professor Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
            >Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for July 24, 1930: “Von Oppel
            (Br.): Bericht aus seinem Hause, von der Schule in Leipzig, namentlich über
              Karg-<tei:sic>Ehlert</tei:sic>, von dem neuen Passacaglia; werde anfangs August
            kommen” (“From Oppel (letter): report of home life, of the school in Leipzig, especially
            about Karg-Elert, of his new passacaglia; he will come at the beginning of
            August”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>längst wollte ich schreiben und Ihnen für den Brief vom <tei:date when="1930-06-22">22.
          6.</tei:date><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of a
          letter on June 22 is not recorded in Schenker’s diary.</tei:note> u. die Karte vom
          <tei:date when="1930-07-03">3. 7.</tei:date> danken.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this picture postcard is recorded in Schenker’s
          diary for July 3: “An Oppel (Ansichtsk.): erster Gruß aus Galtür” (“To Oppel (picture
          postcard): first greeting from Galtür”).</tei:note> Am vorigen Donnerstag kam ich hier an.
        Ich blieb drei Wochen in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002479">Leipzig</tei:rs>, um zu
        sparen. Unterdessen war die Mutter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005266">meiner
          Frau</tei:rs> hier und half ihr. Denn nach so 7 frauenlosen Jahren<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">The boys’ mother, <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-006150">Gertrud Oppel</tei:rs>, had died in 1925 after two years away from
          home in hospital.</tei:note> hat sich allerhand Arbeit angehäuft, die ein Mann nie
        erledigen kann und vor der sich fremde Kräfte immer drücken. Die <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-004801">Jungen</tei:rs> brauchen vielerlei neue Dinge und es geht
        augenblicklich hart über meinen Geldbeutel her. Aber zum Sparen ist jetzt keine Zeit und das
        Leben fordert seine Rechte. <tei:pb n="2"/> Ich bin froh, wenn ich jeden Monat heil ohne
        Schulden - durchkomme. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Sie sind also heil in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>
        gelandet, u. haben hoffentlich Sonne u. schöne Tage u. innere Ruhe zum Arbeiten. Die letzten
        Wochen in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002479">Leipzig</tei:rs> waren anstrengend und
        übel durch die Prüfungen (80 Prüflinge), in keinem Fach eigentlich Leistungen über die
        Durchschnitt. In allgemeinen wird in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002479">L.</tei:rs>
        viel zu sehr der virtuose Drill betont. Das geistige Verständnis bleibt dabei viel zu weit
        hinten. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Dann hatten wir sehr unangenehme Differenzen: wir Theorielehrer haben unserm Vorstand,
        einem gewissen <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005265">Karg-Elert</tei:rs>, 2mal dem Senat
        gegenüber unser Misstrauen ausgesprochen; gleichwohl wollte der famose Herr <tei:pb n="3"/>
        sein Amt nicht niederlegen. Darüber Sitzung um Sitzung, unter uns u. mit der Direction u.
        den Senatsmitgliedern. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wahrscheinlich kommt es im Herbst noch zu einer Ehrengerichtsverhandlung. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-005265">Karg-Elert</tei:rs> wollte absolut sein (Polaritäts-)
        System durchdrücken, wofür wir dankten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Oppel must be using this expression with heavy irony. Karg-Elert’s theory had
          just been, or was about to be, published in book form: <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m"
              >Polaristische Klang- und Tonalitätslehre (Harmonologik)</tei:title> (Leipzig:
            Leuckart, 1930)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> Auch menschlich ist er absolut untauglich als
        Vorstand. Wir sind froh, dass wir uns endlich Luft geschafft haben. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Leider ist uns ein Kollege dabei in den Rücken gefallen, was die Zusammenarbeit für die
        Zukunft wesentlich erschweren wird. Schade, dass soviele Musikanten gänzlich minderwertige
        Menschen u. so wenig anständige Kollegen sind. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>So kam ich nicht zum Schreiben.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Aber nun sehen wir uns ja bald, ich komme spätestens am <tei:date when="1930-08-01">1.
          August</tei:date> nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>. <tei:pb
          n="4"/> In der letzten Zeit habe ich an einer Passac. gearbeitet, bin aber, wie immer, nie
        zufrieden. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Den <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801">Jungen</tei:rs> gehts gut. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> ist meistens nach seiner Werftarbeit
        sehr müde u. geht früh zu Bett. Alle drei futtern zum Schrecken <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-005266">meiner Frau</tei:rs> wie die jungen Löwen. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Der Reichstag ist nun nach Hause geschickt, aber ich glaube, im Herbst gibt es
        Revolten, so kann das bei uns nicht weitergehn. Alles ist verfahren. – </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Alles Gute u. die herzlichsten Grüsse</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>von uns allen Ihnen beiden!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Ihr treuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/>Kiel, <tei:date when="1930-07-21">July 21,
              1930</tei:date>, Feldstrasse 77/4</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor
            Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>For a long time, I wanted to write to you and thank you for your letter of <tei:date
          when="1930-06-22">June 22</tei:date><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> and
        postcard of the <tei:date when="1930-07-03">July 3</tei:date>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
          type="footnote"/> Last Thursday I arrived here. I had stayed for three weeks in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002479">Leipzig</tei:rs>, to economize. In the meantime, my
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005266">wife</tei:rs>’s mother was here and helped her.
        For after seven long years without a wife,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/>
        all sort of work has piled up, which a man can never take care of and alien powers always
        shy away from. The <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801">boys</tei:rs> need all sorts of
        new things, and at the moment that is taking its toll on my wallet. But now is not the time
        to make savings, and life has its demands.<tei:pb n="2"/> I shall be glad if I survive one
        month at a time, without debts.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>So you have arrived safely in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>,
        and I hope that you have sunshine and beautiful days and inner peace in which to work. The
        last weeks in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002479">Leipzig</tei:rs> were exhausting and
        unpleasant on account of the examinations (80 candidates); in no area were there actually
        above-average achievements. In general, the drill of virtuoso performance in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002479">Leipzig</tei:rs> is emphasized far too much; intellectual
        understanding takes too much of a back seat.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In addition, there were very unpleasant disagreements: we theory teachers expressed our
        misgivings about our representative, a certain <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005265"
          >Karg-Elert</tei:rs>, twice before the Senate; nonetheless the famous gentleman <tei:pb
          n="3"/> refused to resign. There was one session after another about this, between us and
        with the administration and the members of the Senate. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Perhaps in the autumn it will still be resolved at a hearing of a court of honour.
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005265">Karg-Elert</tei:rs> was absolutely determined to
        push through his (polarity) system, for which we were grateful.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> From a personal point of view, too, he is
        absolutely unsuited as a representative. We are happy that we have finally created a bit of
        fresh air.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Unfortunately, one of our colleagues has been stabbed in the back over this, which will
        make collaboration in the future significantly more difficult. It is a pity that so many
        musicians are such thoroughly disreputable people and are such indecent colleagues.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>This is why I haven’t written.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>But now we shall indeed see each other soon, as I shall be coming to <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs> on <tei:date when="1930-08-01">August
          1</tei:date> at the latest. <tei:pb n="4"/> I have recently been working on a passacaglia;
        but, as always, I am never satisfied. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>The <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801">boys</tei:rs> are well. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> is usually very tired after his work at
        the shipyard and goes to bed early. All three eat like lions, to my <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-005266">wife</tei:rs>’s horror. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>The Government is now in recess, but I believe that there will be revolts in the
        autumn; things cannot continue like that for us. Everything has gone awry. –</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>All good wishes and the most cordial greetings </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>from all of us to the two of you!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Your faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
