<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="804" sdoID="OJ-11-32_11">OJ 11/32, [11]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPrh" scope="major">Typist Robert Haas</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RH" scope="minor">Robert Haas's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB-MD">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent &amp; Marko Deisinger</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2012</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2012</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2012</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2012-10-24" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>

  </sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-003313">Haas ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-003314">Haas ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-003315">Photogrammarchiv ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-003316">Photogrammarchiv ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


      <dc:title>Typed letter from Robert Haas to Schenker, dated September 15, 1932</dc:title>
      <dcterms:created>1932-09-15T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2012-10-24</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Haas asks Schenker to call on him in relation to a letter from van Hoboken
        regarding the Photogrammarchiv.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Entschliessung; decision; Vorschlag; proposal; Stillegung; shut-down; Board of
        Trustees; Mitglied; member</dc:subject>

      
      
      
    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000320">Haas</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-002452">Photogrammarchiv</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#TPrh"/><tei:placeName>Wien</tei:placeName>, <tei:date when="1932-09-15">15. September
            1932</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>Sehr verehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt
            of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/5, pp. 3773‒3774, September 19,
            1932: "Von Prof. Haas (Br. vom 15. datiert!): möchte mich sprechen, hat leider schon
            geantwortet „ .. hätte gern mit Ihnen gesprochen“ ‒ die Antwort ist unbesonnen, das
            Sprechen kommt zu spät." ("From Prof. Haas (letter dated the 15th!): he would like to
            speak to me, has unfortunately already replied '.. I would have liked to speak with you'
            ‒ the reply is precipitous, speaking comes too late.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Als ich am Montag ins Amt kam, fand ich einen Brief von Herrn <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">van Hoboken</tei:rs> vor, den ich vertraulich auffasste
        und so beantwortete. Er teilt seine bedauerliche Entschliessung mit, <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> zu verlassen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Cf. Hoboken's letter to Schenker of September 5, 1932, OJ
          89/5, [4], in which he states that he is leaving his apartment in Vienna on November 1
          (his furniture being cleared during October), but that this does not mean that he will not
          return; and that he has written "a long letter to Prof. Haas in which I expound my
          position on the future; I enclose a carbon copy for your information." Schenker records
          receipt of this letter, together with that to Haas in carbon copy, in his diary at OJ 4/5,
          p. 3770, September 6. Since the letter, as well as covering the withdrawal of Haas's
          honorarium and reducing that of Kromer, commits to 15,000 shillings for <tei:title level="m">Der freie Satz</tei:title>, Schenker's reaction is primarily one of relief. On
          September 24, 1932 (OJ 4/5, p. 3776), Schenker records receipt of a letter from van
          Hoboken (=OJ 89/5, [6]), which includes a copy of Haas's letter to him and a carbon copy
          of his reply (not filed with letter).</tei:note> und fügt einen Vorschlag wegen des
          <tei:rs key="entity-002452" type="organization">Meisterarchiv</tei:rs>s bei, der
        gleichbedeutend ist mit der Stillegung. Ich musste daraufhin meinen Standpunkt klarstellen,
        dass ich meine Mitwirkung nur einer <tei:hi rend="underline">ganzen</tei:hi> Sache zuwenden
        kann und dass ich bereit bin, vor dem Kuratorium die notwendigen Belege zu geben. Um der
        Sache willen hoffe ich auf eine <tei:pb n="2"/> bessere Einsicht und hätte gern mit Ihnen
        die Sache besprochen, da wir ja als Kuratoriumsmitglieder verantwortlich sind. Vielleicht
        kommen Sie nächste Woche hier vorbei (dann bitte <tei:supplied reason="clarity">ich</tei:supplied> aber vorher um Ansage) oder ich komme auch gern zu Ihnen, wenn Ihnen
        das besser passt.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ihre Karte<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">This
          postcard is not known to survive. </tei:note> wegen <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs> habe ich auf Umwegen erhalten und der Bericht wird ihm
        nochmals zugehen, obwohl er ihm vom <tei:rs key="entity-002452" type="organization">Archiv</tei:rs> aus auch schon einmal zugesendet wurde.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker's diary for September 21, 1932 (OJ 4/5, p. 3775)
          records a meeting: "Von 5‒½8<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> Prof. Haas zur Jause.
          Ich zeige eine Hoboken-„Vitrine“: Generalbaß, Choral, Brahms op. 17<tei:hi rend="supralinear">I‒III</tei:hi> 12 Mazurken von Chopin ‒ das Alles ist ihm von Grund
          aus unbequem: Der Nichtmusiker, Nichthistoriker bäumt sich gegen die ihm fremd drohende
          Ueberlegenheit, er zieht Diagnose u. Therapie immer wieder in sein Arbeitsfeld: Briefe,
          Briefe, Kataloge ‒ Kataloge ‒ ist Alles, was er zum Schutz, zum Auftrieb des Archivs zu
          sagen hat. Nur Spasses halber trage ich meine Idee vom Auftrieb durch eine der Akademie
          anzugliedernde Klasse „Handschiftenkunde“ vor ‒ er warnt mich, macht mir Angst, will aber
          trotzdem „vorfühlen“. Vielleicht hat er dennoch Erfolg mit seiner Kuhhandel-Politik: schon
          hat er statt S. 3000 immerhin S. 6000 erreicht, er hält v. H.'s Taktik lediglich für
          „westeuropäische“ Manier." What is referred to is presumably a portfolio of work that
          Hoboken had been doing for his lessons with Schenker (lesson notes for 1931/32 do not
          survive).<tei:lb/><tei:lb/>("From 5‒7:30 p.m. Prof. Haas for afternoon coffee. I show [him] a
          Hoboken "vitrine": thoroughbass, chorale, Brahms Op. 17, Nos 1‒3, twelve Mazurkas by
          Chopin ‒ all of this makes him deeply uncomfortable. The non-musician, non-historian rises
          up against the superiority, which is strangely threatening to him, and seeks diagnosis and
          therapy constantly from his own area of expertise: letters, letters, catalogs, catalogs is
          all that he has to say about the protection, about the promotion of the Archive. Just as a
          joke I put forward my idea of its promotion by means of a course in "manuscript studies"
          to be attached to the Academy ‒ he warns me, puts the fear of God into me, but will
          nevertheless 'make tentative inquiries.' Perhaps he will nonetheless succeed with his
          cattle-trade politics: already he has reached 6,000 shillings instead of 3,000. He takes
          van Hoboken's tactics merely as 'west-European' manners.") </tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Mit herzlichen Empfehlungen und Grüssen </tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Ihr sehr ergebener</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:handShift new="#RH"/><tei:rs key="entity-000320" type="person">Robert Haas</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#TPrh"/><tei:placeName>Vienna</tei:placeName>, <tei:date when="1932-09-15">September 15,
            1932</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>Highly revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">When I came into the office on Monday I found a letter from Mr <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">van Hoboken</tei:rs>, which I read confidentially and
        then answered. He communicates his regrettable decision to leave <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> and encloses
        a proposal regarding the <tei:rs key="entity-002452" type="organization">Master
          Archive</tei:rs> that is tantamount to shutting it down. In my reply, I had to make my
        position clear that I can devote my participation only to something <tei:hi rend="underline">entire</tei:hi>, and that I am prepared to give the necessary evidence
        before the Board of Trustees. For the sake of the cause, I hope for a <tei:pb n="2"/> better
        understanding and would have liked to speak with you, since as Board members we are in fact
        all responsible. Perhaps you might stop by here next week (but in that case I ask for prior
        notification), or I will gladly come to you if that suits you better.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I have received your postcard<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> regarding <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs>
        by a circuitous route, and the report will go to him once again, although it will also
        already have been sent to him from the <tei:rs key="entity-002452" type="organization">Archive</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">With cordial compliments and greetings,</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Yours very truly,</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:handShift new="#RH"/><tei:rs key="entity-000320" type="person">Robert Haas</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>