<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2191" sdoID="OJ-10-18_1">OJ 10/18, [1]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="AE" scope="sole">Angi Elias's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="MS">
      <tei:persName>Michaela Searfoorce</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006, 2019</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2006, 2019</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2011-03-05" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-007002">EliasA ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">letter</tei:rs>
      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Elias to Schenker, dated August 10, 1922</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1922-08-10T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-01-31</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Miss Elias is unable to get to Galtüt on account of bad weather. — She
        compares prices in the Tyrol with those in Vienna. — She hopes to meet up with the Schenkers
        in Innsbruck on the homeward journey. — She confirms that she will be able to meet her
        financial obligations in teh coming year.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Wetter; weather; Postwagen; post wagon; Telegramm; telegram; Preise; prices;
        Fahrpreise; travel costs; Eisenbahn; railroad; Erholung; vacation; Aufenthalt; stay;
        Pflichte; obligations</dc:subject>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000201">Angi Elias</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:placeName>Pians</tei:placeName>,<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Pians: ski-resort at 3,090 feet in the
            Tyrol, halfway between Landeck and Nauders, and 20 miles east of Galtür (so the journey
            by cart would have been on 20 miles of mountainous road). Schenker's diary for August 10
            tells a rather different story than the letter: "Ans Telephon gerufen: Frl. Elias in
            Pians; will uns besuchen, raten davon ab, da wir Samstag abzureisen beschlossen haben."
            ("Called to the telephone: Miss Elias in Pians; would like to visit us, we advise
            against doing so because we have decided to depart on Saturday."); for August 11 it
            records: "10–1¼<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> mit Frl. Elias im Vermunttal bis
            zur Alm – 5–7<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> auf dem Fädner-Abhang Beeren
            gepflückt. — Frl. Elias, die im Privathaus gewohnt, übesiedelt ins Hotel." ("10:00‒1:15
            with Miss Elias in the Vermunt Valley up to the mountain pasture – picked berries from
            5:00 to 7:00 on the Fädner Slope. — Miss Elias, who was staying in the private house,
            moves into the hotel."); August 15: "½6<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> auf u. mit
            Frl. Elias gegen ½8<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> zum Zeinisjoch; dort das 2.
            Frühstück genommen, zur Echobank. Abschied u. zurück." ("Up at 5:30 and with Miss Elias
            to Zeinisjoch at around 7:30; second breakfast eaten there, to the echo bench. Farewell
            and return.").</tei:note>
          <tei:date when="1922-08-10">10/VIII-22</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Doktor</tei:rs>!<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker's diary does not record
            receipt of this letter, but does record receipt on the 17th of a telegram of thanks, and
            on the 19th of a picture postcard of thanks, both from
          Gargellen.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Ich wollte jetzt eben mit der Post nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292"
          >Galtür</tei:rs> hinauf. Leider ist das Wetter so schlecht, dass ich nun die Fahrt im
        offenen Postwagen doch nicht wagen kann. So sende ich Ihnen auf diesem Wege meine Grüsse. Um
        10 Uhr fahre ich dann wieder nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002304"
          >Innsbruck</tei:rs> zurück. Es hat mir ausserordentlich leid getan <tei:pb n="2"/> durch
        Ihr Telegramm zu erfahren, dass Sie <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>
        bereits verlassen wollen. Ich hätte gedacht, dass die Preise nicht höher sein würden als in
        Wien, wo zum Beispiel (ebenso wie auch in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002382"
          >Seefeld</tei:rs>) 1 kg Butter 30.000K vielleicht jetzt sogar schon noch mehr kostet. Und
        die 4-fach erhöhten Fahrpreise auf der Eisenbahn gelten ja schon vom <tei:date
          when="1922-08-15">15. d. m.</tei:date><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
          place="foot">No new paragraph indicated at this point, but next sentence begins new
          page.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> Ich hätte so sehr gewünscht, dass Sie eine längere Erholung haben.
        Vielleicht haben Sie sich einstweilen doch wieder entschlossen, Ihren Aufenthalt zu
        verlängern. Es würde mich freuen, wenn Sie mir nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002382"
          >Seefeld</tei:rs> schreiben würden wie es Ihnen geht. Wenn Sie so lieb sein wollten mich
        telegraphisch zu verständigen, würde <tei:pb n="4"/> ich Sie auch gerne bei der Durchfahrt
        in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002304">Innsbruck</tei:rs> begrüssen. Ich hätte Ihnen
        noch so manches zu sagen, <tei:sic>dass</tei:sic> ich nicht so in aller Eile aufs Papier
        bringen kann. Nur das Eine möchte ich erwähnen, dass ich aus den Gründen, die ich <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">Ihnen</tei:add> schon in Wien mitteilte, den furchtbaren Tanz
        der Preise ganz leicht mitmachen, daher auch früher versäumte und zukünftige Pflichten gerne
        erfüllen werde.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">upside down in the upper margin:</tei:note><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>Herzliche Grüsse Ihnen u. Ihrer lieben <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
            >Frau</tei:rs></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>von Ihrer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs key="entity-000201" type="person">Angi
          Elias</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>
    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:placeName>Pians</tei:placeName>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
          <tei:date when="1922-08-10">August 10, 1922</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
            type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>I wanted to go up to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs> just now
        by post. Unfortunately the weather is so bad that I cannot now venture the trip in the open
        mail coach. So I send you my greetings by this means. At 10:00 I return again to <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002304">Innsbruck</tei:rs>. I was extremely sorry to learn
          <tei:pb n="2"/> through your telegram that you already want to leave <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>. I would have thought that the prices would be no
        higher than in Vienna, where for example (just as in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002382">Seefeld</tei:rs>) 1 kg of butter costs 30,000 Kronen, perhaps now even
        more. And the fares that have increased four-fold on the railroad have been in effect ever
        since the <tei:date when="1922-08-15">15th of the month</tei:date>.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> I would so very much have wished that you <tei:supplied
          reason="clarity">might</tei:supplied> have a longer vacation. Yet perhaps in the meantime
        you have decided to extend your stay. It would please me, if you were to write me at <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002382">Seefeld</tei:rs>
        <tei:supplied reason="clarity">to tell me</tei:supplied> how you are. If you would be so
        kind as to notify me by telegram, I would <tei:pb n="4"/> be happy to greet you on your way
        through <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002304">Innsbruck</tei:rs>. I would tell you yet
        more that I cannot get down on paper in such a rush. I would mention only the one thing,
        that, for the reasons I already communicated <tei:add place="interlinear-above">to
          you</tei:add> in Vienna, I will quite easily keep pace with the terrible dance of the
        prices, therefore that I will gladly fulfill my future as well as my previously neglected
        obligations.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:pb n="2"/>
        <tei:salute>Cordial greetings to you and your dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
            >wife</tei:rs></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>from your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs key="entity-000201" type="person">Angi
          Elias</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
