<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="601" sdoID="OJ-15-16_51">OJ 15/16, [51]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HW" scope="sole">Hans Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="AH">
   <tei:persName>Alison Hiley</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2009</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-10-27" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated January 14, 1924 </dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1924-01-14T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2011-10-27</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Responding to Schenker's explanation of a recent coldness between them, Weisse
    asserts that his questions arise only from his own studies, not from work with his pupils; it is
    not fear, but dependency on Schenker as a "medium," that drives him to ask such
    questions.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Schüler; pupils; Verdacht; suspicion; Angst; fear; Moral; morality; Stoff; material;
    Mittler; medium; organisch; organic; Zusammenhang; cohesion </dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000951">Weisse</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Verehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this
      letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/6, p. 2621, January 15, 1924: "Von Hans (Br.):
      gewundene Erwiderung, die unfreiwillig gerade das bestätigt, was ich ihm zum Vorwurf mache, z.
      B. wenn er schreibt: . . jede Lösung ein Beitrag zur Reife. – Meine Lösung trägt aber zu
      seiner Reife nichts bei, stillt nur die Neugier. Auch der Anspruch auf das Heimatgefühl legt
      seinen Eigennutz bloß: bequem ist es, überall wo man Vorteile hat zuhause zu sein, selbst aber
      niemand ein Heimatgefühl zu bieten." ("From Hans Weisse (letter): wounded reply, which
      unintentionally confirms precisely what I had reproached him about, e.g. when he writes: . .
      every solution is a contribution to maturity. – My solution though does not contribute
      anything to his maturity, but only awakens his curiosity. Also his pretensions to a sense of
      homeland merely expose his self-interest: it is convenient to be at home everywhere where one
      enjoys advantages, without offering anyone else a sense of home."). </tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Meinen aufrichtigsten Dank für Ihren eben erhaltenen Brief, den ich umso höher einschätze,
    als ich ihm entnehme, daß Ihre persönliche Teilnahme an mir, in früheren Jahren wohl das
    schönste meiner Besitztümer, sich erhalten hat. Daß ich Sie ganz verstehe, brauche ich wohl des
    weitern nicht auszuführen. Daß ich meinen Schülern gegenüber genau so handle, als Sie es
    wünschen, ist nur ein Beleg dafür: Ich nehme nur Werke von A bis Z mit <tei:choice>
     <tei:sic>Ihnen</tei:sic>
     <tei:corr>?ihnen</tei:corr>
    </tei:choice> durch und mein Bestreben ihnen gegenüber gilt <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">word deleted</tei:note> dem einen Ziele: den Blick fürs Ganze aus dem Ganzen
    heraus zu schärfen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Sie hegen, so scheint es mir, den Verdacht, daß die Stellen um die ich Sie oft befrage,
    mich unsicher machen, und ich aus „Angst“ meine Zuflucht zu Ihnen nehme, um mir von den Schülern
    nichts zu vergeben. Dies trifft aber nicht zu. Fürs erste entspringen die Fragen meinen eigenen
    Studienkreisen; so blie<tei:pb n="2"/> be denn nur zu beantworten, was für eine Bewandtnis es
    mit der Angst habe, mit der „Angst vor dem Stoffe“, als welche ihre Bezeichnung wohl verstanden
    werden will: und wenn ich Sie bitte, Sich einen Augenblick in einen Ihrer Schüler zu versetzen,
    so glaube ich <tei:add place="interlinear-above">es</tei:add> im Namen all ihrer tiefer
    veranlagten tun zu dürfen. Erst das Bewußtsein von Gut und Böse läßt Probleme der Moral
    aufkommen: und so ist und muß es eine Begleiterscheinung Ihrer Lehre <tei:del rend="overstrike">sein</tei:del>, die man auch das Bewußtsein der Musik nennen könnte, sein, daß jeder der
    vollen Verantwortung sich inne wird, mit der er nun seinen Beruf auszuüben hat. Angst vor anderm
    braucht sie nicht zu sein, denn lernten wir nicht gleichzeitig von Ihnen, daß wir das notwendig
    falsche Urteil der andern nicht zu fürchten haben? Aber das innige Bedürfnis dem Stoffe bis ins
    Letzte gerecht zu werden kann von der Erkenntnis nicht gelöst werden, daß so etwas <tei:add place="interlinear-above">überhaupt</tei:add> möglich ist. Verstehe ich das also unter Angst,
    und nur so will und kann ich das Wort in Ihrem Zusammenhange deuten. <tei:pb n="3"/> Unsere
    Abhängigkeit vom musikalischen Stoff ist selbstverständlich gleichzeitig eine Abhängigkeit von
    Ihnen als dem Mittler dieses Stoffes. Was uns zu Ihnen treibt mit unseren tausend Fragen
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ist</tei:add> eine Art Heimatgefühl, was sollte <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">sie</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">es</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> stillen können, wenn nicht Sie? – Jede Ihrer Lösungen ist mit ein Baustein zur
    Reife. – </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich wollte nichts, als Ihnen den organischen Zusammenhang unsrer Fragelust mit Ihrer Lehre
     aufzuzeigen<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">corr.</tei:note>. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Im übrigen respektiere ich selbstverständlich Ihren Befehl, und erscheine von nun an nur
    mehr mit <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person">Haydn</tei:rs>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">It is not clear whether Weisse was working on a Haydn project
     (none is mentioned in any of the other letters), or whether he was using the composer’s name as
     a code for matters of a purely musical nature. </tei:note>
   </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mit besten Grüßen an Sie und Frau <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie Lie</tei:rs></tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr dankbarer </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Hans</tei:rs>
    </tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline>
     <tei:date when="1924-01-14">14. Jänner 24</tei:date>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Enclosed with this letter is a handwritten copy of a letter from
      Franz Schubert to the publishers Cappi and Diabelli, identified by Weisse as No. 58 of the
        <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Briefe und Schriften Franz Schuberts</tei:title>, edited by
       Otto Erich Deutsch (Munich: Georg Müller, 1919</tei:bibl>). Schenker published this, word for
      word, in the "Vermischtes" (Miscellanea) of <tei:title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der
       Musik</tei:title> I (1925), pp. 217–18; Eng. trans., vol. I, p. 120. His postscript remark,
      "Heute wie gestern, die Cappi’s u. Diabelli’s sterben nicht aus" ("Today, as yesterday, the
      Cappis and Diabellis of the world are not dying out") is also pencilled at the end of Weisse’s
      copy of the letter.<tei:lb/> That the Schubert letter was withheld for a year – it arrived in
      time to be included among the "Miscellanea" for <tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title>
      – suggests that it may have had an autobiographical resonance for Schenker. In 1923 and 1924
      Schenker was going through a bitter legal wrangle with Emil Hertzka at Universal Edition, and
      for the <tei:title level="j">Meisterwerk</tei:title> yearbooks he changed publishers. Weisse
      was aware of this dispute with Hertzka, as he refers to it in his next letter, OJ 15/16, [52],
      August 28, 1924. </tei:note></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>My most sincere thanks for your letter, which I have just received, and which I appreciate
    all the more since I can infer from it that your personal interest in me – certainly my most
    treasured possession of former years – has been preserved. I understand you fully and feel I do
    not need to explain further. The fact that I approach my pupils just as you wish is merely
    evidence of this. I only go through works with <tei:choice>
     <tei:sic>you</tei:sic>
     <tei:corr>?them</tei:corr>
    </tei:choice> from A to Z, endeavouring always to attain the same goal, namely to tease out a
    sense of the whole from the whole. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>It seems to me that you are harbouring the suspicion that the many passages that I
    frequently ask you about make me unsure of myself and that I come running to you out of fear
    that I might lose face in front of my pupils. That is, however, not the case. In the first place
    my questions arise from my own studies; thus the only question to address is <tei:pb n="2"/>
    what it might have to do with fear, with "fear of the subject," which is how one should
    evidently understand your term. And if I were to ask you to put yourself in the shoes of one of
    your pupils, I would feel justified in doing so in the name of all those whose deeper
    inclination <tei:supplied reason="clarity">you have invoked</tei:supplied>. It is only with an
    awareness of good and evil that moral problems arise; and thus what one might call the
    consciousness of music does, and must, go hand in hand with your teaching, since you enable
    everyone to reach an awareness of the full responsibility with which he must now carry out his
    profession. Fear doesn't need to be involved, for did we not at the same time learn from you
    that we must not be afraid of the inevitably false judgement of others? But the inner need to do
    full justice to the material cannot be separated from the realization that such a thing is
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">at all</tei:add> possible. That is my understanding of fear
    and that is the only way I want and am able to interpret the word as you use it. <tei:pb n="3"/>
    It stands to reason that our dependency on the musical material is simultaneously a dependence
    on you as the medium. The sense that drives us to you with our thousand fold questions <tei:add place="interlinear-above">is</tei:add> like a homecoming – who else to satisfy it but you? –
    Each of your solutions is at the same time a building block towards maturity. – </tei:p>

   <tei:p>I only wanted to exhibit the organic cohesion of our questioning in relation to your
    teaching. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Otherwise I of course respect your command and will appear from now on only with <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person">Haydn</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/>
   </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">With warmest greetings to you and <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie Lie</tei:rs></tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your grateful </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Hans</tei:rs>
    </tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline>
     <tei:date when="1924-01-14">January 14, 1924</tei:date><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>