<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="114" sdoID="OJ-10-1_36">OJ 10/1, [36]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="WDa" scope="sole">Walter Dahms's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="JK">
   <tei:persName>John Koslovsky</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2009</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2009</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2010</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002725">Dahms ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Dahms to Schenker, dated March 15, 1919</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1919-03-15T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-01-30</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Dahms is spending time with Otto Vrieslander, working through Schenker's
    Harmonielehre with him and preparing himself for study with Schenker. He rejoices at the
    crushing of German militarism. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Verhältnisse; conditions; Lehrzeit; period of study; Militarismus; militarism;
    Grossstadt; city; Individualismus; individualism; Geistigkeit; intellectualism</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000149">Dahms</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Hochverehrter, lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>! </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Seit<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
     this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/14, p. 2044, March 23, 1919: "Von Dahms
     (Br.): habe sich fern von Großstadt u. Zeitungen erholt, sei bereits zum Ende der Harmonielehre
     gekommen u. freue sich, schon einigermaßen vorbereitet nach Wien zu kommen. So schmerzlich ihn
     die Verhältnisse in Deutschland berühren, freue er sich doch über den Zusammenbruch des
     Militarismus." ("From Dahms (letter): has been recovering far from city and newspapers, has
     already reached the end of <tei:title level="m">Harmonielehre</tei:title> and looks forward to
     coming to Vienna already somewhat prepared. However painful the conditions in Germany are to
     him, he is glad about the collapse of German militarism.").<!-- XR -->
    </tei:note> langem habe ich nichts mehr von Ihnen gehört, wie Sie sich gesundheitlich befinden
    und ob sich die neuen Verhältnisse nicht noch ungünstiger für Ihre Arbeit gestaltet haben, als
    es die alten zuletzt waren. An jedem Dienstag und Freitag bin ich bei <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002326">Ebersberg</tei:rs>, und Sie stehen nachingemäss stets im Mittelpunkt unserer Gespräche, da wir
    jetzt Ihre "<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724">
     <tei:title>Harmonielehre</tei:title>
    </tei:rs>" nahezu <tei:pb n="2"/> beendet haben. Da kann ich selbstverständlich nicht genug von
    Ihnen, Ihren Meinungen über alle Fragen, die uns angehen usw <tei:add place="interlinear-above">hören</tei:add>. So stehe ich denn jetzt doch schon wenigstens in indirekten Fühlung mit
    Ihnen. Mögen sich nur die Verhältnisse in absehbarer Zeit so bessern, dass einmal <tei:add place="interlinear-above">an</tei:add> einen längeren Aufenthalt in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Wien</tei:rs> für mich zu denken ist. Ich sehne mich sehr danach.
    Wenigstens kann ich diese Zeit jetzt benützen, um mich auf das beste vorzubereiten <tei:pb n="3"/> für eine Lehrzeit bei Ihnen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich finde hier wenigstens äusserlich meine Ruhe. Grösste Vorsicht im Lesen
    von Zeitungen, Vermeidung der Grossstadt, bewahren mich wenigstens einigermassen vor dem
    Widerwärtigen der heutigen Zeit und ihrer Erscheinungen. Dem Individualismus und der Geistigkeit
    scheint man jetzt endgültig das Grab graben zu wollen. Seies drum! Vielleicht oder besser:
    wahrscheinlich hat es so kommen müssen. Ich persönlich <tei:pb n="4"/> empfinde nur eine Freude:
    die über die Zerschmetterung des deutschen Militarismus. So bleibt wenigstens der kommenden
    Generation unser Schicksal erspart. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Vielleicht haben Sie einmal Zeit zu ein paar Zeilen an mich. Dafür wäre Ihnen
    sehr dankbar </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Sie herzlichst grüssender</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">treuergebener</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50">Walter Dahms</tei:signed>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine>Wasserburg a/Inn <tei:date when="1919-03-15">15. III.
      19.</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-05">Villa Nixe</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dear, revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Master</tei:rs>, </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">I<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> have not heard from you for
    a while, how your health is holding up and whether the new conditions have been any less
    conducive for your work than the previous ones were. On each Tuesday and Friday I am at <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>'s place in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002326">Ebersberg</tei:rs>. You are the focus of our conversation most of the time,
    as we have almost <tei:pb n="2"/> finished your <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724">
     <tei:title level="m">Theory of Harmony</tei:title>
    </tei:rs>. I just cannot <tei:add place="interlinear-above">hear</tei:add> enough of you and
    your views on all matters that interest us, etc.. So I remain (at the very least) connected to
    you in feeling, in an indirect way. If only conditions would improve in the foreseeable future,
    then a long sojourn in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Vienna</tei:rs> would finally be
    conceivable. I long so much for this. At the very least I can use this time to best prepare
    myself <tei:pb n="3"/> for a period of study with you. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Here I am finding peace, at least superficially. Taking the greatest caution
    in reading the newspapers and avoiding the city protect me to a certain degree from that which
    is disgusting in life today and its manifestations. Individualism and intellectualism are
    definitively digging their own grave. Never mind all that, though! Perhaps, or even better, most
    likely it had it coming. I personally <tei:pb n="4"/> feel but a single joy: that of the
    crushing defeat of German militarism. The next generation will at least be spared our fate. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">If you have the time to write me but a few lines, I would certainly be
    grateful. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Yours,</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">with warmest greetings, </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">ever-faithfully, </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50">Walter Dahms</tei:signed>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine>Wasserburg on the Inn <tei:date when="1919-03-15">March 15,
      1919</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-05">Villa Nixe</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>