<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3919" sdoID="OJ-13-10_134">OJ 13/10, [134]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="TLJ">
      <tei:persName>Timothy L. Jackson</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2026</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2026</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2026</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated July 18 and 20, 1931</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1931-07-20T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2026-02-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel may not get to Galtür because of the 100 mark tax the government is
        imposing on its citizens for crossing the border. – He writes despairingly of the political
        situation in Germany.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/>
            <tei:placeName>Leipzig</tei:placeName>
            <tei:date when="1931-07-18">18. VII 31</tei:date>.</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Professor Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
            >Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for July 22, 1931: “Von Oppel
            (Br.): Gefährdung der Sommerreise durch die politische Krise (u. M. 100 Einreisetaxe).”
            (“From Oppel (letter): summer trip at risk on account of the political crisis (and a
            100-mark travel tax).”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>heute ist Schluss bei uns im <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002872"
          >Kons.</tei:rs> Ob ich aber reise, ist nach den letzten Entschliessungen der Regierung
        sehr fraglich: die 100 M Passgebühren beim Grenzübertritt sind eine Unverschämtheit, u.
        obendrein eine zwecklose Massregel, da die Leute mit Geld es natürlich längst ins Ausland
        zustehen haben. So bringt man uns noch um unsre Erholung. Die Regierung ist total unfähig,
        auf der ganzen Linie. Die Folge wird sein, dass das Ausland mit der gleichen Massregel
        antwortet. Unsre ganze Politik ist so trostlos, so unmännlich, dass man sich fast schönt,
        ein Deutscher zu sein. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Diese ewige Furcht vor <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002520">Frankreich</tei:rs> auf
        der eine Seite, u. vor dem Bürgerkrieg auf der anderen! Ich fürchte nur, wir geraten noch
        tiefer in den Sumpf. Leider haben <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002510">Amerika</tei:rs>
        u. <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002586">England</tei:rs> auch nur solche Schafsköpfe wie
        wir, alles bangt sich vor der Schamlosigkeit <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002520"
          >Frankreich</tei:rs>s. Zollunion u. unsre neuer Panzerkreuzer als Preis der neuen
        Demütigung. Das würde diesem französ. Raubgeschwindel so fassen, die neuen Erfindungen, die
        der Panzerkreuzer alle hat, ohne jede geistige Mühe einfach so überzuschlucken. Echt
        französisch! <tei:pb n="2"/> Also vorläufig heisst abwarten. Vielleicht bringt der August
        etwas mehr Klärung. Wie lange bleiben Sie in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292"
          >Galtür</tei:rs>? – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Herzlichen Dank für den Mozart-Aufsatz im <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-003014"
            ><tei:title>Kunstwart</tei:title></tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Heinrich Schenker</tei:author>,
              <tei:title level="a">Ein verschollener Brief von Mozart und das Geheimnis seines
              Schaffens,</tei:title>
            <tei:title level="j">Der Kunstwart</tei:title> 44 (July 1931),
          660‒66</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> Er hat mich sehr gefreut. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Inzwischen habe ich ein neues Quartett begonnen. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Das Wetter ist bei uns miserabel, sehr viel Regen u. wenig Sonne jetzt. Hoffentlich
        haben Sie in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs> mehr Sonne. <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002334">Tirol</tei:rs> wird leider mitleiden müssen bei unsern
        Einschränkungen, denn niemand traut die Regierung u. den Verhältnissen, wenn die Zeitungen
        auch von Ruhe berichten, so ist das nur ein Trugschluss. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:date when="1931-07-20">20. VII 31</tei:date>. Die <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002477">Paris</tei:rs>er Zusammenkunft<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot">The most prominent event of July 1931 was the Paris Colonial
          Exhibition, but Oppel must be referring to a less well-known diplomatic meeting, or one
          concerning the Great Depression.</tei:note> war nur ein Beschaffenes der wilden Tiere. Auf
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002643">London</tei:rs> setzte ich auch gar keine
          Hoffnung.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">The allusion is to
          the London Conference, which was convened to address the German financial crisis, and met
          from July 17 to August 11.</tei:note> Wir leben schon in einer verrückten Zeit. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Alles Gute u. herzliche Grüsse!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr treuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/>
            <tei:placeName>Leipzig</tei:placeName>
            <tei:date when="1931-07-18">July 18, 1931</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor
            Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Today is the last day of classes at our <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002872"
          >Conservatory</tei:rs>. However, whether I will be able to travel is very questionable
        after the government's latest decisions: the 100 Reichsmark passport fee for crossing the
        border is an outrage, and moreover, a pointless measure, since people with money have, of
        course, already gone abroad. This is how they're even depriving us of our rest and
        relaxation. The government is completely incompetent, across the board. The consequence will
        be that other countries will respond with the same measure. Our entire political situation
        is so hopeless, so unmanly, that one almost feels ashamed to be German.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>This eternal fear of <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002520">France</tei:rs> on the
        one hand, and of civil war on the other! I only fear that we will sink even deeper into the
        mire. Unfortunately, <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002510">America</tei:rs> and <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002586">England</tei:rs> also only have such blockheads as we do;
        everyone is afraid of <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002520">France</tei:rs>'s
        shamelessness. A customs union and our new armored cruiser as the price of this latest
        humiliation. That would suit this French thieving perfectly, simply snatching up all the new
        inventions that the armored cruiser possesses, without any intellectual effort whatsoever.
        Truly French! <tei:pb n="2"/> So, for the time being, we have to wait and see. Perhaps
        August will bring some more clarity. How long will you be staying in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>? –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Cordial thanks for the Mozart essay in <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-003014"
            ><tei:title level="j">Der Kunstwart</tei:title></tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> I was very pleased with it. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In the meantime, I have started a new quartet. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>The weather here is miserable, a lot of rain and little sunshine lately. I hope you are
        having more sunshine in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>. The
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002334">Tyrol</tei:rs> will unfortunately have to suffer
        along with us because of our restrictions, because nobody trusts the government or the
        current situation, even if the newspapers report calm; that's just a delusion. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:date when="1931-07-20">July 20, 1931</tei:date>. The <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002477">Paris</tei:rs> meeting<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/>
        was nothing but a gathering of wild animals. I had absolutely no hope for <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002643">London</tei:rs> either.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
          type="footnote"/> We are truly living in crazy times.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">All the best and cordial greetings!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
