<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2751" sdoID="OJ-12-59_5">OJ 12/59, [5]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="SFM" scope="sole">Siegfried Fritz Müller's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2022</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2022</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>


    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2011-06-09" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008182">MüllerSF ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Siegfried Fritz Müller to Schenker, dated September 21,
        1924</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1924-09-21T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2022-05-10</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Siegfried Fritz Müller has met with resistence in rural Switzerland to
        Schenker's ideas. -- He describes his daily working practices. -- He plans to return to
        Schenker for lessons in Spring 1925 and lists the works in his prepared
        programs.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000618">SFMüller</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10"><tei:handShift new="#SFM"/>Hochverehrter Herr <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01"
            type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for
            September 23, 1924: “Von Fritz Müller (K.): Schwierigkeit, <tei:title>den
              Tonwille</tei:title> den Musikern beizubringen; bestelle 3 Exemplare für sich, um sie
            nach Gutdünken zu verbreiten; komme bestimmt im Frühling, um ein gegebenes Programm
            durchzuarbeiten.” (“From Fritz Müller (postcard): difficulty teaching <tei:title
              level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title> to the musicians; orders three copies for himself
            to distribute as he sees fit; will definitely come in the spring to work through a set
            program.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">four lines left blank</tei:note><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="indent-20">Verzeihen Sie mein langes Schweigen. Ich habe mir auch Mühe gegeben,
        Subskribenten für das neue Werk<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Müller is referring to <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001749"><tei:title level="j">Das
              Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:title></tei:rs> (Munich: Drei-Masken Verlag, 1925, 1926,
          1930), the successor to <tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title>, the title of which
          was not determined until January 1925</tei:note> zu bekommen, doch leider vergeblich. In
        unsren Dörfern fühlen die Leute sehr wenig Bedürfnis, sich mit musikalischen Problemen
        auseinanderzusetzen, sondern denken, Ihre kostbare „Unmittelbarkeit“ zu verlieren, wenn sie
        wissen, worum <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> ein Meister war.
        Nun hoffe ich, der Sache dadurch einen Dienst zu erweisen, wenn ich auf 3 Exemplare
        subskribieren und diese dann möglichst vielen Leuten zeigen, die dann vielleicht doch
        abonnieren werden. Ich bitte Sie, mir meine schlechten Vorkämpferdienste „nach
          Westen“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">“nach Westen”: In the
          lead article of the first issue of <tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title>, Schenker
          vented his animosity toward the Romance and Anglo-Saxon nations of the west, with their
          civilisation and democracy, in uncomfortably virulent form. Müller perhaps sees himself as
          recruiting “pioneers” (<tei:hi rend="italic">Vorkämpfer</tei:hi>) to fight for the
          Schenker cause in these benighted lands (he himself was in Switzerland, not mentioned by
          Schenker), which he places in quotation-marks.</tei:note> zu verzeihen, es ist halt nicht
        so leicht, den Menschen zu beweisen, daß es eine ganze tiefe Problematik in der Musik gibt
        (Und zu dem ist es auch sehr viel leichter, nach „eigener Auffassung“ zu spielen, als sich
        zu bemühen, den „Sinn des Werkes” aufzufassen.) </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> Vielleicht interessiert es Sie, nach Erledigung des
        „geschäftlichen Teiles,“ einiges von mir zu erfahren. In meiner Stellung geht es mir soweit
        ganz gut, ich trachte danach, mir eine bessere (d.h. künstlerisch anfriedigerende) zu
        verschaffen, mit andern Worten, ich arbeite wie ein Unhold. Endlich hoffe ich, soweit zu
        sein, konsequent arbeiten zu können, ohne Rücksicht auf die Dauer. Morgens früh stehe ich
        auf und arbeite dann zirka 13 Stunden jeden Tag, fast ohne Pause, bis abends 10 Uhr, wo die
        hohe <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">illegible word</tei:note> mir Ruhe
          befiehlt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Müller writes
          continuously at this point, without paragraph-break.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Im Frühjahr komme ich bestimmt zu Ihnen, wenn Sie mich brauchen können.
        Dieser Gedanke treibt mich an, die Freude verleiht der Energie den Schwung. Ich werde bis
        dahin Programme fertig haben, die ich brenne, bei Ihnen spielen und durcharbeiten zu dürfen.
        Erst <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000129">Chopin</tei:rs>, beide Sonaten, die <tei:rs
          type="composition" key="entity-004724">12 Etüden aus op 25</tei:rs> und Stücke. Dann
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
          >Brahms</tei:hi></tei:rs>: <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001354"
              ><tei:title><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Händel</tei:hi>-</tei:title></tei:rs> und
          <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001356"><tei:title><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
              >Paganini</tei:hi>-variationen</tei:title></tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="composition"
          key="entity-005590"><tei:title>Sonate in f-moll</tei:title></tei:rs>, dann <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000055"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Beethoven</tei:hi></tei:rs>,
        die 3 Letzten, <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001208"
            ><tei:title>Waldstein</tei:title></tei:rs> und <tei:rs type="composition"
          key="entity-001226"><tei:title>f moll Sonate</tei:title></tei:rs>. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich hoffe Sie bei bestem Wohlsein und danke Ihnen herzlichst für Ihren
        Brief und besonders auch für die Liste.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Schenker’s letter is not known to survive, nor does it appear to have been
          summarized in his diary. Schenker’s diary gives no clue as to the nature of the list
          (though it could have been a list of known subscribers to <tei:title level="j">Der
            Tonwille</tei:title>).</tei:note> Wie freue ich mich auf den
          „<tei:title>Tonwillen</tei:title>“ im neuen Gewand!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06"
          type="editorial" place="foot">See footnote 2, above.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">In aufrichtiger Ergebenheit verbleibe ich mit den herzlichsten Grüße auch
        an Ihre werte <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Frau Gemahlin</tei:rs>
      </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-55">Ihr dankbarer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-75"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000618">Fritz
          Müller</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004164">St. Gallen</tei:rs>, d. <tei:date
            when="1924-09-21">21. IX. 24</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10"><tei:handShift new="#SFM"/>Highly revered <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000632">Professor</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"
          /></tei:salute>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">four lines left blank</tei:note><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="indent-20">Forgive me my long silence. I have been at pains to acquire
        subscribers for the new publication,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> but
        alas, in vain. In our villages people feel very little necessity to grapple with musical
        problems; they think they will lose their precious “immediacy” if they know <tei:hi
          rend="italic">why</tei:hi>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> was a master. Now I am hoping
        to perform a service to the cause by subscribing to three copies and then showing these to
        as many people as possible, who will then perhaps <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
          >themselves</tei:supplied> subscribe. Please forgive me my feeble efforts to recruit
        campaigners “in the West.”<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> It is not so easy
        just to prove to people that there is a whole, deep problematic issue in music (people to
        whom it is actually very much easier to play according to “one’s own conception” than by
        taking the trouble to understand the “import of the work.”)</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> Perhaps it might interest you, now that I have finished
        the “business part” <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of this letter</tei:supplied>, to learn
        something about myself. Everything so far is going well in my job, I endeavor accordingly to
        provide a better (i.e. artistically more satisfactory) <tei:supplied reason="omission"
          >product</tei:supplied>, in other words I work like a fiend. Ultimately I hope to be able
        to work consistently without regard to the time. I get up early in the morning and work for
        about thirteen hours each day, with almost no break, until 10 p.m., when the high <tei:note
          type="editorial" place="inline">illegible word</tei:note> dictates that I rest.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">In the Spring I will definitely come to you if you can <tei:unclear
          reason="meaning">accommodate</tei:unclear> me. This thought spurs me on, imparts momentum
        to my energy. By that time, I will have prepared programs that I am aching to be allowed to
        play to, and work through with, you. Firstly, of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000129"
          >Chopin</tei:rs>, both sonatas, the <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-004724">twelve
          Etudes Op. 25</tei:rs> and pieces, then <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094"
          >Brahms</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001354"><tei:title>Handel
              <tei:supplied reason="identity">Variations</tei:supplied></tei:title></tei:rs>,
          <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001356"><tei:title>Paganini
          Variations</tei:title></tei:rs>, and <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-005590"
            ><tei:title>F minor Sonata</tei:title></tei:rs>, then <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>, the three last <tei:supplied reason="identity"
          >sonatas</tei:supplied>, the <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001208"
            >“<tei:title>Waldstein</tei:title>”</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="composition"
          key="entity-001226"><tei:title>F minor Sonata</tei:title></tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I hope you are in the best of health and thank you most cordially for your
        letter, especially for the list.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> How I look
        forward to the <tei:title level="j">Tonwille</tei:title> in new garb!<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">In sincere devotion, I remain, with most cordial greetings also to your
        esteemed <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">wife</tei:rs>,</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-55">Your grateful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-75"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000618">Fritz
          Müller</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004164">St. Gallen</tei:rs>, <tei:date
            when="1924-09-21">September 21, 1924</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
