<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3289" sdoID="OJ-10-3_213">OJ 10/3, [213]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPoed" scope="major">Otto Erich Deutsch typist</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="OED" scope="minor">Otto Erich Deutsch's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2023</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IDB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2015-09-18" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002726">DeutschOE ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002712">DeutschOE ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002727">DeutschOE+H ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Typewritten letter from Deutsch to Schenker, dated June 29, 1934</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1934-06-29T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2023-09-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Deutsch responds to queries about the forthcoming publication of Der freie
        Satz, making recommendations about the contract, and the way in which Anthony van Hoboken is
        to be invoiced for his financial support; he offers to proofread the text when the time
        comes. -- His difficulties with Hoboken continue, this time over the purchase of some
        inexpensive editions of music which could be replaced with better ones. -- He is to give a
        course at the Vienna Academy; Hoboken needs to be informed about this, and he would like to
        be able to tell Hoboken that he is offering this course at Schenker’s
        prompting.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000164">DeutschOE</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>PROF. OTTO ERICH DEUTSCH</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Tel. R 45–6–72</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">WIEN II.</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Böcklinstraße 26</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/><tei:date when="1934-06-29">29.
            June 34</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Verehrter</tei:rs>!<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in
            Schenker’s diary for July 2, 1934: “Von Deutsch (Br.): Bemerkungen zum Vertrag [für Der
            freie Satz]; hält im September den Kurs an der Akademie: Was mir versagt wurde, ist dem
            hilflosen Anfänger gern gewährt, dem erst durch mich der Weg zum Archivar, zur richtigen
            Handhabung der Erstdrucke gewiesen worden u. schließlich sogar der Weg zu dem Kurse
            förmlich aufgetragen wurde!!” (“From Deutsch (letter): remarks about the contract [for
            Free Composition]; he is giving the course at the Academy in September: what was denied
            to me is gladly entrusted to the helpless beginner, who by me alone was shown the way to
            becoming an archivist, the correct way to deal with first editions; and, finally, was
            even set on the route to giving courses!!”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Heute endlich kann ich auf Ihre beiden Briefe<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker responded to Deutsch’s postcard of June 11
            (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-10-3_211">OJ 10/3, [211]</tei:ref>) with a
          reassuring letter the following day: “An Deutsch (Br.): nichts von ‘böse’ – gegenseitige
          Schonung Ausdruck unserer gesunkenen Zustände – bitte um schriftliche Mitteilung.” (“To
          Deutsch (letter): not at all ‘angry’– our clemency towards one another is the expression
          of our sunken conditions – I ask for a reply in writing.”). —The writing of a second
          letter, which included the letters from Kalmus (Universal Edition) and the draft contract
          for <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title level="m">Der freie
              Satz</tei:title></tei:rs>, is not recorded in the diary.</tei:note> antworten, und
        auch nur, weil der zweite so dringend scheint. Ich bin sehr beschäftigt seit meiner Heimkehr
        und hatte mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs> neuerdings
        Verdruss, der einen langen Brief kostete. Sie werden alles lesen, wenn Sie wünschen, für
        heute sage ich nur, dass er mir Vorwürfe aus dem früheren Ankauf von Stücken machen wollte,
        die wir jetzt durch bessere ersetzen können. Dabei ist der Ankauf zum Teil ohne mich
        geschehen, und aus geringer Sachkenntnis natürlich, überdies so billig, dass beide Exemplare
        in diesen fünf zufälligen Beispielen jeweils kaum den wahren Wert kosteten, bevor noch das
        überzählige verkauft ist. Ich sende Ihnen nächstens die ganze liebliche Korrespondenz, die
        schon friedlich abgeschlossen schien und jetzt wohl endgiltig ist. Dass Sie ihn eines
        Bessern über mich belehren mögen, wage ich nicht mehr zu bitten. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Meine <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000163">Frau</tei:rs> ist nach
        acht Tagen Spital wieder hergestellt. Es war eine Vergiftung unbekannter Herkunft mit Kolik
        und dann Darmverschluss, ohne dass glücklicher Weise ein operativer Eingriff nötig wurde. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-003103">Saturn</tei:rs> hat mir
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000412">Jonas</tei:rs>’ Buch<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Das Wesen
              des musikalischen Kunstwerks: Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers</tei:title>
            (Vienna: Saturn, 1934)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> angekündigt.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Nun das Dringende: die beiden Briefe der <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002408">UE</tei:rs> und Vertragsentwurf<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04"
          type="editorial" place="foot">The contract for the publication of <tei:rs type="work"
            key="entity-001728"><tei:title level="m">Der freie Satz</tei:title></tei:rs>.</tei:note>
        scheinen mir gut zu sein, bis auf die notierten Punkte: </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">13. Juni: dass der Einband nur nach Bedarf und partienweise, besser:
          serienweise<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">This may refer to
          the publication of <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title level="m">Der freie
              Satz</tei:title></tei:rs> as a two-volume set comprising text and music illustrations;
          a hard binding, if required, would apply to both parts of the set. </tei:note> gemacht
        wird, versteht sich zwar von selbst, sollte aber, weil es sich um das Geld eines Dritten
        handeln, besonders gesagt werden. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">22. Juni: ich glaube, dass es <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380"
          >Hoboken</tei:rs> passen wird, die Rechnungen jeweils innerhalb eines Monats nach Vorlage
        zu bezahlen, wobei man auch schon den Weg zu ihm einberechnet hätte. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Wenn die <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000412">UE</tei:rs> aber, wie
        ihre Lieferanten, das Geld so prompt erwartet, so sollte sie auch es rascher als einmal im
        Jahr zurückzuerstatten suchen. Also statt einmalige Abrech<tei:supplied reason="mistyping"
          >n</tei:supplied>ung womöglich halbjährige oder besser vierteljährige. Aber ich würde
        daraus keine Streitfrage <tei:pb n="2"/> machen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Endlich zum Vertragsentwurf, in den die<tei:del rend="overstrike"
          >se</tei:del> drei Punkte womöglich aufgenommen werden sollten, noch dieses: Im zweiten
        Absatz muss, erste Zeile, gesagt werden „der ersten Auflage“ und soll diese, was nur im
        ersten Brief gesagt ist, in Ziffern angegeben werden: 1000 Exemplare. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich empfehle im Titel <tei:title>Phantasien</tei:title> mit ph zu
        schreiben, weil das Wort neben den <tei:title>Theorien</tei:title> so besser aussieht. Trotz
          Duden.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:title level="m"
            >Duden</tei:title>: publisher of dictionaries and books on German style, spelling,
          orthography, and the like. Words like “Phantasie,” “Telephon,” and “Photographie” were,
          increasingly, being spelled with “f” rather than “ph.”</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">In der zweiten Augusthälfte werde ich in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002578">Salzburg</tei:rs> sein. Ja, ich fahre sogar Sonntag–Montag schon mit
        einem Autobus der Kasinogesellschaft eingeladen hin, zur Eröffnung des
          Spielkasinos,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">The gaming casino
          in Salzburg was established in 1934 and originally located in the Mirabell Palace; it was
          relocated to the Mönchsberg to accommodate a larger clientele.</tei:note> das mich
        eigentlich nichts angeht. Aber wer könnte <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002578"
          >Salzburg</tei:rs> je widerstehen, selbst unter Böller-Huldigungen! Ob ich dann im August
        Sie – wie gerne! – besuchen werden können, hängt von meinem finanziellen Umständen ab. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000420">Kalmus</tei:rs> denkt bei seiner
        Frage übrigens nicht an eine Angabe. Er muss sich nur decken, weil seine Lieferanten nicht
        unbegrenzt warten. Die Zahlungen sind nach Rechnungslegung fällig und werden also jedenfalls
        in Teilen zu erfolgen haben, nach dem Einlauf, und in der Reihe der Arbeiten. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008405">Arch. Schmid</tei:rs> habe ich
        seit seiner Rückkehr noch nicht gesprochen. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380"
          >Hoboken</tei:rs> kommt also so bald nicht nach Wien, erst im Herbst wohl. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich lese natürlich gerne wieder Ihre Korrektur mit, obzwar sich meine
        Hilfe leider nur auf ganz Aeusserliches beziehen kann.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Deutsch had already read the proofs for the second and third
            <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001749"><tei:title level="m"
            >Meisterwerk</tei:title></tei:rs> yearbooks in 1927 and 1930, and advised on the layout
          of the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001755"><tei:title level="m">Fünf
              Urlinien-Tafeln</tei:title></tei:rs> (1932). He was aware that Schenker’s present
          project, <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title level="m">Der freie
              Satz</tei:title></tei:rs>, would be demanding from a musically technical point of
          view.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Meinen <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002591"
        >Akademie</tei:rs>kurs mach ich erst im September genauer mit <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003736">Kobald</tei:rs> ab. Wollen Sie ihn <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs> avisieren?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker wrote to Hoboken on July 12, 1934, <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-89-7_10">OJ 89/7, [10]</tei:ref>, including a very long
          paragraph about Deutsch’s course, the history of its instigation, and his own reaction (“…
          what I was denied, he acquires immediately. Is not that laughable?”).</tei:note> Oder
        lassen wir das bis im Herbst? Und darf ich Sie als Anreger nennen bei <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs>? So war es doch, nicht? </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Meine <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000163">Frau</tei:rs> geht mit
        Gitta nach Hainfeld, Peter zunächst mit Pfadfindern nach <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002334">Tirol</tei:rs>. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Leben Sie wohl in Ihrer schönen Gegend! Und empfehlen Sie mich schönstens
        Ihrer lieben <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Frau</tei:rs>! </tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>2:2!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Aber 3 Blgn.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10" type="editorial"
            place="foot">The two letters from Universal Edition to Schenker, and a draft contract
            for <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title level="m">Der freie
                Satz</tei:title></tei:rs>.</tei:note></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Herzlichst ergeben Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-90"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/><tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000164">O E Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>PROF. OTTO ERICH DEUTSCH</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Tel. R 45–6–72</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">VIENNA II</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-80">Böcklinstraße 26</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#TPoed"/><tei:date when="1934-06-29">June
            29, 1934</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">friend</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Today, finally, I am able to reply to your two letters,<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> and only because the second seems so urgent. I
        have been very busy since returning home, and recently had difficulties with <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs> which cost me a long letter. You shall
        read everything, if you wish; for today I shall only say that he wanted to reproach me for
        earlier purchases of pieces which we are now able to replace with better copies. Some of
        these purchases were made without my involvement, and with an inferior understanding of the
        matter; moreover, they were so cheap that both copies of these five random examples hardly
        cost their true value, even before the extra copy of each is sold. I shall soon send you the
        thoroughly delightful correspondence, which seems already to have been concluded peacefully
        and is probably now finished. That you might like to tell him something better about me is
        something I no longer dare to ask.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">After spending a week in hospital, my <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000163">wife</tei:rs> is back here. It was a poisoning of unknown origin, with
        colic and then obstruction of the bowels, fortunately without the need for an intrusive
        operation.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-003103">Saturn</tei:rs> has
        informed me about <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000412">Jonas</tei:rs>’s book.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Now for the urgent matters. The two letters from <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000412">Universal Edition</tei:rs> and the draft contract<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> seem to be good except for the points I have
        noted:</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:supplied reason="clarity">Letter of</tei:supplied> June 13: That the
        (hard) cover should be made only if required, and in accordance with the parts – or, better,
          serially<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> – is self-explanatory; but
        because the money of a third party is involved, it should be stated specifically.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:supplied reason="clarity">Letter of</tei:supplied> June 22: I think
        that <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs> will agree to pay for each
        of the invoices within a month of their receipt, for which the path to him ought already to
        have been prepared.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">But if <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000412">Universal
          Edition</tei:rs>, like its suppliers, expect the money so promptly, then they should also
        attempt to repay him more frequently than once every year. Thus instead of a single
          <tei:supplied reason="clarity">yearly</tei:supplied> account, one every half-year if
        possible, or better quarterly. But I would not make a contentious point of this.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> Finally, to the draft contract which, in addition to the
        three points that should be incorporated, should also include the following: In the second
        paragraph, first line, “the first printing” must be written; and this should be given in
        numbers, as indicated only in the first of the letters: 1,000 copies. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">For the title, I recommend that you spell <tei:title level="m"
          >Phantasien</tei:title> with “ph,” because that word will look better next to <tei:title
          level="m">Theorien</tei:title>. In spite of Duden.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06"
          type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I shall be in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002578">Salzburg</tei:rs>
        in the second half of August. I am actually going there, by invitation, in a bus belonging
        to the Casino Society, for the opening of the gaming casino.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07"
          type="footnote"/> That does not actually interest me much; but who could ever resist
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002578">Salzburg</tei:rs>, even under volleys of
        cannon-fire! Whether I could then visit you in August – how I would like to do so! – depends
        on my financial circumstances. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">By the way <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000420">Kalmus</tei:rs>, in
        the question he poses, is not thinking of a down payment. He must only cover his costs,
        because his suppliers cannot wait forever. The payments are due after the invoices have been
        issued and will in any event have to be made in installments, as the invoices arrive and in
        the order in which the work is carried out.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"> I have not spoken with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008405"
          >architect Schmid</tei:rs> since his return. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380"
          >Hoboken</tei:rs> will not be returning to Vienna very soon, probably not until the
        autumn.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I shall naturally be happy to read the proofs with you again, even if my
        help can, unfortunately, be applied only in an entirely superficial way.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I shall not make the specific arrangements with <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003736">Kobald</tei:rs> for my course at the <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002591">Academy</tei:rs> until September. Would you like to notify <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs> about it?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09"
          type="footnote"/> Or shall we leave that until the autumn. And may I name you to <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs> as the stimulus? That is surely how
        things were?</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">My <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000163">wife</tei:rs> is going with
        Gitta to Hainfeld, Peter at first to the <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002334"
          >Tyrol</tei:rs> with the Pathfinders.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Enjoy life in your beautiful region! And give my best wishes to your dear
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">wife</tei:rs>!</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Best wishes from the two of us to the two of you. </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">But with three enclosures.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn10"
            type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Your most cordially devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-90"><tei:handShift new="#OED"/><tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000164">O. E. Deutsch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
