<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2154" sdoID="OJ-15-16_90">OJ 15/16, [90]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HW" scope="sole">Hans Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2008</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2018</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-10-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Hans Weisse to Schenker, dated March 17, 1933</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1933-03-17T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2018-10-29</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Weisse reports the success of his lecture on the C minor prelude from the
        Well-Tempered Clavier, Book 1. — He is currently giving two lectures on a Haydn's sonata. —
        He inquires about the possibility of having Schenker's foreground graphs for the "Eroica"
        Symphony printed separately and sold to his pupils, for a series of lectures planned for the
        following year; the profits entirely to Schenker. — He sees little prospect visiting Europe
        in the summer, as his financial situation has worsened: the Mannes School has been forced to
        reduce his teaching for the next season. — He expresses his doubts about Vrieslander's
        ability to reshape Schenker's Harmonielehre as a school textbook, and about the value of
        Harmonielehre itself in the light of his teacher's most advanced theoretical
        ideas.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Erfolg; success; Vortrag; lecture; Werk; work; Vortragszyklus; lecture cycle;
        Anfrage; request; Vorlage; plate; Preis; price; cost; Reinertrag; net proceeds; Seminar;
        Kritik; criticism; Schüler; pupil; Grammophon; gramophone; Apparat; equipment; Virtuose;
        performer; Kontrakt; contract; Vertrag; contract; Privatkreise; private domain; Kosten;
        costs; Herstellung; production; Tafel; graph; Neubearbeitung; revision; Schulgebrauch; use
        in schools; Lehre; theory</dc:subject>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:lb/><tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#HW"/><tei:date
            when="1933-03-17">17. März 1933</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber verehter <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"
            >Meister</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/6, pp. 3822‒3823, March 27, 1933:
            "Weisse (Br.): berichtet über den großen Erfolg, bittet um eine Neuauflage der
            Eroica-Bilder, auch der Tonwille-Bilder; erwägt private Kurse, da Mannes um $1000
            reduziert hat." ("Weisse (letter): reports about his great success, requests a new
            printing of the voice-leading graphs for the "Eroica" as well as the graphs in <tei:rs
              type="work" key="entity-001739"><tei:title level="j">Der
            Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>. Is thinking of giving private courses, as Mannes has
            reduced <tei:supplied reason="clarity">his fee</tei:supplied> by
          $1,000").</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>mit grösster Genugtuung möchte ich Sie wenigstens wieder mit ein paar Worten von dem
        unerhörten Erfolg meiner Vorträge, die ja nur Ihrem Werk gelten, un somit von dem ungeheurn
        Erfolg <tei:hi rend="underline">Ihres</tei:hi> Werkes<tei:supplied reason="punctuation"
          >,</tei:supplied> hier unterrichten. Die Leute kommen, selbst bei schlechtestem Wetter,
        (was für <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002510"
          ><tei:country>Amerika</tei:country></tei:rs> sehr viel ist) bringen neue Leute und ich bin
        durchdrungen, dass im nächsten Jahre noch viel mehr Leute kommen werden falls ich die
        Vorträge fortsetze. <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">Mir schwebt</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">Ich plane</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> einen Vortragszyklus von 10 oder 12 Vorträgen für nächstes Jahr: am liebsten
        wäre mir die „<tei:title>Eroica im Lichte Schenker’scher Betrachtung</tei:title>.“ Ich bitte
        Sie nun meine Anfrage so schnell und genau als möglich zu beantworten. Wir brauchen dazu die
          <tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:term>Skizze</tei:term>n</tei:hi>.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Here and elsewhere, Weisse uses the term
          “sketches" to mean voice-leading graphs.</tei:note> Wäre es nun denkbar, die
          <tei:term>Skizze</tei:term>n Ihres <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001752">Buch</tei:rs>es
        150 Stück etwa separat neu drücken zu lassen für diesen speziellen Zweck? Und was wäre der
        Preis? Meines Erachtens müsste das sehr billig herzustellen sein, wenn die Vorlagen noch
        existieren. Wir könnten dann hier das Exemplar mit 25ct<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot">This possibly reads "75 ct": the difference between
          twenty-five cents and one dollar in 1933 would seem too great for the two to be considered
          as suggested prices for the same item.</tei:note> oder 1$ pro Stück verkaufen. Ich würde
        Ihnen vorschlagen, dass wir das in ei- <tei:pb n="2"/> gener Regie machen, damit der
        Reinertrag (so wenig es auch ist) Ihnen sofort <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ganz
          allein</tei:add> zufalle. Konnten Sie nicht überhaupt in Erwägung ziehen, ob das mit
        andern <tei:term>Skizze</tei:term>n aus <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001739"
            ><tei:title>dem Tonwillen</tei:title></tei:rs> und <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001749"><tei:title>den Meisterwerken</tei:title></tei:rs> möglich
        wäre?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>(In meinem Seminar für Kritik an der <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-005886"
          >Universität</tei:rs> haben unlängst meine 14 Schüler nach Erfassung der <tei:rs
          type="composition" key="entity-001037"><tei:title>C moll Fuge</tei:title></tei:rs> an Hand
        Ihrer <tei:term>Skizze</tei:term><tei:supplied reason="punctuation"
          >,</tei:supplied><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">The <tei:hi
            rend="italic">Urlinie-Tafel</tei:hi> (foreground graph) of the <tei:title>C minor
            fugue</tei:title> in <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000027">Bach</tei:rs>'s <tei:rs
            type="composition" key="entity-002952"><tei:title level="m">Well-Tempered
              Clavier</tei:title></tei:rs>, Book 1, Schenker’s analysis of which forms the major
          part of the essay <tei:title level="a">Das Organische der Fuge,</tei:title> published in
            <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001751"><tei:title level="j">Meisterwerk
            2</tei:title></tei:rs>.</tei:note> die ich in <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overwritten">4</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="superimposed">6</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> Stunden verarbeitete, Kritik geübt an der Spielweise <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-004943">Harold <tei:sic>Samuels</tei:sic></tei:rs>, der hier als der „beste
        Bachspieler“ gilt. Ich benützte das Grammophon. Der Erfolg war: <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >vernichtend</tei:hi>! Ich komme mir wie ein richtiger Aufwiegler vor und das Grammophon
        ist ein herrlicher Behelf; wenn die Leute <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ein
          Stück</tei:add> hören gelernt haben in Ihrer Weise<tei:supplied reason="punctuation"
          >,</tei:supplied> und das geht nicht einmal gar so schwer<tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> und man spielt es ihnen nachher auf dem Apparat vor:
        so ist der Erfolg meist: ein Lacherfolg! Ich habe also auch die Absicht<tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> die Virtuosen auf diese Weise praktisch unmöglich zu
        machen. Das wird sich herumsprechen und zum Schluss werden sie (die Virtuosen) auch zu
        diesen Vorträgen kommen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ob ich die Vorträge nicht privat veranstalten soll, ist gegenwärtig noch eine ungelöste
        Frage. Denn <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006044">die Mannes</tei:rs> haben unter dem
        Zwange der Verhältnisse mir einen schlechtern Kontrakt für nächstes Jahr angeboten. Gleich
        um 1000 $ weniger. Nun <tei:pb n="3"/> verstehe ich ihre Lage und akzeptiere den Vertrag,
        mir bleibt in dieser Zeit auch gar nichts <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >anderes</tei:add> übrig<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> doch bin ich
        nicht gewöllt<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> 12 Vorträge mit einem
        Betrag von 200 $ abfertigen zu lassen. Man kann hier leicht Vorträge im Privatkreise
        veranstalten und so was schwebt mir vor.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Das Wichtigste worum ich Sie bitte ist also: genaue Feststellung ob und zu welchem
        Preise 150 Stück Eroica <tei:term>Skizze</tei:term>n herzustellen wären. Die Frage anderer
        Skizzen bitte ich Sie auch in Erwägung zu ziehen und mir etwaige Beträge zu nennen. Die
        materielle Seite stelle ich mir so vor, dass wir gemeinsam die Kosten der Herstellung
        bestreiten, falls sie nicht hoch sind, so dass der Reinertrag Ihnen allein und sofort nach
        Verkauf der <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">word deleted</tei:note>
        <tei:term>Skizze</tei:term>n zufällt.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich habe im vergangenen Vortrage die <tei:term>Skizze</tei:term> der
          <tei:term>Exposition</tei:term> zur <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000344"
          >Haydn</tei:rs> Sonate (G. A. 49.) an drei Tafeln in verschiedenen Farben aufgeschrieben
        gehabt und mache nächsten Montag (es ist schon der 7. Vortrag) die
          <tei:term>Durchführung</tei:term> an Hand Ihrer <tei:term>Skizze</tei:term>.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">The development section of Haydn's
          Sonata in E<tei:g type="flat"/>, Hob. XVI:49, first movement, appears in the <tei:rs
            type="work" key="entity-001755"><tei:title level="m">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln/Five Analyses
              in Sketch-Form</tei:title></tei:rs> of 1932. The graph of the exposition was evidently
          Weisse's own.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Die allgemeine Situation ist hier sehr kritisch. Doch scheints sich nun dem Bessern
        zuzuwenden. Allein was kann <tei:pb n="4"/>
        <tei:supplied reason="omission">man</tei:supplied> in diesen Zeiten voraussagen? Ich
        überlege mir ob es unter den gegebenen Verhältnissen Sinn hat<tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> überhaupt im Sommer nach <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-003147"><tei:region>Europa</tei:region></tei:rs> zu kommen, wie ich eigentlich
          beabsichtigte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">In her letter to
          Schenker of February 15, 1933 (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-15-16_88">OJ 15/16,
            [88]</tei:ref>), Hertha Weisse had stated that their two children would return to Europe
          later in the year.</tei:note> —</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In Ihrer <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724"
          ><tei:title>Harmonielehre</tei:title></tei:rs> scheint mir sovieles einer Neubearbeitung
        notwendig, dass ich mich frage, wie <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922"
          >Vriesl.</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">Weisse's
          letters of spring 1933 are particularly critical of Vrieslander, both as composer and as
          exponent of Schenker's teaching. For further information on Vrieslander's involvement in a
          putative revision of <tei:title level="m">Harmonielehre</tei:title>, see
              <tei:bibl><tei:author>Robert Wason</tei:author>, <tei:title level="a">From
              'Harmonielehre' to 'Harmony': Schenker's Theory of Harmony and Its
              Americanization,</tei:title> in <tei:title level="m">Essays from the Fourth
              International Schenker Symposium</tei:title>, vol. I, ed. <tei:editor>Allen
              Cadwallader</tei:editor> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms Verlag, 2008), pp.
          213‒58</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> das machen kann. Die <tei:term>Stufe</tei:term> gehört doch
        vor allem dem <tei:term>Mittel</tei:term>- und <tei:term>Hintergrund</tei:term> an. Die
          <tei:term>Stufe</tei:term>n des <tei:term>Vordergrund</tei:term>es (Sie selbst bezeichnen <tei:choice>
          <tei:sic>Sie</tei:sic>
          <tei:corr>sie</tei:corr>
        </tei:choice> doch übrigens meist in Klammern) sind nur <tei:term>Scheinstufe</tei:term>n.
        Ihre <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724"><tei:title>Harmonielehre</tei:title></tei:rs>
        nimmt doch noch gar keine Unterscheidung in diesem Sinne vor. Fast möchte ich
          sagen<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> Ihre <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001724"><tei:title>Harmonielehre</tei:title></tei:rs> – ist nicht mehr die
        Ihre. Und grade jetzt beginnt man grade diese zum Schulgebrauch heranzuziehn! Es ist
        eigentlich tragisch. Nur der Wissende vermag mit besonderer Rührung die Stellen in der
          <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724"><tei:title>Harmonielehre</tei:title></tei:rs> zu
        erkennen, in der sich die Keime Ihrer ganzen Lehre regen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wir alle grüssen Sie aufs Herzlichste und hoffen Sie beide sehr wohl.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person"><tei:hi
              rend="lateinschr">H</tei:hi></tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:lb/><tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#HW"/><tei:date
            when="1933-03-17">March 17, 1933</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear, revered <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>With the greatest pleasure, I should like at least to inform you again here, in a few
        words, of the unbelievable success of my lectures, which are concerned only with your work,
        and thus with the immense success of <tei:hi rend="underline">your</tei:hi> work. The people
        come, even in the worst weather ‒ and that, for <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002510"
            ><tei:country>America</tei:country></tei:rs>, is saying a lot. They bring new people
        with them, and I am convinced that even more will come next year if I continue the lecture
        series. I am<tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">contemplating</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">planning</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> a cycle of ten or twelve lectures for next year, my preferred topic being
          <tei:title level="a">The 'Eroica' Symphony in light of Schenkerian Theory.</tei:title> And
        so I shall ask you to answer the following question of mine as quickly and precisely as
        possible. We need the <tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:term>sketch</tei:term>es</tei:hi> for
          this.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> Is it possible to have 150 copies of
        the <tei:term>sketch</tei:term>es from your <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001752"
          >book</tei:rs> printed separately, for this specific purpose? And what should the price
        be? My feeling is that it should be very cheap to reproduce them, so long as the original
        plates still exist. We could sell them here for 25¢<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
          type="footnote"/> or $1 apiece. I would advise you that we do this on our own, <tei:pb
          n="2"/> so that the net proceeds, however small they may be, immediately fall <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">solely</tei:add> to you. Could you not in fact contemplate the
        possibility of doing this with other <tei:term>sketch</tei:term>es from <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001739"><tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs> and <tei:rs
          type="work" key="entity-001749"><tei:title level="j">The Masterwork in
          Music</tei:title></tei:rs>?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In my seminar on criticism at the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-005886"
          >University</tei:rs>, my fourteen pupils, with whom I spent <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overwritten">four</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="superimposed">six</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> hours working through the <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001037"
            ><tei:title level="m">C minor fugue</tei:title></tei:rs> with reference to your
          <tei:term>sketch</tei:term>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> recently
        practiced their criticism with reference to the way in which the work is played by <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-004943">Harold Samuel</tei:rs>, who is regarded here as the
        "best performer of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000027">Bach</tei:rs>." I used a
        gramophone, and the result was: <tei:hi rend="underline">devastating</tei:hi>! I play the
        role of a true agitator, and the record player is a wonderful aid: after people have learned
        to hear <tei:add place="interlinear-above">a piece</tei:add> as you understand it ‒ and that
        is no longer so very difficult ‒ and afterwards one plays it on the equipment, the result is
        usually: a success that makes everyone laugh! It is even my intention, therefore, to use
        this technique to make the celebrated piano virtuosos almost impossible <tei:supplied
          reason="clarity">to take seriously</tei:supplied>. Word will get around, and in the end
        they too (the celebrated piano virtuosos) will also come to these lectures.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Whether I shall have to arrange these lectures privately is, at present, an unresolved
        question. For <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004633">Mr.</tei:rs> and <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-004634">Mrs. Mannes</tei:rs>, under the pressure of the
        financial situation, have offered me a poorer contract for next season, exactly $1000 less.
        Now, <tei:pb n="3"/> I do understand their situation and will accept their contract ‒ I have
        no other <tei:add place="interlinear-above">choice</tei:add> in these times ‒ but I am not
        inclined to prepare twelve lectures for a fee of $200. Here, it is easy to arrange lectures
        for a private circle, and I am contemplating this as a possibility.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>The most important thing I am asking about is thus: to determine precisely whether, and
        at what price, 150 examples of the "Eroica" <tei:term>sketch</tei:term>es could be produced.
        With regard to other sketches, I ask you take these also into account and to name the
        possible sums of money involved. On the material side of things, I imagine that we could
        work out the costs of reproduction together, so long as they are not great, so that the net
        gain would come solely to you, and immediately after the <tei:term>sketch</tei:term>es had
        been sold.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In my last lecture, I wrote out the <tei:term>sketch</tei:term> of the
          <tei:term>exposition</tei:term> of the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000344"
          >Haydn</tei:rs> sonata (Hob. XVI:49) on three large sheets, in different colors, and next
        Monday (that is already the seventh lecture) I will do the <tei:term>development
          section</tei:term> with reference to your <tei:term>sketch</tei:term>.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>The general situation here is very critical. Yet things appear to be turning towards
        the better. What can one, after all, <tei:pb n="4"/> foretell in these times? I am wondering
        whether, given the present conditions, there is any point at all in coming to <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-003147"><tei:region>Europe</tei:region></tei:rs>, as I had
        actually intended.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>In your <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724"><tei:title level="m">Theory of
            Harmony</tei:title></tei:rs>, so much seems to me to require a thorough revision that I
        ask myself: how can <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs><tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> undertake this? The concept of
          <tei:term>scale-step</tei:term> belongs above all to the <tei:term>middleground</tei:term>
        and <tei:term>background</tei:term>. The <tei:term>scale-step</tei:term>s in the
          <tei:term>foreground</tei:term> (in fact, you yourself usually indicate these, in
        parentheses) are only <tei:term>illusory scale-step</tei:term>s. Your <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001724"><tei:title level="m">Theory of Harmony</tei:title></tei:rs>, however,
        makes no distinction whatever in this regard. I would almost say that your <tei:rs
          type="work" key="entity-001724"><tei:title level="m">Theory of
          Harmony</tei:title></tei:rs> is no longer yours. And precisely now, to invoke this very
        book for use in schools! It's a real tragedy. Only those in the know will be able to
        recognize, with a special emotion, the passages in the <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001724"><tei:title level="m">Theory of Harmony</tei:title></tei:rs> in which
        the seeds of your entire theory took root.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>All of us send you our most cordial greetings, and hope that you are both well.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person"
          >H</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
