<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3401" sdoID="OJ-14-4_2">OJ 14/4, [2]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HG" scope="sole">Hans Guttmann's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2011-09-23" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008420">GuttmannH ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Hans Guttmann to Heinrich Schenker, dated May 14,
        1922</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1922-05-14T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-03-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Hans Guttmann expresses concern at Heinrich's recent unwellness, admires his
        adherence to a strict diet, and speaks of his own better health since coming off a diet;
        offers to send provisions to Heinrich and Jeanette; inquires as to the progress of
        Heinrich's work; is reading Heinrich's Harmonielehre with some difficulty; and asks Heinrich
        to perform a financial transaction for him.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000316">HGuttmann</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">written in Sütterlinschrift</tei:note><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#HG"/>S. Gj.<tei:supplied
            reason="abbreviation">urgjerovai</tei:supplied> am <tei:date when="1922-05-14">14/V.
            1922</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Liebste <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Onkel</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
            this letter is recorded in Heinrich’s diary for May 18, 1922: “Von Hans Guttmann (Br.):
            Rückzahlung durch Goldschmidt erbeten.” (“From Hans Guttmann (letter): repayment via
            Goldschmidt requested.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Unverhältnismäßig lange ließ ich nichts von mir hören,<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The last message from Hans is recorded
          in Heinrich’s diary for January 30: “Von Hans Guttmann schickt 150000 Kronen.” (“From Hans
          Guttmann: sends 150,000 Kronen.”), followed by two greetings postcards recorded February
          23 and April 7.</tei:note> aber ich bitte<tei:del rend="overstrike">n</tei:del> wegen
        meiner Faulheit vielmals um Verzeihung! Die allzu reichliche Beschäftigung in der Kanzlei
        nimmt einen derart in Anspruch, daß man in einem Arbeitstage nicht einmal einen Brief
        zusammenbringen kann. — </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">L. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Onkel</tei:rs>, aus Ihrem
          Briefe<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">The last letter from
          Heinrich to Hans is recorded in Schenker’s diary for March 12, 1922: “An Hans Guttmann
          (Br.): habe die Bestätigung erhalten.” (“To Hans Guttmann (letter): have received the
          confirmation.”), preceded by that recorded on February 15: “An Hans Guttmann (Br.): Dank
          u. Begründung der Ablehnung; die Geschichte mit Mozio.” (“To Hans Guttmann (letter):
          thanks and reasoning for rejection; the story with Mozio.”).</tei:note> und dem der l.
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000319">Mama</tei:rs> entnahm ich, daß Sie in der
        letzten Zeit leidend sind. Die Sache ging mir derart nahe, daß ich dies gar nicht zu Papier
        bringen kann; ich hielt mir nämlich vor Augen, daß man in einem Wien von heute nur sehr
        schwer <tei:pb n="2"/> Diät halten kann. Wenn ich der lieben <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000771">Tante</tei:rs> irgendwie Ihre Lage diesbezüglich erleichtern könnte,
        da bin ich dazu selbstverständlich sehr gerne bereit. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Schicken laßen sich von hier Eier, Fett u. Kohl und solltet Ihr
        irgendetwas davon benötigen, dann bitte mir nur zu schreiben und ich werde das sodann sofort
        absenden lassen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Parcels of food,
          fuel, and other necessities were frequently sent to Heinrich and Jeanette by Hans and by
          his <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000319">mother</tei:rs> during the war, and have
          continued since then because of shortages in Vienna.</tei:note> Soviel ich informiert bin,
        sind die Lebensmittel hier bedeutend billiger (nach Umrechnung) als bei Euch und Ihr könntet
        Euch doch einen kleinen Reservevorrat anlegen. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Mir geht es, l. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Onkel</tei:rs>,
        jetzt viel besser, da ich nach Jahren mich endlich einmal <tei:pb n="3"/> sattessen kann.
        Ich war einfach unterernährt und erhole mich zusehends seit der Zeit, wo ich nicht mehr in
        der Beamtenmenage esse. — </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Was machen Ihre Arbeiten, l. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
          >Onkel</tei:rs>? Ist das <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001741">2.te Heft des
            „<tei:title>Tonwillen</tei:title>“</tei:rs> schon erschienen? Ich habe mir den<tei:rs
          type="work" key="entity-001724"> ersten Band Ihres „<tei:title>Muskalischen Theorien u.
            Phantasien</tei:title>“</tei:rs> jetzt aus Wien kommen lassen und bin mit Eifer bei der
        Sache. Anfangs bereitet mir dies noch ziemliche Schwierigkeiten, aber ich hoffe, daß ich
        diese überwinden werde können. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Im Klavierspiele habe ich l<tei:supplied reason="abbreviation"
          >au</tei:supplied>t Aussagen meines Lehrer‘s auch schöne Vorschritte gemacht, obzwar ich
        über <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000344">Haydn</tei:rs> nicht <tei:pb n="4"/>
        hinausgekommen bin. — </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Jetzt, l. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Onkel</tei:rs>, hätte
        ich eine Bitte zu Ihnen! Möchten Sie so lieb sein, u. das Geld, das ich beim <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000774">O. Mozio</tei:rs> erliegen habe, bei <tei:hi
          rend="underline">Herman Goldschmidt, Wien I., Wollzeile 11</tei:hi> zu Gunsten der
        Bibliothek u. <tei:supplied reason="syntax">des</tei:supplied> Lesevereines, S. <tei:hi
          rend="lateinschr">Gjurgjerovai</tei:hi> einzahlen <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >zu</tei:add> lassen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">This
          concerns the 150,000 Kronen from Hans picked up in Vienna (cf. footnote 2 above) and taken
          to Moriz Schenker on February 7, 1922 (cf. the long diary entry for that date). Heinrich’s
          diary for May 24 records: “Bei Goldschmidt 150000 Kronen für Hans Guttmann erlegt.” (“At
          Goldschmidt's, 150,000 Kronen paid for Hans Guttmann.”), and May 26: “An Mozio: kündige
          die Behebung von Hans Guttmann Geld an.” (“To Mozio: notify [him] about withdrawal of Hans
          Guttmann money.”).</tei:note> Ich würde mir den Gegenwert in jugoslav. Währung hier
        auszahlen lassen, da ich an eine Heimreise ernstlich denke und für einen gewissen Zweck
        einen größeren Betrag benötigen. — Stehen Sie mit dem <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000774">O. Mozio</tei:rs> in irgendwelcher Verbindung? </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Jetzt muß ich schließen, da die Pflicht oder – besser gesagt das Büro
        ruft. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Ich grüße u. küsse Sie, sowie </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">die l. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Tante</tei:rs>
          recht herzlich</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Euer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000316"
          >Hans</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in left margin sideways:</tei:note>Ich
          wünsche Ihnen noch, l. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Onkel</tei:rs>, eine
          recht baldige Besserung!</tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>



    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">written in Sütterlinschrift</tei:note><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#HG"/>S. Gjurgjerovai, <tei:date
            when="1922-05-14">May 14, 1922</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Dearest <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Uncle</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">It has been inordinately long since you heard from me,<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> but I earnestly beg forgiveness for my laziness!
        The demands that the unceasing transactions in the Chancellery make on one are such that one
        can never scrape so much as a single letter together in the course of a working day.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Uncle</tei:rs>, from your
          letter<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> and that of my dear <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000319">Mama</tei:rs> I gathered that you have not been well in
        recent days. The matter affected me such that I am completely unable to put it into words;
        that is, I kept wondering how someone in the Vienna of today can adhere to a <tei:pb n="2"/>
        diet only with great difficulty. If, for the sake of my dear <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000771">Aunt</tei:rs>, I could in any way alleviate your situation in this
        regard, I am ready and willing to do so.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Eggs, fat and cabbage can be sent from here, and should you need anything
        of that sort then please just write to me and I will have it sent off immediately.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> As far as I am informed, provisions are
        significantly cheaper here (after conversion) than with you, and you could easily lay in a
        small reserve store for yourselves.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Things are going much better for me, dear <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000632">Uncle</tei:rs>, now that after many years I can finally <tei:pb n="3"
        /> eat until I am no longer hungry. I was simply undernourished, and have been recovering
        markedly ever since I stopped taking my <tei:supplied reason="clarity">midday</tei:supplied>
        meal with my fellow workers..</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">How are your publications going, dear <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000632">Uncle</tei:rs>? Has the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001741">second
          issue of your <tei:title level="j">Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs> yet appeared? I have now
        obtained from Vienna the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724">first volume of your
            <tei:title level="m">Musical Theories and Fantasies</tei:title></tei:rs> and am at work
        on it zealously. To start with, this is still presenting me with considerable difficulties,
        but I hope to be able to overcome these.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">On the piano playing front, I have, according to my teacher’s
        pronouncements, already made good progress, although I have yet to <tei:pb n="4"/> get
        beyond <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000344">Haydn</tei:rs>. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Now, dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Uncle</tei:rs>, I had
        a request to put to you! Might you be so kind as to have the money that I deposited with
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774">Uncle Mozio</tei:rs> paid into <tei:hi
          rend="underline">Herman Goldschmidt, Vienna I, Wollzeile 11</tei:hi> to the benefit of the
        Library and Literary Society of St Gjurjerovai?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05"
          type="footnote"/> I would pay myself the equivalent value here in Yugoslavian currency,
        since I am seriously contemplating a trip home and need a larger sum of money for a certain
        purpose. — Are you at all in communication with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774"
          >Uncle Mozio</tei:rs>?</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I must now close since duty – or better put, the office – calls.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">With greetings and kisses to you, as well as</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">to my dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
            >Aunt</tei:rs>, most cordially your</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000316"
          >Hans</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in left margin sideways:</tei:note>I wish
          you, dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Uncle</tei:rs>, a speedy
          recovery!</tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>
    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
