<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="125" sdoID="OJ-10-1_48">OJ 10/1, [48]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="WDa" scope="sole">Walter Dahms's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="JK">
   <tei:persName>John Koslovsky</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2009</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2009</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2010</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002725">Dahms ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   
   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Dahms to Schenker, dated December 21, 1919</dc:title>
   
   <dcterms:created>1919-12-21T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2010-06-12</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Dahms thanks Schenker for his advice on the next stage of instruction. He wrote
    to Halm, who confirmed what Schenker had said. He congratulates Schenker on the superhuman work
    that he is doing under current adverse circumstances. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Unterricht; study; Unterweisung; instruction; Übersiedelung; move; Anstrengung;
    effort; Verhältnissen; conditions; circumstances; Moralverseuchung; contamination of morals;
    technische Errungenschaften; technical achievements; Kulturfortschritte; cultural progress;
    Kultur; culture; Komfort; comfort; Heroismus; heroism</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000149">Dahms</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address rend="indent-60">
     <tei:addrLine>Wasserburg a/ Inn 340</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:date when="1919-12-21" rend="indent-70">den 21. XII. 19</tei:date>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Lieber verehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>! </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Herzlichsten<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/1, p. 2197, December 27, 1919:
     " Von Dahms (Br.): dankt für meinen Rat, dessen Richtigkeit er schon dadurch bestätigt findet,
     daß Halm die Leitung des Unterrichtes aufzunehmen sich nicht getraut; werde nun allein den Weg
     suchen." ("From Dahms (letter): thanks [me] for my advice, the rightness of which he had
     already found to be confirmed in that Halm does not feel able to take over direction of the
     instruction; will seek the way on his own."). Prior to this, on December 21, 1919, a letter is
     recorded at OJ 3/1, p. 2195: "An Dahms (Br.): ob ich das Geld senden soll." (To Dahms (letter):
     whether I should send the money.").<!-- XR --></tei:note> Dank für Ihren ausführlichen gütigen
     Brief,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">This letter is not known to
     survive, but its writing is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/1, pp. 2192-2193, December 15,
     1919: "An Dahms (Br.): empfehle eher Koch als Halm u. gebe Begründung dafür; erneuere den Rat
     von Tantalier, bis zur Einführung ein beliebiges älteres Werk (z.B. Richter - nur nicht
     Riemann) sich anzusehen, sodann Marpurg zu lesen, gleichzeitig aber selbst im „Wohltemperierten
     Klavier“ Studien zu betreiben: hier, bei den Genies, findet sich zwar auch die
     Durchschnittspraxis, aber darüber hinaus auch noch unnachahmliche Freiheiten, die
     Durchschnittskönner nicht einmal noch gesehen haben! Führe als Beispiele die Exposition in der
     Cisdur-Fuge von Bach, Bdur-Fuge von Brahms, in denen die Einsätze der Exposition ohne
     Zwischenspiel abrollen - die „Geisteszukunft“ dieser Genies erlaubt es ihnen, vom Rezept der
     Duchschnittskönner abzugehen u. auf die Fähigkeit zu vertrauen, daß sie ein wenig später das
     Versäumte durch ein längeres u. interessanteres Zwischenspiel werden nachholen können." ("To
     Dahms (letter): I recommend Koch rather than Halm and give reasons for doing so. I reiterate my
     advice at Tantalier of examining a favorite old work (e.g. Richter - just so long as it is not
     Riemann) by way of introduction, and then to read Marpurg, but simultaneously to pursue studies
     on your own in the <tei:title level="m">Well-tempered Clavier</tei:title>; here, in the company
     of the geniuses, conventional practice itself is nevertheless to be found, and yet out of this
     also inimitable freedoms the likes of which conventional practitioners have never so much as
     seen! I advocate as examples the exposition of the Bach C#-major Fugue, the Brahms B-flat-major
     Fugue, in both of which the entries of the exposition follow on the heels of each other without
     episodes. The "spiritual future" of these geniuses allows them to leave the conventional
     practioners' prescription way behind and to trust in their innate ability such that they can
     make up a little later for what was neglected by way of a longer and more interesting
     episode."). <!-- XR --></tei:note> der mich über vieles beruhigt hat. Sie haben meine Frage so
    offen beantwortet, wie ich es mir nur wünschen konnte. Ich werde Ihrem Rat folgen und mit allen
    Kräften selbst arbeiten und suchen. Übrigens hat mir, und dies ist bezeichnend, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000326">Halm</tei:rs> selbst etwa dasselbe geraten, was Sie mir geraten
    haben. Ich habe ihm nämlich geschrieben und ihn gefragt, ob er überhaupt bereit wäre, eine
    Unterweisung, wie ich sie suche, zu erteilen. Und darauf antwortete er mir sehr offen und
    freundlich, er könne es nicht wagen, sich als Lehrer dieser Art zu empfehlen. Das einzige wozu
    er sich bereit erklären könne, wäre ein gemeinsames Durchsprechen meiner eventl.
    Kompositionsversuche. Damit ist diese Angelegenheit ja <tei:pb n="2"/> für sich schon durchaus
    in Ihrem Sinne erledigt. Der Fall <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000453">Koch</tei:rs>
    verlangte meine Übersiedelung nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>.
    Das wäre der letzte Schritt, den ich tun würde. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich freute mich sehr zu hören, dass <tei:rs key="entity-001737" type="work">op. 101</tei:rs> schon in Sicht ist und dass, nach Ihren Äusserungen zu urteilen, <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001725">II<tei:hi rend="supralinear">2</tei:hi></tei:rs> u.s.w.
    Fortschritte macht. Ich bewundere die übermenschliche Anstrengung, die dazu gehört, unter den
    jetzigen Verhältnissen solche Dinge zu vollbringen. Man erzählt sich hier von <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Wien</tei:rs> Schreckensdinge. Aber was Sie von der Moralverseuchung
    sagen, trifft wohl fast für alle Grossstädte zu, für die ganze Menschheit, möchte man sagen, die
    vollständig aus dem Gleise geworfen ist. Die technischen Errungenschaften, die sogenannten
    „Kulturfortschritte“, (wobei man wohl nur Komfort mit Kultur verwechselt) bewirken, dass sich
    die Seuche <tei:pb n="3"/> schneller fortpflanzt, als etwa im 16. od. 17. Jahrhundert. Und das
    Schlimmste von allem, die Zeitungen, tragen das Gift in jeden Erdenwinkel. Trotzdem muss man an
    eine Zukunft glauben. Und, verehrtester <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>, können auch viele Strebende trotz ehrlichstem Bemühen Ihr Wirken nicht
    bis in alle Konsequenzen hinein verstehen, so ist doch für alle diese schon Ihr Beispiel allein
    in seinem Heroismus anfeuernd und ermutigend und hilft über drohende Untiefen hinweg. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Wir wünschen Ihnen und Ihrer verehrten Frau <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Gemahlin</tei:rs> angenehme Feiertage und grüssen Sie auf das
     herzlichste </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr stets dankbarer</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">getreuer</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60">Walter Dahms</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p>N.B. Hat Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000438">Klammert</tei:rs> vielleicht noch
     eine Aufnahme aus Tantalier, die er mir zum Andenken schicken würde? </tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address rend="indent-60">
     <tei:addrLine>Wasserburg on the Inn 340</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:date when="1919-12-21" rend="indent-70">December 21, 1919</tei:date>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dear revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Master</tei:rs>, </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Many<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> thanks for your most
    detailed and gracious letter,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> which put me at
    ease about many things. You answered my question as openly I could have ever hoped. I will take
    your advice and will work on my own with all the strength I have. Incidentally (and this is
    rather telling), <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000326">Halm</tei:rs> had advised me to do just
    the same as you advised. I wrote him and asked whether he would be willing to give the types of
    instruction I wanted. He replied in a very open and friendly manner that he would not dare to
    put himself forward as a teacher of this kind <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of
     material</tei:supplied>. The only area in which he said he might be of some help would be to
    talk through my eventual attempts at composing. By all means, then, the matter is <tei:pb n="2"/> already (in your sense) closed. The case of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000453">Koch</tei:rs> demanded that I move to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>. And that would be the last thing I would do. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I was delighted to hear that <tei:rs key="entity-001737" type="work">
     <tei:title level="m">Op. 101</tei:title>
    </tei:rs> is already in sight and, judging from your comment, that <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001725">II/2</tei:rs> etc. is making progress. I marvel at the superhuman effort
    that you display under current circumstances to bring such things to completion. People here
    report shocking things about <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Vienna</tei:rs>. But what
    you say of the contamination of morals applies to almost all major cities, for all of humanity,
    one could say, which has completely been derailed. Technical achievements, so-called "cultural
    progress" (which is just a confusion of comfort with culture) come about such that the
    contamination <tei:pb n="3"/> just spreads faster than perhaps it did in the 16th- and 17th
    centuries. And worst of all, the newspapers transmit the toxin to every corner of the world.
    Nonetheless one must believe in the future. And, most revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Master</tei:rs>, even many independent-minded people still cannot understand your work
    in all its consequences, despite their honest efforts. So for all these people your example
    alone is in its heroism an incentive and encouragement, it helps them over the yawning abysses
    that threaten. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">We wish you and your <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">wife</tei:rs> a pleasant holiday and send our warmest greetings. </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ever-thankfully, </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your faithful</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60">Walter Dahms</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p>N.B. Does Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000438">Klammert</tei:rs> perhaps have
     another photo from Tantalier that he would send me as a momento?</tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>