<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="261" sdoID="OJ-15-16_42">OJ 15/16, [42]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HW" scope="sole">Hans Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="AH">
   <tei:persName>Alison Hiley</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2008</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML encoding, 2010</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-12-03" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~ H+JSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   
   

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated July 11, 1920</dc:title>
   
   <dcterms:created>1920-07-11T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-03-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Weisse wishes Schenker an enjoyable summer holiday, and looks forward to visiting
    him. He inquires about the possibility of moving into Reisnerstraße 38, in the event that the
    Schenkers move elsewhere, and informs his teacher about the organization of a lecture series at
    the Vienna Urania. He concludes with some remarks about literary works, Wedekind's Schloß
    Wetterstein and Jean Paul's Levana. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Wetter; weather; Wohnung; apartment; Mietsamt; rental office; Vortrag; lecture;
    Landschaft; landscape; Entwelschung; linguistic purification; Prolongation; Assoziation; association</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000951">Weisse</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Lieber verehter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>


   <tei:p>Ihre<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is
     recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/1, p. 2255, July 14, 1920: " Von Dr. Weisse (Br.): Lafite
     möglicherweise Hindernis der geplanten Vorlesungen in der Urania." ("From Dr. Weisse (letter):
     Lafite possibly a hindrance to the planned lectures at the Urania."). </tei:note> Nachricht,
    daß Ihr Unterkommen in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002382">Seefeld</tei:rs> gesichert ist,
    hat mich sowohl für Sie, als auch die liebe gnädige <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Frau</tei:rs> aufs Höchste erfreut. Möge nun noch ein günstiges Wetter die Erholung
    beschleunigen. Da Sie von der Reise nichts berichten, so hoffe ich, daß sie im vollsten Sinne
    des Wortes Ihr Geld wert war! </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Heute vormittag sprach ich bei Dr. Koch in der Reisnerstrasse<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The landlord of apartment house at Reisnerstrasse 38, Vienna,
     where Heinrich Schenker was living in 1920. Weisse is apparently thinking of moving into the
     Schenkers' apartment once they have moved to the Keilgasse. </tei:note> vor, der mir in
    liebenswürdiger Weise versicherte, daß er persönlich mir keinerlei Schwierigkeiten, in der
    Wohnungsangelegenheit machen werde und auch für den Fall, daß das Mietamt irgend-welchen
    Gewaltakt vornehmen werde dagegen mit der Motivierung, daß die Wohnung bereits vermietet sei,
    protestieren wolle. Ich bitte Sie nur, so bald Sie die endgültige Entscheidung des Mietsamtes
    kennen, mir vielleicht um eine kurze Frist früher als Ihren <tei:pb n="2"/> Hausherrn Dr. Koch
    Mitteilung zu machen, falls Sie übersiedeln können. Ich kann ihn dann schriftlich sofort beim
    Worte nehmen! </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Bezüglich der <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002412">Urania</tei:rs> habe ich in Erfahrung
    gebracht, daß <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000500">Lafite</tei:rs> der Kursleiter sei. Durch
     <tei:persName>Frau Gutherz</tei:persName>, wären auch bereits die Beziehungen zu ihm angeknüpft
    worden, (da sie mit ihm verkehrt hat) wenn der gute Mann nicht bereits in Aussee<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Bad Aussee, a spa town in Styria. </tei:note>
    wäre. Nun besteht die Möglichkeit, daß die „Vortrags“verhandlung <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002483">auf steirischem Boden</tei:rs> im Sommer, noch ehe ich zu Ihnen
     kommen<tei:supplied reason="syntax">,</tei:supplied> ein<tei:del rend="overstrike">e</tei:del>
    bestimmtes Resultat liefern. Allerdings scheint, soweit ich mich erinnere, der Mann keiner Ihrer
    Freunde zu sein. Nun, man wird ja sehen, wie er sich dazu stellt. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Am 15. d. Mts. verlasse ich <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Wien</tei:rs> und
    teile Ihnen dann meine Ankunft in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002339">Ischl</tei:rs>
    sofort mit. Es gab hier mittlerweile recht heiße und nun (die beiden letzten) recht kühle Tage!
    Auf der <tei:add place="interlinear-above">Land</tei:add>karte habe ich mir bereits einen
    Vorgenuß der großen <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002382">Seefeld</tei:rs>er Landschaft
    verschafft und freue mich nun schon auch im Sommer<tei:supplied reason="syntax">,</tei:supplied>
    das „Große“ mit „Schönem, Wahren und Lieben“ vereinigen zu können! </tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> Hoffentlich stört Sie nicht, sooft Sie über Ihre <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002382">Seefeld</tei:rs>er Hausflur treten<tei:supplied reason="syntax">,</tei:supplied> nicht die Assoziation von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000938">Wedekind</tei:rs>s „Schloß Wetterstein<tei:supplied reason="syntax">“</tei:supplied>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:title level="m">Schloss Wetterstein</tei:title>, play by Frank Wedekind, was first performed in
     1910. </tei:note> Es wäre eine Belastung der <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002334">Tirol</tei:rs>er Athmosphäre. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Bei <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000403">J. Paul</tei:rs> in der Levana<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:title level="m">Levana oder
      Erziehlehre</tei:title>, by Jean-Paul Richter, appeared in 1807. </tei:note> fand ich folgende
    von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000206">Engel</tei:rs> nicht aufgenommene in Entwelschung:
    Belvedere der Hoffnung - „Siehdichum“ der Hoffnung und statt Student - Hörling.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">"Siehdichum": a panoramic viewing point;
     "Hörling": lit. young listener. </tei:note> (vielleicht interessiert's die liebe gnädige
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Frau</tei:rs>, der ich wegen <tei:term>Prolongation</tei:term>, <tei:term>Assoziation</tei:term> etc. gegenüber noch ein schlechtes Gewissen habe.) </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich umarme Sie mein teurer Meister von ganzen Herzen und freue mich schon jetzt, auf Ihr
    liebes lachendes Kinderauge! Frau <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Li-li</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">Jeanette
     Schenker's nickname was "Lie-Lie"; Weisse corrects the spelling in subsequent letters.
    </tei:note> bitte alles Liebe zu übermitteln und die besten W Sommerwetter wünsche dazu! </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">von Ihrem getreuen</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Hans</tei:rs></tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1920-07-11">11./Juli 20.</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Dear revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Master</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>


   <tei:p>I<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> was truly pleased, both for you yourself
    and your good lady <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">wife</tei:rs>, to hear your news,
    that your accommodation in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002382">Seefeld</tei:rs> has been
    secured. May fine weather speed your recovery. Since you do not relate anything about your
    journey, I hope that it was, in the true sense of the word, worth every penny! </tei:p>

   <tei:p>This morning I had a discussion with Dr. Koch in the Reisnerstrasse,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> who kindly gave me his personal assurance that he will
    not present me with any difficulties where the apartment is concerned, and will even protest
    should the rental office make an objection on the grounds that the apartment is already rented
    out. Should you be able to move, can I request that you perhaps let me know a little before your
     <tei:pb n="2"/> landlord Dr. Koch, just as soon as you have a definite decision from the rental
    board? I can then take him up on his word immediately in writing! </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Regarding the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002412">Urania</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000500">Lafite</tei:rs> is, as I understand, the course director. If the good
    man were not already in Aussee,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> he would be
    contactable through <tei:persName>Frau Gutherz</tei:persName> (since she has had dealings with
    him). There is now a possibility that the "lecture" negotiations will reach a definite
    conclusion somewhere in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002483">Styria</tei:rs> in the summer,
    before I come to you. As far as I recall, it appears that the man is not numbered among your
    friends. Well, time will tell how he positions himself. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>I am leaving <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Vienna</tei:rs> on the 15th of the
    month and I shall let you know my address in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002339">Ischl</tei:rs> at once. We meanwhile have had some really hot days here and now some
    really cool ones (the last two)! I have been enjoying a foretaste of the great <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002382">Seefeld</tei:rs> landscape by studying the map and am looking
    forward to being able to combine that which is "great" with that which is "beautiful, true, and
    dear" in summer as well! </tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> I hope the association with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000938">Wedekind</tei:rs>'s <tei:title level="m">Schloß Wetterstein</tei:title><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> will not trouble you every time you cross your
     <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002382">Seefeld</tei:rs> threshold. It would pollute the
     <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002334">Tyrol</tei:rs>ean atmosphere. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>In <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000403">Jean-Paul</tei:rs>'s <tei:title level="m">Levana</tei:title><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> I found the following words
    which were dropped by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000206">Engel</tei:rs> in the linguistic
    purification.: "Belvedere der Hoffnung" rather than "'Siehdichum' der Hoffnung" and, "Hörling"
    rather than "Student."<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> (Perhaps it will interest
    your good lady <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">wife</tei:rs>; I still feel guilty where
    she is concerned regarding "<tei:term>prolongation</tei:term>,"
     "<tei:term>association</tei:term>" etc.) </tei:p>

   <tei:p>I embrace you, my beloved master, with all my heart and already look forward to your dear,
    wide-eyed smile! Please give my love to Frau<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">
     Li-Li</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> and best summer weather wishes to you both as well! </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">From your faithful</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Hans</tei:rs></tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1920-07-11">July 11, 1920</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>