<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3886" sdoID="OJ-13-10_174">OJ 13/10, [174]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2025</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated September 12, 1933</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1933-09-12T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-12-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel sends greetings at the start of the teaching term. – His Wind Serenade
        has just been broadcast in Switzerland. – He reports on his extensive reading. –He has been
        following the news of Hitler’s Concordat with the Vatican and the increasing power of the
        Catholic church in Germany.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1933-09-12">12. Sept
            33</tei:date>. W31 Könneritzstr 58<tei:hi rend="supralinear">III</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Professor D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Schenker</tei:rs>!<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in
            Schenker’s diary for September 14, 1933: “Von Oppel (Br.): schildert die Zustände in
            Deutschland mit Gefühl für die tieferen Zusammenhänge – der Katholik Hitler flößt ihm
            Sorgen ein” (“From Oppel (letter): he portrays the conditions in Germany with a feeling
            for the deeper connections – the Catholic Hitler fills him with
          anxiety”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Nun sind Sie wohl zurück aus den Bergen, den geliebten, in die leider nun einmal
        unvermeidliche Grossstadt. Ich hoffe, Sie haben sich beide gut erholt und können mit
        frischer Kraft an das Lebenswerk gehn. <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004067"
          >Mönichkirchen</tei:rs> muss ja auch ein wundervoller Fleck Erde sein. Ja, die Schönheiten
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002334">Tirol</tei:rs>s sind unendlich. Sehr erfreute
        mich die Nachricht, dass der „<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title>fr
            S</tei:title></tei:rs>“ Ende Oct unter die Presse kommt. – <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000320">Haas</tei:rs> „<tei:title>Aufführungspraxis</tei:title>“<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Robert
              Haas</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Aufführungspraxis der Musik</tei:title>
            (Potsdam: Athenaion, 1931)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> werde ich mir ansehn. – Haben Sie was
        v. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000955">Dr Weis<tei:supplied reason="omission">s</tei:supplied>e</tei:rs> etc.
        gehört? – Heute waren bei uns Aufnahmeprüfungen, nur sehr wenig Anmeldungen. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005266">Meiner Frau</tei:rs> u. d. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-004801">Kindern</tei:rs> geht’s gut. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003957">Walter</tei:rs> hat eine Gehaltserhöhung von 100 auf 125 M
        durchgesetzt; <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> schreibt vergnügt
        von seiner Werftarbeit in Wilhelmshaven. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008523"
          >Bepo</tei:rs> ist grade 1 m gross, er entwickelt sich immer weiter gut. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-008524">Brigitte</tei:rs> ist in der Sommerhitze etwas stehn
        geblieben, aber das ist leicht zu beheben. Mir selbst gehts leidlich, ich lebe diät u. gehe
        jetzt zeitiger schlafen. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000866">Straube</tei:rs> ist von der Leitung des
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-005889">Gewandhaus</tei:rs>chores zurückgetreten. Dafür
        wird er sich bei uns im <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002872">Institut</tei:rs>
        umso breiter machen. – Das Konkordat zeitigt schon seine ersten Früchte: die Macht des
        Katholicismus wächst.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Adolf
          Hitler’s “Concordat” (<tei:title level="m">Reichskonkordat</tei:title>, 1933) with the
          Vatican gave Catholics in Germany the freedom to worship and maintain their religious
          institutions, in exchange for the Church not interfering with German politics.</tei:note>
          (<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003109">Hitler</tei:rs> ist nicht vergeblich
        katholisch). Die Bestimmung, dass die kath. Geistlichen für <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002482">Deutschl.</tei:rs> auch in Rom studieren dürfen, <tei:pb n="2"/> ist
        mehr wie verhängnisvoll. Der „heilige Rock“ in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-007157"
          >Trier</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">The “Holy
          Tunic” or “Seamless Robe of Jesus” was a garment said to be worn by Jesus before his
          crucifixion. Trier is only one of several places claiming the relic as their
          own.</tei:note> war wieder ein glänzendes Geschäft, er war mit grossen Scheinwerfern
        beleuchtet u. erwies sich, reciproc. selbst wieder als grosser Scheinwerfer. In einem Streit
        zwischen der politischen Leitung in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004583">Bingen</tei:rs>
        u. dem Bischof v. <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003156">Mainz</tei:rs>
        <tei:del rend="overstrike">be</tei:del> wegen der Rochusprozession<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:hi rend="italic"
            >Rochusprozession</tei:hi>: annual event honoring Saint Roch, the patron saint of plague
          sufferers, particularly in Bingen, in the Rhine Valley, after a plague that hit the town
          in 1666.</tei:note> u. der Versetzung eines separatistischen Pfarrers siegt natürlich die
        Kirche! – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Für die Rundfunkaufführung meiner Bläserserenade in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002342"><tei:hi rend="underline">Bern</tei:hi></tei:rs> (Dauer 30 Min.) bezog
        ich nach der Abrechnung durch die französ. Autorengesellschaft über unsre Genossenschaft 17
        Pfennig. Na, die Direction in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs> haue
        ich morgen oder übermorgen abe<tei:supplied reason="cut-off">nds</tei:supplied> ein
        Schreiben darüber hin, dass sie sich nicht hinter den Spiegel steckt. – Ich las von Paul
        Burg: „<tei:title>das Geheimnis von Mayerling</tei:title>“,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06"
          type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Paul Burg</tei:author>, <tei:title
              level="m">Das Geheimnis von Mayerling</tei:title> (Berlin, 1927)</tei:bibl>. In 1889
          the bodies of Crown Prince Rudolf and his mistress, Maria von Vetsera, the victims of an
          apparent murder-suicide or double-murder, were found at the Imperial hunting lodge in
          Mayerling, a village in the Vienna Woods.</tei:note> an der Darstellung war mir manches
        neu, besonders nach der politische Seite hin. Darüber einmal später mündlich. – In den
        Ferien las ich wieder manches von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003810">Stefan
          George</tei:rs>. Kennen Sie den „<tei:title>Krieg</tei:title>“ von ihm 1917
          erschienen?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">Stefan George’s
            <tei:title level="m">Der Krieg</tei:title>, a 144-line poem, foretold an impending
          disaster for Germany after the First World War. </tei:note> Sehr gut. – Diese Woche will
        ich noch ruhen, die Tage sind so voller Sonne, dass man sie ausnützen muss schon der <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-004801">Kinder</tei:rs> wegen; dann mag der winterliche Tanz
        beginnen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Hat <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000412">Dr. Jonas</tei:rs> s. Buch fertig? – Sehr
        empfohlen wurde mir unterwegs auch Ludwig <tei:hi rend="underline">Klages</tei:hi>,<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot">Ludwig Klages (1872–1956): chemist,
          psychologist and philosopher, and a member of the “Munich Cosmic Circle” which included
          the poet Stefan George.</tei:note> ich kenne aber noch nichts von ihm, philos. Schriften.
        Der Winter bringt Arbeit. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun wünsche ich Ihnen beiden alles Gute, vor allem Kraft und Ruhe zur Arbeit und die
        nötige Gesundheit. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mit den herzlichsten Grüssen von uns allen</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr treuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1933-09-12">September 12,
              1933</tei:date>. <tei:supplied>Leipzig</tei:supplied> W31, Könneritzstrasse 58<tei:hi
              rend="supralinear">III</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor
            Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>You are now probably back from the mountains, the beloved mountains, and have returned,
        unfortunately, to the unavoidable metropolis. I hope that the two of you have recuperated
        well and can approach your life’s work with renewed energy. <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-004067">Mönichkirchen</tei:rs> must indeed be a wonderful corner of earth. To
        be sure, the beauty of the <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002334">Tyrol</tei:rs> is
        infinite. I was very glad to have the news that <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"
            ><tei:title level="m">Free Composition</tei:title></tei:rs> is going to press at the end
        of October. – I shall have a look at <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000320"
        >Haas</tei:rs>’s <tei:title level="m">Performance Practice</tei:title>.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> – Have you heard anything from <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>? from <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000955">Dr. Weisse</tei:rs>? Today we had entrance examinations; there were
        only a few applicants. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005266">My wife</tei:rs> and the <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-004801">children</tei:rs> are well. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003957">Walter</tei:rs> got a pay rise, from 100 to 125 marks; <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> writes cheerfully about his shipyard
        work in Wilhelmshaven. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008523">Bepo</tei:rs> is exactly 1
        metre tall; he continues to develop well. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008524"
          >Brigitte</tei:rs> remained somewhat stationary in the summer heat, but that will be easy
        to overcome. I myself am tolerably well; I follow a diet and now go to bed earlier.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000866">Straube</tei:rs> retired from the
        conductorship of the <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-005889">Gewandhaus</tei:rs> choir. As
        a consequence, he will exert his influence all the more broadly at our <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002872">Institute</tei:rs>. – The Concordat is already
        bearing its first fruits: the power of Catholicism is growing.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
          type="footnote"/> (<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003109">Hitler</tei:rs> is not a
        Catholic in vain.) The decision to allow Catholic clerics for <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002482">Germany</tei:rs> to study even in Rome <tei:pb n="2"/> is more than
        disastrous. The Holy Tunic in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-007157"
          >Trier</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> was again a splendid
        business enterprise; it was illuminated by great floodlights and proved itself a great
        floodlight in its own right. In a dispute between the political leadership in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-004583">Bingen</tei:rs> and the Bishop of <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-003156">Mainz</tei:rs> regarding the Rochus Procession<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> and the redeployment of a separatist priest, the
        Church is of course victorious! – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>For the radio broadcast of my Wind Serenade in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002342"
            ><tei:hi rend="underline">Bern</tei:hi></tei:rs> (which lasted 30 minutes), I received –
        after deduction from the French Society of Authors – 17 Pfennigs from our society. Well, I
        shall throw together a statement to the directorship in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs> tomorrow or the day after about it, to say that they
        should not hide behind the mirror. – I read Paul Burg’s <tei:title level="m">Mayerling’s
          Secret</tei:title>;<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> much was new to me in
        the presentation, especially from a political angle. We’ll speak about that when we next see
        each other. – Over the holidays, I read several things by <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003810">Stefan George</tei:rs>. Do you know his <tei:title level="m">The
          War</tei:title>, published in 1917?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> Very
        good. – This week I shall take things easy; the days are so full of sunshine that one must
        take advantage of them, if only for the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801"
          >children</tei:rs>’s sake. Then the winter’s dance may begin.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Has <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000412">Dr. Jonas</tei:rs> finished his book? –
        The work of Ludwig <tei:hi rend="underline">Klages</tei:hi><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08"
          type="footnote"/> was recommended to me highly while I was travelling; but I haven’t yet
        read any of his philosophical writings. The winter will bring work.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Now, I wish the two of you the best, and above all strength and peace for your work and
        the necessary good health.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">With best wishes from all of us,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
