<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="12" sdoID="OJ-15-16_33">OJ 15/16, [33]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HW" scope="sole">Hans Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="AH">
   <tei:persName>Alison Hiley</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2008</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML encoding, 2010</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
   <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
   <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-02-09" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~ H+JSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   
   
   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated February 18, 1918</dc:title>
   
   <dcterms:created>1918-02-18T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-10-15</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Weisse apologizes profusely for not having paid his condolences to Schenker upon
    the death of his mother. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>apology; condolences; death; mother</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000951">Weisse</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Lieber, verehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>


   <tei:p>Ihr<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"> Receipt of this letter is
     recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/10, p. 844: February 20, 1918. </tei:note><!-- XR -->
     Brief<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"> Schenker's letter is not known
     to survive, but its writing is recorded in Schenker's diary for February 15, 1918 (OJ 2/10, p.
     843) with full summary. <!-- XR --> Weisse had caused offense by writing his condolences on the
     death of Schenker's mother on a postcard, in pencil, and including information about himself.
    </tei:note> traf mich eben wie ein Blitz aus heiterm Himmel, besonders deshalb weil ich hinter
    Ihrem Stillschweigen ganz andere, als persönliche Gründe vermutete! Ich muß gestehen, lieber
    Meister, daß mir Ihr Brief aufs Tiefste wehe tut, weil er Sie verletzt zeigt, und meinem
    Empfinden, meiner Verehrung für Sie, nichts gerade fremder und schmerzender ist, als der
    Gedanke, Sie in einen Zustand der Bitterkeit versetzt zu haben.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Meiner Überzeugung nach bin ich damals nicht zu Ihnen gekommen. Ich wußte doch, seit
    Langem <tei:pb n="2"/> wie sehr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000773">Ihre Mutter</tei:rs> im
    Mittelpunkt Ihres Lebens stand und hätte gar nicht den Mut gehabt, Sie auch nur eine
    Viertelstunde für mich in Anspruch zu nehmen. Was mich darin bestärkte war eben das Bewußtsein,
    daß Sie von mir wüßten, wie sehr ich Sie verehrte und hochhielt<tei:supplied reason="syntax">e</tei:supplied>! Ich wäre damals nie auf den Gedanken gekommen, Sie so verletzen zu
    können.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Seit meiner frühesten Kindheit habe ich dem Tode gegenüber keine andere Ehrenbezeigung
    gekannt, als Stillschweigen, und halte sie auch heute noch nicht minder entsprechend und
    gerechtfertigt.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Sie so aber bewußt-unbewußt verletzt zu haben ist mir ein quälender Gedanke, dessen
     <tei:pb n="3"/> Last mir noch in der nämlichen Stunde, die ich Ihren Brief erhielt, diesen zu
    meiner Rechtfertigung mir abzwingt!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Was Sie mir waren, sind und sein werden, mag ich in diesem Zusammenhange gar nicht
    ausführen, wenn ich es auch gerne täte, um Sie verstehen zu lassen, was es für mich bedeutet,
    Sie <tei:supplied reason="reading">illegible word</tei:supplied> zu wissen.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Für den Mangel einer entsprechenden Form bitte ich Sie, mit Verzicht auf jede weitere
    Rechtfertigung, aus tiefster Seele eine Entschuldigung! Nie dürfen Sie, liebster Meister, die
    Empfindung haben, daß ich, gerade ich, Sie, und <tei:hi rend="underline">alles</tei:hi> was mit
    Ihnen im Zusammenhange steht, nicht genügend hochhalte!</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> Alles andere, als Antwort auf Ihren Brief, möchte ich ein nächtes Mal
    sagen! Diesen Zeilen mögen einzig und allein meiner Entschuldigung dienen und der Bitte, mir
    nicht nachzutragen, was so gar nicht meinem Willen oder meinem Bewußtsein entsprungen
    ist.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Mit herzlichsten Grüßen in alter Treue und Dankbarkeit
     Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-30">Hans</tei:signed>
    <tei:date when="1918-02-18">18/2 18.</tei:date>
   </tei:closer>
  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Dear revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Master</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>


   <tei:p>Your<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> letter<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> struck me just like a flash of lightning from out of a bright sky, especially
    so since I had supposed your silence to have had reasons quite other than personal. I have to
    admit, dear master, that your letter cuts me to the quick, since it reveals you to be hurt;
    nothing could upset my feeling and respect for you more than the thought that I might have
    reduced you to a state of bitterness.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>It was out of conviction that I did not visit you at that time. I had indeed long known
     <tei:pb n="2"/> what a central role your <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000773">mother</tei:rs> played in your life and I would never have presumed to ask for even a
    quarter of an hour of your time. My decision was confirmed by the knowledge that you would know
    how much I revered and admired you! At the time it would never have occurred to me that I could
    hurt you so.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>From my earliest childhood I have known of no way other than silence to show respect for
    death and even today I still consider it no less appropriate or justified.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>But to have hurt you thus, whether consciously or unconsciously, torments me – a thought
     <tei:pb n="3"/> which has forced me into writing this in my defence the very same hour that I
    received your letter!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>In this connection I have no wish to detail that which you have been, which you are and
    which you will be to me, even if I should like to do so in order to make you understand what it
    means to me to know that you are <tei:supplied reason="legibility">illegible
    word</tei:supplied>.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Without attempting any further self-justification, may I ask you from the bottom of my
    heart to excuse my lack of appropriate form. You must never, dear master, be under the
    impression that I, of all people, do not hold you, and <tei:hi rend="underline">everything</tei:hi> that is connected with you, in sufficient esteem!</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> Everything else will be in my next letter, in reply to yours! May these
    lines act purely and solely as my apology and as a plea not to hold something against me that
    absolutely did not arise from any conscious intention on my part!</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Ever yours, Most cordially, truly and gratefully,</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-30">Hans</tei:signed>
    <tei:date when="1918-02-18"> February 18, 1918</tei:date>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>