<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="440" sdoID="OJ-14-45_14">OJ 14/45, [14]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="MV" scope="sole">Moriz Violin's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>


  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2011</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-06-27" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002719">ViolinM ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM+V ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002718">ViolinM+V+F ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>




   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Moriz Violin to Schenker, dated July 24, 1922 </dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1922-07-24T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2011-06-27</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>In this highly emotional letter, Violin describes his personal difficulties in
    the face of spiraling inflation in Germany. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Lebensmitteltheurerung; increase in the price of food; Theurung; inflation;
    Erleichterung; alleviation; Hochschule; highschool; Aktivist; activist; Ideal; Handwerker;
    craftsman; Arbeit; work; Leistung; achievement; Schwierigkeit; difficulty; Höllenqualen;
    torments of hell; Fantasie; fantasy; Hochstapelei; self-delusion; Butter; Luxus;
    luxury</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-40"><tei:placeName>Hamburg</tei:placeName>, <tei:date when="1922-07-24">24 Juli 22.</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Liebster <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in
      Schenker's diary at OJ 3/3, p. 2446, August 1, 1922: "Von Floriz (Br.): über die
      „Musik-Hochschule“ in Hamburg; hofft Weihnachten in Wien zu sein." ("From Floriz (letter):
      about the "Musik-Hochschule" in Hamburg; hopes to be in Vienna for Christmas."). </tei:note>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Noch heute zehre ich von Deinem letzten, guten Brief! Ich wollte Dir danken,
    spürte aber daß er es nicht recht verträgt. Da schlichen sich wieder schwere Zeiten ein. Eine
    unheimliche Lebensmitteltheurerung. Bei allem Unterschied, der <tei:unclear reason="reading">sicher</tei:unclear> in einer traditionellen <tei:unclear reason="reading">Kraft</tei:unclear>
    liegt, ist es in <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Deutschland</tei:country></tei:rs>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">mindestens</tei:hi> so schlimm wie in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs>. Seit vorigem Jahr eine 7fache Theuerung. Ich verdiene jetzt ca.
    60.000 Mark. Ein Betrag mit dem ich voriges Jahr hätte fürstlich leben können. Heute muß man,
    für’s Notwendigste 120.000 haben. <tei:hi rend="underline">Vielleicht</tei:hi> wird zum Herbst
    die Hochschulidee<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">"Hochschulidee": in
     Germany, a "Hochschule für Musik," which caters primarily to university-aged students, is of
     higher pedagogical ranking than a "Konservatorium." It is not clear whether Violin is talking
     about founding a new Hochschule in Hamburg or raising the status of the conservatory at which
     he is teaching to that of a Hochschule. </tei:note> schon durchgedrungen sein. <tei:hi rend="underline">Vielleicht</tei:hi> finde auch ich dadurch Erleichterung. Bin ich doch der
    Aktivste unter denen, die sich mit der Gründung befassen. Und hat man schon ein praktisches
    Ideal erreicht (so viel zu verdienen, daß man leben kann), so ist man glücklicher Handwerker
    geworden. Als Handwerker muß man dann natürlich blöder erscheinen als andere, die nicht mehr
    sind, aber das goldene Handwerk des Schiebers betreiben. Denke die Situation aus: Nichts aus
    eigener Arbeit leisten können (nur damit kann man seine persönlichen Leistungen durchsetzen),
    dafür aber mit den Wölfen „handwerken“ müssen! Zu entsetzlich! Wenn Du also lange nichts von mir
    hörst, denke nur das Eine: Ich weiß wie kein Anderer <tei:hi rend="underline">Deine</tei:hi>
    Schwierigkeiten zu beurteilen, ich möchte Dein belastetes Leben, wenn ich es nicht erleichtern
    kann, mindestens nicht noch beschweren. <tei:hi rend="underline">Ich weiß</tei:hi>: mitfühlen
    müssen, ohne helfen zu können, gehört zu den verfluchtesten Höllenqualen. Ich weiß: Du denkst
    auch ohne meine Nachricht sicher manchmal an mein Leben, so wie ich stets an Deines denke! </tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Nun kam etwas, wofür es so viel zu danken giebt: Dein <tei:rs key="entity-001741" type="work">2<tei:hi rend="supralinear">tes</tei:hi> Heft
      „<tei:title>Tonwillen</tei:title>“</tei:rs>! Und eigentlich <tei:hi rend="underline">nur</tei:hi> deshalb möchte ich Dir heute geschrieben haben. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Du glaubst, durch materielle Not Dein Werk bedroht? </tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:hi rend="underline">Das</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">gibt</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">es</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">nicht</tei:hi>!!! Noch <tei:hi rend="triple-underline">niemand</tei:hi>
    hat sein Werk nicht vollenden können. Entweder hat man keines zu schaffen, oder es <tei:hi rend="underline">muss</tei:hi> vollendet werden. Das richtet Gott schon so ein. <tei:rs key="entity-000612" type="person">Mozart</tei:rs> braucht 32, <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs> 65 Jahre<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Violin’s calculations are approximate: Mozart died shortly before his 36th
     birthday, Brahms just before his 64th. </tei:note> u. Du schreibst so viel Bände als nötig!
    Lebensdauer Nebensache. Vielleicht mußt Du Dir 100 Jahre verschreiben. Auch in dieser Beziehung
    scheint das Genie mehr von seinem Leben zu wissen, als andere Sterbliche! </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Welch unbescheidene Fantasie von mir! Worauf gründet sie sich? Warum glaube ich, daß ich
    Dein Werk miterleben werde? Ist mein Wunsch nur so intensiv? </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Hochstapelei muß auch seine Grenze haben. Ein solcher „Grenzfall“ scheint mir
    die Absicht, zu Weihnachten nach <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> zu
    kommen. So sind die Zeiten! Butteressen = Luxus, Dich früher sehen wollen = Hochstapelei! </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Also alle Gesundheit Dir u. Deiner <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Frau</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Wir alle grüßen herzlichst (<tei:rs key="entity-000909" type="person">Fanny</tei:rs> ist darunter!)</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Dein</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>


  </tei:div>

  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-40"><tei:placeName>Hamburg</tei:placeName>, <tei:date when="1922-07-24">July 24, 1922</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Dearest <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Even today I am nourishing myself on your last, good letter! I wanted to
    thank you, but sensed I would not be able to do justice to it. Difficult times have again
    entered our lives. An unbelievable increase in the price of food. Allowing for all the
    differences that <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">no doubt</tei:unclear> reside in a
    traditional <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">power</tei:unclear>, things are <tei:hi rend="underline">at least as</tei:hi> bad in <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Germany</tei:country></tei:rs> as they are in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>. A seven-fold increase in prices since last year. I am now earning
    about 60,000 Marks, a sum with which I could have lived like a prince last year. Today one must
    have 120,000 for the most basic things. <tei:hi rend="underline">Perhaps</tei:hi> in the autumn
    the idea of a Hochshule<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> will catch hold. <tei:hi rend="underline">Perhaps</tei:hi> even I will find some alleviation in that. I am in fact the
    most active among those who are working towards its foundation. And if one has already reached a
    practical ideal (to earn enough money to live on), then one becomes a happier craftsman. As a
    craftsman, one must of course appear mentally more deficient than others who are no longer
    craftsmen but who purvey the golden handiwork of those who actually turn the wheel. Consider the
    situation: not to be able to accomplish any of one's own work (the only way in which one can
    fulfill one's personal ambitions), and instead having to "work as craftsman" among the wolves!
    It is too disgraceful to contemplate. If, then, you have not heard anything from me for a while,
    think only of this: I am able, as no other, to judge the difficulties that <tei:hi rend="underline">you</tei:hi> face; and if I cannot make your burdened life any easier, at
    least I do not want to make it more difficult. <tei:hi rend="underline">I know</tei:hi> that to
    have to feel sympathetic without being able to help belongs to one of the accursed torments of
    hell. <tei:hi rend="underline">I know</tei:hi> that you sometimes think about my life, even when
    you have not had news from me, just as I always think about yours! </tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> And now something came for which there is much to thank: the <tei:rs key="entity-001741" type="work">second issue of <tei:title level="j">Der
     Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>! And it is really <tei:hi rend="underline">only</tei:hi> for this
    that I want to write to you today. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Do you believe that your work is threatened by material need? </tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:hi rend="underline">There's no such thing</tei:hi>!!! <tei:hi rend="triple-underline">No one</tei:hi> has yet been unable to complete his work. Either he has none that is worth
    doing, or it <tei:hi rend="underline">must</tei:hi> be completed. God takes care of it. <tei:rs key="entity-000612" type="person">Mozart</tei:rs> needed thirty-two years, <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs> 65<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> and you will write as many volumes as is necessary. Longevity is of secondary
    importance. Perhaps you shall have to devote 100 years <tei:supplied reason="clarity">to
     complete your work</tei:supplied>; in this respect, too, the genius seems to know more about
    his life than other mortals </tei:p>

   <tei:p>What presumptuous fantasy on my part! On what is it based? Why do I believe that I shall
    be a witness to your work? Is my wish simply so intensive? </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:supplied reason="clarity">Self</tei:supplied>-delusion must also have
    its boundaries. Such a "boundary issue" seems to me to be the intention of coming to <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs> for Christmas. Such are the times! Eating
    butter is a luxury; hoping to see you sooner is a delusion! </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Thus, may you and your <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs> be in the best of health!</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">We send our most cordial greetings (including <tei:rs key="entity-000909" type="person">Fanny</tei:rs>!)</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>