<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3356" sdoID="OJ-10-13_7">OJ 10/13, [7]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="JPD" scope="major">John Petrie Dunn's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="CH">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2007</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2007</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-23" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008413">DunnJP ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Dunn to Schenker, dated June 16, 1928</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1928-06-16T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-01-31</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Dunn sends Schenker greetings on his 60th birthday; his English adaptation is
        a success, but its impact is limited by the fact that a less enlightened colleague teaches
        first-year counterpoint. – He outlines his latest work, a study of orchestration from a
        theoretical point of view, and hopes that he and his wife might visit the Schenkers the
        following summer.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000178">DunnJP</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">
      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>42, Murrayfield
            Avenue,</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-70">Edinburgh.</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#JPD"/>den <tei:date when="1928-06-16"
            >16. Juni, 1928</tei:date>.</tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>Hochverehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Schenker</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt
            of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for June 19, 1928: “Von Prof. Dunn (Br.):
            schickt ein Bild.” (“From Prof. Dunn (letter): sends a picture.”). The photograph
            survives as OJ 72/4, item 1. — This letter was published in English in
                <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Heinrich Schenker: Selected
                Correspondence</tei:title>, ed. <tei:editor>Ian Bent</tei:editor>, <tei:editor>David
                Bretherton</tei:editor>, and <tei:editor>William Drabkin</tei:editor> (Woodbridge,
              UK: The Boydell Press, 2014), pp. 448–49</tei:bibl>.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Gestatten Sie, dass ich Ihnen zu Ihrem Geburtstag<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker celebrated his sixtieth
          birthday on June 19, 1928.</tei:note> meinen herzlichsten Glückwunsch ausspreche und
        zugleich der Hoffnung Ausdruck gebe, dass es Ihnen vergönnt sein möge, noch viele, viele
        Jahre hindurch tätig zu sein! </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich erlaube mir, eine meiner neuesten Photographien beizulegen<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">A photograph of Dunn, seated, exists (OJ
          72/4, item 1) with holograph inscription to Schenker dated ”June 19, 1928, photographer:
          Moffat, Edinburgh.” Dunn must have dated it not according to the date of his letter but to
          that of Schenker's birthday. (Another photograph, of John and Aline Petrie Dunn, inscribed
          “Marienbad, August 1930,” survives as OJ 72/4, item 2. Schenker reported to Anthony van
          Hoboken in <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-89-2_6">OJ 89/2, [6]</tei:ref>, June
          22, 1928: “Von Prof. Dunn erhielt ich sein Bild u. ein sehr liebes Briefchen dazu.” (“From
          Prof. Dunn I received his picture and a very nice note with it.”).</tei:note> und bitte
        Sie, dieselbe als bescheidenes Merkmal meines Dankbarkeitsgefühles Ihnen gegenüber
        aufzufassen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Es wird Sie vielleicht interessieren zu erfahren, <tei:pb n="2"/> dass ich
        gegenwärtig ein Buch über Orchestrierung verfasse. (“Aspects of Orchestration”, etwa
        “Gesichtspunkte der Orchestrierung”). In einer Abteilung über “Klarheit” (d.h. des Melos)
        habe ich mir erlaubt, einen längeren Passus aus Ihrer <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001731">Schrift über die Neunte</tei:rs> in englischer Uebersetzung
        wiederzugeben. (S. 47 - “So entsinne ich mich nie “- - - - - - bis S. 49 - - - “überflüssige
          Deutlichkeitsgrade.”)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">The
          extract concerns the first eight bars of Beethoven’s Eighth Symphony. Wagner criticizes
          Beethoven’s lack of melodic clarity, by allowing the first oboe (in bar 6) and first flute
          (bar 8) to enter “unthematically.” Schenker, in <tei:bibl><tei:rs type="work"
              key="entity-001731"><tei:title level="m">Beethovens Neunte
              Sinfonie</tei:title></tei:rs> (Vienna: Universal Edition, 1912)</tei:bibl>, pp. 47–49,
          sees no problem with this: Beethoven’s use of the oboe first as a filler part (bars 6–7),
          then as a reinforcement of the melodic line (bars 7–8) is for Schenker no lack of clarity,
          but is rather a more subtle approach to orchestration than a theater-orientated composer
          such as Wagner could have understood. (Eng. transl., pp. 67–68).</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Wie, wo, und wann das Buch erscheinen wird, weiss ich noch
          garnicht.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Dunn presented this
          work to the University of Edinburgh in partial fulfilment of the DMus in 1928. It was
          published as <tei:bibl><tei:title>A Student's Guide to Orchestration</tei:title> (London:
            Novello, 1930)</tei:bibl>, with a dedication to Donald Francis Tovey; a review appeared
          in <tei:title level="j">The Musical Times</tei:title>, 71 (1930), p. 611. True to his
          word, Dunn included the extract from <tei:title level="m">Beethovens neunte
            Sinfonie</tei:title> concerning the opening bars of the Eighth Symphony, in a chapter on
          “Lucidity” (see pp. 79–80); this is probably the first extract from Schenker’s theoretical
          work to appear in English translation. Dunn quotes Schenker approvingly, and recommends
          many of his writings in the Preface (the first three volumes of the <tei:title level="m"
            >Neue Musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:title>, the first two volumes of
            <tei:title level="m">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:title>, and the monograph on the
          Ninth Symphony), but is careful not to expose Schenker as an outright anti-Wagnerian: <tei:cit>
            <tei:q>It would here be explained that Schenker’s words are not intended as an
              endorsement of the charge of “noisiness” so often levelled at Wagner by the ignorant
              layman. His meaning rather is that Wagner under-estimated and consequently disdained
              those very refinements of orchestral treatment which contribute towards making
              Beethoven’s instrumental style the supreme artistic achievement that it is.</tei:q>
          </tei:cit>
        </tei:note> Vielleicht werde ich überhaupt keinen Verleger finden können, der es macht. Der
        Markt wimmelt von elenden kleinen Instrumentenkunden, die alle dasselbe bringen und sich
        gegenseitig <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">words crossed out</tei:note>
        wiederholen. Mein Buch setzt die Kenntnis der einzelnen Instrumente voraus und handelt nur
        von den <tei:pb n="3"/> leitenden Gesichtspunkten der klassischen Orchestrierungskunst, als
        da sind Verdoppelung der Stimmen, Verwandlung eines Continualstimme in eine Wirkliche und
        umgekehrt; Klangfarbe, Farbenmischung und Register; das Gleichgewicht und das <tei:hi
          rend="underline">zusammenfassende</tei:hi> Hören; wie man zuzuhören hat; die Rolle der
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">3</tei:add> Hauptgruppen im Orchestersatz; Klarheit
        u.s.w. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Sollte das Buch einmal herauskommen, so werde ich Sie, beziehungsweise
        Ihren Verleger <tei:del rend="overstrike">auf</tei:del> um die Erlaubnis bitten, den
        besagten Passus zu zitieren. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Die Uebersetzung Ihres “<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001725"
            ><tei:title>Kontrapunkt</tei:title></tei:rs>s” wurde durch Verteilung vieler Exemplare
          <tei:pb n="4"/> meinen Studenten zugänglich gemacht. Alle äusserten sich sehr günstig
        darüber. Es ist mir jedoch nicht möglich, nach dieser Richtung hin meinen Einfluss so weit
        geltend zu machen, wie mir dieses erwünscht wäre, denn gerade der <tei:term>strenge
          Satz</tei:term> wird nicht von mir sondern von einem Kollegen gelehrt. Dieser Herr begeht
        nun gerade die Fehler, die Sie rügen. Er liebäugelt nämlich mit dem freien Satz und
        verbietet z.B. – </tei:p>

      <!-- MUSIC EXAMPLE -->

      <tei:p rend="first">– weil diese Fortschreitungen angeblich verkappte 6/4 Harmonien sind! Die
        Folge <tei:add place="interlinear-above">davon</tei:add> ist dass die Schüler den <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">freien</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above"><tei:term>strengen</tei:term></tei:add>
        </tei:subst>
        <tei:term>Satz</tei:term> als ein zum Bestehen von Prüfung in notwendiger Nebel betrachten! </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="5"/> Viele der Studenten sind der Ansicht, dass ich den
        Elementar-Unterricht übernehmen müsste, weil sie dann gleich den richtigen Begriff davon
        bekommen würden, allein das ist leider unmöglich. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich möchte furchtbar gerne einmal mit Ihnen zusammenkommen und alle
        möglichen Fragen besprechen. Dieses Jahr fahre ich mit meiner <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000177">Frau</tei:rs> auf 14 Tage nach Spiekeroog (bei Norderney).<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Spiekeroog, Norderney: two islands in
          the North Sea, off the coast of Lower Saxony.</tei:note> Nächsten Sommer aber werden wir
        ganz bestimmt nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003993">Bayreuth</tei:rs> fahren.
        Vielleicht haben wir dann Gelegenheit, uns gegenseitig <tei:pb n="6"/> auszusprechen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Mit herzlichsten Grüssen von Haus zu Haus </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Verbleibe ich,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr ganz ergebener</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000178">John Petrie
            Dunn</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>42, Murrayfield
            Avenue</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-70">Edinburgh</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#JPD"/><tei:date when="1928-06-16">June
            16, 1928</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>Highly esteemed Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Allow me to express my most cordial best wishes to you for your
          birthday<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> and, at the same time, give
        expression to the hope that it may be granted that you remain active for many, many years to
        come!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I take the liberty of enclosing one of the most recent photographs of
          myself,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> and ask you to regard it as a
        modest sign of my feelings of gratitude towards you.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">It will probably interest you to learn <tei:pb n="2"/> that I am at
        present writing a book on orchestration (“Aspects of Orchestration,” which may be rendered
        in German as “Gesichtspunkte der Orchestrierung”). In a section on “clarity” (i.e. of the
        melodic line) I permitted myself to reproduce, in English translation, an extended passage
        from your <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001731">book on the Ninth Symphony</tei:rs>, from
        p. 47 (“Thus I cannot remember ever ...”) to p. 49 (“… unnecessary degree of
          clarity”).<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">How, where and when the book will appear I cannot possibly say.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> Perhaps I will be utterly unable to find a
        publisher who will take it. The market is flooded with wretched little instrument handbooks,
        which all offer the same thing, each one repeating what the others say. My book presupposes
        a knowledge of the individual instruments and is concerned only with the <tei:pb n="3"/>
        leading aspects of the classical art of orchestration, viz. the doubling of voices; the
        transformation of a filler voice into a true one, and vice versa; tonal color, mixing of
        colors and register; balance, and <tei:hi rend="underline">synthetic</tei:hi> hearing; how
        one should listen; the role of the <tei:add place="interlinear-above">three</tei:add>
        principal groups of instruments in orchestral composition; clarity, etc.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Should the book ever appear in print, I shall request of you, i.e. of your
        publisher, permission to cite the passage in question.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">The translation of your <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001725"><tei:title
            level="m">Counterpoint</tei:title></tei:rs> was made available to <tei:pb n="4"/> my
        students by the distribution of many copies. All of them expressed their satisfaction with
        it. It is, however, impossible for me to exert my influence in this direction as widely as I
        would like, for the very subject of <tei:term>strict counterpoint</tei:term> is taught not
        by me but by a colleague of mine. This man commits precisely the same mistakes that you
        speak out against. He flirts, in fact, with free counterpoint and forbids, for
        instance,</tei:p>

      <!-- MUSIC EXAMPLE -->

      <tei:p rend="first">because these progressions appear to be disguised six-four harmonies! As a
        consequence, the pupils regard <tei:subst>
          <tei:del>free</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above"><tei:term>strict</tei:term></tei:add>
        </tei:subst>
        <tei:term>counterpoint</tei:term> as a test that has to be passed in necessary
        dimness.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="5"/> Many of the students are of the view that I should take
        over the elementary education, since they would then receive the correct understanding of
        it; unfortunately that is not possible.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I should frightfully like to get together with you and discuss all manner
        of problems. This year I am going with my <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000177"
          >wife</tei:rs> for two weeks to Spiekeroog (near Norderney).<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06"
          type="footnote"/> Next summer, however, we are definitely going to <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-003993">Bayreuth</tei:rs>. Perhaps we will then have the opportunity to
          <tei:pb n="6"/> discuss things face to face.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">With the most cordial greetings from us to you, </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">I remain</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">your entirely devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000178">John Petrie
            Dunn</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
