<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3353" sdoID="OJ-10-13_4">OJ 10/13, [4]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="JPD" scope="major">John Petrie Dunn's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="CH">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2007</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2007</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-23" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008413">DunnJP ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Dunn to Schenker, dated February 1, 1927</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1927-02-01T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-01-30</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>After a long silence, Dunn sends Schenker his abridged translation of
        Kontrapunkt, vol. 2, Parts III–IV, expresses regret that Hoboken’s illness prevented him
        from visiting, and hopes that they might meet up in London in June. </dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000178">DunnJP</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">
      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>42, Murrayfield
            Avenue,</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-70">Edinburgh.</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#JPD"/>den <tei:date when="1927-02-01">1.
            Februar, 1927</tei:date>.</tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>Sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Schenker</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt
            of Dunn’s abridged translation of Schenker’s <tei:title level="m"
              >Kontrapunkt</tei:title> is recorded in Schenker’s diary for February 4, 1927, and
            that of the letter for February 5, 1927: “Von Dunn das Buch! Es macht einen besseren
            Eindruck als das von Roth. — Von Dunn (Begleitbr.): die <tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000177">Frau</tei:rs> habe mitgeholfen; ersucht mich <tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000380">van H.</tei:rs> zu veranlassen, sich anzusagen, am einfachsten,
            wäre eine Begegnung in London, wo Dunn bei Gelegenheit der Beethoven-Woche vorträgt.”
            (“From Dunn, the book! It makes a better impression than that of Roth. — From Dunn
            (accompanying letter): his <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000177">wife</tei:rs> has
            helped him with it; <tei:supplied>he</tei:supplied> asks me to get <tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs> to accept his invitation; simplest would be a
            meeting in London, where Dunn lectures on the occasion of the Beethoven week.”). — This
            letter was published in English in <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Heinrich Schenker:
                Selected Correspondence</tei:title>, ed. <tei:editor>Ian Bent</tei:editor>,
                <tei:editor>David Bretherton</tei:editor>, and <tei:editor>William
                Drabkin</tei:editor> (Woodbridge, UK: The Boydell Press, 2014), pp.
              443–44</tei:bibl>.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ueber mein langes Schweigen werden Sie sich wohl einigermassen gewundert
        haben. Die Arbeit aber, die ich mir vorgenommen hatte, war viel mühsamer als ich erwartet
        hatte. Sie ist aber endlich vollbracht–, und deren Früchte habe ich Ihnen heute zugehen
        lassen, und zwar im Gestalt von einer kurzgefassten Bearbeitung und Uebersetzung des
        III.–IV. Abschnittes des <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001727">Bandes II<tei:hi
            rend="supralinear">2</tei:hi></tei:rs> Ihrer “<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001723"
            ><tei:title>Th. u. Ph</tei:title></tei:rs>.”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker reported to <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000143">Felix-Eberhard von Cube</tei:rs> in <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-5-7a_9">OJ 5/7a, [9]</tei:ref>, February 15, 1927: “Inzwischen ist auch die
          englische Übersetzung meines 3- u. 4stimm. Satzes aus der Feder Prof. John Petrie Dunn’s
          (Universität Edinburgh) erschienen.” (“In the meantime, the English translation of my
          three- and four-voice counterpoint, prepared by Professor John Petrie Dunn (University of
          Edinburgh), has appeared.”). He reported in similar terms to <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000913">Moriz Violin</tei:rs> in <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-6-7_32">OJ 6/7, [32]</tei:ref>, February 16, 1927. Dunn sent a copy of his
          abridged translation to Cube, who commented in <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-9-34_9">OJ 9/34, [9]</tei:ref>, October 29, 1927: “Die Adaptierung Dunns für
          den „Klassengebrauch“ kommt mir – unter uns – gelungener vor, als <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>s; sie ist vertiefter und mehr als eine blosse
          Zusammenfassung des Wesentlichen.” (“Between us: I think that the adaptation of Dunn's
          text for classroom use would meet with greater success than that of <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>'s: it gets deeper into the matter, and is more
          than a mere summary of the main points.”).</tei:note> Hoffentlich gefällt Ihnen <tei:pb
          n="2"/> mein Werkchen, auf dessen Vervielfältigung ich sowie meine <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000177">Frau</tei:rs> viel Zeit und Mühe verwendeten. Das Uebersetzen Ihres
        Buches war überaus schwierig, denn sein gedanklicher Inhalt ist grössenteils neu <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">und tief</tei:add> und stellt an den musikalischen Instinkt und
        die Einbildungskraft des Lesers keine geringen Anförderungen. Sprachlich war es ausserdem
        riesig schwer – </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Das Allerschwierigste, – so zum Beispiel die Begründung der
        Abwärtsauflösung des Vorhalts – musste ich notgedrungen weglassen. Ausserdem habe ich mir
        erlaubt, um es dem Verständnis des jungen Studenten leichter zu machen, einige elementare
        Erläuterungen mit einzuflechten und ich hoffe, dass das in Ihrem Sinne geschehen ist – </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> Es tat uns ausserordentlich leid, dass wir <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000380">Herrn van Hoboken</tei:rs> infolge seiner Krankheit nicht in unserem
        Hause sehen konnten. Wir hoffen aber, dass wir dieser Vergnügung später haben
          werden<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Hoboken explains the
          situation in a letter to Schenker, <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-11-54_12">OJ
            11/54, [12]</tei:ref>, January 28, 1927: “One of the purposes of my journey could not be
          achieved: the visit to Prof. Dunn in Edinburgh had to be canceled, because yesterday I was
          in bed with a fever and therefore could not travel in the evening. This was certainly a
          great pity. I had written him, and had received a letter of reply from him from which I
          could see that he still is greatly interested in your works. I will probably visit him
          this summer as I want to return to England then. Here I can obtain introductions to
          various private collections, and I don't want to fail to do that.”</tei:note> – </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Es würde mir sehr lieb sein, wenn mich <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000380">Herr van Hoboken</tei:rs> zur rechten Zeit von seinem Besuche
        benachrichtigen könnte, denn möglicherweise könnte ich ihn in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002643">London</tei:rs> sprechen, da ich <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >mich</tei:add> im Juni anlässlich eines Radio-Beethovenvortrags eine Woche <tei:pb n="4"
        /> lang in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002643">London</tei:rs> aufhalten muss.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Hoboken visited the Dunns in Edinburgh
          in September 1927, and in <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-11-54_18">OJ 11/54,
            [18]</tei:ref>, September 18, 1927, gave a very full report of John Petrie Dunn’s
          personality and extensive knowledge of Schenker’s writings, and his enthusiasm for his
          theories.</tei:note> –</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">In der Hoffnung, bald wieder von Ihnen zu hören, begrüsse ich Sie mit
        vorzüglicher Hochachtung.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Schenker’s acknowledgment of Dunn’s abridged translation and reply to his letter are
          recorded in his diary for February 13, 1927: “An Dunn (Br.): Dank für das Buch; gebe
          seiner Arbeit den Vorzug vor der von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000737"
            >Roth</tei:rs> wegen der größeren Genauigkeit. Ueberreiche mein Bild als Gegengeschenk.
          Hoboken werde sich melden.” (“To Dunn (letter): Thanks for the book; I give my preference
          to it over that of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000737">Roth</tei:rs> on account of
          its greater precision. I send <tei:supplied>him</tei:supplied> my portrait as a reciprocal
          present. Hoboken is expected to get in touch.”). — The work referred to is presumably
              <tei:bibl><tei:author>Herman Roth</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Elemente der
              Stimmführung</tei:title> (Stuttgart, 1926)</tei:bibl>. The portrait is the mezzotint
          of Schenker created by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000327">Viktor
          Hammer</tei:rs>.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Ihr ganz ergebener,</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000178">John Petrie
            Dunn</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>42, Murrayfield
            Avenue</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-70">Edinburgh</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#JPD"/><tei:date when="1927-02-01"
            >February 1, 1927</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>Dear Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">You will probably have wondered why I have been silent for such a long
        time; but the work that I undertook was much more strenuous than I had expected. It is,
        however, finally completed, and I have sent the fruits of my labours to you today,
        specifically in the form of an abbreviated adaptation and translation of Parts III and IV of
          <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001727">volume II/2</tei:rs> of your <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001723"><tei:title level="m">New Musical Theories and
          Fantasies</tei:title></tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> I hope
        that you will be pleased <tei:pb n="2"/> by my modest achievement, the preparation of
        multiple copies of which cost me and also my <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000177"
          >wife</tei:rs> a great deal of time and effort. Translating your book was especially
        difficult, for its conceptual content is, for the most part, new <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">and profound</tei:add> and makes no small demands on the
        reader’s musical instinct and powers of imagination. From a linguistic point of view as
        well, it was enormously difficult.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">The most difficult of all – for example, the justification for the
        downward resolution of the suspension – I was forced to omit. In addition, I took the
        liberty of weaving in a few elementary elucidations, to make it easier for our young
        students to understand; and I hope that I have done this in a manner that is compatible with
        your ideas.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> We were extremely sorry not to be able to see <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000380">Mr. van Hoboken</tei:rs> at our house, on account of his illness. But
        we hope that we will have this pleasure at a later time.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
          type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I would be most grateful if <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Mr.
          van Hoboken</tei:rs> could inform us in good time of his <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
          >next</tei:supplied> visit, since it might be possible for me to speak with him in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002643">London</tei:rs>, as I shall have to spend a week <tei:pb
          n="4"/> in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002643">London</tei:rs> on account of a radio
        lecture on Beethoven.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">In the hope that I shall hear from you again soon, I send you my most
        respectful greetings.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Your ever devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000178">John Petrie
            Dunn</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
