<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="380" sdoID="OJ-10-1_56">OJ 10/1, [56]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>
  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="WDa" scope="sole">Walter Dahms's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="JK">
   <tei:persName>John Koslovsky</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2010</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2010</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-05-05" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>

 </sdo:collectionDesc>
 <sdo:record ID="r0001">
  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002725">Dahms ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Dahms to Schenker, dated August 19, 1920</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1920-08-19T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2011-05-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Dahms is having difficulty obtaining a passport, but still hopes to see Schenker
    this summer, perhaps in Munich. — He sends his three biographical books to Schenker, but is
    apprehensive of the latter's reaction to their hemeneutic elements; he hopes to writes something
    more fitting.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Pass; passport; treffen; meeting; Manuskript; manuscript; Biographien; biographies;
    Heremeneutik; hermeneutics; Huldigung; homage</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000149">Dahms</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address rend="indent-40">
     <tei:addrLine>Gmain / Reichenhall</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:date when="1920-08-19">19. 8. 20.</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Lieber verehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>! </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
     this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/1, p. 2273, August 23, 1920: " Von Dahms
     (Br.): über Schwierigkeiten der Herreise; werde die Bücher per Post senden; kündigt eine
     Huldigung in der nächsten Arbeit an; fragt, ob er mich nicht in Salzburg treffen könnte. ("From
     Dahms (letter): about difficulties in traveling here; will send the books by mail; says the
     next book will include a homage; asks whether he couldn't meet me in Salzburg."). </tei:note>
    bin untröstlich in dem Gedanken, dass ich Sie möglicherweise in diesem Sommer garnicht sehen und
    Ihnen garnicht die Hand drücken kann. Und ich hätte es so nötig. Ich habe erhebliche
    Schwierigkeiten mit dem Pass; kann mich hier im Brief nicht näher darüber auslassen. Trotzdem
    mache ich morgen doch noch einen Versuch, um ohne Weiterungen und Unannehmlichkeiten zu meinem
    Ziel zu gelangen. Nur hoffe ich, Sie überhaupt noch zu treffen. Wollen Sie Ihren damals
    geäusserten Plan, das Manuskript des <tei:rs key="entity-001727" type="work"><tei:title>Contrapunktes</tei:title></tei:rs> persönlich zu <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002405">Cotta</tei:rs> zu bringen, verwirklichen?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker planned to take the manuscript of <tei:title level="m">Counterpoint
      2</tei:title> in person to Cotta in Stuttgart in September 1920 (CA 171), but in the end
     Vrieslander delivered the first section of it to them in October (CA 180, 181). </tei:note>
    Bitte, bitte, schreiben Sie mir dies. In dem Fall dürfte ich hoffen, Sie in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002286">München</tei:rs> wenigstens auf der Durchreise auf eine Stunde zu
    sehen, wo ich Ihnen vielleicht gar irgendwie behilflich sein könnte. Oder: fahren Sie zurück
    über <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002578">Salzburg</tei:rs>? Vielleicht könnte ich am
    Bahnhof sein und Sie bei der Durchfahrt begrüssen? </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Jedenfalls sehe ich morgen noch einmal wegen des Passes nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002304">Innsbruck</tei:rs> nach. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> Nun weiss ich nicht, was ich sagen soll, da Sie selbst,
    lieber Meister, den Wunsch nach meinen Biographien aussprechen. Ich habe bisweilen den Gedanken
    gehabt, Sie Ihnen zu schicken. Aber immer wieder sagte ich mir, dass dies unsinnig <tei:add place="interlinear-above">sei</tei:add>. Eine Hermeneutik, die Sie mit so überwältigendem Recht
    verneinen und erschlagen, die ich selbst seit dem Tage der <tei:del rend="overstrike">B</tei:del> ersten flüchtigen Bekanntschaft mit Ihren Werken verachte, — dürfte ich Ihnen mit
    einer solchen Hermeneutik unter die Augen treten?! Ich wage <tei:add place="interlinear-above">es</tei:add> nicht, diese Frage zu bejahen. Besonders schwer ist mir die Hermeneutik beim
     <tei:title>Mendelssohn</tei:title><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Walter Dahms</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Mendelssohn</tei:title> (Berlin &amp; Leipzig: Schuster &amp; Loeffler, 1919)</tei:bibl>.
    </tei:note> geworden; denn ich war ja immerhin schon <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>s Schüler. Das einzige Gute, was ich an den drei Büchern<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Three biographies by Dahms:
       <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Mendelssohn</tei:title> (Berlin &amp; Leipzig: Schuster &amp;
      Loeffler, 1919)</tei:bibl>; <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Schubert</tei:title> (Berlin &amp;
      Leipzig: Schuster &amp; Loeffler, 1912)</tei:bibl>; <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Schumann</tei:title> (Berlin &amp; Leipzig: Schuster &amp; Loeffler, 1916)</tei:bibl>. All
     three books were in Schenker's personal library at his death: <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Musik und Theater. Enthaltend die Bibliothek des Herrn Dr. Heinrich Schenker,
       Wien</tei:title> (Vienna: Heinrich Hinterberger [1936])</tei:bibl>. </tei:note> für mich in
    Anspruch nehme, ist die Gesinnung. Ich habe sie im Gefühl des Dienens für den Genius geschrieben
    – mit schwachen Kräften und – leider – untauglichen Mitteln, nämlich dem des beschreibenden,
    poetisierenden Wortes. Im <tei:title>Mendelssohn</tei:title> erlaubte ich mir an einer Stelle
    Ihren Namen zu nennen; ich hoffe aber jetzt über Winter in einem neuen Buch Ihnen meine
    Huldigung in würdigerer Form darbringen zu können. – Nun schicke ich die drei Bücher an Sie ab
    mit der Bitte, Sie freundlich entgegen zu nehmen. Aber dieser Bitte bedarf es wohl kaum; Sie
    haben schon so viel Güte und Nachsicht erwiesen. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihrem Sie stets vererhenden </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">ewig-dankbaren </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000149">Walter
     Dahms</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>


  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address rend="indent-40">
     <tei:addrLine>Großgmain near Reichenhall</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:date when="1920-08-19">August 19,
     1920</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dear revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Master</tei:rs>, </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">I<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> am saddened at the thought
    that I cannot see you at all or shake your hand this summer. And I felt it so necessary. I am
    having formidable difficulties with the passport; I cannot say anything more in this letter.
    Nevertheless I will make yet another attempt tomorrow to attain my goal without complications or
    discomfort. I only hope above all to meet you. Do you want to realize your expressed plan, to
    bring the <tei:rs key="entity-001727" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Counterpoint</tei:title></tei:rs> manuscript personally to <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002405">Cotta</tei:rs>?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> Please, please write to
    me on this matter. In this case I might hope to see you in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002286">Munich</tei:rs> for at least an hour during your stopover, where I could be perhaps of
    some assistance to you. Or, will you travel back through <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002578">Salzburg</tei:rs>? Maybe I could be at the railway station and greet you on your
    transit? </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In any case I will inquire tomorrow once again about the passport to
     <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002304">Innsbruck</tei:rs>. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> Now I don’t know what to say, since you yourself, dear
    master, express the wish for my biographies. I had the idea to send them to you. But I
    continually told myself that this <tei:add place="interlinear-above">would be</tei:add> absurd.
    A hermeneutic that you deny and strike down with such overwhelming correctness, and that I
    myself scorned since the first cursory acquaintance with your work, – ought I to confront you
    with such a hermeneutic?! I dare not answer this question in the affirmative. The hermeneutic in
     <tei:title level="m">Mendelssohn</tei:title><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/>
    has become particularly burdensome since I was after all already a student of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>. The one good thing that I claim for the three
     books<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> is the attitude. I wrote them with the
    feeling that I was serving genius – with weak energy and – unfortunately – with inappropriate
    means, especially with descriptive and poeticized words. In <tei:title level="m">Mendelssohn</tei:title> I allowed myself to mention your name in one place; I hope now during
    the winter to be able to offer a new book showing my homage to you in a more dignified way. –
    For now I send you the three books with the request that you accept them in a spirit of
    friendship. But this request is hardly necessary; you have already shown so much goodness and
    charity. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your ever-admiring, </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">ever-thankful </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000149">Walter
     Dahms</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>