<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">

  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="1488" sdoID="OJ-11-35-23">OJ 11/35, 23</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="AHa" scope="sole">August Halm's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="LR">
      <tei:persName>Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    
    <tei:respStmt xml:id="LR-IB">
      <tei:persName>Lee Rothfarb and Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Footnotes, 2006, 2015</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>  

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2015</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-04-12" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002698">Halm ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated April 6 and 15, 1925</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1925-04-15T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2015-05-18</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Halm explains why he has not written before and reports successful performance
        of his A major Symphony; wishes Schenker luck with move from UE to Drei-Masken Verlag;
        reports events at Freie Schulgemeinde.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Aufführung; performance; Probe; rehearsal; Übersiedlung; move; transfer; Kampf;
        battle; Lehrer; teacher; Gemeinschaftsleben; communal life</dc:subject>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000326">Halm</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1925-04-15">6<tei:add place="interlinear-above"
            >/15</tei:add>.IV.25</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber u. verehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Professor</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt
            of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/7, p. 2810, April 17, 1925: "Von
            Halm (Br.): berichtet über eine Aufführung seiner Sinfonie u. den Erfolg." ("From Halm
            (letter): he reports on a performance of his symphony and its
          success.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:div>
        <tei:p>Es ist mir immer wieder leid gewesen, daß ich Ihnen nicht schrieb. Die Zeit bis zu
          den Osterferien war in mancher Hinsicht ungünstig dafür; eine der Behinderungen aber war
          erfreulich: ich hatte die Aufführung meiner <tei:title>Adur-Sÿmphonie</tei:title>
          vorzubereiten, d.h. die Stimmen dazu zu schreiben. Am <tei:date when="1925-03-23"
            >23.</tei:date> war die Aufführung; Leonhardt in <tei:rs key="entity-002317"
            type="place">Stuttgart</tei:rs> dirigierte sie sehr gut, u. ich hatte, wenn auch schon
          in den vorhergehenden Proben, die größte Freude an dieser meiner Musik u. ihrem
            Klang.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">No paragraph-break at
            this point; but, from the slight gap, and the change of writing, this would appear to be
            the point at which Halm resumed the letter on April 15, after a nine-day
            break.</tei:note></tei:p>

        <tei:p>Zu Ihrer Übersiedlung in den neuen Verlag<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
            type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker moved from Universal Edition to
            Drei-Masken-Verlag of Munich in 1925, and published with them the three volumes of
                <tei:bibl><tei:title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:title> (1925, 1926,
              1930</tei:bibl>).</tei:note> wünsche ich Ihnen u. Ihren Lesern alles Gute; mögen die
          unnötigen zeit<tei:add place="interlinear-above">raubenden</tei:add> u. nervenaufreibenden
          Schwierigkeiten nun alle wegfallen u. nur die sachlich notwendige Mühe, der man sich ja
          gern unterzieht, übrig bleiben! Sie dürfen nicht denken, daß mir <tei:pb n="2"/> das
          Schicksal Ihrer Arbeit nicht am Herzen liegt, weil ich lang nicht schrieb. Ich hatte
          bewegte Zeit: Meine Pflichten in der <tei:rs key="entity-002459" type="organization"
            >Freien Schulgemeinde</tei:rs> hatten sich stark vermehrt u. außerdem war eine
          Übergangszeit mit mancherlei Kämpfen, die wir nun wohl als endgültig beseitigt ansehen
          dürfen; eine Gruppe von Lehrern hat hier eine Neugründung an der Nordsee auf der Insel
          Jüst vorbereitet u. ist nun zu Ostern abgezogen. Die Trennung sollte in
          kamaradschaftlicher Gesinnung vor sich gehen; trotzdem war es eine starke Belastung
          unseres Gemeinschaftslebens. Die wenige freie Zeit mußte ich dazu verwenden, die Stimmen
          einer Sÿmphonie auszuschreiben, die Professor Leonhardt in <tei:rs key="entity-002317"
            type="place">Stuttgart</tei:rs> ‒ —ja das schrieb ich ja schon, wie ich eben sehe. Dann
          kam noch ein Jugendtagung in <tei:rs key="entity-003044" type="place">Halle</tei:rs>, von
          der ich gestern zurückkehrte.</tei:p>

        <tei:p>Hat sich Professor <tei:rs key="entity-000674" type="person">Pollak</tei:rs>
          einstweilen ein- <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">remainder cut
          off</tei:note></tei:p>
      </tei:div>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">written vertically in the left margin,
            top to bottom:</tei:note> Herzlichen Gruß von Ihrem</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000326" type="person">A.
          Halm</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1925-04-15">April 6 <tei:add place="interlinear-above">and
              15</tei:add>, 1925</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear and revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Professor</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:div>
        <tei:p>I regret time and again that I have not written you. The period up until Easter was
          in various regards inconvenient for it. One of the obstacles was heartening. I had to
          prepare for the performance of my <tei:title>A major Symphony</tei:title>, i.e. to write
          out the parts for it. The performance was on the <tei:date when="1925-03-23"
            >23rd.</tei:date> Leonhardt in <tei:rs key="entity-002317" type="place"
            >Stuttgart</tei:rs> conducted it very well, and I had the greatest joy from the music
          and its sound, even in the preceding rehearsals.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
            type="footnote"/></tei:p>

        <tei:p>I wish you and your readers the best on your move to the new publisher.<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> May unnecessary, time<tei:add
            place="interlinear-above">-consuming</tei:add> and nerve-wracking difficulties all
          vanish now, and only the substantively necessary effort remain! You should not think that
            <tei:pb n="2"/> the fate of your work is not on my mind because I have not written in so
          long. I had a busy time. My obligations in the <tei:rs key="entity-002459"
            type="organization">Free School Community</tei:rs> had increased considerably, and
          furthermore there was a transitional period with various conflicts that we may now view as
          definitively over and done with. A group of teachers had prepared for establishing a new
          school on the North Sea island of Jüst, and withdrew at Easter. The separation was
          supposed to take place with a collegial attitude. Despite that, it was a heavy burden on
          our communal life. I had to use the little free time to write out the parts of a symphony
          that Professor Leonhardt in <tei:rs key="entity-002317" type="place">Stuttgart</tei:rs> ‒
          oh, I wrote that already as I now see. Then, there was a youth conference in <tei:rs
            key="entity-003044" type="place">Halle</tei:rs>, from which I returned yesterday. Did
          Professor <tei:rs key="entity-000674" type="person">Pollak</tei:rs> in the meantime
            <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">remainder cut off</tei:note></tei:p>

        <tei:p> </tei:p>
      </tei:div>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">written vertically in the left margin,
            top to bottom:</tei:note> Cordial greetings from your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000326" type="person">A.
          Halm</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>
    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
