<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3878" sdoID="OJ-13-10_166">OJ 13/10, [166]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2025</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated April 27, 1933</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1933-04-27T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-12-08</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel discusses the consecutive fifths in Beethoven’s Quartet Op. 74. -- He
        has been reading books on music by Güldenstein (which discusses Schenker) and Achtélik,
        neither of which he can recommend. -- A pupil of his has compiled a list of Schenkerian
        terms and hopes to present them in a radio broadcast.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1933-04-27">27 IV 3<tei:subst>
              <tei:del rend="overstrike">1</tei:del>
              <tei:add place="interlinear-above">3</tei:add>
            </tei:subst></tei:date>.</tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Professor Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
            >Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for April 29, 1933: “Von Oppel
            (Br.): Dank für Brahms; über ein Buch von Güldenstein, in dem sich der Autor auch mit
            mir auseinandersetzt; über die vortreffliche Analyse eines Schülers, in meinem Sinne
            verfaßt” (“From Oppel (letter): thanks for Brahms; concerning a book by Güldenstein, in
            which the author takes issue with me; concerning an excellent analysis by one of his
            pupils, made according to my principles”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>herzlichen Dank für die <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-003331">Brahms 5 u 8
          Studie</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Oppel had been
          engaged since August 1929 (see <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-13-10_82">OJ 13/10,
            [82]</tei:ref> and subsequent correspondence) in a close examination for Schenker of
          Brahms’s study of parallel 5ths and octaves in music of the 16th to 19th centuries.
          Oppel’s work is nowhere acknowledged in the 1933 publication.</tei:note> Ich habe mich
        sehr gefreut, dass diese Arbeit nun allgemein zugänglich ist. Bei <tei:rs type="composition"
          key="entity-004643">Beeth op 74</tei:rs> gibt <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000013"
          >Altmann</tei:rs> in d. kl. Eulenburgpartitur tatsächlich f im Cello an, eine schlechte
        Correctur, denn der Sinn ist u. bleibt doch <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">music
          example</tei:note>, während <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">music
          example</tei:note> f 2mal dem g das gewollte Übergewicht schmälern würde.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">The two music examples reproduce the
          cello part of Beethoven’s Quartet in E<tei:g type="flat"/>, Op. 74, first movement, bars
          94–96 of the cello part. In the first example, Oppel has simplified the part to show the
          preponderance of a bass G (as the dominant of C); in the second, he reproduces the passage
          in Altmann’s edition, in which the first note of bar 95 is given as F, thus removing the
          parallel fifths between the first violin and cello. (The first edition of Op. 74 and the
          old and new Beethoven collected editions all give G.) </tei:note> – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich hätte längst wieder geschrieben, aber auch Ostern sass ich in Arbeit. Die Partei
        verschlingt viel Zeit, u. ich musste, um klar zu sehn u. zu handeln, die Vorgeschichte
        unsrer <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002872">Anstalt</tei:rs> studieren seit der
        Gründung durch <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008291">Mendelssohn</tei:rs> 1843.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">By “Partei”, Oppel almost certainly
          means the National Socialists, although he does not say so explicitly, nor does his remark
          confirm that he was actually a member of the Nazi Party at the time. In a letter written
          three weeks later, <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-13-10_167">OJ 13/10,
            [167]</tei:ref>, May 21, 1933, he tells Schenker he is working in a “cell” that is
          tasked with writing – or rewriting? – the history of the Leipzig Conservatory, which had
          been founded 90 years before by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008291">Felix
            Mendelssohn</tei:rs>, who was Jewish by birth. Cf. <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-13-10_172">OJ 13/10, [172]</tei:ref>, July 6, 1933, in which he expresses
          approval of Hitler.</tei:note> Verwaltungstechnische u. rechtliche Fragen u.
        Schwierigkeiten harren noch der Lösung u. alles geht bei dem Riesenandrang zur Partei
        langsam, sehr langsam. – Von <tei:hi rend="underline">Gustav Güldenstein</tei:hi> erschien
        ein Buch „<tei:title>Theorie der Tonart</tei:title>“ im Verlag E. Klett, Stuttgart, in dem
        er sich im Kapitel VII (die <tei:term>Chromatik</tei:term>) S. 159–174 auch mit Ihnen
          auseinandersetzt;<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot"
              ><tei:bibl><tei:author>Gustav Güldenstein</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Theorie
              der Tonart</tei:title> (Stuttgart: Klett, 1920)</tei:bibl>; a second edition appeared
          in 1928. Güldenstein (1888–1972) taught music theory at the Basel Conservatory (now the
          City of Basel Music Academy) from 1921 to 1953.</tei:note> ich bitte Sie, hauen Sie dem
        Waisenknaben gelegentlich eine kräftige Ohrfeige herunter. – Mein Schüler <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000299">Goos</tei:rs> hat mir neulich eine grosse Freude
        bereitet: er hat eine vorzügliche <tei:term>Analyse</tei:term> vom Präludium <tei:pb n="2"/>
        der <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-003252">Suite C-dur für Cello solo v.
          Bach</tei:rs> geliefert; ausserdem hatte er aus Ihren Werken „Schenkerworte“
        zusammengestellt, um sie beim Rundfunk in der „nationalen“ Stunde anzubringen. Hoffentlich
        gelingt es ihm. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005266">Meiner Frau</tei:rs> u. den <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-004801">Kindern</tei:rs> geht’s gut. – Wie ich aus den
        Anmerkungen ersah, ist der „<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title>fr
            S</tei:title></tei:rs>“ drückfertig. Und ich schreie dazu dreimal kräftig: Hurrah! Dann
        kommt er im Herbst wohl noch heraus? – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Leider las ich gestern u. heute von Josef Achtélik „<tei:title>der Naturklang als
          Wurzel aller Harmonien</tei:title>“ (Kahnt <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >1922</tei:add> – Leipzig).<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Josef Achtélig (1881–1965), German composer and choral conductor, was appointed to this
          post in 1933, the year in which he joined the Nazi Party.</tei:note> Übel, gänzlich
        verfehlt einseitig harmonisch. Verlorene Zeit. Aber da der Mann hier Vorsitzender des
        Reichsverbandes deutscher Tonkünstler ist, hielt ich für meine Pflicht, mir sein krummes
        Gewächs einmal anzusehn. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wie steht es mit Ihren Sommerplänen? Wollen Sie wieder nach <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>? Ich hoffe, dass ich diesmal wieder in die Berge
        komme, obwohl die Geldfrage noch sehr in schwarzen Wolken hängt; aber nach diesem scharfen
        Winter brauche ich eine gründliche Erholung. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Alles Gute u. die herzlichsten Grüsse</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Ihnen beiden von uns allen!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr treuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1933-04-27">April 27, 193<tei:subst>
              <tei:del rend="overstrike">1</tei:del>
              <tei:add place="interlinear-above">3</tei:add>
            </tei:subst></tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor
            Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Cordial thanks for <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-003331">Brahms’s study of
          consecutive fifths and octaves</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> I
        am very glad that this work is now generally available. In <tei:rs type="composition"
          key="entity-004643">Beethoven’s Op. 74</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000013"
          >Altmann</tei:rs> actually gives F in the cello part: a poor correction, since the sense
        of the passage is always <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">music example</tei:note>
        whereas in <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">music example</tei:note> the twofold
        repetition of F would diminish the intended predominance of G.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
          type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>I would have written again long ago, but I was stuck in work even over Easter. The
        Party consumes much of my time; and, in order to see and deal with things clearly, I had to
        study the prehistory of our <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002872"
          >institution</tei:rs> since its founding by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008291"
          >Mendelssohn</tei:rs> in 1843.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/>
        Administrative-technical and judicial questions and difficulties await a solution, and
        everything goes slowly, very slowly, under the gigantic pressure towards the Party. – A book
        by <tei:hi rend="underline">Gustav Güldenstein</tei:hi>, <tei:title level="m">Theory of
          Key</tei:title>, has been published by Klett in Stuttgart, in which the author even
        discusses your work, in Chapter 7 (“<tei:term>Chromaticism</tei:term>”), pp. 159–74;<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> please give this orphan boy a good cuff around the
        ears sometime. – My pupil <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000299">Goos</tei:rs> has
        recently given me great pleasure: he has supplied an excellent <tei:term>analysis</tei:term>
        of the Prelude <tei:pb n="2"/> from the <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-003252">C
          major Suite for solo cello by Bach</tei:rs>; in addition, he has put together a collection
        of “Schenker words” from your writings, so that he can introduce them on the radio in the
        “national” hour. I hope that he will succeed.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005266">My wife</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-004801">children</tei:rs> are well – As I saw from the notices, <tei:rs
          type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title level="m">Free Composition</tei:title></tei:rs>
        is ready to go to press. And for this I shout three times: Hurrah! So, it will probably be
        published in the autumn?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Unfortunately, I read from Josef Achtélik’s <tei:title level="m">The Chord of Nature as
          the Root of All Harmonies</tei:title> (Leipzig: Kahnt, <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >1922</tei:add>) yesterday.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> Bad: totally,
        mistakably and one-sidedly harmonic. A waste of time. But as the man is the local chairman
        of the Imperial Association of German Musicians, I regarded it as my duty to have a look at his
        fraudulent production. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>How are your summer plans shaping up? Are you hoping to go to <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs> again? I hope that I can get to the mountains again
        this time, although the question of money still hangs very much in dark clouds. After this
        harsh winter, however, I need a thorough recovery.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>All good wishes, and the most cordial greetings </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">to the two of you from all of us!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
