<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="1003" sdoID="OJ-14-45_69">OJ 14/45, [69]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="MV" scope="sole">Moriz Violin's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
      <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-07-13" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002719">ViolinM ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM+V ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002718">ViolinM+V+F ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Violin to Schenker, dated December 27, 1927</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1927-12-27T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2013-07-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Violin reports that his concert (cello recital) has been put back a week
        because of a tendon problem in his left hand. He owes Otto Vrieslander a response to his
        recent written work, but he feels that Vrieslander does not truly understand Schenker's
        cause, does not have the same "orientation" towards it as he, and expresses himself poorly.
        (Weisse, he says, could have done things better.) However, all this pettiness is nothing
        compared with the achievement of Meisterwerk 2, and of the "crowning" work that will soon
        follow.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>


    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-35"><tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>,
            <tei:date when="1927-12-27">27. Dez. 27</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Liebster <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this
            letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/1, p. 3160 (December 29, 1927): "Von Fl.
            (Br.): endlich ein heiterer Brief! Zunächst bringt er Neujahrswünsche dar, dann spricht
            er sich über Vrieslanders Nicht-Eignung zum Hauptpropagandisten aus – seine Schreibweise
            eigne sich mehr für einen Wagner-Apostel als gerade für mich." ("From Floriz (letter):
            finally, a cheerful letter! To start with, he sends New Year's greetings, then he speaks
            about Vrieslander's unsuitability as principal propagandist – his manner of writing is
            more appropriate for an apostle of Wagner than for me particularly.")</tei:note>
        </tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Heute dienstfrei! Ich benütze den Tag Dir u. Frau <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">LieLie</tei:rs> alles Schöne für’s <tei:date when="1928-01-01">neue Jahr</tei:date> zu wünschen. Leider hatte ich u. habe ich in der
        linken Hand eine unangenehme Sehnengeschichte. Offenbar auf rheumatsicher Basis. Ich mache
        Schlamm (Radium) Umschläge. Das Konzert<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">A recital of cello sonatas by <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs> (<tei:rs key="entity-004796" type="composition">Op. 102</tei:rs>)
          and <tei:rs key="entity-000129" type="person">Chopin</tei:rs> (<tei:rs key="entity-004795" type="composition">Op. 65</tei:rs>), mentioned in Violin's previous letter, <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-45_68">OJ 14/45, [68]</tei:ref>.</tei:note> ist auf
        dem <tei:date when="1928-01-14">14<tei:hi rend="supralinear">ten</tei:hi></tei:date>
        verschoben. Hoffentlich ist bis dahin alles gut, sonst werde ich rechts anständig u. links
        schäbig spielen – – – für Dinge die gottlob noch den Baß kennen, – – ein großes Übel! Aber
        das wird <tei:hi rend="underline">man</tei:hi> nicht merken.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs> schulde ich
        noch eine Antwort. Für sie muss ich viel Zeit haben, um sie ihn das Richtige zu sagen.
        Praktisch war die sofortige Antwort nicht nötig, denn ich könnte ihm kaum eine Adresse
        nennen, mit der ich nicht in persönlicher Fühlung hin u. die nicht schon, in meiner Weise,
        orientiert wäre. Meine Orientierungen gesehen mit <tei:hi rend="underline">viel</tei:hi>
        Stolz u Nachdruck, daß kannst Du mir, Liebster, glauben. Damit komme ich auf den Kern meiner
        Bedenken. Ich finde ja richtig u. vor allem rührend, was er in seiner Treue macht u. daß
        überhaupt etwas geschieht. Ich kann nur nicht umhin in seinen Qualitäten, Dir u. Deinem
        Werke gegenüber, nicht ganz genügendes zu finden. <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans Weisse</tei:rs>, dieser menschliche Schwindeling, könnte das besser. <tei:pb n="2"/>
        <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs> „spuckt u. räuspert“ nur!
        Sein Deutsch passte mir auch eher zu <tei:rs key="entity-000924" type="person">Wagner</tei:rs> als zu Dir! Mißverstehe mich nur nicht. Ging alles vom Verleger aus, so
        wäre es nur die gesunde geschäftliche Dosis der Reklame u. halte es nicht für Arroganz, daß
        ich bei <tei:hi rend="underline">mir</tei:hi> die Empfindung hege, daß ein nicht genügend
          <tei:hi rend="underline">Fundierter</tei:hi> Deine Sache in die Hand nahm. Schließlich u.
        endlich schreibe ich <tei:hi rend="underline">Dir</tei:hi> diese <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#MV"><tei:hi rend="underline">alle</tei:hi></tei:del> nur, um Dir begreiflich zu
        machen, wie schwer mir die Antwort fällt, wo ich doch <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">V</tei:rs>’s<tei:note type="editorial">corr</tei:note> rührende u. rührige
        Treue in diesem Briefe nur unterstutzen u. teilen möchte.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Je länger ich Dein <tei:rs key="entity-001751" type="work">27<tei:hi rend="supralinear">er</tei:hi> Jahrbuch</tei:rs> lese, deste mehr empfinde ich, daß
        alles gut ist was geschieht, daß meine Qualitäts-Kleinlichkeitskrämerei nur vor mir eine
        Rolle spielt – – –, daß alles <tei:hi rend="underline">Wurst</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">ist</tei:hi>, – – weil das <tei:hi rend="underline">Jahrbuch</tei:hi> da ist u. die Krönung des ganzen noch kommt.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Also warum schrieb ich Dir’s doch?</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-25">Innigstes von Uns an Euch!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Dein treuester</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-35"><tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>,
            <tei:date when="1927-12-27">December 27, 1927</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dearest <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
        </tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Today is a free day! I am using the day to send you and <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Lie</tei:rs> all good wishes for the <tei:date when="1928-01-01">New Year</tei:date>. Unfortunately I have suffered, and still suffer,
        from an unpleasant problem with a tendon in my left hand. Apparently a rheumatic condition.
        I am getting mud (radium) compresses. The concert<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> has been postponed until the <tei:date when="1928-01-14">14th</tei:date>. I hope that by then everything is okay, otherwise I shall play respectably
        with my right hand and raggedly with my left – for things that, thank God, still understand
        the bass line – a great affliction! But <tei:hi rend="underline">the audience</tei:hi> will
        not notice it.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I still owe <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs>
        a reply. I shall need much time for it, so that I can say the right things for him. In
        practice, an immediate reply was unnecessary, for I could hardly come up with a formulation
        for someone with whom I was not in complete sympathy and who was orientated to my way of
        thinking. My orientation, viewed with <tei:hi rend="underline">much</tei:hi> pride and
        emphasis: that is something that you, dearest friend, can believe. And with this I come to
        the heart of my concerns. While I am indeed happy, and even touched, by what he does in good
        faith, and glad that something happens at all, I just cannot manage to find something
        entirely satisfying about his qualities, with respect to you and your work. <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans Weisse</tei:rs>, that fraudster of a fellow, could
        do it better. <tei:pb n="2"/>
        <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs> only spits and clears his
        throat, so to speak! His German also seems to me more appropriate to <tei:rs key="entity-000924" type="person">Wagner</tei:rs> than to you! Please do not misunderstand
        me. If everything were done according to the publisher's designs, then it would be only the
        healthy business-like dosage of advertisement. And do not take it for arrogance that I
        harbor the feeling that an insufficiently <tei:hi rend="underline">well-versed
          person</tei:hi> took your cause on board. In the end, I am writing these things <tei:hi rend="underline">to you</tei:hi> only so that you can understand how difficult it is for
        me merely respond, though I should still want my letter to show support for and share in
          <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs>'s touching and enterprising
        faith.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">The longer I read your <tei:rs key="entity-001751" type="work">Yearbook
          for 1927</tei:rs>, the more I feel that everything that is happening is good, that my
        petty criticisms about quality are of use only to me – that it doesn't make a bit of
        difference – since the <tei:hi rend="underline">Yearbook</tei:hi> is out and the crowning
        work is still to come.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">So, why did I still write to you about this?</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-25">Most intimate greetings from us to the two of you!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your most faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>