<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="1005" sdoID="OJ-14-45_71">OJ 14/45, [71]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="MV" scope="major">Moriz Violin's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
      <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-07-14" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002719">ViolinM ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM+V ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002718">ViolinM+V+F ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Moriz Violin to Schenker, dated July 18, 1928</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1928-07-18T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2013-07-14</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Owing to a "complete breakdown," Violin is recovering at a sanatorium in
        Schierke, from where he writes. In response to Schenker's previous postcard, Violin had
        written more than once to Prof. [Fritz?] Stein for the return of the manuscript of a Handel
        arrangement by Schenker, and he will chase him up in August. A pupil of his, Harry Hahn, has
        taken upon himself to lecture on Schenker's theories at the local society of composers; for
        this he has prepared classroom-size enlargements of voice-leading graphs of a Bach prelude
        and a Schubert waltz, and has proved a surprisingly competent and persuasive
        speaker.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>


    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:note type="editorial">printed letterhead of the <tei:rs key="entity-004797" type="organization">Sanatorium Schierke</tei:rs></tei:note><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">The complete text of the printed letterhead, which is
          centred at the top of the first page of the letter, reads: "Sanatorium Schierke / Chefarzt
          Dr. R. F. Weiß / Telegramm-Addresse: Sanatorium Schierke – Fernsprecher: Amt Schierke Nr.
          29 und 30 / Bank-Konto: Städtische Sparkasse Wernigerode – Postscheck-Konto: Magdeburg Nr.
          2315 / — / Das ganze Jahr geöffnet".</tei:note><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#printed"/><tei:rs key="entity-004587" type="place">Schierke</tei:rs> im <tei:rs key="entity-004800" type="place">Harz</tei:rs>, den <tei:date when="1928-07-18"><tei:handShift new="#MV"/>18. Juli
              <tei:handShift new="#printed"/>19<tei:handShift new="#MV"/>28</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Mein liebster <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this
            letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/1, p. 3229 (July 20, 1928): "Von Floriz
            (Br. aus dem Sanatorium Schierke): erzählt von seinem Zusammenbruch, von der
            Hilfsbereitschaft seines Schwagers Julo; wird Prof. Stein zur Rücksendung des
            Manuscripts veranlassen. Ein Schüler von ihm, Harry Hahn, der einen Tonkünstler-Verband
            leitet, gibt sich mit der Urlinie ab, zu welchem Zweck er Tafeln aus den Jahrbuchern
            vergrößert vorführt." ("From Floriz (letter from the hospital in Schierke): he writes
            about his breakdown, of the generosity of his brother-in-law Julo; he will ask Prof.
            Stein to return the manuscript. A pupil of his, Harry Hahn, who leads a society of
            composers, devotes himself to the Urlinie, to which purposes he presents enlargements of
            graphs from my Yearbooks.")</tei:note>
        </tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich wollte postwendend Deine l. Karte<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-8-4_55">= OJ 8/4, [55]</tei:ref> (Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000851" type="person">Stein</tei:rs>) beantworten. Ich wurde aber gar plötzlich von einem völligen
        Zusammenbruch überraschend. <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">Vally</tei:rs> schrieb
        in ihrer argen Not an ihren Bruder <tei:rs key="entity-004775" type="person">Julo</tei:rs>,
        der mir gleich telegraphisch das Geld sandte, mit welchem ich im Stande bin, mich hier
        notwendigerweise aufbügeln zu lassen. Es wird alles wieder gut werden. Ich sehe alles so an,
        wie ich es ansehen muss u. bin deshalb auch ganz ruhig u. hoffe, daß diese Mittheilung auch
        Dir keine Secunde trüben wird.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Mit Prof <tei:rs key="entity-000851" type="person">Stein</tei:rs> geht es
        mir, wie es einem immer mit aufgeblasenen Existenzen ergeht. Du ahnst nicht <tei:hi rend="underline">wie</tei:hi> er mir nachlief, um <tei:pb n="2"/> 1) Deine <tei:rs key="entity-000329" type="person">Händel</tei:rs>-Sache durch mich in Ordnung bringen zu
        lassen u. 2) durch mich die Vortragsidee fördern zu lassen. Gleich nach meiner Rückkunft von
          <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs>, schrieb ich ihm 1 Brief <tei:hi rend="underline">u.</tei:hi> 1 Karte in all dieser Angelgegenheit – – – Ich bin bis
          <tei:hi rend="underline">heute</tei:hi> ohne Antwort. Ich werde den Herrn schon erwischen.
        Wegen Deines Manuskripts will ich ihm kurz u. fordernd im <tei:hi rend="double-underline">August</tei:hi> erst schreiben. Da dürfte er, wie alle Menschen, schon zurück von seinen
        Sommerurlaub sein. Jetzt könnte zu leicht eine Nachsendeschiebung für ihn möglich werden u.
        ich will ihm nur Gelegenheit geben, die Rücksendung Deines Manuskripts <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#MV">nur</tei:add> auf Grund meiner Anforderung erfolgen
        zu lassen. Damit bist Du doch einverstanden.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Kurz vor den Ferien, erlebte ich eine sehr nette Affaire u. die
        Mittheilung derselben <tei:pb n="3"/> verzögerte sich ebenfalls durch meine
        Erkrankung.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich habe einen Schüler <tei:rs key="entity-000321" type="person">Harry
          Hahn</tei:rs>, mit dem ich beim Unterricht seit einem Jahr nur über Kunst u. weniger über
        sein nicht gerade zukunftsreiches Klavierspiel sprach. Er ist Leiter einer
        Arbeitsgemeinschaft des hiesigen <tei:rs key="entity-002951" type="organization">Tonkünstlerverbandes</tei:rs>. Innerhalb dieser Gemeinschaft verzapfte er sein Wissen um
          <tei:rs key="entity-000712" type="person">Riemann</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000495" type="person">Kurt<tei:supplied reason="spelling">h</tei:supplied></tei:rs>,
          <tei:term>Ästhetik</tei:term>, <tei:term>Pädagogik</tei:term>, Jugendbewegung u. Tod u.
        Teufel. Ich nahm ihn sehr her u. spannte ihn intensivst in<tei:note type="editorial">corr</tei:note> die Arbeit Deiner Werke ein. Plötzlich überrascht er mich u. hält am
          <tei:date when="1928-06-27">27 Juni</tei:date> einen Vortrag über die
          <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> in der Arbeitsgemeinschaft an. Ich schlug die Hände über den
        Kopf zusammen u. frug ihn wie er sich das vorstelle? Verbieten könnte ich es ihm nicht, denn
        Deine erschienenen Werke sind öffentliches Gut u. solches ist eben – – vogelfrei. Ich ging
        auf seinen Wunsch in den Vortrag u. benahm mich wie der amerikanische <tei:pb n="4"/>
        Beobachter beim <tei:rs key="entity-004743" type="organization">Völkerbund</tei:rs>. Wie es
        auch naturgemäß beschränkt, war – – ich war freudig überrascht, wie <tei:hi rend="underline">geschickt</tei:hi> er es immerhin im Begrifflichen machte, was ich schon daran festellen
        konnte, weil aus dem Auditorium schon <tei:hi rend="underline">sehr</tei:hi> kluge Fragen
        gestellt wurden. Im Herbst wollen sie weitermachen. Lass sie man – wie man hier sagt –; ich
        finde es sehr erfreulich. Ein <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person">Bach</tei:rs>-Praeludium u. ein <tei:rs key="entity-000803" type="person">Schubert</tei:rs>-Walzer in Deiner Urlinienprovenienz, hat er in Schultafelumfang
        vergrößern lassen. Dies schaute bildschön aus. Diese 2 sauberen Exemplare schicke ich Dir im
          <tei:date when="1928-08">August</tei:date> noch nach <tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Nun genug; vor allem leider für mich!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-15">Seid Beide innigst gegrüßt.</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Alles Schöne!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-65">Dein getreuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:note type="editorial">printed letterhead of the <tei:rs key="entity-004797" type="organization">Sanatorium Schierke</tei:rs></tei:note><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#printed"/><tei:rs key="entity-004587" type="place">Schierke</tei:rs> in the <tei:date when="1928-07-18"><tei:rs key="entity-004800" type="place">Harz</tei:rs>, <tei:handShift new="#MV"/>July 18
              <tei:handShift new="#printed"/>19<tei:handShift new="#MV"/>28</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">My dearest <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/>
        </tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">I was hoping to answer your lovely postcard<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-8-4_55">= OJ 8/4, [55]</tei:ref>, concerning Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000851" type="person">Stein</tei:rs>, by return of post. But I was suddenly overcome by a complete
        breakdown. In deepest desperation, <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">Vally</tei:rs>
        wrote to her brother <tei:rs key="entity-004775" type="person">Julo</tei:rs>, who wired me
        the money with which I have been able to get myself sorted out here, as necessary. Things
        will turn out all right. I look at all things in the way I must look at them and am
        therefore also quite at peace; and I hope that this communication will not dampen your
        spirits for a moment, either.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">My relationship with Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000851" type="person">Stein</tei:rs> is the same as I would have with any puffed-up being. You have no idea
          <tei:hi rend="underline">how</tei:hi> he pursued me, so that <tei:pb n="2"/> 1) he could,
        with my help, put your <tei:rs key="entity-000329" type="person">Handel</tei:rs> materials
        in order, and 2) use me to help promote a possible performance. Immediately after I returned
        from <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>, I wrote a letter <tei:hi rend="underline">and</tei:hi> a postcard about the entire matter – – – <tei:hi rend="underline">To this day</tei:hi> I have not received a reply. Somehow I'll catch up
        with the fellow. With regard to your manuscript, I shall not write until <tei:hi rend="double-underline">August</tei:hi>, curtly and insistently. By then he should have
        returned, like everyone else, from his summer holiday. At this moment, it would be too easy
        for him to fiddle things with the forwarding; and I will only give him an opportunity to
        return the manuscript <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#MV">only</tei:add> on the
        basis of a request from me. On this you will surely be in agreement.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Shorly before the holidays, I had a very nice experience; and the
        communication of it <tei:pb n="3"/> was likewise delayed by my illness.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I have a pupil by the name of <tei:rs key="entity-000321" type="person">Harry Hahn</tei:rs>, with whom I have been for a year speaking with him in his lessons
        only about art and less about his not exactly promising piano playing. He is the leader of a
        worker's community of the <tei:rs key="entity-002951" type="organization">local society of
          composers</tei:rs>. Within this community, he babbled his wisdom about <tei:rs key="entity-000712" type="person">Riemann</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000495" type="person">Kurth</tei:rs>, <tei:term>aesthetics</tei:term>,
          <tei:term>pedagogy</tei:term>, youth movement, and death and damnation. I gave him a good
        talking-to, and encouraged him most intensively in the study of your works. Suddenly he
        surprised me, saying that he would be giving a lecture on <tei:date when="1928-06-27">June
          27</tei:date> about the <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> in the worker's community. I threw my
        hands up in horror and asked him how he could imagine doing such a thing. I could not
        prevent him, since your published works are available to all, and so they are indeed – –
        fair game. At his invitation, I went to the lecture, behaving like the American <tei:pb n="4"/> observer at the <tei:rs key="entity-004743" type="organization">League of
          Nations</tei:rs>. As limited as it naturally was, I was pleasantly surprised by how
          <tei:hi rend="underline">skilfully</tei:hi> he managed to do this from the conceptual
        point of view, something that I was able to confirm from the fact that <tei:hi rend="underline">very</tei:hi> intellegent questions were asked by members of the
        audience. In the autumn, they want to go further. "Let them go ahead," as we say here: I
        find it very gratifying. He took a <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person">Bach</tei:rs>
        prelude and a <tei:rs key="entity-000803" type="person">Schubert</tei:rs> waltz from your
        source of <tei:term>Urlinie graphs</tei:term> and had them enlarged to the dimensions of a
        schoolroom blackboard. These looked very attractive. I shall send you these two clear
        examples to <tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs> in <tei:date when="1928-08">August</tei:date>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Enough for now; above all, unfortunately, for me!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-15">Most intimate greetings to the two of you.</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">All good wishes!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-65">Your faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>