<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="2744" sdoID="OJ-14-1_5">OJ 14/1, [5]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="FH" scope="sole">Felix Hupka's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="HeS-IDB">
   <tei:persName>Hedi Siegel &amp; Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2009, 2022</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2009, 2022</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2022</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-11-08" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008179">HupkaF ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Felix Hupka to Schenker, dated November 18, 1921</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1921-11-18T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2022-04-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Hupka reports on his latest concert, in Munich. Otto Vrieslander and Herman Roth
    were present, and Hupka reports their critical reactions to his program. He visited the home of
    Paul Hirsch.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>

   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000399">FHupka</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-75"><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002495">Frankfurt</tei:rs>
     <tei:date when="1921-11-18">18/XI 1921</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
      >Professor</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">This letter is
      misfiled among the items from Felix Salzer to Schenker, in folder OJ 14/1. — Receipt of this
      letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for November 22, 1921: "Von Hupka (Br. aus Frankfurt):
      über das Konzert in München; Vrieslander habe während Brahms-Händel-Variationen den Saal
      verlassen; ein starker Hustenreiz habe die Leistung beeinträchtigt. ("From Hupka (letter from
      Frankfurt): about the concert in Munich; Vrieslander left the hall during the Brahms-Handel
      Variations; a severe throat tickle spoilt the performance."). On the previous day, Schenker
      recorded: "Von Vrieslander (Br.): über Hoboken u. Roth; habe bei Hertzka urgirt u. Hupka im
      Konzert schlecht gefunden." ("From Vrieslander (letter): about Hoboken and Roth; he has put
      pressure on Hertzka, and found Hupka bad in the concert.").</tei:note>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Vorgestern fand mein erstes Konzert in <tei:rs type="place"
     key="entity-002286">München</tei:rs> statt. Der Jahreszeitensaal, ganz wundervoll in Farbe und
    Akustik war bis auf dem letzten Platz mit – Freikarten gefüllt. Da der Saal <tei:hi
     rend="underline">ca</tei:hi> 1200 Personen fasst, war das zu lösende Füllungsproblem ziemlich
    schwierig. Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> und <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000737">Roth</tei:rs> waren anwesend und konnten es nicht über sich
    bringen – was ich eigentlich auf besonderer Bitte des Hr. <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000922">Vriesl.</tei:rs> nicht verraten sollte – bei <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs> im Saale zu bleiben. Dies scheint mir doch zu weit
    getrieben und ihre Abneigung gegen <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs>,
    die sich in solcher krassen Weise offenbart, mehr <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
     >auf</tei:add> Schmockerei als auf wirkliches Verständnis und Überlegenheit zu schliessen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> Was mein Spiel betrifft, so war die Wiedergabe der
     <tei:title>Fantasie</tei:title> vielleicht zu ruhig<tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">; dabei</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above"> und</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> zu langsam geraten. Ganz lebendig gab der ausgezeichnete Bechstein-Flügel die
    Sonaten <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000760">Skarlatti</tei:rs>s wieder – ein Flügel, der
    wahrlich auch ohne Spieler eine Individualität ist. Die Wirkung war stark und scheinbar die
    stärkste des Abends. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Bei <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs><tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl>Brahms, <tei:title>Variations and
       Fugue on a Theme by G. F. Handel</tei:title>, Op. 24</tei:bibl>. Schenker worked with many of
     his students on this piece, and published an extensive analysis of it in <tei:bibl><tei:rs
       type="work" key="entity-001747"><tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title> 8–9</tei:rs> (=
      IV/2–3) (April–September 1924), 1–46; Eng. transl., vol. II, pp. 75–114)</tei:bibl>.
    </tei:note> hatte ich gegen Ende mit einem Hustenreiz zu kämpfen, der mich ganz gewaltig packte,
    und <tei:add place="interlinear-above">nur</tei:add> mit grösster Anstrengung konnte ich die
    Fuge durchhalten. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000589">Mendelssohn</tei:rs> und <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000129">Chopin</tei:rs>'s Mazurken waren nach der Meinung <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000922">Vriesl.</tei:rs> nebst <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000760">Scarlatti</tei:rs> am besten geraten. Dagegen protestierte <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000922">Vr.</tei:rs> gegen meine Auffassung der <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000129">Chop.</tei:rs> Polonaise. Er würde <tei:sic>würde</tei:sic> am liebsten
    alle jene Stellen, welche im Gegensatze zu den Fortissimo Stellen des Themas (2. Wiederholung)
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">stehen</tei:add> auch im Forte bringen und hält natürlich
    seine Auffassung <tei:pb n="3"/> für die einzig richtige. — </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Nun stehe ich wieder mitten in den Vorbereitungen für's hiesige Konzert. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Sehr interessant wars heute bei <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000377"
      ><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Paul Hirsch</tei:hi></tei:rs>, der die grösste <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000027">Bach</tei:rs>manuskript Ausstellung in seinem Hause hat. Bei
    der Erwähnung Ihres Namens sagte er sofort: Ja! Ich kenne wohl alle theoretischen Werke Ihres
    Lehrers – ein streitbarer Herr, Ihr Lehrer! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Wie viele Aufregungen und wieviel Nervenkraft all diese Wege, Besuche etc.
    mir <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">illeg. word</tei:note> haben, kann ich kaum
    schildern; doch habe ich den nötigen Humor, um diesen Weg, der infolge meiner neu hinzutretenden
    Schwierigkeiten einfach ungangbar ist, auch von anderer Seite anzusehen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich schreibe sofort nach dem Konzert.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Viele Empfehlungen an die gnädige <tei:rs type="person"
      key="entity-000771">Frau</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000399"
     >Felix</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-75"><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002495">Frankfurt</tei:rs>,
      <tei:date when="1921-11-18">November 18, 1921</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
      corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">My first concert in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002286">Munich</tei:rs>
    took place the day before yesterday. The Four Seasons Hall, quite wonderful in color and
    acoustics, was full to bursting with – free tickets. Since the hall holds c. 1,200 people, the
    problem that we faced of filling the hall was quite a steep one. Messrs <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000737"
     >Roth</tei:rs> were present and could not bring themselves – and I really ought, at the express
    request of Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>, not to divulge
    this – to remain in the hall during the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094"
     >Brahms</tei:rs>. I think this was altogether over the top, and their dislike of <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs>, which manifested itself in such a crass way,
    stemmed more from journalistic snobbery than from genuine understanding and reflection.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> Where my playing was concerned, my account of the <tei:title
     level="m">Fantasy</tei:title> came out perhaps too tranquil <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
     >and</tei:add> too slow. The <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000760">Scarlatti</tei:rs>
    sonatas sounded really lively on the excellent Bechstein piano — a piano that really has its own
    individuality, even without a player. The effect was powerful – apparently the most powerful of
    the evening.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> toward the end I had to contend with a throat tickle
    that came over me, and <tei:add place="interlinear-above">only</tei:add> with the greatest of
    effort did I manage to keep going in the fugue.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>'s
    opinion, the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000589">Mendelssohn</tei:rs> and <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000129">Chopin</tei:rs>'s mazurkas turned out almost as well as the
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000760">Scarlatti</tei:rs>. On the other hand, <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> protested at my interpretation of the
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000129">Chopin</tei:rs> Polonaise. He would have preferred it
    if all the passages that <tei:add place="interlinear-above">stand in</tei:add> contrast to the
     <tei:hi rend="bold italic">fortissimo</tei:hi> passages of the theme (second repeat) had also
    remained at <tei:hi rend="bold italic">forte</tei:hi>, and needless to say he clung to the
    belief that his interpretation <tei:pb n="3"/> was the only right one.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Now I am again in the throes of the preparations for my concert here.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">It was very interesting today at <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000377"
     >Paul Hirsch</tei:rs>'s, who has the greatest collection of <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000027">Bach</tei:rs> manuscripts in his house. At the mention of your name, he
    immediately said: “I know every single one of the theoretical works of your teacher – a
    pugnacious fellow, your teacher!”</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I can barely describe how much agitation, how much nervous energy all these
    excursions, visits, etc. have <tei:unclear reason="original illegible">cost</tei:unclear> me.
    But I have the necessary humor to look on the bright side of things, even when I simply cannot
    forge ahead because of newly accrued difficulties.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I will write immediately after the concert.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">With kindest regards to your dear <tei:rs type="person"
      key="entity-000771">wife</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000399"
     >Felix</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>



  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
