<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3724" sdoID="OJ-13-10_51">OJ 13/10, [51]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="TLJ-KO">
      <tei:persName>Timothy L. Jackson, ed. Kurt Oppel</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2010</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated January 10, 1928</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1928-01-10T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-08-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel talks about recent works of his colleagues at the Leipzig Conservatory.
        He has been in touch with Oswald Jonas regarding a planned new Schenker journal, and is
        hoping to spend some time in Vienna.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:placeName>Leipzig</tei:placeName>, <tei:date
              when="1928-01-10">10. I 1928.</tei:date>. Grassistr. 8, Konserv.</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt
            of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for January 13, 1928: “Von Oppel (Br.):
            Programm einer Aufführung seines Streichquartetts; erzählt von Straube, einem Antrag
            nach Mainz; er will in den Osterferien nach Wien kommen; sagt seine Mitarbeit an der
            Zeitschrift zu.” (“From Oppel (letter): program of a performance of his String Quartet;
            he talks about Straube and about a job offer in Mainz; he will come to Vienna during the
            Easter holidays; he agrees to contribute to the journal.”). — All paragraph-breaks are
            editorial, based on emdashes in the original text. — Schenker’s reply is recorded on
            January 15, 1928: “An Oppel (Br.): freue mich auf sein Kommen; einige Worte über Straube
            u. Furtwängler.” (“To Oppel (letter): I look forward to his coming; a few words about
            Straube and Furtwängler.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Endlich komme ich dazu, Ihnen zu schreiben. Ich hoffe, dass Sie und <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000771">Ihre liebe Frau</tei:rs> gesund u. wohlauf sind. Für
        1928 wünschen die <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801">Jungen</tei:rs> u. ich Ihnen
        beiden alles Gute, Kraft, Gesundheit und Erfolg bei aller Arbeit. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Weihn. nahmen mich die <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801">Jungen</tei:rs> so in
        Anspruch, dass ich alle geplante Corespond. aufgab. Und hier in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002479">L.</tei:rs> kam ich auch nicht dazu. Nochmals also heissen Dank für
        das <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001751">Jahrbuch II</tei:rs>, aus dem ich wieder Seite
        für Seite gelernt habe. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun ist mir die Stelle des Leiters a. d. neu zu errichtenden Institut für kath. u.
        evang. Kirchenmusik in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003156">Mainz</tei:rs> angeboten
        worden, ich weiss nicht, ob ich sie annehmen soll. <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003156"
          >Mainz</tei:rs> ist viel kleiner, u. <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002479">L.</tei:rs>
        hat seine Vorzüge. Jedenfalls habe ich 12000 M verlangt, wenn ich schon dahin gehe, will ich
        wenigstens pecuniär in Ruhe arbeiten können. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Die Kritiken von der hiesigen Quartettaufführung schicke ich noch. Soweit war der Abend
        ein Erfolg. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000659">Pauer</tei:rs> und der 2. Director
        Davisson waren sehr angetan von dem Stück, u. Davisson sagte mir, er freue sich, dass ein
        starker Musiker am <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002872">Kons.</tei:rs> da sei als
        Gegengewicht gegen die jungen „modernen“ Kollegen, Raphael und Thomas. Letzteren halte ich
        für den begabteren. Von Raphael hörten wir <tei:pb n="2"/> gestern Abend in Halle die 1.
        Symphonie in a-moll.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Günther
          Raphael (1903–60) taught at the Leipzig Conservatory from 1926 to 1934. His first symphony
          was first performed there by the Gewandhaus Orchestra, with Wilhelm Furtwängler
          conducting. Kurt Thomas (1904–73) taught music theory at the Leipzig Conservatory from
          1925 to 1928 before being made choral conductor and composition teacher at the Institute
          for Church Music there. </tei:note> Ein Chaos von fremden Bruchstücken, ohne jegliche
        Konzentration i. d. Form. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000866">Straube</tei:rs> ist
        schon ein Unglück für diese junge Menschen, er will sie um jeden Preis zur äussersten
        Modernität peitschen, anstatt sie sich ruhig u. langsam unbeeinflusst entwickeln zu lassen.
        Zu meiner Messe hat er sich noch <tei:add place="interlinear-above">nicht</tei:add> wieder
        geäussert. Das Quartett hat er sich angehört, aber ich habe ihn noch nicht gesprochen. Mir
        liegt auch gar nichts an ihm, ich gehe doch meine eignen Wege, u. er ist der letzte, auf den
        ich höre. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000659">Pauer</tei:rs> gestand mir übrigens kurz vor
        Weihn, er hätte bis heute nie ein innerliches Verhältnis zu <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000695">Reger</tei:rs> gewinnen können, Kunststück! Und Gott sei Dank, dass
        sich sein gesunder Instinkt dagegen sträubte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
          place="foot">“dass sich sein gesunder Instinkt dagegen sträubte”: Oppel may be punning
          here on the verb <tei:hi rend="italic">sträuben</tei:hi> and the name of his colleague
          Straube.</tei:note> In den Weihnferien las ich eine neue Harmonielehre von <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-003518">Bruno Weigl</tei:rs> (Schott, Mainz), auch eine
        überflüssige Erscheinung, desgleichen eine von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005265"
          >Karg-Elert</tei:rs>, einem meiner Kollegen hier. Die Leute scheinen sich immer noch
        einzubilden, dass eine „moderne“ <tei:title>Harmonielehre</tei:title> das wichtigste zur
        Komposition sei. – Kurz vor Weihn. hielt ein <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000209"
          >Walter Engelsmann</tei:rs> aus <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004005">Dresden</tei:rs>
        drei Vorträge bei uns, von denen ich leider nur den letzten hören konnte, er suchte zu
        beweisen, dass bei <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beeth</tei:rs> alle Themen
        aller Sätze einheitlich aus den Kopfthema des ersten Satzes gebildet seien. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000412">Dr. Jonas</tei:rs> hat mir wegen der zu
        gründ. Zeitschrift <tei:supplied reason="clarity">geschrieben</tei:supplied>,<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">The planned journal, <tei:rs
            type="journal" key="entity-002563"><tei:title level="j">Die
            Tonkunst</tei:title></tei:rs>, never materialized. Schenker’s diary for December 11,
          1927, in the course of a long entry about the planned journal, records that Hans Weisse:
          “bat mich um die Adresse von Dahms, Oppel, Roth u. Vrieslander, die zu schicken ich
          versprach.” (“asked me for the addresses of Dahms, Oppel, Roth and Vrieslander, which I
          promised to send.”); this may perhaps have led to Jonas’s approach to Oppel.</tei:note>
        <tei:pb n="3"/> ich konnte ihm leider noch nicht antworten. Natürlich arbeite ich sehr gern
        mit. Vielleicht telephonieren Sie ihm kurz, dass ich selbstverständlich dazu bereit bin u.
        ich ihm nächste Woche Nachricht gebe. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Anfang März bekommen wir hier Ferien, da das Gebäude zu Messezwecken vermietet wird.
        Ich habe stark vor, die 14 Tage dann in Wien zu verbringen u. hoffe, dass meine Finanzen
        dazu reichen – Heute Abend wird das Quartett nochmals in einer hiesigen Gesellschaft
        gespielt, von der ich noch niemanden kenne. Zum Arbeiten komme ich jetzt gar nicht u. ich
        bin sehr traurig darüber. Aussicht auf Wohnung auch noch immer gleich Null. Über die
        Verhältnisse im <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002872">Konserv.</tei:rs> schreibe
        ich das nächste Mal. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Für heute Ihnen beiden die herzlichsten Grüsse, auch von den <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-004801">Jungen</tei:rs>!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">Ihr treuer </tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:placeName>Leipzig</tei:placeName>, <tei:date
              when="1928-01-10">January 10, 1928</tei:date>, Grassistraße 8,
            Conservatory</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">My dear Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Finally, I am getting around to writing to you. I hope that you and <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000771">your dear wife</tei:rs> are well and in good spirits. My
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801">boys</tei:rs> and I wish the two of you the best
        of strength, health and success in all your work.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>My <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004801">boys</tei:rs> took up so much of my
        attention that I gave up on all the correspondence I had planned. And even here in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002479">Leipzig</tei:rs> I was unable to get to it. Once more,
        then, warmest thanks for the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001751">second
          Yearbook</tei:rs>, from which I have learned something on every page. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Now, the post of director of the newly founded Institute for Catholic and Protestant
        Church Music in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003156">Mainz</tei:rs> has been offered to
        me; I do not know whether I should accept it. <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003156"
          >Mainz</tei:rs> is much smaller, and <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002479"
          >Leipzig</tei:rs> has its advantages. In any event, I have asked for 12,000 marks; if I do
        indeed go there, I shall at least be able to work without financial worries. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I shall send you the reviews of the performance of my string quartet in due course.
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000659">Pauer</tei:rs> and the assistant director were
        very touched by the piece; and Davisson told me that he was glad that a strong musician was
        present at the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002872">Conservatory</tei:rs>, as a
        counterbalance to the young “modern” colleagues, Raphael and Thomas, of whom I regard the
        latter as the more talented. <tei:pb n="2"/> Yesterday evening we heard Raphael’s First
        Symphony in Halle:<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> a chaotic mixture of
        foreign elements, without any focus in its form. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000866"
          >Straube</tei:rs> is indeed a misfortune for these young persons; he wants to whip them
        into the most extreme modernity at any price, instead of letting them simply develop slowly
        in their own time, without influence. He has still <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >not</tei:add> said anything about my Mass. He listened to my Quartet, but I have not yet
        spoken to him. And I am not at all concerned about him; I shall take my own paths, and he is
        the last person of whom I shall take notice. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Moreover, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000659">Pauer</tei:rs> admitted to me,
        shortly before Christmas, that he has never been able to gain a close relationship to
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000695">Reger</tei:rs>: hardly surprising! And thank God
        that his healthy instinct bristled against it.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"
        /> In the Christmas holidays I read a new <tei:title level="m">Theory of Harmony</tei:title>
        by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003518">Bruno Weigl</tei:rs> (Mainz: Schott,
          <tei:supplied reason="date">1925</tei:supplied>), also a superficial piece of work; and
        one by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005265">Karg-Elert</tei:rs>, a colleague of mine
        here. These people still seem to think that a “modern” theory of harmony is the most
        important thing for composition. – Shortly before Christmas, a <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000209">Walter Engelsmann</tei:rs> from <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-004005">Dresden</tei:rs> gave three lectures here, of which I was
        unfortunately able to hear only the last; he sought to prove that, in <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>, all the themes from every movement could be
        coherently derived from the first theme of the first movement. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000412">Dr. Jonas</tei:rs> wrote to me about the
        planned journal;<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/>
        <tei:pb n="3"/> unfortunately I have been as yet unable to reply to him. Of course, I would
        be very happy to collaborate. Perhaps you could make a short telephone call to him to say
        that I am naturally prepared to do so, and that I will inform him next week. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>We shall have holidays at the beginning of March as the building has been rented for
        purposes of the trade fair. I am seriously thinking of spending the two weeks in Vienna and
        hope that my finances will extend to that. This evening, my Quartet will be played again in
        a local society, of which I know no one. I am not getting to my work, and I am very sad
        about that. The prospect of an apartment is also still equal to zero. About the
        circumstances at the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002872">Conservatory</tei:rs>,
        I shall write the next time. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>For today, the most cordial greetings to the two of you, also from my <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-004801">boys</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">Your faithful </tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>
    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
