<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3475" sdoID="OJ-14-10_8">OJ 14/10, [8]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RW" scope="major">Rosa Weil's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="AW" scope="major">Arnold Weil's hand, in Sütterlinschrift</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008456">WeilR ~
        JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008455">WeilR ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008458">WeilA ~
        JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008457">WeilA ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten double letter from Arnold &amp; Rosa Weil to Heinrich &amp; Jeanette
        Schenker, dated July 13–14, 1933</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1933-07-14T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-07-23</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Rosa Weil returns a photograph with thanks, and describes her recent holiday
        in Italy with Lene but without Arnold. — Klara, after initial improvement, has suffered a
        setback. — Arnold thanks Jeanette for the photograph and Heinrich for the announcement of
        the Photogram Archive.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000944">Rosa Weil</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000943">Arnold Weil</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:div type="part_1">
        <tei:opener>
          <tei:dateline rend="indent-10"><tei:handShift new="#RW"/><tei:rs type="place"
              key="entity-002248">Aussig</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1933-07-13">13. Juli
              1933</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
          <tei:salute>Meine Lieben,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
              >Receipt of these two letters is recorded in Heinrich’s diary for July 14, 1933: “Von
              Rosl u. Arnold (Br.): das Bildchen u. den Aufsatz zurück; Rosl u. Lene waren in
              Italien; Klara ist es schon gut gegangen, nun wieder ein Rückfall – Rosl ist sehr
              pessimistisch – Oskar geht nach Karlsbad.” (“From Rosl and Arnold (letter): the
              photograph and the article returned; Rosl and Lene were in Italy; Klara had been doing
              well, but has now suffered another setback – Rosl is very pessimistic – Oskar is going
              to Karlsbad.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:p>Euer erster Brief traf während meiner Abwesenheit hier ein und der zweite kurz nach
          meiner Rückkehr.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">On July 4,
            1933, Schenker recorded: “An Weil (Br.): für das Telegramm Dank, frage nach Klara u.
            Oskar.” (“To Weil (letter): thanks for the telegram; I ask after Klara and Oskar.”) –
            The telegram (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-10_7">OJ 14/10, [7]</tei:ref>)
            had conveyed congratulations on Heinrich’s birthday on June 19. Previous to that, the
            diary for June 18, 1933 records: “An Rosl (Br. Lie-Liechen): das Bildchen aus dem
            Kinsky-Palais u. den Aufsatz M. Komorn; Erkundigung nach Klara usw” (“To Rosl (letter by
            Lie-Liechen): the snapshot of the Kinsky Palace and Maria Komorn’s essay; we ask after
            Klara, etc.”).</tei:note> Vielen Dank für den ausführlichen Bericht und das trotz der
          Kleinheit ausgezeichnete Bild. Inliegend sende ich die Beilagen zurück. </tei:p>

        <tei:p>Ich war mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005248">Lene</tei:rs> in <tei:rs
            type="place" key="entity-002592">Italien</tei:rs>, es war mein schönstes Erlebnis, ich
          werde bis an mein Lebensende an die Erinnerung zehren, Verona, Rom, Neapel, Capri,
          Venedig, in meinen kühnsten Träumen habe ich nie geglaubt, daß ich das Land der Sehnsucht
          einmal betreten werde. </tei:p>

        <tei:p>Leider konnte <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs> nicht mit;
          dringende Arbeiten mußten erledigt werden und fast während meiner ganzen Abwesenheit hat
          er täglich bis ½9<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> gearbeitet. </tei:p>

        <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Auch hätte er es auf die Dauer wohl nicht mitmachen können; denn
          manchmal war die Sache schon ein bißchen strapaziös. Wir kannten aber dort keine
          Müdigkeit, wir waren unermüdlich und fleißig und haben mit Andacht all‘ die Schönheit in
          uns aufgenommen; Natur und Kunst. – Erst nach der Rückkehr; da war es schwer in den Alltag
          zurückzufinden und alles stürmte wieder auf einen ein; da unten im farbenprächtigen Süden
          war es so wohltuend, alles vergessen zu dürfen. </tei:p>

        <tei:p>Nun bin ich aber wieder ganz zuhause, freue mich mit <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000943">Mann</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005248"
            >Kind</tei:rs> und mit meinem wunderschönen Heim. Vor allem damit, daß wir alle G. s. D.
          gesund sind. </tei:p>

        <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> Damit komme ich auf das traurige Thema „<tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-003244">Klara</tei:rs>.“ Bis ungef. 3. Woche Mai ging es ihr so gut, daß sie
            <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs> bei seinem Besuch ins
          Kaffeehaus mitnehmen konnte. Die Ärzte und auch wir waren fest überzeugt davon, daß sie
          Mitte Juni mit dem <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000339">Mann</tei:rs> werde auf
          Urlaub gehen können. Da bekam sie einen schrecklichen Anfall, der sie ganz umgeworfen hat.
          Nun liegt sie seit mehr als 7 Wochen fest und da sie sich zu allem Überfluß auch noch
          einbildet, die Speiseröhre wäre ihr zugewachsen; und sie brächte keine Nährung hinunter,
          muß sie mit der Sonde künstlich ernährt werden. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000339"
            >Oskar</tei:rs> hat sie seither nicht besucht, schreibt ihr aber 2mal wöchentlich. Er
          ist ein wahrhaft armer Teufel und geht Ende d.M. nach <tei:rs type="place"
            key="entity-004561">Karlsbad</tei:rs>, da er eine Erholung wirklich dringend nötig
          hat.</tei:p>

        <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/>
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005248">Lene</tei:rs> wollte heute mal nach ihr schauen,
          schon um zu sehen, ob die Arme wirklich die Pflege hat, die man in einem ersten Sanatorium
          beanspruchen kann. Ich bin ziemlich pessimistisch und es wird mir sehr schwer an eine
          völlige Heilung zu glauben. Es fällt mir oft schwer aufs Gemüt, daß man in diesem Falle so
          ganz ohnmächtig ist und garnicht dazutun kann, diese schreckliche Verwirrung von ihr zu
          nehmen; und doch kann ich die Hoffnung nicht ganz aufgeben. Es geschehen so oft an’s
          Wunderbare grenzende Heilungen, warum sollen wir nicht auch mal so ein Glück haben. </tei:p>

        <tei:p>Nach alledem werdet Ihr begreifen, daß der arme Mann nicht in der Stimmung ist, über
          sein Elend zu schreiben. – <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs> will
          Euch noch schreiben, er kann heuer erst im Oct. an einen Urlaub denken. </tei:p>

        <tei:p>Ich hoffe, Ihr habet Glück mit der Wahl Euerer Sommerfrische<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">The Schenkers spent the summer of 1933
            in Ilz, Styria.</tei:note> und wünsche Euch die allerbeste Erholung. </tei:p>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute>Herzlichst</tei:salute>
          <tei:salute>Euere</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000944">Rosa</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>

        <tei:postscript>
          <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in left margin, sideways:</tei:note> Der
            gestrige Bericht aus Veleslawin<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial"
              place="foot"> i.e. the sanatorium in Prague in which she had been for the past eight
              months (cf. <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-10_3">OJ 14/10, [3]</tei:ref>,
              November 20, 1932.</tei:note> meldet insofern eine leichte Besserung, als sie auf
            Zureden 2mal selbst Nährung <tei:subst>
              <tei:del rend="overstrike">auf</tei:del>
              <tei:add place="interlinear-above">sie sich</tei:add>
            </tei:subst> genommen hat.</tei:p>
        </tei:postscript>
      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="part_2">
        <tei:opener>
          <tei:dateline rend="indent-10"><tei:pb n="5"/>
            <tei:handShift new="#AW"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002248"><tei:hi
                rend="lateinschr">Aussig</tei:hi></tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1933-07-14"><tei:hi
                rend="lateinschr">14. Juli 1933</tei:hi></tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
          <tei:salute>Meine Lieben,</tei:salute>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:p rend="first">Da ich den stark Beschäftigten spiele, kann ich mich nur kurz fassen. </tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">Für die Übersendung der Notiz und des Bildes danke ich bestens, beides
          hat mich sehr interessiert; für deinen Brief, lieber Heinrich[entity-000632], danke ich
          ebenfalls. Der Beginn zu einer <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452">Autogrammsammlung</tei:rs> <tei:del
            rend="overstrike">wurde</tei:del> ist mit demselben erfolgt.</tei:p>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mit herzlichsten Grüßen</tei:salute>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Euer</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943"
            >Arnold</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>
      </tei:div>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:div type="part_1">
        <tei:opener>
          <tei:dateline rend="indent-10"><tei:handShift new="#RW"/><tei:rs type="place"
              key="entity-002248">Aussig</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1933-07-13">July 13,
              1933</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
          <tei:salute>My dear ones,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:p>Your first letter arrived when I was away from home, and your second shortly after my
            return.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> Many thanks for the detailed
          report and the excellent photograph (despite its smallness). I return the enclosures
          herewith.</tei:p>

        <tei:p>I was in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002592">Italy</tei:rs> with <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-005248">Lene;</tei:rs> it was my most enjoyable experience – I
          shall treasure it to the end of my life: Verona, Rome, Naples, Capri, Venice. Never in my
          wildest dreams did I think I would set foot in that country.</tei:p>

        <tei:p>Sadly <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs> was unable to join
          us. He had jobs that had to be dealt with urgently, and throughout almost my entire
          absence he worked every day until 8.30.</tei:p>

        <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Also, the whole time he would have been unable to join in, because so
          often the going was rather strenuous. We, on the other hand, never felt weary while there;
          we were tireless, energetic, and devoted to taking in all the beautiful sights, nature and
          art. – But after we returned, it was difficult to get back into the daily routine, and it
          all hit us like a brick wall. Down there in the brightly-colored south it was so soothing
          to put it all out of our minds.</tei:p>

        <tei:p>Now, however, I am completely settled back into domestic life and enjoying my <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000943">husband</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-005248">child</tei:rs> and my beautiful home – and above all, the fact that
          we are, thank God, all in good health.</tei:p>

        <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> With that, I come to the somber topic of <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-003244">Klara</tei:rs>. Until about the third week in May things were going
          so well with her that <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs> could take
          her along on his trip to the coffee-house. The doctors, and even we ourselves, were firmly
          convinced that she would be able to go on holiday with her <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000339">husband</tei:rs> in mid-June. Then she had a terrible attack, which
          has completely upended her. She has now been grounded for the past seven weeks; and since,
          to make matters worse, she even convinced herself that her oesophagus was blocked and
          couldn’t get any nourishment down, she is having to be fed by tube. Since then, <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000339">Oskar</tei:rs> has not visited her, but writes to her
          twice a week. He is a really poor fellow and is going to <tei:rs type="place"
            key="entity-004561">Karlsbad</tei:rs> at the end of the month because he is in really
          urgent need of respite.</tei:p>

        <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> Today <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005248">Lene</tei:rs> wanted
          to look after her, mainly in order to see whether the poor soul really has the care that
          one can expect of a top-line sanatorium. I’m somewhat pessimistic, and it will be very
          hard for me to believe in a complete recovery. It often weighs heavily on my mind that in
          this case one is so powerless and can do absolutely nothing to take this dreadful
          confusion away from her; and yet I can’t entirely give up hope. One hears so often of
          recoveries bordering on the miraculous – why should we too not have such a piece of good
          fortune?</tei:p>

        <tei:p>After all of this, you will understand that the poor man is in no frame of mind to
          write about his wretchedness. – <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943">Arnold</tei:rs>
          is going to write to you; he can’t even think at the moment of a holiday until at least
          October.</tei:p>

        <tei:p>I hope you have good luck with your choice of a summer holiday<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> and wish you all the best by way of
          recuperation.</tei:p>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute>Most cordially,</tei:salute>
          <tei:salute>Your</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000944">Rosa</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>

        <tei:postscript>
          <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in left margin, sideways:</tei:note>
            Yesterday’s report from Veleslawin<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/>
            conveyed a slight improvement in as much as she has with some coaxing twice fed
            herself.</tei:p>
        </tei:postscript>
      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="part_2">
        <tei:opener>
          <tei:dateline rend="indent-10"><tei:pb n="5"/>
            <tei:handShift new="#AW"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002248">Aussig</tei:rs>,
              <tei:date when="1933-07-14">July 14, 1933</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
          <tei:salute>My dear ones,</tei:salute>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:p rend="first">Since I am acting the role of a very busy man, I can only be
          brief.</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">Best thanks for sending the notice and picture. Both have interested me
          very much. For your letter, dear Heinrich, thank you likewise. The beginning of an
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452">Autogram Collection</tei:rs> meets with the same reaction.</tei:p>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-20">With most cordial greetings</tei:salute>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Your</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000943"
            >Arnold</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>
      </tei:div>


    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
