<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2122" sdoID="OJ-15-16_81">OJ 15/16, [81]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HW" scope="sole">Hans Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2008</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2018</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-10-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated September 5, 1931</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1931-09-05T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2018-10-12</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Weisse outlines his travel plans before leaving for America. He has accepted
        an invitation from Moriz Violin to give a lecture in Hamburg on September 16, the day before
        he sets sail.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Abreise; departure; Vortrag; lecture; Titel; title; Optimist; Gesundheit; good
        health; Bild; photograph; Gegengeschenk; return present</dc:subject>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000951">Weisse</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:lb/><tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#HW"/><tei:date
            when="1931-09-05">5. IX. 31</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber, verehrter <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"
            >Meister</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/4, p. 3654, September 8, 1931: "Von
            Weisse (Br.): spricht am 16. in Hamburg; eine Berliner Adresse u. ein Bildchen von
            Susi!" ("From Weisse (letter): he will speak in Hamburg on the 16th; a Berlin address
            and a little picture of Susi!").</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>ich vermute Sie schon in Wien und hoffe dass diese Zeilen <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">Sie</tei:add> bestimmt erreichen. Für Ihre beiden Briefe danke
        ich Ihnen herzlichst,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Neither
          letter is known to survive, but their writing is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/4,
          pp. 3652‒3653, August 28, 1931: "Nach Tisch an Weisse (Br.): lege die Schwarz-Fotografie
          bei; über seine trüben Erfahrungen mit der Heimat; wiederhole meine Mahnung, sich
          Geldfreunde zu sichern; erzähle die Geschichte des <tei:title>freien Satz</tei:title>es,
          den Schaden durch die Unerreichbarkeit von S. 10000! Schon die juristisch noch nicht
          greifbare Zusage hat die letzte Formung ermöglicht. Das Bildchen als Ersatz für
          Händedruck, Kuss u. Segen!" ("After lunch, to Weisse (letter): I enclose Schwarz's
          photograph; concerning his unhappy experiences with his homeland; I repeat my reminder
          that he secure well-to-do friends; I recount the story of <tei:title level="m">Free
            Composition</tei:title>, the damage caused by the elusiveness of 10,000 shillings! Even
          though it is not legally binding, the acceptance has made the final formulation possible.
          The little photo as a substitute for handshake, kiss, and blessing!"; and at OJ 4/4, p.
          3653, August 29, 1931: "An Weisse (Br.): einige Zeilen darüber, nochmals Dank!" ("To
          Weisse (letter): a few lines about this, thanks once again!").</tei:note> dass <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-005758">Khuner</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Paul Khuner first emerges in a diary entry of June 5, 1931,
          when Weisse informs Schenker that Khuner was willing to guarantee 5,000 shillings for the
          printing of <tei:title level="m">Der freie Satz</tei:title>. On August 5, Schenker wrote a
          letter to Khuner, and on August 29 he received a reply summarized in Schenker's diary as
          "he would rather give me the money on October 15; he wants to become personally acquainted
          with me. What a fortunate turn of events!" (Khuner's letter not known to survive), to
          which Schenker responded on September 3: "I shall introduce and identify myself!" The
          money is given on November 27. Weisse was particularly aggrieved that Khuner was not
          mentioned at all in the acknowledgements in <tei:title level="m">Der freie
            Satz</tei:title>, published posthumously in 1935, and that Antony van Hoboken received
          all the credit for ensuring the publication of the book.</tei:note> die Sache auf diese
        Weise löst, ist wohl sehr erfreulich.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Haben Sie vielleicht schon von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913"
          >Violin</tei:rs> gehört, dass ich einen Tag vor meiner Abreise in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002589">Hamburg</tei:rs> noch eine Lanze breche? Ich habe mich über <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000913">Violin</tei:rs>s Aufforderung, dort zu sprechen, sehr
        gefreut und sofort angenommen. Der Titel meines Vortrages wird läuten:</tei:p>

      <tei:p>„Hörendes Schaffen – schaffendes Hören, Versuch einer Würdigung der Grundgedanken in H.
        Schenkers Werk“<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">.</tei:supplied> Ich spreche am <tei:date
          when="1931-09-16">16. Sept.</tei:date> ganz frei, vor — wie <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000913">Violin</tei:rs>, der Optimist<tei:supplied reason="punctuation"
          >,</tei:supplied> meint, 500 Leuten. Je mehr desto besser, Sie können sich vorstellen,
        dass ich alles dareinsetzen werde, die kühlen Hamburger in Hitze zu versetzen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich freue mich sehr<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">solchen</tei:hi> Abschied nehmen zu können.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich wohne bei <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Violin</tei:rs>, und würde mich
        sehr freuen, noch von Ihnen dort zu hören. Am <tei:date when="1931-09-09">9.ten</tei:date>
        fahre ich mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000952">Hertha</tei:rs>, die mich über
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002763">Nürnberg</tei:rs>, Rothenburg, bis Würzburg
          begleitet<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> fort. Sollten Sie mir noch
        vorher was zu sagen haben, so erreicht mich eine Nachricht von Ihnen am <tei:date
          when="1931-09-14">14.</tei:date> in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501"
          >Berlin</tei:rs>, Halensee, Paulsbornerstrase 92 bei Lachmann.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Probably the family of Nina Lachmann,
          whose name appears in a letter from Oswald Jonas to Schenker (<tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OC-44-22">OC 44/22</tei:ref>, November 10, 1932) in a list
          of subscribers to Jonas's book, then forthcoming, <tei:title level="m">Das Wesen des
            musikalischen Kunstwerkes: Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich
          Schenkers</tei:title>.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Ihre Reise haben Sie hoffentlich gut überstanden und sind im Besitze
        bester Gesundheit in Wien eingetroffen. Für das Bild danke ich Ihnen noch herzlich und sende
        Ihnen als Gegengeschenk eines von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004675">Susi</tei:rs>,
        daran Sie ermessen mögen, was ich hier verlasse und für 9 Monate verliere. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-004676">Moni</tei:rs> geht schon und beginnt bereits zu
        plaudern.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun denn, hinein in’s Leben!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich grüsse Sie beide allerherzlichst, und bin – wie sagte man doch beim
        Militär?: „zu Wasser und zu Lande“</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Der Ihre</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person"><tei:hi
              rend="lateinschr">H</tei:hi></tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:lb/><tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#HW"/><tei:date
            when="1931-09-05">September 5, 1931</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear, revered <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>I imagine you are already back in Vienna, and hope that these lines reach <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">you</tei:add> safely. For your two letters I thank you most
          cordially;<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> that <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-005758">Khuner</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> is
        taking care of the matter in this way is surely most welcome.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Have you, by any chance, already heard from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913"
          >Violin</tei:rs> that I shall be taking up the cudgels once more in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002589">Hamburg</tei:rs>, the day before my departure? I was delighted to have
        been asked by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Violin</tei:rs> to speak there, and
        accepted his invitation immediately. The title of my lecture will be:</tei:p>

      <tei:p>„"Creativity through Listening – Creative Listening: Toward an Appreciation of the
        Basic Ideas in Heinrich Schenker's Work." I shall be speaking on <tei:date when="1931-09-16"
          >September 16</tei:date>, without prepared text. — <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000913">Violin</tei:rs>, ever the optimist, expects 500 people to be there;
        the more, the better. You can imagine that I shall do all in my power to set the cool
        Hamburgers on fire.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I am greatly looking forward to making my departure <tei:hi rend="underline">in this
          way</tei:hi>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I shall be staying with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Violin</tei:rs> and
        would be delighted if I heard from you there. On the <tei:date when="1931-09-09"
          >9th</tei:date>, I am leaving with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000952"
          >Hertha</tei:rs>, who will accompany me to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002763"
          >Nuremberg</tei:rs> and Rothenburg, as far as Würzburg. If you need to get in touch with
        me before <tei:supplied reason="clarity">I reach Hamburg</tei:supplied>, you can get a
        message to me in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>, where I shall be
          <tei:supplied reason="clarity">arriving</tei:supplied> on the <tei:date when="1931-09-14"
          >14th</tei:date>: Halensee, Paulsbornerstrase 92, c/o Lachmann.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> I hope that you survived your journey well, and have arrived in Vienna
        in the best of health. I thank you most cordially for the picture; in return, I send you one
        of my <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004675">Susi</tei:rs>, so that you might have some
        idea what I am leaving here, and what I shall be losing for nine months. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-004676">Moni</tei:rs> is already walking, and is just beginning
        to chatter.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>All right, then, it’s time to get on with things!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I send the two of you my most cordial greetings and am ‒ how does the
        military put it? ‒ "on sea and on land."</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person"
          >H</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
