<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2050" sdoID="OJ-13-25_4">OJ 13/25, [4]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPhr" scope="major">Hermann Rinn as typist</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed-red" scope="minor">printed (red)</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed-black" scope="minor">printed (black)</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HR" scope="minor">Hermann Rinn's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>


    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2017</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2017</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2018</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2012-09-26" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006727">Kunstwart ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006729">RinnH ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Typewritten letter from Rinn to Schenker, dated February 7, 1929</dc:title>
      <dcterms:created>1929-02-07T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2018-01-31</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Rinn reports that publication of "Eine Rettung der klassischen Musik-Texte"
        must be delayed because a copy of the faulty Peters edition of Schubert's Sonata (Op. 78, in
        G major), which is the subject of Schenker's essay, cannot be found anywhere in Munich. He
        asks Schenker to send him his own copy, so that it can be used for the reproduction of the
        musical text. He also mentions the death of August Halm, and his intention of marking the
        event in the same issue in which Schenker's article is now to appear.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Beitrag; article; contribution; Verzögerung; delay; Ausgabe; edition; Menuett;
        minuet; Orientierung; orientation; Heft; issue; volume; Photos; Band; Exemplar; copy;
        Auflage; print-run; Kreise; circle; Mitarbeit; collaboration; Komposition;
        composition</dc:subject>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-006727">Der Kunstwart</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000717">Hermann Rinn</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-30"><tei:handShift new="#printed-red"/><tei:hi rend="bold">Der
              Kunstwart</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed-black"/>____________________</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-20">Schriftleitung: Dr. Hermann Rinn / Verlag Georg D. W.
            Callwey</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-40">München NW 12, Finkenstr. 2</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#TPhr"/><tei:date when="1929-02-07">7. 2.
          29</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"
            >Doktor</tei:rs>:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
            this letter and a package from <tei:title level="j">Der Kunstwart</tei:title> is
            recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/2 p. 3312: "Vom Kunstwart-Verlag ein Paket
            Notenbilder u. die Schubert-Ausgabe von Riemann, die ich nicht brauchen kann. — Von Dr.
            Rinn (Br.): bittet um Hilfe; Berrsche begeistert von meinem Aufsatz. — Ich kaufe bei
            Kern die Peters-Ausgabe von Schubert u. lasse sie recomm. an den Kunstwart-Verlag
            senden." ("From the publishers of <tei:title level="j">Der Kunstwart</tei:title>, a
            package of music examples and the Schubert edition by Riemann, which I cannot use. —
            From Dr. Rinn (letter): he asks for help; Berrsche is inspired by my article. — I buy at
            Kern's the Peters edition of Schubert and have it sent by registered post to the
            publishers of <tei:title level="j">Der Kunstwart</tei:title>.")</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Es ist mir ausserordentlich peinlich, dass ich Ihre Nachsicht anrufen
        muss. Ihr Beitrag<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:title
            level="a">Eine Rettung der klassischen Musik-Texte: Das Archiv für Photogramme in der
            National-Bibliothek, Wien,</tei:title> Schenker's first article for <tei:title level="j"
            >Der Kunstwart</tei:title>, a copy of which is preserved at OJ 20/10, item 1.</tei:note>
        kann nämlich leider erst in der allerdings schon in der letzten Februarnummer auszugebenden
        Märznummer erscheinen. Die Verzögerung entstand dadurch, dass ich die von Ihnen
          inkrim<tei:supplied reason="omission">in</tei:supplied>ierte Ausgabe von <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002422">Peters</tei:rs> nirgends auftreiben konnte. Ich
        liess mir sogar von <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002422">Peters</tei:rs> die
        Nummer 716 besorgen, sie enthält aber das fragliche Menuett, wenn ich recht sehe, überhaupt
        nicht. Ich schicke Ihnen zur Orientierung das Heft zu und bitte Sie es zu behalten, wenn Sie
        Verwendung dafür haben; Sie hatten ohnedies schreckliche Mühe mit der Sache; die beiden
        Photos liegen bei). Die hohe bayrische Staatsbibliothek scheint <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000803">Schubert</tei:rs> nicht zu besitzen, der Band jedenfalls war nicht
        vorhanden. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000067">Berrsche</tei:rs> besitzt eine
        abweichende Ausgabe aus seiner Schülerzeit, desgleichen haben meine sämtlichen musikalischen
        Freunde versagt, so dass ich schon in höchster Not Sie um Ihr Exemplar bitten
          wollte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">No volumes of
          Schubert's piano music survive in either the Oster or Salzer collections of Schenker's
          surviving papers in the New York Public Library.</tei:note> Nun hoffe ich bis morgen Früh
        die richtige Ausgabe zu bekommen und werde mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000067"
          >Berrsche</tei:rs> die Sache genau nachprüfen. Seien Sie bitte über diese Verschleppung
        nicht ungehalten. Vielleicht ist es Ihnen aber doch auch selbst lieber, wenn der Beitrag in
        der Märznummer erscheint, da dieses Heft in erhöhter Auflage gedruckt wird und so grössere
        Kreise erreicht. Wir werden übrigens nicht versäumen, die Gesamtpresse auf den Aufsatz
        aufmerksam zu machen. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000067">Berrsche</tei:rs> ist sehr
        glücklich über Ihre Mitarbeit und sprach begeistert von dem Aufsatz (ich gab ihm die
        Fahnen).</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> Wie Sie gehört haben werden, ist uns <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000326">August Halm</tei:rs> entrissen worden. Es ist ein sehr schmerzlicher
        Verlust. Noch vor ein paar Tagen schrieb er mir, dass er ein paar Reisen vorhabe, sich aber
        seinem Arzt vorstellen müsse, obschon er nicht einsehe, was das für einen Sinn hätte. Wir
        werden im Märzheft eine kleine Komposition von ihm bringen und <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000067">Berrsche</tei:rs> wird ihm bei dieser Gelegenheit einen kleinen
        Nachruf schreiben.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Mit den besten Empfehlungen</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr ergebener</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:handShift new="#HR"/><tei:rs key="entity-000717"
            type="person">Rinn</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-30"><tei:handShift new="#printed-red"/><tei:hi rend="bold">Der
              Kunstwart</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed-black"/>____________________</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-20">Editorship: Dr. Hermann Rinn / Publisher Georg D. W.
            Callwey</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-40">Munich NW 12, Finkenstraße 2</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#TPhr"/><tei:date when="1929-02-07">February 7,
            1929</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Dear Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs
              key="entity-000632" type="person">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">It pains me greatly to ask for your indulgence: your article<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> cannot, unfortunately, be published until the
        March issue, which will appear as soon as the end of February. The delay arose because I
        could not locate the guilty <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002422">Peters</tei:rs>
        edition anywhere. I even obtained from <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002422"
          >Peters</tei:rs> a copy of their edition No. 716; but, if I am not mistaken, it does at
        all not include the minuet in question. For your information I am sending you the volume and
        ask you to keep it if you have use for it; in any case you had a great deal of trouble over
        the matter. The two photographs are enclosed. The great Bavarian State Library does not
        appear to own the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000803">Schubert</tei:rs>; at any rate
        the volume was not available. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000067">Berrsche</tei:rs>
        owns a variant edition from his school days; likewise, all my musical friends have been
        unable to help so that, being in extreme difficulty, I wanted to ask you for your
          copy.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> Now I hope to receive the correct
        edition by tomorrow morning and will go over the thing carefully with <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000067">Berrsche</tei:rs>. Please do not be impatient about the delay.
        Perhaps, however, it is even better for you if the article appears in the March number,
        since this issue will be published with an increased print-run and thus reach a wider
        circle. We will, moreover, not neglect to flag up the issue to the the journalistic world.
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000067">Berrsche</tei:rs> is delighted by your
        collaboration and spoke with great enthusiasm about the article (I gave him the
        galley-proofs).</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> As you will have heard, <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000326">August Halm</tei:rs> has been taken away from us. It is a very painful
        loss. Just a few days ago he wrote to me that he was planning a few trips; but he had to
        consult his doctor, although he did not see what the point of that was. We shall publish a
        short composition of his, and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000067">Berrsche</tei:rs>
        will use this occasion to write a short appreciation of him. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">With best regards,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:handShift new="#HR"/><tei:rs key="entity-000717"
            type="person">Rinn</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
