<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2289" sdoID="OJ-15-15_D">OJ 15/15,[D]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HW" scope="sole">Hans Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008, 2019</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2008, 2019</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-06-25" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated July 20, [1910]</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1910-07-20T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-10-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Weisse has ‒ unfairly, in his view ‒ been failed in Latin. He is spending the
        summer in Ischl, and asks Schenker if he could visit him in the Dolomites, even if for a
        short time, to prove that he is not as immature as some of his schoolteachers seem to
        think.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Nachricht; news; Latein; Latin; Ungerechtigkeit; injustice; heimsuchen; visit at
        home; Arbeit; work; Hotelzimmer; hotel room; Schicksal; fate; Talent; Lehrer; teacher;
        Gymnasium; school; </dc:subject>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000951">Weisse</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HW"/>Liebster Herr <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000632">Doktor</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>


      <tei:p>Die Nachricht, die Sie erwarten, kann leider nicht kommen, da ich aus Latein gefallen
          bin.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">The letter is partly
          undated, lacking its year. That it almost certainly dates from 1910 is suggested by
          internal evidence: (1) 1910 was the only year in which Schenker vacationed in the
          Karerpass (1910 diary: July 3‒September 30); (2) that Weisse is writing to Schenker about
          having failed in Latin suggests that this letter was written no later than the beginning
          of the summer in which Weisse would have graduated from high school. If so, it would
          pre-date Weisse's earliest dated correspondence with Schenker (1911).</tei:note> Es war
        eine enorme Ungerechtigkeit, doch kurz: dies lässt sich nur erzählen; in einem Brief ist
        nicht Platz genug für solchen Unsinn. Momentan bin ich in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002339">Ischl</tei:rs>, wo es bekanntlich viel regnet, und sehne mich aus dem
        Kessel heraus.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun, lieber Herr Doktor<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> kommt eine
        entscheidende Frage: Würde es Ihnen sehr unangenehm sein, wenn ich Sie z. B. auf eine Woche
        am <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004033">Karer</tei:rs>- <tei:pb n="2"/>
        <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004033">pass</tei:rs>e heimsuchen würde? Meine Eltern
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">haben</tei:add> zu diesem kleinen Spritzer bereits <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">I</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="inline">i</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>hre Erlaubnis gegeben und ich würde mich riesig freuen. So hängt es nur mehr von
        Ihnen ab? Ich will selbstverständlich <tei:add place="interlinear-above">nicht</tei:add>
        dass Sie irgendwie durch mich inkommodiert werden, dass Sie meinetwegen nur ein wenig in
        Ihrer Arbeit gestört werden! Wenn es Ihnen aber angenehm wäre, so ersuche ich Sie vielmals
        mir so bald als möglich zu schreiben, wie ich nach Ihrer Meinung von hier am leichtesten zum
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004033">Karerpass</tei:rs>e gelangen könnte, ausserdem
        auch wie lange Sie mich ertragen können, drittens wie- <tei:pb n="3"/> viel das Hotelzimmer
        kostet, damit ich mit genügend Geld <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">ausgesta</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">versehen</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> werde! <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">No such
          visit is recorded in Schenker's 1910 diary, nor is Schenker's reply known to
          survive.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Für mich wäre es selbstverständlich ein Hochgenuss! Denn ich kann auch nicht
          umhin<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> Ihnen zu sagen, wie sehr ich
        meinen Schicksal danke<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> dass es mich mit
        Ihnen zusammengeführt hat, mit Ihnen, durch den ich erst ein richtiges Auge für all die
        herrlichen Dinge bekommen habe und es ist doch sicher: Bei Ihnen kann sich ein kleines
        Talent mehr entfalten, wie ein grosses bei einem andern. ___________</tei:p>

      <tei:p>So würden für mich einige wunderschöne Stunden in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002334">Tirol</tei:rs> blühen <tei:pb n="4"/> und es würde mir vielleicht
          gelingen<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> Sie, als den Lehrer, den ich
        sehr, sehr verehre, zu überzeugen, dass ich doch nicht so unreif bin wie es einige
        feindliche Herren im Gymnasium zu vermuten sich gezwungen (?) sahen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ihrer Nachricht ungeduldig entgegensehend grüsse ich Sie als Ihrer</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">dankbarer kleiner Meister</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
          >Hans</tei:rs>.</tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002339">Ischl</tei:rs>, den <tei:date
            when="1910-07-20">20. Juli</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HW"/>Dearest Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs
              type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>


      <tei:p>The news that you are expecting can unfortunately not be transmitted, as I have failed
          Latin.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> It was a terrible injustice, but in
        brief: I can only explain this in person; in a letter there is not enough space for such
        nonsense. At present I am in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002339">Ischl</tei:rs> where,
        as is well known, it rains a lot, and I am dying to get out of this kettle.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Now, my dear Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity">Schenker</tei:supplied>, comes an
        important question: would it be a great displeasure to you if I were to look you up at home
        while I am at the <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004033">Karer Pass</tei:rs> for, say, a
        week? <tei:pb n="2"/> My parents <tei:add place="interlinear-above">have</tei:add> just
        given their permision for this little adventure, so it depends now only on you. Of course, I
        do not wish in any way for you to be inconvenienced by me, that your work is disturbed even
        a little for my sake! If this appeals to you, however, then I would ask you please to write
        to me as soon as possible, explaining how I can reach the <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-004033">Karer Pass</tei:rs> in the easiest way from here, also for how long
        you could bear me, and thirdly how <tei:pb n="3"/> much the hotel room costs, so that I can
        be provided with sufficient money!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>For me, it goes without saying that this would be a splendid treat. For I cannot help
        telling you how much I thank my lucky stars that they led me to you: to you, through whom I
        first received a proper eye with which to see all the wonderful things. And it is indeed
        true that, in your hands, a small talent can develop more than a great talent in someone
        else's hands. ___________</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Thus a few wondrously beautiful hours in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002334"
          >Tyrol</tei:rs> would bloom for me, <tei:pb n="4"/> and I would probably succeed in
        convincing you, as the teacher whom I honor so very much, that I am not, after all, so
        immature as a few hateful gentleman in the grammar school saw themselves forced to
        suspect.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Impatiently awaiting your news, I greet your as your</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">thankful little master,</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
          >Hans</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002339">Ischl</tei:rs>, <tei:date
            when="1910-07-20">July 20</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
