<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3897" sdoID="OJ-13-10_185">OJ 13/10, [185]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2025</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated June 17, 1934</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1934-06-17T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-12-22</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel has seen a performance of Strauss’s Arabella, of which he is highly
        critical. – He has been judging a choral competition in Bingen am Rhein and seeing a friend
        there, and will see another friend in the Hunsrück. -- He has encountered the music of
        Richard Trunk, who is in great favor with Hitler.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1934-06-07">17. Juni
          1934</tei:date>. Könneritzstr 58<tei:hi rend="supralinear">III</tei:hi>.</tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Professor Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
            >Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for June 20, 1934: “Von Oppel
            (Br. zum Geburtstag): vorläufig zur Seite gelegt.” (“From Oppel (letter, on my birthday
            [June 19]): laid aside for the time being.”). – The diary for June 19 recorded: “An
            Oppel (Ansichtsk.): Adresse, Furtwängler will uns besuchen.” (“To Oppel (picture
            postcard): address, Furtwängler wants to visit us.”). – Schenker’s eventual response is
            recorded on June 25: “An Oppel (Br.): Dank für den Glückwunsch; über den Stand meiner
            Augen, des <tei:title>freien Satzes</tei:title>, über Furtwängler – Strauß, Hoboken als
            Villenbauer, Weisse, Jonas u. a. m.” (“To Oppel (letter): thanks for his best wishes;
            concerning the state of my eyes, <tei:title level="m">Free Composition</tei:title>;
            about Furtwängler – Strauss, Hoboken as a villa builder, Weisse, Jonas, and much
            else.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>nehmen Sie zunächst meine herzlichsten Glückwünsche zu Ihrem Geburtstage entgegen,
        hoffentlich verbringen Sie den Tag mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Ihrer
          lieben Frau</tei:rs> schon in den so wohlverdienten Ferien in den geliebten Bergen. Wie
          <tei:sic>gehts</tei:sic> es? Was machen die Augen? Was sagen die Ärtzte? Und wie weit ist
        die Drucklegung des „<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title>fr
          S</tei:title></tei:rs>“? Sie wissen, wieviele Fragen mich um Sie bewegen. Nun spannen Sie
        nur tüchtig aus! </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich selbst musste in den Pfingstferien nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004583"
          >Bingen</tei:rs> als Preisrichter zu einem Männerchorwettstreit; der Anlass war weniger
        schön, denn die Litteratur ist übel und das Amt eines Richters undankbar, aber ich
        verbrachte so ein paar schöne Tage am Rhein mit meinem alten Freund <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-006121">Knettel</tei:rs>. Nun hause ich seit 8 Tagen allein, <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-005266">meine Frau</tei:rs> ist mit den <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-004801">Kindern</tei:rs> zu ihren Eltern nach <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002495">Frankfurt am Main</tei:rs> zur Erholung. Wir schliessen am <tei:date
          when="1934-07-15">15. Juli</tei:date> und haben jetzt Prüfungen. Musikalisch ist nichts
        Wesentliches passiert. Am Freitag hörte ich <tei:title>Arabella</tei:title> von <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000871">Strauss</tei:rs> und war davon wenig entzückt. Der Stoff
        reicht grade für eine Operette. Das Orchester ist überladen, alles bleibt
          artistisch,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">It is not clear why
          Oppel is using the word <tei:hi rend="italic">artistisch</tei:hi> pejoratively. He may be
          thinking of it as a synonym for <tei:hi rend="italic">künstlich</tei:hi>
          (“artificial”).</tei:note> keine Einfälle, wenig <tei:term>Form</tei:term>, u. immer die
        gleiche fade <tei:term>Auskomponierung</tei:term>. Und eine üble, kümmerliche u. armselige
          <tei:term>Bassauswickelung</tei:term>. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-005889">Gewandhaus</tei:rs>dirigent wird nun
          Abendroth<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Hermann Abendroth
          (1883–1956) was appointed conductor of the Leipzig Gewandhaus Orchestra in 1934,
          succeeding Bruno Walter. He quickly found favor with the Nazi regime but did not join the
          party until 1937</tei:note> aus <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002604">Köln</tei:rs>,
          <tei:pb n="2"/> der aber weit hinter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268"
          >Furtwängler</tei:rs> bleibt. – Am <tei:rs type="orgainzation" key="entity-002872"
          >Institut</tei:rs> gehn unsre socialen Kämpfe weiter. – Die letzte Nummer unsrer <tei:rs
          type="journal" key="entity-002480"><tei:title>Zschr f. Mwiss.</tei:title></tei:rs> brachte
        2 Aufsätze über <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000871">Strauss</tei:rs>, die ich aber gar
        nicht zu Ende las. Lobhudeleien; mit etwas wiss. Anstrich ohne die Tiefe wirklicher
        Erkenntnis. – Zufällig sang grade in den Tagen, die ich am Rhein verbrachte, der Kölner
        Männergesangsverein in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-005401">Kreuznach</tei:rs> unter
        Trunk, der bei <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003109">Hitler</tei:rs>
        <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">persona grata</tei:foreign> ist. Es war schlimm, was der Mann
        sich leistete, als Chorleiter u. als Komponist<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Richard Trunk, an early and enthusiastic member of the Nazi Party, composed
          several works celebrating the new regime, among them <tei:title level="m">Feier der neuen
            Front</tei:title> (composed in 1932–33 and published in 1935) which comprises four
            <tei:hi rend="italic">a cappella</tei:hi> numbers: “<tei:title>Hitler</tei:title>”;
            “<tei:title>Des Führers Wächter</tei:title>”; “<tei:title>O, Land</tei:title>”; and
            “<tei:title>Horst Wessel</tei:title>.”</tei:note> u. als Begleiter seiner singenden
        Frau. Noch schlimmer, dass solch ein Männerchoresel Mitdirector des <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002956">Kölner Konservatorium</tei:rs>s ist. Aber diese Leute haben „Erfolg“.
        Für die Kunst bleiben sie Eintagsfliegen. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In den Ferien gehe ich wieder in den Hunsrück zu <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000207">Engelhardt</tei:rs> u. nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004583"
          >Bingen</tei:rs> und nehme dann <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008523">Bepo</tei:rs>
        mit, der jetzt in dem Alster ist, in dem Kinder nach allem fragen; <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-005266">meine Frau</tei:rs> schrieb mir grade, es sei sehr schwer für sie, ihm
        immer recht zu antworten. Er ist eben ein lebhafter Bub und wird uns schon noch Rätsel genug
        aufgeben. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> besuche ich am nächsten
        Sonntag. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003957">Walter</tei:rs> klagt über zu starke
        Ausnutzung im Geschäft. – Haben Sie noch was von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
          >Weisse</tei:rs> gehört? Will er ganz in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002510"
          >Amerika</tei:rs> bleiben? – Sind Sie wieder in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-006028"
          >Reigersberg</tei:rs>? </tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Alles Gute und die herzlichsten Grüsse</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Ihnen beiden</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">von Ihrem treuen</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1934-06-07">June 7, 1934</tei:date>.
          Könneritzstrasse 58<tei:hi rend="supralinear">III</tei:hi></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor
            Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>First of all, accept my most heartfelt good wishes for your birthday; I hope that you
        are spending the day with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">your dear wife</tei:rs>
        on a well-earned holiday in your beloved mountains. How are you? How are your eyes? What do
        the doctors say? And how far along is the printing of <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001728"><tei:title level="m">Free Composition</tei:title></tei:rs>? You know
        how many questions about you are of concern to me. Now, just unwind thoroughly! </tei:p>

      <tei:p>I myself had to go to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004583">Bingen</tei:rs> during
        the Pentecost holiday, to serve as judge at a competition of male choirs. The occasion was
        less gratifying, as the literature is awful and the office of judge thankless; but I was
        able to spend a few beautiful days on the Rhine with my old friend <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-006121">Knettel</tei:rs>. Now I’m on my own at home; <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-005266">my wife</tei:rs> has gone with the <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-004801">children</tei:rs> to her parents in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002495">Frankfurt am Main</tei:rs>, to recuperate. We finish on <tei:date
          when="1934-07-15">July 15</tei:date> and are now holding examinations. Musically, nothing
        of significance has happened. On Friday, I heard <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000871"
          >Strauss</tei:rs>’s <tei:title level="m">Arabella</tei:title> and was little charmed by
        it. The material is really more appropriate for an operetta. The orchestra is overladen,
        everything remains artistic;<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> no imaginative
        ideas, little <tei:term>form</tei:term>, and always the same dull
          <tei:term>composing-out</tei:term>. And a poor, cumbersome and impoverished
          <tei:term>unfolding of the bass</tei:term>. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>The new conductor of the <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-005889">Gewandhaus</tei:rs>
        is Abendroth<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> from <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002604">Cologne</tei:rs>, <tei:pb n="2"/> who remains far inferior to <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs>. – At the <tei:rs
          type="orgainzation" key="entity-002872">Institute</tei:rs>, our social battles continue. –
        The last issue of our <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002480"><tei:title level="j"
            >Zeitschrift für Musikwissenschaft</tei:title></tei:rs> contained two essays on <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000871">Strauss</tei:rs> which, however, I did not at all read
        to the end. Gushing flattery; with a bit of scholarly veneer, but without the depth of true
        understanding. – By chance, during the days that I spent on the Rhine, the Cologne Men’s
        Choral Society sang in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-005401">Kreuznach</tei:rs> under
        Trunk, who is a favorite of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003109">Hitler</tei:rs>’s.
        What the man accomplished was bad: as choral conductor and as composer,<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> and as the accompanist of his wife who sang. Even
        worse, such a male-choir ass is the co-director of the <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002956">Cologne Conservatory</tei:rs>. But these people are “successful.” For
        art, they remain one-day wonders. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>In the holidays I shall again go to the Hunsrück to see <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000207">Engelhardt</tei:rs>, and to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004583"
          >Bingen</tei:rs>; I shall take <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008523">Bepo</tei:rs>
        with me who is now at the age in which children ask about everything; <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-005266">my wife</tei:rs> has just written to me to say that it is very
        difficult for her to answer him properly. He is indeed a lively boy and will still give us
        plenty of mysteries to solve. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I shall visit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> next Sunday.
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003957">Walter</tei:rs> complains that he is being
        exploited too much by his business. – Have you heard anything from <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs>? Will he stay in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002510">America</tei:rs>? – Will you be going to <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-006028">Reigersberg</tei:rs> again? </tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>All good wishes and the most cordial greetings</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">to the two of you</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">from your faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
