<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3791" sdoID="OJ-13-10_115">OJ 13/10, [115]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2025</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Schenker, dated November 6, 1930</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1930-11-06T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-09-12</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel congratulates Schenker on recovering from his recent illness. — Hertzka
        does not want to authorise the reprinting of “The Mission of German Genius.” — Oppel will
        speak to a Kiel publisher about reprinting Schenker’s Harmonielehre (1906). — He has learned
        that a Fughetta in D attributed to Bach was completed by Carl Czerny. — He comments on his
        work on Brahms’s study of parallel fifths and octaves.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1930-11-06">6. November
            1930</tei:date>.</tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Professor Schenker</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
            >Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for November 8, 1930: “Von Oppel
            (Br.): freut sich meiner Genesung, Hertzka habe den Abdruck verweigert” (“From Oppel
            (letter): he is delighted about my recovery; Hertzka has refused the reprinting”). — All
            but one of the paragraph-breaks are editorial, guided by the emdashes in the original
            text.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p><tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">Als</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="inline">Wie</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> ich eben bei der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094"
          >Brahms</tei:rs>studie<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Brahms’s
          study of parallel fifths and octaves in music from the 16th to 19th centuries, of which
          Schenker, with Oppel’s help, produced a facsimile edition, <tei:bibl><tei:rs type="work"
              key="entity-003331"><tei:title>Johannes Brahms, Oktaven und Quinten
              u.a.</tei:title></tei:rs> (Vienna: UE, 1933)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005626">Cherubini</tei:rs>’s <tei:title>Medea</tei:title>
        controlliere, nach der originalen frzös. Partiturausgabe, finde ich nach dem Titelblatt die
        Widmung des Werkes <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005626">Cherubini</tei:rs> à Mehul; die
        folgende Seite dann lautet:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">In
          the full score of <tei:title level="m">Medea</tei:title> published in Paris by Imbault ca.
          1800, the publisher’s quatrain praising Cherubini appears before, not after, the
          composer’s dedicatory words to Méhul.</tei:note>
        <tei:cit>
          <tei:q><tei:lg>
              <tei:l>Au Citoyen Cherubini</tei:l>
              <tei:l>l’éditeur de la partition de Medée</tei:l>
              <tei:l>Quelque soin que l’on prenne à graver vos ouvrages</tei:l>
              <tei:l>Pour les transmettre à la postérité;</tei:l>
              <tei:l>leur mérite connu, senti dans tous les ages,</tei:l>
              <tei:l>est leur droit le plus sur à l’immortalité</tei:l>
            </tei:lg></tei:q>
        </tei:cit>
      </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wann hat je ein Verleger einem seiner deutschen Autoren solch eine Anerkennung
        öffentlich ausgesprochen? – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>___________________________</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ihr lieber Brief vom <tei:date when="1930-10-31">31. X. 30.</tei:date><tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is recorded in
          Schenker’s diary for October 31, 1930: “An Oppel (Br.): kurzer Dank; erzähle den Verlauf
          der Krankheit, die Hauptlehre heißt: nicht mehr so anstrengen wie bisher!! Ich lege den
          Namen des Kieler Seminarlehrers bei; zweifle, daß Hertzka die Einwilligung zum Abdruck
          geben werde. Meine Frage nach der neuen Auflage des Bd. I noch unbeantwortet” (“To Oppel
          (letter): brief thanks; I recount the course of my illness, from which the principal
          lesson to be drawn is: Do not exert yourself as much as you have been!! I enclose the name
          of the seminar teacher in Kiel, doubt that Hertzka will give his permission to reprint. My
          inquiry about a new edition of volume I still unanswered”).</tei:note> hat mich sehr
        gefreut, sagte mir doch schon Ihre Handschrift, dass es wieder besser geht. Ich muss Ihnen
        sagen, ich war sehr in Sorge. Dass Sie jetzt <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >eine</tei:add> Pause zwischen den einzelnen Stunden einlegen, ist sehr gut; ich weiss,
        was mich altes Droschkenpferd meine 10 Stunden in den ersten <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">3</tei:add> Tagen der Woche immer für Kraft kosten. Lassen sie
        doch v. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380"><tei:sic>Hobocken</tei:sic></tei:rs> mehr
        allein arbeiten, er dankt es Ihnen doch nicht. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Waldemar Schmidt-Carstens hat in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002757">Kiel</tei:rs>
        ein kleines Konservatorium, circa 60 Schüler, er ist ein blasser, blutiger <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000924">Wagner</tei:rs>epigon u. weiter nicht ernst zu nehmen;
        er hat keine Ahnung von Theorie; ich <tei:pb n="2"/> hatte einige Schüler von ihm, die in 3
        Jahren absolut nichts gelernt hatten; die Notiz von ihm i. d.
          <tei:title>Tonkünstlerzeitung</tei:title> hatte ich übrigens gelesen. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356"><tei:sic>Herzka</tei:sic></tei:rs> will
        tatsächlich den Abdruck<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">A
          projected reprinting of <tei:title level="a">Von der Sendung des deutschen
            Genies,</tei:title>
          <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001740"><tei:title level="j">Tonwille</tei:title>
            1</tei:rs>, 1–21, in the Hochschulblätter of Kiel Conservatory.</tei:note> nicht
        erlauben, natürlich aus Feigheit u. Angst. – Wegen des <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001754">I. Band</tei:rs>es II. Auflage<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06"
          type="editorial" place="foot">The idea of a reprinting or revised edition of Schenker’s
          vol. I, <tei:title level="m">Harmonielehre</tei:title> was first raised by <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000922">Otto Vrieslander</tei:rs> in 1915. Oppel’s inquiry to
          Universal Edition in 1929 received the response, <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OC-52-856">OC 52/856</tei:ref>, September 25, 1929, that the volume “is in fact
          now out of print.” Schenker himself then wrote to UE, <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="WSLB-418-1">WSLB 418/1</tei:ref>, December 19, 1929, about the possibility of a
          new edition, to which Hertzka responded, <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-52-857"
            >OC 52/857</tei:ref>, December 20, 1929, that the prospects were “not very promising.”
          Schenker wrote again on October 13, 1930, <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="WSLB-422"
            >WSLB 422</tei:ref>, inquiring as to the costs of producing an unrevised edition, to
          which UE’s <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000735">Ernst Roth</tei:rs> replied, <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OC-52-863">OC 52/863</tei:ref>, November 4, that the
          unchanged text in a similar binding would be 5,000 shillings.</tei:note> will ich einmal
        nächsten Montag mit meinem Freund u. Poelschel sprechen, einem hiesigen Verleger, ob es gegen
        den verdammten <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356"><tei:sic>Herzka</tei:sic></tei:rs>
        keinen Ausweg u. Rechtsmittel gibt. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003957">Walter</tei:rs> besuchte ich vorige Woche auf
        der Durchreise nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002757">Kiel</tei:rs> in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002589">Hamburg</tei:rs>, er hat sich sehr gut i. s. Geschäft
        eingeführt. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Die unvollendete Fuge <tei:add place="interlinear-above">D dur</tei:add> von <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000027">Bach</tei:rs> ist übrigens i. d. <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002422">Edition Peters</tei:rs> von <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000148">Czerny</tei:rs> bereits ausgeführt, wie ich jetzt festgestellt habe u.
        gut gelöst. Ich glaube es war No. 249.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial"
          place="foot">The Fantasy and Fughetta in D major BWV 908 is now believed to be the work of
          Gottfried Kirchhoff, a contemporary of Bach. Czerny’s “completion” consists in the
          realization of the figured bass passages in which fugal counterpoint is suspended. It was
          included in a volume published by C. F. Peters in 1898 comprising keyboard works of Bach
          edited by Czerny, Friederich Conrad Griepenkerl, and Friedrich August Roitsch.</tei:note>
        – </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs> hat sich i. der. 5 u. 8
        Studie sehr überlegt, ob die Tenorstimme wirklich i. d. Tenor lage liegt, u. ist selbst mit
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000612">Mozart</tei:rs> nicht zufrieden, wenn er sie als
        Oberstimme, (resp. Sopranlage) behandelt. In Zukunft werde ich alle Stellen, die wir
        begegnen, daraufhin controllieren.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun arbeiten Sie nicht zuviel, u. auch <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Ihre
          liebe Frau</tei:rs> darf sich nicht überanstrengen; die Natur rächt sich immer! </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Alles Gute u. die herzlichsten Grüsse</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Ihnen beiden</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">von Ihrem treuen</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:date when="1930-11-06">November 6,
            1930</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor
            Schenker</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>While examining <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005626">Cherubini</tei:rs>’s
          <tei:title level="m">Medea</tei:title> in the original French edition of the score as I go
        through <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs>’s study,<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> I found <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005626"
          >Cherubini</tei:rs>’s dedication of the work to Méhul. The page after this reads as
          follows:<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/>
        <tei:cit>
          <tei:q><tei:lg>
              <tei:l>To Citizen Cherubini</tei:l>
              <tei:l><tei:supplied>from</tei:supplied> the publisher of the score of Medea:</tei:l>
              <tei:l>However much trouble one may take over engraving your works,</tei:l>
              <tei:l>In order to transmit them to posterity,</tei:l>
              <tei:l>It is their own merit, known and seen throughout the ages,</tei:l>
              <tei:l>Which is their most certain right to immortality.</tei:l>
            </tei:lg></tei:q>
        </tei:cit>
      </tei:p>

      <tei:p>When did a publisher ever publicly pay such a tribute to one of his German composers?
        –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>____________________________</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Your kind letter of <tei:date when="1930-10-31">October 31, 1930</tei:date><tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> delighted me greatly; your handwriting alone
        indeed told me that you were again feeling better. I must tell you that I was very much
        concerned. It is very good that you are now inserting <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >a</tei:add> break between your individual lessons; I know what my ten lessons in each of
        the first <tei:add place="interlinear-above">three</tei:add> days of the week cost an old
        droshky horse like me. But if you let <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380"
          >Hoboken</tei:rs> work more on his own, he will not thank you for it. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Waldemar Schmidt-Carstens has a small conservatory in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002757">Kiel</tei:rs>, about sixty pupils. He is a dour, full-blooded <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000924">Wagner</tei:rs> epigone and not to be taken seriously
        any further. He has no idea of theory <tei:pb n="2"/> I had a few pupils of his who had
        learned absolutely nothing from him in three years; I have, moreover, read his notice in the
          <tei:supplied reason="title_incomplete"><tei:title level="j"
          >Deutsche</tei:title></tei:supplied>
        <tei:title level="j">Tonkünstlerzeitung</tei:title>. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356">Hertzka</tei:rs> will most certainly not
        permit the reprint,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> naturally out of
        cowardice and fear. – Concerning the second edition of your <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001754">first volume</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/>
        I shall speak next week with my friend and wartime companion Poelschel, who has a publishing
        house here, to see whether there really is no expedient or legal means to be used against
        the accursed <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356">Hertzka</tei:rs>. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p> I visited <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003957">Walter</tei:rs> last week in
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002589">Hamburg</tei:rs>, en route to <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002757">Kiel</tei:rs>; he has fitted in well into his business. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>The incomplete Fugue <tei:add place="interlinear-above">in D major</tei:add> by <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000027">Bach</tei:rs> has, by the way, been realised by <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000148">Czerny</tei:rs> in the <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002422">Peters</tei:rs> edition, as I have just found out, and well worked
        out. I believe it was No. 249.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> –</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs>, in his study of parallel
        fifths and octaves, spent a great deal of time considering whether the tenor voice really
        lies in the tenor register, and is not satisfied even with <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000612">Mozart</tei:rs> when he treats it as an upper voice (that is, in the
        soprano register). In future, I shall look carefully at all the passages we encounter in
        this respect. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Now, do not work too hard; and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">your dear
          wife</tei:rs>, too, should not overexert herself; Nature will always seek
        vengeance!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">All good wishes and the most cordial </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">greetings to the two of you</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">from your faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard
            Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
