<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="552" sdoID="OJ-14-15_1">OJ 14/15, [1]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="AS" scope="sole">Arnold Schoenberg's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="AW">
   <tei:persName>Arnold Whittall</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2011</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-09-13" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-003004">SchoenbergA ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schoenberg to Schenker, dated September 12, 1903</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1903-09-12T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2011-09-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schoenberg reports his progress on orchestrating Schenker's Syrische Tänze, and
    raises the matter of his fee for the work. He has approached Busoni about having his own
    symphonic poem performed. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>instrumentieren; orchestrate; Instrumentation; instrumentation; orchestration; Tanz;
    dance; Honorar; honorarium; fee; Auswahl; selection; performance</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000978">SchoenbergA</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-50">Payerbach <tei:date when="1903-09-12">12/9,
     1903</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute>Lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Doctor</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is not recorded in
      Schenker's diary. The document number adopted here is that assigned in <tei:bibl>Charlotte E.
       Erwin and Bryan R. Simms, <tei:title level="a">Schoenberg's Correspondence with Heinrich
        Schenker,</tei:title>
       <tei:title level="j">Journal of the Arnold Schoenberg Institute</tei:title> v (1981),
       23–43</tei:bibl>. The document from which this edition was made is a photocopy; the
      whereabouts of the original is not known. </tei:note>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">ich habe doch jetzt schon angefangen, Ihre „<tei:rs key="entity-001664" type="composition"><tei:title>Syrier</tei:title></tei:rs>“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker’s <tei:title level="m">Syrische Tänze</tei:title>, for
     piano four hands, were orchestrated by Schoenberg at the instigation of Ferruccio Busoni. The
     orchestrations were first performed on November 5, 1903, by the Berlin Philharmonic Orchestra,
     conducted by Busoni, in the Beethovensaal, Berlin. The score and performance materials have not
     so far been traced, and are presumed lost. </tei:note> zu instrumentieren, und es war gut, denn
    es ist leicht möglich, daß ich länger dazu brauche, als ich zuerst glaubte. Heute habe ich den
    ersten Tanz fertiggemacht. Wann das ganze fertig ist, weiß ich jetzt noch nicht, doch glaube ich
    kaum, daß es vor Ende nächster Woche fertig sein kann. Eher wesentlich später ‒ vielleicht gar
    erst Ende der zweitnächsten. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Und nun, nur damit es nicht dann eventuell doch zu Uneinigkeiten kommt, muß
    ich doch ein Wort über das Honorar sprechen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Busoni had suggested to Schenker that Schoenberg should be satisfied with "an
     opportunity to have his name on the programme also," but left "the eventual [financial]
     arrangement with Schoenberg" up to Schenker ‒ see <tei:bibl>Charlotte E. Erwin and Bryan R.
      Simms, <tei:title level="a">Schoenberg’s Correspondence with Schenker,</tei:title>
      <tei:title level="j">Journal of the Arnold Schoenberg Institute</tei:title> v (1981),
      26</tei:bibl>. </tei:note>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Falls es sich herausstellen sollte, daß <tei:hi rend="underline">Sie</tei:hi>
    die Instrumentation bezahlen müssen, würde ich <tei:add place="interlinear-above">sie</tei:add>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">Ihnen</tei:hi> für 100 Gulden machen. Falls aber <tei:rs key="entity-000946" type="person">Weinberger</tei:rs> dafür zahlt, könnte ich es nicht unter
    mindestens (<tei:hi rend="underline">bitte: mindestens</tei:hi>!) 150 Gulden hergeben. Womöglich
    aber (siehe oben) wesentlich mehr! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich rede von dieser Angelegenheit nur deshalb <tei:pb n="2"/> schon jetzt,
    weil dieses Honorar sich etwas höher stellt, als dasjenige das ich sonst, allerdings aber: für
     <tei:term>Operette</tei:term>n, erhalten habe. Aber ich habe schon an dem ersten Stück (19
     <tei:term>Partitur</tei:term>seiten<tei:del rend="overstrike">)</tei:del> d<tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overwritten">en</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="superimposed">ie</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> ich sonst bequem im 1. Tage mache) gesehen, daß diese Arbeit mir viel mehr Mühe
    mache. So habe ich auf das erste Stück 13 volle Arbeitstage gewendet. So erklärt sich wohl zur
    Genüge die Höhe des Honorars. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich hoffe, daß Sie, falls <tei:rs key="entity-000946" type="person">Weinberger</tei:rs> zahlt, mehr als dieses Minimum herausschlagen. Ich habe es nur angesetzt,
    weil ich die Arbeit gern machen will und <tei:add place="interlinear-above">um</tei:add> nicht
     <tei:hi rend="double-underline">dar</tei:hi>aus Schwierigkeit anstehen zu lassen </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich schicke Ihnen das fertige Stück gleich zu. Sollten Sie Wünsche haben, so
    bitte recht ausführlich zu schreiben. Ich glaube aber, daß es recht gut sein dürfte. Es ist nur
    schade, daß ein bißchen viel <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">ff</tei:hi>
     (<tei:term>fortissimo</tei:term>) in allen Stücken vorkommt. Da giebt es, <tei:pb n="3"/> wie
    man ja sogar ausrechnen kann, im <tei:term>Orchester</tei:term> viel weniger
     <tei:term>Klangfarbe</tei:term>n. Aber das wird kaum ein wesentliches Hindernis sein. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Noch eines: ich habe mich an <tei:rs key="entity-000116" type="person">Busoni</tei:rs>, wegen meiner <tei:term>symphonischen Dichtung</tei:term> gewendet.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:title level="m">Pelleas und
      Melisande</tei:title>, composed between February 1902 and July 1903. Busoni asked Schoenberg
     to send him the score, and wrote to the composer (October 15, 1903) praising his orchestration,
     but he never conducted the work. It was first performed in Vienna, conducted by the composer,
     on January 26, 1905. </tei:note> Gar nichts Verbindliches für Sie, natürlich! Denn ich hätte es
    auch so gethan, wenn ich auf irgend eine andere Art erfahren hätte, daß er seine
     <tei:term>Concert</tei:term>e wiedergiebt. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Zum Schlusse: Wir hatten vergessen, eine „Auswahl“ zu treffen. Ich halte es
    aber für besser, <tei:rs key="entity-000116" type="person">Busoni</tei:rs> nach der 1.
    Orchesterprobe wählen zu lassen, <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">und</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">damit</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> die dann „auserwählten“! Stücke doch diejenige sind, die am besten wirken. Im
    Honorar würde das insbesondere für Sie kaum ein wesentlicher Unterschied sein können, wenn wir
    Eines ausließen, also haben Sie wohl nichts dagegen. Ich sehe Ihre Nachricht entgegen und bin </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">mit besten Grüßen </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-70">Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50">
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798">Arnold Schönberg</tei:rs>
    </tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine>Payerbach 126</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>a/ <tei:unclear reason="reading">S.db.</tei:unclear></tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-50">Payerbach, <tei:date when="1903-09-12">September 12,
      1903</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity">Schenker</tei:supplied></tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">I have indeed made a start on the orchestration of your "<tei:rs key="entity-001664" type="composition"><tei:title>Syrians</tei:title></tei:rs>,"<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> and that is just as well, since it could be that I will
    need longer than I first hoped. I finished the first dance today. I still do not know when they
    will all be completed, but I doubt if it will be before the end of next week. More likely
    considerably later – perhaps towards the end of the week after next. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">And now, in order to avoid any possible misunderstanding later on, a word
    about the fee.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">If it turns out that you have to pay for the orchestration <tei:hi rend="underline">yourself</tei:hi>, I would charge <tei:hi rend="underline">you</tei:hi> 100
    Guilden <tei:add place="interlinear-above">for it</tei:add>. However, if <tei:rs key="entity-000946" type="person">Weinberger</tei:rs> is paying, I would not do it for less
    than (<tei:hi rend="underline">please note: less than</tei:hi>!) 150 Guilden. But if possible
    (see above) considerably more! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I raise this matter now <tei:pb n="2"/> because this fee is – understandably
    ‒ somewhat higher than I have received for <tei:term>operetta</tei:term>s. But I have already
    realised from the first piece (nineteen pages of <tei:term>score</tei:term>, which I could
    normally complete with ease on the first day) that this work will require much more effort on my
    part. I have therefore spent thirteen full working days on the first piece. That should
    sufficiently clarify the level of the fee. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I hope that, if <tei:rs key="entity-000946" type="person">Weinberger</tei:rs>
    is paying, you can obtain more than this minimum. I have fixed it only because I want to do the
    work and <tei:add place="interlinear-above">in order</tei:add> not to delay mentioning any
     <tei:supplied reason="clarity">possible</tei:supplied> difficulties in <tei:hi rend="double-underline">that</tei:hi> respect. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I shall send you the completed piece at once. Please write fully if you have
    any requests. But I think it will be quite good. It is just a pity that there is a little too
    much <tei:hi rend="italic">ff</tei:hi> (<tei:term><tei:hi rend="italic">fortissimo</tei:hi></tei:term>) in all the pieces. <tei:pb n="3"/> As one can imagine, this
    means many fewer <tei:term>orchestral</tei:term>
    <tei:term>tone color</tei:term>s. But this will hardly be a serious drawback. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">One more thing: I have approached <tei:rs key="entity-000116" type="person">Busoni</tei:rs> about my <tei:term>symphonic poem</tei:term>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> Nothing involving you, of course! I did this since I found out by other means
    that he was continuing with his <tei:term>concert</tei:term>s. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In conclusion: we had forgotten to agree on a "selection." I think it would
    be better to leave <tei:rs key="entity-000116" type="person">Busoni</tei:rs> to choose after the
    first rehearsal, <tei:subst>
     <tei:del>and</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">so that</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> the "chosen" pieces can be those that work best. It should make little difference
    to the fee, especially for you, if we were to leave one out, so you should have no objection. I
    look forward to your response and am </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">with best wishes, </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-70">Yours, </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50">
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798">Arnold Schönberg</tei:rs>
    </tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine>Payerbach 126</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>a/ <tei:unclear reason="reading_original">S.db.</tei:unclear></tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>