<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="2881" sdoID="OJ-15-6_5">OJ 15/6, [5]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="FW-pencil" scope="sole">Fritz Wahle's hand, in pencil</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2022</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2022</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2022</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-09-23" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008359">WahleF ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">letter</tei:rs>



   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Fritz Wahle to Schenker, dated November 3, 1904</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1904-11-03T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2022-10-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Fritz Wahle, who was probably at the receiving end of some witticisms of
    Schenker’s during a drinking session after a concert featuring a keyboard concerto by C. P. E.
    Bach, heaps praise on Schenker for having brought the work to life, and for having performed the
    piece so well – with his own cadenzas.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>

   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000925">WahleF</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#FW-pencil"/>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
      >Schenker</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Es muß mir auch so nicht sein! – Die Kneipe<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
     place="foot"><tei:hi rend="italic">Kneipe</tei:hi>: A bar (pub), a place to drink; hence
      <tei:hi rend="italic">kneipen</tei:hi>, to drink in a public locale. Wahle, however, is using
     this word to mean to engage in a sort of debate or argument that might take place in a drinking
     house – a competitive form of banter – in which the victor is the one who comes up with the
     wittiest or cleverest arguments. </tei:note> nach dem Concert erscheint gefährlich dem edlen
    Treiben vor demselben: Ein virtuoser Redner mag mich erlaubten Witz, denn der Humor ist von
    Gottesgnaden, Anfang, Ende schildern, wie es ihm gefällt – das scheint gefährlich, denn wer
    bürgt dafür, dass der Lacher <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">das</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">nicht</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> die höchste Not schildert, weil er sich in seinem weichen Herzen am meisten freut
    über die Kraft, die sie besiegt hat. Und indem er immer an diese sich freut, sonst würde er gar
    nicht kneipen<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> schildert er immer nur das, was
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">schlecht und</tei:del> feindlich scheint, weil er den Kämpfer um so
    schöner darstellt je mehr er seine Not <tei:del rend="overstrike">sch</tei:del> zeigt. Dies mein
    Tribut jenem Gefühle, da<tei:del rend="overstrike">s</tei:del>s einzufinden damit ist, daß man
    nach einem Concert nicht Orgien feiert, den Sinnen nicht völlig freien Lauf lässt, denn sie
    müßten lange schweigen<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> so lange als der Geist
    nach einem Reiche suchte, <tei:choice>
     <tei:sic>dass</tei:sic>
     <tei:corr>?das</tei:corr>
    </tei:choice> vielleicht ist, vielleicht von uns eingebildet ist. Also: wir haben heute nicht
    gekneipt – ich habe keine Rede gehalten, in dem ich Euch lächerlich gemacht habe, wir haben
    nicht Weiber – ich mag nicht weiter sprechen – </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich bin ganz allein in ein <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">illeg.
     word</tei:note> gegangen, habe folgendes gedacht: </tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/>
    <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000025">Ph. E. Bach</tei:rs>. Das Stück<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The piece in question is the Keyboard
     Concerto in A minor, H424, by C. P. E. Bach, with Schenker playing the solo part on piano, the
     orchestra (including Wahle) directed by Moriz Violin. The program, performed in the
     Bösendorfer-Saal on November ?2, 1904, also included a string quartet in C major by W.
     Stenhammer, a set of variations for piano and cello by Beethoven, WoO 46, and the Wind Octet
     (Serenade) in C minor, K 388/384a, by Mozart. Many notices and reviews of the concert are
     preserved in Schenker’s scrapbook (OC 2), pages 15–17.</tei:note> war erschütternd schön!
    Welche Phantasie! Man denke an <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000924">Wagner</tei:rs>, die
    Wagnerianer. Was bleibt für diesen <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000025">Bach</tei:rs>,
    jene, die mit ihm fühlen können – Keine Kneipe! Gut – wir wollen nicht kneipen. Und doch
     <tei:unclear reason="reading">erreiche</tei:unclear> ich einen physischen Rausch<tei:supplied
     reason="punctuation">.</tei:supplied> Meinen Körper möchte ich verbrauchen, wie ich mein Herz
    bedrängt habe!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Wahle writes
     continuously at this point, without paragraph-break.</tei:note>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Und nun <tei:hi rend="underline">Du</tei:hi> mein lieber Schenker – Du hast uns dieses
    herrliche Gut gebracht, Du bist schon reichlich belohnt, solange Du Dich damit beschäftigt hast,
    dein Glück wächst, während Du <tei:del rend="overstrike">uns</tei:del> den herrlichen Schatz vor
    uns niederlegst – und Du erreichst die höchste Stufe wenn das Stück verklungen ist – der Beifall
    führt Dich zurück aus dem Traumreich unter die Menschen: Du darfst das Schlagen meines Herzen
    hören. Du selbst bist mir während des ganzen Spiels beneidenswert glücklich erschienen, denn du
    scheinst bei den Göttern zu weilen. Du <tei:hi rend="underline">dürftest</tei:hi> diesen
    göttliche Wahrheit verkünden. Und die That! Dein famoses Klavierspiel, die Cadenzen! – Mir
    erschien diese Tat wie die Verkundigung unsäglichen Reichtums<tei:supplied reason="punctuation"
     >.</tei:supplied>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> Ich habe dich beneidet. Ich wollte das noch wiedersagen – auch über die
    anderen Stücke doch mir ist das Schreiben schon längst zuwider. Nächstes mal kneipen wir
    vielleicht – und dann rede ich hoffentlich nicht dummes Zeug, Du denkst an diesen Brief, das
    Ganze kann man dann humoristisch nennen. </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Servus</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Dein</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000925"
     >Fritz</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-008117">Caffe Central</tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10">Donnerstag <tei:date when="1904-11-03">3/11
      1904</tei:date>.</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#FW-pencil"/>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
      >Schenker</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>For me, too, it doesn’t have to be this way! – To have a banter<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> after the concert seems dangerous to the noble
    practice, in the face of itself; a masterly speaker may make a fool of me, for by the grace of
    God he can with humor portray everything in the way that pleases him. This seems dangerous; for
    who will guarantee that the one who laughs is not portraying the greatest need since he takes
    the greatest pleasure in his soft heart over the power which has overcome it? And by always
    taking pleasure in it – otherwise he would not banter at all – he always portrays only that
    which appears inimical since he can portray his adversary all the more attractively the more he
    demonstrates his need. This is my tribute to that feeling which is to be recognized that, after
    a concert, one should not conduct orgies, or given one’s thoughts a completely free reign; for
    they would long have to be silent for as long as the intellect is in search of a realm that may
    exist – or may exist in our imagination. Thus: we have not bantered today, I have not made a
    speech in which I have made the rest of you laughable; we do not have spouses – I may not speak
    any more.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>I have gone entirely on my own into a <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">illeg.
     word</tei:note> and come up with the following thought</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/>
    <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000025">C. P. E. Bach</tei:rs>: the piece<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> was strikingly beautiful! What imagination! One thinks
    of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000924">Wagner</tei:rs>, the Wagnerians. What remains for
    this <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000025">Bach</tei:rs>? Those who are able to feel with
    him – nothing to banter about! Well, then, we don’t want to engage in banter. And yet I reach a
    state of physical intoxication. I want to consume my body, as my heart has pressed me!<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>And now <tei:hi rend="underline">you</tei:hi>, my dear Schenker, you have brought us this
    splendid thing. You are already richly rewarded, having so long devoted yourself to it, your
    happiness increases while you lay this splendid treasure before us; and you reach the highest
    level when the piece is performed; the applause leads you from your realm of dreaming back among
    the people: you may hear the beating of my heart. You yourself appeared enviably happy during
    the entire performance, as you seem to be tarrying among the gods. You <tei:hi rend="underline"
     >may</tei:hi> proclaim this divine truth. And the execution: your splendid piano playing, the
    cadenzas! The performance seemed to me like the proclamation of inexpressible wealth.</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> I have been envious of you. I wanted to repeat that again – also about the
    other pieces – but I have already become averse to writing. The next time, perhaps, we shall
    banter, and then I hope I shall not say foolish things. You will think about this letter, the
    whole of which can be then called humoristic. </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Greetings from </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000925"
     >Fritz</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-008117">Café Central</tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10">Thursday <tei:date when="1904-11-03">November 3,
      1904</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
