<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="1017" sdoID="OJ-14-45_80">OJ 14/45, [80]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="MV" scope="sole">Moriz Violin's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
      <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-07-15" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002719">ViolinM ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM+V ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002718">ViolinM+V+F ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Violin to Schenker, dated November 19, 1929</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1929-11-19T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2013-07-15</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Violin apologizes for not having written, but does not want to burden Schenker
        with negative thoughts. He will try to help find a publisher for the "Eroica" analysis, and
        also offers some thoughts of comfort on hearing the news that Schenker's brother and
        sister-in-law have separated. He has little energy left, but is somehow able to muster it
        when needed, e.g. at a sold-out orchestral concert in which he played better than ever. He
        promises to be in Vienna over Christmas.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-30"><tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>,
            <tei:date when="1929-11-19">19. Nov. 29</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Liebster <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this
            letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/3, p. 3409 (November 21, 1929): "Von
            Floriz (Br.): schön im Gefühl u. Form; will hören, was ich bezüglich der Eroica für
            Ansprüche stelle." ("From Floriz (letter): he is feeling well and doing well, would like
            to know what plans I have for the 'Eroica.'")</tei:note>
        </tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Nur einem Brief<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-6-7_44">=OJ 6/7,
          [44]</tei:ref> von Dir hat das Schämen kein Ende. Auch die Angst daß Du meinst, ich glaube
        Du wartest auf Antwort oder ich will nur Antwort schreiben!! Wenn meine Not am höchsten,
        bist Du mir im<tei:note type="editorial">corr</tei:note> Geist am Nächsten, aber ich
        schreibe nicht, kann nicht schreiben, weil ich Dich als positivsten Menschen u. Freund nicht
        beschweren <tei:hi rend="underline">kann</tei:hi>, wo Du nur Bitterkeit empfinden musst u.
        nicht helfen kannst.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Das wichtigste aus Deinem Brief: die <tei:rs key="entity-001752" type="work"><tei:title>Eroika</tei:title></tei:rs>! Kannst Du mir nicht schreiben, welche
        Bedingungen zu beachten sind<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> die ein
        Verleger Dir zu leisten hat, soll er das Werk zum Druck bekommen? Bitte schreibe es mir; ich
        denke an etwas; es kann was sein oder auch nicht! Ideen schaden nicht u. Du weißt daß Deine
        Ehre jedenfalls bei mir in besten Händen u. größter Hütung ist.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Tagesneuigkeiten hast Du mir nicht wenig geschrieben! Es tut einem leid,
        hört man derartige, an der Ewigkeit nicht physisch teilnehmen zu können. Manches Lügenhaus <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#MV">wird</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#MV">würde</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>
        <tei:pb n="2"/>
        <tei:note type="editorial">illegible word deleted</tei:note> man da einstürzen sehen. Ich
        bin so begabt, daß mir <tei:rs key="entity-000774" type="person">Mozio</tei:rs> noch leid
        tun kann u. doch sehe ich sehr hell das Gewicht der Zeit – – – ; ihn verlässt die Person, um
          derentwille<tei:supplied reason="spelling">n</tei:supplied> er alles verlassen hat. Was
        bleibt ihm? Doch nur das, was er nie hätte verlassen sollen! Weit davon wirst Du als
        Betheiligster an diesem Gedanken, auch nicht denken!!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Meine letzten Energien kommen mir wie die Abschiedskonzerte vor; eine
        allerletzte Energie, eine auf vielseitigen Wunsch bringe ich doch immer noch auf. So
          <tei:date when="1929-11-13">letzten Mittwoch</tei:date>, wo ich im ausverkauften
        Sinfonie-Konzert spielte wie schon lange nicht so gut. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Über dieses, jenes u. anderes reden wir ja bald. Ich bin zu <tei:date when="1929-12-25">Weihnacht</tei:date> in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs>. Diesen Leichtsinn lasse ich mir nicht mehr nehmen.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-25">1000 Grüße, viel tausend Schönes u. Inniges von Uns an Dich u.
          Frau <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Lie</tei:rs></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Dein getreuester</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-75"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-30"><tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>,
            <tei:date when="1929-11-19">November 19, 1929</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dearest <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
        </tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">After one letter<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-6-7_44">=OJ 6/7,
          [44]</tei:ref> from you, my shame has no end. Even the fear that you think that I believe
        that you are waiting for an answer, or that I shall write only a reply!! When my
        difficulties are at their greatest, you are closest to me in spirit; but I do not write, I
        cannot write, because I <tei:hi rend="underline">could</tei:hi> not burden you, as the most
        positive person and friend, with things about which you would feel wretched but could do
        nothing.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">The most important thing in your letter: the "<tei:rs key="entity-001752" type="work"><tei:title>Eroica</tei:title></tei:rs>"! Can you not write to me, what
        conditions are to be noted, that a publisher would have to accomplish for you were he to
        print the work? Please write to me, I shall think of something: something will, or will not,
        come of it. Ideas do not hurt, and you know that, with me, your honor is at any rate in the
        best hands and under the greatest protection.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">You have not spared me the news of the day! One feels sorry, when one
        hears such things, that one is unable ever to share them physically. Many a tissue of lies
        would <tei:pb n="2"/>
        <tei:note type="editorial">illegible word deleted</tei:note> otherwise crumble as a result.
        I am so constituted that <tei:rs key="entity-000774" type="person">Mozio</tei:rs> can still
        harm me; and yet I see very clearly the judgment of time – – – ; he has been abandoned by
        the person for whom he has abandoned everything. What remains for him? Only that, of course,
        which he should never have abandoned. As the person most of all affected, your thoughts,
        too, will not be far from this thought!!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">My last ounces of strength appear to me like <tei:supplied reason="clarity">those needed for</tei:supplied> farewell concerts; I can, however, summon
        a final burst of energy if it is generally desired. So it was <tei:date when="1929-11-13">last Wednesday</tei:date>, when I played at a sold-out symphony orchestra concert than I
        have played for quite a long time.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">About this, that, and other things, we shall indeed speak soon. I shall be
        in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs> for <tei:date when="1929-12-25">Christmas</tei:date>. I shall not forgo this recklessness any longer.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-25">A thousand greetings, many thousands of beautiful and
          affectionate thoughts from us to you and <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Lie</tei:rs>.</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your most faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-75"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>