<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2882" sdoID="OJ-15-6_6">OJ 15/6, [6]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="FW" scope="sole">Fritz Wahle's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2022</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2011-09-23" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008359">WahleF ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Fritz Wahle to Schenker, undated [November ?27–28,
        ?1906]</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1906-11-28T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2022-10-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>In a letter written in the course of two evenings, Fritz Wahle thanks Schenker
        for sending him a copy of his latest book (probably Harmonielehre), which he wants to be
        among the first to read. He congratulates Schenker for having maintained such high goals in
        the writing of the work, which only Philistines would misunderstand, or seek to
        misrepresent. The letter includes an attempt to compare a servant who doesn’t know how to
        wear his master’s clothes to a philistine critic who has no concept of the value of a
        serious act of creation.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000925">WahleF</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#FW"/>Dienstag abends im Winterbierhaus<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">The Winterbierhaus was a popular
            alehouse which occupied the ground floor of the Winterhaus, a building in the first
            district of Vienna bounded by Landkrongasse, Tuchlauben and Wildpretmarkt. Franz
            Schubert found lodgings there for a time; the present edifice dates from
            1902.</tei:note></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs>!<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">This letter is written over two
            successive days, Tuesday and Wednesday. The editorial dating is based on (a) the fact
            that Wahle had moved previously on “11/11”, (b) November 27–28 are a Tuesday–Wednesday
            pair, and (c) the probability that the book sent was <tei:rs type="work"
              key="entity-001724"><tei:title level="m">Harmonielehre</tei:title></tei:rs> (the only
            one of Schenker’s publications not otherwise identifiable in these letters), the
            publication year of which was 1906.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Als ich gestern abends nachhause kam lag dein Buch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot">In all probability, Schenker’s anonymously published
              <tei:bibl><tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724"><tei:title level="m"
                >Harmonielehre</tei:title></tei:rs> (Stuttgart: J. G. Cotta, 1906)</tei:bibl>,
          issued on November 10, 1906. If Wahle had received this shortly after it had been issued,
          then he would have indeed been among the first to begin reading it.</tei:note> auf dem
        Tisch. Als ich heute erfuhr, dass Du es in der Währingerstrasse abgegeben (oder hast abgeben
        lassen) – ich wohne ja seit 11/11 Börsegasse 7 – ärgerte ich mich für Dich. Der Grund ist
        compliciert, wie die Gefühle. Ich war eitel genug, zu glauben, ich werde da unter den Ersten
        sein, die dein Buch in die Hände bekommen, und indem ich meinen Wunsch, mit deiner Absicht
        identificerte fand ich dieselbe um einen Tag geschädigt – so wie meinen Wunsch der
        Prioritaet. Nun mußte ich dein Buch bis heute abends liegen lassen, ich gestehe, dass ich
        von gestern 12<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> bis heute abends voller Erwartungsfreude
        war, das Buch zu lesen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-f4" type="editorial" place="foot">Wahle
          writes continuously at this point, without paragraph-break.</tei:note>
      </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun ich die ersten Capitel gelesen mögen diese Zeilen der Freundschaft an dich
        gerichtet sein. Ich zähle Dich ja auch unter die stille Gemeinde jener Braven, die sich nur
        dann an die Menschen wenden, wenn sie wirklich überzeugt sind, ihnen zu nützen, indem ich
        sie auf ihrem Wege zu begleiten wünschen beherrschen mich Gedanken, Wünsche: Ist er ein
        erster Prophet, hat sein Talent; seine Einsicht ihn wichtige Wege geführt, wird er Kraft
        genug <tei:pb n="2"/> haben, wenigstens die Hauptsachen überzeugend zu predigen? Und die
        Furcht vor der Bestie, die wir aus tausendjähriger Geschichte kennen<tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> bringt mich zu den Wünschen, die ebenso schwer
        aufzuzählen sind, wie die mannigfaltige Gemeinheit–Geringheit der Menschen: dass sie doch
        die elementaren Hauptsachen verstehen wollten, nicht wie die Schafe darüber wegstolpern mit
        dem Geblöcke: das ist ja längst bekannt. Dass sie nicht an das secundäre, da<tei:del
          rend="overstrike">s</tei:del>s sie misverstehen, weil sie das Primäre nicht als solches
        erfasst haben, sich klammern, es an sich reißen, sich seiner bemächtigen, wie der Affe, der
        in seiner dümmsten Triebe den Menschen nachahmt. – <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006822"
          >Savart</tei:rs> ist eben gekommen, ich unterbreche. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>(Mittwoch im Winterbierhaus) bevor ich zu deinem Buche greife will ich den Brief
        vollenden – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Die Kleider seines Herrn sich anzuziehen bemüht – die Ärmel des Rocks sollen ihm für
        die Beine dienen, die Hosen bindet er sich um den Hals, seine Bemühungen erscheinen komisch
        – doch die <tei:unclear reason="reading">jener</tei:unclear> kläglich, <tei:note
          type="editorial" place="inline">word crossed out</tei:note> unfruchtbar, doch oft auch
        gefährlich, denn die Elende zerstücken ein <tei:unclear reason="reading">recht</tei:unclear>
        gemeintes Ganzes, wie die Geier sitzen sie da mit einem <tei:unclear reason="reading"
          >Fegen</tei:unclear> Fleisch eines nicht kräftig frischen Körpers<tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">.</tei:supplied>
      </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> Und der Neid und die Mis<tei:supplied reason="omission"
          >s</tei:supplied>gunst, die Oberflächlichkeit, der Philister wird wie viele noch – sie
        bestimmen alle das Schicksal einer ernsten wolgemeinten Tat. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Dass du vor all dem Unbild bewahrt bleibst, dass deine Ueberzeugung auch die der
        anderen wird, dass du Verständnis, Einverständnis findest wünsche ich dir mit meiner ganzen
        Freundschaft, denn ich bin überzeugt, dass du ein Gutes gewollt, dass dies Buch ein Theil
        deines Lebens ist<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> ein versuchter Ausdruck
        deines Ichs, welches ich hoch schätze wegen seines Ernstes. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Und indem ich nun deinem Buche eine schöne glückliche Reise durch das Reich der Kunst
        wünsche </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Grüße ich dich bestens mit herzlichstem Danke </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">für die Widmung<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial"
            place="foot">Widmung: presumably a handwritten inscription to Wahle, at the front of the
            volume.</tei:note></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Dein</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000925"
          >Fritz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#FW"/>Tuesday evening, in the Winterbierhaus<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>When I returned home yesterday evening, your book<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
          type="footnote"/> lay on my desk. When I learned today that you had dropped it off (or had
        it dropped off) at Währingerstrasse – I have resided at Börsegasse 7 since November 11 – I
        was angry for your sake. My reason is as complicated as my feelings. I was vain enough to
        believe that I would be among the first to receive your book in my hands; and as I
        identified my wish with your intention, I found the latter damaged by one day – as was my
        desire for priority. Now I had to let your book lie until this evening; I admit that since
        noon yesterday until this evening I was full of the joy of expectation of reading your
          book.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Now that I have read the first chapter, may these lines of friendship be directed
        toward you. Indeed, I reckon you among the silent community of those brave people who
        address people only when they are truly convinced that they are able to be of use to them;
        insofar as I wish to accompany them on their way, I am governed by thoughts and wishes: if
        he is a first prophet, if his talent, his insight, led him in important directions, will he
        have sufficient strength <tei:pb n="2"/> at least to preach the major issues convincingly?
        And the fear of the beast which we know from thousands of years of history brings me to the
        desires, which are just as difficult to enumerate as the manifold vulgarity–meagerness of
        humanity: that they nonetheless wanted to understand the elementary principles, and not
        stumble away from them like bleating sheep, is something we have known for a long time; that
        they do not attach themselves to that which is secondary, which they misunderstand because
        they haven’t grasped the primary for what it is, like the ape which, in its stupidest
        activity imitates a human being. – <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006822">Savart</tei:rs>
        has just arrived, I shall interrupt.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>(Wednesday, in the Winterbierhaus): before I tackle your book, I want to finish this
        letter – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Anxious to put on the clothes of his master – the sleeves of the jacket shall serve him
        for legs, the trousers he wraps around his neck, his efforts seem comical – but those of the
          <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">others</tei:unclear> are wretched, unfruitful, but
        often also dangerous; the miserable ones tear to pieces a well-intentioned whole; like
        vultures, they sit there with a <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">piece</tei:unclear>
        of flesh from a not powerfully fresh corpse.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> And the envy and the resentment, the superficiality, how many more
        Philistines there will be – they will all determine the fate of a serious, well-meant
        deed.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>That you will remain safe from all this ignorance, that your convictions will also
        become those of the others, that you find understanding and accord, these are things that I
        wish for you with my entire friendship; for I am convinced that you have wanted something
        good, that this book is a part of your life, an attempt to express your very self, something
        I value highly because of its seriousness.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>And as I now wish your book a beautiful, happy voyage through the realm of art, </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">I greet you heartily, with the most cordial thanks</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">for the dedication.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05"
            type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000925"
          >Fritz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
