<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3803" sdoID="OJ-13-10_195">OJ 13/10, [195]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="RO" scope="sole">Reinhard Oppel's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2025</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008522">Oppel ~
        JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Oppel to Jeanette Schenker, dated November 1,
        1935</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1935-11-01T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-09-22</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Oppel reports that the Leipzig Conservatory has recently shown greater
        interest in Schenker’s writings. – He hopes that a good buyer can be found for Schenker’s
        unpublished papers and library of books and scores.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000643">Oppel</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:placeName>Leipzig</tei:placeName>, W 31.
              <tei:date when="1935-11-01">1 Nov. 1935</tei:date>. </tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Liebe, sehr verehrte <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
            >Frau D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Schenker</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>sehr gern hätte ich früher Ihren lieben Brief <tei:supplied reason="omission"
          >vom</tei:supplied>
        <tei:date when="1935-10-04">4. X.</tei:date> beantwortet, aber vor Arbeit kam ich nicht
        dazu. Inzwischen bekam ich schon den Prospekt des neuen „<tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-006970">Schenker-Institut</tei:rs>es“, der mich lebhaft gefreut hat. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Auch hier tagt es, unser Director hat von mir die <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001731"><tei:title>9. Symph.</tei:title></tei:rs> verlangt. Er will nun alles
        für die Bibliothek bestellen. Seither war nur der <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724">1.
          Band</tei:rs> (doppelt) vorhanden; u alle meine Vorstellungen scheiterten an der elenden
        Finanzlage. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ihren Schritt zur kleineren Wohnung verstehe ich vollkommen;<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">By October 1935, Jeanette Schenker had
          moved from Hofgastein to a room in a guesthouse in Hasenauerstraße, Vienna XVIII. But no
          doubt Oppel is referring to the move from Keilgasse 8, where Heinrich and she had lived
          for twenty-one years, to Hasenauerstraße.</tei:note> auch wie schwer es Ihnen geworden
        sein mag. Aber Sie taten ganz recht damit. Nun können Sie ganz der Ordnung u. Sichtung des
        Nachlasses widmen. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Natürlich schreibe ich Ihnen sehr gern über d. „<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"
            ><tei:title>fr. S</tei:title></tei:rs>“. Ich arbeite fast täglich daran. Kritik aus
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002510">Amerika</tei:rs>? Wer wagt da nach kurzer Lectüre
        ein Urteil? Ich staune, wie schnell manche Leute arbeiten, wozu wir doch halbwegs
        Eingeweihten Jahre brauchen, um alles redlich zu verfolgen! – </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003957">Walter</tei:rs> ist am <tei:date
          when="1935-10-28">28. X</tei:date> zu s. Infanterieregiment nach Kolberg/Ostsee
        eingerückt, um s. Pflichtjahr abzudienen. Warscheinlich wird er Weihn. in Urlaub kommen.
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> büffelt für s. erstes Examen.
        Den kleinen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">i.e. <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-008523">Kurt (Bepo)</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-008524">Brigitte</tei:rs>.</tei:note> gehts gut. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-005266">Meine Frau</tei:rs> hat, wie immer viel Arbeit, besonders jetzt
          <tei:pb n="2"/> bei dem Butter<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">-</tei:supplied> u.
        Fettmangel. Mir geht es leidlich. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Kann ich nicht einmal den Vortrag von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000754"
          >Salzer</tei:rs>, den er in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002578">Salzburg</tei:rs>
        gehalten hat, haben? – Sie wollten mir noch darüber schreiben. – Grosse Freude hatte ich
        neulich bei einem Klavierabend R. v. Koczalsky’s,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Raoul Koczalski (1884–1948), Polish pianist and composer,
          noted especially for his interpretation of the music of Chopin.</tei:note> der <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000129">Chopin</tei:rs> wirklich meisterhaft wiedergab,
        technisch u. geistig. Dagegen war ich entsetzt über die <tei:rs type="composition"
          key="entity-001383">6. Symph. von Bruckner</tei:rs>, die ich z. 1. Male hörte, ein elendes
        Machwerk; es besticht die Masse durch die glänzende Instrumentation; aber die
          <tei:term>Gedanke</tei:term>n u. die <tei:term>Synthese</tei:term> sind jämmerlich. Ich
        musste dabei immer an alle die Schwächen denken, die Meister Schenker so klar blossstellt,
        wie: keine Bass<tei:term>auswickelung</tei:term>, unlogische
        <tei:term>Diminution</tei:term>en u. dergl. mehr. – Ferner hörte ich einen Vortrag v.
        Börries v. Münchhausen über d. Wert des Buches, anlässlich einer Buchhändlertagung, der
        formell u. inhaltlich gleich hervorragend war. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Zum comp. komme ich leider sehr wenig, die Schule kostet zuviel Zeit u. Kraft. Unser
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002872">Institut</tei:rs> ist zwar anerkannte
        Hochschule, doch wird das kaum unsre pecuniäre Lage bessern. Der Staat hat bei dem Neuaufbau
        des Militärs kaum Geld für Kulturzwecke. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Hören Sie etwas von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>? Und
        von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs>? War es Meister Schenkers
        letzter Wille, dass seine Bibliothek u. s. Noten an die <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002686">Nationalbibliothek</tei:rs> gehn? Ich finde, der Staat sollte
        wenigstens einen Annäherungswert dafür geben. Hier in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002482">Deutschland</tei:rs> übernahmen meist Antiquare den Verkauf solcher
        Bibliotheken, so geschah es noch letzthin bei dem Nachlass <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000255">Friedländer</tei:rs>s.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Max Friedlaender (1852–1934), German musicologist, best known for his
          two-volume <tei:title level="m">Das deutsche Lied im 18. Jahrhundert</tei:title> (1902)
          and his editions of the songs of Beethoven, Carl Loewe, Schubert, Mendelssohn, and
          Schumann for the publishers C. F. Peters.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">sideways in left
          margin:</tei:note></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>Nun alles Gute u. die </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>herzlichsten Grüsse von uns allen!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>Ihr sehr ergebener u. treuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard Oppel</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#RO"/><tei:placeName>Leipzig</tei:placeName> W 31.
              <tei:date when="1935-11-01">November 1, 1935</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Dear, very revered<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
            >Mrs. Schenker</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>I would have very gladly answered your kind letter of <tei:date when="1935-10-04"
          >October 4</tei:date>, but I could not get to it on account of work. In the meantime, I
        have already received the prospectus of the new “<tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-006970">Schenker Institute</tei:rs>,” which delighted me greatly.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Here, too, things are dawning; our Director asked me for the <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001731"><tei:title>Ninth Symphony</tei:title></tei:rs>. He now wants to order
        everything for the library. Previously only <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724">volume
          I</tei:rs> (in two copies) was available; and all my suggestions ran aground on account of
        the miserable financial situation.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I completely understand your move to a smaller apartment, and also how difficult it may
        have been.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> But you did the right thing. Now
        you can dedicate yourself entirely to the ordering and examination of the unpublished
        papers. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Of course, I shall be very happy to write to you about <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001728"><tei:title level="m">Free Composition</tei:title></tei:rs>. I work on
        it almost daily. Criticism from <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002510">America</tei:rs>?
        Who would dare to make a judgment after reading it so quickly? I am amazed at how quickly
        many people work on things for which we, who are at least in part well-informed, need years
        to pursue everything conscientiously! –</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003957">Walter</tei:rs> was posted with his infantry
        regiment on <tei:date when="1935-10-28">October 28</tei:date> to Kolberg, on the Baltic Sea,
        for his obligatory year of military service. He is likely to come at Christmas during his
        leave. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000644">Ulrich</tei:rs> is cramming for his first
        examination. The little ones<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> are well.
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005266">My wife</tei:rs> has, as always, a great deal of
        work, especially now <tei:pb n="2"/> that there is a shortage of butter and fat. I am
        reasonably well. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Might I have the lecture that <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000754">Salzer</tei:rs>
        gave in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002578">Salzburg</tei:rs>? – You wanted to write to
        me about it. – Recently, I had the great pleasure of attending a piano recital given by
        Raoul Koczalsky,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> who performed <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000129">Chopin</tei:rs> with true mastery, technically and
        spiritually. By contrast, I was shocked by <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001383"
          >Bruckner’s Sixth Symphony</tei:rs>, which I heard for the first time, a wretched
        concoction; it captivates the masses with its dazzling instrumentation, but the
          <tei:term>idea</tei:term>s and the <tei:term/>synthesis are pathetic. In this regard, I
        always think about the weaknesses that Master Schenker exposed so clearly: no
          <tei:term>unfolding</tei:term> of the bass, illogical <tei:term>diminution</tei:term>s,
        and other such things. – In addition, I heard a lecture by Börries von Münchhausen on the
        value of the book, on the occasion of a bookdealers’ conference, which was outstanding both
        in form and content. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Unfortunately, I seldom get round to composing: the school takes up too much of my time
        and energy. Our <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002872">Institute</tei:rs> is, to be
        sure, a recognized college, but that will hardly improve our financial situation. The state,
        in rebuilding the military, has hardly any money for cultural purposes. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Do you hear anything from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922"
          >Vrieslander</tei:rs>? Or from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs>?
        Was it Master Schenker’s last wish that his library and scores should go to the <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002686">National Library</tei:rs>? I think that the State
        should pay at least what they are approximately worth. Here in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002482">Germany</tei:rs>, antique dealers generally arranged the sale of such
        libraries; that is still what happened recently with the estate of <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000255">Friedlaender</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"
        /></tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">sideways in left
          margin:</tei:note></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>For now, all good wishes and the </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>most cordial greetings from all of us!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>Your very devoted and faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Reinhard Oppel</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
