<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3569" sdoID="OJ-14-8_8">OJ 14/8, [8]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="AS" scope="major">Anna Schiff's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="PS" scope="major">Paul Schiff's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IDB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2025</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008461">SchiffP ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008460">SchiffA ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letters from Paul &amp; Anna Schiff to Heinrich &amp; Jeanette Schenker,
        dated November 27[–29], 1925</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1925-11-27T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2025-02-10</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Paul Schiff thanks Heinrich and Jeanette for the portrait of Heinrich and the
        photograph of Jeanette which suggests she has hardly aged. He has heard that his
        brother-in-law [Viktor Schiff] intends to emigrate to Palestine, which he thinks is a great
        mistake; he will keep them informed if he receives further news.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000782">Paul Schiff</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000781">Anna Schiff</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:div type="part_1">
        <tei:opener>
          <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#PS"/><tei:rs type="place"
              key="entity-002892">Prag</tei:rs>, am <tei:date when="1925-11-27">27. XI.
              1925</tei:date>.</tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
          <tei:salute>Meine Lieben!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
              >Receipt of at least the first of these two letters is recorded in Schenker’s diary
              for December 2, 1925: “Von Paul (Br.): Victors Bild! Lie-Liechen stellt die
              verblüffende Wandlung ins Amerikanische fest” (“From Paul (letter): Viktor's picture!
              Lie-Liechen notices the surprising transformation into the
            American”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:p rend="first">Wir haben der l. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
            >Lie-Lie</tei:rs>s Brief<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"
            >Schenker’s diary for November 23 records the sending of a letter to Paul, but without
            describing its content.</tei:note> u. einen Tag später auch das wundervolle Bild
          erhalten, das überaus kostbar ist.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
            place="foot">From the expression of thanks that Paul Schiff is uttering, and Anna
            asserts later, the picture in question was Viktor Hammer’s mezzotint portrait of
            Heinrich Schenker, completed in early October 1925. </tei:note> Vor allem dafür, daß Ihr
          uns dieses Bild gesandt habt, vielen Dank. Mich bedrückt bei alledem der Gedanke, es
          könnte Euch hiedurch Kosten erwachsen sein, mit denen Ihr ursprünglich nicht gerechnet
          habt. Schreibt mir darüber. Uns war daran gelegen, ein Bild des l. <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs> zu besitzen, das für uns auch dann, wenn es nicht
          so kunstvoll &amp; nicht künstlerisch so wertvoll gewesen wäre, einen lieben Wert besessen
          hätte. Nochmals für dieses Bild vielen Dank, das uns große Freude bereitet. — </tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first"><tei:unclear reason="reading"
            >Mit<tei:supplied>te</tei:supplied></tei:unclear> Montag werde ich mich bemühen, zu
          erfahren, ob die Werke die in dem Verlag, dessen Namen ich aus einem der letzten <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000771">Lie Lie</tei:rs>s mitnehmen kann, <tei:subst>
            <tei:del rend="overstrike">bei</tei:del>
            <tei:add place="interlinear-above">in</tei:add>
          </tei:subst> den größten Buch- &amp; Musikalienhandlungen aufliegen u. zu welchen Preisen
          die Bücher hier verkauft werden. <tei:pb n="2"/> Das zu erfahren kann mir nicht schwer
          fallen, weil ich hier im Buchhandel einen über diese Dinge gut informierten Bekannten
          habe, der mir behilflich sein wird. Ich hoffe, Euch dann schon Freitag kommender Woche
          (heute ist Sonntag)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">November
            27, 1925, the date given at the beginning of this letter, fell on a Friday, not a
            Sunday.</tei:note> über das Ergebnis zu berichten. — </tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Lie-Lie</tei:rs>s Bild habe
          ich vortrefflich gefunden und ich muß sagen – schmeicheleien zu schreiben ist nicht meine
          Art – daß sich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Lie Lie</tei:rs> seit den Tagen,
          in denen ich sie zum letzten Male während des Krieges in Wien gesehen habe, kaum verändert
          hat. Der <tei:hi rend="underline">äußere</tei:hi> Mensch scheint mir unverändert geblieben
          zu sein. Und von der Zahl der Jahre, die seither <tei:subst>
            <tei:del rend="overstrike">ge</tei:del>
            <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ver</tei:add>
          </tei:subst>gangen sind, ist nicht zu <tei:unclear reason="reading">meßen</tei:unclear>.
          Und auch besser als auf dem Bilde von <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002809"
            >D’Ora</tei:rs> erkenne ich auf der während des Sommeraufenthaltes entstandenen
          Photographie meine <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Schwester</tei:rs> und ich
          war erstaunt darüber, wie die Jahre, die alle anderen Schwester immerhin etwas verändert
          haben, an <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Lie Lie</tei:rs>, wie die Bilder
          zeigen, fast spurlos vorübergegangen zu sein scheinen. Es gibt Menschen, die derlei nicht
          andres zu erklären versuchen, als durch die Zunahme großer seelischer Kräfte, großer
          intensiver Arbeit, kurz durch ein Leben, in dem <tei:del rend="overstrike">unser</tei:del>
          die Umstände <tei:pb n="3"/> eine volle Entwicklung der <tei:unclear reason="reading"
              >Bes<tei:supplied>t</tei:supplied>ändigkeit</tei:unclear> gestatten. — </tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">Nach Erhalt <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000783">Viktor</tei:rs>s
          Bild habe ich ihm geschrieben und ihn aufgefordert, mehr von sich hören zu lassen. Daß er
          nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004528">Palästina</tei:rs> auswandern will,
          hebräisch schreibt u. scheinbar auch spricht, ist, wenn ich das von einem Menschen
          erfahre, der die ganze Welt bereist hat, ein geradezu fürchterliches <tei:hi
            rend="underline">Armutszeugnis</tei:hi> – dieser Gesellschaft, die diesen 40jährigen
          noch <tei:supplied reason="syntax">zu</tei:supplied> einer <tei:hi rend="underline"
            >Welten</tei:hi>wanderung zwingt, in den Käfig einer nationalen Gemeinschaft <tei:hi
            rend="underline">Zuflucht</tei:hi> zu nehmen, und die <tei:choice>
            <tei:sic>ihn</tei:sic>
            <tei:corr>ihm</tei:corr>
          </tei:choice> so also die letzten furchtbare Lehre gegeben zu haben, scheint, daß diese
          Welt in allen ihren Teilen von Hühnerhof-Instinkten beherrscht wird. Sollte er meinen
          Brief beantworten, so teile ich Euch darüber näheres mit. — Was man in <tei:rs
            type="place" key="entity-002248">Aussig</tei:rs> zu <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000783">Viktor</tei:rs>s Schreiben gesagt hat weiß ich nicht. — Wir hatten
          letzthin hier <tei:subst>
            <tei:del rend="overstrike">E</tei:del>
            <tei:add place="interlinear-above">e</tei:add>
          </tei:subst>reignisreiche Tage, Wahlen, eine neue Regierung, u. dgl. <tei:hi
            rend="underline">alles</tei:hi> Angelegenheiten, die uns etwas in Spannung hielten. Nun
          ist auch das vorbei und neue Begriffe verdrängen die alten. </tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">Für heute will ich schließen und Freitag fortsetzen.</tei:p>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Herzlichste Grüße &amp; Küsse Euch beiden</tei:salute>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Von Eurem</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000782"
            >Paul</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>

        <tei:postscript>
          <tei:p><tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000783">Viktor</tei:rs>s
              Bild liegt bei.</tei:hi></tei:p>
        </tei:postscript>
      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="part_2">

        <tei:opener>
          <tei:salute><tei:pb n="4"/>
            <tei:handShift new="#AS"/>Liebe <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
              >Lie-Lie</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">This
              undated letter, which follows on from Paul’s, is presumed to have been written and
              sent on the same day; it was common for Anna to add a few lines to Paul’s letters, and
              vice versa</tei:note></tei:salute>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:p>Nun sollte ich endlich Gelegenheit haben Dich kennen zu lernen! Und wenn es vorerst
          auch nur ein liebes Bild war, das mir einen lange gehegten Wunsch erfüllte, so freute ich
          mich darüber sehr. Aus dem Bilde allein schon erkennt man, dass diese Frau
            nichtme<tei:supplied reason="omission">h</tei:supplied>r die Frau ihres <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000632">Mann</tei:rs>es, <tei:del rend="overstrike"
            >ist</tei:del> sondern einem bedeutenden Menschen zugleich Freund und geistiger Kamerad
          ist. </tei:p>

        <tei:p>Der Besitz eines Bildes Deines l. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Heinrich</tei:rs> macht uns sehr stolz. Wenn wir nur durch diesen Besitz nicht zugleich
          auch bedruckt würden! Doch darüber schrieb schon <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000782"
            >Paul</tei:rs>; – <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs>s
          interessanter Kopf tritt fast plastisch aus dem Bild hervor – Radierungen, die Personen
          darstellen, sind selten von solcher lebendiger Wirkung. <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000327">Viktor Hammer</tei:rs> muß ein großer Könner sein. </tei:p>

        <tei:p>-- -- -- </tei:p>

        <tei:p>Während ich schreibe, sitzt <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-007617">Lisl</tei:rs>
          neben mir und hantiert mit Nadel und Schere, eine Arbeit, die meine Aufmerksamkeit
          fortwährend auf das Kind lenkt. </tei:p>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute>Nun grüße ich Dich und den lieben <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
              >Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:salute>
          <tei:salute>recht herzlich</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000781"
            >Anna</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>
      </tei:div>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:div type="part_1">
        <tei:opener>
          <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#PS"/><tei:rs type="place"
              key="entity-002892">Prague</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1925-11-27">November 27,
              1925</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
          <tei:salute>My dear ones,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:p rend="first">We received Lie-Lie’s letter<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
            type="footnote"/> and, a day later, the wonderful portrait, too, which is utterly
            precious.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> Many thanks, above all for
          sending us this picture. I am stricken most of all by the thought that you have as a
          result been burdened with costs with which you hadn’t initially reckoned. Write to me
          about this. We were keen to have a picture of dear <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs> which, even if it were not so artistic and so a
          valuable from an artistic point of view, would have been of value for us. Once again many
          thanks for the picture, which has given us great joy.</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first"><tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">In the course of</tei:unclear>
          Monday I shall make an effort to discover whether the writings issued by the publishing
          house whose name I can retrieve from one of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
            >Lie-Lie</tei:rs>’s recent letters are available <tei:subst>
            <tei:del rend="overstrike">at</tei:del>
            <tei:add place="interlinear-above">in</tei:add>
          </tei:subst> the largest bookshops and music shops, and for how much they are being sold
          here. <tei:pb n="2"/> It should not be difficult to learn this, as I have a friend here in
          the book trade who is well informed about these things, and who will help me. I hope to be
          able to report to you the result as early as Friday of the coming week (today is
            Sunday).<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">I found <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Lie-Lie</tei:rs>'s
          picture excellent; and I must say – it is not my style to write flattering words – that
          Lie-Lie has hardly changed since the last time I saw her in Vienna during the War. The
            <tei:hi rend="underline">exterior</tei:hi> person seems to me to have remained
          unchanged. And the number of years that have since passed cannot be measured. And I
          recognize my <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">sister</tei:rs> better on the
          photograph taken during the summer vacation than on the photograph from <tei:rs
            type="organization" key="entity-002809">d’Ora</tei:rs>; and I was astonished about how
          the years, which have nonetheless changed the appearance of all my other sisters, seem to
          have passed by without leaving a trace on <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
            >Lie-Lie</tei:rs>, as the photographs show. There are people who attempt to explain such
          things as the result of nothing other than the growth of spiritual powers and great
          intensive work, in short, the result of a life in which <tei:del rend="overstrike"
            >our</tei:del> the conditions permit <tei:pb n="3"/> a complete deployment of
            <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">steadfast application</tei:unclear>.</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">After I received <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000783"
            >Viktor</tei:rs>’s picture, I wrote to him and requested that he say more about himself.
          That he wants to emigrate to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004528">Palestine</tei:rs>
          and writes in (and apparently speaks) Hebrew is something which, coming from a person who
          has toured the entire world, a downright frightening <tei:hi rend="underline">witness to
            the poverty</tei:hi> of this society which compels this 40-year-old to undertake another
            <tei:hi rend="underline">mammoth</tei:hi> tour, to seek <tei:hi rend="underline"
            >refuge</tei:hi> in the cage of a national community, and which seems to have given him
          the ultimate frightful lesson that this world is governed by chicken-run instincts in all
          its parts. If he should reply to my letter, I shall let you know more about it. What
          people in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002248">Aussig</tei:rs> have said about <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000783">Viktor</tei:rs>’s letter, I do not know. Here we
          recently had eventful days – elections, a new government, and <tei:hi rend="underline"
            >all</tei:hi> suchlike – which have kept us somewhat in suspense. Now even that is over,
          and new concepts supersede the old.</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">For now, I shall close; I will resume on Friday.</tei:p>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Most cordial greetings and kisses to the two of
            you</tei:salute>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-30">from your</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000782"
            >Paul</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>

        <tei:postscript>
          <tei:p><tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000783">Viktor</tei:rs>s
              picture is enclosed.</tei:hi></tei:p>
        </tei:postscript>
      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="part_2">

        <tei:opener>
          <tei:salute><tei:pb n="4"/>
            <tei:handShift new="#AS"/>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
              >Lie-Lie</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:p>Now I finally have a chance to get to know you! And if for the time being it is just
          a lovely picture, which merely fulfilled a long-cherished desire of mine, then I am very
          happy about it. From the picture alone one can see that this woman is no longer the wife
          of her <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">husband</tei:rs> but rather a significant
          person, both a friend and a spiritual comrade.</tei:p>

        <tei:p>Having your dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">husband</tei:rs>’s
          portrait makes us very proud. And we are also at the same time impressed by our possession
          of it. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000782">Paul</tei:rs> has already written about
          that. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs>’s interesting head
          emerges from the portrait almost in a lifelike way; Drawings that represent people rarely
          have such a vivid effect. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000327">Viktor Hammer</tei:rs>
          must be a very skilled artist.</tei:p>

        <tei:p>-- -- -- </tei:p>

        <tei:p>While I write, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-007617">Lisl</tei:rs> is sitting
          next to me, busying herself with needle and scissors, an activity that continuously draws
          may attention to the child.</tei:p>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute>Now I greet you and your dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
              >Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:salute>
          <tei:salute>most cordially</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000781"
            >Anna</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>
      </tei:div>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
