<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="995" sdoID="OJ-14-45_61">OJ 14/45, [61]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="MV" scope="sole">Moriz Violin's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
      <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-07-12" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002719">ViolinM ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM+V ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002718">ViolinM+V+F ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Moriz Violin to Schenker, dated February 23, 1927</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1927-02-23T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2013-07-12</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Following a brief description of a recent illness, Violin replies to
        Schenker's question about accepting the Order of Merit from the Viennese Academy of Art and
        Science and advises him to accept it. He realizes that staying in Hamburg would be bad for
        his son's long-term health and has spoken to Artur Schnabel about the possibility of moving
        to Berlin or Frankfurt. An influential man in Frankfurt is the father-in-law of Paul Klenau;
        Violin knows of Klenau's respect for Schenker, and asks his friend to write to Klenau in
        support of his application for a post there.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>


    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-40"><tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>,
            <tei:date when="1927-02-23">23. Februar 27</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Liebster <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this
            letter is mentioned in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/9, p. 3041 (February 26, 1927): "Von Fl.
            (Br.): begreift, daß ich das Ehrenzeichen ablehne u. deutet einen Gedankengang an, den
            ich zur Begründung der Ablehnung vorschieben solle. Bittet um Klenaus Vermittlung bei
            dessen Schwiegervater wegen einer zu errichtenden fixen Stelle in Frankfurt." ("From
            Floriz (letter): he understands that I am turning down the Order of Merit and indicates
            a way of thinking that I should advance in order to justify turning it down. He asks for
            Klenau's intervention, through his father-in-law, regarding a fixed post that is to be
            established in Frankfurt.")</tei:note>
        </tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Dein liebster Brief<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-6-7_32">= OJ
          6/7, [32]</tei:ref> hat so viel in mir ausgelöst, daß ich ihn auch gleich beantworten
        muss. Ich hatte eine sehr schwere Grippe durchgemacht u. lange u. noch unter ihrer
        Nachwirkung zu leiden. Eine kleine Herzmuskelschwächung, die – angeblich – wieder behebbar
        ist. Wenn ich Sorgen mir machte, vor allem wegen <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Karli</tei:rs>, der mich braucht. In einer Angelegenheit, die eigentlich <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Karli</tei:rs>s Schicksal ist, wollte ich Dich
        jedenfalls interpellieren. Vorher aber erst zu einer Mittheilung Deines Briefes. Persönlich
        ließe sich das besser beschwatzen. Hoffentlich verstehst Du meinen Gedankengang; besser
        gesagt: verstehe ich ihn auszudrücken.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">No paragraph-break in source.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Staat oder Stadt <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs>
        ist ein Begriff: eine Institution. Löblich <tei:add place="inline" hand="#MV">von
          ihr,</tei:add> wenn sie ihre Kinder auszeichnen<tei:note type="editorial">corr</tei:note>
        will. <tei:pb n="2"/> Die Medaille für Kunst u. Wissenschaft, hat seinerzeit nur <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs key="entity-000181" type="person">Dvorak</tei:rs> geschmückt. Wird sie jetzt an Hinze u. Schultze verliehen?
        Der Stadt <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs>, oder dem Staate sollst Du
        sie nicht ablehnen. Ich verstehe <tei:hi rend="double-underline">dass</tei:hi> Du sie
        ablehnen willst, Da würde ich an die berechtigte Form denken. Die wäre: Ich <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Heinrich Schenker</tei:rs> verkenne nicht die löbliche,
        schwindelhafte Absicht der Staat. „<tei:quote>Ich weiß aber, daß sie nur Exekutor der
          Vorschläge ist, die ihn in diesem Falle ein Musiker ⍻ machte. Mir ist nicht bewußt
          daß die Wiener Musiker u. Musikgelehrten offen u. öffentlich mein Künstlerisches
            Wo<tei:supplied reason="spelling">h</tei:supplied>lergehen fördern wollen, weshalb ich
          die Annahme verweigere, um zu verhüten, daß irgend <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#MV">jemand</tei:add> eine billige <tei:pb n="3"/> Gewissensanetlastung sich
          dadurch leistet, indem<tei:note type="editorial">corr</tei:note> mir durch eine<tei:note type="editorial">corr</tei:note> Hintertürpolitik, durch eine Auszeichnung, eine gnädige
          Anerkennung biete<tei:subst>
            <tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#MV">t</tei:add>
            <tei:del rend="overwritten" hand="#MV">n</tei:del>
          </tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="MV">wollen</tei:del>.</tei:quote><tei:supplied reason="punctuation">“</tei:supplied></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Es muss verstanden werden, daß Du eine Auszeichnung ablehnst, die <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs> annahm!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Und nun zu meiner Sache!!!! <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Karli</tei:rs> muss vom <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>er Klima
        fort. Zu einer Stegreif-Übersiedlung fehlen mir die Kräfte u. alter Wagemut. Ich habe auch
        keinen finanziellen Hinterhalt. Ich habe mit <tei:rs key="entity-000794" type="person">Artur
          Schnabel</tei:rs> letzthin ausführlich daruber gesprochen. Er hatte 2 Ideen. Eine davon
        ist für mich nicht ausführbar. Es ist die <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs>er Idee, d.h. ich soll nach <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs> übersiedeln u. so lange auf 2 Tage wöchentlich nach <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> fahren unterrichten, bis ich meinen
          <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs>er Kreis habe. Die <tei:rs key="entity-002888" type="organization">Berliner Hochschule</tei:rs> ist <tei:hi rend="underline">voll</tei:hi> besetzt.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="4"/> Dagegen nun ist seine 2<tei:hi rend="supralinear">te</tei:hi> Idee sehr lichtvoll u. kommt meinem Princip näher, nach welchem ich eine
        Übersiedlung nun dann ausführen kann, wenn ich irgend wo ein Fidum, eine Berufung bekomme.
          <tei:rs key="entity-000794" type="person">Schnabel</tei:rs> vertraute mir an, daß <tei:rs key="entity-002888" type="organization">Preußen</tei:rs> beabsichtigt <tei:rs key="entity-004751" type="organization">Frankfurt a/Mein</tei:rs> zu verknotlichen. Er
        sagte daß da ein großes Werben losgehen wird. Er selbst würde meine Sache im Ministerium
        unterstützen. Damit ist nicht alles geschehen. Das wichtigste ist, daß eine <tei:rs key="entity-004751" type="organization">Frankfurt</tei:rs>er Persönlichkeit, die er nicht
        kennt, ein Herr <tei:rs key="entity-003744" type="person">Simon oder Simons</tei:rs>
        gewonnen wird, der allmächtig sein soll. Der Dirigent <tei:rs key="entity-000443" type="person">Klenau</tei:rs> in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs>,
        soll Schwiegersohn dieses Mannes sein. Ich erinner<tei:supplied reason="spelling">e</tei:supplied> daß <tei:rs key="entity-000443" type="person">Klenau</tei:rs> zu Deinen
        Verehrern zählt?</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Bist Du in der Lage, mit Deinem ganzen <tei:pb n="5"/> Einfluß auf ihn
        einzuwirken? Ich würde dann, in diesem Falle zu <tei:date when="1927-04-17">Ostern</tei:date> nach <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> kommen, um
        die Sache mit Deiner Hilfe anzubahnen. Du kannst Dir denken, mit welcher Erregung ich an
        diese Möglichkeit denke!!! Bitte schreibe mir gleich ein Wort darüber! Verzeihe den konfusen
        Brief. Er ist das Spiegelbild meiner seelischen u. körperlichen Verfassung. Sowie <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Karli</tei:rs> wieder einen kräftigen<tei:note type="editorial">?</tei:note> Tag hat, will er Dir danken<tei:note type="editorial">corr</tei:note> für das Bild. Einstweilen betraute er mich, Dir es zu sagen. <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">Vally</tei:rs> recht abgerackert, <tei:rs key="entity-000911" type="person">Mädi</tei:rs>, gottlob famos.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Innigstes von Uns an Euch!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-35">Dein getreuester</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-40"><tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>,
            <tei:date when="1927-02-23">February 23, 1927</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dearest <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
        </tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Your most sweet letter<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-6-7_32">= OJ
          6/7, [32]</tei:ref> released so much inside me that I must also answer it immediately. I
        had a serious bout of influenza and suffered a long time from its after-effects. A little
        weakening of a heart muscle which – apparently – is curable. If I get worried, <tei:supplied reason="clarity">it is</tei:supplied> above all because of little <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Karl</tei:rs>, who needs me. In a matter – which is in
        fact <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Karl</tei:rs>'s fate – I wanted to question
        you at any rate. First of all, however, a response to your letter. I could speak more
        persuasively face to face. I hope that you will understand my train of thought; to put it
        better: <tei:supplied reason="clarity">I hope that</tei:supplied> I will know how to express
          it.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">The state, or the city of <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>, is a concept, an institution. It is to its credit if it undertakes to
        single out its children. <tei:pb n="2"/> Some time ago, the medal for art and science graced
        only <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs> and <tei:rs key="entity-000181" type="person">Dvořak</tei:rs>. Is it to be conferred upon every Tom,
        Dick or Harry? You should not refuse the city of <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>, or the state. I understand <tei:hi rend="double-underline">that</tei:hi>
        you wish to refuse; in that case I would think about the correct form <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of the refusal</tei:supplied>. This would be: I, <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Heinrich Schenker</tei:rs>, am not ignorant of the
        laudable <tei:supplied reason="clarity">but</tei:supplied> bogus intention of the city.
          "<tei:quote>I know, however, that it is merely the executor of recommendations, which in
          this case a musician ⍻ has made. I am not conscious that the Viennese musicians and
          music scholars openly and officially wish to promote my artistic welfare, on account of
          which I hesitate to accept, to protect myself from <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#MV">any person</tei:add> succeeding <tei:pb n="3"/> thereby in unburdening his
          conscience easily, by offering a condescending recognition via a back-door political
          act.</tei:quote>"</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">It must be understood that you are turning down an honor that <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs> accepted!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">And now to my matter!!!! <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Karl</tei:rs> must leave the climate of <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>. For an impromptu relocation, I lack the strength and my former bravado.
        Also, I have no financial reserves. I recently spoke at length about this with <tei:rs key="entity-000794" type="person">Artur Schnabel</tei:rs>. He had two ideas. One of them
        is not possible for me to realize. That is the <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs> idea, that is, I should move to <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs> and commute two days a week to <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> until I have established a network in <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs>. The music <tei:rs key="entity-002888" type="organization">Hochschule in Berlin</tei:rs> is <tei:hi rend="underline">completely</tei:hi>
        full.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="4"/> On the other hand, his second idea is a very bright one,
        and is in closer agreement with my principle, according to which I would be able to succeed
        in moving only if I were to get a fixed position, an appointment somewhere. <tei:rs key="entity-000794" type="person">Schnabel</tei:rs> confided to me that <tei:rs key="entity-002888" type="organization">Prussia</tei:rs> is intending to link up with
          <tei:rs key="entity-004751" type="organization">Frankfurt am Main</tei:rs>. He said that
        there would be a great canvassing for it. He would himself support my cause in the Ministry
          <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of Education</tei:supplied>. The most important thing is to
        win over a <tei:rs key="entity-004751" type="organization">Frankfurt</tei:rs> personage,
        whom he does not know, a Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-003744" type="person">Simon or
          Simons</tei:rs>, who is supposed to wield great power. The conductor <tei:rs key="entity-000443" type="person">Klenau</tei:rs> in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs> is supposed to be the son-in-law of this man. If I remember
        correctly, <tei:rs key="entity-000443" type="person">Klenau</tei:rs> is among your
        admirers.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Are you in a position to appeal to him with all your influence? <tei:pb n="5"/> If that were the case, I would come to <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs> at <tei:date when="1927-04-17">Easter</tei:date>, in order to prepare the
        matter with your help. You can well imagine the excitement with which I am thinking about
        this possibility!!! Please send me a line about this immediately! Excuse the confused
        letter. It is the mirror image of my emotional and physical constitution. As soon as little
          <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Karl</tei:rs> has another strong day, he will
        thank you for the picture. In the meantime, he entrusts me to tell you so. <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">Vally</tei:rs> is truly worn out from work; my little
          <tei:rs key="entity-000911" type="person">girl</tei:rs> is, thank goodnes, in great
        shape.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Most affectionate greetings from us to the two of
          you!</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-35">Your most faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>