<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="2300" sdoID="OJ-15-16_19">OJ 15/16, [19]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HW" scope="sole">Hans Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2007</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="AH">
   <tei:persName>Alison Hiley</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2008</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-06-25" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated August 12, 1913</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1913-08-12T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-10-17</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Weisse reports on progress with his string quintet, and lists his travel plans
    for late September.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>opera; works; Rat; advice; Arbeit; work; Satz; movement; componieren; to compose;
    Skizze; sketch; Herbst; fall; autumn; Umarbeit; reworking; Sorge; concern; Scherzo; Trio;
    Adagio; unmelodisch; unmelodic; Composition; Quintett; quintet; Pläne; plans; Reise; travel;
    Kritik; review</dc:subject>



   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000951">Weisse</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HW"/>Liebster, verehrter <tei:rs type="person"
      key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
      place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary at OJ 1/13, p. 401, August
      14, 1913: "Brief von Hans" ("Letter from Hans").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Sie wundern sich wohl über mein langes Stillschweigen und denken dabei an weiss Gott wie
    viel neu entstehende <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">opera</tei:hi>! Dennoch aber befolge ich den
    zweiten Rat Ihres letzten so lieben Briefes<tei:supplied reason="punctuation"
     >,</tei:supplied><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Presumably the
     letter, which is not known to survive, that is recorded in Schenker's diary as dispatched on
     July 14, 1913 (OJ 1/12, p. 379): "Dank an Hans, für Sendung." ("Thanks to Hans for
     package.").</tei:note> nämlich viel spazieren zu gehen<tei:supplied reason="punctuation"
     >,</tei:supplied> mehr als den die Arbeit betreffenden. Ich habe nun 2 Wochen vollständig
    pausiert und will erst nächste Woche wieder fest dazuschauen. Die Arbeit habe ich
     aber<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> und dies ist meiner Meinung nach das
     Beste<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> was geschehen könnte, gründlich
     kennengelernt<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> weil ich zur Einsicht gelangt
    bin, dass da endgül- <tei:pb n="2"/> tigen Ziele und Resultate nicht im Handumdrehen gefasst und
    erreicht werden können. Zum scheinbar <tei:choice>
     <tei:sic>leichtesten Gesellen</tei:sic>
     <tei:corr>Leichtesten gesellen</tei:corr>
    </tei:choice> sich die gleiche Ausdauer wie zu mühseligen Augenblicken: Um diese Erfahrung
    reicher komme ich <tei:unclear reason="reading">hin</tei:unclear><tei:supplied
     reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> begieriger als zuvor, genauer, consequenter als zuvor zu
    Ihnen zurück und freue mich aller kommenden geistigen Nahrung! Den ersten Satz<tei:supplied
     reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> der ganz neu componiert<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
     type="editorial" place="foot">Weisse first announced that he was working on a string quintet on
     July 7, 1912 (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-15-16_6">OJ 15/16, [6]</tei:ref>), after
     which the work continued to be referred to in letters and in Schenker's lessonbooks, where it
     was under discussion in 1913 as late as February 7 ("questions arising from the quintet") and
     February 11 ("on the ordering of the adagio in the quintet"). He was, however, disappointed
     with the first movement, describing it as a "woeful concoction" (<tei:ref type="correspondence"
      cRef="OJ-15-16_18">OJ 15/16, [18]</tei:ref>, July 16, 1913, and had resolved to write a new
     one already on February 11, 1913 (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-15-16_13">OJ 15/16,
      [13]</tei:ref>); it is this that is still on-going in summer 1913.</tei:note>
     wird<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> wie auch den letzten hoffe ich in der
    Skizze fertig mitzubringen: Unter <tei:del rend="overwritten">i</tei:del><tei:add
     place="superimposed">I</tei:add>hrer Aufsicht möchte ich im Herbste erst die
     <tei:term>Instrumentierung</tei:term> besorgen, weil damit das lästige Umarbeiten wegfällt, und
    zugleich auch viele Erfahrungen gewissermassen <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">a priori</tei:hi>
    gemacht werden können. Das einzige Scherzo und Trio<tei:supplied reason="punctuation"
     >,</tei:supplied> das ich so gut noch wie voriges Jahr finde<tei:supplied reason="punctuation"
     >,</tei:supplied> soll ganz zu Ende geändert werden!</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> Meine Sorge aber bildet das Adagio: Wieso ich mich im Vorjahre dazu
    hinreissen lassen konnte es gut, zu finden – einzig und allein, weil es nicht unmelodisch war?!
    Wie in den Wüst, die Verlegenheit, die Unbeholfenheit der <tei:term>Synthese</tei:term> Licht
    und Geist bringen? Schon der erste <tei:term>Gedanke</tei:term> mit seiner unglücklich – ungeheuer<tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">n</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">lich</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> angelegten <tei:term>Liedform</tei:term> verursacht mir Schmerzen und Bitternisse!
    Der zweite <tei:term>Gedanke</tei:term>, der mir melodisch gefällt<tei:supplied
     reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> bedürfte eines besser passenden
     <tei:term>Vordersatz</tei:term>es! Ob es doch nicht besser wäre<tei:supplied
     reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> diesen Satz als Materielager für weitere Compositionen zu
    benützen und mit der Arbeit eines neuen Adagios zu beginnen? Ich harre Ihrer Entschlüsse, ihrer
    Ratschläge: nur habe ich das Eilen und Schnellmachenwollen über den Sommer verlernt und werde
    mich nicht genieren<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> nur das oberwähnte gut,
    statt einer fix und fertig gedrechselten aber schlechten Quintetts zu bringen!</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> Meine Pläne sind: bis <tei:date when="1913-09-15">15. September</tei:date>
    in diesem Neste, das ich heuer trotz schlechten Wetters von neuen lieb gewann zu bleiben und dan
    bis Ende eine Reise durch <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482"
      ><tei:country>Deutschland</tei:country></tei:rs> zu unternehmen: Nürnberg – Würzburg –
    Heidelberg – Frankfurt – Eisenach – Gota – Erfurt – Weimar – Jena – Leipzig – Breslau! Etwaige
    Besorgungen würde ich mit grosser Freude von Ihnen entgegennehmen – und soweit’s in meiner Macht
    liegt ausführen! Die <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000149">Dahms</tei:rs>’ Kritik<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Weisse refers to <tei:title level="a"
      >Musikalische Arbeitungen,</tei:title> signed "Ds," <tei:title level="j">Neue Preussische
      Kreuz-Zeitung</tei:title>, July 15, 1913 (review of Schenker's edition of J. S. Bach's <tei:rs
      type="work" key="entity-001730"><tei:title level="m">Chromatic Fantasy &amp;
      Fugue</tei:title></tei:rs>), a clipping of which is preserved in Schenker's scrapbook, OC 2/p.
     37.</tei:note> fand ich flach und oberflächlich! Derlei Dinge sind nicht für unsereines
    geschrieben!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich grüsse Sie allerinnigst, denke Ihrer viel und herzlich und freue mich
     heuer<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> mich ganz der Ihre nennen zu
    können.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Alles Liebe von Ihrem treuen</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
     >Hans</tei:rs>.</tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1913-08-12">12. Aug. 13</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p>Anbei das Häuschen in dem mein Arbeitszimmer ist. Ein lieber Bauernstüblein! </tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HW"/>Dearest, revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
      >Master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>You will be surprised at my long silence and be thinking that it must signify God knows
    how many newly created <tei:hi rend="italic">opera</tei:hi>! Yet nevertheless I am following the
    second piece of advice in your recent very kind letter<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
     type="footnote"/> more than that which concerned work, namely taking lots of walks. I have now
    had a break of two full weeks and do not intend to get back to it properly until next week.
    However, I have become thoroughly acquainted with work and that is in my opinion the best thing
    that could have happened, because I have come to realize that final <tei:pb n="2"/> goals and
    results cannot be grasped and attained in the twinkling of an eye. Even that which seems the
    easiest thing can demand the same perseverance as times of trouble: all the richer for this
    insight, I now return to you, hungrier than before, more exacting, more consistent than before,
    and I look forward to all the spiritual sustenance ahead! I hope to bring the completed drafts
    of both the first movement (currently being composed afresh<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
     type="footnote"/>]) and the last one. I should like to leave the
     <tei:term>scoring-up</tei:term> until the autumn, when I can tackle it under your supervision ‒
    the tiresome reworking will thus be avoided, and at the same time many things can be learned, so
    to speak, <tei:hi rend="italic">a priori</tei:hi>. The only Scherzo and Trio, which I still find
    as good as I did last year, will be changed last of all!</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> The adagio causes me concern, however: how could I have allowed myself to
    have considered it successful last year ‒ purely and simply because it was not unmelodic?! How
    is one to bring light and spirit to the jumble, the confusion, the unwieldiness of the
     <tei:term>synthesis</tei:term>? Even the first <tei:term>idea</tei:term>, with its unfortunate
    ‒ ridiculously contrived ‒ <tei:term>songform</tei:term>, causes me pain and bitterness! The
    second <tei:term>idea</tei:term>, which I like melodically, could do with a more suitable
     <tei:term>antecedent</tei:term>! Would it not be better to use this movement as a source of
    material for further compositions and start work on a new adagio? I await your decisions, your
    advice, but over the summer I have forgotten how to hurry and make haste and it won't bother me
    if all I can achieve is to effect the above well, rather than producing an elaborately
    ready-made, but inferior, Quintet!</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> My plans are to stay until <tei:date when="1913-09-15">September
     15</tei:date> in this little place, which I've recently come to love despite the bad weather,
    and then to undertake a journey through <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482"
      ><tei:country>Germany</tei:country></tei:rs>: Nuremberg – Würzburg – Heidelberg – Frankfurt –
    Eisenach – Gota – Erfurt – Weimar – Jena – Leipzig – Breslau! It would be a great pleasure to
    hear of anything I could do for you ‒ and to carry it out to the best of my ability. I found
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000149">Dahms</tei:rs>'s review<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
     type="footnote"/> flat and superficial! Such things are not written for the likes of
    us!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>I send you most heartfelt greetings, think of you often and with affection and look
    forward to being able to devote all my time to you soon.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Loving greetings from your faithful</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
     >Hans</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1913-08-12">August 12, 1913</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p>I enclose <tei:supplied reason="clarity">a picture of</tei:supplied> the little house
     where my study is ‒ a dear little country dwelling! </tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>
  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
