<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2155" sdoID="OJ-15-16_91">OJ 15/16, [91]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HW" scope="sole">Hans Weisse's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2008</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2018</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-10-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Hans Weisse to Schenker, dated March 30, 1933</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1933-03-30T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2018-10-29</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>In this long letter, Weisse expresses his bitter regret about Otto
        Vrieslander's reaction to his criticism of a recently published collection of his
        (Vrieslander's) songs, and to Schenker's exaggerated claims of their worth. Weisse defends
        his critical stance on the grounds that objective discussions are the only worthwhile ones,
        and that he took the trouble to write about the songs in a 14-page letter to Vrieslander
        only for the sake of art (in the Schenkerian sense) and feels hurt both by Vrieslander's
        personal reaction to Weisse's criticism and by Schenker's defence of the older pupil. — In
        the final paragraph, he inquires again about gaining permission to make multiple copies of
        Schenker's foreground graph of the "Eroica" Symphony.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>günstig; favorable; Beurteilung; judgment; Werk; work; Schüler; pupil; Lehrer;
        teacher; Glauben; belief; Anhängerschaft; adherence; Empfehlungschreiben; letter of
        recommendation; Meisterbegriff; concept of mastery; Sache; cause; Lieder; song; Äusserung;
        expression; Verhältnis; relationship; Verhältnis; conviction; Nachgestaltung; imitation;
        Eigengestaltung; original work; Neid; envy; Eifersucht; jealousy; Verdacht; suspicion;
        Meinungsaustausch; exchange of opinions; Kritik; criticism; Gedankenaustausch; exchange of
        ideas; Musiker; musician; Schule; school; Gemeinsamkeit; common purpose; verbinden; to
        unite; Meinung; opinion; Gegenäusserung; counter opinion; Verkalktheit; calcification; Gift;
        poison; Skizze; sketch</dc:subject>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:lb/><tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#HW"/><tei:date
            when="1933-03-30">30. März 1933</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Mein lieber, verehrter <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"
            >Meister</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
            this letter is recorded at OJ 4/6, p. 3825, April 10, 1933: "Von Weisse (Br.): zu
            Vrieslander u. meine Kritik der Lieder!" ("From Weisse (letter): concerning Vrieslander,
            and my review of his songs!"). Prior to that, after receiving advice from Otto Erich
            Deutsch on the "Eroica" Urlinie graphs (April 2), Schenker records at p. 3824, April 5,
            1933: "An Weisse (Br.): Zustimmung zur photo-litographischen Abnahme der Eroica-Bilder.
            Dank an Frau Hertha für das Bild der Kinder; beglückwünsche zu den Erfolgen; das <tei:rs
              type="organization" key="entity-002499">Seminar</tei:rs> hat bis jetzt kein
            Urlinie-Heft, vielleicht später. Deutschlands Verhältnisse fordern Opfer auch von uns.
            Furtwängler??" ("ToWeisse (letter): I agree to the photo-lithographic reproduction of
            the "Eroica" graphs. Thanks to Hertha for the photograph of the children; I congratulate
            him on his successes; the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002499"
              >Seminar</tei:rs> has hitherto <tei:supplied reason="clarity">produced</tei:supplied>
            no folder of Urlinie analyses, perhaps later. Germany's condition demands sacrifices
            even from us. Furtwängler??").</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>zu meinem tiefsten Bedauern höre ich von anderer Seite, dass <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>, in dem ich inzwischen einen mich mehr als
        enttäuschenden Brief bekommen habe, trotz seiner 53 Jahre, die er mir in Abwehr vorgehalten,
        sich wie ein Schulknabe benommen hat, <tei:del rend="overstrike">und</tei:del> der, wenn er
        sich angegriffen fühlt, nichts klügeres zu tun weiss als aufzuzeigen: „Bitte<tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> Herr Lehrer, der Weisse hat gesagt . . . .“</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Meine Bemerkung, Ihre günstige Beurteilung seiner Werke <tei:del rend="overstrike"
          >dass</tei:del> sei daraufzurückzuführen, dass Sie die Arbeiten Ihrer Schüler als Lehrer
        betrachten und eventuell gut heissen, halte ich Ihnen gegenüber aufrecht und finde darin
        weder etwas Beleidigendes, noch Verletzendes für Sie.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Von ihm übermittelt, musste Sie diese Bemerkung freilich verdriessen und gegen mich
        verstimmen, und ich glaube, dass es <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922"
          >Vrieslander</tei:rs>s Absicht gewesen sein muss, Ihren Glauben an mich und meine
        Anhängerschaft zu erschüttern und <tei:pb n="2"/> ich halte daher seine <tei:del
          rend="overstrike">An</tei:del>handlungsweise für mehr als indiskret, ich finde sie nahezu
        unsauber.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Um aber die Angelegenheit zwischen uns zu bereinigen, möchte ich Sie nur an eines
        erinnern. Als Sie mir Ihr Empfehlungschreiben für <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002510"
            ><tei:country>Amerika</tei:country></tei:rs> gaben, sprachen Sie darin von mir als einem
        „Wiener Meister“ . . . und ich gab Ihnen den Brief zurück,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot">See the letter of April 15, 1931 (<tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-15-16_74">OJ 15/16, [74]</tei:ref>), in which Weisse asks
          Schenker to change the wording “berühmter Wiener Meister der Musik” in a letter of
          reference regarding a teaching position in the USA.</tei:note> mit der Bitte, ein Wort
        nicht zu missbrauchen, das in Ihrem Munde eine besondere Bedeutung erhalten hatte: Die
        Reinheit des Meisterbegriffes in Ihrer einzigartigen Fassung – „die Sache“ mithin galt mir
        mehr als persönliches Interesse. Ich glaube das somit bewiesen zu haben. Ihre Güte und
          Freundschaft<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> das Nachgeben Ihrer
        Empfindung anerkannte und schätzte ich daran, doch war mir auch klar, dass Sie zu weit
        gegangen waren und dieses persönliche Erlebnis hat mich sicherlich in dem
          befällt<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> was ich <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> zu sagen hatte. Ich gestehe, dass ich es, sogerne
        Sie es auch vielleicht täten, niemals zugeben würde, Sie irgendeines meiner Werke in der
        Weise anzukündigen zu lassen in der Sie die Lieder <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922"
          >Vr.</tei:rs>’s angekündigt haben.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Vrieslander's songs and ländler, two collections of which were published in
          the early 1930s, were highly commended in a review by
              <tei:bibl><tei:author>Schenker</tei:author>, <tei:title level="a">Eine Anzeige und
              eine Selbstanzeige,</tei:title>
            <tei:title level="j">Der Kunstwart</tei:title> 46 (December 1932), 194‒96</tei:bibl>.
          See <tei:bibl>Federhofer (1985), pp. 215–16</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> Meiner Meinung nach,
        schadet eine solche Äusserung von Ihnen der Ideenwelt, die Sie vertreten, <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">mehr</tei:add> als sie dem nützen kann, dem sie gilt. Sie haben
        es gewiss in vollster Überzeugung getan, <tei:pb n="3"/> aber nach aussen hin ist und bleibt
        es eine Äusserung, die als bestimmte Befangenheit erscheinen muss, wenn man das Verhältnis
        kennt, in dem Sie zu <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> stehen.
        Was würden Sie auf eine Äusserung <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798"
          >Schönberg</tei:rs>s über <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003019">Webern</tei:rs> schon
        geben <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">können</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">wollen</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>? Kommt noch hinzu, das die Lieder <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922"
          >Vr.</tei:rs>’s<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> obgleich Sie Züge und
        drgl. aufweisen, meiner vollsten Überzeugung nach blos den Wert von
          Nachgestaltungen<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> nicht aber
        Eigengestaltungen haben, so finde ich, muss ein so weit gehende Äusserung von Ihnen, schon
        in Ihrem Anhängerkreis eine gewisse Verwirrung stiften, wie aber muss sie erst jene Kreise
        anmuten, zu denen vorzudringen und bei denen durchzudringen Ihrem Werke meiner festesten
        Überzeugung nach, <tei:add place="interlinear-above">noch</tei:add> bestimmt ist?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich erröte bei dem blossen Gedanken, dass Sie vielleicht glauben könnten, dass es Neid
        oder Eifersucht sei, die mich zu <tei:add place="interlinear-above">einer</tei:add> solchen
        Äusserung veranlasst haben könnten. Dennoch kann und will ich es nicht glauben, dass Sie
        einen solchen Verdacht <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">abweisen können</tei:del>
          <tei:add><tei:hi rend="underline">in Sich</tei:hi> aufkommen lassen</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>. Ich glaube, mein ganzer Lebensgang und meine Entwicklung zeigen, dass ich für
        nichts anderes leben, als für Ihre Welt, und für Ihre Sache, die dank himmlischer Fügung nun
        so sehr auch die meine geworden ist.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Weisse must have felt particularly aggrieved at this time, as his lectures in
          New York were helping to win many converts to Schenker’s concept of music.</tei:note>
        Nicht gegen Sie – sondern <tei:hi rend="underline">für</tei:hi> Sie ist auch eine solche
        Äusserung aufzufassen, mag <tei:pb n="4"/> ich im Übrigen auch Ihrer Meinung nach ganz im
        Unrecht sein mit meinem Urteil über <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922"
          >Vrieslander</tei:rs>. Die Grösse Ihres Werkes besteht darin, dass Ihr Urteil, wo es die
        Grossen betrifft<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> unwiderlegbar ist, um so
        mehr bekümmert es mich, wenn ein Ausspruch von Ihnen, wie: „diese Lieder werden bald im
        Munde aller Sänger sein“ einfach durch die Welt der Tatsachen widerlegt werden wird. Sollte
        der bedauerliche Fall eingetreten sein, dass es <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922"
          >Vrieslander</tei:rs> gelungen ist, in Ihnen gegen meine Ehrlichkeit Verdacht zu erwecken,
        so wollen diese wenigen Zeilen, nicht mehr und nicht weniger, als Sie <tei:del
          rend="overstrike">zu</tei:del> überzeugen, davon, dass mir nichts höher steht, als Ihr
        Werk und Ihre Leistung. —</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun noch ein Weniges über <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922"
          >Vrieslander</tei:rs>. Mein freundschaftlicher Verkehr mit <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000327">Hammer</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial"
          place="foot">This is the only letter in which Weisse mentions his friendship with
          Hammer.</tei:note> hat <tei:del rend="overstrike">in</tei:del> mich eine Grosszügigkeit
        des Meinungsaustausches kennengelehrt, die das Sachliche weit über alles Persönliche stellt.
        Es gibt nichts, was wir einander nicht sagen können, und sei es noch so starke, <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">strenge</tei:add> Kritik. Kritik, die an <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overwritten">der</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="superimposed">die</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> Sache denkt, ist doch das einzig forderliche in der Welt. Als ich <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> schrieb, hegte ich die Hoffnung,
        dass hier die Möglichkeit eines Gedankenaustausches stattfinden könnte, die zwei Musiker,
        aus gleicher <tei:pb n="5"/> Schule zu tätiger Gemeinsamkeit verbinden könnte. Schliesslich
        brauche ich Ihnen nicht zu sagen, wie einsam ich mich fühle, unter all denen, die sich
        Musiker nennen. Sie haben <tei:add place="interlinear-above">es</tei:add> an Sich erfahren
        und wissen, dass diese Einsamkeit, ein Vermächtnis der Anhängerschaft an Sie ist. Kein
        anderer Gedanke als dieser war es, der mich leitete, als ich mich anschickte <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> einen 14 Seiten langen Brief zu
        schreiben: Meine <tei:add place="interlinear-above">geäusserte</tei:add> Meinung erwartete
        eine Gegenäusserung, die der Sache allein hätte gelten müssen, statt dessen erhielt ich eine
        Antwort, in der jedes Wort gebraucht war, um mich persönlich zu verletz<tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overwritten">t</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="superimposed">e</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>n. Diese Absicht war so offensichtlich, dass sie ihre Wirkung verfehlen musste.
        Ich bedauere ihn nur, denn wer so wenig einer, der Sache geltenden, freundschaftlichen
        Kritik <tei:hi rend="underline">vertraut</tei:hi>, leidet an einer geistigen und seelischen
        Verkalktheit – aus der nimmer mehr Echtes hervorgehen kann. Wer tätige Anteilnahme mit Gift
        und innere Aufgetanheit mit kleinlicher Verdächtigung (als sei ich unbescheiden und
        eingebildet) beantwortet, ist in der Wurzel seines Wesens unfruchtbar. Im übrigen weiss ich
        ja, dass meine persönliche Meinung über <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922"
          >Vr.</tei:rs> für Sie gänzlich wertlos ist, ich führe das auch nur an<tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> weil mir daran liegt, dass <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >Sie</tei:hi> wissen sollen (wenn schon <tei:pb n="6"/> er es nicht verstehen konnte) aus
        welchen Gründen, ich mich ihm gegenüber zu solcher Ausführlichkeit haben verleiten lassen.
        —</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Zu meinem letzten Brief habe ich noch hinzuzufügen, was ich vergessen habe. Wäre es
        vielleicht möglich, die Vervielfältigung blos der <tei:hi rend="underline"
            ><tei:term>Urlinietafel</tei:term></tei:hi> der <tei:title>Eroica</tei:title> in
        Erwägung zu ziehen?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">i.e. the
          booklet, in landscape format, of the foreground graphs of all four movements of the
          "Eroica" Symphony, published as an appendix to <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001752"
              ><tei:title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:title>, vol. 3</tei:rs>
          (1930).</tei:note> Die andern <tei:term>Skizze</tei:term>n liessen sich leicht auf Tafeln
        von mir aufschreiben.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Mit den allerherzlichsten und innigsten Grüssen an Sie beide von uns allen bin ich in
        alter und unveränderter Treue</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person"><tei:hi
              rend="lateinschr">H</tei:hi></tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:lb/><tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#HW"/><tei:date
            when="1933-03-30">March 30, 1933</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>My dear, revered <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"
            >Master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>To my deep dismay I have heard (from another source) that <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>, from whom I have in the meantime received a
        letter that I find more than disappointing, has behaved like a schoolboy in spite of his 53
        years (which he waves at me in his defence) and, when he feels attacked, cannot think of
        anything cleverer than to cry: "Please, Mr. Teacher, Weisse said …."</tei:p>

      <tei:p>My observation, that your favorable judgment of his works may be explained by your
        considering the works of your pupils from a teacher's point of view and being inclined to
        pronounce them good, is something that I regard as appropriate and find nothing either
        regrettable or damaging to you.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Having been transmitted by him, you must have, admittedly, found this observation
        irritating, and one that put me in an unfavorable light; and I believe that it was <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>'s intention to shake your faith in
        me and my adherence to the cause, and <tei:pb n="2"/> I therefore regard his behavior as
        more than indiscreet: I regard it as almost dishonest.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In order, however, to clear up the matter between ourselves, I should like merely to
        remind you of one thing. When you wrote me a letter of recommendation for <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002510"><tei:country>America</tei:country></tei:rs>, you referred
        to me in it as a "Viennese master." And I returned your letter<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> with the request not to misuse a word that has a special meaning when it
        comes from you. The purity of the concept of "master," in your unique conception of it,
        along with "the cause", meant more to me than any personal advantage. I believe that I
        convinced you of this. I recognized and treasured, from your original action, your goodness
        and friendship, and your obedience to your feelings, but it was also clear to me that you
        had gone too far. And this personal experience had, for certain, affected me in what I had
        to say to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>. I admit that,
        however much you might perhaps do so, I would never allow you to refer to any of my works in
        the way in which you have proclaimed <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922"
          >Vrieslander</tei:rs>'s songs.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> In my
        opinion, such an expression coming from you damages the world of ideas that you inhabit
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">more</tei:add> than it can serve the one to whom it
        applies. You have done this, for sure, in complete conviction; <tei:pb n="3"/> but, viewed
        from the outside, it is and remains an expression that must appear self-conscious if one is
        aware of the relationship in which you stand to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922"
          >Vrieslander</tei:rs>. What would you <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">be able</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">wish</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> to make of such an opinion as voiced by <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000798">Schoenberg</tei:rs> about <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003019"
          >Webern</tei:rs>? In addition, I remain thoroughly convinced that <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>'s songs, although you refer to positive traits
        and suchlike in them, have merely the value of imitations, not of original work; and so I
        find that such a far-reaching statement from you would already create a certain amount of
        confusion in your circle of adherents, to say nothing about how they will be interpreted by
        that circle which your work, I am most firmly convinced, is <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">still</tei:add> destined to reach and access.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I blush at the mere thought that you could believe that envy or jealousy could have led
        me to make such <tei:add place="interlinear-above">a</tei:add> statement. Nevertheless, I
        cannot and will not believe that you could <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">reject</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">let</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> any suspicion of this sort <tei:add place="interlinear-above">arise <tei:hi
            rend="underline">in you</tei:hi></tei:add>. I believe that the entire course of my life
        and my artistic development demonstrate that I live for nothing else but your world, and for
        your cause which, by the grace of Heaven, has also become very much my own.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> Such a statement is to be understood not against
        you but rather <tei:hi rend="underline">for</tei:hi> you, even if <tei:pb n="4"/> it is your
        opinion that I am, moreoever, entirely wrong in my judgment of <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>. The greatness of your work resides in the notion
        that your judgment, where it concerns the great composers, is irrefutable; I am thus all the
        more troubled by a statement by you to the effect that "these songs will soon be on the lips
        of every singer," which will simply be contradicted by the world of facts. If the
        unfortunate situation should arise whereby <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922"
          >Vrieslander</tei:rs> succeeds in arousing suspicion in you against me, then these few
        lines are intended to neither more nor less than convince you that nothing is more
        important for me than your work and your accomplishment.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Now, a bit more about <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>.
        My amicable association with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000327"
          >Hammer</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> acquainted me with a
        generosity in the exchange of opinions that places objectivity over all things personal.
        There is nothing that we cannot say to each other, even the strongest, most <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">severe</tei:add> criticism. Criticism that is concerned with the
        subject is indeed the only sort that is useful in the world. When I wrote to <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>, I cherished the hope that here it
        might be possible to effect an exchange of viewpoints, one that could unite two musicians
        from the same <tei:pb n="5"/> school to a common purpose. In conclusion, I need not tell you
        how lonely I feel among all who call themselves musicians. You have experienced <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">this</tei:add> yourself, and will know that this loneliness is a
        legacy of my adherence to you. It was no other thought than this that guided me when I began
        writing <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> a fourteen-page
        letter. The opinion <tei:add place="interlinear-above">that I expressed</tei:add> awaited an
        expression of opinion in return, that should have been concerned with the object alone:
        instead of this, I received a reply in which every word was used in order to wound me
        personally. This intention was so obvious that it had to fail to have any effect. I am only
        sorry for him: for anyone who <tei:hi rend="underline">has so little faith</tei:hi> in an
        amicable criticism that concerns an objective matter suffers from an intellectual and
        spiritual calcification, from which nothing genuine can any longer emanate. Anyone who
        answers active participation with poison, inner openness with small-minded suspicion (as if
        I were arrogant or conceited), will be unfruitful in the roots of his being. Moreover, I
        know that my personal opinion of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922"
          >Vrieslander</tei:rs> is entirely worthless in your eyes; I spell this out because I want
          <tei:hi rend="underline">you</tei:hi> to know (even if <tei:pb n="6"/> he cannot
        understand) the grounds that motivated me to discuss his work with such
        thoroughness.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>To my last letter I must still add what I forgot to say: would it perhaps be possible
        to consider the reproduction merely of the <tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:term>Urlinie
            graph</tei:term>s</tei:hi> of the "<tei:title>Eroica</tei:title>"?<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> The other <tei:term>sketch</tei:term>es I could
        easily arrange to have written on large sheets.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>With the most cordial and heartfelt greetings to the two of you, from the two of us, I
        remain, in old and immutable faithfulness,</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person"
          >H</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
