<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2898" sdoID="OJ-14-23_7">OJ 14/23, [7]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="AFS" scope="sole">A. F. Seligmann's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2022</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2012-09-28" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002735">Seligmann ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Seligmann to Schenker, undated [probably late summer or
        early autumn 1903]</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1903-09-15T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2022-11-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>In this long letter, Seligmann advises Schenker on how to prepare an
        application for a teaching post at the Vienna Conservatory: what to include and whom to get
        in touch with at the Conservatory and the Gesellschaft der Muikfreunde. He thinks that a
        position at the projected Lyceum in Vienna offers a better prospect and advises enlisting
        the help of his patron Baron Rothschild.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000819">Adalbert Franz Seligmann</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">Heinrich Schenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#AFS"/>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000819"
            >Freund</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich halte es für das gerathenste, die Empfehlung an Hartel<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Possibly Privy Counselor Ritter Wilhelm
          von Hartel (1839-1907), classicist and philologist, Minister for Culture and Education
          1900-05, Vice-President of the Akademie der Wissenschaften and member or officer of
          numerous august institutions throughout western and central Europe. (<tei:title level="m"
            >Lehmmans Wohnungs-Anzeiger, Wien</tei:title>)</tei:note> und an <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000961">Wiener</tei:rs> (die letztere halte ich sogar für wichtiger) <tei:del
          rend="overstrike">folgen</tei:del> in der auf beiliegendem Blatt angedeuteten Weise zu
          stylisiren.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">This letter,
          although undated, concerns an application for a teaching position at the Vienna
          Conservatory. It postdates Seligmann’s postcard of June 30, 1903 (<tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-23_5">OJ 14/23, [5]</tei:ref>), which mentions Ludwig
          Bösendorfer and his “normal path” referred to here, and also Baron Rothschild and the
          founding of a Lyceum. Most likely it was written sometime after Seligmann thanked Schenker
          for sending him his “Introduction” to the keyboard works of C. P. E. Bach, i.e. <tei:rs
            type="work" key="entity-001721"><tei:title level="m">Ein Beitrag zur
              Ornamentik</tei:title></tei:rs> (postcard of July 25, 1903). </tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Sie müßten die beiden möglichst kurz und einfach auseinandersetzen, das
        Sie beabsichtigen nun eine <tei:del rend="overstrike">Prof</tei:del> Lehrerstelle am <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002591">Conservatorium</tei:rs> einzureichen und um
        moralische und praktische Unterstützung in dieser Hinsicht bitten. Man kann solchen Leuten
        nur mit einer <tei:hi rend="underline">ganz bestimmt formulierten Bitte</tei:hi>
        <tei:pb n="2"/> kommen, und darf es Ihnen nicht überlassen dies oder jenes zu thun was sie
        für angemessen finden, sonst thun sie <tei:hi rend="underline">gar nichts</tei:hi> oder
        lehnen gleich jede Action ab. Ich wär sogar dafür H. u. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000961">W.</tei:rs> um directe persönliche Befürwortung Ihres Gesuches bei
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">einzelnen</tei:add> Mitgliedern des
        Directorencollegiums zu bitten, was namentlich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000961"
          >Wiener</tei:rs> nicht schwer fallen wird. Zeigen Sie Ihre <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001720"><tei:title>Bach-Ausgabe</tei:title></tei:rs><tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:title level="m">Klavierwerke von
            Philipp Emanuel Bach: Neue kritische Ausgabe von Heinrich Schenker</tei:title>,
          published on February 10, 1903.</tei:note> und <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001721"
          >Einleitung</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot"
              ><tei:bibl><tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001721"><tei:title level="m">Ein Beitrag
                zur Ornamentik</tei:title></tei:rs> (Vienna: Universal Edition, 1st edn [1903]),
            released on July 24, 1903</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> erwähnen Sie Ihre theoretische
          Schrift,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Perhaps the early,
          unpublished treatise <tei:title level="m">Das Tonsystem</tei:title>, which pre-dates
          Schenker’s <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724"><tei:title level="m"
              >Harmonielehre</tei:title></tei:rs> and is preserved in OC file 31 (pp. 360–386). See
              <tei:bibl><tei:author>Robert W. Wason</tei:author>, <tei:title level="a">From <tei:hi
                rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> to <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmony</tei:hi>:
              Schenker’s Theory of Harmony and its Americanization,</tei:title>
            <tei:title level="j">Essays from the Fourth International Schenker
            Symposium</tei:title>, vol. I, ed. <tei:editor>Allen Cadwallader</tei:editor>
            (Hildesheim: Georg Olms Verlag, 2008), 215–22</tei:bibl>. See also
              <tei:bibl><tei:author>Robert W. Wason</tei:author> and <tei:author>Matthew
              Brown</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Heinrich Schenker’s Conception of
              Harmony</tei:title> (Rochester, NY: University of Rochester Press,
          2020)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note>
        <tei:pb n="3"/> oder zeigen Sie sie, wenn sie erschienen ist, <tei:del rend="overstrike"
          >schon</tei:del> vor. Und vor allem – verzeihen Sie meine Bosheit, wenn ich <tei:del
          rend="overstrike">Ihn[en]</tei:del> meine, daß das Ihnen schwer fallen wird – seien Sie in
        den bewußten Unterredungen möglichst <tei:hi rend="underline">präcis</tei:hi>. Von dem
        Lyceumsplan erwähnen Sie gar <tei:hi rend="underline">nichts</tei:hi>; denn über ein
        ungelegtes Ei kann man nicht reden, wenigstens nicht mit Herren dieser Art. Beschränken Sie
        sich darauf kurz zu sagen, das Sie Ihre, Ihrer und anderer Musikanständiger Ansicht nach,
        originellen und praktisch sehr verwendbaren Theorien <tei:pb n="4"/> von einer offiziellen
        Lehrkanzel aus vortragen möchten und daß Ihnen das <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002591">Conservatorium</tei:rs>, eben wegen seiner eigene Verbindung mit der
        praktischen, ausgeübten Kunst, dazu geeigneter erscheint als etwa eine Lectorstelle an der
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-003334">Universität</tei:rs>. Verschaffen Sie sich
        was Ihnen ja nicht schwer fallen kann, ein Verzeichnis der Directoren der <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002430">Gesellsch. der Musikfr.</tei:rs> (Ich nenne Ihnen
        einstweilen Steyer, Gotthelf Mayer, Billing (vorsichtig zu behandeln weil vermutlich ein
        bischen antisemitisch!) Koch von Langentreu, selbstredend <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000667">Perger</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Seligmann’s list includes the writer and businessman Gotthelf Karl Meyer
          (1844–1905); the composer and conductor Richard von Perger (1854–1911), who served as
          Director of the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002430">Gesellschaft der
            Musikfreunde</tei:rs>; the lawyer Heinrich Billing von Gemmen (1834–1908), who served as
          its Vice-President; and the composer Josef Koch von Langentreu (1833–1905). Seligmann
          cautions Schenker about Billing’s possible antisemitism; he may not, however, have known
          of Koch von Langentreu’s <tei:title level="m">Das Judenthum in der Musik</tei:title>, Op.
          36, for male chorus, composed around 1870.</tei:note> und bitten Sie die beiden Herren (H.
        u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000961">W.</tei:rs>) Ihnen entweder ihre persönliche
        oder gar schriftliche Fürsprache bei einem oder dem <tei:pb n="5"/> andern zuzusagen. Dann
        besuchen Sie diese Herren selber, bitten Sie um ihre Stimmen und trachten auch, sich mit den
        wichtigsten Mitgliedern des Schulausschusses vom <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002591">Conservatorium</tei:rs> (ich weiß nicht wer jetzt drin ist) in
        Verbindung zu setzen und ihre Fürsprache zu werben. Dann müßten Sie ein reguläres Gesuch mit
          <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">curriculum
          vitae</tei:hi></tei:foreign>, beilegen, die Ihre Leistungsfähigkeit beweisen, also die
          <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001720"><tei:title>Bach-Ausgabe</tei:title></tei:rs> und
          <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001721">Einleitung</tei:rs> und ein paar Ihrer
        Zeitungsartikel (etwa die aus der <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-005689"
              ><tei:title><tei:hi rend="underline">Wiener Zeitung</tei:hi></tei:title></tei:rs>
        (sehr wichtig!) eine oder andere aus <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002545">der
            „<tei:title>Zeit</tei:title>“</tei:rs> etc. <tei:del rend="overstrike"
          >beilegen</tei:del> an- <tei:pb n="6"/> schließen, erwähnen dass Sie als Lehrer bereits
        praktische Erfahrungen gesammelt und befriedigende Ergebnisse erzielt haben u.s.w., kurz den
        regulären Weg gehen, den <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000090">Bösendorfer</tei:rs> als
        denjenigen empfohlen hat, der das autokratische Gefühl der Herren Directoren und
        Schulausschußmitglieder nicht verletzt. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Freilich habe ich für die ganze Sache nicht viel Hoffnung. Es ist ja eine
        Geldfrage, und da sind diese Herren alle etwas spießig, namentlich wenn es sich um
          <tei:term>Theorie</tei:term> handelt. <tei:pb n="7"/> Ich hielte es – im Vertrauen – für
        angezeigter, wenn Sie versuchen würden – oder doch dem <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000743">Baron R.</tei:rs> gegenüber erwähnten, dass die Sache mit dem Lyceum
        im Werden ist und sich seiner finanziellen Theilnahme versichern würden. Ich glaube <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000743">R.</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002467"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Länderbank</tei:hi></tei:rs> stehen ja in
        Beziehungen. Vielleicht könnte die <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002467"><tei:hi
            rend="lateinschr">Länderbank</tei:hi></tei:rs> – sowie sie die <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002408">Edition Universelle</tei:rs> financiert hat – auch
        ein Unternehmen wie dieses Lyceum anpacken und damit dem ohnedies schon recht verfaulten
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002591">Conservatorium</tei:rs> eine wirksame
        Concurrenz bieten. <tei:pb n="8"/> Wie das Unternehmen angelegt ist, kann es sich auch
        financiell rentiren, sobald Kraft<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> von
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000169"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
          >Dohnanyi</tei:hi></tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000727">Rosé</tei:rs>
        (eventuell <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006219"><tei:hi rend="underline"
            >Hummer</tei:hi></tei:rs>, der <tei:add place="interlinear-above">sicher</tei:add> gerne
        dorthin gienge wenn man ihm mehr bäte als das <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002591">Conservatorium</tei:rs>!) zusagen. Lassen Sie also dieses Eisen, das
        ich für das bessere halte, nicht aus dem Feuer! </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000743">B. Roth<tei:supplied
            reason="omission">s</tei:supplied>ch.</tei:rs> kann ich, da ich ihn <tei:hi
          rend="underline">gar</tei:hi> nicht kenne, nicht, wie Sie gemeint haben, den Text der
        bewußten Empfehlung senden. Ich lege ihn also bei, empfehlen Ihnen aber, mit <tei:choice>
          <tei:sic>Ihm</tei:sic>
          <tei:corr>ihm</tei:corr>
        </tei:choice> womöglich auch über den zweiten Plan <tei:pb n="9"/> zu sprechen.
        Aufrichtigkeit ist in vielen Fällen die beste Diplomatie. Sagen Sie ihm also ganz ruhig, was
        Sie anstreben und benützen Sie dabei vielleicht diesen Brief (Sie brauchen ja meinen Namen,
        den er wol nicht kennt, gar nicht zu nennen,) um Ihm klar zu machen, worum es sich handelt. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Also – beste Grüße und Glückauf</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">von Ihrem </tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000819">Seligmann</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#AFS"/>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000819"
            >friend</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>I regard it as most advisable that you fashion the letters of recommendation to
          Hartel<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> and to <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000961">Wiener</tei:rs> (I regard the latter as actually more important) in
        the manner suggested on the enclosed sheet of paper.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">You must explain to them, as briefly and as simply as possible, that you
        now intend to apply for a <tei:del rend="overstrike">prof</tei:del> teaching post at the
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002591">Conservatory</tei:rs> and are seeking
        moral and practical support. One can approach such people only with a <tei:hi
          rend="underline">request that is formulated quite precisely</tei:hi>; <tei:pb n="2"/> and
        you should not neglect to do anything that they will regard as appropriate, otherwise they
        will do <tei:hi rend="underline">nothing at all</tei:hi> or refuse to take any action. I
        would even be in favor of your asking H. and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000961"
          >W.</tei:rs> for direct personal endorsement of your case with <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">individual</tei:add> members of the Board of Directors,
        something that <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000961">Wiener</tei:rs> would not find
        difficult. Show them your <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001720"><tei:title>edition of
            Bach</tei:title></tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> and the
          <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001721">Introduction</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> mention your theoretical writing;<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/>
        <tei:pb n="3"/> or show it to them if it has <tei:del rend="overstrike">already</tei:del>
        been published. And above all – forgive me for being malicious if I say something that may
        offend you – be as <tei:hi rend="underline">precise</tei:hi> as possible during the
        interviews in question. Of the plan for a Lyceum, say <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >nothing</tei:hi> at all; for one cannot speak about an egg that has not yet been laid,
        least of all with people of this sort. Confine yourself to saying that you would like to
        present your theories, which in your opinion and those of other reputable musicians are
        original and very useful in practice, <tei:pb n="4"/> from an official educational position,
        and that the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002591">Conservatory</tei:rs>, verily
        on account of its special connection with the art as it is exercised in a practical way, is
        more suitable for this than, say, a lectureship at the <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-003334">University</tei:rs>. Get hold of a list of the directors of the
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002430">Society of the Friends of Music</tei:rs>,
        something which you should surely not find difficult; (For now, I mention the names of
        Steyer, Gotthelf Mayer, Billing (treat him cautiously because he seems to be a bit
        antisemitic!), Koch von Langentreu, and of course <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000667"
          >Perger</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> and ask the two
        gentlemen (H. and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000961">W.</tei:rs>) to convey to one or
        the other of these their support for you, either in person or even in writing. <tei:pb n="5"
        /> Then visit these gentlemen yourself, ask them for their endorsement, and strive also to
        contact the most important members of the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002591"
          >Conservatory</tei:rs>’s school board (I do not know who is currently on it) and obtain
        their support. Then you must submit a proper application with curriculum vitae, which
        testifies to your capability, and append your <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001720"
            ><tei:title>Bach edition</tei:title></tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001721">Introduction</tei:rs> and a few of your newspaper articles – for
        instance from the <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-005689"><tei:title level="j"><tei:hi
              rend="underline">Wiener Zeitung</tei:hi></tei:title></tei:rs> (very important!), one
        or two from <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002545"><tei:title level="j">Die
            Zeit</tei:title></tei:rs>, etc.; <tei:pb n="6"/> mention that you have already acquired
        practical experience as a teacher and achieved satisfactory results, etc., in short that you
        will take the normal path that <tei:rs key="entity-000090">Bösendorfer</tei:rs> recommended,
        the one that will not hurt the autocratic sympathies of the directors and the members of the
        school board.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Admittedly, I do not hold out much hope for the whole matter. It is indeed
        a question of money, and all these gentleman are somewhat stingy, especially when it
        concerns <tei:term>theory</tei:term>. <tei:pb n="7"/> Speaking confidentially, I regarded it
        as more advisable for you to attempt – or at least mention to <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000743">Baron R.</tei:rs> that the matter with the Lyceum is in progress – to
        secure his financial support. I believe that <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000743"
          >R.</tei:rs> and the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002467">Länderbank</tei:rs>
        enjoy a good relationship. Perhaps the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002467"
          >Länderbank</tei:rs>, inasmuch as it has financed <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002408">Universal Edition</tei:rs>, will tackle a project such as this Lyceum
        and thus offer an effective competition to the <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002591">Conservatory</tei:rs> which, at any rate, has become quite decadent.
          <tei:pb n="8"/> In the way in which the project has been set up, it can even become
        financially viable, so long as Kraft, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000169"
          >Dohnanyi</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000727">Rosé</tei:rs> (possibly
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006219"><tei:hi rend="underline"
          >Hummer</tei:hi></tei:rs>, who would <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >certainly</tei:add> be happy to go there if he were offered more than what he is getting
        at the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002591">Conservatory</tei:rs>!) accept
        positions there. So do not leave this iron, which I regard as the better one, out of the
        fire!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Since I do not know him <tei:hi rend="underline">at all</tei:hi>, I cannot
        – as you suggested – send <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000743">Baron
          Rothschild</tei:rs> the text of the said letter of reference. I am therefore enclosing it,
        but I recommend that you speak to him, if possible, also about the second plan. <tei:pb
          n="9"/> Honesty is, in many cases, the best policy. Tell him then, quite calmly, what you
        seek and perhaps use this letter (you need not mention my name at all, for he probably does
        not know me), so that he knows what this is about.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">And so, best greetings and good luck </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">from your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000819">Seligmann</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
