<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2712" sdoID="OJ-5-27_3">OJ 5/27, [3]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="JK" scope="major">Jeanette Kornfeld's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="minor">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="MD">
      <tei:persName>Marko Deisinger</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2021</tei:resp>

    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2021</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>


    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2011-06-09" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008169">PairamallE ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter (non-extant) from Schenker to Evenlina Pairamall, dated October
        20, 1916</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1916-10-20T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2022-03-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker describes in detail how he works out Mrs. Pairamall's lesson schedule
        according to her requests, and calculates her fee.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000655">EPairamall</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">The signature assigned to this letter above is a
          false one: the document exists in Schenker’s diary for October 20, 1916, at OJ 1/10, pp.
          474—475. It is not the letter itself but an extended summary of its contents.</tei:note><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">Note: This entry is written as a single paragraph.
          Breaks have been inserted editorially for readability.</tei:note><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p><tei:handShift new="#JK"/>— An <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000655">Fr.
          Pairamall</tei:rs> (Br., 4 Seiten lang!):<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
          place="foot">This summary is entered by Jeanette Kornfeld, at Schenker’s dictation, into
          the latter's diary for October 20, 1916. The letter itself is not known to survive. The
          letter has thus been given the false signature of “OJ 5/27, [3]” purely for purposes of
          entering the item into the <tei:title level="m">SDO</tei:title> container–document
          framework. Folder OJ 5/27 does not contain the letter itself. — The unusually heavy
          editing by Heinrich (perhaps surprising for a document that has already been written) has
          not, for practical reasons, been mirrored in the English translation. <tei:lb/>Schenker’s
          diary contains many other summaries of letters to (and from) Mrs Pairamall: this alone is
          reproduced here because of its extent and level of detail. Moreover, it contains an
          excerpt from the letter itself.</tei:note> setze voraus, daß sie nicht einfach ausspannen
        will, <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">u.</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">wie ferner auch,</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> daß der Betrag, den sie für den Unterricht präliminiert hat, sich aus ihren
        eigenen Andeutungen ungefähr errechnen läßt, u. <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">erkläre</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ziehe draus den Schluß</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>, daß mir somit nur eigentlich die Aufgabe übrig bleibt, über ihre eigene
        Aufforderung einen Vorschlag zu machen, <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">u.</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">der geeignet wäre</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> den bestimmten kleinen Betrag einer Form zuzuführen. Ich spezialisiere <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">nun des Weiteren</tei:add>, auf welche Weise ich den Betrag
        errechnet habe: <tei:add place="interlinear-above">erstens,</tei:add> daß sie offenbar die
        Zahl der Stunden nicht gar zu gering festgesetzt habe, schließe ich aus der Unmöglichkeit,
        für etwas ein Honorar zu empfangen, was sich auf rein gesellschaftlicher Basis besser
        ausführen ließe; <tei:add place="interlinear-above">zweitens</tei:add> schließe ich <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">ferner</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">auf die Zahl der Stunden</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> aus den Erfahrungen, die sie seinerzeit bei <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000523">Leschet<tei:subst>
            <tei:del rend="overwritten">i</tei:del>
            <tei:add place="superimposed">y</tei:add>
          </tei:subst>tzki</tei:rs> gemacht hat, deren Konsequenzen, wie ich eben annehme, sie
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">auch</tei:add> in meinem <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">völlig gegensätzlichen</tei:add> Falle miterwogen hat; u.
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">endlich drittens</tei:add> auch aus dem selbst mit der
        losesten Form der Verabredung von Stunde<tei:del rend="overstrike">n</tei:del> zu Stunde
        noch immer gegebenen Zwange.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Diese immerhin annehmbare kleine Zahl von Stunden <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >nun</tei:add> mit der <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ihrerseits</tei:add> angebotenen
        Erhöhungen multiplizierend, konnte ich das zu riskierende Geld jenseits von Rücksicht auf
        Gesundheit u. materielle Situation feststellen. Nun weise ich <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">aber</tei:add> zunächst die Erhöhung zurück u. erwähne hiebei
        des Falles <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000457">Kolischer</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-003399">Frau Mendl</tei:rs>. Endlich mein Vorschlag: Wir
        reduzieren alles auf die Hälfte, <tei:add place="interlinear-above">eine Form,</tei:add> die
        dann schließlich auch in Friedenszeiten beibehalten werden kann; erkläre mich <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">zugleich</tei:add> bereit, heuer ausnahmsweise die 32 bezw. 33
        Stunden im Laufe von 4 Monaten zusammenzudrängen, so daß wir Ende Februar unserer
        Verpflichtungen gegenseitig ledig wären. Ich erwähne ferner <tei:pb n="475"/> selbst
        etwaiger Differenzen, die zwischen meiner u. ihrer Rechnung sich ergeben mögen, erkläre sie
        aber für zu belanglos, als daß man ihnen <tei:add place="interlinear-above">noch
          eigens</tei:add> nach<tei:add place="interlinear-above">zu</tei:add>gehen <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">müßte</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">hätte</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>, <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">möge</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">gleichviel ob</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> der Verlust von Stunden durch Krankheit oder andere Ursachen <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">kommen</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">einträte</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Endlich zum Beschluss erkläre ich, weshalb ich auf dem <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >Zwang</tei:hi> bestehe, <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">den</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">wie</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> ich <tei:supplied reason="clarity">ihn</tei:supplied> nicht etwa des Erwerbes
        halber in die Sache hineintrage, sondern nur aus der Sache heraushole u. zum Nutzen der
        Schüler stilisiere. Der Zwang <tei:sic>überdieß</tei:sic> auch gesundheitlich eine große
        Wirkung aus u. befreie in unnachahmlich diskreter Weise Lehrer wie Schüler von der leidigen
        Frage nach Rücksicht ins Endlose, nach „Rücksicht auf Rücksicht“ usw. Wohin kämen die
        Schüler, frage ich, wenn der Lehrer, statt sich dem Zwange zu unterwerfen, Rücksicht von
        ihnen einfordern würde u. umgekehrt? <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000294"
          >Goethe</tei:rs> war weise genug, einen Zwang sich sogar künstlich aufzuhalsen, um sich
        durch das Dick u. Dünn seiner Erlebnisse <tei:add place="interlinear-above">wohl</tei:add>
        unter allen Umständen seine Leistung sicherzustellen. Ich schließe mit einer Andeutung, daß
        ich der Sache müde bin u. sie nunmehr für eine Lappalie halte, an die ich weiter keine Mühe
        zu wenden gesonnen bin. —</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Indem ich mich zu diesem Entgegenkommen bereit zeige, züchtige ich die <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000655">Briefempfängerin</tei:rs> mit einem ordentlichen Hieb
        für die Unverschämtheit des Vorwurfes einer angeblichen „Härte im System“; ich erkläre, daß <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overwritten">Hä</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="superimposed">ha</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>rte, d. h. unredliche Erwerbsysteme wo anders zu finden sind! —</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Einzelne Wendungen aus dem Briefe: Die <tei:hi rend="underline">Reichen</tei:hi> l<tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overwritten">ie</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="superimposed">a</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>ßen sich ihr <tei:hi rend="underline">Gehirn</tei:hi> am liebsten nur zwischen
        Weihnachten u. Ostern frisieren, u. machen sich nichts daraus, die übrige Zeit <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">geistig</tei:add> unfrisiert herumzulaufen. Was würde man
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">aber</tei:add> von einer Frau sagen, die sich nur des
        einen Morgens frisieren würde, <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">u.</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">um</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> mit der einen Frisur <tei:add place="interlinear-above">nun</tei:add> einen
        Monat lang ihr Auslangen <tei:add place="interlinear-above">zu</tei:add> finden <tei:del
          rend="overstrike">wollte</tei:del>?</tei:p>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">The signature assigned to this letter above is a
          false one: the document exists in Schenker’s diary for October 20, 1916, at OJ 1/10, pp.
          474—475. It is not the letter itself but an extended summary of its contents.</tei:note><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">Note: This entry is written as a single paragraph.
          Breaks have been inserted editorially for readability.</tei:note><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p><tei:handShift new="#JK"/>— To <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000655">Mrs.
          Pairamall</tei:rs> (letter, four pages long!):<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
          type="footnote"/> I assume that she does not simply want to give up, and in addition that
        the sum that she had preliminarily arranged for her tuition corresponds approximately to her
        own <tei:supplied reason="clarity">previous</tei:supplied> indications; from this I conclude
        that the only thing actually left to do is to make a recommendation on the basis of her
        request, one that would be suitable for providing a shape for the small sum of money.
        Further, I set out in particular the way in which I have calculated the sum. First, as she
        has evidently reckoned a number of lessons that is not overly modest, I exclude the
        possibility of receiving a fee for something that can better be dealt with on a purely
        social basis. Secondly, I infer the number of lessons from the experiences that she had
        previously had with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000523">Leschetizky</tei:rs>, the
        consequences of which – as I now assume – she had taken into consideration even despite my
        completely contrasting arrangement; third and lastly, still from the same given compulsion,
        to make arrangements from one lesson to the next in the most casual way.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Multiplying this apparently small number of lessons now by the <tei:supplied
          reason="clarity">lesson fee</tei:supplied> enhancement that she for her part is offering,
        I was able to determine the money to be risked, apart from considerations of health and
        material circumstances. But now I reject in the first instance the enhancement, and mention
        in this regard the cases of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000457">Kolischer</tei:rs> and
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003399">Mrs. Mendl</tei:rs>. Finally, my suggestion: we
        reduce everything by half, an arrangement that can ultimately be adhered to even during
        peacetime; at the same time I declare myself prepared, exceptionally, to squeeze the
        thirty-two or thirty-three lessons into the space of four months, so that we would be free
        of our responsibilities at the end of February. Further, I mention <tei:pb n="475"/>
        possible differences between my calculations and hers, but declare them to be irrelevant,
        since we still have to go through them again, whether the loss of lessons arises as a result
        of illness or other causes.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Finally, in conclusion, I explain why I insist on <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >pressure</tei:hi>, that I do not introduce this into the matter for sake of earnings but
        rather derive them from the matter and stylize them for the benefits of my pupils. Pressure,
        moreover, exerts a great effect also from the point of view of health; it frees in an
        inimitably discreet way both teacher and pupil from the painful question of allowances, of
        “allowance upon allowances,” etc. Where would the pupils get to, I ask, if the teacher,
        instead of bowing to pressure, demanded allowance from them, and vice versa? <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000294">Goethe</tei:rs> was clever enough to subject himself to
        pressure even artificially, in order to secure his achievement under all circumstances,
        through the thick and thin of his life’s experiences. I conclude by hinting that I am tired
        of the matter and regard it henceforth as a trifle that I am not minded to take further
        trouble over. —</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In showing myself prepared for this compromise, I chastise the <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000655">recipient of the letter</tei:rs> with a proper thumping for her
        criticism of a supposed “severity in the system”; I declare that severities, that is,
        dishonest systems of earning a living, are to be found elsewhere! —</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Individual extracts from the letter: the r<tei:hi rend="underline">ich</tei:hi> prefer
        to groom <tei:hi rend="underline">their brains</tei:hi> only between Christmas and Easter,
        and are not troubled by going about unkempt the rest of the time. But what would one say
        about a woman who did up her hair only on one morning, to earn a living for a whole month
        with just the one hairdo?</tei:p>


    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
