<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3107" sdoID="OJ-5-9_2">OJ 5/9, [2]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2023</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IDB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2023</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2015-09-18" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002726">DeutschOE ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002712">DeutschOE ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002727">DeutschOE+H ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Deutsch, dated April 3, 1930</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1930-04-03T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2023-03-24</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker confirms that a Beethoven sketch for "Neue Liebe, neues Leben" is
        related to the earlier of his two settings of the song. Although he is grateful for
        Nottebohm’s work on the Beethoven sketches, he transcribed only from the surface, not from
        the depths of the composition. -- In a postscript, Schenker complains that, in a recent
        feuilleton, the music critic Julius Korngold has quoted his terminology (e.g.
        Auskomponierung) but failed to mention his name.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000164">DeutschOE</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Mein lieber Prof <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000164">Deutsch</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
            place="foot">Sending of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for April 3, 1930:
            “An Deutsch (Br.): stimme ihm zu, Nottebohm kannte die Simrock-Vorlage wahrscheinlich
            noch nicht, im übrigen ist ein Mißtrauen gegenüber Nottebohm am Platze, da er die
            Handschriften nicht aus der Tiefe der Komposition zu lesen verstand” (“To Deutsch
            (letter): I agree with him that Nottebohm probably did not yet know the Simrock version;
            moreover a mistrust of Nottebohm is not inappropriate, as he was unable to read the
            manuscripts on the basis of a deep knowledge of the
          composition”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>


      <tei:p>Sie haben recht, das Skizzenzitat führt zu <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002448">Simrock</tei:rs>’s erste Ausgabe, (wo haben Sie denn diese
          gefunden)?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">See the last page of
          Deutsch’s letter of April 1 (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-10-3_123">OJ 10/3,
            [123]</tei:ref>), in which he suggests that a sketch for <tei:title level="m">Neue
            Liebe, neues Leben</tei:title> transcribed by Nottebohm, relates to the earlier of
          Beethoven’s two settings of Goethe’s text.</tei:note> Natürlich mußte <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000636"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Notteb</tei:hi>.</tei:rs>
        irregehen, wenn er jene nicht kannte. Das alles tut freilich seinem ersten großen Verdienst
        keinen Abbruch, aber richtiggestellt muß doch alles von ihm Ungerechten oder gar falsch
        gelesenen werden. Ich empfand stets heftigsten Dank für die <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
          >Beethoveniana</tei:hi>, daneben auch Mistrauen. Denn <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000636"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Nottb</tei:hi></tei:rs>. las die Skizzen
        mehr obenhin, nicht aus der Tiefe der Komposition: <tei:pb n="2"/> was mag er alles
        stehengelassen haben, weil er in den Notenköpfchen die künftige Gestalt nicht erkannte. Z.
        B. das mir von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000345">Heck</tei:rs> vor 2 Jahren gezeigte
        Blatt zum letzten <tei:del rend="overstrike">Pasto</tei:del> Satz der <tei:rs
          type="composition" key="entity-001266"><tei:title>Pastorale</tei:title></tei:rs> würde er
        ganz gewiß nicht haben lesen können, u. doch strotzt das Blatt von allerschönsten
        Zusammenhängen. In der „Eroica“-Monogr.,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
          place="foot">The “Eroica” “monograph” was published as the <tei:rs type="work"
            key="entity-001752">third <tei:title level="j">Meisterwerk</tei:title> yearbook</tei:rs>
          in December 1930.</tei:note> Abschnitt Literatur, spreche ich <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">auch</tei:add> darüber einige Worte. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Vielen Dank, beste Grüße Ihnen </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Beiden von uns Beiden</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"><tei:hi
              rend="lateinschr">H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1930-04-03">3. 4. 30</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p>><tei:pb n="3"/> Haben Sie <tei:del rend="overstrike">übrigens</tei:del> in <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000471">Korngold</tei:rs>’s (übrigens nach seinen Kräften
          trefflichem) <tei:title>Wozzek</tei:title>-<tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
            >Feuilleton</tei:hi><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot"
                ><tei:bibl><tei:author>Julius Korngold</tei:author>, <tei:title level="a"
                >Operntheater: ‘Wozzeck’, Oper nach Georg Büchners Drama von Alban Berg,</tei:title>
              feuilleton, <tei:title level="j">Neue Freie Presse</tei:title>, April 1, 1930, pp.
              1–4</tei:bibl>. On p. 3 of this scathing review, Korngold writes, “Atonale Setzweise
            kann eben keinen echten, am wenigstens melodischen Singstoff ergeben, ja, streng
            genommen, kann dies schon einseitig und ausschließlich chromatische Setzweise nicht,
            wenn nicht sinnvolle harmonische Ausdeutung, sogenannte ‘Auskomponierung’ hinzutritt.”
            (“Atonal composition can actually not result in genuine, least of all melodic, material
            for singing; indeed, strictly speaking, this one-sidedly and exclusively chromatic
            manner of composing cannot achieve this unless it is also accompanied by a meaningful
            harmonic interpretation, a so-called ‘composing-out.’”)</tei:note>
          <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Schenker</tei:hi> in „ “ gelesen? Er macht seit langem Anleihen
          bei mir in Begriffs- und Wortprotzungen, diesmal kotiert er auf seine Börse die sogenannte
          „Auskomponierung“ (1906 von mir zuerst gebracht), also „sogenannt“ die Auskg., nur <tei:hi
            rend="lateinschr">Schenker</tei:hi> soll nicht genannt werden. Um wieviel leichter würde
          er schreiben, wenn er sich meiner Hilfe noch geflissentlicher bedienen könnte oder
          wollte!</tei:p>

      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>My dear Prof. <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000164">Deutsch</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"
          /></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>


      <tei:p>You are correct, the sketch quotation refers to <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002448">Simrock</tei:rs>’s first edition (where did you find it?).<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000636">Nottebohm</tei:rs> would of course have had to go
        astray if he did not know it. That of course does not negate his primary great service; but
        everything that he misinterpreted or actually read incorrectly must be put right. I always
        felt immensely grateful for his <tei:title level="m">Beethoveniana</tei:title>, but also
        some mistrust, since <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000636">Nottebohm</tei:rs> for the
        most part read the sketches hastily and not from the depth of the composition: <tei:pb n="2"
        /> how much he must have abandoned because he did not recognize the future shape
          <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of the music</tei:supplied> in those little noteheads. For
        example, he would surely have been unable to read the <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
          >sketch</tei:supplied> leaf for the last movement of the <tei:rs type="composition"
          key="entity-001266"><tei:title>“Pastoral” Symphony</tei:title></tei:rs>, which <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000345">Heck</tei:rs> showed me two years ago; and yet the leaf
        abounds in the most beautiful connections. I shall <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >also</tei:add> say a few words about this in the secondary literature section of my
        monograph on the “Eroica.”<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Many thanks, best greetings </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">to the two of you from the two of us.</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.
          Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1930-04-03">April 3, 1930</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p>><tei:pb n="3"/> Have you <tei:del rend="overstrike">by chance</tei:del> read, in
            <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000471">Korngold</tei:rs>’s feuilleton on <tei:title
            level="m">Wozzeck</tei:title><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> (which is
          by the way very sharp, in relation to his abilities), Schenker in quotation marks? He has
          for a long time borrowed from me by making conceptual and verbal displays; this time he
          has listed for admission to his stock exchange the so-called “composing out,” a term I
          first used in 1906; that is “so-called” composing out – but Schenker’s name should not be
          mentioned. How much more easily could he write if he could – or would – avail himself of
          my help in a more deliberate way.</tei:p>

      </tei:postscript>


    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
