<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="2315" sdoID="OJ-5-45_1">OJ 5/45, [1]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="sole">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="ID-WD">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent and William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2019</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-10-28" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Copy letter from Schenker to Weisse, in Jeanette Schenker’s hand, dated June 17,
    1915</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1915-06-17T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-11-04</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>In a six-page letter, and following harsh exchanges the previous day, Schenker
    castigates Weisse for trying to avoid paying for four lessons, speaking of his own difficulties
    in managing the profession of private teacher, and the unfair ways in which artists are treated
    financially.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>



   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000951">Weisse</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:add place="inline"><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">top line cut
     off</tei:note><tei:lb/> bei mir; da aber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000655">Frau
      P.</tei:rs> um ½6<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> abgesagt hat, so begab ich mich sofort
     an die Arbeit in meiner „Munitionsfabrik“ . . </tei:add><tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Mein lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
     >Hans</tei:rs>![1]</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">So erwarte ich Sie also morgen Freitag gegen ½12^h^,[2] schicke aber hier
    gleich voraus, daß ich den kleinen Betrag, die mir noch zukommen soll, nur so lange in meiner
    Hand behalte, als es nötig ist, ihn auf die Post zu bringen u. dort an die Adresse der „<tei:hi
     rend="underline">Wittwen u. Waisen</tei:hi>“ umzudirigiern,[3] wovon Sie einen Beleg in der
     „<tei:hi rend="underline">N. Fr. Presse</tei:hi>“ unter der <tei:hi rend="underline"
     >Chiffre</tei:hi>: <tei:hi rend="underline">Dr. H. Sch</tei:hi> ^<tei:hi rend="underline"
     >nicht</tei:hi> voller Namen^ finden werden. Grillparzer sagte (beiläufig): „Immer wird das
    Weib vom Manne betrogen“ (gerne hätte ich seine Begründung gehört), in wie viel höherem Maße
    gilt der Spruch in eigener freier Uebertragung: „Immer wird das „<tei:hi rend="underline"
     >Mutter</tei:hi>“land vom „Vater“land betrogen“. Sie, die Wittwen nach den Kriegern, sind immer
    dazu bestimmt, das stärkste Opfer zu bringen, das ihnen das „Vater“land (nach gemachtem
    Gebrauch) niemals dankt. (Auch im Laufe der Saison habe ich wiederholt für die „<tei:hi
     rend="underline">Wittwen</tei:hi>“ Beiträge eingesendet, sicher mehr, als unsere Millionäre an
    ihrem Geldbestand gemessen).</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Doch sind noch einige Worte nötig:</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> Ich schreibe sie so freimütig nieder, als ich es im höheren
    Interesse für notwendig erachte. Mir ist durchaus nicht entgangen, daß Sie nur zu Beginn des
    Monats (wiederholt) erklärt haben, Sie „<tei:hi rend="underline">gehörten sich selbst nicht
     mehr</tei:hi>.“ Ich habe den Wink verstanden, u. wenn ich dennoch gleichsam zuwiderhandelte,
    indem ich Sie noch immer an die Musik zu binden suchte, so geschah es, weil ich <tei:hi
     rend="underline">gerade</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="double-underline">Sie</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">frei</tei:hi> wissen wollte davon, was ich zeitlebens als ein
    Verbrechen an der Kunst bezeichne[.] Sie wissen, daß ich als den einzigen Heroismus meinerseits
    die Leistung bezeichne, ^für^ meine Arbeiten überhaupt erst die <tei:hi rend="underline"
     >Möglichkeit</tei:hi> geschaffen zu haben! Schon heute dürften ^auch^ Sie sich als vom Verleger
    betroffen betrachten (s. Ihre Klavierstücke, Ihre Arbeit), aber die Verleger sind es wahrlich
     <tei:hi rend="underline">nicht allein</tei:hi>, die im Wege stehen.[4] Ich kann sagen, daß ich
    unter günstigeren Bedingunen nicht nur II^2^, sondern auch schon den wichtigsten Teil der „kl.
    Bibl.“, die „Formenlehre“ etc. herausgebracht hätte u. damit Tausenden, u. Millionen von
    Musikern aller späteren Zeiten eine neue, rechtschaffene Betätigungs<tei:hi rend="underline"
     >möglichkeit</tei:hi> (sei es in der <tei:hi rend="underline">Komposition</tei:hi>, oder im
     <tei:hi rend="underline">Unterricht</tei:hi>, in <tei:hi rend="underline"
     >Geschichtsschreiben</tei:hi> etc.) begründet hätte. (Denn <tei:hi rend="underline">mehr als
     Sie wissen</tei:hi> u. ahnen ist diese Entwicklung <tei:hi rend="underline">schon</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">im Zuge</tei:hi>!) Und daß ich allen Erwerb lediglich auf <tei:pb n="3"
    /> die Arbeits<tei:hi rend="underline">bedingung</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">konzentriere</tei:hi>, dürften Sie wohl auch schon herausgefunden
    haben.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Viele Jahre verbrachte ich damit, den eigenen Schülern begreiflich zu machen,
    wie sie über ihre Gegenleistung zu denken haben. Der Geldwahn, an dem die Menschen leiden,
    bringt es mit sich, daß sie die Gegenleistung an Geld immer als ein „Mehr“ empfinden (man trennt
    sich so schwer vom Gelde.), und nur widerwillig ringen sie sich jene ^nur dort^ ab, wo durch den
    Staat geschützte Kategorien keinen Ausweg lassen (Hoteliers, Advokaten, Zahnärzte, Kaufleute
    etc.). Dem Künstler allein gegenüber will die Welt noch immer nicht lernen, die Loslösung vom
    Gelde zu verwinden.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Niemals aber hätten Sie mich je auf Ihrem Lebenswege angetroffen wenn ^nicht
    auch^ ich – lediglich im Interesse der zu verrichtenden Arbeit, die ja den <tei:hi
     rend="underline">Schülern</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">selbst</tei:hi> zu^gute^kommt! – nicht auch dringend für mich in
    Anspruch genommen hätte, was die wirtschaftlichen Kategorien durchgesetzt haben.[5] Ich wäre
    längst tot, u. nichts hätte ich vollbracht, wenn es blos auf die Gedankenlosigkeit der Verleger
    u. Schüler angekommen wäre, die anderseits – welcher Widerspruch! – doch wieder nur das Beste
    bei mir suchten u. auch <tei:pb n="4"/> erwarteten. Ich duldete nicht absurde Gedanken der
    „Förderung“, oder verwandte Ideen des „Raths“, „Austausches“, etc., u. suchte allezeit, schon um
    durch Klarheit auch die <tei:hi rend="underline">Resultate</tei:hi> der <tei:hi rend="underline"
     >Arbeit</tei:hi> zu fördern, darauf hinzuwirken, daß meine Zeit, mein Gesundheit u. Leistung
    nicht zu Gunsten bestimmter kleiner Summen unterschätzt werden. (Ach, ich habe sehr, sehr viel
    Briefe nach dieser Richtung hin schreiben müssen, – II^2^ wäre in doppelt kurzer Zeit
    entstanden.)</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Und nun: Meiner Meinung ^nach^ kam [corr. from kann] es nicht darauf an, daß
    Sie, lieber Hans, „sich selbst nicht mehr gehören“, sondern darauf, daß Sie noch dem Vertrage[6]
     <tei:hi rend="underline">an</tei:hi>gehörten. Obgleich Hochschulen u. sonstige Lehranstalten
    nicht einmal eine vis major[7] gelten lassen <tei:hi rend="underline">(technisch</tei:hi>
    unmöglich), habe ich gerne eine vis major bei Breisach u. Hupka freiwillig respektiert.[8] Doch
    hat in beiden Fällen meine Respectierung erst im Moment der wirklichen Abreise der Betreffenden
    eingesetzt. Das „<tei:hi rend="underline">Vorfeld</tei:hi>“ der vis major aber haben sie selbst
    gar nicht in Anspruch genommen. (Hupka hatte ja nicht nur „Laufereien“, sonder[n] Fahrereien
    (widerholte) nach Pressburg, ließ sich viele Male durch die Schwester im letzten Male Moment
     <tei:pb n="5"/> entschuldigen, kam aber, so lange er nur konnte u. überhaupt da
    war.[9])</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Denken Sie, mit wie viel Recht jeder Mensch aus diesen oder jenen Gründen
    „sich nicht mehr angehört“; müßte ich alle solche Vorfelder respektieren, würde ich schon längst
    zu Grunde gegangen sein. Und das ist ja eben die <tei:hi rend="underline">Wohltat</tei:hi> des
     Lebens<tei:hi rend="underline">zwanges</tei:hi>, daß solche Gesichtspunkte <tei:hi
     rend="underline">nicht</tei:hi> entscheiden. Denn wer geneigt ist, sich nicht mehr
    anzu^ge^hören, wie leicht – <tei:hi rend="underline">will</tei:hi> er auch dann sich nicht mehr
    angehören? Vom ^Nicht-^Wollen gleitet man dann sanft in das Nichtkönnen hinab, u. doch – kann
    man! Es <tei:hi rend="underline">ist auch gut, daß man es kann</tei:hi>! Haben Sie mir je
    angesehen, wie viel Krisen mit obigem Merkmal ich durchgemacht habe?</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In diesem Sinne würde ich, l. Hans, nur gerade die 4 letzten Stunden (vom
    21^ten^ ab) gerne unter den Gesichtspunkt der vis major rücken,[10] da ich aber von vornherein
    weiß, daß Sie nicht zu Ihren Gunsten darauf bestanden hätten, so verfüge ich über den ganzen
    Betrag, als würde er mir ganz gehören u. zw. in dem Eingangs erwähnten Sinne.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich erwarte Sie also morgen, wo ich Ihnen dann auch <tei:pb n="6"/> einen
    hübschen Brief aus Dresden zeigen u. Einiges von Dir. Löwe mitteilen werde.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Mit Dank sende ich Bücher zurück, behalte aber noch Geschriebenes.[11] </tei:p>

   <tei:closer rend="indent-10">
    <tei:salute>Besten herzlichen Gruß</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute>Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">H.
      Sch.</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:date when="1915-06-17">17. VI. 1915</tei:date>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>



  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:add place="inline"><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">top line cut
     off</tei:note><tei:lb/> at my place; since, however, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000655"
      >Mrs. P.</tei:rs> canceled at 5.30, I immediately set to work in my "munitions factory" . . </tei:add><tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
     >Hans</tei:rs>,[1]</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">I thus will expect you tomorrow, Friday, at 11.30 a.m.,[2] but I mention at
    this point that I shall hold on to the small sum still due to me only as long as is necessary to
    take it to the Post Office and there redirect it to the address "Widows and Orphans",[3] of
    which you will find a document in the Neue freie Presse under the box number: Dr. H. Sch, ^not
    full name^. Grillparzer said (in passing): "A woman is always betrayed by her husband" (I would
    love to have heard his reasons), and how much more widely is the saying applicable in my own
    free adaptation: "The 'mother'land is always betrayed by the 'father'land." They, the widows
    left behind by the soldiers, are always called upon to make the greatest sacrifice, for which
    the "father"land (by established custom) never shows any gratitude. (I too, in the course of the
    teaching year, have repeatedly sent contributions for the "Widows" ‒ a lot more, to be sure,
    than our millionaires, in proportion to their wealth.)</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">A few more words are necessary:</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> {2} I am putting them down in writing as candidly as I
    consider it necessary in the interests of higher things. It did not for a moment escape me that
    only at the beginning of the month you (repeatedly) pronounced that you "no longer belonged to
    yourself." I understood what you were hinting at, and if I nevertheless, so to speak, acted
    contrary to that in seeking to bind you evermore to music, then that was because I specifically
    wanted you to know what I have throughout my life denounced as a crime against art. You know
    that I identify as my sole act of heroism the accomplishment of having first of all created the
    possibility ^for^ my works! Already now you ^too^ should view yourself as afflicted by the
    publisher (viz. your piano pieces, your [written] work), but publishers are really not the only
    things that stand in your way.[4] I dare say that under more favorable conditions, I would have
    published not only Counterpoint II, but also already the greater part of my Little Library, my
    Theory of Form, and so on, such that I would have provided thousands, nay millions of musicians
    of all future generations with the foundation for a new, honest possibility for occupation (be
    it in composition, or in teaching, or in historical writing, etc.). (For, more than you know or
    can imagine, this process is already underway!) And you surely ought already to have realized
    that I concentrate all my earnings solely on <tei:pb n="3"/> providing the conditions for my
    work.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I spent many years making my own pupils understand how they should think
    about what they accomplish for their part. The obsession with money from which people suffer
    causes them always to feel monetary recompense as "something extra" (people find it so hard to
    part with their money), and they reluctantly force themselves to do so ^only when^ sectors
    protected by the State leave them no way out (hoteliers, attorneys, dentists, merchants, etc).
    It's only with respect to the artist that the world will never learn to reconcile itself to
    parting with its money.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">However, never in your life would you have encountered me had I ^not also^ ‒
    solely in the interests of the work to be carried out, which surely benefits the pupils
    themselves! ‒ persistently taken advantage of what the commercial sectors have accomplished.[5]
    I would long since have been dead and would have achieved nothing, were it down only to the
    thoughtlessness of my publishers and pupils, who, on the other hand, ‒ what a contradiction! ‒
    nevertheless sought and expected nothing but my best work. <tei:pb n="4"/> I didn't permit
    myself absurd thoughts of "advancement", or related ideas of "advice" or "exchange", etc., and
    sought constantly through clarity to put forward the results of my work, so as to insure that my
    time, my good health and achievements were not supported merely by certain tiny sums of money.
    (Ah! I have had to write many, many letters in this spirit. ‒ Counterpoint II would otherwise
    have seen the light of day in half the time.)</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">And now: in my opinion, it's not a case, dear Hans, of your "no longer
    belonging to yourself," but of your still being a party to the contract.[6] Although colleges
    and other teaching institutions never acknowledge a vis major[7] (that would be technically
    impossible), I have gladly and willingly respected a vis major in the cases of Breisach and
    Hupka. But in both cases my granting of respect did not begin until the moment of their actual
    departure [from my tuition].[8] They did not, however, themselves demand the "preliminary phase"
    of the vis major. (Hupka did not not just "go running about" but undertook long journeys
    (repeatedly) to Pressburg, and <tei:pb n="5"/> excused himself through his sister at the last
    moment; but he did come whenever he could and was actually in town.[9])</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">If you think how justifiably every person for one reason or another "no
    longer belongs to himself"; if I had had to respect all such preliminary phases, I would long
    ago have been ruined. That is precisely the benefit of life's pressure: that such points of view
    are not decisive. How easy it is for anyone who is inclined no longer to belong to himself, then
    also to want no longer to belong to himself? From ^not^-wanting it is then a slippery slope to
    not being able, and yet ‒ one is able! What's more, it is good that one is able! Have you ever
    noticed about me how many crises I have endured in the above manner?</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In this spirit, dear Hans, I would gladly straightway consign just the last
    four lessons (from the 21st on) to the realm of the vis major;[10] but since I knew from the
    start that you would not have insisted on gaining from this arrangement, I shall dispose of the
    entire sum of money as if it belonged entirely to me, namely in the manner mentioned at the
    opening [of this letter].</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I await you tomorrow, when I shall also <tei:pb n="6"/> show you a delightful
    letter from Dresden, and acquaint you with something from Director Löwe.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I return the books with thanks, but am retaining the written
    work.[11]</tei:p>

   <tei:closer rend="indent-10">
    <tei:salute>With best, most cordial greetings,</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute>Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H. Sch.</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:date when="1915-06-17">June 17, 1915</tei:date>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>

 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
