<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="455" sdoID="OJ-5-7a_12">OJ 5/7a, [12] (formerly vC 12)</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
   <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>


  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2011-06-13" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002775">Cube ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated November 9, 1927</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1927-11-09T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-06-22</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker thanks Cube for the pictures enclosed with OJ 9/34, [9] and expresses
    pleasure at Cube's reports of his teaching, composition, listening to the radio, Urlinie
    studies, and advocacy of good editions; refers to Vrieslander's planned monograph on Schenker,
    the prospectus for Meisterwerk I and II, and the call [for the
    Photogrammarchiv].</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000143">Cube</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">von
      Cube</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this
      letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at <!-- XR -->OJ 4/1, p. 3131, November 9, 1927: "An v.
      Cube (Br.): Dank für die Bildchen, allerhand Bemerkungen zu seinen Plänen, kündige den
      Prospekt u. den Aufruf an." ("To von Cube (letter): thanks for the little pictures; sundry
      remarks on his plans; I notify <tei:supplied reason="clarity">him</tei:supplied> of the
      Prospectus and the Appeal").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Da haben Sie uns mit Ihrem Geschenk<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">i.e. <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-34_9">OJ 9/34, [9]</tei:ref>,
     October 29, 1927, with its enclosures, report of Cube's teaching of Schenker's theory, work in
     composition, membership of the Reichsverband Deutscher Tonkünstler und Musiklehrer, and his
     recent contact with John Petrie Dunn.</tei:note> eine große, sehr große Freude bereitet, wir
    danken herzlichst!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Nicht nur unser <tei:term>Zwie-Satz</tei:term>, sondern auch der
     <tei:term>Vierstimmen-Satz</tei:term> das allgemeiner <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">chorus</tei:hi>
    ist <tei:hi rend="lateinschr-underline">unisono</tei:hi> der Meinung, daß Ihr Bildchen die
    besten sind, die <tei:hi rend="underline">je</tei:hi> von uns angefertigt sind, die <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">also</tei:add> nicht ausgenommen, die mit Recht seinerzeit
    als die besten galten. Ihr „Rekord“ greift am höchsten. Ein eigener u. freier künstlerischer
    Wille drängt aus allem hervor, was Sie treiben, u. so auch aus den Bildchen u. Bildern. Vielen
    Dank für diese Erinnerung der <tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs>er
     Tage!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">In <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-34_9">OJ 9/34, [9]</tei:ref>, Cube says he has enclosed "two
     enlargements of portraits I made in Galtür", together with a number of postcards. See the
     explanatory footnote to that statement.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Aber eine fast noch größere Freude bereiten Sie mir mit der Schilderung
    Ihres derzeitiges Standes, der zu besten Hoffnungen berechtigt. Ihre zwei
     <tei:term>Theorieklassen</tei:term>, denen bald eine dritte zuwachsen wird, Ihre
     <tei:term>Urlinie-Anweisungen</tei:term>, Ihre Mühen um gute <tei:term>„Ausgaben“</tei:term>,
    Ihre <tei:term>Sonatenarbeiten</tei:term>, das stille Sich-bilden am Rundfunk (der den Anderen
    ja nur ein Müßiggangsbehelf ist), Alles das gibt das Bild schönsten Strebens, dem der Lohn gewiß
    nicht ausbleiben wird.</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:rs key="entity-002827" type="composition">Sonate II</tei:rs> u. der Vortrag, falls es
    zu einem solchen kommen sollte, erbitte ich zur An- und Einsicht, (womit zugleich die
    Ermächtigung gegeben ist, frei von der gesunden Musikleber weg zu sprechen).<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Cube sent both his piano sonatas to Schenker
     a couple of years later, detailed commentary on them appears in Schenker's letter to Cube
      <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-7a_27">OJ 5/7a, [27]</tei:ref>, August 10,
     1929.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Hauptsache bleibt, die jungen Menschenkinder dazu zu verhalten, endlich mit dem <tei:hi rend="underline">wirklichen Notenlesen einen Anfang zu machen</tei:hi>, d.h. <tei:pb n="3"/>
    sie <tei:hi rend="underline">zumindest zu den <tei:term>„Zügen“</tei:term></tei:hi> zu führen
    (wenn sie der letzthintergründigen Urmutter <tei:term>„Urlinie“</tei:term> nicht zu folgen
    vermögen), als den <tei:hi rend="underline">Trägern eines
     <tei:term>Zusammenhangs</tei:term></tei:hi>, wie er in der Sprache durch Satzbau usw. gegeben
    ist. Daß man erst jetzt, nach mehrhundertjährigem Bestande der Tonkunst, mit dem Lesen anfangen
    muß, ist die Schande der Menschheit, sie wird nur dadurch entschuldigt, daß die
     <tei:term>Tonsprache</tei:term> als <tei:term>„Sprache“</tei:term> eben schwieriger als alle
    anderen Menschen- u. Tiersprachen sind. Daß Sie hiebei aller meiner Verdienste, die ja die
    ersten sind, <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#HS">G</tei:del> „ausdrücklich“ gedanken, kommt
    der Sache nur zugute. <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs> arbeitet
    gegenwärtig, wie er mir sagte, an <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#HS">zu</tei:del> einer
    größeren „<tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Monographie</tei:hi>“ über mich,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Otto Vrieslander's "monograph" is also
     mentioned in Schenker's letter to Cube <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-7a_10">OJ
      5/7a, [10]</tei:ref>, June 1, 1927. It was never published.</tei:note> das bedeutet einen Stoß
    in die Verheimlichungsintrigen unserer Kollegen, <tei:pb n="4"/> die ich übrigens ebenfalls
    entschuldige u. zw. damit, daß sie weder die Musik noch mich verstehen.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Von <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Vriesl.</tei:hi></tei:rs> erhalten Sie demnächst einen von ihm verfaßten „<tei:hi rend="underline">Prospekt</tei:hi>“ zu den <tei:rs key="entity-001750" type="work">Jbüchern
     I</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs key="entity-001751" type="work">II</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der
       Musik</tei:title>; vols. 1 and 2</tei:bibl> came out in 1926 and 1927, a year later than is
     indicated on the title page. The "prospectus" may be similar to an article by Vrieslander
     entitled "Heinrich Schenker", published in the <tei:bibl><tei:title level="j">Deutscher
       Tonkünstler-Zeitung</tei:title> (March 5, 1928)</tei:bibl> "on the occasion of the appearance
     of Yearbook II".</tei:note> u. dazu ein Briefchen, das ich nicht gelesen habe. Solcher
    Briefchen schrieb <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vr.</tei:rs> an 100, an alle
    „Prominenten“ des Reiches, jedem nach seiner Art, u. so hoffe ich, Ihnen ein liebes nach Ihrer
    lieben Art.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ende des Monats erreicht Sie <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hoboken</tei:rs>s
     „Aufruf“<tei:supplied reason="clarity">.</tei:supplied><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">This was a printed appeal to manuscript collectors and libraries,
     the idea being to bring together as many as possible photographic reproductions of autographs
     by major composers, and house them in a special archive at the Austrian National Library in
     Vienna (see <tei:ref type="other" cRef="OJ-9-10_2">OJ 9/10, [2]</tei:ref>). The project was
     financed by Schenker's pupil and patron Anthony van Hoboken, himself a collector of autographs
     and early editions of music.</tei:note>
    <tei:date when="1927-11-11">Freitag</tei:date> halten wir noch eine Kuratoriumstagung ab, u.
    dann geht das Werk los.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Und nun mit herzlichsten Grüßen von mir u. meiner <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Frau</tei:rs> an Sie</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">H
     Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>

    <tei:p rend="hanging">Zu dem Neugeborenen wünschen wir dem Elternpaar viel Glück.</tei:p>

    <tei:p><tei:date when="1927-11-09">9.11.27</tei:date></tei:p>

   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>

  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>My dear Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">von Cube</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Your present brought us great – very great – joy; we offer you our most heartfelt
     thanks.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Not only our strange <tei:term>two-voice counterpoint</tei:term>, but also the
     <tei:term>four-part harmony</tei:term> is of the <tei:hi rend="underline">unanimous</tei:hi>
    opinion that your little pictures are the best that have <tei:hi rend="underline">ever</tei:hi>
    been made of us, <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">i.e.</tei:add> not excluding
    those that were rightly regarded in their own time as the best. Your "record" reaches the
    highest level. An original and free artistic will springs forth from everything that you
    undertake, and thus also from these smaller and larger pictures. Many thanks for this souvenir
    of your time in <tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> But I take almost greater pleasure from the account of your present
    situation, which justifies the highest hopes. Your two <tei:term>theory classes</tei:term>
    (which will soon grow to three), your studies in the <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>, your efforts
    in support of good <tei:term>"editions,"</tei:term> your <tei:term>composition of
     sonatas</tei:term>, your quiet self-education at the radio (an object that, of course, makes it
    easy for others to be lazy): all this gives a picture of the most beautiful striving, which will
    certainly not go unrewarded.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Regarding your <tei:rs key="entity-002827" type="composition">second sonata</tei:rs> and a
    peformance <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of it</tei:supplied>, should that come to pass: please
    let me me have a look at it, so that I can study it closely (whereby I may have the authority to
    speak freely and frankly about them).<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>The main thing remains to get the young children of mankind finally to <tei:hi rend="underline">make a start in reading music correctly</tei:hi>, that is <tei:pb n="3"/> to
    lead them <tei:hi rend="underline">at least to the <tei:term>"linear
     progressions"</tei:term></tei:hi> (even if they are unable to follow the
     <tei:term>"Urlinie"</tei:term> as primeval mother at the very deepest background level), as the
     <tei:hi rend="underline">bearers of a <tei:term>coherence</tei:term></tei:hi> of the sort that
    is granted to speech by means of sentence construction, etc. That only now, after music has been
    in existence for several hundred years, one must begin with the act of reading is the disgrace
    of mankind, which can only be excused by the fact that the <tei:term>language of
     music</tei:term>, as a <tei:term>"language,"</tei:term> is actually more difficult than any
    other human or animal languages. That you intend in this endeavor "expressly" to make use of all
    my accomplishments, which are really the first, can only be of benefit to the cause. <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs>, so he tells me, is currently working on
    a rather large "monograph" about me;<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> that will
    be a blow to the secret intrigues on the part of our colleagues, <tei:pb n="4"/> whom I,
    moreover, likewise excuse, and indeed on the grounds that they understand neither music nor
    me.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>From <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs> you will soon receive
    a "<tei:hi rend="underline">prospectus</tei:hi>" for <tei:rs key="entity-001750" type="work">Yearbooks I</tei:rs> and <tei:rs key="entity-001751" type="work">II</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> together with a short letter that I have not read.
     <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs> writes a hundred such letters,
    to all "prominent people" of the realm, each tailored to the recipient, and so I hope that has
    written a dear one to you, too, tailored to your dear character.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>At the end of the month, <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hoboken</tei:rs>'s
     "appeal"<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> will reach you. On <tei:date when="1927-11-11">Friday</tei:date> we are holding a trustees' conference; then the work will
    get going.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>And now, with most heartfelt greetings from me and my <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs>,</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Yours,</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">H.
     Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>

    <tei:p rend="hanging"><tei:supplied reason="clarity">P.S.</tei:supplied> We wish the parents of
     the newborn child much happiness.</tei:p>

    <tei:p><tei:date when="1927-11-09">November 9, 1927</tei:date></tei:p>

   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>