<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="514" sdoID="OJ-5-7a_38">OJ 5/7a, [38] (formerly vC 38)</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="major">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="minor">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
      <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>


    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2011-10-29" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002775">Cube ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, in Jeanette Schenker's hand, dated June 30, 1931</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1931-06-30T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-11-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker encloses the [Mozart calling] card, and sends an article from Der Kunstwart; he
        emphasizes that Moriz Violin's new institute is a "school," not a "seminar," and offers detailed advice;
        comments that his theory from Harmonielehre to Meisterwerk constitutes a self-contained whole; recommends use of
        C. P. E. Bach's Versuch with his theory applied to the examples; and foretells the Urlinie-Tafeln that should be
        available to Violin/Cub in Hamburg and to Weisse in New York. His eyes have suffered and need complete
        rest.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      
      
    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000143">Cube</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener><tei:handShift new="#JS"/><tei:note type="authorial">diktirt!</tei:note><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter does not appear to be recorded in Schenker's diary. The
          entire letter is written by Jeanette Schenker, apart from the interlinear insertions (and quotation-marks
          around Tonwille) on p.3, and the signature.</tei:note>
        <tei:salute>Lieber Herr Professor <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">v. Cube</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Hier der mehrmals angekündigte Brief. Gleichzeitig geht ein Sonderdruck des <tei:rs key="entity-003014" type="journal"><tei:title>Kunstwart</tei:title></tei:rs>-Aufsatzes an Sie ab.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">This is in all probability a seven-page article by Schenker
          entitled <tei:title level="a">Ein verschollener Brief von Mozart und das Geheimnis seines
            Schaffens,</tei:title> a defense of a purportedly forged letter about Mozart's creative process, which was
          brought to light by Friedrich Rochlitz in 1815. Schenker's article appeared in <tei:bibl><tei:title level="j">Der Kunstwart</tei:title> 44/10 (July 1931), pp. 660–66</tei:bibl>; a copy of this is preserved as
          <!-- XR -->OC 50/12, and a newspaper clipping with a short reply is found in the Schenker Scrapbook
          (<!-- XR -->OC 2/p. 84). Schenker also received two letters (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-50-14">OC
            50/14</tei:ref> and <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-50-15">OC 50/15</tei:ref>), one of them from
          Alfred Einstein, explaining that the musicological world did not accept the letter as genuine.</tei:note> Die
        hier beigelegte Karte ist sozusagen ein Sonderdruck aus dem Sonderdruck u. enthält die stolzeste Aeußerung eines
        Musikgenies über die Musik überhaupt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">"card": Already
          promised by Schenker in <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-7a_36">OJ 5/7a, [36]</tei:ref>, June 6,
          1931. Schenker had already sent one of these to Jonas on April 1, 1931 (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-18-6">OJ 5/18, 6</tei:ref>), remarking in the covering letter: "Enclosed is a calling card of
          Mozart's, which I myself have had produced at the printery. I hardly need tell you how the sight of these
          words, the highest revelation, which came to us from the mouth of genius, made me feel so happy and thankful
          toward God. (More about the origin of the passage in a special essay.)" It is likely that the essay never
          materialized, and there appears to be no copy of the document in OC or OJ. Whether it was a reproduction of an
          original calling card of Mozart's, or a card devised by Schenker using words uttered by Mozart (from the
          wording of this letter, those words may derive from the forged Mozart letter discussed in his <tei:title level="a">Ein verschollener Brief</tei:title>), is unclear.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich weiß nicht wie die Pläne Professor <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs>s reifen, ob seine <tei:rs key="entity-002455" type="organization">Schule</tei:rs> offiziell
        meinen Namen tragen wird, jedenfalls möchte ich den Unterschied hervorheben, der zwischen eine Schule u. einem
        Seminar besteht. Ob Sie in der <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs>-<tei:rs key="entity-002455" type="organization">Schule</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:hi rend="italic">Violin-Schule</tei:hi>: a play on the word for a book of exercises or
          studies for the violin. (Moriz Violin was, in fact, a pianist.)</tei:note> so wie in <tei:rs key="entity-002604" type="place">Köln</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker is referring to Cube's series of lectures and seminars as a visiting teacher at the Hochschule für
          Musik in Cologne in 1929–30.</tei:note> werden verfahren können, möchte ich bezweifeln. Ich denke Sie <tei:pb n="2"/> mir als Lehrer dort gebundener, auch die Schüler. Der Nachteil einer solchen Unterrichtsmethode ist
        der, daß Sie der verschiedentlichen Anregungen einer freien Diskussion entbehren u. Ihre Lösungen mit aller
        Autorität auszuforschen haben. Und da möchte ich Ihnen gegenüber aussprechen, wozu ich – mit Erfolg – <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs> geraten: Sprechen Sie Ihre Meinung ohne Hemmung aus, als Ihr
        derzeit Bestes u. ehrlichst Gegebenes. Es wäre keine Schande, nach Jahren eine bessere Lösung zu finden u.
        einzubekennen. In unserer Sache gibt es nur das eine Prestige: das der Wahrheit. Aus Ihrer <tei:rs key="entity-002621" type="place">Duisburg</tei:rs>er Lehrzeit dürften Sie wohl die Ueberzeugung gewonnen
        haben, daß – freilich bis auf meine letzte methodische Darstellung im <tei:rs key="entity-001728" type="work"><tei:title>freien Satz</tei:title></tei:rs> – der Unterrichtsstoff <tei:pb n="3"/> schon ein geschlossenes
        Ganzes bildet: die <tei:term>Stimmführungs</tei:term>- <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#HS">u.</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">lehre, die</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>
        <tei:term>Harmonielehre</tei:term> im <tei:term>Vordergund</tei:term> u. die Lehre vom
          <tei:term>Hintergrund</tei:term> in den <tei:add hand="#HS" place="inline">„</tei:add><tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work">Tonwille</tei:rs><tei:add hand="#HS" place="inline">“</tei:add>-Heften u. in
        den <tei:rs key="entity-001749" type="work">drei Jahrbüchern</tei:rs>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">"three yearbooks": i.e. <tei:title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der
            Musik</tei:title>. In this extraordinary statement, Schenker likens the early parts of his <tei:title level="m">Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:title>, viz. <tei:title level="m">Harmonielehre</tei:title> and <tei:title level="m">Kontrapunkt</tei:title> – the latter referred to here as
            <tei:title level="m">Stimmführungslehre</tei:title> – to the foreground of his teaching, while the later
          analytical work of the 1920s provides the background, probably because its language is more closely aligned
          with that of the forthcoming <tei:title level="m">Der freie Satz</tei:title>.</tei:note> Ich wäre außerdem
        sehr dafür, daß Sie die Schüler für <tei:rs key="entity-000025" type="person">Em. Bachs</tei:rs>
        <tei:term>Generalbaß</tei:term>lehre<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">This is
            <tei:bibl>Part 2 of Bach's <tei:title level="m">Versuch über die wahre Art das Clavier zu
              spielen</tei:title> (Berlin: Winter, 1763)</tei:bibl>. Schenker owned the <tei:bibl>fifth edition, ed.
            Gustav Schilling (Berlin: Stage, 1856)</tei:bibl> and new edition by <tei:bibl>Walter Niemann (Leipzig:
            Kahnt, 1906)</tei:bibl>: see <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Musik und Theater enthaltend die Bibliothek des
              Herrn Dr. Heinrich Schenker, Wien</tei:title> (Vienna: Heinrich Hinterberger, n.d.), items 8 and
            9</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> interessierten u. sie mit ihnen in der gleichen Weise durchnähmen, in der ich sie
        Ihnen vorgetragen habe, d. h. mit Einbeziehung <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#HS">der</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">unserer</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> Züge in die Beispiele von <tei:rs key="entity-000025" type="person">Bach</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Sollten es im Laufe des nächsten Jahres die Umstände zulassen, so dürften Sie einen Zuwachs an
          <tei:term>Urlinie-Tafeln</tei:term> aus <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> erhalten gemäß
        einer Verabredung mit Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs>; diese Tafeln gingen auch
        nach <tei:rs key="entity-002873" type="place">New York</tei:rs> zu <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs> als Unterrichtsstoff u. bezögen sich auf die <tei:rs key="entity-000129" type="person">Chopin</tei:rs>-Etüden op. 10 N<tei:hi rend="supralinear">o</tei:hi>
        <tei:rs key="entity-001408" type="composition">III</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-001413" type="composition"><tei:choice>
            <tei:sic>IX</tei:sic>
            <tei:corr>VIII</tei:corr>
          </tei:choice></tei:rs> u. <tei:rs key="entity-001402" type="composition">XII</tei:rs> (Edur Fdur, <tei:pb n="4"/> Cmoll), auf die Durchführung in <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person">Haydn</tei:rs>s grosser
          <tei:rs key="entity-001553" type="composition">Sonate in Esdur</tei:rs> (Peters I<tei:hi rend="supralinear">III</tei:hi>), auf <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person">S. Bachs</tei:rs>
        <tei:rs key="entity-001136" type="composition">1. Präludium Cdur</tei:rs> usw. Ich werde Sie noch ganz genau
        darüber informieren, damit Sie nicht schon früher gerade eins von diesem Stücken vorlegen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot">This list bears a close resemblance to the contents of the
              <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln</tei:title>, published by UE simultaneously in Vienna
            and (as <tei:title level="m">Five Analyses in Sketchform</tei:title>) New York in 1932</tei:bibl>: the
            <tei:title>Bach Prelude</tei:title>, the first-movement development of <tei:title>Haydn's Sonata in E flat,
            Hoboken XVI:49</tei:title> (not that of the other "great" <tei:title>E flat sonata, Hoboken
            XVI:52</tei:title>, which had been the subject of a <tei:title level="j">Tonwille</tei:title> essay), and
          two of the <tei:title>Chopin Études</tei:title> mentioned here (Nos. 8 and 12). The fifth work in the set is a
          chorale from <tei:title>Bach's <tei:hi rend="italic">St. Matthew Passion</tei:hi></tei:title>; the other
            <tei:title>Chopin Étude, No. 3 in E major</tei:title>, was intended for a subsequent series of <tei:hi rend="italic">Urlinie-Tafeln</tei:hi> whose publication never materialized. Curiously, Cube ignored his
          teacher's word of caution and proceeded to work out a voice-leading graph of the Bach Prelude – for the second
          time in two years – later in the year. See Cube's letters <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-34_28">OJ
            9/34, [28]</tei:ref>, and <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-34_29">OJ 9/34, [29]</tei:ref>, October
          16 and 20, 1931, and Schenker's reply, <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-7a_40">OJ 5/7a,
            [40]</tei:ref>, undated.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Sie sehen, daß ich die Hilfe meines teueren <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechens</tei:rs> in Anspruch nehme; meine Augen haben über der Arbeit an der <tei:rs key="entity-001263" type="composition"><tei:title>Eroica</tei:title></tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09" type="editorial" place="foot">This long essay on Beethoven's <tei:title><tei:hi rend="italic">Eroica</tei:hi>
            Symphony</tei:title> occupies most of <tei:bibl><tei:title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der
              Musik</tei:title>, vol. 3 (1930)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> so sehr gelitten, daß ich sie jetzt eine Zeitlang
        völlig ruhen lassen will.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Möge Ihnen in <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> ein Erfolg so
        beschieden sein, wie Sie ihn unter den heutigen schwierigen Umständen erwarten dürfen: langsam, aber immer u.
        sicher voran.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-15">Mit den besten Wünschen u. Grüßen von uns Beiden</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-85">Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-45"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Heinrich Schenker</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:signed>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#JS"/><tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs>, den <tei:date when="1931-06-30">30.VI.31</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener><tei:handShift new="#JS"/><tei:note type="authorial">dictated!</tei:note><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
        <tei:salute>Dear Professor <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">von Cube</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Here is the letter I have mentioned several times. At the same time an offprint of the article
        in <tei:rs key="entity-003014" type="journal"><tei:title level="j">Der Kunstwart</tei:title></tei:rs> is being
        sent to you.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> The enclosed card is, so to speak, an offprint from
        the offprint, and contains the proudest statement from a musical genius about music in general.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I do not know how Professor <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs>'s plans
        are shaping up, whether his <tei:rs key="entity-002455" type="organization">school</tei:rs> will officially bear
        my name. In any event I would like to underscore the difference that exists between a school and a seminar. I
        doubt whether you will be able to carry on in the <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs>
        <tei:rs key="entity-002455" type="organization">School</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/>
        as you you were doing in <tei:rs key="entity-002604" type="place">Cologne</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> I imagine that you <tei:pb n="2"/> will be more tied down; so will
        your pupils. The disadvantage of such a method of teaching is that you will have to forego the various
        propositions arising from a free discussion and will have to work out your solutions with all authority. And in
        this connection I should like to tell you the advice that I – successfully – gave to <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs>: Communicate your opinions without constraint, as the best and most honorable
        that you are capable of giving at the time. It would not be a disgrace if, after years had passed, you
        discovered and recognized a better solution. In the cause, there is only one matter of honor: that of the truth.
        From your time as a teacher in <tei:rs key="entity-002621" type="place">Duisburg</tei:rs>, you must have
        certainly gained the conviction that the material for instruction – apart, of course, from my last, methodical
        presentation in <tei:rs key="entity-001728" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Free
          Composition</tei:title></tei:rs> – <tei:pb n="3"/> makes up a self-contained whole: <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">theory of</tei:add>
        <tei:term>voice leading</tei:term> and theory of <tei:term>harmony</tei:term> in the
          <tei:term>foreground</tei:term>, and the theory of the <tei:term>background</tei:term> in the issues of
          <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs> and in the
          <tei:rs key="entity-001749" type="work">three yearbooks</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> In addition, I would strongly recommend that you interest your pupils in <tei:rs key="entity-000025" type="person">Carl Philipp Emanuel Bach</tei:rs>'s treatise on
          <tei:term>thoroughbass</tei:term><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> and that you take them
        through it in the same way in which I conveyed it to you, i.e. by incorporating the features of <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">our</tei:add> theory into <tei:rs key="entity-000025" type="person">Bach</tei:rs>'s examples.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Should the conditions in the course of the next year allow, you may receive an increased
        number of <tei:term>Urlinie graphs</tei:term> from <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>, in
        accordance with a discussion with Professor <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs>. These
        graphs would also go to <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs> in <tei:rs key="entity-002873" type="place">New York</tei:rs>, as teaching material, and would be concerned with <tei:rs key="entity-000129" type="person">Chopin</tei:rs>'s Etudes Op. 10, Nos. <tei:rs key="entity-001408" type="composition">3</tei:rs>,
          <tei:rs key="entity-001413" type="composition"><tei:choice>
            <tei:sic>9</tei:sic>
            <tei:corr>8</tei:corr>
          </tei:choice></tei:rs>, and <tei:rs key="entity-001402" type="composition">12</tei:rs> (in E major, F major,
          <tei:pb n="4"/> and C minor); with the development section in <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person">Haydn</tei:rs>'s great <tei:rs key="entity-001553" type="composition">Sonata in E flat major</tei:rs> (Peters
        Edition, vol. 1, No. 3), with <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person">J. S. Bach</tei:rs>'s <tei:rs key="entity-001136" type="composition">first Prelude in C major</tei:rs>
        <tei:supplied reason="clarity">from the <tei:rs key="entity-002952" type="composition"><tei:title level="m">Well-Tempered Clavier</tei:title></tei:rs></tei:supplied>, etc. I shall give you precise details of this
        in due course, lest you choose one of these very pieces ahead of time.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">As you can see, I am availing myself of the help of my dear <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs>. My eyes have suffered so much from the work on the <tei:rs key="entity-001263" type="composition"><tei:title level="m">Eroica</tei:title></tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09" type="footnote"/> that I want to give them a period of complete rest.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I hope that you are as successful in <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>
        as today's difficult circumstances will allow: slowly, but with steady and secure progress.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-15">With best wishes and greetings from the two of us,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-85">Yours,</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-45"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Heinrich
            Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#JS"/><tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1931-06-30">June 30, 1931</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>