<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="3419" sdoID="OJ-5-38_14">OJ 5/38, [14]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="LR">
   <tei:persName>Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
   <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
   <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008423">SchenkerW ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Heinrich to Wilhelm Schenker, dated December 12,
    1924</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1924-12-12T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-06-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Circumstances have prevented the Schenkers from visiting Wilhelm in the autumn.
    Heinrich suggests to his brother that they visit for a few days at Christmas, or that Wilhelm
    visit them in Vienna.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>
    
    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
    <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000775">Wilhelm Schenker</marcrel:recipient>
    
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Mein lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775"
      >Wilhelm</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this
      letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for December 12, 1924: “An Wilhelm (Br.): erklären uns
      bereit für vier Tage zu kommen; wiederhole unsere Einladung an ihn.” (“To Wilhelm (letter): we
      express our willingness to come for four days; I reiterate our invitation to
      him.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Auf dem Vormerkzettel steht dein Name seit unserer Rückkunft aus <tei:rs type="place"
     key="entity-002334">Tirol</tei:rs>, das schon wie ein Traum weit, weit hinter uns liegt. Aber
    die Ereignisse haben uns derart gebeutelt – eine in dieser Art seltene Erscheinung in unserem
    sonst arbeitsgeruhigem Leben –, daß ich nicht einmal zu einem Brief ausholen konnte! </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Das neue <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000975">Mädchen</tei:rs> aus <tei:rs
     type="place" key="entity-002334">Tirol</tei:rs> gab sehr viel zu schaffen. Nun bewährt sie sich
    aufs Beste. Wir lassen uns aber auch recht viel Geld kosten, Du würdest staunen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Dann mußte ich ständig dem <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408"
     >Verleger</tei:rs> meiner Werke an die Gurgel fahren, denn <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000356">er</tei:rs> machte Miene, die vertraglichen Tantiemen u. Honorare in der
    eigenen Tafeln verschwinden zu machen. Um den entsetzlichen Schädigungen vorzubeugen, habe ich
    mich entschlossen, meine Werke einem <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002627"
     >Verlag</tei:rs> in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002286">München</tei:rs> zu übergeben. Da
    galt es, sich zuvor <tei:pb n="2"/> von dem bisherigen <tei:rs type="organization"
     key="entity-002408">Verlag</tei:rs> loszukoppeln, da ich einen Prozeß vermeiden wollte, der mir
    sicher zwar viel Geld eingetragen, aber viel Zeit geraubt hätte. Ohne Hilfe des Advokaten wollte
    ich den Abschied von Wien, ich meine: vom Wiener Verlag, nicht machen. Das Gelaufe, stundenlange
    Konferenzen, Briefe von beiden Verlagen zu mir, ich zu ihnen u. zum Anwalt. Zu alldem die
    laufende Besorgung meiner <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001749">Vierteljahrschrift</tei:rs> u.
    Stunden, denk’ das nur zusammen!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">For
     a detailed account of the dispute with Universal Edition, see <tei:bibl><tei:author>Heinrich
       Schenker</tei:author>, <tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille: Pamphlets/Quarterly Publication
       …</tei:title>, ed. <tei:editor>William Drabkin</tei:editor>, transl. <tei:editor>Ian
       Bent</tei:editor> and others (New York: Oxford University Press), vol. II (2005), pp.
      v–xii</tei:bibl>.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Und dann noch etwas: ich schlucke eine Fischgräte, sie wandert (ohne sich mir bemerkbar zu
    machen) 1½ Wochen durch den Darm u. bleibt schließlich knapp vor dem Ausgang stecken u. legt
    sich quer. Ein Chirurg mußte eingreifen (keine Operation) u. die Gräte herausnehmen, – ich habe
    geschrien, geweint vor Schmerzen, denn die Gräte, die sich verspießt hat, mußte erst umgedreht
    werden. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich glaube sagen zu können, daß die star- <tei:pb n="3"/> ken Störungen vorüber sind u.
    von nun ab – wir wollen so hoffen – nur der Tag mit seiner Plage sein Recht üben wird. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Wenn Du nicht zu Weihnachten zu <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003354"
    >Grueber</tei:rs>’s fährst, sondern zuhause bleibst, könnten wir dich endlich besuchen u. unser
    Wort mit Vergnügen einlösen. Denn diesmal bildet sich eine Gruppe von 4 Tagen (von Dienstag dem
     <tei:date when="1924-12-25">25.</tei:date> bis Sonntag den <tei:date when="1924-12-28"
     >28.</tei:date>) ganz ungezwungen, so daß wir 3 Tage bei Dir bleiben könnten. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Selbstverständlich geht unser Besuch auf <tei:hi rend="underline">unsere
     Rechnung</tei:hi>, die Zeiten sind heute andere als ehedem. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Wir haben keinerlei Wintersachen, weder ich noch <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
     >LieLiechen</tei:rs> haben einen Pelz, du müsstest also den Wagen mit Pelzen ausrüsten, damit
    wir warm bei Dir einlangen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">“den …
     ausrüsten” (“provide … furs”): underlined, presumably by Wilhelm, and the whole paragraph bracketed by him
     in the left margin.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Solltest du aber zu <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003354">Grueber</tei:rs>’s fahren u.
    also Wien gastieren, so komm doch herauf. Wir können dir zwar kein Bett anbieten, <tei:pb n="4"
    /> wir hatten genug Mühe, 2 Betten auszustatten, da wir in die Wohnung mit leeren Händen
    eingezogen sind –, aber Du sollst <tei:hi rend="underline">ganz vorzüglich bewertet</tei:hi>
    werden, von früh bis Abends, kannst baden, ruhen, schlafen, machen, was dich freut. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Also schreibe uns, was du zu tun gedenkst. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Sollte dir unser Besuch jetzt noch nicht praktisch erscheinen, so werden wir trotzdem
    nicht versäumen, ein andermal zu kommen. Aber, wie gesagt, wir wären schon jetzt bereit. Und
    kommst Du nach Wien, so komme herauf.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot"
     >Heinrich and Jeanette were at home across the Christmas period, and there is no sign of
     Wilhelm having visited them.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Morgen hoffe ich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs> zu
     sehen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker’s diary for December
     13, 1924 records: “Bei Mozio 100 Dollar hinterlegt.“ (“At Mozio's, 100 dollars
     deposited.”).</tei:note></tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute>Nun viele Grüße u. Küsse von uns Beiden</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Deine</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs
      type="person" key="entity-000771">LieLie</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1924-12-12">12. XII 1924</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10">III., Keilgasse 8</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>



  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775"
      >Wilhelm</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Your name has been on our to-do list ever since our return from the <tei:rs type="place"
     key="entity-002334">Tyrol</tei:rs>, which like a dream lies far, far behind us. But the events
    hit us – a seldom occurrence of this type in our otherwise calm life of work – such that I
    couldn’t even manage a letter!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>The new <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000975">maid</tei:rs> from the <tei:rs
     type="place" key="entity-002334">Tyrol</tei:rs> caused a lot of bother. Now, she is proving
    herself splendidly. However, it is costing us quite a lot of money. You would be
    surprised.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">And then I constantly had to go after the throat of the <tei:rs
     type="organization" key="entity-002408">publisher</tei:rs> of my works. <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000356">He</tei:rs> made out as though he was going to make the contractual
    royalties and honoraria disappear into his own pocket. In order to prevent such horrible
    damages, I decided to turn over my works to a <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002627"
     >publisher</tei:rs> in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002286">Munich</tei:rs>. It was
    necessary, then, to disengage beforehand <tei:pb n="2"/> from the previous <tei:rs
     type="organization" key="entity-002408">publisher</tei:rs> because I wanted to avoid a lawsuit,
    which would surely have brought me a lot of money, but would have robbed <tei:supplied
     reason="clarity">me of</tei:supplied> a lot of time. Without the help of the attorney, I did
    not want to take leave of Vienna, I mean take leave of the Viennese publisher. The running
    around, hours-long meetings, letters to me from both publishers, from me to them and to the
    attorney. And on top of all that, the ongoing worry about my <tei:rs type="work"
     key="entity-001749">quarterly journal</tei:rs> and lessons. Just imagine that all
     together!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>And then yet something else: I swallowed a fishbone, it wandered (without making itself
    noticeable to me) for a week and a half through the bowel, and finally got stuck shortly before
    the exit and situated itself sideways. A surgeon had to intervene (no surgery) and extract the
    bone – I screamed, cried from pain because the bone, which had gotten jammed, had first to be
    flipped around.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>I believe I can say that the <tei:pb n="3"/> hefty disturbances are passed, and from now
    on let us hope that only everyday life, with its <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
     >usual</tei:supplied> trouble, will exercise its rights.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>If you are not going to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003354">Grueber</tei:rs>’s for
    Christmas but rather are staying home, we could finally visit you and with pleasure make good on
    our word. This time, a succession of four days comes together completely on its own (from
    Tuesday the <tei:date when="1924-12-25">25th</tei:date> to Sunday the <tei:date
     when="1924-12-28">28th</tei:date>), so that we could stay with you for three days.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Naturally, our visit is <tei:hi rend="underline">at our expense</tei:hi>, the
    times are different today than previously.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>We have no winter things whatsoever. Neither I nor <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000771">LieLiechen</tei:rs> have a fur coat. You would therefore have had to
    provide the car with furs so that we arrive warm at your place.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
     type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>However, should you go to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003354">Grueber</tei:rs>s and
    thus pay a visit to Vienna, do come over. We cannot admittedly offer you a bed – <tei:pb n="4"/>
    we had enough trouble furnishing two beds because we moved into the apartment empty handed. But
    you are to be <tei:hi rend="underline">hosted totally first-rate</tei:hi>, from morning to
    evening, you can bathe, relax, sleep, and do what makes you happy.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>So write us what you intend to do.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Should our visit not yet seem practical to you at the moment, we will nevertheless not
    miss out on coming another time. However, as I said, we are ready even now. And if you come to
    Vienna, come over.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Tomorrow, I hope to see <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/></tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute>Now, abundant greetings and kisses from us both.</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs> and <tei:rs
      type="person" key="entity-000771">LieLie</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1924-12-12">December 12, 1924</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10">Keilgasse 8, Wien III</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>

 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
