<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="2315" sdoID="OJ-5-45_1">OJ 5/45, [1]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="sole">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="ID-WD">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent and William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2019</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-10-28" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Copy letter from Schenker to Weisse, in Jeanette Schenker’s hand, dated June 17,
    1915</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1915-06-17T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-11-04</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>In a six-page letter, and following harsh exchanges the previous day, Schenker
    castigates Weisse for trying to avoid paying for four lessons, speaking of his own difficulties
    in managing the profession of private teacher, and the unfair ways in which artists are treated
    financially.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>



   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000951">Weisse</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:add place="inline"><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">top line cut
     off</tei:note><tei:lb/> bei mir; da aber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000655">Frau
      P.</tei:rs> um ½6<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> abgesagt hat, so begab ich mich sofort
     an die Arbeit in meiner „Munitionsfabrik“ . . </tei:add><tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Mein lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
      >Hans</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this
      letter is recorded in Schenker's diary, p. 955, June 17, 1915: "Brief an Weisse, worin ich
      meinen Standpunkt bezüglich des in Anspruch genommenen Honorars so umfassend als möglich
      darlege. Der Brief wird copiert u. samt Büchern durch einen Dienstmann an ihn befördert."
      ("Letter to Weisse in which I expound as comprehensively as possible my viewpoint regarding
      the fee demanded. The letter is copied and dispatched together with books via a porter.").
      <tei:lb/>What preceded and impelled this letter is an event on the previous day that is
       recorded in Schenker's diary at pp. 953‒54, June 16, 1915: <tei:lb/><tei:lb/>"Um 12<tei:hi
       rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi>, also nach der Stunde des <tei:rs type="person"
       key="entity-000201">Frl. Elias</tei:rs>, erscheint Weisse. Indignirt über die wohlüberlegte
      Schmutzerei lasse ich mich von ihm zu Tisch zum „roten Hahn“ begleiten u. hole, um die Strafe
      zu steigern, in Gegenwart <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs>s sehr
      scharf aus, indem ich direkt einen Verdacht wider Breisach ausspreche u. an diesem Beispiel
      meine Entrüstung über solchen Verrat ausdrücke. W.<tei:hi rend="supralinear">s</tei:hi>
      Verlegenheit war mir Beweis genug dafür, daß ich ins Schwarze getroffen habe. Sein Vorgehen
      war umso strafbarer, als nur 4 Stunden ihm verloren gegangen wären, ein Verlust, den ich wohl
      im Laufe der Jahre durch Ueberstunden u. durch allerhand Stunden im Monat September reichlich
      „vorgegeben“ habe." <tei:lb/><tei:lb/>("At 12 o'clock, hence after <tei:rs type="person"
       key="entity-000201">Miss Elias</tei:rs>'s lesson, Weisse turns up. I ‒ indignant at his
      devious scheming ‒ allow myself to be accompanied by him to lunch at the "Red Cockerel," and,
      in order to heighten the punishment, strike out very sharply in the presence of <tei:rs
       type="person" key="entity-000771">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs>, in the course of which I voice a
      suspicion directly against Breisach, and to this example express my anger at such betrayal.
      Weisse's embarrassment was sufficient evidence for me that I had hit the mark. His reaction
      was all the more reprehensible as only four lessons had been lost to him, a loss that I had
      generously "pre-given" by working overtime and through all manner of lessons [expended on him]
      in the month of September.") </tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">So erwarte ich Sie also morgen Freitag gegen ½12<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
     >h</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The meeting is recorded
     in Schenker's diary at p. 957, June 18, 1915: "Wie aufgefordert erscheint Weisse um ½12<tei:hi
      rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> aufgeregt u. blaß, erlegt das Honorar, bittet mich aber, das
     Geld nicht an die Wittwen u. Waisen zu schicken, da er dies als ein Zeichen ansehen mußte, daß
     ich seiner Beteuerung, der Sache läge blos eine Vergesslichkeit zugrunde, keinen Glauben
     beimessen würde. Hierauf begleitet er uns Beide zu Tisch." ("As requested, Weisse appears at
     11.30 a.m. pale and agitated, pays the fee, but asks me not to send the money to the Widows and
     Orphans, since he would have to take this as a sign that I would give no credence to his
     protestation that the matter was due to a mere moment of forgetfulness. Whereupon he
     accompanied us both to lunch.").</tei:note> schicke aber hier gleich voraus, daß ich den
    kleinen Betrag, die mir noch zukommen soll, nur so lange in meiner Hand behalte, als es nötig
    ist, ihn auf die Post zu bringen u. dort an die Adresse der „<tei:hi rend="underline">Wittwen u.
     Waisen</tei:hi>“ umzudirigiern,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"
     >Schenker's diary accounts for the envelope so "redirected" at p. 954, June 16, 1915: "Abends
     finde ich zuhause einen Brief Weisse’s, worin er, von der gestrigen Auseinandersetzung offenbar
     getroffen, mich um ein Wiedersehen bittet, um mir das angebliche vergessene Couvert zu
     überreichen." ("That evening I find a letter from Weisse at my apartment in which he, evidently
     stricken by yesterday's quarrel, asks to see me again to hand over the alleged forgotten
     envelope.") For the "quarrel," see footnote 1. — Several charitable bodies supporting widows
     and orphans existed at this time in Austria, Hungary, Galicia, and Germany.</tei:note> wovon
    Sie einen Beleg in der „<tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002559"><tei:title><tei:hi
       rend="underline">N. Fr. Presse</tei:hi></tei:title></tei:rs>“ unter der <tei:hi
     rend="underline">Chiffre</tei:hi>: <tei:hi rend="underline">Dr. H. Sch</tei:hi>
    <tei:add place="interlinear-above"><tei:hi rend="underline">nicht</tei:hi> voller
     Namen</tei:add> finden werden. Grillparzer sagte (beiläufig): „Immer wird das Weib vom Manne
    betrogen“ (gerne hätte ich seine Begründung gehört), in wie viel höherem Maße gilt der Spruch in
    eigener freier Uebertragung: „Immer wird das „<tei:hi rend="underline">Mutter</tei:hi>“land vom
    „Vater“land betrogen“. Sie, die Wittwen nach den Kriegern, sind immer dazu bestimmt, das
    stärkste Opfer zu bringen, das ihnen das „Vater“land (nach gemachtem Gebrauch) niemals dankt.
    (Auch im Laufe der Saison habe ich wiederholt für die „<tei:hi rend="underline"
    >Wittwen</tei:hi>“ Beiträge eingesendet, sicher mehr, als unsere Millionäre an ihrem Geldbestand
    gemessen).</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Doch sind noch einige Worte nötig:</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> Ich schreibe sie so freimütig nieder, als ich es im höheren
    Interesse für notwendig erachte. Mir ist durchaus nicht entgangen, daß Sie nur zu Beginn des
    Monats (wiederholt) erklärt haben, Sie „<tei:hi rend="underline">gehörten sich selbst nicht
     mehr</tei:hi>.“ Ich habe den Wink verstanden, u. wenn ich dennoch gleichsam zuwiderhandelte,
    indem ich Sie noch immer an die Musik zu binden suchte, so geschah es, weil ich <tei:hi
     rend="underline">gerade</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="double-underline">Sie</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">frei</tei:hi> wissen wollte davon, was ich zeitlebens als ein
    Verbrechen an der Kunst bezeichne<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">.</tei:supplied> Sie wissen,
    daß ich als den einzigen Heroismus meinerseits die Leistung bezeichne, <tei:add
     place="interlinear-above">für</tei:add> meine Arbeiten überhaupt erst die <tei:hi
     rend="underline">Möglichkeit</tei:hi> geschaffen zu haben! Schon heute dürften <tei:add
     place="interlinear-above">auch</tei:add> Sie sich als vom <tei:rs type="organization"
     key="entity-002408">Verleger</tei:rs> betroffen betrachten (s. Ihre Klavierstücke, Ihre
    Arbeit), aber die Verleger sind es wahrlich <tei:hi rend="underline">nicht allein</tei:hi>, die
    im Wege stehen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Despite Schenker's
     having made representation several times to Emil Hertzka of Universal Edition on behalf of
     Weisse's compositions (e.g. WSLB 116, June 2, 1912, "It only remains for me to congratulate you
     on acquiring Weisse's very, very fine works; they will surely [...] bring you commercial
     success," after which Weisse was interviewed and manuscripts were provided), nothing seems to
     have come of them other than the publication in 1924 of the score of Weisse's <tei:title>Vocal
      Quartets with piano accompaniment, Op. 6</tei:title>.</tei:note> Ich kann sagen, daß ich unter
    günstigeren Bedingunen nicht nur <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001727"><tei:title>II<tei:hi
       rend="supralinear">2</tei:hi></tei:title></tei:rs>, sondern auch schon den wichtigsten Teil
    der „<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001758"><tei:title>kl. Bibl.</tei:title></tei:rs>“, die
     „<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001756"><tei:title>Formenlehre</tei:title></tei:rs>“ etc.
    herausgebracht <tei:del rend="overstrike">hätte</tei:del> u. damit Tausenden, u. Millionen von
    Musikern aller späteren Zeiten eine neue, rechtschaffene Betätigungs<tei:hi rend="underline"
     >möglichkeit</tei:hi> (sei es in der <tei:hi rend="underline">Komposition</tei:hi>, oder im
     <tei:hi rend="underline">Unterricht</tei:hi>, in <tei:hi rend="underline"
     >Geschichtsschreiben</tei:hi> etc.) begründet hätte. (Denn <tei:hi rend="underline">mehr als
     Sie wissen</tei:hi> u. ahnen ist diese Entwicklung <tei:hi rend="underline">schon</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">im Zuge</tei:hi>!) Und daß ich allen Erwerb lediglich auf <tei:pb n="3"
    /> die Arbeits<tei:hi rend="underline">bedingung</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">konzentriere</tei:hi>, dürften Sie wohl auch schon herausgefunden
    haben.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Viele Jahre verbrachte ich damit, den eigenen Schülern begreiflich zu machen,
    wie sie über ihre Gegenleistung zu denken haben. Der Geldwahn, an dem die Menschen leiden,
    bringt es mit sich, daß sie die Gegenleistung an Geld immer als ein „Mehr“ empfinden (man trennt
    sich so schwer vom Gelde.), und <tei:del rend="overstrike">nur</tei:del> widerwillig ringen sie
    sich jene <tei:add place="interlinear-above">nur dort</tei:add> ab, wo durch den Staat
    geschützte Kategorien keinen Ausweg lassen (Hoteliers, Advokaten, Zahnärzte, Kaufleute etc.).
    Dem Künstler allein gegenüber will die Welt noch immer nicht lernen, die Loslösung vom
     Geld<tei:del rend="overstrike">e</tei:del> zu verwinden.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Niemals aber hätten Sie mich je auf Ihrem Lebenswege angetroffen wenn
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">nicht auch</tei:add> ich – lediglich im Interesse der zu
    verrichtenden Arbeit, die ja den <tei:hi rend="underline">Schülern</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">selbst</tei:hi> zu<tei:add place="interlinear-above"
    >gute</tei:add>kommt! – <tei:del rend="overstrike">nicht auch</tei:del> dringend für mich in
    Anspruch genommen hätte, was die wirtschaftlichen Kategorien durchgesetzt haben.<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Over the course of his life Schenker
     delivered many diatribes against the world of commerce, which gives this extraordinary
     statement an added significance.</tei:note> Ich wäre längst tot, u. nichts hätte ich
    vollbracht, wenn es blos auf die Gedankenlosigkeit der Verleger u. Schüler angekommen wäre, die
    anderseits – welcher Widerspruch! – doch wieder nur das Beste bei mir suchten u. auch <tei:pb
     n="4"/> erwarteten. Ich duldete nicht absurde Gedanken der „Förderung“, oder verwandte Ideen
    des „Raths“, „Austausches“, etc., u. suchte allezeit, schon um durch Klarheit auch die <tei:hi
     rend="underline">Resultate</tei:hi> der <tei:hi rend="underline">Arbeit</tei:hi> zu fördern,
    darauf hinzuwirken, daß meine Zeit, mein Gesundheit u. Leistung nicht zu Gunsten bestimmter
    kleiner Summen unterschätzt werden. (Ach, ich habe sehr, sehr viel Briefe nach dieser Richtung
    hin schreiben müssen, – <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001727"><tei:title>II<tei:hi
       rend="supralinear">2</tei:hi></tei:title></tei:rs> wäre in doppelt kurzer Zeit
    entstanden.)</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Und nun: Meiner Meinung <tei:add place="interlinear-above">nach</tei:add>
    <tei:choice>
     <tei:sic>kam</tei:sic>
     <tei:corr>kann</tei:corr>
    </tei:choice> es nicht darauf an, daß Sie, lieber Hans, „sich selbst nicht mehr gehören“,
    sondern darauf, daß Sie noch dem Vertrage<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial"
     place="foot"><tei:hi rend="italic">Vertrag</tei:hi>: Schenker probably refers not to a
     publisher's contract but to one that Weisse has with Schenker, as agreed at the beginning of
     the teaching year.</tei:note>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">an</tei:hi>gehörten. Obgleich Hochschulen u. sonstige Lehranstalten
    nicht einmal eine vis major<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:hi
      rend="italic">vis major</tei:hi>: "superior force" (in legal cases, "act of God").</tei:note>
    gelten lassen <tei:hi rend="underline">(technisch</tei:hi> unmöglich), habe ich gerne eine vis
    major bei <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000098">Breisach</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000399">Hupka</tei:rs> freiwillig respektiert.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08"
     type="editorial" place="foot">When Schenker took him over as a pupil in 1912, Felix Hupka had
     already begun his career as a concert pianist two years earlier. Paul Breisach, who had begun
     lessons with Schenker in the fall of 1913, had been studying with Bruno Walter and Franz
     Schreker since 1914; but whether his career had taken off by the time of this letter is
     unclear.</tei:note> Doch hat in beiden Fällen meine Respectierung erst im Moment der wirklichen
    Abreise der Betreffenden eingesetzt. Das „<tei:hi rend="underline">Vorfeld</tei:hi>“ der vis
    major aber haben sie selbst gar nicht in Anspruch genommen. (<tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000399">Hupka</tei:rs> hatte ja nicht nur „Laufereien“, sonder<tei:supplied
     reason="omission">n</tei:supplied> Fahrereien (widerholte) nach <tei:rs type="place"
     key="entity-004095">Pressburg</tei:rs>, ließ sich viele Male durch die Schwester im letzten
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">Male</tei:del> Moment <tei:pb n="5"/> entschuldigen, kam aber, so
    lange er nur konnte u. überhaupt da war.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09" type="editorial"
     place="foot">"excuse himself": i.e. from a scheduled lesson with Schenker. This remark is
     likely to have caused concern in Weisse, who on June 1, 1912 had appealed to Schenker not to
     favor Hupka to the detriment of himself (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-15-16_4">OJ
      15/16, [4]</tei:ref>). The implication of the final remark is that Weisse was not "generally
     around," earlier because he spent time in Bad Ischl, but now because he had been drafted into
     the army and was on war service.</tei:note>)</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Denken Sie, mit wie viel Recht jeder Mensch aus diesen oder jenen Gründen
    „sich nicht mehr angehört“; müßte ich alle solche Vorfelder respektieren, würde ich schon längst
    zu Grunde gegangen sein. Und das ist ja eben die <tei:hi rend="underline">Wohltat</tei:hi> des
     Lebens<tei:hi rend="underline">zwanges</tei:hi>, daß solche Gesichtspunkte <tei:hi
     rend="underline">nicht</tei:hi> entscheiden. Denn wer geneigt ist, sich nicht mehr anzu<tei:add
     place="interlinear-above">ge</tei:add>hören, wie leicht – <tei:hi rend="underline"
     >will</tei:hi> er auch dann sich nicht mehr angehören? Vom <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
     >Nicht-</tei:add>Wollen gleitet man dann sanft in das Nichtkönnen hinab, u. doch – kann man! Es
     <tei:hi rend="underline">ist auch gut, daß man es kann</tei:hi>! Haben Sie mir je angesehen,
    wie viel Krisen mit obigem Merkmal ich durchgemacht habe?</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In diesem Sinne würde ich, l. Hans, nur gerade die 4 letzten Stunden (vom
     21<tei:hi rend="supralinear">ten</tei:hi> ab) gerne unter den Gesichtspunkt der vis major
     rücken,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10" type="editorial" place="foot">"from the 21st on": either
     past lessons after May 21, or future lessons from June 21 (Heinrich and Jeanette left for
     vacation that year at the end of the month). — Schenker's 1914/15 lessonbook is very thinly
     recorded; it records no lessons for Weisse that year after April 7, 1915 ‒ but that is of no
     consequence since no lessons are recorded for any student at all after that date.</tei:note> da
    ich aber von vornherein weiß, daß Sie nicht zu Ihren Gunsten darauf bestanden hätten, so verfüge
    ich über den ganzen Betrag, als würde er mir ganz gehören u. zw. in dem Eingangs erwähnten
    Sinne.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich erwarte Sie also morgen, wo ich Ihnen dann auch <tei:pb n="6"/> einen
    hübschen Brief aus <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004005">Dresden</tei:rs> zeigen u. Einiges
    von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000542">Dir. Löwe</tei:rs> mitteilen werde.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Mit Dank sende ich Bücher zurück, behalte aber noch Geschriebenes.<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn11" type="editorial" place="foot">Perhaps this refers to a draft of Weisse's
     doctoral dissertation, <tei:title level="m">Der Kunstwaltzer und seine bedeutendsten
      Vertreter</tei:title>, much of which had been drafted before military service, and which was
     completed in 1915 though not submitted to his official adviser Guido Adler until after military
     service, and doctorate being awarded in 1919. The earlier reference to Weisse's "Werke," too,
     probably refers to material not in musical notation.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:closer rend="indent-10">
    <tei:salute>Besten herzlichen Gruß</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute>Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">H.
     Sch.</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
    <tei:date when="1915-06-17">17. VI. 1915</tei:date>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>



  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:add place="inline"><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">top line cut
     off</tei:note><tei:lb/> at my place; since, however, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000655"
      >Mrs. P.</tei:rs> canceled at 5.30, I immediately set to work in my "munitions factory" . . </tei:add><tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
      >Hans</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">I thus will expect you tomorrow, Friday, at 11.30 a.m.,<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> but I mention at this point that I shall hold on to the
    small sum still due to me only as long as is necessary to take it to the Post Office and there
    redirect it to the address "<tei:hi rend="underline">Widows and Orphans</tei:hi>",<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> of which you will find a document in the <tei:rs
     type="journal" key="entity-002559"><tei:title level="j">Neue freie Presse</tei:title></tei:rs>
    under the <tei:hi rend="underline">box number</tei:hi>: <tei:hi rend="underline">Dr. H.
     Sch</tei:hi>, <tei:add place="interlinear-above"><tei:hi rend="underline">not</tei:hi> full
     name</tei:add>. Grillparzer said (in passing): "A woman is always betrayed by her husband" (I
    would love to have heard his reasons), and how much more widely is the saying applicable in my
    own free adaptation: "The '<tei:hi rend="underline">mother</tei:hi>'land is always betrayed by
    the 'father'land." They, the widows left behind by the soldiers, are always called upon to make
    the greatest sacrifice, for which the "father"land (by established custom) never shows any
    gratitude. (I too, in the course of the teaching year, have repeatedly sent contributions for
    the "<tei:hi rend="underline">Widows</tei:hi>" ‒ a lot more, to be sure, than our millionaires,
    in proportion to their wealth.)</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">A few more words are necessary:</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> I am putting them down in writing as candidly as I consider
    it necessary in the interests of higher things. It did not for a moment escape me that only at
    the beginning of the month you (repeatedly) pronounced that you "<tei:hi rend="underline">no
     longer belonged to yourself</tei:hi>." I understood what you were hinting at, and if I
    nevertheless, so to speak, acted contrary to that in seeking to bind you evermore to music, then
    that was because I <tei:hi rend="underline">specifically</tei:hi> wanted <tei:hi
     rend="double-underline">you</tei:hi> to know what I have throughout my life denounced as a
    crime against art. You know that I identify as my sole act of heroism the accomplishment of
    having first of all created the <tei:hi rend="underline">possibility</tei:hi>
    <tei:add place="interlinear-above">for</tei:add> my works! Already now you <tei:add
     place="interlinear-above">too</tei:add> should view yourself as afflicted by the <tei:rs
     type="organization" key="entity-002408">publisher</tei:rs> (viz. your piano pieces, your
     <tei:supplied reason="clarity">written</tei:supplied> work), but publishers are really <tei:hi
     rend="underline">not the only things</tei:hi> that stand in your way.<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> I dare say that under more favorable conditions, I
    would have published not only <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001727"><tei:title level="m"
      >Counterpoint II</tei:title></tei:rs>, but also already the greater part of my <tei:rs
     type="work" key="entity-001758"><tei:title level="m">Little Library</tei:title></tei:rs>, my
     <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001756"><tei:title level="m">Theory of
     Form</tei:title></tei:rs>, and so on, such that I would have provided thousands, nay millions
    of musicians of all future generations with the foundation for a new, honest <tei:hi
     rend="underline">possibility</tei:hi> for occupation (be it in <tei:hi rend="underline"
     >composition</tei:hi>, or in <tei:hi rend="underline">teaching</tei:hi>, or in <tei:hi
     rend="underline">historical writing</tei:hi>, etc.). (For, <tei:hi rend="underline">more than
     you know</tei:hi> or can imagine, this process is <tei:hi rend="underline">already
     underway</tei:hi>!) And you surely ought already to have realized that I <tei:hi
     rend="underline">concentrate</tei:hi> all my earnings solely on <tei:pb n="3"/> providing the
     <tei:hi rend="underline">conditions</tei:hi> for my work.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I spent many years making my own pupils understand how they should think
    about what they accomplish for their part. The obsession with money from which people suffer
    causes them always to feel monetary recompense as "something extra" (people find it so hard to
    part with their money), and they reluctantly force themselves to do so <tei:add
     place="interlinear-above">only when</tei:add> sectors protected by the State leave them no way
    out (hoteliers, attorneys, dentists, merchants, etc). It's only with respect to the artist that
    the world will never learn to reconcile itself to parting with its money.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">However, never in your life would you have encountered me had I <tei:add
     place="interlinear-above">not also</tei:add> ‒ solely in the interests of the work to be
    carried out, which surely benefits the <tei:hi rend="underline">pupils themselves</tei:hi>! ‒
    persistently taken advantage of what the commercial sectors have accomplished.<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> I would long since have been dead and would have
    achieved nothing, were it down only to the thoughtlessness of my publishers and pupils, who, on
    the other hand, ‒ what a contradiction! ‒ nevertheless sought and expected nothing but my best
    work. <tei:pb n="4"/> I didn't permit myself absurd thoughts of "advancement", or related ideas
    of "advice" or "exchange", etc., and sought constantly through clarity to put forward the
     <tei:hi rend="underline">results</tei:hi> of my <tei:hi rend="underline">work</tei:hi>, so as
    to insure that my time, my good health and achievements were not supported merely by certain
    tiny sums of money. (Ah! I have had to write many, many letters in this spirit. ‒ <tei:rs
     type="work" key="entity-001727"><tei:title level="m">Counterpoint II</tei:title></tei:rs> would
    otherwise have seen the light of day in half the time.)</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">And now: in my opinion, it's not a case, dear Hans, of your "no longer
    belonging to yourself," but of your still being a party to the contract.<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> Although colleges and other teaching institutions never
    acknowledge a <tei:hi rend="italic">vis major</tei:hi><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07"
     type="footnote"/> (that would be <tei:hi rend="underline">technically</tei:hi> impossible), I
    have gladly and willingly respected a <tei:hi rend="italic">vis major</tei:hi> in the cases of
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000098">Breisach</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000399">Hupka</tei:rs>. But in both cases my granting of respect did not begin
    until the moment of their actual departure <tei:supplied reason="clarity">from my
     tuition</tei:supplied>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/> They did not, however,
    themselves demand the "<tei:hi rend="underline">preliminary phase</tei:hi>" of the <tei:hi
     rend="italic">vis major</tei:hi>. (<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000399">Hupka</tei:rs> did
    not not just "go running about" but undertook long journeys (repeatedly) to <tei:rs type="place"
     key="entity-004095">Pressburg</tei:rs>, and <tei:pb n="5"/> excused himself through his sister
    at the last moment; but he did come whenever he could and was actually in town.<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn09" type="footnote"/>)</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">If you think how justifiably every person for one reason or another "no
    longer belongs to himself"; if I had had to respect all such preliminary phases, I would long
    ago have been ruined. That is precisely the <tei:hi rend="underline">benefit</tei:hi> of life's
     <tei:hi rend="underline">pressure</tei:hi>: that such points of view are not decisive. How easy
    it is for anyone who is inclined no longer to belong to himself, then also to <tei:hi
     rend="underline">want</tei:hi> no longer to belong to himself? From <tei:add
     place="interlinear-above">not-</tei:add>wanting it is then a slippery slope to not being able,
    and yet ‒ one is able! What's more, it <tei:hi rend="underline">is good that one is
     able</tei:hi>! Have you ever noticed about me how many crises I have endured in the above
    manner?</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In this spirit, dear Hans, I would gladly straightway consign just the last
    four lessons (from the 21st on) to the realm of the <tei:hi rend="italic">vis
     major</tei:hi>;<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn10" type="footnote"/> but since I knew from the start
    that you would not have insisted on gaining from this arrangement, I shall dispose of the entire
    sum of money as if it belonged entirely to me, namely in the manner mentioned at the opening
     <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of this letter</tei:supplied>.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I await you tomorrow, when I shall also <tei:pb n="6"/> show you a delightful
    letter from <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004005">Dresden</tei:rs>, and acquaint you with
    something from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000542">Director Löwe</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I return the books with thanks, but am retaining the written work.<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn11" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:closer rend="indent-10">
    <tei:salute>With best, most cordial greetings,</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute>Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H. Sch.</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
    <tei:date when="1915-06-17">June 17, 1915</tei:date>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>

 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
