<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3444" sdoID="OJ-5-38_30">OJ 5/38, [30]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="LR">
      <tei:persName>Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008423">SchenkerW ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Heinrich to Wilhelm Schenker, dated July 24, 1927</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1927-07-24T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-07-10</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Heinrich reports his reaction to the recent events in Vienna [the July Revolt]
        and transmits some news from Galtür, including the resumption of work on Der freie
        Satz.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>
      
      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000775">Wilhelm Schenker</marcrel:recipient>
      
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Mein lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775"
            >Wilhelm</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for July 24, 1927: “An Wilhelm (Br.): über
            die Wiener Ereignisse u. a. m.”) (“To Wilhelm (letter): about the events in Vienna, and
            much else”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Auch diese schweren Tage sind nun vorüber. Mit <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002304"
          >Innsbruck</tei:rs> hatten wir zwar Verbindung, sogar Extraausgaben sind uns durch die
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>er Auto-chauffeure gebracht
        worden, aber wir konnten aus dem Wirrwarr nicht recht klug werden. Erst als Bahn u. Post
        wieder losgingen u. unsere Zeitungen kamen, wußten wir, die Bedeutung der Ereignisse
          abzuschätzen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The July Revolt
          of 1927, in which the Palace of Justice in Vienna was attacked following the acquittal of
          three members of a right-wing paramilitary organization for killings that had taken place
          in January of that year.</tei:note> An Allem trägt Schuld die Würdelosigkeit, der Unstolz,
        der Mangel an jeglichem Nationalgefühl bei dem Wiener. Er reißt das Maul auf vor jedem
        Engländer, Amerikaner, Franzosen, Polen, Serben usw, als wäre er aus einem mongolischen
          <tei:pb n="2"/> oder afrikanischen Dorf, u. darnach wird er behandelt. Man reißt ihm Land,
        Industrie, Geld aus der Hand, er wehrt sich nicht einmal in Worten. Dazu noch unsere Sozi’s,
        die <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">auf</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">an</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> einer Leiche von einem Staat ihre Eseleien ausprobieren. Und alle sogenannten
        Gebildeten schließen sich den Sozi’s an, statt sie aufs Messer zu bekämpfen. Nun, Wien hat
        für immer ausgespielt! Wie gern würde ich heute diese tote Stadt verlassen, aber wohin
        sollte ich, da ich doch noch abhängig bin von der Welt? Doch genug davon. Mehr mündlich. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Das Wetter hier war all die Zeit her eigentlich schlecht. Heute ist es endlich schön
        geworden u. schon hat uns am <tei:hi rend="underline">Vor</tei:hi>mittag die <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>er Musikkapelle (erst 2 Jahre alt) u. am
          <tei:hi rend="underline">Nach</tei:hi>mittag die Kapelle aus dem benachbarten Dorf <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002339">Ischgl</tei:rs> „erfreut“. Bauernkonkurrenz, die auf das
        Geld der Gäste losgeht: <tei:pb n="3"/> da die <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292"
          >Galtür</tei:rs>er schon früh wußten, daß die <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002339"
          >Ischgl</tei:rs>er Nachmittag kommen, habe sie gleich nach dem Hochamt sich vor unserem
        Hotel produziert u. den Rasen von Schillingen abgeschöpft. Jetzt sind die <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002339">Ischgl</tei:rs>er eingerückt, u. mögen schauen, wie sie
        auf ihre Rechnung kommen . . . . Ach, die guten Leute blasen, trinken, hetzen u. haben keine
        Ahnung, wie es um uns heute steht . . . </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Hier sind auch mehrere große Radio-Apparate da, sie leiten aber, wie wir hören, in der
        Nacht besser, als bei Tag. Die starke Sonne hier soll bei Tag einer guten Vermittlung
        hinderlich sein. Ist das bei dir auch so? </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Soeben habe ich auch nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004104">Reichraming</tei:rs>
        geschrieben u. mich nach <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs>’s Befinden
        erkündigt. Was mag ihm denn fehlen? Du hast ihn ja untersucht. Fehlt ihm <tei:pb n="4"/>
        etwas Organisches? Oder kränkt er sich, weil ihm Amt u. Beschäftigung fehlen? (Das scheint
        mir eher zuzutreffen.) </tei:p>

      <tei:p>In Bälde schließen wir unsere Korrekturen eines neuen Buches ab,<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">The <tei:rs type="work"
            key="entity-001751">second <tei:title level="j">Meisterwerk</tei:title>
            yearbook</tei:rs>, which bears a date of 1926 but was published only in October
          1927.</tei:note> das im September erscheinen wird, arbeiten aber zugleich an einem neuen
        großen, sehr großen Werk.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Schenker’s diary entries for the summer of 1927 record work on <tei:rs type="work"
            key="entity-001728"><tei:title level="m">Der freie
        Satz</tei:title></tei:rs>.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wir freuen uns schon sehr dich bei dir zu sehen. Vorläufig haben wir hier noch einige
        Besuche zu bestehen (hoffentlich kommen sie zustande u. die Sozi’s spucken nicht wieder
        ’rein). Lasse uns bald hören, wie es bei dir ausschaut. Hast du Nachricht von der l. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000319">Sophie</tei:rs>? </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">LieLiechen</tei:rs> u. ich grüßen u.
          küssen dich herzlichst</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">dein</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
          >Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:date when="1927-07-24">24. 7.
          27</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775"
            >Wilhelm</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>These difficult days, too, are now past. We did have contact with <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002304">Innsbruck</tei:rs>. Even extra editions were brought to us by <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs> chauffeurs. But amid the confusion we
        couldn’t figure anything out. Only when the railroad and postal services were restored and
        our newspapers arrived were we able to gauge the significance of the events.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> The lack of dignity bears the blame for it all,
        the lack of pride, the lack of all sense of national identity in the Viennese citizen. He
        opens his mouth wide for every Englishman, American, Frenchman, Pole, Serb, etc., as though
        he were from a Mongolian <tei:pb n="2"/> or African village, and is treated accordingly.
        Territory, industry, money are ripped out of his hand, he doesn’t even defend himself in
        words. Additionally yet, our Soci’s <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">Social
          Democrats</tei:note>, who try out their jack-ass conduct on a corpse of a nation. And all
        so-called educated classes join in with the Soci’s instead of doing battle over the knife.
        Now, Vienna has played out its hand for all time! How gladly I would leave this defunct city
        today. However, since I am still dependent on the world, where should I go? But enough of
        that. More in person.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>The weather here has actually been bad the whole time. Today, it finally turned nice.
        In the <tei:hi rend="underline">fore</tei:hi>noon, the <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs> band (just two years old) and in the <tei:hi
          rend="underline">after</tei:hi>noon the band from the neighboring village <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002339">Ischgl</tei:rs> “delighted” us. A competition among
        farmers that goes after the guests’ money: <tei:pb n="3"/> since the <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs> musicians knew early that the <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002339">Ischgl</tei:rs>er were coming in the afternoon, they played in front
        of our hotel immediately after Mass and skimmed all the shillings from the lawn. Now the
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002339">Ischgl</tei:rs>er have moved in and would like to
        see how they are going to make out . . . . Oh, the good people play their instruments,
        drink, hustle, and have no idea how things stand with us today . . . .</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Here there are also several large radio devices. However, we hear that the reception
        better at night than by day. The strong sunlight here during the day is supposed to impede
        good reception. Is that so where you are too?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I have just now written to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004104"
          >Reichraming</tei:rs> and inquired about <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774"
          >Mozio</tei:rs>’s health. What might he be lacking? You examined him. Is he missing
          <tei:pb n="4"/> something physical? Or is he sick because he misses his professional
        position or engagement? (That seems to me more likely to be true.)</tei:p>

      <tei:p>We will soon finish up our corrections of a new book,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
          type="footnote"/> which will be published in September, but we are also at work on a new
        and large – very large – project.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>We are very happy to see you at your home. For now, we have to get through a few visits
        here (hopefully they will take place and the Soci’s do not spit on it again). Let us know
        soon how things look at your place. Do you have news from our dear <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000319">Sophie</tei:rs>?</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">LieLiechen</tei:rs> and I greet and
          kiss you most cordially</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
          >Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:date when="1927-07-24">July 24,
          1927</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
