<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="1583" sdoID="OJ-5-18-33">OJ 5/18, 33</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="major">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="minor">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="JR-HE">
      <tei:persName>John Rothgeb &amp; Heribert Esser</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006, 2011</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2006, 2011</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2015</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2011-02-10" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002713">Jonas ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002714">Jonas ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated December 21, 1933</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1933-12-21T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2015-11-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker sends article [by Citkowitz]. — In response to Jonas's quoting from a
        Jewish lexikon, he refers to the sermons by Cardinal Faulhaber, and writes of his pride in
        being Jewish but in having assimilated thoroughly enough to establish favorable relations
        with the Catholic church, antisemites, and the news media. — Implying a parallel between
        himself and Jesus, he offers his "monotheistic theory of music" as "a new message to the
        world from the Jews." — He has no copy of his Syrische Tänze; — writes of the work's
        history.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Aufsatz; essay; article; Judaica; Predigt; sermon; Juda; Judah; Jude; jew;
        Judentum; judaism; Bekenntnis; faith; Rasse; race; Verunglimpfung; disparagement;
        Mitarbeiter; colleague; collaborator; Werk; work; project; Lexika; lexicons; Germanen;
        Germans; Buch; book; monotheistisch; monotheistic; Testament; Jesus; Lehre; teaching;
        Verbreitung; propagation; Mission; Offenbarung; revelation; Heiden; heathen; katholisch;
        catholic; antisemitisch; antisemitic; Sache; cause; Menschheitsgut; asset of mankind;
        Weltbotschaft; world message; Discretion; Konzert; concert; Tanz; dance</dc:subject>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000412">Jonas</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">


      <tei:note type="editorial" place="pre-text">This letter is written in the hand of Jeanette
        Schenker, with insertions, underlinings and other annotations in the hand of Heinrich
        Schenker.</tei:note>

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>Geehrter, lieber Herr Doktor <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000412"><tei:hi rend="lateinschrift">Jonas</tei:hi></tei:rs>!<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Dictating of this letter is recorded
            in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/7, p. 3885, December 20, 1933: "Nach dem Abendessen diktire
            ich einen Brief an Jonas: „Juda“ discret behandeln wegen höherer Erfordernisse der
            Sache! Lege den Aufsatz von Citkowitz bei – Lie-Liechen schreibt spät nachts den Brief."
            ("After supper I dictate a letter to Jonas: Deal discreetly with "Judah," on account of
            the greater needs of the cause. I enclose the article by Citkowitz – Lie-Liechen writes
            the letter late at night.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">beiliegend sende ich Ihnen den Aufsatz aus <tei:rs key="entity-002510"
          type="place"><tei:country>Amerika</tei:country></tei:rs>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Israel Citkowitz</tei:author>,
              <tei:title level="a">The Role of Heinrich Schenker,</tei:title>
            <tei:title level="j">Modern Music: A Quarterly Review</tei:title> XI:1 (1933),
            18‒23</tei:bibl>. See <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-18-32">OJ 5/18,
            32</tei:ref> and the reply, <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-12-6_27">OJ 12/6,
            [27]</tei:ref>. The translation survives in an 8-page typescript, "<tei:title level="u"
            >Die Rolle Heinrich Schenkers,</tei:title>" as OJ 58/2, and also in Schenker's scrapbook
          at OC 2/between p.88 and p.89, translator unidentified.</tei:note> Die Wärme des jungen
        Mannes, ja sogar der Tonfall ist ganz erstaunlich hoch gestimmt. Er macht seinem Vornamen
        alle Ehre. Und da bin ich mitten in den Judaica.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Seit den Predigten des <tei:rs key="entity-000219" type="person">Kardinals
          Faulhaber</tei:rs> ist „Juda”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Quotation marks apparently added by Schenker. Michael Cardinal von Faulhaber (1869‒1952),
          Roman Catholic Archbishop of Munich 1917–52. After the boycott of Jewish businesses in
          Germany on April 1, 1933, Faulhaber issued an order to the Catholic clergy on April 24 to
          support the Nazi regime, and is reported also to have said: "We bishops are being asked
          why the Catholic Church, as often in its history, does not intervene on behalf of the
          Jews. This is not possible at this time because the struggle against the Jews would then,
          at the same time, become a struggle against the Catholics, and because the Jews can help
          themselves, as the sudden end of the boycott shows." Faulhaber's Advent sermons of 1933
          were a defense of the Old Testament that avoided pronouncing on the contemporary Jewish
          situation: it may be to one of these sermons (the Advent Sundays being December 3, 10, 17,
          24) that Schenker is referring here. The sermons were published as <tei:bibl><tei:title
              level="m">Judentum, Christentum, Germanentum : Adventspredigten gehalten in St.
              Michael zu München 1933</tei:title> (Munich: A. Huber, 1934), Eng. transl. by
              <tei:editor>George D. Smith</tei:editor> as <tei:title level="m">Judaism, Christianity
              and Germany</tei:title> (New York: Macmillan, 1934)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> gewiß keine
        Schande mehr für die Träger des Bekenntnisses u. der Rasse. Daß ich niemals ein Hehl daraus
        gemacht habe, daß ich ein stürmischer Anbeter des wunderbarsten Denkmals bin, wissen Sie.
        Die Verunglimpfung durch <tei:rs key="entity-000195" type="person">Einstein</tei:rs> kann ja
        nicht mehr ungeschehen gemacht werden u. was sich Ihr Mitarbeiter in dem größeren Werk
        leisten wird, scheinen Sie ja auch nicht zu wissen, eher muten Sie ihm eine Unzulänglichkeit
        zu. Daß diese beiden Lexika den Germanen zu <tei:pb n="2"/> Augen kommen sollten bezweifle
        ich. Es ist demnach so, als wären die beiden Bücher überhaupt nicht vorhanden. Anderseits
        haben wir zu bedenken, daß ein <tei:hi rend="underline">geflissentliches</tei:hi><tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Underscoring apparently by
          Heinrich.</tei:note> Hinaustragen des Bekenntnisses der Sache einigermaßen abträglich sein
        könnte. Ich halte dafür, daß es besser wäre den Germanen meine monotheistische
          <tei:term>Musiklehre</tei:term><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Cf. <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-18-49">OJ 5/18, 49</tei:ref>, and diary
          entries May 17 and 21, 1933, see <tei:bibl><tei:author>H. Federhofer</tei:author>,
              <tei:title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern ...</tei:title> (Hildesheim:
            Georg Olms, 1985), p.320</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> so zu schenken wie das alte Testament
        der ganzen Welt geschenkt worden ist: Nach 2000 Jahren mögen die Nachfahren der Germanen den
        Schenker verleugnen wie sie Rabbi Jesum verleugnen, bis dahin aber hat die Lehre gewirkt u.
        Verbreitung in der Welt gefunden, u. schließlich wird der Trotz der Germanen nur lächerlich
        sein. Vor allem die „Mission“! Geht es zu dieser musikalischen Offenbarung besser u.
        leichter, wenn man die musikalischen Heiden nicht gleich vor den Kopf stoßt, dann vermeide
        man, <tei:pb n="3"/> was überflüssig ist. Bis heute stehe ich im Geruche eines blonden
        Germanen u. war seit jeher deshalb <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">persona
          gratissima</tei:foreign> bei sämtlichen katholischen, antisemitischen u. ä. Blättern (auch
        in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs>)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Parentheses added by Heinrich.</tei:note> gewesen. Also lade
        ich die Wissenden ein, mit mir unter einer Decke zu spielen u. im Interesse der Sache
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>der deutschen
          Musikgenies</tei:add>
        <tei:handShift new="#JS"/>die <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">cued to lower
          margin</tei:note>
        <tei:handShift new="#HS"/>, von den Deutschen unverstanden, verraten, geschändedet, seit
        Langem aber Menschheitsgut ist geworden, nun <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end
          cue</tei:note>
        <tei:handShift new="#JS"/>eine <tei:hi rend="underline">neue Weltbotschaft des
          Judentums</tei:hi><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">Underscoring
          apparently by Heinrich.</tei:note> für die nächsten Ewigkeiten zu sein bestimmt ist,
        stillzuhalten. Ich hoffe, Sie verstehen mich richtig. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Für den kleinen Aufsatz, den Sie beisteuern, sage ich herzlichen Dank. Den
        beiliegenden Aufsatz<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot">Not further
          identified, and not filed with this letter.</tei:note> sollen Sie behalten u.
        Gesinnungsgenossen zeigen doch immer unter Discretion: Zwei Juden auf einmal wären für
        feindlich gestimmte Seelen zu viel.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Leider besitze ich die „<tei:rs key="entity-001664" type="composition"
            ><tei:title>Syrische Tänze</tei:title></tei:rs>“ selbst nicht, weiß auch nicht, wohin
        der Verlag <tei:rs key="entity-000946" type="person">Weinberger</tei:rs> gekommen ist,
        gelegent- <tei:pb n="4"/> lich werde ich die <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization"
          >U.-E.</tei:rs> fragen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Schenker ordered a copy for Jonas from Weinberger in February 1934.</tei:note> Es mag Sie
        interessiren, daß <tei:rs key="entity-000116" type="person">Busoni</tei:rs> die Stücke in
        seinen Konzerten in <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs> gespielt hat,
        in der <tei:term>Orchestrierung</tei:term> von — <tei:rs key="entity-000798" type="person"
          >Schönberg</tei:rs>, den er bei dieser Gelegenheit dem Namen u. der Leistung nach
        kennengelernt hat. <tei:rs key="entity-000116" type="person">Busoni</tei:rs> hat die Stücke
        ursprünglich mit <tei:rs key="entity-000794" type="person">Schnabel</tei:rs> gespielt u.
        schrieb mir daß sie „genial“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Quotation marks in Heinrich's hand. Busoni's letter is OJ 9/27, [11]:
              <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Heinrich Schenker: Selected Correspondence</tei:title>,
            ed. <tei:editor>Ian Bent</tei:editor>, <tei:editor>David Bretherton</tei:editor> and
              <tei:editor>William Drabkin</tei:editor> (Woodbridge: The Boydell Press, 2014), p.
            35</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> seien. Auch heute noch finde ich die Stücke außerordentlich,
        nicht so leicht von irgendjemand nachahmbar. Freilich, Juden würden sich in diesen Tänzen so
        wenig erkennen, wie sich Ungarn in <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person"
        >Brahms</tei:rs>’ <tei:title>ungarischen Tänzen</tei:title> wiederfinden. Mit <tei:rs
          key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs> habe ich Stücke daraus dem alten <tei:rs
          key="entity-000331" type="person">Hanslick</tei:rs> vorgespielt, auch im Bösendorfer Saal
        u. in vielen privaten Häusern so daß ich, über den Erfolg einigermaßen erschreckt, davon
        absah, weitere Hefte zu publizieren.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ob van <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hoboken</tei:rs> sich
        hier angekauft <tei:pb n="5"/> hat weiß ich noch immer nicht. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Mit den besten Grüßen von mir u. meiner <tei:rs key="entity-000771"
          type="person">Frau</tei:rs> u. besten Wünschen für die Festtage </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-90">Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>herzlichst ergebener</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60">
          <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">H
            Schenker</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline>
          <tei:handShift new="#JS"/><tei:placeName>Wien</tei:placeName>, den <tei:date
            when="1933-12-23">21. Dezember 1933</tei:date>
        </tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">


      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>Revered, dear Dr. <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000412">Jonas</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"
          /></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">I send you herewith the essay from <tei:rs key="entity-002510"
          type="place"><tei:country>America</tei:country></tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> The young man's warmth, even the tone, is most amazingly enthusiastic.
        He does his given name full justice. And there I am in the midst of Judaica.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Since the sermons of <tei:rs key="entity-000219" type="person">Cardinal
          Faulhaber</tei:rs>, "Judah"<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> is certainly
        no longer a disgrace to the bearers of the faith and the race. You know that I have never
        made a secret of the fact that I am a passionate devotee of that most marvelous monument.
        The disparagement by <tei:rs key="entity-000195" type="person">Einstein</tei:rs> can no
        longer be undone, and what your colleague in the larger project will get up to, you indeed
        seem also not to know; you instead expect him to fall short. I doubt that these two lexicons
        will come to the <tei:pb n="2"/> attention of the Germanic peoples. It is therefore as if
        the two books did not exist at all. On the other hand we must reflect that an <tei:hi
          rend="underline">assiduous</tei:hi><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/>
        display of commitment to the matter could be in some sense deleterious. I think, rather,
        that it would be better to present the Germanic people with my monotheistic <tei:term>music
          teaching</tei:term><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> as the Old Testament
        was presented to the whole world: after 2,000 years the successors to the Germanic people
        may disavow Schenker as they disavow Rabbi Jesus, but all along the teaching has made its
        effect and achieved propagation in the world, and ultimately the defiance of the Germanic
        peoples will only be ridiculous. Above all, the "Mission"! If this musical revelation will
        come about better and more easily provided we desist from offending the musical heathens,
        let us avoid anything <tei:pb n="3"/> that is unnecessary. Up to now I have maintained the
        repute of a blond Germanic type and have therefore long since been <tei:foreign
          xml:lang="lat"><tei:hi rend="italic">persona gratissima</tei:hi></tei:foreign> among all
        Catholic, antisemitic and such news media (even in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place"
          >Vienna</tei:rs>).<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> Thus I invite those in
        the know to make common cause with me, and, in the interest of the product <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>of the German music-geniuses</tei:add>
        <tei:handShift new="#JS"/>which, <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">cued to lower
          margin:</tei:note>
        <tei:handShift new="#HS"/>ununderstood, betrayed, defiled by the Germans, but long since
        having become an asset of all mankind, is now <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end
          cue</tei:note>
        <tei:handShift new="#JS"/>destined to become a <tei:hi rend="underline">new message to the
          world from the Jews</tei:hi><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> for the
        coming eternities, to hold our peace. I hope you understand me correctly.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Many thanks for the short essay that you contribute. Please keep the
        enclosed essay<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/> and show it to the
        like-minded, but always with discretion: two Jews at once would be too much for antipathetic
        minds.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Unfortunately I myself no longer possess the <tei:rs key="entity-001664"
          type="composition"><tei:title level="m">Syrian Dances</tei:title></tei:rs>, and do not
        know what became of the publishing house of <tei:rs key="entity-000946" type="person"
          >Weinberger</tei:rs>; sometime <tei:pb n="4"/> I will ask <tei:rs key="entity-002408"
          type="organization">Universal Edition</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09"
          type="footnote"/> It may interest you to know that <tei:rs key="entity-000116"
          type="person">Busoni</tei:rs> played the pieces in his concerts in <tei:rs
          key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs>, in the
          <tei:term>orchestration</tei:term> by none other than <tei:rs key="entity-000798"
          type="person">Schoenberg</tei:rs>, whom he got to know by name and accomplishment on that
        occasion. <tei:rs key="entity-000116" type="person">Busoni</tei:rs> originally played the
        pieces with <tei:rs key="entity-000794" type="person">Schnabel</tei:rs> and wrote me that
        they were "touched by genius."<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn10" type="footnote"/> Even today I
        still find the pieces extraordinary, not so easy for just anybody to imitate. Admittedly,
        Jews would recognize themselves in these dances as little as Hungarians rediscover
        themselves in <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs>'s <tei:title
          level="m">Hungarian Dances</tei:title>. With <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person"
          >Violin</tei:rs> I played selections from them for old <tei:rs key="entity-000331"
          type="person">Hanslick</tei:rs>, both in the Bösendorfer Salon and in many private houses,
        so that I, to some extent intimidated by the success, abjured publication of further
        volumes.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Whether van <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hoboken</tei:rs> has
        bought here <tei:pb n="5"/> I still do not know.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">With best greetings from my <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person"
          >wife</tei:rs> and me, and best wishes for the holidays,</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-90">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>cordially devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60">
          <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">H. Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline>
          <tei:handShift new="#JS"/><tei:placeName>Vienna</tei:placeName>, <tei:date
            when="1933-12-23">December 21, 1933</tei:date>
        </tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
