<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="490" sdoID="OJ-5-7a_14">OJ 5/7a, [14] (formerly vC 14)</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
   <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>


  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2011-07-17" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002775">Cube ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated April 29, 1928</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1928-04-29T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-07-12</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker sympathizes with Cube over the hostilities he faces; contrasts his own theory to the
    approach of Riemann. Has arranged for Hammer portraits to be sent to Cube [for bookshop exhibits], and directs him
    to biographical information about himself. Describes the trials of his 20s, which were surpassed by the difficulties
    he faced later with publishers and organizations. Upholds Joachim and Messchaert as models of performance art, and
    speaks of his contact with Brahms. Asks whether Cube will be joining him in Galtür in the summer.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000143">Cube</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Lieber Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">von <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Cube</tei:hi></tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker's diary records at
      <!-- XR -->OJ 4/1, p. 3202, April 28, 1928: "Nach der Jause bei Artaria: zwei Hammer-Bilder an Cube bezahlt: 7150
      S." (After teatime at Artaria: two Hammer portraits paid for, for Cube: 7,150 shillings."). Writing of this letter
      is recorded at OJ 4/1, pp. 3202–3203, April 29, 1928: "An Cube (Br.): einiges Autobiographische, auf Vrieslanders
      Ersuchen." ("To Cube (letter): something autobiographical, at Vrieslander's request.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Der erste Sonntag-Frühmorgen giebt mir Gelegenheit, Ihnen zu antworten. Die Widerstände, die von der Seite der
    Lehrer, der in dieser Frage entscheidenden Menschen„klasse“, kommen, sind nur zu begreiflich; sie fühlen, daß es
    nicht mehr so betriebsbequem bei den neuen Dingen zugehen kann, wie bei den <tei:sic>berichtigten</tei:sic>
    <tei:term>Harmonielehren</tei:term> „mit <tei:term>Schlüssel</tei:term>“ zum Aufgabenbuch, nicht mehr so
    idiotischbequem abgehaspelt werden darf: Bdur – Cdur – fis<tei:hi rend="supralinear">dur</tei:hi> – Mies<tei:hi rend="supralinear">dur</tei:hi><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker writes
      "Mies<tei:hi rend="supralinear">dur</tei:hi>," possibly in jest ("Mi" is the solmization syllable for E, and "Es"
     is the German for E flat), possibly in error. The chord sequence is entirely made up.</tei:note> – f<tei:hi rend="supralinear">moll</tei:hi> – Gis<tei:hi rend="supralinear">dur</tei:hi> u.s.w., sondern daß der Kopf ein
    Wörtchen mitzureden hat, obendrein ein eigenartiger, auf reinste Musik abgezogener <tei:pb n="2"/> Kopf mit tausend
    musikalischen Ohren. Das <tei:unclear reason="reading">nur</tei:unclear> des lieben Ich so brünstig gepflegte
    „Gefühl“, das nicht ohne eine gewisse Überhebung der angeblichen „<tei:term>Reflexion</tei:term>“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:hi rend="italic">Reflexion</tei:hi>: a theme that is
     discussed in the unpublished essay <tei:title level="a">Über den Niedergang der Kompositionskunst,</tei:title> in
     which Schenker criticizes those who regard the Classical masters as "reflective," rather than spontaneously
     creative. See <tei:bibl>Heinrich Schenker, <tei:title level="a">The Decline of the Art of Composition,</tei:title>
      ed. and trans. William Drabkin, <tei:title level="j">Music Analysis</tei:title> 24 (2005), especially pp. 39–40
      (in English translation) and pp. 138–9 (in the German original).</tei:bibl></tei:note> sogar eines <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Beeth.</tei:hi></tei:rs>, eines <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Brahms</tei:hi></tei:rs> entgegengestellt wird, bei dem
    es <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">nur</tei:add> verwunderlich ist, daß gerade die
     <tei:term>reflektierenden Meister</tei:term> sinfonie-potent sind, während sie, die gefühlspotenten,
    sinfonie-impotent sind (wo es doch im Grunde umgekehrt sein müsste!), das selbstherrliche Gefühl soll zum
    Aberglauben geworfen werden – das geht den Lehrern zu weit. Hätte ich freilich diesen Herren die Tafel gedeckt ganz
    so, wie der betriebskundige Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000712" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Riemann</tei:hi></tei:rs> es um ihretwillen in seinen zahllosen „Katechismen“ mit dem Ollendorf-Frage- u.
     Antwortspiel,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">This appears to be an allusion to the
       <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Nouveau cours de langue anglaise, selon la méthode d'Ollendorf</tei:title>
      (1906)</tei:bibl>, which used the method of the catechism.</tei:note> in den „grossen“ u. „kleinen“ <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Komposition</tei:hi>slehrbüchern (für jede „<tei:unclear reason="reading">Perslage</tei:unclear>“
     <tei:note type="editorial">?</tei:note>) <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#HS">bereichert</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">getan</tei:add>
    </tei:subst>, hätte ich durch Ausführung der allengesamtesten <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Literatur</tei:hi> jede,
    jede Verlegenheit <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">ihnen</tei:add> aus dem Wege geräumt, dann, dann
    hätte ich längst den zukommenden Platz <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">auch bei ihnen</tei:add>
     erobert!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">The idea of a substantial collection of theory
     books by a single author as a "meal," to be consumed by musicians or teachers, is something Schenker returns to in
     his letter to Cube <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-7a_21">OJ 5/7a, [21]</tei:ref>, November 20, 1928,
     where he compares his various types of composition – theory books, analyses, editions, Urlinie graphs – as a
     banquet similar to that provided by Riemann.</tei:note>
    <tei:pb n="3"/> Soeben muß es sich in die Länge ziehen u. namentlich ist mein Tod die erste Vorbedingung. Die Sache
    macht aber glänzende Fortschritte . . .</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Nun zur eigentlichen Sache. Sie erhalten längstens binnen einer Woche von der Kunsthandlung <tei:rs key="entity-002413" type="organization"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr-underline">Artaria</tei:hi></tei:rs> 2 <tei:rs key="entity-000327" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Hammer</tei:hi></tei:rs>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Victor Hammer made a mezzotint portrait of Schenker, dated 1926; and there is a
     bronze medallion on which this is inscribed. The two survive as <!-- XR -->OJ 72/14, items 7 and 18.</tei:note>
    (Die frühere Serie ist durchgekauft, <tei:rs key="entity-002413" type="organization"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Artaria</tei:hi></tei:rs> muß eine neue bestellen, dies ist der Grund der kleinen Verzögerung). Von diesen beiden
    Stücken wollen Sie, bitte, eines für sich selbst behalten, zur Erinnerung an die Kämpfe Ihrer Jugend, das andere
    aber bitte ich, da ein Verkauf nicht zu erwarten ist, an mich zurückzusenden.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Am <tei:date when="1928-05-04">Freitag</tei:date> brachte H. <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Vrieslander</tei:hi></tei:rs> einen Wunsch von Ihnen vor, ich übernahm die
    Erfüllung desselben, um es kürzer zu machen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">The
     implication of this statement is that Cube had asked Otto Vrieslander for information about Schenker's life, and
     that Schenker decided to write to Cube himself.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Einiges finden Sie in <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"><tei:rs key="entity-000712" type="person">Riemann</tei:rs>s <tei:title>Lexicon</tei:title></tei:hi> u. in <tei:title><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Kürschner</tei:hi></tei:title>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl>Kürschner's
       <tei:title level="m">Gelehrtenlexicon</tei:title></tei:bibl>.</tei:note> Die neuen Auflagen kenne ich freilich
     <tei:pb n="4"/> nicht, weiß also nicht, ob <tei:rs key="entity-000195" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Einstein</tei:hi></tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09" type="editorial" place="foot">A typewritten copy of the
     article on Schenker in the <tei:bibl>11th edition of Riemann's <tei:title level="m">Lexicon</tei:title></tei:bibl>
     was pasted onto p. 79 of the Schenker Scrapbook (<!-- XR -->OC, file 2).</tei:note> nicht noch mehr gekürzt hat, um
    ein paar Zeilen für irgendeinen <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Jazz</tei:hi>-Schleuderer zu gewinnen. Doch glaube ich,
    daß ein äußeres Gerüst zu finden sein wird, bis auf das Todesdatum, das noch unbekannt ist.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker is joking about the fact that, though he has an entry in
     an important dictionary of music, he is still alive.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich kann sagen, daß alle unendlichen Schwierigkeiten, die ich gleich zu Anfang meiner Zwanzigerjahre zu
    bestehen hatte, da ich den aus fünf Personen bestehenden Familiennachlaß meines <tei:rs key="entity-000772" type="person">Vater</tei:rs>s,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11" type="editorial" place="foot">When Johann Schenker died
     in 1887, five of his six children were alive. The eldest daughter, Rebecka, died two years later; she would
     probably have been in her mid-twenties at the time, though no birth certificates were issued for the first five
     Schenker children. At the time of his father's death, Schenker was just twenty. See <tei:bibl>Hellmut Federhofer,
       <tei:title level="m">Heinrich Schenker, nach Tagebüchern und Briefen</tei:title> (Hildesheim: Olms, 1985), pp.
      4–5</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> der ein sehr gefeierter Landarzt war, aus dem Stunden-Ertrag zu versorgen hatte, in der
    Folge <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">noch</tei:add> überboten wurden durch die Schwierigkeiten, die
    die Menschen, namentlich die Verleger, meine Arbeiten bereiteten. So unvergleichlich vielleicht meine menschliche
    Leistung bei den ersteren Schwierigkeiten gewesen, die Durchsetzung meiner Arbeiten darf ich <tei:pb n="5"/> dennoch
    als die stärkere Leistung bezeichnen. Nirgend kam mir Hilfe, ich mußte den Widerstand in langjährigen Kämpfen
    brechen. Sogar der Lebensvertrag (mit der „<tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">U.E.</tei:hi></tei:rs>“ schützte mich nicht. So kam es, daß mehrere Serien-Arbeiten bis zur Stunde unvollendet
    bleiben mußten, <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">„<tei:rs key="entity-001733" type="work">die letzten fünf Sonaten von
        <tei:abbr>Beeth<tei:ex>oven</tei:ex></tei:abbr></tei:rs>“ entbehren noch das wichtigste<tei:supplied reason="syntax">,</tei:supplied>
     <tei:rs key="entity-001205" type="composition">op.106</tei:rs></tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12" type="editorial" place="foot">The preparation of an <tei:title level="m">Erläuterungsausgabe</tei:title> of
     Beethoven's "Hammerklavier" Sonata (Op. 106) was held up (and eventually abandoned) mainly becuase the autograph
     score could not be traced, and not because Schenker was in dispute with his publishers.</tei:note>
    <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">die Ausgaben der Sonaten</tei:hi> von <tei:rs key="entity-000612" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Mozart</tei:hi></tei:rs> u. <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Haydn</tei:hi></tei:rs>, (auf die ich verträglich ein Recht hatte) konnten nicht zustandekommen, der „<tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work">Tonwille</tei:rs>“ erfuhr äußersten Widerstand) (Vertragsbruch u. Sabotage) des
    eigenen Verlages, usw.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13" type="editorial" place="foot">The long-running dispute between
     Schenker and Universal Edition, which led to the temporary severing of relationships between them, is extensively
     documented by <tei:bibl>Ian Bent and William Drabkin in the General Pefaces to the English edition of <tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title>, vols. 1–2 (New York: Oxford University Press, 2004–5)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note>
    Dieser Verlust an Arbeit, an Erfüllung von Aufgaben, die nur ich allein (als ihr Erfinder) meistern könnte, ist mein
    Schmerzlichstes geblieben, da er nicht mehr gutzumachen ist. Hätte der Verlag mir die Zeit zur Arbeit zur Verfügung
    gestellt, die er für <tei:pb n="6"/> die eigensinnigen Kämpfe in Anspruch nahm, ich hätte noch viel Ersprießliches
    geleistet, das Allen gut bekommen wäre, auch dem Verlag.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Es fehlte in meinem Leben gewiß nicht an ehrende Aufforderungen u. Aufträgen von Seiten verschiedener
    Körperschaften. Alles zerschlug sich aber in dem Augenblick, da ich die Ausführung bekanntgab, da war alles zuviel
    des Guten u. überschritt die Vorstellungen der Werber. Weniger sollte es um die Sache <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overwritten" hand="#HS">G</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#HS">g</tei:add>
    </tei:subst>ehe, die ihnen ja völlig fremd war, als vielmehr um eine billige Ausführung (billig in jeder Hinsicht)
     <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#HS">sozusagen</tei:del> nur <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">wie</tei:add> um sie selbst, die Auftraggeber auszuzeichnen u. zu ehren. Die Sache ging mir leer aus u. so kam es,
    daß ich auch den Lehrinstituten lieber auswich. Ich sah <tei:pb n="7"/> an, daß ich den Kampf vom neutralen Zimmer
    aus zu führen habe.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Die aüßerste Armut getragen zu haben, war mir eine Seligkeit, ich bin auf diese Auszeichnung durch das
    Schicksal stolz. Oblag mir doch die wunderschöne Aufgabe, dem materiellen Minus durch ein geistiges Plus
    entgegenzurücken. (Nie beugte mich die Armut zu einem Demokraten, gar zu einem Sozialde<tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overwritten" hand="#HS">kr</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#HS">mo</tei:add>
    </tei:subst>kraten herab, im Namen des ewig aristokratischen Geistes trug ich seit Kindheit den Kopf hoch über den
    Pöbel hinaus.) Nur weil ich dem Geist treu u. selbstlos diente, konnte ich finden, was nur zu finden von Oben
    beschert war.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Weitere Seligkeiten meines Lebens: <tei:rs key="entity-000404" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Joachim</tei:hi></tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14" type="editorial" place="foot">Although
     Schenker did not know Joachim (1831-1907) personally – see his letter to Cube <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-7a_17">OJ 5/7a, [17]</tei:ref>, July 13, 1928 – he used his recollection of Joachim's string quartet
     performances as a benchmark against which other chamber music ensembles were judged.</tei:note>
    <tei:rs key="entity-000592" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Meschaërt</tei:hi></tei:rs> als Vorbilder der so
    schwierigen Kunst des Vortrags. Die Kunstreise <tei:pb n="8"/> mit <tei:rs key="entity-000592" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">M.</tei:hi></tei:rs> verschaffte mir Einblick in die ganz einzige subtile Werkstatt dieses
    Sängers, den ich ohne Weiteres als den ersten Sänger aller Zeiten u. Zonen bezeichne. Er steht <tei:hi rend="underline">hoch über</tei:hi> den stolzesten italienischen Typen aller Jahrhunderte, also einschließlich des
     <tei:rs key="entity-002918" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Caruso</tei:hi></tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker's admiration for the artistry of the Italian tenor
     Enrico Caruso (1873-1921) is noted in a diary entry of <!-- XR -->February 17, 1928, i.e. just two months earlier.
     See <tei:bibl>Federhofer, <tei:title level="m">Nach Tagebüchern</tei:title>, p. 226</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> leider
    weiß die Welt um seinen Rang noch gar nichts, sie konnte es auch nicht fassen, da <tei:rs key="entity-000592" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">M.</tei:hi></tei:rs> nie in der Oper sang, die ja den einzigen
     Kunsttrog<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn16" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:hi rend="italic">Kunsttrog</tei:hi>
     ("art-trough"), a derogatory neologism that likens the operatic audience to a herd of cattle.</tei:note> der Menge
    bedeutet.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Und daß ich den letzten <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Brahms</tei:hi></tei:rs> erleben, sahen, sprechen, aufführen <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">hören</tei:add> dürfte, über dieses Glück musste ich Tränen schreiben, wenn ich es könnte. Ich wußte es immer, daß
    er der letzte Meister ist, daß die Musik tot ist, ich wußte es lange, lange bevor <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">die</tei:add> Anderen es <tei:pb n="9"/> zur Not begriffen haben. (S. Vorrede zum <tei:rs key="entity-001726" type="work">Kp.<tei:hi rend="supralinear">I</tei:hi></tei:rs>)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn17" type="editorial" place="foot">Much of the foreword to <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Kontrapunkt</tei:title>, vol.
      1 (1910)</tei:bibl> is indeed concerned with the artistic poverty of contemporary music, but the idea that Brahms
     was the last true master is implied rather than being stated outright.</tei:note> Dieser Schmerz um die sterbende
    Kunst trieb mich zur Arbeit, fieberhaft (Tag u. Nacht) warf ich die Gedanken aufs Papier inmitten bedrohtesten
    äußeren Lebens, rang mit den Verlegern, Lesern, nun sehe ich doch – Erfolg.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>In <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Brahms</tei:hi></tei:rs> sah ich den
    Abendhimmel der Kunst, seit diese Glut erloschen, ist es stockfinster in der Welt – für immer. Die Welt hat das hohe
    Glück der großen Meister nie genossen, nie begriffen, nie bedankt, daher ist die Kunst von ihr fort.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich muß schließen, die Gedanken tun weh. Vielleicht können Sie trotzdem <tei:pb n="10"/> Einiges von dem
    hingeworfenen brauchen.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Eine Frage: hat Ihnen die „<tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">U.E.</tei:hi></tei:rs>“ die Werke zur Verfügung gestellt? Woher nehmen Sie denn diese??</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Nach <tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs> kommen heuer Prof <tei:rs key="entity-000178" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Dunn</tei:hi></tei:rs>, Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000643" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Oppel</tei:hi></tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Vriesl.</tei:hi></tei:rs> mit <tei:rs key="entity-002920" type="person">H.
      <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Klaus</tei:hi></tei:rs> (zum 1. Mal in den Bergen), werden Sie auch dabei sein? Das wäre
    sehr schön.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Am <tei:date when="1928-06-15">15. 6</tei:date> verlasse ich diesmal (ausnahmsweise) <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> u. fahre langsam, schrittweise nach <tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs>!</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute>Mit herzlichsten Grüßen von mir u. meiner <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Frau</tei:rs></tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">H Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1928-04-29">29.4.28</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dear Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">von Cube</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>The first Sunday morning gives me the opportunity of replying to you. The hostilities you encounter from the
    teachers, the "class" of people who decide in this matter, are all too understandable. They feel that, with the new
    things, they can no longer proceed with such businesslike smoothness as they can with the authorized
     <tei:term>harmony textbooks</tei:term>, "with <tei:term>keys</tei:term>" to the assignment book; they can no longer
    reel off <tei:supplied reason="clarity">the answers</tei:supplied> with such idiotic convenience – B<tei:g type="flat"/> major, C
    major, F<tei:g type="sharp"/> major, E<tei:g type="flat"/> major,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> F minor, G<tei:g type="sharp"/> major, and so
    on – but that their heads will have to join in the conversation, and moreover a very special head, stripped down
    down to the purest music, <tei:pb n="2"/> with a thousand musical ears. The "feeling" <tei:supplied reason="clarity">for music</tei:supplied>, so obsessively practised by their dear selves, which is set against the so-called
     "<tei:term>reflection</tei:term>"<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> even of a <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs> or <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs> –
    whereby it is <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">merely</tei:add> surprising that it is the
     <tei:term>reflective masters</tei:term> who are capable of the symphonic where as they, who are capable of having
    feelings, are incapable of the symphonic (though in principle the opposite ought to have been the case!) – this
    high-handed feeling should be rejected as superstition, <tei:supplied reason="clarity">but</tei:supplied> that is
    more than the teachers are willing to accept. Had I, of course, laid the table for these men exactly as the
    business-wise Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000712" type="person">Riemann</tei:rs> had done for their sake, in his
    countless "catechisms" with the Ollendorf question-and-answer game,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/>
    in his "great" and "short" composition textbooks (for every <tei:unclear>situation</tei:unclear>), had I saved them
    each and every embarrassment by explaining the entire collected literature <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of
     music</tei:supplied>, then, yes, then I would long ago have won the place that was owing <tei:supplied reason="clarity">to me</tei:supplied>, <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">even among
     them</tei:add>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/>
    <tei:pb n="3"/> For now, things must drag on and, in fact, my death will be the first precondition <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of the recognition of my theories</tei:supplied>. The cause, however, is making magnificent
    progress...</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Now for the matter at hand. You will receive from the art gallery <tei:rs key="entity-002413" type="organization"><tei:hi rend="underline">Artaria</tei:hi></tei:rs> two <tei:supplied reason="clarity">copies of
     my portrait by</tei:supplied>
    <tei:rs key="entity-000327" type="person">Hammer</tei:rs> in at most a week.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> (The earlier series was sold out; <tei:rs key="entity-002413" type="organization">Artaria</tei:rs> has to order a new one, hence the short delay.) Of these two, please be so kind as to keep one
    for yourself, to remind you of the struggles of your youth; the other, however, I ask you to return to me, as it is
    not expected to be sold.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">On <tei:date when="1928-05-04">Friday</tei:date>, <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs> came with a request from you; I took this on myself in order to expedite matters.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">You will find a few things <tei:supplied reason="clarity">about me</tei:supplied> in <tei:rs key="entity-000712" type="person">Riemann</tei:rs>'s <tei:title level="m">Lexicon</tei:title>, and in
     <tei:title>Kürschner</tei:title>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/> I am afraid I haven't seen the
    latest editions, <tei:pb n="4"/> and thus do not know whether <tei:rs key="entity-000195" type="person">Einstein</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09" type="footnote"/> has shortened my entry further in order to gain
    a few lines for some up-and-coming jazz star. Yet I believe that a basic outline may be found there – apart from the
    date of death, which is not yet known.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn10" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>I can say that I had to overcome all unending difficulties, right from my twenties, since I had to take care
    of a family of five which was left to me by <tei:supplied reason="clarity">the death of</tei:supplied> my <tei:rs key="entity-000772" type="person">father</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn11" type="footnote"/> a highly
    respected country doctor, and that, in the further course <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of my life</tei:supplied>,
    these were <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">further</tei:add> surpassed by the difficulties that
    people, i.e. publishers, created for my works. However incomparable my human achievement may have been, with regard
    to the former difficulties, the completion of my work may <tei:pb n="5"/> nevertheless be reckoned as the greater
    accomplishment. I received no help anywhere, I had to overcome resistance in struggles that lasted many years. Even
    the life-long contract (with <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">Universal Edition</tei:rs>) did not
    protect me. Thus it turned out that several series of work have had to remain incomplete to this day: the <tei:rs key="entity-001733" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Erläuterungsausgabe</tei:title></tei:rs> is missing the most
    important volume, on <tei:rs key="entity-001205" type="composition">Op. 106</tei:rs>;<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn12" type="footnote"/> the editions of the sonatas of <tei:rs key="entity-000612" type="person">Mozart</tei:rs> and
     <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person">Haydn</tei:rs>, to which I had a contractual right, could not be
    realized; the <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs> suffered
    the most extreme opposition from my own publishers (breach of contract and sabotage), and so on.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn13" type="footnote"/> This loss of work, of fulfillment of tasks, which I alone was able to
    master (as its discoverer), has remained the most painful thing for me, since it can no longer be made good. Had the
    publishing house granted me the time for work which it <tei:supplied reason="clarity">instead</tei:supplied> took up
    in <tei:pb n="6"/> these stubborn struggles, I would have accomplished even more of value for the good of everyone,
    publisher included.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>In my life, I was certainly short of invitations and assignments on the part of various organizations, which
    would have brought honour to me. But everything fell through in the moment that I gave notice of how I would realize
    them, since there was too much and this exceeded the expectations of the promoters. It was less a question of my
    cause, which was indeed an entirely closed book for them, than rather a cheap realization (cheap in every respect),
    to be accomplished only to confer distinction and the honor upon themselves, the clients. I came away empty-handed,
    and so it came about that I also preferred to keep clear even of the institutions of learning. I realized <tei:pb n="7"/> that I would have to wage the battle from a neutral position.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>To have endured the most extreme poverty was a blessing for me; I am very proud to have thus been marked out
    by fate. For it became my happy duty to set a spiritual plus against the material minus. (Never did poverty reduce
    me to becoming a democrat, still less a social democrat. In the name of the eternal aristocratic spirit, I have,
    since childhood, always held my head high above the mob.) Only by serving the spirit faithfully and selflessly was I
    able to find what was granted from above for me to find.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Further blessings of my life: <tei:rs key="entity-000404" type="person">Joachim</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn14" type="footnote"/>
    <tei:rs key="entity-000592" type="person">Messchaert</tei:rs> as models of the very difficult art of performance.
    The concert tour <tei:pb n="8"/> with <tei:rs key="entity-000592" type="person">Messchaert</tei:rs> furnished me
    with insight into the utterly and uniquely subtle workshop of this singer, whom I readily acknowledge to be the
    greatest singer of all times and places. He towers <tei:hi rend="underline">above</tei:hi> the proudest Italian
    examples of all centuries, including <tei:rs key="entity-002918" type="person">Caruso</tei:rs>;<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn15" type="footnote"/> unfortunately the world knows nothing of his rank, nor could they
    understand anything, since <tei:rs key="entity-000592" type="person">Messchaert</tei:rs> never sang in the opera
    house, which is the only artistic trough from which the masses feed.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn16" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>And that I was able to experience <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs> late in life, to
    see him, <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">to hear him</tei:add> speak, perform, is a joy about which I
    would have to write tears, if I were able to. I always knew that he was the last master, that music is dead is
    something I understood long, long before <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">the</tei:add> others <tei:pb n="9"/> were forced to admit this. (See the preface to <tei:rs key="entity-001726" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Counterpoint</tei:title>, vol. 1.</tei:rs>)<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn17" type="footnote"/> This pain concerning
    the dying art drove me to work feverishly (day and night) I threw my ideas onto paper in the midst of a most
    threatened material existence, I struggled with publishers, with readers; and now I finally see – success.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>In <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs> I saw the twilight sky of art; since this glow
    has been extinguished it has become totally dark over the world – forever. The world has never enjoyed, never
    understood, never shown its gratitude for the higher blessing of the great masters, and thus the art of music has
    gone from them.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>I must close: these thoughts are painful to me. Perhaps you can nevertheless <tei:pb n="10"/> make some use of
    what I have thrown down.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">One question: did <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">Universal Edition</tei:rs> make
    my works available to you? From where, then, will you get these??</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">This year Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000178" type="person">Dunn</tei:rs>, Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000643" type="person">Oppel</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs>
    (with <tei:rs key="entity-002920" type="person">Herr Klaus</tei:rs>: his first trip to the mountains) are coming to
     <tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs>. Will you be there? That would be very nice.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>This <tei:supplied reason="clarity">summer</tei:supplied> I am leaving <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs> exceptionally <tei:supplied reason="clarity">early</tei:supplied>, on <tei:date when="1928-06-15">June 15</tei:date>, and will travel slowly, in stages, to <tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute>With most affectionate greetings from me and my <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Yours,</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">H. Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1928-04-29">April 29, 1928</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>


  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>