<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="647" sdoID="OJ-5-17_1-vsn-1">OJ 5/17, [1, vsn 1]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="sole">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2011</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB-CH">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent and Christoph Hust</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-12-10" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-003127">Hindemith ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


   <dc:title>Handwritten draft letter from Schenker to Hindemith, undated [November 3, 1926] </dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1926-11-03T20:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2011-12-10</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>In response to Hindemith's letter of October 25, 1926, Schenker's 15-page first
    draft states his preference for a meeting with Hindemith in Vienna. Schenker thinks differently
    from Hindemith: the notion of a "good musician" is a delusion; artistic property is comparable
    with material property; the music of today is quite different from that of the past, the rules
    of the masterworks do not govern it, hence it is not art at all. Schenker reserves the right to
    speak his own mind. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>fremd; alien; unknown; Gespräch; conversation; Gedanke; thought; idea;
    Selbsttäuschung; self-delusion; Hausmittel; subterfuge; remedy; Zustimmung; agreement;
    Widerstreit; conflict; Oelquelle; oil well; Eisenbahn; train; Pferdewagen; horse-drawn carriage;
    Gifpel; pinnacle; summit; Kunst; art; Schaffen; creation; creative activity; Theoretiker;
    theorist; Zukunft; future; Natur; Nature; Fortschritt; progress; Vollendung; perfection;
    Geschichte; history; Zuwachs; increase; materiell; material; financial; geistig; spiritual;
    Wohlstand; well-being; Produktion; production; Geheimnis; secret; Hass; hatred; Rache;
    vengeance; Leidenschaft; passion; Rechte; rights</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000373">Hindemith</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:note type="editorial" place="pre-text">This edition presents the first draft (<tei:hi rend="italic">Urschrift</tei:hi>) of the letter, as dictated by Heinrich Schenker to Jeanette
    Schenker on the evening of November 3; all revisions in Heinrich's hand have for these purposes
    been disregarded. </tei:note>

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">No salutation</tei:note><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this draft is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/9,
     p. 2997, November 3, 1926: "Abends [...] Entwurf eines Briefes an Hindemith diktiert." ("In the
     evening [...] Draft of a letter to Hindemith dictated."). A further entry appears at ibid, p.
     2998, November 10, 1926: "An Hindemith (Brief; letzte Fassung verbessert, Lie-Liechen schreibt
     ihn." ("To Hindemith, letter; last version improved, Lie-Liechen writes it out."). Mailing of
     the letter is recorded at ibid, p. 3001, November 13, 1926: "Brief an Hindemith abgeschickt."
     ("Letter to Hindemith sent off."). The finished letter is not known to survive.
    </tei:note><tei:lb/>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Für Ihren freundlichen Brief u. die <tei:term>Partitur</tei:term><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">= OJ 11/51, [1]. </tei:note> ‒ eine zweite
    lag nicht bei ‒ sage ich Ihnen herzlichsten Dank. Ich bin in der angenehmen Lage<tei:supplied reason="syntax">,</tei:supplied> Ihnen erklären zu können, daß ich Ihre Arbeiten kenne, u.
    mehrere besitze,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker is
     presumably referring to Hindemith scores, since the composer did not start producing books
     until 1937, thus there is nothing by him in Schenker's private library of books about music
     sold at his death: <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Musik und Theater enthaltend die Bibliothek
       des Herrn Dr. Heinrich Schenker, Wien</tei:title> (Vienna: Heinrich Hinterberger, [c.
      1926])</tei:bibl>. Whether there were scores in his library cannot be ascertained because the
     catalog for that sale, which was in the form of a card index, has not been traced despite
     extensive inquiries. No writings are preserved in OJ or OC. </tei:note> u. so waren wir uns gar
    nicht fremd beim Eintreffen Ihrer Zeilen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Am liebsten würde ich Sie beim Worte nehmen u. bitten, mir das Vergnügen
    Ihres Besuches zu schenken, wenn Sie einmal in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> sind. Ich meine nicht so sehr Ihren <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person">Bach</tei:rs>-<tei:term>Vortrag</tei:term> ‒ ich habe darüber zu viel Schönes gehört, als daß
    ich Ihrem künstlerischen Selbstgefühl <tei:pb n="2"/> nicht aufrichtig zustimme ‒, nur würde ein
    Gespräch Gelegenheit geben, die <tei:sic>mir</tei:sic> beschäftigenden Fragen gründlicher als
    auf diesem Wege zu erörtern. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2b"/> Bis dahin aber wollen Sie erlauben, daß ich auf Ihre
    Gedanken eingehe in der Reihe, wie sie mir Ihr Schreiben bringt. Ihr „guter Musiker“ ist eine
    Selbsttäuschung. Er sollte mit- u. vorauswissen u. doch darauf warten, bis die fremde Meinung
    gedruckt vorliegt. Warum entdeckt er die Meinung in sich nicht früher? fehlt ihm wirklich nur
    Zeit, Gelegenheit und Lust, das auszusprechen, was ein anderer ausspricht? Hinter meinem Rücken,
    auch mir ins Gesicht ‒ haben sich oft <tei:term>Musiker</tei:term> als solche nachwissende „gute
     Musiker“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">"nachwissend": Schenker is
     alleging (as he did on other occasions) that people read what he has to say and then claim what
     they read as their own, thereby becoming "good musicians" <tei:hi rend="italic">post
      facto</tei:hi>, only through Schenker. </tei:note> empfohlen, doch habe ich das niemals für
    etwas anderes als ein Hausmittel der Natur betrachtet, die den <tei:pb n="2c"/> Menschen eine
    Zustimmung nicht anders abringen kann, als indem sie dem Zustimmenden mit der Einbildung
    schmeichelt, er wäre es, der das Gleiche gedacht. Von Gegenbeweisen in Wort und Tat abgesehen,
    wie macht es nur der „gute Musiker“, daß er wie mit <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Schenker</tei:rs> auch mit <tei:rs key="entity-000025" type="person">Em. Bach</tei:rs>,
     <tei:rs key="entity-000576" type="person">Marx</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000712" type="person">Riemann</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000888" type="person">Thuille</tei:rs>,
     <tei:rs key="entity-000495" type="person">Kurth</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-003123" type="person">Lorenz</tei:rs> u. hundert anderen geht? Fühlt u. denkt er mit <tei:unclear reason="reading">diesen</tei:unclear> allen <tei:unclear reason="reading">mit</tei:unclear>? Zu
    wem hält er, wenn das Vorausempfundene in Widerstreit ist? Sie sehen, verehtester Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000373" type="person">H.</tei:rs>, daß ich in dieser Sache ganz anders denke, als
    Sie, ich gehe so weit anzunehmen, daß <tei:pb n="2d"/> es auch auf dem Gebiet künstlerischer
    Güter so ist, wie auf dem der materiellen: Sagte mir z.B. <tei:rs key="entity-003130" type="person">Morgan</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">John
     Pierpoint Morgan ‒ Schenker apparently had contact with him around this time through Gerald F.
     Warburg regarding autograph manuscripts in his possession; see, e.g. diary OJ 3/9, p. 3031,
     February 3, 1927. </tei:note> er besitze Oelquellen, mir - u. keinem andern <tei:supplied reason="syntax">-</tei:supplied> fiele ein zu sagen; Oelquellen besitze ich auch. Hier ist Mein
    u. Dein gut durchempfunden; auf geistigem Gebiet ist die Annahme fremder Meinungen nur scheinbar
    u. es bleibt jeder bei seinem Besitz. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich habe meine Gedanken immer nur auf die sogenannte vergangene Musik
    bezogen, weil sie nur ihr entnommen waren. Sie hatten die Freundlichkeit auszusprechen, daß sie
    auch für die „heutige Musik“ gelte. <tei:pb n="2e"/> Ich finde das nicht u. meine, Sie sollten
    den Mut haben zu sagen, die heutige Musik sei völlig neu, als daß Sie sie irgendwie in der
    vergangenen zu verankern suchen, oder ‒ in Ihrem Bilde ‒ die sogenannte neue Musik für eine
    Eisenbahn ausgäben, die zugleich ein Pferdewagen ist. Im mündlichen Verkehr pflegte <tei:rs key="entity-000798" type="person">Schönberg</tei:rs> mich zu fragen, ob es so sein <tei:hi rend="underline">müsse</tei:hi> ‒ das so bezog sich auf die Kunst der Meister<tei:supplied reason="syntax">.</tei:supplied> Damit lehnte er deutlich alles ab, was das Wesen der
     <tei:term>Meisterwerk</tei:term>e ausmacht, verschmähte aber nicht, gleichzeitig <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person">S. Bach</tei:rs> als seinen Vorfahren auszugeben, allerdings
     <tei:pb n="2f"/> als einen, der mit seinem Anfang auf den Gipfel <tei:rs key="entity-000798" type="person">Schönberg</tei:rs> zielt. Sie wissen, daß es so weit gekommen ist, daß von den
    Meistern behauptet wird, sie hätten sich nicht auszudrücken vermocht, u. dgl. m. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Sie deuten an, es könnte an mir liegen, wenn ich mit der heutigen Musik nicht
    gehe. Wenn ich davon absehe, daß ich mit ihr gehen müßte, u. begeistert ginge, wenn sie mit der
    Kunst, die ich meine<tei:supplied reason="syntax">,</tei:supplied> Zusammenhang hätte (verzeihen
    Sie, wenn ich es offen als einen Widerspruch bezeichne, daß Sie meine Gedanken über die Kunst
    für verbindlich auch für die gegenwärtige erkläre<tei:supplied reason="syntax">n</tei:supplied>,
     <tei:pb n="2g[1]"/> in einem aber das Verständnis für diese mir irgendwie absprechen), so kann
    ich mit Leichtigkeit nachweisen, daß die heutige Kunst im Sinne der früheren gar keine Kunst
    mehr ist, u. daher auf Ihren Einwand erwidern, wie ich es schon öfters getan: eher ist es so,
    daß Sie die Kunst der Meister noch nicht gehört haben, obwohl Sie sie als Voraussetzung für Ihr
    Schaffen bezeichnen? Sie persönlich machen es allerdings bescheiden, Sie gedenken nicht, sich
    mit <tei:rs key="entity-000803" type="person">Schubert</tei:rs> in einem Athem zu nennen, aber
    der gewisse <tei:rs key="entity-002286" type="place">Münchn</tei:rs>er <tei:pb n="2g[2]"/>
     Theoretiker,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">"Munich theorist":
     unidentified: cf. Schenker's diary, OJ 3/6, p. 2714, August 28, 1924: "Von Reygersberg, (Br.):
     [...] Zitirt ein Tagblatt, worin ein Theorie-Professor in München geschrieben haben soll:
     Beethoven würde heute wie Hindemith komponieren!" ("From Reygersberg, (letter): [...] Quotes a
     daily in which, he claims, a professor of theory in Munich wrote: Beethoven would compose like
     Hindemith [if he were alive] today!"). </tei:note> gegen den allein meine Zeilen gerichtet
    sind, hält schon Sie <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs>. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Bezüglich Ihrer Gedanken über die Zukunft der Musik, über den Charakter
    unserer Zeit möchte ich sagen: <tei:pb n="2h"/> den in Ihrem Schreiben vorgebrachten Gedanken
    kurz zu entgegnen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">"den ...
     entgegnen": Schenker probably meant this clause to be deleted ‒ it is superfluous. This sheet
     was initially the lower part of p. 2, and the line was torn through such that the ascenders of
     the letters appear on p. 2 and the body and descenders on p. 24. </tei:note> ‒ für mich das
    Recht in Anspruch nehme, meine Gedanken auszudrücken, wie jeder ander es tut. Ich habe nicht den
    Ehrgeiz, die Natur verbessern zu wollen, u. beuge mich ihr, wenn sie über die Menschen verhängt,
    daß jegliches Vollbringen sich ihnen nicht anders als in dem Glauben <tei:pb n="3"/> an
    Fortschritt u. Vollendung abringt. Die Natur selbst ist es, die dem Menschen diesen Wahn
    einträufelt, um aus ihnen Arbeit, d.h. Leben, Bewegung herauszuschlagen ‒ ein einfaches
    Hausmittel der Natur ist es. Der Gang der Geschichte lehrt, daß <tei:supplied reason="syntax">es</tei:supplied> unter den Geschlechtern auch Verderben bringende gibt genau so wie unter
    Individuen zu einer gegebenen Zeit. Nicht nur materielle Güter werden von Erben verpraßt, auch
    geistige. Es geht nicht immer einem Zuwachs von materiellem oder geistigem Wohlstand entgegen.
    In diesem <tei:pb n="4"/> Punkte hauptsächlich sind wir nicht einig u. gerade da liegt die
    Wurzel auch der übrigen Unstimmigkeit. Was bleibt übrig, als daß wir uns gegenseitig die
    ehrlichsten Absichten zur Kunst u. Menschheit zugestehen? Lassen Sie auch mich Partei sein, wenn
    Sie Partei sind. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Sie haben Recht, wenn Sie die Notwendigkeit der Produktion betonen, sogar
    möchte ich so krass wie möglich behaupten, daß die elendsten Scribenten notwendig seien, nur
    zweifle ich nicht daran, daß unter Umständen auch <tei:pb n="5"/> einer wichtig ist, der so
    beschaffen ist wie ich wobei ich zu bedenken gebe, daß ich auch um die Produktionsgeheimnisse
    einiges aus Erfahrung weiß. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="6"/> Sie sehen mich also nicht gewillt, um Entschuldigung zu
    bitten daß ich lebe, wirke u. das Recht in Anspruch nehme, mich auszudrükken, wie ich eben
    beschaffen bin. Ist das nun Hass, Rache, Leidenschaft, was ich hier ausgesprochen habe? Gewiß
    nicht! Sie streichen meine Ver- <tei:pb n="7"/> dienste zugunsten des unbekannten guten
    Musikers, Sie streichen mir das Ohr, obwohl Sie seine Brauchbarkeit bestätigen, Sie kommen sich
    trotz alle dem human vor ‒ u. ich fürchte, Sie werden meine Entgegung, erst recht als einen
    Erweis menschlichen u. künstlerischen Mangels empfinden<tei:supplied reason="syntax">.</tei:supplied>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Und doch wollen wir, da uns die gleiche Ehrlichkeit beseelt, uns gegenseitig
    die Rechte einer Partei zuerkennen. ‒ es ist gewiss so, daß Sie gegen mein Gefühl wirken ‒
    obwohl <tei:pb n="8"/> Sie es nicht zugeben, u. so wirke ich begreiflich gegen Sie, was ich aber
    offen zugestehe </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">incomplete</tei:note><tei:lb/>
    <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">No valediction or signature</tei:note>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">No salutation</tei:note><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/><tei:lb/>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">My most cordial thanks to you for your friendly letter and
     <tei:term>score</tei:term><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> ‒ no second score
    was enclosed. I am in the agreeable position of being able to declare myself familiar with your
    works and the owner of several of them,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> hence we
    were not at all unknown to one another when your letter arrived. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I would most prefer to take you at your word and have the pleasure of a visit
    from you next time you are in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>. I am not
    talking so much of a <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person">Bach</tei:rs>
    <tei:term>performance</tei:term> by you ‒ I have heard too many complimentary things about that
     <tei:pb n="2"/> not to concur wholeheartedly with your artistic self-awareness. It is only that
    a conversation would afford the opportunity to discuss the questions that concern me at a more
    fundamental level than by that means. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2b"/> But for now, please permit me to address your ideas in the
    order in which your letter presents them to me. Your "good musician" is a self-delusion. He
    should recognize and foresee, and therefore wait until the unfamiliar opinion is available in
    print. Why does he not discover the meaning for himself sooner? Does he really only lack time,
    opportunity and the desire to enunciate that which another person enunciates?
     <tei:term>Musician</tei:term>s have often commended themselves, behind my back, even to my
    face, as such <tei:hi rend="italic">post-facto</tei:hi>-knowing "good musicians,"<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> but I have never considered it anything other than a
    subterfuge on Nature's part when she is unable to wring an agreement <tei:pb n="2c"/> out of the
    person concerned other than by flattering him with the delusion that it was he who had the very
    same idea. Without contrary evidence in word and deed, just how does the "good musician"
    contrive to agree with <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Schenker</tei:rs> and also with
     <tei:rs key="entity-000025" type="person">C. P. E. Bach</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000576" type="person">Marx</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000712" type="person">Riemann</tei:rs>,
     <tei:rs key="entity-000888" type="person">Thuille</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000495" type="person">Kurth</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-003123" type="person">Lorenz</tei:rs> and a
    host of others? Does he concur and sympathize with all of these? To whom does he adhere when
    what he has previously felt comes into conflict <tei:supplied reason="clarity">with what he now
     encounters</tei:supplied>? You see, greatly revered Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000373" type="person">Hindemith</tei:rs>, that I take quite a different view of this matter than you. I
    go so far as to assume that <tei:pb n="2d"/> in the realm of artistic property things are as
    they are with material property: if, for example, <tei:rs key="entity-003130" type="person">Morgan</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> were to tell me he owns oil
    wells, it would fall to me and to no one else to say: I, too, own oil wells. Here "mine and
    thine" are thoroughly intertwined; in the realm of the mind, adoption of unfamiliar opinions is
    only ostensible, and remains for each his own property. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I have always directed my ideas solely toward so-called "music of the past"
    because it is solely from that that they were derived. You were kind enough to claim that they
    are valid also for the "music of today." <tei:pb n="2e"/> I do not find that so, and take the
    view that you should have the courage to say that today's music is completely new, rather than
    seeking to anchor it in some way to that of the past; or ‒ to use your metaphor ‒ to pass off as
    a train that which is actually a horse-drawn carriage. In the course of conversation, <tei:rs key="entity-000798" type="person">Schoenberg</tei:rs> used to ask me whether it <tei:hi rend="underline">has</tei:hi> to be so ‒ referring to the art of the masters. Thereupon, he
    bluntly rejected everything that constitutes the essence of the
    <tei:term>masterwork</tei:term>s, while at the same time not disdaining to claim <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person">J. S. Bach</tei:rs> as his forebear, at any rate <tei:pb n="2f"/> as someone who with his beginning leads up to the pinnacle <tei:supplied reason="clarity">that is</tei:supplied>
    <tei:rs key="entity-000798" type="person">Schoenberg</tei:rs>. As you know, things have reached
    the point at which it is alleged of the masters that they were incapable of expressing
    themselves, and much more along those lines. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">You imply that it could be my fault if I do not keep abreast of today's
    music. Were I to deny the obligation to keep abreast of it, and <tei:supplied reason="clarity">say that I</tei:supplied> would do so enthusiastically if it bore any relation to art as I
    mean it (Forgive me if I point flatly to a contradiction when you declare my ideas about art to
    be binding upon present-day <tei:supplied reason="clarity">music</tei:supplied>, too, <tei:pb n="2g[1]"/> while in the same breath denying me any understanding of the latter.), then I can
    with alacrity prove that the music of today, by reference to that of earlier times, is not art
    at all. Accordingly I answer your objection as I have often done in the past: it is more likely
    that you have never heard the art of the masters, even though you proclaim it as the
    prerequisite for your creative work. At any rate, you personally act with modesty; you do not
    presume to mention your name in the same breath with that of <tei:rs key="entity-000803" type="person">Schubert</tei:rs>; but the particular <tei:rs key="entity-002286" type="place">Munich</tei:rs>
    <tei:pb n="2g[2]"/> theorist<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> against whom alone
    my remarks are directed already considers you to be <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs>. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">As regards your thoughts on the future of music, <tei:supplied reason="clarity">and</tei:supplied> on the character of our times, I should like to say:
     <tei:pb n="2h"/> To answer briefly the thoughts put forward in your letter<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> ‒ I reserve to myself the right to express my ideas
    just like anybody else. I do not aspire to improve on Nature, and I bow before it if it dictates
    to mankind that any creation is wrung from men exclusively through a belief <tei:pb n="3"/> in
    progress and perfection. It is Nature herself who instills in men this folly, in order to
    inveigle them into doing some work, i.e. life, movement ‒ it is a simple subterfuge. The course
    of history teaches that among the generations there are also those that bring about ruination,
    precisely as among individuals in a given time. It is not only earthly goods that are squandered
    by heirs, but also spiritual ones. <tei:supplied reason="clarity">History</tei:supplied> does
    not always yield an increase in material or spiritual well-being. It is above all on this
     <tei:pb n="4"/> point that we are not of one mind, and precisely there lies the root of our
    remaining disagreement. What is left, <tei:supplied reason="clarity">other</tei:supplied> than
    for each of us from our own side to profess the most noble intentions for arts and mankind? If
    you have your opinions, permit me also to have mine. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">You are right to stress the necessity of production. I might even declare in
    the bluntest possible fashion that the wretchedest hack writers are necessary. Only I have no
    doubt that potentially <tei:pb n="5"/> one <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of them</tei:supplied>
    who is so constituted as I am is important. That leads me to ponder that I also know something
    of the secrets of production from my own experience. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="6"/> As you can see, therefore, I am not prepared to apologize for
    the fact that I live, work and claim the right to express myself just as my make-up dictates.
    Now is what I have uttered here hatred, revenge, intemperance? Not in the least! You discount my
     <tei:pb n="7"/> services <tei:supplied reason="clarity">to art</tei:supplied> in favor of the
    unknown good musician; you discount my ear, although you proclaim its usefulness; despite
    everything, you think yourself humane ‒ and I fear that you will take my reply more than ever as
    proof of human and artistic deficiency. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">And yet we want ‒ since the same integrity animates us ‒ to confer upon each
    other the right to our own opinion. ‒ It is indeed the case that you work contrary to my
    feelings ‒ although <tei:pb n="8"/> you do not admit it, and therefore I understandably work
    against you ‒ which, however, I freely admit </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">incomplete</tei:note><tei:lb/>
    <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">No valediction or signature</tei:note>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>