<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2171" sdoID="OJ-5-34_1">OJ 5/34, [1]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS-ink" scope="major">Heinrich Schenker's hand in ink</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS-pencil" scope="minor">Heinrich Schenker's hand in
        pencil</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="unk-pencil" scope="minor">unknown hand in pencil</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008, 2019</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2008, 2019</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2012-11-19" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006971">RothschildA ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten draft letter from Schenker to Alphons Rothschild, incompletely dated
        [March 2, 1911]</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1911-03-02T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-01-14</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Highly rhetorical letter in which Schenker thanks Alphons Rothschild for the
        financial support for his first two volumes, and notifies him of the forthcoming monograph
        on Beethoven's Ninth Symphony.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Teilnahme; participation, Werk; work; Dankbarkeit; gratitude; Plage; plague;
        Finsterniss; darkness; Wahrheit; truth; Buch; book; Förderung; promotion; Geschenk; gift;
        Renaissance; Tonkunst; music; Komposition; composition; Akademie; academy; Professor;
        Virtuose; virtuoso; Musikant; musician; Künstler; artist; Publikum; public; Schildkröte;
        tortoise; Wiedergeburt; rebirth; Monographie; monograph; Dirigent; conductor; Presse;
        press</dc:subject>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000743">Alphons Rothschild</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:handShift new="#HS-pencil"/><tei:date when="1911-02"
              ><tei:hi rend="underline">February</tei:hi> 1911</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:add resp="unknown" rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#unk-pencil"
          />(Rothschild)</tei:add>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10"><tei:handShift new="#HS-ink"/>Hochgeehrter <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000743">Herr Baron</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01"
            type="editorial" place="foot">The only record of a letter to Alphons Rothschild in
            Schenker's diary for 1911 occurs at OJ 1/10, p. 125, March 2, 1911: "Brief an Baron
            Alphons (s. Blg.)" ("Letter to Baron Alphons (see folder).") If this is the correct date
            (despite the pencil marking in the top-right corner of "February"), then either Schenker
            has had word that the payment is about to be made (see footnote 2 below), or it is a
            tactful reminder.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Ein hochherziger Akt Ihrer Teilnahme an meinem großen Werke<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The <tei:rs type="work"
            key="entity-001723"><tei:title level="m">Neue musikalische Theorien und
              Phantasien</tei:title></tei:rs>: Schenker is crediting Alphons with having undertaken
          to pay the publication costs of the first half of the second volume of this work,
            <tei:title level="m">Kontrapunkt</tei:title> (Stuttgart: J. G. Cotta, 1910), and
          cumulatively with having paid those of the first volume, <tei:title level="m"
            >Harmonielehre</tei:title> (1906). However, those costs went unpaid until March 13, 1911
          (OJ 9/31, [33] = CA 144), when Alphons finally, over five months late, made the necessary
          transfer.</tei:note> gibt mir freudigsten Anlaß, Ihnen meinen herzlichsten Dank u.
        tiefgefühlte Dankbarkeit auszudrücken.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In einer Epoche, wie die gegenwärtige, in der die Welt von den „Plagen“ des Dunkels,
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">der</tei:add> Ignoranz, Charakterlosigkeit, des
        Betruges u. anderen ähnlich heimgesucht wird, wie einmal <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
          >Aegypten</tei:hi> unter <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Pharao</tei:hi> von den berüchtigten
        „10 Plagen,“ ist es doppelt dankbar zu begrüßen, wenn eine starke Hand den Einen stützt u.
        fördert, der in die Finsterniß Licht zu bringen, das Land von den Plagen zu befreien sich
        entschloß.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Sie kennen mich, hochgeehrter Herr Baron, zur Genüge, um zu wissen, daß
        ich niemals so sprechen würde, wenn es nicht die Wahrheit wäre, die selbst aus mir spräche.
        Scheinbar sind es ja nur zwei Bücher: eine <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724"
            ><tei:title>Harmonie-</tei:title></tei:rs> u. ei- <tei:pb n="2"/> ne <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001726"><tei:title><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
            >Kontrapunkts</tei:hi>lehre</tei:title></tei:rs>, scheinbar Bücher, wie so viele andere
        es sind, u. dennoch wage ich es zu sagen, daß Sie mit der Förderung gerade dieser Bände der
        Welt ein schöneres Geschenk gemacht haben, als ein <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006384"
            ><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Carnegie</tei:hi></tei:rs> mit seinen Millionen. Es wird u.
        muß mir gelingen, eine <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Renaissance</tei:hi> der Tonkunst
        herbeizuführen, u. wenn in absehbarer Zeit der Boden der Tonkunst, der inzwischen brach lag,
        neuerdings urbarer geworden, bessere u. schönere Kompositionen an’s Licht getreten sein, u.
        damit auch der wirtschaftliche Aufschwung der Interessenten, <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">wie</tei:add> die Freude bei den Zuhörern eine edlere Grundlage
        gewonnen haben werden, dann werden Sie die Genugtuung Ihres Werkes der Teilnahme
        ernten!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Noch kämpfe ich allein gegen die Akademieen, Professoren, Virtuosen, gegen jeglichen
        Betrug, der wissentlich oder unwissentlich geübt wird, u. es versteht sich, daß die
        Musikanten – ein unwissendes Publikum (das das Tonstück sozusagen absitzt, statt es zu
        hören) u. eine noch unwissendere Presse, (die die Musik misbraucht, um einen <tei:pb n="3"/>
        <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Tour-jargon</tei:hi> in die Welt zu setzen) nennen sie zu
        emphatisch „Künstler“ – sich gegen ihre Entlarvung wahren. Es ist so angenehm, Künstler zu
        heißen, ohne es zu sein, um so angenehmer, als das Publikum u. die <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
          >Salons</tei:hi> hätscheln u. zahlen! Und dennoch wird es bald klarer sein, daß alles
        Musikantreiben heute zu einer</tei:p>

      <tei:p>– Amusement degradiert wurde. Man behauptet, daß Schildkröten ein älteres Geschlecht
        auf Erden seien, als die Menschen: sieht man <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >aber</tei:add> des letzteren Geistestempo an, so neigt man eher zur entgegengesetzten
        Anschauung. Seit urewigen Zeiten erliegen die Menschen dem Scham, dem Irrtum, u. heute ist
        es noch so, wie vor Jahrmillionen, noch bevor – die Schildkröten in der Welt waren!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Erwarten Sie also, hochgeehrter Herr Baron, nicht gerade schon morgen, übermorgen jene
        Wiedergeburt, von der ich sprach, – solches Wunder gelänge keinem Helden –, wohl aber wird
        sie eines Tages da sein, u. die Menschen beglücken, soweit diese in Kunstdingen eines Glücks
        überhaupt nur fähig sind.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> Schon in nächster Zeit erscheint von mir eine <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
          >Mono</tei:hi>graphie über die <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001731"><tei:title><tei:hi
              rend="lateinschr">IX. Symph.</tei:hi> von <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
            >Beethoven</tei:hi></tei:title></tei:rs>, die aufdecken wird, daß die Begeisterung für
        dieses Werk mehr Mode war, als auf Verständnis beruhte, die entlarvten Dirigenten werden zu
        Hause sich schämen, vor der Welt alles wütend tun, das beleidigte Publikum u. die
        beleidigten Presse werden sich in das Schlupfwinkel der Schweigens zurückziehen, – aber man
        wird das Werk endlich zum 1. Mal verstehen lernen. Bis es fertig gedruckt, werde ich
          <tei:unclear reason="reading">nur</tei:unclear>
        <tei:unclear reason="reading">einladen</tei:unclear>, Ihre <tei:note type="editorial"
          place="inline">illegible word</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">unfinished, unsigned</tei:note></tei:p>



    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">
      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:handShift new="#HS-pencil"/><tei:date when="1911-02"
              ><tei:hi rend="underline">February</tei:hi> 1911</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:add resp="unknown" rend="indent-80"><tei:handShift new="#unk-pencil"
          />(Rothschild)</tei:add>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10"><tei:handShift new="#HS-ink"/>HIghly revered <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000743">Baron</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
            type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>A high-minded stage of your participation in my great work<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> affords me a most happy occasion to express to you
        my most hearty thanks and deep-felt gratitude.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In an age such as the present one, in which the world is visited by the "plagues" of
        darkness, <tei:add place="interlinear-above">of</tei:add> ignorance, characterlessness,
        betrayal, and other similar <tei:supplied reason="clarity">pestilences</tei:supplied>, as
        Egypt once was under Pharaoh by the infamous "ten plagues," it is doubly thankfully to be
        welcomed when a strong hand supports and promotes the one person who has decided to bring
        light to the darkness and to free the land from the plagues.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">You know me sufficiently well, highly esteemed Baron, to know that I would
        never speak so if it were not the truth that speaks from out of me. Ostensibly it is really
        only two books: a <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724"><tei:title>harmony
            treatise</tei:title></tei:rs> and a <tei:pb n="2"/>
        <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001726"><tei:title>counterpoint
          treatise</tei:title></tei:rs>; ostensibly books just like so many other books, and
        nevertheless I venture to say that you have bequeathed the world a finer gift with your
        support of these books than did a <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006384"
          >Carnegie</tei:rs> with his millions. I will, I must succeed in bringing about a
        renaissance in composition, and if in the foreseeable future the soil in which composition
        grows, which has meanwhile lain fallow, becomes cultivable anew, and better and more
        beautiful compositions begin to sprout, and with them the economic prospects of the
        interested parties, <tei:add place="interlinear-above">as also</tei:add> the joy of the
        listeners, take root more nobly, then you will reap the harvest of satisfaction from your
        work of participation.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I am still battling alone against the academies, professors, virtuoso performers,
        against every fraud that is committed, knowingly or unknowingly, and it goes without saying
        that musicians ‒ whom an ignorant public (which sits out the piece, so to speak, without
        hearing it) and an even more ignorant press (which abuses music in order <tei:pb n="3"/> to
        introduce the jargon of the travel guide) too emphatically label "artists" ‒ protect
        themselves from being unmasked. It is so agreeable to be called an artist without being one,
        and all the more agreeable when the public and the salons adulate <tei:supplied
          reason="clarity">them</tei:supplied> and pay money! Moreover, it will soon become even
        clearer that the whole music enterprise of today has been reduced to a ‒</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Form of amusement. It is claimed that tortoises are a more ancient species on earth
        than man: <tei:add place="interlinear-above">but</tei:add> when one takes into account the
        speed of the latter's mental processes, one is actually inclined to the opposite view. Since
        time immemorial, men succumb to shame, to error, and it is just the same today as it was
        millions of years ago, long before tortoises came into existence.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>So, highly esteemed Baron, don't expect to see that rebirth of which I spoke right away
        tomorrow, or the day after tomorrow ‒ no hero could achieve such a miracle; but one day, for
        sure, it will be there, and will bestow fortune upon mankind, insofar as the latter is
        capable of having fortune in artistic matters at all.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> In the very near future a monograph by me on the <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001731"><tei:title>Ninth Symphony of Beethoven</tei:title></tei:rs> will be
        published, and this will reveal that the enthusiasm for this work has been a product more of
        fashion than understanding. The conductors that it unmasks will skulk at home in disgrace,
        all the world will be enfuriated, the shamefaced public and shamefaced press will hide
        themselves away in silence ‒ but people will at long last come to know the work for the
        first time. <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">Only</tei:unclear> when it is published,
        will I <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">invite</tei:unclear>, Your <tei:note
          type="editorial" place="inline">illegible word</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">unfinished, unsigned</tei:note></tei:p>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
