<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="605" sdoID="OJ-5-45_3">OJ 5/45, [3]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="sole">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="AH">
   <tei:persName>Alison Hiley</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2009</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-10-28" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Copy, in Jeanette Schenker's hand, of a letter from Schenker to Weisse, dated September
    12, 1923</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1923-09-12T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2011-10-28</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker explains his behavior a few days before, in reply to Weisse’s letter of
    September 7, and his implicit displeasure at his pupil's lengthy trip to Italy in the summer. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Korrekturen; proofs; Manuskript; manuscript; currencies; Bank; Ferienreise; holiday
    trip; Wandervogel; Selbstbetonung; self-emphasis; Politik; politics; Lausbuben; layabout; young
    fellows; Verrat; betrayal; Kapitulation; capitulation; Schaden; harm; Schande; shame;
    Würdelosigkeit; worthlessness; Pflicht; duty; Generation; Schüler; pupils</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000951">Weisse</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:byline><tei:hi rend="underline">An D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi> Hans Weisse am 12
      IX 23</tei:hi></tei:byline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Lieber Hans!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/4, p. 2566,
      September 11, 1923: "Brief an Weisse geschrieben, liegt bei." ("Letter to Weisse written,
      enclosed."). Dispatch is recorded ibid: "Brief an Weisse aufgegeben." ("Letter to Weisse
      posted."). </tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Soeben brachten wir nach starker Hetze op. <tei:rs key="entity-001218" type="composition">90</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs key="entity-001205" type="composition">106</tei:rs>
    (1. Korrekturen)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The first set of
     proofs of Schenker's editions of two Beethoven sonatas. </tei:note> u. Manuscript <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title>Tw.</tei:title></tei:rs> zur <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">U.-E.</tei:rs>, nun erwidere ich:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">This letter is a direct reply to Weisse’s
     letter, OJ 15/16, [49], September 7. </tei:note> Am <tei:date when="1923-06-15">15.
     Juni</tei:date> erwarteten wir Sie über Ihren Wunsch wegen der Franken u. Lire, Sie kamen aber
    nicht. Die Herren <tei:rs key="entity-000614" type="person">Müller</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs key="entity-000034" type="person">Bamberger</tei:rs> hatten Sie zwar gesehen, konnten mir aber
    keine Auskunft geben. – Am <tei:date when="1923-06-26">26.</tei:date> warteten wir bis gegen
    Mittag u. dann mussten wir – auch für uns war höchste Zeit, da das Haus verpackt usw. werden
    sollte – zum <tei:rs key="entity-000774" type="person">Bruder</tei:rs> mit den Franken (der mir
    genau so Bank„spesen“ rechnet wie jeder andere Bankherr), zumal er verreisen wollte. – Am
     <tei:date when="1923-06-28">Donnerstag</tei:date> waren Sie so lieb zu kommen, aber ich
    erwähnte nichts weil ich alles ahnte. – Von <tei:rs key="entity-002592" type="place">Italien</tei:rs> aus schrieben Sie nichts, doch sicher nicht, weil Sie eine Ansichtskarte
    hätten sparen wollen – nun wußte ich es. – Aus <tei:rs key="entity-003072" type="place">Pontresina</tei:rs> schrieben Sie endlich,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">= OJ 15/16, [48], July 15, 1923. </tei:note> mir nichts Neues, aber wie ich glaube
    mit etwas beklommenen Unterbewußtsein. Ich gestand Ihnen, daß ich betroffen war, weiter ging ich
    in der Kritik <tei:hi rend="underline">Ihrer</tei:hi> Ferienreise nicht, obgleich Ihr Brief
    sozusagen eine Vergangenheit hatte. Sie merkten (so schrieben Sie) ein „Beben“, aber Sie fühlten
    sich nicht nur unschuldig, sondern scheinbar auch zu beleidigt, um darauf einzugehen. Sonderbar
    genug – Sie erlauben den schmerzlichen Spass: das Beben hat Sie kalt gelassen, erst das Frostige
    hat Sie erwärmt. Und auch Sie schoben mir Politik unter, wo ich nur Menschlichkeit, Würde
    meinte. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> So schicke ich voraus, dass ich beschlossen habe, über alle
    rein menschliche Fragen kein Wort über meine Lippen kommen zu lassen, so bis zum letzten
    Athemzug. Ich habe vor vielen vielen Jahren es fertig gebracht, auf alle Vorteile der
    Gesellschaft zu verzichten, nur um die Kunst nicht zum Quatschobjekt heruntergesetzt zu sehen;
    nun entziehe ich mir das Thema Mensch, Nation, Welt für immer. Alle Körper- u. Geisteskräfte
    habe ich aufgeboten – ich wurde elend darüber – um die Menschen aus der Stumpfheit zu reißen.
    Ich erntete Überhebung: Jeder fühlte sich ein Höhner, ein Neuer, ein Weltmensch usw, aber keiner
    verstand mich. Im Venezianischen – heimkehrend hörten wir es von einem 14-jährigen
     Wandervogel<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Wandervogel: popular
     youth movement, found in 1896, banned by the Nazis in 1933. </tei:note> – verweigern die Bauern
    einem französischen Menschen eine Schlafstelle im Heu – ist das Politik oder eine (berechtigte)
     Selbstbetonung?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">"Selstbetonung"
     (self-emphasis): allusion to Alfred Adler’s contemporary views on Individual Psychology?
    </tei:note> Was verstehen die Analphabeten dort von Politik? Lesen Sie die beiliegende
     Notiz,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">Probably a newspaper
     clipping, which was sent with the letter. </tei:note> heißen Sie das auch Politik? <tei:rs key="entity-003078" type="person">Frau Dr Bamberger</tei:rs> fand es unerhört, daß zwei
    Lausbuben aus Innsbrück mit ihren Dirnchen, wie sie ihr in der Landtalhütte erzählten, <tei:del rend="overstrike">l</tei:del> nach dem <tei:rs key="entity-003077" type="place">Gardasee</tei:rs> gegangen sind, unerhört deshalb, weil die Italiener vor paar Jahren gerade
    die <tei:rs key="entity-002304" type="place">Innsbruck</tei:rs>er so drangsalierten<tei:supplied reason="syntax">;</tei:supplied> die selbe Dame zürnte den Franzosen, weil sie einen ihr
    nahestehenden Herrn mit Familie plötzlich aus <tei:placeName>Mühlheim</tei:placeName><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot">"Mühlheim" can refer to a number of towns in
     Germany and Austria. </tei:note> hinausgeworfen. Dort also Verständnis für Menschenwürde der
     <tei:rs key="entity-002304" type="place">Innsbruck</tei:rs>er, des
     <tei:placeName>Mühlheim</tei:placeName>er Herrn u. im Namen der Würde eine Kritik – aber sie
    selbst ging nach dem <tei:rs key="entity-003077" type="place">Gardasee</tei:rs>, denn „auch
     <tei:rs key="entity-000294" type="person">Goethe</tei:rs>” usw. Oder: <tei:rs key="entity-000940" type="person">Karl <tei:sic>Weigel</tei:sic></tei:rs> – auch heuer zog er
    durch <tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs> – beschimpfte die <tei:del rend="overstrike"><tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs>er</tei:del> Tiroler
    Wirte (<tei:supplied reason="syntax">„</tei:supplied>sie wuchern, <tei:pb n="3"/>
     schn<tei:supplied reason="spelling">e</tei:supplied>iden die Haut vom Leibe“) u. erzählte
    gleich darauf, daß er nach dem <tei:rs key="entity-003077" type="place">Gardasee</tei:rs> gehe.
    Ich frage ihn: sind denn die Italiener anständiger<tei:supplied reason="syntax">,</tei:supplied>
    rechnen sie denn nicht noch mehr? Er antwortet: <tei:supplied reason="syntax">„</tei:supplied>Ich mache nicht Politik, ich will einfach den <tei:rs key="entity-003077" type="place">Gardasee</tei:rs> sehen.“ Hören Sie den Widerspruch? Er kommt aus einer
    anknitterten Seele. Ich hätte sagen können: und <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs>, u. <tei:rs key="entity-000803" type="person">Schubert</tei:rs>, u. <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person">Bach</tei:rs>, u. <tei:rs key="entity-000784" type="person">Schiller</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000403" type="person">Jean Paul</tei:rs> usw.? Ich ließ
    ihn lieber stehen, denn <tei:hi rend="underline">ich</tei:hi> wußte, daß er die Verurteilung
    seines wirtschaftlichen Verrates mitten im unerhörten Wirtschaftskrieg heute nicht verstehen
    wird: er will „einfach“ den <tei:rs key="entity-003077" type="place">Gardasee</tei:rs> sehen.
    Was bekümmern ihn wir alle anderen? </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Es steht die bedingungslose Kapitulation <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Deutschland</tei:country></tei:rs>s u. der Verlust des <tei:rs key="entity-003079" type="place">Rhein</tei:rs>s bevor. So wollen es die „demokratischen“
    Völker, die die Freiheit lieben, weil sie nicht nur nichts kostet, sondern als Diebs- u.
    Raubwaffe sogar Land u. Menschen einträgt. Da schließe ich meinen Mund u. überlasse
     meine<tei:del rend="overstrike">n</tei:del> deutschen Mitmenschen dem Schaden u. der Schande,
    die sie durch Würdelosigkeit sich selbst auf das Leben luden. Anfänglich dachte ich die Feder
    überhaupt niederzulegen, aber ich tue meine Pflicht: ich sitze am Arbeitstisch, auf dem Band IV,
     <tei:rs key="entity-001728" type="work"><tei:title>der freie Satz</tei:title></tei:rs>,
    ausgebreitet liegt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09" type="editorial" place="foot">In the published
     writings what was to become <tei:title level="m">Der freie Satz</tei:title> was referred to
     initially as "Band II<tei:hi rend="supralinear">3</tei:hi>" (i.e. the third (half-)volume of
      <tei:title level="m">Kontrapunkt</tei:title>), later as "Band III"; however, since Schenker's
     plans by this time were in flux the work is sometimes referred to in correspondence as "Band
     IV." In his published work, Schenker still referred to it as <tei:title level="m">Freier
      Satz</tei:title>, without the definite article. </tei:note> Ich will in der <tei:unclear reason="reading">Setzermaschine</tei:unclear> sprechen, was mich bewegt, aber nicht mehr zu
    Menschen. Es ist Alles vorbei. Halten Sie aber, lieber Hans, nicht für frostig, wenn ich auf die
    gestrichenen Themen nicht zurückkomme. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer rend="indent-10"><tei:salute>Ihnen u. Frau <tei:rs key="entity-000952" type="person">Hertha</tei:rs> beste Grüße von uns Beiden.</tei:salute><tei:lb/>
    <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">unsigned</tei:note></tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:p rend="first">Noch eins: Sie sind nicht blos Nachfahre meiner Generation, sondern auch
     (geistig) Vorfahre Ihrer Schüler, das verpflichtet.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10" type="editorial" place="foot">The last line on the page appears to be the start of a diary
      entry, not part of Schenker's letter to Weisse: "11. Dem Andrang, der mit Goethe's Sehnsucht"
      ("11. The throng which <tei:supplied reason="clarity">journeys there with</tei:supplied>
      Goethe's longing") In the bottom right corner of the page is the sign •/., with which Schenker
      normally indicates a connection to another sheet of paper. The last sheet of OJ 5/45, [3],
      which contains a few more lines in Jeanette's hand, written sideways in the left margin of a
      picture of the Brussels String Quartet, is likewise a fragment that may have nothing to do
      with the letter to Weisse. Its text reads: <tei:q>"<tei:supplied reason="clarity">?Der Anzahl
        der Italien-</tei:supplied> reisenden ist, nach einer privaten Mitteilung des italienischen
       Consuls, das Consulat gar nicht gewachsen; er steigert sich immer noch! Wie viel Milliarden
       Blut wird da unserem Wirtschaftskörper abgezapft u. den Italienern zugeführt, die
        <tei:unclear reason="reading">nun</tei:unclear> ohnehin bei den Zinsen der Anleihe
       aussaufen!" ("The Consulate is simply not equal to <tei:supplied reason="clarity">the number
        of</tei:supplied> travellers <tei:supplied reason="clarity">going to Italy</tei:supplied>;
       according to a private announcement from the Italian consul, it is still on the increase! How
       many billions <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of pints</tei:supplied> of blood will be taken
       from our economic body and given to the Italians, who are <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">now</tei:unclear> downing the loan's interest as it is!")</tei:q>
     </tei:note>
    </tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>



  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:byline><tei:hi rend="underline">To Dr Hans Weisse on September 12,
     1923</tei:hi></tei:byline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Lieber Hans!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">After a mad rush we have just delivered Opp. <tei:rs key="entity-001218" type="composition">90</tei:rs> and <tei:rs key="entity-001205" type="composition">106</tei:rs>
    (first proofs)<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> and the manuscript of <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs> to <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">UE</tei:rs>, so I can now respond to you.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> We were expecting you on <tei:date when="1923-06-15">June 15</tei:date>, regarding your request concerning francs and lire, but you never came.
    Although Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000614" type="person">Müller</tei:rs> and Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000034" type="person">Bamberger</tei:rs> had both seen you, they were unable to
    tell me any more. – On the <tei:date when="1923-06-26">26th</tei:date> we waited until about
    noon, but then we had to leave, partly because it was high time that we packed up the house
    etc., and partly because we needed to take the francs to my <tei:rs key="entity-000774" type="person">brother</tei:rs>, who himself was about to set off on some travels. (He
    incidentally charges me just the same rates as any banker would.) – On <tei:date when="1923-06-28">Thursday</tei:date> you kindly called, but I didn’t mention anything as I
    suspected all. – You sent me nothing from <tei:rs key="entity-002592" type="place">Italy</tei:rs>, but certainly not because you wanted to save yourself the price of a picture
    postcard – so now I knew for certain. – Finally you did write from <tei:rs key="entity-003072" type="place">Pontresina</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> but not with
    any news as such, instead with what I take to be a degree of subconscious anxiety. I confessed
    to you that I was perplexed, but I did not criticize <tei:hi rend="underline">your</tei:hi>
    holiday trip any further, although your letter had what one might term a "history." You noticed
    (so you said in your letter) an "upheaval," but you evidently felt yourself to be not merely
    innocent but, more than that, too offended to take it further. Strangely enough – you must allow
    me this sad joke – the upheaval left you cold, it was only the frostiness that warmed you up.
    And even you accused me of the political, when all I had in mind was humanity, and dignity. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> So I now say in advance that I have decided not to allow one
    single word concerning purely human matters to pass my lips, not until my dying breath. It was
    many, many years ago that I came to the point where I could renounce all the advantages society
    offers, only so that I might not see art being degraded to a mere object of empty chit-chat. I
    now avoid the subjects of human feeling, nationhood and the world, and will do so forever. I
    summoned up all my physical and spiritual powers – it brought misery upon me – in trying to
    wrench people away from sheer dullness. I encountered nothing but presumption: each considered
    himself a derider, a new man, a man of the world etc., but nobody understood me. In the Venetian
     <tei:supplied reason="clarity">?region</tei:supplied> – so we heard on the way home from a
    fourteen-year old Wandervogel<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> member – the
    peasants will refuse a French person a place to sleep in the hay – is that politics or
    (justified) self-emphasis?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> What do the
    illiterate people there know about politics? Read the enclosed note,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> would you call that politics too? <tei:rs key="entity-003078" type="person">Frau Dr Bamberger</tei:rs> found it unheard of that two young
    fellows from <tei:rs key="entity-002304" type="place">Innsbruck</tei:rs> (who told her the story
    in a valley hut) should have gone to <tei:rs key="entity-003077" type="place">Lake
     Garda</tei:rs> with their girls; unheard of , because the Italians oppressed the people of
     <tei:rs key="entity-002304" type="place">Innsbruck</tei:rs> to such an extent a few years ago.
    The same lady was angry with the French for suddenly expelling from
     <tei:placeName>Mühlheim</tei:placeName><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/> a
    Frenchman and his family who were close to her. She thus displayed understanding for the dignity
    of human nature regarding the people of <tei:rs key="entity-002304" type="place">Innsbruck</tei:rs>, and the gentleman from <tei:placeName>Mühlheim</tei:placeName>, and thus
    also, in the name of that dignity, a critical view – yet she herself was on the way to <tei:rs key="entity-003077" type="place">Lake Garda</tei:rs>, since "so did Goethe" etc. Or take Karl
    Weigl – he passed through <tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs> recently as
    well – berated the <tei:del rend="overstrike"><tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs></tei:del> Tirolean landlords (<tei:supplied reason="syntax">"</tei:supplied>they profiteer, and <tei:pb n="3"/> would have the shirt off one’s back") and
    said straight afterwards that he was on the way to <tei:rs key="entity-003077" type="place">Lake
     Garda</tei:rs>. I ask him: are the Italians more reasonable now, do they not calculate even
    more? He answers: <tei:supplied reason="syntax">"</tei:supplied>I am not making a political
    point, I just want to see <tei:rs key="entity-003077" type="place">Lake Garda</tei:rs>." Can you
    hear the contradiction? It comes from a vexed soul. I could have said: and <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs>, and <tei:rs key="entity-000803" type="person">Schubert</tei:rs>, and <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person">Bach</tei:rs>,
    and <tei:rs key="entity-000784" type="person">Schiller</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000403" type="person">Jean Paul</tei:rs> etc.? I chose to let him alone, for <tei:hi rend="underline">I</tei:hi> knew that he will not today understand the condemnation of his economic treachery
    in the midst of the unheard of economic warfare: he "simply" wants to see <tei:rs key="entity-003077" type="place">Lake Garda</tei:rs>. Why should he worry about all of us? </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Germany</tei:country></tei:rs>'s unconditional surrender and the loss of the
     <tei:rs key="entity-003079" type="place">Rhine</tei:rs> are at hand. That's the wish of the
    "democratic" peoples, who love freedom; not only does it cost nothing but, as a weapon of
    robbery and theft, it even yields land and people. I then keep my mouth shut and leave my fellow
    Germans to the harm and shame they have incurred through their own lack of dignity. At first I
    thought I would lay down my pen completely, but I do my duty: I sit at my desk, on which Vol.
    IV, <tei:rs key="entity-001728" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Free
     Composition</tei:title></tei:rs>, is spread out.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09" type="footnote"/> I want to speak to the <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">typesetting
     machine</tei:unclear>, something which moves me, but not to people any more. That is all in the
    past. Dear Hans, don't take it as frostiness if I do not return to the vetoed topics. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer rend="indent-10"><tei:salute>Best wishes to you and <tei:rs key="entity-000952" type="person">Hertha</tei:rs> from us both.</tei:salute><tei:lb/>
    <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">unsigned</tei:note></tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:p rend="first">One more thing: you are not merely my generation's successor; you are also
     the (spiritual) forefather of your pupils, and that binds you by obligation.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn10" type="footnote"/>
    </tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>

 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>