<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="511" sdoID="OJ-5-7a_35">OJ 5/7a, [35] (formerly vC 35)</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
      <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>


    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2011-11-07" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002775">Cube ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated March 28, 1931</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1931-03-28T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-11-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker put Cube's Cologne Highschool proposal to van Hoboken, and now reports on the reaction,
        discussing the latter's character in so doing.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      
      
    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000143">Cube</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Lieber Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">v.
              Cube</tei:hi></tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter
            appears not to be recorded in Schenker's diary.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Nun sollen Sie den wahren Hergang erfahren.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The
          entire letter is concerned with Anthony van Hoboken's response to a proposal set out in Cube's previous
          letter, <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-34_23">OJ 9/34, [23]</tei:ref>, February 10,
          1931.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Nachdem Sie mir den ersten Brief in der Angelegenheit <tei:rs key="entity-002604" type="place">Köln</tei:rs> geschrieben haben, habe ich sofort <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hob.</tei:rs>
        mitgeteilt, daß ich von Ihnen einen wichtigen Bf erhalten habe, dessen Inhalt <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#HS">ich</tei:del> schon jetzt zu verraten <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">ich
          aber</tei:add> für überflüssig halte, da möglicherweise Sie nichts weiter unternehmen. Daß wir Beide
        Geheimniskrämerei treiben, <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">wo der</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">wäre</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> für ihn das Unerträglichste, wenn es durch Zufall ihm bekannt geworden wäre. Nun schreiben Sie, das
        Spiel lag also offen da. Die ersten Worte, die über <tei:pb n="2"/> seine Lippen sprangen, nachdem er mir den
        Inhalt Ihres Briefes mitteilte, lauteten: „<tei:quote><tei:hi rend="underline">Wie komme <tei:hi rend="double-underline">ich</tei:hi> dazu</tei:hi>? Wenn <tei:rs key="entity-002939" type="person">Braunfels</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Walter Braunfels, professor
            of theory at the Cologne Hochschule für Musik, who had given support to Cube's efforts to promote
            Schenkerian theory in northern Germany.</tei:note> will, kann er ja Andere abbauen u. <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">Cube</tei:rs> einsetzen.</tei:quote>“ Da ich <tei:add place="interlinear-above">zu</tei:add> dieser Äußerung nichts sagte – sie gieng ja <tei:hi rend="underline">wissentlich</tei:hi> an Allem vorbei –, verfiel der kleinliche Mann auf folgendes: „<tei:quote>Darf ich Sie
          um einen Rat bitten?</tei:quote>“ Ich durchschaute den Gesellen: ihm genügte zur Befriedigung seines
        Snobismus, seines Geldgefühls schon die Tatsache des Angerufenwordenseins, diese Befriedigung steht ihm, wie wir
        es hier Alle schaudernd<tei:note type="editorial">corr</tei:note> miterlebten, für die Ausführung: er sagt dann
        meinetwegen auch zu, läßt dann aber alle <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">auf</tei:add>sitzen, –
          <tei:hi rend="underline">ohne sich sogar zu entschuldigen</tei:hi>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">So hat er die Gesamt-Ausg. von <tei:rs key="entity-000025" type="person">Em. Bach</tei:rs> auf
          <tei:pb n="3"/> sich genommen, zahllose Personen durcheinander gefegt<tei:note type="editorial">?</tei:note>,
        Reisen zu Verlegern, zu Anwälten machen lassen, (ich wurde zu den Konferenzen aus dem Krankenbett geholt!),
        plötzlich schreibt er an Prof. Dr <tei:rs key="entity-000320" type="person">Haas</tei:rs>:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Robert Haas (1886–1960) was the Director of the Music
          Division at the Austrian National Library 1920–45, and was in charge of the Photogrammarchiv there from its
          establishment in 1927. Plans to issue the collected works of C. P. E. Bach in twenty volumes over a ten-year
          period, under the general editorship of Ernst Fritz Schmid, and to publish a yearbook devoted to Bach
          research, are mentioned several times in the diaries; see <tei:bibl>Federhofer, <tei:title level="m">Heinrich
              Schenker, nach Tagebüchern ...</tei:title> (Hildesheim: Olms, 1985), p. 155</tei:bibl>.</tei:note>
            „<tei:quote><tei:rs key="entity-000025" type="person">Em. Bach</tei:rs> ist ein <tei:hi rend="underline">deutscher</tei:hi> Meister, wie komme <tei:hi rend="underline">ich</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="underline">ein
            Ausländer</tei:hi>, dazu, die G.A. zu machen??</tei:quote>“ Entsetzen Sie sich nicht?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:hi rend="italic">Entsetzen Sie sich nicht?</tei:hi> A
          variant on a common German play on words: "setzen Sie sich!" (sit down); "entsetzen Sie sich!" (be
          outraged).</tei:note> Nicht einmal hat er sich bei Verlegern, <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">bei</tei:add> uns Allen entschuldigt – ein Lausbub! Und ähnliche Erfahrungen haben wir Alle zuhause zu
        verzeichnen. Er ist <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#HS">ein</tei:del> völlig unerläßlich, schäbig, wucherisch,
        lügt schauderhaft, kurz er bewacht sein Geld wie 10 Drachen, nur daß er es nicht lassen kann, sich überall
        anzubiedern, <tei:hi rend="underline">Allen nachzulaufen, um <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">ein
            bischen</tei:add> Ehre für sich zu hausen</tei:hi>!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich erwiderte dem Filou: „<tei:quote>Sie wissen, daß ich <tei:pb n="4"/>
          <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Cube</tei:hi></tei:rs> jede Hilfe
          Ihrerseits vergönne, tun Sie’s also, nur bitte ich Sie, diese Hilfeleistung <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">nicht</tei:add> als eine Zuwendung <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">auch</tei:add>
          an <tei:hi rend="underline">mein</tei:hi> Lebenswerk zu werten. Es wäre ja grotesk, <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">daß,</tei:add> wenn Sie sich mir gegenüber abseits stellen, ich Ihnen
            <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">v. Cube</tei:hi></tei:rs>
          empfehle.</tei:quote>“ Er hätte gern Sie u. mich verpflichtet, eine „<tei:soCalled>Geste</tei:soCalled>“
        getan, ohne auch nur eine Mark auszulegen. Wir kennen ihn schon. Nach Sekunden sagte er: „<tei:quote>Ich werde
          mich mit meiner <tei:rs key="entity-002742" type="person">Frau</tei:rs> beraten</tei:quote>“(!) (sie ist in
          <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs>) – na also, der Rückgang aus der Geste war schon da..
        In der nächsten Stunde vollzog er ihn ganz, da er plötzlich (wohlvorbereitet seit Langem, denn tückisch ist er
        über alle Maßen) erklärte: „<tei:quote>Nein, ich werde <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">C.</tei:hi></tei:rs> Empfehlungen schicken u.s.w.</tei:quote>“ Seine ersten Worte
        behielten Recht. Heute rasselt er in <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Berlin</tei:hi></tei:rs> mit Geld, er spielt mit den Menschen, die er <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">an</tei:add> sich lockt, denen er Alles mögliche vortäuscht, dann <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">remainder in upper margin, inverted:</tei:note> verrät er sie alle, nachdem er sie ausgerechnet
        hat, u. – rasselt mit dem Geld wo anders, das genügt ihm.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Mit besten Grüßen von mir u. meiner <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Frau</tei:rs>
          –</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-90">Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-85"><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">H
              Schenker</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:signed>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-45"><tei:date when="1931-03-28">28.3.31</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dear Professor <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">von Cube</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Now you should learn the true sequence of events.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">After you wrote me your first letter about the opportunity in <tei:rs key="entity-002604" type="place">Cologne</tei:rs>, I informed <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hoboken</tei:rs>
        immediately that I had received an important letter from you; <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">but
          I</tei:add> thought it unnecessary to reveal its content just then, since you might possibly not undertake
        anything further. For us to engage in a secret deal <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">would have
          been</tei:add> the most unbearable thing for him, if by some chance he gained knowledge about it. Now you
        write that the matter is thus <tei:supplied reason="clarity">still</tei:supplied> open. The first words that
          <tei:pb n="2"/> sprang to his lips, after he communicated to me the content of your letter <tei:supplied reason="clarity">to him</tei:supplied> were: "<tei:quote><tei:hi rend="underline">What am <tei:hi rend="double-underline">I</tei:hi> supposed to do about this</tei:hi>? If <tei:rs key="entity-002939" type="person">Braunfels</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> wants, he can certainly get
          rid of others and employ <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:quote>" As I said
        nothing in response <tei:add place="interlinear-above">to</tei:add> this statement – it <tei:hi rend="underline">deliberately</tei:hi> avoided the entire matter – the small-minded man came up with the following:
          "<tei:quote>Might I ask you for some advice?</tei:quote>" I saw straight through the scoundrel: merely the
        fact that he had been called upon was enough to satisfy his snobism, his materialism. For him, this satisfaction
        – as we have all experienced here, to our horror – takes the place of doing something. He will even agree, for
        my sake; but then lets everyone wait – <tei:hi rend="underline">without even so much as
        apologizing</tei:hi>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">This is how he took the collected edition of the works of <tei:rs key="entity-000025" type="person">C. P. E. Bach</tei:rs>
        <tei:pb n="3"/> upon himself, bringing countless people together, arranging trips to publishers, to solicitors
        (I was summoned from my sick-bed to the meetings!); finally he writes to Professor <tei:rs key="entity-000320" type="person">Haas</tei:rs>:<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> "<tei:quote><tei:rs key="entity-000025" type="person">Emanuel Bach</tei:rs> is a <tei:hi rend="underline">German</tei:hi>
          master, why should <tei:hi rend="underline">I</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="underline">a foreigner</tei:hi>, be
          involved in the collected edition?</tei:quote>" Is that not an outrageous thing to say?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> Not once did he apologize to the publishers, <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">to</tei:add> any of us – the rascall! And we all have similar private
        experiences to recount. He is <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#HS">a</tei:del> completely untrustworthy,
        shabby, usorious, a fiendish liar; in short, he guards his money like ten dragons, except that he cannot help
        ingratiating himself everywhere, <tei:hi rend="underline">running after everyone in order to accrue <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">a little</tei:add> honour for himself</tei:hi>!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I replied to the rogue: "<tei:quote>You know that I <tei:pb n="4"/> agree to any help that you
          can give <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">Cube</tei:rs>; do it, then; I merely ask you <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">not</tei:add> to assess this offer of help as a gesture <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">also</tei:add> in respect of <tei:hi rend="underline">my</tei:hi>
          life's work. It would indeed by grotesque for me to recommend <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">Cube</tei:rs> if you stood in opposition to me.</tei:quote>" He would have gladly obliged you and me, made
        a "<tei:soCalled>gesture,</tei:soCalled>" without coughing up a single mark. We know what he is like. After some
        moments he said, "<tei:quote>I'll talk the matter over with my <tei:rs key="entity-002742" type="person">wife</tei:rs></tei:quote>"(!) – she is in <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs> – there
        you have it, the retreat from the gesture was already on the way... Within the hour he had withdrawn it
        entirely, for suddenly (though he had prepared for it long before, for he is a sly one beyond all measure) he
        explained: "<tei:quote>No, I shall write recommendations for <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">Cube</tei:rs>, etc.</tei:quote>" His first words contained the truth. Today he rattles his money in <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs>, he plays with the people to whom he becomes attached, giving
        them the illusion that everything is possible, then, <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">remainder in
          upper margin, inverted:</tei:note> having sized them up, he betrays them all and goes off elsewhere, rattling
        his money; that satisfies him.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>With best greetings from me and my <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-90">Yours,</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-85"><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">H. Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-45"><tei:date when="1931-03-28">March 28, 1931</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>