<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3554" sdoID="OJ-5-38_90">OJ 5/38, [90]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="LR">
      <tei:persName>Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008423">SchenkerW ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Heinrich to Wilhelm Schenker, dated July 12, 1934</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1934-07-12T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-11-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Heinrich expresses some optimism about political affairs in Germany, then
        reports the arrival of Oswald Jonas’s book about his theories. — He has had a positive
        health assessment from the local doctor but feels that he needs extra personal
        assistance.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000775">Wilhelm Schenker</marcrel:recipient>

    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:div type="part_1">

        <tei:opener>
          <tei:address rend="indent-50">
            <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#HS"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002359"
                >Böckstein</tei:rs> –</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003099"
              >Bad-Gastein</tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine>(<tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002578"
              >Salzburg</tei:rs>)</tei:addrLine>
          </tei:address>
          <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:date when="1934-07-12">12. 7.
            34</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
          <tei:salute>Mein lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775"
              >Wilhelm</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing
              of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for July 12, 1934: “An Wilhelm (2.
              Brief): berichte über Jonas’ Buch, Mozios Benehmen u. a.” (“To Wilhelm (second
              letter): I report about Jonas’s book and Mozio’s demeanor, among other
              things”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:p>Wie geht es dir? Und der l. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008450"
          >Marie</tei:rs>?</tei:p>

        <tei:p>Gerade lese ich, daß Major Fey zum Spezialminister für Sicherheit ernannt worden ist,
          der versteht keinen Spaß, <tei:hi rend="underline">das Ende der Nazis ist da</tei:hi>! </tei:p>

        <tei:p>War das aber eine Verwüstung in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482"
            >Deutschland</tei:rs> u. bei uns!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
            place="foot">Reference is presumably to the “Night of the Long Knives” (“Nacht der
            langen Messer”), a purge of political leaders, including members of the <tei:hi
              rend="italic">Sturmabteilung</tei:hi>, in particular Ernst Röhm, all of whom Hitler
            viewed as a threat to his political power, which took place across Germany between June
            30 and July 2, 1934. (<tei:title level="j">wikipedia</tei:title>, 13/11/2024)</tei:note>
          Die 10 Plagen über Pfarao nach Austreibung der Juden waren „a’ Bagatell“ dagegen! <tei:rs
            type="place" key="entity-002482">Deutschland</tei:rs> kann sich nie mehr <tei:pb n="2"/>
          erholen, doch das geht uns gar nicht mehr an. </tei:p>

        <tei:p>Gestern hat mir die Post ein Buch gebracht, dessen Untertitel lautet: „<tei:hi
            rend="underline">Eine Einführung in die Lehre H. Schenkers</tei:hi>“, 221 Seiten groß
          mit 241 Beispielen. (von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000412">D<tei:hi
              rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Oswald Jonas</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="place"
            key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>). Wäre dir der Stoff gemäßer, so würde ich dir das
          Buch schicken, aber <tei:del rend="overstrike">ih</tei:del> die Sache liegt dir gar zu
          fern, so magst du dich mit den ersten Worten auf dem Umschlag erfreuen, die lauten: „Das
          Werk H. Schenkers, <tei:hi rend="underline">nach seiner einzigartigen Bedeutung innerhalb
            der Musikwissenschaft</tei:hi> nur der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000421"><tei:hi
              rend="double-underline">Kant</tei:hi></tei:rs>s in der Philosophie <tei:pb n="3"/>
          vergleichbar usw usw.“ Das will was heißen. Auch daß mich <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000268">D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Furtwängler</tei:rs> jetzt
          gesucht hat, obgleich er „preußischer Staatsrat“ geworden u. weiß, daß ich Jude bin, will
          auch was heißen. </tei:p>

        <tei:p>Wohl hättest du eine größere Freude, wenn ich dir melden könnte, daß sich obige
          Erfreulichkeiten durch erhöhte Einnahmen ausdrücken, leider ist das nicht der Fall. Ich
          wäre sonst gleich jünger um paar Jahre u. könnte leichter die schweren Schmerzen der
          letzten 3 Jahre vermeiden. Zuletzt hatte ich recht viel mit Ärzten zu tun, die mich sehr
          lieben, da ich einer der Wenigen bin, die keiner Krankenkasse zugehören, also 10 S für die
          Or- <tei:pb n="4"/> dination <tei:add place="interlinear-above">zahlen</tei:add>. Der Arzt
          in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003099">Bad-Gastein</tei:rs> hat mich als gesund
          entlassen, <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">cued from top margin:</tei:note>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">d. h. <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat"><tei:hi
                rend="underline">senectus ipse morbus</tei:hi></tei:foreign></tei:add><tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:hi rend="italic">senectus ipsa
              morbus est</tei:hi>: Latin proverb, “Old age is itself a
            disease.”</tei:note>,<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end cue</tei:note>
          diesmal brauche ich aber eine ausgiebige Erholung, namentlich brauchte ich einen halben,
          einen Viertelmenschen um mich, der mir gut will u. auch kann. </tei:p>

        <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs> nimmt von meinen Briefen
          keine Kenntnis, auch interessiert es ihn nicht, wenn ich eine Krankheit melde; gar zu gern
          möchte er die letzten 2.000 S. behalten. Doch werde ich es nicht zugeben. </tei:p>

        <tei:p>„Mutti, wissen die Esel, daß sie Esel sind?“ „„Ich glaube, nein, mein Junge““
            „<tei:hi rend="underline">So dumm sind die Esel</tei:hi>?“</tei:p>

        <tei:p>Ein netter Spaß.</tei:p>

        <tei:p>Schreib recht bald. Wir wünschen Euch einen recht frohen Sommer! </tei:p>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Herzlichste Küsse u. Grüße</tei:salute>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-60">von mir u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
              >LieLiechen</tei:rs></tei:salute>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Dein</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>
      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="part_2">

        <tei:p><tei:pb n="5"/> 1. Ein berühmter Komiker in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002286"
            >München</tei:rs> wird nach seiner politischen Ansicht gefragt. „I’ sog’ gar nichts –
          dös wird man do’ no’ sagen dürfen“! erwidert er. </tei:p>

        <tei:p>_____ _____ </tei:p>

        <tei:p>2. In einem kleinen ungarischen Städchen lebt eine Jüdin, die Zimmer vermietet. Ihr
          Untermieter macht ihr mit viel Körperpflege (Sich-Waschen) Unbequemlichkeiten, sie stellt
          ihn darüber immerfort zur Rede, bis er, abgequält, aufschreit: „Geben Sie endlich Ruh,
          Sie, alte Chonte!“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:hi
              rend="italic">chonte</tei:hi> (Yiddish): prostitute, whore.</tei:note></tei:p>

        <tei:p>Auf der Strasse begegnet die Jüdin dann dem Apotheker des Ortes; sie klagt ihm über
          die Beleidigung, worauf er sagt: „Was wollen <tei:pb n="6"/> Sie, liebe Frau, ich bin
          schon 30 Jahr nicht mehr Apotheker, trotzdem rufen mich Alle „Herr Apotheker“! (!) </tei:p>

      </tei:div>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:div type="part_1">

        <tei:opener>
          <tei:address rend="indent-50">
            <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#HS"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002359"
                >Böckstein</tei:rs> –</tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003099"
              >Bad-Gastein</tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine>(<tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002578"
              >Salzburg</tei:rs>)</tei:addrLine>
          </tei:address>
          <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:date when="1934-07-12">July 12,
            1934</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
          <tei:salute>My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775">Wilhelm</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
              corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:p>How are you? And <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008450">Marie</tei:rs>?</tei:p>

        <tei:p>I am just now reading that Mayor Fey was named Minister for Security. He’s got no
          sense of humor. <tei:hi rend="underline">The end of the Nazis is at hand</tei:hi>!</tei:p>

        <tei:p>That was really some devastation in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482"
            >Germany</tei:rs>, and here!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> The Ten
          Plagues on Pharaoh after the expulsion of the Jews were by contrast “a bagatelle!” <tei:rs
            type="place" key="entity-002482">Germany</tei:rs> can never again <tei:pb n="2"/>
          recover, but that has nothing to do with us.</tei:p>

        <tei:p>Yesterday, the postal delivery brought me a book whose subtitle is: “<tei:hi
            rend="underline">An Introduction to the Theory of Heinrich Schenker</tei:hi>,” 221 pages
          long with 241 music examples (by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000412">Dr. Oswald
            Jonas</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>). If the
          content were more moderate for you, you might be delighted in the initial words on the
          cover, which say, “The Work of Heinrich Schenker, <tei:hi rend="underline">according to
            its unique meaning within musicology</tei:hi>, <tei:pb n="3"/> comparable only with that
          of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000421"><tei:hi rend="double-underline"
            >Kant</tei:hi></tei:rs> in philosophy, etc., etc.” That claims something. That <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000268">Dr. Furtwängler</tei:rs> sought me out, although he
          has become “Prussian State Councilor” and knows that I am a Jew, also means
          something.</tei:p>

        <tei:p>You would surely take greater delight if I could report to you that the
          above-mentioned joys were expressed through added income. Unfortunately, that is not the
          case. I would otherwise at once be younger by a few years and could have more easily
          avoided the pains of the last three years. Recently, I had quite a lot to do with doctors,
          who love me a lot since I am one of the few who is not a member of a health plan, thus
            <tei:pb n="4"/>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">pay</tei:add> 10 Schillings for an appointment. The
          doctor in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003099">Bad Gastein</tei:rs> released me as
          healthy, <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">cued from top margin:</tei:note>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">i.e. <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat"><tei:hi
                rend="underline">Senectus ipsa morbus</tei:hi></tei:foreign></tei:add>.<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end
            cue</tei:note> However, this time I need an extensive recovery time, namely I needed a
          half-time <tei:supplied reason="clarity">or</tei:supplied> a quarter-time person around
          me, who wants, and also can, do well for me.</tei:p>

        <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs> takes no notice of my
          letters. It also doesn’t interest him when I report an illness. He would like all too much
          to keep the last 2,000 shillings. But I’m not giving it up.</tei:p>

        <tei:p>„“Mom, do donkeys know that they are donkeys?” “I don’t think so, my boy.” “<tei:hi
            rend="underline">So dumb are donkeys</tei:hi>?”</tei:p>

        <tei:p>A charming joke.</tei:p>

        <tei:p>Write very soon. We wish you a very enjoyable summer!</tei:p>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Most cordial kisses and greetings</tei:salute>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-60">from me and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
              >LieLiechen</tei:rs></tei:salute>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Your</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>
      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="part_2">

        <tei:p><tei:pb n="5"/> 1. A famous comedian in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002286"
            >Munich</tei:rs> is asked about his political outlook. “I’m not saying anything – one
          may surely still say that”! he replies.</tei:p>

        <tei:p>_____ _____ </tei:p>

        <tei:p>2. In a small Hungarian city lives a Jewess who rents rooms. Her tenant causes her a
          lot of distress because of a lot of body care (washing himself). She confronts him
          repeatedly until, annoyed, he cries out: “Leave me at last in peace, you old <tei:hi
            rend="italic">chonte</tei:hi>!”<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

        <tei:p>The Jewess then encounters the local pharmacist on the street. She complains to him
          about the insult, whereupon he says: “What do you want, <tei:pb n="6"/> dear lady? I
          haven’t been a pharmacist for the last thirty years, yet everyone still calls me ‘Mr.
          Pharmacist’!” (!)</tei:p>

      </tei:div>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
