<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="1301" sdoID="OJ-5-14_1">OJ 5/14, [1]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2007</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2007</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2014</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
   <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
   <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2012-09-26" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-005509">Gesellschaft der
    Musikfreunde ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-005510">MarchetG ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-005511">KrauseC ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde, dated June 29,
    1912</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1912-06-29T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2014-11-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker responds the the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde's invitation to give a
    lecture or series of lectures on a topic of his own choosing; commenting on the reasons behind
    the proposal, and the style of lecture expected, he expresses his willingness, proposes a
    subject, and states his fee.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Vertiefung; deepening; Vorträge; lectures; Hochschulvorlesungen; highschool lectures;
    Schulen; schools; Meister; masters; Bereitwilligkeit; willingness; Institution; kunstpolitisch;
    art-political; Harmonielehre; theory of harmony; Propaganda; Terminologie; terminology;
    Diskussion; discussion; Honorar; honorarium; fee</dc:subject>


   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-002430">Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde</marcrel:recipient>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000564">Gustav Marchet</marcrel:recipient>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000478">Carl Krause</marcrel:recipient>

  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">An die K.K. <tei:rs key="entity-002430" type="organization"
      >Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
      place="foot">Although this letter is signed and dated, it may be a copy retained for the file.
      Schenker reports the Gesellschaft's reply in his diary at OJ 1/11, p. 210, July 29, 1912: "Die
      Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde erklärt mir, in einem Antwortschreiben, daß sie mit Freuden
      meine Zusage begrüßt u. sich die detailirten Besprechungen bezüglich der Vorlesungen u. des
      Honorars für Mitte September vorbehält." ("The Society of the Friends of Music informs me in a
      letter of reply that it welcomes my assent joyfully and reserves detailed discussions
      regarding the lectures and the fee until mid-September.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Für die Ehre, die mir die sehr geehrte <tei:rs key="entity-002430" type="organization"
     >Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde</tei:rs> daduch erweist, daß sie auch mich zur Erfüllung der
    neuen schönen Aufgabe mit heranzieht, erlaube ich mir meinen herzlichsten dank <tei:hi
     rend="underline">abzustatten</tei:hi>.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Weitmehr noch als Ihre erste ruhmvolle Gründung scheint mir die gegenwärtige zweite, die
    so bedeutsam das zweite Jahrhundert Ihres Bestandes einleitet, die Erreichung dessen zu
    ermöglichen, was die <tei:term>Tonkunst</tei:term> meiner Meinung nach heute am dringendsten
    fordert, nämlich die größtmögliche Vertiefung der spezifisch-musikalischen Kenntnisse.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Zwar entnehme ich Ihrem geschätzten Schreiben<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
     type="editorial" place="foot">= OJ 11/22, [2], June 21, 1912.</tei:note> nicht genau, ob die
    geplanten Vorträge den Charakter von Hochschulvorlesungen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
     type="editorial" place="foot">Translation as "highschool" is admittedly misleading here: to
     Schenker (who associated the term with what he regarded as the superior educational system of
     Germany), and indeed to the Austrian educational establishment of the time, the term
     "Hochschule" signified something higher than a (grade) school and something more intellectual
     than a conservatory: "college" or "academy," might perhaps be nearer the mark, but there is no
     English term that provides its counterpart.</tei:note> erhalten sollen; doch wünschte ich vom
    Herzen, daß es so wäre, damit der durch die zahllosen Schulen verursachten Verflachung wirksam
    entgegengearbeitet werde. Endlich <tei:pb n="2"/> soll einmal auch dasjenige, worin sich <tei:hi
     rend="underline">besonders</tei:hi> das <tei:hi rend="underline">Genie</tei:hi> unserer großen
    Meister manifestiert, in die weitesten Kreise zu deren eigenstem Wohle getragen werden. Das wäre
    meines Erachtens die idealste Art von „volkstümlichen Vorträgen.“</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Hiermit <tei:unclear reason="reading">will</tei:unclear> ich freudigst meine
    Bereitwilligkeit ausgedrückt haben, mich Ihren Plänen zur Verfügung zu stellen. Sehr gerne würde
    ich, um der neuen Institution freunde zu werben, über aus kunstpolitischen Gründen momentan
    aktuelle Themen aus dem Gebiete der <tei:term>Tonkunst</tei:term> vorlesen, so z.B. über „Gut u.
    schlecht in der <tei:term>Musik</tei:term>,“ oder über „die Unwandelbarkeit musikalischer
     <tei:term>Form</tei:term>en,“ über „die <tei:term>Technik</tei:term> in den <tei:hi
     rend="lateinschr">Sinfonien</tei:hi> von <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person"><tei:hi
      rend="lateinschr">Brahms</tei:hi></tei:rs>“ u. dgl.; jedoch wäre es ratsam, mir zu gestatten,
     <tei:hi rend="underline">zur Einführung</tei:hi> Vorlesungen über „<tei:hi rend="underline"
      ><tei:term>Harmonielehre</tei:term></tei:hi>“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial"
     place="foot">Schenker's book <tei:title level="m">Harmonielehre</tei:title> [Theory of
     Harmony], vol. I of <tei:title level="s">Neue Musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:title>
     [New Musical Theories and Fantasies] had been published in 1906.</tei:note> zu halten. Wer mich
    kennt, wird gerne bestätigen, daß ich damit durchaus nicht etwa für meine
     <tei:term>Theorie</tei:term>n Propaganda machen möchte u. ich bitte auch die sehr geehrte
    Gesellschaft einem solchen Gedanken gar nicht erst Raum zu geben. Vielmehr erscheint es mir
    unausführbar, Nachweise <tei:hi rend="underline">musikalischer</tei:hi> Natur überhaupt zu
    führen um <tei:pb n="3"/> meine Urteile vor Zuhörern zu begründen, die meiner Terminologie gar
    nicht folgen könnten.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Konkret gesprochen, frage ich die sehr geehrte <tei:rs key="entity-002430"
     type="organization">Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde</tei:rs> an, ob ihr <tei:hi rend="underline"
     >zunächst</tei:hi> Vorlesungen über „<tei:term>Harmonielehre</tei:term>“ willkommen wären. Für
    diesen Fall würde ich solche je 1-mal in der Woche halten, u. zw. so, daß ich eine Stunde den
    Ausführungen selbst widmen, woran sich eine <tei:hi rend="underline">Diskussion</tei:hi> von
    etwa 1/2-stundiger Dauer anschließen würde.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Was das Honorar anbelangt, würde ich für das Musikjahr (Oktober bis <tei:hi
     rend="lateinschr">incl.</tei:hi> Juni) den Betrag von 3000 Fl = 6000 Kr. erbitten.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Einer gefälligen Entscheidung entgegensehend verharre ich</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">in ausgezeichneter Hochachtung</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-40">D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi>
     <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Heinrich
      Schenker</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline><tei:placeName>Wien</tei:placeName>, <tei:date when="1912-06-29">29. Juni
      1912</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">To the Imperial &amp; Royal <tei:rs key="entity-002430"
      type="organization">Society of the Friends of Music</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
      type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>I take the liberty of <tei:hi rend="underline">rendering</tei:hi> my most cordial thanks
    for the honor that the <tei:rs key="entity-002430" type="organization">Society of the Friends of
     Music</tei:rs> accords me by calling upon me to contribute to the fulfillment of the fine new
    task that it has set itself.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Far more even than your first glorious initiative <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
     >is</tei:supplied> a second one belonging to the present day, one that so significantly ushers
    in the second century of your existence, <tei:supplied reason="clarity">which</tei:supplied>
    seems to me to be: to make possible the attainment of that for which <tei:term>music</tei:term>
    in my judgment most pressingly cries out today, namely the greatest possible deepening of the
    specifically musical understanding.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>To be sure, I cannot exactly tell from your esteemed letter<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
     type="footnote"/> whether the planned lectures are intended to have the character of
     highschool<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> lectures. I certainly would wish
    from the bottom of my heart that you will work effectively to counteract the lowering of
    intellectual standards that has been brought about through the countless schools. At last,
     <tei:pb n="2"/> that in which the <tei:hi rend="underline">genius</tei:hi> of our great masters
    is <tei:hi rend="underline">especially</tei:hi> manifested should for once be carried out into
    the farthest circles for their own good. That would in my opinion be the most ideal type of
    "popular lectures."</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">With this, I mean with greatest pleasure to have expressed my readiness to
    make myself available for your plans. I should certainly have liked, in order to recruit friends
    to the new institution, to lecture on currently burning issues in the art-political arena, for
    example, on "Good and Bad in <tei:term>Music</tei:term>," or on "The Immutability of Musical
     <tei:term>Form</tei:term>s," or on "<tei:term>Technique</tei:term> in the
     <tei:term>Symphonies</tei:term> of <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs>,"
    or such like. However, it would be advisable to permit myself to give lectures, <tei:hi
     rend="underline">by way of introduction</tei:hi>, on "<tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:term>theory
      of harmony</tei:term></tei:hi>."<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> Anybody who
    knows me will readily confirm that I would never for a moment wish to make propaganda out of
    this for my <tei:term>theories</tei:term>, and I beg the honored Society not to entertain any
    such thought. What is more, it seems to me impracticable to introduce evidence of a <tei:hi
     rend="underline">musical</tei:hi> nature on <tei:pb n="3"/> which to base my judgments in front
    of an audience that is entirely unable to follow my terminology.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Put in concrete terms, I ask the honored <tei:rs key="entity-002430"
     type="organization">Society of the Friends of Music</tei:rs> whether lectures on
     "<tei:term>Theory of Harmony</tei:term>" would be welcome to it <tei:hi rend="underline">in the
     first instance</tei:hi>. If so, I would lecture once a week, devoting one hour to the lectures
    themselves, to which would be attached perhaps half an hour for <tei:hi rend="underline"
     >discussion</tei:hi>.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">As far as the fee is concerned, I should ask 3,000 Florins = 6,000 Kroner for
    the musical year (October to June inclusive).</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In looking forward to a favorable decision, I remain,</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">In high esteem,</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-40">Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Heinrich
      Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline><tei:placeName>Vienna</tei:placeName>, <tei:date when="1912-06-29">Juni 29,
      1912</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
