<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3509" sdoID="OJ-5-38_56">OJ 5/38, [56]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="LR">
      <tei:persName>Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008423">SchenkerW ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Heinrich to Wilhelm Schenker, dated June 4, 1929</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1929-06-04T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-10-01</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Heinrich offers to have a suit made for Wilhelm; he reports on his latest
        medical tests, which are good; he has closed one of his bank accounts with Mozio, who has
        been slow to release money to him.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000775">Wilhelm Schenker</marcrel:recipient>

    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:date when="1929-06-04">4. 6.
          29</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Mein lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775"
            >Wilhelm</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for June 4, 1929: “An Wilhelm (Br.): biete
            einen Anzug an; über den guten Befund, 0, u. über die Kündigung des Kontos bei Mozio”
            (“To Wilhelm (letter): I offer him a suit; concerning my good state of health, 0[%
            sugar], and about closing my account with Mozio”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Gestern machte <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000053">Jetty</tei:rs> einen Sprung zu
        uns, ich hatte einen Schüler bei mir, also erzählte mir <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000771">LieLiechen</tei:rs> später folgendes: <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-008438">Karli</tei:rs> wäre bei der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000053"
          >Jetty</tei:rs> gewesen u. <tei:add place="interlinear-above">hätte</tei:add> ihr erzählt,
        du wolltest eigens nach Wien wegen eines <tei:hi rend="underline">Anzugs</tei:hi> fahren, du
        könntest dich aber dazu nicht entschließen usw. Ich beeile mich, dir den Antrag zu machen:
        die l. Frau <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008450">Marie</tei:rs> mag ein Maß von dir
        nehmen, es muß ja nicht ganz schneidergerecht sein, u. wir besorgen dir eiligst den Anzug,
        nur mußt du schreiben, <tei:pb n="2"/> ob es ein <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >Sommeranzug</tei:hi> (leicht oder dgl.) sein soll oder ein schwererer? Du ersparst dir
        einen Weg nach Wien, der bei diesen <tei:add place="interlinear-above">Hitze</tei:add>Graden
        nicht erfreulich sein kann, u. uns ist es sehr einfach. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Für dein l. Briefchen u. Beilagen vielen Dank!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker’s diary entry for May 16 records the receipt of a
          cheerful letter from Wilhelm, with enclosures.</tei:note> Denke dir, schon <tei:hi
          rend="underline">zwei</tei:hi> Analysen weisen <tei:hi rend="underline">keinen</tei:hi>
        Zucker (0), <tei:hi rend="underline">keinen</tei:hi> Aceton (0) auf: was sagst du dazu? Die
        zwei Gemüsetage der Woche haben sich sehr bewährt, desgleichen die Verschiebung des
        Mittagstisches von 12<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> auf 1<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
          >h</tei:hi>, dazu u. in erster Linie meines <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
          >LieLiechen</tei:rs>s unerreichte Kochkunst, sie verdiente den Nobelpreis dafür. – Auch
        meine Augen sind besser geworden, wie mir <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006074">Prof.
          Fuchs</tei:rs> Samstag sagte. O! Das war ein Jammer für mich: er befürchtete ein Trübung
        u. befahl, <tei:pb n="3"/>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">die Arbeit einzuschränken</tei:hi>! Nun ist es besser. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich habe <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000324">D<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
            >r.</tei:hi> Halberstam</tei:rs> schon seit Monate – Gott sei Dank – nicht gesehen, weiß
        daher nicht, wo mein Blutdruck hält. Von großer Wichtigkeit wird freilich sein, wie sich der
        l. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs> zu meiner <tei:hi
          rend="underline">Kündigung des Kontos</tei:hi> in diesen Tagen erhalten wird. Eigentlich
        habe ich ihm die Kündigung schon vor 2 Jahren mitgeteilt, habe aber darauf wegen seiner
        Krankheit nicht sogleich bestanden. Nun habe ich ihm Ende 28 ganz bestimmt für <tei:date
          when="1929-06-15"><tei:hi rend="underline">15</tei:hi>.<tei:hi rend="underline"
          >6</tei:hi>./</tei:date> u. <tei:date when="1929-12-15"><tei:hi rend="underline"
            >15</tei:hi>.12/<tei:hi rend="underline">29</tei:hi></tei:date> mein Konto in zwei
        Hälften gekündigt, will ich das Geld, leider, leider, nun selbst wegen verringerter
        Einnahmen brauche. Er aber möchte die Sache gern verzögern, trotzdem ich deutlich mehrmals
        schrieb, daß ich nicht <tei:pb n="4"/> gestatten werde, daß <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000771">LieLiechen</tei:rs> nach meinem Tode ihr eigenes Geld von ihm oder
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003438">Liesl</tei:rs> oder den Kindern in Portionen wie
        50–100 Sch. wie ein Gnadengeschenk bezieht. Nein. Bei der völligen Beziehungslosigkeit
        seiner Familie zu uns, bei dem Undank für die unentgeltliche Unterricht, kann ich nicht
        erlauben, daß mein mit Krankheit erkauftes Ersparnis, das wir doch möglicherweise noch für
        unsere Alterskrankheiten, für die letzten Tage<tei:del rend="overstrike">n</tei:del>
        brauchen werden, in seinem Besitze zurück<tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">lassen</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">bleiben</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>, vielleicht auch noch zum Vorteile seiner <tei:sic>Wittwe</tei:sic> u. seiner
        Kinder, die wir kaum kennen, die nie kommen, nie danken. Ich nehme an, daß <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs> klug genug sein wird, mir den Kummer um
        den Blutdruck zu ersparen, schon aus Dank, wo nicht, müsste ich sofort den <tei:note
          type="editorial" place="inline">in upper margin of p. 4, upside down:</tei:note> Anwalt
        bemühen, wie ich es schon einmal getan, als er der th. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000773">Mutter</tei:rs> zu wenig schickte, weniger als du u. ich.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">See <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-11-26_5">OJ 11/26, [5]</tei:ref>, Max Gross to Moriz Schenker, January 9,
          1914.</tei:note> Bitte <tei:unclear reason="reading">alles</tei:unclear> um das Maß! </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in the upper margin of p. 1, upside
          down:</tei:note> Vielleicht besuchen wir dich heuer wieder! Darüber demnächst noch aus
        Wien.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">left margin, sideways:</tei:note>
          Viele Küße u. Grüße dir u. der l. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008450">Frau
            Marie</tei:rs></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>von mir u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
          >Lieliechen</tei:rs></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Dein</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
          >Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:date when="1929-06-04">June 4,
          1929</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775"
            >Wilhelm</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000053">Jetty</tei:rs> made an excursion to us
        yesterday. I was with a student, so <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
          >LieLiechen</tei:rs> later told me the following. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-008438">Karli</tei:rs> had been at <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000053"
          >Jetty</tei:rs>’s and <tei:add place="interlinear-above">had</tei:add> told her that you
        specifically wanted to drive to Vienna for a <tei:hi rend="underline">suit</tei:hi>, but
        that you couldn’t make up your mind, etc. I hasten to make the proposal to you: <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-008450">Marie</tei:rs> might measure you. It doesn’t have to be
        totally precise for tailoring, and we’ll see to the suit for you as quickly as possible. But
        you have to write <tei:pb n="2"/> whether it should be a <tei:hi rend="underline">summer
          suit</tei:hi> (lightweight or such) or a heavier one? You will save yourself a trip to
        Vienna, which in these <tei:add place="interlinear-above">hot</tei:add> temperatures can’t
        be enjoyable, and it is very simple.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Many thanks for your kind letter and enclosures!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> Just think, <tei:hi rend="underline">two</tei:hi> tests now show <tei:hi
          rend="underline">no</tei:hi> blood sugar (0), <tei:hi rend="underline">no</tei:hi> acetone
        (0). What do you say to that? The two vegetable days per week have proven themselves,
        similarly the shifting of lunch from 12 to 1 o’clock, in addition, and primarily, the
        unmatched culinary art of my <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">LieLiechen</tei:rs>.
        She would merit the Nobel Prize for it. – My eyes, too, have improved, as <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-006074">Professor Fuchs</tei:rs> said on Saturday. Oh! That was
        misery for me: he feared an opacification and ordered <tei:pb n="3"/> a <tei:hi
          rend="underline">restriction on work</tei:hi>! Now, it’s better.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I haven’t seen <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000324">Dr. Halberstam</tei:rs> for
        months – thank God – but don’t know, therefore, what my blood pressure is. It will be of
        great importance how <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs> reacts to my
        recent <tei:hi rend="underline">cancellation of the bank account</tei:hi>. Actually, I
        already notified him about the cancellation two years ago, but because of his illness didn’t
        insist on it. Now, I notified him of splitting my account into two halves very definitely as
        of <tei:date when="1929-06-15"><tei:hi rend="underline">June 15</tei:hi></tei:date> and
          <tei:date when="1929-12-15">December <tei:hi rend="underline">15,
        1929</tei:hi></tei:date>. I need the money now myself, alas and alack, because of reduced
        income. However, he may well delay the matter despite my clearly writing him several times
        that I would not <tei:pb n="4"/> allow after my death that <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000771">LieLiechen</tei:rs> receive her own money from him or <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-003438">Liesl</tei:rs> or from the children in portions of
        50-100 shillings like a gift of grace. No. In light of the complete lack of relationship of
        his family to us, <tei:supplied reason="clarity">and</tei:supplied> of the ingratitude for
        the unremunerated lessons <tei:supplied reason="clarity">for Georg</tei:supplied>, I cannot
        allow my savings, obtained through sickness, which we may well in our final days, possibly
        for illnesses in our old age, <tei:add place="interlinear-above">to remain</tei:add> in his
        possession, perhaps yet even to the advantage of his widow and his children, whom we barely
        know, who never come <tei:supplied reason="clarity">to visit</tei:supplied>, never give
        thanks. I assume that, out of sheer gratitude, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774"
          >Mozio</tei:rs> will be smart enough to spare me the distress over blood pressure if I had
        to immediately engage an <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in upper margin of p. 4,
          upside down:</tei:note> attorney, as I did once already when he sent our beloved <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000773">mother</tei:rs> too little, less than you and I.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> Please, <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear"
          >everything</tei:unclear> in proportion!</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in the upper margin of p. 1, upside
          down:</tei:note> Perhaps we will visit you again this year! More about that soon, while
        I’m still in Vienna.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">left margin, sideways:</tei:note>
          Abundant kisses and greetings to you and dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008450"
            >Marie</tei:rs></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>from me and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
          >Lieliechen</tei:rs></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
          >Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
