<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="1411" sdoID="OJ-5-11_1b">OJ 5/11, [1b]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="major">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="minor">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="CH">
   <tei:persName>Christoph Hust</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2008</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2015</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-06-26" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002728">Furtwängler ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Second draft of a handwritten letter from Schenker to Furtwängler in Jeanette and
    Heinrich Schenker’s hand, dated November 11‒16, 1931</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1931-11-14T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2015-01-21</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description/>
   <dc:subject/>


   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">This second draft includes Heinrich Schenker's
     corrections to his initial dictation, entered on Jeanette's draft copy on November 13‒14. A
     fair copy was subsequently made by Jeanette on November 15‒16 (not known to survive), therefore
     this does not represent the final state of the letter as sent to Furtwängler. For the first
     draft, see <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-11_1a">OJ 5/11, [1a]</tei:ref></tei:note><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
    <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">no address or salutation<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01"
      type="editorial" place="foot">The seven-day-long process of writing this letter is recorded in
      Schenker's diary at OJ 4/5, p. 3676, November 11, 1931: "Nach der Jause diktire ich den ersten
      Teil eines Briefes an Furtwängler." ("After afternoon coffee I dictate the first part of a
      letter to Furtwängler."). — ibid, p. 3677, November 12, 1931: "9‒10<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
       >h</tei:hi>: Brief an Furtwängler zuende diktirt. [...] Lie-Liechen schreibt an dem
      Furtwängler-Brief bis ¼12<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi>" ("9‒10 o'clock: dictating of
      letter to Furtwängler completed. [...] Lie-Liechen works on writing out the Furtwängler letter
      up to a quarter to midnight."). — ibid, November 14, 1931: "Brief-Korrektur beendet."
      ("Correction of letter finished."). ‒ ibid, pp. 3677‒3678 November 15, 1931: "Korrektur des
      Briefes um 11<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> abgeschlossen. [...] Lie-Liechen macht die
      Reinschrift des Furtwängler-Briefes." ("Correction of letter concluded at 11 o'clock. [...]
      Lie-Liechen makes the fair copy of the Furtwängler letter."). — ibid, November 16, 1931:
      "Lie-Liechen schließt den Brief ‒ 18 Seiten." ("Lie-Liechen finishes the letter ‒ 18 pages.").
      — ibid, November 17, 1931: "Postweg (½11‒11<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi>): Furtwängler
      Brief rec. aufgegeben." ("To the Post Office (10.30‒11 o'clock): Furtwängler letter dispatched
      express."). <tei:lb/>This letter-draft is preceded by a small folded piece of paper with the
      following inscription in Heinrich Schenker's hand: "An Furtw. [/] Bf. vom 16–18/11 [/] 1931
      [/] als Antw. auf [/] Bf. Furtw.'s vom 8/11/31" (To Furtwängler [/] letter from November
      16–18, 1931 [/] as answer to [/] Furtwängler's letter of November 8,
     1931").</tei:note></tei:note><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>Das Zeichen Ihrer freundlichen Teilnahme hat mich
    sehr erfreut. Ich bin im Sommer der Weisung der Aerzte gefolgt, die mir eine Schonung der Augen
    streng abforderten. Mein Kampf um die „<tei:title>Eroica</tei:title>“<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The essay <tei:bibl><tei:title level="a"
       >Beethovens Dritte Sinfonie zum erstenmal in ihrem wahren Inhalt dargestellt,</tei:title>
      <tei:title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:title>, vol. III (Munich: Drei Masken
      Verlag, 1930), pp. 25–101 and graphs; Eng. transl. by <tei:editor>Derrick Puffett</tei:editor>
      and <tei:editor>Alfred Clayton</tei:editor> in <tei:title level="j">The Masterwork in
       Music</tei:title>, vol. III (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1997; New York: Dover
      Publications, 2014), pp. 10–68 and graphs</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> war meinerseits etwas zu
    heroisch geführt worden. zeitlich! Ich durfte nur sehr wenig schreiben u. lesen: so schwer dies
    gerade mir fiel, der seit dem 13. Lebensjahr keine Arbeits-Pause kannte, ich hielt mich an das
    Verbot u. seh mich durch die Wiederherstellung der Augen zur Genüge belohnt. (Noch immer ist
    Vorsicht am Platze.)</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Die Erfolge unseres l.<tei:supplied reason="abbreviation"
     >ieben</tei:supplied> D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi>
    <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs> übertreffen wirklich alle Erwartung.
    Noch knapp vor seiner Abreise sprach er einmal in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place"
     >Wien</tei:rs> im „<tei:rs key="entity-002445" type="organization">musikpädagogischen
     Verband</tei:rs>“, begeisterte die „Kollegen“ <tei:pb n="2"/> ohne sie dorthin fortreissen zu
    können, wo er sie in ihrem eigenen Interesse gern hätte haben mögen. Mit blendendem Erfolg
    sprach dann <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs> auch in <tei:rs
     key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> im Konzerthaus.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
     type="editorial" place="foot">The lecture, given at the invitation of Moriz Violin on September
     16, 1931, is reported in Weisse's letter to Schenker of September 5, 1931 (OJ 15/16, [81]). The
     title of the lecture was to be "<tei:title level="u">Hörendes Schaffen – schaffendes Hören,
      Versuch einer Würdigung des Grundgedanken in H. Schenkers Werk</tei:title>" ("Hearing
     Creativity – Creative Hearing: Attempt at an Appreciation of the Fundamental Thought of H.
     Schenker’s Work").</tei:note> Zum Beweis des Erfolges in <tei:rs key="entity-002589"
     type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> lege ich hier das <tei:hi rend="underline">Referat</tei:hi> von
     <tei:rs key="entity-000737" type="person"><tei:hi rend="underline">H. Roth</tei:hi></tei:rs>
    bei, der bei den „<tei:rs key="entity-002547" type="journal"><tei:title>Hamburger
      Nachrichten</tei:title></tei:rs>“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot"
     >The article in question was presumably <tei:bibl><tei:author>Herman Roth</tei:author>,
       <tei:title level="a">Bekenntnis zu Heinrich Schenker,</tei:title>
      <tei:title level="j">Hamburger Nachrichten</tei:title>, September 17, 1931</tei:bibl>, a
     clipping of which is preserved in Schenker’s scrapbook at OC 2/p. 84. </tei:note> an die Stelle
    von Prof. Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000671" type="person">Pfohl</tei:rs> gekommen ist, weil ich
    mich zu erinnern glaube, daß Sie <tei:rs key="entity-000737" type="person">R.</tei:rs> von
     <tei:rs key="entity-002286" type="place">München</tei:rs> her kennen.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich halte es <tei:rs key="entity-000737" type="person">R.</tei:rs> sehr
    zugute, daß er nach vieljähriger Pause sich wieder, wie ehedem, freundlich zu meiner Sache
    stellte. Nur die Entgleisung zum Schluss des Aufsatzes, wo auch er mißverstehend von einer
    „Abstraktion“ spricht, mußte ich richtig stellen in einem Briefe an ihn. Es ist mir wirklich
    unerfindlich, <tei:pb n="3"/> wie Musiker, die Beweise meines gesund denkenden Kopfes in Händen
    haben, mir eine solche „Abstraktion“ unterstellen können! Nie u. nirgend<tei:supplied
     rend="abbreviation">s</tei:supplied> habe ich gesagt, alles gute Komponieren gehe immer vom
     <tei:term>Ursatz</tei:term> u. seinem <tei:term>Terz</tei:term>-, <tei:term>Quint</tei:term>-
    oder <tei:term>Oktavzug</tei:term> aus, pflanze sich dann durch die
     <tei:term>Diminution</tei:term>en der <tei:term>Schicht</tei:term>en so lange fort, bis man z.
    B. eine neue – „<tei:title>Eroica</tei:title>“ in der Hand hält! So ist es nicht. Das Bild des
     <tei:term>Ursatz</tei:term>es u. der <tei:term>Schicht</tei:term>en, das ich biete, stellt nur
    die Logik im <tei:term>Zusammenhang</tei:term> eines <tei:term>Inhalt</tei:term>es dar, wobei es
    völlig gleichgiltig ist, ob die Betrachtung vom Einfachsten <tei:pb n="4"/> im
     <tei:term>Hintergrund</tei:term> zum Buntesten im <tei:term>Vordergrund</tei:term> oder
    umgekehrt vom Buntesten im <tei:term>Vordergrund</tei:term> zum Einfachsten im
     <tei:term>Hintergrund</tei:term> sich bewegt. Das sagt zugleich, daß im
     <tei:term>Vordergrund</tei:term> immer u. überall der <tei:term>Hintergrund</tei:term>
    gegenwärtig ist, d. h. daß mit dem <tei:term>Vordergrund</tei:term> auch der
     <tei:term>Hintergrund</tei:term> mitgeht.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ein Anderes aber ist das „Chronologische“ <tei:pb n="5"/> im wirklichen
    Schaffen. Dieses geht a<tei:supplied reason="agreement">n</tei:supplied> jenem „logischen“ Bande
    durchaus nicht so einher wie das Bild den Mißverstehenden es zu sagen scheint. Die Fantasie des
    Komponisten entzündet sich vielmehr bei <tei:term>improvisatorisch</tei:term>er Begabung
    geheimnisvoll <tei:sic>an</tei:sic> irgend einem Wurf; dieser sei beliebig, wie er wolle,
    entscheidend ist nur, daß, sobald ein Wachstum sich zu regen beginnt, das Werdende sich in eben
    jene „Logik“ fügt, die mein das(?) Bild festhält: Es ist, als komponirte sich ein Meisterwerk in
    die <tei:term>Terz</tei:term>-, <tei:term>Quint</tei:term>- oder <tei:term>Oktavräume</tei:term>
    selbst hinein! Künstler der Sprache können übrigens diesen Vorgang auch aus ihrem Schaffen
    bestätigen. Auch sie hantieren <tei:pb n="6"/>r mit einem gewissen Etwas, das den
     <tei:term>Vordergrund</tei:term> mit einfachster Grundlegung wachsen läßt. Dieses Gefühl ist
    nun gewiß keine „Abstraktion“, wenn es sich in der Komposition so real äußert.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Das Unvermögen der Heutigen zu einem wahren Meisterwerk erklärt sich
    geschichtlich gerade dadurch, daß sie jenes Etwas eingebüßt haben. Durch zunehmende Beteiligung,
    durch Betrieb, wie vor allem durch falschen Unterricht wurde das ehedem sehr gepflegte
     <tei:term>Improvisatorisch</tei:term>e abgetötet, <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"
     >cued from <tei:pb n="6"/>v:</tei:note>das wie spielend die Hauptarbeit im Schaffen leistete u.
    dem Komponisten sozusagen die Mühe des Zusammenklaubens von Teilchen ersparte: notgedrungen
    beschränkte man sich daher in der Folge der Zeiten<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end
     cue</tei:note> auf Erfindung von kurzen „<tei:term>Motiv</tei:term>en“ – die Meister wissen von
     <tei:term>Motiv</tei:term>en solcher Art nichts – die man dann erst durch mechanische
     Wh.<tei:supplied reason="abbreviation"><tei:term>Wiederholung</tei:term>en</tei:supplied>
    strekte, in <tei:term>Vergrößerung</tei:term>, <tei:term>Verkleinerung</tei:term>,
     <tei:term>Umkehrung</tei:term> usw. zu „verarbeiten“ sich bemühte. <tei:pb n="7"/>r Ueber
    dieser öden Mechanik verlor sich der Blick für größere <tei:term>Zusammenhänge</tei:term>, im
    eigenen Schaffen wie leider auch für solche, die schon in den Meisterwerke<tei:supplied
     reason="syntax">n</tei:supplied> niedergelegt sind!</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">cued from <tei:pb n="7"
     />v:</tei:note>Nun zurück zu <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs>s
    Erfolgen. In <tei:rs key="entity-002873" type="place">New-York</tei:rs> gelang es ihm binnen
    Stunden die gesamte Lehrerschaft des <tei:rs key="entity-002454" type="organization"
     >Mannes-Konservatorium</tei:rs>s für sich u. meine Sache zu gewinnen: alle Lehrer, voran der
    vorherige Theorie-Professor der Anstalt,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial"
     place="foot">Presumably Leopold Mannes, son of the <tei:rs key="entity-002454"
      type="organization">Mannes School</tei:rs>'s co-founders, David and Clara Mannes.</tei:note>
    arbeiten sich in regelmäßigen Stunden unter seiner Leitung in die neue
     <tei:term>Lehre</tei:term> ein. Auch Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000939" type="person"
     >Wedge</tei:rs>, der Leiter des „<tei:rs key="entity-002437" type="organization">inst. for
     musical art</tei:rs>,“ der schon früher nach meinen Büchern lehrte, näherte sich ihm. Ich darf
    nun sagen, daß solcherart sich in <tei:rs key="entity-002510" type="place"><tei:country><tei:hi
       rend="lateinschr">U. S. A.</tei:hi></tei:country></tei:rs> „Schenker-Institute“ aufgetan
    haben (als erstes ist das in <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> zur auf
    die Welt gekommen).<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end cue</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ihrer Meinung, es sei mit der „modernen“ Musik zuende pflichte ich bei
    (kennen Sie vielleicht den Aufsatz von <tei:rs key="entity-002793" type="person"
     >Strawinsky</tei:rs> in der <tei:title>Baseler National Zeitung</tei:title>
    <tei:date when="1931-11-03">3. XI. 31</tei:date>?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial"
     place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Igor Stravinsky</tei:author>, <tei:title level="a">Moderne
       Musikauffassung,</tei:title>
      <tei:title level="j">National-Zeitung</tei:title> (Basel), November 3, 1931</tei:bibl>, a
     clipping of which is preserved as OC C/205.</tei:note>), u. da bin ich denn bei Ihren im Sommer
    u. Herbst in der <tei:rs key="entity-002559" type="journal"><tei:title>N. Fr.
     Presse</tei:title></tei:rs> veröffentlichten Aufsätzen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07"
     type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Wilhelm Furtwängler</tei:author>,
       <tei:title level="a">Der verkannte Wagner</tei:title> and <tei:title level="a">Die
       Lebenskraft der Musik,</tei:title>
      <tei:title level="j">Neue Freie Presse</tei:title>, November ?? and ??,
     1931</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> Herzlichst freut mich, daß Sie sich entschlossen haben, Ihre Fahne
    hoch zu schwingen u. den verworrenen <tei:pb n="8"/>r Musikern und Freunden der Musik Wege zu
    weisen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ihr Ruf zu <tei:rs key="entity-000924" type="person"><tei:hi rend="underline"
      >Wagner</tei:hi></tei:rs> ist wirklich zeitgemäß. Gewiß darf u. muß auch gegen diesen
    Riesengeist von der höheren Warte der noch größeren Meister der instrumentalen
     <tei:term>Tonkunst</tei:term> aus dies im Ernst gesagt werden: daß
     „<tei:term>Leitmotiv</tei:term>“ = „<tei:term>Motiv</tei:term>“ s. ob. <tei:note
     type="editorial" place="inline">cued from <tei:pb n="8"/>v:</tei:note>So z. B. kehren die
    Nachteile einer „<tei:term>Motiv</tei:term>“-Technik, s. o., auch bei seiner
     „<tei:term>Leitmotiv</tei:term>“-Technik wieder, sie arbeiten jeglicher
     <tei:term>Synthese</tei:term> entgegen, sogar der <tei:term>Synthese</tei:term> eines
    „Musikdrama“! (Fast dürfte man in <tei:rs key="entity-000924" type="person">Wagner</tei:rs>’s
     „<tei:term>Leitmotiv</tei:term>en“ eine Vorausnahme der heute im Film so überschwenglich
    gebrauchten Einschaltungen von Erinnerungsbilder sehen.) Doch alles dies kommt<tei:note
     type="editorial" place="inline">end cue</tei:note> der heutigen Generation gegenüber gar nicht
    in Frage, denn auch Seinesgleichen hat es nur einmal gegeben, wird es nie wieder in
     <tei:country>Deutschland</tei:country> geben! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In <tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"><tei:rs
       key="entity-003691" type="person">Verdi</tei:rs>'s</tei:hi></tei:hi> Gesamtwerk wüßte ich
    nicht 8 Takte, von denen ein Aufhebens zu machen wäre, wie dies etwa bei <tei:rs
     key="entity-000833" type="person">Smetana</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000181" type="person"
     >Dvořak</tei:rs> u. a. immerhin möglich ist. Für den banalen
    „<tei:term>Melodie</tei:term>“-Appetit von <tei:rs key="entity-000958" type="person"
     >Werfel</tei:rs> u. Genossen reicht er gerade noch hin, nichts mehr. <tei:pb n="9"/> Was die
    frühesten Italiener schrieben, konnte sogar noch unseren Meistern zugute kommen, <tei:rs
     key="entity-003691" type="person">Verdi</tei:rs> dagegen ist ohne Kunstwert. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Daß die Musikgemeinschaft in Auflösung begriffen ist, haben Sie (wie auch
     <tei:rs key="entity-000393" type="person">Hubermann</tei:rs>) endlich in aller Oeffentlichkeit
    festgestellt. Auch haben Sie die Ursache davon, soweit sie im Rundfunk- u. Schallplattenwesen u.
    ä. zu suchen ist, ganz vortrefflich herausgearbeitet.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Eine noch wichtigere Ursache aber scheint mir in der nun 200 Jahre währenden
    allgemeinen Beziehungslosigkeit zur Produktion unserer grossen Meister zu liegen. Bis zur
     <tei:pb n="10"/> Heraufkunft eines <tei:rs key="entity-000329" type="person">Händel</tei:rs>,
     <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person">Bach</tei:rs> brauchte es Jahrhunderte Musik!
    Unmöglich hätten diese beiden Genies schon z. B. im 3. oder 4. Jhrh. unserer Zeitrechnung
    erscheinen können. Erst mußte in der Übung der Kunst das Gefühl für die
     <tei:term>Züge</tei:term> erstarken, damit sie ihnen die immer größere
     <tei:term>Diminution</tei:term>sfracht aufladen konnten. Dazu kam die erhebende Kraft des neuen
    Glaubens, dem man gar nicht genug mit ehrlichster Kunst dienen konnte!</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Heute aber! Da ist vor allem der schwere Irrtum, der allein schon wider
    jegliches Talent der heutigen Generation zeugt: diese hält nämlich ein Genie der Vergangenheit
    grundsätzlich für einen verlorenen Posten der Geschichte, statt es als einen immer auch für die
    Zukunft giltigen Wert, als ein unwandelbares <tei:hi rend="underline">Ziel</tei:hi> zu
    verstehen. Ein Religions-Genie wie Moses ist wahrhaftig nicht <tei:pb n="11"/> tot, wenn noch
    heute in seinem Namen Millionen orthodoxer Juden gegen eine Welt zusammenstehen. Kein Zweifel,
    daß die Juden ihre Bibel gründlich mißverstanden haben – von diesem Mißverständnis wollte sie
    eben Jesus befreien – u. doch: <tei:hi rend="underline">Selbst der Irrtum</tei:hi>, durch den
    sie an Mose gekettet waren u. sind, geriet u. gerät ihnen noch zum Heile – so stark ist der
    Segen eines Genies! (Deswegen setzte ich hier dieses Beispiel an erster Stelle.)</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ist Jesus etwa überholbar? Bleibt er den Menschen nicht ein Ziel auch in
    fernster Zukunft? Ist Plato überholbar? Was immer die Zeiten den Genies an Substrat nehmen
    mögen, in ihrem Werk bleibt ein Göttliches übrig, das jeder Zeit spottet! Von diesem göttlich
    Unzerstörbaren eben ahnt die Welt noch gar nichts! Mir ist kein Zweifel, daß den Deutschen
     <tei:pb n="12"/> in künftigen Jahrhunderten nichts übrigbleiben wird, als ihre großen
    Musik-Genies mit göttlichen Ehren zu pflegen, genau wie die Juden mit dem Alten Testament durch
    die Zeiten wandern. Wie widerspricht dem aber das Treiben der heutigen deutschen Welt namentlich
    in so devot amerikanisierenden Städten! Von Jahr zu Jahr werden neue Genies ausgerufen, denen
    man dadurch Platz zu machen sucht, daß man die Alten als überholt erklärt u. gewaltsam ins
    Ausgedinge schickt – nun Sie wissen das alles ja auch – –</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Unbeantwortet blieb bis heute aber die Frage: was nun? Was soll u. darf,
    nachdem die „moderne“ Musik abgewirtschaftet hat, in dem Vacuum, dem ersten der Musikgeschichte
    überhaupt, geschehen? <tei:pb n="13"/> Geschieht nichts – bald wird ja auch wirklich nichts mehr
    geschehen können –, so ist der völlige Untergang der Musik besiegelt. Daß ein Volk von der
    Geniekraft der Deutschen binnen wenigen Jahren seine größten musikalischen Geister buchstäblich
    hinausgeworfen hat, ist umso unbegreiflicher, als es schon von seinem materiellen Instinkt aus
    (vom geistigen gar nicht zu sprechen) bei so großer materieller Not sich auf den beispiellosen
     <tei:hi rend="underline">Geldwert</tei:hi> der Meisterliteratur – u. Pflege hätte besinnen
    müssen!! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich wage zu behaupten, daß sämtliche Industrien der Welt der deutschen
    Genie-Industrie nicht gleichkommen. Weiß man das, so muß man auch diese Industrie wieder
    sanieren, wie man heute Banken u. allen Geldwert saniert! Den „Kredit“ – ich fahre fort, die
    Ausdrücke der Geldzeit anzupassen –, den deutsche <tei:pb n="14"/> Musik bisher in aller Welt
    genossen hat, darf doch nicht das deutsche Volk selbst untergraben. Es hat die Pflicht, zur
    Größe jener Geist-Währung mit allen Kräften zu stehen. Kann das aber noch geschehen? Ich sage:
    Ja! Nur dürfen darüber nicht die ? - Menschen entscheiden, die von all den Dingen nichts
    wissen.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">So z. B. wäre nichts einfacher, als schon in den untersten Schulklassen mit
    dem Hören-Lehren von <tei:term>Terz</tei:term>-, <tei:term>Quart</tei:term>-,
     <tei:term>Oktavzüge</tei:term>n in den Volksliedern, Choralmelodien, in den kleinen Uebungen,
    in <tei:rs key="entity-005568" type="person">Dussek</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000135"
     type="person">Clementi</tei:rs> u. a. zu beginnen. Dies käme erst <tei:pb n="15"/> dem
    Verfahren gleich, wie in den Schulen die Sprache auf grammatische Begriffe u. Zusammenhänge
    gestellt wird. Tausende Kinder, die sonst der Musik verloren gehen, könnten ihr neu gewonnen
    werden u. den Kunst-Humus<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker
     uses the concept of "humus" to mean the necessary large quantity or number out of which the few
     arise, notably in <tei:bibl><tei:title level="a">Von der Sendung des deutschen
       Genies,</tei:title>
      <tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title>, Heft 1 (1921), pp. 3–21; Eng. transl. by
       <tei:editor>Ian Bent</tei:editor> (New York: Oxford University Press, 2014), pp.
      3–20</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> bilden, den Sie suchen. Wäre Musik nicht eben diese ärmste u. am
    meisten mißverstandene aller Künste, vogelfrei für jedermann, glauben Sie, daß ich nicht schon
    längst vom <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs>er oder <tei:rs
     key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs>er Ministerium zu Rate gezogen worden wäre?
    Schließlich bin ich, wofür mein Lebenswerk zeugt, doch einer von den wenigen <tei:rs
     key="entity-003130" type="person">Morgan</tei:rs>s<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09"
     type="editorial" place="foot">Allusion to John Pierpont Morgan, Jr. (1867–1943), American
     financier, son of the investment banker, art collector, philanthropist, and contributor to the
     New York Metropolitan Museum of Art John Pierpont Morgan, Sr. (1837–1913); creator in 1924 of
     the Pierpont Morgan Library in New York in memory of his father and to house the latter’s
     library and collection, and philanthropist in his own right. This is part of the larger
     financial metaphor that Schenker is creating in this section of the letter.</tei:note> in der
    heutigen Musik – zieht man <tei:rs key="entity-003130" type="person">Morgan</tei:rs> nicht zu
    Rate in allen Nöten? Warum ist <tei:hi rend="underline">Der</tei:hi> oder Jener zu feig, mich um
    Rat zu fragen, fürchten sie, daß ich ihnen etwas zumute, was <tei:pb n="16"/> sie
    überschreitet?</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Kurz: Alle Praktiken, mit denen man den Banken aufzuhelfen sucht, müßten auch
    für die Musik gelten. Den „Amstelbänklern“ müßte schließlich das Handwerk gelegt werden! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Für <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> im besonderen
    wüßte ich eine glänzende Sa- nierung (auch ohne <tei:rs key="entity-002590" type="place"
     >Genf</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-002693" type="place">Basel</tei:rs>, <tei:rs
     key="entity-002477" type="place">Paris</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10" type="editorial"
     place="foot">The allusion of all three locations is perhaps to Stravinsky; alternatively,
     Schenker might perhaps mean: Geneva = Stravinsky; Basel = Paul Sacher?; Paris = Debussy and
     others.</tei:note>). Ich habe den Vorschlag schon oft vorgebracht (im <tei:rs
     key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
     >Tonw</tei:hi>.</tei:title></tei:rs>, vor <tei:rs key="entity-000328" type="person"
     >Hammerschlag</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11" type="editorial" place="foot">Perhaps János
     Hammerschlag (1885–1954), Hungarian composer, music critic, and pioneering early music
     specialist, who founded the chamber music ensemble Musik der Vergangenheit in 1923, and taught
     composition, music history and organ at the National Conservatory in Budapest.</tei:note> u.
    A.): Statt sich ver- zweifelt z. B. an irgendeinen Todestag zu klammern, wäre es selbst für eine
    Fremdenverkehrsindustrie viel ergiebiger, <tei:pb n="17"/>r wenn <tei:rs key="entity-002484"
     type="place">Wien</tei:rs> nach <tei:rs key="entity-003993" type="place">Bayreut</tei:rs>er
    Muster ein „Festspielhaus“ für seine Musik-Götter auferbaute, in dem alljährlich ein erlesenes,
    aus den besten Instrumentalisten der Welt gebildetes Orchester in <tei:hi rend="underline"
     >kanonischer Weise</tei:hi> ihre großen Schöpfungen darböte. Einer wie Sie sollte die Reihe
    eröffnen u. für den Nachwuchs sorgen, so daß die Tradition in die Zeiten fortwirkte! In aller
    Welt wüßte man dann: Nur in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> könne man die
    Meisterwerke am besten hören! <tei:rs key="entity-002578" type="place">Salzburg</tei:rs>
    behielte seine eigene <tei:rs key="entity-000612" type="person">Mozart</tei:rs>-Note, die es
    dann gar nicht mehr zu verfälschen brauchte.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Und noch manchen anderen Weg gäbe es, die Musik zu sanieren! <tei:note
     type="editorial" place="inline">cued from <tei:pb n="17"/>v:</tei:note>Ausgemacht ist nur: Wie
    die Geldkalamitäten wieder nur durch Geld saniert werden können, so eine Musikkalamität wieder
    nur durch Musik. (Homöopathische Kuren!). Kein Paneuropa, keine Politik, – nur die <tei:foreign
     xml:lang="lat"><tei:hi rend="underline">restitutio</tei:hi> in <tei:hi rend="underline"
      >integrum</tei:hi></tei:foreign><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12" type="editorial" place="foot"
      ><tei:hi rend="italic">restitutio in integrum</tei:hi>: legal term (shades of Schenker's legal
     training), the restoration of something to its previous (or original) condition, a principle of
     Roman Law enshrined in the <tei:title level="m">Corpus Juris Civilis</tei:title> (Justinian I,
     529–34), one of the primary guiding principles behind the awarding of damages in common law
     negligence claims. </tei:note>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">unser<tei:supplied reason="syntax">er</tei:supplied></tei:hi> großen
    Kunst kann helfen!<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end cue</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="18"/> Haben Sie gehört, daß man z. B. einen gotischen Dom wegen
    heute geänderter Auffassung in religiösen oder baulichen Sachen in eine „moderne“ Kirche umbauen
    wollte? Noch zeugt jeder stolze gotische Dom für die Vergangenheit wie nicht minder auch für die
    Gegenwart – mit welchem Rechte wagen sich Auffassungen ändernd, fälschend an die gotischen Dome
    in der Musik?! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Versäumen Sie mich nicht zu verständigen, wenn Sie
    einmal in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs>Wien sind! Dann reden wir weiter
    über diesen Stoff.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute>Ihnen u Ihrer Fr. <tei:rs key="entity-003001" type="person"
     >Gemahlin</tei:rs></tei:salute>
    <tei:salute>herzlichste Grüße von uns Beiden</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60">
     <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">H Sch</tei:hi><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13" type="editorial"
      place="foot">The first dictated draft concludes with a note from Jeanette Schenker, omitted
      here: "Meiner Auffassung nach hätte ich das auch morgen schreiben können, statt heute bis in
      die späte Nacht [/] Deine Lie-Lie!" ("By my calculation, I would have been able to do this
      tomorrow instead of today into the late hours. [/] Your Lie-Lie!"). </tei:note>
    </tei:signed>
    <tei:date when="1931-11-13"><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>13.<tei:handShift new="#HS"/> XI.
      <tei:handShift new="#JS"/>31</tei:date>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">This second draft includes Heinrich Schenker's
     corrections to his initial dictation, entered on Jeanette's draft copy on November 13‒14. A
     fair copy was subsequently made by Jeanette on November 15‒16 (not known to survive), therefore
     this does not represent the final state of the letter as sent to Furtwängler. For the first
     draft, see <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-11_1a">OJ 5/11, [1a]</tei:ref></tei:note><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
    <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">no address or salutation<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
      type="footnote"/></tei:note><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
   </tei:opener>


   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>Your gesture of kind sympathy gave me great
    pleasure. This summer, I followed the instructions of my doctors, who strenuously demanded that
    I give my eyes a rest. My battle over the "<tei:title>Eroica</tei:title>"<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> had been waged rather too heroically on my part.
    Insufficient time! I was to do only very little writing and reading, no matter how hard this was
    for me, as someone who has experienced no let-up in work since my thirteenth year of life. I
    held myself to this injunction, and see myself amply rewarded by the restoration of my eyesight.
    (There is still room for caution.)</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Our dear Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs>’s
    successes really do exceed all expectations. Even just immediately before his departure, he
    spoke once in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs> at the <tei:rs
     key="entity-002445" type="organization">Music Pedagogical Association</tei:rs> and enthused his
    colleagues, <tei:pb n="2"/> without being able to carry them off as he would have liked, for
    their own sakes, to be able to do. <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs>
    then also spoke in the concert hall in <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>
    with dazzling success.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> As evidence of his
    success in <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> I am enclosing herewith a
     <tei:hi rend="underline">review</tei:hi> by <tei:rs key="entity-000737" type="person"><tei:hi
      rend="underline">Herman Roth</tei:hi></tei:rs>, who has taken over <tei:rs key="entity-000671"
     type="person">Pfohl</tei:rs>'s place at the <tei:rs key="entity-002547" type="journal"
      ><tei:title level="j">Hamburger Nachrichten</tei:title></tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> because I seem to recall that you have been acquainted
    with <tei:rs key="entity-000737" type="person">Roth</tei:rs> since <tei:rs key="entity-002286"
     type="place">Munich</tei:rs> days. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I very much give <tei:rs key="entity-000737" type="person">Roth</tei:rs>
    credit that after a lull of so many years he has, as in former times, very agreeably become
    active once again in my cause. Only the gaffe at the end of the article, where even he speaks
    erroneously of an "abstraction," obliged me to write him a letter setting him straight. It is
    really incomprehensible to me <tei:pb n="3"/> how musicians with the examples of my right
    thinking available to them can attribute such "abstraction" to me! Never and nowhere have I ever
    said that all good composing always takes the <tei:term>Ursatz</tei:term> and its
     <tei:term>3rd</tei:term>-, <tei:term>5th</tei:term>- or
     <tei:term>octave</tei:term>-<tei:term>progression</tei:term> as its point of departure, and
    that it then continues to propagate itself through the <tei:term>diminution</tei:term>s of the
     <tei:term>layer</tei:term>s until, hey presto!, you finish up with, e.g., a new
     <tei:title>"Eroica</tei:title>"! That is not the way it is. The image of the
     <tei:term>Ursatz</tei:term> and its <tei:term>layer</tei:term>s that I offer has its logic only
    in the <tei:term>connection</tei:term> to a <tei:term>content</tei:term>, whereby it is
    completely immaterial whether one views it as moving from the simplest thing <tei:pb n="4"/> in
    the <tei:term>background</tei:term> to the most colorful thing in the
     <tei:term>foreground</tei:term>, or conversely from the most colorful in the
     <tei:term>foreground</tei:term> to the simplest in the <tei:term>background</tei:term>. That
    indicates at the same time that the <tei:term>background</tei:term> is present always and
    everywhere in the <tei:term>foreground</tei:term>, i.e. the <tei:term>background</tei:term>
    proceeds always in tandem with the <tei:term>foreground</tei:term>.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">But the "chronological dimension" of <tei:pb n="5"/> actual creation is quite
    another matter. This absolutely does not comply with that "logical" progression as fully as the
    image in the mind of the person who has misunderstood it seems to say. Rather, in the context of
    a gift for <tei:term>improvisation</tei:term>, the composer's imagination is secretly set on
    fire by some kind of sweeping intuitive move. The latter can be whatever he wishes; the only
    crucial thing is that at the very moment a growth process gets underway, what is burgeoning
    submits itself to that selfsame "logic" that adheres to my image: It is as if a masterwork
    composed itself into the <tei:term>space</tei:term>s of <tei:term>3rd</tei:term>,
     <tei:term>5th</tei:term>, or <tei:term>octave</tei:term>! Artists who work with language can
    also confirm this process from their own creative activity. They, too, operate <tei:pb n="6"/>r
    with a certain something that causes the <tei:term>foreground</tei:term> to grow in conformity
    with the simplest foundation. This feeling is definitively no "abstraction," if it expresses
    itself in tangible form in the composition.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">The incapacity of today's composers to <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
     >create</tei:supplied> a true masterwork can be explained in historical terms precisely in that
    they have lost that "something." Through increasing complicity, through commercialization, and
    above all through false teaching, the <tei:term>improvisatory</tei:term> impulse, hitherto
    greatly cherished, has been killed off, <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">cued from
      <tei:pb n="6"/>v:</tei:note>that impulse which bears as if effortlessly the brunt of the work
    of creation, and spares the composer, so to speak, the labor of combining the small components.
    Perforce, he confined himself accordingly within the temporal dimension<tei:note
     type="editorial" place="inline">end cue</tei:note> to inventing short
     "<tei:term>motive</tei:term>s" ‒ the master composers know nothing of this sort of
     <tei:term>motive</tei:term> ‒ which he then for the first time extended by means of mechancial
     <tei:term>repetition</tei:term> occupying himself with "fashioning" through
     <tei:term>augmentation</tei:term>, <tei:term>diminution</tei:term>,
     <tei:term>inversion</tei:term>, etc. <tei:pb n="7"/>r With this dreary mechanical working, the
    eye for the larger-scale <tei:term>interconnection</tei:term>s was lost, in his own creativity
    as sadly also for such <tei:supplied reason="clarity">interconnections</tei:supplied> that are
    inscribed in the masterworks!</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">cued from <tei:pb n="7"
     />v:</tei:note>Now back to <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs>'s
    successes. In <tei:rs key="entity-002873" type="place">New York</tei:rs>, he managed in no time
    at all to win over the entire teaching faculty of the <tei:rs key="entity-002454"
     type="organization">Mannes Conservatory</tei:rs> to his way of thinking and to my cause. All
    the teachers, most notably the previous theory professor in the post,<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> are familiarizing themselves with the new
     <tei:term>theory</tei:term> in regular lessons under his direction. Even Mr. <tei:rs
     key="entity-000939" type="person">Wedge</tei:rs>, the Director of the <tei:rs
     key="entity-002437" type="organization">Institute for Musical Art</tei:rs>, who was teaching
    according to my books at an even earlier stage, has allied himself with him. I venture now to
    say that a "Schenker Institute" like that in <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place"
     >Hamburg</tei:rs> (which was the first of its kind in the world) has been opened in the <tei:rs
     key="entity-002510" type="place"><tei:country>USA</tei:country></tei:rs>.<tei:note
     type="editorial" place="inline">end cue</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I endorse your opinion that all is up with modern music (are you perhaps
    familiar with the article by <tei:rs key="entity-002793" type="person">Stravinsky</tei:rs> in
    the <tei:title level="j">Baseler National Zeitung</tei:title> of <tei:date when="1931-11-03"
     >November 3, 1931</tei:date>?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/>), and thus the
    articles that you published during the summer and fall in the <tei:rs key="entity-002559"
     type="journal"><tei:title level="j">Neue Freie Presse</tei:title></tei:rs>.<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> It gladdens my heart that you have after all resolved
    to pin your colors to the mast and show confused <tei:pb n="8"/>r musicians and friends the way
    of music.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Your call to <tei:rs key="entity-000924" type="person"><tei:hi
      rend="underline">Wagner</tei:hi></tei:rs> is really in keeping with the times. Certainly it
    ought to and must be stated in criticism of this giant spirit from the loftier vantage-point of
    the yet greater masters of instrumental <tei:term>music</tei:term> in all seriousness that
     "<tei:term>Leitmotive</tei:term>" = "<tei:term>motive</tei:term>," see above. <tei:note
     type="editorial" place="inline">cued from <tei:pb n="8"/>v:</tei:note>Thus, for example, the
    disadvantages of a <tei:term>motive</tei:term>-based technique (see above) recur also in his
     <tei:term>Leitmotive</tei:term> technique. <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
     >Leitmotives</tei:supplied> work counter to any <tei:term>synthesis</tei:term>, even the
     <tei:term>synthesis</tei:term> of a "music drama"! (One might almost see in Wagner's
     <tei:term>Leitmotive</tei:term>s an anticipation of the flashbacks used in film so copiously
    these days.) But none of this enters the heads<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end
     cue</tei:note> of today's generation, for even in his own day it <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
     >i.e. <tei:rs key="entity-000924" type="person">Wagner</tei:rs>’s work</tei:supplied> was given
    only once and will never be given again in <tei:country>Germany</tei:country>.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In <tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:rs key="entity-003691" type="person"
      >Verdi</tei:rs>'s</tei:hi> entire output, I would not know eight measures that I would like to
    make a fuss about ‒ just as continues to be possible perhaps in <tei:rs key="entity-000833"
     type="person">Smetana</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000181" type="person">Dvořák</tei:rs>, and
    others. Still today he barely satisfies the banal appetite for "<tei:term>melody</tei:term>" of
     <tei:rs key="entity-000958" type="person">Werfel</tei:rs> and his comrades. <tei:pb n="9"/>
    What the earliest Italian composers wrote still benefitted even our masters, whereas <tei:rs
     key="entity-003691" type="person">Verdi</tei:rs> is by contrast of no artistic value. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">You yourself (as also <tei:rs key="entity-000393" type="person"
     >Hubermann</tei:rs>) have finally declared in the full blaze of publicity that the musical
    community is in the process of disintegration. You have also quite excellently adduced the cause
    of that, insofar as it is to be sought in the nature of radio and recordings.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">But an even more important cause seems to me to lie in the lack of
    relationship to the production of our great masters that has been going on now for 200 years.
    Centuries of music <tei:pb n="10"/> were required before the emergence of <tei:rs
     key="entity-000329" type="person">Handel</tei:rs> and <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person"
     >Bach</tei:rs>! It would have been impossible for these two geniuses to appear, for example, as
    early as the third or fourth century of our era. The feeling for the <tei:term>linear
     progression</tei:term>s had first to gain strength in the practice of the art, in order that
    they could shoulder the even greater freights of <tei:term>diminution</tei:term>. Thereafter,
    the new belief for the first time attained its edifying full power ‒ the belief to which people
    just could not pay sufficient service with the most noble art!</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">But today! There, above all, lies the grievous error, which in itself alone
    testifies against any talent whatsoever on the part of today's younger generation: the latter
    considers a genius from the past as fundamentally a long-lost entry in the leger of history
    instead of understanding it as something also enduringly valid for the future, as an immutable
     <tei:hi rend="underline">goal</tei:hi> to strive for. A genius from the world of religion such
    as Moses is truly not <tei:pb n="11"/> dead when still today in his name millions of orthodox
    Jews stand fast against a whole world. There is no doubt that the Jews fundamentally
    misunderstand the Bible ‒ this is exactly the misunderstanding from which Jesus wanted to free
    them ‒ and yet, <tei:hi rend="underline">the error itself</tei:hi>, through which they are
    chained to Moses, redounded ‒ and still redounds ‒ to their benefit. That is how strong the
    blessing of a genius is! (This is why I place this example first here.)</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Is it possible for Jesus to be surpassed? Does he not remain the goal of all
    men, even into the remotest future? Is it possible for Plato to be surpassed? However much
    successive ages may take of these geniuses' substrate, there remains in their work a godlike
    element that disdains each age! Of this godlike indestructibility the world has not the remotest
    inkling! I am in no doubt whatsoever that there will be nothing left for Germans <tei:pb n="12"
    /> in future centuries to do other than to cherish the musical geniuses with exactly that
    godlike honor with which the Jews wander through the ages with the Old Testament. But how the
    pursuits of today's German world contradict that, especially in the so assiduously Americanized
    cities! From year to year, new geniuses are proclaimed, for whom people try to make room so that
    the old geniuses can be declared superannuated and packed off into retirement. — But then, you
    know all this, too ...</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">What remains unanswered to this day, however, is the question: What now? What
    should and ought to happen now that "modern" music has been ruinously mismanaged, in the vacuum,
    the first such ever in the history of music? <tei:pb n="13"/> If nothing happens ‒ soon it will
    not be possible for anything to happen at all ‒ the total extinction of music will be sealed.
    That a people of the power of genius of the Germans has literally within the space of a few
    years discarded its greatest musical spirits is all the more inconceivable since it, out of
    material (to say nothing whatsoever of spiritual) instinct, and overtaken by such great material
    need, ought already to have contemplated the unparalleled <tei:hi rend="underline">monetary
     value</tei:hi> of the master-repertory – and cultivation!!</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I dare to assert that all the industries in the world do not compare with the
    German industry of genius. Once that is recognized, then this industy, too, must again be
    recapitalized, just as banks and other monetary values are being recapitalized today! It is
    imperative that the German people do not themselves undermine the "credit" ‒ I make progress in
    adapting to the expressions of the monetary era ‒ which German <tei:pb n="14"/> music has
    enjoyed throughout the world up to now. They have the duty to stand up with all their might for
    the greatness of that spiritual currency. But is there still any possibility of this happening?
    I say: Yes! Only it must not be the ? ‒ people who make the decisions on this, for they know
    nothing about these matters.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">So, for example, nothing would be simpler than to begin as early as the
    lowest school classes with teaching and listening for <tei:term>3rd</tei:term>-,
     <tei:term>4th</tei:term>-, and <tei:term>octave-progression</tei:term>s in folksong, chorale
    melodies, in small exercises ‒ <tei:rs key="entity-005568" type="person">Dussek</tei:rs>,
     <tei:rs key="entity-000135" type="person">Clementi</tei:rs>, and others. <tei:pb n="15"/> This
    would equate with the method whereby language is taught in schools on the basis of grammatical
    concepts and relationships. Thousands of children, who are otherwise lost to music, could be won
    over anew to it in this way and form the artistic humus<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08"
     type="footnote"/> that you, too, obviously seek. If music were not simply the poorest and most
    misunderstood of all the arts, outlawed for everyone, do you not think that I might long ago
    have been called upon by the <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs> or <tei:rs
     key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs> Ministry as a consultant? After all, I am, as
    my life's work attests, one of the very few <tei:rs key="entity-003130" type="person"
     >Morgan</tei:rs>s<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09" type="footnote"/> in today’s music ‒ does one
    not consult <tei:rs key="entity-003130" type="person">Morgan</tei:rs>s in all times of need? Why
    is <tei:hi rend="underline">this</tei:hi> or that person too cowardly to seek advice from me;
    are they afraid that I might demand something of them that <tei:pb n="16"/> they could not
    fulfill?</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In short, all practices that seek to help out the banks ought to be valid
    also for music. A stop must at last be put to the "Amstelbank" people! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">For <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs> in particular I
    would have in mind a glittering recapitalization, without <tei:rs key="entity-002590"
     type="place">Geneva</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-002693" type="place">Basel</tei:rs>, or
     <tei:rs key="entity-002477" type="place">Paris</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn10"
     type="footnote"/> I have often put my suggestion forward in the past (in <tei:rs
     key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>, before
     <tei:rs key="entity-000328" type="person">Hammerschlag</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn11"
     type="footnote"/> and others). Instead of clinging desperately, for example, to some particular
    death date, it would be far more profitable, even for the foreign tourist industry, <tei:pb
     n="17"/>r if <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs> were to build a "Festival
    Playhouse" for its musical gods along the lines of <tei:rs key="entity-003993" type="place"
     >Bayreuth</tei:rs> in which, annually, a hand-picked orchestra made up of the best
    instrumentalists in the world were to present their great works in <tei:hi rend="underline"
     >canonical fashion</tei:hi>. One such as yourself ought to open the series and take care of its
    subsequent growth, so that the tradition would continue to be effective over time! People
    throughout the world would then know: only in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place"
     >Vienna</tei:rs> can one hear the masterworks to best advantage! <tei:rs key="entity-002578"
     type="place">Salzburg</tei:rs> would retain its own particular <tei:rs key="entity-000612"
     type="person">Mozart</tei:rs>ian character, which it would no longer ever need to
    falsify.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">And there would still be many another way of recapitalizing music! <tei:note
     type="editorial" place="inline">cued from <tei:pb n="17"/>v:</tei:note>What has to be made
    clear is this: just as monetary calamities can be recapitalized only through money, so also a
    musical calamity can be recapitalized through music. (Homeopathic cures!) No Pan-Europe, no
    politics ‒ only the <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat"><tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="underline"
       >restitutio</tei:hi> in <tei:hi rend="underline"
     >integrum</tei:hi></tei:hi></tei:foreign><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn12" type="footnote"/> of
     <tei:hi rend="underline">our</tei:hi> great art can help!<tei:note type="editorial"
     place="inline">end cue</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="18"/> Have you heard that, for example, people wanted to convert a
    Gothic cathedral into a "modern" church because today's interpretation of religious or
    architectural matters has changed? Every proud Gothic cathedral stands as a witness for the
    past, and no less also for its own time. What right do interpretations, changing, falsifying,
    have to tinker with the Gothic cathedrals of Music?!</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Do not neglect to let me know whenever you are in
     <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>! Then we can talk more about this
    matter.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute>To you and your <tei:rs key="entity-003001" type="person"
     >wife</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute>Most cordial greetings from us both,</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Yours,</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60">H. Schenker<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn13" type="footnote"
     /></tei:signed>
    <tei:date when="1931-11-13">November <tei:handShift new="#JS"/>13, 1931</tei:date>
   </tei:closer>


  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
