<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID=" 286" sdoID="OJ-5-18-2">OJ 5/18, 2</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="JR-HE">
   <tei:persName>John Rothgeb &amp; Heribert Esser</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006, 2011</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2006, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-02-09" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002713">Jonas ~ H+JSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002714">Jonas ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   
   
   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated November 26, 1930</dc:title>
   
   <dcterms:created>1930-11-26T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-04-21</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Having misread Jonas in OJ 12/6, [4] as requesting a letter of recommendation to
    Furtwängler, Schenker declines to provide such a letter. Letters of thanks to Schenker from
    other Berlin musicians have not led to more solid connections. Most musicians have not dared to
    take a position publicly on Schenker's teaching.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000412">Jonas</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:note type="authorial"><tei:note type="editorial">written in crayon, in top-left corner of
      p.1</tei:note>2)</tei:note>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10"><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>Sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000412">Doktor</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Daß<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is
     recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/4, pp. 3546-3547, November 26, 1930: "An Jonas (Br.):
     "verweigere eine Empfehlung! Kenne den Inhalt seines Vortrags nicht, insbesondere weiß ich
     nicht, was ich mir unter „ Ausgangspunkt“ zu denken habe; vielleicht stimmt er nicht mit mir,
     ich nicht mit ihm überein, - für keinen Fall darf Furtwängler überlaufen werden. Es rächt sich
     übrigens das bisherige Verhalten von nah u. fern, so daß es mir unmöglich ist, jemand in den
     Betrieb hineinzuhelfen." ("To Jonas (letter): I decline to write a recommendation! I do not
     know the content of his lecture; in particular, I do not know what I am to make of his taking
     me as "point of departure"; maybe he disagrees with me, conversely I with him. – Under no
     circumstances is Furtwängler to be badgered. The pity is that behavior up to now from far and
     near makes it impossible for me to help anyone get into the music trade.").</tei:note> ich
    gleich beginne damit, was Sie gewiß am meisten interessiert: <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">See OJ 12/6, [4], November 17, 1930, para. 3, for the request to
     which this letter is a response.</tei:note> zu schreiben, wäre, richtiger: ist derzeit eine
    Unmöglichkeit für mich. Er hat sich so für <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs> eingesetzt, hat so viel Verdruß wegen
      <tei:persName><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Riezler</tei:hi></tei:persName>s'<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Walter Riezler (1878-1965), German
     musicologist. He had just written a dismissive article "Die Urlinie," in <tei:title level="j">Die Musik</tei:title> xxii/7 (April 1930) which bore a dedication to Furtwängler. See OJ
     12/6, [16].</tei:note> gehabt, hat <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">einen</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">den</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> Aufsatz eines Schülers von mir zu lesen gekriegt, na - ich meine,
     <tei:persName>F.</tei:persName> hat das Recht, <tei:add place="interlinear-above">von
     mir</tei:add> auf lange hinaus in Ruhe gelassen zu werden.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Andere Musiker in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>, meist
    Professoren, schreiben mir Briefe des Dankes, aber festere Beziehungen haben sich nicht
    herausgebildet. <tei:pb n="2"/> Es dürfte wohl so sein, daß ich <tei:del rend="overstrike">zunächst</tei:del> den älteren u. hervorragendsten Musikern <tei:add place="interlinear-above">dort</tei:add> zumindest dem Namen nach bekannt bin - meiner Erfahrung nach wird zuweilen
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">absichtlich, gegen den Tatbestand</tei:add> auch das
    geleugnet -, aber zu einem Recht, an sie zu schreiben, reicht das nicht aus.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Zu alledem kommt noch, daß ich mir kein Bild vom Inhalt Ihrer Vorträge machen kann. Wohin
    hat Sie (in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002286">München</tei:rs>) der weitere Weg von dem
    (in meiner Person) erwähnten „Ausgangspunkt“ geführt? Es könnte ja sein, daß Sie mir in der
    Folge nicht zustimmen, anderseits ich Ihnen nicht zustimme, da könnte eine Empfehlung von mir
     <tei:pb n="3"/> erheiternd wirken . . .</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Es rächt sich zur Zeit eben, daß - bis auf wenige Einzelne, die für mich eintreten, vor
    allem bis auf mich selbst, der wohl am wirksamsten für meine Lehre eintrat – die übrigen
    Musiker, nah u. fern, keine Stellung öffentlich zu nehmen wagten. Ich stand niemals im Betrieb,
    stehe auch heute nicht drin, müssen da nicht Musiker, die Broterwerb suchen, sich <tei:del rend="overstrike">nicht</tei:del> lieber von vornherein an solche Musiker wenden, die ihnen aus
    dem Betrieb heraus <tei:add place="interlinear-above">u. in den Betrieb hinein</tei:add> helfen
    könnten? (ich entschuldige sie Alle). Nun ist es aber, wie es ist, wie <tei:pb n="4"/> es kommen
    mußte, u. ich kann nur herzlich bedauern, Ihnen den erbetenen Dienst nicht leisten zu
    können.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr sehr ergebener</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-30"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1930-11-26">26. 11. 30</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:note type="authorial"><tei:note type="editorial">written in crayon</tei:note>2)</tei:note>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:note type="authorial"><tei:note type="editorial">written in crayon, in top-left corner of
      p.1</tei:note>2)</tei:note>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10"><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000412">Doctor</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>To<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> begin at once with the matter that is
    certainly of greatest interest to you: to write <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> would be – more
    exactly: is – at present an impossibility for me. He has done so much for <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs>, has had so much aggravation because of
     <tei:persName>Riezler</tei:persName>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> has
    received <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">an</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">the</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> essay by a student of mine to read, well – I think,
     <tei:persName>Furtwängler</tei:persName> is entitled to be left in peace <tei:add place="interlinear-above">by me</tei:add> for a good while. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Other musicians in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>, mostly
    professors, write letters of thanks to me, but more solid connections have not developed
    therefrom. <tei:pb n="2"/> It may be true that I am known at least by name to the older and most
    prominent musicians <tei:add place="interlinear-above">there</tei:add> – in my experience even
    that sometimes, <tei:add place="interlinear-above">intentionally and contrary to the facts of
     the case</tei:add>, is denied – but that is not sufficient to give license to write to
    them.</tei:p>

   <tei:p> There is the further consideration that I cannot form a picture of the content of your
    lectures. Where exactly have you been led (in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002286">Munich</tei:rs>) by the path from the "point of departure" mentioned (in my person)? It
    may well be that, later on, you don't agree with me, or on the other hand that I don't agree
    with you; in that case a recommendation from me could <tei:pb n="3"/> seem laughable. .
    .</tei:p>

   <tei:p>The pity just now is that – except for few individuals who support me, above all except
    for myself, as no doubt the most active proponent of my teaching – the other musicians, near and
    far, dared take no position publicly. I have never been in the music-trade, am no more in it
    today; mustn't the musicians who try to earn a living prefer from the outset to turn to those
    musicians who could help them <tei:hi rend="italic">from</tei:hi> the music-trade <tei:add place="interlinear-above">to find a way <tei:hi rend="italic">into</tei:hi> it</tei:add>? (I
    excuse them all.) But things are as they are, <tei:pb n="4"/> and as they had to be, and I can
    only sincerely regret that I am unable to provide the service you request.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Yours most sincerely,</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-30">H. Schenker</tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1930-11-26">November 26, 1930</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:note type="authorial"><tei:note type="editorial">written in crayon</tei:note>2)</tei:note>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>