<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="3408" sdoID="OJ-5-38_4">OJ 5/38, [4]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="LR">
   <tei:persName>Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
   <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
   <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008423">SchenkerW ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Heinrich to Wilhelm Schenker, dated August 18, 1923</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1823-08-18T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-06-07</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker writes a letter of condolence, in response to the news that his brother
    Wilhelm’s wife Dodi has died. He hopes to visit Wilhelm, and to visit their mother’s
    grave.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>
    
    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
    <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000775">Wilhelm Schenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener rend="indent-10"><tei:handShift new="#HS:"/>Mein lieber <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000775">Wilhelm</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
     place="foot">Writing of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for August 18, 1923: “An
     Wilhelm (Br.): über Undank der Kinder; verspreche unsern Besuch u. lade ihn ein, Gruß an den
     Oberinspektor.” (“To Wilhelm (letter): about the thanklessness of the children; promise a visit
     from us and invite him, greetings to the Chief Inspector.”).</tei:note></tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Wir danken dir herzlichst für deinen l. Brief.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
     type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker’s diary entry for August 6 records the receipt of a
     letter from Wilhelm: “Von Wilhelm (Br.): stellt die Mutter-Tragödie <tei:rs type="person"
      key="entity-000767">Dodi</tei:rs>–<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000895">Tonschl</tei:rs>
     dar u. den gegenwärtigen Zustand; hat offenbar ein starkes Gefühl des Dankes für die Verewigte,
     die ohne Zweifel das Entscheidende für seine Berufsausbildung u. den spätern Wohlstand
     beigetragen.” (“From Wilhelm (letter): describes the maternal tragedy <tei:rs type="person"
      key="entity-000767">Dodi</tei:rs>–<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000895">Tonschl</tei:rs>
     and the current state of affairs; he apparently has a strong feeling of gratitude for the
     deceased, who doubtless made the critical contribution to his career training and his later
     wealth.”) — Wilhelm’s wife, Dodi, had died July c.10, 1923.</tei:note> Mehr weniger erfahren
    alle Väter u. Mütter ihrer Kinder Undank, u. doch sage ich, der Undank an sich ist so traurig
    nicht, viel trauriger ist das völlige Unbewußtsein, wogegen es eben, in deiner Sprache zu reden,
    keine Therapie gibt: die Kinder begehen ihre Rohheiten u. wissen nicht einmal, daß es welche
    sind, sind auch jeder Belehrung unzugänglich. Daher ist zwischen Eltern u. Kindern Alles
    hoffnungslos. Und doch muß gelebt werden, u. die Verewigte hatte, auch trotz dem Abfall des
    Sohnes, <tei:hi rend="underline">Pflicht</tei:hi> zum Leben! Wohin käme die Welt, wenn die
    Eltern über jedem Undank der Kinder stürben! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="indent-10">So Manches bleibt uns unklar, so z. B. weshalb <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000895">Tonschl</tei:rs> nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002510"
     >Amerika</tei:rs> gehen mußte? Hat er sein Kapital völlig eingebüßt? Hat er denn nicht einen
    lohnenden Beruf? Ist die klavierspielende (nebbich!), französischbrechende (nebbich)<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">“nebbich”: Yiddish word meaning “dull,”
     “apathetic,” “meek,” “ineffectual.” — It is unclear who the second wife referred to here is: it
     may refer to a second wife of Tonschl, but there is no evidence that such a person
     existed.</tei:note> zweite Frau eine Rabenmutter oder wolltet am Ende <tei:pb n="2"/> Ihr
    selbst die Kinder lieber bei Euch haben? </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Vielleicht gelingt es uns, im September nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002323"
     >Waidhofen</tei:rs> zu fahren, um das Grab der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000773"
     >Mutter</tei:rs> u. den Grabstein zu sehen, dann würden wir auch einen Sprung zu dir machen,
    wenn das überhaupt verkehrstechnisch möglich ist. Jedenfalls werden wir uns bestreben, dich im
    Laufe der kommenden Monate zu besuchen, irgend im Fluge, an einem Feiertag. Das Meiste hängt ja
    von den Bahnverbindungen ab u. ob sich zwei Betten für eine Nacht in deinem Orte fänden. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Bei dieser Gelegenheit erneuern wir auch die Bitte, uns einmal, wenn dich irgendetwas nach
    Wien führt, in der <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002826">Keilgasse</tei:rs> 8, Th. 12 (III
    Bez.) zu besuchen. Du kannst auch bei uns gut essen, dich ausruhen u.s.w. Seinerzeit habe ich
    durch <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000895">Tonschl-Vater</tei:rs> dich eingeladen, später
    mehrere Male durch <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003491">Tonschl-Sohn</tei:rs>, doch weiß
    ich nicht, ob sie dir etwas gesagt haben. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich will dich nicht, als abgesagten Feind von Briefen, <tei:del rend="overstrike"
     >nicht</tei:del> länger aufhalten. Wir wünschen dir Beide Kraft, die neue Lage zu tragen u. zu
    bewältigen, sie führt dich <tei:pb n="3"/> denn auch zur Befriedigung, soweit das eine bieten
    kann. Von uns lieber mündlich, bei Dir oder bei uns. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Herzlichste Grüße von mir u. <tei:rs type="person"
      key="entity-000771">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs></tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-70">dein</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>, <tei:date
      when="1923-08-18">18. August 1923</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p>Die alte <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000773">Excellenz</tei:rs> bitten wir
     ebenfalls untertänig – herzlich zu grüßen, falls er (was ich bezweifle) noch bei Dir weilen
     sollte. Wüßte ichs genau, ich schriebe ihm mehr. </tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>



  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener rend="indent-10"><tei:handShift new="#HS:"/>My dear <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000775">Wilhelm</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"
    /></tei:opener>

   <tei:p>We thank you most cordially for your kind letter.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
     type="footnote"/> All fathers and mothers experience ingratitude from their children, more or
    less, and yet I say ingratitude itself is not so sorrowful, much more sorrowful is the total
    lack of awareness against which, in your lingo, there is simply no therapy: children commit
    their acts of crudeness and don’t even know that these are crude; they are also impervious to
    all admonition. Between parents and children everything is thus hopeless. And yet life must be
    lived; and, despite the fall of the son, the deceased woman had the <tei:hi rend="underline"
     >obligation</tei:hi> to live! What would the world come to if the parents were to die from
    every ingratitude of children!</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="indent-10">Various things remain unclear to us, for example why <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000895">Tonschl</tei:rs> had to go to <tei:rs type="place"
     key="entity-002510">America</tei:rs>? Did he have to completely forfeit his capital? Doesn’t he
    have a remunerative profession? Is the piano-playing (nebbish), French-vomiting
     (nebbish)<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> second wife an uncaring mother or, in
    the end, <tei:pb n="2"/> did you yourselves prefer to have the children with you?</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Perhaps we will be able to travel to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002323"
     >Waidhofen</tei:rs> in September to see <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000773"
     >Mother</tei:rs>’s grave and gravestone, then we would make the side trip to you, if that is
    even logistically possible. We will in any case try to visit you in the course of the coming
    months, somehow fleetingly, on a holiday. It of course depends mostly on the rail connections,
    and on whether two beds for one night are to be found at your location.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>At this opportunity, we also renew the request to visit us at <tei:rs type="place"
     key="entity-002826">Keilgasse</tei:rs> 8, apartment 12 (third district) if something takes you
    to Vienna. You can also eat well with us, rest up, etc. At the time, I invited you through
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000895">Tonschl-the-father</tei:rs>, later several times
    through <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003491">Tonschl-the-son</tei:rs>, but I don’t know
    whether they said anything to you.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>I don’t want to detain you, as a declared enemy of letters, any longer. We both wish you
    strength to bear and successfully manage the new situation, also that it leads you <tei:pb n="3"
    /> to satisfaction, so far as it can offer any. <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
     >More</tei:supplied> from us preferably in person, at your place or ours.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Most cordial greetings from me and <tei:rs type="person"
      key="entity-000771">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs></tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-70">your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>, <tei:date
      when="1923-08-18">August 18, 1923</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p>Likewise, we request, subserviently, to greet his old <tei:rs type="person"
      key="entity-000773">Excellency</tei:rs>, should he still be staying with you (which I doubt).
     If I knew for sure, I would write more to him.</tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>

 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
