<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="3415" sdoID="OJ-5-38_45">OJ 5/38, [45]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="LR">
   <tei:persName>Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
   <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
   <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008423">SchenkerW ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Heinrich to Wilhelm Schenker, dated May 29, 1924</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1924-05-29T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-06-10</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker, on hearing the news that Wilhelm’s adoptive son Tonschl had died, sends
    his condolences and urges his brother to spend two weeks with him and Jeanette in the
    Tyrol.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>

   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000775">Wilhelm Schenker</marcrel:recipient>

  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">



   <tei:opener rend="indent-10"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Mein Lieber <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000775">Wilhelm</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
     place="foot">Writing of this letter is not recorded in Schenker’s
    diary.</tei:note></tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Wieder hat dich ein schwerer Schicksalsschlag heimgesucht, so wider alles menschliche
    Erwarten! Der Partezettel<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Heinrich’s
     diary for May 24, 1924 records: “Parte von Tonschl trifft ein! Ich nehme im ersten Augenblick
     einen Selbstmord an.” (“Death notice of Tonschl arrives! Instantly I assume suicide.”). — That
     for May 26 records: “Mozio erscheint knapp vor 6<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi>;
     bestätigt die Angaben des Partezettels als wahrheitsgemäß.” (“Mozio turns up shortly before
     6:00; confirms the particulars of the death notice as being true.”). There is no reference to
     the funeral in Heinrich’s diary, nor can the death notice or obituary be traced.</tei:note> ist
    uns, weil er falsch adressiert war, <tei:del rend="overstrike">uns</tei:del> zu spät zugekommen
    u. lange hegte ich den Verdacht, daß der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000895">arme
     Mensch</tei:rs> Hand an sich gelegt hat, bis mir der l. <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs> den wahren Sachverhalt erzählt hat. Von ihm haben wir auch
    erfahren, wie du dir beiläufig die Neuordnung denkst, daß du die Kleinen<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"> i. e. Tonschl’s two sons, <tei:rs
      type="person" key="entity-003491">Tonerl</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person"
      key="entity-008438">Karli</tei:rs> Schimatowitsch.</tei:note> zu dir nimmst u.s.w. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Es wird kaum durchzuführen sein, daß wir jetzt, noch vor unserer Sommerreise,
    zu dir hinauskommen, zumal wir gern ein paar <tei:pb n="2"/> Tage, nicht blos paar Stunden, bei
    dir bleiben möchten. Ich habe noch für die Druckerei eine große Arbeit zu leisten, die mir ein
    längeres Fernbleiben von Wien nicht möglich macht. Wohl aber wollen wir auf der Heimreise, statt
    gleich nach Wien zu fahren, bei dir eintreten, so <tei:hi rend="underline">Ende August oder
     Anfang September</tei:hi> u. bei dir noch ein paar Tage verbringen. Auch meint der <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000051">Oberinspektor</tei:rs>, daß dies die schönste Zeit bei Euch
    ist. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Und noch einmal wiederhole ich den Rat, die Bitte, fahre mit uns für 1–2 Wochen nach
     <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002334">Tirol</tei:rs> (Ende Juni, Anfang Juli). Du wirst dich
    gut erholen, eine schöne, neue Welt <tei:pb n="3"/> sehen, was dir für den ganzen Winter
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">Ersche</tei:del> Erfrischung bieten wird. Du kommst nach Wien u. wir
    steigen zu dritt hier ein u. fahren. Wir führen dich in die schönsten Gegenden. Sei doch so lieb
    u. fahre mit. Du wirst es nicht bereuen. Jedenfalls schreibe uns ein paar Zeilen darüber.
    Befolge unseren Rat, komm mit. In 14 Tagen bist du wieder zu Hause, höchstens haben deine
    Patienten 14 Tage länger, um im Sinn deiner Spieße zu sprechen. Wir vermuten ein <tei:hi
     rend="underline">Ja</tei:hi>! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs> u. ich grüßen
    dich aufs herzlichste! </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-80">Dein</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs
      type="person" key="entity-000771">Lie Lie</tei:rs></tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1924-05-29">29. V. 1924</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer><tei:lb/>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p>An Spieß schrieb ich, habe aber keine Antwort.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04"
      type="editorial" place="foot">In his postcard of May 12, Schenker had asked Wilhelm for the
      name and address of a gardener who might have been able to make a border around their mother’s
      grave. Heinrich’s diary for May 17, 1924 records: “An Spieß (K.): bestelle die Grabeinfassung
      u. Epheu.” (“To Spieß (postcard): order the grave bordering and ivy.”).</tei:note></tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>



  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener rend="indent-10"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>My dear <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000775">Wilhelm</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"
    /></tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Again, a heavy stroke of fate has befallen you, against all human expectation! The
     obituary<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> reached us too late because it was
    incorrectly addressed, and for a long time I suspected that the <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000895">poor fellow</tei:rs> took his own life, until dear <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs> related the true circumstances. We also found out from him
    how, in passing, you conceive of the rearrangement of taking in the little ones,<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> etc.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">It will hardly be possible for us to get out to you before our summer trip,
    particularly because we would like to spend a few <tei:pb n="2"/> days with you, not just a few
    hours. I still have a lot of work to do for the printer, which makes an extended absence from
    Vienna impossible for me. However, we do want to stop at your place on the way home instead of
    traveling directly to Vienna, and spend, say, a few days with you at the <tei:hi
     rend="underline">end of August or beginning of September</tei:hi>. The <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000051">Chief Inspector</tei:rs> also thinks that this is the nicest time where you
    are.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>And again I repeat the advice, the request, that you come with us to the <tei:rs
     type="place" key="entity-002334">Tyrol</tei:rs> for one or two weeks (end of June, beginning of
    July). You would have a good rest, <tei:pb n="3"/> see a lovely, new world, which would refresh
    you for the entire winter. Come to Vienna and the three of us will board here and travel
    together. We would take you to the loveliest areas. Be a good sport and go with us. You won’t
    regret it. In any case, write us few lines about it. You’ll be home in two weeks, at most your
    patients will have two weeks longer to wait, to put things into your perspective. We expect you
    to say <tei:hi rend="underline">Yes</tei:hi>!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Lie-Liechen and I send most cordial greetings,</tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-80">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs> and <tei:rs
      type="person" key="entity-000771">Lie Lie</tei:rs></tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1924-05-29">May 29, 1924</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer><tei:lb/>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p>I wrote to Spieß,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> but have had no
     answer.</tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>

 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
