<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3424" sdoID="OJ-5-38_18">OJ 5/38, [18]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="LR">
      <tei:persName>Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008423">SchenkerW ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Heinrich to Wilhelm Schenker, dated June 13, 1925</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1925-06-13T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-06-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Heinrich explains his not having written to his brother for some time; he has
        had difficulties with both his old and new publishers [Universal Edition and Drei Masken
        Verlag]. He urges Wilhelm to visit them in Vienna, and to join them in the Tyrol in the
        summer. </dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>
      
      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000775">Wilhelm Schenker</marcrel:recipient>
      
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Mein lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775"
            >Wilhelm</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for June 13, 1925: “An Wilhelm (Br.): wann
            er hierher kommt; vom Jahrbuch; Einladung nach Tirol.” (“To Wilhelm (letter): When is he
            coming here? About the Yearbook; invitation to Tyrol.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Dein Name auf dem Zettel, nebst, richtiger vor vielen anderen Namen, mahnte mich seit
        Monaten. Ich konnte nicht schreiben, nach keiner Richtung sie Antwort geben: ich hatte ein
        großes Werk nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002286">München</tei:rs> abzuliefern u.
        konnte nicht aufschauen, ein Werk von <tei:hi rend="underline">250 Druckseiten</tei:hi> vom
          <tei:date when="1925-02-27">27/II</tei:date> bis <tei:date when="1925-06-30">Ende
          Juni</tei:date> fertigstellen!!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >i.e. <tei:bibl><tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001750"><tei:title level="j">Das
                Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:title>, vol. I</tei:rs> (Munich: Drei Masken Verlag,
            1925)</tei:bibl>, delivered to the publisher on June 3, 1925, released on June 21,
          1926.</tei:note> Wir sind <tei:del rend="overstrike">schon</tei:del> gestern
        fertiggeworden u. <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ich</tei:add> schreibe schon heute. 4
        Mill. erhalte ich gleich, weitere 4 Mill. bei Ausgabe des Werkes, u. wenn es geht, erhalte
        ich noch Tantièmen, aber da spießt es sich. Die Menschen klagen, daß ich so schwer schreibe,
        u. darum nehme ich von den Werken rein gar nichts ein. Was ist denn das auch. 8 Mill. für so
        ein <tei:pb n="2"/> Buch? Was auch 12 Mill? Darum müß ich mich noch immer an die Stunden
        halten, obschon ich meines Ansehens halber längst keine mehr geben dürfte. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>In meinen Verhandlungen mit dem <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408"
          >früheren Verlag</tei:rs>, dem ich wegen seiner ständigen Betrügereien einfach
        durchgegangen bin, schien es eine Weile – zu den Arbeiten am Werk kamen noch die Laufereien
        zum Advokaten hin, zahllose 2–3 stündige Konferenzen; zahllose Briefe! – als würde ich eine
          <tei:hi rend="underline">Ablöse</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">sämtlicher</tei:hi> Werken durchsetzen können. Der Anwalt nannte
          <tei:hi rend="underline">500 Mill</tei:hi>. u. war bereit, auch weniger für mich zu
        nehmen. Ich habe mich schon im Herzen gefreut, einmal ein paar Schüler wegzugeben, die mir
        nicht zu Gesicht stehen, die ich nur, weil ich muß, unterrichte. Aber vorläufig ist wieder
        nichts mit der Ablöse, u. ich muß die Betrügereien hinnehmen: mein Anwalt <tei:pb n="3"/>
        ist ein „Lemach“,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:hi
            rend="italic">Lamech</tei:hi>, which Schenker writes as <tei:hi rend="italic"
            >Lemach</tei:hi> (Hebrew): the Biblical character Lamech, descendant from Cain, who was
          a polygamist and murderer. The name is usually associated with persons of low standing,
          but why Schenker is using it here is unclear: he may be referring to Lamech’s blindness in
          later years, or that his ancestor (Cain) was unwittingly killed by an arrow shot from his
          bow.</tei:note> dazu noch feig, ein alter Freund von mir, da geht es eben nicht anders;
        neulich hat er mir sogar einen Schaden gemacht, das erzählte ich dir einmal, du wirst lachen
        wie über einen guten Witz. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Nun aber, wann bringst du <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008438"
          >Karli</tei:rs> her? Wir reisen am <tei:date when="1925-06-26">26. Juni</tei:date> wieder
        nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>. Wir schmachten nach Luft,
        denn während der Arbeit sind wir tagelang vom Frühling, von der Luft überhaupt abgeschnitten
        gewesen. Bringst Du also <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008438">Karli</tei:rs>, bevor wir
        reisen? Oder ist die Schule noch nicht aus? Was dann? Weißt Du, wohin Du mit ihm zu gehen
        hast, wenn wir nicht da wären? Erinnerst du dich der Strasse? </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000052">Heini</tei:rs> weiß ich, dass der alte
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000051">Oberinspektor</tei:rs> bei dir war, ist er jetzt
        noch bei dir? Dann grüße ihn herzlichst von mir u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
          >LieLiechen</tei:rs>. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich gebe die Hoffnung nicht auf, dass <tei:pb n="4"/> wir dich einmal nach <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002334">Tirol</tei:rs> bringen, heuer ist für dich die <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-008438">Karli</tei:rs>-Frage noch zu lösen, ich muß den Ausgang
        der Verhandlungen abwarten. Wenn der Augenblick halbwegs günstig ist, <tei:hi
          rend="underline">mußt</tei:hi> Du mit uns fahren, ich werde keine Ruhe geben, bis Du mit
        uns diese großen Freuden teilen wirst, selbstverständlich als unser Gast. <tei:hi
          rend="underline">Schreibe</tei:hi>, wie es Dir geht, ob Du bald nach Wien kommst? Du mußt
        bei uns essen, wenn du kommst. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs>, die alle die Monate
        sich die Finger zerschrieiben, das Gehirn zerdenkt hat, muß<tei:del rend="overstrike"
          >t</tei:del> jetzt die Vorbereitungen für den Sommer treffen, auch eine harte Sache. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Schreibe also:</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Wir küssen dich innigst u. grüßen dich </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>Dein</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="20"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000771">Lie-Lie</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1925-06-13">13. Juni 1925</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775"
            >Wilhelm</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Your name on the slip of paper, next to, more correctly ahead of, other names, has been
        calling out to me for months. I couldn’t write, could not answer along any line: I had to
        submit a large project to <tei:rs key="entity-002286">Munich</tei:rs> and couldn’t envision
        completing a work of <tei:hi rend="underline">250 printed pages</tei:hi> between <tei:date
          when="1925-02-27">February 27</tei:date> and the <tei:date when="1925-06-30">end of
          June</tei:date>!!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> Yesterday <tei:del
          rend="overstrike">already</tei:del> we finished and <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >I</tei:add> am already writing today. I am getting 4 million up front, an additional 4
        million upon publication of the work; and if things work out, I will also get royalties.
        However, that’s where it gets jammed up. People complain that I write in such a difficult
        way, and for that reason I get nothing at all. And what is that, then, 8 million for such a
          <tei:pb n="2"/> book; what would even 12 million be? I therefore have to keep up the
        lessons, although in my view I should long since not have to give them any longer.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In my negotiations with the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">previous
          publisher</tei:rs>, from whom I have simply bolted on account of his cheating – in
        addition to the efforts on the project, there was the running to the attorney, countless
        two- to three-hour consultations, countless letters, – it seemed for a while as though I
        would be able to prevail in getting <tei:hi rend="underline">compensation</tei:hi> for
          <tei:hi rend="underline">all</tei:hi> of the works. The attorney mentioned <tei:hi
          rend="underline">500 million</tei:hi>, and was also prepared to take less for me. I was
        deeply gladdened for once to give away a few students who didn’t suit me, whom I only teach
        because I have to. However, for the time being there is nothing happening with compensation,
        and I have to put up with the cheating. My attorney <tei:pb n="3"/> is a <tei:hi
          rend="italic">Lamech</tei:hi><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> and also
        cowardly, an old friend of mine. It’s no different for him. Recently, he did me a
        disservice. I’ll tell you about it sometime, you’ll laugh as you would about a good
        joke.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">And now, when are you going to bring <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-008438">Karli</tei:rs> here? We are traveling again to <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs> on <tei:date when="1925-06-26">June 26</tei:date>. We
        are longing for fresh air. While working, we were altogether cut off from spring, from fresh
        air for days at a time. Are you bringing <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008438"
          >Karli</tei:rs>, then, before we leave? Or has school not let out yet? What then? Do you
        know where you need to go with him if we were not here? Do you remember the street?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>About <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000052">Heini</tei:rs>, I know that the former
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000051">Chief Superintendent</tei:rs> was staying with
        you. Is he still with you? If so, greet him cordially from me and <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000771">LieLiechen</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I am not giving up hope that <tei:pb n="4"/> we will bring you to the <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002334">Tyrol</tei:rs>. This year, you have to resolve the
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008438">Karli</tei:rs> matter. I will have to await the
        outcome of the negotiations. If the moment is at all convenient, you <tei:hi
          rend="underline">must</tei:hi> travel with us. I will persist until you share that great
        joy with us, of course as our guest. <tei:hi rend="underline">Write</tei:hi> about how you
        are doing, whether you are soon coming to Vienna? You must eat with us when you
        come.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs>, who all these months is
        writing her fingers down to the bone, and overtaxes her brain, must now prepare for the
        summer, also a tough matter.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Write, then. </tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>We kiss you most fervently and greet you</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="20"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs> and
            <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Lie-Lie</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1925-06-13">June 13, 1925</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
