<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="3418" sdoID="OJ-5-38_13">OJ 5/38, [13]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="LR">
   <tei:persName>Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
   <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
   <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008423">SchenkerW ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Heinrich to Wilhelm Schenker, dated August 20, 1924</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1924-08-20T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-06-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>The Schenkers have to postpone their end-of-summer visit to Wilhelm because they
    have to bring their new maid from the Tyrol with them, and train her as a housekeeper. They
    promise to visit as soon as things have settled in Vienna.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>

   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000775">Wilhelm Schenker</marcrel:recipient>

  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address rend="indent-60">
     <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#HS"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292"
       >Galtür</tei:rs> i. <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Tirol</tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:date when="1924-08-20">20. August
     1924</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Mein lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775"
      >Wilhelm</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this
      letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for August 20, 1924: “an Wilhelm (Br.): Aufschub
      unserer Reise wegen des neuen Mädchens.” (“to Wilhelm (letter): we are delaying our trip on
      account of the new maid.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Herzlichsten Dank für deinen l. Brief.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
     place="foot">Heinrich’s diary for August 12, 1924 records: “Von Wilhelm (Br.): über die Lage
     der Kinder; Anschrift vom <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000051">Oberinspektor</tei:rs>.”
     (“From Wilhelm (letter): about the childrens' situation; the <tei:rs type="person"
      key="entity-000051">Chief Inspector</tei:rs>'s mailing address.”).</tei:note> Den alten
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000051">Herrn</tei:rs> habe ich nach Wien schon gedankt für
    seine launige Zuschrift.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
      <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000051">Albin Bednař</tei:rs>’s letter does not seem to have
     been recorded in Heinrich’s diary. — Heinrich’s reply is recorded in his diary for August 18:
     “An Bednař (Ansichtsk.): erwidere Grüße, fahren nicht zu Wilhelm.” (“To Bednař (picture
     postcard): I return the greetings, we are not going to Wilhelm's.”).</tei:note> Also: wir
    müssen wieder einmal die Reise zu dir, auf die wir uns schon so sehr gefreut haben, vertagen, u.
    zw. wegen des <tei:hi rend="underline">neuen <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000975"
      >Mädchen</tei:rs></tei:hi>s.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot"
     >Heinrich and Jeanette had planned to visit Wilhelm on the way back from Galtür to Vienna, at
     the same time visiting Waidhofen to put <tei:ref type="person" cRef="entity-000773">Julia
      Schenker</tei:ref>’s grave in order: see <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-38_45">OJ
      5/38, [45]</tei:ref>, May 29, and <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-38_11">OJ 5/38,
      [11]</tei:ref>, June 13, 1924.</tei:note> Mein <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
     >LieLiechen</tei:rs> hat, wie Du gesehen hast, eine kleine Gehilfin gehabt (aus St. Gilgen bei
     <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002578">Salzburg</tei:rs>). Dieser Fratz aß sich voll zwei
    Jahre hindurch, erwies sich aber als <tei:hi rend="underline">zu blöde</tei:hi>, um Kochen zu
    lernen. Nichts ist in dieses Gehirn hineingegangen, u. mein <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000771">LieLiechen</tei:rs> mußte, bei so viel Arbeit für mich (die Druckereien)
     <tei:pb n="2"/> u. das Haus, <tei:hi rend="underline">für die Gehilfin kochen</tei:hi>, also
     V<tei:supplied reason="abreviation">or</tei:supplied>m<tei:supplied>ittags</tei:supplied> u.
    Abends in der Küche zu bringen u. der Fratz brauchte sich nur zu Tisch zu setzen u. sich das
    schöne Essen gut schmecken zu lassen. Ich war darüber allezeit sehr ungehalten u. wollte diese
    quere Sache nicht zugeben – <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">LieLiechen</tei:rs> als
    Köchin für die Köchin –, aber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Ll.</tei:rs> hoffte,
    hoffte immer. Nun hat sie eingesehen, – freilich nachdem sie darüber 5 Kg. eingebüßt hat –, daß
    das so nicht weitergeht u. sie entschloß sich, ein neues <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000975">Mädchen</tei:rs> zu nehmen. Dieses hat sie nun <tei:hi rend="underline"
     >hier in Tirol</tei:hi> gefunden, das <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000975"
     >Mädchen</tei:rs> ist derzeit als Köchin in der berühmten <tei:rs type="place"
     key="entity-004028">Jamthal-Hütte</tei:rs> tätig u. wir müssen eigens <tei:hi rend="underline"
     >warten</tei:hi>, um es mit uns nach Wien zu führen. Sie traut sich <tei:pb n="3"/> nicht, so
    weit zu fahren – das Tiroler <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000975">Landmädchen</tei:rs> ist
    nur einmal so –, u. wir fürchten auch, daß ihr etwas geschehen könnte von Wagendieben oder den
    berichtigen Bauernfängern auf den Bahnhöfen. Kurz, sie fährt mit uns, sobald sie frei wird, dann
    muß <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">LieLiechen</tei:rs> eine Weile noch zu Hause
    bleiben, um sie in die Wirtschaft einzuführen, das Haus für die nötigen Kochkenntnisse (ich esse
    ja Diät) beizubringen. Dies also ist der Grund der Reiseverzögerung. Wir können nicht einmal den
    Sprung nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002323">Waidhofen</tei:rs> machen, um den
    Grabschmuck auszutragen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Sei also nicht ungehalten, wenn wir erst später kommen. Das versteht sich
    aber, daß wir bei dir nicht auf <tei:pb n="4"/> Deine Rechnung wehren u. essen. Heute ist nicht
    wie ehedem. Die Verhältnisse, die du bestrebst, kannten wir zumeist durch <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs>. Wir kommen aber bestimmt, u. kommst du nach Wien, so schau
    zu uns hinauf, es soll dich nicht reuen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Was sagst du dazu, daß <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000769">Mozio’s Junge</tei:rs>
    Musiker werden will? Ja, der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Onkel</tei:rs> spukt in
    seiner Familie mit Kunst u. Brille. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs>
    selbst hat es was erzählt. Ich habe abgeraten, aber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774"
     >Mozio</tei:rs> meint, der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000769">Junge</tei:rs> wird sich
    nicht abhalten lassen. Die Zeit vergeht schnell, u. ehe du dich umsiehst, sind wir bei dir, bis
    nur „<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000975">Lina</tei:rs>“ (so heißt das Mädchen) eingeführt
    ist. </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Wir grüßen u. küssen dich herzlichst</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Dein</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs
      type="person" key="entity-000771">LieLie</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>



  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address rend="indent-60">
     <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#HS"/><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292"
       >Galtür</tei:rs> in the <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292"
      >Tyrol</tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:date when="1924-08-20">August 20,
     1924</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775"
      >Wilhelm</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Most cordial thanks for your kind letter.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/>
    I already thanked the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000051">elderly gentleman</tei:rs> in
    Vienna for his witty letter.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> So: once again we
    have to postpone a trip to you which we have so very much looked forward to, in particular on
    account of the <tei:hi rend="underline">new <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000975"
      >maid</tei:rs></tei:hi>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> As you have seen, my
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">LieLiechen</tei:rs> has had a little helper (from St.
    Gilgen, near <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002578">Salzburg</tei:rs>). This hussy ate her
    fill for two years, but proved to be <tei:hi rend="underline">too dumb</tei:hi> to learn how to
    cook. Nothing penetrated that brain, and my <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
     >LieLiechen</tei:rs>, with so much work for me (the printing materials) <tei:pb n="2"/> and the
    household, had <tei:hi rend="underline">to cook for the helper</tei:hi>, thus spending morning
    and evening in the kitchen, and the hussy only needed to seat herself at the table and enjoy the
    nice meal. I was always very annoyed by this and didn’t want to concede this skewed matter –
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">LieLiechen</tei:rs> as cook for the cook – but
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">LieLiechen</tei:rs> hoped and always hoped. Now, she
    has agreed – naturally, after she lost 5 kilos – that it could not continue in that way, and
    decided to take on a new girl. This one she found <tei:hi rend="underline">here in the
     Tyrol</tei:hi>. The <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000975">girl</tei:rs> is currently
    employed as cook in the famous <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004028">Jamtal mountain
     hut</tei:rs>, and we specifically have to <tei:hi rend="underline">wait</tei:hi> in order to
    bring her to Vienna with us. She is afraid <tei:pb n="3"/> of traveling so far – that’s just how
    the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000975">Tyrolean country girl</tei:rs> is – and we fear,
    too, that something could happen to her with train-carriage thieves or conmen at train stations.
    In short, she will travel with us as soon as she is free. <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000771">LieLiechen</tei:rs> will then have to stay home for a while in order to
    familiarize her with the household, to teach her the necessary cooking skills (I of course eat a
    special diet). So that is the reason for delaying the trip. We can’t even make the side trip to
     <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002323">Waidhofen</tei:rs> to deal with the tidying-up of the
    grave.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">So don’t be annoyed if we don’t come until later. It is understood, though,
    that we are not going to stay with and eat at your place at <tei:pb n="4"/> your expense. Today
    is not like former times. The conditions you aim for we knew mostly through <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs>. However, we are definitely coming, and if you
    come to Vienna, come up to see us. You won’t regret it.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>What do you say to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000769">Mozio’s boy</tei:rs> wanting
    to become a musician? Surely, the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">uncle</tei:rs>
    haunts the family with art and spectacles. To <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774"
     >Mozio</tei:rs> himself it meant something. I advised against it, but <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs> thinks the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000769"
     >boy</tei:rs> won’t be dissuaded. Time passes quickly, and before you know it we will be with
    you, as soon as “<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000975">Lina</tei:rs>” (that’s the girl’s
    name) is initiated.</tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">We greet and kiss you most cordially,</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs> and <tei:rs
      type="person" key="entity-000771">LieLie</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>

 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
