<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2173" sdoID="OJ-5-34_2">OJ 5/34, [2]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="major">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="major">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008, 2019</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2008, 2019</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2012-11-19" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006971">RothschildA ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten revised draft letter from Schenker to Alphons Rothschild, in Jeanette
        Schenker's hand, undated [August 3‒6, 1934]</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1934-08-06T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-01-14</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Draft accompanying letter for a copy of Oswald Jonas's Das Wesen ... —
        Schenker reiterates his gratitude for previous financial support, and reports that he now
        has 11 published works, many articles, and entries on him in several general encyclopedias.
        — Only in Vienna is he unrecognized. — He describes Wilhelm Furtwängler's faith in his
        theories and the support he has given him. — He mentions his earlier proposal for a
        Rothschild orchestra.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Dank; gratitude; thanks; Buch; book; Lebenswerk; life's work; Erfolg; success;
        Gesamtausgabe; collected edition; Verdienst; service; Lexika; encyclopedias; Diktatur;
        dictatorship; Diktator; dictator; Musik-Kritik; music criticism; Schwindelhandwerk;
        fraudulent trade; bestahlen; stolen; plagiarised; Namensnennung; citation; credit;
        Monographie; monograph; Schüler; pupil; Lehre; theory; teaching; Bedeutung; significance;
        Kulturskandal; cultural scandal; Vorschlag; proposal; Meisterwerk; masterwork</dc:subject>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000743">Alphons Rothschild</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:note>Jeanette's fair copy is heavily edited by Heinrich: this edtion presents only the
          final reading.</tei:note><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>An <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000743">Baron Rothschild</tei:rs>!<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">OJ 5/34, [2] is a seven-page draft
            letter, the initial draft written by Jeanette Schenker from dictation, the text then
            being heavily edited by Heinrich. The text given here presents the final draft
            stage.<tei:lb/> The drafting and finalizing is outlined in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/7,
            pp. 3931‒3932: August 3, 1934: "Von 11–12<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> diktire
            ich einen Briefentwurf an Baron Rotschild: nachträglicher Dank." ("From 11 to 12 o'clock
            I dictate a draft letter to Baron Rothschild: belated thanks."); August 4: "Lie-Liechen
            hat nachts bis 12<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> eine Urschrift des Briefes an
            Rotschild gemacht." ("Lie-Liechen prepared a first draft of the letter to Rothschild up
            to 12 o'clock at night."); August 5: "¾10–½11<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi>
            Spaziergang – dann schreibe ich – in Etappen! – den Brief an Rotschild." ("From 9:45 to
            10:30 a walk, then I write – in stages! – the letter to Rothschild"); August 6: "Brief
            an Rotschild fertig." ("Letter to Rothschild finished."); August 7: Lie-Liechen verpackt
            das Jonas-Buch für Rotschild. [...] Nach der Jause Postsendung an Rotschild, recomm."
            ("Lie-Liechen packs the book by Jonas for Rothschild. [...] After teatime, package sent to
            Rothschild by registered mail."). Susequently, p. 3935 records, August 17: "Von
            Rotschild kommt das Jonas-Buch zurück – eine Antwort auf den Brief fehlt." ("From
            Rothschild, the book by Jonas is returned – there is no reply to my letter."). The two
            items were mailed at the same time, from Böckstein, on August 7: see <tei:ref
              type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-34_3">OJ 5/34, [3]</tei:ref>. No further diary
            entries refer to Rothschild. </tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Das Erscheinen des gleichzeitig an Sie abgehenden Buches von D<tei:hi
          rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000412">Jonas</tei:rs>, „<tei:title>Das Wesen des
          musikalischen Kunstwerks, eine Einführung in die Lehre H Schenkers</tei:title>“<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Oswald
              Jonas</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks: eine
              Einführung in die Lehre H Schenkers</tei:title> (Vienna: Saturn-Verlag,
            1934)</tei:bibl>, which was released on July 3, 1934. </tei:note> nehme ich zum Anlaß,
        Ihnen nach mehr als 30 Jahren, zum zweitenmal für Ihre gütige Teilnahme zu danken, die Sie
        meinem Lebenswerk am Anfang haben angedeihen lassen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Alphons paid the publication costs of the first two
          components of Schenker's <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001723"><tei:title level="m">Neue
              musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:title></tei:rs>: <tei:bibl><tei:rs
              type="work" key="entity-001724"><tei:title level="m"
              >Harmonielehre</tei:title></tei:rs> (Stuttgart: J. G. Cotta, 1906)</tei:bibl>,
              <tei:bibl><tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001726"><tei:title level="m"
                >Kontrapunkt</tei:title> I</tei:rs> (ibid, 1910)</tei:bibl>. </tei:note> Heute bin
        ich nun in der glücklichen Lage Ihnen einen großen künstlerischen u. moralischen Erfolg
        meiner gesamten Arbeit zu melden, – es sind 11 große Bände nebst vielen anderen größeren u.
        kleineren Arbeiten, darunter z. B. die vierbändige <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001753"
            ><tei:title>Gesamtausgabe der Beethoven-Sonaten</tei:title></tei:rs> –,allg. darf ich
        heute meinen Dank an Sie nicht nur figürlich sondern wirklich im Namen der ganzen
        musikalischen Menschheit aussprechen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Sie haben sich mit Ihrer ersten Tat ein unsterbliches Verdienst um die Musik erworben,
        denn von der Un- <tei:pb n="2"/> sterblichkeit meiner Leistung darf ich wohl überzeugt sein.
        Fern von jeder Prahlerei erwähne ich hier nur daß ohne mein Zutun mein Name u. Werk in
        sämtliche Lexika wie: Brockhaus, Mayer, Herder,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Brockhaus, Mayer, Herder: [identify title and first edition
          in which Schenker appears]</tei:note> versteht sich auch in musikalische u. literarische
        aufgenommen worden ist, daß ich einen Weltruf erreicht habe. <tei:note type="editorial"
          place="inline">cued from p. 3:</tei:note> Wäre die Menschheit der Musik gegenüber nur
          <tei:unclear reason="reading">dies</tei:unclear> bescheidenes, nicht immer gleich dabei,
        ihre Gefühlchen schon für wirkliches Verständnis zu halten, würde sie längst auch meinen
        Namen im Munde führen, wie z.B. den <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000194"
          >Einstein</tei:rs>s,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker's
          admiration for Albert Einstein (not the musicologist Alfred Einstein) is shown not only in
          the many articles about him among Schenker's papers in the Oster Collection, but also in
          the undated draft of a letter to him (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-13-18-30">OC
            13/18–30</tei:ref>).</tei:note>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005718">Freud</tei:rs>’s etw., mit denen ich übrigens in
        wissenden Kreisen verglichen werde.<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end
          cue</tei:note> Auch meine Schüler haben es schon zu ansehlichen Namen gebracht u.
        verbreiten allerorten meine Lehre in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003147"
            ><tei:region>Europa</tei:region></tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002510"
            ><tei:country>Amerika</tei:country></tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002534"
            ><tei:country>Japan</tei:country></tei:rs> usw.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Daß es gerade nur in Wien um mich herum stiller als in der übrigen Welt ist, hat
        besondere eigene lokale Gründe: Die „<tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002559"
            ><tei:title>N. Fr. Presse</tei:title></tei:rs>“ hat in den vielen, vielen Jahren weder
        Namen noch Werk von mir genannt ausgenommen in einem Falle da <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000929">Bruno Walter</tei:rs>, mit den Pressen-Verhältnissen in Wien nicht
        vertraut, zufällig <tei:pb n="4"/> meinen Namen erwähnte. Nun, wir hatten zwar niemals eine
        Diktatur in unserem politischen Leben, aber in der kleinen Welt der Musik-Kritik hat <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000471">D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> K.</tei:rs> gar
        zu gern einen Diktator hervorkehrt, der Alle niedermachte oder verschwieg, die seinen oder
        seines Sohnes Interessen entgegentrat. Wie Sie sehen, hat aber seine Diktatur mir nichts
        anhaben können. Doch lebt er, aber wir dürfen ihn doch schon zu den Dahingegangenen zählen,
        während ich, Gott sei es gedankt, noch die Korrekturen eines soeben abgeschlossenen neuen
        großen Bandes leite, der bald erscheinen wird.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial"
          place="foot">i.e. <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title level="m">Der frei
              Satz</tei:title></tei:rs>, volume III of <tei:title level="m">Neue musikalische
            Theorien und Phantasien</tei:title>, published posthumously (Vienna: UE,
          1935).</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Außerdem haben in Wien die Musiker, die Professoren an der <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002591">Musikakademie</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-003334">Universität</tei:rs>, die in musikalischen Dingen so vergnügt ihr
        Schwindelhandwerk treiben sich, wohlweislich vor jeder Verbindung mit mir gehütet sie taten
        so, als wüßten sie nicht einmal, ob der inzwischen weltberühmt gewordene Schenker mit ihnen
        in Wien wohne! Nur konnten sie sich nicht versagen, meiner gewachsenen Bedeutung doch in der
        Form Rechnung zu tragen, daß sie mein geistiges Eigentum <tei:pb n="5"/> zumindest –
        bestahlen, d. h. ohne Namensnennung abdruckten, ja nicht einmal in Gänsefüßchen zitierten.
        Wie oft mögen Sie, was geistig mir gehört hat, für die Münze eines Kritikers genommen haben!
        Die übrige Welt benahm sich aber allezeit u. allerorten korrekt u. respektirte mein Eigentum
        mit <tei:hi rend="underline">Dank</tei:hi> u. Begeisterung.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07"
          type="editorial" place="foot">No paragraph-break in the original.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nehmen Sie es nicht übel, hochverehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000743">Herr
          Baron</tei:rs>, wenn ich, den würdigen Anlaß nützend, der mich heute zu Ihnen führt, noch
        einiges hinzufüge, das sicherlich auch Ihnen Genugtuung bereiten wird. Schon bei seinem
        ersten Erscheinen in Wien, vor etwa 15 Jahren also, hat sich <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000268">D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> F.</tei:rs> an mich, als den
        Verfasser der Monographie über <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001731"><tei:title><tei:hi
              rend="italic">Beethoven</tei:hi>'s IX. Sinfonie</tei:title></tei:rs>, gewendet u.
        seither in jeder Hinsicht an mich angeschlossen. In all den Jahren hat er nie versäumt, mich
        zu besuchen, Stunden bei mir zuzubringen u. allerhand von mir zu lernen. <tei:pb n="6"/> Er
        bezeichnet sich selbst als meinen Schüler, was mich mit nicht wenig Stolz erfüllt. Ihm
        verdanke ich auch eine Ausbreitung meines Namens u. Werkes in aller Welt, er ist rastlos
        darin, meine Lehre als das einzige Heil für die Zukunft der Musik zu verkünden. In einem
        Brief an einen Wiener Hofrat,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Viennese court counselor: i.e. Ludwig Karpath at the Ministry of Education. There are two
          relevant letters, <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-18-46">OC 18/46</tei:ref>,
          January 30, 1933 and <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-18-47">OC 18/47</tei:ref>,
          February 6, 1933. In neither letter is Richard Strauss named. Schenker is most likely
          inferring from the sentence in <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-18-47">OC
            18/47</tei:ref>: "If anyone has, then he <tei:supplied reason="identity"
            >Schenker</tei:supplied>, who has in truth given greater services to music [...] than
            <tei:hi rend="italic">many a currently famous composer</tei:hi>, has deserved honorary
          positions, public distinctions, and expression of gratitude." (italics
          applied).</tei:note> dessen Abschrift vor mir liegt, geht er so weit, mir für die Zukunft
        der Musik eine größere Bedeutung als selbst einem <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000871"
          >Rich. Strauß</tei:rs> zuzumessen. Auch als „Preuss. Staatsrat,“ zuletzt anfangs Juni d.
        J., hat er mich, wie immer, besucht, trotzdem ich ihm gegenüber aus meinem tief überzeugten
        Judentum nie ein Hehl gemacht habe. Sogar hat er seinen Besuch bei mir hier in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002359">Böckstein</tei:rs> angekündigt.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Er nennt es einen „Kulturskandal ohnegleichen“, wenn das offizielle Wien mir den
        schuldigen Dank nicht in <tei:pb n="7"/> Form von allen nur erdenklichen Auszeichnungen u.
        Titeln abstattet, wenn er z. B. einem Gespräch mit Sektionschef <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-005571">D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Pernter</tei:rs> entnimmt, daß
        er meinen Namen gar nicht kennt, obgleich er dem <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-005584">Unterrichtsministerium</tei:rs> zugeteilt ist, also, – kennen
        müsste!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Auf Umwegen hat mir <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">F.</tei:rs>, auch jenen
        Traum aus jungen Jahren erfüllt, den ich Ihnen, hochverehrter Herr Baron, einmal vorgeträumt
        habe: ich unterbreitete Ihnen damals den Vorschlag eines Rothschild-Orchesters, das ich, um
        das bessere Antlitz der Meisterwerke zu zeigen, in die Welt hinausführen wollte. Nun
        bereitet mir das Schicksal, die Genugtuung, mittelbar durch <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000268">F.</tei:rs> diesen Wunsch erfüllt zu sehen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wie bedauere ich, daß ich die Freude eines ähnlichen Berichtes nicht auch dem
        verewigten Prof. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000707">Rettich</tei:rs> machen
        kann.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Meinen tiefstgefühlten Dank so feierlich wie möglich noch einmal zum — Ausdruck
        bringend —</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">unfinished, unsigned</tei:note></tei:p>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">
      <tei:opener>
        <tei:note>Jeanette's fair copy is heavily edited by Heinrich: this edtion presents only the
          final reading.</tei:note><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>To <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000743">Baron Rothschild</tei:rs>:<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">The publication of Dr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000412"
          >Jonas</tei:rs>'s book, <tei:title level="m">The Nature of the Musical Artwork: An
          Introduction to the Theory of Heinrich Schenker</tei:title>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> which is on its way to you simultaneously, affords me the opportunity of
        thanking you after more than thirty years for a second time for the kind participation that
        you bestowed on my life's work at the beginning.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
          type="footnote"/> Today I am now in the happy position of being able to inform you of a
        great artistic and moral success on the part of my assembled work ‒ it comprises eleven
        large volumes along with many other works larger and smaller, among them, for example, the
        four-volume <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001753"><tei:title>collected edition of the
            Beethoven <tei:supplied reason="identity">piano</tei:supplied>
          sonatas</tei:title></tei:rs> ‒ overall I should like to express my thanks to you not just
        figuratively but tangibly on behalf of the whole of musical humanity.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>You have with your initial deed earned undying gratitude in the realm of music, for I
        can be absolutely certain sure of the <tei:pb n="2"/> immortality of my accomplishment. Far
        from wishing to boast, let me mention here just that without any effort on my part my name
        and work has been taken up in all encyclopedias such as Brockhaus, Mayer, Herder,<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> and of course musical and literary ones, and that
        I have attained a worldwide reputation. <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">cued from
          p. 3:</tei:note> If only mankind were self-effacing enough with regard to music not always
        to mistake its own petty feelings for genuine understanding, then my name would long ago
        have been, perhaps joyously, on everybody's lips, as for example those of <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000194">Einstein</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05"
          type="footnote"/> and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005718">Freud</tei:rs>, and would
        have been compared with his in well-informed circles.<tei:note type="editorial"
          place="inline">end cue</tei:note> Moreover, my pupils have already brought to it
        considerable repute, and are disseminating my theory all over <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-003147"><tei:region>Europe</tei:region></tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002510"><tei:country>America</tei:country></tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002534"><tei:country>Japan</tei:country></tei:rs>, etc.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>That in Vienna, of all places, there is less activity going on around me than anywhere
        else in the world is due to its own local reasons: the <tei:rs type="journal"
          key="entity-002559"><tei:title level="j">Neue Freie Presse</tei:title></tei:rs> has in all
        these many, many years cited neither my name nor my work, except on one occasion when
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000929">Bruno Walter</tei:rs>, who was not well up on
        Viennese journalistic affairs, <tei:pb n="4"/> just happened to drop my name. Whereas we
        never had dictatorship in our political life, in the small world of music criticism <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000471">Dr. K.</tei:rs> has all too willingly behaved like a
        dictator who eliminated or silenced anybody who opposed his or his son's interests. But as
        you can see, his dictatorial ways have been unable to do me any harm. He is still alive, but
        we ought to count him among the already departed, whereas I ‒ thanks be to God! ‒ am still
        handling the proofs of a recently completed big new volume that will appear soon.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Moreover, in Vienna, musicians, professors at the <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002591">Music Academy</tei:rs> and the <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-003334">University</tei:rs>, who in musical matters so merrily ply their
        fraudulent trade, have very wisely avoided any contact with me; they act as if they had no
        idea that Schenker, who has become world famous in the meantime, lives alongside them in
        Vienna! But they just could not resist <tei:pb n="5"/> taking into account my increased
        importance by at least stealing my intellectual property, i.e. they published without
        crediting me, indeed they never once quoted me between quotation marks. How often might you
        have taken what belonged intellectually to me to be the coinage of a critic! All the rest of
        the world, by contrast, conducted itself correctly always and everywhere, and respected my
        property with <tei:hi rend="underline">thanks</tei:hi> and enthusiasm.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Please do not take it amiss, highly esteemed <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000743"
          >Baron</tei:rs>, if I take advantage of the occasion that has led me to you today to add
        one more thing that will surely afford you satisfaction, too. Already at his first
        appearance in Vienna, i.e. fifteen years ago, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Dr.
          Furtwängler</tei:rs> turned to me as the author of the monograph on <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001731"><tei:title>Beethoven's Ninth Symphony</tei:title></tei:rs>, and has
        since then allied himself with me in every respect. In all these years he has never once
        neglected visiting me, spending hours in my company, and learning all kinds of things from
        me. <tei:pb n="6"/> He calls himself a pupil of mine ‒ which fills me with not a little
        pride. I have him to thank, also, for spreading my name and work far and wide; in so doing,
        he unceasingly proclaims my theory as the sole salvation for the future of music. In a
        letter to a Viennese court counselor<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/> a copy
        of which lies before me, he goes so far as to attach greater importance for the future of
        music to me even than to a <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000871">Richard
          Strauss</tei:rs>. What is more, as "Prussian State Counselor" since the beginning of June
        this year, he visited me as he has always done, despite my having never made any secret to
        him of my deeply held Jewishness. He even declared that he would visit me here in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002359">Böckstein</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>He calls it a "cultural scandal without comparison" when Viennese officialdom does not
        record the thanks it owes me in the <tei:pb n="7"/> form of all conceivable manner of honors
        and titles, and when, for example, he gathers from a conversation with department head
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005571">Dr. Pernter</tei:rs> that my name is completely
        unknown to the latter, even though he is assigned to the <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-005584">Ministry of Education</tei:rs> and so ought to have known it!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>By other means, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs> has even
        fulfilled for me that dream from early days that I once expressed to you, highly esteemed
        Baron, as an aspiration. I put to you then the proposal of a Rothschild Orchestra, which I
        wanted to present to the world so as to show the masterworks in a better light. Now fate has
        given me the satisfaction of seeing this wish fulfilled directly through <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>How I regret that I cannot give the late Prof. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000707">Rettich</tei:rs> the joy of a similar report also.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Putting into words once again as solemnly as possible my most deeply felt
        thanks</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">unfinished, unsigned</tei:note></tei:p>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
