<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
    xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
    xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
    <sdo:collectionDesc>
        <sdo:source>
            <sdo:correspondence mfID="2788" sdoID="OJ-5-19-2">OJ 5/19, 2</sdo:correspondence>
        </sdo:source>

        <tei:handNotes>
            <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>

        </tei:handNotes>

        <tei:respStmt xml:id="WP">
            <tei:persName>William Pastille</tei:persName>
            <tei:resp>Transcription, 2022</tei:resp>
            <tei:resp>Translation, 2022</tei:resp>
        </tei:respStmt>

        <tei:respStmt xml:id="IDB">
            <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
            <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2022</tei:resp>
        </tei:respStmt>

        <tei:revisionDesc>
            <tei:change when="2011-04-15" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
        </tei:revisionDesc>
    </sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:record ID="r0001">

        <sdo:itemDesc>
            <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008335">KalbeckM ~
                HSchenker</tei:rs>
            <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
            <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Kalbeck, undated [?April or May
                1889]</dc:title>

            <dcterms:created>1889-05-01T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
            <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2022-07-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
            <dc:description>Schenker thanks Kalbeck for the critique. — He is preparing for his
                state examination in Roman law, and looks forward to an eventual career in music
                theory. — He will send Kalbeck three sonatas.</dc:description>
            <dc:subject/>



            <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
            <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000418">KalbeckM</marcrel:recipient>
        </sdo:itemDesc>


        <tei:div type="transcription">

            <tei:opener>
                <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person"
                        key="entity-000418"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
                        >Redacteur</tei:hi></tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
                        place="foot">This letter and <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-19-1"
                            >OJ 5/19, [1]</tei:ref> are written in Sütterlinschrift; words in
                        italics here are in Lateinschrift in the original. On the basis of the
                        designation “stud. iur.” (“student of law”) and reference to exams, Wayne
                        Alpern states: “Schenker finished his coursework in the spring semester of
                        1888 and received his degree on February 1, 1890. He probably wrote this
                        letter as he prepared for exams in 1889, during the same period he studied
                        with Anton Bruckner,” <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Schenkerian
                                Jurisprudence: Echoes of Schenker’s Legal Education in His Music
                                Thought</tei:title> (PhD diss., City University of New York,
                            2005)</tei:bibl>, p. 16, fn. 2. He took his oral examination (<tei:hi
                            rend="italic">Staatsprüfung</tei:hi>) on May 15, 1889, on Roman, German,
                        and Austrian legal history, hence the editorially proposed dating. — Cf. the
                        letter from Schenker to Ludwig Bösendorfer, <tei:ref type="correspondence"
                            cRef="GdM-Briefe-HS_1">GdM Briefe HS, [1]</tei:ref>, undated
                        (1889/1890), in which Schenker refers to his state
                    examinations.</tei:note></tei:salute>
            </tei:opener>

            <tei:p>Ich eile mich herzlichst zu bedanken für das Urtheil und die wohlgemeinte
                    Warnung.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">No letter
                    from Kalbeck to Schenker at this time is known to survive.</tei:note> Das Leben
                hat mich schon schöner Träume abgewöhnt! Energie und Selbstvertrauen hab’ ich noch,
                und ich brauche sie dringend, denn ich habe – – schwere Pflichten! Arm aufgewachsen,
                arm, in unharmonischesten Verhältnissen lebend verdanke ich Alles Zufällen und mir.
                Ich hatte und habe keinen Lehrer, und fürchte – nur wegen meiner Armuth – auch
                keinen zu bekommen. Ich bin also nicht einmal im ersten Stadium. </tei:p>

            <tei:p>Ich bereite mich eben zur ersten Staatsprüfung vor. Spät Abends, so oft ich das
                göttliche „römische Recht“ von der Hand lege, gönne ich mir die reinste Freude, ein
                wenig musikalisch zu denken. </tei:p>

            <tei:p>Jeder Abend bringt mir einen Gedanken.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
                    type="editorial" place="foot">For an examination of this remark and the previous
                    paragraph, see <tei:bibl><tei:author>Wayne Alpern</tei:author>, <tei:title
                            level="a">Musical Justice and Tonal Inequality in the Theory of Heinrich
                            Schenker,</tei:title> in <tei:editor>Allen Cadwallader</tei:editor>,
                            <tei:editor>Karen Bottge</tei:editor>, and <tei:editor>Oliver
                            Schwab-Felix</tei:editor>, eds, <tei:title level="m">New Horizons in
                            Schenkerian Research</tei:title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms Verlag,
                        2022</tei:bibl>), p. 211.</tei:note> In der Nacht notire ich – für mich und
                meine <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000319">Schwester</tei:rs>, die fern von
                hier vielleicht an mich denkt und mich Armen bedauernd weint! </tei:p>

            <tei:p>Ich weiß aber, daß nach bestandener Prüfung, und nachdem <tei:pb n="2"/> ich mir
                vielleicht die ärmlichste Existenz werde errungen haben (bis nun zu lebe ich doch
                nur provisorisch), ich – allein – mich an die fremde „<tei:term>Theorie</tei:term>“
                und an die Meisterwerke, daran ich nur sehr, sehr wenig kenne, heranwagen werde.
                Fleißig zu sein verstehe ich, und vielleicht gelingt es mir, ohne „Jus“ zu
                schmälern, doch Etwas von der gewaltigen <tei:term>Theorie</tei:term> mir
                anzueignen! </tei:p>

            <tei:p>Viel später werde ich mir die Freiheit nehmen, drei Sonaten, die notirt
                    sind,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">The reference
                    in paragraph 3 to composing suggests that these are early compositional forays –
                    no sonatas by Schenker are known to survive.</tei:note> an Sie, sehr geehrter
                Herr <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Redacteur</tei:hi>, einzusenden. Belästigen werde ich
                aber nie! </tei:p>

            <tei:p>Nochmals mich für die mich sehr ehrende Antwort bedankend </tei:p>

            <tei:closer>
                <tei:salute rend="indent-65">zeichne mich</tei:salute>
                <tei:salute rend="indent-65">mit Hochachtung</tei:salute>
                <tei:signed rend="indent-65"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"><tei:hi
                            rend="lateinschr">Heinrich Schenker</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
                <tei:affiliation rend="indent-70"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">stud.
                    iur.</tei:hi></tei:affiliation><tei:lb/>
            </tei:closer>

        </tei:div>

        <tei:div type="translation">

            <tei:opener>
                <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000418"
                        >Editor</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"
                    /></tei:salute>
            </tei:opener>

            <tei:p>I hasten to thank you for the critique and the well-intended warning.<tei:ptr
                    corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> Life has already put me off beautiful
                dreams! I still have energy and self-confidence, and I need them desperately,
                because I have – – burdensome responsibilities! Raised poor, living poor in the most
                inauspicious conditions, I owe everything to happenstances and to myself. I have and
                have had no teacher, and I fear – only on account of my poverty – that I will not
                get one either. So I am not even at the first stage.</tei:p>

            <tei:p>I am preparing now for the first state examination. Late in the evening, whenever
                I lay aside the sublime “Roman Law,” I allow myself the purest pleasure, thinking a
                little musically.</tei:p>

            <tei:p>Every evening brings me an idea.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/>
                In the night I jot down a few notes – for myself and my <tei:rs type="person"
                    key="entity-000319">sister</tei:rs>, who, far from here, may perhaps be giving
                me a thought and weeping sorrowfully for poor me!</tei:p>

            <tei:p>But I know that after passing the examination, and after <tei:pb n="2"/> I
                eventually obtain, perhaps, a very meager livelihood for myself (up till now I have
                been living day-to-day), I – by myself – will dare to approach the remote
                    “<tei:supplied reason="clarity">music</tei:supplied>
                <tei:term>theory</tei:term>” and the masterpieces, of which I know only very, very
                little. I know how to be industrious, and perhaps I will succeed, without detracting
                from the “Law,” in acquiring a bit of the imposing
                <tei:term>theory</tei:term>!</tei:p>

            <tei:p>Much later, I will take the liberty of sending to you, dear Editor, three sonatas
                that are written out.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> But I will
                never pester you! </tei:p>

            <tei:p>Once again expressing my thanks for the response, which honors me deeply,</tei:p>

            <tei:closer>
                <tei:salute rend="indent-65">I remain</tei:salute>
                <tei:salute rend="indent-65">most respectfully</tei:salute>
                <tei:signed rend="indent-65"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich
                        Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
                <tei:affiliation rend="indent-70">student of law</tei:affiliation><tei:lb/>
            </tei:closer>

        </tei:div>
    </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
