<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3516" sdoID="OJ-5-38_60">OJ 5/38, [60]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="LR">
      <tei:persName>Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008423">SchenkerW ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Heinrich to Wilhelm Schenker, dated September 8,
        1929</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1929-09-08T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-10-07</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Heinrich thanks Wilhelm for the hospitality he and his wife provided and
        summarizes what lies immediately ahead in the weeks to come. He also reports on a
        composition he received from Reinhard Oppel, and on a lecture on Bach in which Oppel invoked
        Schenker’s work.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000775">Wilhelm Schenker</marcrel:recipient>

    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Sonntag, <tei:date
            when="1929-09-08">8. 9. 29</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Mein lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775"
          >Wilhelm</tei:rs>![1]</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Über die <tei:hi rend="underline">Kiste</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="double-underline">ohne</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">Federn</tei:hi>, die uns nach <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-005362">Sigmundsherberg</tei:rs> führte, läßt sich lachen u. weinen, je nach
        der Laune. Jeden Augenblick schwebten wir in der Luft, dann fielen wir wieder auf die
        Hintere so hart, als fielen wir auf die Steine der Strassen. In Tulln empfanden wir die
        erste Erleichterung, die Sonne gieng wieder. Wir kamen in Wien rechtzeitig genug an, um noch
        für Abend u. Morgen einzukaufen. Der erste Sturm der Post war sehr groß, er gab viel zu
        schaffen, dann begann das erste Heraus- {2} -schälen der Tische, Betten, Sessel –
          kurz<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">‚</tei:supplied> erst heute komme ich, inmitten
        noch notdürftiges erster Ordnung, dazu, dir u. der l. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008450">Frau Marie</tei:rs> für die
        unendliche Mühe u. Liebe zu danken, mit der Ihr Beide uns umgeben habet. Es ist so schade,
        daß unser Aufenthalt bei Euch so kurz bemessen ist, doch bin ich Euerer Einsicht u.
        Zustimmung sicher: zwar wisst Ihr schon genug von den absonderlichen Schwierigkeiten meines
        Lebens, wüsstet Ihr aber noch genaueres, Ihr würdet es selbst gar nicht anders haben wollen.
        Solange ich auf die „Praxis“ von Stunden angewiesen bin, muß ich nach Schülern ausblicken –
        Schande genug für Österreich[entity-002506] u. Deutschland[entity-002482].</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="3"/> Gleich mit der ersten Post wurde LieLiechen[entity-000771]
        von einem sehr würdigen Geschenke Prof D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi>
        Oppel[entity-000643]’s aus Leipzig[entity-002479]–Kiel[entity-002757] überrascht, mit der
          <tei:hi rend="underline">Widmung</tei:hi> einer prachtvollen <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >Komposition</tei:hi>.[2] Da heißt es gleich danken, schön danken, – ich hatte noch eine
        besondere Ursache dazu, da der genannte Professor[entity-000643] ein sehr treuer Anhänger
        meiner Lehre ist; so hatte er in Halle[entity-003044] einen Vortrag über S.
        Bach[entity-000027] u. mich gehalten, er wirbt in allen Schulen für mich u. s. w. So laufen
        die Fäden u. ich muß sie, <tei:hi rend="underline">wenn ich nur einfach leben will</tei:hi>,
        immer in den Fingern haben, – daher so viel Mühe noch neben der Mühe {4} der Werke u. des
        Unterrichts. Doch im Grunde solltest du mir das Klagen verbieten: im Alter von 62 Jahren[3]
        darf der Mensch noch nicht Schluß machen, sonst lasse er sich gleich begraben,
        nicht?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Morgen Montag gehen wir zu Prof. Fuchs[entity-006074] (wegen meiner Augen) u. zum
        Zahnarzt (wegen einer Plombe) und so geht es dann fort.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wir haben uns erlaubt, Euch den erwünschten Tee zu schicken, möge er Euch gut
        bekommen!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Nochmals herzlichsten, besten Dank </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>für Alles Liebe u. schönste Grüße</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>von mir u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
          >LieLiechen</tei:rs></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">dein</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
          >Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Sunday, <tei:date when="1929-09-08"
            >September 8, 1929</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775"
          >Wilhelm</tei:rs>,[1]</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>The <tei:hi rend="underline">old jalopy</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="double-underline">without</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">springs</tei:hi>, which took us to <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-005362">Sigmundsherberg</tei:rs>, brings on laughing and crying, according to
        the mood. At any moment, we floated in the air, then fell down again on our backsides so
        hard as though on stones in the street. We felt the first relief only in Tulln, the sun set.
        We arrived in Vienna in good time to do some shopping for the evening and morning. The first
        onslaught of mail was very big, leaving plenty to do. Then began the initial undraping {2}
        of the tables, beds, armchairs – in short, in the midst of the necessities of first order
        only today am I getting around to thanking you and your dear wife Marie for the endless
        effort and love with which you two surrounded us. It is such a shame that our stay with you
        was so short, but I am certain of your insight and agreement: you two already know enough of
        the peculiar difficulties of my life, but if you knew the details more closely, you would
        not want to have it any different yourselves. As long as I am dependent on the “praxis” of
        lessons, I have to be on the lookout for students – sufficient disgrace for Austria and
        Germany.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="3"/> Right with the first batch of mail LieLiechen was
        surprised with a very worthy gift from Professor Dr. Oppel from Leipzig and Kiel, with the
          <tei:hi rend="underline">dedication</tei:hi> of a magnificent <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >composition</tei:hi>.[2] That deserves immediate thanks, sincere thanks, – I had another,
        special motivation for thanks since the aforenamed professor is a very devoted disciple of
        my theory. Thus he gave a lecture in Halle on Johann Sebastian Bach and me. He advocates for
        me in all schools, etc. So run the threads, and <tei:hi rend="underline">if I want to live
          even simply</tei:hi>, I must always have them in my fingers, – thus so much effort
        alongside of the effort {4} of the projects and of the instruction. But at bottom you should
        forbid me any complaining. At the age of 62 years[3] one may not yet call it quits.
        Otherwise, he could be buried on the spot, right?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>On Monday morning we are going to Professor Fuchs (about my eyes) and to the dentist
        (about a filling), and so it goes onward.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>We allowed ourselves to send you the requested tea. May it very much agree with
        you!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Again, most cordial, abundant thanks</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>for everything,and warmest greetings</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>from me and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
          >LieLiechen</tei:rs></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
          >Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
