<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2574" sdoID="OJ-5-24_1">OJ 5/24, [1]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="sole">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006, 2021</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2006, 2021</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2021</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2012-11-19" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008066">LambergE ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


      <dc:title>Handwritten draft letter from Schenker to Ernst Lamberg, dated July 8,
        1924</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1924-07-08T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2021-10-08</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Draft letter in which Schenker contends that Sofie Deutsch's intentions for
        the administration of the stipends for composers that she created through her will are being
        disregarded with the passing of the capital sum to the Academy for Music and Performing
        Arts, and instructs Dr. Lamberg to write to Josef Marx, Director of the Academy, in these
        terms.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Beschränkung; limitation; Ausübung; discharge; Pflicht; duty; Erblasserin;
        deceased; Testament; will; Stipendium; stipend; Akademie; academy; Schule; school; Künstler;
        artist; musician; Ehre; honor; Gerechtigkeit; impartiality; Verantwortlichkeit;
        answerability; Ableben; death; Zufall; accident; Ehrensache; matter of honor; Zinsen;
        interest</dc:subject>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000502">Ernst Lamberg</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">
      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#JS"/><tei:hi rend="double-underline">An <tei:rs
              type="person" key="entity-000502">D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi>
              Lamberg</tei:rs> – <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>, den
              <tei:date when="1924-07-08">8. Juli 1924</tei:date>.</tei:hi><tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Drafting and dictation of this letter
            is recorded in Schenker’s diary for July 8, 1924: “Lie-Liechen an der Reinschrift, ich
            schreibe einen Brief an Dr. Lamberg (den Brief diktiert): möchte noch einen letzten Rest
            von Pietät retten u. vom Terna-Vorschlag befreit sein.” (“Lie-Liechen works on the fair
            copy, I write a letter to Dr. Lamberg (letter dictated): I would like to save a last
            remnant of piety and be freed of the terna proposal.”). The reply, <tei:ref
              type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-12-31_3">OJ 12/31, [3]</tei:ref>, July 11, acknowledges
            Schenker's "letter of the 8th inst"; thus, clearly, the finished letter – which is not
            known to survive – was drawn up the same day. There are diary entries on the two
            following days that may refer to this same letter: 9th: “Mit Lie-Liechen die Reinschrift
            durchgegangen u. verbessert.” (“The fair copy gone through with Lie-Liechen and
            improved.”); 10th: “Lie-Liechen setzt die Reinschrift-Feile fort.” (“Lie-Liechen
            continues polishing the fair copy.”), in which case the text of the letter will have
            been changed; however, since Ernst Lamberg replied on the 11th and the letter had to
            travel from the Tyrol to Vienna, these would appear to refer to some other
            letter.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ihr geschätztes Schreiben vom <tei:date when="1924-07-01">1.
          VII.</tei:date><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-12-31_2">OJ 12/32, [2]</tei:ref>, July 1,
          1924.</tei:note> hat mich in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>
        erreicht, wo aber die Post weniger flüßig ist als in Wien. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich nehme in dieser Frage einen andern Standpunkt ein.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"> At issue here is Josef Marx’s proposal,
          reported in Ernst Lamberg’s letter <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-12-31_2">OJ
            12/31, [2]</tei:ref>, July 1, 1924, that the Academy should present Schenker with a
          slate of three candidates for each stipend to be awarded, from which he would choose.
          Schenker is objecting to the limitation, both institutional and individual, placed on his
          judgement by this.</tei:note> Nicht ein einziges Mal seit den Tagen, da sie erörtert
        wurde, also seit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000590">Fritz Mendl</tei:rs>s, <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000902">D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi>
        Türkel</tei:rs>s, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000257">D<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
            >r.</tei:hi> Friedman<tei:supplied reason="omission">n</tei:supplied></tei:rs>s Tagen u.
        auch nicht von Ihnen u. dem Hofrat<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial"
          place="foot">The title “Hofrat” (Court Counselor) could refer either to Fritz Mendl or to
          Josef Marx.</tei:note> hörte ich je den Gedanken einer Beschränkung in der Ausübung der
        von mir zu übernehmenden Pflicht. Und das allein trifft den Sinn der <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000165">Erblasserin</tei:rs>, den sie im Testament ausgesprochen hat, längst
        aber auch schon mündlich oft u. oft auszudrücken pflegte. Im Gefühl, daß sie ein <tei:hi
          rend="underline">beträchtliches</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">Stipendium</tei:hi> hinterläßt – daß es so völlig anders kommen
        sollte, ahnte sie nicht, sonst hätte sie das Testament anders abgefaßt – dachte sie durchaus
        nicht an ein sozusagen locales Stipendium, gebunden an eine Akademie oder sonst welche
        Schule, sondern an Künstler in der ganzen Welt, denen aus irgend einem Grunde beizuspringen
        wäre, mögen sie auch schon Namen u. Ehre tragen. (Z.B. wurden die zwei Millionen Kronen, die
        ich zum Geschenk darbot, von der Berliner Centrale<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Hermann Wunsch states in <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-15-31_1">OJ 15/31, [1]</tei:ref> that he received his 2M Kronen from the
            <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002443">Deutsche Nothilfe</tei:rs> (German
          Assistance). The money had been transferred to the Austrian Provincial Bank under the
          control of Schenker’s younger brother <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774">Moriz
            Schenker</tei:rs>, and transferred from there to the Deutsch Nothilfe. A similar
          procedure was used to award the same sum to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000149"
            >Walter Dahms</tei:rs>, who received it in lire since he was then in Italy (diary
          December 20 and 24, 1923).</tei:note> dem <tei:pb n="2"/> Sinfoniker <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000983">H. Wunsch</tei:rs> in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501"
          >Berlin</tei:rs> übergeben, für den sich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000341"
          >Hausegger</tei:rs> so sehr einsetzt. Von vielen Seiten werde ich auf den alten Arnold
          Mendelssohn<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Arnold Mendelssohn
          (1855–1933), composer and essayist who rejected romanticism and advocated a purer,
          polyphonic musical style based on J. S. Bach and Schütz. (<tei:title level="m"
            >NGDM2</tei:title>). Reference is apparently to a prize or stipend in his
          name.</tei:note> aufmerksam gemacht usw. <tei:del rend="overstrike">)</tei:del> An
        ähnliche Fälle dachte <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Frau Deutsch</tei:rs>, im
        Vertrauen auf das beträchtliche Geld u. meine Gerechtigkeit u. Verantwortlichkeit.) </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">So wenig lag ihr die übliche Art des Stipendiums im Sinn, daß sie doch
        ausdrücklich im Testament erklärte, das Stipendium<tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >geld</tei:add> habe nach meinen Ableben <tei:hi rend="underline">dem</tei:hi>
        <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002425"><tei:hi rend="underline"
          >Verein</tei:hi></tei:rs>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">anheim</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">zu</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">fallen</tei:hi>! </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Haben zwar die Dinge nun einmal einen anderen Verlauf genommen, hat sich
        der <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002425">Verein</tei:rs> aufgelöst, so sehe ich
        noch immer den Grund nicht ein, weshalb der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165"
          >Erblasserin</tei:rs> auch der letzte Rest von Pietät verweigert werden müßte vom <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002425">Verein</tei:rs>, von Ihnen, der <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002591">Akademie</tei:rs> u. mir. Ich meine: Der <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002591">Akademie</tei:rs> müßte es willkommen sein, die
        gebotene Pietät mit etwas Geduld zu vereinen, sie kommt zu dem Stipendium ja nicht gerade
        über Wunsch der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Erblasserin</tei:rs>, doch nur
        durch Zufall u. sollte diesen durch Dank ehren. Wenn es auch so ist, daß mein Werk – wir
        sind unter uns – alle Akademien der Welt überleben wird, so wird doch körperlich die <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002591">Akademie</tei:rs> mich über- <tei:pb n="3"/>
        leben, u. so findet sie wahrlich noch Zeit, Zeit, Zeit genug, des Stipendiums nach ihrem
        Ermessen zu walten. Aber so lange ich lebe sollte <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002591">sie</tei:rs> es sich zu einer Ehrensache machen, den Wunsch der
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Erblasserin</tei:rs> zu erfüllen, umso mehr, als
        sie gesonnen ist, das Stipendium mit ihrem Namen zu schmücken. Demnach bitte ich Sie, Herrn
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000577">D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi>
          Marx</tei:rs> (den ich persönlich nicht kenne) dies alles mitzuteilen u. bei ihm den
        Wunsch der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Erblasserin</tei:rs> durchzusetzen, was
        Ihnen gewiß nicht schwer fallen kann. Ich habe gegen <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000577">D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Marx</tei:rs> gewiß nichts,
        auch nicht gegen die <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002591">Akademie</tei:rs>, aber
        der Fall liegt zunächst anders. Die <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002591"
          >Akademie</tei:rs> hat Zeit. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">In diesem Sinne bitte ich Sie auch die <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002591">Akademie</tei:rs> zu beauftragen, daß sie mir die Zinsen rechtzeitig
        zur Verfügung stellt, damit ich das Kleingeld geheim dorthin lenken kann, wo ein bereits
        erworbenes Verdienst irgendwie schwer gekränkt wird. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Mit ausgezeichneter Hochachtung</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">unsigned</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">
      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#JS"/><tei:hi rend="double-underline">To <tei:rs
              type="person" key="entity-000502">Dr. Lamberg</tei:rs> – <tei:rs type="place"
              key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1924-07-08">July 8,
              1924</tei:date></tei:hi><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Your esteemed letter of <tei:date when="1924-07-01">July
          1</tei:date><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> has reached me in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>, where the postal service is less swift
        that in Vienna.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I adopt a different standpoint on this question.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> Not once since the days in which it was first
        discussed, hence not since the time of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000590">Fritz
          Mendl</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000902">Dr. Türkel</tei:rs>, and <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000257">Dr. Friedman<tei:supplied reason="omission"
            >n</tei:supplied></tei:rs>, nor even of you yourself or the Counselor,<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> have I ever heard the idea of limiting the
        discharge of the duty that I was to undertake. What the <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000165">deceased</tei:rs> enunciated in her will alone captures her intention,
        but long before then she had also been accustomed to expressing it again and again by word
        of mouth. In bequeathing a <tei:hi rend="underline">considerable stipend</tei:hi> ‒ never
        did she dream that something so utterly different might arise, otherwise she would have
        drafted her will differently ‒ she was not for a moment thinking of a so-to-speak local
        stipend linked to an academy or school of some sort but of artists anywhere in the world, to
        whom assistance was to be brought for any reason whatsoever, even if they were already known
        and well regarded. (For example, the 2 million Kronen that I offered as a present were
        handed over by the Berlin Central<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> to the
          <tei:pb n="2"/> symphonic composer <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000983">H.
          Wunsch</tei:rs> in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs> for whom
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000341">Hausegger</tei:rs> strove so very hard. In many
        ways I am reminded of old Arnold Mendelssohn,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"
        /> etc. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165">Mrs. Deutsch</tei:rs> had in mind similar
        cases in placing reliance on the considerable sum of money and my impartiality and sense of
        responsibility.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">So far from her mind was the customary type of stipend that she expressly
        explained in her will that the stipend <tei:add place="interlinear-above">money</tei:add>
        was to <tei:hi rend="underline">revert to the <tei:rs type="organization"
            key="entity-002425">Association</tei:rs></tei:hi> after my death.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Even though, to be sure, things have now taken a different path, even
        though the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002425">Association</tei:rs> has taken
        voluntary liquidation, I really still cannot see why the last vestiges of the <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000165">testatrix</tei:rs>’s piety have to be denied by the
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002425">Association</tei:rs>, by you, by the
          <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002591">Academy</tei:rs>, or by me. What I mean
        is: the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002591">Academy</tei:rs> ought to welcome
        the opportunity to exhibit a little patience in absorbing the piety offered; it is coming
        into the stipend in no way directly at the wish of the <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000165">testatrix</tei:rs>, but only by accident, and it ought to honor this
        with gratitude. Even if it is the case that my work ‒ just between ourselves ‒ will outlive
        all the academies in the world, nonetheless physically the <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002591">Academy</tei:rs> will outlive me, <tei:pb n="3"/> so it really still
        has time, ample time, to take control of the stipend at its own discretion. However, so long
        as I might live <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002591">it</tei:rs> should make it a
        matter of honor to fulfil the wishes of the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000165"
          >testatrix</tei:rs>, all the more so since it has in mind to adorn the stipend with her
        name. Accordingly, I beg you to impart all this to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000577"
          >Dr. Marx</tei:rs> (whom I do not know personally) and get over to him the wishes of the
        testatrix, which surely cannot strike him as severe. I have absolutely nothing against
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000577">Dr. Marx</tei:rs> or against the <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002591">Academy</tei:rs>. But for the time being the
        situation is another matter altogether. The <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002591"
          >Academy</tei:rs> has time on its side.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">In this spirit, I ask you also to instruct the <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002591">Academy</tei:rs> to place the interest at my disposal in good time, so
        that I can distribute the money secretly to where merit already gained has in some way been
        severely incapacitated.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>With kind regards,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">unsigned</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
