<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="3404" sdoID="OJ-5-38_0a">OJ 5/38, [0a]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="LR">
   <tei:persName>Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
   <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
   <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008423">SchenkerW ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Heinrich to Wilhelm Schenker, undated, c. 1896</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1896-01-01T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-06-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker admonishes his brother Wilhelm for not supporting the family
    financially.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>
   
   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000775">Wilhelm Schenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Liebster <tei:rs type="person"
      key="entity-000775">Wilhelm</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
      place="foot">The date of this letter can be determined (a) by handwriting – the entire letter
      is written in <tei:hi rend="italic">Lateinschrift</tei:hi> – and (b) by Alphons von
      Rothschild’s departure for Paris and the discontinuing of his lessons with Schenker. Assuming
      that Rothschild, who was born in 1878, received his <tei:hi rend="italic">Matura</tei:hi>
      (high school diploma) about the age of 18, that would put the letter in or around the year
      1896.</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Ich muss bei Zeiten an gewisse Dinge dich erinnern, den es sieht eine Weile so aus, als ob
    du gegenüber Fremden besser dich benehmst, als gegenüber deinem eigenen Bruder. So lange ich
    konnte, habe ich die Lasten getragen, u. ich wollte, es wäre nicht zu spät, mich selbst zu
    retten, aus mir etwas Gutes zu machen. Heute aber steht die Sachlage schlimmer, als im Vorjahre.
    Ich habe kein Pauschale mehr, also keine fixen 50 fl. mehr – ein grosser Verlust. <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000743">Rothschild</tei:rs> hat Matura gemacht u. ist nach <tei:rs
     type="place" key="entity-002477">Paris</tei:rs> – das bedeutet wieder einen Verlust von
    ziemlich 42 fl. Und wer weiss, wie es mit den anderen Stunden noch stehen wird? Es mehren sich
    die Anzeichen dafür, dass ich nun büssen muss, was ich versäumt habe an Bildung mit
    einzubringen. 6 Jahre, <tei:del rend="overstrike">wir</tei:del> habe ich schwere Opfer gebracht,
    nun kommt die Strafe des Schicksals für meine Opfer- <tei:pb n="2"/> lust.<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Heinrich writes continuously at this point,
     without paragraph-break.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs> bekommt nur <tei:hi
     rend="underline">31 fl.</tei:hi> monatlich!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
     place="foot">Moriz Schenker, the youngest of the Schenker children (born August 31, 1874),
     would have been 21 or 22 years old, if the editorial dating of this letter is
     correct.</tei:note> Pensionsfondsabzüge machen an 15. <tei:hi rend="underline"> “ !</tei:hi>
    aus, so dass der Arme weniger gegenwärtig hat als zuvor. Wir mussten von dem gewissen Geld für
    den Sommer herunternehmen – es fehlen schon 400 fl. Wir entschlossen uns <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000318">Gutmann</tei:rs> zu uns zu nehmen, damit wir die 40 fl nicht zu zahlen
    brauchen. Übrigens braucht er nur das letzte theoreticum noch zu machen, die practica des III
    hat er vor den Ferien gemacht. – Schliesslich hat <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000319"
     >Sophie</tei:rs> nicht einmal Wäsche, u. sie muss man doch ihr gönnen.<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Sophie Schenker, would have been either about
     31 or 32 years old or 23 or 24 years old (her birthdate is unclear), if the editorial dating of
     this letter is correct; she married Salo Guttmann on January 6, 1898. Guttmann, as indicated
     above, was in the late stages of his medical training. — Heinrich writes continuously at this
     point, without paragraph-break.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich bin nicht imstande heute, alles zu besorgen, da es mir, wie ich sehe, schlechter gehen
    will heuer, als im Vorjahre. Drum bitte ich dich sehr, Geld für die Promotionstaxen und
    Ausstattung bereit zu halten, und <tei:pb n="3"/> sonst viel mehr um mich zu bekümmern, da es
    höchste Zeit ist, dass du mir den Dienst, den ich dir erwiesen, zurückgiebst u. mich etwas
    werden lassest, wo<tei:add place="interlinear-above">durch</tei:add> ich ruhig mein Geld
    verdienen kann. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich hoffe, dass du von der Entfernung nicht herzlos profitiren wirst u. meinem Wunsch
    entsprechen wirst. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Herzlichst dein,</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>



  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Dearest <tei:rs type="person"
      key="entity-000775">Wilhelm</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"
     /></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>I must remind you promptly of certain things, for it appears for a time now as though you
    conduct yourself toward strangers better than toward your own brother. I have borne the burdens
    as long as I could, and wish that it is not too late to salvage making something good of myself.
    Today, however, the situation is worse than last year. I no longer have a stipend, that is, no
    set 50 Florins – a big loss. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000743">Rothschild</tei:rs>
    finished his high school exam and went to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002477"
     >Paris</tei:rs> – that translates into a loss of around 42 Florins. And who knows how things
    will yet be with the other lessons? Signs look increasingly like I must now pay for what, in
    gaining, I missed in education. For six years <tei:del rend="overstrike">we</tei:del> I made
    weighty sacrifices; now comes the fateful punishment for my sacrificial <tei:pb n="2"/>
     lust.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs> is now earning only <tei:hi
     rend="underline">31 Florins</tei:hi> per month, pension deductions come to 15 Florins <tei:hi
     rend="underline">monthly</tei:hi>, so that the poor fellow has at present less than
     before.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> We had to draw on the money intended
    for the summer – 400 Florins are already missing. We decided to take in <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000318">Gutmann</tei:rs> so that we would not have to pay the 40 Florins. By the
    way, he only needs yet to do the final <tei:hi rend="italic">theoreticum</tei:hi>, he already
    did the third <tei:hi rend="italic">practicum</tei:hi> before the vacation. Finally, <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000319">Sophie</tei:rs> doesn’t even have linens, and we must surely
    allow her that.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>I am today not able to provide for everything because, as I see, things are going to be
    worse for me than last year. I thus implore you to have money ready for the promotion fees and
    furnishings, and <tei:pb n="3"/> otherwise be much more mindful of me, because it is high time
    that you repay the service that I rendered to you, and let me become something where<tei:add
     place="interlinear-above">by</tei:add> I can calmly earn my money.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>I hope that you won’t heartlessly turn a profit at a distance, and will comply with my
    wish.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Most cordially, your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>

 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
