<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3516" sdoID="OJ-5-38_60">OJ 5/38, [60]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="LR">
      <tei:persName>Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008423">SchenkerW ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Heinrich to Wilhelm Schenker, dated September 8,
        1929</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1929-09-08T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-10-07</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Heinrich thanks Wilhelm for the hospitality he and his wife provided and
        summarizes what lies immediately ahead in the weeks to come. He also reports on a
        composition he received from Reinhard Oppel, and on a lecture on Bach in which Oppel invoked
        Schenker’s work.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000775">Wilhelm Schenker</marcrel:recipient>

    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Sonntag, <tei:date
            when="1929-09-08">8. 9. 29</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Mein lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775">Wilhelm</tei:rs>!<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is recorded in
            Schenker’s diary for September 8, 1929: “An Wilhelm (Br.): Dank; halte mich seiner
            Einsicht u. Zustimmung für sicher” (“To Wilhelm (letter): thanks; I can be sure of his
            understanding and agreement”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Über die <tei:hi rend="underline">Kiste</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="double-underline">ohne</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">Federn</tei:hi>, die uns nach <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-005362">Sigmundsherberg</tei:rs> führte, läßt sich lachen u. weinen, je nach
        der Laune. Jeden Augenblick schwebten wir in der Luft, dann fielen wir wieder auf die
        Hintere so hart, als fielen wir auf die Steine der Strassen. In Tulln empfanden wir die
        erste Erleichterung, die Sonne gieng wieder. Wir kamen in Wien rechtzeitig genug an, um noch
        für Abend u. Morgen einzukaufen. Der erste Sturm der Post war sehr groß, er gab viel zu
        schaffen, dann begann das erste Heraus- <tei:pb n="2"/> -schälen der Tische, Betten, Sessel
        – kurz<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">‚</tei:supplied> erst heute komme ich, inmitten
        noch notdürftiges erster Ordnung, dazu, dir u. der l. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-008450">Frau Marie</tei:rs> für die unendliche Mühe u. Liebe zu danken, mit
        der Ihr Beide uns umgeben habet. Es ist so schade, daß unser Aufenthalt bei Euch so kurz
        bemessen ist, doch bin ich Euerer Einsicht u. Zustimmung sicher: zwar wisst Ihr schon genug
        von den absonderlichen Schwierigkeiten meines Lebens, wüsstet Ihr aber noch genaueres, Ihr
        würdet es selbst gar nicht anders haben wollen. Solange ich auf die „Praxis“ von Stunden
        angewiesen bin, muß ich nach Schülern ausblicken – Schande genug für <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002506">Österreich</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482"
          >Deutschland</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="3"/> Gleich mit der ersten Post wurde <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000771">LieLiechen</tei:rs> von einem sehr würdigen Geschenke <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000643">Prof D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi>
          Oppel</tei:rs>’s aus <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002479">Leipzig</tei:rs>–<tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002757">Kiel</tei:rs> überrascht, mit der <tei:hi
          rend="underline">Widmung</tei:hi> einer prachtvollen <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >Komposition</tei:hi>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Oppel’s
          waltz arrived the previous day; Schenker wrote enthusiastically about its unusual form and
          excellent content, and the elegance of Oppel’s penmanship. — The letters concerned, both
          dated September 3, 1929, are OJ 13/10, [84] to Heinrich and OJ 13/10, [85] to Jeanette,
          the latter beginning “Please accept this waltz as a small token of me gratitude for all
          the love and good and kind things that you showed me and my boy during the
          vacation!”</tei:note> Da heißt es gleich danken, schön danken, – ich hatte noch eine
        besondere Ursache dazu, da der genannte <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643"
          >Professor</tei:rs> ein sehr treuer Anhänger meiner Lehre ist; so hatte er in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-003044">Halle</tei:rs> einen Vortrag über <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000027">S. Bach</tei:rs> u. mich gehalten, er wirbt in allen Schulen für mich
        u. s. w. So laufen die Fäden u. ich muß sie, <tei:hi rend="underline">wenn ich nur einfach
          leben will</tei:hi>, immer in den Fingern haben, – daher so viel Mühe noch neben der Mühe
          <tei:pb n="4"/> der Werke u. des Unterrichts. Doch im Grunde solltest du mir das Klagen
        verbieten: im Alter von 62 Jahren<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Schenker was in fact 61 years old, having celebrated his most recent birthday earlier in
          the summer.</tei:note> darf der Mensch noch nicht Schluß machen, sonst lasse er sich
        gleich begraben, nicht?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Morgen Montag gehen wir zu <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006074">Prof.
          Fuchs</tei:rs> (wegen meiner Augen) u. zum Zahnarzt (wegen einer Plombe) und so geht es
        dann fort.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wir haben uns erlaubt, Euch den erwünschten Tee zu schicken, möge er Euch gut
        bekommen!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Nochmals herzlichsten, besten Dank </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>für Alles Liebe u. schönste Grüße</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>von mir u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
          >LieLiechen</tei:rs></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">dein</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
          >Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Sunday, <tei:date when="1929-09-08"
            >September 8, 1929</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775">Wilhelm</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>The <tei:hi rend="underline">old jalopy</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="double-underline">without</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">springs</tei:hi>, which took us to <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-005362">Sigmundsherberg</tei:rs>, brings on laughing and crying, according to
        the mood. At any moment, we floated in the air, then fell down again on our backsides so
        hard as though on stones in the street. We felt the first relief only in Tulln, the sun set.
        We arrived in Vienna in good time to do some shopping for the evening and morning. The first
        onslaught of mail was very big, leaving plenty to do. Then began the initial undraping
          <tei:pb n="2"/> of the tables, beds, armchairs – in short, in the midst of the necessities
        of first order only today am I getting around to thanking you and your dear <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-008450">wife Marie</tei:rs> for the endless effort and love with
        which you two surrounded us. It is such a shame that our stay with you was so short, but I
        am certain of your insight and agreement: you two already know enough of the peculiar
        difficulties of my life, but if you knew the details more closely, you would not want to
        have it any different yourselves. As long as I am dependent on the “praxis” of lessons, I
        have to be on the lookout for students – sufficient disgrace for <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002506">Austria</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482"
          >Germany</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="3"/> Right with the first batch of mail <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000771">LieLiechen</tei:rs> was surprised with a very worthy gift from <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000643">Professor Oppel</tei:rs> from <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002479">Leipzig</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002757"
          >Kiel</tei:rs>, with the <tei:hi rend="underline">dedication</tei:hi> of a magnificent
          <tei:hi rend="underline">composition</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> That deserves immediate thanks, sincere thanks, – I had another, special
        motivation for thanks since the aforenamed <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643"
          >professor</tei:rs> is a very devoted disciple of my theory. Thus he gave a lecture in
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003044">Halle</tei:rs> on <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000027">Johann Sebastian Bach</tei:rs> and me. He advocates for me in all
        schools, etc. So run the threads, and <tei:hi rend="underline">if I want to live even
          simply</tei:hi>, I must always have them in my fingers, – thus so much effort alongside of
        the effort <tei:pb n="4"/> of the projects and of the instruction. But at bottom you should
        forbid me any complaining. At the age of 62 years<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
          type="footnote"/> one may not yet call it quits. Otherwise, he could be buried on the
        spot, right?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>On Monday morning we are going to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006074">Professor
          Fuchs</tei:rs> (about my eyes) and to the dentist (about a filling), and so it goes
        onward.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>We allowed ourselves to send you the requested tea. May it very much agree with
        you!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Again, most cordial, abundant thanks</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>for everything,and warmest greetings</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>from me and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
          >LieLiechen</tei:rs></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
          >Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
