<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3455" sdoID="OJ-5-38_41">OJ 5/38, [41]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="LR">
      <tei:persName>Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008423">SchenkerW ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Heinrich to Wilhelm Schenker, dated December 23,
        1927</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1927-12-23T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-07-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Heinrich sends Wilhelm Christmas greetings, but does not know what to give him
        as a present. — He reports that Moriz’s son Georg has left the Vienna Academy so that he can
        study privately with him and earn money playing in the Baden theater orchestra. — Moriz is
        planning to set up an export house in Egypt in the spring. — Schenker also encloses a copy
        of the “Appeal” published by the Photogram Archive.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>
      
      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000775">Wilhelm Schenker</marcrel:recipient>
      
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Mein lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775"
            >Wilhelm</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for December 22, 1927: “An Wilhelm (Br.):
            wissen kein Geschenk u. so bleibe es bei der Erinnerung; erwähne, daß Georg bei mir
            Unterricht nimmt, daß ich ein Honorar zur Sicherstellung des Erfolges fordere. Lege den
            Aufruf bei” (“To Wilhelm (letter): we cannot think of any present, and so our
            recollection must suffice; I mention that Georg is studying with me and that I am
            demanding a fee, to be sure of success. I enclose a copy of the
          Appeal”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Lange dachten wir nach, was wir dir zur Erinnerung an Weihnacht 27 schenken könnten u.
        finden nichts. Gebrauchsgegenstände hast du selber – wir konnten es mit eigenen Augen sehen
        –, auf Luxus u. diegleichen legst du keinen Wert. Was dir fehlt, ist ja Geld, das dir
        möglich machen würde, bequem u. behaglich auszuruhen – von diesem Artikel haben wir
        gewissermaßen noch weniger, wenn du unsere komplizierteren Verhältnisse (Stadt, Beruf usw)
        berücksichtigst, <tei:pb n="2"/> so schicken wir dir diese Zeilen liebevollen Gedankens als
        Zeichen, daß du immer unter uns bist. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ihr müsst jetzt bitter unter der Kälte leiden in dieser freien Landschaft, wo
        gewissermaßen keine Hemming da ist für Wind u. Frost.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker’s diary entries for the previous two days record
          temperatures in Vienna of minus 14 and minus 12 degrees Celsius. </tei:note> Was? Wir
        heizen, was nur geht, um die Räume warm zu halten für Zwecke des Unterrichts sowohl wie der
        eigenen Arbeiten. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Das Neueste: <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000769">Georg</tei:rs> hat
        die <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002591">Akademie</tei:rs> verlassen, meiner
        Ansicht nach sehr zu <tei:hi rend="underline">seinem eigenen</tei:hi> Schaden! Er lernt
        jetzt bei mir, wenn man 1 Stunde die Woche „Lernen“ heißen kann. Ich habe noch kein
        abschließendes <tei:pb n="3"/> Urteil über den Fall. Schon verstehe ich nicht, daß <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000769">Georg</tei:rs> im <tei:hi rend="underline">Badener
          Theater spielt</tei:hi> (dazu in Liesing, <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004066"
          >Mödling</tei:rs>), um nahezu 300 Sch. zu erwerben. Es muß doch nicht sein? Darüber kommt
        er nicht zum Lernen. Muß übrigens der Anfang so ausgehen? Ich habe <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">aus Verantwortungsgefühl</tei:hi> empfohlen, nur die Stunde zu
        honorieren, damit der Junge sich <tei:hi rend="underline">bemüssigt sieht</tei:hi>, das Geld
        abzustudieren: ich habe viel Erfahrung in diesem Artikel, jeder Nachlaß hat <tei:del
          rend="overstrike">schon</tei:del> den Schüler verdorben u. faul gemacht („es kostet ja
        nichts“). Auch muß ich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs> noch über
        manches befragen, ich bat ihn für nächste Zeit zu mir. <tei:pb n="4"/> Ich verstehe das Haus
        nicht. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs> eröffnet in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-004639">Aegypten</tei:rs> ein Exporthaus in Comp. unter seinem
        Namen, Schenker &amp;, etwa im Frühling geht er dorthin ab. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Beiliegend ein „<tei:rs type="other" key="OJ-9-10_2">Aufruf</tei:rs>“, die du lesen
        magst, der Stifter ist der reiche <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380"
          >Holländer</tei:rs>, mein Schüler, von dem ich Euch erzählt habe. Die Idee ist von mir,
        wie du auf der 2. Seite liesest. (Das Geld hat er!) Das Kuratorium ist ein Ehrenamt,
        versteht sich. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Was macht dein Zucker? Wegen des meinen werde ich das Laboratorium erst in der 2.
        Jännerwoche befragen. Mein <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">LieLiechen</tei:rs> hat
        alle Hände voll zu tun, wie doch wahrscheinlich auch die l. Frau <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-008450">Marie</tei:rs>. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Wir wünschen <tei:add place="interlinear-above">Euch</tei:add> angenemste
          Feiertage,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>glücklichster Neujahr.</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="70">Die Deinen</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000771">Lielie</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1927-12-23">23. 12. 27</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775"
            >Wilhelm</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>We reflected extensively about what we could give you as a remembrance of Christmas
        1927 and have come up with nothing. You already have practical items – we could see with our
        own eyes – you put no value on luxury items and the like. What you lack is of course money,
        which could make it possible for you to relax comfortably and contentedly – in a certain
        sense, we have even less of that item when you take into account our complicated
        circumstances (city, profession, etc.). <tei:pb n="2"/> So, we are sending you these lines
        of fond thoughts as a sign that you are always with us.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>You two must be suffering bitterly from the cold in that open countryside where to some
        extent there is no restraint for wind and frost.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> Right? We heat <tei:supplied reason="clarity">the
          apartment</tei:supplied> only enough to keep the rooms warm for purposes of teaching as
        well as for our own work.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">The latest: <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000769">Georg</tei:rs> has
        left the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002591">Academy</tei:rs>, in my view much
        to his <tei:hi rend="underline">own detriment</tei:hi>! He is now studying with me, if one
        can call one hour per week “studying.” I don’t yet have a final <tei:pb n="3"/> judgment on
        the case. I can’t even understand that <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000769"
          >Georg</tei:rs>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">is playing at the Badener Theater</tei:hi> (in Liesing, <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-004066">Mödling</tei:rs>) in order to earn almost 300 shillings.
        That certainly isn’t necessary! Because of that, he doesn’t come for his studies. Does the
        start <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of his studies</tei:supplied>, incidentally, have to
        end that way? <tei:hi rend="underline">Out of a sense of obligation</tei:hi>, I recommended
        to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs> to pay for the lesson only so
        that the boy is <tei:hi rend="underline">obliged to see</tei:hi> that the money is used for
        studying. I have a lot of experience in this matter; every slackening spoils the student and
        makes him lazy (“it doesn’t cost anything”). I must also question even <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs> about some things. I asked him to come and see me soon.
          <tei:pb n="4"/> I don’t understand that household.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs> is opening an export business
        in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004639">Egypt</tei:rs> under his name, Schenker &amp;.
        He will go there sometime in the spring.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Included here, an “<tei:rs type="other" key="OJ-9-10_2">Appeal</tei:rs>” which you may
        want to read. The founder is the rich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380"
          >Dutchman</tei:rs>, the student of mine about whom I told you both. The idea comes from
        me, as you will read on the second page. (He has the money!) That the board of trustees is
        an honorary office goes without saying.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>How is your sugar level? I will first ask the laboratory about mine in the second week
        in January. My <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">LieLiechen</tei:rs> has her hands
        full with things to do, as does probably dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008450"
          >Marie</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>We wish <tei:add place="interlinear-above">you both</tei:add> the most pleasant
          holidays,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>and the happiest New Year.</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="70">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs> and
          Lielie</tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1927-12-23">December 23, 1927</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
