<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <!-- encoding in progress -->
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="453" sdoID="OJ-5-7a_10">OJ 5/7a, [10] (formerly vC 10)</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
   <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>


  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2011-06-12" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002775">Cube ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated June 1, 1927</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1927-06-01T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-06-17</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker congratulates Cube on appointment to professorship; reports that Oppel
    has been appointed to a professorship at the Leipzig Conservatory, and on the spread of
    Schenker's theory elsewhere; looks forward to visit from Cube.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>

   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">Heinrich Schenker</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000143">Felix-Eberhard von Cube</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Lieber Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">v. <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
       >Cube</tei:hi></tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Zu der nun offiziell gewordenen Professur wünsche ich u. meine Frau Ihnen das Allerbeste!
    Von Gottes Gnaden ist zwar mehr als von Professoren Gnade, aber die Welt hält auf Professoren
    (und muß es wohl auch tun, da Gott ihr ununsichtbar u. unhörbar bleibt), da tun Sie also gut,
    auch ihr Zeugnis hinzunehmen. Den Rest haben Sie mit Gott abzumachen, der Sie reichlich
    ausgestattet hat. Auf dem von Ihnen zu beschreitenden Weg wird Sie ermüntern zu hören, daß H.
    Prof. Dr. R. Oppel - den ich Ihnen wohl genannt haben mag - auf an das Leipziger Konservatorium
     <tei:pb n="2"/> als Prof. für Theorie berufen worden, in welcher Eigenschaft er, wie er mir
    mitteilt, mein System offiziell lehren wird. Die Wirkung breitet sich mehr u. mehr aus:
    Edinburgh, (auch New-York),<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"/> Leipzig
    Stuttgart, Wien (ich und Weisse), Vrieslander in München (er schreibt eine große Monographie
    über mich),<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"/> Sie in Duisburg, u.
    Halm usw usw. Das Alles zeigt, daß - trotz Schoenbergs und Hindemiths - auch unsere Stunde
    schlägt; diese Stunde aber dauert eine Ewigkeit, weil sie die Wahrheit, nicht blos eine Mode,
    trägt. Oppel erhält bei 20 Stunden 700 MK,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
     place="foot"/> - das zahlt die Wiener Akademie gewiß nicht. Haben Sie schon Schüler im
    Privat-Unterricht?</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Wir reisen schon am 25.6 nach Galtür. Daß Sie uns besuchen wollen,<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot"/> macht uns <tei:pb n="3"/> Freude schon zum
    Voraus, sie wird noch größer sein, wenn Sie die Absicht wirklich ausführen werden. Ich weiß
    nicht, ob Sie Wien oder Galtür meinen, jedenfalls merke ich an: Galtür im Paznauntal, erreichbar
    auf einer Fußwanderung von der Voralberger Seite, oder am besten mit Auto aus Landeck (oder
    Wiesberg). Prof. Oppel wird uns ebenfalls in Galtür besuchen, auch Direktor Altmann
     (Berlin),<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot"/> Hoboken (vielleicht mit
    Vrieslander).</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Nun auf Wiedersehen. Unser Beider beste Grüsse sendet</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-70">Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">H
     Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1927-06-01">1.6.27</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>

  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Dear Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">von Cube</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Regarding your professorship, which has now become official, my wife and I offer you our
    very best wishes. The grace of God is, of course, more than the grace of professors, but the
    world relies on professors (as it surely has to, since God remains invisible and inaudible to
    it). You are thus doing the right thing to take up your credentials. For the rest, you will have
    to settle your accounts with God, who has endowed you richly. As you follow the path that has
    been set out for you, it will give you encouragement to hear that Professor Reinhard Oppel,
    whose name I have probably mentioned to you, has been appointed <tei:pb n="2"/> Professor of
    Music Theory at the Leipzig Conservatory, in which capacity--so he tells me--he will officially
    teach my system. The effect continues to broaden: Edinburgh (also New York),<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> Leipzig, Stuttgart, Vienna (myself and Weisse),
    Vrieslander in Munich (he is writing a long monograph about me),<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
     type="footnote"/> yourself in Duisburg, and Halm, etc., etc. All this shows that, in spite of
    Schoenberg and Hindemith, the hour has struck for us, too, but this hour will last an eternity
    because it bears the truth, not merely a fashion. Oppel will receive 700 marks for twenty hours
    of teaching;<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> the Vienna Academy certainly does
    not pay as well. Do you already have private pupils?</tei:p>

   <tei:p>On June 25, we are travelling to Galtür. To hear that you are hoping to to visit
     us<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> fills us <tei:pb n="3"/> with delight, which
    will be all the greater if your intentions are actually realized. I do not know whether you mean
    Vienna or Galtür, but let me note in any event: Galtür in the Paznaun Valley, accessible by
    footpath from the Vorarlberg side, or (better) by automobile from Landeck (or Wiesberg).
    Professor Oppel will likewise visit us in Galtür, so will Director Altmann (Berlin),<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> and Hoboke (possibly with Vrieslander).</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Until we see each other again, I send best greetings from the two of us.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-70">Yours,</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">H.
     Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1927-06-01">June 1, 1927</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
