<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3428" sdoID="OJ-5-38_22">OJ 5/38, [22]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="LR">
      <tei:persName>Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008423">SchenkerW ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Heinrich to Wilhelm Schenker, dated February 11,
        1926</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1926-02-11T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-06-15</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Heinrich has sent Wilhelm copies of the portrait of him made by Viktor Hammer,
        and of the medallion cast by Alfred Rothberger. He offers to purchase a radio receiver for
        him, and urges him to visit him in Vienna.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>
      
      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000775">Wilhelm Schenker</marcrel:recipient>
      
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Mein lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775"
            >Wilhelm</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for February 11, 1926: “An Wilhelm (Br.):
            zur Sendung; trage ihm auch einen Rf.-Apparat an.” (“To Wilhelm (letter): on the package
            I sent; I also offer him a radio.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Vielen Dank für Deinen l. Brief.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Schenker’s diary entry for January 23 records the receipt of a letter from
          his elder brother: “Von Wilhelm (Br.): <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003438">Lisl
            Schenker</tei:rs> zahlt für Karli monatlich 70 Schilling; verspricht seinen Besuch.”
          (“From Wilhelm (letter): <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003438">Lisl Schenker</tei:rs>
          is paying 70 shillings a month for Karli; he promises to visit.”).</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Zunächst einmal ließ ich Dir durch die Kunsthandlung <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002413">Artaria</tei:rs> das Bild<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot">A mezzotint portrait of Schenker, made by <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000327">Viktor Hammer</tei:rs> in 1925.</tei:note> sowie die
          Plakette<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">A small bronze
          medallion of Schenker, designed and engraved by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000738"
            >Alfred Rothberger</tei:rs> in the first months of 1925.</tei:note> von mir übersenden.
        Nimm beide freundlich auf! Gewiss sind diese Stücke Zeichen einer gewissen allgemeinen
        Anerkennung, doch darfst du nicht glauben, daß ich nach Ruhm strebe. Ich bin glücklich in
        meiner Aufgabe, in meiner Pflicht gegenüber der Kunst u wann der Ruhm mitkommt, so geschieht
        das von selbst ohne mein Zutun. Der Nichtruhm <tei:del rend="overstrike">sch</tei:del> würde
        meine Freude an die Musik nicht schmälern, <tei:pb n="2"/> u. der Ruhm tut auch nichts dazu.
        Nicht einmal Geld. Aber wenn wir zu essen haben, was fragen wir auch Geld! Übrigens geht es
        jetzt etwas besser als in den beiden verflossenen Jahren. Neue Schüler sind da u. ich
        verdiene eben mehr, kann also auch für spätere Tage etwas zurücklegen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Über die Bilder erzähle ich mehr, bis du zu uns kommst. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Auch über den Radio Apparat möchte ich mit Dir unterhalten. Hast Du jemand, der dir den
        Apparat aufstellen könnte? Das Ohrensausen wird nicht schlechter durch den Apparat. Ich litt
        ja entsetzlich darunter, habe <tei:pb n="3"/> es aber schon seit geraumer Zeit verloren, nur
        wenn ich (in den Stunden) viel spreche oder sonst eine große Aufregung erlebe, kommt es
        wieder für kurze Zeit.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Es würde mir eine Freude machen, dir einen Apparat zu verehren, wenn ich
        nur wüsste, ob <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ihn</tei:add> dir jemand <tei:del
          rend="overstrike">ihn</tei:del> aufstellen kann. Wenn du in Wien bist, besprechen u.
        ordnen wir diese Angelegenheit. Augenblicklich hört der ganze III Bezirk etwas schlechter,
        aber das wird sich hoffentlich geben. Du könntest leichte, leichteste Musik hören, Vorträge,
        usw. usw. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> Vergiß nur nicht zu kommen!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Bald erscheint ein neues Werk von mir.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial"
          place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001750"><tei:title level="j">Das
                Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:title></tei:rs>, vol. I (Munich: Drei Masken Verlag,
            1925)</tei:bibl>, released on June 21, 1926 (<tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OC-54-90">OC 54/90</tei:ref>).</tei:note> Wir arbeiten inzwischen schon an einem
        neuen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">LieLiechen hat wieder 4 Kg verloren vor
          lauter Plage u. Küche, Haus u. an meinen Arbeiten. Ich sehe das nicht gern, u. bestehe
          darauf, daß sie mehr ißt. Meine letzten beiden Analysen waren sehr erfreulich: 0 Zucker, 0
          Aceton. Jetzt habe ich vielleicht wieder eine Kleinigkeit (Arbeit, Arbeit!), aber das gibt
          sich wieder. </tei:rs>
      </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Vergiß nicht zu kommen! Und – schreibe recht bald. </tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="10">Deine dich herzlichst küssenden</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="20"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000771">Lie-Lie</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1926-02-11">11. II. 1926</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775"
            >Wilhelm</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Many thanks for your kind letter.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"
        /></tei:p>

      <tei:p>First and foremost, I have had the picture<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
          type="footnote"/> as well as the medallion<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/>
        sent from me to you through the art dealer <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002413"
          >Artaria</tei:rs>. Kindly accept both! These pieces are surely a sign of a certain general
        recognition, but you ought not to believe that I am pursuing fame. I am content in my
        mission, in my obligation vis-à-vis art, and if fame follows, it happens on its own, without
        my help. The lack of fame would not diminish my joy in music, <tei:pb n="2"/> and fame
        doesn’t add anything to it. Not even money. But if we have something to eat, why are we
        asking for money too! By the way, things are now somewhat better than in the past two years.
        New students have come and I am simply earning more, can thus put away something for future
        times.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I will tell more about the pictures when you come to us.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I also want to talk to you about the radio. Do you have anyone who could set it up for
        you? The aural whooshing won’t worsen because of the radio. I suffered terribly from it,
          <tei:pb n="2"/> but got rid of it some time ago. It returns for a short time only when (in
        lessons) I speak a lot or otherwise experience great excitement.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">It would bring me joy to honor you with a radio if I only knew whether
        someone could set <tei:add place="interlinear-above">it</tei:add> up for you. When you are
        in Vienna, let’s discuss and arrange the matter. At the moment, listening in the entire
        third district is somewhat worse, but that will hopefully soon resolve itself. You could
        listen to light music, the most popular music, lectures, etc., etc.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> Just don’t forget to come!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>A new work of mine will soon appear.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> In
        the meantime, we’re already working on a new one.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">LieLiechen has lost an additional 4 kilograms
          from pure hard work and kitchen duty, housework, and my projects. I don’t like seeing that
          and insist that she eat more. My last two blood tests were very gratifying: 0 sugar, 0
          acetone. Now, I perhaps again have a little bit (work, work!), but that will again take
          care of itself.</tei:rs>
      </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Don’t forget to come! And – write really soon.</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="10">Your most cordially kissing</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="20"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs> and
            <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Lie-Lie</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1926-02-11">February 11,
        1926</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
