<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3451" sdoID="OJ-5-38_37">OJ 5/38, [37]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="LR">
      <tei:persName>Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008423">SchenkerW ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Heinrich to Wilhelm Schenker, dated September 24,
        1927</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1927-09-24T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-07-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Heinrich reports on making inquiries on behalf of Tonerl; he also tells his
        brother that the new denture fits perfectly, and that he can eat and speak with
        ease.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>
      
      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000775">Wilhelm Schenker</marcrel:recipient>
      
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Sonntag, <tei:date
            when="1927-03-28">24. 9. 27</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Mein lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775"
            >Wilhelm</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for September 25, 1927: “An Wilhelm (Br.):
            über das Ergebnis der Umfrage, über das Gebiß usw.” (“To Wilhelm (letter): concerning
            the result of the general inquiries, about the denture, etc.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Seit einer Woche trage ich schon die neuen Zähne u. bin darüber <tei:hi
          rend="underline">beglückt</tei:hi>! Alle meine Angstvorstellungen, die mir den Sommer so
        gründlich verdorben haben, sind zu Schanden geworden, hätte ich es nur schon vor 2 Jahren
        gemacht! <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000646">D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi>
          Orlay</tei:rs> war so genau, mir einen einzigen Original-Zahn noch immer zu belassen (zog
        also nur einen <tei:add place="interlinear-above">Zahn</tei:add>, statt zwei). Noch am
        selben Tage konnte ich flott sprechen, schreien, u. am <tei:hi rend="underline">Abend
          desselben Tages</tei:hi> konnte ich auch schon essen, <tei:hi rend="underline">über
          Erwarten gut essen</tei:hi>! <tei:pb n="2"/> Mir ist, als wäre die neue Zähne wie eigen,
        so gut vertragen <tei:add place="interlinear-above">sie</tei:add> sich <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">unter</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">mit</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>einander der eigenen Zahn und die neuen. Wegen des Honorars steht die Rechnung
        noch aus, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000646">D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi>
          Orlay</tei:rs> bleibt also bei seiner Nettigkeit, die Rechnung erst zum Jahresschluß
        vorzulegen. (Umso besser für mich.) Das Alles erzähle ich dir, um dich über die Zukunft
        deines Gebisses zu beruhigen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Im Laufe von 9 Tagen habe ich 2 Kg 30 zurückerobert! Ich fühle mein Gewicht noch immer
        wachsen, was mich sehr, sehr freut, denn meine Tätigkeit fräße mich sonst auf. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000324">Direktor Halberstam</tei:rs>, bei dem ich
        vorigen Sonntag vorsprach, fand mich <tei:hi rend="underline">ausgezeichnet</tei:hi>.
          <tei:pb n="3"/> Gegen meine ständige Neigung zur Diarrhoë (bei so viel Fett, das ja das
        Hauptstück der Zucker-Diät ist) verschrieb er mir 2 Dinge, eins davon ist (glaube ich) das
        schwarze Ding, das du einnimmst.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >The visit to Dr. Halberstam is recorded in Schenker’s diary for September 18; the
          black substance is not identified.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun zum Wichtigsten:</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wegen des l. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003491">Tonerl</tei:rs> haben wir
        gestern an einer Stelle gefragt, die Motor-Räder auf den Markt bringt. Dazu gehört freilich
        ein „Mechaniker“, aber der Herr versprach sich anderweitig zu bekümmern. <tei:hi
          rend="underline">Unser Schlosser</tei:hi> war noch immer nicht bei uns, obwohl er etwas zu
        tun hat. Da müssen wir noch warten. Darüber sowohl wie über das Ergebnis weiterer Bemühungen
        werde <tei:pb n="4"/> ich dir berichten, wir werden uns alle erdenkliche Mühe geben. Schon
        aus dem einen Gespräch mit H. Kellner<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Probably Kellner and Sons, furniture and official articles, Mariahilfe Straße
          51, Vienna VI, from whom Schenker bought furniture over many years.</tei:note> entnehme
        ich, daß die Sache nicht gar so leicht ist, nämlich heute, da ich außerdem seit nahezu 25
        Jahren alle Beziehungen freiwillig aufgegeben habe. Doch, wie gesagt, wir wollen uns die
        Mühe gewiß nicht verdichten lassen und weiter sehen, hier u. dort. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Den l. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs> u. den l. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000769">Georg</tei:rs> haben wir schon bei uns gesehen. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Dir, der l. Frau <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008450">Marie</tei:rs> sowie
            <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003491">Tonerl</tei:rs></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>unser Beide beste Grüße</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="70">dein</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
          >Heinrich</tei:rs><tei:lb/></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p>Wir erwarten einen „Lautsprecher“ von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004819">Prof.
            Richtera</tei:rs></tei:p>

        <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">sideways in left and upper
            margins:</tei:note> Zum Orthopäden fanden wir noch den Weg nicht, so viel Wichtigeres
          kam allemal dazwischen.</tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Sunday, <tei:date when="1927-03-28"
            >September 24, 1927</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775"
            >Wilhelm</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>I have been using the new teeth for a week and am very <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >happy</tei:hi> about them! All of my imagined anxieties that so thoroughly ruined the
        summer for me were swept away. If I had only done it two years ago! <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000646">Dr. Orlay</tei:rs> was so precise in leaving me a single original
        tooth (thus he pulled only one <tei:add place="interlinear-above">tooth</tei:add> instead of
        two). I was able to speak fluently, yell, on the same day, and in the <tei:hi
          rend="underline">evening of the same day</tei:hi> I could already eat, and <tei:hi
          rend="underline">eat well beyond expectation</tei:hi>! <tei:pb n="2"/> To me, it is as
        though the new teeth were my own, so well do <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >they</tei:add> fit <tei:add place="interlinear-above">with</tei:add> one another, my own
        teeth and the new ones. Regarding the fee, the bill is still outstanding. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000646">Dr. Orlay</tei:rs> thus remains in his kind way by not
        issuing the bill until the end of the year. (All the better for me.) I am telling you all of
        this in order to reassure you about the future of your teeth.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In the past nine days, I have put on 2.30 kilograms! I feel my weight still increasing,
        which makes me very, very happy, because my activity would otherwise consume me</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000324">Director Halberstam</tei:rs>, with whom I
        spoke last Sunday, found me to be <tei:hi rend="underline">in excellent shape</tei:hi>.
          <tei:pb n="3"/> Against my ongoing tendency toward diarrhea (with so much fat, which is
        the main element in a diabetic diet), he prescribed for me two things. One of them is (I
        believe) the black thing that you take.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"
        /></tei:p>

      <tei:p>And now to come to the most important matter:</tei:p>

      <tei:p>On behalf of dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003491">Tonerl</tei:rs>, we
        inquired yesterday at a location that brings motorbikes on the market. That naturally
        includes a “mechanic,” but the fellow indicated that he was concerned with other things.
          <tei:hi rend="underline">Our locksmith</tei:hi> has still not come by, although he has
        some work to do. We still have to wait. <tei:pb n="4"/> I will report to you on that, as
        well as on the result of our further efforts. We will take all conceivable care. From the
        one conversation with H. Kellner,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> I already
        gather that the matter is not at all so easy, namely today, since I, moreover, have
        voluntarily given up all connections almost twenty-five years ago. Nevertheless, as I said,
        we certainly don’t want to let our efforts run aground and we shall keep our eyes open here
        and there.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>We have already seen <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs> and
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000769">Georg</tei:rs> at our place.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>To you, your wife <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008450">Marie</tei:rs>, as
          well as to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003491">Tonerl</tei:rs></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>best regards from us both,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="70">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
          >Heinrich</tei:rs><tei:lb/></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p>We’re expecting a “loudspeaker” from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-004819">Prof.
            Richtera</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

        <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">sideways in left and upper
            margins:</tei:note> We didn’t get to the orthopedist yet; so many other, more important
          things came up in the interim.</tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
