<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="3405" sdoID="OJ-5-38_0b">OJ 5/38, [0b]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="LR">
   <tei:persName>Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
   <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
   <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008423">SchenkerW ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Heinrich to Wilhelm Schenker, undated, c. 1897</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1897-01-01T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-06-06</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker asks his brother Wilhelm to provide further financial support for the
    family, especially in view of their sister Sophie’s forthcoming marriage to Salo
    Gutmann.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>
   
   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000775">Wilhelm Schenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Liebster <tei:rs type="person"
      key="entity-000775">Wilhelm</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
      place="foot">This must be an early letter, as Moriz Schenker was here still in school
      (training) and Sophie was engaged but in need of a dowry. As Sophie married Salo Gutmann on
      January 6, 1898, the letter may date from the previous year, 1897.</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Also es geht <tei:hi rend="underline">nicht</tei:hi><tei:supplied>.</tei:supplied>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">Die Statuten sind unüberwindlich</tei:hi>, nicht einmal <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000743">B Rotschild</tei:rs>, der Verwaltungsrath der Base ist,
    konnte mit seinem Empfehlungsschreiben, das du selbst nicht herzlicher hättest abfassen können,
    helfen. Damit du den Fall der Statuten verstehst, würde ich dir empfehlen, ins Nonnenkloster zu
    gehen. Nicht einmal der Papst könnte dir da helfen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Die <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000319">Sophie</tei:rs> ist eben nicht als Tochter
    deines Eisenbahnbeamten geboren<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The
     allusion is undoubtedly to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000051">Albin Bednař,
     snr</tei:rs>, Oberinspektor of the Aspang railway, and a close friend of the Schenker family,
     especially of Wilhelm’s family.</tei:note> – und da nützt keine Protektion. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>– – – Es thut mir nur leid, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000743">B. Rotsch.</tei:rs>
    bemüht zu haben, denn nicht sobald kann ich wieder anklopfen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>. . . . Im Übrigen hätte es mich gefreut, wenn es gegangen wäre, denn ich dachte mit
    diesem Schock eigentlich nur dir eine momentane Erleichterung zu verschaffen. Denn es naht, es
    ist vielmehr die Zeit da, wo ich dich sehr stark belasten muß, gegen meinen Plan und gegen
    meinen Willen die Sorgen und Aufregungen der ersten paar Wochen, die ich in Wien verlebte, die
    gegenwärtigen Sorgen <tei:pb n="2"/> um die du dich nicht einmal kümmerst. Die schrecklichen
    Pflichten, die ich zu erfüllen hatte und habe,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
     place="foot">Heinrich is referring to the responsibilities for the family that he took on after
     the death of his father Johann in 1887, three years after he had moved to Vienna. At the time,
     he was completing his legal studies at the University, and had just enrolled at the
     Conservatory, and the death had – according to his testimony (<tei:ref type="correspondence"
      cRef="DLA-69.930-10">DLA 69.930/10</tei:ref>) – obliged him to take on piano pupils in order
     the finance his support of family members.</tei:note> haben mich <tei:add
     place="interlinear-above">in</tei:add> einen permanenten Zustand von Nervosität und
    Kopfschmerzen geschleudert, den ich gar nicht beseitigen kann. Ich kann nicht mehr arbeiten und
    wenn du nicht glaubst, so werde ich dir <tei:hi rend="underline">ein Zeugnis</tei:hi> von
     <tei:hi rend="underline">Prof. D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi>
     Benedikt</tei:hi><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Possibly Moriz
     Benedikt (1835–1920), distinguished Viennese neurologist and Professor of Neurology at the
     University of Vienna. Schenker also corresponded with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000060"
      >Moriz Benedikt</tei:rs> (1849–1920), editor of the <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002559"
       ><tei:title level="j">Neue Freie Presse</tei:title></tei:rs>, but the only surviving letter
     from him dates from much later (November 18, 1918).</tei:note> schicken, der eine Ruhepause von
    ein paar Monaten für mein überangestrengtes, sorgenzerquet<tei:del rend="overstrike"
    >z</tei:del>schtes Gehirn verlangt. Ich kann nichts dafür, daß meine Gesundheit total versagt.
    Es kostet mir Mühe, eine einzige Stunde nur zu geben. Du dachtest immer in deiner Sorglosigkeit,
    ich bin halt ein gutes, brauchbares Vorspannpferd. Nur siehe da, ich selber glaubte es, und es
    ist doch nicht wahr. Ich bin total zerrüttet. Ich befürchte sehr, überhaupt <tei:hi
     rend="underline">definitiv ins Bett gehen zu müssen</tei:hi>, oder irrsinnig zu werden. Ich
    fühle so krank, daß ich nicht einmal zu gestehen wage. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Das ist so die erste Frucht deines Verhältnisses zu mir. Ich rede jetzt nicht von den
    Opfern an Talent, Zukunft, die du von mir immer <tei:pb n="3"/> zu deinem Gunsten verlangtest
    und verlangst, aber du wirst nicht blind sein, einzusehen, daß meine Gesundheit <tei:hi
     rend="underline">Voraussetzung ist für die ganze Familie</tei:hi>. Besuche mich in Wien, so
    wirst du dich überzeugen, wie rasend der Kopfschmerz wächst, und wie unfähiger ich werde, von
    Tag zu Tag, etwas zu leisten. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Gestern hatten wir Zins gezahlt. <tei:hi rend="underline">Du mußt uns etwas Geld
     schicken</tei:hi>, ich weiß nicht mehr, wo zu leihen – und diese Sorge ertrage ich überhaupt
    jetzt nicht mehr. Besinne doch auf deine Pflichten!!! </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich schreibe kau, den Brief, so bin ich müde seit gestern Abend. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Für die <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000319">Sophie</tei:rs> ist eine Heirath <tei:hi
     rend="underline">garantirt</tei:hi>, eine prächtige Partie, das der <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000318">junge Mann</tei:rs>, mir gut bekannt, 100 fl fixen Gehaltes hat, – und was
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000319">sie</tei:rs> braucht, ist 2000 fl Mitgift. Du weißt,
    daß mich <tei:unclear reason="reading">die</tei:unclear>
    <tei:hi rend="italic">Stern</tei:hi> so lange nicht braucht, als ich nicht fest engagirt bin,
    und du weißt, daß ich schon längst engagirt wor- <tei:pb n="4"/> den wäre, wenn du nur halben
    Verstand gehabt hättest, – es ist durchaus deine Schuld, wenn ich der <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000319">Schwester</tei:rs> jetzt nicht einmal das <tei:hi rend="underline"
     >Opfer</tei:hi> bringen kann, das ich sonst gebracht hätte. Heute wirst du mir vielleicht
    glauben, daß ich mit der Baronin Königswarter,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial"
     place="foot">Königswarter (Koenigswarter): a Jewish Austrian-Hungarian noble family, who made
     their fortune in banking in the 19th century; possibly referred to might be Hélène Joséphine
     Kœnigswarter (1873–1922) or Alice de Kœnigswarter (1878–1963). — Nothing is known of Baron
     Bozecny.</tei:note> Baron Bozecny gesprochen habe, aber ohne Erfolg. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich hoffe, daß du in Rücksicht auf unseren Zustand ganz anders handeln wirst, als bis nun
    – sonst <tei:hi rend="underline">wird es zu spät</tei:hi>, und dann wirst du <tei:hi
     rend="underline">jämmerlich weinen</tei:hi>, und Gewissensbusse machen, einen Bruder
     um<tei:supplied reason="obscured_by_fold_in_paper">ge</tei:supplied>bracht zu haben, der
     <tei:supplied reason="obscured_by_fold_in_paper">es</tei:supplied> mit Allen besser
     <tei:supplied reason="obscured_by_fold_in_paper">mach</tei:supplied>t, als du. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Beliebe sofort zu antworten</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">deinem</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p>Schreibe noch heute, zu uns, – da ja all das kein Geheimnis mehr ist, seit einer Woche! </tei:p>

    <tei:p>Herzlichen Gruß – an die l. Frau <tei:unclear reason="reading"
      >Schimatov</tei:unclear><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Probably
      abbreviation of “Schimatowitsch,” i.e. the mother of “<tei:rs type="person"
       key="entity-000766">Tonschl</tei:rs>.” She died in 1921, after which Wilhelm took over
      responsibilities for the care of Tonschl’s two children. She may have been a former partner of
      Wilhelm.</tei:note></tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>



  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Dearest <tei:rs type="person"
      key="entity-000775">Wilhelm</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"
     /></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>So, it will <tei:hi rend="underline">not</tei:hi> work. <tei:hi rend="underline">The
     statutes are insurmountable</tei:hi>. Not even <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000743">Baron
     Rothschild</tei:rs>, who is the administrative attorney of my cousin, was able to help with his
    letter of recommendation, which not even you could have formulated more sincerely. So that you
    understand the case of the statutes, I would recommend that you go to a nunnery. Not even the
    Pope would be able to help you there.</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000319">Sophie</tei:rs> was not just born as daughter of
    your railway official<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> – and in that case no
    protection is of use.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>– – – I am just sorry to have troubled <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000743">Baron
     Rothschild</tei:rs>, because I shall not be able to knock at his door again so soon.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>. . . . Apart from that, I would have been happy had it worked it out, because with that
    shock I thought to give only you momentary relief. For it is getting close, or rather the time
    is here, when I must burden you very heavily, contrary to my plan and contrary to my will, with
    the worries and commotion of the first few weeks that I experienced in Vienna, the present
    worries <tei:pb n="2"/> about which you don’t even bother yourself. The horrible
    responsibilities that I had and still have to fulfill<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
     type="footnote"/> have cast me <tei:add place="interlinear-above">into</tei:add> a permanent
    condition of nervousness and headaches from which I cannot free myself. I can no longer work,
    and if you don’t believe me, then <tei:hi rend="underline">I will send you a report from
     Professor Dr. Benedikt</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> who insists on
    a break of a few months for my overworked, worry-crushed brain. It’s not my fault that my health
    is totally breaking down. It requires effort for me to work even a single hour. In your
    worry-free condition, you always thought that I am simply a good, useful horse hitched to a
    wagon. And just look, I myself believed it, and it is nevertheless not true. I am a total wreck.
    I greatly fear that <tei:hi rend="underline">I shall be definitively bedridden</tei:hi> or go
    insane. I feel so sick that I don’t even dare to admit it.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>That is in a way the first fruit of your relationship with me. I am not talking now about
    the sacrifices in talent and future prospects, which you always <tei:pb n="3"/> demanded and
    continue to demand of me to your benefit. But you won’t be blind to the understanding that my
    good health <tei:hi rend="underline">is a precondition for the entire family</tei:hi>. If you
    visit me in Vienna, you will then convince yourself of how furiously the headaches are growing
    and how much more incapable I am becoming from one day to the next of accomplishing
    anything.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Yesterday, we paid rent. <tei:hi rend="underline">You have to send us some money</tei:hi>.
    I no longer know where to borrow – and I can now no longer tolerate that worry at all. Do
    consider your obligations!!! </tei:p>

   <tei:p>I can barely write this letter, so tired am I since yesterday evening.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>A wedding is <tei:hi rend="underline">guaranteed</tei:hi> for <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000319">Sophie</tei:rs>, a splendid event. The <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000318">young man</tei:rs>, whom I know well, has a stable salary of 100 Florins,
    and what <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000319">she</tei:rs> needs is a dowry of 2,000
    Florins. You know that Mr.[?] Stern doesn’t need me unless I am steadily employed, and you know
    that I would have long since been employed <tei:pb n="4"/> if you had had only half an
    understanding – it is completely your fault if now I can’t even make the <tei:hi
     rend="underline">sacrifice</tei:hi> for our <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000319"
     >sister</tei:rs> that I would otherwise have made. You will perhaps believe me today that I
    have spoken with Baroness Königswarter,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> Baron
    Bozecny, but without success.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>In light of our condition, I hope that you will act very differently than up to now. It
    will otherwise <tei:hi rend="underline">be too late</tei:hi>, and then you will <tei:hi
     rend="underline">woefully cry</tei:hi> and have pangs of conscience for having killed a brother
    who does better than you with everyone.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>I appeal to you to answer immediately.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p>Write to us even today since all of this is no longer a secret, for a week,</tei:p>

    <tei:p>Warm greetings to dear Mrs. Schimatov<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"
     /></tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>

 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
