<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="606" sdoID="OJ-5-45_5">OJ 5/45, [5]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="sole">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2011</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>


  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-11-09" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002737">Weisse ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002715">Weisse ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Copy of letter from Schenker to Weisse, in Jeanette Schenker’s hand, dated January 12,
    1924</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1924-01-12T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2011-11-09</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker outlines his attitude to Bamberger's leaving him, and offers advice to
    Weisse. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Stunden; lessons; Natur; nature; Studium; study; Reife; maturity; Lieblingsplan;
    favorite plan; Gesetz; law; Inspirationsnerv; nerve of inspiration; Theorie; theory; Praxis;
    practice </dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000951">Weisse</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:byline><tei:hi rend="double-underline">An D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi> Hans
      Weisse</tei:hi>
     <tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:del rend="overstrike">14</tei:del>. I. 24</tei:hi><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is recorded in
      Schenker's diary at OJ 3/6, p. 2619, January 12, 1924: "An Weisse (Brief, von Lie-Liechen
      abgeschrieben): gegen seinen Rat an Bamberger: Angst ein ritenuto; Ehrenjahre oder –Monate
      tragen nichts ein, alles ist die Sphäre u. die warme Einstellung – daher wünsche ich auch
      Rückkehr zu Haydn. Krethi u. Plethi müssen draußenbleiben!" ("To Weisse (letter, copied out by
      Lie-Liechen): against his advice to Bamberger: fear [is] a ritenuto; honorable years or months
      do not bring any returns, everything you need is in a sphere, [and] heartfelt in approach –
      that is why I wish to return to Haydn. Krethi and Plethi must stay outside!").
     </tei:note></tei:byline>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Eigens nehme ich mir Zeit, um Ihnen zu sagen u. zu begründen, daß Ihr Rat an
    unseren <tei:rs key="entity-000034" type="person">Bamberger</tei:rs> nicht zutreffend ist.
    Montag werde ich ihm sagen, daß ich, selbst wenn die Entfernung der Amerikanerin mir Stunden
    übrigließe, ihm keine Extrastunden geben werde: sie wären schädlich. Ich denke so: Junge Leute,
    verlassen ihre Lehrer meist im Gefühl des Ueberdrusses, sie fühlen irgendwie, daß sie nichts
    Rechtes gelernt haben, oder aber sie stürmen hinaus in wirklicher Unschuld, ohne Ahnung, daß
    etwas zu lernen gewesen wäre, zu lernen sei. Aller Rest ist Folgerichtigkeit der Natur. Reife
    muß Eigenprodukt bleiben, sie ist nicht übertragbar, nicht erzwingbar durch vermehrte Jahre des
    Studiums. Angst aber ist der <tei:del rend="overstrike">S</tei:del> schlimmste Führer zur Reife.
    Sie kennen das Gesetz des <tei:term>ritenuto</tei:term>: einmal ihm ohne Grund ergeben, kommt
    man nicht mehr heraus u. findet das <tei:term>Tempo</tei:term> nicht, man verdirbt dieses erst
    recht; Angst aber ist das unseligste <tei:term>ritenuto</tei:term>. Daß ich <tei:rs key="entity-000034" type="person">Bamberger</tei:rs> gern habe, wissen Sie. Ich habe mir alle
    Mühe um ihn genommen. Auch meinen Lieblingsplan habe ich ihm entworfen: Nur für die Besten aufs
    Beste zu wirken! Aber der Umstände Herr ist weder er, noch weniger bin ich es. Vielleicht ist es
     <tei:rs key="entity-000034" type="person">Bamberger</tei:rs>s Bestimmung bei der Oper zu
    bleiben – wer weiß das? Auf seinen Vater <tei:unclear reason="reading">einzuwirken</tei:unclear>
    ist heute um <tei:pb n="2"/> viele Jahre zu spät, kurz u. gut: es wird kommen, wie es kommen
    muß. Er kam zu mir, <tei:sic>fibernd</tei:sic> vor Angst des Bleibenmüssens. Er hat diese Angst
    überwinden gelernt, nun <tei:subst>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">soll</tei:add>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">will</tei:del>
    </tei:subst> er mit Angst schließen? Er muss sich auf sich stellen – es ist das ein
    unerbittliches Gesetz der Natur. Noch ehe ein<tei:del rend="overstrike">e</tei:del> junges
    Frauengeschöpf selbst erzogen ist, hat sie schon ein Wimmerl an der Brust u. muß erziehen, ohne
    es zu können. Man sagt, Reue kommt zu spät – zu spät kommt leider auch die Reife – aber die
    Natur will es so. Er muß also hell von mir fort u. mache Dummheiten so viele zu ihm eben
    gehören. Eine Zusicherung dagegen gibt es nicht. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Und bei dieser Gelegenheit möchte ich auch Ihnen raten: zurück zu <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person">Haydn</tei:rs>, Krithi u. Rithi<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:hi rend="italic">Kriti</tei:hi> and <tei:hi rend="italic">riti</tei:hi>: terms used in the classical music of southern India (Carnatic music). In
     choosing terms that rhyme with each other, Schenker may at the same time be mocking Weisse’s
     interest in non-Western music. </tei:note> lassen Sie draußen. Schade um <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs>
    <tei:rs key="entity-001352" type="composition">III.</tei:rs>, der Sie untreu wurden, schade ist
    um <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person">Haydn</tei:rs>. Sie sehen ja, wie ich es halte:
    Wenn Sie mir etwas vorlegen, sage ich, ich improvisiere; ich habe zu viel Respekt vor dem
    Inspirationsnerv eines Großen, als daß ich mir einbildete, über plötzliche Anfrage sofort auf
    jenen <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">illegible word</tei:note> stoßen zu können.
    Machen Sie es doch auch so. Sie geben gewiß Ihr bestes Ihren Schülern; wird es noch besser
    werden in 5 – 10 Jahren, dann umso besser. Alles aber ist die Sphäre des Werkes, die warme
    Einstellung. Ihr Ehrenjahr mit den tausend Fragen hat Ihnen sicher nicht <tei:add place="interlinear-above">so</tei:add> viel <tei:pb n="3"/> eingetragen, als eine völlig
    gesammelte Einstellung; jedenfalls hat es Sie in der rein künstlerischen u. menschlichen Anlage
    mehr geschädigt, als es Ihnen wirklichen Gewinn eintrug. Denken Sie solche Ehrenmonate bei
    unserem <tei:rs key="entity-000034" type="person">Bamberger</tei:rs>: in 5 – 10 Jahren kommt er
    gelegentlich an das eine oder das andere Werk, die Erinnerung ist verdunkelt, ein Mißverständnis
    kommt dazu, was hat er davon? nicht den geringsten Halt. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Daher komme ich zurück (<tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">ceterum
     censeo</tei:foreign><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:hi rend="italic">ceterum censeo</tei:hi> (Lat.): lit. "however, I reckon," "For the rest, it is
     my opinion." </tei:note>) u. sage: Wir machen <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person">Haydn</tei:rs> u. sonst nichts. Ist das Ganze eigentlich überflussig, so kann es Sinn nur
    haben, wenn wir die ganze Kunst in einem solchen Stücke suchen. Vergessen Sie sonst Alle u.
    Alles. <tei:rs key="entity-000034" type="person">Bamberger</tei:rs> können Sie ja diesen Brief
    zeigen, damit er sich überzeuge, daß ichs gut mit ihm meine, wenn er auch für den Augenblick das
    Gefühl hätte, etwas zu verlieren. Ich werde ihm Montag von dem Brief selbst sprechen<tei:del rend="overstrike">,</tei:del> u. sagen, daß ich Ihnen schrieb, weil ich auch Sie in Theorie u.
    Praxis noch immer auf einem falschen Wege sehe. Angst verloren, dann ist alles gewonnen, Angst
    behalten, ist alles verloren! </tei:p>

   <tei:closer rend="indent-60"><tei:salute>Ihr </tei:salute><tei:lb/>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Schenker</tei:rs>
    </tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-70"><tei:date when="1924-01-12">12. I. 24</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>



  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:byline><tei:hi rend="double-underline">To Dr. Hans Weisse</tei:hi>
     <tei:hi rend="underline"> January <tei:del rend="overstrike">14</tei:del>,
      1924</tei:hi><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:byline>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">I am especially taking the time to tell you that, and to explain why, your
    advice to our <tei:rs key="entity-000034" type="person">Bamberger</tei:rs> is inapplicable. On
    Monday I shall tell him that I shall not give him any additional lessons, even if the departture
    of the American lady allows me spare hours for lessons. My reasoning is as follows: young people
    leave their teachers usually with a feeling of weariness; they somehow feel that they have not
    learned anything useful; or, on the other hand, they storm out in an actual state of innocence,
    without realising that there had been or is anything to learn. All the rest is the consequence
    of nature. Maturity must be one’s own product; it is not transferable, it cannot be forced upon
    one by many years of study. Fear, however, is the worst guide to maturity. You know the law of
      <tei:term><tei:hi rend="italic">ritenuto</tei:hi></tei:term>: once one gives into it without
    justification, one cannot escape and regain the <tei:term>tempo</tei:term>, one gets entangled
    in the problem even more so; fear, however, is the most wretched <tei:term><tei:hi rend="italic">ritenuto</tei:hi></tei:term>. That I like <tei:rs key="entity-000034" type="person">Bamberger</tei:rs> is something of which you are aware. I have taken every care with him. I
    have even devised my favourite plan for him: to give my best students the very best! But he is
    not master of his fate; still less am I. Perhaps it is <tei:rs key="entity-000034" type="person">Bamberger</tei:rs>’s calling to remain in the opera house – who knows? It is too late, by many
    years, to exert an influence on his father; <tei:pb n="2"/> in short, let come what may. He came
    to me in a feverish anxiety of having to stay. He learned to overcome this anxiety, now will he
    have done with anxiety? He must rely upon himself – that is indeed an inexorable law of nature.
    Even before a young female being has herself grown up, she has a mark on her breast and must
    nurture, without knowing how. It is said that regret arrives too late – maturity, too,
    unfortunately arrives to late – but Nature wills it thus. He must therefore make a clean break
    with me, and do as many foolish things as he has within him. A guarantee against this does not
    exist. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">And may I on this occasion advise you, too: back to <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person">Haydn</tei:rs>, leave <tei:hi rend="italic">Kriti</tei:hi>
    and <tei:hi rend="italic">riti</tei:hi><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> behind.
    A pity about <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs>’s <tei:rs key="entity-001352" type="composition">Third</tei:rs>, to which you were unfaithful; a pity,
    too, about <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person">Haydn</tei:rs>. You understand, for sure,
    how I see things. When you put something in front of me, I say that I am improvising; I have too
    much respect for the inspirational nerve of a great figure that I should delude myself into
    thinking that I could immediately come up with the answer to a sudden question. You should do
    the same. You must certainly be giving your pupils your best; if things continue to improve over
    the next five to ten years, then so much the better. Everything, however, is the sphere of the
    artwork, the proper attitude. Your year of honor, with its thousand questions, has certainly not
    brought you so much <tei:pb n="3"/> as a fully serene attitude; in any event it has done you
    more damage in the purely artistic and human realm as it has brought you true gain. Think about
    such months of honor with regard to our <tei:rs key="entity-000034" type="person">Bamberger</tei:rs>: in five to ten years he may occasionally come across some work or other,
    his memory of which is obscured; a misunderstanding creeps in, and what does he have over it?
    Not the slightest control. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">And so I come back (<tei:foreign xml:lang="lat"><tei:hi rend="italic">ceterum
      censeo</tei:hi></tei:foreign><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/>) and say: let us
    do <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person">Haydn</tei:rs> and nothing else. If the whole is in
    fact superfluous, it can only have meaning if we seek out the whole of art in one such piece.
    Forget everyone and everything else. You can of course show this letter to <tei:rs key="entity-000034" type="person">Bamberger</tei:rs>, so that he may be convinced that I mean
    well by him, even if at the moment he has the feeling of losing something. I will speak to him
    about the letter myself, and tell him that I wrote to you because I see you, too, are still
    taking a false path in theory and practice. When your fear is gone, everything is won; hold on
    to your fear, and everything is lost! </tei:p>

   <tei:closer rend="indent-60"><tei:salute>Your </tei:salute><tei:lb/>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Schenker</tei:rs>
    </tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline rend="ident-70"><tei:date when="1924-01-12">January 12,
     1924</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>

 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>