<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3459" sdoID="OJ-5-38_46">OJ 5/38, [46]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="LR">
      <tei:persName>Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008423">SchenkerW ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Heinrich to Wilhelm Schenker, dated June 12, 1928</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1928-06-12T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-07-12</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>The Schenkers are leaving for Galtür earlier than usual, to avoid any fuss
        being made over his 60th birthday. The sugar in his urine is reduced, and his blood pressure
        is good. They would like to pay Wilhelm and his wife Marie a visit at the end of the summer,
        but this is dependent on their finding a new maid.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>
      
      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000775">Wilhelm Schenker</marcrel:recipient>
      
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute>Mein lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775">Wilhelm</tei:rs>!<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is recorded in
            Schenker’s diary for June 12, 1928: An Wilhelm (Br.): melde die vorzeitige Abreise u.
            kündige unseren Besuch als möglich an” (“To Wilhelm (letster): I announce our early
            departure and inform him that we may visit him”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Ausnahmsweise verlassen wir Wien diesmal schon den <tei:date when="1928-06-16"
            >16<tei:hi rend="supralinear">ten</tei:hi></tei:date> u. treffen in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs> am <tei:date when="1928-06-18">18<tei:hi
            rend="supralinear">ten</tei:hi></tei:date> ein.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Heinrich and Jeanette departed Vienna June 16 arriving
          Galtür June 18, and departed Galtür August 29, arriving Vienna September 1.</tei:note> Ich
        will nämlich mit meinen bevorstehenden Geburtstag so manchen Leuten keine Unbequemlichkeiten
        machen u. flüchte mich daher vorzeitig nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002334"
          >Tirol</tei:rs>. Das Vorzeitige hat mir nicht wenig Mühe verursacht, denn einfach einen ½
        Monat den Schülern zu schenken gieng nicht an, da ich sonst zu den 3 ohnehin einkommenslosen
        Monaten des Sommers aus eigenen Verschulden einen ½ hinzugefügt, mir selbst also 3½
        einkommenslose Monate beschert hätte! So konnte es <tei:pb n="2"/> nicht sein. Also gab ich
        mir Mühe<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> die entfallenden Stunden <tei:hi
          rend="underline">vorauszugeben</tei:hi>, u. das dauerte von April bis heute, bis ich die
        gesamte Schuld aufarbeiten konnte. Die große Mühe hat mir aber glucklicherweise nicht
        geschadet, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000324">Direktor Halberstam</tei:rs> war
        neulich – trotz 1° Zucker, das ich nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292"
          >Galtür</tei:rs> führe – <tei:hi rend="underline">sehr zufrieden</tei:hi>, namentlich mit
        dem „Blutdruck“, der bedeutend besser geworden. (Was ist das nur der „Blutdruck“? Weißt du
        das??). Für den Herbst hat mir <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000324">Dir.
          Halberstam</tei:rs> eine <tei:hi rend="underline">Veränderung in der Diät</tei:hi>
        angekündigt nach den <tei:hi rend="underline">neuesten</tei:hi> bewährten Errungenschaften
        der Wissenschaft (ich glaube: weniger Fett, mehr Brod, genaues werde <tei:pb n="3"/> ich
        erst erfahren). </tei:p>

      <tei:p>In <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs> mache ich mich sofort an
        die Arbeit, an der ich in diesem Winter hier sehr behindert worden bin. Wenigstens will ich
        ein großes Stück vorwärtsbringen, ehe die Besucher eintreffen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wir freuen uns schon sehr auf die Luft von 1600<tei:hi rend="supralinear">m.</tei:hi>,
        hier ist es schon niederdrückend heiß, so daß ich auch dadurch schwer arbeiten kann. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Aus <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs> zurückgekehrt wollen wir
        dir gern wieder einen Besuch abstatten – den Weg kennen wir ja schon<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">The previous summer the Schenkers were
          given instructions to get to Horn, Lower Austria, by changing trains at St.
          Pölten.</tei:note> – vorausgesetzt, daß die Schwierigkeit der „Hausgehilfin“ bis dahin
        behoben sein wird! Denke dir: </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> In Mai kündigte uns das <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000975"
          >Mädchen</tei:rs> nach mehr als 2 Jahren (!) bei <tei:hi rend="underline">60</tei:hi> S.
        des Monats u. <tei:hi rend="underline">Geschenken</tei:hi> u. beträchtlichen <tei:hi
          rend="underline">Trinkgeldern</tei:hi> der Gäste‘,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04"
          type="editorial" place="foot"> “bei … Gäste” (“at … guests”): square-bracketed in ink, by
          either Heinrich or Wilhelm.</tei:note> nachdem sie im Laufe der 2 Jahre an 15 Millionen
        erspart hatte! U. zw. in dem Augenblick, da Handwerker im Hause waren . . . „Zu viel Arbeit“
        sagte sie in diesem Augenblick u. ging. Die Vermittlerin schickte uns ein Mädchen, dieses
        wäre vielleicht brauchbar gewesen, aber da stellte sich heraus, daß sie geschlechtskrank ist
        u. an einem Blasenkatarrh leidet. Zu viel des Guten. Also wird sie ausgezahlt, wir aber
        müssen wieder suchen! Ein Pech, bei solchem Lohn nichts zu finden! </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Aus Aus <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs> wird
        fortgesetzt.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Dir u. die l. Fr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008450"
          >Marie</tei:rs></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>unser Beider beste Grüße</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="60">Dein treuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
          >Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1928-06-12">12. 6. 28</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute>My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775">Wilhelm</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>As an exception, we are leaving Vienna this time already on the <tei:date
          when="1928-06-16">16th</tei:date> and arrive in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292"
          >Galtür</tei:rs> on the <tei:date when="1928-06-18">18th</tei:date>.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> In particular, I don’t want to make some people
        uncomfortable with my approaching <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">60th</tei:note>
        birthday and am therefore fleeing early for the <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002334"
          >Tyrol</tei:rs>. The earliness caused me more than a little effort, for simply gifting the
        students half a month would not work because I would otherwise have added, by my own fault,
        half a month to the three summer months without income as it is, thus granting myself three
        and a half months without income! It couldn’t <tei:pb n="2"/> be that way. So I made the
        effort to teach the cancelled lessons <tei:hi rend="underline">in advance</tei:hi>, and that
        took from April up to now until I could work off the entire debt. But luckily the grand
        effort did me no harm. Director <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000324"
          >Halberstam</tei:rs> was recently <tei:hi rend="underline">very satisfied</tei:hi> –
        despite 1° of sugar, which I am taking to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292"
          >Galtür</tei:rs> – especially with my “blood pressure,” which was significantly better.
        (Just what is “blood pressure”? Do you know what it is??) For the autumn, Director <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000324">Halberstam</tei:rs> announced a <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >change in the diet</tei:hi> according to the <tei:hi rend="underline">latest</tei:hi>
        proven achievements of science (I believe: less fat, more bread, I have <tei:pb n="3"/> yet
        to find out specifics).</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>, I will immediately launch
        into the work on which I was severely hampered this winter. I will at least make progress on
        a large section before the visitors arrive.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>We are very much looking forward to the fresh air at 1,600 meters, here it is already
        oppressively hot, and so it is difficult for me to work.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>On returning from <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs> we again
        would like to pay you a visit – we already know the route<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
          type="footnote"/> – on the condition that the difficulty with the “house maid” has been
        resolved by then! Just imagine:</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> In May our <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000975">maid</tei:rs> gave
        notice, after more than two years (!) (at <tei:hi rend="underline">60</tei:hi> shillings a
        month and <tei:hi rend="underline">gifts</tei:hi> and considerable <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >tips</tei:hi> from guests),<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> after which
        in the course of two years she had saved close to 15 million! To wit, at the time when
        workmen were in the house . . . “Too much work,” she said at that moment, and left. The
        intermediary agent sent us a girl, who perhaps might have been usable, but it came to light
        that she has venereal disease and suffers from a bladder infection. Too much of a good
        thing. So, she will be paid off. But we have to search again! Bad luck to find nothing at
        such a wage.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>More from <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>To you and your dear wife <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008450"
            >Marie</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>best greetings from us both,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="60">Your trusty</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
          >Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1928-06-12">June 12, 1928</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
