<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3422" sdoID="OJ-5-38_16">OJ 5/38, [16]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="LR">
      <tei:persName>Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2024</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-11" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008423">SchenkerW ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Heinrich to Wilhelm Schenker, dated February 3,
        1925</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1925-02-03T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2024-06-12</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Heinrich offers Wilhelm advice and help on finding a career placement for his
        adoptive grandson Karli.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>
      
      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000775">Wilhelm Schenker</marcrel:recipient>
      
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Mein lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775"
            >Wilhelm</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for February 2, 1925: “An Wilhelm (Br.): ob
            er Karli zum Kunstgewerbler machen will?” “To Wilhelm (letter): would he like to make
            Karli a commercial artist?”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Wir danken Dir herzlich für deinen l. Brief<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker’s diary entry for January 20 records the receipt of
          a letter from his elder brother: “Von Wilhelm (Br. u. Zeitungsausschnitt): er bestreitet
          Mozios Angaben, auch die Angaben von dessen <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003438"
            >Frau</tei:rs>. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003491">Tonerl</tei:rs> habe er schon
          untergebracht, habe also nur noch Sorge um die Fortbildung <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-008438">Karli</tei:rs>; er fragt, ob ich eine Idee habe.” (“From Wilhelm
          (letter and newspaper clipping): he disputes Mozio's claims, and those of Mozio's <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-003438">wife</tei:rs> as well. He has already found a spot for
            <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003491">Tonerl</tei:rs>, so his only remaining concern
          is about <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008438">Karli</tei:rs>'s education in the
          future; he asks whether I have any ideas”).</tei:note> u. die Feuilleton-Beilage, die wir
        mit dem nötigen Verständnis gelesen haben. In der Beziehung von Dir zu <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs> habe ich immer mehr Teilnahme vermutet, als sie
        offenbar in Wirklichkeit vorhanden ist. Alle Menschen klagen so sehr über seinen
        überstiegenen Eifer, das Schönste zuzusagen, u. <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >über</tei:add> den Widerspruch in den Taten. Wozu er das tut, weiß ich nicht; er <tei:hi
          rend="underline">muß es ja nicht</tei:hi>, er macht ja nur Schaden den Anderen,
        überflüssigen Schaden obendrein. Näheres mündlich. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Was <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008438">Karli</tei:rs> anbelangt, bitte ich, dich
        etwas näher bezüglich seines Zeichentalentes auszulassen. Ist es blos des Großvaters
        Meinung, die begreiflich wäre, oder auch des <tei:hi rend="underline">Lehrers aus
          Horn</tei:hi>? Würdest du dich <tei:pb n="2"/> getreuen, <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">ihn</tei:add> auf das sie, was Du von seinem Talent hälst, in
        die <tei:hi rend="underline">Kunstgewerbeschule</tei:hi> zu schicken? Merkst Du eine
        wirkliche Leidenschaft bei ihm, wie du sie doch bei mir als Jungen zu sehen Gelegenheit
        hattest? Oder ist das mehr eine schulmäßige Leistung? Die Laufbahn eines Kunstgewerblers ist
        ja schwierig, trauht[recte: traut] die <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008438"
          >Karli</tei:rs> die Kraft <tei:del rend="overstrike">da</tei:del>zu? Wenn ich nach meiner
        Nase erteilen sollte, möchte ich <tei:add place="interlinear-above">sie</tei:add> ihm
        absprechen. Solche Dinge gehen auf Leben u. Tod, d. h. Du müsstest <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >schon längst eine gut aus</tei:hi>geprägte Neigung bei <tei:hi rend="underline">ihm
          </tei:hi><tei:hi rend="double-underline">gesehen haben</tei:hi>. Irre ich mich, so
        berechtige mich. Dann hieße es, mich umsehen, ob ich nicht Leute wüsste, die mithelfen
        könnten. Es wäre nicht unmöglich, daß ich Verbindungen hätte, ich spreche <tei:hi
          rend="underline">vorsichtig</tei:hi>, obwohl ich sagen könnte ich habe sie. Aber
        wirkliches starkes Talent muß gegeben sein. Sonst stürzest du <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-008438">Karli</tei:rs> ins Unglück. Aus Eitelkeit würde er <tei:pb n="3"/> das
        Kunstgewerbe nicht mehr aufgeben wollen, u. würde jämmerlich zerschellen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Solltest du an eine solche Laufbahn nicht denken, so wollen wir hier bei
        einer städtischen Stelle uns zunächst erkundigen, welche Wege einem Bürgerschüler überhaupt
        offenstehen. Wir würden diese Auskunft dir mitteilen u., wenn du erlaubst, antreten,
        mithelfen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000052">Heini</tei:rs> ist, wie er uns auf Strasse
        sagte – <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000053">Jetty</tei:rs> ist bös („brojges“<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:hi rend="italic">broyges</tei:hi>
          (Yiddish): bitter dispute or feud, or irreconcilable anger.</tei:note>), weil ich während
        ihres Prozesses auf <tei:hi rend="underline">seiner Seite</tei:hi> stand – zur Post
        gegangen. Ist das nicht etwas auch für <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008438"
          >Karli</tei:rs>? Vorausgesetzt, daß „Bürgerschule“ genügt. Und vielleicht paßte er für das
        Militär? </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wir werden jedenfalls bei jener Stelle nach den Möglichkeiten fragen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wann glaubst Du einmal hier zu <tei:pb n="4"/> sein? </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Mein <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">bisheriger Verlag</tei:rs> hat
        mich furchtbar betrogen. Ich wechsele augenblicklich zu einem <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002627">Verlag in München</tei:rs> hinüber. Bis zum <tei:date
          when="1925-07-01">1. Juli 1925</tei:date> soll <tei:choice>
          <tei:sic>ist</tei:sic>
          <tei:corr>ich</tei:corr>
        </tei:choice> ein <tei:hi rend="underline">Buch</tei:hi> von <tei:hi rend="underline">250
          Seiten</tei:hi> abliefern. Kannst dir denken, wie wir schaffen. Wir sind aber Beide, Gott
        sei Dank, gesund. Schon die dritte Analyse zeigt 0 Zucker, <tei:hi rend="underline">gar
          keine Spur</tei:hi>! </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Hoffentlich geht es Dir zumindest gesundheitlich gut? Lasse bald von dir hören, wir
        bitten sehr,</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">u. grüßen u. küssen Dich herzlich</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Dein</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
          >Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:signed> u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Lie
          Lie</tei:rs><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1925-02-03">3. 2. 1925</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>My dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775"
            >Wilhelm</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>We thank you cordially for your kind letter<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> and for the enclosed feuilleton, which we read with the necessary
        understanding. Regarding your relationship to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774"
          >Mozio</tei:rs>, I always presumed more sympathy than was obviously evident in reality.
        All people complain so much about his excessive eagerness to promise the finest things, and
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">about</tei:add> the contradiction in his actions. To
        what purpose he does that, I don’t know. He <tei:hi rend="underline">doesn’t have to do
          it</tei:hi>, he just harms others, needless harm from the start. Specifics when we see
        each other.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>As far as <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008438">Karli</tei:rs> is concerned, I ask
        that you expand on his drawing talent. Is it just the grandfather’s opinion, which would be
        understandable, or also that of the <tei:hi rend="underline">teacher from Horn</tei:hi>?
        Would you <tei:pb n="2"/> trust yourself to send <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >him</tei:add> to the <tei:hi rend="underline">School of Commercial Arts</tei:hi> based on
        what you think about his talent? Do you notice a genuine passion in him, as you had occasion
        to see in me in my youth? Or is it more a schoolboy achievement? The career of a commercial
        artist is rather difficult. Does <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008438">Karli</tei:rs>
        believe he has the strength for it? If I were to make a determination according to my
        instinct, I would advise him against <tei:add place="interlinear-above">it</tei:add>. Such
        things end up as a matter of life or death, that is, you would have to have <tei:hi
          rend="underline">long since seen in him a well-marked inclination</tei:hi>. If I am wrong,
        then correct me. It would then mean that I look around to see whether I know of people who
        could help. It wouldn’t be impossible that I might have connections. I am speaking <tei:hi
          rend="underline">cautiously</tei:hi>, although I could say that I have them. However, a
        truly strong talent must be evident. Otherwise, you will plunge <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-008438">Karli</tei:rs> into misfortune. Out of vanity he would <tei:pb n="3"/>
        no longer want to give up commercial art, and would be woefully shattered.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Should you not want to think about such a career, let me inquire here at a
        municipal agency about which pathways are even open to a secondary school student. We would
        convey this information to you, and if you’ll allow it, get involved, and help out.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000052">Heini</tei:rs> went to the post office, as he
        told us on the street – <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000053">Jetty</tei:rs> is angry
          (“broyges”<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/>) because I <tei:hi
          rend="underline">sided with him</tei:hi> during her trial. Isn’t that something for
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008438">Karli</tei:rs> as well? On the condition that
        “secondary school” suffices. And perhaps he would be suitable for the military?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In any case, we will inquire about possibilities for that position.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>When do you think you’ll be <tei:pb n="4"/> here?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>My <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">erstwhile publisher</tei:rs>
        betrayed me terribly. I am at the moment transferring to a <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002627">publisher in Munich</tei:rs>. By <tei:date when="1925-07-01">July 1,
          1925</tei:date>, I am supposed to submit a <tei:hi rend="underline">book of 250
          pages</tei:hi>. You can imagine how we are working. We are both, however, healthy, thank
        God. Even the third <tei:supplied reason="clarity">urine</tei:supplied> analysis shows 0%
        sugar, <tei:hi rend="underline">not even a trace</tei:hi>!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I I hope you are at least in good health? Let us hear from you soon, we ask
        urgently,</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">and greet and kiss you cordially</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
          >Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:signed> and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Lie
          Lie</tei:rs><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1925-02-03">February 3,
        1925</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
