<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="498" sdoID="OJ-5-7a_22">OJ 5/7a, [22] (formerly vC 22)</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
   <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>


  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2011-08-09" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002775">Cube ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, date not visible (April 1929)</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1929-04-08T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-08-01</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker expresses pleasure at what Cube has sent him in OJ 9/34, [16] and [17],
    and offers advice and a warning: ordinary people are not interested in beauty in art, but look
    for quick, easy judgments.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000143">Cube</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-05">Lieber Herr (Professor)<tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">von Cube</tei:hi></tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is not recorded in Schenker's diary. From
      the postscript to this letter, it is evident that Schenker was replying to both of Cube's
      recent letters, <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-34_16">OJ 9/34, [16]</tei:ref> and
       <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-34_17">OJ 9/34, [17]</tei:ref>, March 26 and April
      5, and probably very soon after receiving the second of them.</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Eine reizende Überraschung war das! Der Programm,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">i.e. the programme of music by Duisburg composers.</tei:note> die
     Kritiken,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">The newspaper reviews of
     the concert; only one of these was found among Cube's letters to Schenker.</tei:note> die
     Bilderchen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Pencil caricatures of Dr
     Eduard Kreuzhagen and Alfred Ahrens, Cube's colleagues in Duisburg, drawn at the start of
     Cube's letter <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-34_16">OJ 9/34, [16]</tei:ref>, March
     26, 1929.</tei:note> u. das Briefchen, kurz: ein sehr heiteres Beruf-Stilleben im
    Briefumschlag. Nur so weiter!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Die Kritiken finde ich ja sehr gut, auch Sie dürfen damit sehr zufrieden sein. Erfreulich
    ist auch Ihr Erfolg in <tei:rs key="entity-002604" type="place">Köln</tei:rs> zu nennen. An den
    Widerstand ist die Sache (auch ich in ihrem Namen) gewohnt aber sie <tei:pb n="2"/> schreitet
    darüber hinweg u. fort. Die Menschen, verankert in Schlafen, Essen u. Zeugen, wollen die
    unangestrengt angenehme Art, mit der sie diese Triebe der Natur erledigen, auch auf die
    künstlichen Produkte des Geistes (Kunst, Wissenschaft, ja sogar die sozialen u. politischen
    Gebilde) übertragen: wie sie ohne Vorbildung u. Vorgreifung schlafen, essen u. zeugen, genau so
    wollen sie ohne Vorschule auch auf dem Gebiete des Geistes sich tummeln. Aber eine Komposition
    ist doch noch etwas anderes als der Geschlechtsakt: dort liegt die Sache doch schwieriger als
    hier. Namentlich die Musik wird in die „<tei:soCalled>Gefühle</tei:soCalled>“ herabgezogen,
     <tei:pb n="3"/> als wäre sie ein Naturprodukt.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich sage das zur Warnung: Aus Ihrem Schreiben geht nämlich hervor, daß Ihre Zuhörer
    offenbar auch Ihnen die übliche Falle gelegt haben. Mit der oben dargestellten Art der Menschen
    hängt es zusammen, daß sie nicht so sehr die Wahrheit u. Schönheit der Kunst suchen, als ein in
    kürzester Form u. <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">auf</tei:add> leichtfassliche
    Weise geprägtes „<tei:soCalled>Urteil</tei:soCalled>“ über den oder jenen Komponisten, dies oder
    jenes Werk. Worin ist zB <tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Reger</tei:hi></tei:rs> oder <tei:rs key="entity-000924" type="person">Wagner</tei:rs>
    schlechter als die grossen Meister, fragen sie <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">schon</tei:add> in der 2. Minute der Unterhaltung, kaum daß sie das erste Wort von einem
     <tei:term>Hintergrund</tei:term>, <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">der</tei:add>
    <tei:term>Url.</tei:term>, einem <tei:term>Zug</tei:term> gehört haben. Nichts von alldem
    interessiert <tei:pb n="4"/> sie; nur die Frage, ob <tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Reger</tei:hi></tei:rs> schlechter ist. Die Enscheidung über den
    Wert ist ihnen das Wesentliche. Zuletzt ist das eine Machtfrage: hinter <tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Reger</tei:hi></tei:rs> stehen
    heute noch Tausende, Millionen von Menschen(eseln), ich aber stehe noch schlank da – also stoßen
    heute die Menschen lieber noch, sozusagen in Eile, zu der großen Herde als zu mir. Außerdem sind
    Sie selbst ja noch so jung, stellen somit für Ihre Zuhörer nicht einmal noch eine „<tei:hi rend="underline">physische</tei:hi> Macht“ vor, die sie beugte!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">No paragraph-break at this point.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>In <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> wollten die Zuhörer ebenso
    etwas von <tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Reger</tei:hi></tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000373" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Hindemith</tei:hi></tei:rs> hören, u. <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">auch</tei:add> ich würde so lange (auch von <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs>) wegen <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"><tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person">Reger</tei:rs>s</tei:hi>’ und <tei:rs key="entity-000924" type="person">Wagner</tei:rs>s gequält, – ich werde davon reden, wenn ich es an der Zeit halte, u. Ihnen
    rate ich, solchen Gelüsten sowenig <tei:note type="editorial">in upper margin,
     inverted:</tei:note> als möglich nachzugeben: zunächst einmal sollen die Leute die
    Grundbegriffe lernen, dann ..</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute>Von mir u. meiner <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Frau</tei:rs> beste
     Wünsche u. Grüße</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial">in upper margin of p. 1:</tei:note> Die Adresse des <tei:rs key="entity-002782" type="person">Frl. S.</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Edith Sauerbrey, mentioned in Cube's letter <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-34_17">OJ 9/34, [17]</tei:ref>, April 5, 1929, a music
      student in Duisburg who was intending to meet Schenker during a three-week trip to
      Vienna.</tei:note> werde ich Ihnen bekanntgeben, sobald sie erscheint.</tei:p>

   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-05">Dear Mr. (Professor) <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">von
      Cube</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>What a delightful surprise! The programme,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/>
    the critical notices<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> the drawings<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> and your nice letter: in short, a very agreeable
    still-life of the profession inside an envelope. Keep at it!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>The critical notices I found very good; and you, too, ought to be very satisfied with
    them. Success in <tei:rs key="entity-002604" type="place">Cologne</tei:rs> must also be numbered
    among your joys. The cause (and I, in its name) is accustomed to encountering opposition, but it
     <tei:pb n="2"/> strides above it and goes its own way. Ordinary people, anchored as they are in
    sleeping, eating and procreating, want to transfer the agreeable manner in which they despatch
    these drives of nature also to the artistic products of the intellect (art, science, indeed even
    the social and political structures); just as they sleep, eat and procreate without prior
    training or attention, so also in the realm of the intellect they wish to splash about, without
    prior education. (But a musical composition is something very different from the sex act: in the
    former, the matter is indeed more difficult.) Specifically, music is dragged down to the level
    of "<tei:soCalled>feelings</tei:soCalled>," <tei:pb n="3"/> as if it were a product of
    nature.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>I am saying this by way of warning. From what you have written, it is clear that your
    listeners have evidently set the usual trap for you, too. The type of person that I have
    described above is disposed not so much to look for truth and beauty in art but rather to
    imprint a "<tei:soCalled>judgment</tei:soCalled>," in the shortest terms and <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">in</tei:add> the most easily graspable way, of this or
    that composer, or this or that work. In what respect <tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person">Reger</tei:rs> or <tei:rs key="entity-000924" type="person">Wagner</tei:rs>, for example, is
    worse than the great masters is something they will ask <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">already</tei:add> in the second minute of the discussion, hardly having heard the
    first thing about a <tei:term>background layer</tei:term>, <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">the</tei:add>
    <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>, or a <tei:term>linear progression</tei:term>. None of all this is
    of any interest to <tei:pb n="4"/> them; only the question of whether <tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person">Reger</tei:rs> is worse. Determining the value of something
    is the crucial thing for them. In the end it is a question of power: today <tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person">Reger</tei:rs> still has the support of thousands, even
    millions of people (– asses), but my support is still thin. Today, then, the people would rather
    meet up – in haste, so to speak – with the great herd than with me. Moreover, you yourself are
    still so very young, and thus do not even represent a "<tei:hi rend="underline">physical</tei:hi> force" that would bend them!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>In <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> the listeners likewise want
    to hear something about <tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person">Reger</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000373" type="person">Hindemith</tei:rs>; and I <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">too</tei:add> have been pestered for a long time (even by <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs>) about <tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person">Reger</tei:rs> and <tei:rs key="entity-000924" type="person">Wagner</tei:rs>; I
    shall speak about this when time permits, and I advise you to give in to such cravings as little
     <tei:note type="editorial">in upper margin, inverted:</tei:note> as possible. First, people
    should learn the basic principles; then ...</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute>From me and my <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs> best wishes
     and greetings.</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Yours,</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">H.
     Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>

    <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial">in upper margin of p. 1:</tei:note>
     <tei:supplied reason="clarity">P.S.</tei:supplied> I shall give you the address of <tei:rs key="entity-002782" type="person">Miss S.</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> as soon as she appears.</tei:p>

   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>