<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="549" sdoID="OJ-6-7_6">OJ 6/7, [6]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2011</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-08-24" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002720">ViolinM ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002721">ViolinM+V ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002722">ViolinM+V+F ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Heinrich Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated July 20,
    1923</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1923-07-20T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2011-08-24</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker describes his efforts to make Der Tonwille more widely read, through its
    distribution by his pupils and its display in music shop windows. He needs more help from pupils
    and friends with the dissemination of his work, but complains that Hans Weisse has let him down
    on more than one occasion by not writing about his work. Finally, he asks Violin’s advice about
    whether he should accept an invitation to speak at a conference in Leipzig, or whether he should
    simply stay at home and continue to write. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject> </dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-60">Galtür, <tei:date when="1923-07-20">20. VII
     1923</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Fl</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ
      3/4, p. 2536, July 20, 1923: "An F. (Br): nehme den Antrag seines Enthusiasten an, wiederhole
      meine Ansprache an die Schüler, besonders das Stichwort, daß es nicht darauf ankomme, den
      Inhalt der Hefte zu verstehen; erzähle die Erlebnisse mit Haslinger u. Kern, ersuche umgehend
      um Rat wegen Leipzig." ("To Floriz (letter): I accept the proposal of his enthusiast, repeat
      my injunction to my pupils, especially the dictum that it is not essential to be able to
      understand the content of the Tonwille issues. I recount my experiences with Haslinger and
      Kern, seek advice by return about Leipzig."). </tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Zwischen Karte u. gegenwärtigen Brief hat sich ganz plötzlich aus <tei:del rend="overstrike">ei</tei:del> bisher unbekannter Ursache (vielleicht Fehlgriff in zu viel
    kaltem Trunk nach 3-stundigem Marsch in starker Hitze oder so etwas) ein<tei:del rend="overstrike">e</tei:del> Thema mit 15 Variationen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">A reference to Beethoven’s Fifteen Variations and Fugue on an
     Original Theme, Op. 35, the so-called "Eroica" Variations. </tei:note>
    <tei:add place="interlinear-above">eingeschlichen, das sich</tei:add> binnen einem Tag
    abgespielt u. mich so matt gesetzt hat, daß ich weder etwas essen u. noch weniger schreiben
    konnte. „Sentendo nuova forza“ (mit <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Beeth.</tei:hi></tei:rs> zu schreiben)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Another Beethoven reference: in the third movement of his A-minor
     String Quartet, Op. 132, the "Heiliger Dankgesang," Beethoven wrote above the second strain
     (Andante) "Neue Kraft fühlend (Sentendo nuova forza)." </tei:note> hole ich meine Zusage als
    Erstes nach. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>In der That heiße ich das rasch u. findig, was du mir da durch deinen <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Musikent<tei:supplied reason="spelling">h</tei:supplied>usiast</tei:rs>en darbietest. Vielen, vielen Dank. <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Ihm</tei:rs> selbst zu danken, sei dem Zeitpunkt vorbehalten, wo ich von seiner
    Güte werde Gebrauch machen können, u. ich hoffe es kommt dazu. Schon zum Abschluß meiner Stunden
    im Juni habe ich meinen Schülern gesagt, daß sie mir je 50 Abnehmer sichern müssen für 2–<tei:hi rend="underline">4 Hefte</tei:hi> jährlich – ist die Sache einmal in gutem Gange, wird sich
    auch mehr <tei:hi rend="underline">von</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">selbst</tei:hi> machen lassen –, was die Spucke von 24 bis 48.000 Kr.
    jährlich ausmacht (<tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> rechnet 12000 K
    per Heft), wozu kommt, daß von solchen Abnehmern sicherlich die Meisten ihre Buchhändler haben,
    die ihnen Rabatte geben, so daß selbst die Hauptziffer von 48000 K auf wenig mehr als 40.000 K
    fallen dürfte. Das Hauptwort aber, das ich an meine Schüler richtete, <tei:pb n="2"/> war, (in
    Zorn u. Schmerz herausgeschrieen, denn ich schämte mich, es überhaupt erst nötig zu haben, daß
    ich es sage): „Wärt Ihr Schüler von <tei:rs key="entity-000798" type="person">Schönberg</tei:rs>, oder <tei:rs key="entity-000802" type="person">Schrecker</tei:rs>, oder
     <tei:rs key="entity-000116" type="person">Busoni</tei:rs> oder irgendso einem ähnlichen
    Vorüberhörer u. Danebenlehrer, stündet Ihr Kopf, liefet Ihr in allen Gassen, in allen Städten,
    u. Vereinen herein, ließet Euch Geld kosten, um dabei u. dafür zu sein, so aber berührt von der
    Wahrheit, schlaft u. schnarcht am hellichten Tag, als gäbe ich Opium statt der Wahrheit.“ Und
    noch heftiger schrie ich sie an: „Saget allen denjenigen, an die Ihr Euch wenden werdet, in
    meinem Namen, daß sie sich nicht unterstehen dürfen einzuwenden, daß sie vom „<tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title>TW</tei:title></tei:rs>“ nichts verstehen, da sie in
    ihren Büchereien sicher Werke stehen haben, die sie nie gelesen, oder wenn gelesen, so nicht
    verstanden haben, daß es um der Kulturdisziplin <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">halber</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">willen</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> auch den „<tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title>TW</tei:title></tei:rs>.“ in die Bücherei, ungelesen, unverstanden, einzurechen
    notwendig ist, sei es schließlich in der stillen Hoffnung, daß die Kindskinder ihn mit Nutzen zu
    sich nehmen werden.“ Ich sah genau, wie sie mein Zerren aus ihrem Schlaf störte, aber ich mußte
    es tun. Es geht wirklich nicht so weiter, daß ich Alles fast ganz allein besorge, <tei:add place="interlinear-above">1)</tei:add> Arbeit um das Werk (u. welche!!), <tei:add place="interlinear-above">2)</tei:add> das Werk, u. <tei:add place="interlinear-above">3)</tei:add> die <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Propaganda</tei:hi> des Werkes (statt des Verlegers
    u. der Schulen) – das ist zu viel, zumal noch so viel Arbeit aussteht, vor Allem doch der
     <tei:rs key="entity-001728" type="work">IV<tei:supplied reason="syntax">.</tei:supplied>
     Band</tei:rs>, der halbfertig daliegt, die Krone des Ganzen, das hellste Licht der
     Bände.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">That is, vol. 4 of the series
      <tei:title>Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:title>, to which Schenker eventually
     gave the title <tei:title level="m">Der freie Satz</tei:title>. No paragraph-break at this
     point in source. </tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Die Schüler versprechen es zu tun, sogar <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Weisse</tei:hi></tei:rs>, dieser sehr fatale Knabe, der in meinem <tei:pb n="3"/> Namen außerordentlich Zulauf hat (6 Schüler täglich), sich schließlich erlauben konnte,
    10.000 K für die Stunde anzusetzen u., was ich heute noch nicht machen kann, die Vormittage der
    eigenen Arbeit vorzubehalten u. nur an den Nachmittagen zu unterrichten, der trotz Allem in
    wichtigen Augenblicken abseits steht (so hat er <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> den Aufsatz über mich im „<tei:rs key="entity-002555" type="journal"><tei:title>Anbruch</tei:title></tei:rs>“ verweigert, aber auch die selbstständige <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Monographie</tei:hi>, die er zu drucken bereit war, bereit ist,<tei:del rend="overstrike">)</tei:del> immer mit dem Blick auf <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Haydn</tei:hi></tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000612" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Mozart</tei:hi></tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Beeth</tei:hi></tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000803" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Schubert</tei:hi></tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Brahms</tei:hi></tei:rs>, die nicht auch geschrieben
    haben u. die Reihe <tei:rs key="entity-000025" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Em.
      Bach</tei:hi></tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000808" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Schumann</tei:hi></tei:rs> u.A. misachtend, die daneben Einiges geschrieben) sogar <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs>, sage ich, <tei:del rend="overstrike">se</tei:del> versprach es aufs bestimmteste<tei:supplied reason="syntax">.</tei:supplied>
    <tei:rs key="entity-000201" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Fr. Elias</tei:hi></tei:rs>
    ist ja leider höchst ungeschickt u. außer jeder gesellschaftlichen Beziehung, wird sich aber
    gewiß u. gern anstrengen. Sie hat sofort zu Haslinger<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Probably the heirs of the publishing-house of Tobias (later Carl)
     Haslinger, situated near the Graben in first district of Vienna. </tei:note> 1 <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Exempl.</tei:hi> gebracht u. in meinem Namen ersucht, es in die Auslage zu
    geben – <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> schickt nur den „<tei:rs key="entity-002555" type="journal"><tei:title>Anbr.</tei:title></tei:rs>“, aber niemals den
     „<tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title>TW</tei:title></tei:rs>.“! –, Haslinger hat
    es getan, aber am nächsten Tag <tei:del rend="overstrike">hat</tei:del> war es auch schon weg:
    der Dummkopf hat es verkauft. <tei:rs key="entity-000201" type="person">Elias</tei:rs> ging
    nochmals hinein u. wiederholte die Bitte, obgleich sich die Unverkäuflichkeit eines geschenkten
     <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Ex.</tei:hi> von selbst verstand, – es wurde ihr die Erfüllung
    zugesagt, ob aber auch gehalten, läßt sich von hier nicht sagen. Oder: ich u. <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lieliechen</tei:rs> bringen ein <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Exemplar</tei:hi> zu Rosé (heute: Kern)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Alex Rosé was a dealer in sheet music and books at Vienna I, Kärntnerring 11 in
     1905. </tei:note> u. bitten ihn, es auszustellen. <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Ll.</tei:rs> macht in feinster Weise aufmerksam, daß das Heft <tei:hi rend="underline">nicht</tei:hi> mehr <tei:hi rend="underline">verkäuflich</tei:hi> sein kann, da sie dies u.
    jenes unterstrichen, u. die <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> nach außen gewendet <tei:pb n="4"/>
    hat. Auf einmal sagt Kern lieblichst lachend jüdelnd – ach, ein großes Geschäft trat in Sicht!?!
    –: „das w<tei:hi rend="underline">e</tei:hi>r' ich <tei:hi rend="underline">ja</tei:hi>
    verkaufen!“ Mehr Eselei oder mehr Gier? Oder beides in gleicher Wa<tei:supplied reason="spelling">a</tei:supplied>ge? Jedenfalls aber hoffe ich Abnehmer zusammen<tei:supplied reason="syntax">zu</tei:supplied>bringen, wodurch aber das Unternehmen von vornherein für
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">de</tei:del>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">jeden Verleger</tei:hi> einen genau zu ermittelnden Reingewinn abwerfen
    müsste u. das soll mein Rückgrat sein. An <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Vriesl.</tei:hi></tei:rs> habe ich ebenfalls die Frage gerichtet, was er in
     <tei:rs key="entity-002286" type="place">München</tei:rs>
    <tei:add place="interlinear-above">zu</tei:add> erreichen sich versprechen könnte. Aber nun zur
    Frage <tei:rs key="entity-002479" type="place"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Leipzig</tei:hi></tei:rs>:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">This
     probably refers to a conference of musicologists scheduled for the fall of 1924. </tei:note>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Soll ich also auf dem Kongreß den erbetenen Vortrag halten? Steht es dafür,
    die große Arbeit, die ich augenblicklich wälze, im Stich zu lassen, den Stundenverlust u. die
    Reisekosten auf mich zu nehmen, die Berührung mit den „Kollegen“ – vielleicht nur das eine Mal –
    zu wagen, oder ists nicht besser, aus der <tei:rs key="entity-002826" type="place">Keilgasse</tei:rs> zu wirken, wie bisher? Schließlich kann ich im „<tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title>TW</tei:title></tei:rs>.“ es noch besser u. freier sagen, als vor den
    „gekränkten Leberwürsten“ u. fest steht, was du einmal sehr richtig schreibst, daß sie mich doch
    nicht verstehen werden. Denn zu diesen Geheimnissen, den vorletzten, denn die letzten sind in
    Gott u. unergründlich, sind auch nicht zum Ergründer da, gehören unser beider Ohren, die sie
    doch Alle mitsammen nicht haben – du brauchst, <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Fl</tei:rs>., nicht züchtig zu erröten, ich schäme mich ja auch nicht es zu schreiben – also
    kurz u. gut: soll ich nach <tei:rs key="entity-002479" type="place"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Leipzig</tei:hi></tei:rs> oder nicht? </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Kommst du, so zeige ich dir hier allerlei Interessantes. Vorläufig also dir u. Allen
    deinen herzlichste Grüße von mir u. der ewig schreibenden <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">LieLiechen</tei:rs>. </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">2:5 (<tei:rs key="entity-000909" type="person">Fanny</tei:rs>!) </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60">Dein <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.</tei:rs>
    </tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">upper margin, upside down:</tei:note><tei:lb/>
     V. Heft bringt V<tei:supplied reason="syntax">.</tei:supplied> Sinf. And., Scherzo u. Finale,
      <tei:hi rend="underline">also Ganz</tei:hi>!</tei:p>

    <tei:p>VI<tei:supplied reason="syntax">.</tei:supplied> " <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs>' Händelvar., <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person">S.Bach</tei:rs>'s Solostücke für Vl., Vcl, u. gegen <tei:rs key="entity-000495" type="person">Kurt</tei:rs>s „linearen Kp.“ </tei:p>

    <tei:p>VII<tei:supplied reason="syntax">.</tei:supplied> " Sinfon. G<tei:hi rend="supralinear">m</tei:hi>
     <tei:rs key="entity-000612" type="person">Moz.</tei:rs>, D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">dur</tei:hi>
     <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person">Haydn</tei:rs>, oder <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs>' III. [—] bei <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs>freiheit rücke ich <tei:add place="interlinear-above">sofort</tei:add> mit
      <tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person"><tei:hi rend="underline">Reger</tei:hi></tei:rs>
     heraus, mit <tei:rs key="entity-000924" type="person"><tei:hi rend="underline">Wagner</tei:hi></tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot">By
      “Hertzkafreiheit,” Schenker is referring to the recent difficulties he had with his publisher
      over his polemical writing, some of which had been suppressed from the <tei:title level="m">Erläuterungsausgabe</tei:title> of Op. 101 and <tei:title level="j">Tonwille 3</tei:title>.
      — Most of the works listed in this postscript were the subjects of analyses published in the
      mid-1920s, but several appeared not in <tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title> but in
      vols 1 and 2 of <tei:title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:title> (1925, 1926).
      There was, however, no analysis of a Haydn or Brahms symphony, and Schenker’s opposition to
      Wagner is aired only briefly in some of the published essays. </tei:note>
    </tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-60">Galtür, <tei:date when="1923-07-20">July 20,
     1923</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Between <tei:supplied reason="clarity">your letter</tei:supplied>card and the present
    letter, suddenly and for some unknown reason (perhaps unwisely choosing a drink that was too
    cold after a three-hour-long walk in extreme heat, or something of that sort) a Theme and
    Fifteen Variations<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/>
    <tei:add place="interlinear-above">crept in, which</tei:add> overcame me within a day, and
    rendered me so weak that I could not eat anything, still less put pen to paper. "Sentendo nuova
    forza" (in <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs>'s words),<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> the first thing I am doing is to make good on my
    promise. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>I do indeed call that which you are offering me through your <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">music enthusiast</tei:rs> timely and ingenious. Many, many thanks. Thanking the
     <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">man himself</tei:rs> should be reserved for the
    moment at which I shall be able to make use of his generosity, and I hope we will get to that
    point. As soon as my lessons ended in June, I told my pupils that they must each secure fifty
    subscribers <tei:supplied reason="clarity">to <tei:title level="j">Der
     Tonwille</tei:title></tei:supplied> for between two and <tei:hi rend="underline">four
     issues</tei:hi> a year, which will make up between 24,000 and 48,000 Kronen per year – <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> reckons <tei:supplied reason="clarity">a
     cost of</tei:supplied> 12,000 Kronen per issue. (Once this scheme is in full swing, it will
    actually make more <tei:hi rend="underline">by itself</tei:hi>.) What is more, most of these
    subscribers will surely have their own book dealers, who give them discounts, so that even the
    basic sum of 48,000 Kronen will probably be reduced to little more than 40,000 Kronen. But the
    principal point that I directed at my pupils <tei:pb n="2"/> (cried out in pain and fury, for I
    was ashamed that it should ever have been necessary to say it), was: "Were you the pupils of
     <tei:rs key="entity-000798" type="person">Schönberg</tei:rs>, or <tei:rs key="entity-000802" type="person">Schreker</tei:rs>, or <tei:rs key="entity-000116" type="person">Busoni</tei:rs>,
    or anyone else who similarly cannot hear properly or teach correctly, you would be standing on
    your heads, running into the streets, through every town and society, parting with your money in
    order to be with them and to support them; but so touched are you by the truth that you sleep
    and snore in the broadest daylight, as though I were giving you opium rather than the truth."
    And I cried out to them with an even louder voice, saying: "Say to all those to whom you will
    turn, in my name, that they should not dare to raise the objection that they understand nothing
    in <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Der
     Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>, for they surely have in their libraries works that they have
    never read – or, if they have read them, they have not understood that, <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">on account of</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">for the sake of</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> the cultural discipline, it is necessary to include <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs> too in their libraries,
    unread or uncomprehended, if only in the secret hope that ultimately their children’s children
    will profitably take to them." I saw very clearly how my protestations disturbed their slumber,
    but I had to do it. I really cannot go on in such a way that I have to take care of everything
    almost entirely on my own, <tei:add place="interlinear-above">1)</tei:add> preparation for the
    work (and how much of that there is!!), <tei:add place="interlinear-above">2)</tei:add> the
    writing of the work, and <tei:add place="interlinear-above">3)</tei:add> the promotion of the
    work (instead of leaving this to the publisher and the schools) – that is too much, above all
    while so much work remains to be done, above all <tei:rs key="entity-001728" type="work">volume
     4</tei:rs>, which languishes half-finished, the culmination of the whole, the brightest light
    of the volumes.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>My pupils promise to do it; even <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs>, this fatal boy, who in my <tei:pb n="3"/> name has such an extraordinarily
    large following (six pupils a day), was finally in a position to stipulate 10,000 Kronen per
    lesson, and – something I myself still cannot manage today – to reserve the mornings for his own
    work, and to teach only in the afternoons, who despite everything steps to one side at the
    crucial moments (thus he has turned down writing the article about me for <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> in the <tei:rs key="entity-002555" type="journal"><tei:title level="j">Anbruch</tei:title></tei:rs> but also the independent
    monograph <tei:supplied reason="clarity">about me</tei:supplied> that <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> was – and still is – prepared to publish,
    always referring to <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person">Haydn</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000612" type="person">Mozart</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000803" type="person">Schubert</tei:rs> and <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs>, who also did not write about music, in
    disregard of the lineage of <tei:rs key="entity-000025" type="person">C. P. E. Bach</tei:rs> and
     <tei:rs key="entity-000808" type="person">Schumann</tei:rs>, among others, who wrote about
    music alongside composing; even <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs>, I
    tell you, promised it most explicitly. Miss <tei:rs key="entity-000201" type="person">Elias</tei:rs> is, unfortunately, highly unskilled and lacking all social connections; she
    will nonetheless certainly and willingly exert herself. She promptly took one copy to
     Haslinger’s<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> and asked them in my name to
    display it in their shop window – <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs>
    sends them only the <tei:rs key="entity-002555" type="journal"><tei:title level="j">Anbruch</tei:title></tei:rs>, never <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>! – Haslinger did so, but by the next day it was
    already gone: the idiot had sold it. <tei:rs key="entity-000201" type="person">Elias</tei:rs>
    went back to them and repeated her request, notwithstanding the fact that it was self-evident
    that the copy that had been presented was not for sale; they promised to honor her request, but
    whether or not they kept their word I cannot say. On another occasion, <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs> and I took a copy to Rosé’s shop (now
    owned by Kern)<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> and ask him to put it on display.
     <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs> makes it clear to him, in the
    most polite manner, that the issue <tei:hi rend="underline">can no longer be for sale</tei:hi>
    since she has underlined things here and there, and has unfolded the <tei:term>Urlinie
     graph</tei:term>. <tei:pb n="4"/> Suddenly Kern, with the most charming laugh and <tei:supplied reason="clarity">sensing</tei:supplied> a big deal in sight(!?!), says in a Jewish accent: "I
    will sell that <tei:hi rend="underline">easily</tei:hi>!" Which is the greater, the stupidity or
    the greed? Or are the two in equal measure? At any rate, however, I hope to be able to build up
    a number of subscribers, by means of which the undertaking would from now on unfailingly bring
    in for <tei:hi rend="underline">any publisher</tei:hi> a precisely calculable clear profit, and
    that is to be the basis on which I operate. To <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs> I have likewise directed the question as to what he could expect to
    achieve in <tei:rs key="entity-002286" type="place">Munich</tei:rs>. But now to the question of
     <tei:rs key="entity-002479" type="place">Leipzig</tei:rs>:<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Shall I give the requested lecture to the congress? Is it worthwhile
    abandoning the great work over which I am at present toiling, absorbing the loss of lessons and
    the travel costs, risking contact with "colleagues" (perhaps only the one time); or is it not
    better to work out of the <tei:rs key="entity-002826" type="place">Keilgasse</tei:rs>, as I have
    been doing up to now. Finally, I can say <tei:supplied reason="clarity">what I have to
     say</tei:supplied> far better and more freely in <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs> than in front of those thin-skinned
    liver-sausages. And what you once very rightly said holds true: these people will certainly not
    understand me. For to these secrets, the penultimate ones (for the ultimate ones reside in God
    and are unfathomable, not even to the one who penetrates these mysteries himself), belong our
    two ears, which is more than these people have among them — <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Floriz</tei:rs>, you need not blush in modesty; I am not ashamed to write this:
    in short, should I go to <tei:rs key="entity-002479" type="place">Leipzig</tei:rs>, or not? </tei:p>

   <tei:p>If you can get here, then I will show you all manner of interesting things. Provisionally,
    then, to you and all yours, most cordial greetings from me and from the ever-writing <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs>. </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">From the two of us to the five of you (including <tei:rs key="entity-000909" type="person">Fanny</tei:rs>), </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60">Your <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.</tei:rs>
    </tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">upper margin, upside down:</tei:note><tei:lb/>
     Issue 5 includes the Andante, Scherzo, and Finale of <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs>’s</tei:supplied> Fifth Symphony, <tei:hi rend="underline">i.e. complete</tei:hi>! </tei:p>

    <tei:p>Issue 6 <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs>'s Handel Variations,
      <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person">J. S. Bach</tei:rs>'s solo pieces for violin and
     cello, contra <tei:rs key="entity-000495" type="person">Kurth</tei:rs>'s <tei:title level="m">Linearer Kontrapunkt</tei:title>
    </tei:p>

    <tei:p>Issue 7 <tei:rs key="entity-000612" type="person">Mozart</tei:rs>'s G-minor Symphony,
      <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person">Haydn</tei:rs>'s D-major, or <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs>'s Third. [—] <tei:hi rend="underline">If
       <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> grants me the freedom</tei:hi>, I
     shall <tei:add place="interlinear-above">immediately</tei:add> have it out with <tei:hi rend="underline">Reger</tei:hi>, with <tei:hi rend="underline">Wagner</tei:hi>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/>
    </tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>