<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="963" sdoID="OJ-6-7_51">OJ 6/7, [51]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="major">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
      <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-07-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002720">ViolinM ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002721">ViolinM+V ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002722">ViolinM+V+F ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter, with envelope, from Schenker to Violin, dated October 21,
        1930</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1930-10-21T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2013-07-01</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Writing after a long and serious illness, Schenker assures his friend that he
        is alive and well. The doctors have pronounced him generally fit, but he suffers from a
        painful tightening of the thorax, and also a flickering that causes him to "lose" letters
        and notes. He has had to give many double-lessons of late, in theory, which he finds tiring.
        To Hoboken, who, though gifted, is concerned only about his money and often comes to lessons
        without having prepared anything, he would rather play than give over-long lectures. He is
        concerned, for his own sake as much as for Weisse's, about the lectures in Berlin that
        Weisse will deliver, and about his eagerness to debate with Alfred Lorenz; he is glad that
        Violin is going to Berlin, and will give him instructions about what to do there. His
        Beethoven sonata edition brings in 100 shillings per month – a good deal for the publishers
        – and his brother still has half of his inheritance. But he is still alive – with Der freie
        Satz.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">letter:</tei:note>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Fl</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this
            letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/4, p. 3527 (October 20–21, 1930): "Ich
            beginne einen Brief an Floriz. / Der Brief an Floriz beendet, 8 Seiten." ("I begin a
            letter to Floriz. / The letter to Floriz finished, eight
          pages.")</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Nun siehst du mich, du lieber, den Auferstandenen. Wie gerne hätte ich
        fliegend schon den ersten Bf<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-45_87">= OJ 14/45,
          [87]</tei:ref> beantwortet, der mich durch deine Teilnahme an den <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs>er Möglichkeiten so beglückt hat! Alles,
        alles ist vorüber, u. mein 35–40 Jahre mir vertrauter <tei:rs key="entity-000324" type="person">Hausarzt</tei:rs> meinte abschiedsnehmend: „<tei:quote>Wenn ich nicht selbst
          dabei gewesen wäre, würde ich überhaupt nicht merken, daß etwas vorgefallen
          ist.</tei:quote>“ Ich habe erstaunlicherweise sogar das Sommergewicht wieder!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Noch vor einem Jahr schloß Prof. D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi>
        <tei:rs key="entity-003665" type="person">Kronfeld</tei:rs> aus dem Bild meiner Augen auf
        einen Stand meines Körpers, gleich dem eines Mannes von 50 Jahren. <tei:pb n="2"/> Noch in
        diesem Jahre, kurz<tei:note type="editorial">corr</tei:note> vor meiner Ausreise fand mich
        Dir. D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi>
        <tei:rs key="entity-000324" type="person">Halberstam</tei:rs>, höchst befriedigend: kein
        Zucker, fast kein Blutdruck.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Paragraph-break in source.</tei:note> Und doch hat mich wie abscheulicher Exzeß
        umgeworfen, so daß ich mich im Bett nicht rühren durfte, folglich auch nichts essen
        usw.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wie du weißt, steckt <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">mir</tei:add> das
        Exzedieren im Blute. Ich übertreibe die Arbeit in Tiefe, Hast, immer in Gedanken schon an
        die nächste Arbeit, wenn nicht gar an mehrere Arbeiten; ich übertreibe – um das mir selbst
        so eigen zubereiteten Stoffes <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">willen</tei:add>
        – meine Hingabe an den Unterricht; ich übertreibe meine Bereitwilligkeit, fernsten Fragern
        Rede u. Antwort zu stehen (mit Notenbeisp. usw.), Korrekturen durchzuführen, ich übertreibe
        meine Güte auch in der Gesellschaft, <tei:pb n="3"/> wo ich immer nach allen unmöglichen
        Dingen gefragt werde, kurz – in Allem u. Jedem, im Essen, Reden, Schreien, in Aufregung
        übertreibe ich. Namentlich <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#HS">hat</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">habe ich</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> in <tei:hi rend="underline">den letzten Jahren Raubbau getrieben</tei:hi>! Seit
        etwa 3 Jahren suchen mich sog. Oppressionen heim, wenn ich sehr überschrieen, zerredet,
        zerarbeitet bin, <tei:hi rend="underline">ein Zusammenziehen des Brustkorbes</tei:hi> tritt
        auf, das mich sehr quält. Seit vielleicht 5 Jahren quälen mich die Augen, ein <tei:hi rend="underline">unaufhörliches Flimmern</tei:hi> macht mich toll, ich verliere die
        Buchstaben, die Notenköpfe, u. doch nehmen die Ärzte weder jene Oppressionen noch die Augen
        zu ernst: „<tei:quote>Nichts Anstrengen</tei:quote>“ heißt die Ordination, im Übrigen werde
        ich für das Leben gesund u. tauglich befunden!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Müßte ich doch schon im vorigen Jahr zweimal <tei:pb n="4"/> ins Bett gehen, so
        übermüdet war ich von den Pflichten. Na, du wirst ja in höchstens 3-4 Woche <tei:rs key="entity-001752" type="work">das neue Buch</tei:rs> in der Hand haben – ich spreche
        nicht von dem Inhalt, siehst du aber die Notenbilder, dann wirst du den Jammer begreifen,
        der für mich unausweichlich ist: in dem Teil kann micht <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#HS">nich</tei:del> Niemand ersetzen, während mein <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">LieLiechen</tei:rs> nur im Textteil u. bei den Korrekturen doch höchst
          <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#HS">ausführl</tei:del> ansehnliche Dienste leisten kann
        u. auch leistet.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Entsetzlich setzen mir H. <tei:rs key="entity-000007" type="person">Albersham</tei:rs>s
        u. <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hoboken</tei:rs>s <tei:hi rend="underline">Doppelstunden</tei:hi> zu! Eine wahre Todesmarter, die ich nun, auf Befehl der Ärtzte,
        abschaffen mußte. 3 solcher Doppelst. in der Woche: an denselben Schüler <tei:hi rend="underline">Theorie 2 Stunden</tei:hi>, in der Woche scolcher 6 Stunden!</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="5"/> Zumal <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hob.</tei:rs> erschien
        zu solchen Doppelstunden meistens ohne Hausarbeit (obschon sonst ein tüchtig musik. mensch)
        – u. da hatte ich 2 Stunden Stoff um Stoff zu verbrauchen, zu misbrauchen<tei:note type="editorial">?</tei:note>, etwa von 10 zu 10 Minuten zu wechseln, ich hielt „Vorträge“
        in einer Länge, wie sie nie gehalten werden. Der Nabob, ganz verloren in sein Geld, bildet
        sich aber ein (wie es sich später herausstellte), er würde mir eine <tei:hi rend="underline">große Erleichterung geboten</tei:hi>
        <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS"><tei:hi rend="underline">haben</tei:hi></tei:add> (in seiner Denkweise gesprochen: Das Geld für die 2 Stunden im
        Grunde geschenkt <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">haben</tei:add>), wenn er
        blos zuhörte! Sehr viel überhaupt <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hob.</tei:rs>
        <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">hat</tei:add> am Gewissen dadurch, daß er, ein
        schmutziger Kerl sondermaßen, den Wahn nähert, er hätte das <tei:rs key="entity-002452" type="organization">Archiv</tei:rs> mir geschenkt u. sich das Recht erworben, von <tei:hi rend="underline">mir</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">Gegen</tei:hi>leistungen jenseits <tei:pb n="6"/> der Stunde zu
        erheben. Wahrlich, das <tei:rs key="entity-002452" type="organization">Archiv</tei:rs> habe
        ich zu teuer bezahlt!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Kaum aber bin ich wieder auf den Beinen, muß ich wieder schwere Opfer an <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans</tei:rs> bringen, wie ich es gleich geahnt habe.
          <tei:hi rend="underline">Begreiflicherweise</tei:hi> hat er Angst, vor dem <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berl.</tei:rs> Forum fehlzugehen, hat aber zugleich den
        Ehrgeiz <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#HS">vor</tei:del> den Hörern Beisp. vorzulegen,
        die ich nocht nicht gebracht habe, etwa 10 Stück, die er kopiert den Hörern in die Hand
        geben wird. Er wird <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">mir</tei:add> alle Stücke
        zeigen – du darfst es mir glauben, daß die eigentliche Arbeit nun mir zufallen wird, denn
          <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans</tei:rs> ist durchaus nicht sicher, ja er
        ist oft sogar noch zu abwegig. Schon gleich die <tei:rs key="entity-004715" type="composition">2-stim. Invent. V (Es d.)</tei:rs> zeigte mir, was mir bevorsteht,
          <tei:pb n="7"/> er will da gegen <tei:rs key="entity-003123" type="person">Lorenz</tei:rs>
          (<tei:rs key="entity-002286" type="place">München</tei:rs>) polemisieren, ist aber selbst
        gestrauchelt. Nun, kann u. darf ich aber <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">H.</tei:rs> im Stiche lassen? Nein, gewiß nicht, schon um meinetwillen nicht, wohl auch
        um seinetwillen nicht. (Sein <tei:rs key="entity-002973" type="composition">Oktett</tei:rs>
        war <tei:hi rend="underline">ganz famos</tei:hi>, das neueste Stück werde ich erst im
          <tei:date when="1931-01">Jänner</tei:date> hören.) Jedenfalls <tei:hi rend="underline">freue ich mich sehr</tei:hi> zu wissen, daß du nach <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs> gehst. Für die Reise werde ich dir noch besondere
        Instruktionen mitgeben.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun habe ich dir den Beweis erbracht, daß ich – lebe.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Die Mitteilung des Frl. <tei:rs key="entity-000049" type="person">Becker</tei:rs> hat
        mich sehr gefreut u. interessiert. 1.200 S. jährlich beträgt meine Tantieme der <tei:pb n="8"/>
        <tei:rs key="entity-001753" type="work">B. Ausg.</tei:rs>, also 100 S. per Monat: ein gutes
        Geschäft für den <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">Verlag</tei:rs>. Mit meinem
        Geld bei <tei:rs key="entity-000774" type="person">Mozio</tei:rs> bin ich noch immer nicht
        im Reinen. Also genug Themen für ein weiteres Leben, u. daher lebe ich fort.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Dir u. all deinen lieben Deinen herzlichste Grüße deines<tei:note type="editorial">corr</tei:note> noch immer zum Leben (na, u. der „<tei:rs key="entity-001728" type="work"><tei:title>Fr. S.</tei:title></tei:rs>“?)
          aufgesparten</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p>Ein Kapitel für sich, was mein <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lieliechen</tei:rs> während meiner Bettzeit zu opfern hatte! Tag u. <tei:hi rend="underline">Nacht</tei:hi>!</tei:p>
        <tei:p><tei:date when="1930-10-21">21. 10. 30</tei:date></tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

      <tei:fw type="envelope"><tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">envelope:</tei:note><tei:lb/>
        <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="recto"/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied reason="clarity">An:</tei:supplied>
            <tei:handShift new="#HS"/>H Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">M.
              Violin</tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-40"><tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-40">Haynstr. 13</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:fw type="postmark">|| 1 WIEN 1 | 16–17 | 21. X. | 1930 | * 4b * ||</tei:fw><tei:lb/>
        <tei:lb/><tei:milestone unit="folio" n="verso"/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-45"><tei:supplied reason="clarity">Absender:</tei:supplied>
            <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-30"><tei:handShift new="#printed"/><tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">WIEN</tei:rs> III., <tei:rs key="entity-002826" type="place">KEILGASSE</tei:rs> 8 <tei:handShift new="#HS"/>/12</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
      </tei:fw>

    </tei:div>

    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">letter:</tei:note>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Now, my dear friend, you see me, the risen one. How I would have liked to
        reply swiftly to your first letter<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-45_87">= OJ
          14/45, [87]</tei:ref>, which so pleased me on account of your participation in the <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs> matters! Everything, absolutely
        everything is over, and my trusted family <tei:rs key="entity-000324" type="person">doctor</tei:rs> for 35 or 40 years said, as he took his leave: "<tei:quote>If I myself
          had not been there, I would not have noticed that anything was amiss.</tei:quote>"
        Astonishingly, I even have regained my summer weight!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Only a year ago, Prof. Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-003665" type="person">Kronfeld</tei:rs>
        deduced from a picture of my eyes, on the basis of my body, that it was like that of a man
        of fifty years. <tei:pb n="2"/> Even in this year, shortly before I went on holiday,
        Director Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000324" type="person">Halberstam</tei:rs> found me in a
        highly satisfactory condition: no sugar <tei:supplied reason="clarity">in my
          urine</tei:supplied>, hardly any blood pressure.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> Even so, a horrendous excess <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of
          work</tei:supplied> knocked me over, so that I was not permitted to budge from my bed and,
        consequently, was also not allowed to eat anything, etc.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>As you know, exceeding my capacity is in my bloodstream. I overdo my work in deep
        thinking, haste, always thinking ahead to the next piece of work, if not actually to several
        pieces of work. I overdo – for sake of the material that I prepare so individually – my
        dedication to teaching. I overdo my readiness to provide the most distant questioners with
        explanations and answers (with music examples, etc.), to go through the correcting of
        proofs. I overdo my kindness even in society, <tei:pb n="3"/> where I am always asked about
        all sorts of impossible things. In short: in each and every thing, in eating, speaking,
        shouting, and excitement, I overdo. In particular, <tei:hi rend="underline">in recent years
          I have been practising overwork</tei:hi>! For three years or so, I have been haunted by
        so-called oppressions; if I am hoarse from shouting, or have spoken too long, or worked too
        long, I suffer a <tei:hi rend="underline">tightening of the thorax</tei:hi>, which I find
        very painful. For five years, perhaps, my eyes have tormented me: an <tei:hi rend="underline">incessant flickering</tei:hi> drives me crazy, I cannot find the letters,
        the noteheads. And yet the doctors take neither those oppressions nor my eyes very
        seriously: "<tei:quote>Don't overdo things</tei:quote>" is the prescription; otherwise, I am
        pronounced healthy and fit for life!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In fact, even the previous year I had to rest in bed, <tei:pb n="4"/> so overtired was
        I from my responsibilities. Okay, you will have <tei:rs key="entity-001752" type="work">the
          new book</tei:rs> in your hands in three to four weeks at most – I shall not talk about
        its contents, but if you look at the music illustrations you will understand the pain which
        I am unable to avoid: in this part of the book, no one can replace me, whereas my <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs> can, and does, render highly
        respectable services in correcting of the proofs of the text.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000007" type="person">Albersham</tei:rs>'s and Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hoboken</tei:rs>'s <tei:hi rend="underline">two-hour
          lessons</tei:hi> increased my affliction alarmingly! Veritably a fatal ordeal, which I
        must discontinue, on the order of my doctors. Three such double-lessons per week: for the
        same pupil, <tei:hi rend="underline">theory for two hours</tei:hi>, six such hours per
        week!</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="5"/>
        <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hoboken</tei:rs> in particular appeared at such
        double-lessons often without preparing any homework (although he is otherwise a capable
        musical person) – and then I had two hours to get through, making use – or rather misuse –
        of one topic after another, changing the subject every ten minutes; I gave lectures of a
        length of which they have never been given. But the nabob, totally absorbed in his money,
        pretended (as it later turned out) that he would have offered <tei:hi rend="underline">to
          make things much easier</tei:hi> for me (as his thought process ran): the money for the
        two lessons he has basically made a gift to me, merely by listening! In general <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hoboken</tei:rs> has a lot on his conscience for coming
        close to harboring the delusion – the immeasurably greedy fellow that he is – that he had
        made me a present of the <tei:rs key="entity-002452" type="organization">Archive</tei:rs>
        and can claim the right to services <tei:hi rend="underline">from me</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="underline">in return</tei:hi>, outside of lesson times. <tei:pb n="6"/> Indeed, I
        have paid too dearly for the <tei:rs key="entity-002452" type="organization">Archive</tei:rs>!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Hardly have I been back on my feet again than I must offer up great sacrifices to
          <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans</tei:rs>, as I immediately suspected.
          <tei:hi rend="underline">Understandably</tei:hi> he is afraid of going wrong in front of
        the <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs> forum; at the same time,
        however, he has the ambition to present to his listeners examples that I have not not yet
        used: about ten pieces, copies of which he will put in their hands. He will show <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">me</tei:add> all the pieces – and you can believe me
        that the real work will fall to me, for <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans</tei:rs> is not at all secure, indeed he is often to wide of the mark. Already
          <tei:supplied reason="clarity">his work on</tei:supplied> the <tei:rs key="entity-004715" type="composition">Two-part Invention No. 5 (in E flat major)</tei:rs> showed me what lies
        ahead of me, <tei:pb n="7"/> he wants to to make a polemic against <tei:rs key="entity-003123" type="person">Lorenz</tei:rs> (<tei:rs key="entity-002286" type="place">Munich</tei:rs>), but has himself gone astray. Now, can – may – I leave
          <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans</tei:rs> in the lurch? No, of course not,
        surely not on my account, and probably also not on his account. (His <tei:rs key="entity-002973" type="composition">Octet</tei:rs> was <tei:hi rend="underline">absolutely splendid</tei:hi>; the most recent piece I shall not hear until <tei:date when="1930-01">January</tei:date>.) At any rate, <tei:hi rend="underline">I am very much
          delighted</tei:hi> to know that you will be going to <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs>. I shall give you further specific instructions for this
        trip.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Now, I have given you the evidence, that I am – alive.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>The communication from Miss <tei:rs key="entity-000049" type="person">Becker</tei:rs>
        pleased and interested me greatly. My annual royalty for the <tei:rs key="entity-001753" type="work">Beethoven edition</tei:rs> amounts to 1200 shillings, <tei:pb n="8"/> i.e. 100
        shillings per month; a good business for the <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">publisher</tei:rs>. As for my money held by <tei:rs key="entity-000774" type="person">Mozio</tei:rs>, I am still now not in the clear. These are enough themes for a further
        life, and thus I live on.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>To you and to all your loved ones, most affectionate greetings from yours, whose
          life has still been spared (and what about <tei:rs key="entity-001728" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Der freie Satz</tei:title></tei:rs>?),</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p>What my <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs> had to
          sacrifice during the period of my confinement – day and <tei:hi rend="underline">night</tei:hi>! – would be a chapter in itself!</tei:p>
        <tei:p><tei:date when="1930-10-21">October 21, 1930</tei:date></tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

      <tei:fw type="envelope"><tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">envelope:</tei:note><tei:lb/>
        <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="recto"/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied reason="clarity">to:</tei:supplied>
            <tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">M.
              Violin</tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-40"><tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-40">Haynstrasse 13</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:fw type="postmark">|| 1 WIEN 1 | 16–17 | 21. X. | 1930 | * 4b * ||</tei:fw><tei:lb/>
        <tei:lb/><tei:milestone unit="folio" n="verso"/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-45"><tei:supplied reason="clarity">sender:</tei:supplied>
            <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-30"><tei:handShift new="#printed"/><tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">VIENNA</tei:rs> III., <tei:rs key="entity-002826" type="place">KEILGASSE</tei:rs> 8 <tei:handShift new="#HS"/>/12</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
      </tei:fw>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>