<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="943" sdoID="OJ-6-7_23">OJ 6/7, [23]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
   <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2013</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2013-06-09" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002720">ViolinM ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002721">ViolinM+V ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002722">ViolinM+V+F ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated July 26, 1925</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1925-07-26T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2013-06-09</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Two weeks after arriving in Galtür for the summer holidays, Schenker reports that
    he has caught up on his sleep and has already dictated an essay on Reger's Variations and Fugue
    on a Theme of J. S. Bach, Op. 81. He will not allow the legal wrangle with Universal Edition to
    interfere with his holiday, but he is annoyed about not having been paid by Drei Masken Verlag
    for the manuscript of Meisterwerk 1. He has responded to a critique of his Erläuterungsausgabe
    of Op. 110, in an essay in Meisterwerk 1, but will not pursue other attacks upon his work and
    those of his pupils. The Schenker medallion designed by Alfred Rothberger is going to a second
    impression; but the mezzotint portrait by Viktor Hammer, which Jeanette finds a superior work,
    has not yet been printed. Throughout the letter, Schenker urges Violin to bring his family to
    Galtür sometime during the summer.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>



  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Fl</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ
      3/7, p. 2846, July 25, 1925: "An Fl. (Br.): Bericht über das Laufende, auch über die
      U.-E.-Frage u. den Drei Masken Verlag; Einladung." ("To Floriz (letter): report on how things
      are developing, also about the UE question and the Drei Masken Verlag;
      invitation.")</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Über zwei Wochen haben wir Schlaf gehalten, – <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">LieLiechen</tei:rs> war die erste, die sich den Schlaf aus den Augen rieb u.
    bemerkte, daß sie ja in <tei:rs key="entity-002334" type="place">Tirol</tei:rs> ist, ich bin
    etwas später eingelaufen, heute weiß ich es auch. Ja, sogar habe ich inzwischen <tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person">Reger</tei:rs>’s <tei:rs key="entity-001659" type="composition">Bach-Var. Op. 81</tei:rs> unter dem Titel
     „<tei:term>Gegenbeispiel</tei:term>“ diktiert u. für das <tei:rs key="entity-001751" type="work"><tei:title>Jahrb. II</tei:title></tei:rs> vorbereitet. Ich werde den guten Ton
    bewahren, aber die schauerlichsten Dinge vorlegen. Nützen kann das alles freilich <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">gar</tei:add> nicht, denn geradeso wie <tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person">Reger</tei:rs> komponiert, <tei:hi rend="underline">gerade so
     hören ja die Massen</tei:hi>, vom 16<tei:hi rend="supralinear">tel</tei:hi> to 16<tei:hi rend="supralinear">tel</tei:hi>, so reden sie, so leben sie. Ein <tei:term>Terz-</tei:term>,
     <tei:term>Quint-</tei:term>, <tei:term>Quartzug</tei:term>? Ein Anfang, ein Ende? Nichts davon,
    in jedem Augenblick fänge es an, in jedem hört es auf, dieses Ohr-Schieben sagt ihnen am besten
    zu. Aber was geht das mich an???</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Auch haben wir all die Tage her fleißig gelesen, sommerlich durheinander, von
     <tei:rs key="entity-000429" type="person">Keller</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-003460" type="person">Plutarch</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000784" type="person">Schiller</tei:rs>
    usw., dazu die drei Zeitungen, die so manches Lesenswerte bringen. Und damit unser Erholung
    nicht <tei:pb n="2"/> vergiftet werden, habe ich D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi>
    <tei:rs key="entity-000048" type="person">Baumgarten</tei:rs> untersagt, eine Korrespondenz mit
     <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> u. D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi>
    <tei:rs key="entity-000779" type="person">Scheu</tei:rs> zu führen, u. ihm mitgeteilt, daß im
    Herbst geklagt werden <tei:hi rend="underline">muß</tei:hi>, da <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">H.</tei:rs> auch schon die Einnahmen aus den <tei:rs key="entity-001753" type="work">Sonaten</tei:rs> kürzte u. seine Briefe genauso verleugnet, wie er <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Temming</tei:rs>s Abonn. bestritten hat. Ich hätte es nicht
    für möglich gehalten, daß sich ein Mensch findet, der von der Rechnerei noch weniger versteht,
    als ich, u. doch – D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi>
    <tei:rs key="entity-000048" type="person">B.</tei:rs> ist es! Zwar weiß ich nicht genau worin
    der Betrag steckt, u. wie hoch er ist, aber doch habe ich ein <tei:hi rend="underline">juristisch</tei:hi>-deutliches Gefühl, daß die Rechnungen anders, namentlich höher zu lauten
    haben.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Für die nächste Saison hat sich <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs>’s Schüler, der reiche <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">van
     Hoboken</tei:rs><tei:supplied reason="puctuation">,</tei:supplied> angesagt. Er kommt mir
    gerade gelegen, eine Lücke auszustopfen, leider konnte ich von ihm nicht mehr als 5 Doll. per
    Stunde verlangen, da ein <tei:hi rend="underline">ihm</tei:hi> sehr gut bekannter <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">Junge</tei:rs> (ebenfalls aus <tei:rs key="entity-002286" type="place">München</tei:rs> u. Schüler von <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vriesl.</tei:rs>) ja auch mir so viel sahlt, u. ich durchaus nicht so erscheinen wollte, als
    würde ich seinen übermäßigen Reihtum ausnützen wollen. Den Stand von <tei:date when="1922">1922</tei:date> kann ich, wie ich sehe, nicht wieder erreichen u. aus den Werken – na! Denke
    dir, die <tei:rs key="entity-002627" type="organization">3 Masken</tei:rs> haben mir <tei:pb n="3"/> nicht einmal noch den vertragsmäßig fälligen ersten Betrag von blos 250 M.
    eingeschickt, trotzdem sie das Msc. schon seit <tei:date when="1925-06-15">15. Juni</tei:date>
    haben. Nach solcher selbstmörderischer Arbeit nicht einmal eine solche kleine Schuldigkeit von
    selbst zu entrichten, das ist doch gewissenslos! Ich habe die <tei:rs key="entity-002627" type="organization">3 M.</tei:rs> heute gemahnt.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Wo steckt Ihr allesamt? In <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>? Bei
     <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>? So kommt doch hierher! In <tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs> sind augenblicklich fast lauter Deutschen,
    offenbar ists ihnen billig genug. Das Dorf ist überfüll, aber wenn Ihr kommen wolltet, finden
    wir schon einen Weg. Das Wetter war bisher im Allgemeinen ungünstig, gerade das aber läßt schöne
    Tage erhoffen, u. was schöne Tage in den <tei:rs key="entity-004629" type="place">Alpen</tei:rs>
    bedeuten, das wißt Ihr ja. Also packet, u. kommt. Ihe erspart noch!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Was macht der <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">kleine</tei:rs>? Wie hält er es
    mit der Schule? Die <tei:rs key="entity-000911" type="person">kleine</tei:rs> dürfte die
    Zöpfchen vorne tragen, wie wir das öfter sehen, nicht?</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Hast du in der „<tei:title>Musik</tei:title>“ eine Kritik über <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vriesl</tei:rs>’s <tei:rs key="entity-000025" type="person">Em. Bach</tei:rs> u.
    jetzt über den „<tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title>TW</tei:title></tei:rs>“,
    Hefte <tei:rs key="entity-001744" type="work">5</tei:rs>–<tei:rs key="entity-001745" type="work">6</tei:rs>(!!!) <tei:pb n="4"/> gelesen? O, sie zielen nach mir, ich lache. Ein Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000209" type="person">Englsmann</tei:rs> schrieb in <tei:rs key="entity-002317" type="place">Stuttgart</tei:rs> gegen <tei:rs key="entity-001735" type="work">mein op.
     110</tei:rs>, die Antwort findest du im „<tei:rs key="entity-001750" type="work"><tei:title>Jahrb. I</tei:title></tei:rs>“, – das eine mal gab ich einen „Patsch“, die Anderen
    lasse ich lasse ich laufen. Meine Sache ist es, etwas vorzulegen, Alles andere haben die blöden
    Menschen mit sich selbst auszutragen.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Die erste Serie der Plakette ist schon vergriffen, eine neue wurde aufgelegt, sogar Frau
     <tei:rs key="entity-000072" type="person">Bienenfeld</tei:rs> hat eine erworben, wie mir Frau
     <tei:rs key="entity-000655" type="person">Pairamall</tei:rs> schreibt. Wenn nur auch schon
     <tei:rs key="entity-000327" type="person">Hammer</tei:rs>s Bildnis draußen wäre, <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">LieLiechen</tei:rs> findet diese Arbeit unendlich überlegen,
    – ich selbst weiß doch nicht recht, wie ich aussehe u. der Spiegel war nie mein
     „<tei:soCalled>Confidant</tei:soCalled>“.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute>Also: Kommt! Mit diesem Wort, unterstrichen auch von meinem <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">LieLiechen</tei:rs>, schließe ich das Bfchen, grüßen u.
     grüßend allzumal!<tei:note type="editorial">?</tei:note>
    </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute>Euer aller</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-35"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs> u.
      <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">LieLie</tei:rs></tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline><tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1925-07-26">26. VII., 1925</tei:date>.</tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">For two weeks we have been sleeping things off. <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs> was the first who rubbed the sleep from her eyes and
    observed that she is indeed in the <tei:rs key="entity-002334" type="place">Tyrol</tei:rs>. It
    took me somewhat more time to realize this; now I know it, too. Indeed, in the meantime I have
    dictated <tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person">Reger</tei:rs>'s <tei:rs key="entity-001659" type="composition">Bach Variations, Op. 81</tei:rs>, with the title
     "<tei:term>Counter-example</tei:term>" and prepared it for the <tei:rs key="entity-001751" type="work"><tei:title>second Yearbook</tei:title></tei:rs>. I shall retain a positive tone but
    lay bare the most dreadful things. All this cannot, of course, do any good <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">whatsoever</tei:add>: just as <tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person">Reger</tei:rs> composes, <tei:hi rend="underline">so, exactly do the masses
     hear</tei:hi>, from one sixteenth note to the next. That is how they speak, that is how they
    live. A <tei:term>third-</tei:term>, <tei:term>fifth-</tei:term>,
     <tei:term>fourth-progression</tei:term>? A beginning, an ending? There is nothing of the sort
    to be found: there is a beginning in every instant, an end in every instant. This crude aural
    behavior they find most agreeable. But of what concern is that to me???</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In addition, we have been using all this time to read assiduously, all sorts
    of things in no particular order, as befits the summer season: <tei:rs key="entity-000429" type="person">Keller</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-003460" type="person">Plutarch</tei:rs>,
     <tei:rs key="entity-000784" type="person">Schiller</tei:rs>, and the three newspapers which
    offer so much worthwhile. And so that our recovery is not <tei:pb n="2"/> contaminated, I have
    forbidden Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000048" type="person">Baumgarten</tei:rs> from corresponding
    with <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> and Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000779" type="person">Scheu</tei:rs>, and told him that legal action <tei:hi rend="underline">must</tei:hi> be taken in the autumn, since <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> has already reduced my income from the <tei:rs key="entity-001753" type="work"><tei:supplied reason="clarity">edition of the
      Beethoven</tei:supplied> sonatas</tei:rs>, and his letters equally betray how he has queried
     <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Temming</tei:rs>'s subscriptions. I would not have
    thought it possible that there could be such a person who understands even less about arithmetic
    than I do, and yet – Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000048" type="person">Baumgarten</tei:rs> himself
    is the man! True, I do not know what is holding up payment, or how high it is, but I have a
     <tei:hi rend="underline">legally</tei:hi> clear feeling that the payments ought to be
    different, i.e. greater.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>For next season I have accepted <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs>'s pupil, the wealthy <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">van
     Hoboken</tei:rs>. He comes at just the right time to fill a gap. Unfortunately I could not
    demand from him more than five dollars per lesson, since <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">a young man</tei:rs> who is well known to <tei:hi rend="underline">him</tei:hi>
    (likewise a pupil of <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs>'s, from
     <tei:rs key="entity-002286" type="place">Munich</tei:rs>) is paying me exactly as much, and I
    certainly do not want to give the impression that I am exploiting his enormous wealth. I shall
    not, so far as I can see, be able to reach the position I enjoyed in <tei:date when="1922">1922</tei:date>. And from proceeds of my works? Well, just consider this: the <tei:rs key="entity-002627" type="organization">Drei Masken Verlag</tei:rs> have <tei:pb n="3"/> not
    yet even sent me the first payment, of a mere 250 marks, which is contractually due, in spite of
    the fact that they have had my manuscript since <tei:date when="1925-06-15">June 15</tei:date>.
    Not even to have paid this small debt as a matter of course, after such suicidal work: that is
    surely unconscionable! I warned <tei:rs key="entity-002627" type="organization">the
     publisher</tei:rs> today.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Where are you all hiding? In <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>?
    Near <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>? Then come over here! In <tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs> there are at the moment almost exclusively
    Germans; apparently it is cheap enough for them. The village is overcrowded, but if you would
    like to come we shall surelly find a way. The weather was, until now, generally unfavorable; but
    even that allows to hope for beautiful days, and what beautiful days in the <tei:rs key="entity-004629" type="place">Alps</tei:rs> means is something you well known. So pack your
    bags, and come: you will still save money!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>What is the <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">little boy</tei:rs> up to? How is he
    getting on in school? The <tei:rs key="entity-000911" type="person">girl</tei:rs> is probably
    wearing her braids in front, as we often see.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Have you read in <tei:title level="j">Die Musik</tei:title> a review of <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs>'s book on <tei:rs key="entity-000025" type="person">C. P. E. Bach</tei:rs>, and now a review of <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>, issues <tei:rs key="entity-001744" type="work">5</tei:rs>–<tei:rs key="entity-001745" type="work">6</tei:rs>(!!!)? <tei:pb n="4"/> Oh, they have their sights on me; and I am laughing. A Mr.
     <tei:rs key="entity-000209" type="person">Engelsmann</tei:rs> wrote in <tei:rs key="entity-002317" type="place">Stuttgart</tei:rs> in opposition to my <tei:rs key="entity-001735" type="work"><tei:supplied reason="clarity"><tei:title>Erläuterungsausgabe</tei:title> of</tei:supplied> Op. 110</tei:rs>; you will find
    my reply in <tei:rs key="entity-001750" type="work"><tei:title>Yearbook 1</tei:title></tei:rs>.
    I've given him a "slap"; the others I shall not pursue. My task is to present something; the
    imbecilic people can come to terms with everything else for themselves.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>The first impression of <tei:supplied reason="clarity"><tei:rs key="entity-000738" type="person">Rothberger</tei:rs>'s</tei:supplied> medallion is already sold out; a new one
    will be brought out. Even Mrs <tei:rs key="entity-000072" type="person">Bienenfeld</tei:rs> has
    acquired on, as Mrs. <tei:rs key="entity-000655" type="person">Pairamall</tei:rs> informs me. If
    only <tei:rs key="entity-000327" type="person">Hammer</tei:rs>'s portrait were on sale – <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs> finds this work incomparably superior –
    I myself do not really know what I look like, and the mirror was never my
     "<tei:soCalled>confidant</tei:soCalled>."</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute>And so: Come! With this word, underscored also by my <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs>, I close this note, send you all our greetings, our
     greetings as ever.</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-35"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs> and
      <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Lie</tei:rs></tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline><tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1925-07-26">July 26, 1925</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>