<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2689" sdoID="OJ-6-8_1">OJ 6/8, [1]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2015</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2015</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IDB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-07-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002720">ViolinM ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002721">ViolinM+V ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002722">ViolinM+V+F ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Violin, dated January 9, 1931</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1931-01-09T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2022-02-25</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>In this long and wide-ranging two-part letter, which includes a graphic
        analysis of J. S. Bach’s Two-part Invention in E-flat major, Schenker praises the work of
        Hans Weisse, who has recently returned from lecturing in Berlin and may be offered a post
        there (on Furtwängler’s recommendation), emigrate to America (with the help of Gerald
        Warburg), or even found an institute that would give employment to Felix Salzer and other
        Schenkerian disciples under one roof. — A letter from Violin, which has just arrived in the
        morning post, speaks of Violin’s own intention to establish a Schenker Institute in Hamburg.
        For this, Schenker recommends Felix-Eberhard von Cube (in preference to Reinhard Oppel) and
        Otto Vrieslander as possible theory teachers, if not Weisse himself. — The letter concludes
        with a tirade against those who have caused him financial misery (including his brother
        Mozio), culminating in a cynical passage in which Schenker advises his friend to look after
        himself and engage some dull pedagog to teach conventional theory. In the end, he wishes
        Violin luck with the enterprise, and thanks him for having helped rescue him from Hertzka’s
        clutches.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:fw type="envelope">
          <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold">envelope</tei:hi></tei:note><tei:lb/>
          <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="recto"/>
          <tei:address>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied reason="clarity">An:</tei:supplied>
              <tei:handShift new="#HS"/>H Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">M.
                Violin</tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50"><tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place"><tei:hi
                  rend="underline">Hamburg</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">Haynstr. 13</tei:addrLine>
          </tei:address><tei:lb/>
          <tei:fw type="postmark">|| 3 WIEN 60 | -9.1.31.17 | * 4d * ||</tei:fw>
          <tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        </tei:fw>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold">letter</tei:hi></tei:note>
        <tei:salute><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Fl</tei:rs>!<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is recorded in
            Schenker's diary for January 9, 1931: “An Floriz (Br., 12 Seiten): über Weisses Vortrag;
            über mein wirklich heldenhaftes Eintreten für das Jahrbuch mit S. 7000 u. die Gründe,
            die mich dazu bestimmten: die Augen u. die Aussichtslosigkeit bei Br. u. H.” (“To Floriz
            (letter, 12 pages): concerning Weisse’s lecture; concerning my truly heroic intercession
            on behalf of the Yearbook with 7,000 shillings, and the reasons that made me do so: my
            eyes, and the hopeless prospect <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of
              publication</tei:supplied> by Breitkopf &amp; Härtel”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Wie ich deiner <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000909">Fanny</tei:rs> sagte, die
        vorvorgestern bei uns war, so muß es sein: ich kann mich nicht an einem Brief zu dir
        hinsetzen, bevor ich nicht Alles sonstige aus dem Felde geräumt habe, Sammlung, Andacht
        sollen mich zu dir führen . . . </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Der wirtschaftliche Jammer ist ohnegleichen, meine Verluste sind <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">nicht</tei:add> kleiner als die deinen! <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >Alle</tei:hi> Briefschreiber von draußen klagen! <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000107">Brünauer</tei:rs> war – im 28.<tei:hi rend="supralinear">ten</tei:hi>
          Jahr!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">If, by this reckoning,
          Schenker means that Brünauer had been his pupil for 28 years until the summer of 1930,
          then his lessons would have commenced in the 1902/03 season. However, in his diary for
          December 1, 1927, Schenker uses the same figure to imply that Brünauer‘s pupillage with
          him went back to about 1899: “der Konflikt, den er nun ungefähr 28 Jahre mit seinem Geiz
          zu bestehen hat, spiegelt ihm das Mäzenatentum vor.” (“the conflict that he has had to
          survive with his vanity for about twenty-eight years deludes him into thinking that he is
          my patron.”).</tei:note> – der Allererste, der <tei:add place="interlinear-above">nur aus
          gewohntem Übermut seines Schmutzes</tei:add> schon im Sommer von den 2 Stunden per Woche
        eine zurückgelegt hat! Das gab mir einen Stich, dessen Folgen ich noch trage. Schüler sind
        kaum mehr zu erwarten: die 4 Jahrgänge junger Menschenkinder, die heute zwischen 16–20 Jahre
        alt wären, fehlen ja!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker is
          apparently writing off the four wartime years (1914–18) as a time when very few children
          were conceived, 1915 marking the first year in which few children were born on Austria.
          But he seems to have counted in the wrong direction from 1914: children who were born
          during the war would be between twelve and sixteen, not between sixteen and
          twenty.</tei:note> Und wer wollte heute Musik studieren, wenn er keine Aussichten hat! </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/>Ein teuflischer Zug: zur <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >angeborenen</tei:add>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">musik</tei:hi>alischen <tei:hi rend="underline"
        >Unzu</tei:hi>länglichkeit der Welt gesellt sich die <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >wirtschaftliche</tei:hi> ... der Mensch will sich auf einen Esel reduzieren, ohne zu
        ahnen, daß diese<tei:del rend="overstrike">r</tei:del> Verwandlung ihn schließlich mit
          <tei:hi rend="underline">Hunger u. Tod bedroht</tei:hi>, so verlockend sie sonst mag, als
        Entlastung von geistiger oder körperlicher Mühe. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
          >Weisse</tei:hi></tei:rs> – daß du so lieb warst, nach <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002501"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Berlin</tei:hi></tei:rs> zu gehen,<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Weisse gave two lectures at the
          Zentralinstitut für Erziehung und Unterricht in Berlin in December 1930, for which a trial
          run had taken place at Schenker’s apartment on December 5: see <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-15-15_50">OJ 15/15, [50]</tei:ref>, November 30, 1930,
          from Weisse to Schenker, and <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-45_116">OJ 14/45,
            [116]</tei:ref>, December 10, 1930, Violin to Schenker; see also
              <tei:bibl><tei:author>Timothy L. Jackson</tei:author>, <tei:title level="a"><tei:hi
                rend="italic">Punctus contra punctus</tei:hi> …,</tei:title>
            <tei:title level="j">Journal of Schenkerian Studies</tei:title> iv (2010), pp. 87–186,
            esp. 115–17</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> mir zu schreiben, das Alles bewahre ich in meinem
        Herzen als Zeichen unvertilgbarer Seelen- u. Schick<tei:supplied reason="omission"
          >s</tei:supplied>alsgemeinschaft – hat bei mir gesprochen, ganz ausgezeichnet. Ich habe
        schon zu Hause den Eindruck gewonnen, daß er jede „Fortschritts“hysterie entgültig abgelegt
        hat u. – zu seinem eigenen besten – streng bei seinem „Väterchen“<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">From the early 1920s, after completing
          his formal studies in composition, theory, and piano with Schenker, Weisse looked upon his
          teacher as his “spiritual father.”</tei:note> bleibt. Er hat von mir <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overwritten">d</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="superimposed">s</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>ogar den Rat angenommen, <tei:hi rend="underline">nicht</tei:hi>, wie er
        jahrelang es tat, auf <tei:add place="interlinear-above"><tei:hi rend="underline"
            >unbedingte</tei:hi></tei:add>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">Sicherheit</tei:hi> zu pochen, sondern seine Weisheit <tei:pb n="3"
        /> so vorzutragen, wie er sie eben vorrätig hat. Jene Sucht nach „Sicherheit“ (Angst vor
        einer nachträglichen Blamage) nannte er sehr ungeschickt seine „<tei:hi rend="underline"
          >Hemmung</tei:hi>“ u. da er davon immer in Verbindung mit mir, vor mir u. auch vor Anderen
        sprach, hatten wir Alle den Eindruck, <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">als tyrannisierte ich ihn</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">als beschuldigte er mich, ihn zu
              <tei:supplied>tyrannisier</tei:supplied>en</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>. Der Sinn seiner „Hemmung“ definiert er heute fast cynisch: „Ich hatte früher
        so viel Hemmungen, jetzt sehe ich, daß man den Menschen Alles auf den Kopf <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">zu</tei:add> sagen kann; wie <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >sie</tei:hi> reden, rede unbedenklich auch <tei:hi rend="underline">ich</tei:hi>.“ In der
        Linie meines Rates lag es <tei:add place="interlinear-above">denn</tei:add> auch, ihm (wie
        ich es bisher hielt) zu <tei:hi rend="underline">verschweigen</tei:hi>, daß ausnahmslos
          <tei:hi rend="underline">sämtliche</tei:hi> Beweisführungen <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >unrichtig</tei:hi> sind. Ich lobte ihn mit echtester Überzeugung, denn, worauf es heute
        uns Allen anzukommen hat, ist die Einsicht bekanntzugeben u. über alle Dächer zu verbreiten,
        daß die Musik einen <tei:hi rend="underline">eigenen</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">Zusammenhang</tei:hi> hat, <tei:pb n="4"/> sei u. heiße er wie er
        will, (nur <tei:hi rend="underline">der</tei:hi> ist es <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >nicht</tei:hi>, den die Schulen lehren!) Und diese Schuldigkeit hat <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000951">Hans</tei:rs> auf <tei:hi rend="underline">das
          Allerglänzendste</tei:hi> gelöst: seine Formulierungen, (die natürlich auch die meinen
        sind) waren u. sind glänzend, die Sprache, der Vortrag hinreißend, begeisternd, begeistert. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nur die <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-004715"><tei:title>Invention Es<tei:hi
              rend="supralinear">d</tei:hi></tei:title></tei:rs> hat er mir vorgelegt, hier erbat er
        Hilfe, u. da traf es sich, daß er den Fehler, den er dem H. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003123">Prof. Lorenz</tei:rs> vorhielt, doch auch selbst begangen hat. Er
        hatte irrtümlich eine <tei:g type="cap3"/>, die ich in <tei:g type="cap5"/> verbesserte.
        Leider begriff er in seiner Zeitbedrängnis mein<tei:del rend="overstrike">e</tei:del>
        kleines Bildchen nicht: <tei:lb/><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">MUSIC EXAMPLE
          HERE</tei:note>
        <tei:lb/>den Ausbau der <tei:term>Nbn</tei:term> c<tei:hi rend="supralinear">3</tei:hi>, die
        die Handlung retardiert, bis endlich die <tei:g type="cap4"/> – <tei:g type="cap1"/> kommen.
        Er nahm die <tei:g type="cap5"/> an, verstand aber den Baß nicht, u. richtete einen
        ordentlichen Mischmasch an.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Weisse used J. S. Bach’s <tei:title>Invention No. 5 in E-flat major</tei:title>, BWV 776,
          as the focal point of his Berlin lecture: see <tei:bibl><tei:author>Timothy L.
              Jackson</tei:author>, <tei:title level="a"><tei:hi rend="italic">Punctus contra
                punctus</tei:hi> …,</tei:title>
            <tei:title level="j">Journal of Schenkerian Studies</tei:title> iv (2010), pp. 87–186,
            esp. 115–16</tei:bibl>.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="5"/> Bis heute verschwieg ich <tei:del rend="overstrike">ihn</tei:del>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Weisse</tei:hi></tei:rs>
        meine Meinung. Hatte ich nicht Recht? u. heute auch? Niemand hat die Fehler bemerkt, wohl
        aber hatten die Zuhörer etwas zu hören gekriegt, was sie so<tei:del rend="overstrike"
          >nst</tei:del> nicht gehört haben. O! Käme wieder die Zeit, wo ich dir z. B. auf einem
        Kafeehaustischchen, bei dir oder bei mir, die in Frage kommende Besserungen mit Stift zeigen
        könnte, wie ehedem! </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Mit meiner Vermutung hatte ich Recht. Kein Zweifel ist für mich, daß <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000951">W.</tei:rs> an <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268"
          >Furtw.</tei:rs> appelliert hat, nun geht <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
          >W.</tei:rs> Anfang des nächsten Jahres <tei:hi rend="underline">wirklich nach</tei:hi>
        <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501"><tei:hi rend="underline lateinschr"
          >Berlin</tei:hi></tei:rs> (in Wien hat er leider nichts mehr zu suchen!!); <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtw.</tei:rs> schrieb ihm aus <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-003075">St. Moriz</tei:rs>, daß er eine Konferenz mit <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000431">Kestenberg</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000809"><tei:hi
            rend="lateinschr">Schünemann</tei:hi></tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000802"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Schreker</tei:hi></tei:rs> Anfang Jänner
        habe, wo <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">W</tei:rs>’s Berufung auf dem Programm
        stehen wird. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">W.</tei:rs> ihm ist um ein fixum zu
        tun (wegen der Kinder, auch wegen <tei:pb n="6"/> seiner vorgeschrittenen Jahre); sollte er
        die offizielle Stelle nicht erhalten, will er nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002510"
          >Amerika</tei:rs> u. dort mit Hilfe <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000934"
          >Warburg</tei:rs>s u.s.w.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">The
          ellipsis suggests that Schenker believed Warburg to be enthusiastic about bringing Weisse
          to New York. Weisse was, in fact, to emigrate to the USA and take up a teaching post at
          the Leopold Mannes Music School in the autumn of 1931.</tei:note> Ich denke aber, daß er
        in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
          >Berlin</tei:hi></tei:rs> seinen Weg <tei:hi rend="underline">machen wird</tei:hi>; bei
        Stelle oder ohne sie wird er sehr bald ein <tei:hi rend="underline lateinschr"
          >Seminar</tei:hi><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot">By “seminar”
          Schenker is probably thinking of a regular course of lectures, not a small group of active
          participants or an actual department of theory at some music school. But Schenker later
          talks about the prospect of a “Schenker Institute” under Weisse’s leadership.</tei:note>
        errichten, wo er Treffliches leisten wird. (Die Seminarpreise sind niedrig u. ermöglichen
        eine große Zahl von Teilnehmern.) Er denkt an ein<tei:del rend="overstrike">e</tei:del>
        Schenker-Institut, das Alle derzeit Heimatlose (wie z. B. auch <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000754">D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Salzer</tei:rs>) beschäftigen
        würde. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun wäre Zeit, daß ich <tei:add place="interlinear-above">dir</tei:add> noch ein
        Geheimnis verriete, aber meine Augen versagen bereits . . Ich vergesse gewiß nicht, darauf
        im nächsten Brief zurückzukommen . . </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Hier nur noch: der Schriftleiter des „<tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-003014"
            ><tei:title>Kunstwart</tei:title></tei:rs>“ <tei:pb n="7"/> in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002286">München</tei:rs> (begründet von <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003347">Avenarius</tei:rs>) hat solchen Gefallen an meinem „Vermischten“
        gefunden, daß er 9 Seiten mit Auszügen füllte. In <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002757"
          >Kiel</tei:rs> drucken die „Hochschulblätter“ <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001740"
            ><tei:title>TW <tei:hi rend="underline">1</tei:hi> (19<tei:hi rend="underline"
              >2</tei:hi>0)</tei:title></tei:rs> ab. .<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Munich: The editor of <tei:title level="j">Der Kunstwart</tei:title> at this
          time was <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000717">Hermann Rinn</tei:rs>. See Rinn’s
          correspondence with Schenker, e.g. <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-13-25_12">OJ
            13/25, [12]</tei:ref>, November 17, 1930.— Kiel: The <tei:title level="j"
            >Schleswig-Holsteinsche Hochschulblätter</tei:title> reprinted the lead article from
              <tei:title><tei:hi rend="italic">Tonwille</tei:hi> 1</tei:title>, <tei:title level="a"
            >Von der Sendung des deutschen Genies.</tei:title> See Schenker’s scrapbook (OC, file
          2), p. 80.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Soeben 9½ Vm. läuft dein Bf ein mit der sensationeller Wendung, welche Überraschung!!
        Prof. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143"><tei:hi rend="underline lateinschr">v.
            Cube</tei:hi></tei:rs> (<tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002621">Duisburg</tei:rs>) käme
          <tei:hi rend="underline">vor</tei:hi>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Oppel</tei:rs> in Betracht, <tei:hi
          rend="underline">ganz vorzüglich</tei:hi> wäre <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922"
            ><tei:hi rend="double-underline lateinschr">Vrieslander</tei:hi></tei:rs> für
            <tei:term><tei:hi rend="underline lateinschr">Kp</tei:hi></tei:term> u.
            <tei:term><tei:hi rend="underline lateinschr">Gb</tei:hi></tei:term>., <tei:note
          type="editorial" place="inline">cued from lower margin:</tei:note>Selbstverständlich wäre
        auch die „<tei:term>Url</tei:term>“ bei ihm gut aufgehoben, so daß er eigentlich <tei:hi
          rend="underline">als der Einzige</tei:hi> mit <tei:hi rend="underline">Wirkung</tei:hi> in
        Frage kommt!<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end cue</tei:note> nur ist eine Schule
        gar nicht <tei:sic>eingerrichtet</tei:sic> darauf, diesen Disziplinen Aufmerksamkeit,
        geschweige Zeit u. Geld zu widmen. Vielleicht greift <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000951"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Weisse</tei:hi></tei:rs> zu, das wäre ein –
          <tei:hi rend="underline">Haupttreffer</tei:hi>! Ich fürchte, er will sich hinaus,
        namentlich Geld verdienen, um sich u. seine Kinder zu schützen. Wärst <tei:hi
          rend="underline">du hier, würde</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">ich selbst</tei:hi>, um unserer Sicher- <tei:pb n="8"/> stellung
        willen, die Theorie<tei:supplied reason="omission">-</tei:supplied>Stelle übernehmen. Denn –
        gleichzeitig lief der Brief meines Anwaltes ein, der <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs> wegen <tei:hi rend="underline">14.000 S.</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">klagt</tei:hi>, da ich ihm <tei:sic><tei:hi rend="underline"
            >baar</tei:hi></tei:sic> übergeben habe. Auf <tei:hi rend="double-underline"
          >dieses</tei:hi> Geld habe ich in meinem <tei:hi rend="double-underline">Augen</tei:hi>-
        u. <tei:hi rend="underline">Zeit</tei:hi><tei:hi rend="double-underline">not</tei:hi>
        gerechnet, als ich das <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001752"><tei:title>Jb.
            III</tei:title></tei:rs> – mit <tei:hi rend="double-underline">7.000 S.</tei:hi> ganz
        auf <tei:hi rend="underline">meine</tei:hi> Rechnung stellte! Ein Verrat an meinem <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000771">LieLiechen</tei:rs>, die aber nicht eine Mi<tei:supplied
          reason="omission">e</tei:supplied>ne verzieht, ein<tei:del rend="overstrike">e</tei:del>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">Selbstmord</tei:hi>!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Hätte ich mich um die Augen bringen sollen (sieh nur die Eroica-Bilder an!)?! <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000356">Hertzka</tei:rs> betrog mich um ein <tei:hi
          rend="underline">ganzes Jahr</tei:hi>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Schenker is referring to the article <tei:bibl><tei:title level="a"
              >Beethovens Dritte Sinfonie zum erstenmal in ihrem wahren Inhalt
              dargestellt,</tei:title> in <tei:title level="j">Das Meisterwerk</tei:title>, iii
            (1930), 25–101</tei:bibl>, and specifically to the graphs that follow p. 121 (Eng.
          transl., pp. 10–68, where the graphs are incorporated into the text). — Read in context,
          this sentence suggests that, in spite of Schenker having broken with Hertzka over
            <tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title>, Universal Edition had been approached as
          a possible publisher of the study of the “Eroica” in monograph form, complementing
          Universal’s publication of Schenker’s monographs on the Ninth and Fifth Symphonies (1912,
          1925).</tei:note>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtw.</tei:rs> erfuhr davon <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">durch mich selbst</tei:add>, tat alles Mögliche, erreichte, daß
        sich <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002890">Br &amp; Härtel</tei:rs>
        <tei:del rend="overstrike">sie</tei:del> zur Verfügung stellten, ich war aber aus <tei:hi
          rend="underline">Augen-Verzweiflung</tei:hi> schon mit den <tei:pb n="9"/>
        <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002627">3 Masken</tei:rs> verbunden u. befürchtete
        sicher mit Recht, daß <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002890">Br &amp; H.</tei:rs>
        gemäß der heutigen Lage die Drucklegung auf Jahre hinaus verschieben u. mir dadurch einen
        großen Schaden bereiten würden, sofern ich den „<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"
            ><tei:title>Fr. Satz</tei:title></tei:rs>“ nicht ausarbeiten könnte. Ich habe erwartet,
        daß <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtw.</tei:rs> irgendeiner <tei:hi
          rend="lateinschr">Berliner</tei:hi>
        <tei:unclear reason="reading">Dreckjüdin</tei:unclear> die 3.000 Mk abenehmen wird, aber er
        kann nicht so. Ich muß es erlegen, noch ehe <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774"
          >Mozio</tei:rs> mir mein Geld zurückzahlt! </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Eine wahre Kreuzigung! Ich bin darüber krank geworden . . Behalte das Geheimnis bei
        dir. Zumindest habe ich erreicht, daß ich weiter arbeiten kann. Denn die ewigen Reibungen
        mit den Verlagen rauben das Leben u. die Arbeit. In den letzten 10 Jahren <tei:pb n="10"/>
        habe ich die <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> aufgestellt, 10 Hefte <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001739"><tei:title>Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001749"><tei:title>3 Jahrb.</tei:title></tei:rs> u. die <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001753"><tei:title>Gesamtausgab. <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
            >Beeth</tei:hi></tei:title>.</tei:rs> herausgegeben u. den „<tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001728"><tei:title>Freien Satz</tei:title></tei:rs>“ vorbereitet – wessen
        Leistung kann sich mit dieser vergleichen?! – , u. zuletzt mußte ich außer der Arbeit auch
        noch meinen Spargroschen an die Welt schenken. Daher würde ich noch heute eine Stelle
        annehmen – ich weiß aber, daß es nicht geht. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
          >Vriesl</tei:hi></tei:rs>. käme vor allem in Frage. Aber<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker has placed a large bracket around the last three
          lines on p. 10 and around the first four on p. 11 (“Aber … an dich!!” – “But … of
          yourself!!”), for emphasis.</tei:note> mein ernster Rat geht dahin: <tei:hi
          rend="double-underline">Rette dich</tei:hi> u. die deinen, kümmere dich <tei:hi
          rend="underline">nicht um der Theorie</tei:hi>, überlasse <tei:pb n="11"/> die Klasse
        einem beliebigen Menschen, der die Jungen so oder so unterrichtet, nach <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000888"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Thuille</tei:hi></tei:rs>,
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000712"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
          >Riemann</tei:hi></tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002783"><tei:hi
            rend="lateinschr">Richter</tei:hi></tei:rs>, ganz egal,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12"
          type="editorial" place="foot">That is, a quite ordinary teacher could be brought in to
          teach from one of the standard sets of theory books in use in the early 20th
          century.</tei:note> –– denk <tei:hi rend="underline">an dich</tei:hi>!! </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Und sollst du Glück haben, was ich dir aus tausend Herzen wünschen, wirst du mir beim
          „<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title>Freien Satz</tei:title></tei:rs>“
        wieder einmal so glücklich helfen, wie du es öfter schon früher getan. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Was wäre ich heute ohne die „<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001749"
              ><tei:title>Jahrbücher<tei:supplied reason="omission">“</tei:supplied>
            I–III</tei:title></tei:rs>? was wäre <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"><tei:hi
            rend="lateinschr">Weisse</tei:hi></tei:rs>? Die Loslösung von <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000356">Hertzka</tei:rs> aber, die erst die Arbeit ermöglichte, verdanke ich
        dir u. dem Hamburger Herrn.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Schenker is thinking of the generosity of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000884">Max
            Temming</tei:rs> and of Violin’s untiring efforts to help with the sale and distribution
          of <tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title> in 1924, as a means of putting pressure
          on Hertzka at Universal Edition.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
          >Vriesl</tei:hi></tei:rs>.’s Adresse ist für alle Fälle: <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:pb n="12"/>
            <tei:hi rend="underline">Locarno-Solduno</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Villa Olga </tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Schweiz, Tessin</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
      </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Viel, viel Glück!!! Ende blaut der Himmel auch über uns Allen! </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Beste Wünsche, Grüße dir u. den l. deinigen </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>von mir u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
          >Lie-Liechen</tei:rs></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Dein</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
          >H</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1931-01-09">9. 1. 31</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:fw type="envelope">
          <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold">envelope</tei:hi></tei:note><tei:lb/>
          <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="recto"/>
          <tei:address>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied reason="clarity">An:</tei:supplied>
              <tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">M.
                Violin</tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50"><tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place"><tei:hi
                  rend="underline">Hamburg</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
            <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">Haynstr. 13</tei:addrLine>
          </tei:address><tei:lb/>
          <tei:fw type="postmark">|| 3 VIENNA 60 | -9.1.31.17 | * 4d * ||</tei:fw>
          <tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        </tei:fw>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold">letter</tei:hi></tei:note>
        <tei:salute><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>As I told your sister <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000909">Fanny</tei:rs>, who was
        at our place the day before yesterday, it must be thus: I cannot sit down to write you a
        letter until I have cleared everything else from my mind; collectedness and devotion are
        conditions that should lead me to you … .</tei:p>

      <tei:p>The economic troubles are unparalleled; my losses are <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">no</tei:add> smaller than yours. <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >Everyone</tei:hi> who writes to me from afar complains! <tei:rs key="entity-000107"
          >Brünauer</tei:rs> – in his twenty-eighth year <tei:supplied reason="clarity">with
          me</tei:supplied>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> – was the very first
        who <tei:add place="interlinear-above">merely from the usual flaunting of his
          niggardliness</tei:add> had withdrawn from one of his two weekly lessons even last summer!
        That gave me a sharp pain, whose consequences I still feel. New pupils can hardly be
        expected: the <tei:supplied reason="clarity">last</tei:supplied> four years’ worth of youth,
        who today would be between sixteen and twenty years old, simply do not exist!<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> And who would want to study music, without any
        prospects!</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> It is a devilish trait: the <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >innate</tei:add>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">musical</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">inadequacy</tei:hi> of the world is joined by an <tei:hi
          rend="underline">economic</tei:hi> one: man would like to lower himself to the level of
        beast, without realizing that this transformation will in the end <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >threaten him with starvation and death</tei:hi>, enticing though it may be as relief from
        intellectual or physical effort.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>With regard to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs>: that you were
        so kind as to go to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> and to write to me, are things that I shall
        treasure in my heart as signs of an ineradicable bonding of our souls and fates. He gave a
        talk at my place, a thoroughly excellent one. Already at home I have gained the impression
        that he has set aside all his hysteria about “progress” and is doing his best to remain
        faithful to his “Papa.”<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> He has even taken my
        advice <tei:hi rend="underline">not</tei:hi> to look for <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
            ><tei:hi rend="underline">absolute</tei:hi></tei:add>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">certainty</tei:hi>, as he had been doing for years, but rather to
        express his wisdom <tei:pb n="3"/> in just the way that he possesses it. That addiction to
        “certainty” (fear of subsequent disgrace) he referred to, very clumsily, as his “<tei:hi
          rend="underline">inhibition</tei:hi>”; and since he spoke about it in connection with me –
        in front of me and also in front of others – we all had the impression that <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">I was tyrannizing him</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">he was blaming me for tyrannizing him</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>. Today he defines the meaning of his “inhibition” almost cynically: “I used to
        have so many inhibitions; now I see that one can say anything and everything to people to
        their faces: as <tei:hi rend="underline">they</tei:hi> speak, so too do <tei:hi
          rend="underline">I</tei:hi>, without fear. Following the lines of my advice, it was
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">therefore</tei:add> also a question of <tei:hi
          rend="underline">concealing</tei:hi> from him (as I had hitherto done) the fact that,
        without exception <tei:hi rend="underline">each and every</tei:hi> presentation of evidence
        is <tei:hi rend="underline">false</tei:hi>. I praised him with the most genuine conviction
        since – and this is what it amounts to these days, for us all – the insight must be
        publicized, and proclaimed from every rooftop: that music has its <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >own coherence</tei:hi>, <tei:pb n="4"/> whatever it may be and whatever it may be called
        – except that it is <tei:hi rend="underline">not</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">what</tei:hi> is taught in schools! And <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000951">Hans</tei:rs> has fulfilled this responsibility in <tei:hi
          rend="underline">the most excellent possible way</tei:hi>: his formulations (which are, of
        course, also my own) were and are splendid; his language and its delivery are captivating,
        inspiring, inspired.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>It was only the <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-004715"><tei:title>Invention in
              E<tei:g type="flat"/> major</tei:title></tei:rs> that he set in front of me, asking
        for help with it; and it turns out that he himself committed the very mistake that he
        accused <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003123">Prof. Lorenz</tei:rs> of having made. He
        erroneously had <tei:supplied reason="clarity">identified the primary tone as</tei:supplied>
        a <tei:g type="cap3"/>, which I corrected to <tei:g type="cap5"/>. Unfortunately, he was
        pressed for time and did not understand my little sketch, <tei:lb/><tei:note
          type="editorial" place="inline">MUSIC EXAMPLE HERE</tei:note>
        <tei:lb/><tei:supplied reason="clarity">and</tei:supplied> the expansion by the
          <tei:term>neighbor note</tei:term> c<tei:hi rend="supralinear">3</tei:hi>, which holds
        back the course of events until finally the progression <tei:g type="cap4"/>–<tei:g
          type="cap1"/> arrives. He accepted the <tei:g type="cap5"/> but did not understand the
        bass, and created a real mishmash.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="5"/> Until now I had withheld my interpretation from <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs>. Was I not right to have done so? And now, too? No one
        observed the mistake; but the audience would have had something to listen out for, which
        they have as a result not heard. Oh, if only the time would return when I could, for
        example, at a table in a coffee-house, or at your place or mine, show you the relevant
        improvements in writing, as in the past!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>My suspicions turned out to be correct. I am in no doubt that <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs> appealed to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268"
          >Furtwängler</tei:rs>; now he will <tei:hi rend="underline">surely go to <tei:rs
            type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs></tei:hi> next year (in Vienna he has,
        unfortunately, no further prospects!). <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268"
          >Furtwängler</tei:rs> wrote to him from <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003075">St.
          Moritz</tei:rs>, to say that he had a meeting with <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000431">Kestenberg</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000809"
          >Schünemann</tei:rs>, and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000802">Schreker</tei:rs> at
        the beginning of January, where the offer of an appointment for <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs> would be on the agenda. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs> is looking to him to find a permanent job (on account
        of his children, and also on account of <tei:pb n="6"/> his advancing years); if he does not
        obtain an official position, he will go to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002510"
          >America</tei:rs> and there, with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000934"
          >Warburg</tei:rs>’s help, … .<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> I believe,
        however, that he <tei:hi rend="underline">will carve</tei:hi> a path for himself in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>; with or without a position, he will
        establish a <tei:hi rend="underline">seminar</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08"
          type="footnote"/> (The cost of <tei:supplied reason="clarity">enrolling in</tei:supplied>
        a seminar is low, enabling a great number to take part.) He is thinking about a Schenker
        Institute, which would give employment to all who are currently homeless (as is, for
        example, also <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000754">Dr. Salzer</tei:rs>).</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Now would be the time for me to let <tei:add place="interlinear-above">you</tei:add> in
        on another secret, but my eyesight is beginning to fail: I shall certainly not forget to
        return to it in my next letter … .</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Let me add merely that the editor of <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-003014"
            ><tei:title level="j">Der Kunstwart</tei:title></tei:rs>
        <tei:pb n="7"/> in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002286">Munich</tei:rs> (<tei:supplied
          reason="clarity">the journal</tei:supplied> founded by <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003347">Avenarius</tei:rs>) enjoyed my “Miscellanea” so much that he filled
        nine pages with extracts from it. In <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002757">Kiel</tei:rs>,
        the Conservatory newsletter reprinted <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001740"
              ><tei:title><tei:hi rend="italic">Tonwille</tei:hi>
            <tei:hi rend="underline">1</tei:hi> (19<tei:hi rend="underline"
          >2</tei:hi>0</tei:title></tei:rs>).<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09" type="footnote"
        /></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Just now, at 9:30 in the morning, your letter arrived with the sensational news: what a
        surprise! <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143">Professor von Cube</tei:rs> (<tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002621">Duisburg</tei:rs>) should be considered <tei:hi
          rend="underline">ahead of</tei:hi>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Oppel</tei:rs>; <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> would be <tei:hi rend="underline">quite
          excellent</tei:hi> for <tei:term><tei:hi rend="underline">counterpoint</tei:hi></tei:term>
        and <tei:term><tei:hi rend="underline">thoroughbass</tei:hi></tei:term>. <tei:note
          type="editorial" place="inline">cued from lower margin:</tei:note>It goes without saying
        that the “<tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>” would be well covered by him; thus he is in fact the
          <tei:hi rend="underline">only one</tei:hi> under consideration who will have an <tei:hi
          rend="underline">impact</tei:hi>!!<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end
          cue</tei:note> But you cannot found a school on the basis of giving due notice to these
        disciplines, to say nothing of devoting time and money to them. Perhaps <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs> will pitch in; that would be – <tei:hi
          rend="underline">hitting the bull’s eye</tei:hi>! I fear that he will want to leave
          <tei:supplied reason="clarity">Austria and Germany</tei:supplied>, specifically to earn
        money to provide for himself and his children. If <tei:hi rend="underline">you were
          here</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="underline">I myself</tei:hi>
        <tei:pb n="8"/> would take the theory position, for the sake of our own secure footing. For
        – in the same post – a letter arrived from my solicitor, who is <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >taking action</tei:hi> against <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs>
        on account of <tei:hi rend="underline">14,000 shillings</tei:hi>, which I handed over to him
          <tei:hi rend="underline">in cash</tei:hi>. I had been counting on <tei:hi
          rend="double-underline">this</tei:hi> money when, amid <tei:hi rend="double-underline"
          >difficulties</tei:hi><tei:hi rend="underline"> with my </tei:hi><tei:hi
          rend="double-underline">eyes</tei:hi> and <tei:hi rend="underline">under severe time
          pressure</tei:hi>, I paid <tei:hi rend="double-underline">7,000 shillings</tei:hi> out of
          <tei:hi rend="underline">my own</tei:hi> pocket for the printing of the <tei:rs
          type="work" key="entity-001752">third <tei:title>Yearbook</tei:title></tei:rs>! This was a
        betrayal of my <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs> who, however,
        did not bat an eyelid over it; an <tei:hi rend="underline">act of suicide</tei:hi>!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Should I have killed myself on account of my eyes (just take a look at the music
        illustrations for the “Eroica” <tei:supplied reason="clarity">article</tei:supplied>!)?!
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356">Hertzka</tei:rs> deceived me for a <tei:hi
          rend="underline">whole year</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn10" type="footnote"/>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs> learned of this <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">directly from me</tei:add>, did all that he could, managed to
        get <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002890">Breitkopf &amp; Härtel</tei:rs> at my
        disposal; but, owing to <tei:hi rend="underline">despair about my eyes</tei:hi> I was
        already <tei:pb n="9"/> committed to <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002627">Drei
          Masken Verlag</tei:rs> and feared – correctly, I am sure – that <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002890">Breitkopf &amp; Härtel</tei:rs> would have held up
        the publication for years, on account of the current situation, and would cause me a great
        financial loss, in so far as I would not have been able to work on <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001728"><tei:title level="m">Free Composition</tei:title></tei:rs>. I expected
        that <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs> would have relieved some
          <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">filthy rich</tei:unclear> Berlin <tei:unclear
          reason="original_unclear">Jewess</tei:unclear> of 3,000 marks, but he cannot do so. I must
        take care of it, until <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000774">Mozio</tei:rs> gives me
        back my money! </tei:p>

      <tei:p>A veritable crucifixion, which has made me ill … . Keep the secret to yourself. I have
        at least managed to be able to continue work. For the eternal frictions with the publishing
        houses rob me of my life and work. In the last ten years <tei:pb n="10"/> I have established
        the concept of “<tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>,” published ten issues of <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001739"><tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>, <tei:rs
          type="work" key="entity-001749"><tei:title>three Yearbooks</tei:title></tei:rs>, and the
          <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001753"><tei:title>Beethoven <tei:supplied
              reason="clarity">piano sonata</tei:supplied> collected edition</tei:title></tei:rs>,
        and prepared <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title level="m">Free
            Composition</tei:title></tei:rs>. Who can compare his accomplishments with these? And
        finally, in addition to my work, I also had to give the world my life savings. For this
        reason, I would even today accept a position; I know, however, that this is not
        possible.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> should be considered
        first of all. But<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn11" type="footnote"/> my most serious piece of
        advice is this: <tei:hi rend="double-underline">save yourself</tei:hi> and your family, do
          <tei:hi rend="underline">not</tei:hi> concern yourself <tei:hi rend="underline">with
          theory</tei:hi>; leave <tei:pb n="11"/> the class to some person who would teach the
        children in any old way – according to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000888"
          >Thuille</tei:rs>, or <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000712">Riemann</tei:rs>, or
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002783">Richter</tei:rs>: it makes no difference which
        one of these<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn12" type="footnote"/> – think only <tei:hi
          rend="underline">of yourself</tei:hi>!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>And if you are fortunate, which is something I wish from the bottom of my heart, then
        you may be so kind as to help me once more, with <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"
            ><tei:title level="m">Free Composition</tei:title></tei:rs>, as you have so often done
        in the past. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>What would I be today without the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001749"
            ><tei:title>Yearbooks I–III</tei:title></tei:rs>? What would <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs> be? But to be freed from <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000356">Hertzka</tei:rs>, which in fact made it possible for me to work, is
        something for which I have you and the Hamburg gentleman to thank.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn13" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>’s address, in any event,
        is: <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:pb n="12"/>
            <tei:hi rend="underline">Locarno-Solduno</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Villa Olga,</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Ticino, Switzerland.</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
      </tei:p>

      <tei:p>The best, the very best of luck!!! In the end, the skies will also brighten over all of
        us.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Best wishes and greetings to you and your lovely family </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs> and
          myself</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
          >H</tei:rs>.</tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1931-01-09">January 9, 1931</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
