<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="2820" sdoID="OJ-6-3_13">OJ 6/3, [13]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="major">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS-pencil" scope="minor">Heinrich Schenker's hand in pencil</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2022</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2022</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2022</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-09-23" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002719">ViolinM ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



   <dc:title>Handwritten letter with envelope from Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated February 8,
    1900</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1900-02-08T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2022-09-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>When Violin returns from Berlin, Schenker will send him his Zweistimmige
    Inventionen, Op. 5: he inquires whether Busoni has said anything about them. -- He raises the
    substitute lessons he is giving to the Wiener and Leiner families: Violin has failed to instruct
    him on the fee to be charged. Can he ask 10 Florins? -- He disagrees with Mahler's performance
    of the "Eroica."</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>

   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:fw type="envelope"><tei:lb/>
     <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold">envelope:</tei:hi></tei:note><tei:lb/>
     <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="recto"/><tei:lb/>
     <tei:address>
      <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Herrn Moriz Violin</tei:addrLine>
      <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10">Tonkünstler</tei:addrLine>
      <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10"><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501"
       >Berlin</tei:rs>:</tei:addrLine>
      <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10">S. W. Bernburgerstr. 33.</tei:addrLine>
     </tei:address>
     <tei:fw type="postmark">|| <tei:gap reason="illegible"/> | 3/3 <tei:supplied reason="blurred"
       >WIEN 49</tei:supplied> | <tei:gap reason="illegible"/> N ||</tei:fw><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
     <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="verso"/><tei:lb/>
     <tei:address>
      <tei:addrLine>Abs: D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> H Schenker</tei:addrLine>
      <tei:addrLine>III/3 Reisnerstr. 38</tei:addrLine>
     </tei:address>
     <tei:fw type="postmark">|| Bestellt | vom | Postamte 40 | 14/II. 00 | A | 10½–11¾ V.
      ||</tei:fw><tei:lb/>
     <tei:add><tei:handShift new="#HS-pencil"/>Klavierspieler / <tei:gap reason="illegible"
      /></tei:add><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
     <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold">letter:</tei:hi></tei:note>
    </tei:fw>
    <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#HS-pencil"/><tei:date when="1900-02-08">8/II
     00</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Liebster <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913"
      >Floriz</tei:rs>!<tei:lb/>Theuerster.</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Jehovah sendet dir Glück! Da hast du Recht. Er wird dir noch mehr senden. Du bist <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overwritten">J</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="superimposed">i</tei:add>
    </tei:subst>hm seitjeher mehr Liebling gewesen, als ich, der ich Ihn doch so sehr verstehe u.
    liebe, u. zu Ehren bringe. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Geniesse das Glück, vor Allem im Bewusstsein, es doch zu verdienen! Letzteres ist einem
    Künstler sehr nöthig. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Bis<tei:del rend="overstrike">t</tei:del> du am eigenen Herd, sende ich die
     <tei:title>Inventionen</tei:title>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
     >Schenker, <tei:title level="m">Zweistimmige Inventionen</tei:title>, Op. 5 for piano (Leipzig:
     Breitkopf &amp; Härtel, 1898, 1901), four pieces.</tei:note> von mir selbst schön geschrieben.
    Hat <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000116">Busoni</tei:rs> etwa minder gut vor Dir darüber
     <tei:pb n="2"/> sich <tei:del rend="overstrike">darüber</tei:del> geäussert (mir schrieb er
    noch gar nichts), so lass dich ebensowenig, dadurch irre machen, als ich selbst, der von der
    Vortrefflichkeit dieser Kleinigkeiten nach wie vor überzeugt bin. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Nun zu einer tristen Sache. <tei:unclear reason="reading">Pintsch</tei:unclear>,
     <tei:unclear reason="reading">Alt</tei:unclear>, als du weggingst, vergassest du mir von den
     „Wiener“s<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">“Pintsch, Alt” or
     “Pietsch, Alt”: a slang expression of some sort? “Wieners”: cf. <tei:ref type="correspondence"
      cRef="OJ-6-3_19">OJ 6/3, [19]</tei:ref>, November 2, 1900, in which the Wieners and fee levels
     are discussed, and two places below.</tei:note> zu sagen! Bald darauf erhielt ich 2 Schreiben
    von deinen guten Schwestern,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">i.e.
      <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-008350">Nina</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person"
      key="entity-000909">Fanny</tei:rs>.</tei:note> betriffs dieser Stunde, enthaltend wohl den
    Vermerk, dass sie à 3fl (!!) zu geben wäre. Am Nachmittag desselben Tages – hier eben steckt die
    Unfreundlichkeit Jehovas zu mir, über die ich klage – treffe ich D<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
     >r.</tei:hi> Hirschl<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">No Dr. Hirschl
     is so far known in the Schenker papers. Lehmann’s street directory of Vienna for 1900 gives:
     “Hirschl, Josef Adolf, MD, Assistant at University Psychiatric Clinic 2, Vienna IX, Alserstraße
     4 (2–3).”</tei:note> im Caféhaus, u. <tei:pb n="3"/> theile ihm mit, eine Frage beantwortend,
    dass ich dich hier u. dort substituire, „Auch leider bei Wieners“ – jammere ich u. will die
    Misere andeuten des Honorars (ich habe dazumal noch gar keine Stellung gehabt u. war noch
    unentschlossen, da ich wenig Stunden zuvor die Briefe erst erhalten habe); hierauf D<tei:hi
     rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> H. einfallend: „das ist ja meine Cousine“. — Tableau! Ich
    verschwieg, was ich noch zu sagen hatte, u. dachte bei mir; hier musst du hereinspringen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich wusste nicht mehr, was beginnen. Folgende Ausweg, der einzige – bot sich hernach dar:
    ich ging hin, <tei:pb n="4"/> u. erklärte, dass ich dich substituire (das würde mit Freuden
    angenommen), betriffs des Honorars aber, <tei:add place="interlinear-above">es</tei:add> möchte
    das Geld einfach bis zur Entscheidung, ob du in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501"
     >Berlin</tei:rs> bleibst, gehäuft werden. Ich habe je als Substitut nicht das Recht, höhere
    Honorare zu fordern, wenn ich dich nicht compromittiren will. Hast du bestimmt, dass du in
     <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs> bleibst, u. würde ich in eigener Regie
    diese Stunde mith zu entschliessen annehmen, – das war der versteckte Inhalt jener Erklärung, –
    würde ich dann, ohne dich zu <tei:pb n="5"/> verletzen, ein grösseres Honorar verlangen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Das Mädchen passt mir nicht, es ist zu hysterisch (auch gegen 5fl), der Weg auch zu weit. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>1) <tei:hi rend="underline">Sind die Wieners‘ vermögend</tei:hi>? Wenn nicht, werde ich
    die Stunde noch vor deiner Entscheidung fallen lassen. 3fl sind doch zu wenig, als definitives
    Honorar. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>– Übrigens ward Frau <tei:hi rend="underline">Leiner</tei:hi> bereit, ein grösseres
    Honorar mir zu zahlen. Sie trug es selbst an. Ich aber, von dir hierüber nicht unterrichtet, war
    im Augenblick verwirrt, <tei:pb n="6"/> fand aber sofort die Geistesgegenwart, den einzig
    möglichen Standpunkt auch hier zur Geltung zubringen, nämlich den, dich vorläufig nicht zu
    compromittiren. Ich sagte: ich weiss von Honorar nichts, ich habe nur zu vertreten, im Übrigen
    sei es vorläufig, wie es war. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich habe den Eindruck, als wollte sie mir 10fl für die Stunde, zahlen, dann aber nur eine
    Stunde wöchentlich (was mir ohnehin lieber wäre)<tei:supplied reason="punctuation"
     >.</tei:supplied> Dass ich 10fl mehr als <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000210"
     >Epstein</tei:rs> oder consortes verdienen </tei:p>

   <!-- -->
   <!-- FEUILLETON -->
   <!-- -->

   <tei:p>______________________________<tei:lb/>Feuilleton.<tei:lb/>Grüsse bestens
     Brodes’.<tei:lb/><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000582">Frau Mayerh.</tei:rs> grüsst dich
     sehr!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker draws a line then
     places this at the bottom of p. 6 in emulation of a feuilleton at the foot of page 1 of a
     newspaper.</tei:note><tei:lb/>______________________________</tei:p>

   <!-- -->
   <!-- FEUILLETON-END -->
   <!-- -->

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="7"/> brauche ich dir nicht zu sagen.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Sie selbst trug das höhere Honorar an, so kann sie doch nur 10fl. gemeint haben? Nicht
    wahr? </tei:p>

   <tei:p>2) Bis du die Entscheidung getroffen, kann ich dann im eigenen Namen 10fl verlangen? </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Öfter, ja leider täglich, seh‘ ich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000556"
     >Mahler</tei:rs> im Caféhaus, dem ich neulich den Kopf gewaschen habe wegen der <tei:rs
     type="composition" key="entity-001263"><tei:title>Eroica</tei:title></tei:rs>-Aufführung.
    Darüber <tei:hi rend="underline">nächstens</tei:hi>. In den nächsten Tagen besuche ich deine
    Leute! </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-80">Dein</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-90"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs>
    </tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:fw type="envelope"><tei:lb/>
     <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold">envelope:</tei:hi></tei:note><tei:lb/>
     <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="recto"/><tei:lb/>
     <tei:address>
      <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Mr. Moriz Violin</tei:addrLine>
      <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10">Musician</tei:addrLine>
      <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10"><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>
       S.W.</tei:addrLine>
      <tei:addrLine rend="indent-10">Bernburgerstrasse 33</tei:addrLine>
     </tei:address>
     <tei:fw type="postmark">|| <tei:gap reason="illegible"/> | 3/3 <tei:supplied reason="blurred"
       >VIENNA 49</tei:supplied> | <tei:gap reason="illegible"/> p.m. ||</tei:fw><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
     <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="verso"/><tei:lb/>
     <tei:address>
      <tei:addrLine>From: Dr. H. Schenker</tei:addrLine>
      <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied reason="identity">Vienna</tei:supplied> III/3, Reisnerstrasse
       38</tei:addrLine>
     </tei:address>
     <tei:fw type="postmark">|| Delivered | from | Post Office 40 | 14/II. 00 | A | 10.30–11.45 a.m.
      ||</tei:fw><tei:lb/>
     <tei:add><tei:handShift new="#HS-pencil"/>Pianist / <tei:gap reason="illegible"/></tei:add><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
     <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="bold">letter:</tei:hi></tei:note>
    </tei:fw>
    <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#HS-pencil"/><tei:date when="1900-02-08">February 8,
      1900</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Dearest <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913"
      >Floriz</tei:rs>,<tei:lb/>most precious one,</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Jehovah sends you good luck! You are right. He will send you more. From the very outset,
    you have become more of a favorite to him than I myself – I who understand and admire him so
    much and hold him in high regard.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Enjoy the good luck, above all consciously, so as to earn it! The latter is very necessary
    to an artist.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>When you are next at your own place, I will send the <tei:title level="m"
     >Inventions</tei:title>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> beautfully written in
    my own hand. If <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000116">Busoni</tei:rs> has by any chance
     <tei:pb n="2"/> said anything less favorable to you about them (he has not written a word to
    me), then don’t let yourself be disturbed by that, any more than I myself, who am, now as
    before, convinced of the excellence of these little trifles.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Now on to something sad. <tei:unclear reason="reading">Pintsch</tei:unclear>, <tei:unclear
     reason="reading">Alt</tei:unclear>, as you left, you forgot to tell me about the
     Wieners!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> Soon afterwards, I received two
    letters from your good sisters<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> regarding this
    lesson, containing moreover the comment that she <tei:supplied reason="clarity">Mrs.
     Wiener</tei:supplied> would be giving at the rate of 3 florins(!!). In the afternoon of the
    same day – this is just where Jehova’s antipathy toward me, about which I complain, comes in – I
    run into Dr. Hirschl<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> in the coffee-house and
     <tei:pb n="3"/> tell him, in answer to a question, that I act as a substitute for you here and
    there, “Unfortunately also at the Wieners’ place[?]” – I moan, and go to tell him the state of
    affairs over the fee (I really had had no standing whatsoever at that time, and was still
    undecided, since I had only just received the letters a few hours earlier); at this, Dr. H.
    chimed in “That’s my cousin!” – I froze! I stifled what I had been going to say and thought to
    myself: this is where you <tei:supplied reason="clarity">Moriz Violin</tei:supplied> must come
    in.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>I had no idea how to begin. The following way out, the only one – presented itself after
    that; I went up <tei:supplied reason="clarity">to him</tei:supplied>
    <tei:pb n="4"/> and explained that I substitute (for) you (that was accepted with pleasure), but
    as regards the fee, the money might simply be left to accumulate until you decide whether to
    remain in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>. I have no right as a
    substitute to demand higher fees if I don’t wish to compromise you. Were you to decide
    definitely to remain in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>, and were I to
    agree to take this lesson over into my own practice – that was the ulterior motive of that
    explanation – I would then, without <tei:pb n="5"/> injuring you, ask for a higher fee.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>The girl doesn’t suit me at all; she is too hysterical (also around 5 florins), the
    distance is also too great.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>1) <tei:hi rend="underline">Are the Wieners wealthy</tei:hi>? If not, then I will give up
    the lesson<tei:supplied reason="plural">s</tei:supplied> even before you have decided. 3 Florins
    is definitely too low as an agreed fee.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>– Anyway, Mrs. <tei:hi rend="underline">Leiner</tei:hi> was prepared to pay me a higher
    fee. She made me an offer herself. However, not having been instructed by you, I was confused on
    the spot, <tei:pb n="7"/> but summoned up the presence of mind to advance the only possible
    argument, namely, that I couldn’t risk putting you in a difficult position. I said: I know
    nothing of fees; my job is just to act as a substitute; apart from that, let it stay as it
    is.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>I have the impression that she wanted to pay me 10 Florins per lesson, but only one lesson
    a week (which would anyhow be preferable). That I earn 10 Florins more than <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000210">Epstein</tei:rs> and his colleagues.</tei:p>

   <!-- -->
   <!-- FEUILLETON -->
   <!-- -->

   <tei:p>______________________________<tei:lb/>Feuilleton.<tei:lb/>My best greetings to
     Brodes.<tei:lb/><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000582">Mrs. Mayerhofer</tei:rs> sends you
    her warm greetings!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"
    /><tei:lb/>______________________________</tei:p>

   <!-- -->
   <!-- FEUILLETON-END -->
   <!-- -->

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="7"/> I don’t need to tell you.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>She herself offered the higher fee, so she can surely only have meant 10 Florins, don’t
    you think?</tei:p>

   <tei:p>2) Until you have made up your mind, can I ask for 10 Florins in my own name?</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Often – sadly, daily in fact – I see <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000556"
     >Mahler</tei:rs> in the coffee-house. Recently I gave him a piece of my mind over his “<tei:rs
     type="composition" key="entity-001263"><tei:title>Eroica</tei:title></tei:rs>” performance.
    I’ll tell you about that <tei:hi rend="underline">the next time we meet</tei:hi>. I will visit
    your folk in the next few days.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-80">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-90"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs>
    </tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>


  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
