<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="548" sdoID="OJ-6-7_5">OJ 6/7, [5]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2011</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-08-23" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002720">ViolinM ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002721">ViolinM+V ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002722">ViolinM+V+F ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Heinrich Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated July 9,
    1923</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1923-07-09T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2011-08-23</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Having settled into country life in the Tyrol, Schenker returns to his work, in
    particular to the ongoing battles with Hertzka over the publication of Der Tonwille. He asks
    Violin’s opinion about a subscription plan for a periodical that would appear four times a year
    (instead of the current two), and hopes that his friend might spare a few days to visit him in
    Galtür. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject> </dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-60">Galtür, <tei:date when="1923-07-09">9. VII.
     1923</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Fl</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ
      3/4, p. 2531, July 9, 1923: "An Fl. (Br.): über eine geheime Hertzka-Krise; entwickle meinen
      Abonnementplan als Versuch eines Gegendrucks; – ersuche um Rat." ("To Floriz (letter): about a
      secret Hertzka crisis; I develop my plan for subscriptions as an attempt to apply
      counter-pressure; – I ask for advice."). </tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p><tei:rs key="entity-002334" type="place"><tei:region><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Tirol</tei:hi></tei:region></tei:rs> ist uns wieder einmal zur Wahrheit geworden, die wie
    jede Wahrheit traumartig ist. Da wir hier zum 3. Male sind, beginnen wir erst sehend zu werden
    u. begreifen so, daß das einmalige Sehen überhaupt keins ist. Im Vorjahre noch sind wir verlegen
    gewesen, wo die große Enzian, die herrlichen Alpenrosen zu holen wären, vor lauter sozusagen
    nervöser Suche sind wir <tei:add place="interlinear-above">überall</tei:add> zu spät gekommen,
    aber heute ist <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs>s Griff sicher:
    dort stehen die Alpenrosen, hier der Enzian u.s.w. (Es wiederholt sich, was vor der Kunst gilt,
    in noch viel größerem Ausmaß von der Natur: die Sicherheit will nur allmälich gewonnen werden.
    Darum die Lüge des <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Expressionismus</tei:hi>, der Alles auf den
    Augenblick des (ohnehin so augenblicklichen) Menschen stellt.<tei:supplied reason="syntax">)</tei:supplied> Vor paar Tagen kamen wir auf unser Lieblingsjoch (<tei:rs key="entity-002350" type="place">Zeinisjoch</tei:rs> Übergang ins <tei:rs key="entity-002305" type="place">Montavontal</tei:rs>) – 1¼ – 1½ Stunden Wegs blos – in den Vorfrühling hinein; weiter, weiter
    Schnee, u. dort, wo ihn die Sonne geschmolzen, die <tei:hi rend="underline">allerersten</tei:hi>
    Blümchen: Krokus, Primeln u.s.w.! </tei:p>

   <tei:p>In den ersten Tagen konnten wir nur eine Aufgabe, zu schlafen, <tei:pb n="2"/>
    <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs>s ruchlose Plagen auszuschlafen. Vergessen
    ist nun Alles u. wir arbeiten bereits wieder. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Wie hältst du es mit dem Sommer? Ich sah <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>er ja immer in <tei:rs key="entity-002334" type="place"><tei:region>Tirol</tei:region></tei:rs> – vielleicht entsinnst auch <tei:add place="interlinear-above">du</tei:add> dich aus <tei:rs key="entity-002396" type="place">Steinach</tei:rs> solchen Menschen –, oder gibt es dort, weil nördlich, weniger Sucht nach
    Frische? Daraus, daß <tei:rs key="entity-000909" type="person">Fanny</tei:rs> zu Euch reist,
    wäre ja zu schließen, daß Ihr Alle zu Hause bleibt? Wegen des <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Junge</tei:rs>n? Oder mußt du auch am Sommer sparen? Wie machst du denn die
    Sprünge der Währung mit? Ist's mit der Hochschule nichts? Unterrichtest du blos privat, oder
    doch auch noch in der Schule? </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich nehme an, daß du das <tei:rs key="entity-001743" type="work">4. Heft
      <tei:title>TW.</tei:title></tei:rs> erhalten u. den Aufsatz in der „<tei:rs key="entity-002556" type="journal">Musik</tei:rs>“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">In the same month that <tei:title level="j">Tonwille</tei:title>
     4 was released, Schenker’s analysis of the Prelude in C minor from Book 1 of the <tei:title level="m">Well-Tempered Clavier</tei:title> was published in <tei:title level="j">Die
      Musik</tei:title> 15/9 (June 1923), 641–51; this is his only analysis for a journal other than
     those he edited himself. (A revised version of the analysis was published in <tei:title level="j">Meisterwerk</tei:title> 2, together with that of its companion fugue which forms the
     basis of the essay <tei:title level="a">Das Organische der Fuge</tei:title>). </tei:note>
    gelesen hast. Wieder auch beim <tei:rs key="entity-001743" type="work">4. Heft</tei:rs> gab es
    ein Ringen um den Erscheinungstermin: <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs>
    gelang es unter durchsichtigst-blöden Vorwänden Ende Juni zu erreichen, das macht also per Jahr
    2 Hefte = 4 Bogen = Vernichtung des „<tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title>TW.</tei:title></tei:rs>“. Wie sollte ich so viel Sonaten, Sinf,
    Kammermusikstücke, <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person">Bach</tei:rs>'sches Werk
    durcharbeiten, geschweige, daß ich, dem Wunsch von so viel Seiten entsprechend, einen <tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person">Reger</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000924" type="person">Wagner</tei:rs><tei:supplied reason="syntax">,</tei:supplied> eine <tei:rs key="entity-000798" type="person">Schönberg</tei:rs>. H<tei:supplied reason="abbreviation">ar</tei:supplied>m<tei:supplied reason="abbreviation">onielehre</tei:supplied>
    <tei:add place="interlinear-above">zu</tei:add> entlarven die Möglichkeit hätte? Keine
    Möglichkeit zu erfüllen, was der Esel <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">H.</tei:rs>,
    wenn ers fertig vor sich sähe <tei:add place="interlinear-above">auch selbst</tei:add>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">gewiß mit Freuden annehme</tei:hi> z.B. die <tei:rs key="entity-002882" type="work">32. Son. von <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">B</tei:hi>. mit ihren
      <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>n</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Brahms</tei:hi></tei:rs> Sinf. mit <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>n, die Kl.
    Prel. von <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">S.
     Bach</tei:hi></tei:rs> und <tei:term>Url</tei:term>. – dazu gehörten, im Jahr blos 2 Hefte
     <tei:pb n="3"/> gerechnet, über 200 Jahre, lebe ich denn das? Viel vernünftiger wäre ja dann,
    nicht Heft-, sondern Bücherweise diese Literatur zu erledigen. So hat mir <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">H.</tei:rs> beim <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title>TW.</tei:title></tei:rs> mitgespielt u. ganz anders redete er, schrieb er all die
    8 Jahre, in denen er um<tei:del rend="overstrike">so</tei:del> dieses Werk warb! Er ist nun
    einmal mein Gegner, der davor Angst hat, ich könnte seine Dada's demolieren. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Wie habe ich kürzlich <tei:rs key="entity-000471" type="person">Korngold</tei:rs>
    beneidet, als er in einem <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Feuilleton</tei:hi> über die „neue
     Musik“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Julius Korngold, <tei:title level="a">Neue Musik: Die Frankfurter Kammermusikwoche,</tei:title>
     <tei:title level="j">Neue Freie Presse: Morgenblatt</tei:title>, July 4, 1923, pp. 1–3; July 6,
     pp. 1–4; and continued July 14, pp. 1–4 (not preserved in Schenker's scrapbook). </tei:note>
    all das Gesindel einschließlich <tei:rs key="entity-000798" type="person">Schönberg</tei:rs>'s
    ganz fast versohlte! Ich genieße die „Freiheit“, die ein gerissener jüdischer „Demokrat“, im
    Hauptberuf ein gewöhnlicher Geldstrolch – seine Abrechnungen sind ein wahrer Kasseneinbruch –
    zumißt, – ich kann gar nicht mehr weiter. Gestern schrieb ich ihm von hier einen Brief,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">= OC 52/577-579, copy dated July 9, 1923,
     letter to Hertzka (Universal Edition), the writing of which is recorded in Schenker's diary at
     OJ 3/4, pp.2530–2531, July 8, 1923. </tei:note> worin ich <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ihn</tei:add> höflich auffordete, “„Farbe zu bekennen“ als Gegner oder zumindest Objektivität
    eines Verlegers zu wahren, ein Inserat in die „<tei:rs key="entity-002556" type="journal"><tei:title>Musik</tei:title></tei:rs>“ einzurücken (die Leute wissen ja nicht, wo „<tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title>TW.</tei:title></tei:rs>“ zu holen ist u.
     haben<tei:supplied reason="syntax">’</tei:supplied>s wirklich umsoschwieriger, als „<tei:rs key="entity-002456" type="organization">TW</tei:rs>“ kein Verlag, nur eine fingierte
    Angelegenheit ist), schließlich sagte <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ich</tei:add> es ihm
    geradeheraus, daß er mich hinter <tei:rs key="entity-000798" type="person">Schönberg</tei:rs>s
    „Machwerk, das ins XI Jahrh. oder nach Kagran gehört“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Probably a derogatory view of Schoenberg’s <tei:title level="m">Harmonielehre</tei:title> that had been expressed informally by Hertzka to Schenker on some
     previous occasion. “To belong to the eleventh century” means to be of little value to the
     modern world, of no practical worth. Kagran is part of the Donaustadt, the 22nd district of
     Vienna; “nach Kagran gehören” was probably a Viennese colloquial term of abuse. </tei:note>
    deutlich zurücksetzt, was umso auffälliger u. ungerechtfertigter ist, als ich ihm auch einen
    kompletten <tei:rs key="entity-001725" type="work">Kp.</tei:rs> gegeben habe, den <tei:hi rend="underline">einzigen</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">des</tei:hi>
    <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization"><tei:hi rend="underline">Verlags</tei:hi></tei:rs>! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Dieser ewige Kampf frißt mir viel Nerven auf. Augenblicklich übe <tei:pb n="4"/> ich passive Resistenz, indem ich <tei:rs key="entity-001218" type="composition">op.
     90</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs key="entity-001205" type="composition">106</tei:rs>, die korrigiert
    sind, nicht imprimire u. so die <tei:rs key="entity-001753" type="work">G.Ausgabe</tei:rs> in
    Frage stelle. Aber ist das eine Lösung? </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich dachte u. denke daran, durch Heranziehung meiner Schüler, die um einen großen
    Abonnentenkreis sich bemühen sollten – 3–4 Hefte im Jahr kosten doch <tei:del rend="overstrike">nicht</tei:del> nur erst 48–56.000 Kr. <tei:add place="interlinear-above">im Jahr</tei:add>,
    was doch ein <tei:choice>
     <tei:sic>Pappenspiel</tei:sic>
     <tei:corr>Pappenstiel</tei:corr>
    </tei:choice> ist –, sollte man wirklich nicht hier u. in <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Deutschland</tei:country></tei:rs> ein paar hundert Menschen
    zusammenbekommen, die den Betrag von 2 Fleischspeisen <tei:hi rend="underline">jährlich</tei:hi>
    opferten für den <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title>T.W.</tei:title></tei:rs>?
    Das wäre nun ein <tei:hi rend="underline">fixierter Reingewinn</tei:hi> für den Verleger, um
    dessen Willen der kleinste wie größte Verleger das <tei:hi rend="underline">risikolose
     Geschäft</tei:hi> gern <tei:add place="interlinear-above">müsste</tei:add> übernehmen wollen.
    Zumindest könnte ich auf <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">H.</tei:rs> bestimmtesten
    Druck üben: „die Abonnementen verlangen 4 Hefte jährlich“ würde ich sagen, u. er müsste sich
    fügen um des sicheren Gewinnes willen. Was sagst du zu diesem Plan? Wenn du nur irgend Zeit hast
    oder nicht durch häusliche Schwierigkeiten behindert bist, sage umgehend, was du dazu meinst.
    Muß ausgerechnet <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ich</tei:add> in <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">H</tei:rs>'s Hand geraten, der sich, seiner Frau <tei:rs key="entity-000357" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Jella</tei:hi></tei:rs> gleich, in den Kopf gesetzt
    hat, eine fortschreitende Eselswelt Jüngels anzuführen?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">The exact meaning of this sentence is unclear. It may be that
     Schenker is relating Hertzka’s pseudo-benevolent work as a publisher to the numerous
     philanthropic activities of his wife. </tei:note>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Auf deine <tei:term>Kp</tei:term>-Frage vom 28.IV. komme ich im nächsten Schreiben
     zurück.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">Schnker is referring
     Violin’s question about cadence formulas in second-species counterpoint, posed in OJ 14/45,
     [21]. He did not, in fact, return to the topic in either of the remaining two letters of 1923,
     OJ 6/7, [6] and [7]. </tei:note> Kommst du nicht, <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>er, nach <tei:rs key="entity-002334" type="place"><tei:region>Tirol</tei:region></tei:rs>? Auf ein paar Tage? Was treibt deine <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">Frau</tei:rs>? Wie gehts dem <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Junge</tei:rs>n? Von der <tei:rs key="entity-002938" type="person">kleinen</tei:rs> hoffen wir, daß <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in left margin,
     written sideways:</tei:note> sie noch immer so tapfer wie „ehemals“ durch das Schlaraffenland
    ihrer Kindheit <tei:add place="interlinear-above">sich</tei:add> durchißt, was? </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Seid Alle herzlichst von uns gegrüßt </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Dein </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">HS</tei:rs>
    </tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-60">Galtür, <tei:date when="1923-07-09">July 9,
     1923</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:salute><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>The <tei:rs key="entity-002334" type="place"><tei:region>Tyrol</tei:region></tei:rs> has
    once again become a reality for us, which, like every reality, is like a dream. This being our
    third time here, we are beginning to have our eyes opened and to realize that to see things once
    is not to see them at all. Last year, we were still confused as to where the great gentians and
    the magnficent alpine roses were to be collected: just because we were, so to speak, anxious
    whenever we searched for them, we <tei:add place="interlinear-above">invariably</tei:add> turned
    up too late; but this time <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs> has
    got a firmer grasp on things: that is where the alpine roses are, this is where the gentians
    are, and so on. (What is true for art is true to an even greater extent of nature: a sure touch
    is acquired only gradually. This gives the lie to Expressionism, which presents everything at
    the instantaneous perception of the perceiver (who is already so instantaneous).<tei:supplied reason="syntax">)</tei:supplied> A few days ago we found ourselves at our favorite pass (the
     <tei:rs key="entity-002350" type="place">Zeinis Pass</tei:rs> leading into the <tei:rs key="entity-002305" type="place">Montafon Valley</tei:rs>) – a mere 1¼ to 1½ hour’s walk –
    transported into early Spring; snow as far as the eye could see, and where the sun had melted it
    the <tei:hi rend="underline">very first</tei:hi> tiny flowers: crocuses, primroses, etc! </tei:p>

   <tei:p>For the first few days there was only one thing we could do: sleep, <tei:pb n="2"/> sleep
    away the foul torments of <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>. Now all of
    that is forgotten, and we are back at work again. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>How is the summer working out for you? Everywhere I went, I saw <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> people in the <tei:rs key="entity-002334" type="place"><tei:region>Tyrol</tei:region></tei:rs> – perhaps <tei:add place="interlinear-above">you</tei:add> too recall such people from <tei:rs key="entity-002396" type="place">Steinach</tei:rs> – or because it is further north is there less addiction there
    to fresh air? Since <tei:rs key="entity-000909" type="person">Fanny</tei:rs> is coming to you,
    did you decide you would all stay home? On account of your <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">son</tei:rs>? Or must you save even in summer? And how are you coping with the
    leaps in the currency? Has nothing come of the Hochschule? Do you have only private pupils, or
    are you still teaching at the school as well? </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I imagine that you have received the <tei:rs key="entity-001743" type="work">fourth issue of <tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs> and have read my
    article in <tei:rs key="entity-002556" type="journal"><tei:title level="j">Die
     Musik</tei:title></tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> Yet again with the
     <tei:rs key="entity-001743" type="work">fourth issue</tei:rs>, there was a struggle over the
    date at which it was released: On idiotically transparent pretexts, <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> managed to stretch it out to June, which makes for two issues (=
    four gatherings) a year: the annihilation of <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>. How was I to work through so many sonatas,
    symphonies, chamber music pieces, and works by <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person">Bach</tei:rs>, quite apart from the fact that, in response to requests from so many quarters,
    I had the possibility of exposing <tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person">Reger</tei:rs>,
     <tei:rs key="entity-000924" type="person">Wagner</tei:rs>, and <tei:rs key="entity-000798" type="person">Schoenberg</tei:rs>'s <tei:title level="m">Harmonielehre</tei:title>. There is no
    possibility of my fulfilling what <tei:add place="interlinear-above">even</tei:add> the ass
     <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs>
    <tei:add place="interlinear-above">himself</tei:add>, if only he could see see it finished
    before his eyes, <tei:hi rend="underline">would certainly accept with joy</tei:hi>, e.g. the
     <tei:rs key="entity-002882" type="work">thirty-two sonatas of Beethoven with Urlinien</tei:rs>,
     <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs> symphonies with
     <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>n, the Little Preludes of <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person">J. S. Bach</tei:rs> and their <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>n – reckoned at merely two issues
    per year, <tei:pb n="3"/> that would take over 200 years; can I expect to live so long? It would
    surely be much more sensible now to handle this literature not issue by issue, but in book form.
    Thus has <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> treated me with <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>; and he
    talked and wrote in quite different terms throughout the eight years in which he was courting
    this work! He has now become my adversary, and is afraid that I could demolish his Dadaists. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>How much have I been envying <tei:rs key="entity-000471" type="person">Korngold</tei:rs>,
    who in a feuilleton on "New Music"<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/>
    comprehensively lambasted all that rabble, <tei:rs key="entity-000798" type="person">Schoenberg</tei:rs> included. I relish the "freedom" that a shrewd Jewish "democrat" whose
    main profession is that of a common thief – his accounts are veritable bank hold-ups – can
    indulge in … I cannot possibly go on. Yesterday I wrote him a letter from here,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> in which I politely exhorted <tei:add place="interlinear-above">him</tei:add> to "show his true colors" as an opponent or at least
    safeguard the objectivity of a publisher to insert an advertisement in <tei:rs key="entity-002556" type="journal"><tei:title>Die Musik</tei:title></tei:rs> (people do not
    know where <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs> is to be obtained, and it is really all the more difficult since
     <tei:rs key="entity-002456" type="organization">Tonwille</tei:rs> is not a publisher, only a
    fake arrangement). Finally <tei:add place="interlinear-above">I</tei:add> said outright to him
    that he clearly rates me lower than <tei:rs key="entity-000798" type="person">Schoenberg</tei:rs>'s "shoddy work, which belongs in the 11th century, or in Kagran,"<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> which is all the odder and more unjust in view of the
    fact that I also wrote for him a complete <tei:rs key="entity-001725" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Kontrapunkt</tei:title></tei:rs>, the <tei:hi rend="underline">only one published by
     his <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">firm</tei:rs></tei:hi>! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">This eternal battle consumes much of my nervous energy. At present, I am
    practicing <tei:pb n="4"/> passive resistence by not giving the imprimatur for Opp. <tei:rs key="entity-001218" type="composition">90</tei:rs> and <tei:rs key="entity-001205" type="composition">106</tei:rs>, which are corrected, and so am putting the <tei:rs key="entity-001753" type="work">collected edition</tei:rs> in jeopardy. But is that a solution? </tei:p>

   <tei:p>I was thinking, and still am: by enlisting my pupils to make an effort to form a large
    subscription circle – three to four issues a year cost no more than 48,000 to 56,000 Kronen
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">annually</tei:add>, which is really only a drop in the ocean
    – might one not assemble a few hundred people here and in <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"><tei:country>Germany</tei:country></tei:rs>, who would sacrifice the price of two
    meat dishes a year for <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Der
      Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>? Now that would be a <tei:hi rend="underline">guaranteed clear
     profit</tei:hi> for the publisher, for which sake publishers small and large alike would
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">be bound to</tei:add> gladly take on the <tei:hi rend="underline">risk-free business</tei:hi>. I could at least exert the most decided pressure
    on <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs>: "The subscribers are demanding
    four issues a year," I would say, and he would surely have to comply for sake of a sure profit.
    What do you say to this plan? If you have any time whatsoever, or are not hampered by domestic
    difficulties, tell me by return post what you think of it. Must I of all people have to end up
    in the hand of <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> who, like his wife
     <tei:rs key="entity-000357" type="person">Jella</tei:rs>, has taken it into his head to lead an
    asinine progressive world of blind adherents.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p>I shall return to your <tei:term>counterpoint</tei:term> question of April 28 in my next
     letter.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> Are you not, my <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> friend, coming to the <tei:rs key="entity-002334" type="place"><tei:region>Tyrol</tei:region></tei:rs>? For a couple of days?
    What is your <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">wife</tei:rs> busy doing? How are things
    with the young <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">lad</tei:rs>? About the <tei:rs key="entity-002938" type="person">little ones</tei:rs>, we hope in <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">left margin, written sideways:</tei:note> they are still making their way
    through the enchanted world of their childhood as ever valiantly as "in the olden days," no? </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Most cordial greetings to all of you, </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">HS</tei:rs>
    </tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>