<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="136" sdoID="OJ-6-6_10">OJ 6/6, [10]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB-WD">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent and William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2009</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2009</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2010</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-06-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002720">ViolinM ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002721">ViolinM+V ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002722">ViolinM+V+F ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Heinrich Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated August 17,
    1919</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1919-08-17T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-05-07</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker hopes that colleagues will support Moriz Violin. – The court has favored
    Emil Kornfeld unduly. – A move to Germany might save Schenker money, but he is uncertain how
    many of his pupils would follow him there (only Pairamall has indicated willingness). – He asks
    Weisse to act as an intermediary in booking a supply of wood for burning. – Dahms and Weisse are
    due for simultanous visits. – He is glad to hear Valerie Violin is better. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Schüler; pupils; Übersiedlung; move; emigration; Gerichtsbeschluss; court decree;
    Gericht; court; Gesetz; law; Mitgift; settlement; Gesetz; furniture; Ofen; oven; Holzkarte; wood
    ration card; Wärmemangel; lack of warmth; Arbeit; work; Bibliothek; library; Holzhändler; wood
    merchant</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Fl</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">The writing of this letter, which is done at the Schloß
      Tantalier, Altenmarkt, in the Pongau, on vacation, is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/14,
      p. 2118-2119 (=37-38): "An Fl. (Br.): zum Thema Deutschland teile ich mit, wie gerade jetzt
      auch für mich die Uebersiedlung günstig, ja Geld-sparend wäre mit Rücksicht darauf, daß
      Lie-Liechens Ehe nun endlich getrennt wird; lege meine speziellen Verhältnisse zu den Schülern
      dar, wiefern sie die Uebersiedlung fördern könnten oder nicht u. komme schließlich auf die
      Bitte, bei einem Holzhändler intervenieren." ("To Floriz (letter): on the topic of Germany I
      let him know that just now, even for me, emigration would be advantageous, indeed economical,
      in view of the fact that Lie-Liechen's marriage is now being dissolved. I explain my special
      relationships with my pupils, to what extent they might or might not assist the emigration,
      and finally get round to asking him to act as an intermediary with a wood merchant.") Three
      diary entries record the intervening correspondence, none of which is known to survive: OJ
      2/14, p. 2111-2112 (=30-31): "Von Frau Vally (Br.): Bericht über den eigenen u. des Gatten
      Zustand." ("From Vally (letter): report on her own and her husband's condition."); OJ 2/14, p.
      2112 (=31), August 7: "An Fl. (Br.): Trostworte u. Einladung." (To Floriz (letter): words of
      comfort, and invitation."); OJ 2/14, p. 2118 (=37), August 16: "Von Fl. (expreß Br.):
      Erwiderung auf meinem Trostbrief - wie er sich seinen Weg nach Deutschland vorstellt." (From
      Floriz (express letter): Response to my letter of sympathy--how he envisions his way to
      Germany.") </tei:note>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Hoffen will ich doch, daß deine ehemaligen Kollegen, die dir die Adresse zukommen ließen,
    ein kräftiges Wort mitreden werden; beinahe will ich Ähnliches auch von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000542">Löwe</tei:rs> erhoffen - - Potz Teufel! mir reimt sich schon lange nicht,
    welcher Art Hinderniß denn noch immer da obwalten mag! Das ist ja nicht mehr <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Wien</tei:rs>, sondern <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002605">Warschau</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002401">Lemberg</tei:rs>, <tei:unclear reason="reading">Attingi</tei:unclear>, so was. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich selbst würde den Schritt beherzter riskieren, wenn ich nur recht wüßte, wieviel meiner
    Schüler mitzögen, die mir so übers Erster hinweghälfen. Wie gut würde sich die Übersiedlung in
    den schönen Zeitpunkt einfügen, da mein <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Lieliechen</tei:rs> in allernächster Zeit den Namen Kornfeld wird abtun dürfen, um nach
    „Gesetz.“ meinen eigenen Namen dafür einzutauschen!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The separation between Jeanette and Emil Kornfeld was authorized
     on November 10, 1919, and the marriage ceremony was conducted the same day, so these remarks
     are made only three weeks before the event (see the account in Schenker's diary, OJ 3/1, pp.
     2173-2175). </tei:note>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000288">Glässner</tei:rs> hat die Eingabe vor paar
    Wochen gemacht, u. kraft <tei:hi rend="underline">einfachen</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">Gerichtsbeschlusses</tei:hi> wird die Trennung ausgesprochen. Wegen der
    Mitgift u. Möbel muß noch gekämpft werden, u. man darf, da die neuen Gesetze hierüber sich noch
    nicht <tei:add place="interlinear-above">geäußert haben (nicht tschechisch)</tei:add>, wohl auf
    das Resultat <tei:pb n="2"/> gespannt sein. Daß <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000466">K.</tei:rs> nicht einen Heller freiwillig herausgeben wird, obgleich getrennt, obgleich ihm
    noch immer an 30.000 K. Reingewinn verbleiben (bei normaler Verzinsung), obgleich er zu großem
    Kriegsgewinn gelangt ist, steht für mich fest, der ihn von Anfang an im Gegensatz zu Allen als
    solcher Züge fähig befunden hat. Anderseits ist kaum anzunehmen, daß ihm das Gericht auch noch
    jetzt Alles zuerkennt, - unter welchem Titel wäre es möglich, außer dem rein tschechischer
    Aneignungstechnik? </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Wie gesagt, würde ich bei einer Übersiedlung sogar Geld sparen, statt daß ich jetzt in
     <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Wien</tei:rs> zunächst meinen Ofen umsetzten lassen
    muß, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Liel.</tei:rs> noch bei B. belassen, u.s.w. Und
    sollte ich nach einer Wohnung mich umsehen, nach Möbeln, wenn ich Hoffnung hätte, eine Wohnung
    in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482">Deutschland</tei:rs> zu nehmen? Schon daraus
    ersuchst du, welches Interesse ich daran habe, die Frage zur ehester Entscheidung zu bringen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Frau <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000655"> Pairamall </tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Pairamall appears in the lessonbooks as
     having lessons from Schenker in 1919/20 season, although her entry is much shorter than that
     for 1918/19 studying only three works, so it is possible that he dismissed her at some stage;
     however, she continued lessons the following season. </tei:note> schrieb mir, sie wäre bereit,
    mit mir nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482">D.</tei:rs> zu gehen, allerdings, nachdem
    ich sie wegen Schmutzes in Geld- u. sonstiger Gesinnung hinaus- <tei:pb n="3"/> geworfen habe.
    Würden <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000201"> Elias </tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000399"> Hupka </tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"> Weisse
    </tei:rs> mitkommen, so würde ich auch sie mitnehmen, um fürs Erste einige Deckung zu haben.
    Aber leider weiß ich es von den Erstgenannten nicht bestimmt: ich vermute blos, daß sie
    mitgingen, u. das ist zu wenig. Im Herbst will ich sondieren, - brieflich geht so was nicht
    recht. So muß ich mich bis dahin noch Wiener Sorgen anheimgeben . . Und da komme ich mit einer
    Frage, die, sobald du intervenieren könntest, sich automatisch in eine Bitte um Intervention
    verwandelt, nämlich: </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Wir lesen von einer Holzkarte! Was ich im Winter unter Wärmemangel gelitten habe, war
    weniger an sich entsetzlich, <tei:add place="interlinear-above">als</tei:add> daß es mich ganz
    u. gar in der Arbeit am Tisch zu Hause, wo nebenan die Bücher u. Bibliothek sind, u. auch Raum
    zu den Millionen Notizen, lahmgelegt hat. Zu der Kohle, die ich habe (hoffentlich ist während
    meiner Abwesenheit nichts davon abhandengekommen) brauche ich Holz, 10 Säcke à 50 Kg. hartes in
    Ofenscheiten. Gleichzeitig habe ich bei <tei:persName><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Winternitz</tei:hi></tei:persName>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Winternitz: presumably not the musicologist Emanuel Winternitz, but rather a fuel
     merchant in Vienna. </tei:note> der mir mehrere Jahre lang Kohle in größeren Quantitäten
    lieferte, u. auch bei <tei:persName>Baumann</tei:persName><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Baumann: presumably a fuel merchant in Vienna. </tei:note>
    angefragt, ob u. zu welchem Preise sie mir zwischen 15-20 IX jene<tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overwritten">n</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="superimposed">s</tei:add>
    </tei:subst>
    <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">Quantum</tei:foreign> liefern wollten. Die Schwierigkeit <tei:pb n="4"/> scheint mir in der <tei:hi rend="underline">Voraus</tei:hi>bestellung allein zu liegen,
    sofern die Holzhändler nur erklären könnten, daß es ihnen um jene Zeit <tei:hi rend="underline">vielleicht nicht mehr erlaubt sein</tei:hi> könnte, die Lieferung auszuführen. Vielleicht
    weißt du einen Holzhändler aus <tei:hi rend="underline">eigenem</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">Gebrauche</tei:hi>, dem du mündlich mit einer Erklärung nachhelfen
    könntest, (die ich ja zu Papier nicht so gut bringen kann,) der eine solche Vorausbestellung dir <tei:choice>
     <tei:sic>zu lieber</tei:sic>
     <tei:corr>zuliebe</tei:corr>
    </tei:choice> auf sich nähme. Das wäre sehr sicher, jedenfalls werde ich die <tei:choice>
     <tei:sic>allerhöchsten</tei:sic>
     <tei:corr>allernächsten?</tei:corr>
    </tei:choice> Entscheidungen der obererwähnten Herren dir zur Kenntnis bringen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>
    <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000149"> Dahms </tei:rs>, u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"> Weisse </tei:rs> dürften beide erst am 25<tei:hi rend="supralinear">ten</tei:hi> hier sein u. <tei:add place="interlinear-above">mehr</tei:add> durch Zufall
    zusammentreffen, als durch meine Hand. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Daß es der l Frau <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000914">Wally</tei:rs> besser geht,
    darf man aus deinem Schreiben wohl entnehmen, also was war denn das? </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">So seid denn gegrüßt herzlich wie immer </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">2 : 5 </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-30">
     <tei:note type="editorial">unsigned</tei:note>
    </tei:signed>
    <tei:date when="1919-08-17">17. August 1919</tei:date>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>I very much hope that your former colleagues, who let you have their addresses, will put
    in a strong word <tei:supplied reason="clarity">on your behalf</tei:supplied>. I hope for
    something similar from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000542">Löwe</tei:rs>, too – – Confound
    it all! I have not for a long time been able to understand what sort of obstacles could continue
    to prevail! This is certainly no longer <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Vienna</tei:rs>, but <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002605">Warsaw</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002401">Lemberg</tei:rs>, <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">Attingi</tei:unclear>, and such like. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>I myself would be more courageous about taking the step if only I knew for sure how many
    of my pupils would move with me and help me get over the initial stages. How well the timing of
    the move would fit with that magical moment when my <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Lieliechen</tei:rs> will be permitted shortly to discard the name "Kornfeld" and by "law"
    exchange it for my own name!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000288">Glässner</tei:rs> filed the petition a few weeks
    ago, and the separation will be pronounced by <tei:hi rend="underline">simple court
     decree</tei:hi>. We still have to fight over the settlement and furniture, and we may be kept
    in suspense for the result, since the laws on this have not yet <tei:add place="interlinear-above">been articulated (not in Czech terms)</tei:add>. <tei:pb n="2"/> That
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000466">K.</tei:rs> will not of his own free will hand over a
    single penny – even though he is separated, even though he is left with 30,000 Kronen of clear
    profit (at the normal rate of interest), even though he has achieved a great victory – is quite
    clear to me who, in contrast to all the others, found him capable of such actions from the very
    start. On the other hand, it is hard to believe that the court is still persisting in awarding
    him everything – under what other authority is that possible than the purely Czech technique of
    appropriation? </tei:p>

   <tei:p>As I have said, I might even save money by moving, instead of having to have my oven
    replaced and leaving <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Lieliechen</tei:rs> with B., etc.
    And should I look around for an apartment, for furniture, when I might have hoped to find a
    place to live in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482">Germany</tei:rs>? Even from these
    remarks you can work out the interest that I have in reaching the earliest possible decision. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Mrs. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000655">Pairamall</tei:rs> wrote telling me she was
    prepared to go with me to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482">Germany</tei:rs>, but only
    after I had thrown her out on account of her sordid attitude toward money and other matters.
     <tei:pb n="3"/> If <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000201">Elias</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000399">Hupka</tei:rs>, and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs> would come with me I would take them, too, in order to provide some initial
    cover. But unfortunately I do not know it for sure about the first-mentioned: I only suspect
    that they would go with me, and that is insufficient. I will take soundings in the autumn – this
    sort of thing is not so easily done in writing. So until then I shall just have to entrust
    myself again to Viennese tribulations . . And this brings me to a question that would
    automatically be converted into a request for intervention as soon as you were able to
    intervene, to wit:: </tei:p>

   <tei:p>We have read about a <tei:supplied reason="clarity">fire</tei:supplied>wood ration card!
    My suffering for lack of warmth last winter was less horrific in itself <tei:add place="interlinear-above">than</tei:add> that it utterly and completely crippled me in my work
    at my desk at home, with my books and library and also space for millions of notes close to
    hand. In addition to the coal that I have (I hope none of it has gone missing during my
    absence), I need wood: ten sacks, 50 Kg each of hardwood, split for the stove. At the same time,
    I have inquired of <tei:persName>Winternitz</tei:persName>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> who for several years supplied me with large quantities of coal, and also of
     <tei:persName>Baumann</tei:persName>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> whether
    they can supply me with that quantity between September 15 and 20, and if so, at what price. The
    difficulty <tei:pb n="4"/> seems to me to lie solely in ordering <tei:hi rend="underline">in
     advance</tei:hi>, in as much as that the wood merchants could only tell me that, <tei:hi rend="underline">around that time</tei:hi>, they would <tei:hi rend="underline">probably no
     longer be allowed</tei:hi> to fulfill the delivery. Maybe you know of a wood merchant whose
    services <tei:hi rend="underline">you yourself</tei:hi> use, to whom you could help me out by
    explaining the situation in person (which I really could not achieve on paper), who would
    undertake it as a favor to you. That would make things very secure <tei:supplied reason="clarity">for me</tei:supplied>; in any event, I will bring to your attention the
    decisions of the above-mentioned gentlemen at the very earliest opportunity. </tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000149">Dahms</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs>&gt; are due here not until the 25th, and will coincide,
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">more</tei:add> by accident than by design. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>I gather from your letter that dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000914">Wally</tei:rs> is better. So what was it? </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Please accept my cordial greetings as ever, </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">2 : 5 </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-30">
     <tei:note type="editorial">unsigned</tei:note>
    </tei:signed>
    <tei:date when="1919-08-17">August 17, 1919</tei:date>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>