<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="1637" sdoID="OJ-6-6_5">OJ 6/6, [5]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB-WD-LR">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent, William Drabkin, and Lee Rothfarb</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2016</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2016</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2016</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
   <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
   <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-02-15" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM+V ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002718">ViolinM+V+F ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002723">ViolinV ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002716">ViolinV ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Valerie Violin, dated December 30, 1917</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1917-12-30T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2016-02-01</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>In response to the Violins' condolences on the death of his mother, Schenker
    reflects sadly on her life and needs between 1890 and the late 1910s, attributing blame largely
    to his younger brother Moriz, less to his older brother Wilhelm; — He explains why he and
    Jeanette are unable to visit the Violins in the cold and without adequate
    clothing.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Teilnahme; condolences; Gewissensbisse; pang of conscience; Trennung; separation;
    Haushalt; household; Möbel; furniture; übersiedeln; to move house; Wohnung; apartment;
    Gelderfahrungen; financial state; Bindeglied; liaison; Schmerzen; pain; schandvoll; shameful;
    undankar; ungrateful; Genugtuung; amendments; Geheimnis; secret; Hinauskommen; visit;
    Ausrüstung; gear; Frierzustände; freezing conditions; Einkäufen; shopping; Schuhwerk; footwear;
    Arbeit; work; Hauptwerk; principal work; Einnahmen; earnings; Schüler; pupil; Umständen;
    conditions; Fernreise; long journey; Kinder; children</dc:subject>


   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Liebe Frau <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person"
      >Wally</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this
      letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/9, p. 820, December 30, 1917: "An Frau Wally
      (Br.): knüpfe an Fl. Brief an u. suche seine irrige Vorstellung richtigzustellen, da ihm
      beliebte anzunehmen, als würde ich Reue darüber empfinden, mich von der Mutter überhaupt
      getrennt zu haben. Daran schließe ich eine Darstellung der Gründe an, die uns hindern hinaus
      zu kommen: mangelhafte Bekleidung, besonders der Füße, die vielfache u. gehetzte Tätigkeit
      Lie-Liechens u. endlich die Arbeit. Zum Schluß ersuche ich sie, dem Beispiel zu folgen, das
      wir selbst all die Jahre her gegeben haben u. ohne Etikette gelegentlich nach uns zu fragen."
      ("To Mrs. Wally (letter): I answer it together with Floriz's letter and seek to put right his
      erroneous conception, since it was his fancy to assume that I would altogether feel remorse
      about having separated myself from my mother. To this I add a statement of the reasons which
      prevent us from getting out: lack of apparel, particularly of footwear, Lie-Liechen's profuse
      and stressful activities and ultimately the work. Finally I request her to follow the example,
      which we ourselves have set all these years, and without undue formality occasionally to
      inquire as to our well-being.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Herzlichen Dank für Ihre warme Teilnahme!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
     place="foot">Valerie Violin's communication of sympathy on the death of Heinrich's mother is
     not known to survive. The diary entry (see footnote 1) indicates that Schenker is here reacting
     to remarks made by Moriz (in a communication that also is not known to survive), not by Valerie
     herself.</tei:note> Der gute <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Floriz</tei:rs> schrieb
    mir einen rührenden Brief, worauf ich nicht erst nach <tei:rs key="entity-002543" type="place"
     >Marburg</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Moriz Violin was
     in Maribor in Slovenia ‒ Marburg an der Drau, then still part of Austria-Hungary ‒ on war
     service at the time.</tei:note> antworten zu müssen glaubte, da er ja wieder unterwegs sein
    könnte. Ich habe mir <tei:add place="interlinear-above">aber</tei:add> durchaus keine
    Gewissensbisse wegen der Trennung von der <tei:rs key="entity-000773" type="person"
     >Mama</tei:rs> gemacht, denn sie selbst war es, die den Haushalt in der <tei:rs
     key="entity-006162" type="place">Traungasse</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04"
     type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker lived at Vienna III, Traungasse 1 from November 1892 to
     October 1896. The wording of this and the subsequent sentence suggests that her departure, and
     the dismantling of the household, caused Schenker himself to move to Reisnerstraße 18.
     Schenker's diary entry for December 23, 1917 seems to imply that for some part of the time at
     Traungasse 1, Sophie was present and acted as a buffer between Julia and Heinrich, whose
     teaching work Julia "frequently obstructed."</tei:note> auflöste, die Möbel (!, was wir damals
    so nannten) verkaufte, u. zur <tei:rs key="entity-000319" type="person">Schwester</tei:rs>
     zog.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">In August of that year Sophie
     (Shifre) Schenker and her husband Salo Guttmann, having married in 1898, were living in
     Wilhemsburg, near Sankt Pölten, according to the birth registration for their son
     Johann.</tei:note> Von dort gieng sie auch wieder selbst zu <tei:rs key="entity-000775"
     type="person">Wilhelm</tei:rs> nach <tei:rs key="entity-002301" type="place"
     >Kautzen</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Wilhelm Schenker
     seems to have lived in Kautzen from c.1910 to 1918. Moreover, Schenker's diary entry for
     December 23, 1917 states that Julia's move to Kautzen occurred in "such difficult times of
     war," implying that it took place during the period 1914‒18. However the latter refers to the
     final move of her life, whereas the reference in this letter was clearly not the final
     one.</tei:note> dann zur <tei:rs key="entity-000193" type="person">Tante</tei:rs> nach <tei:rs
     key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial"
     place="foot">Presumably Dora Einschenk, whom Schenker almost invariably calls "Tante" ("aunt"),
     though her relationship to the Schenker family complex is still unclear.</tei:note> u. <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">als</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">nachdem</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> sie mit dieser fertig geworden, übersiedelte sie von selbst zu völlig fremden
     Leuten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot">Cf. Schenker's diary entry
     for December 23, 1917 (OJ 2/9, p. 815): "it was the fault of this youngest son [i.e. Moriz
     Schenker] that our mother was forced, for years, to seek accommodation among poor Jews whom she
     did not know"; also ibid: "The fact that at the moment she moved away from my aunt's I did not
     take her back to myself was perhaps even more tragic than her experience with her other
     sons."</tei:note> Dies gieng mir immer sehr nahe, aber ich war, damals schon in der <tei:rs
     key="entity-002277" type="place">Reisnerstr.</tei:rs> wohnhaft, völlig außer Stande, die
     <tei:rs key="entity-000773" type="person">Mutter</tei:rs> zu mir zu nehmen.<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn09" type="editorial" place="foot">The earliest correspondence item delivered to
     Schenker at Vienna III, Reisnerstraße 18<tei:hi rend="supralinear">II</tei:hi>, No. 10 is
     postmarked October 8, 1896 (Meschaert: OJ 12/54, [1]). Cf. Schenker's diary at OJ 2/9, p. 816,
     December 23, 1917: "Even less than in the previous period, my financial means would not allow
     me to start all over again, taking on a household, purchasing furniture, engaging a cook or
     similar personnel in the house."</tei:note> Selbst wenn ich eine größere Wohnung hätte
    aufnehmen u. neu möblieren können ‒ dzt wie wenig ich es dazumal konnte, weiß <tei:rs
     key="entity-000913" type="person">Fl.</tei:rs> wohl am besten aus traurigen Gelderfahrungen ‒,
    hätte ich der armen <tei:rs key="entity-000773" type="person">Mutter</tei:rs> doch nicht auch
    zugleich das jüdische <tei:foreign xml:lang="fro">Milieu</tei:foreign> geben können, dessen sie
    vor Allem bedürfte. Solange die <tei:rs key="entity-000319" type="person">Schwester</tei:rs> im
    Hause war, fungierte sie auf glücklichste Weise als Bindeglied zwischen uns u. den etwaigen
    Freundinnen der <tei:rs key="entity-000773" type="person">Mutter</tei:rs>; <tei:pb n="2"/> mit
    mir selbst aber hat man diesbezüglich niemals was Rechtes anfangen können. Das Alles ist es also
    nicht, was mir Schmerzen verursacht, nur einzig das schandvolle undankbare Verhalten <tei:rs
     key="entity-000774" type="person">Mozio</tei:rs>s gegenüber der <tei:rs key="entity-000773"
     type="person">Mutter</tei:rs>, die ohne Genugtuung aus dem Leben gehen müßte. Hätte ich <tei:rs
     key="entity-000774" type="person">Mozio</tei:rs>'s Geheimnis vor 10 Jahren gewußt, dann
    freilich hätten wir die <tei:rs key="entity-000773" type="person">Mama</tei:rs> nach <tei:rs
     key="entity-004091" type="place">Podhajce</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10"
     type="editorial" place="foot">Podhajce was Julia Schenker's place of birth.</tei:note> bringen
    können, wohin es sie immer zog. Leider erfuhr ich zu spät von seinen Einkünften . .</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Was unser Hinauskommen anbelangt, so stellen sich uns leider unüberwindliche
    Schwierigkeiten entgegen. Vor Allem eine mangelhafte winterliche Ausrüstung. Ich will meinem in
    diesen Jahren wirklich schwergeprüften <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person"
     >Lieliechen</tei:rs> nicht zumuten, daß sie Frierzustände auf sich nimmt, wo sie schon bei den
    Einkäufen (die sie, vergessen Sie das nicht, jeden Tag auch bei schlechtestem Wetter u.
     <tei:foreign xml:lang="fre">miserabl</tei:foreign>em Schuhwerk leider immer nur selbst zu
    besorgen hat) genug solcher zu bestehen hat. Ich bin froh, wenn sie nach dem härtesten Muß in
    die Wärme kommt u. Schuhe ablegt oder dgl. Und dazu kommt noch das Dringliche meiner
     Arbeit.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker is here referring
     to Jeanette's contribution to his theoretical work and teaching: dictation, stenography,
     fair-copying, contacting students, and so on. </tei:note> Der Krieg war für mich ein Denkzettel
    ersten Ranges u. ich muß mich u. <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lieliechen</tei:rs>
    vor der Wiederkehr solcher betrüblicher Erfahrungen schützen. Wenn mir so Manches heute noch
    zustoßen kann, wo meiner die Menschen immerhin noch bedürfen, wie würde es aussehen, wenn sie
    meines als eines alten <tei:pb n="3"/> Mannes nicht mehr bedürfen würden, da heißt es energisch
    vorbauen. Und als sturmerprobter Selbstversorger weiß ich nur einen Weg hiezu, ‒ die Vollendung
    des Hauptwerkes, auf dessen Einnahmen ich nun nach den immer größer werdenden Erfolgen wohl bis
    zu einem gewissen Grade rechnen darf. Was das aber heißt, diese schwierigste Arbeit meines
    Lebens bei 3‒4 Stunden täglich <tei:add place="interlinear-above">zu machen</tei:add>, hinter
    denen noch immer weitere 1‒2 Stunden Arbeit für die Schüler steckt, davon mögen Sie sich
    vielleicht wirklich keine Vorstellung machen, zumal unter den Umständen, wie sie heute gegeben
    sind.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ob wir wollen oder nicht, müssen wir uns daher, solange diese Verhältnisse andauern, mit
    dem brieflichen Ausweg behelfen. Ihnen muten wir ja gar nicht zu, daß Sie unter den für Sie
    obwaltenden Schwierigkeiten die „Fernreise“ zu uns ‒ man muß ja heute beinahe so sagen ‒ machen,
    u. wir können es schon gar nicht unternehmen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12" type="editorial"
     place="foot">The journey from the Rennweg at Reisnerstraße, in the third district (southeast),
     to Sechhausterstraße 126 within a short distance of the Schönbrunn palace (west), would have
     involved at least three trams and buses (or train from the Karlsplatz). Under normal conditions
     it would have taken more than an hour, and in wintertime under wartime conditions it would have
     been much more arduous.</tei:note> Es bleibt mir nur übrig, Sie zu bitten, gelegentlich mal ein
    Kärtchen uns „hinein“zuschreiben, wie es Ihnen, Ihren Kindderchen ergeht ‒ ich wollte, mein
     Band<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13" type="editorial" place="foot">i.e. <tei:title level="m"
      >Kontrapunkt</tei:title>, second half-volume, eventually published in 1922, of which Schenker
     was at this time, as his diaries record, drafting sections.</tei:note> könnte so von selbst
    gedeihen u. wachsen, wie diese glücklichen Geschöpfe ‒; wir werden uns ja auch einfinden, dafür
    bürgt unsere Vergangenheit, da wir doch im Laufe der Jahre ohne jede <tei:foreign xml:lang="fre"
     >Etikette</tei:foreign> wenn ich nicht irre stets als die Ersten u. oft sogar zudringlich
    frugen, <tei:pb n="4"/> nicht wahr?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14" type="editorial" place="foot"
     >In this convoluted construction Schenker is implicity chiding Valerie Violin without doing so
     overtly; the meaning behind it is baldly stated in the diary summary (see footnote
     1).</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Einen anderen Weg weiß ich heute nicht. Kommen wieder mal Schuhe ins Land, u.s.w., dann
    erscheinen wir unverzüglich, um uns an der Familie zu sättigen.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Mit beste<tei:supplied reason="syntax">n</tei:supplied> Grüßen an
     Sie von mir u. <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lieliechen</tei:rs></tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">H
     Sch</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline>Sonntag <tei:date when="1911-12-30">30. XII. 1917</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>
  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dear <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person"
      >Wally</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Cordial thanks for your warm condolences!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/>
    Good old <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Floriz</tei:rs> wrote me a touching letter,
    to which I didn't at first think I needed to respond to <tei:rs key="entity-002543" type="place"
     >Marburg</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> since he might well be on the
    move again. I have <tei:add place="interlinear-above">however</tei:add> felt absolutely no pangs
    of remorse regarding my separation from <tei:rs key="entity-000773" type="person">Mama</tei:rs>,
    for it was she herself who dissolved the household in the <tei:rs key="entity-006162"
     type="place">Traungasse</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> who sold the
    furniture (!, as we called it in those days), and moved to my <tei:rs key="entity-000319"
     type="person">sister</tei:rs>'s.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> From there she
    moved, again at her own initiative, to <tei:rs key="entity-000775" type="person"
     >Wilhelm</tei:rs> in <tei:rs key="entity-002301" type="place">Kautzen</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> then to my <tei:rs key="entity-000193" type="person"
     >aunt</tei:rs> in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> and <tei:add place="interlinear-above">after</tei:add>
    she had got tired of the latter moved at her own decision to completely unfamiliar
     people.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/> This distressed me greatly but, by then
    already living in the <tei:rs key="entity-002277" type="place">Reisnerstraße</tei:rs>, I was not
    remotely in a position to take my <tei:rs key="entity-000773" type="person">mother</tei:rs>
     in.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09" type="footnote"/> Even if I had been able to take on a larger
    apartment and to furnish it anew ‒ and <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Floriz</tei:rs>
    knows best from <tei:supplied reason="clarity">my</tei:supplied> sorry financial state at that
    time how little I could have afforded that ‒ there was no way I could have at the same time have
    provided my <tei:rs key="entity-000773" type="person">mother</tei:rs> with the Jewish milieu of
    which she was above all in need. So long as my <tei:rs key="entity-000319" type="person"
     >sister</tei:rs> was in the house, she did the best possible job of being the liaison between
    us and whatever friends my <tei:rs key="entity-000773" type="person">mother</tei:rs> had;
     <tei:pb n="2"/> with me on my own, on the other hand, I could never have begun to provide what
    was needed in this regard. So, all of that is not what causes me pain; <tei:supplied
     reason="clarity">it is</tei:supplied> only the shameful, ungrateful behavior of <tei:rs
     key="entity-000774" type="person">Mozio</tei:rs> toward <tei:rs key="entity-000773"
     type="person">mother</tei:rs>, who was destined to depart this life without amends having been
    made. Had I known <tei:rs key="entity-000774" type="person">Mozio</tei:rs>'s secret ten years
    ago, then we could of course have moved <tei:rs key="entity-000773" type="person">Mama</tei:rs>
    to <tei:rs key="entity-004091" type="place">Podhajce</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn10"
     type="footnote"/> to which she always felt drawn. Unfortunately, I learned too late about his
    income ....</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">As concerns our getting out <tei:supplied reason="clarity">to visit
     you</tei:supplied>, sadly insuperable difficulties stand in our way, above all a lack of winter
    gear. I will not demand of my <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lieliechen</tei:rs>, who
    in recent years has been utterly sorely tried, that she subject herself to freezing conditions
    when she already has enough of that to cope with when doing the shopping (which, don't forget,
    alas, she always has to take care of by herself every day, even in the worst weather and with
    atrocious footware). I am happy when after direst necessity she comes into the warm and takes
    off her shoes or suchlike. And on top of that there are still the pressing demands of my
     work.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn11" type="footnote"/> The war has been for me an object lesson
    of the first order, and I must protect <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person"
     >Lieliechen</tei:rs> and myself from the recurrence of such distressing experiences. If these
    days so much can still go wrong with me, where people are still constantly in need of me, how
    would it look if they were no longer to need me as an old <tei:pb n="3"/> man? This has to be
    energetically guarded against. As a storm-tested self-provider I know only one way to do this ‒
    the completion of my principal work, on the income from which I am to a considerable extent
    still dependant <tei:supplied reason="clarity">even</tei:supplied> after my ever-increasing
    successes. What that means, however ‒ <tei:add place="interlinear-above">to do</tei:add> this,
    the most difficult work of my life, at the same time as <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
     >giving</tei:supplied> three or four lessons a day plus a further one to two hours of work for
    my pupils ‒ of this you really cannot have any conception, particularly given conditions as they
    are today.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Whether we like it or not, as long as these conditions prevail we must content ourselves
    with resorting to letters. Given the difficulties that you face, we certainly don't expect you
    to make the "long journey" (as one has almost to call it these days) to us, and we most
    certainly can't undertake it ourselves.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn12" type="footnote"/> All that
    is left is for me to ask you to pen us a short postcard from time to time telling us how things
    are going with you and your little children. ‒ I only wish my volume<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn13" type="footnote"/> could prosper and grow as spontaneously as
     <tei:supplied reason="clarity">do</tei:supplied> these fortunate creatures. ‒ We, too, will
    send reports of ourselves (our past record can vouch for that) as over the years without undue
    formality, if I am not mistaken, we were always the first to inquire, often even pressingly
     <tei:pb n="4"/> ‒ isn't that true?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn14" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>I don't see any other way at the moment. Once shoes again become available, etc., then we
    will appear immediately in order to savor the pleasures of family life. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">With best greetings to you from <tei:rs key="entity-000771"
      type="person">Lieliechen</tei:rs> and me,</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">H
     Sch</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline>Sunday <tei:date when="1911-12-30">December 30, 1917</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
