<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="944" sdoID="OJ-6-7_24">OJ 6/7, [24]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
   <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2013</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2013-06-09" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002720">ViolinM ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002721">ViolinM+V ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002722">ViolinM+V+F ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated August 15, 1925</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1925-08-15T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2013-06-09</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>After expressing his sympathy for Violin, in response to his friend's depressing
    postcard, Schenker gives an account of some of the summer events, including a visit from
    Vrieslander and Hoboken and work on two essays for Meisterwerk 2. While continuing to rail
    against Hertzka and Universal Edition, he repeats the story of Drei Masken Verlag failing to
    send him 250 Marks upon receipt of the manuscript of Meisterwerk 1. His brother Moses is,
    however, acquainted with the principal owner of Drei Masken, Felix Sobotka, and through this
    connection the payment has been made.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>



  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Fl</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ
      3/7, p. 2853, August 15, 1925: "An Fl. (Br.): Bestürzung über seine mißliche Lage, Hilfeanbot;
      über den Besuch der beiden Herren, den durch Baumgarten mir verursachten Schaden, die
      Zurückhaltung der 250 Mark, über die Reger- u. Chaos-Arbeit." ("To Floriz (letter): dismay
      over his unfortunate situation, offer of help; about the visit of the two men, the damage
      caused by Baumgarten, the withholding of the 250 marks, about the Reger and Chaos
      work.")</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Was du so flüchtig hingeworfen u. angedeutet hast, hat mich ganz entsetzt.
    Ich dachte dich über ein Äußerstes solcher Art hinaus – eigentlich weiß ich nicht, warum ich mir
    das dachte – u. stand plötzlich vor einem gespenstigen Wort in deiner Karte . . Ich fasse es
    nicht. Deine <tei:rs key="entity-000909" type="person">Schwester</tei:rs> hat uns von den großen
    Kosten des Konzertes erzählt, die dich so arg hineinrissen, mehr wußte auch sie nicht. Daß ich
    dir Hilfe anböte, wäre lächerlich in anbetracht der Menschen, die heute meine Umgebunrg bilden,
    u. dennoch – wenn du dine Erlaubnis gibst – müßte jeder Gedanke zurückgestellt u. der Versuch
    gemacht werden. Es gibt Überraschungen in der Welt, vielleicht erblühte eine dir?! Sage ein
    Wort!</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hoboken</tei:rs> sind mit des Letzteren Auto hierhergekommen
    u. hielten sich 3 Tage auf, – das Wetter stand sehr im Wege beim Kommen u. Gehen. Erst nach
    ihrer Abreise gab es ein <tei:pb n="2"/> prächtiges Wetter. Ich weiß nicht, ob ich dir
    mitgeteilt habe, daß <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hoboken</tei:rs> zu mir nach
     <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> kommt. Als Honorar nannte ich die
    gleichen 5 Doll. per Stunde, wie sie die ungleich ärmere Schüler entrichten. Hoffentlich gibt er
    mir keine Veranlassung, mich gegen eine Übertriebenheit an gesellschaftlichen Forderungen wehren
    zu müssen, denn dann wäre ich schlimmer daran, als mit den Anderen. Wir wollen ja sehen. Das
    Seltsame ists, daß ich auch mit <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hob.</tei:rs> den
    Stand von <tei:date when="1923">1923</tei:date>
    <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">noch</tei:add>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">nicht wieder</tei:hi>gewinnen kann,(!) was mich nur darum so peinigt,
    weil (wie ich sehe) aus den Werken nicht einmal mehr ein Sommer herauszuschlagen ist. (Wir sind
    dem Sommer <tei:date when="1924">1924</tei:date> gegenüber beträchtlich erhöht worden.)</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Was ich mit D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi>
    <tei:rs key="entity-000048" type="person">Baumg.</tei:rs> vorhabe, schreibe ich dir demnächst:
    er hat mir einen sehr großen Schaden verursacht. Wenn er nur eine <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#HS">ers</tei:del>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">ernste</tei:hi> Miene gemacht hätte (zu klagen, meine ich), hätte ich
    schon längst die Ablöse erreicht. Ich bin aber in ein Demokraten-Nest geraten, alle desto
    eingebildeter, ja eselhafter, u. so würfeln sie förmlich um mich, sie wollen es auf demokratisch
    machen u. wissen nicht, <tei:pb n="3"/> daß <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> blos ein Gauner, aber kein Demokrat ist. Bis in meine kärglichen Rechnungen,
    die sich um ein Dreck von Geld drehe, dringt die „<tei:soCalled>demokratische</tei:soCalled>“
    Heuchelei u. Betrügerei!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Vielleicht erfreut dich die Mitteilung, daß ich hier als Erstes gleich die <tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person">Reger</tei:rs>schen</tei:hi>
    <tei:rs key="entity-001659" type="composition"><tei:title>Bach-Var. für Klavier (op.
      81)</tei:title></tei:rs> fertiggemacht habe (für das <tei:rs key="entity-001751" type="work"><tei:title>Jahrb. II</tei:title></tei:rs>), u. gestern auch das
    „<tei:title>Chaos</tei:title>“ von <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person">Haydn</tei:rs>.
     „<tei:title>Ein Gegenbeispiel</tei:title>“ lautet der Titel der Arbeit über <tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person">Reger</tei:rs>. Hätte ich nur schon <tei:rs key="entity-001750" type="work"><tei:title>Jahrb. I</tei:title></tei:rs> in der Hand! Auch da
    hat sich gleich etwas ereignet, was ich für so ziemlich ausgeschlossen hielt: bei Ablieferung
    des Mscp. hätte ich sogleich 250 MK erhalten sollen, ich sandte Mitte <tei:date when="1925-06">Juni</tei:date>, das Mscp. ein, aber bis Mitte <tei:date when="1925-07">Juli</tei:date> regte
    sich gar nichts. Um eine solche Wirtschaft nicht einreißen zu lassen, schrieb ich an <tei:rs key="entity-000774" type="person">Mozio</tei:rs> – der Direktor der „Treuga“<tei:note type="editorial">?</tei:note>
    <tei:rs key="entity-003627" type="person">Sobotka</tei:rs> ist der Hauptbesitzer der <tei:rs key="entity-002627" type="organization">3 Masken</tei:rs> – u. es kam durch zufälliges Hin u.
    Her dazu, daß <tei:rs key="entity-003627" type="person">Sobotka</tei:rs> den <tei:rs key="entity-000774" type="person">Mozio</tei:rs> die 250 Mk für mich anweisen ließ. <tei:pb n="4"/> Gar so lustig fängt es also nicht an. Unsere Mühen waren schier todtlich, – 4
     Wochen<tei:note type="editorial">corr</tei:note> brauchte ich hier, um die Augen aufzumachen,
    ja D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi>
    <tei:rs key="entity-000324" type="person">Halberstam</tei:rs> wollte mir <tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs> diesmal verbieten – u. lumpige 250 MK werden
    zurückgehalten entgegen dem Vertrag! Das kommt freilich alles, alles von den – großen Meistern
    her, von denen sich die Welt abgewandt hat, die nie ja von ihnen wußte! Alles was ich biete, ist
    folgerichtig schwierig, zu schwierig für die Leute, na<tei:note type="editorial">corr</tei:note>
    – ich werde es schon machen!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Wir haben uns schon erholt, – hohe Zeit war es –, im Herbst u. Winter gilt es wieder
    größten Anstrengungen gewachsen sein!</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">LieLiechen</tei:rs> schreibt soeben das
     „<tei:title>Chaos</tei:title>“ in ihrer ewig ruhigen, unchaotischen Weise, die zu <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person">Haydn</tei:rs>’s Kunst im Chaos sehr gut paßt. Gelassen u.
    ruhig <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">also</tei:add> grüßen wir dich <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#HS">also</tei:del><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">"also," not "dich," crossed out by mistake.</tei:note> Beide, dich, deine <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">Frau</tei:rs> u. die Kinderchen!</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute>Lasse bald von dir etwas hören!</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-80">Dein</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-90"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H</tei:rs></tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1925-08-15">15.VIII.1925</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Fl</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">What you so hastily threw down and hinted at thoroughly shocked me. I thought
    you had gotten over such an extreme situation of this sort – actually, I do not know what led me
    to think so – and I suddenly stood before a ghostly word in your card. I just cannot comprehend
    it. Your <tei:rs key="entity-000909" type="person">sister</tei:rs> told us about the enormous
    costs of the concert, which affected you so adversely; more she did not know, either. That I
    were to offer help would be ludicrous when you consider the people who constitute my circle
    these days. And yet, if you give me your permission, every thought would have to be set aside
    and an attempt would be made. There are surprises in the world; perhaps one will blossom for
    you?! Say the word!</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs> and <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hoboken</tei:rs> came here, in the latter's automobile, and
    stayed for three days. The weather greatly prevented us from getting out and about. Only after
    their departure did we have <tei:pb n="2"/> magnificent weather. I do not know whether I told
    you that <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hoboken</tei:rs> is coming to study with me
    in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>. As a fee, I asked for the same five
    dollars per lesson that will take its toll on my incomparably less well-off pupils. I hope that
    he will give me no occasion to make me defend myself against a flood of social demands; for then
    I would be worse off than with the others. We shall have to see. The strange thing is that, even
    with <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hoboken</tei:rs>, I <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">still</tei:add>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">cannot retrieve</tei:hi> my <tei:supplied reason="clarity">financial</tei:supplied> position of <tei:date when="1923">1923</tei:date>(!), something that
    pains me only because, as I see, I cannot pay with the income from my works for a summer
    holiday. Compared to the summer of <tei:date when="1924">1924</tei:date>, we are paying
    considerably more.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>About my plans with Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000048" type="person">Baumgarten</tei:rs>, I
    shall write to you soon: he has caused me great loss. If only I had made my intentions <tei:hi rend="underline">serious</tei:hi> (about taking legal action, I mean), I would have reached a
    settlement long ago. I have, however, fallen into nest of democrats, all the more vain, indeed
    assinine. And so they play games about my situation; they want to do things democratically, not
    realizing <tei:pb n="3"/> that <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> is no
    more than a scoundrel, and no democrat. The "<tei:soCalled>democratic</tei:soCalled>" hypocricy
    and deceitfulness penetrates right into my meager accounts, which hinge upon a trifling amount
    of money!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Perhaps you will be glad to learn that the first thing I did here was to complete
     <tei:supplied reason="clarity">my essay on</tei:supplied>
    <tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person">Reger</tei:rs>'s</tei:hi>
    <tei:rs key="entity-001659" type="composition"><tei:title>Bach Variations for piano, Op.
      81</tei:title></tei:rs> (for <tei:rs key="entity-001751" type="work"><tei:title>Yearbook
      2</tei:title></tei:rs>), and yesterday the "<tei:title><tei:supplied reason="clarity">Representation of</tei:supplied> Chaos</tei:title>" <tei:supplied reason="clarity">from
      <tei:rs key="entity-001551" type="composition"><tei:title level="m">The
      Creation</tei:title></tei:rs></tei:supplied> by <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person">Haydn</tei:rs>. "<tei:title>A Counter-example</tei:title>" is the title of the piece on
     <tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person">Reger</tei:rs>. If only I already had <tei:rs key="entity-001750" type="work"><tei:title>Yearbook 1</tei:title></tei:rs> in my hands! Even
    here something has just occurred, which I would have thought to be virtually impossible. Upon
    dispatch of the manuscript, I should have received 250 marks immediately; I sent off the
    manuscript in the middle of <tei:date when="1925-06">June</tei:date>, but nothing happened until
    the middle of <tei:date when="1925-07">July</tei:date>. So as not to allow this business
    practice to become a habit, I wrote to <tei:rs key="entity-000774" type="person">Mozio</tei:rs>
    – the director of the "Treuga<tei:note type="editorial">?</tei:note>," <tei:rs key="entity-003627" type="person">Sobotka</tei:rs>, is the principal owner of <tei:rs key="entity-002627" type="organization">Drei Masken Verlag</tei:rs>, and it came about by
    chance to-ing and fro-ing that <tei:rs key="entity-003627" type="person">Sobotka</tei:rs>
    arranged for <tei:rs key="entity-000774" type="person">Mozio</tei:rs> to be paid the 250 marks
    for me. <tei:pb n="4"/> Things certainly did not begin so cheerfully. Our efforts were purely
    fatal – I needed four weeks here in order to open my eyes; in fact Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000324" type="person">Halberstam</tei:rs> wanted to forbid me from going to <tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs> this year – and a miserable 250 marks were
    held back, in contradiction to the contract! All, all of this comes of course from none other
    than the great masters, on whom the world has turned its back, never having really known about
    them! Everything that I offer is, consequently, difficult, too difficult for the people; well –
    I shall prevail in the end!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>We have recovered somewhat now – it was high time; in the autumn and winter we shall have
    to be prepared to confront the greatest pressures!</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs> is at this moment writing
    out "<tei:title>Chaos</tei:title>" in her ever quiet, unchaotic way, which fits in very well
    with <tei:rs key="entity-000344" type="person">Haydn</tei:rs>'s art in chaos. Calmly and
    quietly, then:<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> the two of us send you, your
     <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">wife</tei:rs> and the children our greetings.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute>Let us hear something from you soon!</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-80">Yours,</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-90"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1925-08-15">August 15, 1925</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>