<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="940" sdoID="OJ-6-7_20">OJ 6/7, [20]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
   <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2013</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2013-06-08" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002720">ViolinM ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002721">ViolinM+V ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002722">ViolinM+V+F ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated May 4, 1925</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1925-05-04T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2013-06-08</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>In a wide-ranging letter, Schenker sends Violin money for arranging the order of
    Der Tonwille (which must consist of multiple copies of Tonwille 1); Hertzka's representative,
    Robert Scheu, is currently studying the papers relating to Schenker's threat of legal action.
    Schenker continues to express his astonishment at Furtwängler's ignorance of sonata form, a fact
    that does not prevent him from earning huge fees for conducting in New York. He has turned down
    a request from a lady who teaches in New York and a former pupil (now in St. Gallen), who wish
    to spend some time with him in Galtür. He enquires about the personal difficulties that Violin
    writes about in his letter, and asks him to say more; they will invite his sister for a visit.
    He will send him a copy of the medallion (designed by Alfred Rothberger); the portrait by Viktor
    Hammer is not yet finished.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>



  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Fl</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ
      3/7, p. 2815, May 4, 1925: "An Fl. (Br.): 5 Dollar recomm.; Bericht über den Stand der
      U.-E.-Angelegenheit u. das Eingreifen D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Scheus;
      Ablehnung des Sextetts durch Simrock; über die Plaquette; frage nach seinen Sorgen." ("To
      Floriz (letter): 5 dollars registered; report on the status of the UE matter and Dr. Scheu's
      involvement; refusal of <tei:supplied>Weisse's</tei:supplied> Sextet by Simrock; about the
      medallion; I ask about his concerns.")</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Beiliegend 5 Doll. zur Begleichung deiner <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title>TW</tei:title></tei:rs>-Auslagen. Tausend Dank. Es ist höchste Zeit, daß
    die Bestellung gemacht <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#HS">wird</tei:del> u. mir die <tei:hi rend="double-underline">Bestätigung</tei:hi> eingesendet wird. <tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:date when="1925-07">Juli</tei:date></tei:hi> hat <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">H.</tei:rs> Rechnung zu legen! Nicht vergessen:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Violin has underlined the words "Nicht vergessen."</tei:note> das
     <tei:rs key="entity-001740" type="work"><tei:hi rend="triple-underline">allererste</tei:hi>
     <tei:hi rend="underline">Heft</tei:hi></tei:rs> der <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title>Tw.</tei:title></tei:rs> überhaupt ist aus dem J. <tei:date when="1921">1921</tei:date>, sonst war alle Mühe vergebens. <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">H.</tei:rs> macht eben Miene, das <tei:rs key="entity-001740" type="work">1. Heft</tei:rs>
    nicht mehr auszuweisen, als ein Stück, nach dem angeblich nicht mehr gefragt wird; was
     da<tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#HS">s</tei:del> noch verkauft wird, steckt er eben
    ein.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Angeblich ist der Stand so, daß <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">H.</tei:rs>
    seinen Vertreter D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi>
    <tei:rs key="entity-000779" type="person">Rob. Scheu</tei:rs> mit den Verhandlungen betraut hat.
     <tei:rs key="entity-000779" type="person">Scheu</tei:rs> studiert erst die Papiere. Was kommt,
    weiß ich also nicht.</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs> war vor einigen Wochen bei
    uns des Abends. Ich habe <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs> (der, wie er
    sagt, dir inzwischen geschrieben hat) als „Zeugen“ zugezogen u. es hat gelohnt. Denn es stellte
    sich das wohl Un- <tei:pb n="2"/> erklärte heraus, daß <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">F.</tei:rs> nicht einmal weiß, was ein „<tei:term>Sonatensatz</tei:term>“ ist. Darunter
    versteht er nämlich auch das <tei:term>Adagio</tei:term> in einer <tei:term>Sonate</tei:term>,
     <tei:term>Sinfonie</tei:term>! Aber die besondere <tei:term>Form</tei:term> des
     <tei:term>Sonatensatzes</tei:term> ist ihm fremd <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">gewesen</tei:add> – seit jenem Abend weiß er es freilich schon. Das hindert nicht, daß er in
     <tei:rs key="entity-002873" type="place">New-York</tei:rs> 70 Mill. Kr. für <tei:hi rend="underline">einen</tei:hi> Abend erhielt: 3 solcher Abende in der Woche machen 210 Mill.
    aus, dazu das Erträgnis der anderen Abende der Woche. Begreifst du also, weshalb die deutschen
    Musiker nach <tei:rs key="entity-002873" type="place">N-York</tei:rs> rennen, per Schiff, per
    Flugzeug usw?</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Und da bin ich auch bei der Frage, die ich schon längst stellen wollte, jedesmal aber
    unterdrückt habe. Du schreibst schon zweimal von Sorgen um die deinen, die dich quälen, wie habe
    ich das zu verstehen? Hast du einen Schüler-Rückgang? Der ist ja allgemein. Man lernt nicht mehr
    gern, nicht ordentlich, der Schüler will es kurz haben, heute eintreten u. schon morgen als der
    „gefeinerteste Pianist“ <tei:pb n="3"/> die gewissen Geld-Lorbeeren ernten! Es ist der
    allgemeine Zug der geldbegeisterten Zeit von heute. Auch ich nehme jetzt weniger ein, als im
    Vorjahre. Oder: kannst du nicht weiter erhöhen u. das bring dicht in Rückstand gegenüber der
    zunehmenden Teuerung, ist es das? Dasselbe ist bei mir. Ich darf über 5 Doll. nicht hinaus,
    inzwischen ist alles teurer geworden. Galtür kostet jetzt schon 90–100.000 K. per Tag, im
    Vorjahre zahlten wir 70.000 K. Ich bin machtlos dagegen. Oder sind deine Sorgen noch anderer
    Natur?</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:rs key="entity-002448" type="organization">Simrock</tei:rs> hat dem <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs> zunächst zugesagt, dann aber doch abgelehnt,
    frech genug unter dem Titel, daß das <tei:rs key="entity-004627" type="composition">Sextett</tei:rs> „<tei:quote>nichts Neues</tei:quote>“ vorstelle!
     „<tei:soCalled>Neu</tei:soCalled>“, schlecht, gleichviel, wenn nur das gewisse “Geschäft” zu
    machen ist.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In der zweiten Hälfte des <tei:date when="1925-05">Monats</tei:date> erhielst
    du die neue Plaquette von mir. Das Schabblatt<tei:note type="editorial">corr</tei:note> von
     <tei:rs key="entity-000327" type="person">Hammer</tei:rs> ist noch nicht fertig.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Augenblicklich trete ich in den <tei:pb n="4"/> letzten Abschnitt meiner
     „<tei:rs key="entity-001750" type="work"><tei:title>Jahrbuch</tei:title></tei:rs>“-Arbeit ein.
    Es gibt nich viel, viel Arbeit bis Ende <tei:date when="1925-06">Juni</tei:date>: dann werden
    wir wohl rasten müssen, ob wir wollen oder nicht. Nach <tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs> wollten mitkommen eine Lehrerin aus <tei:rs key="entity-002873" type="place">New-York</tei:rs> u. ein ehemaliger Schüler, jetzt Prof. in <tei:rs key="entity-004164" type="place">St. Gallen</tei:rs>: ich habe abgelehnt.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Schreibe also Näheres über deine Sorgen, ich bitte darum. . . Nächstens bitten wir deine
     <tei:rs key="entity-000909" type="person">Schwester</tei:rs> zu uns, vielleicht weiß sie
    etwas.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Nun sei mit den deinen aufs allerherzlichste wie immer gegrüßt! Machst du dir schon
    Vorstellungen über den Sommer? </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute><tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">LieLiechen</tei:rs> schreibt u. schreibt
     u. schreibt, feilt u. feilt u. feilt, grüßt u. grüßt u. grüßt, u. mit<tei:note type="editorial">corr</tei:note> auch dein</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H</tei:rs></tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1925-05-04">4. Mai 1925</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Fl</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Enclosed are five dollars, as reimbursement for your outlay for the copies of
     <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>.
    A thousand thanks. It is high time that the order is made and the <tei:hi rend="double-underline">receipt</tei:hi> sent to me. In <tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:date when="1925-07">July</tei:date></tei:hi>
    <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> will have to show his accounts! Do
    not forget:<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> the <tei:rs key="entity-001740" type="work"><tei:hi rend="triple-underline">very first</tei:hi>
     <tei:hi rend="underline">issue</tei:hi></tei:rs> ever of <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs> dates from the year
     <tei:date when="1921">1921</tei:date>; otherwise all efforts would be in vain. <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> is actually giving the impression that he is
    no longer offering <tei:rs key="entity-001740" type="work">issue no. 1</tei:rs>, treating it as
    a piece of work in which no one seems any longer to be interested; from the copies that are
    sold, however, he in fact pockets <tei:supplied reason="clarity">the profits</tei:supplied>
    himself.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Apparently the situation is such that <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> has entrusted his representative Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000779" type="person">Robert Scheu</tei:rs> with the business dealings. <tei:rs key="entity-000779" type="person">Scheu</tei:rs> is first studying the papers. What will come then, I do not know. </tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs> was with at our place in
    the evening, a few weeks ago. I made <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs>
    (who tells me that he has since written to you) come along as a "witness," and it was worth the
    effort. For it <tei:pb n="2"/> turned out that <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs> does not know actually know what a "<tei:term>sonata form
     movement</tei:term>" is. Specifically, he includes <tei:term>adagio movements</tei:term> in
     <tei:term>sonatas</tei:term> and <tei:term>symphonies</tei:term>! But the special
     <tei:term>form</tei:term> of a <tei:term>sonata movement</tei:term> has <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">been</tei:add> unknown to him; since that evening, of
    course, he know what it is. That does not prevent him from receiving 70 million Kronen for
     <tei:hi rend="underline">an</tei:hi> evening in <tei:rs key="entity-002873" type="place">New
     York</tei:rs>; three such evenings per week add up to 210 million, plus what he receives on the
    other evenings of the weeks. Can you understand, then, why German musicians are flocking to
     <tei:rs key="entity-002873" type="place">New York</tei:rs>, by ship, by airplane, etc?</tei:p>

   <tei:p>And now I come to the question that I have been meaning to ask you for a long time but
    have always suppressed. You have written already twice about your worries about your affairs,
    which torment you; how am I to understand these. Have you suffered a lost of pupil numbers? That
    is indeed generally the case. One no longer cares about learning, not properly. Pupils want to
    take a short route, to begin today and to earn their laurel wreaths of gold as "the most refined
    pianist" already by the following day! <tei:pb n="3"/> It is the general characteristic of
    today's money-driven times. I too am taking fewer <tei:supplied reason="clarity">pupils</tei:supplied> than I did last year. Or is it that you cannot raise your fees to keep
    up with the rising cost of living: is that it? I experience the same thing. I dare not ask for
    more than five dollars; in the meantime, everything has become more expensive. <tei:supplied reason="clarity">A holiday in</tei:supplied> Galtür now costs as much as 90–100,000 Kronen per
    day; last year we were paying 70,000. I am powerless against this. Or are your troubles of a
    different kind?</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:rs key="entity-002448" type="organization">Simrock</tei:rs> initially accepted
     <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs>, then turned him down after all, with
    the impudent remark that his <tei:rs key="entity-004627" type="composition">Sextet</tei:rs>
    represented "<tei:quote>nothing new</tei:quote>." "<tei:soCalled>New</tei:soCalled>," bad: it
    makes no difference; all that matters is a certain amount of business.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In the second half of the <tei:date when="1925-05">month</tei:date>, you will
    receive the new <tei:supplied reason="clarity"><tei:rs key="entity-000738" type="person">Rothberger</tei:rs></tei:supplied> medallion of me; <tei:rs key="entity-000327" type="person">Hammer</tei:rs>'s mezzotint <tei:supplied reason="clarity">portrait</tei:supplied> is not yet
    finished.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">At the moment I am embarking on the <tei:pb n="4"/> last section of my work
    on the "<tei:rs key="entity-001750" type="work"><tei:title>Yearbook</tei:title></tei:rs>." There
    is still a great deal of work to do by the end of <tei:date when="1925-06">June</tei:date>; then
    we shall probably want to take a break, whether we wish to or not. A teacher from <tei:rs key="entity-002873" type="place">New York</tei:rs> and a former pupil of mine who is now a
    professor in <tei:rs key="entity-004164" type="place">St. Gallen</tei:rs> want to accompany me
    to <tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs>; I turned them down.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Write to me in greater detail about your troubles – please do this. We shall soon invite
    your <tei:rs key="entity-000909" type="person">sister</tei:rs> to us; perhaps she knows
    something.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>For now, accept on behalf of your family, our most cordial greetings, as ever! Do you yet
    have plans for the summer?</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute><tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs> writes and writes and
     writes, refines and refines and refines, greets and greets and greets, and with her also
     your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H</tei:rs></tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1925-05-04">May 4, 1925</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>