<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="953" sdoID="OJ-6-7_35">OJ 6/7, [35]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
      <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-06-14" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002720">ViolinM ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002721">ViolinM+V ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002722">ViolinM+V+F ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Violin, dated August 5, 1927</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1927-08-05T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2013-06-14</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>In a wide-ranging letter, Schenker underscores the importance of his friend's
        taking a holiday, and tries to persuade him to visit him in Galtür. There he was visited by
        Reinhard Oppel, who has been appointed to a theory post at the Leipzig Conservatory, where
        he will teach from Schenker's texts. He comments at length on the decline of society, as
        exemplified by the July Revolt. The second Meisterwerk volume has gone to the bookbinders;
        until it is published, he will be working on Der freier Satz.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:date when="1927-08-05">5. 8.
          27</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Fl</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is not recorded
            in Schenker's diary.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Zunächst sei dem Frl. <tei:rs key="entity-000909" type="person">Fanny</tei:rs> für ihre l. Karte<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Not known to survive, recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/9, p. 3097 (August
          3, 1927): "Von Fanny Violin (Ansichtsk.): Grüße aus Hamburg u. kurzer Bericht über das
          Haus" ("From Fanny Violin (picture postcard): greetings from Hamburg and short report on
          the family.")</tei:note> herzlichst gedankt, – immerhin ein Lebenszeichen u. ein Bericht.
        Ich möchte aber gern noch mehr wissen: Es hieß ja daß du auf Ferien gehst. wirst du fort
        oder nicht? Wenn nicht, wegen des l. <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Karli</tei:rs> oder wegen Geldmangels? Ich brauche dir nicht zu sagen, wie nötig auch für
        dich eine Erholung ist. Vielleicht kommst du um die <tei:sic>Weichnachtszeit</tei:sic> nach
          <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs>, wie du es (wenn ich nicht irre) im
        Vorjahre plantest? Und wie steht es mit der gewissen Angelegenheit? In den Blättern finde
        ich noch gar nichts. Könnte nicht auch <tei:rs key="entity-000798" type="person">Schönberg</tei:rs> im Ministerium ein Wort sagen? Er führt ja (so sonderbar es auch ist)
        das große Wort u. ich zweifle nicht, daß er für dich eintritt. Vielleicht bedient <tei:pb n="2"/> er sich einer Mittelperson. Übrigens: hier war Ende <tei:date when="1927-07">Juli</tei:date> Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000643" type="person">Oppel</tei:rs> (bisher in
          <tei:rs key="entity-002757" type="place">Kiel</tei:rs>) zu Besuch; er wurde, trotzdem er
        schon 48 Jahre zählt, an das <tei:rs key="entity-002872" type="organization">Konservatorium</tei:rs> in <tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:rs key="entity-002479" type="place">Leipzig</tei:rs></tei:hi> berufen, wo er alle
        <tei:term>Theorie</tei:term>-Fächer lehren wird (nebenbei: nach meinen Bänden). Allerdings
        ist das <tei:rs key="entity-002872" type="organization">Leipziger Cons.</tei:rs> keine
        staatliche Hochschule (oder?), doch fällt mir auf daß das Alter kein Hinderniß war. <tei:rs key="entity-000643" type="person">Oppel</tei:rs> übersiedelt nach <tei:rs key="entity-002479" type="place">Leipzig</tei:rs> (6000 MK Gehalt) u. verspricht sich
        Privatstunden. Er wird mich End <tei:date when="1927-12">Dez.</tei:date> in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> besuchen, u da um diese Zeit auch <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs> noch in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> sein dürfte, so könnte es ja ganz lustig werden, wenn auch du
        kämst.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Die Ereignisse in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs>
        haben mich entsetzt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">The
          so-called "July Revolt." On <tei:date when="1927-07-27">July 27, 1927</tei:date>, a day on
          which the city of Vienna came to a standstill as a result of industrial action, civil
          unrest boiled over and the Palace of Justice was set on fire by demonstrators seeking
          vengeance for the acquittal earlier that month of three right-wing "Frontkämpfer" accused
          of murder during a disturbance in the village of Schattendorf in Burgenland at the
          beginning of the year. To quell the uprising, the police fired into the crowd, killing 89
          demonstrators.</tei:note> Wer weiß, wie sie sich noch auswirken werden. Jedenfalls
        bedeuten sie einen Schritt näher dem Abgrund. Die Deutschen stürzen rasch, die Deutschen
        überhaupt meine ich, – in weniger als 10 Jahren wird das Juden-Schicksal auf jeder deutschen
        Stirn genau so zu lesen sein, wie auf jeder <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#HS">d</tei:del> jüdischen Stirn. Sie zanken um <tei:pb n="3"/>
        <tei:rs key="entity-002907" type="person">Luther</tei:rs>, sie zanken um <tei:rs key="entity-000578" type="person">Marx</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs key="entity-000519" type="person">Lenin</tei:rs>, <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">um Krieg oder
          Frieden</tei:add>, usw. u. merken nicht, daß ihnen die menschenfresserischen Völker Land
        u. Menschen aus dem Leibe reißen. Sie opfern sich für jeden
          „<tei:soCalled>Fortschritt</tei:soCalled>“, für jedes Volk, u. merken nicht, daß sie
        gestorben sind, daß an ihnen fortgesetzt Leichenschändung getrieben wird. Wenn zum ersten
        Ahasver noch ein zweiter sich gesellt, dann ist es um diese Legende getan. Man weiß, wie es
        zugeht: Mangel an Stolz auf die Heimat, die eigene Religion, die eigene Kunst, ein ewiges
        Nachlaufen minderwertigen Pack gegenüber.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich stehe vor dem Imprimatur schon einen Monat, u. warte noch immer
        vergebens. In diesen Tagen hatte ich das <tei:rs key="entity-001751" type="work"><tei:title>Jb. II</tei:title></tei:rs> endlich der Buchbinderei übergeben zu können. Im
          <tei:date when="1927-09">September</tei:date> dürfte des ausgegeben werden. (Inzwischen
        arbeite ich am „<tei:rs key="entity-001728" type="work"><tei:title>Freien
          Satz</tei:title></tei:rs>“).</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> Uns stehen noch einige Besuche hier bevor. Schade aber, daß du nicht
        gekommen <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">bist</tei:add>
        <tei:note type="editorial">corr</tei:note>! Z.B. ein Tag, wie der heute, würde dich für ein
        ½ Jahr gesund machen, so wohltätig schön ist er, eine erste Sommer-Schönheit erseten
        Ranges.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Entschließe dich, bitte, zu ein paar Zeilen eines Berichtes darüber, wie es um dich u.
        all die l. deinen steht. Mit großer Freude nahmen wir den immerhin günstigen Bericht deiner
          <tei:rs key="entity-000909" type="person">Schwester</tei:rs> über den l. <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Karli</tei:rs> zur Kenntnis. O, ich begreife den Jungen,
        wie er sich von dem Ort seines Verderbens fortsehnt u. nach einem weicherem Ort hin.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Und viele, viele Grüße von mir u. <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">LieLiechen</tei:rs> Euch Allen, Allen</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-55">dein</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-65"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:date when="1927-08-05">August 5,
          1927</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">First of all, most cordial thanks to <tei:rs key="entity-000909" type="person">Fanny</tei:rs> for her lovely postcard<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> – at least, a sign of life and a report. But I should like to know still
        more. It says that you are going on holiday: are you going away or not? If not, on account
        of your dear son <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Karl</tei:rs> or on account of
        financial hardship? I need not tell you how important a period of recovery is, for you too.
        Perhaps you will come to <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs> over the
        Christmas holidays, as (if I am not mistaken) you had planned the year before. And how do
        things stand with that certain matter: in the newspapers, I can still find nothing at all.
        Could not <tei:rs key="entity-000798" type="person">Schoenberg</tei:rs>, too, put in a word
        for you at the Ministry. His words carry a lot of weight (as strange as they are), and I do
        not doubt that he would support your cause. Perhaps he could avail himself <tei:pb n="2"/>
        of a go-between. Moreover: at the end of <tei:date when="1927-07">July</tei:date>, Prof.
          <tei:rs key="entity-000643" type="person">Oppel</tei:rs> (until now in <tei:rs key="entity-002757" type="place">Kiel</tei:rs>) was visiting us here; in spite of being
        already 48 years old, he has been appointed to the <tei:rs key="entity-002872" type="organization">Conservatory</tei:rs> in <tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:rs key="entity-002479" type="place">Leipzig</tei:rs></tei:hi>, where he will teach all
        branches of music <tei:term>theory</tei:term> (by the way: on the basis of my books).
        Admittedly, the <tei:rs key="entity-002872" type="organization">Leipzig
          Conservatory</tei:rs> is not a state Hochschule (or is it?), but I am struck by the fact
        that his age was not an obstacle. <tei:rs key="entity-000643" type="person">Oppel</tei:rs>
        is moving to <tei:rs key="entity-002479" type="place">Leipzig</tei:rs> (salary of 6000
        marks) and promises himself private lessons <tei:supplied reason="clarity">with
          me</tei:supplied>. He will visit me in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs> at the end of <tei:date when="1927-12">December</tei:date>; and since
          <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs> is also supposed to be
        still in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs> around this time, it could
        be most delightful if you were to come, too.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">The events in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Veinna</tei:rs>
        have shocked me.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> Who knows how things will
        turn out as a result. In any event, they signify one step closer to the abyss. The Germans
        are sinking quickly, I refer to the Germans in general – in less than ten years one will be
        able to read the fate of the Jews on the brow of every German, just as on the brow of every
        Jew. They quarrel over <tei:pb n="3"/>
        <tei:rs key="entity-002907" type="person">Luther</tei:rs>, they quarrel over <tei:rs key="entity-000578" type="person">Marx</tei:rs> and <tei:rs key="entity-000519" type="person">Lenin</tei:rs>, <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">over war and
          peace</tei:add>, etc., and do not observe that the cannibalistic peoples are tearing land
        and people from their body. They sacrifice themselves for every
          "<tei:soCalled>progress</tei:soCalled>," for every people, and do not observe that they
        are dead, that the desecration of corpses continues to be perpetrated upon them. If to a
        first Ahasuerus a second is joined, then it is done for sake of this legend. One knows how
        it will proceed: lack of pride in one's country, one's own religion, one's own art, an
        eternal chase after an inferior pack.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I have been awaiting the imprimatur for a month already, and am still
        waiting in vain. In the last few days I was finally able to hand over the <tei:rs key="entity-001751" type="work">second <tei:title>Yearbook</tei:title></tei:rs> to the
        bookbinder. In <tei:date when="1927-09">September</tei:date> it is supposed to be published.
        (In the meantime, I am working on <tei:rs key="entity-001728" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Der freie Satz</tei:title></tei:rs>.)</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> We are still expecting a few visitors here. A pity, though, that you
        did not come<tei:note type="editorial">corr</tei:note>! For example, a day like today would
        make you healthy for half a year, as it is so beneficently beautiful here, a summer beauty
        of the first rank.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Please resolve to write a few lines of a report on how things are with you and all your
        loved ones. It was with great pleasure that we received the report – at least a favorable
        one – from your <tei:rs key="entity-000909" type="person">sister</tei:rs> concerning dear
        little <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Karl</tei:rs>. Oh, I can understand how the
        boy is yearning to leave the place of his ruin and wants to get to a more tender
        land.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>And many, many greetings from me and <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs> to every one of you.</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-55">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-65"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>