<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2248" sdoID="OJ-6-5_2">OJ 6/5, [2]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="major">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="JK" scope="major">Jenny Kornfeld's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2019</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2019</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2011-06-02" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002720">ViolinM ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002722">ViolinM+V+F ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten double letter from Heinrich Schenker and Jenny Kornfeld to Moriz Violin,
        dated August 26, 1911</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1911-08-26T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-07-19</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>With Heinrich and Jenny Kornfeld still in Sulden (Tyrol), Heinrich alludes to
        the uncertainty about their return on account of a recent storm and destruction to the road;
        — they have decided that, on return to Vienna, Jenny shall stay in a hotel until an
        apartment is found for her; — Violin is asked to mail a letter to Schenker's attorney which
        concerns Jenny's maintenance payments; Jenny reports that she is unrecognized in
        Sulden.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Colli; parcels; Notbrücke; temporary bridge; Quartiermacher; landlord; Quartier;
        accommodation; Blühen; flowers; Hotel; Zimmer; room; Nähe; neighborhood; Advokat; attorney;
        Rate; installment; Schwierigkeiten; difficulties; Adresse; address</dc:subject>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JKornfeld</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:div type="part_1">
        <tei:opener>
          <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>L. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913"><tei:hi
                rend="italic">Fl</tei:hi></tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
              place="foot">The writing of this letter is not recorded in Schenker's
              diary.</tei:note></tei:salute>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:p>Das war eine Überraschung, deine Karte von heute,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
            type="editorial" place="foot">This postcard is not known to survive. The reference to
            "Klammer 'günstig'" is therefore unclear.</tei:note> zumal die Klammer „günstig“. Nun
          müssen wir uns diese kurze Notiz genug sein lassen, besser als keine, besser als eine
          ungünstige.</tei:p>

        <tei:p>Was uns hier ereilt hat,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"
            >Schenker's diary records that a major storm struck the Sulden area on August 22,
            causing rock falls (moraines), washing out roads, and leaving communications broken for
            several days. The Schenkers were unable to leave Sulden until August 31.</tei:note> hast
          du aus der Zeitung wohl schon entnommen. Wir schwanken zwischen Aufteilung der <tei:hi
            rend="lateinschr">Colli</tei:hi>, um sie (unter 50kg.) postfähig zu machen, u. dem
          Abwarten von Notbrücken zwischen <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Gomagoi</tei:hi> u. <tei:hi
            rend="lateinschr">Prad</tei:hi>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial"
            place="foot">Gomagoi: Gomagoi: village (1,275m) 11km (6½ miles) north-northwest of
            Sulden, in the South Tyrol. It lies in the Trafoi Valley at the point where the Sulden
            Valley branches off to the south-southeast toward Sulden; Prad: Prad am Stilfser Joch:
            9km (5 miles) north-north-east of Sulden. For both of these, see Schenker's diary for
            August and September 1911.</tei:note> Ich bin für das erstere u. ich glaube, daß wir
          heute packen werden, um die großen <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Colli</tei:hi> an unsere
          Quartiermacher nach <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Wien</tei:hi> abzusenden. (Regnet es doch
          heute neuerdings in Strömen!)</tei:p>

        <tei:p>Wegen des Quartiers haben wir beschlossen: <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
            >Lie-Liechen</tei:rs> soll doch lieber in ein Hotel für ein paar Tage; bei mir kann sie
          nicht installiert werden, weil ich ja Besuche zu empfangen habe, u. sie soll doch
            Blühen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Blühen: presumably
            plants in soil (dug up in the Sulden area), which would now need to be
            watered.</tei:note>
          <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">etc</tei:hi>. bequem auspacken u. zur Hand haben können. Vom
          Hotel aus werden wir meine Umgebung absuchen, eventuell <tei:rs type="place"
            key="entity-002277"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Reisner</tei:hi>str.</tei:rs> 29<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Since Heinrich had not previously
            lived at No. 29, this may imply that Jenny had done so. No. 29 was a two-storey building
            with nineteen apartments, owned by Josef Legat.</tei:note> für nur sehr kurze Zeit noch
          einmal beziehen, um erst <tei:pb n="2"/> dann die letzte Anordnung zu treffen. Daher
          ergeht an dich die Bitte, im Lehmann<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial"
            place="foot">Lehmann: the Vienna street directory, <tei:title level="m">Adolph Lehmann’s
              allgemeiner Wohnungs-Anzeiger</tei:title>.</tei:note> nachzusehen, wie das <tei:hi
            rend="lateinschr">Hotel</tei:hi> in der <tei:hi rend="lateinschr underline"
            >Beatrix</tei:hi>gasse<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot"
            >Beatrixgasse: district III (Landstraße), runs from Am Heumarkt to the Landstraße
            Hauptstraße, crossing the Reisnerstraße and the Rechte Bahngasse. The address of the
            Hotel-Restaurant Beatrix was Vienna III, Hauptstraße 10/12, entrance on the Beatrixgasse
            60.</tei:note> (nahe der <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002308">Hauptstrasse</tei:rs>)
          heißt ‒ ich glaube „<tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Beatrix</tei:hi>hof“‒, dort könnte sie ihre
            <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Colli</tei:hi> entgegennehmen, u. ein Zimmer beziehen. Sie
          möchte in meiner Nähe sein, u. die Landstrasse hat ja leider keine <tei:hi
            rend="lateinschr">Hotels</tei:hi> in meiner Gegend. Soll sie einfach vorfahren, oder
          schon von hier aus bestellen? Ich glaube, Ersteres wäre besser, weil sie sonst, nach
            <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002256">Sulden</tei:rs> taxiert, sofort „nur 1. Etage“
          oder dgl. erhalten würde, während sie ein einfaches Zimmerchen braucht. Meinst du nicht
          auch?</tei:p>

        <tei:p>Du wirst ferner ersucht, beiliegenden Brief an den Advok. abzusenden, worin er
          angewiesen wird, der Septemberrate <tei:hi rend="underline">zu deinen Händen</tei:hi>
          einzusenden. Der Alte ist nämlich in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002386"
            >Winzendorf</tei:rs>, u. wir haben keine Zeit mehr, Frage u. Antwort durchzusetzen, wie
          lange sie dort bleibt, ob sie dort auch <tei:del rend="overstrike">die</tei:del> zum
            3<tei:hi rend="supralinear">ten</tei:hi> Mal eine Rate entgegennehmen könnte
          u.s.w.</tei:p>

        <tei:p>So ist einfacher. Ebenso eventuelle Nachricht auch sonstigen Inhalts <tei:pb n="3"/>
          per <tei:hi rend="underline">deine</tei:hi> Adresse. Wir sind <tei:add
            place="interlinear-above">ja</tei:add> bald in Wien, u. da hat diese Verlegenheit eine
          Ende. Freilich, der größere steht noch aus. Doch darüber lieber mündlich.</tei:p>

        <tei:p>Ist Wien einigermaßen erträglicher geworden?</tei:p>

        <tei:p>Soviel in Eile, da wir zur Post laufen müssen, um <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
            >uns</tei:add> den Schwierigkeiten anzubequemen.</tei:p>


        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Beste Grüße an dich, Olly<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09"
              type="editorial" place="foot">Olly, Frau Olli: cf. "Frau O." in Schenker's diary for
              September 12, 1911; seemingly someone with whom Moriz Violin was in a relationship.
              See also <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-6-5_1">OJ 6/5, [1]</tei:ref>, August
              18, 1911.</tei:note> u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000909"
            >Fanny</tei:rs></tei:salute>
          <tei:signed rend="indent-60">Dein <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"><tei:hi
                rend="italic">H.</tei:hi></tei:rs>
          </tei:signed><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
          <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1911-08-26">26. 8. 1911</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        </tei:closer>
      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="part_2">
        <tei:opener>
          <tei:salute><tei:pb n="4"/><tei:handShift new="#JK"/>Sehr geehrter lieber Herr <tei:rs
              type="person" key="entity-000913">Professor</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:p rend="first">Der l. Heinrich vergaß zu erwähnen, daß eine <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000771">Frau Kornfeld</tei:rs> in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002256"
            >Sulden</tei:rs> nicht bekannt ist, ein<tei:supplied reason="agreement">e</tei:supplied>
          Antwort des <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000288">D<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
              >r.</tei:hi> Glässner</tei:rs> also unter der Adr. Schenker hierher gelangen
          soll!</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">In Eile wünsche ich nun daß <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
            >sich</tei:add>, was Sie so plötzlich nach W. gerufen im allergünstigsten<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn10" type="editorial" place="foot">"allergünstigen": intensified allusion
            to "günstig" in Violin's postcard.</tei:note> Sinne erledige, grüße Sie, Frau Olli u.
          Fr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000909">Fanny</tei:rs></tei:p>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute>herzlichst Ihre</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
            >Lie-Lie</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>

      </tei:div>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:div type="part_1">
        <tei:opener>
          <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913"
              >Floriz</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:p>Your postcard of today<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> came as a
          surprise, especially the parenthetical "auspicious." We will have to make this short note
          sufficient for now ‒ better than none at all, better than inauspicious.</tei:p>

        <tei:p>You will surely already have gathered from the newspaper what has befallen us
            here.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> We vacillate between dividing
          things up into parcels so as to make them eligible for posting (50 kg.) and waiting for
          temporary bridges to be constructed between Gomagoi and Prad.<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> I am for the former, and I believe that we will
          pack today so as to dispatch the large parcels to our landlady in Vienna. (We have a yet
          another heavy downpour going on today!)</tei:p>

        <tei:p>We have made up our minds concerning accommodation. <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000771">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs> will for preference definitely <tei:supplied
            reason="clarity">book</tei:supplied> into a hotel for a few days. We cannot install her
          at my place because I have to receive visitors, and she needs to be able to unpack
            plants<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> etc. in comfort and have them to
          hand. From the hotel we will explore my neighborhood, possibly once more occupying <tei:rs
            type="place" key="entity-002277">Reisnerstraße</tei:rs> 29<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06"
            type="footnote"/> for only a very short time, so as <tei:pb n="2"/> then to come up with
          a definitive solution. Accordingly, please will you look up in Lehmann<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> what the name of the hotel in the <tei:hi
            rend="underline">Beatrix</tei:hi>gasse<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/>
          (close to the <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002308">Hauptstraße</tei:rs>) is ‒ I have
          an idea it's the "Beatrixhof"? There she could receive her parcels and take a room. She
          would like to be in my neighborhood, but there are unfortunately no hotels in my part of
          the Landstraße district. Should she simply come on spec, or make a reservation from here
          in advance? I think the former would be better because, calling from <tei:rs type="place"
            key="entity-002256">Sulden</tei:rs> she would promptly be offered "first floor only" or
          the like, whereas all she needs is a simple, small room. Don't you agree?</tei:p>

        <tei:p>You are further requested to mail the enclosed letter to the attorney, in which he is
          instructed to deliver the September installment <tei:hi rend="underline">into your
            hands</tei:hi>. The old fellow is in fact in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002386"
            >Winzendorf</tei:rs>, and we have no time to get embroiled in an argument as to how long
          she will stay there, whether for yet a third time she could receive an installment there,
          and so on.</tei:p>

        <tei:p>It is simpler that way. Likewise, possible news, even with other contents, <tei:pb
            n="3"/> via <tei:hi rend="underline">your</tei:hi> address. We will <tei:add
            place="interlinear-above">very</tei:add> soon be in Vienna, and then this confusion will
          be at an end. Admittedly, the bigger one is still to come. But more about that when we
          next meet.</tei:p>

        <tei:p>Is Vienna any less insufferable?</tei:p>

        <tei:p>In great haste since we must run to the post in order to prepare <tei:add
            place="interlinear-above">ourselves</tei:add> for the difficulties <tei:supplied
            reason="clarity">ahead</tei:supplied>.</tei:p>


        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Beste Grüße an dich, Olly<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09"
              type="footnote"/> u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000909"
            >Fanny</tei:rs></tei:salute>
          <tei:signed rend="indent-60">Dein <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"><tei:hi
                rend="italic">H.</tei:hi></tei:rs>
          </tei:signed><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
          <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1911-08-26">26. 8. 1911</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        </tei:closer>
      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="part_2">
        <tei:opener>
          <tei:salute><tei:pb n="4"/><tei:handShift new="#JK"/>Very dear <tei:rs type="person"
              key="entity-000913">Professor</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:p rend="first">Dear Heinrich forgot to mention that a <tei:rs type="place"
            key="entity-000771">Mrs Kornfeld</tei:rs> in not known in <tei:rs type="place"
            key="entity-002256">Sulden</tei:rs>; accordingly an answer from <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000288">Dr. Glässner</tei:rs> sent here must be addressed in the name of
          Schenker!</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">In haste, I hope that that which summoned you to Vienna so suddenly
          sorts <tei:add place="interlinear-above">itself</tei:add> out in the most auspicious
            manner.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn10" type="footnote"/> I send greetings to you, Olli,
          and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000909">Fanny</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute>Most cordially, your</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
            >Lie-Lie</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        </tei:closer>


      </tei:div>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
