<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="936" sdoID="OJ-6-7_16">OJ 6/7, [16]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
   <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2013</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2013-06-05" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002720">ViolinM ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002721">ViolinM+V ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002722">ViolinM+V+F ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated January 24, 1925</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1925-01-24T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2013-06-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Responding point by point to Violin's previously letter (OJ 14/45, [41]),
    Schenker congratulates his friend on the success of his recent concert. He writes at length
    about Hertzka's last efforts to hold onto Der Tonwille, and about successful negotiations with
    Drei Masken Verlag over its successor, Das Meisterwerk in der Musik. He has now to prepare
    enough material for a yearbook comprising fifteen gatherings by July 1, so that the volume can
    be published by Christmas. Finally, he echoes Violin's assessment of Hans Weisse, adding a few
    disparaging remarks about his character.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>



  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:add place="margin-top" hand="#HS"><tei:note type="editorial">In top margin:</tei:note> Ja,
     ja, ja, um die Antworten der <tei:abbr>Univers.<tei:ex>itäten</tei:ex></tei:abbr> bitte ich
     sehr, schicke sie mir.</tei:add>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Fl</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is recorded in
      Schenker;'s diary at OJ 3/7, p. 2776–7, January 24, 1925: "An Floriz (Br.): die Karte der
      U.-E. an Frl. Bekker zurück; erkundige mich, ob ihn der Erfolg zum Solospiel ermutigt? Ueber
      die letzten Abenteuer mit der U.-E., über Weisses Charakter als Komponist u. Mensch." ("To
      Floriz (letter): UE's postcard to Miss Becker returned; I ask whether his success emboldens
      him to pursue solo performance? About the latest adventures with UE, about Weisse's character
      as a composer and a person.")</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Vor mir die beiden letzten Briefe von dir, die Karte an Frl. <tei:rs key="entity-000049" type="person">Becker</tei:rs>, u. ein seit einem Monat bereitgehaltenes
    Couvert mit der fertigen Anschrift u. Bfmarken drin. Und nun:</tei:p>

   <tei:p>1. Die Bfmarken sandte mir einmal die <tei:rs key="entity-004623" type="organization">preussische Staatsbibliothek</tei:rs> als Restbetrag ein; ich habe keine Verwendung für sie u.
    schicke sie daher mit.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">These were
     probably sent to Schenker along with photographs of autograph of the opening chorus of Bach's
      <tei:title level="m">St Matthew Passion</tei:title>, the subject of the leading essay in
      <tei:title level="m">Tonwille 10</tei:title>.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>2. Dein Bericht über das Konzert hat mir eine tiefe Freude gebracht. Als solistische
    Production sollte ich erst die Komposit. von <tei:rs key="entity-000619" type="person">M.-Hartmann</tei:rs> verstehen?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Probably <tei:rs key="entity-000619" type="person">Robert Müller-Hartmann</tei:rs>'s <tei:rs key="entity-004624" type="composition"><tei:title level="m">Passacaglia</tei:title></tei:rs>
     for solo piano.</tei:note> Gleichviel, es will dich sehr viel heißen, wenn die so völlig anders
    gerichtetes Spiel, das den Sinn der Massen so sehr entgegensteht, eine solche Wirkung erzielen
    konnte. Wird dich das bestimmen, öfter auch solistisch hervorzutreten? Daß du <tei:rs key="entity-004625" type="organization">Klinglers</tei:rs> Sinn für dein Spiel zeigten, freut
    mich für <tei:hi rend="underline">sie</tei:hi>. Wie immer du die <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>-Erfolge künstlerisch auswertest, die dir ja von Anbeginn treu
    waren, so scheinen sie doch bestimmt zu sein, dir dein äußeres Leben erträglicher zu machen.
     <tei:pb n="2"/> Mußt du schon die Unterrichtstätigkeit fortsetzen, da die solistische Bahn
    materiell nicht lohnend genug wäre, so sind Erfolge so ungewöhnlicher Art als
    Honorar-Coëffiziente sehr willkommen. Einen Erfolg bezahlt man gern auch teuer. Was hast du
    übrigens mit <tei:note type="editorial">name crossed out</tei:note>
    <tei:rs key="entity-004625" type="organization">Klingler’s</tei:rs> gespielt? Sende mir dein
    Programm ein!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">This sentence
     underlined by Violin.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">3. Anbei die Karte <tei:rs key="entity-000049" type="person">Becker</tei:rs>.
    Ich wäre dafür, daß sie die Differenz einfordert u. mir das Ergebnis mitteilt. Denn in meiner
    Abrechnung müsste ja ebenfalls jenen überhohen Satz zufinden sein, wenn er ja gilt. Für alle
    Fälle ersuche Frl. <tei:rs key="entity-000049" type="person">Becker</tei:rs> ihn Beweisstücke
    noch zu behalten. Mir scheint ein Prozess gegen <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> unvermeidlich, früher oder später.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>4. Zuletzt bot mir <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">H.</tei:rs>
    <tei:del rend="overstrike">an</tei:del>, 4 fix zu bezahlende 2-Bogen-Hefte des Jahres an. Schon
    damals hatte ich einen gewissen Rückhalt an den <tei:rs key="entity-002627" type="organization">3 Masken</tei:rs>
    <tei:rs key="entity-002286" type="place">München</tei:rs>, u. so habe ich das Anbot abgelehnt,
    weil es mich, wie D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi>
    <tei:rs key="entity-000048" type="person">Baumgarten</tei:rs> sich im Bfentwurf ausdrückte, vor
    Sabotage doch nicht schützt. Wie sehr ich mit der Ablehnung Recht hatte, konnte ich erst
    gerstern erfahren. <tei:pb n="3"/> Da kommt endlich der so lang erwartete Bf. der <tei:rs key="entity-002627" type="organization">3 Masken</tei:rs> u. enthüllt, das <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">H.</tei:rs>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">von Anbeginn</tei:hi>, statt der vertragsmäßig vorgesehene je 2000 Ex.
    per Heft, <tei:hi rend="underline">blos je 800 Ex.</tei:hi> druckte, also eine Zurückhaltung
    schon vom <tei:rs key="entity-001740" type="work">ersten Heft</tei:rs> ab ins Auge faßte. Darum
    gab er auch keine Annonce, keine Einladung aus. Er bezahlte die 800 Ex. <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">obendrein</tei:add> mit <tei:hi rend="underline">meinem
     eigenen Gelde</tei:hi> (aus den <tei:rs key="entity-001753" type="work">B-Ausgaben</tei:rs>) u.
    brauchte einer kaufmännischen Ausbeutung nicht nachzugehen, da er keine Investition machte. Eine
    Privatangelegenheit, eine nicht zu umgehende Aufmerksamkeit für mich war es, um mich zu
    behalten. so trieb es der Schurke 4 Jahre, machte mich krank, stahl mir Arbeit usw. Erst
    vorgestern schickte er <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">mir</tei:add>, <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">eigentlich</tei:add> die „<tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">U. E.</tei:rs>“, da ich mit <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">H.</tei:rs> längst außer Verkehr bin, seinen Brief an die Sortimenter ein, als Beweis einer
    Propaganda. Seit 4 Jahren wendet er sich zum 1. Mal an die Sortimenter! Was für
    Bubenstück!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Die <tei:rs key="entity-002627" type="organization">3 Masken</tei:rs> können also die 10
    Hefte nicht erreichen, u. da schlagen sie vor, ein <tei:hi rend="underline">15-Bogen</tei:hi>
    (!) starkes (<tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">H.</tei:rs> bot 8 Bg. an)
     <tei:quote>„Jahrbuch von <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">H.
      Sch.</tei:rs><tei:supplied reason="grammar">“</tei:supplied></tei:quote> unter dem titel:
      „<tei:quote><tei:rs key="entity-001749" type="work">Das Meisterwerk in der
     Musik</tei:rs></tei:quote>“, <tei:pb n="4"/> den ich selbst vorschlug. Ob ein Abonnement bei
    einem „Jahrbuch“ oder nur eine Einladung auf Subscription erfolgen wird, weiß ich nicht. Bald
    sende ich meine Zustimmung zur neuen Form ein, dann kommt der Vertrag, dann
      <tei:abbr>ev.<tei:ex>entuell</tei:ex></tei:abbr> gleich die Unterschrift oder eine kleine
    Untersendung dazwischen, jeden- falls dann eine fürchterliche Arbeit: 15 Bogen bis <tei:date when="1925-07-01">1. Juli</tei:date>, damit zu <tei:date when="1925-12-25">Weihnachten</tei:date> das <tei:rs key="entity-001750" type="work">erste Jahrbuch</tei:rs>
    vorliegen kann. Furchtbar. Mit 32 Mill. Kr. jährlich hätte ich eine Vierteljahresschrift
    unabhängig von allen Verlegern der Welt mir leisten <tei:supplied reason="clarity">können</tei:supplied> u. reden dürfen, daß die Ozeane u. Erdteile zittern. Aber <tei:hi rend="underline">für mich</tei:hi> wächst nirgen<tei:supplied reason="spelling">d</tei:supplied>s Geld, der Stern, unter dem ich geboren bin, war jedenfalls der Merkur
    nicht.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">5. Mit <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs> hast du
    recht. Er sagte mir es selbst, daß er „<tei:quote>nicht ursprünglich ist u. mir Alles
     verdankt</tei:quote>,“ aber er hat Intelligenz u. Ausdauer, um zu schreiben. Ein <tei:rs key="entity-004627" type="composition">Sextett</tei:rs> kommt jetzt, ich kenne es noch nicht.
    Als Mench ist er ohne Wärme, eigensüchtig, empfindlich, u. kümmert sich wenig darum, was er den
    Anderen antut. Eitel, sehr eitel; Bescheiden? ja u. nein; feige ganz bestimmt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">No paragraph-break in
    source.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p> Nun aber schließe ich. Bis <tei:rs key="entity-002627" type="organization">3
     Masken</tei:rs> bereinigt sind, schreibe ich sofort.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">No paragraph-break in source.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-45">Viele, viele Grüße dir, deiner Frau, deinen Kleinen von mir u.
      <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">LieLiechen</tei:rs></tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">dein</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-75"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H</tei:rs></tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1925-01-24">24. I. 1925</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>



  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:add place="margin-top" hand="#HS"><tei:note type="editorial">In top margin:</tei:note> Yes,
     please: I entreat you to send me the replies from the universities.</tei:add>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">I have in front of me your last two letters, the card addressed to Miss
     <tei:rs key="entity-000049" type="person">Becker</tei:rs>, and an envelope that I addressed a
    month ago with stamps enclosed.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>1. The stamps were sent to me some time ago by the <tei:rs key="entity-004623" type="organization">Prussian State Library</tei:rs>, as left over from a payment that I made. I
    have no use for them and am thus enclosing them.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>2. Your report about the concert brought a deep joy to me. I suppose that your soloistic
    production was the performance of the composition by <tei:rs key="entity-000619" type="person">Müller-Hartmann</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> At any rate, it
    means a great deal if a manner of playing that points in a direction so different from that
    understood by the masses can achieve such an effect. Would that make you determined to perform
    more often in public, also as a soloist? That you demonstrated the <tei:rs key="entity-004625" type="organization">Klingler Quartet</tei:rs>'s understanding of your way pleases me, for
     <tei:hi rend="underline">their</tei:hi> sake. However you may evaluate from an artistic
    standpoint your <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> successes, which were
    indeed from the outset fully deserved, they at least seem guaranteed to make your everyday life
    more bearable. <tei:pb n="2"/> If you must continue your activities as a teacher, because the
    soloistic path is not sufficiently rewarding from a material point of view, then successes of
    such an uncommon nature are still very welcome as honorary coefficients. One gladly pays dearly
    for a success. By the way, what did you play with the <tei:rs key="entity-004625" type="organization">Klingers</tei:rs>? Send me a program!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">3. I enclose the card <tei:supplied reason="clarity">from <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">Universal Edition</tei:rs></tei:supplied> to Miss
     <tei:rs key="entity-000049" type="person">Becker</tei:rs>. I would be in favor of her demanding
    that she be repaid the difference and to tell me the result. For in my reckoning the amount
    overpaid should be found, if it is indeed an overpayment. In any event, persuade Miss <tei:rs key="entity-000049" type="person">Becker</tei:rs> to hang on to the receipts. Court proceedings
    against <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs>, sooner or later, seem to me
    unavoidable.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>4. Most recently <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> offered me
    four issues, each comprising two gatherings, to be paid at a fixed rate. Even then I had a
    certain commitment to <tei:rs key="entity-002627" type="organization">Drei Masken
     Verlag</tei:rs> in <tei:rs key="entity-002286" type="place">Munich</tei:rs>, and so I declined
    his offer as it would still not protect me from sabotage, as Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000048" type="person">Baumgarten</tei:rs> expressed in the draft letter. How much I was in the right to
    decline is something I learned only yesterday. <tei:pb n="3"/> It was then that the long-awaited
    letter from <tei:rs key="entity-002627" type="organization">Drei Masken Verlag</tei:rs> arrived,
    revealing that <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> – <tei:hi rend="underline">right from the beginning</tei:hi> – <tei:hi rend="underline">had printed only
     800 copies</tei:hi> of each issue, not the 2000 that were contractually planned; that is, he
    was contemplating a reduction right from the <tei:rs key="entity-001740" type="work">first
     issue</tei:rs>. That was why he issued no advertisements, no invitation to subscription.
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">Moreover,</tei:add> he paid for the 800 copies
    with <tei:hi rend="underline">my own money</tei:hi>, from the profits from the <tei:rs key="entity-001753" type="work">Beethoven edition</tei:rs>; and he had need to make any
    financial outlay, since he was making no investment <tei:supplied reason="clarity">in the
     project</tei:supplied>. It was a private matter, a unavoidable courtesy to me, to keep me on.
    And so the scoundrel carried on for four years, making me ill, stealing my work, etc. Not until
    yesterday did he – or <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">rather</tei:add>
    <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">Universal Edition</tei:rs>, since I have not had
    any direct contact with <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> for some time
    – send <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">me</tei:add> his letter to the book
    retailers, as proof of that he is advertising my work. After four years, he approaches the book
    retailers for the first time: what a knavish trick!</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:rs key="entity-002627" type="organization">Drei Masken</tei:rs> cannot publish as
    many as ten issues, and so they suggest a <tei:quote>"yearbook by <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Heinrich Schenker</tei:rs>"</tei:quote> comprising <tei:hi rend="underline">fifteen gatherings</tei:hi> (<tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs>
    offered eight gatherings <tei:supplied reason="clarity">per year</tei:supplied>) and called
      "<tei:quote><tei:rs key="entity-001749" type="work">Das Meisterwerk in der
     Musik</tei:rs></tei:quote>," <tei:pb n="4"/> a title I myself suggested. Whether a
    subscription, or merely an invitation to subscription, will follow in the case of a "Yearbook"
    is something that I do not know. I shall send my word of agreement for the new format; a
    contract will then follow, then perhaps I shall sign immediately or send them a provisional
    acceptance letter. In any event, I have an immense amount of work ahead of me: fifteen
    gatherings by <tei:date when="1925-07-01">July 1</tei:date>, so that the <tei:rs key="entity-001750" type="work">first yearbook</tei:rs> can appear by <tei:date when="1925-12-25">Christmas</tei:date>. Frightful. For 32 million Kronen a year, I could have
    afforded <tei:supplied reason="clarity">to publish</tei:supplied> a quarterly journal
    independent of all the publishers in the world and would have been allowed to say things that
    would make the oceans and continents tremble. But money <tei:hi rend="underline">for me</tei:hi>
    does not grow anywhere: the star under which I was born was, in any event, not Mercury.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">5. You are right about <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs>. He has himself said that he "<tei:quote>is not original and owes me
     everything</tei:quote>" but he has intelligence, and the persistence to write. A <tei:rs key="entity-004627" type="composition">Sextet</tei:rs> will soon be ready; I have not yet seen
    it. As a person, he is without warmth, self-serving, sensitive, and he is not concerned about
    how his actions affect others. Vain, very vain. Modest? Yes and no; he is most definitely a
     coward.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>But now it is time to close. As soon as the <tei:rs key="entity-002627" type="organization">Drei Masken</tei:rs> business is cleared up, I shall write to you
     immediately.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-45">Many, many greetings to you, your wife, and the children from me
     and <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs>.</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Yours,</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-75"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich
     </tei:rs></tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1925-01-24">January 24, 1925</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>