<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="570" sdoID="OJ-6-7_11">OJ 6/7, [11]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2011</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-10-04" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002720">ViolinM ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002721">ViolinM+V ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002722">ViolinM+V+F ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated November 6, 1924</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1924-11-06T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2011-10-04</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker has received a photographic reproduction of the opening chorus of Bach's
    St Matthew Passion. — Gives account of delays to the publication of Tonwille 8/9 and 10, blaming
    Hertzka for being slow to send work to the engraver, and has written to him with a request to
    dissolve the Tonwille contract with UE. — Refers to a recent review by (Julius) Korngold, and
    recounts a long story about his piano dealer, Bernhard Kohn. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject> </dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:epigraph rend="block">
     <tei:p>Motto: Alle guten Geister zum Gruße, ich meine, die gelebt haben, denn keine werden mehr
      kommen. </tei:p>
    </tei:epigraph>
    <tei:salute><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Fl</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ
      3/7, p. 2751, November 6, 1924: "An Fl. (Br.): Abbitte an Altmann, der sowohl ihm wie mir Wort
      gehalten hat. Erzähle die Leidensgeschichte des Doppelheftes." ("To Floriz (letter): apology
      to Altmann, who kept his word with him as well as with me. I tell him the tale of suffering
      regarding the double issue."). </tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>An erster Stelle muß ich <tei:rs key="entity-000013" type="person">Altm.</tei:rs> Abbitte
    leisten für die Verdächtigung, die ich vorzeitig ausgesprochen. Auch bei mir hat er sich
    eingefunden, vor paar Tagen, mit einer Mitteilung, daß er mir die photographischen Platten der
    autographen Stimmen zur <tei:rs key="entity-001172" type="composition"><tei:title>Matthp.</tei:title></tei:rs> einsandt u. daß ich nur Porto 2 MK zu schicken habe.
    Er hält also seine Zusage ein u. erspart mir 6 Mill. Glücklicherweise werde ich die allfälligen
    Ergebnisse noch in <tei:rs key="entity-001748" type="work">Heft 4/1924</tei:rs>, also in dem
    nächsten, zu verwerten in der Lage sein, wo ich das Geheimnis der ersten Choralph. 12/8 Em.
    lüfte: der Aufsatz steht an der Spitze des Heftes.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The essay on the open chorus of the <tei:title level="m">St Matthew
      Passion</tei:title> in Tonwille 10 does not include any specifically text-critical remarks.
    </tei:note>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi>
    <tei:rs key="entity-000048" type="person">Baumg.</tei:rs> hat die falsche Verrechnung von
     <tei:rs key="entity-002456" type="organization">Gutmann</tei:rs> an <tei:rs key="entity-000049" type="person">Frl Becker</tei:rs> als „Prallerei“ bezeichnet.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">This remark refers to the overcharging of Violin's pupil Agnes
     Becker for a copy of <tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title>. See Violin's letter of
     October 22, 1924 (OJ 14/45, [36]). </tei:note> Es ist am Platz, daß sie das Zuviel verlangte
    zurückfordert. Jedenfalls bitte ich dich, die beiden Belege bei dir zu behalten u. nötigenfalls
    zu meiner Verfügung zu stellen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Hast du vielleicht durch Zufall gelesen, wie <tei:rs key="entity-000471" type="person">Korngold</tei:rs> den H. <tei:rs key="entity-000057" type="person">Becker</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> offentlich
    verprügelt hat?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker is referring
     to a recent essay or review by Julius Korngold, a conservative critic whose music journalism
     Schenker regularly saved in a file of clippings. (Most of the Korngold clippings are in OC File
     C.) The piece by Korngold in closest chronological proximity to the present letter is his
     review of <tei:title level="a">The New Music and Theater Festival</tei:title> in Vienna,
     published in the <tei:title level="j">Neue Freie Presse</tei:title> on October 21, 1924;
     unusually, it is located not in File C but among the correspondence with UE: OC 52/582-583. In
     it, Korngold expresses his distaste for the spread of twelve-tone music among a new generation
     of composers; and while he mentions by name neither Hertzka nor Schenker's long-standing
     adversary in the world of journalism, Paul Bekker, he does acknowledge that his outspoken
     criticism of "contemporary atonal music" has "upset the circles of the party" and occasioned an
     "open letter" addressed to him in "a music journal published by UE," i.e. the <tei:title level="j">Musikblätter des Anbruch</tei:title>. Bekker´s <tei:title level="a">Brief an Julius
      Korngold</tei:title> did appear in the <tei:title level="j">Anbruch</tei:title>, vi/9 (October
     1924) 379-80. </tei:note> Er macht es sehr gut. Das ist die Art, mit diesem Pack umzugehen, das
    vom <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">terror</tei:hi></tei:foreign> lebt u.
    die Abwehr der anderen für <tei:pb n="2"/>
    <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">terror</tei:hi></tei:foreign> erklärt. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Was ist das doch für eine Leidensgeschichte, die des jetzt fälligen <tei:rs key="entity-001747" type="work">Heftes 2/3</tei:rs>! Schon am <tei:date when="1924-08-05"><tei:hi rend="underline">5. August</tei:hi></tei:date> begann <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">H.</tei:rs> einen Teil des Heftes, Vortrag des <tei:rs key="entity-001354" type="composition"><tei:title>Br-Hdl-Var.</tei:title></tei:rs>, zurückzuhalten; unter meinem
    ständigen Druck läßt er ihn setzen u. mir zukommen, gegen <tei:hi rend="underline">Ende
     Sept</tei:hi>; am <tei:date when="1924-10-06"><tei:hi rend="underline">6.</tei:hi>
     <tei:hi rend="underline">Okt.</tei:hi></tei:date> kommt das Heft <tei:hi rend="underline">umbrochen</tei:hi>, da fehlte <tei:hi rend="underline">eine</tei:hi> Figur u. <tei:hi rend="underline">ein</tei:hi> Trillerzeichen (~~); nach 14 Tagen(!) kommt der zweite Umbruch,
    u. dem <tei:hi rend="underline">fehlt noch immer</tei:hi> die Figur u. ~~; ich tobe über diese
    Unverschämtheit – endlich am <tei:date when="1924-10-23">23. X</tei:date> kann ich das
    Imprimatur geben, das Heft ist aber bis heute <tei:date when="1924-11-06">6. XI</tei:date> nicht
    da! Und es könnte schon Anfangs Oktober <tei:del rend="overstrike">her</tei:del> kommen, hätte
    kommen müssen! Und alles das, nur um <tei:rs key="entity-001748" type="work">Heft 4</tei:rs> zu
    verschleppen bis ins J. <tei:date when="1925">1925</tei:date>. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Gerade heute habe ich D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi>
    <tei:rs key="entity-000048" type="person">B</tei:rs>’s Brief an die „<tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">U. E.</tei:rs>“ – mit <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">H.</tei:rs>
    habe ich jeden Verkehr aufgegeben – gerichtet, worin ich ihm Erklärung bezüglich der Lösung des
     „<tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title><tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work">TW.</tei:rs></tei:title></tei:rs> Vertrages“ erbitte. D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi>
    <tei:rs key="entity-000048" type="person">B.</tei:rs> ist sonst dafür, daß ich die Angelgenheit
     <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat"><tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">via
       facti</tei:hi></tei:hi></tei:foreign> austrage, d.h. einfach zu den <tei:rs key="entity-002627" type="organization">3 Masken</tei:rs> oder zu <tei:rs key="entity-002978" type="organization">Piper</tei:rs> gehe, da <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">H.</tei:rs> mich zu verklagen ganz <tei:unclear reason="reading">außerstande</tei:unclear>
    ist, so belastend ist das Material wider ihn. Aber, da hapert’s ja, ich möchte den neuen Verlag
    nicht mit Unannehmlich- <tei:pb n="3"/> keiten belasten u. muß doch befürchten, das <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">H.</tei:rs>, nur aus Rache, etwas wider den neuen Verlag
    unternimmt. Und doch muß ich etwas wagen, denn sonst bringt er mich um den Jahrg. 1925 u. fügt
    zu den bisherigen Schäden von 4 Jahren noch den eines 5. Jahres hiezu. Wüßte ich nur, wie lange
    so ein Prozeß geht! Wenn es kurz gienge, würde es mir Spaß machen, aus ihm Schadenersatz usw.
    herauszuschlagen u. diesen Schurken an den Pranger zu stellen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Übrigens H. <tei:rs key="entity-000456" type="person">Kohn</tei:rs>! Ich stand mit ihm in
    Verbindung seit 1905. Sein <tei:rs key="entity-003033" type="organization">Blüthner</tei:rs>
    stand bei mir 15 Jahren. Als er vor 2 Jahren mit den Steigerungen begann, wollte ich <tei:hi rend="underline">dieses Instr. abkaufen</tei:hi>, gegen einen größeren Betrag auf einmal u.
    Raten auf ein paar Jahre verteilt. Er lehnte ab, weil <tei:rs key="entity-003033" type="organization">Bl.</tei:rs> angeblich nur wenige Instr. hinanschickt, in Wahrheit weil er
    mir das Instr. immerhin billiger hatte abgeben müssen, als einem Nichtmusiker. Er verrät sich
    sogar, indem er sagte: <tei:hi rend="underline">Ihnen</tei:hi> gibt <tei:rs key="entity-003033" type="organization">Bl.</tei:rs> das Instrum. um 20 Mill (damals) usw. Plötzlich zeigt <tei:rs key="entity-000456" type="person">Kohn</tei:rs> ein große Interesse für mein Instr., es müsse
    restauriert werden (nach Bericht des Klavierstimmers), u. da dies 2½ Mill. <tei:pb n="4"/>
    kostet, so müsste er die Kosten durch Steigerung hereinbringen. (Wahrheitsgemäß bezeige ich, daß
    ich blos 150.000 K monatlich zu zahlen hatte, was gewiß entgegenkommend war). Da ich im Sommer
    von dir hörte, wie <tei:rs key="entity-003033" type="organization">Bl.</tei:rs> sich dir
    gegenüber nett betragen, regte ich <tei:rs key="entity-000456" type="person">Kohn</tei:rs> an,
    nachzudenken, ob nicht <tei:hi rend="underline">er</tei:hi> (nach 15 Jahren) zumindest auf
    weitere Steigerungen verzichten könnte, u. zw. dadurch, daß ich deinen Fall erzählte (Nebenbei
    wollte ich ihn für die seinerzeitige Gemeinheit strafen.) Er aber verstand mich nicht, d.h.
    wollte mich nicht verstehen u. wandte sich an <tei:rs key="entity-003033" type="organization">Bl.</tei:rs> selbst wegen eines Instrumentes für mich. Diesen Bf kenne ich nicht, wohl aber
    die Antwort <tei:rs key="entity-003033" type="organization">Bl.</tei:rs>’s, die sehr treffend u.
    lehrreich war; er schrieb: „Sie könnten, <tei:hi rend="underline">wie so Viele</tei:hi>, das
     <tei:hi rend="double-underline">kleine</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">Opfer</tei:hi> bringen“ u. stimmte damit in meinem Gedanken ein, den
    ich <tei:rs key="entity-000456" type="person">K.</tei:rs> gegenüber freilich nicht
     aussprach.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">No paragraph-break in
     source. </tei:note>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Aber siehe! <tei:rs key="entity-000456" type="person">K.</tei:rs> meinte zu dieser Stelle,
     <tei:rs key="entity-003033" type="organization">Bl.</tei:rs> hat leicht, mir das Opfer
    aufzubinden, ich kann ja das <tei:del rend="overstrike">Ist</tei:del> Instr., nach
    entsprechender Restaurierung, noch immer um 60-70 Mill. verkaufen(!!), ja für die Miete wollte
    mir ein Aegypter vor 2 Jahren 1½ Mill. monatlich zahlen, das kann ich Ihnen freilich nicht
    berechnen, aber – Ist Ihnen 700.000 K monatlich zuviel? Das wären Zinsen von 40 Mill. jährlich,
    u. <tei:pb n="5"/> da hätte ich erst nur die Zinsen.”(?!?) Und <tei:rs key="entity-003033" type="organization">Bl</tei:rs>’s Brief lag vor uns auf dem Tisch! Wir waren zu stolz, um etwas
    zu entgegnen u. nun, das Beste, da er dies (Ausländer-) Erhöhung – das nahezu 5-fache des
    früheren – an mich gebracht hat, tut er die Restaurierung, die ihm ursprünglich Vorwand gewesen,
    mit den Worten ab: „Stört Sie das?“ Ich sage gelassen: nein, u. so blieb blos 8 Mill. jährlich
    Miete übrig für das Instr., das schon 15 Jahre bei mir stand, u. entgegen <tei:rs key="entity-003033" type="organization">Bl.</tei:rs>’s Meinung, u. ohne Restaurierung! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich war entschlossen, ihm das Instr. zurückzugeben, denn bei jährlichen 8
    Mill. noch den Vorwurf zu dulden, daß ich ihm um weitere 20–30 Mill bringe, war mir
    unerträglich. Wir laufen zu September. Er gab mir einen Konzertflügel von <tei:rs key="entity-003052" type="organization">Ehrbar</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">"Ehrbar" – the name is not written clearly in Schenker's letter –
     was the name of a prominent piano manufacturing firm in Vienna, founded by Friedrich Konrad
     Ehrbar in 1855. An important rival to Bösendorfer in the Austrian capital, it continued to make
     instruments until the 1980s. </tei:note> der taugt aber nichts u. ich muß weiter suchen. So
    eine Beschämung, wo ich doch <tei:rs key="entity-000456" type="person">K.</tei:rs> einige
     <tei:rs key="entity-003033" type="organization">Bl</tei:rs>-Kaüfer, auch <tei:rs key="entity-002880" type="organization">Steinway</tei:rs>-Käufer vermittelt habe! Das zu
     <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> addiert, ergibt ein schönes Wiener
    Leid, wo mir doch in jeder Musikschule ein kleines Denkmälchen gebührt für das Geleistete. </tei:p>

   <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

   <tei:p>Spielst du <tei:rs key="entity-000619" type="person">M.-Hartmann</tei:rs>’s Passac.
    auswendig? Strengen dich die Vorbereitungen zum Konzert an? </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Wie geht es <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Karli</tei:rs>? Wir freuen uns
    schon, ihm in <tei:rs key="entity-002334" type="place"><tei:region>Tirol</tei:region></tei:rs>
    unseren Besuch abzustatten. Grüße die Kleinen herzlichst von uns. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Die Analyse von heute ist sehr <tei:add place="interlinear-above">er</tei:add>freulich:
    Zustand nicht bestimmbar, also 0%!! </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Wie steht es mit <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Themming</tei:rs> u. den
    Seminaren? <tei:rs key="entity-000643" type="person">Oppel</tei:rs> (<tei:rs key="entity-002757" type="place">Kiel</tei:rs>) meldet 20 Ab. an. Wenn ich dir ein Exempl., (außer deinem Ehrenex).
    schickte, könntest du veranlassen, das irgend ein nenneswertes Musikhaus es in die Auslage
    stellte? </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Nun aber sei geschlossen. </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Dir u. deiner <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">Frau</tei:rs> unser beiden beste Grüße </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Dein</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1924-11-06">6. XI. 1924</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>



  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:epigraph rend="block">
     <tei:p>Motto: All the good spirits send greetings; I mean those that have lived, since no more
      shall come. </tei:p>
    </tei:epigraph>
    <tei:salute><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>First of all, I owe <tei:rs key="entity-000013" type="person">Altmann</tei:rs> an apology
    on account of the suspicion that I expressed too hastily. He, too, has been in touch with me, a
    few days ago, to tell me that he sent me the photographic plates of the autograph parts of the
     <tei:rs key="entity-001172" type="composition"><tei:title level="m">St. Matthew
      Passion</tei:title></tei:rs> and that I have to send him only 2 Marks to cover the shipping
    costs. He has thus kept his promise and has saved me six million <tei:supplied reason="clarity">Kronen</tei:supplied>. Fortunately I shall be in a position to make use of whatever results
    they bring in <tei:rs key="entity-001748" type="work">issue 4 for 1924</tei:rs>, i.e. the next
    issue, in which I reveal the secret of the first Choral Fantasy, in E minor in 12/8 time: this
    will be the lead article of the issue.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000048" type="person">Baumgarten</tei:rs> regards the
    false accounting on <tei:rs key="entity-002456" type="organization">Gutmann</tei:rs>'s part,
    with respect to Miss <tei:rs key="entity-000049" type="person">Becker</tei:rs>, as
     "heavy-handedness."<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> It would be fitting for her
    to demand a rebate for having been overcharged. In any event, I ask you to keep the two
    documents, and to let me make use of them if it proves necessary. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Have you perhaps read, by chance, how <tei:rs key="entity-000471" type="person">Korngold</tei:rs> openly gave Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000057" type="person">Bekker</tei:rs> and <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> a good
     lambasting?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> He has done a good job of it. This
    is the way that one should deal with this pack, which lives by terrorizing and accuses others of
    terrorizing when they defend themselves. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> What a sorry story this has been regarding the <tei:rs key="entity-001747" type="work">double-issue 2/3</tei:rs>! Back on <tei:date when="1924-08-05"><tei:hi rend="underline">August 5</tei:hi></tei:date>, <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> began to hold back a part of the issue, concerning the
    performance of the <tei:rs key="entity-001354" type="composition"><tei:title>Brahms Handel
      Variations</tei:title></tei:rs>; following constant pressure from my part he had it typeset
    and sent to me, toward the <tei:hi rend="underline">end of September</tei:hi>. On <tei:date when="1924-10-06"><tei:hi rend="underline">October 6</tei:hi></tei:date> the issue arrives
     <tei:hi rend="underline">in page-proof</tei:hi>, with <tei:hi rend="underline">one</tei:hi>
    music example and <tei:hi rend="underline">one</tei:hi> trill sign (~~) missing. After two weeks
    (!) the second page-proofs arrives, and the example and trill sign ~~ <tei:hi rend="underline">are still missing</tei:hi>. I get furious about this shameless state of affairs; finally on
     <tei:date when="1924-10-23">October 23</tei:date> I can give the go-ahead for publication, but
    the issue is still not published even now, on <tei:date when="1924-11-06">November 6</tei:date>!
    And it could have – should have – appeared back at the beginning of October. And all this merely
    to delay the publication of <tei:rs key="entity-001748" type="work">issue 4</tei:rs> until the
    year <tei:date when="1925">1925</tei:date>. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">This very day I have sent Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000048" type="person">Baumgarten</tei:rs>'s letter to <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">UE</tei:rs> (I
    have altogether given up communicating with <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> directly), in which I ask him for his agreement regarding the dissolution of
    the <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>
    contract. Dr <tei:rs key="entity-000048" type="person">Baumgarten</tei:rs> is otherwise in favor
    of my dragging out the matter <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat"><tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:hi rend="italic">via facti</tei:hi></tei:hi></tei:foreign>, that is, that I simply approach
     <tei:rs key="entity-002627" type="organization">Drei Masken Verlag</tei:rs> or <tei:rs key="entity-002978" type="organization">Piper</tei:rs>, as <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> is in no position whatsoever to take legal action against me:
    the material against him is too damaging. But – here's the problem – I do not want to burden the
    new publisher with any disadvantages <tei:pb n="3"/> and I am indeed afraid that <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> will undertake something against the new
    publisher, purely for the sake of vengeance. And yet I must take take some risk, otherwise he
    will bring me into 1925 and add to the damages of the previous four years those of a fifth year.
    If only I knew how long such a trial would last! If it were over quickly, I would enjoy it,
    wringing compensation for damages from him and having the rogue pilloried. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>And now Mr <tei:rs key="entity-000456" type="person">Kohn</tei:rs>! I had dealings with
    him going back to 1905. I had a <tei:rs key="entity-003033" type="organization">Blüthner</tei:rs> piano of his for fifteen years. When he began to increase the rental charges
    two years ago, I offered <tei:hi rend="underline">to buy this instrument from him</tei:hi>, in
    return for a larger initial payment and installment payments spread over a few years. He
    declined, ostensibly on the grounds that <tei:rs key="entity-003033" type="organization">Blüthner</tei:rs> sends <tei:supplied reason="clarity">him</tei:supplied> only a few
    instruments, but in reality because he would have at any rate had to give the instrument to me
    for a lower price than to a non-musician. He actually betrayed himself when he said: <tei:rs key="entity-003033" type="organization">Blüthner</tei:rs> would sell <tei:hi rend="underline">you</tei:hi> the instrument for 20 Million <tei:supplied reason="clarity">Kronen</tei:supplied> (at that time), etc. Suddenly <tei:rs key="entity-000456" type="person">Kohn</tei:rs> shows a great interest in my instrument: it must be restored (according to a
    report from the piano tuner) and, as this will cost 2½ million, <tei:pb n="4"/> he must absorb
    these costs in a higher price. (For sake of accuracy, I show him that I have to pay him only
    150,000 Kronen monthly, which would have certainly been obliging.) When I heard this summer how
    nicely <tei:rs key="entity-003033" type="organization">Blüthner</tei:rs> had treated you, I
    pressed <tei:rs key="entity-000456" type="person">Kohn</tei:rs> to consider whether, after
    fifteen years, <tei:hi rend="underline">he</tei:hi> could at least forgo further rent increases.
    (In addition, I wanted to punish him for his earlier meanness). He, however, did not understand
    me, that is, he did not want to understand me; and he turned to <tei:rs key="entity-003033" type="organization">Blüthner</tei:rs> themselves regarding an instrument for me. I do not know
    the content of his letter, but I do know <tei:rs key="entity-003033" type="organization">Blüthner</tei:rs>'s answer, which hit the mark in a most informative way; they wrote: "You
    could, <tei:hi rend="underline">like so many</tei:hi>, make this <tei:hi rend="double-underline">small</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">sacrifice</tei:hi>" and thus agreed with my thoughts, which I
    admittedly did not voice in front of <tei:rs key="entity-000456" type="person">Kohn</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p>But listen to what <tei:rs key="entity-000456" type="person">Kohn</tei:rs> said on the
    spot: <tei:supplied reason="syntax">"</tei:supplied>It is easy for <tei:rs key="entity-003033" type="organization">Blüthner</tei:rs> to force this sacrifice upon me. I can, after the
    necessary restorations have been made, still sell the instrument for 60 or 70 million
    Kronen(!!); two years ago an Egyptian would have payed me 1½ million a month, a sum that I of
    course cannot charge you. But is 700,000 Kronen a month asking too much of you? This would be
    the annual interest on 40 Million, and <tei:pb n="5"/> I would have had only the interest."(?!?)
    And <tei:rs key="entity-003033" type="organization">Blüthner</tei:rs>'s letter stood in front of
    us on the desk! We were too proud to make any sort of reply; and now, best of all, having
    mentioned to me the increased rate (for foreigners), which was nearly five times the earlier
    charge, he will forgo the restoration work (which had originally been the pretext <tei:supplied reason="clarity">for the increase</tei:supplied>), with the words: "Does that bother you?" I
    answer, with composure: "No." And so all that remained was merely 8 million Kronen yearly for
    the instrument that was already in my possession for fifteen years: against <tei:rs key="entity-003033" type="organization">Blüthner</tei:rs>'s opinion, and without restoration! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I was determined to return the instrument to him, since I found it impossible
    to put up with the fact that, in addition to the eight million a year, I bring him a further 20
    to 30 million <tei:supplied reason="clarity">from other customers</tei:supplied>. We now move on
    to September. He gave me a concert grand piano from <tei:rs key="entity-003052" type="organization">Ehrbar</tei:rs>;<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> this,
    however, is useless, and I must search further. Such a humiliation, given that I've acted as
    intermediary for <tei:rs key="entity-000456" type="person">Kohn</tei:rs> in the sale of several
    pianos by <tei:rs key="entity-003033" type="organization">Blüthner</tei:rs>, also by <tei:rs key="entity-002880" type="organization">Steinway</tei:rs>. Add this to <tei:rs key="entity-000356" type="person">Hertzka</tei:rs> and you have a pretty Viennese sorrow, where
    in fact in every music school a small monument might be erected in memory of what I have
    achieved. </tei:p>

   <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

   <tei:p>Are you playing <tei:rs key="entity-000619" type="person">Müller-Hartmann</tei:rs>'s
    Passacaglia from memory? Are the preparations for the concert stressful? </tei:p>

   <tei:p>How is <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">little Karl</tei:rs>? We are already
    looking forward to making good our visit to him in the <tei:rs key="entity-002334" type="place"><tei:region>Tyrol</tei:region></tei:rs>. Give the children our warmest greetings. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>My <tei:supplied reason="clarity">blood-sugar level</tei:supplied> analysis today is very
    good news: indeterminable, therefore 0%!! </tei:p>

   <tei:p>How are things with <tei:rs key="entity-000884" type="person">Temming</tei:rs> and the
    university music departments? <tei:rs key="entity-000643" type="person">Oppel</tei:rs> (in
     <tei:rs key="entity-002757" type="place">Kiel</tei:rs>) reports twenty subscriptions. If I send
    you a copy (other than your complimentary copy), could you arrange to have it displayed in some
    reputable music shop? </tei:p>

   <tei:p>But let me close now. </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">To you and your <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">wife</tei:rs>, best greetings from the two of us </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1924-11-06">November 6, 1924</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>
  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>