<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="964" sdoID="OJ-6-7_52">OJ 6/7, [52]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="major">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="minor">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="MV" scope="minor">Moriz Violin's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
      <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-07-02" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002720">ViolinM ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002721">ViolinM+V ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002722">ViolinM+V+F ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Letter from Schenker to Moriz Violin, in Jeanette Schenker's hand, dated November
        26, 1930</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1930-11-26T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2013-07-02</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker summarizes the achievements and ambitions of several of his pupils
        and followers (Albersheim, Cube, Vrieslander, Roth, Jonas, and Weisse), noting that Weisse
        is the most ambitious of all of these though he is not completely at home in the new theory.
        He fears that something might go wrong at Weisse's forthcoming lecture at the Central
        Institute for Music Education, and hopes that Violin will listen with a sharp ear. Weisse
        will give a trial run of the lecture at the Schenkers' apartment.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:add place="margin-top" hand="#MV"><tei:note type="editorial">added in top right corner,
            in Moriz Violin's hand:</tei:note>
          <tei:handShift new="#MV"/><tei:date when="1930-11-26">26/XI <tei:hi rend="supralinear">30</tei:hi></tei:date></tei:add><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="authorial" place="margin-top"><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>diktirt!</tei:note>
        <tei:salute><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Fl</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is recorded in
            Schenker's diary at OJ 4/4, p. 3547 (November 26, 1930): "An Floriz (Br. 10 Seiten,
            diktirt): über das Schicksal meiner Schüler, von denen die einen sich in den
            naturgezogenen Grenzen bescheiden, die andern aber in intellektuellem Wahn befangen,
            durchaus „fortschreiten“, namentlich über mich hinaus wollen! ich nenne Vrieslander noch
            als harmlosen Fall, Roth aber schon als bedenklicher, nun Jonas – ganz sonderbar –,
            Weisse, der mit Recht Ehrgeizigste, bis heute aber noch nicht ganz sicher." ("To Floriz
            (letter, 10 pages, dictated): about the fate of my pupils, of whom some keep to the
            boundaries drawn by Nature, others however are caught up in an intellectual madness and
            want to make thorough "progress," in particular over an above what I have done. I
            describe Vrieslander still as a harmless case, Roth already as something more serious,
            and now Jonas – quite special – and Weisse, who is rightly the most ambitious but to
            this day is still not entirely secure.")</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Soeben teilt mir <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs>
        mit, daß Du nun wirklich nach <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs>
          reist.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Violin had said that he
          would be going to Berlin to hear Hans Weisse's lecture on Schenker's theories at Central
          Institute for Music Education. A written version of this lecture, "What is Counterpoint?,"
          is preserved as OC file 17, item 3.</tei:note> Der Inhalt dieses Briefes macht mir jede
        weitere Einleitung u. Begründung ersparen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Die Leidenschaft meines eigenen Wesens hat bei mehreren Schülern die Folge
        gehabt, daß sie gleichsam durch die Kraft meines Wurfes weiter geflogen sind, als mir in
        ihrem eigenen Interesse wilkommen war u. ist. So viel Freude es mir macht, sie von meiner
        Leidenschaft so erfüllt zu sehen, so betrübt bin ich anderseits darüber, daß sie die Grenze
        überschreiten u. dadurch der eigenen Existenz schaden. Diese Leute haben weniger Lebens-
          <tei:pb n="2"/> klugheit als ich. Auf mir lastete die furchtbare Aufgabe, das Werk zu
        zimmern, unterzubringen, u. – zu leben. Ich kann wohl mit der Ergebnis zufrieden sein. Die
        Schüler aber haben keine Mühe mit dem Stoff, u. so entlastet glauben sie, weiter vortasten
        zu dürfen, zumal die Zeit von heute sie mit dem Ruf nach „Fortschritt“ geradezu
          betäubt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">No paragraph-break in
          source.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Z. B.: Professor <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">v. Cube</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000007" type="person">Albersheim</tei:rs> hielten sich allezeit in ihren
        Grenzen, aber schon der arme <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs>
        hat es sich mit seiner Existenz bezahlen müssen, daß er ohne mich noch verstanden zu haben,
          <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#JS">U</tei:del> aus Eitelkeit
            „<tei:term><tei:soCalled>Urtöne</tei:soCalled></tei:term>“ in die Welt setzen wollte!
        (Ich habe sie ihm gegenüber nie berichtigt!) Oder: <tei:pb n="3"/> Professor <tei:rs key="entity-000737" type="person">Roth</tei:rs> in seiner Lehre vom
          <tei:term>Kontrapunkt</tei:term> hat meine schönsten Gedanken – um Redensart des Juden zu
        gebrauchen, der bei drohendem Konkurs das Geschäft auf seine Frau umschreibt! –, einfach auf
        sich umgeschrieben u. mir die Urheberschaft von Kleinigkeiten bescheinigt, obwohl er in der
          <tei:rs key="entity-004733" type="journal"><tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:title>Stuttgarter
              Zeitung</tei:title></tei:hi></tei:rs> sehr charaktervoll u. mir gegenüber gerecht
        ausgeholt hat.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Oder: sogar Dr <tei:rs key="entity-000412" type="person">Jonas</tei:rs>
        hat den Mut mir zu schreiben, er habe in <tei:rs key="entity-002286" type="place">München</tei:rs> einen Vortrag gehalten u. meiner als
          „<tei:quote>Ausgangspunkt</tei:quote>“ erwähnt. Nun bat er um eine Empfehlung an <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs>, die ich <tei:pb n="4"/> ihm
        natürlich verweigern mußte, weil ich keine Ahnung habe, wohin er von dem
          „<tei:quote>Ausganspunkt</tei:quote>“, den ich für ihn vorstelle, steuern will.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Und nun auch unser lieber <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans
          Weisse</tei:rs>! Er war zeitlebens von einem Fortschritts-Auftrieb geplagt, der zu sehr
        intellektuell war, etwa: „<tei:quote> . . ich muß ja weitergehen?</tei:quote>“ . . Seine
        Kompositionserfolge, ich meine seine inneren Erfolge, mehrten die Lust zum Weiterschreiten,
        verfälschten aber den wahren Sachverhalt. So sonderbar es Dir klingen mag: <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">W.</tei:rs> hat mir nicht ein einziges Mal ein
          <tei:term>Stimmführungsbild</tei:term> gebracht u. bekannte dazu offen: „<tei:term>Ich
          weiß nicht, bin <tei:pb n="5"/> ich feig oder zu dumm . . </tei:term>“. Er bat mich, die
        Dinge vor ihm zu improvisieren, aber nichts brachte ihn aus seiner Zurückhaltung heraus!
        Erst im letzten Jahr legte er mir in einem Brief ein <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs>-Bild vor, das war aber wirklich trostlos. Noch trostloser
        freilich war die Erfahrung, daß er jahrelang mit allerlei Plänen umging, die eben durch eine
        zu starke intellektuelle Beimischung getrübt, mir sofort verrieten, daß er bei mir noch
        nicht ganz zuhause ist. Sein geschicktes Sprechen täuscht ihn selbst, aber ich hatte fast
        bei jeder Begegnung die Aufgabe, ihm über die Grundelemente <tei:pb n="6"/> meiner
        Betrachtung die Augen zu öffnen. Er kam z. B. u. sagte: „<tei:quote>Meister, ich weiß es ja,
          aber wie soll ich es meinen Schülern erklären?</tei:quote>“ Und nun fragt er mich, ob die
          <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> nicht auch nur aus – einer <tei:term>Nebennote</tei:term>
        bestehen kann, also z. B. in der <tei:rs key="entity-004709" type="composition">Edur-Partita</tei:rs> von <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person">Bach</tei:rs>
          (<tei:rs key="entity-001751" type="work">Jahrb.</tei:rs>)[8] ein e–fis–e. Bis zum vorigen
        Jahr hat er die <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> nicht deutlich genug als den Raum eines Stückes
        empfunden oder glaubte der <tei:term>Form</tei:term> eine nebengeordnete Bedeutung geben zu
        sollen usw. Ich stellte alle diese Irrungen richtig, bin aber besorgt, ob er im Vortrag sich
        in den im zukommenden Grenzen halten werde. Er scheint sogar, was mich das Beste hoffen
        läßte, <tei:pb n="7"/> sich eine gewisse Zurückhaltung in der Darstellung von
          <tei:term>Urlinien</tei:term> auferlegen zu wollen; er bemerkte nämlich, daß in seiner
        Polemik wider Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-003123" type="person">Lorenz</tei:rs> verunglückt
        wäre, wenn ich ihm nicht den richtigen Weg gewiesen hätte. Also scheint er aus Vorsicht den
        Hörern nur die Notentexte in die Hand zu geben u. den Rest der freien Rede zu überlassen,
        die unverbindlich ist. So denke ich mir den Sachverhalt. Möglich aber, daß er die Sache
        richtig u. auch charaktervoll, was mich ihm seinetwillen freuen würde. Es ist für mich kein
        Zweifel, daß er meine Kunst der Lese niemals erreichen wird, auch ahnt er der- <tei:pb n="8"/> zeit noch nicht, was <tei:rs key="entity-001728" type="work"><tei:title>der freie
            Satz</tei:title></tei:rs> bringen wird, so viel er auch in den Stünden u. Briefen von
        mir schon gehört hat. Und da würde ich es seinetwegen bedauern, wenn er sich durch einen
        falschen Appetit den Rückzug zur Wahrheit selbst versperrte. Daß die jungen Leute so viel
        von mir gelernt haben, nur eben das Wichtigste nicht, ganz u. gar rein in der Lehre
        aufzugehen, ohne jede Nebenabsichten. Hätte ich denn je so viel erreicht, wenn ich über
          <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000612" type="person">Mozart</tei:rs>
        hätte hinausgelangen wollen?</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Also: Dir schreibe ich davon, damit Du gut zuhören magst u. mir den
        Eindruck mitteilst: ob er mehr sich oder mich vorgetragen hat! <tei:pb n="9"/>
        <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs> wird mir u. meinen Schülern die
        Vorträge vorlesen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Weisse's talk
          at Schenker's apartment took place on Friday, December 5, from 6:30 to 9:15 in the
          evening. An account of it is given in Schenker's diary (OJ 4/4, pp. 3551-53).</tei:note>
        ich werde mir also auch hier ein Bild davon machen können, ob aber in der Hitze des
        Gefechtes sich nicht ein Unziemliches begibt, darüber erbitte ich ein Wort von Dir. – Nach
          <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs> kommt auch <tei:rs key="entity-000643" type="person">Oppel</tei:rs>, vielleicht <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">v. Cube</tei:rs> aus <tei:rs key="entity-002621" type="place">Duisburg</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Das <tei:rs key="entity-001752" type="work"><tei:title>Jahrbuch
            III</tei:title></tei:rs> düftest Du um jene Zeit schon in der Hand haben. Bitte, Grüße
        an <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000643" type="person">Oppel</tei:rs> u. sonstige Bekannte zu
        bestellen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Wie geht es der lieben Frau <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">Wally</tei:rs> u. den Kindern? Also angenehme Reise u. bringe Erfreuliches <tei:pb n="10"/> nachhause mit!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:dateline><tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs>, den <tei:date when="1930-11-26">26. November 1930</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Dein</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        <tei:salute>dessen Augen sein <tei:hi rend="underline">lie</tei:hi>bes, <tei:hi rend="underline">lie</tei:hi>bes <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person"><tei:hi rend="underline">Lie</tei:hi>-<tei:hi rend="underline">Lie</tei:hi>- <tei:hi rend="underline">Lie</tei:hi>chen</tei:rs> hiermit zu schonen beflissen
          war.</tei:salute>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:add place="margin-top" hand="#MV"><tei:note type="editorial">added in top right corner,
            in Moriz Violin's hand:</tei:note>
          <tei:handShift new="#MV"/><tei:date when="1930-11-26">November 26,
          1930</tei:date></tei:add><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="authorial" place="margin-top"><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>dictated!</tei:note>
        <tei:salute><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs> has just
        informed me that you are in fact going to <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> The content of this
        letter will spare me any further explanation or justification.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">The passion of my very own being has had the effect that several of my
        pupils have, so to speak, drawn strength from my effort and flown further than was, or is,
        something that I welcome, for their own sake. As much joy as it gives me to see them so
        filled with my passion, so saddened am I, on the other hand, that they have exceeded the
        boundary and, in so doing, damaged their own being. These people have less of life's <tei:pb n="2"/> wisdom than I. It was to me that the awesome task fell: of assembling the work, of
        formulating it, and – of living it. I can, indeed, be satisfied with the result. My pupils,
        however, have not toiled with the material and, being spared this burden, they believe that
        they may be permitted to grope further, all the more since they are indeed deafened in this
        day and age by the call to "progress."<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">von Cube</tei:rs> and <tei:rs key="entity-000007" type="person">Albersheim</tei:rs>, for example, have stayed at all
        times within their limits. But already poor <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs> has had to pay with his being, since, without having understood me,
        he had the vanity to introduce to the world the concept of
            "<tei:term><tei:soCalled>Urtöne</tei:soCalled></tei:term>"! (I have never corrected him
        in this matter!) Further, <tei:pb n="3"/> Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000737" type="person">Roth</tei:rs>, in his textbook on <tei:term>counterpoint</tei:term>, simply expropriated
        my most attractive ideas as his own – to put it in Jewish terms: when threatened with
        bankruptcy, he transferred the business to his wife's name –, simply by transferring them to
        himself and giving me credit only for trivial matters, although he has, to be sure, written
        with a great deal of character and support for me in the <tei:rs key="entity-004733" type="journal"><tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:title level="j">Stuttgarter
              Zeitung</tei:title></tei:hi></tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">And even Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000412" type="person">Jonas</tei:rs> has
        had the temerity to write to me that he gave a lecture in <tei:rs key="entity-002286" type="place">Munich</tei:rs> in which he mentioned my work a "<tei:quote>point of
          departure</tei:quote>." Recently he asked me to write a letter of recommendation to
          <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs>; <tei:pb n="4"/> naturally
        I had to refuse him, as I had no whither he was steering himself from the "<tei:quote>point
          of departure</tei:quote>" that I provided for him.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">And now, too, our dear <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans
          Weisse</tei:rs>! He was plagued by an impulse towards progress that was far too
        intellectual. Thus he asked "<tei:quote>Must I, in fact, continue?</tei:quote>" His
        successes in composition – I mean his inherent successes – increased his appetite to move
        on, but in so doing he falsified the true picture. As strange as it may sound to you,
          <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs> never once brought me a
          <tei:term>voice-leading graph</tei:term>, and openly acknowledged, "<tei:term>I do not
          know why: either <tei:pb n="5"/> I am timid or too stupid.</tei:term>" He asked me to
        improvise these things in front of him, but nothing brought him out of his reticence! It was
        only last year that he presented me with a graph of a work by <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs>, which was truly lamentable. It was even more lamentable for
        me to learn that he had spent the entire year making all sorts of plans, which were likewise
        spoiled by things that were too strongly intellectual being mixed in with them; then he
        immediately betrayed to me the fact that he was not entirely at home with my work. His own
        facility with words deceives him; but I had the task, at almost every encounter, of opening
        his eyes to the basic principles of <tei:pb n="6"/> my theory. He came, for instance, and
        said: "<tei:quote>Master, I know it, indeed, but how am I supposed to explain it to my
          pupils?</tei:quote>" And now he asks me whether the <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> might not
        also consist of just – a <tei:term>neighbor note</tei:term>, for instance, e–f<tei:g type="sharp"/>–e in <tei:supplied reason="clarity">the Prelude to</tei:supplied>
        <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person">Bach</tei:rs>'s <tei:rs key="entity-004709" type="composition">E major Partita for solo violin</tei:rs>, about which I wrote in the
          <tei:rs key="entity-001751" type="work">second Yearbook</tei:rs>. Until last year he did
        not understand the <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> clearly enough as the tonal space of a
        piece; or he believed that it was supposed to give a subordinate meaning to the
          <tei:term>form</tei:term>, etc. I set all these misconceptions aright, but I am concerned
        as to whether he will stick to the proper boundaries in his lecture. He actually appears –
        this is the best I can hope for – <tei:pb n="7"/> to want to impose a certain amount of
        restraint in his presentations of <tei:term>voice-leading graphs</tei:term>, for he remarked
        that he would have come to grief in his polemic against Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-003123" type="person">Lorenz</tei:rs> had I not shown him the correct path. Thus he appears, for
        sake of prudence, to provide his listeners only with the score, and to leave the rest to
        improvised talk, which does not bind him <tei:supplied reason="clarity">to a particular
          interpretation</tei:supplied>. This is the way I see things. It is possible, however, that
        he will explain the matter correctly, and also with character, which will give me pleasure
        for his sake. I have no doubt, however, that he will never achieve my level of reading; and
        at present he has <tei:pb n="8"/> no idea of what will be contained in <tei:rs key="entity-001728" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Der freie Satz</tei:title></tei:rs>,
        in spite of all that he has already heard from me, in lessons and letters. And for this
        reason I would be sorry, for his sake, if the path leading back to the truth were to be
        blocked by a false appetite. <tei:supplied reason="clarity">It is true</tei:supplied> that
        the young people have learned a great deal from me, but not the very thing that is most
        important: to apply themselves fully and solely to the theory itself, without any peripheral
        intentions. Would I have achieved so much had I wanted to go beyond <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs>, and <tei:rs key="entity-000612" type="person">Mozart</tei:rs>?</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Very well, then: I am writing to you about this so that you might listen
        carefully and give me your impression as to whether he lectured more about himself or about
        me! <tei:pb n="9"/>
        <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs> will be reading his lectures to me
        and my pupils,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> so I will be able to form a
        view of them here, too. Whether, in the heat of battle, he might commit an error of
        judgement is something I would like you to communicate to me. <tei:rs key="entity-000643" type="person">Oppel</tei:rs> will be coming to <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs>; perhaps <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">Cube</tei:rs>, too,
        from <tei:rs key="entity-002621" type="place">Duisburg</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">You may have already received a copy of <tei:rs key="entity-001752" type="work"><tei:title>Yearbook 3</tei:title></tei:rs> by that time. Please send my
        greetings to <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000643" type="person">Oppel</tei:rs> and other acquaintances.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">How are your dear wife <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">Vally</tei:rs> and the children? I hope that you have a safe journey and bring good news
          <tei:pb n="10"/> home with you!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:dateline><tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1930-11-26">November 26, 1930</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Yours</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich</tei:rs></tei:signed>
        <tei:salute>whose <tei:hi rend="underline">love</tei:hi>ly, <tei:hi rend="underline">love</tei:hi>ly, <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person"><tei:hi rend="underline">Lie</tei:hi>-<tei:hi rend="underline">lie</tei:hi>-<tei:hi rend="underline">lie</tei:hi>chen</tei:rs> was concerned to spare his eyes.</tei:salute>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>