<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="949" sdoID="OJ-6-7_30">OJ 6/7, [30]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
      <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-06-12" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002720">ViolinM ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002721">ViolinM+V ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002722">ViolinM+V+F ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated December 19, 1926</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1926-12-19T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2013-06-12</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker expresses his delight that his friend received sufficient financial
        help to be able to move into a new apartment for the sake of his son Karl's health. He
        reports having shown Agnes Becker some straightforward examples of the Urlinie, out of
        desperation (she shows little aptitude for piano playing), and then explains that a great
        deal of time, patience and faith are needed to understand such things. Of his current
        pupils, only Elias, Brünauer, Hoboken and (to some extent) Albersheim are capable of
        following the ramifications of the new theory, which he sees as his unique gift to the
        world. At present, he is working on his "crowning work," Free Composition.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:date when="1926-12-19">Sonntag
          19.12.26</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Fl</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is recorded in
            Schenker's diary at OJ 3/9, p. 3013 (December 19, 1926): "An Fl. (Br.): ermahne ihn,
            sich der müßigen Neugier von Schülerinnen zu erwehren u. die Urlinie vorsichtig zu
            dosieren; schreibe in diesem Sinne an Frl. Bekker." ("To Floriz (letter): I advise him
            to shield himself from the useless curiosity of <tei:supplied reason="clarity">his</tei:supplied> female pupils, and to give out the Urlinie in carefully measure
            doses; I shall write in these terms to Miss Becker.")</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Dein „<tei:soCalled>Glück im Unglück</tei:soCalled>“ hat uns wundersam
        ergriffen, – daß es heute so etwas noch gibt, ist ein Märchen vor Gott. Desto besser, wenn
        es dir zufliegt. Ich wollte postwendend antworten, so beglückt war ich über diese
        Mitteilung, u. siehe, was draus geworden!! Nun, wie geht es heute dem l. tapferen <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Jungen</tei:rs>? Wenn du eine Sekunde erübrigst, setzte
        eine Zeile auf.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Als die Sendung von Frl. <tei:rs key="entity-000049" type="person">B.</tei:rs>
          kam,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this mail is
          recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/9, p. 3004 (November 22, 1926): "Von Frl. Bekker
          (Br.): eine angebliche Urlinie zu op. 109! will die Arbeit unter Anleitung Violins gemacht
          haben." ("From Miss Becker (Br.): a supposed Urlinie for Op. 109! She is supposed to have
          done the work under Violin's supervision."). Schenker's reply is recorded in the diary on
          p. 3013–14 (December 19, 1926): "An Frl. Bekker (Br.): Korrektur des Blattes zu op. 109,
          1. Satz; empfehle, sich mehr an das Instrument zu halten, die Urlinie mag nachfolgen."
          ("To Miss Becker (Br.): correction of the page concerning the first movement of Op. 109; I
          advise her to concentrate more on her instrument; the Urlinie can come later.")</tei:note>
        war ich nicht wenig – ärgerich über den <tei:hi rend="underline">unbewußten</tei:hi>
        Mutwillen dieses gewiß sehr netten Mädchens, die dich mitten in solchem Elend mit solchen
        überflüßigen Dingen plagt. Ich bin dazu aus <tei:hi rend="underline">Verlegenheit</tei:hi>
        gekommen: da sie nichts weniger als Pianistin ist, <tei:pb n="2"/>
        <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#HS">sie</tei:del> wenig Liebe u. fast keine Geduld <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#HS">zu</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">in</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> den Fragen der Ausführung bezeigt, griff ich aus Not zu
          <tei:term>Url-Skizzen</tei:term> in leichten Fällen. Ich habe aber genug Schüler u.
        Schülerinnen, mit denen ich diese Sachen <tei:hi rend="underline">gar nicht</tei:hi>
        erörtern: die einen wollen es selbst nicht, da es ihnen eingestandenermaßen zu schwer ist,
        die andern haben zu wenig Stunden, um sich solchen Luxus zu gönnen u.s.w<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">.</tei:supplied> Kurz u. gut: die <tei:term>Url-Studien</tei:term>,
        die dasselbe wie <tei:term>Stimmf.</tei:term>, <tei:term>Form</tei:term>,
          <tei:term>Stufen</tei:term> bedeuten, sind durchaus nicht obligater Gegenstand auf meiner
          „<tei:soCalled>Akademie</tei:soCalled>“, gar viele Umstände stehen da im Wege. Z. B. sind
        es augenblicklich nur 3½ Schüler, die so etwas machen, die zwei älteren (<tei:rs key="entity-000201" type="person">Elias</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs key="entity-000107" type="person">Brünauer</tei:rs>) u. <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hoboken</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs key="entity-000007" type="person">Albersheim</tei:rs>/2 von
        den jüngeren (bei dem letzteren nur so so), die <tei:pb n="3"/> übrigen lasse ich spielen,
        ich erläutere viel, aber die Hand weg von jenen Dingen. Ich sage dir das ausdrücklich, weil
        mein Verfahren mit Frl. <tei:rs key="entity-000049" type="person">B.</tei:rs> dir vielleicht
        eine falsche Vorstellung erweckt haben könnte. Zur <tei:term>Url.</tei:term> gehört <tei:hi rend="double-underline">viel Musse</tei:hi>, auch Anstrengung der Vision, der Begläubigung
        durch die einzelnen Schichten – ist es denn nicht ein Wunder, wenn sich <tei:hi rend="underline">ein</tei:hi>
        <tei:term>Klang</tei:term> durch eine <tei:hi rend="underline">ganzes</tei:hi> Stück
        ausdrückt, alle Wege u. Stege in <tei:hi rend="underline">eine</tei:hi> Horizontale münden,
        die eben der <tei:term>Klang</tei:term> ist, u. so Stück,
          <tei:term>Tonalität</tei:term><tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#HS">,</tei:del> durch eine
          <tei:term>diatonische Tonreihe</tei:term> in <tei:term>Sekundschritten</tei:term> lebendig
        wird, ist ein <tei:hi rend="underline">solches </tei:hi><tei:hi rend="double-underline">Eins</tei:hi> nicht ein Wunder des Geistes, desto größer, ja unfreiwilliger es ist! –, da
        lasse ich nicht Alle darauf herumtrampeln. Die Fratzen von Schülern würden es wie Kinder
        gern machen: ohne eigentlichen Zwang immer zu fragen, heute in diesem, morgen in jenem
        Stück; <tei:pb n="4"/> kein Stück imponiert ihnen, kein Geheimnis, es kostet ja nur ein
        Fragen, der Lehrer mag sehen, wie er sich mit solchen tiefen Meistern über- u. unterirdisch
        in Verbindung setzt! Ich werde ja körperlich zugrunde gehen, wenn ich den Allen Alles
        gewähren ließe: ich dosiere mäßig. Freilich, je mehr ich arbeite, desto weniger verstehe
        ich, wie gerade mir das einfallen wollte. Nun habe ich das Bewußtsein, etwas der Welt u. der
        Musik geschenkt zu haben, was aus der Welt u. aus der Musik nie mehr kommt. Könnte ich nur
        2000 Jahre leben, um das große Gut zu bergen! Augenblicklich arbeite ich am „<tei:rs key="entity-001728" type="work"><tei:title>Freien Satz</tei:title></tei:rs>“, dem
        Krönungswerk. (An Frl. <tei:rs key="entity-000049" type="person">Becker</tei:rs> gebe ich
        Bericht über die Arbeit, mit Absicht kurz, um sie von solchen Dingen abzulenken, die bei ihr
        nur Spielerei sein können.)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">No
          paragraph-break in source.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Dir, Frau <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">Wally</tei:rs>, den
          Kinderchen von mir u. meinem <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">LieLiechen</tei:rs>
          herzlichste Grüße u. beste Wünsche zu <tei:date when="1926-12-25">Weihnacht</tei:date> u.
            <tei:date when="1927-01-01">Neujahr</tei:date></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-65">dein</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:date when="1926-12-19">Sunday, December 19,
            1926</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Your "<tei:soCalled>fortune in misfortune</tei:soCalled>" moved us in the
        wondrous way – that such a thing exists today is a fairy-tale before God. All the better
        when it befalls you. I wanted to reply by return of post, so overjoyed was I by your
        communication; and see what has come of it!! And now, how is the dear, brave <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">boy</tei:rs>? If you have a moment, write me a
        line.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>When the mail from Miss <tei:rs key="entity-000049" type="person">Becker</tei:rs>
          arrived,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> I was not a little angry about
        the unconscious <tei:hi rend="underline">shamelessness</tei:hi> of this girl – who is
        certainly very nice – who is plaguing you with such superfluous matters in the midst of such
        sorrow. In <tei:hi rend="underline">desperation</tei:hi> I came up with the following: as
        she is anything but a pianist, <tei:pb n="2"/> showing little love and almost no patience in
        matters of execution, I grabbed in desperation at <tei:term>Urlinie sketches</tei:term> at
        an elementary level. I have, however, plenty of pupils with whom I <tei:hi rend="underline">do not at all</tei:hi> discuss this sort of thing: some do not want it themselves, as it
        is somewhat too difficult for them; other have two few lessons to profit from such a luxury,
        etc. To put it briefly: the <tei:term>studies of the Urlinie</tei:term>, which amount to the
        same as <tei:term>voice-leading</tei:term>, <tei:term>form</tei:term> and
          <tei:term>scale-step</tei:term>, are by no means an obligatory part of my
          "<tei:soCalled>Academy</tei:soCalled>": a great many circumstances get in the way. For
        example, at the moment there are only 3½ pupils who do this sort of thing, the two elder
          (<tei:rs key="entity-000201" type="person">Elias</tei:rs> and <tei:rs key="entity-000107" type="person">Brünauer</tei:rs>) and <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hoboken</tei:rs> and ½<tei:rs key="entity-000007" type="person">Albersheim</tei:rs> among
        the younger (the last of whom only so-so); <tei:pb n="3"/> the remaining students I let
        play, explaining much but keeping my hands off such things. I say this to you expressly,
        since my experience with Miss <tei:rs key="entity-000049" type="person">Becker</tei:rs>
        could possibly have given rise to a false impression. The <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>
        requires <tei:hi rend="double-underline">a great deal of time</tei:hi>, also an exertion of
        the imagination and of verification through the individual layers – is it not indeed a
        wonder that <tei:hi rend="underline">a single</tei:hi>
        <tei:term>chord</tei:term> can express itself through an <tei:hi rend="underline">entire</tei:hi> piece, all the byways and bridges joining together in <tei:hi rend="underline">a single</tei:hi> horizontal entity which is that very
          <tei:term>chord</tei:term>, so that the piece and the <tei:term>tonality</tei:term> are
        animated by a <tei:term>diatonic</tei:term>
        <tei:term>series of tones</tei:term> proceeding by <tei:term>step motion</tei:term>? Is not
          <tei:hi rend="underline">such a </tei:hi><tei:hi rend="double-underline">unity</tei:hi> a
        wonder of the intellect? All the greater when it is more involuntary! I do not let everyone
        trample about on it. My pupils would be quick to make grimaces, like children: without real
        compulsion, they would constantly be asking questions, today about one piece, tomorrow about
        another. <tei:pb n="4"/> No piece impresses them, no secret; the only cost, after all, is
        the asking of questions; the teacher can see how he puts himself into a relationship with
        such deep masters, transcendentally and subterraneously! I would become a physical wreck if
        I entrusted all this to everyone: so I give out moderate doses. Of course, the more I work,
        the less I understand how I myself hit upon it. Now I am conscious of having made a gift to
        the world, and to music, one which will never come again from the world or from music. If
        only I could live 2000 years, to rescue the great treasure! At the moment I am working on
          <tei:rs key="entity-001728" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Der freie
          Satz</tei:title></tei:rs>, my crowning work. (I shall send Miss <tei:rs key="entity-000049" type="person">Becker</tei:rs> a report about the work, with the simple
        intention of steering her away from such things, which can only be playthings for
          her.)<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>To you, <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">Wally</tei:rs>, the children,
          from me and my <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs>, most
          heartfelt greetings and best wishes for <tei:date when="1926-12-25">Christmas</tei:date>
          and the <tei:date when="1927-01-01">New Year</tei:date>.</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-65">dein</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>