<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="959" sdoID="OJ-6-7_47">OJ 6/7, [47]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
      <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2013</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-06-29" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002717">ViolinM ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002720">ViolinM ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002721">ViolinM+V ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002722">ViolinM+V+F ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Violin, dated March 2, 1930</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1930-03-02T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2013-06-29</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker reports on two concerts at which Hans Weisse's Octet was performed
        for the first time. Furtwängler was enchanted by it, Schenker was impressed by the quality
        of the voice-leading in general, the construction of the finale movement (a passacaglia) in
        particular. He was touched to see that a pupil of Weisse's, Dr. Felix Salzer, had subvented
        the cost of the rehearsals and concerts, and the provision of food and drink for the
        audience; this he compared with Antony van Hoboken's reluctance to help him with the
        publication costs of his recent work.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000909">ViolinF</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000914">ViolinV</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-55"><tei:date when="1930-03-02">2. März
          1930</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Fl</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is recorded in
            Schenker's diary at OJ 4/3, p. 3448 (March 1, 1930): "An Fl. (Br.): Dank für die gute
            Absicht – was hat Berlin eingebracht? Der Stich der Eroica steht bevor; über Weisses
            Oktett, vom Raufen mit Mozio! ("To Floriz (letter): thanks for his good intentions –
            what came of the trip to Berlin? The engraving of the "Eroica" is imminent; concerning
            Weisse’s Octet, concerning my scuffle with Mozio!")</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Etwas spät komme ich mit dem Dank für deine l. Zeilen<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-45_84">= OJ 14/45, [84]</tei:ref>. Dazwischen lag eine
        so entsetzliche Überarbeitung – seit <tei:date when="1929-10">Oktober</tei:date> keine
        Ruhepause, nicht an Sonn-, nicht nicht an Feiertagen, nicht zu <tei:date when="1929-12-25">Weihnacht</tei:date>, zu <tei:date when="1930-01-01">Neujahr</tei:date> usw – , daß ich
        schließlich mir einige Ruhe zu nehmen durch den <tei:rs key="entity-000324" type="person">Arzt</tei:rs> verhalten wurde. Es geht mir wieder besser.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich hoffe in Bälde die Notenbilder zur <tei:rs key="entity-001752" type="work"><tei:title>Eroica</tei:title></tei:rs> dem Stich bei <tei:rs key="entity-002402" type="organization">Waldh. &amp; Eberle</tei:rs>, die es doch am besten machen, übergeben
        zu können. Wegen des Verlages erzähle ich dir später. Vorläufig danke ich dir innigst für
        deine wie immer liebe Absicht.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Wie ist dir die <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs>er
        Reise <tei:pb n="2"/> ausgegangen? Hast du die erhofften Früchte heimgebracht?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Augenblicklich ringe ich mit dem Schandbuben <tei:rs key="entity-000774" type="person">Mozio</tei:rs> um mein eigenes Ersparnis, nämlich die 2.<tei:hi rend="supralinear">te</tei:hi> Hälfte, die ich jetzt sehr brauche. Ich bin angesichts seiner dir bekannten
        Rücksichtslosigkeiten zum äußersten Schritt einer Klage bereit, wie ich den Weg durch den
        Anwalt schon einmal in der Angelegenheit der th. <tei:rs key="entity-000773" type="person">Mutter</tei:rs> gegangen bin. Er hält <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">auch</tei:add> mit Lügnereien sie, eigentlich schon seit 2 Jahren. Er ist doch ein –
        Blödian!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Vor kürzem hörte ich das neue <tei:rs key="entity-002973" type="composition">Oktett</tei:rs> von <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans W.</tei:rs> Auch
          <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs> hat es gehört – ein paar
        Tage zuvor – u. es freute mich für <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtw.</tei:rs>, daß er in echter <tei:pb n="3"/> begeisteter Aufwallung, wie mir <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans</tei:rs> sagte, die Worte ausrief: „<tei:quote>Ich
          hatte es nicht für möglich gehalten, daß heute so etwas noch geschrieben werden
          kann.</tei:quote>“ Er hat Recht, vom Standpunkt des ringsum Verfertigten ist das <tei:rs key="entity-002973" type="composition">Okt.</tei:rs> ein <tei:hi rend="underline">Koloss
          an Erfindung u. Ausführung</tei:hi>, du würdest über den letzten Satz, den <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"><tei:term>passacaglia</tei:term></tei:hi>, ordentlich die Ohren
        aufreißen! Der Grundzug ist natürlich <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">brahms</tei:rs>isch, was aber <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans</tei:rs>
        nicht gern wahrhaben will, die Naturgabe ist nach wie vor dieselbe, also geringfügig, aber
        umso erstaunlicher, was er auch ohne sie zustandebringt. Ende <tei:date when="1929-09">Sept.</tei:date> hat er mir <tei:rs key="entity-004687" type="composition">6 Bagatellen
          für das Klavier</tei:rs> vorgespielt, die den Versuch einer Anbiederung an das
        Dissonanzenleben vorstellen sollten; wie er mir sagte, wollte er <tei:hi rend="underline">zeigen</tei:hi>, wie man mit <tei:term>Quarten</tei:term> u. dgl. auch gut schreiben
          <tei:pb n="4"/> kann. Ich machte aus meiner Meinung kein Hehl. Umso erfreuter war ich, als
        ich das <tei:rs key="entity-002973" type="composition">Oktett</tei:rs> in guter
          <tei:term>Stimmführung</tei:term> vorschreiten hörte. <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtw.</tei:rs> versprach ihm, bei <tei:rs key="entity-002890" type="organization">Br. &amp; H.</tei:rs> wegen des Stiches zu intervenieren.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">No paragraph-break in
        source.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Sehr erfreulich war auch dabei, daß ein Schüler von <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans</tei:rs>, D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi>
        <tei:rs key="entity-000754" type="person">Salzer</tei:rs> (zur <tei:rs key="entity-004688" type="person">Wittgensteinfamilie</tei:rs> gehörig) fur die sehr, sehr beträchtlichen
        Kosten der <tei:hi rend="underline">14</tei:hi> Proben von <tei:hi rend="underline">8</tei:hi> Musikern mit <tei:hi rend="underline">zwei</tei:hi> Konzertmeistern, auch für
        die Abfütterung von etwa 100 Gästen an zwei Abenden aufgekommen ist. So etwas passiert mir
        nicht. Da sitzt bei mir der ungleich reichere <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hoboken</tei:rs>, ein wahre Nabob, u. trotz aller Mühe, die ich mir nehme, kann ich seine
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">materielle</tei:add> Teilnahme für meine
        Lebensarbeit nicht erreichen, da hört er weg, er steht noch auf dem Standpunkt, daß er mir
        schon mit seinem <tei:hi rend="underline">Stunden</tei:hi>honorar ein
          „<tei:soCalled>Mäzen</tei:soCalled>“ ist – es ist buchstäblich so – wo ich ihn übrigens um
          <tei:note type="editorial">continuing in top margin, upside down:</tei:note> dasselbe Geld
        wie die Wiener unterrichte, statt das doppelte zu fordern! <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hob.</tei:rs> hat sich aber, wenn ich nicht irre, in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> unmöglich gemacht wegen seines unan-
          <tei:note type="editorial">continuing in left margin, top to bottom:</tei:note> gemessenen
        Betragens. Ihm ist nicht zu helfen. Vorläufig rede nicht weiter darüber.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">No paragraph-break in
        source.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wie geht est sonst bei dir?</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Viele Grüße Euch Allen von mir und <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">LieLiechen</tei:rs></tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">dein</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-55"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">HSch</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-55"><tei:date when="1930-03-02">March 2,
          1930</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">I am rather late in sending you my thanks for your kind message<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-45_84">= OJ 14/45, [84]</tei:ref>. In the meantime, I
        had been so dreadfully overworked – since <tei:date when="1929-10">October</tei:date>, I
        have not had any free time: not on Sundays or holidays, not at <tei:date when="1929-12-25">Christmas</tei:date> or <tei:date when="1930-01-01">New Year's</tei:date>, etc. – until I
        was compelled by my <tei:rs key="entity-000324" type="person">doctor</tei:rs> to take short
        break. I am feeling better again.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I am hoping that I can soon hand over the music illustrations for the "<tei:rs key="entity-001752" type="work"><tei:title>Eroica</tei:title></tei:rs>" for engraving by
          <tei:rs key="entity-002402" type="organization">Waldheim &amp; Eberle</tei:rs>, who can
        indeed do this best of all. Concerning a publisher, I shall let you know later. For the time
        being, I thank you most sincerely for ever-kind intentions.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">How did the trip to <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs>
        <tei:pb n="2"/> turn out? Did you bring home the hoped-for fruits?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>At the moment, I am wrestling with that scurrilous boy <tei:rs key="entity-000774" type="person">Mozio</tei:rs> for my savings, specifically the second half, which I
        desperately need now. I am prepared to take the extreme step of legal action in the light of
        his inconsiderateness (which is well known to you), as I went through a lawyer already once
        before, in a matter concerning my dear <tei:rs key="entity-000773" type="person">mother</tei:rs>. He has actually kept them for two years now, <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">even</tei:add> saying untruths. He is indeed an –
        idiot!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Recently I heard <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans Weisse</tei:rs>'s new
          <tei:rs key="entity-002973" type="composition">Octet</tei:rs>. <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs>, too, had heard it a few days earlier, and it pleases
        me, for <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs>'s sake, that he
          <tei:supplied reason="clarity"><tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs></tei:supplied> spoke out with a genuine <tei:pb n="3"/> flood of
        emotion, as <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans</tei:rs> reported to me:
          "<tei:quote>I would not have thought it possible that something like this can be written
          today.</tei:quote>" He is right: viewed in terms of its overall production, the <tei:rs key="entity-002973" type="composition">Octet</tei:rs> is a <tei:hi rend="underline">colossus of invention and realization</tei:hi>. Your ears would really be torn open by
        the last movement, a <tei:term>passacaglia</tei:term>! The essential features are,
        naturally, <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs>ian, which is something
        that <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans</tei:rs> would not happily admit. His
        natural gift is the same as it has always been, i.e. limited; but what he is able to come up
        with in its absence is all the more astonishing. At the end of <tei:date when="1929-09">September</tei:date> last year, he played me his <tei:rs key="entity-004687" type="composition">six bagatelles for piano</tei:rs>, which are supposed to represent an
        essay in ingratiating himself with the world of dissonance. He wanted specifically to
          <tei:hi rend="underline">demonstrate</tei:hi>, so he told me, how one can even compose
        well using <tei:term>fourths</tei:term> and suchlike. <tei:pb n="4"/> I did not keep my
        opinions to myself. I was all the more pleased, then, to hear the <tei:rs key="entity-002973" type="composition">Octet</tei:rs> proceed with good
          <tei:term>voice-leading</tei:term>. <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs> promised to intervene on his behalf in connection with publication
        by <tei:rs key="entity-002890" type="organization">Breitkopf &amp; Härtel</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>It is also very gratifying to report that a pupil of <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Hans</tei:rs>'s, Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000754" type="person">Salzer</tei:rs> (a member of the <tei:rs key="entity-004688" type="person">Wittgenstein
          family</tei:rs>), took care of the very, very considerable costs of <tei:hi rend="underline">fourteen</tei:hi> rehearsals with <tei:hi rend="underline">eight</tei:hi>
        musicians (<tei:hi rend="underline">two</tei:hi> of whom are concert masters), and for the
        provision of food and drink for about 100 guests on two evenings. Things of that sort do not
        happen to me. I have the incomparably wealthier <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hoboken</tei:rs> at my side, a real nabob; and in spite of all the trouble that I take, I
        cannot gain his <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">material</tei:add> support for
        my life's work. He simply will not listen; he takes the view that, by paying me his <tei:hi rend="underline">hourly</tei:hi> fee, he is my "<tei:soCalled>benefactor</tei:soCalled>" –
        that is literally how he puts it – though I charge him <tei:note type="editorial">continuing
          in top margin, upside down:</tei:note> the same amount as my Viennese pupils, instead of
        asking for twice as much! If I am not mistaken, <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hoboken</tei:rs> has, however, made himself very unpopular in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs> on account of his <tei:note type="editorial">continuing in
          left margin, top to bottom:</tei:note> improper behavior. He is not to be helped. For the
        time being, do not say anything further about it.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>How are you otherwise?</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Many greetings to all of you from me and <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen</tei:rs>.</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Yours,</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-55"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Heinrich
            Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>