<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2487" sdoID="OJ-70-35_2">OJ 70/35, [2]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="AS" scope="sole">Arnold Schoenberg's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB-WD">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2011, 2020</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2020</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2020</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-07-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-007495">ViolinM ~
        ASchoenberg</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schoenberg to Moriz Violin, dated April 10, 1902</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1902-04-10T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-08-19</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schoenberg rarely goes to the [Buntes] Theater. He insists on receiving a
        report from Violin on a performance of his Verklärte Nacht.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Theater; Tournee; touring company; Tanz; dance; Sextett; sextet; Bericht; report;
        Gegner; opponents; Kritik; review; Programmusik; program music; Analyse;
        analysis</dc:subject>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000798">ASchoenberg</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:placeName>Berlin</tei:placeName>
          <tei:date when="1902-04-10">10/IV. 1902</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Violin</tei:rs>,<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">The document from which this edition
            was made is a photocopy; the whereabouts of the original is not
          known.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Sie müssen entschuldigen, daß ich Ihnen erst heute schreibe. Aber da Sie ‒ von mir
        ohnedies nicht erfahren können, was Sie erster Linie interessiert, wird die Verspätung doch
        hoffentlich nicht zu ernst genommen. Ich komme nämlich äußerst selten und nur auf Augenblick
        ins Theater und weiß daher gar nicht was dort vorgeht. Es ist das zum großen Theil Absicht,
        da ich möglichst wenig von dieser Pestilenz-Bande wissen will. Außerdem ist es mir angenehm
        im Arbeiten nicht gestört zu sein. ‒ Das einzige was ich weiß, ist, daß die <tei:hi
          rend="lateinschr">Tournee</tei:hi>'ler kaum noch zürückkehren werden und daß Frau <tei:hi
          rend="lateinschr">D’Estree</tei:hi><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Olga d'Estrée, singer associated with Wolzogen's Buntes Theater.</tei:note>
        mit ist. Die einzigen von Theater mit denen ich hie und da rede sind <tei:unclear
          reason="reading"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Levetzon</tei:hi></tei:unclear> und
        Wendland.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Ihre letzte Karte<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Violin's postcard is not known to survive.</tei:note> war mir <tei:choice>
          <tei:sic>theilsweis</tei:sic>
          <tei:corr>theilweise</tei:corr>
        </tei:choice> unverständlich. Insbesondere der Satz in dem von<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Schoenberg has omitted to cross out this "von" after having
          changed from passive to active voice midway through the sentence.</tei:note> Sie von einem
        Tanz sprechen den <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000727">Rosé</tei:rs> und die
        Leihanstalt zu meinem Sextett<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Schoenberg's <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-004781"><tei:title level="m"
              >Verklärte Nacht</tei:title></tei:rs> for string sextet, completed in December 1899,
          was first performed at the Vienna Musikverein on March 18, 1902.</tei:note> brauchen. Was
        meinen Sie <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">damit</tei:hi>? Bitte erklären Sie mir das näher. Ich
        habe von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000727">Rosé</tei:rs> kaum Nachricht, weiß also
        garnicht, was das bedeuten soll und kann daher die Anspielung nicht verstehen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Von Ihrem versprochenen Briefe mit 2färbigem Bericht über mein Sextett
        kann ich Sie nicht los sprechen. Den müssen Sie mir noch schreiben. Und dann auch was Sie
        von Gegnern „sachliches“ gehört haben. Aus den Kritiken kann man ja gar nichts
        diesbezügliches entnehmen. Schwätzereien über Kunstformen, Programmusik und dergleichen
          <tei:pb n="3"/> interessieren mich nicht. Dagegen würde ich gerne einiges musikalisches
        darüber hören. Davon war in den Kritiken natürlich nichts zu lesen. Ich habe zwar nicht die
        Absicht mich nach den Rathschlägen der Kritik zu bessern, auch habe ich keine eingehende
        Analyse erwartet.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Aber ich möchte doch wissen, was meine Gegner <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >musikalisch-sachlich</tei:hi> gegen mein Werk einwenden. Also bitte schreiben Sie. Auch
        ausführlich Ihr Verhältnis dazu. —</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Außer <tei:hi rend="underline">diesem</tei:hi> nicht mehr Neuen nicht noch
        eine <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overwritten">G</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="superimposed">g</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>anze Unzahl anderer ebenfalls nicht mehr neuer Dinge <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >nicht</tei:hi>. Berichten kann ich Ihnen also sonst nichts. Aber Sie herzlichst grüßen
        und Ihnen sagen, daß ich auch auf Ihren Brief freue.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798">Arnold
            Schönberg</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine>Berlin N./58 Letterstraße 9. I - rechts</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:placeName>Berlin</tei:placeName>, <tei:date
            when="1902-04-10">April 10, 1902</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Violin</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>You must excuse me for writing to you only now. But since in any event you cannot learn
        from me that which interests you most of all, then I hope that you will not take the delay
        too seriously. In fact I very rarely go to the Theater, and only on the spur of the moment,
        and so do not know anything about what goes on there. That is in great part intentional,
        since I want to have as little to do with this band of trouble-makers. In addition, I do not
        like to be disturbed when working ‒ The only thing that I know is that the touring companies
        will hardly ever return, and that Mrs. D'Estree<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> is among them. The only theaters with which I am occasionally in contact
        are the <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">Levetzon</tei:unclear> and the
        Wendland.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Your last postcard<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> was
        partly unintelligible to me. In particular, the sentence in which you speak of a dance,
        which <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000727">Rosé</tei:rs> and the pawnbrokers need for
        my Sextet.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> What do you mean by this? Please
        explain in greater detail. I hardly ever get news from <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000727">Rosé</tei:rs> and so have no idea what that might mean and can
        therefore not understand your allusion.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I cannot absolve you from writing your promised letter with a two-color
        report about my Sextet; you must still write it to me. And then also any "objective"
        comments you have heard from my opponents. From the reviews, one cannot gather anything
        along these lines. Blathering about art-forms, program music and the like <tei:pb n="3"/> do
        not interest me. On the other hand, I would gladly like to hear something of musical
        substance about it; there was, naturally, nothing of this in the reviews. It is of course
        not my intention to improve myself according to the critics' advice; nor have I expected a
        detailed analysis.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">But I would still like to know what my opponents have to say, <tei:hi
          rend="underline">from a musically objective point of view</tei:hi>, against my work. So
        please write. And also, at length, your own relationship to it. —</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Apart from <tei:hi rend="underline">this</tei:hi>, nothing further that is
        new, <tei:hi rend="underline">not</tei:hi> even a multitude of things that are no longer
        new. Thus I cannot report to you anything further. Except to greet you most cordially and to
        tell you that I look forward to your letter.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798">Arnold
            Schönberg</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine>Berlin N./58 Letterstraße 9. I - right</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
