<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="867" sdoID="OJ-71-20_2">OJ 71/20, [2]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>
  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="sole">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2013</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML encoding, 2013</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
   <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
   <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2013-03-24" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>
 <sdo:record ID="r0001">
  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-004398">Kestenberg ~
    HWeisse</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>


   <dc:title>Handwritten copy of a letter from Leo Kestenberg to Hans Weisse, in the hand of
    Jeanette Schenker, dated August 4, 1930</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1930-08-04T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2013-03-24</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Pleased that Weisse is intent on promoting Schenker’s theoretical work,
    Kestenberg invites Weisse to give a lecture at the Central Institute for Music Education and
    Teaching, and offers his support for Weisse speaking at the Academy for Church and School Music
    and the Conservatory [Hochschule für Musik] in Charlottenburg.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Vortrag; lecture; Aufgabe; assignment; Ueberblick; survey; klassisch; classical;
    Titel; title; Thema; theme; topic; Verwirklichung; realization; Musikabteilung; Music
    Department; Pädagogik; pedagogy</dc:subject>



  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000431">Kestenberg</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000152">HWeisse</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#JS"/><tei:supplied reason="identity">Absender:</tei:supplied>Ministerialrat Kestenberg</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>Berlin W 8, den <tei:date when="1930-08-04">4 August
      1930</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>Unter den Linden 4</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address><tei:lb/>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-20"><tei:supplied reason="identity">An: </tei:supplied>Herrn
       D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi> Hans Weisse</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">Wien dzt XVIII</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">Khevenhüllergasse 6</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:salute>Sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Doktor</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Two copies of
      this letter, both in Jeanette Schenker's hand, are preserved in OJ 71/20. Schenker records
      first having seen these letters in his diary at OJ 4/3, p. 3507, August 20, 1930: "Von Weisse
      (Br.): zwei Briefe von Ministerialrat Kestenberg u. Weisses beide Antworten – ein Erfolg, wie
      ich ihn so bald nicht zu erleben hoffen durfte! Furtwänglers Anstrengung scheint nun Früchte
      zu zeitigen. Schließlich werden meine Erfolge auch die seinen sein, denn wozu taugt noch ein
      Dirigent, wenn die „Neue Musik“ sich kraft der Propaganda u. der Wucht der Zerstörung zuletzt
      behauptet? Der Ton Kestenbergs ist so überschwänglich, wie ihn die Sache wirklich verdient."
      ("From Weisse (letter): two letters from Minister Kestenberg and Weisse's two replies – a
      success which I would never have expected him to experience so soon! Furtwängler's efforts
      thus appear to have borne fruit. In the end, my successes will also be his, for what value
      does a conductor still possess if the “New Music” asserts itself in the end, thanks to
      publicity and the force of destruction? — The tone of Kestenberg’s letter is as enthusiastic
      as the cause truly deserves.").<tei:lb/> The copying of the letters is recorded ibid, p. 3508,
      August 23, 1930: "Lie-Liechen fertigt eine Abschrift der Kestenberg-Briefe aus." ("Lie-Liechen
      writes out a copy of the Kestenberg letters."), and Schenker returned the letters to Weisse
      the same day. The making of the second, paleographically identical copy of each seems not to
      be recorded. </tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ihre liebenswürdigen Zeilen vom <tei:date when="1930-07-18">18. v.
     M.</tei:date><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Weisse's communication
     is not known to survive.</tei:note> begegnen meinem größten Interesse. Ich danke Ihnen
    aufrichtig für Ihr ausführliches Schreiben, durch das ich ein lebhaftes Bild Ihrer geistigen
    Herkunft und Entwicklung empfangen habe. Daß Heinrich Schenkers Werk im Mittelpunkt Ihres ganzes
    Wollens und Wirkens steht, berührt mich außerordentlich sympathisch. Ich freue mich zu hören,
    daß Sie sich der wichtigen Aufgabe unterziehen, einen kritischen Ueberblick über die
    zeitgenössischen, <tei:term>musiktheoretisch</tei:term>en Gedanken zu geben. Das Ergebnis, zu
    dem Sie kommen und das Sie wiederum zur Erkenntnis der großen Bedeutung von Schenker führt, hat
    für mich nichts Ueberraschendes: die gegenwärtige Situation in der <tei:term>musikalischen
     Komposition</tei:term> führt ja geradezu zu einer Erneuerung und Wiedergeburt der klassischen
    Grundgesetze (mit Ihrem Thema „Neuland der klassischen Musik“ scheinen Sie mir auf eben diese
    Zusammenhänge hinzudeuten), und deshalb steht Schenkers Werk nicht beziehungslos als leere
     <tei:term>Theorie</tei:term> da, sondern in engster Verbindung zur <tei:term>Praxis</tei:term>.
    Ich darf hier gleich hinzufügen, daß ich es besonders begrüße, daß auch Sie bei allen Vor-
     <tei:pb n="2"/> schlägen, die Sie mir unterbreiten, diesen Zusammenhang mit dem lebendigen
    Kunstwerk wahren.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Sie werden aus meinen einleitenden Bemerkungen bereits ersehen haben, daß die
    Titel, die Sie mir für Ihre Vorträge vorschlagen, im allgemeinen meine vollste Billigung finden.
    Sollte ich mich für einige von diesen Themen im besonderen entscheiden, so würde ich vielleicht
    folgende drei herausgreifen: „Kritik der musikalischen Grundbegriffe“, „Schöpferisches Hören“
    und „Was ist <tei:term>Kontrapunkt</tei:term>“.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">The last of these topics, "What is Counterpoint?", was written up by Weisse as a
     formal essay, a copy of which is preserved as OC 17/3. Weisse also gave a lecture in Hamburg in
     September 1931 entitled "Creative Hearing, Hearing-based Creativity" („Schöpferisches Hören,
     hörerisches Schöpfen“). </tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Was nun die praktische Verwirklichung der Vorträge betrifft, so könnte ich
    Ihnen zunächst in Aussicht stellen, daß ich Sie von der Musikabteilung des <tei:rs key="entity-003058" type="organization">Zentralinstituts für Erziehung und Unterricht</tei:rs>
    zu einem Vortrag für den Winter 1930/31 auffordern werde. Es wäre mich lieb, wenn wir dann auf
    eines der drei von mir genannten Themen zurückkommen könnten. Ich glaube, daß Sie gerade im
     <tei:rs key="entity-003058" type="organization">Zentralinstitut</tei:rs> einen Hörerkreis
    finden würden, der an einer Darstellung der zeitgenössischen
     <tei:term>musiktheoretisch</tei:term>en Grundbegriffe lebhaft interessiert wäre. Daß bei einem
    Vortrag im <tei:rs key="entity-003058" type="organization">Zentralinstitut für Erziehung und
     Unterricht</tei:rs> die Beziehung zur Pädagogik in besonderem Maße herausgestellt werden müßte,
    versteht sich von selbst. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Um Ihnen zu ermöglichen, daß Sie dem Vortrag im <tei:rs key="entity-003058" type="organization">Zentralinstitut</tei:rs> noch andere folgen lassen können, will ich
    versuchen die Leitungen der <tei:rs key="entity-004399" type="organization">Akademie für
     Kirchen- und</tei:rs>
    <tei:pb n="3"/>
    <tei:rs key="entity-004399" type="organization">Schulmusik</tei:rs> und die <tei:rs key="entity-003096" type="organization">Hochschule für Musik in Charlottenburg</tei:rs> für Sie
    zu interessieren.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Bitte lassen Sie mich recht bald wissen, wie Sie zu meinem Vorschlag eines
    Vortrages im <tei:rs key="entity-003058" type="organization">Zentralinstitut für Erziehung und
     Unterricht</tei:rs> stehen würden</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Mit verbindlichsten Empfehlungen bin ich</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr sehr ergebener</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000431" type="person">Leo
     Kestenberg</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>
  </tei:div>

  <tei:div type="translation">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#JS"/><tei:supplied reason="identity">From:</tei:supplied>Ministerial Counsellor Kestenberg,</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>Berlin W 8, <tei:date when="1930-08-04">4 August 1930</tei:date>,</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>Unter den Linden 4</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address><tei:lb/>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-20"><tei:supplied reason="identity">To: </tei:supplied> Dr. Hans
      Weisse,</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">Vienna currently at XVIII,</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-50">Khevenhüllergasse 6</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:salute>Dear Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Your kind message of the <tei:date when="1930-07-18">18th of <tei:supplied reason="clarity">last</tei:supplied> month</tei:date><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> meets with my greatest interest. I thank you sincerely for your informative
    letter, from which I have gained a lively picture of your intellectual background and
    development. That Heinrich Schenker’s work stands at the center of your entire life and work
    touches me in a most deeply sympathetic way. I am delighted to hear that you are undertaking the
    important assignment of offering a critical survey of contemporary
     <tei:term>music-theoretical</tei:term> thought. The results that you have arrived at, and that
    in turn lead to the recognition of the great importance of Schenker, come as no great surprise
    to me: the current situation of <tei:term>musical composition</tei:term> must lead to nothing
    short of a renewal and rebirth of basic classical principles ‒ with your topic "Reclaimed
    Territory of Classical Music," you seem to be referring to these very connections ‒ and
    therefore Schenker's work does not exist in isolation as empty <tei:term>theory</tei:term>, but
    rather is most closely related to <tei:term>practice</tei:term>. I might add here straightaway
    that I am especially pleased to see that you, too, in all the suggestions <tei:pb n="2"/> that
    you have made to me, preserve this relationship to the living work of art.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">From these introductory remarks of mine, you will have already realized that
    the titles that you have suggested for your lectures generally meet with my complete approval.
    Were I to decide upon some of these topics in particular, I would single out the following
    three: "Critique of the Basic Concepts of Music," "Creative Hearing," and "What is
     Counterpoint?"<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Now, as far as the practical realization is concerned, I can in the first
    instance offer you the prospect of an invitation from the Music Division of the <tei:rs key="entity-003058" type="organization">Central Institute for Education and Teaching</tei:rs>
    to give a lecture during the winter of 1930/31. For me it would be attractive if we could return
    to one of the three topics that I named. I believe that, precisely in the <tei:rs key="entity-003058" type="organization">Central Institute</tei:rs>, you would find a circle of
    listeners who are actively interested in a demonstration of contemporary fundamental
     <tei:term>music-theoretical</tei:term> principles. It goes without saying that, at a lecture at
    the <tei:rs key="entity-003058" type="organization">Central Institute for Education and
     Teaching</tei:rs>, the relationship to pedagogy ought to be emphasised to a considerable
    degree.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In order that you will be able follow your lecture at the <tei:rs key="entity-003058" type="organization">Central Institute</tei:rs> with others, I shall seek to
    interest the administrations of the <tei:rs key="entity-004399" type="organization">Academy for
     Church and</tei:rs>
    <tei:pb n="3"/>
    <tei:rs key="entity-004399" type="organization">School Music</tei:rs> and the <tei:rs key="entity-003096" type="organization">Conservatory of Music in Charlottenburg</tei:rs> in
    your work.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Please let me know as soon as possible what you think of my suggestion for a
    lecture at the <tei:rs key="entity-003058" type="organization">Central Institute for Education
     and Teaching</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">With my most sincere regards, I am </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Yours very truly,</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000431" type="person">Leo
     Kestenberg</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>
  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>