<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2547" sdoID="OJ-70-1_1">OJ 70/1, [1]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="MV" scope="major">Moriz Violin's hand, in ink</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="unk" scope="minor">unknown hand, in pencil</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2020</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2020</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2020</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-07-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-007675">Violin ~
        Schwabacher</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-007495">ViolinM ~
        ASchoenberg</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten draft letter from Moriz Violin to Mrs. Schwabacher, undated [c. July 10,
        1941]</dc:title>
      <dcterms:created>1941-07-10T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-09-18</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Violin reports – perhsps protests – to Mrs. Schwabacher on his interview with
        her agent, Mr. Pettis.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Interesse; interest; Unterredung; conversation; Intervention; mediation;
        Betreibung; pursuit; Ziel; goal; Rucksack; Bericht; report; Erklärungen; explanatory
        comments; Zutrauen; trust; Wahrheit; truth; Sachlichkeit; objectivity; Menschlichkeit;
        humanity; Diskussion; discussion; Lebenslauf; curriculum vitae; Ideen; ideas; Theorie;
        theory; Denkfehler; fallacy; Management; Notwendigkeit; need; Westen; west; Osten; east;
        Mangel; lack; deficiency; Beschwerden; complaints; Betätigungsfeld; prospects;
        Verhältnissen; conditions; Musikleben; musical life; Beteiligung; attendance; Composition;
        modern; unmodern; not modern; Recht; right; Unrecht; wrong; Memorandum; Beurteilung;
        judgement; Politik; politics; Chance</dc:subject>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-007674">Mrs. Schwabacher</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:add><tei:handShift new="#unk"/>wrong inference</tei:add>
        <tei:salute><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">no salutation</tei:note><tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">This four-page document comprises (1)
            a completely drafted German text in ink in Violin's hand, initialled rather than
            formally signed, and without salutation; (2) an incomplete English translation in pencil
            in uncertain hand (not included here), with partial salutation "Dear Mrs. . . . :", and
            with crossings-out and insertions. — Editorial identification of the recipient, on the
            basis of the above "Mrs.", is determined by the content of surrounding Violin/Schoenberg
            letters. Whether a final version, either in German or in English, was produced, and if
            so whether that was sent, is unknown. — Editorial dating is taken from Violin's remark
            in <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="LC-ASC-27-45_26">LC ASC 27/45, [26]</tei:ref>,
            March 29, 1941: "In the coming days I will have the first discussion here about my idea
            of an institute in San Francisco" and his letter to Schoenberg of July 20, 1941
              (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="LC-ASC-27-45_29">LC ASC 27/45, [29]</tei:ref>).
            — The content of the letter parallels to a large extent Violin's letter to Schoenberg of
            July 20, 1941 (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="LC-ASC-27-45_29">LC ASC 27/45,
              [29]</tei:ref>), with significant detail in each that does not appear in the
            other.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p><tei:handShift new="#MV"/>Darf ich Ihnen durch 3 Gründe erklären warum ich es wage mich
        wieder an Sie zu wenden? </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich tue es: 1.) weil Sie die erste Persönlichkeit waren die Interesse für
          unsere<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">"unsere" ("our"): by
          this, also other occurrences in this letter and a remark in the penultimate paragraph, it
          is clear that Violin means himself and Schoenberg. In the Violin/Schoenberg correspondence
          of 1940–41, "Idee" ("idea" – usually singular) typically refers to Violin's plan to
          establish an "institute" in San Francisco, involving Schoenberg, himself, Eduard
          Steuermann, and one other person (cf. in particular <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="LC-ASC-27-45_27">LC ASC 27/45, [27]</tei:ref>, April 14, 1941).</tei:note> “Ideen”
        zeigte, <tei:lb/>2.) weil ich in der Zwischenzeit eine Unterredung hatte, die durch Ihre
        freundliche Intervention zustande kam u. die blitzartig das jenige aufreizte, was ich Ihnen
          seinerzeit<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">In January–April
          1941, Violin had given a course of lectures at the Jewish Center in San Francisco. One of
          those who attended was a Mrs. Schwabacher, and after hearing Violin talk about and play
          Bach she was enthusiastic and declared that something must be done to keep Violin in San
          Francisco (see Violin's letter to Schoenberg of July 20, 1941, <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="LC-ASC-27-45_29">LC ASC 27/45, [29]</tei:ref>). Thus
          Violin's "prediction" must have occurred in an exchange between him and Mrs. Schwabacher
          at some point between January and mid-July. The "Unterredung" referred to here is the
          interview with Mr. Pettis (see footnote 4, below).</tei:note> voraussagte, <tei:lb/>3.)
        weil ich, schon aus ernstem Respekt vor <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798"
          >Schönberg</tei:rs>, mich und ihn davor bewahren möchte durch Betreibung einer eventuell
        aussichtslosen Sache, die Zeit zu versäumen, die wir <tei:del rend="overstrike">unbedingt
          aufbringen</tei:del> dringend verwenden müssen um ein Ziel zu erreichen, um unsere
        Rucksäcke zu packen u. alles dort zu versuchen, wo es vielleicht doch möglich ist. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Einen ausführlichen Bericht mit Erklärungen habe ich Ihnen nun zu geben
        über meine Unterredung mit Mr. Petis.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Mr. Pettis was an agent of some sort for Mrs. Schwabacher. She instructed
          Pettis to interview Violin, an interview which took place in early/mid-July 1941, as
          described in Violin's letter to Schoenberg of July 20, 1941 (<tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="LC-ASC-27-45_29">LC ASC 27/45, [29]</tei:ref>). That
          description parallels the description given here, with some independent detail.</tei:note>
        Wenn ich nun aus meinem Herzen keine Mördergrube machen werde, so können Sie nur dadurch zum
        Verständnis u. nie zum Mißverständnis meiner Worte kommen, wenn Sie Zutrauen zu einem
        Menschen fassen wollen, der durch jahrzentelange Erfahrungen, bittere Erfahrungen, nur die
        Resultate der Wahrheit sehen will u. kann u. sie nur aus sachlichen Gründen aussprechen will
        u. kann.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich habe in der ganzen Unterredung mit Mr. P. nie Ihren Namen erwähnt, der
        aber ungenannt hinter ihr stand, da Sie sie ja gütigst herbeiführten.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Sie werden den Unterschied zwischen Sachlichkeit u. irregehender
        Menschlichkeit sofort erkennen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich kam zu Mr. P’s Wohnung u. wartete 25 Minuten auf ihn u. als er kam
        begrüßten wir uns freundlichst. Er wartete auf die Eröffnung der Diskussion u. ich, der
        nicht wusste was ich von ihm verlangen sollte oder wollte, stellte mich ihm durch den von
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798">Schönberg</tei:rs> geschriebenen Lebenslauf vor
        u. begann, um zu beginnen, mit der Erzählung unserer Ideen. Trotzdem er z.B. nichts über die
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs>’sche Theorie wusste, fand die
        Koppelung mit <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798">Schönberg</tei:rs> recht
          <tei:sic>interressant</tei:sic>. Doch lag in seiner ersten Reaktion der Denkfehler No. I.
        — Er erzählte mir frank u. frei daß er berufen ist eine Erweiterung des <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-007670">S. F. Conservatorium</tei:rs>s zu arrangieren, daß
        es schädlich ist mit so viel neuen (!) Ideen aufzumarschieren, weil eine der anderen schaden
        kann u. daß es <tei:pb n="2"/> besser ist die Dinge unter <tei:choice>
          <tei:sic>einem</tei:sic>
          <tei:corr>einen</tei:corr>
        </tei:choice> Hut zu bringen. Ich konnte ihm nicht sagen daß für uns eine Idee neu ist, wenn
        die Idee neu ist. Wenn aber die Idee eines neuen <tei:term xml:lang="eng"
          >Management</tei:term> auftritt, so ist nur das <tei:term xml:lang="eng"
          >Management</tei:term> neu, u. das heißt Totes auf Totes legen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Der Denkfehler No II kam bei der Besprechung der Notwendigkeiten für den
        Westen u. der Vergleichung mit dem Osten zustande. <tei:hi rend="underline">Sein</tei:hi>
        beabsichtigter Schritt kann doch nur die Consequenz der Erkenntnis eines Mangels sein u.
        wenn ich, gestütz durch einen Artikel von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-007665">Prof.
          Elkus</tei:rs> im <tei:title>Chronicle</tei:title>, gestütz durch Berichte aus dem Osten,
        gestützt durch Beschwerden hier, warum alles nach dem Osten geht wodurch der Betätigungsfeld
        der Musiker hier so eingeengt ist, sprach, wenn ich weiters davon sprach daß <tei:hi
          rend="underline">unsere</tei:hi> Idee sogar Menschen aus dem Osten anlocken müsste, gab er
        mir, ich glaube etwas geärgert so ungefähr zur Antwort, daß ich nichts von amerikanischen
        Verhältnissen weiß u. daher nicht weiß, daß trotz der 8 Millionen Menschen in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002873">New York</tei:rs>, das Musikleben dort gering gegen
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002921">S. F.</tei:rs> ist u. ebenso ist das Verhältnis
        mit dem Interesse u. der Beteiligung. Alles ist hier viel entwickelter, historischer u.
        traditioneller. Ist dann aber nicht alles in schönster Ordnung? Warum dann alles?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun kam aber der merkwürdigste Denkfehler No 3. Er fragte mich ob ich Compositionen
        habe. Als ich vorbeugend sagte daß ich nicht zwischen moderner oder unmoderner, sondern nur
        zwischen guter oder schlechter Musik unterscheide, stimmte er mir zu indem er mir sagte, daß
        er auch nur von kontemporären Componisten spreche. Er fragte mich wann ich mein
        Streichquartett komponierte. Ich sagte vor 30 Jahren. Er meinte das wäre zu lange her. Ich
        sagte ihm daß <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798">Schönberg</tei:rs> zu dieser Zeit
          “<tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-005683"><tei:title>Pierrot</tei:title></tei:rs>”
          “<tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-004704"
          ><tei:title>Gurrelieder</tei:title></tei:rs>” etc. komponierte. Er sagte dann daß sich
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798">Schönberg</tei:rs> ganz geändert habe.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich wollte ihn nicht beleidigen, sonst hätte ich Mr. P. sagen müssen daß
        wir seinerzeit gelacht hätten wenn jemand sich geweigert hätte das <tei:rs
          type="composition" key="entity-004907"><tei:title>Trio op. 8</tei:title></tei:rs> von
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs> zu spielen, weil <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs> bereits ein <tei:rs type="composition"
          key="entity-007676"><tei:title>Trio op. <tei:choice>
              <tei:sic>104</tei:sic>
              <tei:corr>114</tei:corr>
            </tei:choice></tei:title></tei:rs> geschrieben hat.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Op. 104 is a set of five songs. Brahms's Trio in B major,
          Op. 8, for violin, cello, and piano,was composed in 1853–54; his Trio in A minor, Op. 114,
          for clarinet (or viola), cello, and piano, was composed in 1891, thus 37 years later.
          (Violin has "114" correctly in <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="LC-ASC-27-45_29">LC
            ASC 27/45, [29]</tei:ref>, July 20, 1941.)</tei:note> Nun <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >heute</tei:hi> wird <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-004907"><tei:title>op.
            8</tei:title></tei:rs> gespielt u. nicht <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-007676"
            ><tei:title>op. <tei:choice>
              <tei:sic>104</tei:sic>
              <tei:corr>114</tei:corr>
            </tei:choice></tei:title></tei:rs>. Ob mit Recht oder Unrecht ist eine andere Frage.
          <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-007676"><tei:title>op. <tei:choice>
              <tei:sic>104</tei:sic>
              <tei:corr>114</tei:corr>
            </tei:choice></tei:title></tei:rs> ist wirklich bedeutender.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="3"/> Ich möchte noch sagen, daß ich vor Bescheidenheit in die
          <tei:sic>Kniee</tei:sic> sinken würde, wenn <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094"
          >Brahms</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000116">Busoni</tei:rs>, <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000798">Schönberg</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003351"
          >Nikisch</tei:rs> u.s.w. einen Componisten empfehlen würden u. nicht sagen: “Lassen Sie
        mich etwas sehen.” Ich meine: Es könnte sich ereignen daß mir die Komposition nicht zusagt —
        — dann würde ich sie unter einer Ausrede einfach nicht spielen u.s.w.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Mister P. <tei:sic>interressiert</tei:sic> sich für das Memorandum von mir
        u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798">Schönberg</tei:rs>.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">"Memorandum": in <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="LC-ASC-27-45_27">LC ASC 27/45, [27</tei:ref>], April 14,
          1941, Violin wrote of a desire to visit Schoenberg to discuss "finalizing ideological and
          practical matters in the form of a memorandum" concerning his plan to establish an
          "institute" in San Francisco. There is no indication whether such a document was ever
          drafted, although in the final paragraph here Violin seems to imply that it exists. The
          word is not used in Violin's report to Schoenberg of his encounter with Mr. Pettis of July
          20, 1941 (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="LC-ASC-27-45_29">LC ASC 27/45,
            [29]</tei:ref>), but as they parted Pettis said that Mrs. Schwabacher expected Violin to
          ask Schoenberg "to draw up general guidelines (<tei:hi rend="italic">gemeinsame
            Richtlinien</tei:hi>)," and that he would be "very interested in those."</tei:note> Ich
        weiß aber genau daß <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798">Sch.</tei:rs> es nie einem
        Musiker zur Beurteilung vorlegen würde, sondern nur Menschen die einer toten Idee finanziell
        helfen wollten.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Sie sehen es kam wie ich es voraussagte. Wir sind fehl am Orte der
        Politik. Darf ich Sie also im Principe nochmals fragen ob Sie für das Memorandum Interesse
        haben u. ob Sie überhaupt an eine Chance glauben?</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr sehr dankbarer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">MV</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:add><tei:handShift new="#unk"/><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi
              rend="italic">in English:</tei:hi></tei:note>wrong inference</tei:add>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#MV"/><tei:supplied reason="omission">Dear Mrs.
            Schwabacher,</tei:supplied><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="italic">in
          German:</tei:hi></tei:note> May I explain to you why, on three accounts, I take the
        liberty of turning to you once again?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I do so: (1) because you were the first person to show an interest in our<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> "ideas," <tei:lb/>(2) because in the meantime, I
        have had a conversation that came about through your kind mediation and, like a bolt from
        the blue, raised the specter of that which I had earlier<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
          type="footnote"/> predicted to you. <tei:lb/>(3) because, out of deep respect for <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000798">Schoenberg</tei:rs>, I should like to protect both him
        and myself from time wasted pursuing a cause that may prove hopeless – time that we need
        urgently to employ in achieving a goal, and in packing our bags and putting all our efforts
        somewhere else, where it actually <tei:hi rend="italic">is</tei:hi> possible <tei:supplied
          reason="clarity">to make headway</tei:supplied>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I now have to give you a detailed report, with explanatory comments, of
        the conversation I had with Mr. Petis.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> If I
        lay bare my most private thoughts, then you can come to understand – and not misunderstand –
        my words if only you are willing to place your trust in a person who through decades of
        experience – bitter experience – will and can see only the results of the truth, and will
        and can articulate them only for objective reasons.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Throughout my conversation with Mr. P., I never once mentioned your name
        which, however, lurked unspoken in the background, since it was you who most kindly brought
          <tei:supplied reason="clarity">the conversation</tei:supplied> about.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">You will instantly recognize the difference between objectivity and errant
        humanity.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I arrived at Mr. P.'s home and was kept waiting 25 minutes for him. When
        he appeared, we greeted one another in the friendliest manner. He left me to open the
        discussion, and I, not knowing what I should ask of or want from him, introduced myself by
        offering him the <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">curriculum vitae</tei:foreign> written by
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798">Schoenberg</tei:rs>. Then I began, so as to get
        things started, with a presentation of our ideas. Despite the fact that, for example, he
        knew nothing of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs>'s theory,
          <tei:supplied reason="clarity">he</tei:supplied> found the connection with <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000798">Schoenberg</tei:rs> really interesting. — It was in his
        first reaction that fallacy no. 1 arose. — He told me quite openly that he had been given
        the job of expanding the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-007670">San Francisco
          Conservatory</tei:rs>, and that it is detrimental to come forward with so many new (!)
        ideas because any one idea can undermine the others; that it <tei:pb n="2"/> is better to
        marshall them under one main idea. I couldn't say to him that for us an idea is new when the
        idea itself is new. When, on the other hand, the idea is one of a new management, then only
        the management is new, and that amounts to the laying of one inanimate thing on
        another.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Fallacy no. 2 emerged in the discussion of what is needed for the west
          <tei:supplied reason="clarity">coast</tei:supplied> and the comparison with the east
          <tei:supplied reason="clarity">coast</tei:supplied>. <tei:hi rend="underline">His</tei:hi>
        deliberate next move can surely only have been the consequence of an awareness of
        deficiency. When I spoke – supported by an article by <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-007665">Prof. Elkus</tei:rs> in the <tei:supplied reason="abbreviation"
            ><tei:title level="j">San Francisco</tei:title></tei:supplied>
        <tei:title level="j">Chronicle</tei:title>, reinforced by reports from the east
          <tei:supplied reason="clarity">coast</tei:supplied>, and bolstered by complaints here as
        to why everything heads eastward, as a result of which the prospects for musicians here are
        so limited –, when I went further and said that <tei:hi rend="underline">our</tei:hi> idea
        would even be sure to attract people from the east <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
          >coast</tei:supplied>, he replied – I believe somewhat in anger – to the effect that I
        know nothing of American conditions and therefore am unaware that despite the eight million
        people living in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002873">New York</tei:rs>, the music life
        there is negligible by comparison with <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002921">San
          Francisco</tei:rs>, and that the same is true with regard to level of interest and
        attendance. Here everything is much more advanced, has a longer history, and is more
        traditional. Is not everything therefore in excellent order? Why then all <tei:supplied
          reason="clarity">this need for change</tei:supplied>?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Now came the most remarkable fallacy no. 3. He asked me whether I had any compositions.
        When, seeking to forestall him, I said that I made no distinction between modern and not
        modern music, only between good and bad, he concurred with me, saying that he too was
        speaking only of contemporary composers. He asked me when I composed my String Quartet. I
        replied thirty years ago. He said that that was too long ago. I pointed out that at that
        time <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798">Schoenberg</tei:rs> was composing his <tei:rs
          type="composition" key="entity-005683"><tei:title level="m">Pierrot</tei:title></tei:rs>,
          <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-004704"><tei:title level="m"
            >Gurrelieder</tei:title></tei:rs>, etc. He responded that <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000798">Schoenberg</tei:rs> had <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
          >since</tei:supplied> changed his style altogether.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I didn't want to insult him, otherwise I would have had to say to him that
        in those days we would have laughed if somebody had refused to play the <tei:rs
          type="composition" key="entity-004907"><tei:title>Trio Op. 8</tei:title></tei:rs> of
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs> because <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs> had already written a <tei:rs type="composition"
          key="entity-007676"><tei:title>Trio Op. <tei:choice>
              <tei:sic>104</tei:sic>
              <tei:corr>114</tei:corr>
            </tei:choice></tei:title></tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> Now
          <tei:hi rend="underline">today</tei:hi>
        <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-004907"><tei:title>Op. 8</tei:title></tei:rs> is
        played and <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-007676"><tei:title>Op. <tei:choice>
              <tei:sic>104</tei:sic>
              <tei:corr>114</tei:corr>
            </tei:choice></tei:title></tei:rs> isn't – whether rightly or wrongly is another
        question. <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-007676"><tei:title>Op. <tei:choice>
              <tei:sic>104</tei:sic>
              <tei:corr>114</tei:corr>
            </tei:choice></tei:title></tei:rs> is definitely the more important work.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="3"/> I should like also to say that I would sink to my knees
        out of modesty if <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs>, <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000116">Busoni</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000798">Schoenberg</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
          >Schenker</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003351">Nikisch</tei:rs> etc. were
        to recommend a composer and not say "Let me see something." What I mean is: it could happen
        that the composition is not to my liking — — then I would make an excuse and simply not play
        it, and so forth.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Mr. P. is interested in the memorandum by <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000798">Schoenberg</tei:rs> and myself.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06"
          type="footnote"/> But I know for sure that <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798"
          >Schoenberg</tei:rs> would never present it to a musician for judgement, only to people
        who wanted to offer financial aid to an idea that is dead.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">You see: it turned out just as I predicted. We are out of place in the
        world of politics. May I ask you therefore in principle once again whether you have any
        interest in the memorandum, and whether you believe there is any prospect
        whatsoever?</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your very grateful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">MV</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
