<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2542" sdoID="OJ-70-35_9">OJ 70/35, [9]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="AS" scope="sole">Arnold Schoenberg's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB-AW">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent &amp; Arnold Whittall</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2020</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2020</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2020</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-07-19" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-007495">ViolinM ~
        ASchoenberg</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten open letter from Schoenberg dated September 16, 1949, with handwritten
        letter from Schoenberg to Moriz Violin, dated October 14, 1949</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1949-10-14T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-09-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schoenberg sends a copy of his open letter on his 75th birthday, embedded
        within a letter in which he expresses pleasure at Violin's report of his Carmel
        performance.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000798">ASchoenberg</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:recipient>

    </sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:div>
        <tei:opener>
          <tei:address>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#AS"/>an Herrn <tei:rs type="person"
                key="entity-000913">Moriz Violin</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002921"
                >San Francisco</tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
          </tei:address>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:floatingText>
          <tei:body>
            <tei:div>
              <tei:opener/>
              <tei:lb/>
              <tei:p>Erst nach dem Tode anerkannt werden - - - - - !<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01"
                  type="editorial" place="foot">The document from which this edition was made is a
                  photocopy held by the Oswald Jonas Memorial Collection; the whereabouts of the
                  original is not known. There exists also (LC ALS) a typed version of the letter in
                  English translation (see footnote 2, below). Schoenberg's open letter is known to
                  have gone also to Helene Berg, Edward Clark, E. S. Coolidge, Luigi Dallapiccola,
                  Rudolf Goehr, Alma Mahler, Hans Nachod, Dika Newlin, Josef Rufer, Nicolas
                  Slonimsky, Leonard Stein, Eduard Steuermann, Gerald Strang, and Adolf Weiss, and
                  many others.</tei:note></tei:p>

              <tei:p rend="first">Ich habe in diesen Tagen viel persönliche Anerkennung gefunden,
                worüber ich mich sehr gefreut haben, weil sie mir die Achtung meiner Freunde und
                anderer Wohlgesinnter bezeugt.</tei:p>

              <tei:p rend="first">Andrerseits aber habe ich mich seit vielen Jahren damit
                abgefunden, dass ich auf volles und liebevolles Verständnis für mein Werk, für das
                also, was ich musikalisch zu sagen habe, bei meinen Lebzeiten nicht rechnen darf.
                Wohl weiss ich, dass mancher meiner Freunde sich in meine Ausdrucksweise bereits
                eingelebt hat und mit meinen Gedanken vertraut worden ist. Solche mögen es dann
                sein, die erfüllen, was ich vor genau siebenunddreissig Jahren in einem Aphorismus
                voraussagte:</tei:p>

              <tei:p rend="first">„Die zweite Hälfte dieses Jahrhunderts wird durch Ueberschätzung
                schlecht machen, was die erste Hälfte durch Unterschätzung gut gelassen hat an
                mir.“</tei:p>

              <tei:p rend="first">Ich bin etwas beschämt über all diese Lobpreisungen. Aber ich sehe
                dennoch auch etwas Ermutigendes darin. Nämlich: Tat es denn so selbstverständlich,
                dass man trotz dem Widerstand der ganzen Welt nicht aufgibt, sondern fortfährt
                aufzuschreiben, was man produziert?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
                  place="foot">", sondern ... produziert" (", but rather ... produces"): this clause
                  is not present in the typewritten version of the letter in translation (see
                  footnote 1, above).</tei:note></tei:p>

              <tei:p rend="first">Ich weiss nicht, wie Große darübergedacht haben. <tei:rs
                  type="person" key="entity-000612">Mozart</tei:rs> und <tei:rs type="person"
                  key="entity-000803">Schubert</tei:rs> waren jung genug, dieser Frage nicht näher
                treten zu müssen. Aber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>,
                wenn <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000306">Grillparzer</tei:rs>, die <tei:rs
                  type="composition" key="entity-001269"><tei:title>Neunte</tei:title></tei:rs>
                konfus nannte, oder <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000924">Wagner</tei:rs>, wenn
                der <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003993">Bayreuth</tei:rs>er Plan zu versagen
                drohte, oder <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000556">Mahler</tei:rs>, wenn alle
                ihn trivial fanden ‒ wie konnten diese weiterschreiben?</tei:p>

              <tei:p rend="first">Ich weiss nur eine Antwort: Sie hatten Dinge zu sagen, die gesagt
                werden mussten. Ich wurde einmal beim Militär gefragt, ob ich wirklich dieser
                Komponist A.S. bin. „Einer hat es sein müssen,“ sagte ich, „keiner hat es sein
                wollen, so habe ich mich dazu hergegeben.“</tei:p>

              <tei:p rend="first">Vielleicht musste auch ich Dinge sagen, unpopuläre erscheinend,
                die gesagt worden mussten.</tei:p>

              <tei:p>———</tei:p>

              <tei:p rend="first">Und nun bitte ich Sie alle, die Sie mir mit Ihren Glückwünschen
                und Ehrungen wirkliche Freude bereitet haben, dies anzunehmen als einen Versuch,
                meine Dankbarkeit auszudrücken ‒</tei:p>
              <tei:closer>
                <tei:salute>Vielen, herzlichsten Dank!</tei:salute>
                <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798">Arnold
                    Schoenberg</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
                <tei:dateline>Los Angeles, California, <tei:date when="1949-09-16">16. September
                    1949</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
              </tei:closer>
            </tei:div>
          </tei:body>
        </tei:floatingText>

        <tei:p>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Freund</tei:rs>!</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">wie schade, dass Sie nicht kommen konnten. Wir haben <tei:hi
            rend="underline">nicht</tei:hi> gefeiert.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
            place="foot">Schoenberg's birthday fell on September 13, thus he would have been 75 on
            that date in 1949. Hence the words " Lobpreisungen ... Glückwünschen und Ehrungen"
            ("eulogies ... congratulations and tributes") in the open letter.</tei:note> Wir haben
          allen Leuten sagen lassen, dass wir fort fahren <tei:pb n="2"/> werden, sind aber dann
          doch allein zuhause geblieben und nur wenig gestört worden. Wenn Sie gekommen wären hätten
          wir wirklich plaudern können.</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">Sie erinnern mich, dass auch Sie aufgehört haben, ein Jüngling zu sein.
          Wie geht es Ihnen. Ich hoffe, Sie sind gesünder als ich.</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">Ich habe mich sehr über Ihren Bericht über Ihr <tei:foreign
            xml:lang="eng">Lecture</tei:foreign>-Konzert gefreut.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04"
            type="editorial" place="foot">The third paragraph of this letter is clearly a response
            to <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="LC-ASC-27-45_34">LC ASC 27/45, [34]</tei:ref>,
            undated, in which Violin reports on his successful performance at the Carmel Bach
            Festival.</tei:note> Ich bin immer sicher gewesen, dass Sie dafür ein Publikum finden.
          Es scheint eine Zeit für <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000025">Philip Emanuel
            Bach</tei:rs> heranzukommen! Ich persönlich kann mich allerdings nicht für ihn
          entscheiden. Ich nehme es ihm dauernd übel, dass er seinen Vater veraltet
            genannt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">There are crosses in
            blue crayon in the left margin (presumably by Violin) against "Lecture-Konzert"
            ("lecture concert") and "Ich persönlich ... entscheiden" ("personally ...
            outmoded").</tei:note></tei:p>

        <tei:p>So Unrecht darf man nicht haben. Das erzeugt eine Stellung an der
            Geschichte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">There is a cross
            in blue crayon in the left margin (presumably by Violin) beside this
            paragraph.</tei:note></tei:p>

        <tei:p>Gerne würde ich seine Musik durch Sie näher kennen lernen.</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">Hoffentlich können Sie doch einmal kommen.</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">Ich muss soviele Dankbriefe schreiben!</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">Also hoffentlich! auf baldiges Wiedersehen.</tei:p>


        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Herzlichst Ihr</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798">Arnold
              Schoenberg</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
          <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1949-10-14">X/14. 1949</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        </tei:closer>

      </tei:div>
    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:div>
        <tei:opener>
          <tei:address>
            <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#AS"/>To: Mr. <tei:rs type="person"
                key="entity-000913">Moriz Violin</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002921"
                >San Francisco</tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
          </tei:address>
        </tei:opener>

        <tei:floatingText>
          <tei:body>
            <tei:div>
              <tei:opener/>
              <tei:lb/>
              <tei:p>To be recognized only after one's death - - - - - !<tei:ptr
                  corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

              <tei:p rend="first">In recent days I have received much personal recognition, which
                has given me great joy because it bears witness to the esteem of my friends and
                other well-disposed people.</tei:p>

              <tei:p rend="first">On the other hand, I have, however, for many years now resigned
                myself to the fact that I may not count in my lifetime on full and loving
                understanding for my work, hence for what I have said through music. I well know
                that many a friend of mine has already become accustomed to my mode of expression,
                and has become familiar with my ideas. It is they, then, who may fulfil what I
                prophesied in an aphorism precisely thirty-seven years ago:</tei:p>

              <tei:p rend="first">"The second half of this century will through overvaluation spoil
                what the first half through undervaluation has left intact of me."</tei:p>

              <tei:p rend="first">I feel somewhat shamefaced at all these eulogies. Nevertheless, I
                see in them also something heartening, to whit: Is it then so self-explanatory that
                one does not give up, despite the opposition of the whole world, but rather
                continues to compose what one produces?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
                  type="footnote"/></tei:p>

              <tei:p rend="first">I do not know what great men have thought about this. <tei:rs
                  type="person" key="entity-000612">Mozart</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person"
                  key="entity-000803">Schubert</tei:rs> were young enough not to have to address
                this question. But <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>,
                when <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000306">Grillparzer</tei:rs> deemed the
                  <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001269"><tei:title>Ninth
                    Symphony</tei:title></tei:rs> "confused," or <tei:rs type="person"
                  key="entity-000924">Wagner</tei:rs>, when his <tei:rs type="place"
                  key="entity-003993">Bayreuth</tei:rs> plan was under threat of rejection, or
                  <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000556">Mahler</tei:rs>, when everybody found
                him trivial – how could these men go on composing?</tei:p>

              <tei:p rend="first">I know only one answer: They had things to say that had to be
                said. I was once asked by the military whether I was really this composer A.S.:
                "Somebody had to be him," said I, "nobody else wanted to be, so I took it upon
                myself."</tei:p>

              <tei:p rend="first">Perhaps I, too, had things to say, seemingly unpopular things,
                that had to be said.</tei:p>

              <tei:p>———</tei:p>

              <tei:p rend="first">And now I ask all of you, you who with your congratulations and
                tributes have afforded me genuine joy, to accept this as an attempt to express my
                gratitude.</tei:p>
              <tei:closer>
                <tei:salute>Most cordial thanks!</tei:salute>
                <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798">Arnold
                    Schoenberg</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
                <tei:dateline>Los Angeles, California, <tei:date when="1949-09-16">September 16,
                    1949</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
              </tei:closer>
            </tei:div>
          </tei:body>
        </tei:floatingText>

        <tei:p>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Friend</tei:rs>,</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">What a shame you couldn't come visit. We did <tei:hi rend="underline"
            >not</tei:hi> celebrate.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> We let
          everybody know that we were going away, <tei:pb n="2"/> but then stayed all alone at home
          and were disturbed only a little. If you had come, we really could have had a good
          chat.</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">You remind me that even you have ceased being a youth. How are things
          with you? I hope you are in better health than I am.</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">I was delighted at your report of your lecture-concert.<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> I continue to be sure that you will find a
          public for it: It seems the time has come for <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000025">C.
            P. E. Bach</tei:rs>! Personally, however, I am in no position to take his side: I can
          never forgive him for calling his father outmoded.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05"
            type="footnote"/></tei:p>

        <tei:p>No one should suffer such an injustice. It sets up a historical bias.<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

        <tei:p>I would very much like to get to know his music through you.</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">I hope you will be able to come visit one of these days.</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">I have so many thankyou letters to write!</tei:p>

        <tei:p rend="first">Alright then. Let us hope to get together soon.</tei:p>


        <tei:closer>
          <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Most cordially, your</tei:salute>
          <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798">Arnold
              Schoenberg</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
          <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1949-10-14">October 14, 1949</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        </tei:closer>

      </tei:div>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
