<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2523" sdoID="OJ-70-35_7">OJ 70/35, [7]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPas" scope="major">Arnold Schoenberg as typist</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="AS" scope="minor">Arnold Schoenberg's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="stamp" scope="minor">stamp</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2020</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2020</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2020</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2013-07-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-007495">ViolinM ~
        ASchoenberg</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Typewritten letter from Schoenberg to Moriz Violin, dated April 9, 1940</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1940-04-09T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-09-03</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schoenberg tempers Violin's reaction to R. E. Stuart's letter, offering a
        sympathetic portrayal of the American character as courteous, unlike the Germans, and
        describing the attitude and degree of preparation of American students. All German criteria
        are inapplicable.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>persönlich; face-to-face; Kontakt; contact; average; Durchschittsmusiker; mediocre
        musician; Pionnier; pioneer; Höflichkeit; courtesy; Unhöflichkeit; discourtesy; boches;
        Schüler; pupils; Studenten; students; Entschuldigung; forgiveness; Massstab;
        criterion</dc:subject>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000798">ASchoenberg</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000913">ViolinM</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#stamp"/>ARNOLD SCHOENBERG</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>116 N. ROCKINGHAM AVE.</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>BRENTWOOD PARK</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>LOS ANGELES, – CALIF.</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>TELEPHONE W. L. A. 35077</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#TPas"/>Herrn Moriz Violin</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>1703 Scott Street</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>San Francisco, Calif.</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:date when="1940-04-09">April 9,
          1940</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Freund</tei:rs>:<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">The document from which this edition
            was made is a photocopy; the whereabouts of the original is not known. A number of
            typing errors have been silently corrected. — A carbon copy of this letter is preserved
            as LC ASC 7/50, [12].</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">aufrichtig gestanden: ich bin sehr froh, dass Sie nicht den Fehler gemacht
        haben, den ich in den ersten drei, vier Jahren gemacht habe. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000294">Goethe</tei:rs>s Götz<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
          place="foot">The principal character in Goethe's historically-based drama, <tei:title
            level="m">Götz von Berlichingen</tei:title> (1773). Violin had mentioned it in his
          letter of the day before, <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="LC-ASC-27-45_20">LC ASC
            27/45, [20]</tei:ref>.</tei:note> konnte mich leider nicht abhalten, mir Feinde zu
        machen, Hauptleute noch dazu, die mir grössere Freundlichkeiten hätten erweisen können, als
        die, die auch Götz nicht erreicht hat. Und wer weiss ob sie ihm wohl bekommen hätte.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">aufrichtig gestanden: dieser Brief<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Letter from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-007671">Robert
            Emmett Stuart</tei:rs> of the St. Louis Institute of Music to Moriz Violin, <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-70-38_1">OJ 70/38, [1]</tei:ref>, April 2,
          1940.</tei:note> ist in keiner Weise unverschämt <tei:hi rend="sperr">gemeint</tei:hi>. In
        einigen Jahren werden Sie mir recht geben: Amerikaner tun das nicht.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Er meint in der Tat bloss, dass er von einem Menschen, den er engagieren
          sol<tei:supplied reason="spelling">l</tei:supplied>, einen persönlichen Eindruck haben
        muss, den kein Brief, keine Empfehlung, keine Fotografie vermitteln kann, sondern nur
        persönlicher Kontakt. Und er meint, dass er, ohne Ihnen Garantie zu geben, nicht verlangen
        kann, dass Sie auf Ihre Kosten diese Reise machen. Das hätte vielleicht auch ich bedenken
        können, aber auch ich bin, nach sieben Jahren noch immer kein Native und weiss solche Sachen
        auch besser im Nachhinein.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Auch, ich bin fest überzeugt, dieses "average" ist ein Missverständnis von
        Ihnen. Er meint selbstverständlich nicht, dass Sie ein Durchschnittsmusiker sind. Amerikaner
        praktizieren noch immer dieselbe Höflichkeit, die sie als Pionniere anwenden mussten, wo
        hinter einer Unhöflichkeit die Notwendigkeit zu schiessen stand. Ausserdem sind ja alle
        Völker höflicher als Deutsche, als wir "boches". Er meint, jeder Europäer (im Durchschnitt
        jeder) insbesondere jeder Deutsche, braucht Jahre, um <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002510"><tei:country>Amerika</tei:country></tei:rs> zu verstehen, und das kann
        ich <tei:sic>bestättigen</tei:sic>, der ich heuer gesagt habe: "Nach sieben Jahren habe ich
        nun endlich beiläufig einen Begriff, wie ich amerikanische Schüler zu behandeln habe, was
        sie lernen können und wollen und wie man sie dafür interessieren kann. Sie sehen übrigens,
        dass er ausdrücklich hinzufügt, dass, wenn seine Studenten älter wären, sie viel durch Sie
        lernen würden:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">"If our students
          were older, we can well understand that you would have a great deal to give to them
          because of your association with Brahms, Busoni, and other masters." (<tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-70-38_1">OJ 70/38, [1]</tei:ref>, April 2,
          1940).</tei:note> aber und dass werden Sie sicher eines Tages einsehen: in unserem Sinn
        sind sie um 5‒8 Jahre jünger; unsere siebzehnjährigen können oft mehr, als ihre 22-jährigen:
        in gewisser Hinsicht, aber durchaus nicht in jeder. Vor allem, z.B. drückt sich jeder
        amerikanische Student schriftlich und mündlich viel klarer aus, als selbst gute Deutsche.
        Das ist auch eine Geistesschulung.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Es tut mir so leid, dass ich Ihnen durch diese <tei:pb n="2"/> Empfehlung
        eigentlich nur Aufregung verursacht habe. Ich habe die Entschuldigung, dass man so leicht
        vergisst, was man selbst nicht gewusst und erst mühsam gelernt hat. Sie wissen, dass ich
        nicht konventionell und nicht feige bin. Aber in der Tat ich habe hier etwas gelernt, was
        mir fremd war: die Sitten der Amerikaner sind von den Unsrigen so verschieden, dass alle
        unsere Massstäbe unanwendbar sind. Hinter all dem, was uns süsslich, oder hypokritisch, oder
        oberflächlich, oder sogar banal erscheint, verbergen sich Tugenden und Vorzüge, die denen
        gleichkommen, die sich hinter deutscher Rauheit, Unfreundlic<tei:supplied reason="spelling"
          >h</tei:supplied>keit und ‒ wenn man so sagen darf: Treue verbergen. Sie verbergen sich
        besser und sind umso sicherer vorhanden.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ich weiss, Sie werden mir so wenig recht geben, als ich Freunden recht gab, die 25
        Jahre länger hier waren, als ich. Das ist vielleicht etwas, was man selbst, widerstrebend
        herausfinden muss.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Hoffentlich höre ich bald wieder von Ihnen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Not having heard back from Violin, Schoenberg wrote again on
          May 19, <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="LC-ASC-7-50_14">LC ASC 7/50,
          [14]</tei:ref>.</tei:note> Ich bin sehr froh zu hören, dass <tei:sic>ihre</tei:sic>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000911">Tochter</tei:rs> schon hier ist. Und dass sie so
        bald Beschäftigung gefunden hat ist ein erfreuliches Zeichen ihrer Tüchtigkeit.</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Mit vielen herzlichsten Grüssen, Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed><tei:handShift new="#AS"/><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798">Arnold
            Schoenberg</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#stamp"/>ARNOLD SCHOENBERG</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>116 N. ROCKINGHAM AVE.</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>BRENTWOOD PARK</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>LOS ANGELES, – CALIFORNIA</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>TELEPHONE W. L. A. 35077</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#TPas"/>Mr. Moriz Violin</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>1703 Scott Street</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>San Francisco, California</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:date when="1940-04-09">April 9,
          1940</tei:date></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:salute>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Friend</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Frankly speaking, I am very happy that you have not made the mistake that
        I made in my first three or four years. Sadly, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000294"
          >Goethe</tei:rs>'s Götz<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> could
        unfortunately not restrain me from making enemies for myself – of prominent people, what's
        more, who could have extended greater friendships to me than those that even Götz failed to
        make. And who knows whether they would have welcomed him.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Frankly speaking, this letter<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
          type="footnote"/> is in no way outrageously <tei:hi rend="italic">intended</tei:hi>. In a
        few years you will see that I am right: Americans don't do that.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">All he means in fact is that he must have a personal impression of anyone
        whom he is to appoint – an impression that no letter, no recommendation, no photograph can
        convey, only face-to-face contact. And he means that, without giving you a guarantee, he
        cannot expect you to make the journey at your own expense. Even I would perhaps have thought
        that, but even I, after seven years, am still no native, and know such matters even better
        after the event.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Moreover, I am firmly convinced that this "average" is a misunderstanding
        on your part. Of course he doesn't mean that you're a mediocre musician. Americans continue
        to practise the same courtesy that they had to employ as pioneers, when impoliteness was met
        with a bullet. In addition, all peoples are more polite than Germans, than we "boches." He
        means that every European (on average, each one), especially every German, needs years to
        understand <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002510"
          ><tei:country>America</tei:country></tei:rs>, and I can confirm that, I who have this year
        said: "After seven years I now finally more or less have an idea of how I need to handle
        American students, what they are capable of learning, what they want to learn, and how one
        can get them interested in that. You see, by the way, that he expressly adds that if his
        students were older they would learn a lot from you:<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
          type="footnote"/> and that is something you will surely learn one of these days. In
        comparison with our experience, they are around five to eight years younger; our
        17-year-olds are often capable of more than their 22-year-olds: in certain respects, but not
        in every single one. Above all, for example, every American student expresses himself much
        more clearly in writing and orally than even good Germans ones. That is also a form of
        intellectual training.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I am so sorry that through this <tei:pb n="2"/> recommendation I have in
        reality caused you nothing but agitation. I can only plead the excuse that it is so easy to
        forget what one did not oneself know and first had laboriously to learn. You know that I am
        not conventional and not fainthearted. But in fact I have learned something from this that
        was unknown to me: the customs of the Americans are so different from ours that all our
        criteria are inapplicable. Behind all that appears saccharine, hypocritcal, superficial, or
        even banal to us, there lie virtues and merits that compare with those that lie behind
        German coarseness, unfriendliness and – if one may say so: loyalty. They are better
        concealed and are all the more securely present.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I know you will agree with me no more than I agreed with friends who were here
        twenty-five years before me. That is perhaps something that one has to find out grudgingly
        for oneself.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I hope to hear back from you very soon.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/>
        I am greatly pleased to hear that your <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000911"
          >daughter</tei:rs> is already here. And that she has found employment so quickly is a
        welcome sign of her capability.</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">With most cordial greetings, Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed><tei:handShift new="#AS"/><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798">Arnold
            Schoenberg</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
