<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="334" sdoID="OJ-89-2_6">OJ 89/2, [6]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="JR">
   <tei:persName>John Rothgeb</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2009</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2009</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-05-02" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002730">Hoboken ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002731">Hoboken ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Hoboken, dated June 22, 1928 </dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1928-06-22T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2011-05-02</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>With thanks for birthday greetings, Schenker expresses how highly he values the
    Photogrammarchiv while endorsing van Hoboken's turning down of an "honor" that he was offered. —
    Schenker has, at Einstein's request, updated his entry in Riemann's Musiklexikon. — With the
    success of the Urlinie through Der Tonwille, he no longer considers himself isolated. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Geburtstag; birthday; Verleger; publisher; kämpfen; fight; Auszeichnung; Ehrung;
    commemoration; honor; lexicon; dictionary; Formular; form; Ergänzung; supplement; Leser; reader;
    Käufer; buyer; Musiker; musician; Isoliertheit; isolation; Erfolg; success; Akademien;
    academies; Konservatorien; conservatories; Kunst; art; Genies; genius; Sammlung; collection;
    Seminar; seminar; Telegramm; telegram; Ferien; holidays; Reise; journey; travel</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000380">Hoboken</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-05">Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">van
      Hoboken</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Ihren<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is
     recorded at OJ 4/1, p. 3217, June 22, 1928: "An Herrn u. Frau van Hoboken (Br.): Dank!" ("To
     Mr. and Mrs. van Hoboken (letter): thanks!"). </tei:note> so freundlichen u. anspornenden
     Geburtstagszuruf<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">This letter is not
     known to survive, but receipt of the two letters concerned is recorded in Schenker's diary at
     OJ 4/1, p. 3216, June 20, 1928: "Von v. Hoboken u. Frau (Briefe): Glückwünsche; H. teilt mit,
     daß er zur Auszeichnung vorgeschlagen war – ich auch; er habe aber darauf bestanden, daß mir
     eine höhere Auszeichnung werde – darüber zerschlug sich das Ganze." ("From van Hoboken and his
     wife (letters): congratulations; H. tells me that he was proposed for the honor – I also;
     however, he has insisted that a higher honor [is due?] to me – on that point the whole thing
     disintegrated"). It is possible that other letters written in the three-month gap that
     separates this letter from OJ 11/54, [23] of March 21, 1928 are missing as well. </tei:note>
    höre ich mit Freuden u. großem Dank! Ja, ich will u. muß mein Werk beenden: der „<tei:rs key="entity-001728" type="work"><tei:title>freie Satz</tei:title></tei:rs>,“ <tei:rs key="entity-001756" type="work"><tei:title>„Formen“lehre</tei:title></tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-001757" type="work"><tei:title>„Vortrags“lehre</tei:title></tei:rs> (auf der
    methodischen Grundlage des „<tei:rs key="entity-001728" type="work"><tei:title>freien
      Satzes</tei:title></tei:rs>“), „<tei:rs key="entity-001759" type="work"><tei:title>Niedergang
      der Komp.</tei:title></tei:rs>“ usw, Sie schütteln Ihr jügendliches Haupt u. meinen: wann will
    denn der „<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">alte Herr</tei:rs>“ diese Dinge machen? An mir
    wird es weniger liegen, als an den Verlegern, die einem außer dem Werk auch die Zeit stehlen.
    Doch – der „<tei:rs key="entity-001728" type="work"><tei:title>fr. S.</tei:title></tei:rs>“ muß
    einmal vorliegen, u. heute will ich Ihnen wieder <tei:pb n="2"/> u. wieder nur wärmstens danken
    für Ihre so tapfere Gesinnung! Ich sehe u. fühle genau, wie heldenhaft Sie für das <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archiv</tei:rs> kämpfen, nicht minder für das, was Ihr Ohr für allein
    richtig erfaßt hat. Sagen diese Taten nicht mehr als Worte? </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Sie wissen, wie hoch ich das <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archiv</tei:rs>
    einschätze. Auch die höchste Auszeichnung bleibt noch ausser Verhältnis zum Verdienst an dieser
    Gründung! Einer solchen Tat ist nur die Auszeichnung gemäß, die in ihr selbst liegt. Sie taten
    also recht, die Ihnen zugedachten Ehrung<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">What the honor referred to was is unknown. </tei:note> abzulehnen, wiewohl der von
    Ihnen ausgesprochene Gedanke an sich richtig ist, daß in den Augen der Menge eine solche Ehrung
    auch auf das Werk zurückstrahlt. Wenn ich Sie recht verstehe, befahl Ihnen das Herz, hohe
    Kameradschaft mit mir einzuzetzen u. lieber zu verzichten, als ein Unrecht <tei:pb n="3"/> (wie
    Sie glaubten) an mir zu dulden u. zu fördern. Nicht zum ersten Mal sehe ich Sie so mannhaft für
    mich eintreten, aber auch das hat einen besseren Lohn in sich, als es in meinen Worten finden
    könnte – lassen Sie auch fortan die Wortstille walten, ich sehe, fühle u. danke immerzu. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Übrigens gilt jede Auszeichnung gerade nur für die knappsten ersten Augenblick. Schon in
    den nächsten 10 Jahren fällt sie von der Person ab u. nur das Werk spricht gemäß seiner inneren
    Kraft. Nicht einmal die <tei:foreign xml:lang="gre">Lexica</tei:foreign> nehmen Kenntnis von
    diesen Bluffs. Wir aber dürfen ruhig auf die Jahrhunderte vertrauen, unsere Sache ist nicht vom
    Tage. </tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"><tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">ad vocem</tei:foreign>
     <tei:foreign xml:lang="gre">Lexica</tei:foreign></tei:hi> teile ich Ihnen mit, daß mich hier
    ein Briefchen von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000195">Einstein</tei:rs> erreicht hat
    (gedrucktes <tei:pb n="4"/> Formular) mit dem Ersuchen, den bisherigen Ausschnitt aus dem
      <tei:title><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000712">Riemann</tei:rs>-Lex.</tei:title> zu
     ergänzen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Einstein's letter = BerkAE
     7/898, [3]. <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Hugo Riemanns Musiklexikon</tei:title>, 11th
      edition, ed. Alfred Einstein. 2 vols. (Berlin: Max Hesse, 1929)</tei:bibl>. For text and
     translation, see OJ-2-79_4 = OJ 2/p. 79, [4]. For text and translation of the 1919 edition,
     referred to here, see ML100-R52-1919_1 = ML100.R52 1919. </tei:note>. Ich las den Ausschnitt
    zum 1. Mal u. fand ihn sonderbar: dem fehlte der <tei:rs key="entity-001727" type="work"><tei:title>Kp. II<tei:hi rend="supralinear">2</tei:hi></tei:title></tei:rs>, die <tei:rs key="entity-001753" type="work"><tei:title>„G-A.“ der Kl.-Son. von
     Beethoven</tei:title></tei:rs>, ja sogar der Titel „<tei:rs key="entity-001749" type="work"><tei:title level="j">das Meisterwerk i. d. Musik</tei:title></tei:rs>“ (obgleich dieser
     <tei:rs key="entity-001749" type="work"><tei:title>Jahrbücher</tei:title></tei:rs>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">u. der <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002627">3 M</tei:rs></tei:hi>
    bereits gedacht wird!!) </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Nun, ich habe die Ergänzungen angebracht, so manches Andere verbessert – bin aber
    neugierig, wie sich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000195">Einstein</tei:rs> dazu stellen wird.
    Der „<tei:term>Url.</tei:term>“ hat schon <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000195">E.</tei:rs> selbst gedacht, u. ich muß wirklich staunen, mit welcher
    Wucht sich dieser neue (doch gewiß nicht verstandene) Begriff durchgesetzt hat, schon nur auf
    Hand des „<tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title>Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>n,“
    den der edle <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356">Hertzka</tei:rs> auf ein Nebengeleise
    abgeschoben, vertragswidrig in der Auflage um die Hälfte gekürzt u. sonst sabatiert hat. Über
    allen Widerstand siegten schon <tei:pb n="5"/> die ersten Blätter u. die ersten Leser. Unser
    liebe <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> unterschätzt gewiss die Zahl
    meiner Leser, ihrer sind gewiß viel, viel mehr als Käufer (denken Sie doch nur an <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs>, der von all den Dingen weiß, aber das Buch
    nicht kauft; ich denke an die vielen, vielen jüngen Musiker, von denen ich <tei:hi rend="underline">weiß</tei:hi>, daß sie mich lesen, aber nicht kaufen können). Gewiß ist auch,
    daß die „<tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">U.E.</tei:rs>“ ein gutes Geschäft an mir
    gefunden; kein Zweifel für mich, daß die <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002627">3 M</tei:rs>
    ebenfalls auf ihre Rechnung kommen werden, nur freilich langsam. Von einer „Isoliertheit“ kann
    ich also nicht sprechen, demnach begreife ich Sie in Ihrer Güte u. herzlichen Anteilnahme, wenn
    Sie nur wünschen, daß wir noch mehr an äußerem Erfolg beschieden sein möge. Ich wollte es ja
     <tei:pb n="6"/> auch selbst, aber – der „Betrieb“ steht dem entgegen, mit dem ich nichts zu
    schaffen habe. Im Gegenteil, ich schätze mich glücklich so viele junge Musiker der Schande
    unserer Akadamien u. Konservatorien entrissen <tei:del rend="overstrike">zu haben</tei:del> u.
    ihnen die Kunst von der Seite der Genies gezeigt zu haben; daß sie es nicht weiter gebracht
    haben, fällt nicht auf mich. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Über die Vorgänge in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs> war ich
    schon unterrichtet, noch ehe Ihre l. Zeilen eintrafen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Wie freue ich mich des Zuwachsens an beiden Stellen, im <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archiv</tei:rs> wie in Ihrer Sammlung! Nun wird es bald Zeit, der Welt Rechenschaft davon
    zu legen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Von Prof. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000178">Dunn</tei:rs> erhielt ich sein Bild
     <tei:pb n="7"/> u. ein sehr liebes Briefchen dazu. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs> u. seinem Seminar traf eine
    schöne „Adresse“ ein, usw. usw. </tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> wie immer selbstlos, beglückt
    u. auch beglückend! H. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000164">Deutsch</tei:rs> war rührend
    lieb, auch Dr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000320">Haas</tei:rs>, u. besonders wohltuend war
    das Telegramm des <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archiv</tei:rs>s:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Probably = OJ 9/10, [1]. </tei:note> dieses
    edle Glöcklein wird weit hinaustönen. Vielen, vielen Dank Ihnen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Aber nun wünsche ich Ihnen, u. mit mir auch meine <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Frau</tei:rs>, schönste Ferien auf der Reise u. am Ziel </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr aufrichtig ergebener</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">HSchenker</tei:rs></tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline><tei:placeName>Galtür</tei:placeName>, <tei:date when="1928-06-22">22. Juni
      28</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>



  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-05">My dear Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">van
      Hoboken</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>I<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> hear your very nice and prodding
     birthday-cheer<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> with joy and greatest thanks!
    Yes, I will and must finish my work: <tei:rs key="entity-001728" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Free Composition</tei:title></tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-001756" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Theory of Form</tei:title></tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-001757" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Theory of Performance</tei:title></tei:rs> (on the
    methodological foundation of <tei:rs key="entity-001728" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Free
      Composition</tei:title></tei:rs>), <tei:rs key="entity-001759" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Decline of the Art of Composition</tei:title></tei:rs>, etc. You shake your youthful
    head and ask: when will the "<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">old man</tei:rs>" get
    around to these things? It is less a question of me than of the publishers, who steal not only
    your work but also your time. But – <tei:rs key="entity-001728" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Free Composition</tei:title></tei:rs> must be ready at some point, and today I want to thank
    you again <tei:pb n="2"/> and again most warmly for your very courageous outlook! I see and feel
    exactly how heroically you fight for the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archive</tei:rs>,
    and no less for that which your ear has identified as the only right thing. Do these deeds not
    speak louder than words? </tei:p>

   <tei:p>You know how highly I value the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archive</tei:rs>.
    Even the highest commemoration fails to do justice to the service provided by its founding! Such
    a deed is properly recognized only by the commemoration that is intrinsic to it. You therefore
    did right to refuse the honor intended for you,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/>
    for all that the thought you expressed is correct in itself that in the eyes of the world such
    an honor also reflects back onto the work itself. If I understand you correctly, your heart
    commanded you to strike up high comradeship with me and to prefer to refuse rather than to
    suffer and support an injustice <tei:pb n="3"/> (as you considered it) to me. This is not the
    first time I have seen you stand up so bravely for me, but that has an intrinsic reward which is
    better than could be found in my words – henceforth, no more talk of it: I see, feel, and am
    thankful continuously. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Any commemoration, by the way, is good only for the briefest first moment. Within the
    first ten years it departs from the person, and only the work speaks, in proportion to its inner
    strength. Not even the <tei:foreign xml:lang="gre">lexica</tei:foreign> take notice of this
    bluff. We, however, can confidently depend on the centuries; our cause is not of the day. </tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">A propos</tei:hi> of the <tei:foreign xml:lang="gre">lexica</tei:foreign> I can tell you that a note from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000195">Einstein</tei:rs> has reached me here (printed <tei:pb n="4"/> form) with the request to
    supplement the existing entry from the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000712">Riemann</tei:rs>
    <tei:title level="m">Lexicon</tei:title>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> I read
    the entry for the first time and found it curious: it lacks <tei:rs key="entity-001727" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Counterpoint II/2</tei:title></tei:rs>, the <tei:rs key="entity-001753" type="work"><tei:title>"collected edition" of the piano sonatas of
      Beethoven</tei:title></tei:rs>, even the title <tei:rs key="entity-001749" type="work"><tei:title level="j">The Masterwork in Music</tei:title></tei:rs> (although these <tei:rs key="entity-001749" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Yearbooks</tei:title></tei:rs>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">and <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002627">Drei Masken
     Verlag</tei:rs></tei:hi> have already been mentioned!!) </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Well, I have provided the supplements, and improved so many other things – am curious,
    though, how <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000195">Einstein</tei:rs> will handle it.
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000195">Einstein</tei:rs> himself has mentioned the "<tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>," and I must really marvel at the weight this
    new (but certainly not understood) concept has carried, just on the strength of <tei:rs key="entity-001739" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>, which
    the fine fellow <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356">Hertzka</tei:rs> has shunted onto a
    side-track, shortened by half in the printing through breach of contract, and otherwise
    sabotaged. Against all opposition, <tei:pb n="5"/> the first issues and the first readers
    carried the day. Our dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> certainly
    underestimates the number of my readers; there are certainly far, far more of them than of
    purchasers (just consider <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs>, who
    knows of all the things, but doesn't buy the book; I think of the many, many young musicians who
    I <tei:hi rend="underline">know</tei:hi> read me but are unable to buy). It is a certainty that
     <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">UE</tei:rs> has found good business in me; I have no
    doubt that <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002627">Drei Masken</tei:rs> too will get their money's
    worth, but slowly, I'll warrant. Thus I cannot speak of a state of "isolation," so I understand
    you in your kindness and enthusiastic participation when you wish only that we could have a bit
    more outwardly visible success. I would indeed like it <tei:pb n="6"/> myself, but – the
    "management," with which I have nothing to do, stands in the way. On the contrary, I count
    myself as lucky to have extricated so many young musicians from the pitiful milieu of our
    academies and conservatories, and to have shown them art from the perspective of the geniuses;
    it's not my fault that they haven't made more of it. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Concerning the happenings in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs> I
    was already informed even before your nice lines arrived. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>How delighted I am about the increase in both places, in the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archive</tei:rs> and in your collection! Now it will soon be time to
    give the outside world an accounting of the progress. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>From Prof. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000178">Dunn</tei:rs> I received his picture
     <tei:pb n="7"/> and a very nice note with it. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>From <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs> and his seminar a very
    beautiful "address" arrived, etc. etc. </tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> as always, selfless,
    cheerful, and also spreading cheer! Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000164">Deutsch</tei:rs>’s kindness was touching, also that of Dr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000320">Haas</tei:rs>, and the telegram from the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archive</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> was a
    special lift: this noble little bell will ring far and wide. Many, many thanks to you. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Now I, and with me my <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">wife</tei:rs> as well,
    fervently wish you the most wonderful holiday on the journey and also at the destination. </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Yours most sincerely, </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.
     Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed>
    <tei:dateline><tei:placeName>Galtür</tei:placeName>, <tei:date when="1928-06-22">June 22,
      1928</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>