<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="1892" sdoID="OJ-89-7_2">OJ 89/7, [2]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="JR-HE">
   <tei:persName>John Rothgeb and Heribert Esser</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2017</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2017</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2017</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2012-10-08" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002730">Hoboken ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002731">Hoboken ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Hoboken, dated January 13, 1934</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1934-01-13T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2017-02-23</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker encourages Hoboken to continue to live in Vienna, praising its racial
    diversity; — Der freie Satz is near completion; — sales of Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie are going
    well.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Rasse; race; Inzucht; inbreeding; Kunst; art; Aufsatz; essay; article; Kapitel;
    chapter; Exemplar; copy</dc:subject>

   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000380">Hoboken</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:date when="1934-01-13">13. 1. 34</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">van
      Hoboken</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this
      letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/7, p. 3890, January 13, 1934: "An v. H. (Br.):
      bestätige den Empfang des Geldes, gebe meiner Freude Ausdruck über den Ankauf des
      Grundstückes, rate noch einmal zu Wien – der Abschluß des freien Satzes steht bevor." ("To
      Hoboken (letter): I confirm the receipt of the money, express my delight about the purchase of
      the plot of land, advise him once more in favor of Vienna – the completion of <tei:title
       level="m">Free Composition</tei:title> is imminent.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Es hat längere Zeit gebraucht, bis ich auf die letzte Zeile im mir zugekommenen Formular
    der <tei:rs key="entity-004424" type="organization"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
     >Rotterdam</tei:hi>'schen Bank</tei:rs> aufmerksam wurde, nun weiß ich es u. bestätige an Ihre
    Adresse den Empfang des angewiesenen Betrages von S. 3120.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
     type="editorial" place="foot">Financial support toward the printing costs of <tei:title
      level="m">Der freie Satz</tei:title>.</tei:note> Vielen Dank. (An die Bank schreibe ich nicht,
    sollte es dennoch notwendig sein, so wird mich die Bank wohl noch einmal erinnern.)</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Daß Sie den Grund in Grinzing erworben haben,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
     type="editorial" place="foot">Communicated in <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-89-7_1"
      >OJ 89/7, [1]</tei:ref>. Grinzing: northwestern suburb of Vienna, noted for its vineyards and
     viticulture; an independent municipality until 1892, it is now incorporated within the 19th
     District (Döbling).</tei:note> ist sehr Grund für uns Alle, uns dessen <tei:pb n="2"/> sehr zu
    freuen, warum fügten Sie aber dieser schönen Mitteilung Worte hinzu, die einen Rückgang des
    Kaufes immerhin noch möglich erscheinen lassen? Also warte ich die endgültige Entscheidung ab —
    der Aberglaube in mir gebietet es so —, dann will ich mit Wunsch u. Segen herausrücken. Mir
    scheint <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> heute der plausibelste Ort für
    Sie zu sein, schon weil sich hier — lachen Sie nicht — die Juden in der Musik betätigen können
    u. allerhand Spielarten (zum Verdruß, zur Unterhaltung) zeigen. „Rasse“ ist gut, der Rasse
    „Inzucht“ aber ist trüb (wie die Römer sagten: auch die Tugend darf nicht übertrieben werden),
    die Kunst steht ganz wo anders, also ist es ganz nett in der Welt eingerichtet, wenn in Wien
     <tei:pb n="3"/> noch allerhand Fremdrassige<tei:hi rend="overstrike">n</tei:hi> interessante
    Farbenflecke vorstellen (Juden, Ungarn, Slaven, Italiener usw usw.)<tei:supplied
     reason="punctuation">.</tei:supplied></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Der Empfang der Aufsätze sei auch noch bestätigt.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Noch zwei Kapitel, dann schließe ich den „<tei:rs key="entity-001728" type="work"
      ><tei:title>fr. S</tei:title></tei:rs>“ — so unglaublich es in heutiger Zeit Klingen mag —
    ganz ab! Vorgestern war Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000420" type="person">Kalmus</tei:rs> bei mir,
    doch davon lieber mündlich. (Er erzählte mir, daß von der <tei:rs key="entity-001731"
     type="work"><tei:title>„IX“ Sinf</tei:title></tei:rs>. (1000 Ex-Aufl.) bis heute 900 Ex
    verkauft wurden, da darf ich wohl zufrieden sein.<tei:supplied reason="punctuation"
     >)</tei:supplied></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Hoffentlich geht es Ihnen Beiden in der <tei:pb n="4"/> Gesundheit andauernd gut,
    namentlich Ihrer verehrten <tei:rs key="entity-000093" type="person">Gattin</tei:rs>, die
    zuletzt wohl mehr als Sie in Frage kam.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Lassen Sie recht bald die erfreuliche Nachricht an uns gelangen!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Mit besten Grüßen, Wünschen u Empfehlungen an Sie Beide von uns Beiden</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
       >H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p>PS.<tei:lb/>
     <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtw.</tei:rs> soll <tei:hi rend="underline"
      >gedroht</tei:hi> haben, daß er <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"
       ><tei:country>Deutschland</tei:country></tei:rs> verlassen werde, haben Sie davon etwas
     gehört? Vermutlich will er, falls das garnicht auf Wahrheit beruht, etwas durchsetzen.</tei:p>

   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>



  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:date when="1934-01-13">January 13,
     1934</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>My dear Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">van Hoboken</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
      corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>It has taken a longer time for me to become aware of the last line in the form that came
    to me from the <tei:rs key="entity-004424" type="organization">Bank of Rotterdam</tei:rs>; now I
    am aware of it, and confirm, to your address, receipt of the transferred amount of 3,120
     shillings.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> Thank you. (I am not writing to the
    bank; should that nevertheless be necessary, the bank will no doubt remind me.)</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">That you have acquired the plot of ground in Grinzing<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> is ample grounds for us all <tei:pb n="2"/> to rejoice
    very much; but why have you added to this wonderful report words that make a reversal of the
    purchase seem possible? Thus I await the ultimate decision ‒ the superstition in me commands it
    so ‒, then I will pay off with wish and blessing. <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place"
     >Vienna</tei:rs> today seems to me to be the most plausible location for you, just because here
    ‒ don't laugh ‒ the Jews can make their mark in music and show many varieties (e.g. annoyance,
    entertainment). "Race" is good, "inbreeding" of race, however, is murky (as the Romans used to
    say: even virtue must not be overdone), Art occupies a completely different place, so it is
    perfectly appropriate in the world that in Vienna <tei:pb n="3"/> racial aliens still represent
    interesting flecks of color (Jews, Hungarians, Slavs, Italians, etc., etc.).</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Let receipt of the essays be confirmed as well.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Two more chapters, then ‒ however incredible it may sound at the present time ‒ and I am
    completely finished with <tei:rs key="entity-001728" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Free
      Composition</tei:title></tei:rs>! Day before yesterday Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000420"
     type="person">Kalmus</tei:rs> visited me, but about that, better when we talk. (He told me that
    of the <tei:rs key="entity-001731" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Ninth
     Symphony</tei:title></tei:rs> (print-run of 1,000 copies) thus far 900 copies have been sold,
    so I may well be satisfied.)</tei:p>

   <tei:p>I hope all continues to go well for you both in matters of <tei:pb n="4"/> health,
    especially for your esteemed <tei:rs key="entity-000093" type="person">wife</tei:rs>, who most
    recently was cause for more concern than yourself.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Let us have the happy news very soon!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>With best greetings, wishes, and regards to you both from both of us.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.
     Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p>P.S.<tei:lb/>
     <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs> is said to have <tei:hi
      rend="underline">threatened</tei:hi> to leave <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place"
       ><tei:country>Germany</tei:country></tei:rs>; have you heard anything of that? Presumably, if
     that is not factual, he wants to accomplish something. </tei:p>

   </tei:postscript>
  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
