<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="1895" sdoID="OJ-89-7_5">OJ 89/7, [5]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="JR-HE">
   <tei:persName>John Rothgeb and Heribert Esser</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2017</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2017</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2017</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2012-10-08" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002730">Hoboken ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002731">Hoboken ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Hoboken, dated February 25, 1934</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1934-02-25T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2017-05-29</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker comments on Eva van Hoboken's visit [of February 18]; — Encloses a
    collection of articles, praises Hoboken's opposition to Ganche, and comments sardonically about
    Schering, Kretzschmar, and Riemann.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Lokal; Café; Zuschrift; letter; Sammlung; collection; Aufsatz; article; essay; Genie;
    genius</dc:subject>

   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000380">Hoboken</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:date when="1934-02-25">25. 2. 34</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
       >van Hoboken</tei:hi></tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
      >Writing of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/7, p. 3896, February 25, 1934:
      "An v. Hoboken (Begleitbrief): über den Besuch der Frau v. H., Freude an seiner Weiterarbeit
      gegen Ganche; zu Schering." ("To Hoboken (covering letter): concerning his wife's visit,
      delight about his further work in opposition to Ganche; about
     Schering.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>War das eine Überraschung, als Ihre verehrte <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000093"
     >Gattin</tei:rs>, eben „gesund entlassen,“ auch wirklich gesund aussehend, bester Stimmung, mit
    einem wunderschönen Bäumchen in der Hand bei uns eintrat! Für die Grüße, die sie von Ihnen
    brachte, danken wir herzlichst, wir freuten uns sehr zu hören, daß es auch Ihnen sehr gut geht.
    Das alles gab einen schönen Auftakt zu Stunden wirklichen Froh- u. Schönsinns!<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The visit of Eva van Hoboken was prefaced on
     February 16, as reported in Schenker's diary: "Auf telephonischem Wege über Deutsch meldet sich
     Frau van Hoboken! Lie-Liechen bittet sie für morgen zur Jause." ("Via a telephone call to
     Deutsch, Mrs. van Hoboken gets in touch! Lie-Liechen invites her for afternoon snack
     tomorrow."). Her visit on February 17 is then recorded in Schenker's diary: "Von 5–¾7<tei:hi
      rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> Frau van Hoboken: anscheinend in unserem Lager, für die Arbeiten
     des Gatten interessirt, gibt sich beglückt, dankt für den „wunderschönen Abend“." ("From 5
     o'clock to 6:45, Mrs. van Hoboken: apparently in our camp, interested in her husband's work,
     seems delighted, thanks us for the 'wonderful evening'."), and again the next day: "Um 6<tei:hi
      rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> Deutsch, dann Frau van Hoboken! Verlasse sie früher wegen zu
     großer Wärme im Lokal." ("At 6 o'clock, Deutsch; then Mrs. van Hoboken! I leave them early, on
     account of the uncomfortably warm temperature in the café.").</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p> Schade, daß ich am Sonntag Pech mit dem <tei:pb n="2"/> überheizten <tei:rs type="place"
     key="entity-006247"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Sacher</tei:hi></tei:rs><tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">The Café Sacher, Vienna I, Opernring 11. See
     footnote 2 above for the circumstances.</tei:note> hatte, wie schon einmal kurz vorher, wo ich
    das Lokal nach 1‒2 Minuten verlassen mußte. Hohe Temparaturen sind mir nur im Kopfe und Herzen
    willkommen, nicht außen, so ging es mir immer u. geht auch noch jetzt, s. <tei:rs type="place"
     key="entity-002380"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Igls</tei:hi></tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="place"
     key="entity-003095"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Reigersberg</tei:hi></tei:rs>! Gerade haben wir
    uns die jüngsten Witze mitgeteilt, was ohnehin eine erhöhte Temparatur bedeutet, da mußte ich
    davon, weil dazu die Zentralheizung einige Grade drauflegte. Schade.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Mit wahrem Vergnügen hörte ich, daß Sie am Anti-<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003553"
      ><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Ganche</tei:hi></tei:rs> fortarbeiten! <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
     >Scharlott’s</tei:hi> Zuschrift an die „<tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002559"
      ><tei:title>N. fr. Presse</tei:title></tei:rs>“ lege ich <tei:note type="editorial"
     place="inline">cued from bottom margin:</tei:note> in der gleichzeitig an Sie abgesandten
    Sammlung von Aufsätzen<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end cue</tei:note>
    verabredetermaßen bei, niemals kann Können <tei:pb n="3"/> u. Wissen so unverschämt, so
    überheblich sein, wie das Nichtkönnen u. Nichtwissen ‒ in aller Unschuld ‒ es sind! Schließlich
    siegt doch aber jenes, Sie kennen ja mein Sprüchlein, von der braven Kuh, die gute Milch gibt,
    u. daher gehängt wird. Nur gemach!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Dies soll uns ein Trost sein auch gegenüber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006131"
      ><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Schering</tei:hi></tei:rs>,<tei:note type="editorial"
     place="inline">cued from bottom margin:</tei:note> für dessen frdl. Einsendung ich besonders
    herzlich danke,<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end cue</tei:note> der neuen „Muse“ der
    Musik! Unseren „Genie“sonnen am Himmel antworten unten die (mit <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-006131"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Schering</tei:hi></tei:rs> zu sprechen)
    „amusischen“ <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000484"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
      >Kretschmar</tei:hi></tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000712"><tei:hi
      rend="lateinschr">Riemann</tei:hi></tei:rs> u. nun der „musische“ <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-006131"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Schering</tei:hi></tei:rs>, ein köstliches Trio,
    wirklich reif für ein Musik-Witzblatt zur Aufheiterung einer leidenden Menschheit! Aber in
    seiner ewigen Güte setzt <tei:pb n="4"/> Gott auch solcher Virilität eine Grenze, sie ist eben
    erreicht, nun kann wirklich nichts Schlimmeres mehr kommen. Jeder Beitrag dieser Ztschrift eine
    wahre Fußnoten-Kaserne, drin lauter Musikrekruten wieseln, 100 mal tote, dazu die Fußnoten unter
    dem Strich als Unterkellerung, auch das wird bald bei den Nach-<tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-006131"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Scheringen</tei:hi></tei:rs> ein Ende nehmen.
    Gott ist gütig, auch die Mechanik alles Unrats geht an sich selbst zu Grunde. Bleibt Gott bei
     seinen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Here Schenker neglects to
     capitalize the first letter of a pronoun denoting the deity. Compare "Seine" corrected from
     "seine" ("His" corrected from "his") later in the sentence.</tei:note> Lieblingen, durch deren
    Mund Er gleichsam selbst Musik machte, das ist <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overwritten">s</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="superimposed">S</tei:add>
    </tei:subst>eine „Sphärenharmonie“. Amen.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ihnen Beide beste Grüße von uns Beiden</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
       >H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>



  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:date when="1934-02-25">February 2,
     1934</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Dear Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">van Hoboken</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
      corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Was that a surprise, as your esteemed <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000093"
     >wife</tei:rs>, "dismissed in good health," also appearing quite healthy, in the best mood,
    with an exceedingly beautiful seedling in hand, joined us! For the greeting that she brought
    from you, we thank you most sincerely; we were very happy to hear that you too are quite well.
    All of that provided a beautiful upbeat to hours of truly good cheer and beatitude!<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Pity that on Sunday I had bad luck with the <tei:pb n="2"/> overheated <tei:rs
     type="place" key="entity-006247">Sacher</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"
    /> as already one other time recently, when I had to leave the restaurant after 1-2 minutes.
    High temperatures I find welcome only in head and heart, not outside, it has always been that
    way and remains so now as well, recall <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002380">Igls</tei:rs>
    and <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-003095">Reigersberg</tei:rs>! We had just recounted for
    each other the most recent jokes, an activity that in any case signifies an elevated
    temperature; then I had to leave, because the central heating was adding a few degrees as well.
    Pity.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>With true pleasure I heard that your anti-<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003553"
     >Ganche</tei:rs> work is progressing! As agreed, I include <tei:note type="editorial"
     place="inline">cued from bottom margin:</tei:note> in the collection of essays just now being
    sent you<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end cue</tei:note> Scharlott's letter to the
    editor of the <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002559"><tei:title level="j">Neue freie
      Presse</tei:title></tei:rs>; never can ability <tei:pb n="3"/> and knowledge be so impudent,
    so arrogant, as inability and ignorance ‒ in all innocence ‒ are! But ultimately the former
    wins; you do know my saying about the good cow that gives good milk, and therefore is hanged.
    Just go easy!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Let this be a comfort for us regarding <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006131"
     >Schering</tei:rs>
    <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">cued from bottom margin:</tei:note> For the cordial
    forwarding of which I am especially grateful,<tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">end
     cue</tei:note> as well, the new "muse”" of music! Our "genius"-suns in the heavens are now
    answered from below by the (to use <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006131">Schering</tei:rs>'s
    terms) "a-musical" <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000484">Kretzschmar</tei:rs> and <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000712">Riemann</tei:rs> and now the "musical" <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-006131">Schering</tei:rs>, an exquisite trio, truly ripe for a musical-humor-page
    for the amusement of a suffering human race! But in his eternal goodness, <tei:pb n="4"/> God
    sets even for such virility a boundary, it is just reached, now really nothing worse can come.
    Each contribution to this journal a real footnote-barracks, inside of which all musical recruits
    scurry about, dead a hundred times over, furthermore the footnotes beneath the line as
    cellar-abutments, which likewise in the post-<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006131"
     >Schering</tei:rs> period will come to an end. God is gracious; even the mechanics of all
    garbage will perish of its own volition. If God remains with those he<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> loves, through whose mouth <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overwritten">h</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="inline">H</tei:add>
    </tei:subst>e Himself, in a way, made music — that is His “harmony of the spheres.”
    Amen.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Best greetings to you both from both of us.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.
     Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
