<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="323" sdoID="OJ-89-1_4">OJ 89/1, [4]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="JR-HE">
   <tei:persName>John Rothgeb &amp; Heribert Esser</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008, 2010</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="JR">
   <tei:persName>John Rothgeb</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2008</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-03-31" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002730">Hoboken ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002731">Hoboken ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to van Hoboken, dated September 6, 1927</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1927-09-06T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-06-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker comments on Hoboken's Appeal [for the Photogrammarchiv], sets out what
    is necessary for correctly reading an autograph manuscript and understanding its relationship to
    the first edition, and rails against the tendency of performers, including Furtwängler, to think
    such matters trivial. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Handschrift; manuscript; Erstdruck; first edition; Aufruf; appeal; Divergenz;
    divergence; variant; Herausgeber; editor; Musiker; musician; Fehler; error; mistake; Historiker;
    historian; Pianist; pianist; Dirigent; conductor; Text; Ausführung; performance; Händler;
    dealer; Liebhaber; music lover; connoisseur; Wahrheit; truth</dc:subject>



  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000380">Hoboken</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>



  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Wien</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1927-09-06">6. 9. 27</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-05">Lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">van
      Hoboken</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Durch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is
     recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/9, p. 3111, September 6, 1927: "An Hoboken (Br.): entlarve
     Furtwängler u. sage, daß er von der Frage der Handschriften nichts verstehe." ("To Hoboken
     (letter): I unmask Furtwängler and say that on the question of autograph manuscripts he
     understands nothing.").</tei:note> den Besuch eines <tei:persName>Neffe</tei:persName>n von mir
    sowie durch die Vorbereitungen zur Abreise u. zum Besuch bei meinem älteren <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775">Bruder</tei:rs> war ich in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs> in den letzten Augusttagen verhindert, einiges zu Ihrem
    Besuch bei <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs> zu bemerken. Da ich
    gestern endlich heimgekehrt bin, war ich im Begriffe, das Vorgehabte heute nachzuholen, als Ihr
    zweiter lieber Brief (über <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>) hierherkam.
    Ich muß offen sprechen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">An einer Stelle Ihres schönen <tei:ref type="other" cRef="OJ-9-10_2">Aufruf</tei:ref>s sprechen Sie von der Bedeutung der Handschriften u. sagen, daß auch
    diejenigen, die sie einsehen, von ihrem Wert nicht sonderlich überzeugt sind, da ihnen die etwa <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overwritten">anzutreffenden</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="superimposed">angetroffenen</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> Divergenzen zu gering- <tei:pb n="2"/> fügig erscheinen. Einen Augenblick lang
    gelüstete es mich, Sie zu ermutigen, die volle Wahrheit auszusprechen, daß die Herausgeber u.
    Musiker so sagen können u. müssen, weil sie <tei:hi rend="underline">die Handschrift nicht zu
     lesen verstehen</tei:hi> im Einklange mit dem Gewollten. <tei:note type="editorial">cued from
     lower margin:</tei:note> Im nächsten Augenblick gewann der Gedanke doch Oberhand in mir, daß
    Sie in Ihrem „Aufruf“ besser tun, etwas diskreter zu sprechen, wie Sie es eben getan
     haben.<tei:note type="editorial">end cue</tei:note> Die Sache steht so: erstens muß man die
     <tei:term>Komposition</tei:term> aus dem Innersten verstehen, zweitens muß man die Handschrift
    in ihrem Sinne lesen, drittens muß man die Unterschiede von Erstdruck u. Handschrift <tei:hi rend="underline">nach der <tei:term>Komp.</tei:term> zu werten wissen</tei:hi>, denn so gewiß
    es ist, daß der <tei:term>Komponist</tei:term> sich zuweilen im Erstdruck verbessert (was aber
    bei den Meistern <tei:hi rend="underline">sehr, sehr, sehr selten</tei:hi> vorkommt!), so
    geschieht es noch häufiger, daß (von solchen Verbesserungen abgesehen) die Handschrift noch
    lange nicht gut genug durch den Erstdruck wiedergegeben erscheint. So <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">galt</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">gilt</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> es denn also, diesen Vorzug der Handschrift festzustellen, nicht nur die <tei:pb n="3"/> groben Fehler des Erstdruckes zu berichtigen, sondern noch darüberhinaus alles das ins
    Licht zu stellen, was der Erstdruck <tei:hi rend="underline">wiederzugeben gar nicht den Versuch
     machte</tei:hi>. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Solange ich davon rede, höre ich (von den Historikern, von den <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000435">Kinsky</tei:rs>'s u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000013">Altmann</tei:rs>s, den Pianisten u. <tei:del rend="overstrike">H</tei:del>Dirigenten) das
    leicht hingeworfene Wort von der Geringfügigkeit aller dieser Dinge, von dem überragenden Wert
    des Erstdrucks – aber das sind alles Menschen, denen die <tei:term>Komp.</tei:term> vollständig
    unbekannt ist, daher auch die Handschrift trotz all ihren Zaubern des besonderen Ausdrucks
    nichts mehr bedeutet als ein Musealstück. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Und eben, daß zu diesen Menschen ehedem ein <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000110">Bülow</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000533">Liszt</tei:rs> u.s.w. <tei:add place="interlinear-above">gehörten</tei:add> u. heute ein <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtw.</tei:rs> gehör<tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overwritten">en</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="superimposed">t</tei:add>
    </tei:subst>, <tei:hi rend="underline">das macht die Schande u. den Schaden aus</tei:hi>! Nicht
    nur, daß die Wiedergabe in <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Text</tei:hi> u. Ausführung fehlerhaft,
    kindisch, kindlich, anfängerhaft <tei:pb n="4"/> lautet, daß über dieser verlorensten
    Unwissenheit die Gefahr des Unterganges aller Handschriften als angeblich überflüssiger Dinge
    schwebt, sodaß man allen Ernstes Ursache hat, sich <tei:hi rend="underline">der Händler</tei:hi>
    u. Liebhaber <tei:hi rend="underline">zu freuen</tei:hi>, die die Handschriften schon zum Zweck
    des Gewinns solange wie möglich am Leben erhalten. Kürzer: unser <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtw.</tei:rs> versteht von alldem gar nichts; wenn ihm nur <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">per</tei:foreign> Abend 3-4000 Doll. u. in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482">Deutschland</tei:rs> sou<tei:supplied reason="clarity">nd</tei:supplied>soviel MK geboten wird, der Rest greift ihm nicht an's Herz, leider auch nicht
    an's Ohr! Das ist es ja, unsere Ersten sind noch viel zu schlecht u. zu untauglich u. darum kam
    es so katastrophenhaft - ein Zufall ist das nicht, es ist die Folge von Ursachen. Ist es nicht
    schauerlich, wenn ich sagen muß, <tei:add place="interlinear-above">daß</tei:add> mein Freund
    Prof. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Violin</tei:rs> in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002589">Hamburg</tei:rs> u. Sie besser hören (feiner meine ich) als unser <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">F.</tei:rs>? Sehen Sie nur den <tei:pb n="5"/> Lauf der Welt:
    Sie unterdrücken im Aufruf eigens die Schärfe, die geboten wäre, ich unterdrücke die Lust, Sie
    zur Schärfe zu veranlassen, wir tun uns einen Zwang an, aber die Bösewichte aus Unwissenheit tun
    sich gar keinen Zwang an u. nötigen uns, wie mich hier, die Schärfe nachzutragen. Beim besten
    Willen: es geht nicht ohne Schärfe, wenn man die Sache nicht verraten will; man wird zur Schärfe
     <tei:hi rend="underline">durch die Menschen genötigt</tei:hi>, die Schaden stiften u. nicht
    rasten in der Zerstörung. Wie gern <tei:pb n="6"/> gäbe ich <tei:add place="interlinear-above">mich</tei:add> zahmer, aber das wäre Verrat. Mit dem Schwert der Wahrheit u. des Zornes muß es
    gelingen u. es wird gelingen! </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Viel Glück auf Ihren Wegen u. beste Grüße von uns Beiden </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">HSchenker</tei:hi></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>



  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Vienna</tei:rs>,
      <tei:date when="1927-09-06">September 6, 1927 </tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-05">Dear Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">van
      Hoboken</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>, </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Through<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> the visit of a
     <tei:persName>nephew</tei:persName> of mine and also through the preparations for departure and
    for a visit to my older <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000775">brother</tei:rs>, I was
    deterred in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs> in the last days of August
    from commenting on a few points regarding your visit with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs>. As I finally returned home yesterday, I had planned
    today to follow up on that intent when your second kind letter (via <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs>) arrived. I must speak openly. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In one place in your excellent <tei:ref type="other" cRef="OJ-9-10_2">Appeal</tei:ref> you speak of the significance of the manuscripts and state that even those
    who examine them are not particularly convinced of their value, since various divergences
    encountered appear to them to be too trivial. <tei:pb n="2"/> For a moment I felt inclined to
    encourage you to speak the complete truth, that the editors and musicians can and must say this
    because they <tei:hi rend="underline">do not know how to read the manuscript</tei:hi> in terms
    of what it means to express. <tei:note type="editorial">cued from lower margin:</tei:note> A
    moment later I reconsidered, and thought that you were better advised in your "Appeal" to speak
    somewhat more discreetly, just as you have in fact done.<tei:note type="editorial">end
     cue</tei:note> The matter stands thus: in the first place one must understand the
     <tei:term>composition</tei:term> down to the core; second, one must read the manuscript in the
    spirit of that core content; and third, one must <tei:hi rend="underline">know how to
     evaluate</tei:hi> the differences between first edition and manuscript <tei:hi rend="underline">in relation to the <tei:term>composition</tei:term></tei:hi>; because however certain it is
    that the <tei:term>composer</tei:term> sometimes makes improvements in the first edition (which
    however happens <tei:hi rend="underline">very, very, very seldom</tei:hi> with the masters), a
    far more common occurrence is that (apart from such improvements) the manuscript is far from
    being well enough represented by the first edition. What must be done, then, is to establish
    this advantage of the manuscript, not only in order to correct the <tei:pb n="3"/> crude errors
    of the first edition, but also, above and beyond that, to shed light on all that the first
    edition <tei:hi rend="underline">does not even attempt to reproduce</tei:hi>.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>As long as I am speaking of this, I hear (from the historians, from the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000435">Kinsky</tei:rs>s and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000013">Altmann</tei:rs>s, the pianists and conductors) the facile word about the
    triviality of all of these things, about the superior value of the first edition – but those are
    all people to whom the <tei:term>composition</tei:term> is completely unknown, and thus to whom
    the manuscript as well, despite all of its marvels of particular expression, signifies nothing
    more than a museum-piece. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>And precisely that this group used to include a <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000110">Bülow</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000533">Liszt</tei:rs>, etc., and today
    includes a <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs>, – <tei:hi rend="underline">that completes the damage and the pity</tei:hi>! Not only that the
    reproduction in text and performance sounds faulty, childlike, childish, amateurish, <tei:pb n="4"/> and that because of this most irremediable ignorance the danger threatens of the
    destruction of all manuscripts as allegedly superfluous objects, so that one quite seriously has
    reason to <tei:hi rend="underline">appreciate the dealers</tei:hi> and music lovers who keep the
    manuscripts just for the purpose of profit so long as possible. More concisely: our <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs> understands nothing of all that; when he
    is offered 3-4,000 dollars, and in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482">Germany</tei:rs> so
    and so many Marks per evening, the other things don't go to his heart, and unfortunately also
    not to his ear! There's the problem, you know: our best people are still much too bad and too
    ill-suited, and therefore things got so catastrophic – that is no accident, it is the result of
    causes. Is it not frightening that I have to say that my friend Prof. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Violin</tei:rs> in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002589">Hamburg</tei:rs> and you hear better (with more refinement, I mean) than our <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs>? Just look at <tei:pb n="5"/> the way of
    the world: you deliberately suppress in your Appeal the stridency that would be called for, I
    suppress the urge to recommend stridency to you, we restrain ourselves, but the
    ignorance-begotten monsters practice no restraint whatever, and they oblige us, oblige me here,
    to take a strident tone. With the best of intentions: stridency cannot be suppressed without
    betrayal of the cause; one is <tei:hi rend="underline">obliged to use strident language by the
     people</tei:hi> responsible for the damage and whose destructiveness knows no rest. How I would
     <tei:pb n="6"/> like to take a milder tone, but that would be betrayal. With the sword of truth
    and of anger it must succeed and it will succeed! </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Good luck on your quest and best greetings from us both, </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Yours,</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60">H. Schenker</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>



  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>