<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="1905" sdoID="OJ-89-7_15">OJ 89/7, [15]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="JR-HE">
   <tei:persName>John Rothgeb and Heribert Esser</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2017</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2017</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2017</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2012-10-08" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002730">Hoboken ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002731">Hoboken ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Hoboken, dated December 25, 1934</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1934-12-25T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2017-08-16</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker and Jeanette thank Hoboken for their Christmas gifts; Shenker alludes to
    the forthcoming publication of Der freie Satz as the "summit" of his career, and reports that he
    has been invited to inspect the new accommodation for the Photogramarchiv.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Gaben; gifts; Gipfel; summit; peak; Ziel; goal; Dank; thanks; Räume;
    rooms</dc:subject>

   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000380">Hoboken</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:date when="1934-12-25">25. 12. 34</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Meine lieben, verehrten Herrschaften!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
      place="foot">Writing of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/8, p. 3965,
      December 25, 1934: "An v. Hoboken (Br.): Dank." ("To Hoboken (letter):
     thanks.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Die süße Torte dem zuckersüßen „Professor,“ die schöne, ach so schöne Blume meiner Blume,
    der „<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Frau Professor</tei:rs>“ — wie weise u. treffend
    eingeteilt, wir danken denn auch entsprechend süß u. schön, d.h. von ganzem Herzen für beide
    Gaben! —, aber: dem herrlichen Gotteswort vom Tage folgend: „Seid guten Willens“ haben wir, eben
    guten Willens, einander, wie folgt, anders eingeteilt: die Torte erhält die <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000771">Frau Prof.</tei:rs>, die Blume nimmt sich der H.
     Prof.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker writes continuously
     at this point, without paragraph-break.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ja, warum <tei:pb n="2"/> denn?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"
     >Schenker here punctuated at first with a comma, but on second thoughts completed the
     question-mark by placing its hook above the comma itself (personal communication from Heribert
     Esser). He thus combined the two marks, creating a kind of portmanteau punctuation.</tei:note>
    höre ich Sie Beide fragen, insgeheim u. doch mit Recht auf Heiteres gefaßt. Also: Wer wie ich
    zurzeit etwa 500-1000 Meter vom Gipfel (= „Mount <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
     >Everest</tei:hi>“)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker is
     presumably referring to the publication of <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title
       level="m">Der freie Satz</tei:title></tei:rs>, which did not occur until May 25, 1935, which
     he did not live to see. The latter part of this paragraph is perhaps alluding to the fact that
     Hoboken was financing the publication.</tei:note> entfernt ist, darf sich nichts zumuten, das
    ihn zur Umkehr zwingen müsste. (In der Welt der Touristik geht so etwas immerhin an: andere
    Männer werden den Gipfel erreichen, aber ich selbst darf mir eine solche Hoffnung nicht
    vergönnen.) Trotz allem Leichtsinn möchte ich, dem Ziele so nahe, so nahe, mich in Zurückhaltung
    üben, zumal in Voraussicht dessen, daß Sie, lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000380">v <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Hoboken</tei:hi></tei:rs>, nach vollbrachter
    Tat, mir gern 2 Torten spenden werden, die ich in strotzendem Leichtsinn, aber mit
     Überzeu<tei:supplied reason="omission">g</tei:supplied>ung gern, ganz allein zu mir nehmen
    werde, denn <tei:add place="interlinear-above">sie</tei:add> ist, (wie ich es <tei:hi
     rend="underline">schon</tei:hi> weiß), <tei:hi rend="double-underline">ganz
     ausgezeichnet</tei:hi>!</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> Dafür verlege ich mich mehr auf den Blumen<tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">topf</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">korb</tei:add>
    </tei:subst>, mein <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">LieLiechen</tei:rs> führt mir Nase
    u. Aug’ durch diese Herrlichkeiten.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Natürlich, gar so streng machen wir es uns nicht. Denn daß ich von der Torte noch naschen
    werde, weil ich muß, verrate ich schon heute. Ausgeschlossen ist es auch, daß mein <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000771">LieLiechen</tei:rs> mir den Blumentopf überließe, also kommen
    wir mit Notwendigkeit schließlich doch auf Ihre weise Einteilung zurück: mir die Torte, dem
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">LieLiechen</tei:rs> die Blume. Nur daß ich auch zu
    mir selbst „guten Willens“ bleiben muß, das Gotteswort meint es gut u. klug mit uns
    Allen.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Nehmen Sie, meine lieben verehrten Herrschaften, noch einmal unser Beider freudigsten Dank
     <tei:pb n="4"/> für die holden Aufmerksamkeiten entgegen!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Prof. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000320"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
     >Haas</tei:hi></tei:rs> nutzte die Gelegenheit des Weihnachtsgrußes, mich in die neuen Räume
    Ihres <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archiv</tei:rs>s einzuladen.<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">The enlargement of the <tei:rs
      type="organization" key="entity-002452">Photogram Archive</tei:rs>, including new rooms within
     the Austrian National Library, fireproof cabinets for storage of the photographic materials,
     and special American equipment for viewing them, were finally opened in February 1936 ‒ see
     invitation <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-10_4">OJ 9/10, [4]</tei:ref>.</tei:note>
    Wie freue ich mich dessen! Freue ich mich <tei:add place="interlinear-above">doch</tei:add> in
    diesem Falle doppelt, für mich, wie für Sie! Mit Gott so fort, Er lohnt immer diejenigen, die
    „guten Willens“ den Meistern folgen als Mittlern seiner geheimsten Kunst.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Wir grüßen u. wünschen Allerbestes u. Festlichstes,</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Die Ihren</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-10"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
       >Henrich</tei:hi></tei:rs> u <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"><tei:hi
       rend="lateinschr">LieLie Schenker</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>



  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:date when="1934-12-25">December 25,
     1934</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>My dear, revered friends,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"
     /></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>The sweet cake for the sugar-sweet "Professor," the beautiful, oh so beautiful blossom for
    my blossom, the "<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Frau Professor</tei:rs>" – how wisely
    and appropriately allocated; we in turn thank with fitting sweetness and beauty, that is, from
    the bottom of our hearts, for both gifts! But: in keeping with the splendid divine bidding of
    the day: "be of good will," we have, precisely by reason of good will, allocated differently to
    each other as follows: the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Frau Professor</tei:rs>
    receives the cake, the Herr Professor takes the blossom for himself.<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>But why?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/>
    <tei:pb n="2"/> I hear you both ask, secretly and yet altogether prepared for something jocund.
    Thus: whoever, like me at present, is about 500‒1,000 meters from the summit (= "Mount
     Everest")<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> may not demand anything of himself
    that would have to force him to turn around. (In the world of tourism such a thing may be
    possible: other men will reach the summit, but I myself may not permit me such a hope.) Despite
    all light-heartedness, I ‒ so near, so near to the goal ‒ would like to remain cautious,
    especially in the prospect that you, dear Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">van
     Hoboken</tei:rs>, will, after all is said and done, gladly dispense <tei:hi rend="italic"
     >two</tei:hi> cakes to me, which I alone, teeming with light-heartedness, but with conviction,
    will myself gladly consume, because <tei:add place="interlinear-above">they</tei:add> are (as I
     <tei:hi rend="underline">already</tei:hi> know) <tei:hi rend="double-underline">really
     excellent</tei:hi>!</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> On the other hand I take more to the flowers, my <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000771">LieLiechen</tei:rs> leads my nose and eye through these beauties.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Naturally, we are not so strict about all of this. For that I will still try some of the
    cake, because I must, I confess already today. And it is moreover out of the question that my
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">LieLiechen</tei:rs> will pass the flowers along to
    me; thus we necessarily at last return to your wise allocation: the cake for me, for <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000771">LieLiechen</tei:rs> the flowers. Except that I too must
    remain "of good will" even to myself ‒ the divine bidding applies well and wisely to us
    all.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Please accept, my dear esteemed friends, once again most delighted thanks <tei:pb n="4"/>
    from us both for your sweet present!</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Prof. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000320">Haas</tei:rs> used the occasion of
    Christmas greetings to invite me into the new rooms of your <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-002452">Archive</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> How
    pleased I am! <tei:add place="interlinear-above">But</tei:add> I am pleased in this case twice
    as much: for myself and for you! With God, ever the same: He always rewards those who, "of good
    will," follow the masters as the transmitters of His most secret Art.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>We greet you and wish all the best and most festive,</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-10"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Henrich</tei:rs> and
      <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">LieLie Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>


  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
