<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2035" sdoID="OJ-89-6_6">OJ 89/6, [6]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="JR-HE">
      <tei:persName>John Rothgeb and Heribert Esser</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2017</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2017</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2017</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2012-10-08" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002730">Hoboken ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002731">Hoboken ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Hoboken, dated May 3, 1933</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1933-05-03T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2017-12-08</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker congratulates Hoboken and Eva Boy on their engagement, and comments
        on a Frankfurter Zeitung article that Hoboken has sent him, and satirizes the laws that
        Hitler has recently introduced. — He encloses his own article, "Was wird aus der Musik?" —
        He encloses an invoice from Universal Edition.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Vermählung; engagement; Sprache; language; Hebräisch; Hebrew; Aufsatz; article;
        Verfasser; author; Hitler; fremde Rasse; alien race; Schicksal; fate; Eigensprache; native
        language; Motto; Rechnung; invoice; Betrag; sum; Erlagschein; deposit slip</dc:subject>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000380">Hoboken</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1933-05-03">3. V. 33</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Mein lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380"
              ><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">van Hoboken</tei:hi></tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01"
            type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at
            OJ 4/6, p. 3830, May 2, 1933: "An Hoboken (Br. u. Aufsatz aus der DAZ; Frankf. Ztg.
            zurück, Rechnung der U.-E.): Wünsche zur Vermählung, Begleitworte zu den Stücken." ("To
            Hoboken (letter, and article from the <tei:title level="j">DAZ</tei:title>; the
              <tei:title level="j">Frankfurter Zeitung</tei:title> returned, invoice from UE): best
            wishes for his marriage; accompanying words for the [enclosed]
          items.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Nicht allein, weil <tei:del rend="overstrike">d</tei:del> ich den Brauch von heute
        nicht kenne, sondern aus Überzeugung folge ich der alten Sitte: ich glaube an eine Gnade
        Gottes, an die Kraft der Wünsche, also wünsche ich Ihnen Beiden zur Vermählung, von der ich
        durch Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000164" type="person">Deutsch</tei:rs> erfahre, Erfüllung
        alles dessen, was Sie ersehnen, erhoffen. Meine <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person"
          >Frau</tei:rs> wünscht herzlichst mit!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Endlich kann ich Ihre „<tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002537"><tei:title>Frkf.
            Ztg</tei:title></tei:rs>“ zurückstellen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Schenker acknowledged receipt of this article from Hoboken in <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-89-6_4">OJ 89/6, [4]</tei:ref> of March 22, when he said
          he would defer reading it. He is now commenting on and returning it.</tei:note> Diese
        Sprache! Ist es überhaupt eine Sprache? Offenbar in Erinnerung an ein Spaniertum der Habs-
          <tei:pb n="2"/> bürger nennt der Wiener Volksmund ein ähnlich Unverständliches „Spanisch,“
        oder ist das schon das „Hebräisch,“ das in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482"
            ><tei:country>Deutschland</tei:country></tei:rs> heute aufdiktiert<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">"aufdiktiert" ("mandatory"): Schenker's
          coinage: Hitler, who had come to power only shortly before this letter was written,
          absurdly stipulated that Jews living in Germany were not Germans but were really Hebrews,
          and that whatever they wrote was originally <tei:hi rend="italic">written in the Hebrew
            language</tei:hi> and only subsequently translated into German.</tei:note> wird? Doch
        sind die spanische wie hebräische Sprache ganz gewiß durchleuchteter, begabter, als der
        jämmerliche Unrat in Worten, den der Aufsatz in die Nase stäubt. Verstehen Sie etwas davon?
        Wehe Ihnen, wenn . . . Der Verfasser kenne ich von <tei:rs type="journal"
          key="entity-002556">der „<tei:title>Musik</tei:title>“</tei:rs> her, der er pünktlich die
        hochtrabendsten Schweinereien liefert.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nun lege ich zum Dank meinen Aufsatz aus der „<tei:rs type="journal"
          key="entity-002992"><tei:title>D.A.Z.</tei:title></tei:rs>“ vom <tei:date
          when="1933-04-28">28.IV</tei:date><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial"
          place="foot">An essay by <tei:bibl><tei:author>Schenker</tei:author>, <tei:title level="a"
              >Was wird aus der Musik?</tei:title>
            <tei:title level="j">Deutsche allgemeine Zeitung</tei:title>, April 28, 1933</tei:bibl>,
          copies of which are preserved at OC A/274 and OJ 20/11. See also <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-18-25">OJ 5/18, 25</tei:ref>, from Schenker to Oswald
          Jonas, dated May 4, 1933. The article was reprinted in the <tei:bibl><tei:title level="j"
              >Basler National-Zeitung, Sonntags-Beilage</tei:title>, Jg. 14, No. 241, May 28,
            1933</tei:bibl>, a copy of which is preserved at OC 30/5. — The editor's Vorbemerkung
          mentioned here later reads: "Wir geben folgenden Ausführungen gerne Raum, gestehen aber,
          nicht immer gleicher Meinung zu sein." ("We gladly give space to the following remarks,
          but confess that we do not always concur with its opinions.")</tei:note> bei: Weder habe
        ich mich seinetwegen taufen lassen ‒ was übrigens ja gar nicht genützt hätte ‒, noch habe
        ich ihn im Original hebräisch geschrieben, u. doch hat es sich begeben, wie, weiß ich selbst
        nicht; ich habe ihn mitten Februar eingeschickt (noch vor <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003109">Hitler</tei:rs>).<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial"
          place="foot">Hitler was appointed German Chancellor on January 30, but it was on March 24
          that he was granted full powers, independent of the Reichstag. — This elaborate outbreak
          of irony is a sendup of the Hitlerian nonsense recounted in footnote 3.</tei:note>
        <tei:pb n="3"/> Daß im Umkreise der vielen „Musiker,“ „Kritiker,“ die das Blatt bedienen,
        meine „fremde Rasse“ nicht schon festgestellt worden wäre, glaube ich nicht. Ein Anderes
        ists: daß ebendiesen Herren mein Aufsatz unverständlich, eben „hebräisch“ bleiben muß. Daher
        die Vorbemerkung der Redaktion, auf die ich ebenso stolz bin, wie darauf, daß der
        Musikschreiber in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002495">Frankf.</tei:rs> meinen Namen
        nicht nennt. Der Aufsatz ist zur Korrektor nicht vorgelegen, daher allerhand Druckfehler u.
        sonstige Unebenheiten. Sie sind gewiß Einer der sehr Wenigen, die wissen, was ich meine. Im
        Übrigen ist das Schicksal der Musik ja eben darum so traurig, daß von ihr allein in ihrer
        Eigensprache nicht gesprochen werden darf! Eine originelle <tei:pb n="4"/> Zustimmung ist
        mir aber postwendend zugekommen: ein Mitglied der Kant-Gesellschaft in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002501"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Berlin</tei:hi></tei:rs> hat mir eine kleine
        Arbeit verehrt, auf die er als Motto die letzten Worte meines Aufsatzes gesetzt
          hat.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Starting from the premise
          that, built from intervals, counterpoint, diatony, coherence, and synthesis, music has
          achieved the status of <tei:hi rend="italic">Gleichnis ihrer selbst</tei:hi> ("image of
          itself"), Schenker's article asserts that composers, in the name of "progress," have now
          thrown this away and music has become "chaos." The final sentence of the article reads:
          "Am Ende von jahrhundertelangen Erfahrungen mag der Menschheit der Triumph beschieden
          sein, die Musik in ihrem Gleichnis zu erschauen, dann mag ihr auch der erhebende Trost
          winken, gerade durch die abgezogene, nur in sich selbst ruhende Kunst der Musik Gottes
          Schöpfung als ein Gleichnis Gottes zu verstehen, Gott als Gleichnis Seiner selbst!" ("At
          the end of centuries-long experiences, may the triumph be granted to mankind of beholding
          music in its own image. Then may the uplifting comfort also encourage it, precisely
          through the abstracted, purely self-sufficient art of music, to understand God's creation
          as an image of God: God as image of Himself!")</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Endlich lege ich noch die Rechnung der „<tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408"
          >U.E.</tei:rs>“ bei. Den Betrag, der kleiner geworden ist, als ich befürchtet habe ‒ was
        mag darum noch emporbetragen sein! ‒ habe ich schon erlegt. Den „Erlagschein“ behalte ich zu
        meiner Deckung noch hier. Den Rest erlege ich in Ihre Hand. Somit ist von dem mir von Ihrem
        so lieb zugedachten Betrag die in der Rechnung ausgewiesene Summe in Abzug zu
        bringen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nochmals vielen, vielen Dank!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Hoffentlich lassen Sie sich recht bald bei uns sehen!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Mit besten Grüßen Ihnen Beiden von uns Beiden,</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"><tei:hi
              rend="lateinschr">H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1933-05-03">May 3, 1933</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">My dear Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">van
            Hoboken</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Not only because I do not know the custom of today, but out of conviction, I follow the
        old manner: I believe in a divine grace, in the power of wishes; therefore, I wish you both
        on the occasion of your engagement, of which I learn through Prof. <tei:rs
          key="entity-000164" type="person">Deutsch</tei:rs>, fulfillment of all that which you
        desire and hope for. My <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs> joins most
        sincerely in that wish!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>At last I can return your <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002537"><tei:title
            level="j">Frankfurter Zeitung</tei:title></tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/> This language! Is it a language at all? Obviously in recollection of an
        Hispanic ethos of the Habsburgs, <tei:pb n="2"/> the Viennese folk-tongue calls anything
        similarly incomprehensible "Spanish"; or is that already "Hebrew," which in <tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002482"><tei:country>Germany</tei:country></tei:rs> today is
          "mandatory"?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> But the Spanish as well as
        the Hebrew language is more luminous, more gifted, than the miserable verbal garbage with
        which the essay assaults the nose. Do you understand any of that? Poor you, if . . . I
        recognize the author from <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002556"><tei:title level="j"
            >Die Musik</tei:title></tei:rs>, to which he punctually delivers the most ostentatious
        filth.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Now I am including out of gratitude my essay from the <tei:rs type="journal"
          key="entity-002992"><tei:title level="j">D.A.Z.</tei:title></tei:rs> of <tei:date
          when="1933-04-28">April 28</tei:date><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> I
        have neither deafened myself for its sake ‒ which, incidentally, would not have helped ‒ nor
        have I written Hebrew in the original; and yet it happened ‒ how, I myself do not know; I
        sent it off in mid-February (still before <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003109"
          >Hitler</tei:rs>).<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/>
        <tei:pb n="3"/> That in the circle of the many "musicians," "critics" who follow the
        journal, my "alien race" would not already have been discovered, I do not believe. It is
        something else: that to these very gentlemen my essay would necessarily remain
        incomprehensible, exactly "Hebrew." Thus the preliminary note by the editors, of which I am
        just as proud as I am of the fact that the music writer in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002495">Frankfurt</tei:rs> fails to mention my name. The essay was not
        submitted to the proofreader, and as a result contains all manner of misprints and other
        incongruities. You are certainly one of the very few who know what I mean. For the rest, the
        fate of music is, to be sure, just for that reason so sad that one may not speak of it alone
        in its native language! An original <tei:pb n="4"/> message of concurrence, however, has
        come to me through the mail: a member of the Kant Society in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs> has done me the honor of presenting me with a small
        work in which he has used as a motto the closing words of my essay.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Finally, I include as well the invoice from the <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002408">Universal Edition</tei:rs>; the amount due, which turns out to be less
        than I feared ‒ how much they may have marked up there! ‒ I have already paid. For now, I am
        keeping the deposit slip as my security. The rest I'll pay into your hand. Therefore the
        amount shown in the invoice has to be deducted from the total you so kindly allocated to
        me.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Again I say: many, many thanks!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>We hope that you will pay us a visit quite soon!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>With best greetings to you both from both of us,</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.
          Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
