<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="351" sdoID="OJ-89-4_4">OJ 89/4, [4]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="TPavh" scope="sole">Anthony van Hoboken as typist</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="JR">
      <tei:persName>John Rothgeb</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2016</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2016</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2016</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2012-11-19" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002730">Hoboken ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002731">Hoboken ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <dc:title>Typewritten letter (carbon copy) from Hoboken to Schenker, dated March 29,
        1930</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1930-03-29T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2016-08-04</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Hoboken questions Schenker's separation of "artist" from "person," and says
        that he does not want to become an eternal student.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject>Rückreise; return; Mensch; person; Künstler; artist; Beurteilung; judgment;
        chronisch; chronic; Schüler; student; pupil; begabt; gifted; Arbeitstrieb; work ethic;
        Fleiss; industry; mechanistisch; mechanistic</dc:subject>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000380">Hoboken</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:date when="1930-03-29">29 März
          1930</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>Hochverehrter und lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Dr.</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/3, p. 3461, March 31, 1930: "Von v.
            H. (Br.): verteidigt sich indem er erklärt, Breithaupt nicht aus Neugier aufgesucht zu
            haben – keinesfalls werde ihn etwas von mir wegführen. Das Wort „chronischer Schüler“
            bleibt mir u. Lie-Liechen dunkel." ("From Hoboken (letter): he defends himself by
            explaining that he did not seek Breithaupt out of curiosity – under no circumstance will
            anything take him from me. The expression "chronic pupil" remains obscure to me and
            Lie-Liechen."). [...] "An Deutsch (Br.): schicke den Brief H.<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
              >s</tei:hi>, bitte um Aufklärung der dunkeln Stelle." ("To Deutsch (letter): I send
            him Hoboken's letter, ask for an explanation of the obscure passage."). <tei:rs
              key="entity-000164" type="person">Deutsch</tei:rs>'s answer is recorded at ibid, p.
            3462, April 2, 1930: "Von Deutsch (Br.): Waldheims u. v. H.<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
              >s</tei:hi> Brief zurück; v. H. fürchte sich vor dem ernsten Unterricht, vor dem
            Haydn-Katalog, vor dem Archiv u. vor der Bibliothek." ("From Deutsch (letter):
            Waldheim's and Hoboken's letters returned; Hoboken is afraid of serious tuition, of the
            Haydn catalogue, of the Archive and of his library!"). — Hoboken presumably means that
            he does not want to become an "eternal (or life-long) student."</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Noch möchte ich Ihnen schriftlich danken für Ihren letzten Brief,<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">= <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-89-4_3">OJ 89/4, [3]</tei:ref>, undated [March 23, 1930].</tei:note> da meine
        Rückreise nach <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> wohl noch um einigen
        Tagen <tei:choice>
          <tei:sic>hinausgeschieben</tei:sic>
          <tei:corr>hinausgeschoben</tei:corr>
        </tei:choice> werden dürfte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Hoboken resumed lessons with Schenker on April 8, at which meeting the matter of the
          Breithaupt consultation and lessons was discussed: "Nehme zum letztenmal Stellung zu
          seinen Breithaupt-Uebungen u. spreche über eine Technik des Inhalts, der gegenüber
          keinerlei Technik an sich aufkommt. Der Widerstand ist offenbar!" ("For the last time, I
          express an opinion on his Breithaupt exercises, and speak about a technique of content, in
          comparison with which no other technique can in itself come into question. His resistance
          is plain to see!") (lessonbook OC 3/4, 1929/30, p. 21).</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Warum trennen <tei:supplied reason="omission">Sie</tei:supplied> so scharf
        den Menschen vom Künstler in Ihrer Beurteilung? Ich bin immer bestrebt diese beiden im
        Einklang mit einander zu bringen indem ich z.B. niemals künstlerisch etwas unternehmen
        würde, was ich menschlich nicht verantworten könnte und dafür umgekehrt hoffe, dass mein
          menschliche<tei:supplied reason="syntax">s</tei:supplied> Tun stets vom künstlerischen
        beeinflusst werden möge. So möchte ich auch meinen jetzigen Schritt,<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">The consultation of piano pedagogue
          Rudolf Breithaupt, and the writer's subsequent decision to seek a series of lessons with
          him. See <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-89-4_2">OJ 89/4, [2]</tei:ref> and
            <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-89-4_3">OJ 89/4, [3]</tei:ref>.</tei:note> der,
        ich möchte das noch einmal extra betonen, nicht von Ihnen wegführen soll, von beiden
        Gesichtspunkten aus betrachtet wissen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich muss mich <tei:choice>
          <tei:sic>dafür</tei:sic>
          <tei:corr>davor</tei:corr>
        </tei:choice> hüten, chronischer Schüler (im buchstäblichen Sinne dieses Wortes) zu werden;
        infolge meiner Trägheit neige ich nur allzu sehr dazu.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich weiss auch selber ganz genau, dass ich zwar begabt bin, aber nicht zu
        arbeiten verstehe und freute mich daher besonders über den Zusatz Ihres Briefes, worin Sie
        das auf so liebenswürdiger Weise zum Ausdruck bringen. Arbeitstrieb muss einem auch etwas
        angeboren sein; nur von der materiellen Lage hängt das nicht ab indem ebensoviele
        Unbemittelte es höchstens zum Beamtengebracht haben als wie Begüterte von ihren frühesten
        Jugend an Fleiss gezeigt haben. Zu den letzteren habe ich nun einmal nie gehört, aber ich
        habe immer spielend leicht gelernt. Mechanistisch kann man sich dadurch allein aber nicht
        ausbilden. Wenn nun dieser Teil der Kunst mich doch noch anfängt zu interessieren und ich
        versuchen will, eine meinem Alter entsprechende Beherrschung des Klavieres dennoch zu
        erwerben, so möchten Sie darin nicht lediglich die Befriedigung einer Neugier sehen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Mit den besten Grüssen bin ich, wie immer,</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">Ihr ganz ergebener</tei:salute><tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline" rend="indent-60">unsigned</tei:note><tei:lb/>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>



    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:date when="1930-03-29">March 29,
          1930</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute>HIghly revered and dear Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs
              type="person" key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Once again I want to write in thanks for your last letter,<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> as my return to <tei:rs key="entity-002484"
          type="place">Vienna</tei:rs> will probably be delayed by a few days.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Why do you so sharply separate the man from the artist in your judgment? I
        have always tried to bring these two into agreement, in that, for example, I would never
        undertake anything artistic for which I could not be responsible as a man, and on the other
        hand I hope that my activity as a man may always be influenced by my artistic work. Thus I
        would like to have my present action,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> which
        ‒ I want to emphasize again ‒ is not to lead away from you, considered from both
        vantage-points.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I must avoid becoming a chronic pupil (in the literal sense of this word);
        as a consequence of my laziness, I all too easily tend in that direction.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I myself know very well that I am, it is true, gifted, but am not disposed
        to work, and thus I was especially pleased by the addendum to your letter, in which you so
        kindly bring that to expression. The work ethic has to be inborn; it does not depend on
        material resources, and just as many people without means have risen at most to the level of
        bureaucrat as those more fortunate who have shown industry from earliest youth. I have never
        belonged to this latter group, although I have always been a quick learner. But from that
        alone one cannot train oneself mechanistically. If this aspect of art now does begin to
        interest me and I want to try to achieve a mastery of the piano in keeping with my age,
        please do not view that only as satisfaction of a curiosity.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">With best greetings I am, as always,</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-70">Your wholly devoted</tei:salute><tei:lb/>
        <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline" rend="indent-60">unsigned</tei:note><tei:lb/>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
