<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="320" sdoID="OJ-89-1_1">OJ 89/1, [1]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="JR-HE">
   <tei:persName>John Rothgeb &amp; Heribert Esser</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008, 2010</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="JR">
   <tei:persName>John Rothgeb</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2008</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2011-03-11" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc><tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
    <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002730">Hoboken ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
    <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002731">Hoboken ~ H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to van Hoboken, dated July 3, 1927</dc:title>
   
   <dcterms:created>1927-07-03T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-02-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker gives Hoboken Furtwängler's summer address and urges him to contact the
    latter, which could yield advantage, not least for the Photogrammarchiv. — Has seen Schindler's
    Beethoven biography with notes on performance. — Notifies Hoboken of the normalizing of his fee
    at 50 schillings per lesson.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject> </dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000380">Hoboken</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>



  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-05">Lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">van
      Hoboken</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>



   <tei:p>Von<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is
     recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/9, pp. 3083-3084, July 2, 1927: "An Hoboken (Br.):
     empfehle, die Nachbarschaft in der Schweiz zu einem Besuch bei Furtwängler auszunützen, da ich
     ohnehin an F. wegen Oppels Messe zu schreiben habe, will ich den Besuch ankündigen. Bei dieser
     Gelegenheit teile ich die allgemeine Erhöhung des Honorars auf 50 Schillinge mit; zwei
     Beilagen: über Schönberg von einem seiner Schüler u. über die Aufführung der „Kunst der Fuge“
     im Sinne Gräsers." ("To Hoboken (letter): I recommend taking advantage of the proximity of
     Switzerland to make a visit to Furtwängler; since I in any case have to write to Furtwängler
     regarding Oppel's Mass, I will let him know of the visit. I use this occasion to notify him of
     the across-the-board raising of my fee to 50 schillings; two enclosures: about Schoenberg by
     one of his pupils, and about the performance of the <tei:title level="m">Art of
      Fugue</tei:title> in the spirit of Gräser.").</tei:note>
    <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Dr. Weisse</tei:rs>, der uns am letzten Freitag vor unserer Abreise
    den Abschiedsbesuch machte, erfuhr ich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs>'s Sommeradresse. Da Sie bald oder sehr bald nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002313">Sils Maria</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">See also Schenker's letter to Furtwängler, of
     July 3, 1927, Sbb 55 Nachl 13, [2], which covers some of the same topics.</tei:note> gehen,
    teile ich sie Ihnen mit: <tei:hi rend="underline">Moriz-Dorf, <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">acla
      silva</tei:hi></tei:hi>. Noch heute oder morgen schreibe ich an <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">F.</tei:rs>, um ihn für <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Oppel</tei:rs>'s Messe zu gewinnen; ich tue es gern, obgleich
    ich weiß, daß <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">F.</tei:rs> in solchen Fällen lieber der
    10. oder 15. Dirigent ist als der 1. In diesem Schreiben will ich mir die Freiheit nehmen, Ihren
    Besuch anzukündigen, was für Sie aber nicht bindend ist. Doch möchte ich die Vorteile nicht
    unerwähnt lassen, die ein Besuch bei <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">F.</tei:rs> mit
    sich bringen könnte<tei:del rend="overstrike">n</tei:del>: mir schwebt die Möglichkeit vor,
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">F.</tei:rs> für die künstlerische Verwirklichung der
    Ziele zu gewinnen, die Sie mit ihrer historisch höchstbedeutsamen Stiftung verbinden. Gelänge es
    Ihnen, einige Fäden schon bei Ihrem ersten Besuch zu spinnen, oder gar ihn in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Wien</tei:rs> in Ihr Haus zu bitten, <tei:pb n="2"/> wo auch ich
    mittun könnte, wer weiß, ob es nicht zu erreichen wäre, daß er sich an die Spitze der Dirigenten
    stellt, die die <tei:term>Meisterwerk</tei:term>e nach den <tei:term>Handschrift</tei:term>en aufführen, daß er sozusagen die „neue
    Mode“ kreiert, die für die Späteren maßgebend wäre. Vielleicht ist es die Eitelkeit, vielleicht
    der Ehrgeiz, veilleicht auch die Liebe zur Kunst, die ihn uns geneigt machen könnte, - ein
    Versuch scheint mir jedenfalls wagenswert. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>In der letzten Stunde hat mir Frau <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000655">Pairamall</tei:rs> den <tei:hi rend="underline">Erst</tei:hi>druck von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002743">Schindler</tei:rs>'s
      „<tei:title><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Beethoven-Biographie</tei:hi></tei:title>“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl>Anton Schindler, <tei:title level="m">Biographie Ludwig van Beethovens</tei:title> (Münster, 1840; 2/1845;
      3/1860).</tei:bibl>
    </tei:note> gezeigt, den sie gegen Kaution von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000320">Dr.
     Haas</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">The Austrian National Library is not a lending library, but Dr. Haas apparently
     made an exception in consideration of Mrs. Pairamall's deposit.</tei:note> ausgefolgt erhielt:
    der Erstdruck enthält <tei:hi rend="underline">Spielanweisungen</tei:hi>, die <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">dem</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">im</tei:add>
    </tei:subst> Neudruck fehlen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker's notes on these performance instructions (or, more exactly, reports by Schindler on
     Beethoven's playing) were published posthumously. See <tei:bibl>Heinrich Schenker, <tei:title level="a">Ein Kommentar zu Schindler, Beethovens Spiel betreffend,</tei:title>
      <tei:title level="j">Der Dreiklang</tei:title> 8/9 (1937-38), 190-99</tei:bibl>. See also
      <tei:bibl>Oswald Jonas, <tei:title level="a">Nachtrag zu Schenkers Aufsatz über
       Schindler,</tei:title>
      <tei:title level="j">Der Dreiklang</tei:title> 8/9 (1937-38), 200-07</tei:bibl>. </tei:note>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p> Von unserer Reise nur folgendes Notizchen. Hören Sie u. staunen Sie: im Hotel Post
    Landeck finden sich auch schon Zimmer mit warm u. kalt fließendem Wasser, sogar mit Baderwanne!
    Die schwersten Amerikaner haben, so erzählte uns der Hotelier, diesen Fortschritt in einem
    Provinznest angestaunt. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Zum Beschluß eine Mitteilung, von der ich glaube, daß ich <tei:pb n="3"/> sie Ihnen schon
    jetzt schulde: </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich glaube, es Ihnen schon einmal gesagt oder gar geschrieben zu haben, daß das Honorar
    von 5 doll. schon etwa seit 5 Jahren in Anwendung ist. Meiner Passivität in
    Honorarangelegenheiten haben die ältesten Schüler immer aus Eigenem vorgebeugt, u. auch Sie
    hatten die Liebenswürdigkeit, die Korrekturen auf sich zu nehmen. Wie ich es heute weiß, war es
    durchaus nicht eine üble Gesinnung, die mehrere andere Schüler an die Korrektur nicht denken
    ließ; einfach nur Unachtsamkeit war es. Gleichviel, mit der Zahl der Jahre u. Stunden hat sich
    der Verlust immer vergrößert, sodaß ich, zuletzt auch von Frau <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000655">Pairamall</tei:rs> angeregt, die Frage neu zu erwägen hatte. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>In den letzten Tagen habe ich mich vor Allem mit den <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Wien</tei:rs>er Schülern in Verbindung gestezt, denen ich Rücksicht aus sehr vielen
    Gründen schulde und die ich für das Maß nehmen muß, da ich gern bei einer Einheitlichkeit
    bleibe, ausgenommen die Fälle, wo ich aus Menschlichkeitsgründen den Unterricht unentgeltlich
    leite. Aus den mündlichen u. schriftlichen <tei:pb n="4"/> Verhandlungen ergab sich die
    Möglichkeit für mich, bei allem Respekt vor dem Völkerbund, vor der Sanierung (an die zu glauben
    mir anbefohlen wurde), vor dem Dollar jene 5-dollar-Einheit gegen eine Schilling-Einheit
    auszutauschen. Ich habe im Kriege durch meine persönliche Haltung furchtbar viel verloren, in
    der Nachkriegszeit nicht minder viel durch meinen Glauben an die Sanierung, kurz u. gut, so
    durfte ich es nicht weiter treiben. Mir war schon seit Langem bekannt, daß mich sogar
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Dr. Weisse</tei:rs>
    <tei:del rend="overstrike">schon</tei:del> überholt hat, um nicht von den „Prominenten“ zu
    sprechen. Ich ließ die Dingen hingehen, weil ich „Prestige“ in Geldsachen nicht kenne. Nur wuchs
    der Schade zu sehr an u. das zwang mich zu einer Neuordnung: ich habe mit den ältesten Schülern
    das Honorar von 50 S. per Stunde vereinbart u. rechne hiebei auch auf Ihre freundliche
    Zustimmung. Der Modus bleibt sonst der gleiche, nur daß an Stelle der 5 Dollars, bzw. 6 Doll die
    Einheit von 50S. tritt. Wenn es Ihnen paßt, können Sie auch weiterhin Dollars anweisen lassen,
    auch sonst es halten, wie Sie belieben. </tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="5"/> Es hätte leicht geschehen können, daß Sie von irgend einer anderen Seite
    durch Zufall davon erfahren - nicht etwa, weil das Honorar als „abnorm“ von sich reden machen
    würde, ich bleibe auch mit dem neuen hinter Nicht-Prominenten zurück - u. da hielt ich es
    einfach für meine Pflicht, Sie sogleich zu verständigen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Beiliegend 2 Aufsätze,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">These
     enclosures are not preserved with the letter. As Schenker's diary entry records, these are
     "about Schoenberg by one of his pupils," and "about the performance of the <tei:title level="m">Art of Fugue</tei:title> in the spirit of Gräser."</tei:note> die ich zu lesen u., wenn
    möglich, für mich aufzubewahren bitte. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Haben Sie die Tour nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002673">Gmunden</tei:rs> schon
    gemacht? </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Wie geht es Ihrer verehrten <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002742">Gemahlin</tei:rs>? </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Vergessen Sie nicht, die <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002672">Hallstätt</tei:rs>er
    See zu besuchen, aber nur bei Sonne! </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Als unser Wagen in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002623">Ischgl</tei:rs> eintrat,
    stießen wir auf Schnee, einen leibhaftigen, winterlichen Schneefall, der uns recht übel
    mitspielte. Heute freilich lenzt es schon, aber noch nicht ganz verläßlich. Ob Winter oder
    Frühling draußen, <tei:pb n="6"/> wir haben noch viel zu schlafen u. nichtszutun um uns von den
    großen Mühen der Saison zunächst zu erholen. Doch versteht sich, daß geistige Arbeit schon
    mitläuft. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> hatte ich einen Brief,
    worin er seinen Besuch in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Wien</tei:rs> ankündigt. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ihnen und Ihrer Frau <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002742">Gemalin</tei:rs> unser Beider
    beste Wünsche für Ihr Sommer! </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">HSchenker</tei:hi></tei:signed>
    <tei:lb/><tei:dateline/><tei:date>3. Juli 1927</tei:date>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>



  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-05">Dear Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">van
      Hoboken</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>



   <tei:p>From<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> Dr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs>, who last Friday made a farewell visit to us before our departure, I
    learned <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs>'s summer address. As you
    will go soon or very soon to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002313">Sils
     Maria</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> I will give it to you:
     <tei:hi rend="underline">Moriz-Dorf, acla silva</tei:hi>. Later today or tomorrow I will write
    to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs> to enlist him for <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000643">Oppel</tei:rs>'s Mass; I am glad to do it, although I know that
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs> in such cases would rather be the
    tenth or fifteenth conductor than the first. In this letter I will take the liberty of
    mentioning your visit, which however places you under no obligation. But I should not fail to
    mention the advantages that a visit to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs> could yield: I envision the possibilty of enlisting him for the
    artistic realization of the purposes that you associate with your extremely historically
    important foundation. If you could spin a few threads already in your first visit, or even
    invite him to your house in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Vienna</tei:rs>, <tei:pb n="2"/> where I could also take part, who knows whether it would not be possible to get him to
    spearhead the movement among conductors who would perform the <tei:term>masterwork</tei:term>s according to the <tei:term>manuscript</tei:term>s, and to bring about the "new mode," so to speak, which would be
    definitive for successors. Perhaps it would be vanity, or ambition, or even the love of art,
    that would incline him in our direction – it seems to me in any case worth trying. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>At the last lesson Mrs. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000655">Pairamall</tei:rs> showed
    me the <tei:hi rend="underline">first</tei:hi> edition of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002743">Schindler</tei:rs>'s
     "<tei:title>Beethoven-Biography</tei:title>,"<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/>
    which she obtained from Dr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000320">Haas</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> for a security deposit: the first edition includes
     <tei:hi rend="underline">performance instructions</tei:hi>, which are lacking in the
     reprint.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p>From our trip, the following mini-report. Listen and marvel: in the Hotel Post Landeck
    there are now rooms with hot and cold running water, even with bathtub! The most typical
    Americans, so the hotelier told us, were astonished at this progress in a one-horse town. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>In conclusion, a communication that I believe I <tei:pb n="3"/> owe you without delay: </tei:p>

   <tei:p> I think at one time I told you or even wrote to you that the fee of $5 has already been
    in effect for five years. The pupils from earliest times have always voluntarily compensated for
    my passivity in fee matters, and you too were so kind as to make the adjustments yourself. As I
    know today, it was not out of bad faith that several other pupils failed to think of adjustment;
    it was only inattention. In any case, with the number of years and lessons the shortfall has
    ever increased, so that, partly at the instigation of Mrs. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000655">Pairamall</tei:rs>, I have had to reconsider. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>In the last days I have first been in touch with the Viennese pupils, whom I owe
    consideration for very many reasons, and whom I must take as the standard, since I prefer to
    maintain uniformity, with the exception of cases in which, for humanitarian reasons, I provide
    free instruction. From oral and written <tei:pb n="4"/> transactions, the possibility arose for
    me, with all due respect to the League of Nations, in the face of the financial reconstruction
    (which I have been ordered to credit) regarding the dollar to replace the five-dollar amount
    with an amount in schillings. In the war I lost a great deal because of my personal policy, and
    no less in the post-war period through my faith in the reconstruction; in short, I cannot
    continue this way. I have known for a long time that even Dr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs> had surpassed me, not to speak of the "prominent" teachers. I let
    matters slide, because I know no "prestige" in money matters. But the damage grew out of control
    and that obliged me to a reorganization: with the oldest pupils I have arrived at a fee of 50
    schillings per lesson and I am counting on your kind consent to this arrangement too. The mode
    of payment remains the same, except that instead of $5 or $6 the sum of 50 schillings will
    apply. If this suits you, you can continue to pay in dollars, or in some other form, as you
    wish. </tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="5"/> It could have easily happened that you had learned of this by coincidence
    from some other source – not because the fee would cause talk of its being "abnormal" (with the
    new one I am still lower than "non-prominents") – and so I simply considered it my duty to let
    you know at once. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Two essays are enclosed<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> which I request
    that you read and, if possible, keep for me. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Have you already made the tour to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002673">Gmunden</tei:rs>? </tei:p>

   <tei:p>How is your dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002742">wife</tei:rs>? </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Don't forget to visit the Lake of <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002672">Hallstatt</tei:rs>, but only in sunny weather! </tei:p>

   <tei:p>As our car entered <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002623">Ischgl</tei:rs>, we ran into
    snow, a real winter snowfall, which quite got us down. Today, admittedly, spring is here, but
    not that dependably so. Whether winter or spring outside, <tei:pb n="6"/> we still have much
    sleeping and idling to do in order first to rest up from the hard work of the season. But it
    goes without saying that the mind is already at work. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>I had a letter from <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> in which
    he announces his visit in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Vienna</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Our best wishes to you and your <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002742">wife</tei:rs> for
    your summer! </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Yours,</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60">H. Schenker</tei:signed>
    <tei:lb/><tei:dateline/><tei:date>July 3, 1927</tei:date>
   </tei:closer>


  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>