<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="1875" sdoID="OJ-89-5_2">OJ 89/5, [2]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="JR-HE">
   <tei:persName>John Rothgeb and Heribert Esser</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2016</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2016</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2016</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2012-10-08" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002730">Hoboken ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002731">Hoboken ~
    H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Hoboken, dated February 27, 1932</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1932-02-27T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2016-11-03</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker thanks Hoboken effusively for the letter of guarantee [for Der freie
    Satz publication costs].</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Brief; letter; Testament; will; Drucklegung; printing; Wittwe; widow; Hilfe; help;
    Druckerei; printer; Bestellung; order; Verpflichtung; commitment; Erscheinen; publication;
    Lehrbuch; textbook; Betrag; sum; Beispiel; music example; Musiker; musician; Laie; amateur;
    Dank; thank you</dc:subject>

   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000380">Hoboken</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Mein Lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">van
      Hoboken</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this
      letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/5, p. 3709, February 27, 1932: "An v. Hoboken
      (Br. Express): Dank für das Dokument!" ("To v. Hoboken (express letter): thanks for the
      document!").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Es drängt mich, Ihnen noch einmal und schriftlich allerherzlichst für den Brief zu danken,
    den Sie mir gestern persönlich zu übergeben die Güte hatten!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
     type="editorial" place="foot">The handing over of the document in question is recorded in
     Schenker's diary, ibid, February 26, 1932: "v. H. übergibt mir nun wirklich ein Schreiben, in
     dem er 12–15000 S. für <tei:title>den freien Satz</tei:title> auswirft! Meinen Einwand gegen
     die Form entkräftet er – ich nehme den Brief an." ("Hoboken actually hands me a written
     statement that says he will shell out 12–15,000 shillings for <tei:title level="m">Free
      Composition</tei:title>! He refutes my objection to the form [of the statement] – I accept the
     letter.").</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich habe ihn sofort zu meinem Testament gelegt,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
     type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker’s will and testament, dated June 18, 1929, is preserved
     at <tei:ref type="other" cRef="OJ-35-6_1">OJ 35/6, [1]</tei:ref>.</tei:note> damit für den
    Fall, daß ich, was Gott verhüten wolle, während der Drucklegung abberufen würde, die <tei:rs
     key="entity-000771" type="person">Wittwe</tei:rs> weiß, wo sich die Hilfe findet, die von mir
    gegenüber dem <tei:rs key="entity-002408" type="organization">Verlag</tei:rs> oder der Druckerei
    bei <tei:pb n="2"/> der Bestellung eingegangen Verpflichtungen einzulösen. Doch will ich hoffen,
    daß wir Alle besten Muts das Erscheinen des <tei:rs key="entity-001728" type="work">großen
     Werkes</tei:rs> erleben, das ohne Zweifel bestimmt ist, der Zeit u. dem Werte nach das erste
    Lehrbuch der Musik zu sein. Neben diesem Werke werden ‒ das ist beileibe keine neide
    Ruhmredigkeit, heute habe ich das Gefühl, daß ich dies auch mit Ihrer Zustimmung ausspreche ‒
    nur zwei Werke ewige Geltung behalten: die <tei:term>G<tei:supplied reason="abbreviation"
      >eneral</tei:supplied>b<tei:supplied reason="abbreviation">aß</tei:supplied></tei:term>-Bücher
    von Bach Vater u. Sohn, sonst aber <tei:pb n="3"/> kein Werk der Literatur mehr.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Besonders danke ich Ihnen dafür, daß der mir gerichtete Betrag die Möglichkeit im Werke
    freier mit den Beispielen zu schalten gestattet. Doch will ich anderseits sehr fest darauf
    achten, daß das Werk nicht überflüssig Grenzen überschreite, daß es auch minderbemittelten
    Musikern u. Laien leicht zugänglich bleibe. Wollen wir der Menge, die sonst das Dunkle liebt,
    von Herzen gönnen, an der Taghelle des Werkes nach ihrem Vermögen teilzunehmen!</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> Und nun noch einmal: Dank, Dank, Dank!</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mit bestem Gruß</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
       >H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1932-02-27">27. 2. 32</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>



  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">My dear Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">van
      Hoboken</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>I hasten to thank you most heartily and in writing for the letter that you were so good
    yesterday as to give me personally.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I have immediately placed it along with my last will and testament,<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> so that in case my time should come, God forfend,
    during the printing, my <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">widow</tei:rs> will know where
    to look for the aid in fulfilling the commitments I made to the <tei:rs key="entity-002408"
     type="organization">publisher</tei:rs> or the printer at <tei:pb n="2"/> the time of the order.
    But I persist in the hope that we all will live to witness in best spirits the publication of
    the <tei:rs key="entity-001728" type="work">major work</tei:rs>, which without doubt is
    destined, in terms of time and value, to be the premier text on music. Along with this work ‒
    this is by no means naive boastfulness; today I have the feeling that I can say this with your
    agreement ‒ only two works maintain eternal value: the <tei:term>thoroughbass</tei:term> books
    of Bach father and son, and <tei:pb n="3"/> not a single other work of the literature.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>I thank you especially that the sum allotted will make it possible for me to be more
    liberal with the examples. But on the other hand I will take extra care that the work not
    unnecessarily exceed limits, that it remain easily affordable also for less affluent musicians
    and amateurs. Let us generously grant the masses, who otherwise love the dark, participation,
    according to their abilities, in the light of day that beams from the work!</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> And once again: thank you, thank you, thank you!</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">With best greetings,</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.
     Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
    <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1932-02-27">February 27, 1932</tei:date></tei:dateline>
   </tei:closer>
  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
