<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="484" sdoID="OJ-9-34_39">OJ 9/34, [39]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="FEvC" scope="sole">Felix-Eberhard von Cube's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
      <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2011-11-12" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002775">Cube ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated April 29, 1934</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1934-04-29T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-10-09</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Cube has broken his silence; believes he is defeated: encloses letter from his employer; will try
        to enlist Furtwängler's support. He is known as "the" Schenkerian; others now avoid Schenker's name to protect
        themselves. Does Schenker know of any possibility for him and his family in Austria? Encloses
        graph.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      
      
    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000143">Cube</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-35">Hamburg 13, Mittelweg 126, Haus Ia/<tei:hi rend="supralinear">II.</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:date when="1934-04-29">29.IV.34</tei:date>
        </tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Lieber, hochverehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is
            recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/7, p. 3908, May 2, 1934: "Von v. Cube (Br. u. Bild des Dd-Präl. I):
            wurde wegen der Schenker-Theorie gekündigt, hat sich an Furtwängler gewendet." ("From von Cube (letter and
            graph of the D major Prelude <tei:supplied>from <tei:title level="m">WTC</tei:title> Book</tei:supplied> I):
            was given his notice on account of the Schenker theory, has turned to
          Furtwängler.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich habe lange geschwiegen, denn ich musste schweigend kämpfen. Nun bin ich, glaube ich,
        unterlegen. Ich haben Ihnen und der Wahrheit die Treue gehalten, solange meine Kräfte reichten. Nun fürchte ich,
        bricht das Unheil auch über mich herein. Der beilegende Brief meiner derzeitigen Brotherren<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:hi rend="italic">Brotherren</tei:hi> = employers, but
          literally "the gentlemen who provide bread".</tei:note> erübrigt jeden Kommentar!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">This letter does not appear to have survived in either OJ or OC.</tei:note> Ich
        werde nicht kampflos weichen. In diesen Tagen versuche ich durch <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs> Unterstützung von oben her zu erhalten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Furtwängler did write to Cube, around August 9, 1934. Cube copied this letter at the start of a
          very long letter to Schenker, dated October 4, 1934 (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-34_42">OJ 9/34,
            [42]</tei:ref>).</tei:note> Doch glaube ich nicht sehr an Erfolg, da mein letzter Brief an ihm (mit Bitte um
        Empfehlungsschreiben) unbeantwortet blieb. Ebenso erhoffe ich mir wenig Hilfe von alteingesessenen Verehrern
        Ihrer Lehre (Prof. Spengel<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Professor Spengel:
          probably refers to to the composer <tei:rs key="entity-002849" type="person">Julius Heinrich Spengel</tei:rs>
          (1853–1936); his personal papers are preserved at the Brahms Institute of the State Music Conservatory in
          Lübeck.</tei:note> und <tei:rs key="entity-000427" type="person">Th. Kaufmann</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Theodor Kaufmann (1892–1972) was a Hamburg-based pianist,
          teacher and composer, who had studied with Busoni in Berlin. His <tei:title>Piano Sonata No. 1</tei:title>, a
          large and difficult one-movement work that was among the few compositions to survive the Allied bombing of
          Hamburg in 1943, has recently been recorded. For further biographical details, see: <tei:ref target="http://www.romana-hamburg.de/Theodor%20Kaufmann.htm" type="external">http://www.romana-hamburg.de/Theodor%20Kaufmann.htm</tei:ref> (accessed June 9, 2008).</tei:note>), da
        dieselben gegen jene, die es in der Hand haben, nichts vermögen. Ich bin nun mal bekannt als „der“
        Schenkerianer, und habe alles auszubaden, wenngleich andere schon zwanzig Jahre vor mir hier dasselbe lehrten;
        ihnen wird man nichts tun, den sie haben sich gehütet<tei:supplied reason="grammar">,</tei:supplied> Ihren Namen
        zu nennen, als es brenzlich wurde! Ich hoffe immer noch, dass mein Fall nicht sÿmptomatisch für <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place">Deutschland</tei:rs> ist, sondern eine lokale kleine Machtprobe einiger
        anonÿm (naturlich!) arbeitender „<tei:soCalled>Kollegen</tei:soCalled>“, die mich auf diese Weise erledigen, und
        sich damit noch Verdienste erwerben. <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs> muss sich
        nun entscheiden! <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">Hic Rhodus, hic salta</tei:foreign>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:hi rend="italic">Hic Rhodus, hic salta</tei:hi>: a Latinized form of the
          punch-line of Aesop's fable of the athlete who boasted of feats he never actually performed: "Here is Rhodes,
          here is where you <tei:supplied reason="clarity">must</tei:supplied> jump." Cube is using it to imply that
          Furtwängler must summon his moral courage and publicly proclaim that Schenker, a Jew, has made an important
          contribution to German musical culture.</tei:note> Ich glaube das Ergebnis vorauszuwissen! Und aus diesem
        Grunde frage ich erstmalig informatorisch bei Ihnen an, ob Sie für mich eine Mögligkeit sehen, mit meiner
        Familie (im <tei:date when="1934-08">August</tei:date> werden wir selbdritt sein) der sicheren Vernichtung zu
        entgehen? <tei:foreign xml:lang="fre">A propos</tei:foreign>: Noch ist die Gafahr latent, doch muss ich
        beizeiten Vorkehrungen treffen. Inwieweit Verwandtenhilfe und <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs>s Macht in- (oder ausserhalb) des Reiches in Frage kommen, will ich Ihnen mitteilen,
        sobald ich sondiert habe.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot">No paragraph-break in
          original.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Zur beiliegenden <tei:term>Tafel</tei:term>: Das letzte Dritteil gefällt mir selber noch nicht!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09" type="editorial" place="foot">Probably a voice-leading graph of the <tei:rs key="entity-001145" type="composition">D major prelude</tei:rs> from Bach's <tei:title level="m">Well-Tempered Clavier</tei:title>, Book 1. Schenker's brief response (postcard of May 8, 1934) is followed
          by a letter from Cube (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-34_40">OJ 9/34, [40]</tei:ref>, June 2, 1934)
          in which a revised Ursatz is written into the body of the text.</tei:note> Aber ich wollte den Brief
        abschicken, und allzuweit werde ich wohl nicht vorbeigeschossen haben. Auch plagt mich heute
          Rheumatismus<tei:supplied reason="grammar">,</tei:supplied> dass ich nicht viel schreiben kann.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10" type="editorial" place="foot">No paragraph-break in original.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Noch dies: Ich hatte vor einem halben Jahr eine Unterredung mit <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs>, in der er Sie sehr überzeugt verteidigte – allerdings unter vier Augen. —</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Mit herzlichsten Grüssen von Haus zu Haus</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-65">Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143">Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial">in lower left margin:</tei:note> P.S.1) mein Bekenntnis zum neuen <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place">Deutschland</tei:rs> wird an sich dadurch nicht berührt! –<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11" type="editorial" place="foot">See Cube's letter, <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-34_37">OJ 9/34, [37]</tei:ref>, May 11, 1933, in which he proclaims his allegiance to the new
            Germany for the first time.</tei:note></tei:p>

        <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial">sideways in left margin, top to bottom:</tei:note> P.S.2) Für einen etwaigen
          Domizilwechsel kommt nur etwas <tei:hi rend="underline">ganz Sicheres</tei:hi> wenn auch <tei:hi rend="underline">noch so bescheiden</tei:hi> in Frage!</tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-35">Hamburg 13, Mittelweg 126, House Ia/<tei:hi rend="supralinear">II.</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:date when="1934-04-29">April 29, 1934</tei:date>
        </tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Dear, most revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">I have remained silent for a long time, for I had to struggle in silence. Now I am, I believe,
        defeated. I remained faithful to you and to the truth, so long as my powers were sufficient. Now I fear that
        disaster will befall me, too. The enclosed letter from those who at present employ me<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> requires no explanation!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> I shall not give way without a struggle. In the next few days I shall seek to gain support from above, from
          <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> Yet I have little expectation of success, as my last letter to him (with a request for a letter of
        recommendation) went unanswered. I can look forward to as little help from old established admirers of your
        theory (Professor Spengel<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> and <tei:rs key="entity-000427" type="person">Theodor Kaufmann</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/>), since they can do
        nothing against those who are in power. I am now generally known as <tei:hi rend="italic">the</tei:hi>
        Schenkerian and have to take the consequences for all of that, even though others were teaching the same thing
        twenty years before me; nothing will happen to them, because they have protected themselves by not mentioning
        your name when things began to heat up. I am still always hopeful that my case is not symptomatic for <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place">Germany</tei:rs>, but rather a small, local test of power on the part of a
        few "<tei:soCalled>colleagues</tei:soCalled>" who are working anonymously (naturally!) to bring me down in this
        way and thereby gain some merits. <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs> must now make
        up his mind! <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">Hic Rhodus, hic
          salta</tei:foreign></tei:hi>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> I believe that I can predict the
        result. And for this reason I am asking you for the first time for information as to whether you see a
        possibility in your vicinity for me and my family (in <tei:date when="1934-08">August</tei:date> there will be
        three of us), to avoid certain destruction. <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:foreign xml:lang="fre">A
            propos</tei:foreign></tei:hi>: The danger is still only latent, yet I must take precautions in good time.
        The extent to which the help of relatives and <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs>'s
        power inside (or outside) the state will be useful is something I shall let you know as soon as I have taken
          soundings.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Regarding the enclosed <tei:term>graph</tei:term>: I am myself still not satisfied with the last
          third,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09" type="footnote"/> but I wanted to send the letter, and I don't believe I
        am so far off the mark. Also, rheumatism is plaguing me today, so I cannot write much.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn10" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Just one other thing: half a year ago I had a talk with <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs> in which he defended you with great conviction, at any rate privately.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Cordial greetings from my family to yours.</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-65">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143">Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial">in lower left margin:</tei:note> P.S.1) My faith in the new <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place">Germany</tei:rs> has not in itself been affected by this!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn11" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

        <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial">sideways in left margin, top to bottom:</tei:note> P.S.2) For a possible
          change of domicile, only something <tei:hi rend="underline">quite definite</tei:hi> will do, even if it is
            <tei:hi rend="underline">only very modest</tei:hi>!</tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>