<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="2187" sdoID="OJ-9-30_6">OJ 9/30, [6]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="TC" scope="sole">Toni Colbert's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2007, 2019</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2007, 2019</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>


  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2011-06-09" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006997">Colbert ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Tony Colbert to Schenker, dated November[?] 2[?],
    1914</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1914-11-02T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-01-29</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Mrs. Colbert has done no piano practice, and explains her circumstances; but she
    asks Schenker to fit her in for a lesson every two weeks.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Erinnerungen; remembrances; Ausflug; trip; Erholung; recuperation; Operation; üben;
    to practise; Wohnung; home; apartment; Schülerin; pupil (female); Schüler; pupil (male);
    Monatsgeld; monthly income; Stunde; hour; lesson</dc:subject>


   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000137">ColbertT</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60">IV Kolschitzkygasse</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="ident-70"><tei:date when="1914-11-02"><tei:unclear reason="reading"
       >N2</tei:unclear> 14</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Lieber verehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">D<tei:hi
       rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi></tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
      place="foot">The month and day of this letter are uncertain. No receipt of a letter from
      Colbert is recorded in Schenker's diary around November 3. The diary does, however, record the
      following at OJ 1/16, p. 761, November 2, 1914: "Frau Colbert kommt zu spät zur Stunde u.
      erhält dafür eine Rüge u. da sie darüber unwillig wird, erhält sie eine desto schärfere Rüge."
      ("Mrs. Colbert turns up too late for her lesson, and thus receives a rebuke; and since she is
      indignant about this, she receives a rebuke that is all the
     stronger.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Schönsten Dank für Ihre beiden lieben Erinnerungen<tei:supplied reason="punctuation"
     >.</tei:supplied><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">"Erinnerungen":
     reminders: Schenker sent her a "Karte der Erinnerung" on October 10 (not surviving) to remind
     her of her lesson on October 12. The only dates that are recorded for Colbert lessons in the
     Fall of 1914, all Mondays, are: October 12 (diary), October 26 (lessonbook), November 2
     (diary), December 28 (diary). There are none for the first half of 1915, and there are no
     references to her in the 1915 diary; however, the 1914/15 lessonbook is severly
     truncated.</tei:note> In <tei:date when="1914-06">Juni</tei:date>
    <tei:unclear rend="reading">eben</tei:unclear> waren wir nur auf einem Ausflug von <tei:rs
     type="place" key="entity-006399">Toblach</tei:rs> aus wo wir 14 Tage recht angenehm gebrachten.
    Leider sind wir schon seit <tei:date when="1914-08-15">15ten August</tei:date> in Wien u die
    Erholung schon ¾ weg, hauptsächlich durch meinen <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000136"
     >Mann</tei:rs>, der seit <tei:date when="1914-06">Juni</tei:date> am Fussschmerzen litt, sich
    viel behandeln liess – wenig gehen konnte u jetzt in Wien endlich eine kleine Operation
    durchmachte, die ihn 8 Tage vom Geschäft ferne hielt, wo er <tei:del rend="overstrike"
     >jetzt</tei:del> ganz allein die Führung innehat.</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Ich habe leider noch gar nicht geübt u sehne mich mächtig es thun zu
     können<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">.</tei:supplied> In 8 Tagen reist mein Sohn nach
     Budweis<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Budweis: now České
     Budějovice, in the Czech Republic, 200 km (124 miles) north-west of Vienna (famous for its
     beer), at the confluence of the Vltava (Moldau) and Malse (Maltsch) rivers.</tei:note> den ich
    dort in neuer Umgebung heimlich machen muss u dann hoffe ich endlich ruhig studiren zu können.
    Meine Wohnung ist bis auf Kleinigkeiten ganz fertig. 2 Dinge bestimmen mich nun Sie herzlich zu
    bitten mich in Gnaden als Schülerin aufzunehmen wenn ich auch nur alle 14 Tage eine Stunde
    nehmen kann. I<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">.</tei:supplied> muss ich diesen Winter
    gesellschaftlicher meine <tei:unclear rend="reading">Tochter</tei:unclear> zuliebe – leben, wir
    sprachen <tei:pb n="3"/> schon einmal darüber, Sie wissen also warum. II. hat mein Schüler
     Matura<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">"Matura": Austrian for the
     German "Abitur." The identity of the pupil is unknown.</tei:note> hinter sich u macht sein
     Freiwilligen<tei:unclear rend="reading">dienst</tei:unclear> u ich habe daher nicht die Summe
    die mir sonst meine Monatsgeld ergänzt hat. Also 2 gewichtige Momente die Sie als gutes
    einsichtsvoller Freund gelten lassen werden. Auf <tei:unclear rend="reading">einen</tei:unclear>
    Tag od. eine bestimmte Stunde capricire ich mich nicht, sondern wo Sie mich einschachteln ist
    mir’s recht. Glück auch für die Vollendung Ihres <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001725"
      ><tei:title>Contrapunkt</tei:title></tei:rs>es.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Herzliche Grüsse</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihre</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000137">Tony
     Colbert</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60"><tei:supplied reason="place">Vienna</tei:supplied> IV,
      Kolschitzkygasse</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="ident-70"><tei:date when="1914-11-02"><tei:unclear reason="reading"
       >N2</tei:unclear>, 1914</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Dear and revered Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs type="person"
       key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
      type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Warmest thanks for your two lovely reminders.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
     type="footnote"/> In <tei:date when="1914-06">June</tei:date>, we were <tei:unclear
     reason="original_unclear">just</tei:unclear> away on a trip from <tei:rs type="place"
     key="entity-006399">Toblach</tei:rs>, where we spent two weeks very pleasantly. Sadly, since
     <tei:date when="1914-08-15">August 15</tei:date> we have been in Vienna and the recuperative
    effects are three-quarters gone, principally because of my <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000136">husband</tei:rs>, who has been suffering from foot pain since <tei:date
     when="1914-06">June</tei:date> and has had a lot of medical treatment – could barely walk and
    now finally underwent a small operation in Vienna that kept him away from the business for a
    week, where he is <tei:del rend="overstrike">now</tei:del> entirely in charge of the
    management.</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Sadly, I have still not done any practise, and yearn mightily to be able
    to do so. In a week's time, my son travels to Budweis,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
     type="footnote"/> and I must settle him in there in new surroundings, and then I hope at long
    last to be able to study in peace. My home is all ready, save for a few details. Two things
    prompt me now to ask you earnestly to be so gracious as to admit me as a pupil, even if I can
    take a lesson only once every two weeks, because: I. this winter I must live more socially for
    the sake of my <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">daughter</tei:unclear> ‒ we spoke <tei:pb
     n="3"/> about this once before, so you know why; II. my pupil has his school-leaving
     examination<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> behind him and is doing his
    voluntary <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">service</tei:unclear>, and so I do not have the
    sum of money that has hitherto supplemented my monthly income. Those are two powerful reasons
    that you, as a good, insightful friend will appreciate. I have not set my heart on a particular
    day or time, but wherever you can slot me in will be all right with me. Best wishes for the
    completion of your <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001725"><tei:title level="m"
      >Counterpoint</tei:title></tei:rs>.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">With cordial greetings,</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000137">Tony
     Colbert</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>


  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
