<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="480" sdoID="OJ-9-34_35">OJ 9/34, [35]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="FEvC" scope="sole">Felix-Eberhard von Cube's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2008</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2008</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
   <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2011-11-03" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002775">Cube ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated December 7, 1932</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1932-12-07T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-06-30</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Cube reports on his current state of mind, his work on a Bach graph (commenting
    on a graph by Angi Elias), promises to send an article on Schenker that has appeared in the
    Frankfurter Zeitung, on the difficulties of the Schenker-Institut, and on Moriz and Karl
    Violin.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000143">Cube</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-25">Hamburg 13, Beneckestr. 2; bei <tei:rs key="entity-003092" type="person">Alexander Schmidt</tei:rs>.</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:date when="1932-12-07">7.XII.32.</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Sehr verehrter, lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this
      letter is not recorded in Schenker's diary.</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Lange habe ich nichts von mir vermeldet. Das lag hauptsächlich daran, dass
    ich mir meine Nerven immer noch nicht so gut erzogen habe, dass sie mich doch bei diesen
    herrlichen Zeiten<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Cube is using these
     words with heavy irony.</tei:note> in etwa nachgegeben hätten, und ich mich von der allgemeinen
    Apathie anstecken liess. Der Massendepression kann man immer nur innere Energien
    entgegenstellen, und dieses Reservoir ist bei mir keineswegs unerschöpflich, wenn man so gar
    keine äusserlichen Aufmunterungen erlebt. Nun habe ich mich über Weihnachten doch wieder etwas
    zurechectgerüttelt, und sehe den weiteren Notverordnungen mit grösserer Gelassenheit entgegen.
    —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Die <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person">Bach</tei:rs><tei:term>tafel</tei:term><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Probably a graphic analysis of the <tei:rs key="entity-001136" type="composition"><tei:title>Prelude in C</tei:title></tei:rs> from the <tei:title level="m">Well-Tempered
      Clavier</tei:title>, Book 1. Reference to the work of Angi Elias later in this letter suggests
     that Cube is still revising his own work on this piece, though the <tei:title level="m">Fünf
      Urlinie-Tafeln</tei:title> (which includes an analysis of this prelude) was published in the
     fall of 1932.</tei:note> habe ich nun in Arbeit genommen, nachdem meine Schüler sie sich
    eifrigst abgeschrieben haben. Ganz neu sind mir die <tei:term>Balkungen</tei:term> anstelle der
     <tei:term>Bogen</tei:term> (wie auch in der <tei:title>Eroica</tei:title>),<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">i.e. Schenker's analysis of the <tei:rs key="entity-001263" type="composition">Eroica Symphony</tei:rs>, in <tei:bibl><tei:rs key="entity-001752" type="work"><tei:title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der
       Musik</tei:title>, vol. 3</tei:rs> (Munich: Drei-Masken Verlag, 1930)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note>
    das Bild wird dadurch von bedeutender Klarheit. Ich glaube, dass an Frl. <tei:rs key="entity-000201" type="person">Elias</tei:rs>’ <tei:term>Tafel</tei:term><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Angi Elias prepared many of the fair copies
     of his analytical graphs. According to a personal communication from Cube, it was Elias who hit
     upon the idea of beaming together notes that were conceptually important in the background and
     middleground, leaving slurs to indicate arpeggiations, linear progressions, etc. that were
     nearer the musical foreground. See <tei:bibl>William Drabkin <tei:title level="a">Felix-Eberhard von Cube and the North German Tradition of Schenkerism,</tei:title>
      <tei:title level="j">Proceedings of the Royal Musical Association</tei:title> 111 (1985),
      180-207</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> immerhin noch einige Präzisierungen vorzunehmen sind. Besonders
    der Verblieb der <tei:term>Mittelstimme</tei:term> g am Schluss. Derzeit erwäge ich eine Lösung.
    Meine nächsten Arbeiten werden <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs>
    <tei:rs key="entity-001377" type="composition">gis-moll Walzer</tei:rs>, und das <tei:rs key="entity-003093" type="person">Paganini</tei:rs>-Thema sein.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Neither the Brahms waltz (Op. 39, No. 3) nor the theme of
     Paganini's famous <tei:rs key="entity-003094" type="composition"><tei:title>Caprice in A minor,
       Op. 1, No. 24</tei:title></tei:rs>, is included among the analyses in Cube's unpublished
      <tei:title level="m">Lehrbuch der musikalischen Kunstgesetze</tei:title>. Schenker, however,
     included a graph of the Paganini theme in <tei:title level="m">Der freie
     Satz</tei:title>.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Die <tei:rs key="entity-002537" type="journal"><tei:title>Frankfurter
      Zeitung</tei:title></tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">There
     are no articles from the <tei:title level="j">Frankfurter Zeitung</tei:title> from 1932 in
     Schenker's Scrapbook (<!-- XR -->OC 2) or clippings collection (<!-- XR -->OC C). It seems,
     then, that Cube did not send this to his teacher.</tei:note> brachte einen längeren Artikel
    über Ihre Werke, den ich Ihnen bald zuschicke. Besonders weitgegangen fand ich ein Passus, der
    die Forderung nach <tei:term>Schenker-Unterricht</tei:term> an den Hochschulen ausdrückt, sowie
    die Bemerkung, dass Ihre Bücher in allen Bibliotheken, Universitäten und Musikschulen gehören.
    Sonst manches kunterbunt, und vieles missverstanden. Gesamteindruck erfreulich. —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Das <tei:rs key="entity-002455" type="organization">Institut</tei:rs> kämpft
    einen <tei:hi rend="underline">schweren</tei:hi> Existenzkampf. <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs> hat dem Hauswirt vorsorglich gekündigt, um die Miete zu drücken.
    Hoffentlich <tei:supplied reason="cutoff">ist</tei:supplied> der Mann vernünftig! Es liegt in
    der Natur der Dinge, dass wir die Abenteur nicht in demselben Maaße zu spüren bekamen, wie die
    “Betriebs”-Konservatorien. <tei:pb n="2"/> Indess sind uns auch grösste Opfer auferlegt. Ich
    habe manchen Schüler zum Bleiben <tei:supplied reason="cutoff">be</tei:supplied>wogen, und auch
    eine neue Schülerin eingebracht, einige weitere Eisen sind im Feuer. Aber es fehlt uns ein gutes
    Drittel immer noch an der notwendigsten Rentabilität. —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Vorträge liegen im Argen! Selbst unentgeltliche. Es fehlt an Konzentration
    bei den Hörern. Die gehen ins Kino und betäuben sich. Die “Konkurrenz” hat gottlob jetzt soviel
    eigene <tei:foreign xml:base="yid">Zores</tei:foreign>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:hi rend="italic">Zores</tei:hi>: Yiddish for troubles,
     sorrow.</tei:note> dass sie uns in Ruhe lässt. Ein schwacher Trost. Ich liege wie ein Luchs auf
    der Lauer, alle Möglichkeiten einzufangen, aber man greift immer nur ins Leere. Die nächsten
    drei Monate bringen meines Erachtens nach die Entscheidung über manche Fragen, die man sich nur
    ruhig eingestehen soll. Wenns sein <tei:hi rend="underline">muss</tei:hi>, ich fange noch ein
    Dutzendmal von vorne an. Hoffen wir, dass <tei:hi rend="underline">dieser</tei:hi> Kelch an uns
    vorübergeht. —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs> sieht müde aus. Uns
    allen tut die lähmende Ungewissheit nicht gut. <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Karli</tei:rs> ist gottlob wohlauf.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09" type="editorial" place="foot">A reference to a serious illness that had befallen Moriz Violin's son Karl in 1931.</tei:note>
    Diese Sorge ist wenigstens gebannt. Ich bin keineswegs ein Pessimist geworden! Nun das nicht!
    Aber ich sehe mit offenen Augen, und was ich sehe ist leider sehr eindeutig. Dass wir uns im
    kommenden Vierteljahr auf dem gegenwärtigen Status halten können, ist das Günstigste, was ich zu
    hoffen wage. —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In normalen Zeiten wären wir sehr obenauf! Unsere Schüler sind begeistert,
    das Unterrichten eine reine Freude. Die gehen müssen, weil sie nicht mehr können, sind ehrlich
    verzweifelt. Aber alle können wir nicht umsonst unterrichten. Es werden auch wieder andere
    Zeiten kommen. Was war eigentlich mit Herrn <tei:rs key="entity-000919" type="person">Voss</tei:rs>?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10" type="editorial" place="foot">Erich Voss, a music
     student in Cologne who befriended Cube and travelled to Vienna in the hope of studying with
     Schenker. (See the correspondence between Schenker and Cube from May 14 to July 18,
     1929.)</tei:note> Das ist auch ein Ungeduldiger Vogel, aber sonst goldrichtig! Ich höre wenig
    von ihm, er schei<tei:supplied reason="cutoff">nt</tei:supplied> aber in <tei:rs key="entity-002790" type="place">Münster</tei:rs> kräftig für die Sache einzutreten. —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Mir geht es so leidlich. Mein persönlichster Schmerz ist, dass ich seit drei
    Jahren als “ewiger Bräutigam” herumlaufe.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:hi rend="italic">Ewige Bräutigam</tei:hi> ("eternal bridegroom"): Cube had
     gotten married earlier that year, but was still unable to secure a stable domestic life in
     Hamburg. The expression is probably a play on the expression <tei:hi rend="italic">ewiger
      Jude</tei:hi> ("Wandering Jew").</tei:note> Auch das ist so eine Zeiterscheinung. Aber das
    wird auch nochmal klappen. Was macht der <tei:rs key="entity-001728" type="work"><tei:title>freie Satz</tei:title></tei:rs>?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Der freie Satz</tei:title> (Vienna: UE,
      1935)</tei:bibl>, on which Schenker was working hard at this time, and which was ultimately
     published posthumously.</tei:note> Und Ihr und Ihrer Frau <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Gemahlen</tei:rs> Wohlbefinden?</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-35">Für diesmal mit allerherzlichsten Grüssen</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-75">Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-85"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143">Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-25">Hamburg 13, Beneckestrasse 2, c/o <tei:rs key="entity-003092" type="person">Alexander Schmidt</tei:rs>.</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:date when="1932-12-07">December 7, 1932</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Most revered, dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">For a long time I have communicated nothing about myself. This was primarily
    because I have never trained my nerves well enough that they were able to relax a bit in these
    splendid times,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> and that I could become infected
    by the general apathy. Mass depression can only be combated by internal energy, and my reservoir
    is by no means inexhaustible, when there is absolutely nothing in the way of external
    encouragement. Now, during the Christmas period, I have again been aroused to a somewhat more
    favourable state of mind, and view further emergency measures with somewhat greater
    composure.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I have begun working on the <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person">Bach</tei:rs>
    <tei:term>graph</tei:term>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> after my pupils
    copied it down with great zeal. What is entirely new to me are the <tei:term>beamings</tei:term>
    that replace the <tei:term>slurs</tei:term> (as are also found in the <tei:title level="a">Eroica</tei:title>);<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> the picture will gain
    significantly in clarity. I believe that there are, nevertheless, still some things that should
    be made more precise in Miss <tei:rs key="entity-000201" type="person">Elias</tei:rs>'s
     <tei:term>graph</tei:term>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> especially the
     <tei:term>inner-voice</tei:term> g, which is left hanging at the end. At the moment, I am
    trying to find a solution. My next projects will be <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs>'s <tei:rs key="entity-001377" type="composition">Waltz in G sharp
     minor</tei:rs>, and the <tei:rs key="entity-003093" type="person">Paganini</tei:rs>
     theme.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">The <tei:rs key="entity-002537" type="journal"><tei:title level="j">Frankfurter Zeitung</tei:title></tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/>
    published a lengthy article about your works, which I shall send you soon. I was particularly
    struck by a passage which expressed the the need for <tei:term>Schenkerian tuition</tei:term> in
    the high schools, and by the remark that your books belong in every library, university and
    conservatory. Otherwise, some things were garbled, and much was misunderstood. The overall
    impression was favorable.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">The <tei:rs key="entity-002455" type="organization">Institute</tei:rs> is
    fighting a <tei:hi rend="underline">difficult</tei:hi> battle for survival. <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs> gave notice to the custodian, as a
    precautionary measure, so as to keep the rent down. Let us hope that the man is reasonable! It
    is in the nature of things that we were not affected by the adventure to the same extent as the
    "management" conservatories. <tei:pb n="2"/> In the meantime we have had to make the greatest
    sacrifices. I have persuaded some pupils to remain, and I also have acquired a new pupil; there
    are some further irons in the fire. But just to make ends meet, a good third of our pupils are
    missing.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Lectures are in a bad way – even those that are unpaid! The audience is
    unable to concentrate. They go to the cinema and become deaf. The "competition" has, thank God,
    just so much trouble<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/> of its own that it leaves
    us in peace. Small comfort. I am lying in ambush, like a lynx, to grab at any opportunity, but
    can only grab at emptiness. The next three months will, I believe, settle many questions, which
    one should only accept peacefully. If it <tei:hi rend="underline">must</tei:hi> be, I will begin
    again from the beginning. Let us hope that <tei:hi rend="underline">this</tei:hi> cup of sorrow
    passes over us.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs> looks tired. The
    paralysing uncertainty does none of us any good. <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Karli</tei:rs> is, thank God, in good shape; that sorrow is, at least, banished.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09" type="footnote"/> I have by no means become a pessimist! Not that, for
    sure. But I look at things with my eyes open, and what I see is, unfortunately, all too clear.
    That we might be able to hold our present position is the most favourable thing that I dare to
    hope.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In normal times, we would be in very buoyant spirits! Our pupils are
    inspired, and teaching is an unalloyed pleasure. Those who must leave because they no longer
    afford to stay, are genuinely downhearted. But we cannot teach everyone for free. Other times
    will come again. What actually happened with Mr <tei:rs key="entity-000919" type="person">Voss</tei:rs>?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn10" type="footnote"/> There's another impatient bird,
    but otherwise good as gold. I hear little from him; he seems, however, to be working hard for
    the cause in <tei:rs key="entity-002790" type="place">Münster</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I am so very unhappy. My most personal pain is that I have been moving about
    for the last three years as the "eternal bridegroom".<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn11" type="footnote"/> That, too, is so much a sign of the times. But that too will eventually work
    out. How are things going with <tei:rs key="entity-001728" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Der
      freie Satz</tei:title></tei:rs>?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn12" type="footnote"/> And your
    health, and that of your <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs>?</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-35">For now, with all my most affectionate greetings,</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-75">Yours,</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-85"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143">Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>