<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="468" sdoID="OJ-9-34_21">OJ 9/34, [21]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="FEvC" scope="sole">Felix-Eberhard von Cube's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
   <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2011-08-16" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002775">Cube ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated June 25, 1930</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1930-06-25T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-10-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Acknowledges OJ 5/7a, [29] and offers mitigation for Vrieslander's
    non-acquaintance with the Urlinie (to which Cube has just introduced new violin teachers).
    Reports on Erich Voß, and on concert plans at Conservatory. Reports on his teaching. Threat of
    financial difficulties; he has offered his services to the Hochschule für Musik in
    Berlin.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000143">Cube</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">top-left corner: stationery motif of a crown above a
     shield</tei:note>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-45">Duisburg, <tei:date when="1930-06-25">den 25.VI.30.</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-15">Sehr verehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this
      letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at <!-- XR -->OJ 4/3, p. 3490, July 5, 1930: "Von v.
      Cube (Br.): äußert sich treffend über Vrieslander ‒ hält es durch die Abstammung (?) bedingt
      wenn er sich der Urlinie versagt. Legt eine Kritik aus der Deutschen Tonkünstler Zeitung bei,
      die bei aller Anerkennung von der Urlinie als einer Idée fixe spricht. Voß bleibe des Vaters
      wegen in der Nähe." ("From von Cube (letter): has apposite things to say about Vrieslander –
      attributes it to his regional background (?), especially when he rejects the Urlinie. Encloses
      a review from the <tei:title level="j">Deutsche Tonkünstler Zeitung</tei:title> that, for all
      its approbation, speaks of the Urlinie as an <tei:foreign xml:lang="fre">idée
       fixe</tei:foreign>. Voß is remaining in the neighborhood on account of his
      father.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Zuvor vielen Dank für Ihren Brief, und den Artikel von <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Probably <tei:bibl>Vrieslander, <tei:title level="a">Heinrich
       Schenker,</tei:title>
      <tei:title level="j">Der Kunstwart</tei:title> XLIII (June 1930), pp. 181-89</tei:bibl>.
     Jeanette made a note of this essay in Schenker's Scrapbook (<!-- XR -->OC 2/p. 80); the article
     survives, part-photocopy, in <!-- XR -->OJ 58/21.</tei:note> Wenn <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs> der <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> noch nicht in dem Maasse
    nahegekommen ist, wie Sie es wünschen würden, so mag es meines Erachtens nach darin begründet
    sein, das er von niedersächsisch schwerbeugsamer Art ist, somit sich dem stärkeren Neuen nicht
    geschmeidig beugt, sondern, vielleicht in unbewussten Widerstand, versucht, einiges seiner
    eigenen, etwas dogmatischen Persönlichkeit mit in den neuen Zustand hinüberzuretten, durch
    welchen frommen Selbstbetrug natürlich die Erkenntnisfähigkeit getrübt wird. Doch fürchte ich
    nicht, das die Leser des Artikels sich von solch subtilen Erwägungen leiten lassen werden; denn
    – ist <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs> immerhin schon im nächsten
    An- <tei:pb n="2"/>
    <tei:note type="editorial">pasted in top-left corner: published Review (<tei:ref type="other" cRef="OJ-9-34_21b">OJ 9/34, [21b]</tei:ref>) of <tei:title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der
      Musik</tei:title></tei:note> ziehungsbereich der <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>, so bewegen sich
    seine Leser immer noch in Siriusfernen<tei:supplied reason="syntax">,</tei:supplied> wie Figura
     zeigt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">An arrow in the text points
     to a Review (<tei:ref type="other" cRef="OJ-9-34_21b">OJ 9/34, [21b]</tei:ref>) by <tei:rs key="entity-002631" type="person">Oscar Guttmann</tei:rs> of <tei:title level="j">Das
      Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:title>, which has been pasted on to the page. Beneath the
     review, Cube has indicated the source as the <tei:bibl><tei:title level="j">Deutsche
       Tonkünstlerzeitung</tei:title>, volume 11</tei:bibl>. It is clear from the text of the review
     that the reviewer had the first two volumes of <tei:title level="j">Meisterwerk</tei:title> to
     hand.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000919" type="person">Voss</tei:rs> ist inzwischen
    bei mir „<tei:soCalled>eingekehrt</tei:soCalled>“.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Erich Voss, a young musician who encountered Schenker's theories through Cube's
     visit to Cologne, and who went to Vienna in the hopes of studying with Schenker: see also
      <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-34_18">OJ 9/34, [18]</tei:ref>, May 14, 1929;
      <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-7a_23">OJ 5/7a, [23]</tei:ref>, May 15, 1929;
      <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-7a_24">OJ 5/7a, [24]</tei:ref>, July 6, 1929;
      <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-7a_25">OJ 5/7a, [25]</tei:ref>, July 14, 1929;
      <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-34_19">OJ 9/34, [19]</tei:ref>, July 18, 1929. Voss
     does not appear in Schenker's Lesson Books.</tei:note> Er ist eben auch ein Opfer
    derVerhältnisse, und muss nun in der Nähe suchen, was ihm anfänglich in die Ferne zog. Soviel
    ich herausbekommen habe, spielen da auch Differenzen mit seinem Vater eine Rolle. (Oh, diese
     Väter!)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Cube is alluding to the
     difficulties he had with his own father, especially concerning lessons with Schenker in
     Vienna.</tei:note> Ich wollte Ihnen schon früher Mitteilung gemacht haben, schob aber den Brief
    mit dem Termin eines Konzertes immer weiter hinaus. Nun ist der Brief im Entstehen, das Konzert
    ist aber endgültig auf den Herbst verlegt worden. Es handelt sich um einen Abend der
     „<tei:soCalled>Hauskomponisten</tei:soCalled>“ des <tei:rs key="entity-002780" type="organization">Konservatorium</tei:rs>s, von diesem als Schülerabend veranstaltet. Ich
    stehe <tei:pb n="3"/> auf dem Programm mit meinen <tei:rs key="entity-002785" type="composition">Variationen</tei:rs>, sowie beiden Sonaten. Die entstehenden Hohlräume werden
    (konzessionsweise) mit Liedern meiner Komponierkollegen ausgefüllt; (auf dass einen jeden ein
    Strahl der Publikumssonne treffe<tei:supplied reason="cutoff">.)</tei:supplied> Es ist so
    unerträglich im Schatten zu bleiben. Dabei werde ich nie gefragt, wenn mal die
    ander<tei:supplied reason="cutoff">en</tei:supplied> was veranstalten. Nach dem Motto: Der
    eigene Hund macht keinen Lärm – – er bellt blos. Das ganze Konzert wird von Schülern bestritten
    <tei:supplied reason="cutoff">–</tei:supplied> gute Könner, es wird viel Reiz haben, – und ich
    eine Menge Arbeit vorher. —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Eine unserer frischgebackenen Geigenlehrerinnen bat mich, mit ihr <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs>sonaten zu spielen. Ich nahm an, und die
    Gelegenheit wahr, ihr auf den <tei:term>Urliniezahn</tei:term> zu fühlen. Am dritten Abend kam
    die Erleuchtung über sie, und allbereits stürmt sie mit den üblichen, viel zu grossen Schritten
    ins neue Land hinein. Ich will abwarten, wie lange die Begeisterung vorhält, ehe ich
    registrier<tei:supplied reason="cutoff">e:</tei:supplied> Wieder eine Seele gerettet!
    —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="4"/> Mit der Oberklasse mach ich jetzt auch <tei:term>strengen
     Satz</tei:term> und <tei:term>leichte Analysen</tei:term>. Im <tei:rs key="entity-002780" type="organization">Seminar</tei:rs> wird es jetzt Mode, an meinen Vorlesungen teilzunehmen.
    Die Hörer mehren sich – zu meiner Freude; (ob auch zu der der <tei:term><tei:rs key="entity-002780" type="organization">Seminar</tei:rs>theoristen</tei:term> bleibt
    dahingestellt.) —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Im Allgemeinen leide ich zur Zeit an den Auswirkungen unserer fabelhaften
     Finanzreformen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">In the late spring
     of 1930 the government of Heinrich Brüning, Chancellor of the Weimar Republic, was unsuccessful
     in gaining a majority vote in the Reichstag for a financial reform bill designed to curb
     unemployment and the steep rise in unemployment insurance payouts. Article 48 was invoked,
     allowing the bill to be passed without a parliamentary vote, but in July 1930 the Reichstag
     voted to invalidate it anyway. (The consequent political turmoil led to the dissolution of the
     Reichstag and the call for new elections, at which the National-Socialists and Communists made
     great gains at the expense of the more moderate parties.)</tei:note> Noch habe ich ein Dach
    überm Kopf und satt zu essen. Aber manche kleine Bequemlichkeit ist schon dem Pleitegeier zum
    Opfer gefallen. Ich hätte nichts dagegen, gelegentlich <tei:rs key="entity-002621" type="place">Duisburg</tei:rs> wegzukommen. Neulich habe ich – mit Protektion – meine Dienste der <tei:rs key="entity-002888" type="organization">Charlottenburger Hochschule</tei:rs> (Direktion <tei:rs key="entity-000802" type="person">Schreker</tei:rs>)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">This is the Hochschule für Musik in Berlin, where the composer
     Franz Schreker was the director.</tei:note> angeboten, aber noch keine Antwort bekommen.
    Sollten Sie in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> mal was erfahren, wäre ich
    Ihnen für einen Wink dankbar. <tei:rs key="entity-002621" type="place">Duisburg</tei:rs> ist gut
    genug als Sprungbrett, aber es bietet keine anderen Entwicklungsmöglichkeiten, als auf das
    Ableben seiner Vordermänner zu warten.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Für heute beste Grüsse Ihnen und Ihrer Frau <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Gemahlin</tei:rs>, auch den <tei:rs key="entity-002925" type="person">Türtschers</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot">Acquaintances
     of the Schenkers in Galtür, mentioned in Cube's letter <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-34_13">OJ 9/34, [13]</tei:ref>, July 6, 1928.</tei:note> von</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-55">Ihrem</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-75"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143">Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">top-left corner: stationery motif of a crown above a
     shield</tei:note>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-45">Duisburg, <tei:date when="1930-06-25">June 25, 1930</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-15">Most revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">To begin with, many thanks for your letter, and for <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs>'s article.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> If <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs> is not as
    intimate in matters concerning the <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> as you would have hoped, then I
    believe this might be based on the fact that he is a rather inflexible Lower Saxon type and thus
    does not bow gracefully before that which is new and stronger; rather, and perhaps with an
    opposition of which he is unconscious, he tries to salvage things by incorporating something of
    his own, somewhat dogmatic personality in the new situation, through which pious self-deception
    his power of understanding naturally becomes blurred. But I do not fear that the readers of his
    article will be misled by such subtle considerations; for even if <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs> is already in the nearest <tei:pb n="2"/>
    <tei:note type="editorial">pasted in top-left corner: published Review (<tei:ref type="other" cRef="OJ-9-34_21b">OJ 9/34, [21b]</tei:ref>) of <tei:title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der
      Musik</tei:title></tei:note> field of gravitational pull to the <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>,
    his readers are still as distant as Sirius, as the attached illustration shows.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Mr <tei:rs key="entity-000919" type="person">Voss</tei:rs> has, in the
    meantime, "<tei:soCalled>returned</tei:soCalled>."<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> He, too, is a victim of the economic situation, and must now seek at close hand that which
    initially directed him afar. So far as I have been able to make out, disagreements with his
    father also played a part in this. (Oh, these fathers!)<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> I wanted to tell you this sooner, but kept postponing the letter until the
    date of a concert. Now I am writing the letter, but the concert is definitively postponed until
    the autumn. It will be an evening of "<tei:soCalled>house composers</tei:soCalled>" of the
     <tei:rs key="entity-002780" type="organization">Conservatory</tei:rs>, organized as an evening
    of <tei:rs key="entity-002780" type="organization">Conservatory</tei:rs> pupils. I will be
    represented <tei:pb n="3"/> on the programme with my <tei:rs key="entity-002785" type="composition">Variations</tei:rs>, and both sonatas <tei:supplied reason="clarity"><tei:rs key="entity-002787" type="composition">No. 1</tei:rs> and <tei:rs key="entity-002827" type="composition">No. 2</tei:rs></tei:supplied>. The gaps that arise will be plugged (as a
    concession) with songs of my composition colleagues, so that a ray of audience sunshine might
    fall upon each of them: it is so unbearable to remain in the shadows. I am never asked when the
    others organize something. As the saying goes, "One's own dog makes no sound, he merely barks."
    The entire concert will be performed by our pupils – the ones with ability – there will be a lot
    of charm, and I will have a lot of work to do beforehand.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">One of our newest violin teachers asked me to play <tei:rs key="entity-000055" type="person">Beethoven</tei:rs> sonatas with her. I accepted, aware of the
    opportunity to give her a <tei:term>taste of the Urlinie</tei:term>. On the third evening the
    light fell upon her, and already she was marching – with far too large steps, as usual – into
    the new territory. I shall wait to see how long the inspiration remains before I declare:
    Another soul has been saved!</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="4"/> With the advanced class, I am also doing <tei:term>strict
     counterpoint</tei:term> and <tei:term>elementary analysis</tei:term>. Here at the <tei:rs key="entity-002780" type="organization">Conservatory</tei:rs> it has become fashionable to take
    part in my lectures. The listeners increase in number, to my delight. (Whether this is also to
    the delight of the <tei:term><tei:rs key="entity-002780" type="organization">Conservatory</tei:rs> theorists</tei:term> is something one cannot say.)</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In general, I am suffering from the consequences of our fabulous financial
     reforms.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> I still have a roof over my head, and
    enough to eat. But many small pleasures have fallen victim to the vulture of bankruptcy. I would
    have nothing against leaving <tei:rs key="entity-002621" type="place">Duisburg</tei:rs>, should
    the chance arise. Recently I have – with support – offered my services to the <tei:rs key="entity-002888" type="organization">Conservatory in Charlottenburg</tei:rs> (where <tei:rs key="entity-000802" type="person">Schreker</tei:rs> is the director),<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> but have not yet had a reply. If you should hear about
    anything in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>, I would be thankful for a
    hint. <tei:rs key="entity-002621" type="place">Duisburg</tei:rs> is good enough as a
    springboard, but it offers no further possibilities for development, except to wait for one's
    superiors to die.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">For today, best greetings to you and your <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs>, and also to the <tei:rs key="entity-002925" type="person">Türtschers</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/> from</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-55">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-75"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143">Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>