<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="2186" sdoID="OJ-9-30_5">OJ 9/30, [5]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="TC" scope="major">Toni Colbert's hand</tei:handNote>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2007, 2019</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2007, 2019</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>


  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2011-06-09" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006997">Colbert ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Tony Colbert to Schenker, undated [September 13,
    1914]</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1914-09-13T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-01-28</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Mrs. Colbert pleads for reduction of lessons to once every other week on account
    of the war work she is doing and the difficulties that she and her husband are
    facing.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Stunden; lessons; Friedenszeiten; peacetime; Sohn; son; Hilfe; help; Leiterin;
    leader; Hausfrau; housewife; Vorsitz; chairmanship; Sitzung; meeting; Bezirk; district; Antrag;
    petition; Annahme; acceptance; Klavier; piano; Zeit; time; Sonntagsruhe; Sunday rest;
    Tagesblatt; newspaper; Herausgeber; editor; Finanzlage; financial situation; Studium; study;
    Lehrer; teacher</dc:subject>


   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000137">ColbertT</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/><tei:hi rend="bold">T C</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
     <tei:lb/>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="ident-70"><tei:handShift new="#TC"/><tei:date when="1914-09-13"
      >Sonntag</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Sehr verehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">D<tei:hi
       rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi></tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
      place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 1/16, p. 705,
      September 14, 1914: "Brief von Frau Colbert mit dem sonderbaren Antrag, die ohnehin so karge
      Zahl der Stunden neuerdings auf die Hälfte zu reduzieren. Die Begründung in ihrem Briefe legt
      mir dringend die Vermutung nahe, daß es wieder nur ein Akt privaten Schmutzes ist, der zur
      Kenntnis des Mannes überhaupt nicht gelangt ist. So beruft sie sich z. B. auf die prekäre
      Situation des „<tei:title>Morgen</tei:title>s“, gibt aber wiederspruchsvoll genug auch schon
      im selben Briefe gleich wieder zu, daß sich inzwischen die Situation gebessert hat. Aehnliche
      Schachzüge erwarte ich noch von anderen Schülern, doch immer sich die Zukunft eben erst walten
      lassen."<tei:lb/> ("Letter from Mrs. Colbert with the strange petition to have the number of
      her lessons, in any event sparse in number, now reduced by half. The reason given in her
      letter compels me to suspect that it is again merely an act of private greed, one which has
      not in any way come to the attention of her husband. Thus for example she appeals to the
      precarious situation of <tei:title level="j">Der Morgen</tei:title>, but in contradiction
      readily admits again in the same letter that the situation has meanwhile improved. I am
      expecting further similar chess moves from other pupils, who will however let the future
      govern their actions."). — Since the previous day was a Sunday, the date of this letter must
      be September 13, 1914. The entry of September 15, 1914 (OJ 1/16, p. 706) presumably relates to
      the same letter.<tei:lb/> Schenker's reply is recorded in the diary the following day: "Der
      schon dem Termin nach so schlau angelegte Brief von Fr. Colbert mahnt mich zur Vorsicht u. ich
      schreibe nun selbst an <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000098">Breisach</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs
       type="person" key="entity-000201">Frl. Elias</tei:rs>, um je früher desto besser vollen
      Ueberblick über die Saison zu gewinnen. In der Antwort an Frau C. aber nehme ich die sicher
      originelle Haltung ein, mich vorläufig zwar nur für 2 Stunden des Monats honorieren zu lassen,
      sie aber für den Rest zu belasten, bis eine gelegenere Zeit ihr die Begleichung ermöglicht.
      Vielleicht ist dieser Vorschlag einer jener masurischen Sümpfe, der mir die Gegnerin gefangen
      ausliefert."<tei:lb/> ("The letter that Mrs. Colbert crafted so cleverly, merely judging by
      the deadline she gave me, warns me to be on my guard; and I now write myself to <tei:rs
       type="person" key="entity-000098">Breisach</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person"
       key="entity-000201">Miss Elias</tei:rs> in order to gain a complete view of the teaching
      season, the sooner the better. In my reply to Mrs. Colbert, however, I take a certainly
      original position, by saying that I will for the time being request payment for only two
      lessons per month and burden her with the rest only when a more opportune time makes the
      payment possible. Perhaps this suggestion is one of those Masurian bogs which will deliver me
      from my opponent, who has been caught in it."). </tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Vor allem will ich erklären daß ich absolut nicht die Absicht habe die Stunden zu
     sistieren<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The letter referred to
     here is not known to survive.</tei:note> denn sie bilden einen Theil meines Lebens – in
     Friedenszeiten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Austria declared war
     on Serbia on July 28, 1914, Germany declared war on Russia on August 1 and on France on August
     3. </tei:note> Aber ich muss Sie herzlichst um 2 Dinge bitten u werde Ihnen auch dafür die
    Gründe angeben. Als mein Sohn am 27ten Juli aus <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002589"
     >Hamburg</tei:rs> hierher telegrafisch gerufen wurde er war gerade den ersten Monat fix
    angestellt gewesen, um einzurücken was auch am 28ten Juli geschah waren mein <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000136">Mann</tei:rs> u ich in einer bösen Verfassung.</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Wir suchten nach einer Tätigkeit die uns das nachdenken erliess nichts war
    ärger als das Bewußtsein was geschieht. Ich bat meine Hilfe in der Kinderfürsorge des
    Reichsorganisation der Hausfrauen Österreichs<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial"
     place="foot">Reichsorganisation der Hausfrauen Österreichs (ROHÖ): founded in 1902 "to
     influence legal and administrative measures concerning domestic interests, to involve
     housewives in all relevant consultations and decision-making; <tei:supplied reason="clarity">to
      achieve</tei:supplied> official recognition of housewives", its leaders being Fanny
     Freund-Marcus, Elsa Beer-Angerer, Helene Granitsch, Adele Hirschenhauser, and Stephanie
     Endlicher.</tei:note> an u wurde nach ein par Tagen unermüdlichen Arbeitens von 9 Früh– bis 7
    uhr ab<tei:supplied reason="abbreviation">ends</tei:supplied> als Leiterin ernannt. Am 10ten
    August berief mich der Bürgermeister in die Zentrale im Rathaus wo wir 17 Frauen unter dem
    Vorsitz des Bürgermeisterpaares<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot"
     >"Bürgermeisterpaar": it is unclear whether there were at this time two Mayors, or whether
     reference is to the Mayor and his deputy, or to the Mayor and his wife. It is at least
     plausible that the wife might have been involved where a wholly women's organization was
     concerned, and then Mrs. Colbert might have wanted to stress the wife's part in her work in
     this letter; however, in that case Mrs. Colbert might have used "Bürgermeisterehepaar."
    </tei:note> jeden Donnerstag unsere Sitzung abhalten wo alle wichtigen Dinge die die Hilfsaktion
    der Frauen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">"Hilfsaktion der Frauen":
     an arm of ROHÖ founded at the beginning of World War I under the chairmanship of Bertha
     Weiskirchner, with working committees for each of the twenty-one districts of Vienna, their
     work being the collection of goods and money, distribution of relief meals, child-care, and
     work-placement. Note articles: <tei:bibl><tei:author>Colbert, Tony</tei:author>: <tei:title
       level="a">Die Frauen-Hilfsaktion im Kriege,</tei:title>
      <tei:title level="j">Neues Frauenleben</tei:title>, Year 16, Nos. 8/9 (1914</tei:bibl>);
       <tei:bibl><tei:author>Colbert, Carl</tei:author>: <tei:title level="a">Der Abbau der
       Kriegsarbeit der Frau,</tei:title>
      <tei:title level="j">Neues Frauenleben</tei:title>, Year 20, Nos. 1–2
     (1918)</tei:bibl></tei:note> betrifft, beschlossen u von da aus in die 21 Bezirke<tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">Vienna comprised twenty-one districts from
     1900 to 1938, twenty-six from 1938 to 1946, and twenty-three currently. </tei:note>
    hinausgegeben wird. Es ist ein sehr mühevolles u verantwortungs- <tei:pb n="3"/> volles Amt das
    ich mir auferlegt habe aber ich thue es mit voller Hingebung. Dass ich dabei meine ganzen Kräfte
    aufbrauche <tei:unclear reason="reading">woran</tei:unclear> mir doch keine Stunde von Wien
    fort, ist überflüssig zu sagen.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich stelle Ihnen daher folgenden Antrag um dessen Annahme ich Sie recht sehr bitte
    verehrter Herr D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi>. I<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08"
     type="editorial" place="foot">unclear: Colbert inserts "I" as if perhaps about to enumerate
     other points but then loses track. </tei:note> aus den vorher erwähnten Gründen des Mangels an
    Zeit u ich muss es gestehen ich wäre auch nicht im Stande mich jetzt an ein Klavier zu setzen
    was ich einen ganzen Monat vollkommen unterliess so möchte Sie bitten mir alle 14 Tage eine
    Stunde zu geben. Da ich aber jetzt <tei:pb n="4"/> in diesen Monaten, ich hoffe von ganzem
    Herzen dass unser Schicksal sich bald wenden möge ich uberhaupt keine Viertelstunde für mich
    habe, so möchte ich dann alle Stunden einbringen die ich jetzt nicht nehmen kann so dass Sie
    absolut keinen Schaden dabei haben sollen, sondern ich von Oktober bis Ende Juni meine Stunden
    alle 14 Tage honorire auch wenn Sie die Güte haben mir erst zu einem späteren Zeitpunkt die
    Stunden zu geben.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09" type="editorial" place="foot">This sentence is
     somewhat convoluted. The only lesson recorded in the lessonbook for Colbert in 1914/15 occurred
     on Saturday October 26, when she had the second of the two lessons that day; however, the
     lessonbook is clearly incomplete, so we cannot be sure how often she
    attended.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p>Mein <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000136">Mann</tei:rs> hatte durch das Aufheben der
     Sonntagsruhe<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10" type="editorial" place="foot">i.e. the observance of
     Sunday as a rest-day, presumably for purposes of the war and relief effort. </tei:note> einen
    schweren <tei:pb n="5"/> Existenz Kampf zu führen denn es erschienen am Montag Morgen sämmtliche
    Tagesblätter u nur den verzweifelsten Anstrengungen u dem Hinweis dass nicht nur wir Herausgeber
    sondern auch so u so viele andere Menschen brotlos würden gelang es den Staatsanwalt u die Herrn
    im Ministerium zu überzeugen. Dass die Papiere der <tei:title>Wr. Mode</tei:title><tei:note
     xml:id="r0001-fn11" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:title level="j">Wiener Mode</tei:title>
     (Viennese Fashion), magazing founded jointly by Carl Colbert and Ernst Ziegler in 1887.
    </tei:note> auch dieses Jahr nichts tragen werden brauche ich doch mal gar nicht zu erwähnen
    denn wir sind mit grossem Opfer bereit gewesen <tei:pb n="6"/> den Angestellten trotz
    vollkommene Betriebslosigkeit die Hälfte ihres Gehaltes auszuzahlen.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Und trotz all’ dieser prekären Finanzlage will ich alles thun um mein Studium bei Ihnen
    weiter bilden zu können u ich hoffe Sie sehen mein heisses Bemühen ein u ich habe nicht nur den
    Lehrer überzeugt sondern auch der Freund erhalten.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Bitte meine herzlichste Grüsse <tei:rs type="person"
      key="entity-000771">Frau Kornfeld</tei:rs> auszurichten</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihre</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000137">Tony
     Colbert</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p>Ich glaube wir besprechen das lieber mündlich u Sie sind so gut u geben mir einen Tag an
     zwischen 6–7 Ab<tei:supplied reason="abbreviation">ends</tei:supplied>.</tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#printed"/><tei:hi rend="bold">T C</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
     <tei:lb/>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="ident-70"><tei:handShift new="#TC"/><tei:date when="1914-09-13"
      >Sunday</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Highly revered Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs type="person"
       key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
      type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Before all else, I want to make clear that I have absolutely no intention of stopping my
     lessons,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> for they constitute a part of my life
    ‒ in peacetime.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> But I must earnestly beg two
    things of you, and will put before you my reasons for this. When my son was summoned here from
     <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002589">Hamburg</tei:rs> by telegraph on July 27, and
    immediately engaged for the first month to join the forces, which happened on July 28, my
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000136"> husband</tei:rs> and I were in a bad frame of
    mind.</tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> We sought an activity to take our minds off it. Nothing was more dreadful
    than the knowledge of what had happened. I offered my assistance in the child-care of the
    Imperial Organization for the Housewives of Austria,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
     type="footnote"/> and was appointed leader after several days of unwearying work from 9 a.m. to
    7 p.m. On August 10 the Mayor summoned me to the central office in the Town Hall, where we
    seventeen women hold our meeting every Thursday under the chairmanship of the two
     Mayors,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> where all the important matters
    concerning the Women's Relief Action<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> are decided
    and then allocated to the twenty-one districts.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/>
    It is a very arduous and responsible <tei:pb n="3"/> job that I have charged myself with, but I
    do it with total dedication. It goes without saying that I exhaust all my strength in doing it,
    which leaves me not a single hour away from Vienna.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>I therefore make the following petition, the acceptance of which I earnestly beg of you,
    revered Doctor: for the above-mentioned reasons of lack of time ‒ and I must confess that I am
    not even in a state to sit down these days at a piano, which I have wholly neglected to do for
    an entire month ‒ I should like to ask you to give me a lesson every two weeks. But since now
     <tei:pb n="4"/> in recent months ‒ I hope with all my heart that our fate may soon change ‒ I
    do not have a single quarter-hour to myself, I should like to make up then all the lessons that
    I cannot take now so that you will suffer absolutely no detriment as a result; rather, I will
    pay for my lessons every two weeks from October to the end of June, if only you will do me the
    kindness of not giving me my lessons until a later time.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09"
     type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p>My <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000136">husband</tei:rs> had to <tei:pb n="5"/> fight
    hard for his very existence as a result of the lifting of Sunday rest,<tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn10" type="footnote"/> for all the newspapers appeared on Monday morning, and
    only the most desperate efforts and the evidence that not only we editors but also such and such
    a number of other people would be out of work convinced the state attorney and the people at the
    Ministry. That the issues of <tei:title level="j">Wiener Mode</tei:title><tei:ptr
     corresp="#r0001-fn11" type="footnote"/> will also bring in nothing this year I surely scarcely
    need to mention, for we have already made great sacrifices <tei:pb n="6"/> to pay our employees
    half their pay despite wholesale loss of business.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>And in spite of this whole precarious financial situation, I will do everything possible
    to be able to carry forward my study with you, and I hope that you recognize my ardent endeavor
    and that I have not only convinced my teacher but also held on to my friend.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Please give my most cordial greetings to <tei:rs type="person"
      key="entity-000771">Mrs. Kornfeld</tei:rs> auszurichten</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000137">Tony
     Colbert</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p>It would be better to discuss this in person, if you will be so good as to let me know a
     day between 6 and 7 p.m.</tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>


  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
