<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="485" sdoID="OJ-9-34_40">OJ 9/34, [40]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="FEvC" scope="sole">Felix-Eberhard von Cube's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
      <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2011-11-13" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002775">Cube ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, June 2, 1934</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1934-06-02T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-10-09</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Quotes part of a letter from the Reichsmusikkammer regarding grounds for his
        dismissal, and reports subsequent conversation with the Conservatory administration.
        Encloses review of a recent lecture. Includes revised Ursatz for Bach Prelude in body of
        letter. Inquires about Hans Wolf, and reports on Furtwängler.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000143">Cube</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-40">Hamburg 13, Mittelweg 126, Ia/<tei:hi rend="supralinear">II.</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-65"><tei:date when="1934-06-02">2.VI.34.</tei:date>
        </tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:epigraph rend="indent-55">
          <tei:cit>
            <tei:quote>Jeder denkt, sie sind perdü, <tei:lb/>aber nein, noch leben sie!</tei:quote>
            <tei:lb/>
            <tei:bibl>(<tei:rs key="entity-000115" type="person">Wilhelm Busch</tei:rs>.)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Wilhelm Busch (1832-1908), artist
                and poet, most famous for his picture stories, among which <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Max und Moritz</tei:title> (1865)</tei:bibl> became a children's
                classic.</tei:note></tei:bibl>

          </tei:cit>
        </tei:epigraph>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-25">Hochverehrter, lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
            this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at <!-- XR -->OJ 4/7, p. 3914, June 4, 1934:
            "Von Cube (Br.): hält mich auf dem Laufenden über seine Lebenschwierigkeiten, grüßt auch
            die „liebe Frau“ usw." (From Cube (letter): brings me up to date on the difficulties of
            his life, sends greetings also to my "dear wife" etc.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich habe weidlich nach verschiedenen Seiten geknurrt und die Zähne
        gefletscht, nach anderen Seiten hinwiederum aufklärend und überzeugend gewirkt und
        gearbeitet; item ich in die bröckelnde Mauer des Starrsinnes einen soliden Haken getrieben
        habe, an dem ich mich vielleicht wieder anseilen kann.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:hi rend="italic">Haken</tei:hi> (a thin wedge driven
          into a rockface, used as a safety device in mountaneering) and <tei:hi rend="italic">anseilen</tei:hi> (to tie into a rope) are terms that Schenker, a keen Alpinist, would
          not only have understood but also have been pleased to see used metaphorically.</tei:note>
        Folgendermaßen läutet ein Schreiben, das ich vom Landesleiter der <tei:rs key="entity-003121" type="organization">Reichsmusikkammer</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:hi rend="italic">Reichmusikkammer</tei:hi> (Reich Music Chamber): the body controlling music throughout
          Germany during the period of National Socialism, itself subdivided into departments for
          composition, soloists, orchestras, entertainment music, music education, choral music,
          church music, concert agencies, etc., and 31 regional offices. It was one of seven
          sub-chambers of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Reichskulturkammer</tei:hi> (Reich Culture
          Chamber), founded in 1933, the year that Hitler came to power, under the authority of the
          Propaganda Minister Joseph Goebbels. Its President for the first two years was Richard
          Strauss.</tei:note> erhielt: <tei:lb/><tei:quote rend="block">„Sehr geehrter Herr von
            <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">Cube</tei:rs>! <tei:lb/> Ich teile Ihnen mit,
          dass ich mich über die Gründe Ihrer Kündigung beim <tei:rs key="entity-003118" type="organization">Deutschen Konservatorium</tei:rs> direkt informieren werde. Eine
          Stellungnahme zur „<tei:term><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Schenker</tei:rs>-Theorie</tei:term>“ scheint mir zurzeit durchaus nicht erforderlich
          und ist es mir unerfindlich, weshalb Sie mit einer derartigen Begründung gekündigt wurden.
          ........“</tei:quote></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Es folgen dann noch Bemerkungen über die Einflussnahme der <tei:rs key="entity-003121" type="organization">R.M.K.</tei:rs> auf Anstellungsverträge. Ich habe
        nach diesem Schreiben meiner Direktion auf den Kopf zu gesagt, dass der Kündigungsgrund um
        ein fauler Vorwand für unsaubere geschäftliche Machenschaften war, (denn ich kenne jetzt
        auch meinen Nachfolger!), worauf wir den schönsten Krach kriegten, und ich erst recht
        rausgeschmissen wurde! Immerhin habe jetzt <tei:hi rend="underline">ich</tei:hi> die reine
        Weste, und meine <tei:hi rend="underline">Direktion</tei:hi> den Fleck auf der Conduite! Was
        mir allerdings nun ein ehrenvoller, aber leider kein stofflicher Ersatz für die verlorene
        Verdienstquelle ist. Einige beherzte Schüler sind mit mir „<tei:soCalled>in die
          Verbannung</tei:soCalled>“ gegangen. Aber erst nebelhaft erheben sich am Horizonte die
        Umrisse einer neuen eventuellen Arbeitsstätte. Jetzt kommen erst die Ferien und mitten darin
        unser Familienzuwachs, sodass mir alle Haare einzeln zu Berge stehen, und ich ein S.O.S. an
        die Verwandten losgelassen habe. Obs hilft??? —</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> Einliegend finden Sie ferner die Besprechung eines
        Vortrages, den ich kürzlich mit dem Mute der Verzweiflung gehalten habe. Es schien mir der
        einzigmögliche Weg, die Wahrheit zur Sprache zu bringen, ohne auf eine <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">a-priori</tei:foreign>-Ablehnung zu stossen. Der Erfolg übertraf meine
        Erwartungen, und auch die Besprechung – von mir leicht inspiriert – zeigt, dass es noch
        Leute gibt, die eine geistige Verantwortung auf sich zu nehmen bereit sind. Curioserweise
        hatte der Vortrag ein Echo aus – – – – – <tei:rs key="entity-002495" type="place">Frankfurt</tei:rs>! Von dort schrieb mir ein Professor <tei:rs key="entity-003122" type="person">Alfred Hoehn</tei:rs> (kennen Sie ihn?),<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Alfred Hoehn: teacher of piano at the Frankfurt Conservatory
          (taught, among others, the conductor Hans Rosbaud).</tei:note> dass er von diesen Dingen
        mehr erfahren möchte. Ich werde ihm ein paar zusammenhängende Notizen und eine
        „selbstgezogene“ <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> schicken.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">No paragraph-break in original.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Beim <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person">Bach</tei:rs><tei:rs key="entity-001145" type="composition">präludium</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">This is a follow-up graph to an analysis sent with Cube's
          previous letter to Schenker, <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-34_39">OJ 9/34,
            [39]</tei:ref>, April 29, 1934.</tei:note> habe ich mich zu folgendem
          <tei:term>Ursatze</tei:term> durchgerungen: <tei:lb/><tei:figure type="musical_example">
          <tei:graphic url="OJ-9-34_40-ex1-ger.png" mimeType="image/png" n="thumb"/>
        </tei:figure></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">Cum grano salis</tei:foreign> natürlich! Jetzt
        arbeite ich auch an der <tei:rs key="entity-001043" type="composition">Fuge</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot">Voice-leading
          graphs of both the Prelude and the Fugue in D major from the <tei:title level="m">Well-Tempered Clavier</tei:title>, Book 1, are included in Cube's unpublished
            <tei:title level="m">Lehrbuch der musikalischen Kunstgesetze</tei:title>. (They are
          dated 1956 and 1957, respectively.)</tei:note> Dies ist auch so ähnlich. Im Übrigen bin
        ich mit „<tei:soCalled>Nestbau</tei:soCalled>“ beschäftigt, streiche meine Möbel, tapeziere
        Wände, zimmere Tische und Garderoben, denn Handwerker bezahlen ist nicht möglich, und
        ausserdem wird das Selbstgefühl gesteigert! —</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Gott und mein Glaube an die Ewigkeit alles Deutschen – auch im neuen
          <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place">Deutschland</tei:rs> – helfe mir weiter!
          —<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09" type="editorial" place="foot">On his "allegiance to the new
          Germany," see Cube's previous letter, <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-34_39">OJ
            9/34, [39]</tei:ref>, April 29, 1934, and also Cube's <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-34_37">OJ 9/34, [37]</tei:ref>, May 11, and Schenker's <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-7a_46">OJ 5/7a, [46]</tei:ref>, May 14,
          1933.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Mit vielen herzlichen Grüssen von uns beiden an Sie und Ihre
          liebe <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Gattin</tei:rs> bich ich
          stets</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-65">Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143">Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>

        <tei:note type="editorial">in lower left margin:</tei:note>

        <tei:p>Was macht <tei:rs key="entity-000973" type="person">Hans Wolf</tei:rs>?</tei:p>

        <tei:p>Ach so: <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs> will sich
          Mitte <tei:date when="1934-06">Juni</tei:date> mit mir in Verbindung setzen!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10" type="editorial" place="foot">Cube's last letter to Schenker,
              <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-34_42">OJ 9/34, [42]</tei:ref>, October 4,
            1934, quotes in full the letter written by Wilhelm Furtwängler in support of his
            dedication to the teaching of Schenker's theories.</tei:note></tei:p>

      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-40">Hamburg 13, Mittelweg 126, Ia/<tei:hi rend="supralinear">II.</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-65"><tei:date when="1934-06-02">June 2, 1934</tei:date>
        </tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
        <tei:epigraph rend="indent-55">
          <tei:cit>
            <tei:quote>Everyone thinks the game is up, <tei:lb/>But, no, there's life in them
              yet!</tei:quote>
            <tei:lb/>
            <tei:bibl>(<tei:rs key="entity-000115" type="person">Wilhelm Busch</tei:rs>.)<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:bibl>

          </tei:cit>
        </tei:epigraph>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-25">Most revered, dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p rend="first">I have growled and flashed my teeth in many directions, and again been
        active and at work on other fronts to enlighten and convince, with the result that I have
        driven a solid hook into the crumbling wall of obstinacy, onto which I may be able to rope
        myself once more.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> A letter, which I received
        from the provincial leader of the <tei:rs key="entity-003121" type="organization">Reichsmusikkammer</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> reads as
        follows: <tei:lb/><tei:quote rend="block">"Dear Mr. von <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">Cube</tei:rs>! <tei:lb/> This is to let you know that I shall inform
          myself directly concerning the grounds of your dismissal from the <tei:rs key="entity-003118" type="organization">German Conservatory</tei:rs>. An opinion
          concerning "<tei:term><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Schenker</tei:rs>ian
            theory</tei:term>" seems to me at this time entirely unnecessary, and I cannot
          understand why you were dismissed on grounds of that sort..."</tei:quote></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">There then follow remarks about the extent to which the <tei:rs key="entity-003121" type="organization">Reichsmusikkammer</tei:rs> exerts an influence
        over employment contracts. After receiving this letter I spoke face to face with the
        administration, saying that the reason for my dismissal was a lame pretext for shady
        business dealings (for I also know now who my successor is!), whereupon we had the fiercest
        row and I was categorically thrown out! None the less, it is <tei:hi rend="underline">I</tei:hi> who wears the clean shirt, and the <tei:hi rend="underline">administration</tei:hi> which has a black mark for conduct! This is at any rate for me an
        honorable, though unfortunately not a material, substitute for the lost sources of income. A
        few brave pupils went with me "<tei:soCalled>into banishment</tei:soCalled>." But the
        outlines of a new possibility for work are rising only hazily on the horizon. Now the summer
        holidays are intervening, and in the midst of this the new member of our family, so that all
        of my hairs are standing up like mountains and I have issued an S.O.S. to our relatives. But
        will that help???</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="2"/> I have also enclosed for you the review of a lecture that
        I gave recently, with the courage of despair. It seemed to me the only possible way of
        giving voice to the truth, without meeting an <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">a priori</tei:foreign></tei:hi> objection. The success exceeded my
        expectation, and even the review – lightly drawing inspiration from me – shows that there
        are still people who are prepared to bear intellectual responsibility. Strangely enough, the
        lecture received an echo from, of all places, <tei:rs key="entity-002495" type="place">Frankfurt</tei:rs>! From there a Professor <tei:rs key="entity-003122" type="person">Alfred Hoehn</tei:rs> (do you know him?)<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/>
        wrote to me, saying that he wanted to learn more about these things. I shall send him a few
        related notices and a "self-drawn" <tei:term>Ursatz</tei:term>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">In the <tei:rs key="entity-000027" type="person">Bach</tei:rs>
        <tei:rs key="entity-001145" type="composition">Prelude</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> I have arrived at the following
          <tei:term>Ursatz</tei:term>: <tei:lb/><tei:figure type="musical_example">
          <tei:graphic url="OJ-9-34_40-ex1-eng.png" mimeType="image/png" n="thumb"/>
        </tei:figure></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:supplied reason="clarity">You may take this,</tei:supplied> of
        course, with a pinch of salt! Now I am also working on the <tei:rs key="entity-001043" type="composition">fugue</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/> This is
        also very similar. Otherwise, I am busy "<tei:soCalled>building a nest</tei:soCalled>,"
        painting my furniture, papering the walls, and building tables and wardrobes, since paying a
        builder is impossible and, in addition, my self-esteem is thereby increased.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">May God and my belief in the eternity of everything German – even in the
        new <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place">Germany</tei:rs> – help me further!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">With many cordial greetings from the two of us to you and your
          dear <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs>, I am always</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-65">Yours,</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143">Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>

        <tei:note type="editorial">in lower left margin:</tei:note>

        <tei:p><tei:supplied reason="clarity">P.S.:</tei:supplied> What is <tei:rs key="entity-000973" type="person">Hans Wolf</tei:rs> up to?</tei:p>

        <tei:p>Oh, yes: <tei:rs key="entity-000268" type="person">Furtwängler</tei:rs> will get in
          touch with me in the middle of <tei:date when="1934-06">June</tei:date>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn10" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>