<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="451" sdoID="OJ-9-35_2">OJ 9/35, [2]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="GvC" scope="major">G von Cube</tei:handNote>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="major">printed</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2011</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2011-06-10" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002866">CubeG ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Gustav von Cube to Schenker, dated August 24, 1926</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1926-08-024T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2011-06-10</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Responding to Schenker’s demand for final payment for his son’s lessons, Gustav
    von Cube has arranged for 250 Marks to be paid to Schenker in Galtür; he will send the remainder
    to Vienna. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Zahlungserleichterungen; easement of payment; Lehrtätigkeit; activity as a teacher </dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-002866">CubeG</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:fw type="envelope">
     <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">envelope</tei:note><tei:lb/>
     <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="recto"/><tei:lb/>
     <tei:address>
      <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied reason="clarity">An: </tei:supplied> Herrn Prof. Dr. Heinrich
       Schenker</tei:addrLine>
      <tei:addrLine rend="indent-20"><tei:hi rend="underline">Galtür</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
      <tei:addrLine rend="indent-40">Tirol.</tei:addrLine>
     </tei:address>
     <tei:address>
      <tei:addrLine><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">printed sender address as at head of
        letter</tei:note></tei:addrLine>
     </tei:address>
     <tei:fw type="postmark">|| DUISBURG | 24. 8. 26 9-10 V | * 1 * ||</tei:fw>
    </tei:fw><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
    <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">letter</tei:note>
    <tei:lb/>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">printed letterhead, all in double
      rule-frame:</tei:note>
     <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="printed"/>PROFESSOR DR. ING. GUSTAV VON CUBE UND ARTHUR
      BUCHLOH </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>ARCHITEKTEN B.D.A. </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>DUISBURG A/RH. </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>A. E. G.-HAUS SONNENWALL </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>FERNSPRECHER NR. 3933 </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">and further contact information </tei:note>
     <tei:lb/>


    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-60">DEN <tei:date when="1926-08-24"><tei:handShift new="GvC"/>24.
      August 1926.</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-15">Sehr geehrter Herr<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
      this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/8, pp. 2969-2970, August 25, 1926: "Von
      Cube sen. (Br.): mein Brief an ihn zurück; sendet 250 Mark u. verspricht, den Rest nach Wien
      zu schicken; er bedauert, daß ich seine wirtschaftliche Not nicht begreifen will! Eine recht
      sonderbare Veranlagung dieses Mannes: er legt es deutlich darauf an, mir einen unentgeltlichen
      Unterricht an seinen Sohn abzunötigen (das ganze Jahr hindurch), schließlich sogar mit der
      spitzigen Bemerkung, ich hätte ohnehin schon viel an seinem Sohn verdient; Diese eigensüchtige
      Denkweise nun, die gar nicht Kenntnis nimmt von der Beschaffenheit des Menschen, denn er sie
      zumutet, gehört so zu seiner Natur, daß er sich dieses Charaktermangels gar nicht bewußt wird
      u. nur den andern des Mangels an Engtgegenkommen beschuldigt, auf das er ein gegründetes Recht
      hätte. Mein Brief hat ihm diesen inneren Mangel gewissermaßen ins Bewußtsein gebracht, aber
      gerade weil er ein Hineinleuchten war, hat er sich von sich selbst erst recht zurückgezogen in
      seine Rechthaberei. Seine Unlauterkeit gestattet ihm nicht anders zu denken, als daß ich
      schuldig wäre, auf seine wirtschaftliche Lage Rücksicht zu nehmen – das Gegenteil fiel diesem
      das Charlatanmäßige schon streifenden Menschen nicht ein." ("From Cube snr (letter): my letter
      to him returned; [he] is sending 250 marks and promises to send the remainder to Vienna; he
      regrets that I do not wish to recognize his financial difficulties! A truly odd character
      trait of this person: he is clearly determined to compel me to teach his son without charge
      (throughout the year), even going so far as to add the barbed remark that I had already earned
      a great deal from his son. This selfish mode of thought, which takes no account of the
      character of the person upon whom he is prevailing, is so much a part of his nature that he is
      not at all aware of this shortcoming in his character and only accuses the other of a lack of
      cooperation, to which he has an established right. My letter has somehow brought this inner
      shortcoming to his attention; but precisely because it offered illumination, he withdrew from
      this to an even greater extent, into [a state of] disputaciousness. His dishonesty prevents
      him from thinking anything except that I was obliged to take into account his financial
      situation – the opposite did not occur to this person, whose character borders on the
      charlatanic."). </tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich liess Ihnen heute durch die Bank 250 M. in Schillingen nach <tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs> überweisen. Der Rest folgt demnächst nach
     <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs>. Es scheint schwer Ihnen die Überzeugung
    beizubringen, daß die wirtschaftliche Not mich zwingt von Ihnen Zahlungserleichterungen zu
    erbitten. Leicht fällt es mir nicht bei Ihrer Einstellung mir gegenüber. Wegen der angeblich von
    mir über Sie gemachten Äusserung<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">i.e.
     that Schenker "had made enough money out of his son," remark alleged in Schenker's letter of
     August 18, 1926: <tei:ref cRef="OJ-5-8_1" type="correspondence">OJ 5/8, [1]</tei:ref>.
    </tei:note> interpellierte ich meinen <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">Sohn</tei:rs>.
    Er bestreitet energisch Ihnen eine Bemerkung in dieser Fassung kolportiert zu haben und stellt
    die Sache dahin richtig, daß ich die für mich immerhin hohen Aufwendungen betonte, die ich für
    ihn leisten mußte. Sie können mir glauben, daß ich es ihm bis zum letzten Moment ermöglichen
    wollte des Vorzuges Ihrer Lehrtätigkeit teilhaftig zu werden, die ich stets als ein Glück für
    ihn empfand; von einem Spott kann keine Rede sein, weil die ganze Sache zu tragisch ist. Sie
    haben sicherlich in einem Moment von Überempfindlichkeit zur Feder gegriffen und ich möchte
    Ihnen den Vorschlag machen den Brief zurückzunehmen und mir so Gelegenheit zu geben ohne
    Missklang meine Verpflichtungen Ihnen gegenüber zu erfüllen. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Mit vozüglicher Hochachtung</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000144">G. v.
     Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>


  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:fw type="envelope">
     <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">envelope</tei:note><tei:lb/>
     <tei:milestone unit="folio" n="recto"/><tei:lb/>
     <tei:address>
      <tei:addrLine><tei:supplied reason="clarity">To: </tei:supplied> Prof. Dr. Heinrich
       Schenker,</tei:addrLine>
      <tei:addrLine rend="indent-20"><tei:hi rend="underline">Galtür</tei:hi>,</tei:addrLine>
      <tei:addrLine rend="indent-40">Tyrol</tei:addrLine>
     </tei:address>
     <tei:address>
      <tei:addrLine><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">printed sender address as at head of
        letter</tei:note></tei:addrLine>
     </tei:address>
     <tei:fw type="postmark">|| DUISBURG | 24. 8. 26 9-10 AM | * 1 * ||</tei:fw>
    </tei:fw><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
    <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">letter</tei:note><tei:lb/>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">printed letterhead, all in double
      rule-frame:</tei:note>
     <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="printed"/>PROFESSOR Dr.Eng. GUSTAV VON CUBE AND ARTHUR
      BUCHLOH </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>ARCHITECTS B.D.A. </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>DUISBURG ON THE RHINE</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>A. E. G.-HAUS SONNENWALL </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>TELEPHONE NO. 3933 </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">and further contact information </tei:note>
     <tei:lb/>

    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:date when="1926-08-24"><tei:handShift new="GvC"/>August 24,
      1926</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-15">Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Today I arranged for my bank to send you in <tei:rs key="entity-002292" type="place">Galtür</tei:rs> 250 marks, to be paid in shillings. The rest will follow soon, in
     <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>. It seems difficult to convince you
    that the financial crisis compels me to ask you to make it easier for me to make payment. I do
    not take lightly your position with respect to me. With regard to the statement that I had made
    about you,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> I interrogated my <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">son</tei:rs>. He vigorously denies having transmitted a
    comment of this sort, and set the matter straight: that I stressed the considerable expenditures
    that I must make for him. You can believe me that I wanted to make it possible for him to take
    advantage of your activity as a teacher, which I always felt to be a joy for him. About a joke
    there can be no question, for the entire matter is too tragic. You have, for sure, taken up your
    pen in a moment of over-sensitivity, and I would recommend that you retract your letter and give
    me the opportunity to fulfill my obligations to you without feeling resentment. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">With highest esteem, </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000144">G. v.
     Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>



  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>