<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="2182" sdoID="OJ-9-30_2">OJ 9/30, [2]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="TC" scope="sole">Toni Colbert's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2007, 2019</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2007, 2019</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>


  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2011-06-09" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006997">Colbert ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Tony Colbert to Schenker, dated August 23, [1912]</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1912-08-23T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-01-26</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Mrs. Colbert pleads to resume piano lessons with Schenker.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>hartherzig; hard-hearted; fleissig; industrious; Heiligthum; sanctuary; Offenbarung;
    revelation; Stunde; lesson</dc:subject>


   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000137">ColbertT</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="ident-70"><tei:placeName>Wien</tei:placeName>
     <tei:date when="1912-08-23">23/VIII</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Lieber verehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">D<tei:hi
       rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi></tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
      place="foot">Schenker's belated reaction to this letter is recorded in his diary at OJ 1/11,
      p. 243, September 30, 1912: "Brief der Colbert vom 23. August. Schüler frage ich prinzipiell
      nicht an, ob sie kommen. Entschied mich für sie, weil der Mann in Kenntnis gesetzt wurde u. 3.
      Instanz. Soll ich auf Einnahme verzichten? Außerdem Unsicherheit bezgl. der fremden Hilfe u.
      des Kommens. Kein Widerspruch zwischen machen wollen u. nicht können. Erklärung meines
      Unterrichtssystems im Gegensatz zum üblichen teueren; von meinen Schülern, die ich zur Nobless
      zwingen muss; sie nehmen, geben aber nicht. Ohren communizieren nicht mit dem Geldbeutel."
      ("Letter from Mrs. Colbert of August 23. As a matter of principle, I shall not inquire of
      pupils as to whether they will come. I decided in her favor because her husband was informed,
      and it was the third time around. Should I forgo income? In addition, uncertainty with respect
      to help from outsiders and the future. No contradiction between wishing to do, and not being
      able to do. Explanation of my method of teaching in contrast to the usual, more expensive
      ones; concerning my pupils, whom I must compel to act nobly; they take but do not give. Ears
      do not communicate with a purse of money.").<tei:lb/>Earlier, on September 15, Schenker wrote
      to her husband, <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-1-B-15">OC 1B/15</tei:ref>, for which
      the diary records: "Brief an Herrn Colbert in Sachen seiner Frau Colbert gerichtet; völlig
      offene Aussprache des wahren Sachverhaltes." ("Letter addressed to Mr. Colbert in matters
      concerning Mrs. Colbert; completely open airing of the true facts of the matter."), and Mrs.
      Colbert had written to Schenker on September 16 and 27 (<tei:ref type="correspondence"
       cRef="OJ-9-30_3">OJ 9/30, [3]</tei:ref> and <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-30_4"
       >OJ 9/30, [4]</tei:ref>.</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Ich hoffe sehr dass Sie dieses Jahr nicht so hartherzig sein werden wie das vergangene.
    Ich habe die ehrliche Absicht sehr fleissig zu studiren u möchte Sie doch sehr bitten mich zu
    Ihr Heiligthum wieder einzulassen u mir jede Woche eine Stunde zu geben. Ich lechze nach neuen
     <tei:pb n="2"/> Offenbarungen u will mit gewissenhafter Pünklichkeit meine Stunde
    einhalten.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Nicht mehr, bester Herr D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> ich habe nicht vergebens
     <tei:sic>angeklaght</tei:sic>, mir wird auch aufgethan.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich bin diesen Sommer mit Ausnahme von 3 Wochen Vöslau<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
     type="editorial" place="foot">Bad Vöslau, a health resort 35 km (22 miles) south of
     Vienna.</tei:note> in <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Wien</tei:hi> gewesen weil ich Grossmutter
    eines lieben herzigen Mäds wurde.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Euer guten frohen Nachricht</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">entgegensehend Ihre</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000137">Tony
     Colbert</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="ident-70"><tei:placeName>Vienna, </tei:placeName>
     <tei:date when="1912-08-23">August 23</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Dear, revered Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs type="person"
       key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
      type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>I very much hope you will not be so hard-hearted this year as last. I have the honest
    intention to study very industriously, and should very much like to ask you to readmit me to
    your sanctuary and to give me one lesson a week. I thirst after new <tei:pb n="2"/> revelations,
    and will keep to my lesson with scrupulous punctuality.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>No more for now, dear Doctor. Not in vain have I <tei:unclear reason="original-unclear"
     >petitioned</tei:unclear>, may the door be opened to me.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Other than three weeks in Vöslau,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> I have
    been in Vienna all this summer because I have become grandmother to a dear little girl.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Looking forward to hearing good, joyful news from you,</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000137">Tony
     Colbert</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>


  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
