<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="470" sdoID="OJ-9-34_23">OJ 9/34, [23]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="FEvC" scope="sole">Felix-Eberhard von Cube's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
   <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2011-09-06" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002775">Cube ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated February 10, 1931</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1931-02-10T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-11-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Cube acknowledges issue of Der Kunstwart; encloses a letter from Walter Braunfels responding to his
    plans to establish a Rhineland base for Schenkerian teaching at the Cologne Hochschule für Musik; wonders whether
    Anthony van Hoboken might be approached for financial assistance on this, and if so how the approach should be
    made.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000143">Cube</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-45">Duisburg/Rheinland. Kuhstr. 23–25/<tei:hi rend="supralinear">I.</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-55"><tei:date when="1931-02-10">10.II.31.</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-15">Sehr verehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ
      4/4, p. 3577, February 12, 1931: "Von Cube (Br.): ein Brief von Braunfels liegt bei – er bedauert wegen
      finanzieller Schwierigkeiten Cubes Ansuchen nicht erfüllen zu können. v. C. macht den Vorschlag, eine solche
      Stelle durch einen Mäzen für 1–2 Jahre stiften zu lassen u. denkt – an van Hoboken." ("From Cube (letter): a
      letter from Braunfels is enclosed – he regrets because of financial difficulties not being able to fulfill Cube's
      request. Von Cube suggests having such a post supported for one or two years by a patron, and is thinking of – van
      Hoboken.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Zunächst vielen Dank für die Übersendung des neuen „<tei:rs key="entity-003014" type="journal"><tei:title>Kunstwart</tei:title></tei:rs>“,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The
      <tei:bibl>January 1931 issue of <tei:title level="j">Der Kunstwart</tei:title>, vol. 44, No. 4</tei:bibl>,
     contained a notice of <tei:bibl>Schenker's <tei:title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:title>, vol.
      3</tei:bibl>, by Otto Vrieslander.</tei:note> worüber ich gleich noch einiges zu erzählen haben werde. Vorher aber
    das Wichtigste. Der einliegende Brief gibt Ihnen Aufschluss über die derzeitige Situation meiner <tei:rs key="entity-002604" type="place">Köln</tei:rs>er Pläne. Ich schrieb nämlich <tei:rs key="entity-002939" type="person">Braunfels</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Walter Braunfels,
     professor of theory at the Cologne Hochschule für Musik, who had given support to Cube's efforts to promote
     Schenkerian theory in northern Germany.</tei:note> einen seemeilenlangen Brief über die mehr und mehr in den
     <tei:term>Vordergrund</tei:term> pädagogischen Interesserückende Notwendigkeit der Schaffung einer staatlich
    sanktionierten Basis für <tei:term>Schenkerunterricht</tei:term> im <tei:rs key="entity-003015" type="place">Rheinlande</tei:rs>; die Fortschritte, die im Reich zu verzeichnen sind, wie auch die Tagung in <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs> wurden gebührend erwähnt. Die Antwort <tei:rs key="entity-002939" type="person">Braunfels</tei:rs>’, die eigentlich nur <tei:hi rend="underline">einen</tei:hi> triftigen, zeitlich
    bedingten Hinderungsgrund aufweist, kann zweierlei Bedeutung haben: eine reale und eine politische. Real insofern,
    als die Finanzen der <tei:rs key="entity-002956" type="organization">Hochschule</tei:rs> tatsächlich besonders
    schlecht sind; politisch wäre denkbar, dass auch <tei:rs key="entity-002939" type="person">Braunfels</tei:rs> den
    unheilvollen Einfluss der „entfesselten Pädagogen“ in <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs>
    (trotz <tei:rs key="entity-000431" type="person">Kestenberg</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Leo Kestenberg (1882–1962), who taught at both the Stern Conservatory and the Klindworth-Scharwenka
     Conservatory in Berlin, and was appointed to the Ministry of Science, Art, and Education in 1918, rising to a high
     position in the division of Art. His name frequently comes up in the correspondence as someone favorably disposed
     toward the dissemination of Schenker's ideas by German educators.</tei:note>) fürchtet, und mit ausgezeichneter
    Höflichkeit das diplomatische Mittel des Abwartens einem Stich ins Wespennest vorzieht. Ich persönlich halte jedoch
    die erstere Bedeutung für durchaus wahrscheinlich!</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Um indes keine „<tei:term>Stimmführungsmöglichkeit</tei:term>“ unversucht zu lassen, möchte ich
    Sie um Ihren Rat, möglicherweise sogar <tei:pb n="2"/> um Ihre Fürsprache in der Angelegenheit bitten, die ich Ihnen
    im Folgenden unterbreiten will:</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Die Schaffung geregelten <tei:term>Schenkerunterrichts</tei:term> an der <tei:rs key="entity-002956" type="organization">Kölner Hochschule</tei:rs> würde einen ganz erheblichen Schritt nach
    vorwärts bedeuten! Würde Ihre Gedankenwelt doch den ganzen, bis jetzt ziemlich unbeleckten westlichen Provinzen
    erschlossen werden, und der Vorantritt der <tei:rs key="entity-002956" type="organization">Hochschule</tei:rs>
    manche andere Musikpflegestätte bei einiger Überredung zu änhnlichen Einrichtungen veranlassen. Ich will hierbei der
    grossen Schwierigkeiten gedenken, die mir von den einfach unbelehrbaren Machthabern an der <tei:rs key="entity-002904" type="place">Essen</tei:rs>er <tei:rs key="entity-003125" type="organization">Folkwangschule</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">The Folkwang-Schule in Werden,
     near Essen, was founded in 1927 as an interdisciplinary school devoted to music, dance and speech. In 1963 it
     gained the status of a Hochschule, and today there are four Folkwangs-Hochschulen in the Ruhrgebiet: Essen-Werden,
     Duisburg, Bochum and Dortmund. Cube had gone there three years before in the hope of introducing Schenker's
     approach (see letter <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-34_14">OJ 9/34, [14]</tei:ref>, October 4, 1928),
     but he encountered mainly "folk-dancing and chorale singing" and made little headway with the young musicians
     there.</tei:note> sowie selbst in meinem eigenen Wirkungskreis bereitet wurden und noch werden!</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Die <tei:rs key="entity-002956" type="organization">Hochschule</tei:rs> wäre an sich bereit, die
    Sache sofort anzupacken. Ich warte nicht weit davon, bereit meine Kräfte an einem Orte anzuspannen, dessen
    Unternehmungen in weitestem Umkreis beachtet, besprochen und nachgeahmt werden. Was zu dem vollständigen Dreiklang
    noch fehlt, ist eine – und noch dazu verhältnismässig geringe <tei:supplied reason="grammar">–</tei:supplied>
    Geldsumme, die die Einrichtung einer oder mehrerer Klassen für <tei:term>Harmonie</tei:term>,
     <tei:term>Kontrapunkt</tei:term>, <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> etc. ermöglichen könnte!</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Es ist naheliegend, in diesem Zusammenhange an einen Mann zu denken, der in grossherzigster Weise
    die Lösung kultureller Aufgaben durch Beistellung von Mitteln ermöglicht hat, die gewiss erheblicher waren, als die
    zu obbesagtem Zwecke benötigen sein würden. Glauben Sie, lieber Herr Professor, dass es aussichtsreich wäre, sich in
    dieser Angelegenheit <tei:pb n="3"/> an Herrn <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Anthony van
     Hoboken</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Anthony van Hoboken was a pupil of
     Schenker's in the 1920s, one of his wealthiest patrons, and a keen supporter of some of his enterprises. In the
     end, he declined to support Cube's initiative in Cologne; Schenker devotes a whole letter <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-7a_35">OJ 5/7a, [35]</tei:ref>, March 28, 1931, to Hoboken's attitude towards the
     establishment of a Schenker base in Cologne.</tei:note> zu wenden, und ihn zu bitten, diesem doch gewiss <tei:hi rend="underline">nur</tei:hi> nützlichen Vorhaben seinen Beistand zu gewähren? Es würde sich wie gesagt um nicht
    viel Geld, und das auch nur auf ein bis zwei Jahre handeln, denn ich bin überzeugt, dass nach dieser Zeit,
    möglicherweise schon früher, ein ernsthaft aufgezogener Unterricht an der <tei:rs key="entity-002956" type="organization">Hochschule</tei:rs> von selbst obligatorisch würde, und seinen Platz im Etat des Schuldezernats
    erobern und behaupten könnte.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Es wäre da noch die Frage, ob ich mich selbst sofort an Herrn <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">van Hoboken</tei:rs> wenden soll, oder ob Sie selbst auf Grund meines und <tei:rs key="entity-002939" type="person">Braunfels</tei:rs>’ Brief mit Herrn van Hoboken verhandeln möchten. Möglicherweise könnte man sogar
    eine Einigung mit der <tei:rs key="entity-002956" type="organization">Hochschule</tei:rs> insofern anstreben, dass
    diese wenigstens einen <tei:hi rend="underline">Teil</tei:hi> der nötigen Mittel selbst dazugibt! Meines Erachtens
    nach würde schon eine <tei:hi rend="underline">prinzipielle</tei:hi> Zusage Herrn <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">van Hoboken</tei:rs>s genügen, um die <tei:rs key="entity-002956" type="organization">Hochschule</tei:rs> zu Zugeständnissen zu veranlassen. Über die <tei:hi rend="underline">Form</tei:hi> einer
    eventuellen Beihilfe, ob Stiftung, Widmung oder rückzahlbares Darlehen, müssten natürlich auch erst direkte
    Verhandlungen mit der <tei:rs key="entity-002956" type="organization">Hochschule</tei:rs> Klarheit schaffen. Ich
    selbst warte mit Schmerzen auf den Augenblick, der mir die Möglichkeit gibt, mich in der vordersten Kampflinie zu
    bewähren. Obwohl ich noch viel schreiben wollte, muss ich jetzt schliessen. Sehr bald berichte ich Ihnen von meinen
    sonstigen Erlebnissen, Meinungen und Versuche. Für heute beste Grüsse Ihnen und Ihrer <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Frau Gemahlin</tei:rs>, und ergebenste Empfehlungen an Herrn <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">van Hoboken</tei:rs>, auch an Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143">Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>

  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-45">Duisburg, Rhineland, Kuhstrasse 23–25/<tei:hi rend="supralinear">I.</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-55"><tei:date when="1931-02-10">February 10, 1931</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-15">Most revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">First of all, many thanks for forwarding the latest issue of <tei:rs key="entity-003014" type="journal"><tei:title level="j">Der Kunstwart</tei:title></tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> about which I shall presently have a few things to tell you. First of all, the most important
    matter. The enclosed letter gives you information about the present state of my <tei:rs key="entity-002604" type="place">Cologne</tei:rs> plans. In fact I wrote a mile-long letter to <tei:rs key="entity-002939" type="person">Braunfels</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> about the necessity, which
    continues to make its way into the <tei:term>foreground</tei:term> of pedagogical interest, of establishing a
    state-sanctioned basis for <tei:term>Schenkerian teaching</tei:term> in the <tei:rs key="entity-003015" type="place">Rhineland</tei:rs>. The progress that has taken place in the country, and also the symposium in <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs>, were duly mentioned. <tei:rs key="entity-002939" type="person">Braunfels</tei:rs>'s answer, which actually raises only <tei:hi rend="underline">one</tei:hi> legitimate argument
    against it at the present time, can be understood as having two meanings: a real one and a political one. Real, in
    so far as the finances of the <tei:rs key="entity-002956" type="organization">Hochschule</tei:rs> are indeed
    particularly bad; and politically one can imagine that even <tei:rs key="entity-002939" type="person">Braunfels</tei:rs> fears the malevolent influence of the "chained pedagogues" in <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs> (in spite of <tei:rs key="entity-000431" type="person">Kestenberg</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/>), and, with extraordinary politeness, prefers the diplomatic tactic of
    waiting to stirring a hornet's nest. Personally, I regard the first of these interpretations as highly
    probable!</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">So as to leave no <tei:term>voice-leading</tei:term> stone unturned, so to speak, might I in the
    meantime ask for your advice, possibly even your <tei:pb n="2"/> good word in the matter that I shall amplify in the
    following way:</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">The creation of a regulated programme of <tei:term>Schenkerian instruction</tei:term> at the
     <tei:rs key="entity-002956" type="organization">Cologne Hochschule</tei:rs> would signify a truly palpable step
    forwards! Your world of ideas would be made accessible to all the western provinces, which have hitherto been
    untouched. And the involvement of the <tei:rs key="entity-002956" type="organization">Hochschule</tei:rs> might lead
    to other musical institutions being persuaded to set up similar programes. I am thinking here of the great
    difficulties that have been created for me, and will continue to be created, by the authorities of the <tei:rs key="entity-003125" type="organization">Folkwang School</tei:rs> in <tei:rs key="entity-002904" type="place">Essen</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> who are simply unteachable, and those in my own
    sphere of influence!</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">The <tei:rs key="entity-002956" type="organization">Hochschule</tei:rs> ought to be in and of
    itself ready to get to work on the matter immediately. I am waiting, not far away, to concentrate all my strength in
    a place whose undertakings will be regarded, talked about and imitated in the widest imaginable area. What is still
    missing from the complete triad is a sum of money – and, I might add, a relatively small sum – which would make
    possible the establishment of one or several classes in <tei:term>harmony</tei:term>,
     <tei:term>counterpoint</tei:term>, <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>, etc!</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In this connection, one naturally thinks of a man who has, in the most generous way, enabled
    cultural projects to be realized by providing financial assistance that was certainly more substantial than the
    purposes described above would require. Do you believe, my dear Professor, that there may be good reasons to
    approach <tei:pb n="3"/> Mr <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Anthony van Hoboken</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> in this instance, and to ask him to provide assistance for this plan, which
    can surely be <tei:hi rend="underline">only</tei:hi> a profitable one? As I said, it would not amount to a great
    deal of money, and only for one or two years; for I am convinced that by this time, perhaps even sooner, a seriously
    mounted program of studies at the <tei:rs key="entity-002956" type="organization">Hochschule</tei:rs> would of
    itself become obligatory, and could win and assert its place in the "balance sheet" of the school
    administration.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">There is the further question as to whether I should write immediately to Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">van Hoboken</tei:rs> myself, or whether you would like to deal with him
    personally, on the basis of my letter and that of <tei:rs key="entity-002939" type="person">Braunfels</tei:rs>.
    Possibly one could even strive for an agreement with the <tei:rs key="entity-002956" type="organization">Hochschule</tei:rs>, to the extent that it provides at least a <tei:hi rend="underline">part</tei:hi> of the
    necessary funds itself! In my view, an agreement in <tei:hi rend="underline">principle</tei:hi> from Mr <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">van Hoboken</tei:rs> would be enough to persuade the <tei:rs key="entity-002956" type="organization">Hochschule</tei:rs> to make the necessary concessions. Regarding the <tei:hi rend="underline">form</tei:hi> of the assistance – whether it is to be a trust fund, a grant, or a repayable loan – would naturally
    have to await direct negotiations with the <tei:rs key="entity-002956" type="organization">Hochschule</tei:rs>. I
    myself wait in agony for the moment that gives me the opportunity to stand in the front-most line of battle.
    Although I wanted to write yet more, I must close now. Very soon I shall report to you about my other experiences,
    opinions and attempts. For today, best greetings to you and your <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs>, and most devoted regards to Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">van Hoboken</tei:rs>,
    also to Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Yours,</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143">Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>