<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="472" sdoID="OJ-9-34_27">OJ 9/34, [27]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="FEvC" scope="sole">Felix-Eberhard von Cube's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
      <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2011-10-04" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002775">Cube ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated September 8, 1931</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1931-09-08T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-07-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Line drawing of Moriz Violin. Cube reports on health of Violin's son; discusses his
        relationship with Violin, and the prospects of the Schenker Institute in Hamburg; Cube will be assisting at
        a lecture given by Hans Weisse.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      
      
    <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000143">Cube</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:note type="editorial">top left corner:</tei:note>      
        <tei:lb/><tei:figure type="drawing">
          <tei:graphic url="OJ-9-34_27-p1.jpg" n="thumb" rend="left-img" width="150px" height="203px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
        </tei:figure>
        <tei:lb/><tei:note type="editorial">begining top right:</tei:note><tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-55">Hamburg, Beneckestr. 2,</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60">bei <tei:rs key="entity-003092" type="person">Alexander
            Schmidt</tei:rs>.</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-75"><tei:date when="1931-09-08">8.IX.31.</tei:date>
        </tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Sehr verehrter, lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is
            recorded in Schenker's diary at <!-- XR -->OJ 4/4, p. 3659, September 9, 1931: "Von v. Cube (Br.): 6
            Seiten. Stellt seine u. die Instituts kritische Lage dar. Weisse wird am 16. auf Kosten Violins vor
            geladenen Gästen sprechen." ("From von Cube (letter): six pages. Presents his own critical state and
            that of the Institute. Weisse will speak before invited guests on the 16th at Violin's
            expense.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Diesen Brief schicke ich Ihnen schon nach <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs>. Von
          <tei:rs key="entity-000909" type="person">Violins Schwester</tei:rs>, die augenblicklich in <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> weilt, erfuhr ich, dass Sie zurzeit in <tei:rs key="entity-002578" type="place">Salzburg</tei:rs> seien, und demnächst nach <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> zurückfahren wollten; anstatt Ihnen nachzureisen, soll Sie der Brief lieber in
          <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> erwarten. —</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Nebenstehend habe ich versucht, Herrn Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs> in karrikaturistichen Form, so wie Sein Äusseres sich meinem Linien-Sinn eingeprägt hat,
        darzustellen. Ich glaube, man kann ihn erkennen! Es ist erfreulich, zu vermelden, dass <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">seines Sohnes</tei:rs> Befinden in letzter Zeit eine deutliche
        Besserung zeigt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The illness of Moriz Violin's
          son Karl (Karli) is mentioned in Cube's previous letter of August 19, 1931 (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-34_26">OJ 9/34, [26]</tei:ref>), and in Schenker's postcard of August
            22<tei:note type="editorial">?</tei:note>, 1931 (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-7a_39">OJ
            5/7a, [39]</tei:ref>).</tei:note> Die Temperatur ist schon seit Tagen normal, und er sieht viel
        frischer und besser aus, fühlt sich auch bedeutend wohler. Die Ärtzte urteilen noch sehr vorsichtig, zumal
        er ja auch immer noch unter der Einwirkung der Bekämpfungsmassnahmen steht, doch sind sie zufrieden schon
        allein mit der Tatsache, dass das Leiden offenbar eine bekämpfbare Form angenommen hat. Der beinahe
        extatische Lebenswille, und die geradezu bewunderungswürdige Energie des lieben Jungen werden wohl einen
        Hauptanteil an der Besserung haben! Ich wünsche Herrn Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs> von ganzem Herzen, dass <tei:hi rend="underline">diese</tei:hi> Prüfung nun endlich zu
        Ende gehe!</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Andere Sorgen gibt es genug. Die Verhältnisse haben immerhin in den letzten drei
        Monaten eine so gewaltige Änderung zum Schlechten erfahren, dass die Voraussetzungen für das “<tei:rs key="entity-002455" type="organization">Schenker–Institut</tei:rs>”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">For a later document describing this institute, see <tei:ref type="other" cRef="OJ-58-4_1">OJ 58/4, [1]</tei:ref>.</tei:note> davon nicht unberührt bleiben konnten. Materielle
        Ausfälle, unerquickliche Auseinandersetzungen mit dem früheren <tei:rs key="entity-003054" type="organization">Konservatorium</tei:rs>sdirektor <tei:rs key="entity-003053" type="person">Vogt</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">According to <tei:bibl>Cube's
            unpublished autobiographical essay <tei:title level="m">Todeskampf oder Wiederauferstehung der
              Musik</tei:title> (p. 77)</tei:bibl>, Friedrich Vogt was the founder and proprietor of a music school
          at which Violin had been enagaged as a teacher. When Violin left to set up the Schenker Institute, he
          took many of his pupils with him.</tei:note>
        <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Karli</tei:rs>s Erkrankung, Alles das ist viel, selbst für
          <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs>s kampferprobte Nerven. Nun hat er auch noch
        mich dazubekommen. Da die Familien<tei:supplied reason="grammar">,</tei:supplied> denen er mich zugedacht
        hatte, auch der Zeit zum Opfer gefallen sind, bin ich <tei:hi rend="underline">sein</tei:hi> Gast, bis
        meine Einnahmen mir eine eigene Lebenshaltung gestatten werden. Das alles wirkt auch ein wenig hemmend auf
        mich selbst; nicht etwa, das ich fürchtete ihm zur Last zu fallen <tei:supplied reason="grammar">–</tei:supplied> dazu sind unsere Wünsche zu gemeinsam, aber, dass ich noch so arg wenig für die Sache
        tun und leisten kann. Ich habe erst eine Stunde, bekomme allerdings noch zwei dazu, und im <tei:date when="1931-10">Oktober</tei:date> sind wohl noch etliche Schüler fällig, die vorerst bei <tei:rs key="entity-003053" type="person">Vogt</tei:rs> bleiben müssen, da dieser <tei:rs key="entity-003056" type="person">Shylock</tei:rs> auf seinem Pfunde besteht! Wie es mit den Kursen wird, hängt noch an allen
        möglichen Voraussetzungen. Wichtig und entscheidend ist vor Allem der Wiederhall, den der für den <tei:date when="1931-09-06">16. Sept.</tei:date> angesetzte Vortrag: “<tei:title>Hörendes Schaffen – schaffendes
          Hören</tei:title>”, den Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs> auf der Durchreise
        nach <tei:rs key="entity-002510" type="place">Amerika</tei:rs> hier halten wird, bei Fachleuten, Publikum
        und Presse erwecken wird.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">On his trip from
          Berlin to New York in September 1931, Hans Weisse stopped in Hamburg and gave a lecture on Schenker's
          teachings.</tei:note> Die Sache ist ganz gross angelegt, und kostet sehr viel Geld. Die grösste
        Konzertdirektion arrangiert den Vortrag unter ihrem Namen, lädt ein und inseriert in allen Zeitungen (auf
          <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs>s Kosten.) Das “<tei:rs key="entity-002455" type="organization">Schenker-Institut</tei:rs>” hält sich – scheinbar – aus taktischen Erwägungen
        abseits. Es wäre schön, wenn wir gleichzeitig unsere Kurse inserieren könnten, aber aber dazu fehlt das
        Geld. So muss die geladene Presse, worunter einige sind, die uns wohlgesinnt und im Übrigen “im Bilde”
        sind, soweit dies möglich ist, unsere Bestrebungen und die Mission des “<tei:rs key="entity-002455" type="organization">Schenker-Institut</tei:rs>es” im redaktionellen Teil besprechen, was eben unter
        günstigen Umständen viel besser wirken kann, als Annoncen. Hat die gegenwärtige Zeit die Eröffnung des
          <tei:rs key="entity-002455" type="organization">Institut</tei:rs>es einerseits erst ermöglicht, muss man
        auch die grossen <tei:pb n="3"/> Nachteile dieser Zeit in Kauf nehmen. Immerhin sind wir guten Muts, und
        zuversichtlich. Es wird sich schon einrichten! Gesprochen wird schon aller Orten darüber. Eine Anfrage kam
        aus <tei:rs key="entity-002495" type="place">Frankfurt</tei:rs>(!), angeblich auf Grund einer
        Zeitungsnotiz! Ich kann mir’s nur so erklären, dass ein Herr von der <tei:rs key="entity-002537" type="journal">Frankfurter Zeitung</tei:rs>, der mir befreundet ist, diese Notiz lanciert hat. —</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich lebe mich ganz gut hier ein. <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> ist eine bezaubernd schöne Stadt mit einem bezaubernd scheusslichen Klima. Die
        Säuglinge sollen hier schon mit Gummischuhen zur Welt kommen. Leider konnte ich mir noch nicht viel
        sehenswertes betrachten. Zeit hatte ich genug; aber die amerikanische Erscheinungsform der Zeit hat mein
        Portemonnaie noch allzuwenig belastet. —</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich bin fast den ganzen Tag bei <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs>s, übe Klavier, lese und schreibe. Am <tei:date when="1931-09-16">16.</tei:date> assistiere
        ich <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs> am Flügel.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">According to a clipping from an unidentified Hamburg newspaper, preserved
          in the Schenker Scrapbook (<!-- XR -->OC 2/p.84: dated by Jeanette September 17, 1931), Cube did indeed
          assist Weisse at the piano at the lecture, both in a "Bach demonstration" and in a counter-example taken
          from Schoenberg's <tei:title>Suite for Piano</tei:title>, Op. 25. The highly favourable review of the
          event, written by another of Schenker's former pupils (Herman Roth) is said to have augmented the initial
          enrollment at the Schenker Institute (<tei:title level="m">Todeskampf</tei:title>, p. 78).</tei:note>
        Abends trinke ich ein Glas hellen Bieres, und verfüge mich hierauf in meine Gemächer, bei den Eltern eines
        unserer jungen Lehrer. Ich bin nur froh, dass ich mich in <tei:rs key="entity-002621" type="place">Duisburg</tei:rs>, wie es mir noch gut ging, nicht verehelicht habe, das wäre jetzt ein schönes
          <tei:foreign xml:lang="fre">Débacle</tei:foreign>. Meine <tei:rs key="entity-003059" type="person">Verlobte</tei:rs> ist aber ein sehr verständiger Kamerad.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">Cube married Henriette Reich the following year.</tei:note> Wenn das Trauerjahr vorbei
          ist,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot">"Trauerjahr": a reference to the suicide
          of Cube's father Gustav earlier in the year.</tei:note> und ich nicht genug für zweie bei bescheidenen
        Ansprüche haben sollte, so wird sie eben mitarbeiten. Wie viele müssen das heute! —</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Von meiner verflossenen <tei:rs key="entity-002851" type="person">Stiefmutter</tei:rs>
        höre ich nichts Gutes.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09" type="editorial" place="foot">After the death of his
          first wife, Gustav von Cube married a woman much younger than himself, by whom he had another child. The
          engagement initially provoked a hostile reaction among his father's friends and associates in Duisburg.
          (See <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-34_1">OJ 9/34, [1]</tei:ref>, Cube's letter of January 21,
          1925.)</tei:note> Sie scheint ganz aus dem Geleise geworfen. Weiss der Himmel wie das enden wird. Ich
        kann ihr nicht helfen. Ein Glück, dass mein kleiner Bruder bei seiner Grossmutter untergeschlüpft ist.
        —</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">So ist es nun also. Der Kampf geht weiter, und Regen wie Sonnenschein strömen in schöner
        Regelosigkeit auf uns hernieder, wie’s nun mal so der Brauch bei Stadt- und Weltchronik. Mich soll’s nicht
        kümmern. “Twingen lot ick mi nich, segg de Bur, da wollte he sick no ne Floh kratzen, wo he nich
          darankonnte”.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10" type="editorial" place="foot">An attempt to render in dialect
          "Zwingen lasse ich mich nicht, sagt der Bursche, da <tei:supplied reason="clarity">= doch</tei:supplied>
          wollte er noch einen Floh kratzen, wo er nicht darankonnte." ("'I will not be forced <tei:supplied reason="clarity">I cannot be bothered</tei:supplied>,' said the boy, though he wanted to scratch
          another flea<tei:supplied reason="clarity">-bite</tei:supplied> where he could not reach": a variant of
          the proverb of the fox and the sour grapes.)</tei:note> —</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Mit den herzlichsten Grüssen Ihnen und Ihrer Frau <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Gemahlin</tei:rs> bin ich Ihr immergetreuer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143">Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:note type="editorial">top left corner:</tei:note>      
        <tei:lb/><tei:figure type="drawing">
          <tei:graphic url="OJ-9-34_27-p1.jpg" n="thumb" rend="left-img" width="150px" height="203px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
        </tei:figure>
        <tei:lb/><tei:note type="editorial">begining top right:</tei:note><tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-55">Hamburg, Beneckestrasse 2,</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60">c/o <tei:rs key="entity-003092" type="person">Alexander
            Schmidt</tei:rs>.</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-75"><tei:date when="1931-09-08">September 8, 1931</tei:date>
        </tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Most revered, dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>I am sending this letter to you directly to <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>.
        I learned from <tei:rs key="entity-000909" type="person">Violin's sister</tei:rs>, who is staying at the
        moment in <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>, that you were now in <tei:rs key="entity-002578" type="place">Salzburg</tei:rs> and were planning to return to <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs> soon. Instead of following you, it is better that the
        letter await you in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">In the accompanying drawing, I have sought to portray Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs> in caricature, so far as his external appearance has made an impression on
        my sense of line. I hope that he is recognizable. It is a delight to report that <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">his son</tei:rs> shows clear signs of progress recently.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> His temperature has been normal for several days, and he looks
        much fresher and healthier, and is also feeling significantly better. The doctors are very cautious with
        their prognosis, particularly as he remains under influence of treatments; yet they are at the very least
        satisfied with the fact that his suffering has assumed a treatable form. The almost extatic will to
        survive, and the veritably amazing energy of the dear boy will surely play a major part in his recovery! I
        dearly wish for Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs>, with all my heart, that
          <tei:hi rend="underline">this</tei:hi> trial will soon be over for good!</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> We have enough other things to worry about. The economic climate has continued to
        change so precipitously for the worse that the prospects for the "<tei:rs key="entity-002455" type="organization">Schenker Institute</tei:rs>"<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> cannot
        remain unaffected. Material shortages, disagreements with the previous head of the <tei:rs key="entity-003054" type="organization">conservatory</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-003053" type="person">Vogt</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/>
        <tei:rs key="entity-000912" type="person">Karli</tei:rs>'s illness: all this is a great deal, even for
          <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs>'s well-tested nerves. And now he has also me to
        cope with. Since the families with whom he placed me have fallen victim to the times, I am <tei:hi rend="underline">his</tei:hi> guest until my income is sufficient to sustain my own livelihood. This also
        has a somewhat hampering effect on myself; not that I am afraid of becoming a burden on him – for that, our
        interests are too much alike – but rather that I can still be of such dreadfully little use to him, and
        achieve so little. I have just one hour; I expect to get two more, and in <tei:date when="1931-10">October</tei:date> a few pupils will come to me who must first remain with <tei:rs key="entity-003053" type="person">Vogt</tei:rs>: for this <tei:rs key="entity-003056" type="person">Shylock</tei:rs> insists
        on his pound of flesh! How the courses will go depends on all sorts of conditions. What is important and
        crucial, above all, is the way in which professionals, audience and press will react to the lecture
        scheduled for <tei:date when="1931-09-16">September 16</tei:date>, "<tei:title>Creativity through Listening
          – Creative Listening</tei:title>," which Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs>
        will give here en route to <tei:rs key="entity-002510" type="place">America</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> The event has been advertised very widely, and will cost a lot of
        money. The largest concert agency is arranging the lecture under its name, is taking care of the
        invitations, and is placing an advertisement in every newspaper, at <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs>'s expense. (The "<tei:rs key="entity-002455" type="organization">Schenker
          Institute</tei:rs>" will remain in the background, for tactical reasons. It would be nice if, at the same
        time, we could advertise our courses; but for this there is not enough money.) Thus the invited press,
        among which are a few who are sympathetic to us and, moreover, "in the picture" will have to speak of our
        efforts, and the mission of the "<tei:rs key="entity-002455" type="organization">Schenker
          Institute</tei:rs>" in the editorial section, so far as this is possible; under favourable circumstances,
        this will indeed have a better effect than advertisements. If the present time has, on the one hand, made
        possibly the opening of the <tei:rs key="entity-002455" type="organization">Institute</tei:rs> in the first
        place, one must also take <tei:pb n="3"/> the disadvantages of the timing into the balance. At any rate, we
        are of good hope and circumspect. Things will work out! People are already talking about it everywhere. An
        enquiry came from <tei:rs key="entity-002495" type="place">Frankfurt</tei:rs>(!), apparently on account of
        a notice in the newspaper! The only explanation that I can offer for this is that a journalist working for
        the <tei:rs key="entity-002537" type="journal"><tei:title level="j">Frankfurter
          Zeitung</tei:title></tei:rs>, with whom I am on friendly terms, launched this notice.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I am thoroughly getting used to life here. <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> is a bewitchingly beautiful city, with a bewitchingly awful climate; babies ought to be
        born already wearing their galoshes. Unfortunately, I have not yet done much sight-seeing. I had enough
        time, but the American manifestation of time has filled my wallet all too frugally.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I spend almost the whole day at <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs>'s place, practising the piano, reading and writing. On the <tei:date when="1931-09-16">16th</tei:date> I shall assist <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs> at the
          piano.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> In the evening I drink a glass of light beer, and
        walk here to my rooms, in the home of the parents of one of our young teachers. I am only glad that I did
        not get married in <tei:rs key="entity-002621" type="place">Duisburg</tei:rs>, where things were still
        going well for me: that would have been a pretty debacle now. My <tei:rs key="entity-003059" type="person">fiancée</tei:rs> is, however, a very understanding comrade.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> If, when the year of mourning is over,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/>
        I am not earning enough to keep two people with modest needs, she, too, will find a job. How many
          <tei:supplied reason="clarity">married women</tei:supplied> must do that today!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Of my poor <tei:rs key="entity-002851" type="person">stepmother</tei:rs>, I hear nothing
          good.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09" type="footnote"/> She appears to have come off the rails completely.
        Heaven knows how that will end. I cannot help her. It's a blessing that my little <tei:supplied reason="clarity">step-</tei:supplied>brother has found refuge with his grandmother.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">That is the way things are now. The struggle goes on; and rain and sunshine stream down
        on us with fine unpredictability, as now seems to be the custom in this city, and in the world at large. I
        should not worry: "'I will not force myself,' said the boy, yet he wanted to scratch another
          flea<tei:supplied reason="clarity">-bite</tei:supplied>, where he could not reach."<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn10" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">With most affectionate greetings to you and your <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs>, I am your ever-faithful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143">Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>