<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2721" sdoID="OJ-9-12_2">OJ 9/12, [2]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="CB" scope="sole">Carl Bamberger's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2022</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2022</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>


    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2011-06-09" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-000034">BambergerC ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Carl Bamberger to Schenker, dated February 18,
        1925</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1925-02-18T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2022-04-09</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Bamberger reports that after six months of repetiteur work he has been granted
        some conducting. -- He laments the lack of musical education of the Danzig citizens, and its
        impact on the theater's repertory. Talent is not appreciated by the theater's
        administrators. He wants to move on from Danzig, suggesting Dessau. -- He reports on his
        reading of Der Tonwille, and his success in encouraging others to subscribe. -- He asks
        Schenker a question about Schubert's song "Wohin?"</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>


      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000034">CBamberger</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#CB"/><tei:rs type="place"
            key="entity-003999">Danzig</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1925-02-18">18. Februar
            1925</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Sehr ve<tei:supplied reason="omission">r</tei:supplied>ehrter,
          lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>![1]</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Es ist ein halbes Jahr vorüber<tei:supplied reason="omission">ge</tei:supplied>gangen,
        ohne <tei:sic>ein</tei:sic> irgend ein Lebenszeichen von mir. Meinen Sie nicht, daß ich
        deshalb auch Ihrer vergessen habe, obwohl es so scheinen könnte.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Es war eine Zeit voll – vielfach überflüssiger – Theaterarbeit, die ich
        nur auch durchmachen und erleben musste.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Das Weihnachtsmärchen, das ich dirigierte, brachte mir guten Erfolg: ich
        bekomme seither alle Operetten zu dirigieren, die wir hier herausbringen. Es war für mich
        eine kleine Befriedigung, daß es mir gelang, <tei:pb n="2"/> im Weihnachtsmärchen, gute
        Musiker zu verwenden, was erst – natürlicherweise – auf Widerstand stieß. Der Erfolg blieb
        nicht aus und der Intendant sah ein, daß ich Recht behalten hatte und war sichtlich
        befriedigt und erfreut.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Das Volk in Danzig ist nämlich in musikalischen Dingen das unerzogenste,
        das Sie sich denken können. Nur spießerische Bürger sind hier zu Hause, die an nichts
        denken, als an den Schnaps und an Weiber! Jetzt sehe ich erst, was Wien für eine Stadt ist!
        Jeder schwingt doch dort mit, mit der Musik, die gespielt wird. Hier ist der
            <tei:title><tei:hi rend="underline">Fidelio</tei:hi></tei:title>[entity-002541] ganz
        leer, 6 Leute sind im Theater, und die dummste Operette macht ein ausverkauftes Haus. Sie
        können sich denken, daß dadurch der Spielplan sehr darunter leidet. Das ist nun sehr
        traurig! Bis jetzt kein Mozart[entity-000612]!!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="3"/> So kommts auch, daß ich in der letzten Zeit einen
        reichlichen widerwärtigen Eckel vor dem „Theatergeschäft“ empfinde, so wie ichs nie empfand.
        Gerade seitdem ich dirigiert habe; Das Orchester – eigentlich das wesentlichste für die
        Arbeit – spielt gerne unter mir und musiziert gerne mit mir. Neulich sagte mir ein Geiger zu
        meiner großen Freude: „Her Bamberger, ich weiß nicht woran das liegt, wenn Sie dirigieren,
        können wir etwas, was wir sonst nie können, wir können den <tei:hi rend="underline">Bogen
          ausstreichen</tei:hi>.“ Das berichte ich Ihnen nicht aus Eigendünkel, bloß aus dem Gefühl
        der freudigen Dankbarkeit; ich weiß doch zu gut, wie oft wir über diese Art des
        Orchestermusizieren gesprochen haben, wie ich dies alles nun Ihnen danke. —</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="4"/> Brennend gerne würde ich im nächsten Jahre eine
        Dirigentenstelle annehmen. Wie das anstellen? Hier hat sich schon erreignet, daß mein
        Kollege der Vorstellungen an mich zum Dirigieren abgibt, das im letzten Moment zurückgezogen
        hat, weils ihm nicht angenehm war, daß ichs besser dirigiere, als er. Die Dinge, die ich nie
        geglaubt, muss ich jetzt alle am eigenen Leibe erfahren. Ich könnte hier im nächsten Jahre
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">bestenfalls</tei:add> 3. Kapellmeister werden, der
        hauptsächlich Operetten einstudiert u. dirigiert.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Die Intendanten sehen selten auf die Begabung eines Menschen, sondern
        meist auf das Alter u. die „Theatererfahrung“ – die sie für etwas so wichtiges halten.
        Wenn’s nach dem Intendantenzug, konnte ich im nächsten Jahre wieder so korrepetieren, wie
        heuer u. 30 Mal das Weihnachtsmärchen dirigieren. Entsetzlich!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="5"/> Ich berichtete Ihnen so viel von mir. Nun genug dieser
        öden Scheußlichkeiten. Ich wollte Ihnen damit nur sagen, daß ich der Alte geblieben bin und
        noch immer meine Ziele wo anders suche als im namhaften Theaterkapellmeister.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">– Die „<tei:title>Tonwillen</tei:title>[entity-001739]“ habe ich erhalten
        und bereits das meiste gelesen. Ich freue mich innig, über die Veröffentlichung des
          <tei:title>Matthäuspassion</tei:title>[entity-001172] – Einleitungschores.[2] In Danzig
        habe ich bisher 3 Abonnenten gewonnen, die glühendes Interesse für die Sache an den Tag
        legen. Nach Finnland[entity-006634] sandte ich wieder eine <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >Menge</tei:hi> Ihrer Werke zu Kilpinen[entity-000434], der mir in beiliegendem Brief
        dankte. Ich sende ihn Ihnen, damit Sie lesen, daß es doch verstreut im hohen Norden Menschen
          <tei:pb n="6"/> gibt, die Sinn für <tei:unclear reason="reading">gerade</tei:unclear>
        Dinge besitzen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Frau Sachs[entity-003847] – die <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">geschiedene</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ehemalige</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> Gattin D^r^ Rob. Brünauer[entity-000107]s, hat auf meine Veranlassung auch den
          <tei:title>Tonwille</tei:title>n abonniert.[3]</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Besonderen Eindruck machte mir in Heft 2/3 = 8/9 der kurze Aufsatz
        „Erläuterungen“,[4] der <tei:add place="interlinear-above">in</tei:add> so wundervoller
        Weise, das Urwesen alles Kompositorischen darlegt ich meine damit in erster Linie <tei:note
          type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="italic">music example: treble stave,
            vertical C major chord</tei:hi></tei:note> u. <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"
            ><tei:hi rend="italic">music example: treble stave, arpeggiated C major
          chord</tei:hi></tei:note>; das habe ich eigentlich nie so klar gesehen, wie
        jetzt!!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ich danke Ihnen ganz besonders für dies Stückchen reinsten Goldes!! </tei:p>

      <tei:p>——————</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Wie nun wegkommen von Danzig? Ich dachte schon an Dessau[entity-002788].
        Dort ist Hoesslin[entity-000381] General-Musikdirektor. Würden Sie, falls ich mich bewerbe,
        ihm ein paar Zeilen über mich schreiben? Das wäre viel wert für mich. – Was hören Sie
        übrigens von Hupka[entity-000399]? Ist <tei:pb n="7"/>
        <tei:sic>Er</tei:sic> schon Kapellmeister? Meines Wissens wollte er ja nach
        Köln[entity-002604].</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Diese äußerlichen Kämpfe sind mir sehr widerlich, nun darf man nicht
        locker lassen, um einen Arbeitsboden zu gewinnen.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Die Abgeschnittenheit Danzigs durch Polen vom deutschen Reich macht sich
        in jeder Beziehung unangenehm bemerkbar. Bis man nur eine Partitur oder ein Buch über die
        Grenze <tei:add place="interlinear-above">bekommt</tei:add>: Die Zeit und die Zölle, die es
        benötigt</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">— Wie gehts Ihnen? Sind die Radierungen von Viktor Hammer[entity-000327]
        schon veröffentlicht? Ich würde gerne eine bei mir haben. Es waren ja numerierte Exemplare
        geplant. Hoffentlich ist noch eines für mich übrig! <tei:pb n="8"/> Sprachen Sie
        Furtwängler[entity-000268]?[5] Ist er schon mutige<tei:supplied reason="omission"
          >r</tei:supplied> geworden? In der „<tei:title>Musik</tei:title>[entity-002556]“ las ich
        jüngst einen gegnerisch abgefassten Artikel gegen Sie und Ihr Werk.[6] Die Gegenbeweise sind
        leide Beweise grober A-Musikalität des Unterzeichneten (dessen Name mir entfiel.) –
        –</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Am Schlusse eine Frage (verzeihen Sie mir die Belästigung)<tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">.</tei:supplied> Ich begleitete neulich<tei:del rend="overstrike"
          >e</tei:del> einen Sänger „Wohin?“ von Schubert[entity-000803]. Er nahm<tei:del
          rend="overstrike">e</tei:del> es recht langsam, mit der Behauptung, das Tempo sei ja
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">mit</tei:add> „Mäßig” bezeichnet; <tei:hi
          rend="double-underline">ich</tei:hi> behaupte das „Mäßig“ bezieht sich hier durchaus auf
        die 2/4 Bewegung, <tei:del rend="overstrike">wo daß die</tei:del> u. nicht auf die
        1/16-Triolen in der Begleitung?!!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Mit sehr herzlichen Grüßen an Sie und Ihre <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000771">Frau Gemahlin</tei:rs>
        </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Ihr aufrichtig dankbarer</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000034">Carl
            Bamberger</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:dateline rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#CB"/><tei:rs type="place"
            key="entity-003999">Danzig</tei:rs>, <tei:date when="1925-02-18">February 18,
            1925</tei:date></tei:dateline>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Greatly revered, dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Master</tei:rs>,[1]</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Six months have passed without any sign of life from me. Do not think on that account
        that I have forgotten about you, although it may seem that way.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">It has been a time full of – oftentimes trivial – theater work that I just
        simply had to grin and bear.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">The Christmas show that I conducted earned me plenty of success: since
        then, I have been assigned all the operettas that we put on here. It was a source of
        satisfaction to me that <tei:pb n="2"/> in the Christmas show I got to use good musicians,
        to which – as you might expect – I at first encountered resistance. The success did not
        fade, and the Intendant realized that I had been right and was manifestly gratified and
        delighted.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">The folk of Danzig are musically the most poorly educated that you could
        imagine. The people who live here are stick-in-the-mud types who think of nothing but
        Schnapps and women. Now for the very first time I realize what a city Vienna is! There
        everyone really resonates with the music that is played. Here, for <tei:hi rend="underline"
            ><tei:title level="m">Fidelio</tei:title></tei:hi> the house is totally empty, a mere
        six people in the audience; whereas the stupidest operetta makes for a sell-out. You can
        imagine how much the repertory suffers, with that sort of response. It is so very sad! So
        far, no Mozart!!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="3"/> That’s how it comes about that in recent times I have been
        overcome by a sickening loathing for the theater business, such as I have never before felt.
        Precisely since I have been conducting <tei:supplied reason="clarity">them</tei:supplied>,
        the orchestra – which is the core of our work – like playing under me, and enjoy making
        music with me. Recently one violinist remarked to me, to my great joy: “Mr. Bamberger, I
        don’t know how it comes about; but when you conduct, we are able to do something that we
        never otherwise can: we can <tei:hi rend="underline">bow expansively</tei:hi>.” I report
        that to you not out of conceit but purely from a feeling of joyous gratitude. I remember all
        too well how often we used to speak about this art of orchestral music-making – I have you
        to thank now for all of this. —</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="4"/> I would fervently love to take on a conducting position in
        the coming year. How do I set about that? Already it has happened that my colleague has
        assigned me to the conducting of performances that he has at the last minute withdrawn
        because he doesn’t like the feeling that I conduct better than he does. I have now had to
        experience at first hand things that I would never have believed possible. Here I could in
        the coming year <tei:add place="interlinear-above">at best</tei:add> achieve third
        conductor, whose job it is primarily to study and conduct operettas.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">The intendants rarely take into account a person’s talent, mostly just
        their age and “theatrical experience,” which they value so very highly. If it were left to
        the intendants, in the next year I could repetiteur as much as I do today, and conduct the
        Christmas show thirty times. Horrendous!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="5"/> I’ve reported so much of myself to you. Now, enough of
        these abominable matters. I only wanted to tell you that I remain my old self and continue
        to set me sights on the role of conductor elsewhere at one of the prestigious opera
        houses.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">– I have received the issues of <tei:title level="j">Der
          Tonwille</tei:title>, and have read most of their contents already. I take deep pleasure
        in the article on the <tei:title level="m">St. Matthew Passion</tei:title> introductory
        chorus.[2] In Danzig I have so far procured three subscriptions, which are evincing keen
        interest in your cause. I again sent a <tei:hi rend="underline">bundle</tei:hi> of your
        works to Kilpinen in Finland, who thanked me in the enclosed letter. I send it to you so
        that you may read that there are people scattered about in the far north, <tei:pb n="6"/>
        who possess a feeling for precisely such things.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Mrs Sachs – the <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">divorced</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">former</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> wife of Dr. Robert Brünauer – has at my inducement taken out a subscription for
          <tei:title level="j">Der Tonwille</tei:title>.[3]</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">What made a specially strong impression on me was the short article in
        issue 2/3 = 8/9 entitled “Elucidations,”[4] which lays out <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">in</tei:add> so wonderful a fashion the ultimate essence of all
        composition – I have in mind particularly <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi
            rend="italic">music example: treble stave, vertical C major chord</tei:hi></tei:note>
        and <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="italic">music example: treble
            stave, arpeggiated C major chord</tei:hi></tei:note>; never before have I seen that so
        clearly as now!!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Thank you most especially for this little piece of purest gold!!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>——————</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:supplied reason="clarity">The question</tei:supplied> now is how to
        get away from Danzig? I’ve thought already of Dessau. Hoesslin is General Music Director
        there. Would you, if I apply, pen a few lines to him about me? That would be very valuable
        to my case. – By the way, what do you hear of Hupka? Does <tei:pb n="7"/> he already have a
        conducting post? To my knowledge, he really wanted to go to Cologne.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">These petty battles are highly obnoxious to me; this is not the time to
        hold back from seeking a haven for one’s work.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">That Danzig, in Poland, is cut off from the German Empire rears its ugly
        head in all one’s dealings. Before you <tei:add place="interlinear-above">receive</tei:add>
        even just a score or book from across the border, the time you have to wait, and the customs
        duties!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">— How are you? Are Viktor Hammer’s etchings yet released? I would love to
        have one for myself. Numbered copies were planned. I hope there may still be one for me!
          <tei:pb n="8"/> Have you spoken to Furtwängler? Has he already shown any greater
        willingness?[5] In <tei:title level="j">Die Musik</tei:title> I recently read an
        antagonistic article against you and your work.[6] His adversarial comments are sorry
        evidence of the sheer lack of musicality of the writer (whose name escapes me.) – –</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">To finish with, a question (forgive me for bothering you). I recently
        accompanied a singer in Schubert’s “Wohin?” He took it really slowly on the grounds that the
        tempo marking is “moderato.” <tei:hi rend="double-underline">I myself</tei:hi> countered
        that the “Mässig” applies solely to the 2/4 movement <tei:supplied reason="clarity">in the
          voice</tei:supplied>, and not to the sixteenth triplets in the accompaniment?!!</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">With most cordial greetings to you and your <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000771">wife,</tei:rs>
        </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">your sincerely grateful</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000034">Carl
            Bamberger</tei:rs></tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
