<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="471" sdoID="OJ-9-34_25">OJ 9/34, [25]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="FEvC" scope="sole">Felix-Eberhard von Cube's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
   <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2011-10-03" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002775">Cube ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated May 9, 1931</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1931-05-09T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-11-09</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Cube describes his feelings and final dealings with the Conservatory in Duisburg,
    and preparations for work with Violin in Hamburg; he reports on his two best pupils, Erich Voss
    and Lieselotte Müller.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000143">Cube</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-35">Duisburg, Gellerstr. 2.</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:date when="1931-05-09">9.V.31.</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-15">Sehr verehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this
      letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at <!-- XR -->OJ 4/4, p. 3616, May 11, 1931: "Von v.
      Cube (Br.): erster längerer Bericht; nun werde er <tei:gap reason="illegible" extent="1" unit="words"/><!--  geliebkost? - ask Bill --> eingeladen u. wegen seines Erfolges in Hamburg
      sogar von Collegen gefeiert. Schließt den Brief mit einen Witz." ("From von Cube (letter):
      first longish report: now he is <tei:gap reason="illegible" extent="1" unit="words"/> invited
      and on account of his success in Hamburg he is even fêted by his colleagues. Ends the letter
      with a joke.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Allgemach habe ich mich wieder in den – nun etwas veränderten Alltag
    hineingefunden. Ich beginne bereits die Stadt <tei:rs key="entity-002621" type="place">Duisburg</tei:rs> etwas wie aus der Entfernung zu betrachten, denn länger als etwa sieben oder
    acht Wochen werde ich nicht mehr hier sein. Am <tei:date when="1931-08-01">1. August</tei:date>
    trete ich in <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> bei Herrn Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs> an, um meinen Teil an den nötigen Vorarbeiten
    zu leisten. Am <tei:date when="1931-09-01">1. September</tei:date> geht es dann los.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The Schenker Institute in Hamburg was due to
     open on September 1, 1931</tei:note> Vorher, in den Pfingstferien<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Pentecost Sunday was May 24 in 1931.</tei:note> gibt es noch eine
    kurze Besprechung in <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>, darnach ich
    meine Vorbereitungen treffe. Dies werde ich sehr wahrscheinlich mit einem 3–4 wöchigen
    Erholungsaufenthalt in <tei:hi rend="underline">Oberösterreich</tei:hi> verbinden <tei:pb n="2"/> (seit drei Jahren der erste Urlaub), wo ich bei Bekannten eingeladen bin. Am <tei:rs key="entity-002780" type="organization">Duisburger Konservatorium</tei:rs> habe ich bereits
    gekündigt, wobei man mich zuvorkommenderweise von dem vertrags’chen Termin (<tei:date when="1931-10">Oktober</tei:date>) entbunden hat. Einige Genugtuung bereitet mir die Tatsache,
    dass mein Posten nicht so leicht zu besetzen ist. Gute Aussichten hat ein Anwärter aus <tei:rs key="entity-002840" type="place">Düsseldorf</tei:rs>. Sei dem wie ihm sei, ich habe im
    pädagogisch praktischen Sinne hier eine ganze Menge gelernt. —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Alle Welt hofiert mich jetzt. Gerade die, die am grimmigsten gegen mich
    gewühlt haben, sind jetzt eitel Wohlwollen und Zuvorkommenheit. Sie haben “schon immer” gesagt,
    das <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Schenker</tei:rs> eine fabelhafte Sache sei, und
    sie hätten “gerade jetzt” sich entschlossen, ernsthaft an die Sache “ranzugehen”. Zu schade,
    dass ich nun gerade wegfahre! Mein “grosser” Konkurrent <tei:rs key="entity-003047" type="person">Eccarius</tei:rs> hat mir sogar das ver- <tei:pb n="3"/> trauliche “Du”
    angeboten. Es juckte mich in allen Eingeweiden zu sagen: “Sie werden lachen, ich bleibe hier!”
    —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Der Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000919" type="person">Voss</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Erich Voss had came into contact with Cube in
     Cologne, then went to Vienna in the hope of studying with Schenker but, unable to make ends
     meet, returned to north Germany. See letters and postcards <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-34_18">OJ 9/34, [18]</tei:ref>, May 14 and <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-7a_23">OJ 5/7a, [23]</tei:ref>, May 15, 1929; <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-7a_24">OJ 5/7a, [24]</tei:ref>, July 6, <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-7a_25">OJ 5/7a, [25]</tei:ref>, July 14, and <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-34_19">OJ 9/34, [19]</tei:ref>, July 18, 1929; <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-7a_29">OJ 5/7a, [29]</tei:ref>, June 8, and <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-34_21">OJ 9/34, [21]</tei:ref>, June 25, 1930)</tei:note> entwickelt eine prächtige
    Betriebsamkeit. Er hält Kurse und Arbeitsgemeinschaften ab, gibt Stunden in
     <tei:term>Kontrapunkt</tei:term>, und geht jetzt in <tei:rs key="entity-003049" type="place">Dortmund</tei:rs> aufs Seminar um einesteils sich aufs Staatsexamen vorzubereiten,
    andererseits um “<tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Schenker</tei:rs>-Zellen” zu bilden,
    wie er sich ausdrückt. Er besitzt genügend Kenntnisse und überzeugende Redekunst, um Erfolge
    haben zu können. Wir haben <tei:term>Harmonie</tei:term>, <tei:term>Stimmführung</tei:term> und
    manches andere gearbeitet, und er hat sich gut entwickelt, und wird der Sache sehr nützlich
    sein! Leider ist er noch etwas von westfälischem, ja, beinahe holländischen Eigenschaften
    belastet, doch wird er diese schon noch ablegen lernen. Ein vorzügliches Horosokop stelle ich
    meiner besten Schülerin <tei:rs key="entity-003048" type="person">Lieselotte
     Müller</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Lieselotte Müller
     is not mentioned anywhere else in the Cube-Schenker correspondence. His fondness for using
     Schenkerian terminology notwithstanding, it is not clear what Cube means by this. (If Müller
     has the better musical mind, and in this sense more "fundamental," then the expression should
     perhaps be reversed: Voss = Dreiklang, Müeller = Stufe.)</tei:note> die schon beinahe
    unheimlich begabt ist. Auch sie muss sich <tei:pb n="4"/> zunächst die Staatsprüfung gefallen
    lassen, dann werde ich Himmel und Hölle in Bewegung setzen, um sie in <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> weiter unterrichten zu können. <tei:rs key="entity-000919" type="person">Voss</tei:rs> ist ein guter Arbeiter, die <tei:rs key="entity-003048" type="person">Müller</tei:rs> aber verhält sich zu ihm wie ein
     <tei:term>Dreiklang</tei:term> zu einer <tei:term>Stufe</tei:term>. Um diese beiden willen hat
    sich <tei:rs key="entity-002621" type="place">Duisburg</tei:rs> schon gelohnt. Schade, dass die
     <tei:rs key="entity-003048" type="person">Müller</tei:rs> so sehr jung und noch ganz am Anfang
    ist! —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Die Ironie des Schicksals hat es gebracht, dass es mir nun ausgerechnet die
    letzten zwei Monate hier noch besonders dreckig gehen soll. Mit <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> vor Augen ertrage ich es mit Humor, und lasse mich im Übrigen von
    allen Leuten zum Essen einladen. <tei:foreign xml:lang="fre">À propos</tei:foreign>
    Geschäftslage: Zwei Herren fahren von <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs>
    nach <tei:rs key="entity-002495" type="place">Frankfurt</tei:rs>; beide sprechen kein Wort. Kurz
    vor <tei:rs key="entity-002495" type="place">Frankfurt</tei:rs> seufzt der eine tief auf. Darauf
    der andere: “Mir wollen Sie was erzählen?”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Presumably, the punch-line indicates that things are so bad in Germany that two
     businessen cannot find anything to talk about even on a long train trip.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Einstweilen beste Grüsse Ihnen und Ihrer Frau <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Gemahlin</tei:rs>, und sofort nach <tei:date when="1931-05-24">Pfingsten</tei:date> folgt genauer Bericht von</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-45">Ihrem</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143">Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine rend="indent-35">Duisburg, Gellerstraße 2.</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:date when="1931-05-09">May 9, 1931</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-15">Most revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Little by little I have found myself again in the – somewhat modified –
    pattern of daily life. I am already beginning to view the city of <tei:rs key="entity-002621" type="place">Duisburg</tei:rs> somewhat from a distance, for in about seven or eight weeks I
    shall no longer be here. On the <tei:date when="1931-08-01">first of August</tei:date> I arrive
    in <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> at Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Violin</tei:rs>'s, to accomplish my part of the necessary
    preliminary work. On the <tei:date when="1931-09-01">first of September</tei:date>, things
     begin.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> Before that, during the Pentecost
     holidays,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> I have a short meeting in <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>; then I shall get on with my preparations. I
    will most probably combine this with a three-to-four-week period of relaxation in <tei:hi rend="underline">Upper Austria</tei:hi>
    <tei:pb n="2"/> (my first holiday for three years), where I have an invitation from friends. I
    have already given notice to the <tei:rs key="entity-002780" type="organization">Duisburg
     Conservatory</tei:rs>, whereby I have been courteously relieved of my obligations to the end of
    my contract (<tei:date when="1931-10">October</tei:date>). The fact that my post will not be so
    easy to fill afforded me some satisfaction; a candidate from <tei:rs key="entity-002840" type="place">Düsseldorf</tei:rs> has good prospects <tei:supplied reason="clarity">to be
     appointed to it</tei:supplied>. All things considered, I have learned quite a lot in a
    pedagogically practical sense.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Everyone is now courteous to me. The very people who agitated most
    unpleasantly against me now show me vain goodwill and courtesy. They have said "all along" that
     <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Schenker</tei:rs> is a fabulous thing, and they were
    about to decide "precisely at this time" to "get going" with it. What a pity that I am leaving
    at this very moment! My "great" rival <tei:rs key="entity-003047" type="person">Eccarius</tei:rs> even offered to address me with the <tei:pb n="3"/> intimate "Du". I had a
    feeling in my gut to want to say: "You shall laugh: I am staying here!"</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Mr <tei:rs key="entity-000919" type="person">Voss</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> is developing a splendid enterprise. He arranges
    courses and working groups, gives lessons in <tei:term>counterpoint</tei:term>, and is now going
    to the Seminar in <tei:rs key="entity-003049" type="place">Dortmund</tei:rs>, partly to prepare
    for the state examination, partly to form "<tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">Schenker</tei:rs> cells," as he likes to call them. He has enough knowledge and convincing
    oratorical skills to be successful. We have worked on <tei:term>harmony</tei:term>,
     <tei:term>voice-leading</tei:term> and many other things, and he has developed well; he will be
    very useful in the matter. Unfortunately he is still encumbered by Westphalian – Dutch, one
    might almost say – qualities, but he will soon learn to cast these off. I envisage an excellent
    future for my best pupil, <tei:rs key="entity-003048" type="person">Lieselotte
     Müller</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> who is already unusually
    talented. She, too, must <tei:pb n="4"/> first pass the state examination; then I will move
    heaven and earth so that she can continue in <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs> as a teacher. <tei:rs key="entity-000919" type="person">Voss</tei:rs> is a
    good worker; but <tei:rs key="entity-003048" type="person">Müller</tei:rs> is to him as a
     <tei:term>triad</tei:term> to a <tei:term>harmonic degree</tei:term>. Just on account of these
    two, <tei:rs key="entity-002621" type="place">Duisburg</tei:rs> was worth it. A pity that
     <tei:rs key="entity-003048" type="person">Müller</tei:rs> is so very young, and at the very
    beginning!</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">The irony of fate is that things will be particularly unpleasant for me
    during my last two months here. With <tei:rs key="entity-002589" type="place">Hamburg</tei:rs>
    ahead of me, I can bear it with good humour; and moreover I accept everyone's invitation to
    dinner. <tei:foreign xml:lang="fre"><tei:hi rend="italic">À propos</tei:hi></tei:foreign> of the economic situation: Two
    gentlemen are travelling from <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place">Berlin</tei:rs> to
     <tei:rs key="entity-002495" type="place">Frankfurt</tei:rs>; neither speaks a word. Shortly
    before they are to arrive in <tei:rs key="entity-002495" type="place">Frankfurt</tei:rs>, one of
    them sighs deeply. The other replies: "Did you want to tell me something?"<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">For the time being, best wishes to you and your <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs>; and immediately after <tei:date when="1931-05-24">Pentecost</tei:date> you will get a more precise report from</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-45">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143">Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>