<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="450" sdoID="OJ-9-35_1">OJ 9/35, [1]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="GvC" scope="major">G von Cube</tei:handNote>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="major">printed</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2011</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2011-06-09" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002866">CubeG ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Gustav von Cube to Schenker, dated September 7, 1925</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1925-09-07T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-06-09</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Finding himself adversely affected by the current financial crisis, Gustav von
    Cube asks Schenker to help find work for his son Felix, to help help him finance his
    studies.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Forstschritte; progress; Studium; study; Verhältnisse; conditions; Sorgen; troubles;
    Schüler; pupils</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-002866">CubeG</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">printed letterhead, all in double
      rule-frame:</tei:note>
     <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="printed"/>PROFESSOR DR. ING. GUSTAV VON CUBE UND ARTHUR
      BUCHLOH </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>ARCHITEKTEN B.D.A. </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>DUISBURG A/RH. </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>A. E. G.-HAUS SONNENWALL </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>FERNSPRECHER NR. 3933 </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">and further contact information </tei:note>

    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-60">DEN <tei:date when="1925-09-19"><tei:handShift new="GvC"/>7.
      September 1925.</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-15">Sehr verehrter Herr<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of
      this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/7, p. 2865, September 9, 1925: "Vom Vater
      Cube (Br.): bittet um Schüler für den Jungen." ("From Cube's father (letter): asks for
      students for his son."). </tei:note>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Es lag schon lange in meiner Absicht Ihnen meine dankbare Freude auszudrücken
    über die guten Fortschritte, die mein Sohn <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">Felix</tei:rs> dank Ihrer Bemühungen bis jetzt zu verzeichnen hatte. Er scheint uns beiden
    gleichermaßen ans Herz gewachsen zu sein und wir beiden erhoffen von ihm das Allerbeste. Bis
    jetzt ist es mir vergönnt gewesen, wenn auch mit Schwierigkeiten ihm sein Studium zu
    ermöglichen. Nun aber beginnen die wirtschaftlichen Verhältnisse mich für die allernächste
    Zukunft mit großen Sorgen zu erfüllen und ich sehe den Moment kommen, wo ich nicht mehr in der
    Lage bin für <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">Felix</tei:rs> die immerhin
    beträchtlichen Summen für Unterhalt und Studium aufzubringen. Unter diesem Gesichtspunkt möchte
    ich nun an Sie die herzliche Bitte richten meinem Sohn <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">Felix</tei:rs> behilflich zu sein die Möglichkeit zu erhalten, sich selbst Geld zu verdienen,
    sei es durch Stundengeben oder durch andere Betätigungen in seinem Fache.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">No paragraph-break in original. </tei:note>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Es giebt sicherlich viele jungen Leute, die neben ihrem Musikstudium Zeit und
    Gelegenheit finden etwas zu verdienen. Es liegt mir viel daran, daß <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">Felix</tei:rs> seine Studien bei Ihnen beendiget, wenn er es ermöglichen könnte
    dieses Ziel zu erreichen ohne daß ich ihn restlos aus meiner Tasche zu erhalten brauche, so wäre
    es ja sehr erfreulich. Sie haben sicher so viel Interesse an ihn, daß Sie in richtiger
    Beurteilung meiner Lage eine große Sorge von der Seele genommen würde. <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">Felix</tei:rs> ist ja eine sehr bescheidene Natur und geht
    aus <tei:pb n="2"/> reiner Passion ganz in seinem Berufe auf. Sein guter Humor wird ihn auch
    über manche Conflikte hinwegbringen, die sich aus der neuen Situation für ihn ergeben werden.
    Soweit ich es beurteilen kann, hat er ja auch alle Qualitäten ein tüchtiger Musiker zu werden,
    denn es sitzt in ihm, dabei besitzt er auch die künstlerische Bescheidenheit, die sich
    namentlich dann äußert wenn er voller Begeisterung und Bewunderung von Ihnen als seinem großen
    Lehrer spricht. Sie würden, verehrter Meister, wie gesagt, mir einen großen Gefallen tun, wenn
    Sie sich in besagtem Sinne für <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">Felix</tei:rs>
    verwenden würden. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Mit herzlichen Grüßen</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr ergebenster</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000144">G. v.
     Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">printed letterhead, all in double
      rule-frame:</tei:note>
     <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="printed"/>PROFESSOR Dr.Eng. GUSTAV VON CUBE AND ARTHUR
      BUCHLOH </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>ARCHITECTS B.D.A. </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>DUISBURG ON THE RHINE </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>A. E. G.-HAUS SONNENWALL </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>TELEPHONE NO. 3933 </tei:addrLine>
     <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">and further contact information </tei:note>

    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:date when="1925-09-19"><tei:handShift new="GvC"/>September
      7, 1925</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-15">Highly revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Professor</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">For[1] a long time I had intended to express my thanks to you about the good
    progress that my son <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">Felix</tei:rs> has hitherto been
    able to demonstrate, thanks to your efforts. He seems to have grown very fond of the two of us,
    in equal measure, and we are hoping for the very best for him. Until now, I have been fortunate
    in being able to provide for his studies, albeit with difficulty. Now the financial conditions
    have begun to create great troubles for me for the foreseeable future, and I can see the moment
    arrive in which I am no longer in a position to find the not inconsiderable sum of money needed
    to maintain him and support his studies. In view of this situation, I should like to direct my
    sincere request to you to be of assistance to my son <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">Felix</tei:rs>, so that he may be able to look after himself by earning his own money, whether
    it be by giving lessons or through some other activity in his profession.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">There must, for sure, be many young people who, alongside the study of music,
    find the time and opportunity to earn something. It matters a great deal to me that <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">Felix</tei:rs> completes his studies with you; if it were
    possible for him to achieve this goal without constantly needing to dig into my pockets, that
    would indeed be very satisfying. You are, of course, sufficiently concerned about him that,
    given a proper judgement of my position, you would relieve me of a great concern. <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">Felix</tei:rs> is indeed a very modest personality, and is
    growing <tei:pb n="2"/> in his profession with pure passion. His good sense of humor will keep
    him from many conflicts that will arise from the new situation. So far as I am able to judge, he
    has all the qualities to become an excellent musician, for he has innate gifts for it; in
    addition he also possesses the artistic modesty that expresses itself in particular on the
    occasions when he speaks of you as his great teacher with complete enthusiasm and admiration.
    You will, honored master, do me a great service if you would you would intercede for <tei:rs key="entity-000143" type="person">Felix</tei:rs> in accordance with these thoughts. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">With most cordial greetings, </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your most devoted </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-70"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000144">G. v.
     Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>