<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="466" sdoID="OJ-9-34_19">OJ 9/34, [19]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="FEvC" scope="sole">Felix-Eberhard von Cube's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
   <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2011-08-05" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002775">Cube ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated July 18, 1929</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1929-07-18T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-08-31</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Acknowledges two postcards; no word from Eric Voss; reports on teaching activities; reports on
    composing and sends two sonatas for Schenker's comment.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000143">Cube</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine>Duisburg /Rhld.</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="intent-05">Pulverweg 41.</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-75"><tei:date when="1929-07-18">18.VII.29.</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-25">Sehr verehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at
      <!-- XR -->OJ 4/2, p. 3355, July 20, 1929: "Von v. Cube Paket: 2 Sonaten u. Brief: über neue Pläne; bittet um
      Ratschläge u. um Empfehlung eines Verlags." ("From von Cube, packet: two sonatas and letter: about his new plans;
      asks for advice and for recommendation of a publisher.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Vielen Dank für die beiden Karten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">i.e. <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-7a_24">OJ 5/7a, [24]</tei:ref>, July 6, and <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-7a_25">OJ 5/7a, [25]</tei:ref>, July 14.</tei:note> Von Herrn <tei:rs key="entity-000919" type="person">Voss</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Erich
     Voss: see <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-34_18">OJ 9/34, [18]</tei:ref>, May 14, 1924; <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-7a_23">OJ 5/7a, [23]</tei:ref>, May 15; <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-7a_24">OJ 5/7a, [24]</tei:ref>, July 6; <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-7a_25">OJ 5/7a,
      [25]</tei:ref>, July 14, 1929. Voss does not appear in Schenker's Lesson Books.</tei:note> habe ich seit seinem
    Brief nichts mehr vernommen. Damals schien von finanziellen Schwierigkeiten noch nichts wahrnehmbar. Inzwischen wird
    er – wie so viele – dem wirtschaftlichen „Aufbau“ zum Opfer gefallen sein. Ich hoffe, dass er trotzdem seinen Weg zu
    Ihnen finden wird. —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Hier ist inzwischen die saure Gurken Zeit ausgebrochen. Wir haben 38° im Schatten (soweit von
    Schatten überhaupt gesprochen werden kann) und man tut gut, jede körperliche Bewegung auf das notwendige Minimum zu
    beschränken. Jede freie Stunde wird zur Flucht ins Strandbad benützt. Für die Ernte das gegebene Wetter – mir
    persönlich wäre im Augenblick ein möglichst hartnäckiger Landregen mit etwas polarer Ventilation sympathischer.
    —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Das „Geschäft“ ist auch im Sommerschlaf versunken. Den ganzen Winter, bis jetzt war ich recht
    zufrieden. Augenblicks ist wiedermal flaue Zeit. Wenn ich überhaupt wegfahren kann, wird es wohl nicht weit werden.
    Momentan habe ich im <tei:rs key="entity-002780" type="organization">Konservatorium</tei:rs> 8 Schüler und drei
     <tei:term>Theorieklassen</tei:term>, privat nur drei Schüler. Getragen von der Hoffnung auf bessere Zeiten, kann
    man auch davon leben. —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Meine <tei:rs key="entity-002827" type="composition">zweite Sonate</tei:rs> ist jetzt endlich
    fertig. <tei:pb n="2"/> Ich habe einen neuen Schlusssatz ziemlich rasch komponiert. Es ging wie von selbst, und ich
    glaube nicht dass er schlecht ist. Anbei sende ich Ihnen beide Sonaten; die <tei:rs key="entity-002787" type="composition">erste</tei:rs> kennen Sie ja, bis auf den langsamen Satz, und Teile des Rondos. Die <tei:rs key="entity-002787" type="composition">erste</tei:rs> geht nach <tei:rs key="entity-002479" type="place">Leipzig</tei:rs> zum <tei:rs key="entity-002739" type="organization">C. F. Kahnt-Verlag</tei:rs>, dessen Besitzer,
    Herr <tei:rs key="entity-002965" type="person">Hoffmann</tei:rs>, nicht abgeneigt scheint, sie zu drucken. Erste
    Auflage natürlich ohne Honorar! Die <tei:rs key="entity-002827" type="composition">zweite</tei:rs> möchte ich einem
    grösseren Verlag andrehen. Ich wäre Ihnen <tei:hi rend="underline">sehr</tei:hi> dankbar für Rat- und Vorschläge,
    habe ich doch noch gar keine Verbindung zu solchen Leuten. Wer hat denn Dr. <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs>s und Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000643" type="person">Oppel</tei:rs>s Sachen gedruckt?
    Vielleicht könnte Ihre Begutachtung und die <tei:rs key="entity-002621" type="place">Duisburg</tei:rs>er Kritik (als
    Beweis der „Uraufführung“) doch einen Verleger bewegen<tei:supplied reason="clarity">,</tei:supplied> einen Versuch
    damit zu machen. —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich gehe schon wieder mit neuen Plänen schwanger, indes ist die Hitze zu gross um klare Gedanken
    zu krystallisieren. Auf jedenfall habe ich jetzt nach der Vollendung zweier grösseren Sachen viel Mut und Lust für
    Weiteres. —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Durch meine <tei:rs key="entity-003124" type="person">Schwester</tei:rs> öffnen sich neuerdings
    Perspektiven nach <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place"><tei:hi rend="underline">Berlin</tei:hi></tei:rs>. Im
    Winter fahre ich hin, um die Lage zu sondieren. Bis dahin wird die hohe Protektion bearbeitet. –</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Wenn ich von <tei:rs key="entity-002479" type="place">Leipzig</tei:rs> Antwort habe, schreibe ich
    sofort.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Für heute viele herzliche Grüsse Ihnen und Ihrer Frau <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Gemahlin</tei:rs>, und gute Erholung!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">None of
     Schenker's letters of 1929 speaks of illness; <tei:hi rend="italic">Erholung</tei:hi> here refers merely to the
     general recovery from the stress of the year's activity in Vienna.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-55">Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-65"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143">Felix v. Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine>Duisburg, Rhineland</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="intent-05">Pulverweg 41</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-75"><tei:date when="1929-07-18">July 18, 1929</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-25">Most revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Many thanks for your two cards.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> Since receiving
    his letter, I have heard nothing more from Mr <tei:rs key="entity-000919" type="person">Voss</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> At the time I did not perceive any financial difficulties. In the meantime
    he, like so many others, has probably fallen victim to commercial "development". I hope that he might, in spite of
    this, find his way to you.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Here, in the meantime, the quiet season is in full swing. The temperature is 38° in the shade
    (insofar as one as able to speak of shade at all), and one does well to restrict one's bodily movements to the
    necessary minimum. Every free hour is used for the flight to the beach. It's just the right weather for the harvest;
    personally, I would find a steady downpour, as persistent as possible, with a somwhat polar ventilation, more
    agreeable at the moment.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Business has also sunk into summer sleep. The entire winter, and up to now, I was entirely
    satisfied. At the moment it is again slack time. If I can get away at all, it will probably not be to a far-off
    place. At the moment I have eight pupils and three <tei:term>theory classes</tei:term> at the <tei:rs key="entity-002780" type="organization">Conservatory</tei:rs>, but only three private pupils. Sustained by the hope
    of better times, one can also live on this.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">My <tei:rs key="entity-002827" type="composition">second sonata</tei:rs> is now, finally,
    complete. <tei:pb n="2"/> I wrote a new finale rather quickly. It went almost automatically, and I do not believe
    that it is bad. I am sending you both sonatas herewith; you of course know the <tei:rs key="entity-002787" type="composition">first one</tei:rs>, apart from the slow movement and parts of the rondo. The <tei:rs key="entity-002787" type="composition">first</tei:rs> is being sent to the <tei:rs key="entity-002479" type="place">Leipzig</tei:rs> publishing house of <tei:rs key="entity-002739" type="organization">C. F. Kahnt</tei:rs>, whose
    owner, Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-002965" type="person">Hoffmann</tei:rs>, does not seem disinclined to publish it: for
    the first impression, naturally, there will be no honorarium. For the <tei:rs key="entity-002827" type="composition">second sonata</tei:rs>, I would like to approach a larger publishing house. I would be <tei:hi rend="underline">very</tei:hi> grateful to you for advice and suggestions. Who, for instance, published Dr <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse</tei:rs>'s and Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-000643" type="person">Oppel</tei:rs>'s things? Perhaps a reference from you, together with the <tei:rs key="entity-002621" type="place">Duisburg</tei:rs> reviews (as evidence of the "premiere") could indeed movate a publisher to have a go with
    it.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I am once again pregnant with new plans; at the moment the heat is too great to crystalize clear
    thoughts. In any event, now that two rather large sonatas are finished, I have a lot of courage and appetite for
    further things.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Through my <tei:rs key="entity-003124" type="person">sister</tei:rs>, perspectives are lately
    emerging in <tei:rs key="entity-002501" type="place"><tei:hi rend="underline">Berlin</tei:hi></tei:rs>. I shall go
    there in the winter, to test the waters. Until then, I shall work on obtaining the patronage of important
    people.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">As soon as I have an answer from <tei:rs key="entity-002479" type="place">Leipzig</tei:rs>, I
    will write to you.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">For today, many affectionate greetings to you and your <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs>, and best wishes for your recovery!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-55">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-65"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143">Felix von Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>