<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="463" sdoID="OJ-9-34_15">OJ 9/34, [15]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="FEvC" scope="sole">Felix-Eberhard von Cube's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
   <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2011-08-04" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002775">Cube ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated November 7, 1928</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1928-11-07T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-07-30</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Cube reports his activities in Cologne, especially his work with Heinrich Lemacher, who is a
    "connoisseur of the Urlinie"; reports on his compositions. Will visit Hupka and Albersheim next
    time.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000143">Cube</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine>Duisburg /Rhld.</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="intent-05">Pulverweg 41.</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:date when="1928-11-07">7.XI.28.</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-25">Sehr verehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at
      <!-- XR -->OJ 4/2, pp. 3283–3284, November 13, 1928: "Von Cube (Br.): meldet unerwartete Erfolge in Köln, die
      erfreuliche Hilfe von Braunfels u. Prof. Lemacher; er habe ein Auditorium von etwa 100 Menschen, beginne am 28.
      XI. Eine Eröffnungsrede zum Thema Schubert als Gegenstand einer Kritik, die beiliegt. (Noch hat Prof. Lemacher die
      Wirkung auf das Auditorium nicht wahrgenommen, er dürfte selbst ein Anfänger sein, u. schon drängt er wegen
      einiger Gegenbeispiele z.B. von Bruckner, Wagner.)" ("From Cube (letter): communicates unexpected successes in
      Cologne, the welcome help of Braunfels and Prof. Lemacher; he has an audience of some one hundred people, begins
      on November 28. An opening lecture on the subject of Schubert as the object of a review, which is enclosed. (Prof.
      Lemacher has still not appreciated his effect on the audience; he must himself be a beginner, and is already
      pressing on account of some counter-examples, e.g. Bruckner, Wagner.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Nunmehr kann ich berichten: Die Sache mit <tei:rs key="entity-002604" type="place">Köln</tei:rs>
    lässt sich über alles Erwarten gut an. <tei:rs key="entity-002939" type="person">Braunfels</tei:rs>, der sich
     <tei:hi rend="underline">sehr</tei:hi> schön über Ihr Werk äusserte, unterstützte meinen Plan gleich mit aller
    Autorität. Er attachierte mir als Mitarbeiter Herrn Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-002955" type="person">Lemacher</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Heinrich Lemacher (1891–1966),
     German composer, Professor of Theory at the Hochschule für Musik in Cologne, where he had earlier
     studied.</tei:note> den <tei:term>Theoriegewaltigen</tei:term> der städt. Musikschule, die mit der <tei:rs key="entity-002956" type="organization">Hochschule</tei:rs> vereinigt ist. <tei:rs key="entity-002955" type="person">Lemacher</tei:rs> hat mir die Organisation der Angelegenheit sehr erleichtert. Der Reihe nach stellte
    er mich seinen Seminaristen, sowie den Schul- und Kirchenmusikern vor, worauf ich mein Sprüchlein sagte, und die
    Interessenten sofort festgenagelt wurden. Heute Abend, da der „grosse Chor“ versammelt war, wurde die letzte
    Schlacht geschlagen. <tei:rs key="entity-002939" type="person">Braunfels</tei:rs> selbst führte den Vorsitz, und
    sekundierte mir nach Kräften. Auch die Hauptfragen der Zeiteinteilung und Finanzierung wurden geregelt. Die
    Beteiligung ist sehr erfreulich, ich habe ein Auditorium von etwa hundert Schülern zu erwarten. Es sind vorerst acht
    Vorlesungen festgesetzt; jede Woche eine. Die ersten vier noch vor <tei:date when="1928-12-25">Weihnachten</tei:date> (am <tei:date when="1928-11-28">28.XI.</tei:date> geht’s los), der Rest nach den Ferien. Je
    nach Aufnahme und Bedürfnis(!) soll der Kursus eventuell wiederholt werden. Über die Beteiligung der Lehrerschaft
    bin ich noch im Unklaren, doch denke ich, dass dem Beispiel Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-002955" type="person">Lemacher</tei:rs>s, der sich alles mitzuhören will (er ist immerhin ein <tei:hi rend="underline">Kenner</tei:hi>
    der <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>), noch andere folgen werden. Meine eigenen Ansprüche habe ich im Interesse der
    Sache nicht sehr hochgeschraubt, um die finanziell angestrengten Hochschüler nicht von Anfang an durch zu grosse
    Neubelastung zu vergrämen, immerhin wird mir jeder Monat über hundert Mark einbringen, und ich bin willens und
    gesonnen, an der <tei:rs key="entity-002956" type="organization">Hochschule</tei:rs> noch einmal sehr viel mehr zu
    verdienen. Ich fange gleich mit winzigen <tei:term>Urlinien</tei:term> an, und erläutere Ihre
     <tei:term>Harmonie-</tei:term> und <tei:term>Stimmführungstheorien</tei:term> gleich am lebenden Objekt. Mit der
    Zeit kommen dann schwerere Sachen, und nach Möglichkeit – auch auf Wunsch <tei:rs key="entity-002955" type="person">Lemacher</tei:rs>s – „Gegenbeispiele“, etwa <tei:rs key="entity-000104" type="person">Bruckner</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person">Reger</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000373" type="person">Hindemith</tei:rs>. So
    wird es ganz von selbst kommen, dass es nicht bei den acht Vorlesungen bleibt. Wer erst einmal den Segen <tei:pb n="2"/> der „<tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>“ erfasst hat, der ist ihr auch fürderhin verbunden und verpflichtet.
    —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Damit auch der Humor zu seinem Rechte bekommt, lege ich Ihnen eine Kritik eines <tei:rs key="entity-000803" type="person">Schu<tei:subst>
      <tei:del hand="#FEvC" rend="overwritten">f</tei:del>
      <tei:add hand="#FEvC" place="superimposed">b</tei:add>
     </tei:subst>ert</tei:rs>abends bei, den ich gebührend „eingeleitet“ habe. Es war eine schöne Predigt. Noch heute
    klingen den Leute die Ohren davon. Sie haben’s aber nett hingenommen, und zum Schluss sehr lieb geklatscht. Es hat
    viel Eindruck gemacht, und wildfremde Leute konnten nicht umhin mir ihre Ergriffenheit aus – und die Hand zu
    drücken. Wie meistens hat der Recensent (er ist übrigens seines Zeichens Nationalökonom) das Wenigste
    „mitbegriffen“. Das mit <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs> und <tei:rs key="entity-000104" type="person">Bruckner</tei:rs> war nur ein halber Relativsatz – dennoch konnte er ihn nicht verdauen. Immerhin
    können <tei:hi rend="underline">Sie</tei:hi> mit Leichtigkeit aus der Kritik entnehmen <tei:hi rend="underline">was</tei:hi>, und <tei:hi rend="underline">wie</tei:hi> ich's gesagt habe. Im übrigen waltet in ihr die übliche
    Hilfslosigkeit dem Kern der Dinge gegenüber. Ein „<tei:quote>blutlos-resignierender</tei:quote>“ Essay voll
     „<tei:quote>grosslinigen</tei:quote>“ Kleinverstandes.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Cube may be parodying the words of the review (which does not survive)</tei:note> —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs key="entity-002787" type="composition">Sonate N<tei:hi rend="supralinear"><tei:hi rend="underline">o</tei:hi></tei:hi> 1.</tei:rs> befindet sich bereits im Komponistenwettbewerb. Zu <tei:date when="1929-04-08">Ostern 1929</tei:date> höre ich wieder davon. <tei:rs key="entity-002827" type="composition">N<tei:hi rend="supralinear"><tei:hi rend="underline">o</tei:hi></tei:hi> 2.</tei:rs> geht langsam aber sicher
    ihrem Ende entgegen. Schon skizziere ich einen Allegro-Entwurf zu einem Klavierkonzert. Ich habe wieder zwei
    Privatschüler. Die Lage scheint sich in Besserung zu gefallen. —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Dies für heute. Wie immer werde ich Sie des weiteren über mein „Arbeitszimmer“ auf dem Laufenden
    halten.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Mit herzlichsten Grüssen Ihnen und Ihrer <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Frau
     Gemahlin</tei:rs>, auch <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person"><tei:sic>Vrieslandern</tei:sic></tei:rs> und
     <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hoboken</tei:rs> (ihm schulde ich noch Nachricht)</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">von Ihrem</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-65"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143">Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>

    <tei:p rend="hanging">P.S. <tei:rs key="entity-000399" type="person">Hupka</tei:rs> und Herrn <tei:rs key="entity-000007" type="person">Albersheim</tei:rs> werde ich besuchen sowie ich einen ganzen Tag in <tei:rs key="entity-002604" type="place">Köln</tei:rs> bin.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Cf.
       <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-7a_20">OJ 5/7a, [20]</tei:ref>, October 8, 1928</tei:note></tei:p>

   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine>Duisburg, Rhineland</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine rend="intent-05">Pulverweg 41</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:date when="1928-11-07">November 7, 1928</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-25">Most revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">I can report to you once again: my dealings with <tei:rs key="entity-002604" type="place">Cologne</tei:rs> are going well, beyond all expectation. <tei:rs key="entity-002939" type="person">Braunfels</tei:rs>, who was <tei:hi rend="underline">highly</tei:hi> complimentary about your work, immediately
    threw all his weight behind my plan. He assigned me to work with Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-002955" type="person">Lemacher</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> the <tei:term>theoretical
     heavyweight</tei:term> at the <tei:rs key="entity-002956" type="organization">municipal school of music</tei:rs>,
    which is associated with the Conservatory. <tei:rs key="entity-002955" type="person">Lemacher</tei:rs> made the
    organization of my visit much easier. He introduced his seminar students to me in turn, and also the school and
    church musicians, whereupon I said my little piece and their interest was immediately nailed down. As the "great
    chorus" assembled this evening, the last battle was fought. <tei:rs key="entity-002939" type="person">Braunfels</tei:rs> himself chaired the meeting, and seconded me to the best of his ability. Even the basic
    questions of scheduling and financing were sorted out. Participating in this is very agreeable; I can expect an
    audience of about a hundred students. To begin with, eight lectures have been fixed at the rate of one a week. The
    first four will take place before <tei:date when="1928-12-25">Christmas</tei:date> (we start on <tei:date when="1928-11-28">28 November</tei:date>), the remainder after the holidays. Depending on how they are received and
    what the need is (!), the course might possibly be repeated. Whether or not the teachers will take part is still
    unclear to me, but I believe that others will follow the example of Prof. <tei:rs key="entity-002955" type="person">Lemacher</tei:rs>, who wants to attend everything (he is at any rate a <tei:hi rend="underline">connoisseur</tei:hi> of the <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>). In the interest of the matter, I did not make my own
    demands too great, lest I were to antagonize the financially stretched conservatory students from the outset by
    imposing too great an additional burden. At the very least, however, each month will bring me more than a hundred
    marks, and I am willing and disposed to earn a great deal more at the <tei:rs key="entity-002956" type="organization">Conservatory</tei:rs> once again. I start immediately with tiny <tei:term>voice-leading
     graphs</tei:term>, and explain your theories of <tei:term>harmony</tei:term> and <tei:term>voice-leading</tei:term>
    as regards the living object. Time will then bring more difficult things, and where possible – at <tei:rs key="entity-002955" type="person">Lemacher</tei:rs>'s request – "counter-examples," for instance <tei:rs key="entity-000104" type="person">Bruckner</tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000695" type="person">Reger</tei:rs>,
     <tei:rs key="entity-000373" type="person">Hindemith</tei:rs>. So it may turn out automatically that there will be
    more than eight lectures. Anyone who has understood what a blessing <tei:pb n="2"/> the
     "<tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>" is will, from that time on, be captivated and duty-bound.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">That the humorous side of life may also come into its own right, I enclose a newspaper review of
    a <tei:rs key="entity-000803" type="person">Schubert</tei:rs> evening that I fittingly "introduced". It was nice
    sermon, which is still ringing in people's ears. They were a very appreciative audience, and at the end applauded
    very warmly. It made a big impression, and total strangers could not help expressing their captivation to me and
    shaking my hand. As usual, the reviewer "took in" the least (the way he signed the review, moreover, identified him
    as a national economist). What I said about <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs> and <tei:rs key="entity-000104" type="person">Bruckner</tei:rs> was just half of a relative clause; and still he was unable to
    swallow it. Nevertheless, <tei:hi rend="underline">you</tei:hi> will have an easy time figuring out <tei:hi rend="underline">what</tei:hi> I said and <tei:hi rend="underline">how</tei:hi> I said it; otherwise, the review is
    marked by the usual helplessness regarding the heart of the matter: a "<tei:quote>bloodless, resigning</tei:quote>"
    essay in which the author's intellectual impoverishment is portrayed "<tei:quote>in broad
     strokes</tei:quote>."<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs key="entity-002787" type="composition">Sonata No. 1</tei:rs> has already been entered in
    the composers' competition; I will hear about this again <tei:date when="1929-04-08">next Easter</tei:date>. <tei:rs key="entity-002827" type="composition">No. 2</tei:rs> is moving slowly but surely towards completion. I am already
    sketching a draft of an Allegro for a piano concerto. I again have two private pupils. Things appear to be getting
    better.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">So much for today. As always, I shall keep you in the picture regarding further developments in
    my "workroom".</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">With most affectionate greetings to you and your <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs>, also to <tei:rs key="entity-000922" type="person">Vrieslander</tei:rs> and <tei:rs key="entity-000380" type="person">Hoboken</tei:rs> (whom I still owe some news)</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">from your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-65"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143">Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>

    <tei:p rend="hanging">P.S. I shall visit <tei:rs key="entity-000399" type="person">Hupka</tei:rs> and <tei:supplied reason="clarity">Dr.</tei:supplied>
     <tei:rs key="entity-000007" type="person">Albersheim</tei:rs> the next time I am able to spend an entire day in
      <tei:rs key="entity-002604" type="place">Cologne</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>