<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="373" sdoID="OJ-9-34_9">OJ 9/34, [9]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="FEvC" scope="sole">Felix-Eberhard von Cube's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
   <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2011-04-16" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002775">Cube ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated October 29, 1927</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1927-10-29T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-06-21</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Cube has had 'flu; reports on his [conservatory] teaching of Schenkerian theory
    (though disguised from the authorities), his private teaching, his work in composition; he has
    joined the Reichsverband deutscher Tonkünstler und Musiklehrer. Dunn has sent him his
    translation [of part of Kontrapunkt], which he thinks may serve classroom use better than that
    of Vrieslander. He is enjoying using his radio; sends two Galtür portraits; his father has had a
    son.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000143">Cube</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine>Duisburg, Rhld.</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>Pulverweg <tei:hi rend="underline">41</tei:hi>.</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:date when="1927-10-29">29.X.27.</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-15">Sehr verehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this
      letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at <!-- XR -->OJ 4/1, p. 3130, November 5, 1927: "Von
      Cube die in Galtür gemachten Aufnahmen u. ein langer Bericht über den Stand des Unterrichts."
      ("From Cube, the photographs taken in Galtür, and a long report on how his teaching is
      going.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Schon lange soll dieser Brief geschrieben worden sein. Indes geriet ich in
    die Gewalt des mit Recht sehr unbeliebten <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">Trypanosomus communis
     canensis</tei:foreign>, oder des hundsgemeinen Grippenbazillus,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">"hundsgemein", literally "dog-common", i.e. common or vulgar in a
     nasty sense. Cube translates this into Latin (... communis canensis), emphasizing the
     seriousness of his condition by the use of a verbal joke. (See also following note.)</tei:note>
    und hatte während vier Wochen ausreichende Gelegenheit über die Einwirkungen obbesagten
    Mikroorganismus auf den menschlichen Körper tiefgehende Betrachtungen anzustellen. Jetzt bin ich
    ja soweit wieder im Schwung, und vermag meinen Geschäften nachzugehen, aber noch vor zehn Tagen
    vermeinte ich, teils aus Gummi, teils aus noch nachgiebigeren Substanzen zu bestehen. —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Trotzallemdiesem hat sich in der Zwischenzeit mancherlei ereignet. Gleich
     <tei:pb n="2"/> zwei <tei:term>Theorieklassen</tei:term> auf einmal sind mir anvertraut worden,
    und vielleicht kommt bald eine dritte dazu. Abgesehen von der künstlerischen Befriedigung, die
    mir dieses neue Betätigungsfeld gewährt, werden die Stunden höchst angenehmerweise mit R. M. 6.
    – honoriert, und bedeuten somit eine nicht zu unterschätzende Einnahmequelle. Ich fange ganz
    klein an, mit <tei:term>Harmonie</tei:term>, <tei:term>Formenlehre</tei:term>,
     <tei:term>Gehörbildung</tei:term> und <tei:term>„Orthographie“</tei:term> – alles schöne Namen,
    hinter denen sich nichts anderes verbergen wird, als jene Dinge, die Ihnen und Ihren Schülern am
    Herzen liegen, aber die Herren <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">Professores</tei:foreign><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Cube uses the Latin form of the plural,
     rather than the German "Professoren", to emphasize the pedantic nature of the conservatory
     authorities.</tei:note> wollen „Lehrpläne“ sehen; gut, so macht man halt welche!
    Selbstverständlich wird Ihre <tei:term>Theorie</tei:term>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">ausdrücklich</tei:hi> gelehrt. Diejenigen Schüler, die nach
    abgelaufenem Semester <tei:pb n="3"/> ausreichende Begabung zeigen, kommen in eine
    Fortbildungsklasse, und lernen dort die Lehre von der <tei:term>Stufe</tei:term> in Verbindung
    mit der <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>, sowie <tei:term>Contrapunkt</tei:term> etc. Von meinen
    Klavierschülern erhalten zwei bereits Unterweisung in der <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> (die
    andern eignen sich noch nicht dafür), und eine Schülerin davon liest bereits sehr hübsch
    allerhand <tei:term>Züge</tei:term>. Die beiden sind leider im Seminar des Direktors, und meinem
    allgemeinen <tei:term>Theorieunterricht</tei:term> dadurch entzogen. Traurigerweise ist es
    infolge der blödsinnigen Schulamtsbestimmungen und des zusammengewürfelten Schülermaterials im
    Augenblick nicht möglich eine einheitliche <tei:term>Schenkerklasse</tei:term> aufzustellen,
    doch werde ich dieses Ziel sicher erreichen, sobald ich einen Stamm von Schülern erst mal zum
    Verständnis dieser Dinge halbwegs <tei:pb n="4"/> erzogen habe. Abwarten und Aufbauen; hier
    lerne ich geduldig sein, und dazu eine kamelhafte Ausdauer enwickeln. —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">An Privatschülern habe ich bis jetzt zwei, und ich zweifle nicht, dass es
    bald mehr werden. Diese machen mir mehr Freude, und ich unterrichte sie genau in der Art, wie
    ich es selbst gelernt habe, mit Fingersätzen und Vortragsbezeichnung. Man zahlt mir ohne Weiters
    10 Mark für die Stunde. —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Auch das Componieren geht weiter. Eine <tei:rs key="entity-002827" type="composition">zweite Sonate</tei:rs>, die schon besser wird, als die <tei:rs key="entity-002787" type="composition">erste</tei:rs>, ist in Arbeit; der erste Satz fertig,
    sonst Skizzen. <tei:rs key="entity-002787" type="composition">Die Vorige</tei:rs> wird im
     <tei:date when="1928-01">Januar</tei:date> hier aufgeführt, von einem recht guten, und vor
    allen Dingen bekannten und beliebten Klavieronkel. —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Dem <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002404">Reichsverband deutscher
     Tonkünstler und Musiklehrer</tei:rs> bin <tei:pb n="5"/> ich auch beigetreten, nehme an seinen
    Versammlungen und Diskussionen teil, und will demnächst einen Vortrag über Sie und Ihr Werk
    halten, Ihr Einverständnis natürlich vorausgestzt. Auch für die Zeitschrift des <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002404">Verband</tei:rs>es denke ich zu schreiben. —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Im <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002780">Konservatorium</tei:rs>
    habe ich die <tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:term>Ausgabenfrage</tei:term></tei:hi> mit
    unerwartetem Erfolg angeschnitten. Es soll Einheitlichkeit in der Verwendung guter
     <tei:term>Ausgaben</tei:term> angestrebt werden. Eine von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002828">Scharwenka</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Philipp Scharwenka (1847-1917), Polish-German composer of opera, choral,
     orchestral and instrumental works.</tei:note> bewirkte schweinische <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000589">Mendelssohn</tei:rs>bearbeitung liegt derzeit (nebst
     <tei:term>Faksimile</tei:term> zum <tei:term>Vergleich</tei:term>) zur allgemeinen Abschreckung
    im Sekretariat zur Einsicht auf. —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Beiliegend erhalten Sie zwei Vergrösserungen der in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs> gemachten<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Cube was skilled in making line-drawings of people, and it is unclear whether
     these were drawings or photographs: (1) <!-- XR -->OJ 72/14, item 10, is "Portrait, head and
     shoulders <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of Heinrich Schenker</tei:supplied>, left profile,
     with spectacles. Mounted. Signed in pencil on the mount: 'v. Cube. 1927'. Together with
     enlarged print, reversed." (2) <!-- XR -->OJ 72/16, item 4, is "Portrait <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of Jeanette Schenker</tei:supplied>, head and shoulders, right profile,
     mounted. Signed: "v. Cube. 1927" These may perhaps be the pictures referred to in <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-7a_11">OJ 5/7a, [11] (formerly vC 11)</tei:ref> and <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-7a_12">OJ 5/7a, [12] (formerly vC 12)</tei:ref>.</tei:note>
    <tei:pb n="6"/> Porträtaufnahmen, sowie eine Anzahl Postkarten, falls Sie <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> und anderen Ihr neuester Konterfei
     <tei:sic>etwan</tei:sic> zukommen lassen möchten. —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich glaube Sie wissen noch nicht, dass mein <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000144">Papi</tei:rs> einen kleinen Sohn hat.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Cube's father had recently remarried, despite initial social
     pressures against his union with a teenage ballet dancer (see <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-34_1">OJ 9/34, [1]</tei:ref>, January 21, 1925).</tei:note> Er ist furchtbar
    niedlich, und die Sensation von <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002621">Duisburg</tei:rs>. Die
    kleine Mama ist sehr charmant, und meine Erfahrung in Stiefmüttern die denkbar beste! —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Mein neues Radio macht mir viel Freude. Ich höre viel gutes, bereichere meine
    Kenntnis in Kammermusik und Sinfonie, auch von den ganz alten und zum Teil ausgefallenen Helden
    wie <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002829">Dittersdorf</tei:rs> und <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002838">Stamitz</tei:rs>, und ausserdem lerne ich eine Menge
     <tei:term>„Moderne“</tei:term> kennen, wie <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002831">Milhaud</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002832">Honegger</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000482">Krenek</tei:rs>, etc. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002830">Prokofieff</tei:rs> und <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002833">Scriabine</tei:rs> kommen mir noch am <tei:pb n="7"/> wenigsten <tei:foreign xml:lang="yid">meshugge</tei:foreign> vor.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">Cube's
     use of a Yiddish term "meshugge"(meaning "crazy," "foolish") here is a characterstic linguistic
     deflection, and possibly also a nod to his teacher's Jewish background and sense of
     humour.</tei:note> Ein englischer Componist, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002834">Coleridge-Taylor</tei:rs> gefällt mir sogar!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot">Samuel Coleridge-Taylor (1875–1912), English composer, whose most celebrated work
     is the cantata <tei:title level="m">Hiawatha's Wedding Feast</tei:title> (1898).</tei:note>
    —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">A propos <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002586">England</tei:rs>! <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000178">Professor J. P. Dunn</tei:rs> hat mir, zusamt einem sehr
    netten Brief, seine Übersetzung geschickt!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker greatly admired Dunn for having translated a portion of his writings into
     English.</tei:note> Ich habe mich sehr bedankt – mehr konnte ich nicht tun. Ich kam mir
    jedenfalls richtig beschenkt vor. —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Die Adaptierung <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000178">Dunn</tei:rs>s für
    den „Klassengebrauch“ kommt mir – unter uns – gelungener vor, als <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>s;<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10" type="editorial" place="foot">Nothing is known of an adaptation of <tei:title level="m">Kontrapunkt</tei:title>
     by Otto Vrieslander; however, he apparently wrote a "commentary" on <tei:title level="m">Harmonielehre</tei:title> of around 450 pages (<!-- XR -->OC 18/5, November 9,
     1932).</tei:note> sie ist vertiefter und mehr als eine blosse Zusammenfassung des Wesentlichen.
    Trotzalledem verwende <tei:hi rend="underline">ich</tei:hi>
    <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="FEvC">ich</tei:del> im Unterricht doch die Originale von Ihnen
    selbst. Es ist bei jedem Schüler verschieden, was <tei:pb n="8"/> man ich zumuten kann, und was
    man eventuell weglässt. —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Und nun genug für heute! Recht viele und herzliche Grüsse Ihnen und Ihrer
    Frau <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Gemahlin</tei:rs></tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">von</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihrem</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143">Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:addrLine>Duisburg, Rhineland,</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>Pulverweg <tei:hi rend="underline">41</tei:hi>.</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:date when="1927-10-29">29 October 1927.</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-15">Most revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">This letter should have been written long ago. In the meantime, I fell victim
    to the cruelty of the rightly unpopular <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat">trypanosomus communis
     canensis</tei:foreign>, otherwise known as the nasty common flu bacterium,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> and for four weeks had ample opportunity to undertake
    profound contemplations of the effects of the above-named micro-organism on the human body. Now
    I am indeed on my feet again, and am able to carry out my affairs; but just ten days ago I
    thought I consisted partly of rubber, partly of yet more bendable materials.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In spite of all this, several things have happened in the meantime. At once
     <tei:pb n="2"/> two <tei:term>theory classes</tei:term> were entrusted to me, and perhaps there
    will soon be a third one. Apart from the artistic satisfaction this new field of activity brings
    me, these classes will be paid most agreeably at the rate of 6 Reichsmark per hour, and thus
    signify a not inconsiderable source of income. I am beginning very modestly, with
     <tei:term>harmony</tei:term>, <tei:term>theory of form</tei:term>, <tei:term>aural
     training</tei:term>, and <tei:term>"orthography"</tei:term>: these are pretty names behind
    which are concealed nothing other than those things that lie close to your heart, and those of
    your pupils. But the dignified professors<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> want
    to see "teaching plans": good, so I shall go ahead and make them! It goes without saying that
    your <tei:term>theory</tei:term>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">in particular</tei:hi> will be taught. Those pupils who show sufficient
    talent by the time the semester has finished <tei:pb n="3"/> will be put into an advanced class,
    where they will learn the theory of the <tei:term>harmonic degree</tei:term> in connection with
    the <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>, and also <tei:term>counterpoint</tei:term>, etc. Among my
    piano pupils, two are already receiving instruction in the <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> (the
    others are not suited to this), of whom one (female) is already quite capable of working out all
    manner of <tei:term>linear progressions</tei:term>. These two are, unfortunately, in the
    director's seminar, and have for that reason withdrawn from my class in general <tei:term>theory
     instruction</tei:term>. Sadly, as a result of the decision taken by the education authorities,
    and the jumbling together of educational materials, it is not possible at this moment to set up
    a class with a unified <tei:term>Schenkerian</tei:term> approach; but I shall surely achieve
    this goal as soon as I have succeeded in giving a core of pupils a reasonable understanding of
    these matters. <tei:pb n="4"/> Patience and fortitude: here I am learning to be patient, and in
    addition to develop a camel's endurance.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I now have two private pupils so far, and do not doubt that there will be
    more. They give me more pleasure, and I teach them precisely in the way in which I myself
    learned, with fingering and performance indications. I am willingly paid 10 marks per
    hour.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I have also made progress in composition. A <tei:rs key="entity-002827" type="composition">second sonata</tei:rs>, which will be better than the <tei:rs key="entity-002787" type="composition">first</tei:rs>, is in progress; the first movement is
    finished; the rest exists only in sketches. The <tei:rs key="entity-002787" type="composition">first sonata</tei:rs> will be performed here in <tei:date when="1928-01">January</tei:date> by
    a well-known, popular old hand who is very good in these matters.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I have also joined the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002404">Society of German Musicians and Music Teachers</tei:rs>. <tei:pb n="5"/> I take part in their
    meetings and discussions, and will soon give a lecture on you and your work – assuming, of
    course, that I have your agreement. I am also thinking of writing for the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002404">Society</tei:rs>'s journal.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">At the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002780">conservatory</tei:rs>,
    I have had unexpected success regarding <tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:term>choice of
      editions</tei:term></tei:hi>. We should all be striving to use good
     <tei:term>editions</tei:term>. A brutish arrangement of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000589">Mendelssohn</tei:rs> by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002828">Scharwenka</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> (with a
     <tei:term>facsimile</tei:term>
    <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of the <tei:term>autograph</tei:term></tei:supplied> for
    comparison) is on display in the administrative office, for general revulsion.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I enclose two enlargements of portraits I made in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002292">Galtür</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/>
    <tei:pb n="6"/> together with a number of postcards, in case you would like <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> and any other of your latest disciples
    to get in touch.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I believe that you do not yet know that my <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000144">dad</tei:rs> has a little boy.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> He is frightfully cute, and the sensation of <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002621">Duisburg</tei:rs>. The little mama is very charming, and my experience with
    stepmothers is the best imaginable!</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">My new radio brings me great pleasure. I hear much that is good, and enrich
    my knowledge of chamber and symphonic music, including that of very old and, in some cases,
    forgotten heroes like <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002829">Dittersdorf</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002838">Stamitz</tei:rs>. In addition, I am learning a lot of music
    by the <tei:term>"moderns"</tei:term>, like <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002831">Milhaud</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002832">Honegger</tei:rs>, and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000482">Krenek</tei:rs>. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002830">Prokofiev</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002833">Scriabin</tei:rs> still
    strike me as the least <tei:foreign xml:lang="yid">meshugge</tei:foreign>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/>
    <tei:pb n="7"/> I actually like the music of an English composer, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002834">Coleridge-Taylor</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Speaking of <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002586">England</tei:rs>:
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000178">Professor J. P. Dunn</tei:rs> sent me his translation
     <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of part of Schenker's <tei:rs key="entity-001725" type="work">Counterpoint</tei:rs></tei:supplied>, together with a very nice letter!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09" type="footnote"/> I thanked him profusely for it – more I could not do.
    At any rate I found this very generous of him.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Between us: I think that the adaptation of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000178">Dunn</tei:rs>'s text for classroom use would meet with greater success than
    that of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>'s:<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn10" type="footnote"/> it gets deeper into the matter, and is more than a mere
    summary of the main points. Nonetheless, <tei:hi rend="underline">I</tei:hi>
    <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#FEvC">I</tei:del> use only your original texts for my
    teaching. Each student is different with respect to <tei:pb n="8"/> what they can be entrusted
    with, and what should perhaps be omitted.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">And that's enough for today. Many affectionate greetings to you and your
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">wife</tei:rs></tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">from</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143">Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>