<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="2183" sdoID="OJ-9-30_3">OJ 9/30, [3]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="TC" scope="sole">Toni Colbert's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2007, 2019</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2007, 2019</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>


  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2011-06-09" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006997">Colbert ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Tony Colbert to Schenker, undated [September 16,
    1912]</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1912-09-16T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-01-27</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Mrs. Colbert begs to be accepted back as a pupil on one lesson a week. She has
    asked Sofie Deutsch whether she would give over one of her two lessons to her and Mrs. Deutsch
    has declined; she now asks whether Mrs. Stirling might agree to do the same.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Drang; urge; Absage; refusal; Egoistin; egotist; peinlich; painful; Schülerin; pupil
    (female)</dc:subject>


   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000137">ColbertT</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="ident-60">
     <tei:date when="1912-09-16">Montag Nachm.</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Sehr verehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">D<tei:hi
       rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi></tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
      place="foot">This letter acknowledges <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-1-B-15">OC
       1B/15</tei:ref> of September 15, 1912, and September 16 was a Monday, hence the editorially
      supplied dating. Moreover, Schenker's receipt of the letter is recorded at OJ 1/11, p. 228,
      September 17, 1912: "Frau Colbert akzeptiert alle Bedingungen u. ein letzter Briefwechsel
      bestätigt es nachdrücklich." ("Mrs. Colbert accepts all conditions, and a final exchange of
      letters emphatically confirms it.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Mein <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000136">Mann</tei:rs> dankt Ihnen vielmals für Ihr
    freundlich ausführliches Schreiben.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">=
      <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-1-B-15">OC 1B/15</tei:ref>.</tei:note> Er bittet Sie
    um Entschuldigung dass er nicht selbst antwortet aber gerade in diesen Tagen ist er mehr denn je
    beschäftigt 1. durch den Austritt seines engsten Collegen u <tei:supplied reason="enumeration"
     >2.</tei:supplied> durch die Abwesenheit des anderen Verwaltungsrathes u so bin ich so frei Ihr
    wertes Schreiben zu beantworten. Ich wusste gar nicht, hatte keine Ahnung, dass mein <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000136">Mann</tei:rs>
    <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Prof. Violin</tei:rs> ersuchen werde bei Ihnen <tei:pb
     n="2"/> zu intevenieren, da ich ja auch nicht wusste dass derselbe meinen <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000136">Mann</tei:rs> besuchen würde. Ich war allerdings sehr niedrig erschlagen
    durch Ihre Absage<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">She may be
     referring to Schenker's refusal as recorded in his diary at OJ 1/10, p. 126, May 30, 1911:
     "Definitive Absage an Frau <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Colbert</tei:hi>. Alle meine Humanität
     reichte nicht hin, ihr das schmutzige Betteln um lumpige paar Gulden auszutreiben : ich dachte
     ihr ein <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Programm</tei:hi> zu, sorgte für Vermehrung ihrer Kenntnissen
     schon des herannahenden Alters halber, — sie aber starrte unablässig in das Geld, u. lieber,
     als Alles, was ich ihr klug u. human zugedacht, lieber, als alles Interesse für die Kunst, war
     ihr, eine Stunde zu umgehen, nur um sie nicht bezahlen zu müssen! Anders aber freilich lauten
     (nach Frauenart) ihre Briefe an mich : diese glühen von Liebe zur Musik, von Dankbarkeit für
     meine Führung! <tei:hi rend="italic">Volenti non fit injuria!</tei:hi>"<tei:lb/>("Definitive
     rejection given to Mrs. Colbert. All my humanity was not sufficient to cure her of her squalid
     begging for a measly few florins: I intended to prepare a program for her that would bring
     about an increase in her awareness of advancing age. ‒ But her mind was forever fixed on money,
     and rather than all that I ingeniously and humanely planned for her, rather than any interest
     in music, she preferred to dodge a lesson merely so as not to have to pay for it! Her letters
     to me on the other hand (typically of a woman) clearly say something else: they glow with her
     love for music, with gratitude for my guidance! <tei:hi rend="italic">Volenti non fit
      injuria!</tei:hi>").</tei:note> u die Vorschläge die mir mein <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000136">Mann</tei:rs> andere Lehrer betreffend machte wies ich selbstverständlich
    zurück. Da mein <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000136">Mann</tei:rs> weiss dass ich in gar
    keiner anderen Weise als in der Musik meine Befriedigung finde so that ich ihm leid um ganz naiv
    die Wahrheit zu sagen.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich bin im ganzen Leben (leider) keine Egoistin gewesen, möchte es aber jetzt sein weil
    mein Drang ernst zu ar- <tei:pb n="3"/> beiten zu mächtig ist, als das<tei:supplied
     reason="spelling">s</tei:supplied> ich die Aussicht, auch wenn sie nur schwer gemacht wird
    aufgehen könnte zu Ihnen kommen zu dürfen. Da es mir aber peinlich ist eigentlich nicht gern
    aufgenommen zu werden so wandte ich <tei:add place="interlinear-above">mich</tei:add> an <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000165">Frau Deutsch</tei:rs><tei:supplied reason="punctuation"
     >,</tei:supplied> die 2 Stunden in der Woche hat, ob sie die Freundlichkeit hätte mir die eine
    Stunde zu überlassen. Sie thut es nicht, erinnerte sich aber dass eine Ihrer Schülerinnen
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000861">Frau Stirling</tei:rs> statt bisher 2 Stunden
    wöchentlich nur eine nehmen möchte. Sollte sich diese Vermuthung bestätigen so wäre uns
    vielleicht allen geholfen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">During the
     1912/13 season, Sofie Deutsch took lessons on Mondays and Thursdays, Mrs. Stirling on Tuesdays
     and Fridays, and Toni Colbert only on Thursdays (after an initial lesson on a Friday). Thus,
     Schenker must have acquiesced to her plea for one lesson a week; he gave no lessons to
     Vrieslander that year.</tei:note></tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> Auf jeden Fall bitte ich Sie aber verehrter Herr D<tei:hi
     rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> mich wieder als Schülerin aufzunehmen u es mich nicht allzuhart
    entgelten zu lassen<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> dass statt der Jugend das
    Alter zu Ihnen kommt jedoch nur äusserlich<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied>
    innerlich nicht<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">.</tei:supplied></tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">In treuer Ergebenheit</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihrer</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000137">Tony
     Colbert</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="ident-60">
     <tei:date when="1912-09-16">Monday p.m.</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Highly revered Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs type="person"
       key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
      type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>My <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000136">husband</tei:rs> thanks you profusely for
    your kind and detailed letter.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> He apologizes for
    not answering in person, but is busier than usual at the moment because 1. his closest colleague
    has left and <tei:supplied reason="enumeration">2.</tei:supplied> his other board member is
    away. And so I take the liberty of answering your esteemed letter. I was totally unaware, I had
    no inkling, that my <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000136">husband</tei:rs> would ask <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000913">Professor Violin</tei:rs>
    <tei:pb n="2"/> to intercede with you, nor did I for one moment think the latter would pay a
    visit to my <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000136">husband</tei:rs>. I was, though, utterly
    distraught at your refusal,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> and needless to say
    rejected the suggestions that my <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000136">husband</tei:rs> made
    to me as regards other teachers. Since my <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000136"
     >husband</tei:rs> knows there is no way in which I find contentment other than in music, I was
    cross with him, to tell you the truth quite frankly.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>In my whole life, I have (more's the pity!) never been an egotist; but I wish I were one
    now because my urge to do serious work <tei:pb n="3"/> is too great for me to be able to give up
    the prospect, however forcibly presented, of being allowed to come to you. However, since it is
    actually painful for me not to be accepted willingly, I turned to <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000165">Mrs. Deutsch</tei:rs>, who has two lessons a week, to see whether she would
    be kind enough to make over one lesson to me. She would not do that, but recalled that one of
    your lady pupils, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000861">Mrs. Stirling</tei:rs>, wanted to
    take just one lesson a week rather than two. Should this surmise prove to be the case, then we
    could perhaps all benefit from it.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> In any case, I beg you, revered Doctor, to accept me back as your pupil,
    and not to make me suffer too severely because it is age that comes to you rather than youth ‒
    outwardly, though, not inwardly.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">In true devotion,</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000137">Tony
     Colbert</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>


  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
