<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="2190" sdoID="OJ-9-30_6a">OJ 9/30, [6a]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="TC" scope="sole">Tony Colbert's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2007, 2019</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2007, 2019</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>


  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2011-06-09" who="#IB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-006997">Colbert ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Tony Colbert to Schenker, dated July 13</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1916-07-13T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-01-30</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Mrs. Colbert thanks Schenker for flowers sent while she was in the
    sanatorium.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Sanatorium; sanatorium; Blumen; flowers; Krämpfe; cramps; Fasten; fasting; Schuld;
    debt</dc:subject>


   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000137">ColbertT</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#TC"/><tei:placeName>Wien</tei:placeName>
     <tei:date when="1916-07-13">13 Juli</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Verehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">D<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
       >r.</tei:hi></tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">This letter
      is undated as to year. It is bound to be after 1910 (Jeanette's arrival in Vienna), and since
      relations between Schenker and Mrs. Colbert were bad in 1911 and 1912 it is more likely that
      it dates from between then and 1916, after which she appears not to have had lessons, and
      probably not 1914, when the Schenkers did not spend the summer away. The figure of "80 Marks"
      in the last paragraph does not help because the period covered is undeclared. Once the diary
      for 1915 and 1916 is transcribed, we may know more precisely.</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Ich weiss nicht ob mein Schreiben<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
     place="foot">This letter is not known to survive.</tei:note> Sie noch in Wien trifft, ich denke
    aber, es wird Sie erreichen. Also nochmals allerschönsten Dank für die wundervollen Blumen, sie
    waren von solch apartem Geschmack wie ich selten welche gesehen habe. Eine veredelte
    Wiesenblume. Ganz Frau Lie-lie musste ich immer denken, aus so gesundem <tei:add
     place="interlinear-above">Kern</tei:add> u Wesen die verfeinerte Kultur. <tei:pb n="2"/> Es
    machte mir grosse Freude dass Sie Beide an mich dachten u ich danke <tei:rs type="person"
     key="entity-000771">Frau Lie-Lie</tei:rs> u Ihnen besten Herr D<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
     >r.</tei:hi> vielemale aufrichtigst dafür.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich war 14 volle Tage im Sanatorium weil ich mir durch rohes Obst <tei:sic>daß</tei:sic>
    man mir mitbrachte furchtbare Krämpfe zuzog u die auch durch 3 tägiges Fasten meine Kräfte
    wieder verminderte. Nun ist aber das alles überstanden u ich hoffe langsam in mein gewohntes
     <tei:pb n="3"/> Leben zurückkehren zu können. Wohin ich gehen werde auf ein par Wochen weiss
    ich noch nicht, denn ich warte auf meinen <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000136"
     >Mann</tei:rs>, der es furchtharnötig hat ein par Tage auszuspannen.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Sehr erfreuen würde es mich zu hören wo Sie den Sommer verbringen. Meine Schuld von 80
    M. beglich ich durch die Postsparkasse. Sie dürften es erhalten haben.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute>Mit besten Grüssen an Sie Beide</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihre</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000137">Tony
     Colbert</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#TC"/><tei:placeName>Vienna</tei:placeName>,
      <tei:date when="1916-07-13">July 13</tei:date></tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute>Revered Dr. <tei:supplied reason="identity"><tei:rs type="person"
       key="entity-000632">Schenker</tei:rs></tei:supplied>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
      type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>I do not know whether my letter<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> has yet
    reached you in Vienna, but I think it will get to you. In any case, once again, warmest possible
    thanks for the wonderful flowers, which were in such strikingly good taste, such as I have
    seldom seen before: a cultivated meadow flower. I could not help thinking constantly of <tei:rs
     type="person" key="entity-000771">Mrs. Lie-Lie</tei:rs> ‒ such refined culture to the very
    core. <tei:pb n="2"/> It gave me great pleasure that the two of you thought of me, and I thank
    Mrs. Lie-Lie and you, good Doctor, most sincerely for doing so.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>I was in the sanatorium for two full weeks because I contracted fearful cramps from some
    unripe fruit that someone brought me, added to which my strength was reduced as a result of
    three days of fasting. Now, however, that is all behind me and I hope gradually to be able to
    return to my accustomed <tei:pb n="3"/> way of life. I do not yet know where I shall go to for a
    couple of weeks because I am waiting for my <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000136"
     >husband</tei:rs>, who terribly badly needs a few days' relaxation.</tei:p>

   <tei:p> I should love to hear where you are spending the summer. I paid the 80 Marks that I owe
    you via the Post Office Bank. You should have received it.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute>With best greetings to you both,</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000137">Tony
     Colbert</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>


  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
