<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2856" sdoID="OJ-9-27_7">OJ 9/27, [7]</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="FB" scope="sole">Ferruccio Busoni's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2013, 2022</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2013, 2022</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2011-09-23" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-008356">BusoniF ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Busoni to Schenker, dated February 19, 1898</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1898-02-19T02:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2022-10-03</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Busoni acknowledges receipt of Schenker's letter, the manuscript of his
        Fantasie, and [a printed copy of] his Fünf Klavierstücke. He praises the Fantasie while
        suggesting that the two new linking passages are perhaps over-long. He cautions Schenker
        over the subjectivity of the work, and advocates cutting two of the variations from the
        final section. He reiterates that he will support the work [while not directly answering
        Schenker's question regarding Breitkopf &amp; Härtel].</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000116">BusoniF</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#FB"/>Verehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >Freund</tei:rs>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">A copy of
            this item is preserved in Jeanette Kornfeld’s hand in the same folder; pp. 2–3 of the
            original are missing and have been supplied from the Jeanette copy. — This letter is
            reproduced in full in German in Federhofer (1985), pp. 80–81, and in full in translation
            in <tei:bibl><tei:editor>Ian Bent</tei:editor>, <tei:editor>David
                Bretherton</tei:editor>, and <tei:editor>William Drabkin</tei:editor>, eds.,
                <tei:title level="m">Heinrich Schenker: Selected Correspondence</tei:title>
              (Woodbridge: The Boydell Press, 2014)</tei:bibl>, pp. 20–21.</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Ich besitze Ihren Brief u. das Manuscript, vorher erhielt ich auch eine Karte<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The postcard is not known to
          survive.</tei:note> und die <tei:title>5 Stücke (cinq morceaux piano-pieces)</tei:title>
        bei <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002890">Breitkopf</tei:rs>.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>Heinrich
              Schenker</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Fünf Klavierstücke</tei:title>, Op. 4
            (Leipzig: Breitkopf &amp; Härtel, 1898</tei:bibl>), released in January
        1898.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Für Alles besten Dank und herzlichste Anerkennung. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ihre <tei:title>Phantasie</tei:title> verdient den Namen, denn sie ist phantasievoll,
        im ganzen bedeutend, durchwegs interessant, von großem Zug und feinster Ausarbeitung. Diese
        Vorzüge (und es sind nicht geringe) anzuerkennen ist mir eine Herzensfreude: ich thue es
        unbeschränkt. ‒ </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/> Im Bau des Stückes glaube ich zu bemerken, dass die Verbindungstheile
        zwischen den drei Sätzen (an sich spannend und inhaltsreich) doch vielleicht über Gebühr
        ausgesponnen sind, so dass man in Wahrheit anstatt dreier Stücke derer fünf aufweisen kann.
        Anderseits muss ich bewundern, wie sie den organischen Zusammenhang herstellen und wiederum
        aus den drei Theilen <tei:hi rend="underline">einen</tei:hi> machen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Nicht verschweigen darf ich, dass Ihre Subjectivität hie u. da höchst subjectiv das
        Wort redet, es ist, als ob Sie in Ihren eigenen vier Waenden, allein u. nur für sich Musik
        machten. Nur ein Publikum, das Sie <tei:hi rend="underline">persönlich</tei:hi> kennt
          <tei:hi rend="double-underline">und</tei:hi> liebt, wird solche Stellen auffassen und
        genießen koennen ‒ ein solches <tei:hi rend="double-underline">Publikum</tei:hi> giebt es
        aber nicht. Als ein prägnantes Beispiel dieser Art sind die Variationen VI u. VII
        anzuführen, die ich wirklich ganz auszumerzen rathen würde. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Daß ich mit meinen geringen Kräften und meinem noch geringeren Einfluss für das Werk
        eintreten werde, habe ich wiederholt ausgesprochen und ich bleibe dabei. Auch lasse ich mich
        nicht von meinem Versprechen, sondern von meiner Überzeugung leiten. </tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> Ich bin so beschäftigt, dass ich enden <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >muss</tei:hi>, so gerne ich weiter schriebe. Am <tei:date when="1898-03-08">8.
          März</tei:date> in Wien werde ich das Vergnügen haben, das Gespräch mündlich fortzuführen. </tei:p>



      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Herzlichste Grüße</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Ihr sehr ergebener</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000116">F Busoni</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:p>Meine <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000117">Frau</tei:rs> grüsst
          freundlichst.</tei:p>
        <tei:p rend="indent-40"><tei:placeName>Berlin</tei:placeName>
          <tei:date when="1898-02-19">19. 2. 98.</tei:date></tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#FB"/>Revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
            >friend</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>I am in possession of your letter and the manuscript, and previously I also received a
          postcard<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> and the <tei:title level="m">Five
          Pieces</tei:title> / <tei:title level="m">Cinq morceaux</tei:title> published by <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002890">Breitkopf</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
          type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>For all of these my warmest thanks and most heartfelt appreciation.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Your <tei:title level="m">Fantasy</tei:title> deserves its name, for it is full of
        fantasy, significant as a whole, interesting throughout, with a broad sweep to it and finely
        crafted development. It gives me wholehearted joy to be able to pay tribute to these
        distinguished features (which are no small matter). I do so unreservedly.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="2"/>I think I should comment that in the construction of this piece the
        linking passages to the three sections (in themselves exhilarating and rich in content) are
        however perhaps unduly drawn out, such that instead of three sections there are in truth
        five that can be discerned. On the other hand, I have to admire the way in which they
        establish organic connection and in turn fashion a <tei:hi rend="underline">single
          whole</tei:hi> out of the three parts.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I cannot refrain from saying that from time to time your subjectivity makes its case in
        a highly subjective way; it is as if you, within your own four walls, were making music
        alone and only for yourself. Only a public that knows you <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >personally</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="double-underline">and</tei:hi> loves will be able to understand and enjoy such
        passages ‒ but such a <tei:hi rend="double-underline">public</tei:hi> does not exist. Let me
        cite, as a good example of this, variations VI and VII, which I really would advise cutting
        out altogether.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I have reiterated again and again that I will speak up in support of the work with my
        limited powers and still more limited influence, and I abide by that. And it is not by my
        promise that I will be guided, but by my conviction.</tei:p>

      <tei:p><tei:pb n="4"/> I am so busy that I <tei:hi rend="underline">must</tei:hi> stop, much
        though I should like to carry on writing. I will have the pleasure of continuing our
        discussion in person in Vienna on <tei:date when="1898-03-08">March 8</tei:date>.</tei:p>



      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">With most cordial greetings,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Your very devoted</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-40"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000116">F. Busoni</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:p>My <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000117">wife</tei:rs> sends friendly
          greetings.</tei:p>
        <tei:p rend="indent-40"><tei:placeName>Berlin</tei:placeName>
          <tei:date when="1898-02-19">February 19, 1898</tei:date></tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>



    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
