<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="419" sdoID="OJ-9-34_2">OJ 9/34, [2]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="FEvC" scope="sole">Felix-Eberhard von Cube's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
   <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2011-06-01" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002775">Cube ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated August 14, 1926</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1926-08-14T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-05-29</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Cube is having difficulty getting his father to pay Schenker for lessons given over the previous
    year, and asks Schenker to write firmly to the latter; speaks of his attempts to make contacts within Düsseldorf
    artistic circles.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000143">Cube</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline>„Hennenhof“, den <tei:date when="1926-08-14">14.VIII.26.</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-15">Sehr verehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at
      <!-- XR -->OJ 3/8, p. 2967, August 18, 1926: "Von Felix v. Cube (Br.): der Vater könnte seine Pflicht erfüllen,
      will aber nicht: sonderbarer Geiz am unrechten Platz, aus einer eigentümlichen Nervosität; er empfiehlt mir einen
      Brief zu schreiben in bestimmten Ton." ("From Felix von Cube (letter): his father could fulfill his duty, but does
      not want to: singular misplaced stinginess, the result of a characteristic nervousness: he recommends me to write
      a letter taking a firm line.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Meine Bitten und Vorstellungen meinem <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000144">Vater</tei:rs>
    gegenüber haben bisher keinerlei Erfolg gezeitigt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Cube's
     lessons with Schenker, which began in late 1923, were cut short in early 1926 when his father Gustav recalled him
     to Duisburg, citing financial hardship. Apparently, not all the lessons had been paid for, though Schenker had
     presumably been in touch with either Cube or his father (or both) about the missing payments.</tei:note> Es liegt
    dies meiner Meinung nach weniger an mangelndem guten Willen, als an seiner derzeitigen Nervosität, die ihn an
    falschen Orten geizen lässt. Da er aber faktisch im Stande ist, Ihre Forderungen zu erfüllen, und die Dringlichkeit
    derselben sich nur nicht plausibel machen lässt, möchte ich Sie bitten, sich einmal selbst in bestimmendem Tone an
    ihm zu wenden, worauf der Erfolg meines Erachtens nach nicht länger ausbleiben kann! —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Sie können sich vorstellen, wie unendlich peinlich mir das alles ist, zumal ich es derzeit nicht
    wagen kann, zwischen meinem <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000144">Vater</tei:rs> und mir bestehende
    Meinungsdifferenzen auf die Spitze zu treiben, denn die Gefahr einer Entfremdung besteht nun einmal seit seiner
    Verheiratung, obgleich ich mich mit meiner <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002851">kleinen Stiefmutter</tei:rs>
    wie mit einer Schwester verstehe, und sie mir auch in der gegenwärtigen Angelegenheit zu helfen sucht, so gut es ihr
    ihre neunzehn Jahre eingeben. —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Darf ich Sie also nochmals ersuchen, meine Bemühungen um eine galante Auflösung dieser Dissonanz
    durch ein Schreiben an meinen <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000144">Vater</tei:rs> zu unterstützen. —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Mit meinem „Fach“ habe ich auch einige Last. Hier sehe ich mich vollends auch mich selbst
    gestellt. Die hartnäckige Sparsamkeit, die Nervosität und der Zeitmangel meines <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000144">Vater</tei:rs>s lähmen und verzögern viele meiner Unternehmungen; immerhin habe ich in diesen
    Dingen manches durch resolutes Auftreten meiner <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002851">„kleinen Mama“</tei:rs>
    erreicht. Ich brauche Bewegungsfreiheit, und die <tei:pb n="2"/> kostet Geld, und solches ist aus dem guten <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000144">Papa</tei:rs> derzeit schwerer herauszuholen, denn die
     <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> aus einem Werk von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002793">Strawinsky</tei:rs>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker's antipathy to
     Stravinskian neoclassicism is enshrined in a brief analytical counterexample in <tei:bibl><tei:title level="j">Das
       Meisterwerk in der Musik 2</tei:title> (1926), pp. 17–18</tei:bibl>. Although Cube did not yet have any copies of
      <tei:title level="m">Masterwork</tei:title>, he may well have heard the Stravinsky example, and his teacher's
     opinion of it, during one of his lessons.</tei:note> —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Hoffentlich kann ich Ihnen bald etwas Positives bezüglich meiner musikalischen Anstrengungen
    mitteilen, und sei es auch nur auf einem Gebiet wie Tanz oder Revue. Ich probiere eben <tei:hi rend="underline">alles</tei:hi>. —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Neuestens habe ich Fühlung mit <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002840">Düsseldorf</tei:rs>er
    Künstlerkreisen durch die erste Frau meines Onkels <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000858">Carl
     Sternheim</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Carl Sternheim (1878-1942), German
     playwright and novelist, best known for his comedies, of which <tei:title level="m">Die Hose</tei:title> ("The
     Underpants", 1911) was the most widely acclaimed.</tei:note> bekommen, was mir von Wichtigkeit scheint. Leider sind
    noch viel zu viel Leute auf dem Lande. Vor <tei:date when="1926-09">September</tei:date> ist gesellschaftlich nicht
    viel los. —</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Einstweilen also viele herzliche Grüsse Ihnen und Ihrer <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">Frau</tei:rs>, und seien Sie wegen der Dissonanz um Gottes Willen nicht gram</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihrem</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143">Felix v. Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline>Hennenhof, <tei:date when="1926-08-14">August 14, 1926</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-15">Most revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">My pleas and representations to my <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000144">father</tei:rs> have
    hitherto resulted in no success at all.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> The reason for this, in my
    opinion, lies less in a lack of good will than in a current nervousness that leads to a misplaced stinginess. Since,
    however, he is actually in a position to fulfil your demands, and it is only of the urgency of these that he is not
    convinced, I should like to ask you to address him yourself, in a firm tone, upon which the success will not, in my
    opinion, have long to wait!</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">You can imagine how infinitely painful all this is to me, all the more as I dare not at present
    carry things too far concerning the differences of opinion between my <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000144">father</tei:rs> and myself; for the danger of alienation now exists since his marriage, although I get along with
    my <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002851">little stepmother</tei:rs> as if she were my sister, and she also tries
    to help me in the present matter, so far as her nineteen years will allow.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">May I ask you, then, once more to support my efforts at an elegant resolution of this dissonance
    by writing to my <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000144">father</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I am also having some difficulty with my "profession". Here, I see myself entirely thrown back on
    my own resources. My <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000144">father</tei:rs>'s obstinate frugality, nervousness,
    and lack of time hinder and delay many of my projects; nevertheless I have achieved much in these matters by the
    resolute intercession of my <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002851">"little mother"</tei:rs>. I need freedom of
    movement, and this <tei:pb n="2"/> costs money, and at the present time this is more difficult to get out of my good
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000144">father</tei:rs> than the <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> from a work by
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002793">Stravinsky</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I hope I can soon communicate to you something positive concerning my musical efforts, even in a
    field such as dance or revue. I am actually trying <tei:hi rend="underline">everything</tei:hi>.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Lately I have had contact with artistic circles in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002840">Düsseldorf</tei:rs>, through the first wife of my uncle, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000858">Carl
     Sternheim</tei:rs>;<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> this appears to be of significance.
    Unfortunately, far too many people are still on holiday. Until <tei:date when="1926-09">September</tei:date> there
    is not much going on socially.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In the meantime, then affectionate greetings to you and your <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771">wife</tei:rs>; and, for God's sake, please do not be cross about the dissonance with</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143">Felix von Cube.</tei:rs></tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>