<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
 xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
 xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
 xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="461" sdoID="OJ-9-34_13">OJ 9/34, [13]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="FEvC" scope="major">Felix-Eberhard von Cube's hand</tei:handNote>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
   <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2011-07-09" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002775">Cube ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated July 6, 1928</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1928-07-06T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-07-16</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Cube reports on Scheuermann exhibit, and consequent interest and sales, encloses
    associated newspaper article; also on recent lecturing and composition activity. He is unlikely
    to visit Schenker this year; recalls people at Galtür.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>

   <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000143">Felix-Eberhard von Cube</marcrel:correspondent>
   <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">Heinrich Schenker</marcrel:recipient>
  </sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:fw type="header" rend="inline">
     <tei:note type="editorial">printed letterhead:</tei:note>
     <tei:handShift new="#printed"/>FELIX E. VON CUBE</tei:fw><tei:lb/>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:note type="editorial">handwritten:</tei:note>
     <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#FEvC"/>Duisburg. / Rhld.</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>Pulverweg 41.</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:date when="1928-07-06">6.VII.28.</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Sehr verehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
      >Meister</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this
      letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at <!-- XR -->OJ 4/1, pp. 3224-3225, July 10, 1928:
      "Von Cube (Br. u. Aufsatz aus der Duisburger Zeitung): längerer Bericht, auch Briefe von
      Sekles u. Braunfels liegen bei; die Auslage ist zustande gekommen, der Aufsatz wurde an
      mehreren Stellen abgelehnt, schließlich doch gedrückt, der Vortrag in Düsseldorf müßte wegen
      Mangel an Beteiligung verschoben werden." ("From Cube (letter and article from the <tei:title
       level="j">Duisberger Zeitung</tei:title>): longish report, also letters from Sekles and
      Braunfels are enclosed; the window display has materialized; the article was rejected in
      several quarters, but finally printed; the lecture in Düsseldorf had to be postponed on
      account of lack of interest.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Sicher war es unrecht von mir, solange mit Nachrichten zu zögern, indes lag
    in meiner Absicht, erst alle Auswirkungen der Sache abzuwarten, um einen umso vollständigeren
    Bericht abzufassen. Hier ist er:</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Die Ausstellung lief gegen 14 Tage bei der besagten Buchhandlung
    Scheuermann.1 Bis auf den "Tonwillen" war alles von Ihnen mehrfach vertreten. In einem der
    grossen Schaufenster stand die Hammer-Radierung, umgeben von Büchern und Notenausgaben. (Die
    Nieloff-Tabelle fungierte zwei Tage als Gobelin2). Ausserdem waren ständig einige Photogramme
    ausgestellt. Bei Chopin op.54, und Beethoven op.27/2 legten wir gute und schlechte Ausgaben zum
    Vergleich dazu.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Mein biographischer Artikel erschien in Duisburgs gelesenster Zeitung.3
    Einige andere haben ihn ohne Angabe von Gründen abgelehnt. Dieser Artikel war mein erste Versuch
    dieser Art. Ich habe mich bemüht, das Richtige zu treffen. Hoffentlich findet er Ihre Billigung.
    Abzüge habe ich an mehrere "prominente" Leute geschickt, so auch an Damrosch4 <tei:pb n="2"/>
    und J. P. Dunn.5 Zwei Rückäusserungen lege ich Ihne bei, mit der Bitte, sie mir wieder zugehen
    [recte: zu geben] zu lassen. Köln werde ich allen Ernstes bearbeiten. Möglicherweise kann für
    mich was Gutes daraus entstehen. -</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Von der Ausstellung wird hier viel gesprochen. Es ist auch einiges verkauft
    worden. Meistens "Theorien" und Beethoven Sonaten. Die Stadtbibliothek hat für ihre
    Musikabteilung vorläufig die 9. u. 5. Sinfonie, den "Beitrag", die Sonaten, und die Jahrbücher
    angeschafft. Weiteres wird folgen. Der Direktor der Bücherei, Dr. Sallenthin, hat übrigens
    schöne Erstausgaben aus der Zeit von Haydn, Mozart und anderen. Auch die "zweyte Auflage" vom
    "Versuch", leider ohne die Probestücke. Da diese meistens fehlen, möchte ich anregen, diese
    Beilage zum "Versuch" in die Archivbestände6 aufzunehmen. Viele Bibliotheken würden sie wohl
    anschaffen. Besser in Faksimile, als garnicht. -</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Als letzte Auswirkung vor den Ferien spreche ich im Seminar einen ganzen
    Vormittag über Ihre Theorien, über die Urlinie mit vielen Beispielen, und über die
    Ausgabenfrage. Die Zahl der Überzeugten ist noch gering, aber verlässlich - das liegt in der
    Natur der Sache. Am nächsten Dienstag werde ich dann wohl wieder etliche Seminaristen bekehren.
    -</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In Düsseldorf war ich eingeladen[,] Vortrag zu halten. Es erschienen 10
    Zuhörer.7 Da habe ich den Vortrag verschoben. Dem Veranstalter war es peinlich, aber er <tei:pb
     n="3"/> versprach mir fürs nächstemal ein zahlreiches auditorium.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Hier ist ein grosser Komponistenwettbewerb ausgeschrieben, an dem ich mich
    mit zwei Sonaten beteiligen werde. An der zweiten fehlt noch einiges am letzten Satz, doch das
    wird wohl bis Oktober zum Ablieferungstermin fertig sein. -</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Die zweite Radierung8 ist nicht benützt worden. Ich konnte mich der Essener
    Buchhandlung nicht genügend widmen. Soll ich sie Ihnen nach Galtür schicken, oder wünschen Sie
    eine andere Adresse? -</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ob ich diesen Sommer kommen kann ist mehr als fraglich. Es "kriselt" mal
    wieder in der Wirtschaft, was zur Folge hat, dass mir die Schüler in Scharen weglaufen. Aber sie
    werden schon wieder kommen. Ich werde aus Prinzip nicht billiger. Mein Tarif ist derzeit 10.
    Mark. -</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich sende Ihnen also umso herzlichere Gedanken und Wünsche nach Galtür, und
    geselle mich im Geiste an Ihren Fenstertisch zu Luftbrot, Schlagobers und Riesenschnitzeln. Auch
    lasse ich Familie Türtscher bestens grüssen. Nicht zu vergessen den Hausdiener-Kapellmeister,
    und das zuckerlverzehrende Murmeltier.9 -</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Ihnen und Ihrer Frau <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person"
      >Gemahlin</tei:rs> alles Herzliche von</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Ihrem</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143"
     >Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:fw type="header" rend="inline">
     <tei:note type="editorial">printed letterhead:</tei:note>
     <tei:handShift new="#printed"/>FELIX E. VON CUBE</tei:fw><tei:lb/>
    <tei:address>
     <tei:note type="editorial">handwritten:</tei:note>
     <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#FEvC"/>Duisburg, Rhineland,</tei:addrLine>
     <tei:addrLine>Pulverweg 41.</tei:addrLine>
    </tei:address>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-80"><tei:date when="1928-07-06">July 6, 1928.</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Most revered <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632"
      >Master</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">It was certainly wrong of me to delay with news for so long; but it had been
    my intention to wait for all the consequences of the matter, so that I could prepare an all the
    more complete report. Here it is.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">The exhibition ran for two weeks at Scheurermann's bookshop,1 of which I
    spoke. Apart from Der Tonwille, all of your work was available in multiple copies. In the big
    shop window stood Hammer's engraving, surrounded by books and editions of music. (Niloff's
    Instrumentation Table functioned for two days as backcloth.2) In addition, a few photocopies of
    autograph manuscripts were on display at all times. For Chopin's Scherzo Op.54 and Beethoven's
    "Moonlight" Sonata we additionally placed good and bad editions side by side, for
    comparison.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">My biographical article appeared in Duisburg's most widely read newspaper.3
    (A few other papers turned it down, without giving reasons.) This article was my first essay of
    this kind. I made an effort to hit upon what was right. I hope it meets with your approval. I
    have sent copies to "prominent" people, thus also to Damrosch4 <tei:pb n="2"/> and J. P. Dunn.5
    I enclose two replies; please be so kind as to return them to me. I will work on the Cologne
    project with all seriousness; perhaps something good for me can come out of it.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">There has been much talk her about the exhibition [of your work], and a few
    things have been sold: mainly the [Neue musikalische] Theorien [und Phantasien] and [your
    edition of the] Beethoven sonatas. The municipal library has, for the present, acquired the
    [monographs on] the ninth and fifth symphonies [of Beethoven], the Beitrag [zur Ornamentik], the
    sonata edition, and the [Meisterwerk] yearbooks for its music section. More will follow. The
    director of the library, Dr. Sallenthin, has, moreover, beautiful first editions from the period
    of Haydn, Mozart, and others, and also the "second edition" of [Carl Philipp Emanuel Bach's]
    Versuch, though unfortunately without the test pieces. Since these are missing from most copies,
    might I suggest that this supplement to the Versuch be included in the holdings of the Archive.6
    Better if as a photographic reproduction than not at all.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">My last activity before the holidays, I shall speak at the Conservatory for
    an entire morning about your theories, about the Urlinie (with many examples), and about the
    question of editions. The number of converts is still limited, though reliable--that lies in the
    nature of the subject. The following Tuesday, I shall probably proselytize a few more
    conservatory students.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">In Düsseldorf, I was invited to give a lecture. Ten listeners appeared.7 And
    so I postponed the lecturer. The organizer was disappointed by this, but he <tei:pb n="3"/>
    promised me a sizeable audience the next time.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Here a big composers' competition has been announced, which I shall enter
    with two sonatas. There is still some things missing from the last movement of the second, but
    these will be finished by the October deadline.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">The second engraving8 was not used: I could not devote myself sufficiently to
    the bookshop in Essen. Shall I send it to you in Galtür, or would you prefer a different
    addess?</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">It is very unlikely that I shall be able to come this summer. Business is
    again in crisis, the consequence of which is that my pupils are leaving in droves. But they will
    come again. As a matter of principle, I am not lowering the rate for my lessons, which currently
    stands at 10 marks.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I therefore send you all the more heartfelt thoughts and wishes to Galtür,
    and will be present in spirit at your table by the window with Luftbrot, whipped cream and
    gigantic cutlets. I also send my warmest greetings to the Türtscher family. Nor am I forgetting
    your servant-Kapellmeister, and the marmot who eats sweets.9</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">To you and your <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person"
      >wife</tei:rs>, all affectionate feelings from</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Your</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-80"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143"
     >Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
