<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="422" sdoID="OJ-9-34_1">OJ 9/34, [1]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="FEvC" scope="major">Felix-Eberhard von Cube's hand</tei:handNote>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="printed" scope="minor">printed</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
   <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2006</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2006</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="DB">
   <tei:persName>David Bretherton</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2011</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2011-06-06" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002775">Cube ~ HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated January 21, 1925</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1925-01-21T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-05-29</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Cube has had to extend his holiday to take care of his father, who has been forced to abandon his
    second marriage under pressure from his firm.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject/>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000143">Cube</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>

  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:note type="editorial">printed letterhead of father's architectural firm</tei:note><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">The letter is written in Cube's home town of Duisburg in northern Germany, on headed
     notepaper from his father's architectural partnership. The printed heading, enclosed in a double box spanning the
     entire width of the page, reads as follows: "PROFESSOR Dr. ING. GUSTAV VON CUBE und ARTHUR BUCHLOH / ARCHITEKTEN
     B.D.A. / FERNSPRECHER NR. 3933 / DUISBURG a/RH. / A.E.G.-HAUS, SONNENWALL", followed by names of banks in which the
     partnership had accounts, and an address for telegrams.</tei:note>
    <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>DEN <tei:date when="1925-01-21"><tei:handShift new="#FEvC"/>21.I.<tei:handShift new="#printed"/>19<tei:handShift new="#FEvC"/>25.</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>BETRIFFT: <tei:handShift new="#FEvC"/>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">Meister</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Receipt of this
      letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at <tei:ref type="diaries" cRef="OJ-03-07_1925-01:r0029">OJ 3/7, p.
       2778</tei:ref>, January 29, 1925 " Von Cube (Br.): erzählt von einer Katastrophe, die seinen Vater betrifft; der
      Trennung von einer Tänzerin, die die Gesellschaft erzwingt; er will bis in den Februar bei dem Vater bleiben."
      ("From Cube (letter): tells about a catastrophe having to do with his father; forced by society to break up with a
      female dancer; he wants to stay with his father until into February.").</tei:note></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Es haben sich hier malheureuse Dinge ereignet. Ich möchte Ihnen heute schon davon schreiben,
    obwohl ich noch ganz unter dem Druck der Ereignisse stehe, und mein Kopf mir nicht weniger verrückt ist, als dem
    armen Gretchen bei <tei:rs key="entity-000803" type="person">Schubert</tei:rs>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">A reference to Schuberts early song, <tei:rs key="entity-001680" type="composition"><tei:title>"Gretchen am Spinnrade"</tei:title></tei:rs>, which had been the subject of a textual and analytical
     study a few years before, in the sixth issue of <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Der Tonwille</tei:title>
      (1923)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> Das Schicksal, wie so oft in der Gestalt einer weidlich bekannten, verlogenen und
    demoralisierten Gesellschaftsklasse, hat meinem <tei:rs key="entity-000144" type="person">Vater</tei:rs> einen
    schlimmen Stoss versetzt. Er stand direct vor seiner Weiderheiratung mit einem <tei:rs key="entity-002851" type="person">Mädchen</tei:rs> von ausserordentlichen Qualitäten, <tei:sic>die</tei:sic> wie keine andere geeignet
    gewesen wäre, dem einsam gewordenen als lieber Kamerad zur Seite zu stehen. Ich lernte die <tei:rs key="entity-002851" type="person">junge Dame</tei:rs> kennen und schätzen, und freute mich an dem Glück und der
    Zufriedenheit der beiden, bis <tei:date when="1925-01-20">gestern</tei:date> eine Katastrophe eintrat. Die
    obengenannte Gesellschaft <tei:sic>wiedersetzte</tei:sic> sich der Verbindung, und – – drohte mit Boykott.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Was dies letztere für einen Geschäftsmann bedeutet, wissen Sie! Und alles, weil das <tei:rs key="entity-002851" type="person">Mädchen</tei:rs>, das über jeden Tadel erhoben ist, trotzdem sie nicht den
    obersten Kreisen entstammt, sich ihr Brot bisher als Solotänzerin an einer grossen Rheinischen Opernbühne verdient
    hat, wie es <tei:pb n="2"/> heute viele Mädchen mit der Schreibmaschine, oder den Nadel tun müssen. Und der Chef des
    Hauses von Cube darf keine „Tänzerin“ heiraten, weil das den alten verkalkten Geheimratsgattinnen nicht passt. Man
    würde ihn verhungern lassen. Also – – – Trennung! Ich kann nicht wiedergeben, in welchem Zustand mein <tei:rs key="entity-000144" type="person">Vater</tei:rs> sich befindet. Sicher wird er mit der Zeit ruhiger werde,
    vielleicht sogar vergessen. Aber Sie werden verstehen, wenn ich Sie bitte darüber hinwegzusehen, wenn ich den kurz
    gedachten Urlaub so lange ausdehne. Ich kann meinen <tei:rs key="entity-000144" type="person">Vater</tei:rs> jetzt
    nicht allein lassen. Es mag immerhin in den <tei:date when="1925-02">Februar</tei:date> hinein dauren, bis ich
    wieder nach <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien</tei:rs> fahre. Ich arbeite halt hier weiter an <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Probably the <tei:rs key="entity-001354" type="composition"><tei:title>Variations and Fugue on a theme of Handel,
       Op. 24</tei:title></tei:rs>, a favorite teaching piece of Schenker's and the main article in a double issue
      <tei:bibl>(8/9) of <tei:title level="m">Der Tonwille</tei:title> (1924)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> Und die Dollars – –
    die muss ich jetzt halt doch schicken.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Das sind wunderliche Dinge, die einem passieren können. Hätte nicht gedacht, dass es <tei:hi rend="underline">so</tei:hi> schlechte Menschen gibt.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="indent-10">Ich freue mich sehr, Sie wieder zu sehen. Bis dahin viele Grüsse Ihnen und Ihrer <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Frau Gemahlin</tei:rs> von mir, und meinem <tei:rs key="entity-000144" type="person">Vater</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-45">Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143">Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>

  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:note type="editorial">printed letterhead of father's architectural firm</tei:note><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
    <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>THE <tei:date when="1925-01-21"><tei:handShift new="#FEvC"/>21 January
       <tei:handShift new="#printed"/>19<tei:handShift new="#FEvC"/>25.</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#printed"/>SUBJECT: <tei:handShift new="#FEvC"/>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">master</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Terrible things have happened here. I want to write to you about them as early as today, even
    though I still remain under the weight of the events and my head is no less in turmoil than that of <tei:rs key="entity-000803" type="person">Schubert</tei:rs>'s poor Gretchen.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> Fate, as it often <tei:supplied reason="clarity">comes</tei:supplied> in the shape of an only too well-known,
    mendacious and demoralized class of society, has dealt my <tei:rs key="entity-000144" type="person">father</tei:rs>
    a painful blow. He was on the point of getting married for the second time, to a <tei:rs key="entity-002851" type="person">young lady</tei:rs> of extraordinary qualities, who would have been suited like no other to stand as
    a dear companion to this lonely man. I became acquainted with the <tei:rs key="entity-002851" type="person">young
     woman</tei:rs> and grew to treasure her, and I was rejoicing in the happiness and contentment of the pair – until
     <tei:date when="1925-01-20">yesterday</tei:date>'s catastrophe. The above-mentioned society stood in opposition to
    their bond – and threatened with a boycott.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">What the latter means for a businessman is something you understand! And all this because the
     <tei:rs key="entity-002851" type="person">girl</tei:rs> (who stands above all reproach) has, in spite of not coming
    from the highest social circles, earned a living as a solo dancer in a major Rhineland opera house, just as <tei:pb n="2"/> today many girls must do with the typewriter or with needle and thread. And the head of the House of Cube
    may not marry any "dancer", because this does not suit the old, calcified wives of the Privy Councillors. They would
    let him starve. Therefore – – – separation! I cannot convey the condition in which my <tei:rs key="entity-000144" type="person">father</tei:rs> finds himself. To be sure, he will become quieter with the passage of time, and might
    even forget <tei:supplied reason="clarity">the matter</tei:supplied>. But you will understand stand if I ask you to
    excuse me for greatly extending what I had planned to be a short holiday. I cannot leave my <tei:rs key="entity-000144" type="person">father</tei:rs> alone now. It may be well into <tei:date when="1925-02">February</tei:date> before I am able to return to <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna</tei:rs>. I
    shall just be working further on <tei:rs key="entity-000094" type="person">Brahms</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> And the money <tei:supplied reason="clarity">we owe you</tei:supplied> – –
    I suppose I shall have to send them to you now.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">These are extraordinary things that can happen to someone. I would not have thought that there
    are people who are <tei:hi rend="underline">so</tei:hi> bad.</tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="indent-10">I am greatly looking forward to seeing you again. Until then, many greetings to you and your
     <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">wife</tei:rs> from me and my <tei:rs key="entity-000144" type="person">father</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-45">Yours,</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000143">Cube</tei:rs>.</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>