<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>

    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3941" sdoID="ROC-K-5_14">ROC K/5, 14</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="major">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="minor">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="TLJ">
      <tei:persName>Timothy L. Jackson</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2026</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2026</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2026</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-04-22" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">
    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002734">Oppel ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Heinrich Schenker to Reinhard Oppel, dated August 16,
        1932</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1932-08-16T11:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2026-02-23</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>In a wide-ranging letter, Schenker offers further thoughts on Handel’s
        Keyboard Fugue in C minor (HWV 610), broadly in agreement with Oppel’s conclusions, and on
        analyzing fugue subjects and answers in terms of their content and relation to the Urlinie.
        – He advocates study of the arrangements that great composers made of their own works. – He
        praises Dvořák’s music and makes a special plea for Otto Vrieslander’s latest published
        collection of songs, remarking on how valuable it would be for his own work were Oppel’s and
        Weisse’s music available to the public. – He rails against the French, citing in particular
        Édouard Ganche’s recent edition of Chopin, and notes in closing that Free Composition is
        nearing completion.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>



      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000643">ROppel</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:salute rend="indent-20"><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>Mein lieber <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000632">Professor Oppel</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of his letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for
          August 15: “Vorbereitungen zu einem Brief an Oppel, bis 10<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
            >h</tei:hi>. – Ein Diktat dazu bis ½12<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi>. […]
            ¼12–¾12<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> diktire ich den Brief zuende.”; and August
          16: “Lie-Liechen vollendet den Brief (10 Seiten!), bringt ihn um 12<tei:hi
            rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> zur Post, rec.” (“Preparations for a letter to Oppel until
          10 o’clock. – Dictation of it until 11:30. […] From <tei:sic>11:15</tei:sic> to 11:45 I
          finish dictating the letter”; and August 16: “Lie-Liechen completes the letter (ten
          pages!), takes it to the Post Office at 12 o’clock, sent by registered mail.”) — There is
          a series of heavy underlinings throughout this document: whether they are by
          Heinrich/Jeanette or Oppel cannot be determined.</tei:note></tei:salute>

      <tei:p rend="first">Zu Ihrem Brief vom <tei:date when="1932-04-21">21. IV.</tei:date><tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">= <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-13-10_147">OJ 13/10, [147]</tei:ref>.</tei:note> u. den folgenden habe ich noch
        in Wien ein Exemplar der 6. Fuge von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000329"
          >Händel</tei:rs> beigelegt, die mich über Ihre Fragen aufklärt. Leider habe ich 1–5 nicht
        hier, so daß ich in Bezug auf diese nicht Rede u. Antwort stehen kann. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Zur 6. Fuge wiederhole ich: Sie haben mit der Ableitung der Klavierfuge
        vom Triosatz ganz recht. Wie <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000329">Händel</tei:rs>
        selbst einen Triosatz begleitet haben mag darüber werden wir uns den Kopf vergeblich
        zerbrechen. Wer so die Stimmen führt wie <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000329"
          >Händel</tei:rs>, bleibt vollständig unberechenbar; doch möchte ich darauf hinweisen, daß
        in allen 4- oder 5-stimmigen Fugen die 4. u. 5. Stimme nicht re- <tei:pb n="2"/> gelmäßig
        mittun, so daß im Grunde die Dreistimmigkeit vorherrscht die Vier- oder Fünfstimmigkeit mehr
        durch die Oktaven-Disposition als durch organische Stimmennotwendigkeit entsteht. Deutlich
        konnte ich mich davon wieder beim Vergleich der Klavierfuge mit dem von Ihnen geschickten
        Triosatz überzeugen: Nichts ist lehrlicher als zu sehen, an welchen Stellen der Fuge Meister
        wie <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000329">Händel</tei:rs> oder <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000027">Bach</tei:rs> zur Stimmenmehrung schreiten. Meist gibt es Aufschluss
        über die Form. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Daß Sie auch in den Klavierfugen trotz ihrem Ursprung <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000329">Händel</tei:rs>s letzten Willen sehen, ist entschieden
        richtig. Ob nun wie bei der 6. Fuge auch eine Verbesserung mitgeht, ist für diese Frage
        gleichgiltig. Letzter Wille sind gewissermassen alle Redaktionen aus früherer oder späterer
        Zeit sie mögen nebeneinanderstehen, auch wenn die eine aus der an- <tei:pb n="3"/> deren
        kommt. Schließlich ist eine Stelle, die ein Meister zu verbessern für nötig findet, auch
        noch interessant genug. Wie schön wäre es, wenn wir Alle nur so irregingen u. uns so
        verbessern könnten! </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Uebrigens sind die <tei:hi rend="underline">Umarbeitungen</tei:hi> sehr
        lehrreich die die großen Meister aus diesen oder jenen Gründen gemacht haben. Man könnte mit
        ihrem Studium Jahrhunderte füllen immer zum Nutzen der Lernenden u. Fertigsten. Mir fällt
        z.B. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000027">S. Bach</tei:rs>s Redaktion des <tei:rs
          type="composition" key="entity-001176">Violinkonzertes Edur</tei:rs> als Klavierkonzert
        Ddur ein wie mir denn auch die so für nichts gehaltenen Klavierauszüge der Meister
        imponieren, die sie von ihren Sinfonien, Kammermusiken oder Oratorien gemacht haben,
        gleichsam als Zugabe zum Manuscript, als Geschenke für den Verleger, doch aber in meiner
        Erkenntnis, daß die schön- <tei:pb n="4"/> ste Sinfonie nicht gangbar ist, wenn man sie
        nicht in einer vierhändigen Ausgabe freilich in einer allerbesten, unter die Leute bringt.
        Mir <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">ist</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>war</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> es peinlich zu sehen, wie sich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
          >Weisse</tei:rs> gegen meinem Rat sträubte, seine Kammermusik selbst vierhändig zu setzen;
        offenbar fehlt hier etwas, wenn er dazu die Lust nicht hat. Sie wissen, daß <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> einmal öffentlich sagen wir: damit
        geprotzt hat, daß solche Übertragungen nur er u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000612"
          >Mozart</tei:rs> machen können, u. damit hatte er, den wir ruhig einen ewigen Rechthaber
        nennen können, auch wieder recht. Wo <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006381"
          >Diabelli</tei:rs> ihm den zweihändigen Satz der <tei:rs type="composition"
          key="entity-001267">VII. Sinfonie</tei:rs> zur Korrektur vorlegte, schrieb er an den Rand
        mehrerer Blätter „Esel“, „Esel“ – weil <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006381"
          >Diabelli</tei:rs> im letzten Satz die Triolen wörtlich übernommen hatte. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="5"/> Gerade fällt mir noch ein anzumerken, daß mir auch bei
        Betrachtung einer Fuge am wichtigsten scheint, <tei:term>Dux</tei:term> u.
          <tei:term>Comes</tei:term> auf den <tei:term>Inhalt</tei:term> in meiner Weise zu prüfen,
        z. B. in der 6. Fuge wie in der <tei:hi rend="underline">Beilage</tei:hi>. Diese Fuge schon
        für die „<tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>“ zu nehmen, wie <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-005056">Souchay</tei:rs> in meinem Namen getan hat ist natürlich falsch, denn
        die <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> bezieht sich auf das Ganze; wohl aber kann auch der <tei:hi
          rend="underline">Einzelklang</tei:hi> eine Ausgestaltung nach dem Muster der
          <tei:term>Urlinie-Züge</tei:term> erfahren, u. das ist auch bei <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >jedem</tei:hi>
        <tei:term><tei:hi rend="underline">Dux</tei:hi></tei:term> der Fall. Nur auf diese Weise
        können noch kleinere <tei:term>Züge</tei:term>, z.B. ein <tei:term>Terzzug</tei:term>, oder
        größere, die für kleine stehen, u. schließlich auch <tei:term>Quart-</tei:term> u.
          <tei:term>Quintzüge</tei:term>, <tei:add place="interlinear-above"><tei:handShift
            new="#HS"/>die</tei:add> ohne die Bedeutung eines <tei:term>Dux</tei:term> u.
          <tei:term>Comes</tei:term>
        <tei:add place="interlinear-above"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>sind</tei:add>, unterschieden
        werden. Zuletzt kann man auch sehen, wie sich der <tei:term>Außensatz</tei:term> häufig
        eigentlich in <tei:term>8-</tei:term> oder <tei:term>5-Folgen</tei:term> bewegt u. wie die
        Diminution ihnen ausweicht. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="6"/> Nun zu anderen Pünkten, die Sie berühren. Ob u. in welcher
        Weise <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268"><tei:hi rend="underline"
            >Furtwängler</tei:hi></tei:rs> die <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094"
          >Brahms</tei:rs>‘sche Einrichtung auswerten wird, weiß ich nicht, möglich daß ich es
        erfahre, wenn er den Besuch hier macht den er in Aussicht stellt.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:hi rend="italic"
            >Einrichtung</tei:hi> (arrangement): this references Brahms’s arrangement of Handel’s
            <tei:title level="m">Saul</tei:title>.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Ob Ihnen <tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs>s</tei:hi> Lieder zusagen? Fast fürchte ich, daß
        diese Art Musik Ihnen weniger imponiert. Mir aber macht die Sicherheit seiner Wege viel
        Freude – wo finden wir dergleichen heute noch? Voraussichtlich bringt <tei:rs type="journal"
          key="entity-003014"><tei:title>der „<tei:hi rend="underline"
            >Kunstwart</tei:hi></tei:title></tei:rs>“ einige Zeilen sowohl über die Lieder wie über
        die „<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001755"><tei:title>Fünf
          Urlinie-Tafeln</tei:title></tei:rs>“ aus meiner Feder, mit denen ich Sie
        selbstverständlich sofort bekanntmachen werde. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Es ist immer ein großes Entzücken, von einem Meister unerwartet ein Neues
        zu hören. So werden auch von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000344"><tei:hi
            rend="underline">Haydn</tei:hi></tei:rs> heute noch neue Stücke entdeckt, doch sind es
        quantitative <tei:pb n="7"/> Entdeckungen, seine qualitative Entdeckung wird wohl für immer
        ausbleiben! Wie mich das freut, in den <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001755"
            ><tei:title>Urlinie-Tafeln</tei:title></tei:rs> die Durchführung geboten zu haben! </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Sie haben recht: <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000181"><tei:hi
            rend="underline">Dwořak</tei:hi></tei:rs> verdiente ein begeisterte Würdigung. Ein
        wahrer Naturquell, ein nationales Naß, aber immer in deutsche
          <tei:term>Stimmführung</tei:term> gefaßt, ein Beweis, daß es nur eine
          <tei:term>Stimmführung</tei:term> gibt, die über den Nationen steht. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000363"><tei:hi rend="underline">Heuberger</tei:hi></tei:rs> erzählte mir, daß
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094"><tei:hi rend="underline"
          >Brahms</tei:hi></tei:rs>
        <tei:sic>Trähnen</tei:sic> in den Augen hatte, wenn er eine Neuerscheinung von <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000181">Dwořak</tei:rs> sah, denn an nichts hatte <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs> so viel Freude wie an dem naturhaft
        Hervorbrechenden. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Was Sie über die Schwierigkeit der Aufführung Ihrer Kompositionen
        schreiben macht mir vielleicht mehr Verdruß als Ihnen, denn so sehr ich die Ueberzeugung
        teile, daß wirk- <tei:pb n="8"/> liche Werte warten können, so hielte ich es doch für
        außerordentlich ersprießlich, wenn man sie nach Tunlichkeit herausstellte. Denn nur so
        vermag der Komponist der Kraft des Werkes sozusagen die eigene physische noch hinzuzufügen
        zum Vorteil des Werkes wie der Zeitgenossen. Schon aus diesem Grunde freue ich mich, daß
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> – wenn auch mit fremder
        Hilfe – die Lieder veröffentlichen konnte. Und sehr wurde ich Ihnen wünschen daß auch Sie
        eine solche Hilfe fänden! All die Jahre her habe ich auch <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000951">Dr. Weisse</tei:rs> das selbe gepredigt. Denken Sie doch nur, um
        wieviel überzeugender unser <tei:add place="interlinear-above"><tei:handShift new="#HS"
          />aller</tei:add> Wirken dastände, wenn Ihre u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
          >Weisse</tei:rs>s Musik draußen wäre! </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Was alles ließe sich zu einzelnen Punkten Ihrer Briefe noch sagen! Was die
          <tei:hi rend="underline">Politik</tei:hi> anlangt halte ich an meinem <tei:foreign
          xml:lang="lat">ceterum censeo</tei:foreign><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial"
          place="foot"><tei:hi rend="italic">ceterum censeo</tei:hi> (Latin): “Furthermore, I
          propose,” a formulaic expression, often used to end a speech.</tei:note> fest: <tei:pb
          n="9"/>
        <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002520">Frankreich</tei:rs> ist der Feind Europas, der
        Menschheit u. ihrer Gesittung, einschließlich der Zivilisation! Was will denn dieses letzte
        Volk den übrigen europäischen Völkern bieten, wenn es die Führung beansprucht? Es ist ja
        wirklich nicht alles in der Welt: ihr Gold, ihr Parfum, es gibt noch andere <tei:unclear
          reason="reading">Weibe</tei:unclear>, die aber sind <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002520">Frankreich</tei:rs> unbekannt! Nur von der „Bank von Frankreich“ aus
        zu diktiren ist ein eselhaftes Unterfangen. Wohin ist man mit dem Pöbeldiktat der
        „französischen Revolution“ gekommen, wohin mit den „Napoleoniaden“, wohin mit den
        „Versailler Verträgen“, die heute von allen als Gipfel des Unsinns verlacht werden? Sagt man
        aber einem Deutschen, wie tief ein Franzose unter ihm stehe, dann entgegnet der Töpel:, ...
        aber das Gemüse, das sie haben, u. wie sie essen“! Die französisch <tei:pb n="10"/>
        psychopatische Sucht zu diktiren dringt sogar in <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">eine</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>ihre</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000129">Chopin</tei:rs>-Ausgabe ein: <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003553">Ganche</tei:rs>, der Herausgeber der neuen französischen <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000129">Chopin</tei:rs>-Gesamtausgabe,<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">The
              Oxford Original Edition of Frédéric Chopin</tei:title>, edited by <tei:editor>Édouard
              Ganche</tei:editor>, was published by Oxford University Press in London
            (1928–1932</tei:bibl>).</tei:note> schlägt im Vorwort buchstäblich einen Versaille-Ton
        an: weil er Franzose ist, glaubt er auch in Sachen <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000129"
          >Chopin</tei:rs>s diktiren zu können, als ob Musik ein französischer Athem wäre. Keine
        andere Ausgabe hat so viel Verfehltes, wie diese Gesamtausgabe. Wenn auch Deutsche wie
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000712">Riemann</tei:rs>, Litolff u. a. Abscheuliches
        sich geleistet haben, so ha<tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">ben</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>tten</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> sie doch immerhin „Theorien“ – wenn auch falsche – zum Ausgangspunkt genommen –
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003553">Ganche</tei:rs> aber ist von Musik völlig
        unbeleckt, ein einfacher Literat, er beschmutzt das Material, weil er dazu nichts denken
        kann, nichts in der Tat von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000129">Chopin</tei:rs>,
        nichts in der Tat von meinetwegen verfehlten Theorien, <tei:pb n="11"/> überhaupt gar
        nichts. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">An Ihrer Zusage für das nächste Jahr muß ich mir für heuer genug sein
          lassen;<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Paragraph 3 of <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-13-10_152">OJ 13/10, [152]</tei:ref>, July 20,
          1932.</tei:note> hoffentlich wird eine Inflation bei uns vermeiden, denn dann wüßte ich
        nicht, wie wir nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002334">Tirol</tei:rs> kommen könnten. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/><tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"
            ><tei:title>Der „fr. Satz“</tei:title></tei:rs> geht den Ende zu.</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Und so grüsse ich Sie u. Ihr Haus</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>in meinem u. meiner <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000771"
            >Lieliechen</tei:rs>s</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>Namen auf das herzlichste</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.
          Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1932-08-16">16. 8. 32</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:salute rend="indent-20"><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>My dear <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000632">Professor Oppel</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
          type="footnote"/></tei:salute>

      <tei:p rend="first">Regarding your letter of <tei:date when="1932-04-21">April
          21</tei:date><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> and those that followed, I
        have enclosed a copy of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000329">Handel</tei:rs>'s Sixth
        Fugue, which clarifies your questions. Unfortunately, I don't have Fugues 1–5 here, so I
        cannot answer your questions regarding those.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Regarding the Sixth Fugue, I repeat: You are quite right about deriving
        the piano fugue from the trio sonata. How <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000329"
          >Handel</tei:rs> himself might have accompanied a trio sonata is something we will rack
        our brains over in vain. Anyone who controls the voices as <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000329">Handel</tei:rs> does remains completely unpredictable; however, I
        would like to point out that in all four- or five-part fugues, the fourth and fifth voices
        do not participate regularly, so that <tei:pb n="2"/> basically the three-part texture
        predominates, and the four- or five-part texture arises more through octave doubling than
        through organic voice leading. I was able to clearly reconfirm this by comparing the keyboard
        fugue with the trio sonata you sent me: Nothing is more instructive than seeing at which
        points in the fugue masters like <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000329">Handel</tei:rs>
        and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000027">Bach</tei:rs> proceed to add voices. This
        usually provides insight into the form.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Your observation that even in the keyboard fugues, despite their origin,
        you see <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000329">Handel</tei:rs>'s final intention, is
        decidedly correct. Whether, as in the case of the Sixth Fugue, an improvement is also
        involved is irrelevant to this question. All revisions from earlier or later periods are, in
        a sense, expressions of the final intention; they may stand side-by-side, even if one
        derives <tei:pb n="3"/> from the other. Ultimately, a passage that a master deems necessary
        to improve is still interesting enough. How wonderful it would be if we could all go astray
        and in the same way improve ourselves!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Incidentally, the <tei:hi rend="underline">arrangements</tei:hi> that the
        great masters made for one reason or another are very instructive. One could spend centuries
        studying them, always to the benefit of both learners and accomplished musicians. For
        example, I'm reminded of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000027">J. S. Bach</tei:rs>'s
        arrangement of the <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001176">Violin Concerto in E
          major</tei:rs> as a Keyboard Concerto in D major, just as I am impressed by the keyboard
        reductions of the masters – which are often considered insignificant – that they made of
        their symphonies, chamber music, or oratorios, as if just as an addendum to the manuscript,
        as gifts for the publisher; yet in my understanding, the most <tei:pb n="4"/> beautiful
        symphony is unviable unless it is made available to the public in a four-hand arrangement,
        preferably a first-rate one. I <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">am</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>was</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> embarrassed to see how <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
          >Weisse</tei:rs> resisted my advice to arrange his chamber music for four hands himself;
        clearly, something is lacking if he doesn't have the inclination to do so. You know that
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> once publicly, let's say,
        boasted that only he and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000612">Mozart</tei:rs> could
        make such arrangements, and in this, he, whom we can rightly call an eternal stickler for
        correctness, was once again right. When <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006381"
          >Diabelli</tei:rs> presented him with the two-hand arrangement of the <tei:rs
          type="composition" key="entity-001267">Seventh Symphony</tei:rs> for correction, he wrote
        "idiot," "idiot" in the margins of several pages – because <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-006381">Diabelli</tei:rs> had literally copied the triplets in the last
        movement.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="5"/> It just occurred to me to add that when examining a fugue,
        I find it most important to examine the <tei:term><tei:hi rend="italic"
          >dux</tei:hi></tei:term> and <tei:term><tei:hi rend="italic">comes</tei:hi></tei:term> in
        terms of their <tei:term>content</tei:term> in my own manner, e.g., in the Sixth Fugue as
        shown in the <tei:hi rend="underline">appendix</tei:hi>. To take this fugue <tei:supplied
          reason="clarity">subject alone</tei:supplied> as the "<tei:term><tei:hi rend="italic"
            >Urlinie</tei:hi></tei:term>" itself, as <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-005056"
          >Souchay</tei:rs> did in my name, is of course wrong, for the <tei:term><tei:hi
            rend="italic">Urlinie</tei:hi></tei:term> refers to the whole; but the <tei:hi
          rend="underline">individual realization</tei:hi> can also be an
          <tei:term>elaboration</tei:term> according to the model of the <tei:term><tei:hi
            rend="italic">Urlinie</tei:hi></tei:term>
        <tei:term>progression</tei:term>s, and this is also the case with <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >every</tei:hi>
        <tei:term><tei:hi rend="underline">dux</tei:hi></tei:term>. Only in this way can smaller
          <tei:term>progression</tei:term>s, e.g., a <tei:term>third-progression</tei:term>, or
        larger ones that stand for smaller ones, and finally also <tei:term>fourth-</tei:term> and
          <tei:term>fifth-progression</tei:term>s, <tei:add place="interlinear-above"><tei:handShift
            new="#HS"/>which are</tei:add> distinguished without the significance of a
            <tei:term><tei:hi rend="italic">dux</tei:hi></tei:term> and <tei:term><tei:hi
            rend="italic">comes</tei:hi></tei:term>, be understood. Finally, one can also see how
        the <tei:term>outer voices</tei:term> often actually move in sequences of 8ths or 5ths, and
        how the <tei:term>diminution</tei:term> deviates from them.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:pb n="6"/> Now to other points that concern you. Whether and in what
        way <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268"><tei:hi rend="underline"
          >Furtwängler</tei:hi></tei:rs> will evaluate <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094"
          >Brahms</tei:rs>'s arrangement, I don't know; it's possible I'll find out when he makes
        the visit here that he has planned.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Do you like <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000922"><tei:hi
            rend="underline">Vrieslander's</tei:hi></tei:rs> songs? I almost fear that this kind of
        music will impress you less. But I take great pleasure in the assurance of his approach –
        where do we find anything like that today? <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-003014"
            ><tei:title level="j"><tei:hi rend="underline">Der
          Kunstwart</tei:hi></tei:title></tei:rs> will probably publish a few lines about both the
        songs and the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001755"><tei:title level="m">Five Graphic
            Analyses</tei:title></tei:rs> from my pen, which I shall, of course, share with you
        immediately.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">It is always a great delight to hear something new unexpectedly from a
        master. Even today, new pieces by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000344"><tei:hi
            rend="underline">Haydn</tei:hi></tei:rs> are still being discovered, but these are
        quantitative <tei:pb n="7"/> discoveries; his qualitative discovery will probably remain
        elusive forever! How happy I am to have presented the realization of this in the <tei:rs
          type="work" key="entity-001755"><tei:title level="m"><tei:supplied reason="completion"
              >Five</tei:supplied> Graphic Analyses</tei:title></tei:rs>!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">You are right. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000181"><tei:hi
            rend="underline">Dvořák</tei:hi></tei:rs> deserved enthusiastic recognition. A true
        wellspring of nature, a national source, but always expressed in German
          <tei:term>voice-leading</tei:term>, proof that there is only one
          <tei:term>voice-leading</tei:term> that transcends nations. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000363"><tei:hi rend="underline">Heuberger</tei:hi></tei:rs> told me that
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094"><tei:hi rend="underline"
          >Brahms</tei:hi></tei:rs> had tears in his eyes when he saw a new work by <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000181">Dvořák</tei:rs>, because nothing gave <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs> as much joy as the naturally
        spontaneous.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">What you write about the difficulty of performing your compositions
        perhaps causes me more distress than it does you, for while I share the conviction that true
          <tei:pb n="8"/> values can wait, I would nevertheless consider it extraordinarily
        beneficial if they were brought to light whenever possible. For in this way, the composer
        can, so to speak, add his own physical energy to the power of the work, to the benefit of
        both the work and his contemporaries. For this reason alone, I am glad that <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000922">Vrieslander</tei:rs> – albeit with outside help – was
        able to publish the songs. And I would very much wish that you, too, would find such
        assistance! For all these years, I have preached the same thing to <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000951">Dr. Weisse</tei:rs>. Just think how much more convincing <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>all</tei:add> our work would be if
        your and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs>'s music were available to
        the public!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">So much more could be said about individual points in your letters! As far
        as <tei:hi rend="underline">politics</tei:hi> is concerned, I stand by my <tei:foreign
          xml:lang="lat"><tei:hi rend="italic">ceterum censeo</tei:hi></tei:foreign>:<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/>
        <tei:pb n="9"/>
        <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002520">France</tei:rs> is the enemy of Europe, of
        humanity, and of its civilization! What can this nation, of all nations, offer the other
        European peoples if it claims leadership? After all, it's not everything in the world: their
        gold, their perfume; there are other <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear"
          >women</tei:unclear>, but these are unknown to <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002520"
          >France</tei:rs>! To dictate solely from the "Bank of France" is a foolish undertaking.
        Where did the mob rule of the "French Revolution" lead? Where did the "Napoleonic campaigns"
        lead? Where did the "Treaties of Versailles" lead, which are now ridiculed by everyone as
        the height of absurdity? But if you tell a German how far beneath him a Frenchman stands,
        the simpleton replies, "... but the vegetables they have, and how they eat!" The French
          <tei:pb n="10"/> psychopathic urge to dictate permeates even <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">a</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>its</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000129">Chopin</tei:rs> edition: <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-003553">Ganche</tei:rs>, the editor of the new French complete edition of
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000129">Chopin</tei:rs>'s works,<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> literally strikes a Versailles tone in the
        Preface: because he is French, he believes he can dictate even in matters concerning <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000129">Chopin</tei:rs>, as if music were a French breath. No
        other edition has so many flaws as this complete edition. Even though Germans like <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000712">Riemann</tei:rs>, Litolff, and others <tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">have</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>had</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> committed abominations, they at least took "theories" – albeit false ones – as
        their starting point. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003553">Ganche</tei:rs>, however, is
        completely ignorant of music, a mere man of letters; he defiles the material because he
        cannot think about it, nothing at all about <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000129"
          >Chopin</tei:rs>, nothing at all about, for all I care, flawed theories, <tei:pb n="11"/>
        absolutely nothing.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I must be content with your promise for next year;<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> let us hope we avoid inflation here, because then
        I would not know how we could get to the <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002334"
          >Tyrol</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/><tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"
            ><tei:title level="m">Free Composition</tei:title></tei:rs> is approaching the
        end.</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>And so I greet you and your family</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>in my Lieliechen’s and my name</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>most cordially,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H.
          Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1932-08-16">August 16, 1932</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
