<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="148" sdoID="Sbb-55-Nachl-13_1">Sbb 55 Nachl. 13, [1]</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="CH">
   <tei:persName>Christoph Hust</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2009</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2009</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2010</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-06-26" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc>
   <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002728">Furtwängler ~
    HSchenker</tei:rs>
   <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Furtwängler, dated November 5, 1919</dc:title>

   <dcterms:created>1919-11-05T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-05-07</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Having attended for the first time a concert conducted by Furtwängler, Schenker
    congratulates him on his achievement then, proclaiming him a "counterweight" to the present [in
    his opinion inadequate] generation of conductors, and heir to the Mahler mantle. Schenker
    comments on Viennese concert-goers and their fickleness. — He commends Moriz Violin to
    Furtwängler, in case the latter can provide an introduction to Hausegger. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Theater; theater; Konzerte; concerts; audiences; Schüler; pupil; Operation;
    operation; surgery; Wein-Gartenlauben; Wine Bower; Foxtrott; foxtrot; Temperament; temperament;
    Einbildung; imagination; pikant; piquant; Rhythmik; rhythm; Kokotte; coquette; Autorität;
    authority; Berühmtheiten; celebrities; Künstlerzimmer; artists' dressing room; green room;
    konzertieren; concertize; Kampf; fight; Ausbildungsklasse; senior training class; Akademie;
    Academy; Ohr; ear; Kenner; connoisseur; Dirigieren; conducting; Geste; gesture</dc:subject>

   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs>!
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Ein<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">The writing of this letter
     is not specifically recorded in Schenker's diary; but at OJ 3/1, p. 2171, November 5, 1919,
     there occurs the entry: "An Floriz (pn.): wegen der Befristung der Ringe u. die Mitteilung vom
     Brief an Furtwängler." ("To Floriz (pneumatic): regarding the date by which the [wedding] rings
     are needed and information about the letter to Furtwängler.").<!-- XR -->
    </tei:note> Mensch mit normalem Pflichtenkreis, mit normaler Arbeitsleistung muß sich heute in
    offenbarem Widerspruche zu den übrigen Menschen befinden, die schon von 3, oder 5 oder 6h
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ab</tei:add> die Theater u. Konzerte füllen. Wer sind denn
    diese Menschen u. was treiben sie sonst an Nachmittagen? Daß ich Sie gestern zum 1<tei:hi rend="supralinear">male</tei:hi> zu hören bekam,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">The occasion is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/1, pp. 2169–2170, November 4,
     1919: "Zum Conzert Furtwängler; Egmont-Musik mit Wüllner: störend zu lange Bogenstriche der
     Geiger vor einem sf, wodurch die Gänge eher schwerfällig werden. V. Symphonie in sehr runder
     folgerichtiger Form wiedergegeben, die Zeichen des Dirigenten vorläufig treffend, oft
     überraschend glücklich ausmalend, so insbesondere bei der Cdur-Stelle im Scherzo, wie überhaupt
     die Führung des Orchesters gar nichts zu wünschen übrig ließ. Anderseits aber ward mir sofort
     auch klar, daß dem Dirigenten jene gewissen letzten Geheimnisse der Komposition nicht vertraut
     waren, weshalb sie auch im Vortrag fehlen mußten; schon die beiden ersten Fermaten waren bloß
     coordiniert, nicht aber im Sinne des Autors aufeinander so abgestimmt, daß sie zu einer
     viertaktigen Periode würden verhelfen können. Willkürlich u. störend war die Wiedergabe im 2.
     Gedanken des 1. Satzes; in der Durchführung fehlte die Takttriole. Das Tempo im Andante war
     fließend u. natürlich, dagegen fehlte die richtige Ausführung des cresc. bei den Geigern in der
     Gruppe T. 15ff. Manche Fermaten oder Pausen waren übertrieben im äußerlichen Sinne, wodurch
     sich zwar eine gewisse dramatische Spannung einfand, die doch anderseits aber gar zu billig
     erreicht wurde. Das Scherzo vergriffen im Tempo u. der Führung des Auftaktes von zwei Takten.
     Der letzte Satz sehr gut im Großen wie im Einzelnen. Kein Zweifel, daß der junge Dirigent den
     Weingartner, Nikisch, Strauß überlegen ist, so daß nur zu bedauern übrigbleibt, daß er in die
     Komposition nicht noch tiefer eingedrungen. " ("At the Furtwängler concert: <tei:title level="m">Egmont</tei:title> music with Wüllner; irritatingly over-long bowstrokes by the
     violinists before a <tei:hi rend="italic">sf</tei:hi>, rendering the lines all the more
     ponderous. Fifth Symphony reproduced in very round, consistent form; the conductor's gestures
     appropriate this time, often surprisingly happily pictorial, especially in the C-major passage
     in the Scherzo, as in general the handling of the orchestra left nothing whatsoever to be
     desired. On the other hand, it also became instantly apparent to me that the conductor was not
     au fait with certain innermost secrets of the composition, such that they were bound to be
     lacking in the performance. Right at the outset, the first two fermatas were merely
     coordinated, but not matched to one another as the composer intended so that they could
     coalesce to form a four-bar period. The way that the second theme of the first movement was
     played was arbitrary and irksome; the three-measure group in the development section was
     lacking. The tempo in the Andante was fluid and natural; however, the right performance of the
      <tei:hi rend="italic">crescendo</tei:hi> by the violins in the group mm. 15ff was lacking.
     Several of the fermatas or pauses were exaggerated in the external sense, as a result of which
     a certain dramatic tension did indeed build up, but on the other hand it was achieved far too
     cheaply. The Scherzo [was] misguided in its tempo, and in its rendering of the two-bar upbeat.
     The last movement [was] very good in general and in detail. [There is] no doubt that the young
     conductor is superior to Weingartner, Nikisch, and Strauss; that made it all the more
     regrettable that he had not penetrated more deeply into the composition.").<!-- XR --> The
     opening measures and fermatas are discussed and graphed by Schenker in <tei:title level="j">Der
      Tonwille</tei:title>, Heft 1 (1921), p. 29 (Eng. trans., p. 27); the "three-measure group" is
     denoted in the Urlinie graph by a curly bracket under mm. 208-10 (Eng. trans., p. 29).
    </tei:note> verdanke ich sozusagen einer ungefährlichen, eine Woche vorher angekündigten
    Operation eines Schülers,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker's
     pupils in November 1919 were Brünauer, Elias, Figdor, Fried, Gärtner, Hupka, Jonas, Kahn,
     Kaposi, Klammerth, Mond, Moscisker, Pairamall, Schaab, and Weisse, but none of their lesson
     notes refers to illness. Unfortunately, the notes for that autumn are sketchy, and there are no
     dates. In the diary, there are two pertinent entries: "31. [X. 19] I ask Brünauer if we could
     put back his lesson to Tuesday, which would make it possible for me to hear Furtwängler. 'Can
     you take me with you,' he asks!" (OJ 3/1, p. 2166); "4. XI. 19 [...] Brünauer for 4pm to 5pm.
     At the Furtwängler concert ..." (OJ 3/1, p. 2169). </tei:note> – kurz ich konnte Sie hören u.
    mich Ihrer Leistung herzlich erfreuen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Endlich einmal ein prachtvolles Gegengewicht gegen die fatalen
     „Wein-Garten“lauben,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">This is a
     double play on words, on Weingartner's name, and on: Weingarten = "vineyard"; Gartenlaube =
     "arbor", "bower". </tei:note> gegen Straußens <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Foxtrott</tei:hi> (auf
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beeth.</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094"> Brahms </tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000612">Moz.</tei:rs>
     appliziert),<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Presumably Johann
     Strauß: according to the <tei:title level="m">Österreichisches Musiklexikon</tei:title>, Strauß
     visited Vienna in 1916: "An attempt to establish a foothold in Vienna (1916) failed;
     thereafter, there were only isolated incursions by great events in Vienna." </tei:note> gegen
    die abscheuliche Temperamentlosigkeit, die sich für „Temperament“ hält, wenn sie nur Eins u.
    Zwei 100 Takte lang in derselben Hast u. Undifferenziertheit forteilt. Wie ich mich gestern
    überzeugen konnte, haben Sie die bösen Wiener bereits ganz auf Ihrer Seite, nur schätze ich die
    neue Gefolgschaft noch lange nicht zu Gunsten der Wiener <tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overstrike">aus</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ein</tei:add>
    </tei:subst>, da diese lieben Kinder ja ebenfalls mehr am „Temperament“ <tei:pb n="2"/> in der
     <tei:hi rend="underline">Einbildung</tei:hi>, als in der That leiden, sich folglich am nächsten
    Abend wieder der „pikanten Rhytmik“ der <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002590">Genf</tei:rs>er
    Welt-Kokotte zuwenden können,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">i.e.
     Igor Stravinsky, who lived in Swiss exile from 1914 to 1920. Stravinsky had several connections
     to Geneva in 1919: He sold the manuscript score of <tei:title level="m">Firebird</tei:title> to
     Jean Bartholoni "who later presented it to the local Conservatoire de Musique," and a chamber
     music concert took place on December 17: Eric Walter White, <tei:title level="m">Stravinsky:
      The Composer and his Works</tei:title> (Berkeley/Los Angeles: University of California Press,
     1966, 2/1979, p. 70). In 1915, he had already been at Geneva's Maxim's with Ernest Ansermet to
     hear Aladar Racz play the cimbalon (ibid, p. 55, 242). </tei:note> die ihrer Öde aufs Haar
    genau entspricht. Die Wiener jubeln halt so gern, u. noch mehr gefallen sie sich in dieser an
    sich recht unbeträchtlichen Eigenschaft. Anlaß spielt keine Rolle – der Anlaß von heute darf dem
    von morgen sogar widersprechen –, wenn es nur irgendwie zu Jubel Gelegenheit gibt. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Fast ist es schon so weit, daß Ihnen nach so kurzer Zeit des Wirkens die Autorität u.
    Rolle <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000556">Mahler</tei:rs>'s zugebilligt wird, wodurch
    allerdings Ihre Angelegenheit für die Wiener zugleich auch ernsten Charakter angenommen hat. Sie
    selbst können freilich nichts Besseres machen, als die Barbarismen der „Berühmtheiten“ von
    gestern auslöschen, u. wie sehr ich selbst mich darauf zu freuen Ursache habe, brauche ich nicht
    erst weitausholend darzustellen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Gerne hätte ich Ihnen gestern im Künstlerzimmer die Hand gedrückt, aber da ich noch etwas
    zu sagen hatte, was sich dort nicht sagen läßt, so mußte ich zu diesem Ausweg greifen. Es dürfte
    Ihnen bei Frau <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000343">Hauser</tei:rs> ihr Lehrer-Freund Prof.
     <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">M.</tei:hi>
    <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913"> Violin </tei:rs> bekannt geworden sein, der auch mir
    seit jüngsten Tagen ein treuer Freund ist. H. <tei:persName><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Violin</tei:hi></tei:persName> möchte nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002589">Hamburg</tei:rs> gehen, um dort zu konzertieren <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">etc</tei:hi>.
    Voriger Tagen bat er mich daher, Ihnen eine Aufklärung über ihn zu geben, die Ihnen möglich
    machen könnte, gegebenenfalls ihn an <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000341"> Hausegger
    </tei:rs> zu empfehlen. Ich kann mich da kurz fassen, um das Meiste zu sagen: <tei:pb n="3"/> er
    hat ein Ohr, wie nur ganz wenige unter den Musikern heute. Seinem Ohr nach, seinem Verständnis
    nach müßte er in fester Stellung stehen, aber Kampf ist nicht seine Sache, obwohl, wie das schon
    Spiel der Natur ist, er selbst eine Kampfnatur zu haben glaubt. Er war Professor der <tei:hi rend="underline">Aus</tei:hi>-bildungsklasse an unserer <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002591">Akademie</tei:rs>, ist es aber heute nicht mehr –, nun davon können Sie ja
    von ihm selbst oder von beliebig anderer<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">Akademie: i.e. the Vienna Conservatory, since 1909 renamed the Akademie für Musik
     und darstellende Kunst. The piano division of the Academy was divided into Vorbereitungskurs
     (preparatory course), Vorbildungsklasse (preliminary training class), Ausbildungsklasse (senior
     training class), and Meisterklasse (masterclass), each with its own teaching faculty. The
     Ausbildungsklasse was staffed by distinguished teachers such as Paul de Conne (1901–15) and
     Schenker's own former teacher Ernst Ludwig (1883–1914). </tei:note> Seite nur das Ehrenvollste
    hören, so nämlich davon, weshalb er nach Kriegsschluß nicht wieder in die Akademie
     heimgefunden.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker is skirting
     round the fact that Violin mounted opposition to, and published a pamphlet against the
     Academy's President and Director in 1912, and left the Academy's faculty after that opposition
     failed. It is notable that Schenker says nothing about Violin's piano technique or
     interpretation. </tei:note>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Wie gesagt, das Ohr ist singulär, ein Meisterstück der Natur, für Kenner ein <tei:unclear reason="reading">Rechtes</tei:unclear> heute. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>So viel schriftlich. Vielleicht läßt sich, wenn nötig, mündlich noch etwas nachziehen,
    wenn sich dazu, was ich wohl hoffe, Gelegenheit finden sollte. </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Nun grüße ich Sie aufs beste</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60">
     <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">H Schenker</tei:hi>
    </tei:signed>
    <tei:date when="1919-11-05">5. Nov. 1919</tei:date>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p>Ein Wörtchen noch: ich habe genau Ihr Dirigieren verfolgt, Bewegung um Bewegung, u. da
     fiel mir ein: Wie, wenn Sie zu <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000183"> Ebert </tei:rs>, u.
      <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000705"> Renner </tei:rs> einen Sprung machen würden, um
     ihnen eine gewisse Taktstock<tei:hi rend="underline">geste beizubringen</tei:hi>: „Marsch
     hinaus, eckles Franzosen- u. Angelsachsenpack“. Die Geste müßte unwiderstehlich wirken u. wir
     würden auf einmal der 10 Plagen los! </tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute>Dear Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000268">Furtwängler</tei:rs>,
    </tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>


   <tei:p>Anyone<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> with a normal complement of
    obligations, with a normal work output, must find himself these days in flagrant contradiction
    to other people, who throng the theaters and concert halls from as early as 3 p.m., or 5 p.m.,
    or 6 p.m. <tei:add place="interlinear-above">onward</tei:add>. Who on earth are these people,
    and how do they otherwise spend their time in the afternoons? The fact that I got to hear you
    for the first time yesterday<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> was thanks, so to
    speak, to surgery – not life-threatening, and known about a week in advance – undergone by one
    of my pupils;<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> in short, I was able to hear you,
    and to take heartfelt pleasure in your accomplishment. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>At long last, <tei:supplied reason="clarity">we have</tei:supplied> a magnificent
    counterweight to the fatal "Wine Bower,"<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> to the
     <tei:persName>Strauß</tei:persName> foxtrot (applied to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>,<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094">
     Brahms</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000612">Mozart</tei:rs>),<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> to the execrable lack of temperament that fancies
    itself to be "temperament" if it merely hurtles along with a one-and-a-two for a hundred
    measures at a time in the same haste and lack of differentiation. I persuaded myself yesterday
    that you had already totally won over the pernicious Viennese to your side; however, I don't
    think any the better of the Viennese for your new following, since these childish people in fact
    suffer more from "temperament" <tei:pb n="2"/> in the <tei:hi rend="underline">imagination</tei:hi> than in reality and so might easily tomorrow evening turn to the "piquant
    rhythms" of the world demimondaine of <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002590">Geneva</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> which matches their aridness
    to a tee. The Viennese simply love rejoicing, and even more do they indulge in this quality,
    which in itself is truly trivial. Reason plays no part in it – today's reason may flatly
    contradict that of tomorrow –, so long as it somehow provides an occasion for rejoicing. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Things have already almost reached the point at which, although you have been in action
    for so short a while, you are accorded the mantle and authority of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000556">Mahler</tei:rs>, as a result of which, of course, your situation has become
    a serious matter for the Viennese. To be sure, you yourself could do nothing better than to
    eradicate the barbarisms of the "celebrities" of yesterday, and I do not need to dwell at length
    on how great a cause I myself have for joy at that. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>I would have liked to shake your hand in the artists' dressing room yesterday; but because
    I had something to say that could not have been said there, I had to resort to the alternative
    of <tei:supplied reason="clarity">writing</tei:supplied> this <tei:supplied reason="clarity">letter</tei:supplied>. You may have become acquainted at Mrs. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000343">Hauser</tei:rs>'s house with her teacher-friend Professor <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913"> Moriz Violin </tei:rs>, who has been a faithful friend to
    me, too, since earliest days. Mr. <tei:persName>Violin</tei:persName> would like to go to
     <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002589">Hamburg</tei:rs> in order to give concerts etc. there.
    Consequently, a day or so ago he asked me if I could put in a good word for him to you, such
    that you might be in a position, if the occasion arises, to recommend him to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000341">Hausegger</tei:rs>. To be brief, most of what you need to
    know is: <tei:pb n="3"/> He has an ear such as very few musicians of today possess. In keeping
    with the quality of his ear and of his intellect, he really should be in a permanent position,
    but fighting is not his forte, although, as is so often nature's way, he himself believes that
    he has the fighting spirit. He was professor of the <tei:hi rend="underline">senior</tei:hi>
    Training Class at our <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002591">Academy</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn10" type="footnote"/> but is so no longer. Regarding that, you will hear only
    the most honorable things from him himself or from any other quarter you may choose, as for
    example why he has not found a home at the <tei:orgName>Academy</tei:orgName> again since the
    end of the war.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/>
   </tei:p>

   <tei:p>As I have already said, his ear is unique, a masterstroke of nature, exactly what is
     <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">needed</tei:unclear> for the connoisseur these days. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Enough in writing. Perhaps it may be possible, if need be, to take the matter a little
    further in person, if, as I very much hope, the occasion should arise. </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Finally, I send you my best wishes, </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Yours, </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60">H. Schenker</tei:signed>
    <tei:date when="1919-11-05">November 5, 1919</tei:date>
   </tei:closer>

   <tei:postscript>
    <tei:p>One last word: I have examined your conducting in minute detail, arm motion by arm
     motion, and it occurs to me that, if you could make contact with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000183">Ebert </tei:rs>, and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000705">Renner
     </tei:rs> and <tei:hi rend="underline">teach them</tei:hi> a certain baton <tei:hi rend="underline">gesture</tei:hi>
     <tei:supplied reason="clarity">that says</tei:supplied>: "Get out of here, you pack of French
     and Anglo-Saxon scum," the gesture would be bound to have an irresistible effect, and we would
     immediately be rid of the ten plagues! </tei:p>
   </tei:postscript>


  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>