<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="97" sdoID="WSLB-303">WSLB 303</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>
  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="major">Jeanette Kornfeld/Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="minor">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2009</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2009</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2010</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
   <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
   <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-05-04" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>


 <sdo:record ID="r0001">
  <sdo:itemDesc><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002700">Hertzka ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002701">UE ~ H+JSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002702">UE ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   
   
   
   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Hertzka (UE), dated June 12, 1919 </dc:title>
   
   <dcterms:created>1919-06-12T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-05-01</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker promises to send Hans Weisse to see Hertzka. In reacting unfavorably to
    Hertzka's suggestions that the Foreword to Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven, Op. 111 be
    discarded for its second edition, Schenker puts up a stout defense of his use of polemic in his
    writings, contending that art, life, and politics are inextricably interconnected. He claims
    that his pronouncements on politics now will prove correct in the long run. His sole concern is
    with the truth; he is not interested in pandering to his readers.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Vorwort; Foreword; Krieg; war; Polemik; polemics; Wahrheit; truth; Chauvinismus;
    chauvinism; Deutschtum; Germanity; Entente; organische Zusammenhang; organic
    relationship</dc:subject>

   
   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000356">Hertzka</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-002408">UE</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Sehr geehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356">Herr
      Direktor</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">Es<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this
     letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/14, p. 2079, two days earlier, June 10, 1919:
     "An Hertzka (Br.): wegen des Vorwortes (liegt im Copierbuch)." ("To Hertzka (letter):
     concerning the Foreword (is in the copybook).")<!-- XR --> Then on OJ 2/14, p. 2080, June 13:
     "An Hertzka recomm. Brief abgeschickt." ("To Hertzka registered letter sent off.")<!-- XR -->
    </tei:note> dürfte wohl das Vernünftigste u. Kürzeste sein, wenn ich Ihnen den jungen D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r</tei:hi> mus. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</tei:rs>
    (samt opus) zuschicke, was auch in Bälde geschehen wird. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Weit mehr aber als Ihre Klage über Papiernot u. erhöhte Kosten<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">in OJ 52/923, June 6, 1919. </tei:note> hat
    mich Ihr mein <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title>op. 111</tei:title></tei:rs>
    betreffendes P. S. erschreckt. Meinerseits noch zu mehreren Arbeiten für die „<tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">U.-E.</tei:rs>“ bereit, wie zur „<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001758">Kleinen Bibliothek</tei:rs>“, zum Abschluß der nun einmal begonnenen
     <tei:rs key="entity-001733" type="work">Sonaten-Serie</tei:rs>, ja sogar zu einer Ausgabe der
     <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001753">Klaviersonaten von Beethoven</tei:rs>, fühle ich mich
    in meiner zunächst nur rein theoretischen Bereitschaft schon wie gelähmt wenn ich befürchten
    muß, daß auch nur nachträglich meine bereits gedruckten Gedankengänge irgendwelchen
    anderweitigen Interes- <tei:pb n="2"/> se geopfert werden könnten. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich bin gewohnt zu denken u. zu schreiben ganz allein nur so, wie der Stoff
    es fordert; es kann mir also niemals widerfahren, daß ich etwas zu bereuen oder zu widerrufen
    hätte. Auch dort, wo es für oberflächliche Leser den Anschein haben könnte, als hätte ich ein
    falsches oder ungerechtes Urteil abgegeben, braucht es eben nur der Zeit, damit man sich von der
    Sicherheit meiner Betrachtung überzeuge. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich erachte es aber auch nicht einmal für meines Lesers Sache, zu beurteilen,
    ob ich mit mehr oder wenigen Berechtigung den Krieg in die Debatte gezogen habe, denn meine
    Gründe gehen so ins Tiefe, daß er weder fürs erste noch fürs tausendste begreifen könnte,
    weshalb ich es getan. Erst bis mein Gesamtwerk in Erscheinung getreten ist, wozu ich natürlich
    auch alle noch zu veröffentlichenden Arbeiten zähle, wird man vielleicht zu beurteilen vermögen,
    weshalb ich den organischen Zusammenhang der Musik mit allen <tei:pb n="3"/> übrigen also auch
    politischen Lebensäußerungen der Menschheit so hoch veranschlagt habe. Schreiben doch auch Sie
    selbst: „Die Stadt <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>s, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000612">Mozart</tei:rs>s, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000803">Schubert</tei:rs>s wird das überleben“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">in OJ 52/923, June 6, 1919.</tei:note> u. drücken damit, ohne zu wollen, einen
    Zusammenhang zwischen Kunst u. Politik aus. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Sie verstehen, daß mich aus eben diesem Grunde die augenblickliche Empfindung
    einzelner Leser gar nicht interessiert u. ich am allerwenigsten wohl geneigt wäre, der
    persönlichen oder gar nationalen Eitelkeit desselben Rechnung zu tragen. Vielmehr hat sich
    umgekehrt der Leser für den Autor zu interessieren, nach dessen Werk er langt, um eine Lehre zu
    empfangen, die er bis dahin nicht kannte: Bin nur ich allein es, der ihn heute unter Allen am
    besten belehrt<tei:supplied reason="syntax">,</tei:supplied> dann muß er sich wohl auch in die
    Art fügen, mit der ich ihn zur Wahrheit führe, u. sei die Art ihm persönlich noch so unangenehm.
    Oder aber – er lasse das Werk stehen u. gehe weiter als Ignorant durch die Welt! Selbst die
    Wahrheit verliert am <tei:pb n="4"/> Wucht, wenn man sie bloß nach der <tei:foreign xml:lang="fre">Fasson</tei:foreign> der Leser, die naturnotwendig eine niedere sein muß,
    mundgerecht machen will. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich treibe Wahrheit, aber durchaus nicht Chauvinismus (der, wie schon das
    Wort sagt, eine echt französische Original-Marke ist), u. wenn ich dem Deutschtum den höchsten
    Rang zugewiesen habe, so waren mit mir bis zum Kriege selbst unsere Feinde darum
     einig<tei:supplied reason="syntax">.</tei:supplied> Im Laufe des Krieges wurden allerdings die
    immerzu geschlagenen Feinde um eine Million Grade infamer als sie schon früher gewesen, darum
    aber ist meine Wahrheit nicht um einen Grad nationaler geworden. Bloß also zu seiner Belehrung
    u. nicht zur Beleidigung will ich es dem Leser gesagt haben, wenn ich ihm zu ahnen u. zu
    verstehen aufgab, daß ein <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> niemals,
    bis ans Ende aller Zeiten niemals etwa auch in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002586">England</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002520">Frankreich</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002592">Italien</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002595">Serbien</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002596">Tschechien</tei:rs>, geschweige denn in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002510">Amerika</tei:rs>, dem letzten aller
    heutigen Kulturländer würde je erstehen können. Denn schärfe ich so <tei:pb n="5"/> erst dem
    Leser die überhohe Bedeutung eines Meisters wie <tei:persName>Beethoven</tei:persName> ein, so
    erwirbt er dann umso eher auch die Fähigkeit vom Meister zu lernen, weit eher, als wenn ich ihm
    gestatten wurde, einen <tei:persName>Beethoven</tei:persName> nach heutiger Unverfrorenheit u.
    Verwilderung zu bagatellisieren u. zu glauben es könnte seinesgleichen heute, morgen wohl auch
    andererswo geben. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Wie Sie sehen, mache ich es mit meinen Arbeiten – um einen Scherz zu wagen –
    zwar dem Verleger billig, aber aus wichtigen Gründen niemals meinem Leser. Ich dulde es auch
    niemals, daß der Leser von meinem Geistestische gesättigt sich erhebe, sein Gefühl aber wie sein
    Urteil sofort wider mich richte, als hätte er den Tisch sich selber gedeckt. Der ist niemals ein
    fähiger Leser von mir gewesen, der solches von sich gab. Die Art, in der andere Schriftsteller,
    wie gleichsam geistige Kellner im Frack, den zahlenden Leser-Gast „bedienen“, habe ich immer für
    falsch befunden – vielmehr bin ich <tei:pb n="6"/> mit Überzeugung des Lesers Herr u. Meister. </tei:p>
   <tei:p rend="first">Ich schreibe ja auch nicht für die Gegenwart, sondern – nur es mit vollem
    Bewußtsein auszusprechen – für Jahrtausende, da man mich dann als die allereinzige Quelle für
    die Blüte-Epoche der Musik zu erkennen u. zu schätzen gelernt haben wird etwa wie z.B.
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002527">Aristoteles</tei:rs> als Quelle für die Erkenntnis
    griechischen Wesens. Daher greife ich ins Volle der Zusammenhänge u. verschmähe es, des Lesers
    Eitelkeit zu ködern. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Uebrigens bin ich überzeugt, daß die absolute Rücksicht, wie ich sie die
    Wahrheit gegenüber übe, der Weiterverbreitung des Werkes weit förderlicher ist, als es die
    Rücksicht gegenüber Lesern sein könnte. Es hat auch einem <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000524">Lessing</tei:rs> durchaus nicht geschadet, wenn bis zum heutigen Tag in seiner
    vielgelesenen „<tei:title>Hamburgische Dramaturgie</tei:title>“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Gotthold Ephraim Lessing, <tei:title level="m">Hamburgische
      Dramaturgie</tei:title> (1767), a treatise on poetry and drama, which can be seen as a new
     interpretation of Aristotle's theory of drama. </tei:note> z.B. der Satz: „Wie englisch, wie
    unanständig“ stehen geblieben ist u. daselbst auch sonst noch so viele Verspottungen u.
    Richtigstell- <tei:pb n="7"/> ungen von geistigen Fälscherkunststücken der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002597">Corneille</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000685">Racine</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000916">Voltaire</tei:rs> usw,
    Richtigstellungen, die allesamt doch wirklich nicht als Aeußerung eines deutschen Chauvinismus
    zu betrachten, sondern vielmehr als echte Wahrheitsliebe zu werten sind. Und was liest man nicht
    sonst noch alles an heftigsten Kritiken fremder Nationen bei <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000294">Goethe</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000784">Schiller</tei:rs>,
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002587">Herder</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000403">Jean
     Paul</tei:rs>? Was geht denn auch die Meister irgend eine Rücksicht auf Eitelkeit an?
    Haben denn Franzosen oder Engländer sich je ein Blatt vor den Mund genommen? Haben sie nicht
    vielmehr sogar bewußte Lügen in die Welt geschleudert, was doch gewiß verdammenswerter ist, als
    bloß die Wahrheit zu sagen? </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Und was nun speziell das Vorwort zu <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work">op. 111</tei:rs> anlangt, so steht doch die Sache so, daß heute selbst <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Wien</tei:rs>er Tagesblätter den Sieg der Entente<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">(Triple) Entente: the alignment between Great
     Britain, France, and Russia agreed in 1907 as a counter force to the Triple Alliance of
     Germany, Austria-Hungary, and Italy. </tei:note> nur mit Gänsefüßchen als „Sieg“ anführen, d.
    h. die Fochiade<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker used the
     word "Fochiade" also in his "The Mission of German Genius," <tei:title level="j">Der
      Tonwille</tei:title> Heft 1 (1921), 12 (Eng. trans., p. 12), the suffix "iade" generally
     implying a celebration or competition (e.g. "Olympiade"), but being freighted here with scorn
     in referring to Foch's part (and also Wilson's two words later) in the Treaty of Versailles.
    </tei:note> u. Wilsoniade eben nicht für einen wirklichen Sieg halten. Und ist dies nur eine
    erst journalistische Betrachtung, mit wie <tei:pb n="8"/> viel mehr Recht schrieb ich darüber,
    der den Sieg ja nicht allein auf die errungenen Siege auf den Schlachtfeldern (die nicht
    weggelogen werden können) bezog, sondern auf Siege höherer Art. Und dieses nun aber zu
    beurteilen, ob ich einen Sieg der Deutschen mit Recht prophezirt habe, überlasse ich nicht dem
    Leser des Jahres 1920 oder 1921, sondern erst den späteren. Habe ich denn bezüglich
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000966">Wilson</tei:rs>s u. der Engländer überhaupt usw. nicht
    schon heute Recht behalten? Nun aber genug. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Ich bin also, um es mit einem Wort zu sagen, nicht allein <tei:hi rend="underline">durchaus</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">nicht</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">einverstanden</tei:hi> mit Ihrem Vorschlag sondern bitte Sie sogar
    ausdrücklich, die Ausgabe <tei:hi rend="underline">gerade</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">nur so</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">stehen zu lassen</tei:hi>, wie sie aus meiner Feder gekommen ist: ich
    trage gern u. stolz die Verantwortung für jedes Wort, ja ich habe sogar vor, in den künftigen
    Arbeiten mir ebensoviel Rechte herauszunehmen, wie sie sich Menschen herausgenommen haben,
     <tei:pb n="9"/> denen es mit weniger als mir zugekommen ist, wozu ich eben auch die
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000966">Wilson</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000534">Lloyd-George</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000134">Clemenceau</tei:rs>
    rechne, einschließlich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000948">Weingartner</tei:rs> u. wie sie
    alle heißen <tei:del rend="overstrike">M</tei:del> mögen. Musik ist ja – vergessen Sie es nicht,
    lieber Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356">Direktor</tei:rs> – nicht bloß Angelegenheit
    einer Privatstunde, eines häuslichen oder öffentlichen Konzertes, eines Konservatoriums, sondern
    eine eminent öffentliche Angelegenheit der Menschheit, in deren Interesse nun die Wortführer
    volle Freiheit des Wortes genießen müssen, ausgenommen die Freiheit eines Betruges am Stoffe! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Uebrigens freut es mich, daß Sie so weit sind, eine II. Auflage veranstalten
    zu können, da ich mir sonst nicht zu erklären wüßte, wie Sie gerade im Falle <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work">op. 111</tei:rs> das Vorwort vom Texte loslösen wollten. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-25">mit besten Grüßen</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Ihr ergebener</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-55">
     <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">H Schenker</tei:hi>
    </tei:signed>
    <tei:date when="1919-06-12">12. Juni 1919</tei:date>
   </tei:closer>
  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356">Director</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p rend="first">It<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> would clearly be most
    sensible and efficacious if I were to send the young <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Hans
     Weisse</tei:rs>, PhD (Mus.), to you (together with his opus), and this I shall do
    forthwith. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">However, your P.S. concerning my <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work">
     <tei:title level="m">Op. 111</tei:title>
    </tei:rs> has given me a far bigger fright than your lament about scarcity of paper and
    increased costs.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> Prepared as I remain to
    contribute several works to <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">UE</tei:rs>, such as the
     <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001758">
     <tei:title level="j">Little Library</tei:title>
    </tei:rs>, the completion of the already begun <tei:rs key="entity-001733" type="work">sonata
     series</tei:rs>, indeed even an edition of the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001753">Beethoven piano sonatas</tei:rs>, I feel as if my legs had already been cut from under me in
    my preparedness on the for now purely theoretical front if I must fear that even my already
    published trains of thought <tei:pb n="2"/> could subsequently be sacrificed in the interests of
    something else. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I am accustomed to thinking and writing entirely in isolation, solely as the
    material itself demands. That way, I should never live to regret or have to revoke something.
    Even where to superficial readers it might appear as if I had pronounced a false or incorrect
    verdict, it will be only a matter of time before people will be convinced of the rectitude of my
    viewpoint. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">However, I do not for a moment consider it a matter for my reader to judge
    whether or not I am justified in having drawn the war into my line of argument, for my reasons
    run so deep that he could not possibly even begin to fathom why I had done it. Only when my
    entire life's work has been completed (among which I of course count all those works yet to be
    published) will people perhaps be in a position to judge why I have rated so highly the organic
    relationship between music and all <tei:pb n="3"/> other manifestations of human life, including
    even political ones. Even you yourself in fact write: "The city of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000612">Mozart</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000803">Schubert</tei:rs> will
    outlive it,"<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> and in so saying, without intending
    to, you imply a relationship between art and politics. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">You must understand that, for this very reason, the feelings of individual
    readers at this particular moment do not interest me in the slightest, and least of all would I
    be inclined to take account of the personal or national vanity of those persons. On the
    contrary, all the more must the reader interest himself in the author whose work he takes up, in
    order to assimilate a theory of which until then he knew nothing. If today I am the only one
    among all others who can best instruct him, then he must just submit to the method by which I
    lead him toward the truth, however uncongenial he may personally find that method. Otherwise,
    let him drop the work, and go through life as an ignoramus! Even the truth loses <tei:pb n="4"/>
    weight if after the fashion of readers – which must of absolute necessity be a lower fashion –
    people merely want to render it palatable. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I pursue truth, but never for one moment chauvinism (which, as the word
    itself signifies, bears the hallmark of something quintessentially French), and if I have
    accorded the highest status to Germanity, then even our enemies would have agreed with me on
    that up until the war. In the course of the war, however, our enemies, while constantly being
    defeated, became a million times more infamous than they had been earlier; but my truth did not
    become one iota more nationalistic on that account. Thus it was solely to instruct the reader
    and not to insult him that I said to him, when I <tei:unclear reason="reading">gave</tei:unclear> him his first inkling and understanding, that a <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> would never, not until the end of time, be able to
    arise in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002586">England</tei:rs>,
     <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002520">France</tei:rs>,
     <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002592">Italy</tei:rs>,
     <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002595">Serbia</tei:rs>,
     <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002596">Czechoslovakia</tei:rs>,
    let alone <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002510">America</tei:rs>,
    the worst of all today's cultural lands. For if I impress upon <tei:pb n="5"/> the reader from
    the outset the supreme importance of a master such as <tei:persName>Beethoven</tei:persName>, he
    then acquires the ability to learn from the master all the sooner, far far sooner than if I had
    allowed him to belittle a <tei:persName>Beethoven</tei:persName> in the manner of today's
    insolence and degeneracy, and to believe that there could be people of his ilk today, and
    tomorrow things could be quite quite different. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">As you can see, with my works – if I may venture a joke – I make things easy
    for the publisher, whereas for very good reason I never do so for my reader. I never once
    tolerate the reader getting up from my intellectual table fully sated but turning his feelings
    and also his judgment immediately against me as if he had himself set the table. There has never
    been a competent reader of my work who has behaved in such a way. I have always considered false
    the way in which other writers, like, so to speak, intellectual waiters in tails, "serve" the
    paying reader-customer. Instead, <tei:pb n="6"/> I am lord and master in convincing my reader. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">I do not write for the present time, but – and I am fully conscious of what I
    am saying here – for millenia, since people will then come to recognize and value me as the one
    and only source for the supreme epoch of music, rather like, for example, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002527">Aristotle</tei:rs> as the source for our knowledge of Greek way of
    life. This is why I delve into the relationships <tei:supplied reason="clarity">between art and
     life</tei:supplied> in all their fullness, and repudiate all pandering to the reader's vanity. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">Incidentally, I am convinced that the uncompromising approach as I practice
    it in regard to the truth is far more advantageous to the wide dissemination of my work than the
    approach that privileges the reader ever could be. It has done even a <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000524">Lessing</tei:rs> not the slightest harm that, for example, the phrase
    "how English, how unseemly" has stood the test of time in his widely read <tei:title level="m">Hamburg Dramaturgy</tei:title><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> to the present
    day, whereas intellectually counterfeit minor works of art by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002597">Corneille</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000685">Racine</tei:rs>,
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000916">Voltaire</tei:rs> and their likes have received so much
    derision and recitification, <tei:pb n="7"/> rectification that without exception can in no way
    be seen as an expression of German chauvinism, but rather deserve appreciation as exhibiting a
    genuine love of the truth. And besides all of that, does one not read the sternest of criticisms
    of foreign nations by <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000294">Goethe</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000784">Schiller</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002587">Herder</tei:rs>, and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000403">Jean Paul</tei:rs>? So when
    did the masters ever show any kind of regard for vanity? So have Frenchmen or Englishmen ever
    minced matters? Have they not instead spread patent lies far and wide, and is that not all the
    more heinous than speaking the truth? </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">And now as specifically concerns the Foreword to <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work">
     <tei:title level="m">Op. 111</tei:title>
    </tei:rs>, the situation is such that even the <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Vienna</tei:rs> daily papers are today reporting the victory of the Entente<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> as a "victory" only within quotation-marks, i. e. they
    do not consider the Fochiade<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> and Wilsoniade as a
    real victory. And if this is a merely journalistic way of looking at it, with <tei:pb n="8"/>
    how much greater justice did I write about this when I portrayed the victory not only in terms
    of battlefield victories (which cannot be dismissed with lies) but also in terms of victories or
    a higher order. But I leave judging whether I was correct in prophesying a victory by the
    Germans not to the reader of the year 1920 or 1921 but to even later years. Have I not in fact
    already been proved right over <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000966">Wilson</tei:rs> and the
    English etc? But that's enough of that. </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">So – to put it in a nutshell – not only do I <tei:hi rend="underline">completely disagree</tei:hi> with your suggestion, but I ask you expressly to leave the
    edition <tei:hi rend="underline">exactly as it is</tei:hi>, just as it flowed from my pen: I
    stand by every word gladly and proudly, indeed I even intend in my future works to take quite as
    many liberties as other people have taken <tei:pb n="9"/> whom it befits even less than it does
    me, among whom I count even the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000966">Wilson</tei:rs>s,
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000534">Lloyd-George</tei:rs>s, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000134">Clemenceau</tei:rs>s, including <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000948">Weingartner</tei:rs>, and whatever else their names may be. Music is truly – and don't
    you forget it, dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356">Director</tei:rs> – not just the
    business of the private lesson, of the domestic or public concert, of the conservatory, but a
    pre-eminent public business of humankind, in the interests of which its spokesmen must enjoy
    full freedom of verbal expression, with the exception of the freedom to lie about the substance! </tei:p>

   <tei:p rend="first">By the way, I am delighted that you have reached the point at which you can
    arrange for a second edition – I see no other way to interpret the fact that in the very case of
     <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work">
     <tei:title level="m">Op. 111</tei:title>
    </tei:rs> you were wanting to detach its Foreword from its text. – </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-25">With cordial greetings, </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Yours truly, </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-55">H. Schenker</tei:signed>
    <tei:date when="1919-06-12">June 12, 1919</tei:date>
   </tei:closer>
  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>