<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2891" sdoID="WSLB-Hds-95664">WSLB-Hds 95664</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2022</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2012-09-28" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002735">Seligmann ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Seligmann, dated July 22, 1903</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1903-07-22T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2022-11-19</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker is sending Seligmann a copy of his Beitrag zur Ornamentik, which he
        hopes will be grounds for receiving a letter of recommendation from Gustav Mahler (for a
        post at the Vienna Conservatory). The writing of it has caused him great anguish, and there
        are even more things he wants to say, which would require writing another book, but without
        a professorship no one will pay attention to him. He also expresses his desire for female
        companionship, to help with his work.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">Heinrich Schenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000819">Adalbert Franz Seligmann</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Gmunden, <tei:hi rend="underline"
              >Esplanade 13</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>L. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000819">Fr.</tei:rs></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Ich übersende Ihnen heute ein Exemplar meiner <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
          >Broschure</tei:hi><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Heinrich
          Schenker, <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001721"><tei:title level="m">Ein Beitrag zur
              Ornamentik</tei:title></tei:rs> (Vienna: Universal Edition, 1st edn [1903]), released
          on July 24, 1903.</tei:note>
        <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">per</tei:hi></tei:foreign> Kreuzband.
        Und nun: bitte, lesen Sie gef. die ersten Blätter, u. sagen Sie, ob sich die Sache eignet,
        gerade von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000556">Mahler</tei:rs> eine Empfehlung an
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000961">Wiener</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Karl von Wiener, then an official in the Austrian Ministry
          of Education who was responsible for overseeing the transition of the Vienna Conservatory
          to a state institution, and became its President in 1909, when it was renamed the <tei:rs
            type="organization" key="entity-002591">Akademie für Musik und darstellende
            Kunst</tei:rs>.</tei:note> zu erbitten. (Menschlich u. persönlich würde er es mir wohl
        machen, so glaube ich wenigstens, – wenn nicht Sachliches dazwischen käme.) </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Sie aber selbst wollen der Schrift zugute halten die Ueberstü<tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overwritten">z</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="superimposed">r</tei:add>
        </tei:subst>zung im Monat Mai, den plötzlichen Auftrag, den Ekel an einer Arbeit, die man
        zumal um den Preis von 100fl längst <tei:pb n="2"/> hinter sich glaubte – u. das Gefühl, daß
        ich unsagbare Dinge, der noch nie in Büchern, in Schulen erörtert worden, obgleich sie das
        wichtigste, <tei:unclear reason="reading">sagen</tei:unclear> u. dass sich diese Geheimnisse
        nicht anders sagen lassen, ausgenommen, dass ich ihnen ein eigenes Buch widme. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Außerdem hat mich mitten in der Arbeit eine Nervosität, durch eine Schicksalsperipetie
        hervorgerufen, geplagt: dazu Sorgen u.s.w. Also urtheilen Sie, l. Fr., nicht zu strenge. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Im Übrigen aber glaube ich fest, eine, dem Inhalt wenigstens nach, klassische
        Monographie der Musikliteratur geschenkt zu <tei:del rend="overstrike">sehe</tei:del> haben
        voll wichtigsten <tei:pb n="3"/> Inhalts u. bester prägnantesten Ausdrücksweise, – wie sie
        augenblicklich die Literatur (die technische nämlich) gar nicht besitzt, u. ehedem nur wenig
        besaß. Das glaube ich, – wer glaubt es aber mir? Es könnte leicht ein unentbehrliches
        Büchlein werden, man wird es zu Rathe ziehen, aber da der Professorstitel fehlt, wird
        niemand meinen Namen citiren, nennen, u. so werde ich noch trotz allem um die Chancen des
        Fortkommens gebracht werden. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Also: ob <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000556"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
            >Mahler</tei:hi></tei:rs>?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Mir fehlt ein Weibliches, das am besten <tei:add place="interlinear-above">in</tei:add>
        mir dichtet: das will ich mit der Professur mir erwirtschaften. Ich bin doch zu feminin, u.
        brauch es meiner <tei:pb n="4"/> Entfaltung halber. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="indent-20">Nun genug. Lassen Sie mich nicht zu lange auf Antwort warten, damit
        ich noch jetzt <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000556"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
            >Mahler</tei:hi></tei:rs> ev. kommen kann.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wie froh bin ich, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003210"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
            >Redl</tei:hi>.</tei:rs> u <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000275">Gaertner</tei:rs>,
        u.s.w. – hinter mir zu haben!!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Josef Redlich and Emil Gärtner were close friends and are mentioned together several
          times in Schenker’s diary in 1906 and 1907. By having these, and others, “behind him,”
          Schenker must be saying that he is now on a financially more secure
        footing.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="indent-20">Zu irgend einer musikalischen, oder sonstigen Gesellschaftlichen
          <tei:foreign xml:lang="ita"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Stretta</tei:hi></tei:foreign>
        (finale) in Aschau<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Aschau:
          village in the Ziller Valley, in the Tyrol.</tei:note> oder <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002339">Ischl</tei:rs> mit Vergnügen jederzeit <tei:del rend="overstrike"
          >zur</tei:del> nach Bedarf zur Verfügung stehend </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">bleibe Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H Schenker</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1903-07-22">22 Juli 1903</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">sideways in the left margin</tei:note>
          Knapp vor der Abreise aus <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004084">Payerbach</tei:rs>
          erhielt ich einen sehr lieben Brief von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000150"
            >d’Albert</tei:rs>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">=
              <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-6_35">OJ 9/6, [35]</tei:ref>, July 18,
            1903.</tei:note> worin er mir zusagt mir zu helfen.</tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Gmunden, <tei:hi rend="underline"
              >Esplanade 13</tei:hi></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000819">friend</tei:rs></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Today I am sending you a copy of my booklet,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
          type="footnote"/> as printed papers. Please read the opening pages and tell me whether the
        matter is suitable for me to ask <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000556">Mahler</tei:rs>
        to send a letter of recommendation to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000961"
          >Wiener</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> (From a human and
        personal perspective, he would probably do this for me, at least I believe so, if nothing
        objective were to get in the way.)</tei:p>

      <tei:p>You yourself however should bear in mind, regarding the book, my hastiness in the month
        of May, the sudden commission, the aversion to a piece work which one thought had long been
        done with – moreover at a price of 100 Florins – <tei:pb n="2"/> and the feeling that I had
        untold things that had never before been discussed in books or in schools, although they
          <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">said</tei:unclear> what was most important, and
        that these secrets could not be said in any other way than by my devoting a book of its own
        to them.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In addition, I was suffering from a nervousness, brought about by a sudden turn of
        events in my destiny; to which may be added troubles, and so on. And so, dear friend, do not
        be too harsh a judge.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Moreover, I firmly believe that I have given to music literature – at least in content
        – a classical monograph, full of the most important <tei:pb n="3"/> content, such as the
        literature (by which I mean the technical literature) does not possess at all at the present
        moment, and in past times possessed only to a small extent. This I believe – but who will
        believe me? It could easily become an indispensable little book; but because I am without
        the title of professor, no one will cite my name or refer to me, and so in spite of
        everything I shall be denied the opportunities of advancement. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>So: what do you think of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000556"
        >Mahler</tei:rs>?</tei:p>

      <tei:p>I am without a female element, which will best work poetically <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">within</tei:add> me; that is something I want to earn with my
        professorship. But I am too feminine, and I need it <tei:pb n="4"/> for the sake of my
        development.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="indent-20">Enough for now. Do not leave me waiting too long for a reply, so that
        I might even now possibly approach <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000556"
        >Mahler</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>How happy I am to have the likes of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003210"
          >Redlich</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000275">Gaertner</tei:rs> behind
          me!!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="indent-20">Available – with pleasure – for any musical or other social
          <tei:foreign xml:lang="ita"><tei:hi rend="italic">stretta</tei:hi></tei:foreign> (finale)
        in Aschau,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> or <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002339">Ischl</tei:rs>, </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">I remain your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H. Schenker</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1903-07-22">July 22, 1903</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">sideways in the left margin</tei:note>
          Shortly before my departure from <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-004084"
            >Payerbach</tei:rs>, I received a very kind letter from <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000150">d’Albert</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/>
          in which he promises to help me.</tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>


    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
