<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="96" sdoID="WSLB-302">WSLB 302</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2009</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2009</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2010</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
   <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
   <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-05-04" who="#IB">XML code revised</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002700">Hertzka ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002701">UE ~ H+JSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002702">UE ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   
   
   
   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Hertzka (UE), May 18, 1919 </dc:title>
   
   <dcterms:created>1919-05-18T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-05-01</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker reminds Hertzka of Hans Weisse's doctoral dissertation, Der Kunstwalzer,
    and recommends it for publication. He laments, in provocatively vulgar language, that the
    Viennese have become subservient to the French.</dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Doktordissertation; doctoral dissertation; Kriegsdienst; war service; Honorar;
    honorarium; Polemik; polemic; Phrasensyphilis; syphillitic word-mongering; deutsche Kaiserreich;
    German empire; Wiener; Viennese Eckel; Ekel; disgust</dc:subject>

   
   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000356">Hertzka</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-002408">UE</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Sehr geehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356">Herr
      Direktor</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Schon<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is
     recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/14, pp. 2071-2072: "An Hertzka (Br.): wegen Weisses
     Arbeit; einige Zeilen politischen Exkurses, die den Ekel vor Wien ausdrücken sollen." ("To
     Hertzka (letter): regarding Weisse's work; a few lines of political excursus, intended to
     express my distaste for Vienna.") </tei:note> vor längerer Zeit erwähnte ich Ihnen gegenüber
    (in einem Schreiben<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">= WSLB 235,
     December 29, 1914. </tei:note>) einer Arbeit des H. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Hans
      Weisse</tei:rs>, „<tei:title>Der Kunst<tei:hi rend="underline">walzer</tei:hi></tei:title>“,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">The work remained unpublished; a typescript, entitled "Der Kunstwalzer und seine
     bedeutendsten Vertreter," inscribed to Schenker and dated February 1915, is preserved in the
     Oster Collection. </tei:note> die ich Ihnen wegen ganz besonderer Vorzüge der Sprache wie
    Inhaltsführung aufs Allerwärmste empfahl. In etwas erweiterter Form – auch die Walzer von
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000869">Strauss</tei:rs> etc. sind miteinbezogen worden – hat
    nun je<tei:subst>
     <tei:del rend="overwritten">d</tei:del>
     <tei:add place="superimposed">n</tei:add>
    </tei:subst>e Arbeit als Doktordissertation gedient u. nun wäre der junge Autor (der auch
    Kriegsdienste hinter sich hat u. daher erst jetzt hervortritt) bereit, die Arbeit zu
    veröffentlichen. <tei:hi rend="underline">Mit</tei:hi>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">Beispielen</tei:hi> etwa 300 S. Maschinschrift. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Wären Sie geneigt, dieser Arbeit näherzutreten? In Anbetracht dessen, daß die Arbeit schon
    als Dissertation gedient hat, wäre H. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs>
    bereit, die Honorarfrage durchaus nicht tragisch zu nehmen. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Ich kann nur noch einmal sagen, daß Sie nicht bald eine schönere Arbeit erhalten werden. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Wäre nur schon unsere Krisis zu Ende, damit schließ<tei:supplied reason="cut-off">lich</tei:supplied>
    <tei:pb n="2"/> auch ich selbst meine <tei:rs key="entity-001727">Arbeit</tei:rs> zu
     <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002405">Cotta</tei:rs> bringen kann. Die Gesinnungslosigkeit der
     <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002506">Österreich</tei:rs>, u.
    ganz besonders unserer lieben Wiener, einschließlich der Adler (<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000005">Vater</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000002">Sohn</tei:rs>), der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000022">Austerlitz</tei:rs>e,
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000477">Karl Kraus</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000031">Hermann Bahr</tei:rs> u. <tei:unclear reason="reading">wie</tei:unclear> alle diese
    Prachtkerle von Auslandslakaien heißen, ist mir sehr nahe gegangen, u. wie nahe geht mir jetzt
    gar erst unsere Abstieg zu einem französischen <tei:foreign xml:lang="fre">Departement</tei:foreign>! Schon tausendmal vom Franzmann betrogen - auf jedem Blatt der
    Geschäfte ists zu lesen –, traut der ehrlose, blöde Wiener wieder einmal der französischen
    Phrasensyphilis. Heute die Phrase, morgen der Fußtritt, aber der Wiener drängt sich förmlich zum
    – Sie erlauben das einzige gemäße Wort – Arschkuß, u. nicht einmal soviel <tei:hi rend="underline">geschäftlicher</tei:hi> Klugheit besitzt der elende Tropf, zu sehen, wie sich
    das <tei:hi rend="underline">Nationalgefühl in Geld umsetzt</tei:hi>. (S. das deutsche
    Kaiserreich, u. soeben die Erträgnisse der Westler, die alle an ihren Nationen kramphaft
    festhielten u. sich dafür in Geld bezahlt machen). Also nicht einmal noch Geldvorteile weiß der
    dumme Wiener zu erkennen! </tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> Verzeihung für den Exkurs, der mir in die Feder von selbst gekommen,
    jedenfalls aber bezeugt, wie voll ich des Eckels bin, den <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Wien</tei:rs> (in gar das der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000022">Austerlitz</tei:rs>e!) mir verursacht. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Einer gef., hoffentliche<tei:supplied xml:lang="syntax">n</tei:supplied> auch zustimmenden
    Antwort entgegensehen. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Zeichne mit besten Grüßen</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60">
     <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">H Schenker</tei:hi>
    </tei:signed>
    <tei:date when="1919-05-18">18. Mai 1919</tei:date>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>



  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356">
     Director</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>A<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> long, long time ago, I mentioned to you
    (in a letter<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/>) a piece of work by Mr.
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</tei:rs>,
     <tei:title level="m">The Art <tei:hi rend="underline">Waltz</tei:hi></tei:title>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> which I recommended to you in the warmest possible
    manner on account of the special merits of its language as well as the organization of its
    content. In a somewhat extended form – even the waltzes of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000869">Strauss</tei:rs> etc. have been incorporated – this work has served as a doctoral
    dissertation, and now its young author (who has war service behind him, which is why he is
    coming forward only now) is ready to publish the work. <tei:hi rend="underline">With music
     examples</tei:hi>, <tei:supplied reason="clarity">it amounts to</tei:supplied> something like
    300 pages of typescript. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Would you be interested in examining this piece of work? In view of the fact that the work
    has already served as a dissertation, Mr. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs> would be willing not to treat the question of his honorarium overly
    seriously. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>I can only say once again that you will not readily come across a finer piece of work. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>If only our crisis were already over, so that I myself, too, could at long last <tei:pb n="2"/> deliver my <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001727">book</tei:rs> to <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002405">Cotta</tei:rs>. It distresses me deeply to see the unprincipled nature
    of <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002506">Austria</tei:rs>, and
    especially that of our dear Viennese people, including the Adlers (<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000005">father</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000002">son</tei:rs>), the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000022">Austerlitz</tei:rs>es,
     <tei:persName>Karl Kraus</tei:persName>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000031">Hermann
     Bahr</tei:rs>, and whatever all these foreign-lackey types <tei:unclear reason="reading">are called</tei:unclear>; and how it cuts me to the quick now to see us reduced to the status
    of a <tei:foreign xml:lang="fre">département</tei:foreign> of France! Betrayed already a
    thousand times by the Frenchies – it is there to be read in every business newspaper – yet again
    the dishonorable, feeble-minded Viennese trust the French syphillitic word-mongering. Today the
    word-mongering, tomorrow the kick up the backside, but the Viennese people literally cannot wait
    to – forgive me, but this is the only way to put it – kiss <tei:supplied reason="clarity">the
     French</tei:supplied> arse, and the wretched good-for-nothings do not have the <tei:hi rend="underline">commercial</tei:hi> acumen to see how <tei:hi rend="underline">national
     feeling translates itself into money</tei:hi>. (Look at the German empire, and now
     <tei:supplied reason="clarity">look at</tei:supplied> the profits of the westerners, all of
    whom clung desperately to their nations and that paid off financially). So the stupid Viennese
    are not even capable of recognizing financial advantages. </tei:p>

   <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> Please forgive the excursus. My pen had a mind of its own, but this at
    least testifies to how full I am of the disgust to which <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002484">Vienna</tei:rs> (and especially the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000022">Austerlitz</tei:rs>es) gives rise in me. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>In looking forward to a hopeful and also affirmative reply, </tei:p>




   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">I remain, with best wishes, </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Yours, </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-60">H. Schenker</tei:signed>
    <tei:date when="1919-05-18">May 18, 1919</tei:date>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>