<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2909" sdoID="WSLB-Hds-94476">WSLB-Hds 94476</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2022</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2012-09-28" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002735">Seligmann ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Seligmann, dated July 17, 1909</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1909-07-17T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2022-11-23</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker thanks Seligmann for helping him to get a friend’s essay on Byron’s
        Manfred published in a Viennese newspaper. He then asks whether it would be possible to make
        a judgment about painters, and paintings, on purely objective grounds, as he (Schenker) has
        been aiming to do with composers and musical works.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">Heinrich Schenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000819">Adalbert Franz Seligmann</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/><tei:rs type="place"
              key="entity-002396"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Steinach
            a/Brenner</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000819">Freund</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Herzlichst danke ich für Lektüre u. Empfehlung.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01"
          type="editorial" place="foot">This concerns an essay on Byron’s <tei:title level="m"
            >Manfred</tei:title> written by a friend of Schenker’s; in his previous letter (<tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="WSLB-Hds-94475">WSLB-Hds 94475</tei:ref>), he had asked
          Seligmann to read it and to send a letter of recommendation to the <tei:title level="j"
            >Neue Freie Presse</tei:title>, or some other Viennese newspaper, if he thought it
          worthy of publication.</tei:note> Ich weiß nicht, ob Sie in Ihrem Schreiben an H.
          Novak<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Herr Novak: possibly Karl
          Franz Nowak, member of the editorial department of the <tei:title level="j">Neue Freie
            Presse</tei:title> (<tei:title level="m">Lehmanns Wohnungs-Anzeiger
          Wien</tei:title>).</tei:note> auch meinen Namen mitgenannt haben; wenn ja, habe ich alle
        Ursache zu befürchten, daß H. N. Rache für <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000471"
          >Korngold</tei:rs> gerade an mir nehmen könnte. Denn am Tage, an dem <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000471">Korngold</tei:rs>s Vertreter unseren <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs> öffentlich furchtbar blosgestellt hat, hatten
        Gärtner[which?] u. ich gefällig Gelegenheit, H. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000471"
          >Kgld</tei:rs> mindestens vor der Redaktion zu blamieren, u. zw. wegen des <tei:foreign
          xml:lang="lat"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">lapsus</tei:hi></tei:foreign>: <tei:rs
          type="composition" key="entity-001490"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Chopin</tei:hi>
          <tei:title>Nocturne G<tei:hi rend="supralinear">dur</tei:hi></tei:title></tei:rs> für
          <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-003177"><tei:title>Impromptu Fis<tei:hi
              rend="supralinear">dur</tei:hi></tei:title></tei:rs>. Unser Brief kam auch an H.
        Novak, freilich offen von uns signiert. Es wäre schade, wenn der <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat"
          >horrende <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">lapsus</tei:hi></tei:foreign>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000471">Kgld</tei:rs>’s auch noch das Opfer eines guten
        Aufsatzes überflüssigerweise fordern würde. Indessen will ich hoffen, das H. Nov. die Dinge
        auseinanderzuhalten verstehen wird. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Mich freut es sehr, daß Sie indirekt mein Verhalten gegenüber den
        anmaßenden <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Secundogenitoren</tei:hi><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
          type="editorial" place="foot">There are two possible explanations for this puzzling term:
          (1) the expression <tei:hi rend="italic">secondo genitore</tei:hi> (Italian: “second
          parent”), in this case presented as the latinized <tei:hi rend="italic"
            >Secundogenitoren</tei:hi> (with German dative plural agreement -n) is sometimes used to
          describe a teacher who has an especially close relationship to his or her pupil, or an
          adult relative who acts as a “second parent” to a child; (2) <tei:hi rend="italic"
            >Secundogenitoren</tei:hi> (which can be read as <tei:hi rend="italic"
            >Secundogenituren</tei:hi>), i.e. beneficiaries of “secundogeniture,” which grants the
          right of a second-born son, or younger sons, to inherit part of an estate, contrary to
          “primogeniture.”</tei:note> billigen. Noch mehr aber freue ich mich auf Ihre angekündete
        Ar– <tei:pb n="2"/> beit. Wenn Sie doch einmal versuchen wollten, öffentlich darzutun, uns
        den Unterschied zwischen einer wirklich genialen Leistung u. einer blos „talentierten“ in
        Ihrer Kunst ausmacht? In der Musik läßt es sich ganz genau sagen, dass eine Symphonie z. B.
        von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000181">Dvořak</tei:rs>, Herzogenberg, Sinding,
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000265">Fuchs</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Heinrich von Herzogenberg (1843–1900), Austrian composer;
          Christian Sinding (1856–1941), Norwegian composer; Robert Fuchs (1847–1927), Austrian
          composer, who taught harmony, counterpoint, and composition at the Vienna Conservatory
          from 1874 to 1912. Fuchs was, notably, admired by Brahms; but Schenker was critical of his
          compositional technique; see diary entry for January 27, 1907: “… a very short-breathed
          and spiritually too primitively shaped Serenade by Fuchs.”.</tei:note> überhaupt noch
          <tei:hi rend="underline">keine</tei:hi> Symphonie ist, da diese Autoren alles aufzubieten
        scheinen, um eine gegenteilige Wirkung hervorzubringen. Z. B. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000808"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Schumann</tei:hi></tei:rs>, <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000900">Tschaikovsky</tei:rs> schreiben <tei:hi
          rend="lateinschr">Symph</tei:hi>. u. Quartette meistens als Sammlungen von kleinen
          <tei:term>Liedform</tei:term>en; eine <tei:term>Liedform</tei:term> um die andere ergiebt
        zwar am Ende <tei:add place="interlinear-above">auch</tei:add> eine Länge, aber die Summe
        ist doch was anderes, als das Gefüge einer <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000344"
          >Haydn</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000612">Mozart</tei:rs>, <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000055"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Beeth</tei:hi></tei:rs>,
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000589"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
          >Mendelssohn</tei:hi></tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000094"
          >Brahms</tei:rs>’ <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Symphonie</tei:hi>. Man kann sogar erklären,
        warum es so sein – müsse, wie es in den <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Symph</tei:hi>. der
        letzgenannten Meister eben zugeht. Von hier aus gelange ich dann zu begreifen, was zur
        vollen Erfüllung eines Problems (rein technisch) gehört, u. sodann vom Meister den
        Nichtkönner zu scheiden. Ich meine: dass die Welt auch <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000265">Fuchs</tei:rs> einen „Meister“ nennt, macht mich nicht irre; <tei:pb
          n="3"/> ich weiß sehr wohl, warum er keiner ist. Nun aber – u. dieses Rätsel plagt mich
        seit Langem – lese ich immer wieder auch in Ihren Berichten (die ich nebenbei gesagt alle
        sammle) von nahezu 50–100 Meistern. Nehmen Sie das wörtlich, oder nicht? Aber mir scheint,
        als ob es in der Malerei doch etwas anders wäre, als in der Musik, u. daß es dort vielleicht
        mehr Meister wirklich geben könnte. Mich interessiert diese Frage nicht wegen der Zu- bezw.
        Aberkennung des Meistertitels – das wäre doch zu kindisch – <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">sondern</tei:add> nur, weil ich wissen möchte, ob man <tei:hi
          rend="underline">technische</tei:hi> Gründe hat (oder was dasselbe: ob das Problem selbst
        die Forderungen aufstellt), <tei:add place="interlinear-above">z. B.</tei:add>
        <tei:sic><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Rembrant</tei:hi></tei:sic> von Horovitz<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Leopold Horovitz (1838–1917),
          (Austro-)Hungarian painter, who became a successful portrait artist. </tei:note> zu
        scheiden. Vielleicht haben Sie einmal Gelegenheit, darauf an der <tei:rs type="journal"
          key="entity-002559"><tei:title>N. Fr. Pr.</tei:title></tei:rs> zu antworten; vor der
        Drucklegung des III<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">.</tei:supplied> Bandes<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">The third volume of Schenker’s major
          theoretical project, the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001723"><tei:title level="m">Neue
              Musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:title></tei:rs>. In this context, it refers
          to the long essay <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001759"><tei:title level="m">Über den
              Niedergang der Kompositionskunst</tei:title></tei:rs> (“The Decline of the Art of
          Composition”), which was intended to follow <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001725"
              ><tei:title level="m">Kontrapunkt</tei:title></tei:rs> but remained unpublished in
          Schenker’s lifetime.</tei:note> möchte ich gerne Ihre Meinung über jenen Punkt hören. – </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs> hat hier einen
        Flügel. Und ich, – hätte ich nur wo zu excedieren! <tei:pb n="4"/> Eine kleine Hoffnung habe
        ich …, aber Arbeit geht vor dem Vergnügen, so viel hat mich der ewige Canon der Arbeit schon
        gelehrt. </tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Nochmals besten Dank u. </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">beste Grüße</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H Schenker</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1909-07-17">17. 7. 09</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Fl.</tei:rs> läßt bestens u. herzlichst
          grüßen!</tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine rend="indent-60"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/><tei:rs type="place"
              key="entity-002396">Steinach am Brenner</tei:rs></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000819">friend</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Most cordial thanks for reading and recommendation.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
          type="footnote"/> I do not know whether in your letter to Mr. Novak,<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> you also mentioned my name; if so, I have every
        reason to fear that Mr. N. could actually take vengeance on me, on behalf of <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000471">Korngold</tei:rs>. For on the day on which <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000471">Korngold</tei:rs>’s representatives publicly exposed our
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs> in the most frightful way,
        Gärtner and I happened to have the opportunity to embarrass <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000471">Korngold</tei:rs> before the editorial office <tei:supplied
          reason="clarity">of the <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002559"><tei:title level="j"
              >Neue Freie Presse</tei:title></tei:rs></tei:supplied>, and indeed on account of his
        mistaking <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-001490">Chopin’s <tei:title>Nocturne in G
            major</tei:title></tei:rs> for the <tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-003177"
            ><tei:title>Impromptu in F<tei:g type="sharp"/> major</tei:title></tei:rs>. Our letter
        also reached Mr. Novak, openly signed by us, of course. It would be a pity if <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000471">Korngold</tei:rs>’s horrendous error would unnecessarily
        exact even the sacrifice of a good essay. Nonetheless, I will hope that Mr. Novak will
        understand to keep the matters separate.</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">I am very glad that you indirectly endorse my attitude towards the
        presumptuous <tei:hi rend="italic">secondi genitori</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
          type="footnote"/> But I am even more looking forward to your forthcoming work. <tei:pb
          n="2"/> Would you, however, be willing to attempt once to demonstrate to us openly the
        difference between a true accomplishment of genius in your art, and a merely “talented” one?
        In music, it is possible to say quite precisely that a symphony by, for example, <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000181">Dvořák</tei:rs>, Herzogenberg, Sinding or <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000265">Fuchs</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
          type="footnote"/> is <tei:hi rend="underline">by no means</tei:hi> yet a symphony, as
        these composers seem to offer everything in order to produce the opposite effect. <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000808">Schumann</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000900">Tchaikovsky</tei:rs>, for example, write symphonies and quartets
        mainly as collections of small <tei:term>song-form</tei:term>s; one
          <tei:term>song-form</tei:term> after another will, for sure, <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">also</tei:add> result in a long work, but their sum is actually
        something different from the structure of a symphony by <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000344">Haydn</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000612"
          >Mozart</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>, <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000589">Mendelssohn</tei:rs> or <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000094">Brahms</tei:rs>. One can even explain why it is – must be – that way,
        as it actually happens in the symphonies of the last-named masters. From here, I then
        succeed in understanding what is necessary for the complete solution to a problem (from a
        purely <tei:hi rend="underline">technical</tei:hi> perspective), and then to distinguish a
        non-artist from a master. What I am saying is this: That the world calls even <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000265">Fuchs</tei:rs> a “master” does not surprise me; <tei:pb
          n="3"/> I know quite well why he isn’t one. But now – and this puzzle has plagued me for a
        long time – I am forever reading, even in your reviews (which, by the way I collect in their
        entirety), about well-nigh 50 to a 100 masters. Do you mean this literally, or not? But it
        seems to me that things are somewhat different in the art of painting than in music, and
        that in the former there really could well be a greater number of masters. The question
        interests me not because of the conferring or revocation of the title of “master” – that
        would indeed be too childish – but <tei:add place="interlinear-above">only</tei:add> because
        I would like to know whether one has technical grounds (or, what amounts to the same thing,
        whether the problem itself establishes the claims) for distinguishing, <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">for example,</tei:add> Rembrandt from Horovitz.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> Perhaps you will some day have the occasion to
        reply to this in the <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002559"><tei:title level="j">Neue
            Freie Presse</tei:title></tei:rs>. I would gladly hear your views on that point before
        volume III<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> goes to press. –</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs> has a piano
        here. And I – if only I had somewhere to make mischief! <tei:pb n="4"/> I have a small
        amount of hope … but work takes precedence over pleasure, this much the eternal canon of
        work has already taught me.</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Once again, best thanks and </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-20">best greetings.</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H. Schenker</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1909-07-17">July 17, 1909</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Floriz</tei:rs> sends his best and most
          cordial greetings!</tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>


    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
