<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2921" sdoID="WSLB-Hds-95654">WSLB-Hds 95654</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2022</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2012-09-28" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002735">Seligmann ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Seligmann, dated July 24, 1916</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1916-07-24T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2022-11-28</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker tells Seligmann that he has arranged for copies of his critical
        editions of Beethoven’s Op. 110 and Op. 111 to be sent to him. He speaks of the positive
        interest his works have received in Germany, and about Hugo Riemann asking him to provide
        autobiographical material for an entry in the next edition of his music
        lexicon.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">Heinrich Schenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000819">Adalbert Franz Seligmann</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>St. Anton a/Arlberg (Tirol)</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Hotel Post</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000819">Freund</tei:rs>!<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is recorded in
            Schenker’s diary for July 24, 1916: “an Seligmann Brief: Motiviere die Verspätung der
            Sendung u. füge eine Darstellung der Erfolge hinzu, mit Seitenhieben gegen Riemann,
            Kretzschmar usw. ” (“letter to Seligmann: I explain the delay of the package and add an
            account of the successes, with sideswipes at Riemann, Kretzschmar,
          etc.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Endlich könnte ich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356">Direktor Herzka</tei:rs>
        den Auftrag geben, daß er Ihnen mein <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001735">op.
          110</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001736">111</tei:rs> von <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> zukommen lassen. Daß Sie <tei:rs
          type="work" key="entity-001734">op. 109</tei:rs> besitzen, glaube ich nicht zweifeln zu
        müssen. Als <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001735">op. 110</tei:rs> im Vorjahre, pardon vor
        2 Jahren erschien, wird <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356">Hertzka</tei:rs>’s
        Patriotismus derart in die Höhe geschnellt, daß er nicht dazu zu bewegen war, an etwas
        Anderes u. wäre es auch an seine Pflichten zu denken; er ließ das Geschäft förmlich ruhen –
        am Ende halten Sie es für wirtschaftliche Feigheit eines kurzblickenden Krämers? — u. weder
        ich selbst noch auch diejenigen Personen, denen ich Ehrenexemplaren zukommen lassen wollte,
        konnten zu solchen gelangen. Nach <tei:hi rend="underline">einem</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">Jahr</tei:hi> erfuhr ich, daß <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000356">Hertzka</tei:rs> nicht einmal an einen <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000454">Herrn in Fkft. a/Main</tei:rs> das schuldige Exemplar abzusenden sich
        entschließen konnte, obgleich dieser sein kostbares <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
          >Autograph</tei:hi> in liebenswürdigster Weise zur Verfügung gestellt hat!<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker is referring to the Frankfurt
          jeweler Louis Koch (1862–1930), whose collection of Beethoven manuscripts included the
          autograph score of the sonata Op. 101. This manuscript was to be consulted for Schenker’s
          critical edition of that work, not published until 1921, and not of any of the three
          sonatas that had already appeared. </tei:note> (NB. habe ich dann selbst dieses
        Wienerische nach meinen besten Kräften korrigiert.) Erst heute beginnt <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000356">H.</tei:rs> einigermaßen „zu sich“ zu kommen, u. da ist er nun,
        besonders nachdem ich ihm mitgeteilt, daß ich die Bände noch <tei:pb n="2"/> ausständigen
        Sonaten <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001737">op. 101</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001738">106</tei:rs> nicht mehr mache, etwas „läufiger“ geworden, um mich
          <tei:hi rend="underline">geziemend</tei:hi> ordinär <tei:del rend="overstrike"
          >zu</tei:del> auszudrücken, u. tut nun gerne, was ohnehin nur seine verdammte Pflicht ist.
        Dies die kurze <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356">Hertzka</tei:rs>-getränkte
        Geschichte der Sendung, die Sie entweder schon erreicht hat oder bald erreichen wird. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Da ich Sie so lange nicht gesehen habe, bin ich gewissermaßen genötigt, hinzuzufügen,
        das die Stücke <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001734">op. 109</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001735">110</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001736">111</tei:rs> in
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482">Deutschland</tei:rs> nicht geringes Aufsehen
        gemacht haben u. wie aus Jahrbüchern, Katalogen usw. ersichtlich ist, viel gelesen, um nicht
        zu sagen studiert werden. Die Wirkung auch meiner früheren Arbeiten, der <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001724"><tei:title level="m">Harmonie</tei:title></tei:rs>- wie <tei:rs
          type="work" key="entity-001726"><tei:title level="m"
          >Kontrapunktslehre</tei:title></tei:rs>, ist derart in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002482">Deutschland</tei:rs> gestiegen (Belege sind in vielen
        Musikzeitschriften, auch politischen Tagebl. <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002286"
          >München</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs> etc. in
        allerhand Formen zu finden, in Studien nach meinen Mustern mit Zitaten u.s.w), daß ich in
          <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001736">op. 111</tei:rs> es wagen dürfte, zu Nutz u Freude
        des Lesers auch den Weltkrieg in die <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055"
          >Beethoven</tei:rs>-Debatte mithineinzuziehen, freilich in Fußnoten, die meistens, wie ich
        zu sagen pflege<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> Fußtrittnoten sind,
          <tei:hi rend="underline">leider</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">sein</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="double-underline">müssen</tei:hi>. Eben diese allgemeinen Betrachtungen in der
          <tei:hi rend="underline">Literatur</tei:hi>rubrik <tei:add place="interlinear-above">von
            <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001736"><tei:hi rend="underline">op.
            111</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:add> möchte ich Ihrem Interesse zuvörderst empfehlen,
        vorausgesetzt, daß Sie augenblicklich Zeit u. Lust hiezu <tei:pb n="3"/> aufbringen. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Und da ich schon einmal den Punkt der Erfolge berührt habe, so will ich nur erwähnen,
        daß schon vor etwa 2 oder 3 Jahren sich H. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000712">Prof.
            <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Riemann</tei:hi></tei:rs>, der einzige in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002482">Deutschland</tei:rs> in Frage kommende „Konkurrent“, höchstpersönlich
        an mich wandte, mit der Bitte um Daten für sein Lexicon. Da ich diesen Engländer
          kannte,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker did not know
          Riemann personally: he is making a disparaging comment on his character. – A form letter
          from Riemann is preserved as <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-13-23_1">OJ 13/23,
            [1]</tei:ref>, April 15, 1913.</tei:note> machte ich mir den Spaß, in 3 Sätzen (nach Art
        des alten <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Rabbi Hillel</tei:hi><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04"
          type="editorial" place="foot">Hillel the Elder (fl. 30 BCE – 10 CE), Jewish sage and
          religious leader, known for his pithy maxims.</tei:note>) den Inhalt meiner Theorien –
        soeben bin ich im Begriffe, den <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001727">2. Halbband des
            <tei:title>Kontrapunkt</tei:title></tei:rs>es abzuschließen, um ihn in sehr absehbarer
        Zeit zu <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002405"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
            >Cotta</tei:hi></tei:rs> zu bringen – zu comprimieren, um ihm die Möglichkeit einer
        Fälschung zu benehmen. Aber da entpuppte sich der „<tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
          >Baralong</tei:hi>“-<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000712"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
            >Riemann</tei:hi></tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Schenker compares Riemann’s professional behavior with the actions of the captain and
          crew of the British warship <tei:hi rend="italic">HMS Baralong</tei:hi> in the Irish Sea,
          in the summer of 1915, which Germany regarded as war crimes.</tei:note> wider Erwarten
        noch „baralonger: u. brachte im <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Lexicon</tei:hi>, nachdem er das
        Unwichtigste ausführlich brachte, die Hauptsache so: „<tei:hi rend="underline"
        >Auch</tei:hi>(!) schriebe er über die IX Sinf. von B. u. verfaßte eine Harm.- u. Ktplehre.“
        Nun kommt, wie Sie es doch von mir erwarten, die ordentliche Justifizierung dieses Mannes,
        der ohnehin nur mehr auf einer Lunge pfeift (die „Lexicon“-Bronchien arbeiten noch!) – den
        anderen Lungenflügel (Theorien) habe ihm schon längst exstirpiert, wie H <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000484">Dir. <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
              ><tei:sic>Kretschmar</tei:sic></tei:hi></tei:rs> in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs> beide Flügel auf einmal. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Daß unser l. Wien nicht als Gegenbeweis der Erfolge angeführt werden darf, brauch ich
        Ihnen nicht zu sagen. Und als kürzlich mir mitgeteilt wurde, H. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000076">Bittner</tei:rs> habe gemeint, es wäre nur „Kleinigkeiten“, auf die es
        nicht ankommt – kein Zweifel, daß er die Arbeiten gar nie gelesen hat u. der reichen Dame
        gegenüber <tei:add place="interlinear-above">es</tei:add> nur nicht zugeben wollte – so
        erwiderte ich, diese „Kleinigkeiten“ machen schließlich den „großen“ Unterschied zwischen
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000076">Bittner</tei:rs> u. einem Meister aus u.s.w. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Sie sehen, ich bin guter Dinge. Bin ich doch am <tei:date
          when="1916-07-11">11. d. M.</tei:date> von der Musterungskomission freigegeben worden (nun
        schon zum 2. Mal) u. darf den <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001727"
            ><tei:title>Kp.</tei:title></tei:rs> fertigmachen, der, ohne Eitelkeit ist es gesagt,
        schon so lange erwartet u. begehrt wird! </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Könnte ich Sie denn nicht einmal in Wien wo sehen, Abs, Nächstens in einem
        Cafehaus? </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Seien Sie nach alter Art aufs Beste gegrüßt</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">von Ihrem</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H Schenker</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1916-07-24">24. Juli 1916</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>St. Anton am Arlberg (Tyrol)</tei:addrLine>
          <tei:addrLine>Hotel Post</tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
        <tei:salute>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000819">friend</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Finally, I was able to ask <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356">Director
          Hertzka</tei:rs> to have my critical editions of <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001735"
          >Op. 110</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001736">Op. 111</tei:rs> by <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> sent to you. That you possess <tei:rs
          type="work" key="entity-001734">Op. 109</tei:rs> is something I do not believe that I must
        doubt. When <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001735">Op. 110</tei:rs> appeared last year –
        sorry, two years ago –<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356">Hertzka</tei:rs>’s
        patriotism soared to the extent that he was not to be motivated to think of anything else,
        even if it was one of his responsibilities. He verily let the business go silent – do you
        ultimately regard this as businesslike cowardice of a short-sighted shopkeeper? – and
        neither I myself nor those to whom I wanted to give complimentary copies could obtain these.
          <tei:hi rend="underline">After a year</tei:hi>, I learned that <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000356">Hertzka</tei:rs> did not even send the copy that he owed to a <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000454">gentleman in Frankfurt am Main</tei:rs>, although he had
        most kindly placed his precious autograph score at my disposal!<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> (NB: I then used my best powers to correct this
        Viennese act <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of neglect</tei:supplied>.) Only now is <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000356">Hertzka</tei:rs> beginning to come “to his senses,” to
        some extent; and after I informed him that I would no longer do the two remaining volumes,
        On <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001737">Op. 101</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001738">Op. 106</tei:rs>, <tei:pb n="2"/> he has become a little more “in
        heat,” if I may express myself in a <tei:hi rend="underline">becomingly</tei:hi> ordinary
        way; and he is now happy to do that which in any event is only his damned duty. That is the
        brief <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356">Hertzka</tei:rs>-imbued story of the package
        that either has already reached you or will soon reach you.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>As I have not seen you for such a long time, I am obliged to a certain extent to add
        that my works on Opp. <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001734">109</tei:rs>, <tei:rs
          type="work" key="entity-001735">110</tei:rs>, and <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001736"
          >111</tei:rs> have aroused not a small sensation in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002482">Germany</tei:rs> and, as can be seen from yearbooks and catalogues and
        the like, are much read, not to mention studied. The effect of my earlier works, <tei:rs
          type="work" key="entity-001724"><tei:title level="m">Theory of
          Harmony</tei:title></tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001726"><tei:title
            level="m">Counterpoint</tei:title></tei:rs>, has increased in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002482">Germany</tei:rs> to such an extent (proofs may be found in many music
        journals, also political newspapers in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002286"
          >Munich</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs> etc., and in
        all sorts of forms), that I could dare to include in <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001736"
          >Op. 111</tei:rs> the world war in the <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055"
          >Beethoven</tei:rs> debate, for the benefit and joy of its readers – of course in
        footnotes, which for the most part are (and <tei:hi rend="underline">unfortunately must
          be</tei:hi>) for the most part, as I am accustomed to saying, “foot-step notes.” Precisely
        these general observations in the <tei:hi rend="underline">secondary-literature</tei:hi>
        section <tei:add place="interlinear-above">of <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001736"
              ><tei:hi rend="underline">Op. 111</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:add> are things I would
        recommend first and foremost for your interest, assuming that you <tei:pb n="3"/> have the
        time and for this, and are in the mood.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>And as I have already touched on the matter of my successes, I shall mention only that,
        even two or three years ago, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000712">Prof.
          Riemann</tei:rs> – the only person in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482"
          >Germany</tei:rs> that could be called my “competitor,” approached me most personally with
        the request for information for his dictionary. As I knew <tei:supplied reason="clarity">the
          character of</tei:supplied> this Englishman,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"
        /> I had the fun of summarizing the content of my theories in three sentences (in the style
        of the ancient Rabbi Hillel<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/>) – I am at the
        point of finishing the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001727">second half-volume of
            <tei:title level="m">Counterpoint</tei:title></tei:rs> so that I can give it to <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002405">Cotta</tei:rs> soon – to prevent him from possibly
        falsifying them. But then the <tei:hi rend="italic">Baralong</tei:hi>-<tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000712">Riemann</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/>
        against all expectation, revealed his true colors in an even more Baralong fashion by
        expressing the main matter of my work (after discussing the least important material
        extensively): “He <tei:hi rend="underline">also</tei:hi>(!) wrote about Beethoven’s Ninth
        Symphony and is the author of a theory of harmony, and of counterpoint.” And now, as you
        would of course expect from me, the proper execution of this man, who at any rate is
        breathing only with one lung (the <tei:title level="m">Lexikon</tei:title> bronchial tubes
        are still functioning) – the other wing of his lungs (theories) I have long ago extirpated –
        as I did, both wings at the same time, to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000484">Director
          Kretzschmar</tei:rs> in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>That our dear Vienna cannot be adduced as counter-proof to my successes {4} is
        something I need not tell you. And as I was recently informed that Mr. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000076">Bittner</tei:rs> said they were only “bagatelles” that are of no
        significance – no doubt, he has never read them and just didn’t want to admit <tei:add
          place="interlinear-above">that</tei:add> in front of the wealthy woman – I replied that
        these “bagatelles” ultimately mark the “great” difference between <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000076">Bittner</tei:rs> and a master, etc. </tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">As you can see, I am in cheerful spirits. And I was even dismissed by the
        enlistment commission on the <tei:date when="1916-07-11">11th of the month</tei:date> (for
        the second time now) and may finish <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001727"><tei:title
            level="m">Counterpoint</tei:title></tei:rs> which – it can be said without vanity – has
        been awaited and desired!</tei:p>

      <tei:p rend="first">Could I not see you sometime, somewhere in Vienna, in the evening, at
        night in a coffee-house?</tei:p>




      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Accept the best greetings, in the good old way, </tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">from your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H. Schenker</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1916-07-24">July 24, 1916</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
