<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
    xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
    xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
    <sdo:collectionDesc>
        <sdo:source>
            <sdo:correspondence mfID="3145" sdoID="WSLB-Hds-191-570">WSLB-Hds 191.570</sdo:correspondence>
        </sdo:source>

        <tei:handNotes>
            <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="major">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
            <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="minor">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
        </tei:handNotes>

        <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
            <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
            <tei:resp>Transcription, 2023</tei:resp>
            <tei:resp>Translation, 2023</tei:resp>
        </tei:respStmt>

        <tei:respStmt xml:id="IDB">
            <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
            <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2023</tei:resp>
        </tei:respStmt>

        <tei:revisionDesc>
            <tei:change when="2015-09-18" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
        </tei:revisionDesc>
    </sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:record ID="r0001">

        <sdo:itemDesc>
            <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002726">DeutschOE ~
                H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
            <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002712">DeutschOE ~
                HSchenker</tei:rs>
            <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002727">DeutschOE+H ~
                H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
            <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

            <dc:title>Letter from Schenker to Deutsch in Jeanette Schenker’s hand, dated October 12,
                1930 </dc:title>

            <dcterms:created>1930-10-12T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
            <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2023-05-17</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
            <dc:description>Schenker will follow all of Deutsch’s recent suggestions regarding the
                page formatting of the third Meisterwerk yearbook, for which he is most grateful. --
                He then launches a further attack upon Anthony van Hoboken’s
                character.</dc:description>
            <dc:subject/>


            <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
            <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
            <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000164">DeutschOE</marcrel:recipient>

        </sdo:itemDesc>


        <tei:div type="transcription">

            <tei:opener>
                <tei:add><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>diktiert.</tei:add><tei:lb/>
                <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>Mein lieber Professor <tei:rs
                        key="entity-000164" type="person">Deutsch</tei:rs>!<tei:note
                        xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Sending of this letter is
                        recorded in Schenker’s diary for October 12, 1930: “An Deutsch (Br.
                        diktirt): Hobokeniana von Donnerstag.” (“To Deutsch (letter, dictated)”:
                        Thursday’s Hoboken saga.”).</tei:note></tei:salute>
            </tei:opener>

            <tei:p>Vielen Dank für Ihren Rat,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
                    place="foot">Deutsch’s letter <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-54-325">OC
                        54/325</tei:ref> of October 11, 1930 advising Schenker about negotiating
                    proof-correction costs with the publishers.</tei:note> ich habe in meiner
                Antwort an den <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002627"
                    >Verlag</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"
                    >Schenker’s diary entry of October 12, 1930 records a letter (not surviving) to
                    Drei Masken Verlag: “An den Verlag (Br. diktirt): ich lehne ab, für alle
                    Korrekturen aufzukommen, bitte um eine detaillirte Rechnung; ein Bindemuster
                    wäre willkommen.” (“To the publishers (letter, dictated): I decline to be held
                    responsible for all proof-correction <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
                        >costs</tei:supplied>, ask for a detailed account. A sample cover would be
                    appreciated.”).</tei:note> mich fast wörtlich Ihrer Wendungen bedient, nur um ja
                nicht fehlzugehen. </tei:p>

            <tei:p>Ich habe nach Möglichkeit gesucht, mich darüber nicht mehr zu grämen, als mir gut
                tut; auch darin folgte ich Ihrer liebgedachten Empfehlung. </tei:p>

            <tei:p>Was <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Herrn v. Hoboken</tei:rs>
                anlangt:</tei:p>

            <tei:p>Es fiel ihm plötzlich ein, einen Scheck zu schicken, der eine Erhöhung des
                Honorars für die Stunde um 5 S. enthielt. Da er in seinem Brief kein Wort darüber
                verlauten ließ, habe ich ihn bei der Jau- <tei:pb n="2"/> se gefragt, ob er sich
                geirrt habe, worauf er mit einer unvergleichlich gut gespielten Verstellung
                erwiderte, er habe doch auch schon im Vorjahre das höhere Honorar gezahlt. Leider
                waren wir nicht in der Lage ihm das bestätigen zu können u. er meinte dann, daß er
                in seinen Büchern nachsehen wolle. Was sagen Sie nun dazu, daß er mir ein Honorar in
                der Einbildung wohl gegönnt hat, was hinderte ihn aber es nachzutragen? Bedenken Sie
                den mir zugedachten Mehrbetrag, addieren Sie dazu was er für geleistete Mehrarbeit
                wirklich zu zahlen gehabt hätte, es käme ein ansehnlicher Betrag als Gegenleistung
                für seine Hilfe bei <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001751">Jhrb. II</tei:rs>
                zustande. </tei:p>

            <tei:p>Als ich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">v. H.</tei:rs> mitteilte, daß
                ich die <tei:pb n="3"/> Doppelstunden auflösen müsse, habe ich mich bereit erklärt,
                ihm 4, 3 oder 2 Einzelstunden zu geben. Da hätten Sie sehen sollen, mit welcher Gier
                er sich auf 3 Stunden stürzte, um mit dem Ersparnis einer 4. Stunde ein Geschäft zu
                machen. </tei:p>

            <tei:p>Wohl aber das Tragischste war dieses: Als ich von der Unmöglichkeit der
                Doppelstunden sprach,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">It
                    is likely that, during a period of intensive care from his physicians the
                    previous month, Schenker was advised not to teach for more than one hour at a
                    time. This may also be the reason for dictation of the letter.</tei:note>
                versuchte ich ihn zur Erkenntnis zu bringen, daß er durch seinen eigenmächtigen
                Eingriff in meinen Lehrgang diese Häufung von vier Theoriestunden in einer Woche
                verschuldet habe. Aber in seinem hartgesottenen Egoismus empfand er den Sachverhalt
                ganz anders, denn er erklärte mir, daß er sich der neuentstande- <tei:pb n="4"/> nen
                Schwierigkeit wohl bewußt war u. deshalb später zur Stunde erschien u. sonst mit mir
                über verschiedene Dinge plauschte. Also gerade das, was meine unerhörte physische
                Pein gewesen, von je 10 zu 10 Minuten den Stoff wechseln zu müssen, empfand er als
                eine mir zugedachte Erleichterung. Mochte ich die Bibliothek plündern u. ihm das
                Schönste vorlegen, – er ist sich nur einer Schenkung an mich bewußt. Und das sagte
                er als Gast an meinem Tisch – s. außerdem Punkt 1 u. 2. </tei:p>

            <tei:p>So stellt sich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">H. v. H.</tei:rs> die
                Beziehung zu mir vor; er fühlt sich sicher als mein ergebener Freund, aber nur weil
                er meine Vorteile genießt: er sieht <tei:pb n="5"/> mich bereit u. aufgeschlossen,
                in der Einbildung sieht er sich ebenso – wie gut, daß nicht alle Schüler mir so gute
                Freunde sind. Das Geld, das <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">v. H.</tei:rs>
                in die Erstdrucksammlung investirte, ist eine sehr gute Kapitalsanlage, das Geld,
                das er für das <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archiv</tei:rs> u.
                für die Gesamtausgabe<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">The
                    collected edition of the works of C. P. E. Bach, a project associated with the
                    Photogram Archive, which did not come to fruition.</tei:note> schenkt, schenkt
                ihm die soziale Position; leider bedeutet ihm <tei:del rend="overstrike"
                    >ist</tei:del> das, was ich ihm ins Gehirn gestopft habe u. noch stopfe, keine
                Kapitalsanlage, auch nützt es ihm zur Verbesserung der Position gar nicht, daher
                    <tei:add place="interlinear-above">(was aber nicht meine Schuld ist)</tei:add>
                sein im Kreise meiner Schüler nicht dagewesenes Betragen mir gegenüber. </tei:p>

            <tei:closer>
                <tei:salute rend="indent-40">Mit herzlichstem Gruß</tei:salute>
                <tei:salute rend="indent-80">Ihr</tei:salute>
                <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/><tei:rs key="entity-000632"
                        type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">H
                    Schenker</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
                <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#JS"/><tei:placeName>Wien</tei:placeName>,
                        <tei:date when="1930-10-12">12. X. 30</tei:date></tei:dateline>
            </tei:closer>

        </tei:div>

        <tei:div type="translation">

            <tei:opener>
                <tei:add><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>dictated</tei:add><tei:lb/>
                <tei:salute><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>My dear Professor <tei:rs key="entity-000164"
                        type="person">Deutsch</tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01"
                        type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
            </tei:opener>

            <tei:p>Many thanks for your advice.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> In
                my reply to the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002627"
                    >publisher</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> I have used
                your formulations almost literally, and indeed only not to go astray.</tei:p>

            <tei:p>I have tried as much as possible not to trouble myself about this any more than
                is good for me; in this respect, too, I followed your thoughtful advice.</tei:p>

            <tei:p>As concerns <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Mr. van
                Hoboken</tei:rs>:</tei:p>

            <tei:p>It suddenly occurred to him to send me a check that contained a five-shilling
                increase in the hourly lesson fee. As he said not a word about it in his letter, I
                asked him over our afternoon snack <tei:pb n="2"/> whether he had made a mistake,
                whereupon he replied – with well-played dissemblance, that he had indeed paid the
                higher lesson fee already in the previous year. Unfortunately we <tei:supplied
                    reason="clarity">Jeanette and Heinrich</tei:supplied> were not in a position to
                confirm that to him; and he said that he would consult his account books. Now, what
                do you say to this, that he would have granted me a <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
                    >higher</tei:supplied> lesson fee in his imagination, but what prevented him
                from following it up? If you consider the additional payment that he intended and
                add that which he really ought to have paid for the additional work I did for him,
                that would amount to a substantial sum as a quid pro quo for his help with the
                    <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001751">second yearbook</tei:rs>.</tei:p>

            <tei:p>When I told <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs> that I
                    <tei:pb n="3"/> had to terminate the two-hour lessons, I declared myself ready
                to give him four, three or two one-hour lessons. You should have seen with what
                greed he jumped at the idea of three lessons, in order to make a good business deal
                by dispensing with the fourth lesson.</tei:p>

            <tei:p>But the most tragic thing of all was this: When I spoke of the impossibility of
                the two-hour lessons,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> I sought to
                make him understand that, by his unilateral engagement in my course of studies, he
                was responsible for this accumulation of four weekly theory lessons. But in his
                obstinate egoism he conceived the matter in a different way; for he explained to me
                that he was well aware of the newly arisen <tei:pb n="4"/> difficulty and therefore
                appeared later at his lesson and otherwise chatted about various things. Thus
                precisely that which caused my unimagined physical pain, having to change the
                subject from one ten-minute period to the next, he thought of as providing intended
                relief. If I wished to plunder his library and present the most beautiful things to
                him – he is only conscious of making a gift to me. And that he said to me as a guest
                at my dinner table – see also points 1 and 2. </tei:p>

            <tei:p>Thus <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000380">Mr. van Hoboken</tei:rs> presents
                his relationship to me. He feels himself secure as my devoted friend, but only
                because he enjoys my benefits: he sees <tei:pb n="5"/> me at the ready and
                approachable; in his vanity he sees himself likewise – how good it is that not all
                my pupils are such good friends. The money that <tei:rs type="person"
                    key="entity-000380">Hoboken</tei:rs> invested in his collection of first
                editions is a good capital investment; the money that he provides for the <tei:rs
                    type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archive</tei:rs> and for the collected
                    edition<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> gives him his social
                position; unfortunately, that which I have stuffed into his brain, and which I
                continue to stuff, does not signify to him an improvement of his position at all,
                and thus <tei:add place="interlinear-above">(though it is not my fault)</tei:add>
                his unprecedented behavior towards me in my circle of pupils. </tei:p>

            <tei:closer>
                <tei:salute rend="indent-40">With cordial greetings,</tei:salute>
                <tei:salute rend="indent-80">Your</tei:salute>
                <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/><tei:rs key="entity-000632"
                        type="person">H. Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/>
                <tei:dateline><tei:handShift new="#JS"/><tei:placeName>Vienna</tei:placeName>,
                        <tei:date when="1930-10-12">October 12, 1930</tei:date></tei:dateline>
            </tei:closer>

        </tei:div>
    </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
