<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="43" sdoID="WSLB-298">WSLB 298</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2009</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2009</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2010</tei:resp>

  </tei:respStmt>
  <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
   <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
   <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>

  <tei:revisionDesc>
   <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
   <tei:change when="2010-03-02" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
  </tei:revisionDesc>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">

  <sdo:itemDesc><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002700">Hertzka ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002701">UE ~ H+JSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002702">UE ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   
   
   
   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Hertzka (UE), dated April 17, 1918 </dc:title>
   
   <dcterms:created>1918-04-17T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-05-01</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker returns the article by Maurice Kufferath and comments on it critically.
    -- Beethoven did give phrase-markings, thus Schenker advocates inserting fingering but not
    additional phrase-marks. -- Diatribe against Hans von Bülow's editions and those who have
    emulated him. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>review; polemic; freedom; editing; quartet; orchestra; opera; Lusitania; war; World
    War I; Phrisierung; Friseur; window-dressing; Mode; fashion</dc:subject>

   
   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000356">Hertzka</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-002408">UE</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Sehr geehrter <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356">Herr
      Direktor</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Mit<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Writing of this letter is
     recorded at OJ 2/10, p. 877 with a full summary<!-- XR -->. </tei:note> bestem Dank stelle ich
    anbei den possierlichen <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000491">Franzosen</tei:rs><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">See WSLB 295, March 3, and OC 52/205, April
     10. </tei:note> zurück. Daß er dort, wo ich außer paar Zeilen Vorworts u. einer
     Fußnote<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Of Schenker, <tei:title level="m">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven ... op. 111</tei:title> (Vienna: UE, 1915).
     Schenker understates the case here; he engages in inflammatory polemics in the Foreword, in a
     long footnote on the sinking of the Lusitania (p. 80), in a still longer footnote about World
     War I (pp. 83-85), and in several other shorter footnotes, including an attack on Debussy (p.
     69). The passage alluded to later in this paragraph occurs in paragraph 4 of the footnote on p.
     80, of which his wording in this letter is a slight paraphrase: "begriff er <tei:supplied reason="clarity">the Anglo-American, i.e. Woodrow Wilson</tei:supplied> doch auch die Ohrfeige
     der Lusitania-Torpedierung nur deshalb, weil sie so schallend war" ("he really understood the
     box around the ears of the torpedoing of the Lusitania only because it was so resounding").
     Further to that footnote, see William Pastille, <tei:title level="a">Aesthetic Education: On
      the Origins of Schenker's Musical Politics,</tei:title> in <tei:title level="m">Essays from
      the Fourth International Schenker Symposium</tei:title>, ed. Allen Cadwallader (Hildesheim:
     Georg Olms, 2008), pp. 183-95, esp. 184-86. </tei:note> eine umfangreiche Darstellung des
    Inhaltes biete, sich nur gerade mit jenen paar Zeilen beschäftigt, kann auch in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482">Deutschland</tei:rs> vorkommen u. kommt
    auch vor. Daß er aber an manchen Stellen mein <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Original</tei:hi> u.
    seine Ǘbersetzung anführt, damit nur die Leser an seiner Ehrlichkeit nicht zweifeln, u. doch an
    einer recht wichtigen Stelle „<tei:hi rend="underline">schallende</tei:hi> Ohrfeige“ in
     „<tei:lang xml:lang="fre">
     <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">un soufflet <tei:hi rend="underline">légitimement</tei:hi>
      appliqué</tei:hi>
    </tei:lang>“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">"a slap in the face
     legitimately delivered"; quoted from the review. </tei:note>
    <tei:hi rend="underline">umfälscht</tei:hi>, ist spezifisch französisch u. bestätigt, was ich
    schrieb, im kleinen nicht minder, wie die soeben enthüllte grobe, plumpe Fälschung des
     Kaiserbriefes<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Kaiserbrief: a letter,
     written by the Austrian Emperor Karl I to the Prince Ferdinand of Bourbon-Parma, seeking peace
     negotiations and offering certain concessions. The letter was exposed in April 1918, and
     published by Clemenceau, leading to the resignation of Karl's foreign minister, Ottokar
     Czernin. </tei:note> (auf dem Wege von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000830">Sixtus</tei:rs>
    zum <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000673">
     Poincaré
    </tei:rs>) im Großen. Ja, die Herren Franzosen sind Spezialisten in „Freiheiten,“ nur sehe
    man: welche, - in der „Freiheit“ <tei:del rend="overstrike">auf</tei:del> der Fälschung, der
    Eroberungen des Rheins einer unmenschlichen Gefangenenbehandlung u. lauter solchen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot"> "u. ... solchen" written in the line above
     after "Rheins," then marked to be transposed to this point. (There is clearly something wrong
     with this sentence.) </tei:note> anderen Freiheiten mehr.</tei:p>

   <tei:p>Zur Frage der Ausgaben ein Wort: Sie irren sich, wenn Sie glauben, daß <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">
     Beeth.
    </tei:rs> so unphrasiert auf die Welt gekommen ist, wie z.B. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000027">
     Bach S.
    </tei:rs> Seine <tei:hi rend="underline">eigene</tei:hi>
    <tei:term>Phrasierung</tei:term> ist so genau, ja so
    übergenau, daß sie seit den ersten Tagen bis auf die heutigen noch allen Sologeigern, Quartett-,
     <tei:pb n="2"/> Orchester-, Operngesellschaften (<tei:rs key="entity-002541" type="composition"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Fidelio</tei:hi></tei:rs>, <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Messen etc</tei:hi>) ausgereicht u. Allen Köpfe u. Hände voll zu schaffen
    gemacht hat! Liegt es nicht also auf der Hand, daß die paar Bearbeiter<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial" place="foot">"Bearbeiter": Schenker means editors who
     "work on" their editions, inserting fingerings, performance instructions, phrase-markings, etc.
     On this, see OC 52/205 : April 10, 1918. </tei:note> aus Eitelkeit u. Frechheit sich putzig
    machen mit ihren „Phr<tei:hi rend="underline">i</tei:hi>sierungen,“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08" type="editorial" place="foot">"Phrisierungen," from "frisieren": literally "hairdressing" or
     "hair-styling" (from French, "Friseur," hairdresser), with the implication of fakery. Schenker
     is deploying a play on words between "Phrisierung" and "Phrasierung," the latter an object of
     Schenker's strongest censure in editing practices. </tei:note> die das volle Gegenteil von
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beeth</tei:rs>'schen <tei:term>Phr<tei:hi rend="underline">a</tei:hi>sierung</tei:term>en sind? Die Verleger
    baten zuerst um <tei:term>Fingersätze</tei:term> - <tei:hi rend="underline">das</tei:hi> ist verständlich -, der Bearbeiter gab dann noch als <tei:unclear reason="reading">Zuwege</tei:unclear>, eine nicht einmal erbetene, auch <tei:hi rend="underline">seine</tei:hi> Phrasierung! Diese niederträchtige Protzerei ließ natürlich den
    zweiten, dritten Bearbeiter nicht ruhen, u. so phrisieren sie um die Wette, während, wie gesagt,
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000727">
     Rosé
    </tei:rs>, <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">etc</tei:hi>. noch immer nach der ersten Phrasierung
    spielen, u. doch wohl auch mit Erfolg. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Also <tei:term>Fingersätze</tei:term>, ja, - nur aber
    die Original<tei:term>phrasierung</tei:term>. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Was die <tei:term>Erläuterung</tei:term> anbelangt,
    ist nur folgendes zu sagen: Wenn bei einer völlig <tei:add place="interlinear-above">falschen</tei:add> Darstellung die Ausgabe von <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000110">
     Bülow
    </tei:rs> so viele Jahrzehnte vorhielt, vorhält u. noch vorhalten wird, blos wegen der
    Erläuterungen, die ja auch falsch sind, wie müßte erst vorhalten eine Ausgabe, der Niemand
    falschen Text u. falsche Erläuterungen vorwerfen könnte?! Was hat ein solches Werk, das
    gleichsam über den Moden stünde, mit den Bedürfnissen der Verlage nach neuen Herbst-Auslagen zu
    tun? Gar nichts. Neben Bülow kamen u. giengen ja <tei:pb n="3"/> so viel Mode-Bearbeiter, - er
    blieb, trug Geld ein u. trägt <tei:supplied reason="cutoff">es</tei:supplied> noch. Güte ist ein
    ewiger Mode-Artikel für sich. -- </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Leider kam der franz. Aufsatz in eine schmutzige Hand<tei:supplied reason="syntax">;</tei:supplied> ich brauche nicht erst zu sagen, daß es auch eine reiche Hand ge<tei:supplied reason="cutoff">wesen,</tei:supplied> so bitte ich um Entschuldigung wegen des Zustandes, in
    dem <tei:supplied reason="cutoff">ich</tei:supplied> Ihnen den Aufsatz zurückzustellen genötigt
    bin. </tei:p>


   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-5"><tei:gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" extent="8"/> bestens
     dankend u. herzlichst grüßend </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr sehr ergebener </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50">
     <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">H Schenker</tei:hi>
    </tei:signed>
    <tei:date when="1918-04-17">17. April 1918</tei:date>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>



  <tei:div type="translation">

   <tei:opener>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-20">Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356">Director</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Herewith<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> enclosed, I return the ridiculous
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000491">Frenchman</tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> with many thanks. Whereas I, aside from a few lines of Foreword and a
     footnote,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> offer a comprehensive presentation of
    the content, he concerns himself solely with just those few lines. This is something that can
    happen, and does happen, in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002482">Germany</tei:rs>, too. But the way that in many places he
    quotes my original and his translation, such that his readers wil not doubt his honesty, and
    indeed at one really important point renders "<tei:hi rend="underline">resounding</tei:hi> box
    around the ears" <tei:hi rend="underline">falsely</tei:hi> as "<tei:lang xml:lang="fre">un
     soufflet <tei:hi rend="underline">légitimement</tei:hi> appliqué</tei:lang>",<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> is quintessentially French and confirms what I wrote,
    in small matters no less than in large, cf. the coarse, crude falsification of the Emperor's
     letter<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> recently exposed (en route from
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000830">Sixtus</tei:rs> to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000673">Poincaré</tei:rs>). Yes, these French fellows are specialists in "freedoms"; one need
    only consider, in the "freedom" of falsification, in the conquests of the Rhine, in an inhumane
    treatment of prisoners, and other such<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> freedoms. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>A word about the matter of editions: you are mistaken in believing that <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> saw the light of day as unphrased as, e.g.,
     <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000027">J. S. Bach</tei:rs>. His <tei:hi rend="underline">own</tei:hi>
    <tei:term>phrasing</tei:term> is so precise, indeed so
    super-precise, that from early days up to the present day it has sufficed for all solo
    violinists, quartet ensembles, <tei:pb n="2"/> orchestral and opera companies (<tei:rs key="entity-002541" type="composition"><tei:title level="m">Fidelio</tei:title></tei:rs>, masses, etc.) and given everybody plenty to work with
    creatively. Is it not thus apparent that the few heavy-handed editors,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> out of vanity and impertinence, sully themselves with
    their "window dressing,"<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/> which is in total
    contrast to <tei:persName>Beethoven</tei:persName>'s phrase indications? At first, publishers
    asked for <tei:term>fingering</tei:term>s -- <tei:hi rend="underline">that</tei:hi> is understandable --, then the heavy-handed editor threw in
    something else that had not been asked for, his <tei:hi rend="underline">own</tei:hi> phrasing!
    This low-minded ostentation naturally forced the hand of the next arranger, and then the next,
    and so they vied with each other in window-dressing, while, as has been said, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000727">Rosé</tei:rs>, etc. continue to play according to the first phrasing,
    what's more with great success. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>So <tei:term>fingering</tei:term>s, yes, but only the
    original <tei:term>phrase markings</tei:term>. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>On the subject of <tei:term>elucidation</tei:term>,
    let me say just the following: if with a totally <tei:add place="interlinear-above">false</tei:add> presentation, the edition of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000110">von
     Bülow</tei:rs> has lasted so many decades, still lasts, and will continue to last, solely
    on account of its elucidations, which themselves are totally false, how long must an edition
    last that is irreproachable as to its musical text and its elucidations?! What has such a work
    that is, so to speak, above all fashion, to do with the requirements of publishers for their new
    autumn window displays? Nothing whatsoever. Alongside <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000110">von
     Bülow</tei:rs>, <tei:pb n="2"/> so many modish editors came and went; he has outlived
    them, raked in the shekels, and is still raking them in. Benevolence is itself an eternal
    article of fashion. -- </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Unfortunately, the French article found its way into dirty hands. I hardly need say that
    they were wealthy hands, so I ask your forgiveness for the condition in which I am obliged to
    return the article to you. </tei:p>



   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-5"><tei:gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" extent="8"/> with best
     thanks and most cordial greetings, </tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Yours very truly, </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-50">H Schenker</tei:signed>
    <tei:date when="1918-04-17">April 17, 1918</tei:date>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>