<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?><sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
 <sdo:collectionDesc>
  <sdo:source>
   <sdo:correspondence mfID="107" sdoID="WSLB-304">WSLB 304</sdo:correspondence>
  </sdo:source>

  <tei:handNotes>
   <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
  </tei:handNotes>

  <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
   <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
   <tei:resp>Transcription, 2009</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>Translation, 2009</tei:resp>
   <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2010</tei:resp>
  </tei:respStmt>
 </sdo:collectionDesc>

 <sdo:record ID="r0001">
  <sdo:itemDesc><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002700">Hertzka ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002701">UE ~ H+JSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002702">UE ~ HSchenker</tei:rs><tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>
   
   
   
   <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Hertzka (UE), dated December 7, 1919</dc:title>
   
   <dcterms:created>1919-12-07T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
   <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2010-05-06</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
   <dc:description>Schenker suggests date, place, and time for a meeting. </dc:description>
   <dc:subject>Entschließung; decision; meeting</dc:subject>

   
   
   
  <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent><marcrel:recipient key="entity-000356">Hertzka</marcrel:recipient><marcrel:recipient key="entity-002408">UE</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc>


  <tei:div type="transcription">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-50">Sonntag, <tei:date when="1919-12-07">7. Dez 1919</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356">Direktor</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>Im<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">The writing of this letter
     does not appear to be recorded in Schenker's diary. </tei:note> Sinne Ihres letzten
     Schreibens<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Unclear which letter is
     referred to. Schenker's diary for December 3, 1919 (OJ 3/1, p. 2185) records: "Von Hertzka
     (Br.): erklärt sich bereit, sowohl op. 101, als sämtliche Beethoven Sonaten mit Fußnoten
     anzunehmen." ("From Hertzka (letter): declares himself willing to take on both Op. 101 and the
     collected Beethoven sonatas with footnotes.") That letter is not known to survive. However, the
     present letter also responds to the request in OC 52/924, June 16, 1919, for a meeting.
    </tei:note> schlage ich also vor: z. B. <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002289">Café Vindobona</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002600">Schwarzenbergplatz</tei:rs> – in Ihrer u. meiner
    Nähe am <tei:hi rend="underline">Freitag</tei:hi>, den 12<tei:hi rend="supralinear">d.M.</tei:hi>, zwischen 2-2½<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi>. Nachmittag.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">This meeting is reported in Schenker's diary
     at on OJ 3/1, p. 2191, December 12: "Mit Lie-Liechen nach Tisch ins Café Vindobona, wo wir mit
     Hertzka zusammentreffen; er erklärt sich zu op. 111 bereit, 3000 Kronen als Basis anzunehmen u.
     davon das Fünffache zu bezahlen, wie er selbst nur das Fünffache des Friedenspreises fordere,
     worauf ich eingehe; der Preis für sämtliche Sonaten: 50000 M. = 150000 Kronen schien ihm
     jedenfalls zu hoch, so daß er in der gegenwärtigen Zeit der Valutaschwankungen die Erledigung
     dieses langfristigen Unternehmens nicht für ersprießlich gehalten. Der wahre Grund der
     Gleichgiltigkeit zeigte sich alsbald, da er plötzlich nach der „Kleinen Bibliothek“ fragte; so
     zeigte sich, daß er dafür ein überaus starkes Interesse hat, auch ohne daß er von deren Inhalt
     Näheres wußte oder auch nur wissen könnte; er schlägt ein Bogenhonorar vor u. zwar 600 Kronen,
     räumt mir das Recht ein, so viele Bogen jährlich zu liefern, als mir nur paßte, sie sämtliche
     sofort in die Druckerei zu bringen u. „großzügige Propagande“ zu machen; mehr als das: er
     verpflichtet sich, zu einem neuen Honorar bei einer etwaigen neuen Auflage usw.- kurz, er macht
     das Anbot sehr verlockend u. nur der Umstand, daß wir hierüber gar nicht nachgedacht haben,
     also nicht im geringsten vorbereitet gewesen, hat es uns wünschenswert erscheinen lassen, die
     endgiltige Antwort uns noch vorzubehalten; er betrug sich überaus devot u. vielleicht
     aufrichtig verehrungsvoll." ("With Lie-Liechen to lunch at the Café Vindobona, where we meet up
     with Hertzka. On <tei:title level="m">Op. 111</tei:title>, he declares himself willing to take
     3,000 Kronen as the basis, and to pay five times that, as he himself demands five times the
      <tei:unclear reason="meaning">peace prize</tei:unclear>, to which which I agree. The price for
     the collected sonatas, 50,000 Marks = 150,000 Kronen, appeared to him at all events too high,
     such that in the current period of fluctuating exchange-rates he did not consider the
     settlement for this long-term undertaking to be profitable. The real reason for his nonchalance
     soon showed itself when he suddenly inquired after the <tei:title level="m">Little
      Library</tei:title>; it was evident that he had a keen interest in that, even though he did
     not, or could not possibly know details of its content. He proposes an honorarium per
     gathering, namely 600 Kronen, grants me the right to deliver so many gatherings per year, as
     suits me, will send them to the printer immediately, and engage in 'generous publicity.' More
     than that: he commits himself to a new honorarium for any new edition, etc. In short, he makes
     the offer very enticing, and only because we have not had time to think this over, thus are in
     the slightest prepared for it, does it seem desirable to us to defer giving a final answer. He
     betrayed himself as utterly devoted and perhaps genuinely full of admiration.")
     <!-- XR --></tei:note> Gewährsmänner dieses Kaféhauses garantieren für völlige Ungestörtheit,
    freilich aber auch für völlige Kälte des Raumes. Vielleicht wissen Sie ein anderes
    Caféhauslokal, wo Wärme u. Ungestörtheit vereint sind, so nennen Sie es getrost, ich komme
    dorthin. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Jedenfalls erwarte ich noch Ihre Entschließung u. lasse bei den postalischen Misständen
    von heute eigens den nötigen Zeitraum hiefür. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Hoffentlich verlassen wir das Lokal, Arm in Arm das Jahrhundert der Eselei herausfordern,
    im Begriff der Menschheit ein schöneres Jahrhundert der Wahrheit u. Aufklärung zu schenken. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Mit besten Grüßen</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr</tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-55">
     <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">H Schenker</tei:hi>
    </tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>


  <tei:div type="translation">
   <tei:opener>
    <tei:dateline rend="indent-50">Sunday, <tei:date when="1919-12-07">December 7, 1919</tei:date>
    </tei:dateline>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356">Director</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
   </tei:opener>

   <tei:p>In<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> the spirit of your latest
     letter,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> let me suggest, therefore, e.g.
     <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002289">Café Vindobona</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002600">Schwarzenbergplatz</tei:rs> – in your neighborhood and mine
    on <tei:hi rend="underline">Friday</tei:hi> the 12th between 2:00 and 2:30 p.m..<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> The custodians of this coffee-house guarantee total
    privacy, but also – I must admit – totally arctic conditions, for the room. Maybe you know of
    some other coffee-house whose premises combine warmth with privacy, in which case do not
    hesitate to name it, and I will be right there. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>At all events, I still await your decision and, with the deplorable state of the post
    these days, shall set aside expressly the time required for this. </tei:p>

   <tei:p>Let us hope that we shall leave the premises, in joint defiance of the century of folly,
    resolved to present mankind with a beautiful century of truth and enlightenment. </tei:p>

   <tei:closer>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-10">With best wishes,</tei:salute>
    <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Yours, </tei:salute>
    <tei:signed rend="indent-55">H Schenker</tei:signed>
   </tei:closer>

  </tei:div>
 </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>