<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2919" sdoID="WSLB-Hds-94477">WSLB-Hds 94477</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2022</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2012-09-28" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002735">Seligmann ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Seligmann, dated May 22, 1912</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1912-05-22T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2022-11-27</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker congratulates Seligmann on the recent exhibition of his paintings. He
        is about to send him a copy of his Beethoven’s Ninth Symphony and asks him to read the
        section on the secondary literature and consider whether the same might be applied to the
        literature on painting.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">Heinrich Schenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000819">Adalbert Franz Seligmann</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000819">Freund</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Erst gestern hatte ich Muße genommen, Ihre Werke bei Heller zu sehen. Wie das doch für
        die von Ihnen u. mir verfochtenen Gedanken heilsam fördernd wirkt, daß Sie als schaffender
        Künstler so Ihren Mann stellen! Wie schön ist der einzig zulässige <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
          >Typus</tei:hi> eines „Kritikers“ in Ihnen verkörpert! Noch war ich aber im „<tei:rs
          type="place" key="entity-002360">Künstlerhaus</tei:rs>“ nicht u. habe daher die Ausführung
        der Skizze (<tei:hi rend="lateinschr">pragm. Sanct.</tei:hi>) nicht gesehen.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">“Die Verlesung der Pragmatischen
          Sanktion” (The Reading of the Pragmatic Sanction) by Seligmann, oil on canvas, c. 1912.
          This painting depicts the reading of the <tei:foreign xml:lang="lat"><tei:hi rend="italic"
              >Sanctio pragmatica</tei:hi></tei:foreign> of 1713, an edict issued by Charles VI,
          Holy Roman Emperor, according to which a future daughter of his could inherit the throne
          in the event of his producing no male offspring.</tei:note> Die größte Überraschung boten
        mir Ihre Landschaftsbilder, sowohl die hellen als gedämpften. Ich erinnere mich nicht, je in
        Ihrem <tei:foreign xml:lang="fre"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Atelier</tei:hi></tei:foreign>
        ähnliche Bilder gesehen zu haben. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>In wenig Wochen erhalten Sie von mir eine große, 400 S. umfassende <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001731"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Monographie</tei:hi> über
              „<tei:title><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Beeth</tei:hi>. IX Symph.</tei:title></tei:rs>“
        (die „<tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">U. E.</tei:rs>“ fügt als II Band eine
          Taschen<tei:hi rend="underline">partitur</tei:hi>
        <tei:add place="interlinear-above">bei</tei:add>, mit aus dem Werk gezogenen Anmerkungen
          versehen)<tei:supplied reason="punctuation">.</tei:supplied><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
          type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:rs type="work" key="entity-002408">Ninth Symphony
            score</tei:rs>: a suggestion from Emil Hertzka in 1911 that Schenker might produce a
          score of Beethoven’s Ninth Symphony with “Erläuterungen” in conjunction with his
          monograph. The project foundered on technical complications and costs.</tei:note>
        <tei:pb n="2"/> Schon jetzt äußere ich die Bitte an Sie: lesen Sie die Literaturrubrik,
        worin ich meine kritische <tei:foreign xml:lang="fre"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
            >Patrouille</tei:hi></tei:foreign> absolviert habe, <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
          >genau</tei:hi> (vorausgesetzt, daß Sie Zeit und Lust dafür finden), und sagen Sie mir, ob
        nicht Ähnliches in der Malerei gemacht werden könne? Von jeher behaupte ich, daß man Fehler
        in der Kunst gegen Jedermann <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">nachweisen</tei:hi> kann, daß dieses
        Geschäft zu verrichten in einer Epoche notwendig wird, die allen Unfug auf das <tei:hi
          rend="lateinschr">Princip</tei:hi>: „so höre ich, so seh’ ich es“ – (welch überflüßige
        Tautologien!) – stellt. Ich bestreite es, daß es bei „Erfüllung“ eines Vorwurfs soviel
        Willkür gebe, als man heute zum Schutz der Indolenz allgemein vorgiebt. – Nun aber ist es
        höchste Zeit, in den Sommer zu gehen . . . </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Besten </tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Angenehmen Sommer wünscht Ihnen</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H Schenker</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1912-05-22">22. Mai 1912</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:p>Kennen Sie die horrible <tei:foreign xml:lang="fre"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
              >Affaire</tei:hi></tei:foreign> Presse–<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000356"
            >Bopp</tei:rs>-<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000961">Wiener</tei:rs> u. – <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000913">Violin</tei:rs>?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03"
            type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker alludes to the protest that Moriz Violin made
            against the treatment and forcing into retirement of existing staff of the <tei:rs
              type="organization" key="entity-002591">Akademie für Musik und darstellende
              Kunst</tei:rs>, including a pamphlet the subtitle of which was “A Word about the
            Leaders of the Institution, Messrs von Wiener and Bopp,” which resulted in his
            retirement from the institution.</tei:note></tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000819">friend</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>It was not until yesterday that I had the occasion to see your works at Heller’s. What
        a salutary effect does it have on the causes we are championing that you present yourself in
        such a way as a creative artist! How beautiful is the uniquely permissible type of “critic”
        embodied in you. I have not yet been to the <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002360"
          >Künstlerhaus</tei:rs>, and so I have not yet seen the realization of the sketch (pragm.
          Sanct.).<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> The greatest surprise was
        provided by your landscape paintings, the bright ones as much as those that are subdued. I
        do not remember ever having seen similar paintings in your studio.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>In a few weeks you will receive from me a large, 400-page <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001731">monograph on <tei:title>Beethoven’s Ninth
          Symphony</tei:title></tei:rs> (<tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">Universal
          Edition</tei:rs> is including, as a second volume, a study <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
          >score</tei:hi> provided with notes drawn from the book.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
          type="footnote"/>
        <tei:pb n="2"/> Already now, I make this request of you: <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
          >carefully</tei:hi> read the section on the secondary literature, in which I dispatch my
        critical patrol (assuming that you find the time and inclination to do so), and tell me if
        something like that could be done in painting? I have always maintained that one can <tei:hi
          rend="lateinschr">ascertain</tei:hi> mistakes in art against everyone, and that it is
        necessary to undertake this business in an age which presents all nonsense according to the
        principle: “this is how I hear, this is how I see” – what unnecessary tautologies! I dispute
        the notion that, with the “fulfillment” of an accusation there is just as much arbitrariness
        as one now generally professes for the protection of indolence. – But now it is high time to
        enter into summer . . .</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Best thanks for your invitation! And, as I said, please read that section!</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10">I wish you a pleasant summer.</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H. Schenker</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1912-05-22">May 22, 1912</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:p>Do you know about the horrendous affair press–<tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000356">Bopp</tei:rs>-<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000961"
            >Wiener</tei:rs> and – <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000913"
            >Violin</tei:rs>?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
