<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
    xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
    xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
    <sdo:collectionDesc>
        <sdo:source>
            <sdo:correspondence mfID="3033" sdoID="WSLB-Hds-191-563">WSLB-Hds 191.563</sdo:correspondence>
        </sdo:source>

        <tei:handNotes>
            <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
        </tei:handNotes>

        <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
            <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
            <tei:resp>Transcription, 2023</tei:resp>
            <tei:resp>Translation, 2023</tei:resp>
        </tei:respStmt>

        <tei:respStmt xml:id="IDB">
            <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
            <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2023</tei:resp>
        </tei:respStmt>

        <tei:revisionDesc>
            <tei:change when="2015-09-18" who="#DB">XML code created</tei:change>
        </tei:revisionDesc>
    </sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:record ID="r0001">

        <sdo:itemDesc>
            <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002726">DeutschOE ~
                H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
            <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002712">DeutschOE ~
                HSchenker</tei:rs>
            <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002727">DeutschOE+H ~
                H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
            <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>

            <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Deutsch, dated June 22, 1928</dc:title>

            <dcterms:created>1928-06-22T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
            <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2023-02-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
            <dc:description>Schenker thanks Deutsch for his birthday greetings, explaining that,
                although he feels alienated from the musical world of the present day, he is
                convinced that his work will have a lasting effect on future
                generations.</dc:description>
            <dc:subject/>


            <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">HSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
            <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000771">JSchenker</marcrel:correspondent>
            <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000164">DeutschOE</marcrel:recipient>
            <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000163">DeutschH</marcrel:recipient>

        </sdo:itemDesc>


        <tei:div type="transcription">

            <tei:opener>
                <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Lieber Herr <tei:rs key="entity-000164" type="person"
                        >Deutsch</tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
                        place="foot">Writing of this letter is not recorded in Schenker’s
                        diary.</tei:note></tei:salute>
            </tei:opener>

            <tei:p>Daß Sie mitten im <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000803"><tei:hi
                        rend="lateinschr">Schubert</tei:hi></tei:rs>-Rummel meiner bei einem im
                Grunde so belanglosen Anlaß so herzlich gedachten, erfüllte mich mit aufrichtiger
                Freude. Ich bin der letzte, <tei:add place="interlinear-above">Sie</tei:add> von
                einem <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000803"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
                        >Schubert</tei:hi></tei:rs> abzulenken, umso wärmer danke ich Ihnen für Ihre
                frdl. Glückwunsch.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"
                    >Schenker is responding to birthday greetings from Deutsch in the letter
                        <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-10-3_89">OJ 10/3, [89]</tei:ref>,
                    June 17, 1928; he is noting that his 60th birthday has fallen in the year in
                    which the musical world is celebrating the 100th anniversary of Schubert’s
                    death.</tei:note></tei:p>

            <tei:p>Nur weil mein Lebenswerk eine rein künstlerische Leistung ist, daher weniger
                übertragbar u. weniger erlernbar ist als eine beliebige Wissenschaft (in der Art des
                    <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000712"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
                        >Riemann</tei:hi></tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000888"
                        ><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Thuille</tei:hi></tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person"
                    key="entity-000576"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">A. B. Marx</tei:hi></tei:rs>
                usw.), bin ich der großen Menge entfremdet. Markt- <tei:pb n="2"/> gängig kann ich
                wohl niemals werden, am allerwenigsten im Sinne des heute so beliebten
                „Fremdenverkehrs“genüßen, doch ebenso bestimmt ist es, daß mein Werk die fernsten
                Zeitalter der Menschheit erreichen wird, als der erste u. letzte Aufschluß über die
                Musik. Nichts vor mir, nichts nach mir wird sich meiner Deutung, die eine
                    <tei:sic>selber</tei:sic> Kunst ist, vergleichen. Meine Freunde u. Leser sind
                schon heute zahlreicher als Sie es wissen mögen; <tei:note type="editorial"
                    place="inline">cued from bottom margin:</tei:note> sie sind <tei:add
                    place="interlinear-above">nur zu</tei:add> verstreut, unorganisiert, scheu, zu
                wenig hervortretend, um in ihrer beträchtlichen Menge überblickt zu werden!<tei:note
                    type="editorial" place="inline">end cue</tei:note> sie reichen <tei:add
                    place="interlinear-above">, da sie nicht arm sind,</tei:add> nicht hin, um dem
                Verleger Gewinne nach der Art des „<tei:rs type="composition" key="entity-004803"
                        ><tei:title>Jonny spielt auf</tei:title></tei:rs>“ zuzuschanzen, doch daß
                die Verleger, einschließlich der <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002627"
                    >3M</tei:rs>, schließlich zu ihrem Held gekommen sind oder kommen werden, ist
                für mich nach allen bisherigen Erfahrungen ausge- <tei:pb n="3"/> macht. </tei:p>

            <tei:p>Am schwierigsten fiel mir bis jetzt die Unterbringung meiner Arbeiten, weniger
                das Schaffen (trotz der Unterrichtstätigkeit); wollte Gott, daß ich endlich <tei:add
                    place="interlinear-above">auch</tei:add> den „<tei:rs type="work"
                    key="entity-001728"><tei:title>Freien Satz</tei:title></tei:rs>“ der Welt
                übermitteln kann. Ich gebe mir die denkbar größte Mühe, ihm eine Form zu geben, die
                weniger Kosten verursacht, u. hoffe eben darum, nicht gerade mit dem IV. Bd. stecken
                zu bleiben.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Other
                    projected volumes in the series of “<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001723"
                            ><tei:title level="m">New Musical Theories and
                        Fantasies</tei:title></tei:rs>” included a study of performance, and a study
                    of form.</tei:note></tei:p>

            <tei:p>Das ist Alles, was ich mir wünsche, wovon ich übrigens weiß, daß auch Sie es mir
                nicht minder heiß wünschen wie ich selbst. </tei:p>

            <tei:p>Zu den bevorstehenden Vorträgen wünsche ich Ihnen viel Glück! Und von uns Beiden
                Ihnen Beiden beste Wünsche für den Sommer! </tei:p>

            <tei:closer>
                <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Ihr</tei:salute>
                <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"><tei:hi
                            rend="lateinschr">H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:signed>
                <tei:dateline><tei:placeName>Galtür</tei:placeName>, <tei:date when="1928-06-22">22.
                        Juni 1928</tei:date></tei:dateline>
            </tei:closer>

        </tei:div>

        <tei:div type="translation">

            <tei:opener>
                <tei:salute rend="indent-10">Dear Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-000164" type="person"
                        >Deutsch</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"
                    /></tei:salute>
            </tei:opener>

            <tei:p>That you remembered what is essentially such an insignificant occasion so
                cordially, in the midst of your <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000803"
                    >Schubert</tei:rs>ian hustle and bustle, filled me with genuine delight. I would
                be the last person to divert <tei:add place="interlinear-above">you</tei:add> from
                the likes of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000803">Schubert</tei:rs>, and so I
                thank you all the more warmly for your kind congratulations.<tei:ptr
                    corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

            <tei:p>Only because my life’s work is a purely artistic achievement, and thus less
                transferable and more difficult to learn than any other scholarship (like that of
                    <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000712">Riemann</tei:rs>, <tei:rs
                    type="person" key="entity-000888">Thuille</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person"
                    key="entity-000576">A. B. Marx</tei:rs>, etc.), I have become alienated from the
                great throng. <tei:pb n="2"/> I can probably never become marketable, {2} least of
                all in the sense of “tourism” pleasures which are so popular these days. And yet it
                is likewise undeniable that my work will reach the furthest age of humanity, as the
                first and the ultimate sources of musical understanding. Nothing that has come
                before me, nothing that will come after me will be comparable with my
                interpretation, which is an art in its own right. My friends and readers are even
                today more numerous than you may imagine; <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"
                    >cued from bottom margin:</tei:note> they are <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
                    >just too</tei:add> widely scattered, disorganized, shy, and not prominent
                enough to be surveyed in their considerable size!<tei:note type="editorial"
                    place="inline">end cue</tei:note>
                <tei:add place="interlinear-above">Because they are not impoverished,</tei:add> they
                are unable to guarantee a publisher gains of the sort that accrue to a <tei:rs
                    type="composition" key="entity-004803"><tei:title level="m">Jonny spielt
                        auf</tei:title></tei:rs>; but that the publishers, including the <tei:rs
                    type="organization" key="entity-002627">Drei Masken Verlag</tei:rs>, have in the
                end come to their hero (or will come to him) is something of which, on the basis of
                all previous experiences, I am absolutely certain.</tei:p>

            <tei:p><tei:pb n="3"/> For me the most difficult thing until now has been the placement
                of my works, less than their creation (in spite of my activity as a teacher); would
                to God that I could finally transmit <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
                    >even</tei:add>
                <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title level="m">Free
                        Composition</tei:title></tei:rs> to the world. I shall make the greatest
                imaginable effort to put it into a form that reduces the cost; and I hope for that
                very reason that I shall not remain stuck at the fourth volume.<tei:ptr
                    corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

            <tei:p>That is all that I wish for myself, of which I know moreover that you, too, are
                no less desirous of this than I am myself.</tei:p>

            <tei:p>For your forthcoming lectures, I wish you much luck! And from the two of us to
                the two of you, best wishes for the summer!</tei:p>

            <tei:closer>
                <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your</tei:salute>
                <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">H.
                        Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed>
                <tei:dateline><tei:placeName>Galtür</tei:placeName>, <tei:date when="1928-06-22"
                        >June 22, 1928</tei:date></tei:dateline>
            </tei:closer>

        </tei:div>
    </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
