<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2929" sdoID="WSLB-Hds-94479">WSLB-Hds 94479</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2022</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2012-09-28" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002735">Seligmann ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Seligmann, dated February 26, 1931</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1931-02-26T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2022-11-29</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker asks Seligmann to read the opening essay in the third volume of Das
        Meisterwerk in der Musik. He quotes from a letter to his pupil Hans Weisse which
        demonstrates the attention his theories have been gaining in Germany, especially Berlin, and
        expresses his regret that no one in Vienna shows similar respect for him.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">Heinrich Schenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000819">Adalbert Franz Seligmann</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000819">Freund</tei:rs>!<tei:note
            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker’s diary for February 26, 1931
            records: “An Seligmann (Br.): Begleitschreiben zum Jahrbuch. Vom Rotary-Heft ausgehend
            nehme ich sein Interesse für die Frage vom Zusammenhang an. Den Tonfall auf S. 20–22
            bitte ich mir zugute zu halten! Zitire Kestenberg, erwähne Weisses Erfolge, um den
            Gegensatz meiner Behandlung in Wien recht krass zu malen. Der Prominenteste wird
            totgeschwiegen, der für das Archiv unbedankt ist, auch für die materiellen Zuwendungen
            an Stadt u. Staat, von den geistigen Verdiensten ganz abgesehen. Ich lege ihm nahe, sich
            auch einmal der Gänsefüßchen zu bedienen, um Korngold einen Kinnhaken zu geben.” (“To
            Seligmann (letter): covering letter for the Yearbook. Proceeding from the issue of The
              <tei:title level="j">Rotarian</tei:title>, I applaud his interest in the matter of
              <tei:supplied>musical</tei:supplied> coherence. I ask him to accept my tone of voice
            on pp. 20–22! I quote Kestenberg, mention Weisse’s successes, in order to depict quite
            bluntly the way in which I, by contrast, have been treated in Vienna. The most prominent
            person is surrounded by silence: the one who has not been thanked for the Archive, not
            even for the material benefits to city and state, quite apart from my intellectual
            services. I suggest that he might sometime also make use of quotation marks to give
            Korngold a hook to the chin”).<tei:lb/> The diary for February 27, 1931 records: “An
            Seligmann (K.): das III. Jhrb. wird ihm vom Verlag zugehen.” (“To Seligmann (postcard):
            the third Yearbook will be sent to him by the publishers.”). </tei:note></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000680">Prof. Dr <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">E.
            Preetorius</tei:hi></tei:rs> hat in der „<tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-005906"
              ><tei:title><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Rotary</tei:hi>“-Zeitschrift</tei:title>,
          München</tei:rs>, – unbekannterweise – ungewöhnlich ehrend meines Lebenswerkes gedacht als
        einer Lösung der Frage nach dem „Zusammenhang“, de<tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overwritten">s</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="superimposed">r</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> Voraussetzung einer „künstlerische Qualität“ überhaupt.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker’s diary for January 24, 1931
          records: “Von Oppel (K): macht auf die Rotary-Zeitschrift aufmerksam, in der Prof.
          Preetorius mich „sehr gut“ erwähne! […] Nach der Jause in der Stadt […] Bestelle bei
          Gerold die Rotary-Zeitschrift.“ (“From Oppel (postcard: he alerts me to the <tei:title
            level="j">Rotary Newspaper</tei:title>, in which Prof. Preetorius mentions me as being
          ‘very good’ […] After teatime, in the city […] I order the <tei:title level="j">Rotary
            Newspaper</tei:title> from Gerold.”) — Diary February 8, 1931: “Kaufen im
          Oesterreichischen Museum Karten zum Vortrag Preetorius.“ (“At the Austrian Museum, we buy
          tichets for Preetorius’s lecture.”) A report of the lecture and his conversation with
          Preetorius is recorded in the diary for February 9.</tei:note> So nehme ich denn an, daß
        Sie den ersten Aufsatz in den kürzlich ausgegebenen <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001752"
            ><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Jahrb</tei:hi>. III meines
          „<tei:title>Meister</tei:title></tei:rs>- <tei:pb n="2"/>
        <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001752"><tei:title>werkes in der Musik</tei:title></tei:rs>“
        betitelt: „<tei:title>Rameau oder Beeth.?</tei:title>“ nicht ohne Interesse zur Kenntnis
        nehmen werden. Ihnen, dem alten Musikus, wird der Aufsatz auch von der musikalischen Seite
        hier keine Schwierigkeit machen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"
          >Schenker’s diary for February 11, 1931 records his order to <tei:rs type="organization"
            key="entity-002627">Drei Masken Verlag</tei:rs> to send a copy of <tei:title level="j"
            >Meisterwerk 3</tei:title> to Praetorius; OC 54/257, February 9, 1931, letter from DMV,
          is annotated in Schenker’s hand with a list of additional recipients, which includes
          „Preetorius.“ That letter contains a typewritten list of those to whom copies were to be
          sent, and this includes the <tei:title level="j">Neue freie Presse</tei:title>, with whom
          Seligmann worked, but not one to his home address. — February 12 records: “Brief an
          Preetorius diktirt: Uebereinstimmung aller Künste vielleicht im Zusammenhang zu suchen,
          wie ich ihn in der Musik klargelegt habe; – Lie-Liechen macht sogleich die Urschrift.”
          (“Letter to Preetorius dictated: it is perhaps worth trying to understand the unity among
          all the arts in relation to the way in which I have explained coherence in music; –
          Lie-Liechen immediately makes the first draft.”) Schenker writes the fair copy the next
          day and dispatches it. The letter is preserved as <tei:ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-5-30_1a">OJ 5/30, [1a]</tei:ref>. Hans Weisse wrote to Schenker about the lecture
          in <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-15-15_55">OJ 15/15, [55]</tei:ref>, February
          13, 1931).</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Wenn Sie so manches im Tonfall <tei:add place="interlinear-above">(nämlich S.
          20–22)</tei:add> stören sollte, so vergessen Sie es mir zuliebe als nicht durchaus im
        Zusammenhang stehend mit der Lehre vom „Zusammenhang“. Und doch . . Bedenken Sie, daß
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000431">Ministerialrat Prof Dr Kestenberg</tei:rs>,
        Dirigent des preußischen Ministeriums für Wiss., Kunst u. Volksbildung, an einen <tei:hi
          rend="underline">Schüler</tei:hi>(!) von mir, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
            >D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi>
          <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Weisse</tei:hi></tei:rs>
        <tei:pb n="3"/> bei Gelegenheit einer Einladung zu Vorträgen in <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002501"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Berlin</tei:hi></tei:rs><tei:supplied
          reason="punctuation">,</tei:supplied> schrieb: „daß H. <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
          >Schenker</tei:hi>s Werk im Mittelpunkt Ihres ganzen Wollens u. Wirkens steht, berührt
        mich <tei:add place="interlinear-above">ausser</tei:add>ordentlich sympatisch. . . . . Das
        Ergebnis, zu dem Sie kommen u das Sie wiederum zur Erkenntnis der großen Bedeutung von
          <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Sch</tei:hi>. führt, hat für mich nichts Überraschendes: die
        gegenwärtige Situation in der musikalischen Komposition führt ja geradezu zu einer
        Erneuerung u. Wiedergeburt der klassischen Grundgesätze . . . u. deshalb steht Sch’s Werk
        nicht beziehungslos als leere Theorie da, sondern in engster Verbindung zur <tei:hi
          rend="lateinschr">Praxis</tei:hi>.“ So schreibt ein Ministerialbeamter an einen Schüler
        von mir, derselbe Mann, der <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798"><tei:hi
            rend="lateinschr">Schönberg</tei:hi></tei:rs> nach <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002501"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Berlin</tei:hi></tei:rs> gerufen hat (u. es
        heute bereut). <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">D<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
            >r.</tei:hi>
          <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Weisse</tei:hi></tei:rs> wurde neuerdings eingeladen, <tei:pb
          n="4"/> in <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs> Vorträge zu halten in
        der <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-005851"><tei:hi rend="underline"><tei:hi
              rend="lateinschr">Akademie</tei:hi> der Künste</tei:hi></tei:rs> (neben <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000495">Kurth</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000798"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Schönberg</tei:hi></tei:rs>), in der
        „Hochschule für Musik“. Wien wird vermutlich <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"
            ><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Weisse</tei:hi></tei:rs> an <tei:rs type="place"
          key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs> verlieren, aber hier wurde er ja trotz zahlreicher
        Kammermusik gar nicht genannt, blos weil er mein Schüler ist. Und ich selbst? Kennt mich
        Jemand im <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-005584">Ministerium</tei:rs>? Würde Einer
        dort ein Briefchen schreiben an mich wie <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000431"
          >Kestenberg</tei:rs> an <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951"><tei:hi
            rend="lateinschr">Weisse</tei:hi></tei:rs>? Hat sich das <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-005584">Ministerium</tei:rs> bei mir für das Geschenks des „<tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archiv</tei:rs>s“, das doch im Grunde von mir
        stammt, auch bei mir nur bedankt? Und habe ich <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >nicht</tei:add> nach Wien reifste Schüler gebracht, die sich hie meinet<tei:subst>
          <tei:del rend="overstrike">wegen</tei:del>
          <tei:add place="interlinear-above">halb</tei:add>
        </tei:subst> mit ihren Reichtümern niederließen u. dem <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >Staat</tei:hi> u. der <tei:hi rend="underline">Stadt</tei:hi> sicher mehr eingebracht
        haben als mir. Kein Dank auch dafür! Wie <tei:hi rend="underline">pflegt</tei:hi>
        <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Berlin</tei:hi></tei:rs>
        sogar seine Irrtümer, hier <tei:add place="interlinear-above">aber</tei:add> zum eigenen
          <tei:hi rend="underline">wirtschaftlichen</tei:hi> Schaden <tei:note type="editorial"
          place="inline">top margin, upside down:</tei:note> nicht eine Pflege anerkannten
        Verdienstes. Der „Prominenste“ wird <tei:sic>todgeschwiegen</tei:sic>. </tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Beste Grüße u. Wünsche von uns Beiden</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>jugendlicher, sogen. „alter“</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H Schenker</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1931-02-26">26. 2. 31</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:p><tei:pb n="1"/><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">top margin:</tei:note>
          Heiter wäre der Spaß, wenn Sie mal <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000471"
            >Korngold</tei:rs>’s Manier <tei:add place="interlinear-above">sich</tei:add> mit meinen
          Termini in „“ zu behelfen, ohne den Namen der Gans zu nennen, von der er die Füßchen
            hat,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker is playing on
            the word <tei:hi rend="italic">Gänsefüsschen</tei:hi> (“little goose feet”), used
            colloquially for quotation marks.</tei:note><tei:subst>
            <tei:del rend="overstrike">in</tei:del>
            <tei:add place="interlinear-above">mit</tei:add>
          </tei:subst> der gleichen, eben ungefährlichen Weise erwiderten u. ein „“ riskierten!
            (<tei:hi rend="underline">ohne</tei:hi> Namensnennung!) </tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000819">friend</tei:rs>,<tei:ptr
            corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000680">Prof. E. Praetorius</tei:rs>, writing in the
          <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-005906"><tei:title level="j">Rotary
            Newspaper</tei:title> (Munich)</tei:rs> without my knowing of it, has spoken of my
        life’s work with uncommon reverence, as a solution to the problem of “coherence” as a
        precondition of “artistic quality” in general.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"
        /> And so I assume that you will take note of the first essay in the recently published
          <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001752">third yearbook</tei:rs> of my <tei:pb n="2"/>
        <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001752"><tei:title level="j">Meisterwerk in der
            Musik</tei:title></tei:rs>, entitled <tei:title level="a">Rameau or
          Beethoven?</tei:title> not without interest. To you, an old musician, the essay will
        present no difficulties on the musical side.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"
        /></tei:p>

      <tei:p>If so much in the tone of voice <tei:add place="interlinear-above">(especially pp.
          20–22)</tei:add> should upset you, then forget it, for my sake, as something not connected
        to the theory of “connection.” And yet … consider that the <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000431">Ministerial Counselor Prof. Kestenberg</tei:rs>, Director of the
        Prussian Academy for Science, Art, and Education, wrote to a <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >pupil</tei:hi> (!) of mine, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Dr.
        Weisse</tei:rs>, <tei:pb n="3"/> on the occasion of an invitation to give lectures in
        Berlin: “That Mr. Schenker’s work stands in the center of all your desires and activities is
        something that touches me in an <tei:add place="interlinear-above">extra</tei:add>ordinarily
        sympathetic way … The result at which you arrive, and which leads you in turn to recognize
        the great significance of Schenker, contains nothing that surprises me: the present
        situation in musical composition leads, for sure, directly to a renewal and renascence of
        basic classical principles … and for this reason Schenker’s work stands not in isolation as
        empty theory, but rather in the closest connection to practice.” This is how a ministerial
        officer wrote to a pupil of mine, the same man who summoned <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000798">Schoenberg</tei:rs> to Berlin (and regrets it today). <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000951">Dr. Weisse</tei:rs> was recently invited <tei:pb n="4"/>
        to give lectures in Berlin at the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-005851"><tei:hi
            rend="underline">Academy of the Arts</tei:hi></tei:rs> (alongside <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000495">Kurth</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000798"
          >Schoenberg</tei:rs>), in the “<tei:hi rend="underline">Hochschule</tei:hi> for Music“.
        Vienna will, I suppose, lose <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs> to
        Berlin; but here he is not known at all, in spite of having composed a great deal of chamber
        music, merely because he is my pupil. And what about me? Does anyone in the <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-005584">Ministry</tei:rs> know me? Would anyone there
        write a note to me, as <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000431">Kestenberg</tei:rs> wrote
        to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000951">Weisse</tei:rs>? Did the <tei:rs
          type="organization" key="entity-005584">Ministry</tei:rs> even thank me once for the gift
        of the “<tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002452">Archive</tei:rs>,” which essentially
        originates with me? And have I <tei:add place="interlinear-above">not</tei:add> brought the
        most mature pupils to Vienna, who on my account have settled here with their riches and
        surely brought in more to the <tei:hi rend="underline">state</tei:hi> and the <tei:hi
          rend="underline">city</tei:hi> than to me? No thanks for that either! How Berlin <tei:hi
          rend="underline">cultivates</tei:hi> even its errors; <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
          >but</tei:add> here, to its own <tei:hi rend="underline">financial</tei:hi> damage,
          <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">top margin, upside down:</tei:note> no
        cultivation of a recognized service. The “celebrity” is deemed not to exist.</tei:p>

      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute>Best greetings and wishes from the two of us.</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute>Your youthful, so-called “old” <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
            >friend</tei:supplied>,</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H. Schenker</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1931-02-26">February 26, 1931</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

      <tei:postscript>
        <tei:lb/>
        <tei:p><tei:pb n="1"/><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">top margin:</tei:note> It
          would be amusing for you if you were to reply to <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000471"
            >Korngold</tei:rs>’s practice of availing <tei:add place="interlinear-above"
            >himself</tei:add> of my terminology in quotation marks without naming the goose from
          whom he has got his little feet,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> in the
          same, even in approximately the same way and risked a “ ”! (<tei:hi rend="underline"
            >Without</tei:hi> naming names!)</tei:p>
      </tei:postscript>

    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
