<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="3021" sdoID="WSLB-129">WSLB 129</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2007, 2023</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2007, 2023</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2023</tei:resp>

    </tei:respStmt>
    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2010-03-04" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002700">Hertzka ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002701">UE ~
        H+JSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002702">UE ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">Letter</tei:rs>



      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Hertzka (UE), dated August 6, 1912</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1912-08-06T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2023-02-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker informs Hertzka that he has been approached by the Gesellschaft der
        Musikfreunde with a view to his teaching a course at the Society's new "free high school"
        beginning in October, and inquires whether Hertzka will meet his demands so that he can
        proceed with Die letzen fünf Sonaten Beethovens.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">Heinrich Schenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000356">Emil Hertzka</marcrel:recipient>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-002408">Universal Edition</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>


    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Sehr geehrter Herr <tei:rs
            type="person" key="entity-000356">Direktor</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Im Bewußtsein, keine sonderliche Störung des <tei:foreign xml:lang="ita"><tei:hi
            rend="lateinschr">dolce far niente</tei:hi></tei:foreign><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01"
          type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:hi rend="italic">dolce far niente</tei:hi>: "pleasant
          idleness." The phrase is (intentionally or unintentionally) ironic, since Hertzka is
          currently intensely busy, with the première of Schreker's opera <tei:title level="m">Der
            ferne Klang</tei:title> (August 18, Frankfurt) and other matters.</tei:note> Ihnen zu
        verursachen, (da doch die Hauptsache in Ordnung ist,) bitte ich Sie der <tei:hi
          rend="underline">vollsten</tei:hi>
        <tei:hi rend="underline">Sicherheit</tei:hi> halber um Auskunft, ob ich mich nun an die
        Arbeit machen darf.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker
          hotly contested one of the clauses of the draft contract for <tei:rs type="work"
            key="entity-001733"><tei:title level="m">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von
              Beethoven</tei:title></tei:rs> in <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="WSLB-128">WSLB
            128</tei:ref>, July 21, 1912, and an impasse seems to have existed since then. (There is
          no surviving correspondence over the two whole past weeks.) The matter is referred to by
          Hertzka in <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-52-95-96">OC 52/95-96</tei:ref>, August
          22, 1912 and resolved in the final contract, <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-494"
            >OC 52/494</tei:ref>, August 25, 1912.</tei:note> Ich bin zu dieser Frage, die
        vielleicht keine sein sollte, durch besondere neu hinzugekommene Umstände genötigt. Knapp
        vor meiner Abreise hat die <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002430">K. K.
          Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde</tei:rs> (gez. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000564"
          >Marchet</tei:rs> u. <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000478">D<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
            >r.</tei:hi> Kraus</tei:rs>) mit ausführlichem u. sehr ehrenvollem Schreiben mich für
        Vorlesungen in der neu zu kreierenden freien Hochschule angeworben.<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">The letter from the Gesellschaft der
          Musikfreunde (previously mentioned in <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="WSLB-124">WSLB
            124</tei:ref>, June 27, 1912) is <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-11-22_2">OJ
            11/22, [2]</tei:ref>, June 21, 1912, after which several letters from Schenker to the
          signatories survive.</tei:note> Von <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002310"><tei:hi
            rend="lateinschr">Bozen</tei:hi></tei:rs> aus erklärte ich mich einverstanden u. schlug
        Vorlesungen über „<tei:term>Harmonielehre</tei:term>“ vor, um allmälig meine Zuhörer
        einzuführen u. sie zu befähigen, mit mir über „Gut u. Schlecht in einem musikalischen Werk,“
        oder über „Die Unwandelbarkeit musikalischer Formen“ nachzudenken. In einem Antwortschreiben
        der <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002430">K. K. Ges. d. Mskfr.</tei:rs> wurde
        meine Zusage <tei:pb n="2"/> freudig begrüßt u. für Mitte September eine Konferenz über den
        von mir vorgeschlagenen Modus der Vorlesungen wie des Honorars angesetzt. Es will mir
        scheinen, als würde eine Einigung sehr leicht zu Stande kommen, da vorläufig ja auch keine
        Differenz vorliegt, u. da muß ich wohl im Interesse der für die „<tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002408"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">U.E</tei:hi>.</tei:rs>“ zu unternehmenden
        Arbeit an eine Einteilung alles meiner Pflichten denken.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04"
          type="editorial" place="foot">No paragraph-break in original.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Sollte es zu den Vorlesungen kommen, so würde ich, da sie schon am <tei:date
          when="1912-10-01">1. Okt.</tei:date> beginnen, in der 2. Septemberhälfte Vorbereitungen
        dafür zu treffen haben, u. so würde es mir sehr gut passen, die bis dahin währende Zeit der
        Arbeit an der <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001734"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
            >Sonate</tei:hi></tei:rs> zu widmen. Fast kommt es mir leichtsinnig u. kindisch vor,
        eine so gelegene Arbeitszeit wie die gegenwärtige zu versäumen, wobei ich das Versäumnis
        durch gar nichts rechtfertigen kann. Eine wirkliche Sünde ist es! Kam doch jener Punkt noch
        niemals in unseren Verträgen vor, u. sind deshalb meine Arbeiten je schlecht ausgefallen?
        Was soll nun plötzlich der Punkt <tei:hi rend="underline">heute</tei:hi>??<tei:note
          xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">No paragraph-break in
          original.</tei:note></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Zudem kommt, daß ich endlich auf die Spur des vielgesuchten <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
          >Manuscripts</tei:hi><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">The
          manuscript of Beethoven's sonata Op. 109, previously referred to in <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="WSLB-123">WSLB 123</tei:ref>, June 24, and <tei:ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="WSLB-128">WSLB 128</tei:ref>, July 21, 1912.</tei:note>
        gekommen bin u. nach so viel Korrespondenzen, die ich gepflogen haben, plötzlich stecken
        bleibe, weil ich nicht weiß, ob ich der <tei:pb n="3"/>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000970">Besitzerin</tei:rs> des <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
          >Manuscripts</tei:hi> zu schreiben habe oder nicht.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07"
          type="editorial" place="foot">The manuscript of Op. 109 had been in the possession of the
          family of its publisher, Schlesinger, was auctioned in 1907 and entered the possession of
          the Wittgenstein family of Vienna. Schenker had been apprised of its current whereabouts
          as recorded in his diary for August 2, 1912: "<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000562"
            >Mandyczewski</tei:rs> teilt mir mit, daß das Manuscript op. 109 in Wien sich befindet!"
            ("<tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000562">Mandyczewski</tei:rs> informs me that the
          manuscript of Op. 109 is located in Vienna!"). Mandyczewski's postcard to this effect, OJ
          12/49, [3], August 1, 1912, reads: "Das Autograph von op 109 ist im Privatbesitz,
          merkwürdigerweise in <tei:hi rend="underline">Wien</tei:hi>, bei Frau Poldy Wittgenstein,
          Alleegasse." ("The autograph manuscript of Op. 109 is in private possession, strangely
          enough in <tei:hi rend="underline">Vienna</tei:hi>, with Mrs. Poldy Wittgenstein,
          Alleegasse.").</tei:note> Erlösen Sie mich also aus all diesen recht <tei:hi
          rend="underline">kostspieligen</tei:hi> Zweifeln mit einem Kräftigen „Ja,“ damit ich Zeit
        für die Arbeit gewinne, für das Studium des <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Manuscriptes</tei:hi>
        u. dgl. mehr. (Und vergessen Sie nicht, das von mir so oft wiederholte <tei:hi
          rend="underline">Anliegen</tei:hi> betreffs der „<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001731"
            ><tei:title level="m">IX Sinf.</tei:title></tei:rs>“!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08"
          type="editorial" place="foot">In <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="WSLB-116">WSLB
            116</tei:ref>, June 2, Schenker asked for an additional 400 Kronen for reading the
          proofs of <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001731"><tei:title level="m">Beethovens neunte
              Sinfonie</tei:title></tei:rs>, and in <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-52-427"
            >OC 52/427</tei:ref>, June 3 and repeated the request several times since then; Hertzka
          responded that he hoped to be able to do this, but that the printing costs had been
          high.</tei:note>) Ihre <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Annonce</tei:hi> in <tei:rs
          type="journal" key="entity-002556"><tei:title>der „Musik“</tei:title></tei:rs> habe ich
        gelesen. Eine Zeitlang werden meine lieben Fachkollegen noch „Strampeln“, aber ich werden
        die Schnur noch fester zuziehen, bis sie aufhören werden, Betrug u. Unwissenheit für
        „Fortschritt“ auszugeben! </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Ein paar Zeilen erbittet so bald als möglich</tei:p>



      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">Ihr ergebener,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">Sie herzlich Begrüßender</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50">
          <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">H
            Schenker</tei:hi></tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-005514">Paneveggio</tei:rs>, <tei:date
              when="1912-08-06">6. August 1912</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-10"><tei:handShift new="#HS"/>Dear <tei:rs type="person"
            key="entity-000356">Director</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Conscious of not wishing to cause any great disturbance to your <tei:hi rend="italic"
          >dolce far niente</tei:hi><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> (since the main
        preoccupation is definitely in good shape), I beg you, so as to be <tei:hi rend="underline"
          >absolutely certain</tei:hi>, to inform me whether I may now get down to work.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> I am obliged to ask this question, which ought
        perhaps to be superfluous, because of special circumstances that have just arisen. Just before my
        departure, the <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002430">Imperial-Royal Society for
          the Friends of Music</tei:rs>, in a detailed and very honorable letter (signed by <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000564">Gustav Marchet</tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="person"
          key="entity-000478">Dr. Kraus</tei:rs>), enlisted me to give lectures in the free high
        school soon to be created.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> Writing from
          <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002310">Bolzano</tei:rs>, I declared myself agreeable and
        proposed lectures on "<tei:term>Theory of Harmony</tei:term>" so as to introduce my audience
        gradually and to enable it to reflect with me on "good and bad in a musical work" or on “the
        immutability of musical form.” In a letter of reply from the <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002430">Imperial-Royal Society for the Friends of Music</tei:rs>, my consent
        was greeted <tei:pb n="2"/> with delight and a meeting was scheduled for the middle of
        September to discuss the type of the lectures suggested by me, as well as the fee. It looks
        to me as if agreement might be reached very easily, since at present no sign of any
        difference of opinion has emerged, and since, in the interests certainly of the work that I
        am to undertake for <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">UE</tei:rs>, I must
        think in terms of planning out all my obligations.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04"
          type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Should the lectures come about, then since, their being due to begin already on
          <tei:date when="1912-10-01">October 1</tei:date>, I would have to prepare for them in the
        second half of September, it would suit me very well to devote the time between now and then
        to working on the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001734">sonata</tei:rs>. It is almost
        reckless and childish for me to neglect such opportune working time as the present ‒
        negligence that I cannot possibly justify. It is a veritable sin! That one point has never
        arisen before in our contracts ‒ and have my books ever turned out badly as a result? Why
        should it suddenly do so <tei:hi rend="underline">today</tei:hi>??<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/></tei:p>

      <tei:p>Add to that, that I am finally on the trail of the much-sought-after
          manuscript,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> and that after so much
        correspondence that I have conducted I am suddenly stalled because I do not know whether I
        have to write to the <tei:pb n="3"/>
        <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000970">owner</tei:rs> of the manuscript or not.<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> So release me from all these rather <tei:hi
          rend="underline">costly</tei:hi> doubts with a resounding "Yes," so that I can gain time
        for the work, for study of the manuscript, and for many other such things. (And don’t forget
        my <tei:hi rend="underline">request</tei:hi>, so oft-repeated, regarding the <tei:rs
          type="work" key="entity-001731"><tei:title level="m">Ninth
          Symphony</tei:title></tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/>) I have
        read your advertisement in <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002556"><tei:title level="j"
            >Die Musik</tei:title></tei:rs>. My dear professional colleagues will still "kick" for a
        while, but I will tie the noose ever tighter until they stop perpetrating deception and
        ignorance in the name of "progress"!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>A line or two as soon as possible is requested by</tei:p>



      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-30">your devoted,</tei:salute>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-60">who greets you cordially</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-50">
          <tei:rs key="entity-000632" type="person">H. Schenker</tei:rs></tei:signed><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
        <tei:address>
          <tei:addrLine><tei:rs type="place" key="entity-005514">Paneveggio</tei:rs>, <tei:date
              when="1912-08-06">August 6, 1912</tei:date></tei:addrLine>
        </tei:address>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>

  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
