<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
  xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
  xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
  <sdo:collectionDesc>
    <sdo:source>
      <sdo:correspondence mfID="2913" sdoID="WSLB-Hds-95663">WSLB-Hds 95663</sdo:correspondence>
    </sdo:source>

    <tei:handNotes>
      <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
    </tei:handNotes>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="WMD">
      <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>Transcription, 2022</tei:resp>
      <tei:resp>Translation, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
      <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
      <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2022</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT">
      <tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name>
      <tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp>
    </tei:respStmt>

    <tei:revisionDesc>
      <tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change>
      <tei:change when="2012-09-28" who="#IB">revision of XML code</tei:change>
    </tei:revisionDesc>
  </sdo:collectionDesc>

  <sdo:record ID="r0001">

    <sdo:itemDesc>
      <tei:rs role="correspondence" type="correspondence" key="entity-002735">Seligmann ~
        HSchenker</tei:rs>
      <tei:rs role="corr-item-type" type="corr-item-type" key="entity-002744">letter</tei:rs>

      <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Seligmann, dated April 26, 1910</dc:title>

      <dcterms:created>1910-04-26T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
      <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2022-11-24</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
      <dc:description>Schenker thanks Seligmann for a copy of his recently published collected
        essays. He announces the imminent publication of the first half-volume of his Kontrapunkt,
        which has been long in preparation.</dc:description>
      <dc:subject/>

      <marcrel:correspondent key="entity-000632">Heinrich Schenker</marcrel:correspondent>
      <marcrel:recipient key="entity-000819">Adalbert Franz Seligmann</marcrel:recipient>
    </sdo:itemDesc>

    <tei:div type="transcription">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute>Lieber <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000819">Freund</tei:rs>!</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>Als ich heute, den 26<tei:hi rend="supralinear">ten</tei:hi>, ins Cafehaus kam, nach
        langen Wochen wieder zum ersten Mal, traf mich dort die schönste Überraschung, die ich mir
        nur wünschen könnte, Ihr neuestes Buch!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
          place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:author>A. F. Seligmann</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m"
              >Kunst und Künstler von gestern und heute: Gesammelte Aufsätze</tei:title> (Vienna:
            Konegen, 1910)</tei:bibl>.</tei:note> Daß ichs aber gleich sage, dieses Buch – neuen
        Inhalt ausgenommen – besitze ich in meiner Bibliothek schon seit Jahren: habe’ich doch alle
        Ihre Aufsätze selbst gesammelt, mit Datum versehen in größter Ordnung aufgestapelt, so daß
        Sie fehlendes aus meiner Mappe beziehen konnten. Aber gerade deshalb freue mich des Buches
        doppelt: nicht nur daß ein mir lieber u. nahestehender Inhalt wirklich doppelt gegenwärtig
        ist; sondern, daß auch Sie ähnlichen Wert darauf gelegt haben, wie ich, freut mich doch
        meinethalb ganz besonders! </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Bald, sehr bald werde ich Ihnen umgekehrt mit meiner Novität, dem <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001726">ersten Halbband des „<tei:title><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
            >Kp</tei:hi></tei:title>.</tei:rs>“ <tei:add place="interlinear-above">auf</tei:add>.
        (Ach, eine „Frühgeburt“ ist es wahrhaftig nicht; vielleicht an 8<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
          >mal</tei:hi>
        <tei:pb n="2"/> niedergeschrieben, ist das Buch bald 2 Jahre in Druck: nur noch 12 kleinen
        Fahnen u. – die Vorrede, die, wie Sie dann sehen werden, mich fast krank machen mußte! Meine
        Wut <tei:unclear reason="reading">reißt</tei:unclear> los, die Vorrede aber ist zu kurz
        dazu, u. vom „<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001759"><tei:title>Niedergang der
            Komp.</tei:title></tei:rs>“ trennt mich noch ein Abstand von 2–3 Jahren. Eine schwere
        Reise! Alles in Allem aber glaube ich sagen zu können, daß der heutige Stand unserer Kunst
        trostloser ist, als der der Malerei. Und das geht nur fast zu nahe. </tei:p>

      <tei:p>Sehe ich Sie mal wieder, so erzähle ich Ihnen mehrere absonderliche Geschichten von der
          <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000199">Frau <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
          >Eissler</tei:hi></tei:rs>, der „<tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408"><tei:hi
            rend="lateinschr">U. E.</tei:hi></tei:rs>“ u. Wien u. dgl. Bis dahin besten,
        herzlichsten Dank für Ihre Erinnerung u. Buch! </tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">I<tei:supplied reason="omission">h</tei:supplied>r</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H Schenker</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1910-04-26">26. 4. 10.</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>

    </tei:div>


    <tei:div type="translation">

      <tei:opener>
        <tei:salute>Dear <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000819">friend</tei:rs>,</tei:salute>
      </tei:opener>

      <tei:p>When I came into the coffee-house today, the 26th, for the first time in many weeks, I
        was met by the most beautiful surprise that I could only wish for: your latest book!<tei:ptr
          corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> At the same time I could say that I have already
        had this book – its latest content excepted – in my library for years: for I have collected
        all your essays myself, provided them with dates and arranged them in the best order, so
        that you could draw on any missing items from my folder. But for this very reason, I am
        doubly happy about the book: not only because a content that is dear and close to me is
        actually twice present; but also, because you have laid a similar value on it as I have,
        that delights me especially for my sake!</tei:p>

      <tei:p>Soon – very soon – I shall for my part send you my newest item, the <tei:rs type="work"
          key="entity-001726">first half-volume of my <tei:title level="m"
          >Counterpoint</tei:title></tei:rs>. Ah, it was definitely not “born prematurely”; written
        down close to eight times, <tei:pb n="2"/> the book has been in press for nearly two years:
        only twelve short galley proofs and – the Preface, which, as you will soon see, must have
        made me almost ill!) My anger <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">breaks
          loose</tei:unclear>; the Preface, however, is too short, and a space of a further two to
        three years separates me from <tei:supplied reason="clarity">the publication
          of</tei:supplied>
        <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001759"><tei:title level="m">The Decline of the Art of
            Composition</tei:title></tei:rs>. A difficult journey! All things considered, however, I
        believe I can say that the present state of our art is bleaker than that of painting. And
        the latter is fast catching up.</tei:p>

      <tei:p>If we see each other again, I shall tell you several bizarre stories about <tei:rs
          type="person" key="entity-000199">Mrs. Eissler</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="organization"
          key="entity-002408">Universal Edition</tei:rs>, Vienna, and the like. Until then, most
        cordial thanks for thinking of me, and for your book!</tei:p>


      <tei:closer>
        <tei:salute rend="indent-50">Your</tei:salute>
        <tei:signed rend="indent-60"><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000632">H. Schenker</tei:rs>
        </tei:signed><tei:lb/>
        <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1910-04-26">April 26, 1910</tei:date></tei:dateline>
      </tei:closer>


    </tei:div>
  </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
