<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 10/13, [7] : 6-16-28 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  Deemed to be in the public domain.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2007.
© Translation William Drabkin, 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1928-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Deemed to be in the public domain; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 06/16/1928 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Dunn ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Dunn to Schenker, dated June 16, 1928</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-05-03</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Sends S greetings on his 60th birthday;  his English adaptation is a success, but is limited by the fact that a less enlightened colleague teaches first-year counterpoint;  outlines his latest work, a study of orchestration from a theoretical point of view;  hopes that he and his wife might visit the Schenkers the following summer.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Dunn, John Petrie; Schenker, Heinrich,  birthday wishes;  photograph;  Aspects of Orchestration;  Beethoven;  Ninth Symphony;  Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie;  Beethoven's Ninth Symphony;  orchestration;  publisher;  Kontrapunkt;  Counterpoint;  adaptation;  translation;  Spekeroog;  Norderney;  meeting</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  42 Murrayfield Avenue, Edinburgh</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Dunn to Schenker, dated June 16, 1928</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[printed address (on each <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>):]
42 Murrayfield Avenue,
Edinburgh, 
den 16. Juni, 1928</tei:p><tei:p>Hochverehrter Herr Schenker!</tei:p><tei:p>Gestatten Sie, dass ich Ihnen zuIhrem Geburtstag<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> Schenker celebrated his sixtieth birthday on June 19, 1928.  Receipt of this letter is recorded in S’s diary, OJ 4/1, p. 3216.</tei:note> meinen herzlichsten Glückwunschausspreche und zugleich der Hoffnung Ausdruck gebe, dass es Ihnen vergönnt sein möge, noch viele, viele Jahre hindurch tätig zu sein!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich erlaube mir, eine meiner neuesten Photographien beizulegen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  A photograph of Dunn, seated, exists (OJ 72/4, 1) with holograph inscription to Schenker dated June 19, 1928, photographer: Moffat, Edinburgh.  D must have dated it not according to the date of his letter but to that of S's birthday.  (Another photograph, of John and Aline Petrie Dunn, inscribed "Marienbad, August 1930,” survives as (OJ 72/4, 2.)</tei:note> und bitte Sie, dieselbe als [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] bescheidenes Merkmal meines Dankbarkeitsgefühles Ihnen gegenüber aufzufassen.</tei:p><tei:p>Es wird Sie vielleicht interessieren zu erfahren, <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> dass ich gegenwärtig ein Buch über Orchestrierung verfasse. (“Aspects of Orchestration”, etwa ”Gesichtspunkte der Orchestrierung”).  In einer Abteilung über “Klarheit” (d.h. des Melos) habe ich mir erlaubt, einen längeren Passus aus Ihrer Schrift über die Neunte in englischer Uebersetzung wiederzugeben. (S. 47 - “So entsinne ich mich nie “- - - - - - bis S. 49 - - - “überflüssige Deutlichkeitsgrade.”)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> The extract concerns the first eight bars of Beethoven’s Eighth Symphony. Wagner criticizes Beethoven’s lack of melodic clarity, by allowing the first oboe (in bar 6) and first flute (bar 8) to enter “unthematically.”  Schenker sees no problem with this:  Beethoven’s use of the oboe first as a filler part (bars 6-7), then as a reinforcement of the melodic line (bars 7-8) is for Schenker no lack of clarity, but is rather a more subtle approach to orchestration than a theatre-orientated composer such as Wagner could have understood. (= Eng. trans., pp. 67–68)</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Wie, wo, und wann das Buch erscheinen wird, weiss ich noch garnicht.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> Dunn presented this work to the University of Edinburgh in partial fulfilment of the DMus in 1928.  It was published as <tei:hi rend="italic">A Student's Guide to Orchestration</tei:hi> (London: Novello, 1930), with a dedication to Donald Francis Tovey;  a review appeared in <tei:hi rend="italic">The Musical Times</tei:hi>, 71 (1930), p. 611.  True to his word, Dunn included the extract from <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie</tei:hi> concerning the opening bars of the Eighth, in a chapter on “Lucidity” (see pp. 79–80);  this is probably the first extract from Schenker’s theoretical work to appear in English translation.  Dunn quotes Schenker approvingly, and recommends many of his writings in the preface (the first three volumes of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue Musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:hi>, the first two volumes of <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, and the monograph on the Ninth), but is careful not to expose Schenker as an outright anti-Wagnerian:</tei:note>  Vielleicht werde ich überhaupt keinen Verleger finden können, der es macht.  Der Markt wimmelt von elenden kleinen Instrumentenkunden, die alle dasselbe bringen und sich gegenseitig [<tei:hi rend="italic">words crossed out</tei:hi>] widerholen.  Mein Buch setzt die Kenntnis der einzelnen Instrumente voraus und handelt nur von den <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> leitenden Gesichtspunkten der klassischen Orchestrierungskunst, als da sind Verdoppelung der Stimmen, Verwandlung eines Continualstimme in eine Wirkliche und umgekehrt; Klangfarbe, Farbenmischung und Register; das Gleichgewicht und das +zusammenfassende+ Hören; wie [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] man zuzuhören hat;  die Rolle der ^3^ Hauptgruppen im Orchestersatz;  Klarheit u.s.w.</tei:p><tei:p>Sollte das Buch einmal herauskommen, so werde ich Sie, beziehungsweise Ihren Verleger -auf- um die Erlaubnis bitten, den besagten Passus zu zitieren.</tei:p><tei:p>Die Uebersetzung Ihres “Kontrapunkts” wurde durch Verteilung vieler Exemplare <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> meinen Studenten zugänglich gemacht.  Alle äusserten sich sehr günstig darüber.  Es ist mir jedoch nicht möglich, nach dieser Richtung hin meinen Einfluss so weit geltend zu machen, wie mir dieses erwünscht wäre, denn gerade der strenge Satz wird nicht von mir sondern von einem Kollegen gelehrt.  Dieser Herr begeht nun gerade die Fehler, die Sie rügen.  Er liebäugelt nämlich mit dem freien Satz und verbietet z.B. –</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>– weil diese Fortschreitungen angeblich [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] verkappte 6/4 Harmonien sind!  Die Folge ^davon^ ist dass die Schüler den -freien- ^strengen^ Satz als ein zum Bestehen von Prüfung in notwendiger Nebel betrachten!  <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> Viele der Studenten sind der Ansicht, dass ich den Elementar-Unterricht übernehmen müsste, weil sie dann gleich den richtigen Begriff davon bekommen würden, allein das ist leider unmöglich.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich möchte furchtbar gerne einmal mit Ihnen zusammenkommen und alle möglichen Fragen besprechen.  Dieses Jahr fahre ich mit meiner Frau auf 14 Tage nach Spiekeroog (bei Norderney).<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> Spiekeroog, Norderney: two islands in the North Sea, off the coast of Lower Saxony.</tei:note>  Nächsten Sommer aber werden wir ganz bestimmt nach Bayreuth fahren.  Vielleicht haben wir dann Gelegenheit, uns gegenseitig <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> auszusprechen.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit herzlichsten Grüssen von Haus zu Haus</tei:p><tei:p>Verbleibe ich,
Ihr ganz ergebener
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] John Petrie Dunn.</tei:p><tei:p>––––––––––</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Dunn to Schenker, dated June 16, 1928</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[printed address (on each <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>):]
42 Murrayfield Avenue,
Edinburgh,
June 16, 1928</tei:p><tei:p>Most esteemed Mr. Schenker,</tei:p><tei:p>Allow me to express my most cordial wishes to you for your birthday<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> and, at the same time, give expression to the hope that it may be granted that you remain active for many, many years to come!</tei:p><tei:p>I take the liberty of enclosing one of the most recent photographs of myself,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> and ask you to regard it as a modest sign of my feelings of gratitude towards you.</tei:p><tei:p>It will probably interest you to learn <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> that I am at present writing a book on orchestration (“Aspects of Orchestration,” which may be rendered in German as “Gesichtspunkte der Orchestrierung”).  In a section on “clarity” (i.e. of the melodic line) I permitted myself to reproduce, in English translation, an extended passage from your book on the Ninth Symphony, from p. 47 (“Thus I cannot remember ever...”) to p. 49 (“…unnecessary degree of clarity”).<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/></tei:p><tei:p>How, where and when the book will appear I cannot possibly say.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  Perhaps I will be utterly unable to find a publisher who will take it.  The market is flooded with wretched little instrument handbooks, which all offer the same thing, each one repeating what the others say.  My book presupposes a knowledge of the individual instruments and is concerned only with the <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> leading aspects of the classical art of orchestration, viz. the doubling of voices;  the transformation of a filler voice into a true one, and vice versa;  tonal color, mixing of colors and register;  balance, and synthetic hearing;  how one should listen;  the role of the ^three^ principal groups of instruments in orchestral composition;  clarity, etc.</tei:p><tei:p>Should the book ever appear in print, I shall request of you, i.e. of your publisher, permission to cite the passage in question.</tei:p><tei:p>The translation of your <tei:hi rend="italic">Counterpoint</tei:hi> was made available to <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> my students by the distribution of many copies.  All of them expressed their satisfaction with it.  It is, however, impossible for me to exert my influence in this direction as widely as I would like, for the very subject of strict counterpoint is taught not by me but by a colleague of mine.  This man commits precisely the same mistakes that you speak out against.  He flirts, in fact, with free counterpoint and forbids, for instance,</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>because these progressions appear to be disguised six-four harmonies!  As a consequence, the pupils regard strict counterpoint as a test that has to be passed in necessary dimness. <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi>  Many of the students are of the view that I should take over the elementary education, since they would then receive the correct understanding of it;  unfortunately that is not possible.</tei:p><tei:p>I should frightfully like to get together with you and discuss all manner of problems.  This year I am going with my wife for fourteen days to Spiekeroog (near Norderney).<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  Next summer, however, we are definitely going to Bayreuth.  Perhaps we will then have the opportunity to <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> discuss things face to face.</tei:p><tei:p>With the most cordial greetings from us to you,</tei:p><tei:p>I remain
your entirely devoted
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] John Petrie Dunn.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>