<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="ea">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Die letzten f&#xFC;nf Sonaten von Beethoven (Erläuterungsausgabe)</title>
        <title type="sub">The Last Five Sonatas of Beethoven (Elucidatory Edition)</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="ea">Erl&#xE4;uterungsausgabe</term>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt><sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc></fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Work</term>
          <term subtype="basename">ea</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Die letzten f&#xFC;nf Sonaten von Beethoven (Erläuterungsausgabe)</head>
      <div>
        <p>Schenker's edition of four of the last five piano sonatas of Beethoven, published
          separately, and based in each case on surviving autograph manuscript and sketch materials,
          and early editions, and drawing on Nottebohm's publications and private notes. This
          edition is in each case accompanied by Schenker's elucidations (<hi rend="italic"
            >Erläuterungen</hi>), which describe the sources, analyze structure and thematic content
          (with copious music examples, and in the case of Op. 101 Urlinien), provide detailed
          guidelines for performance, and encompass a survey of the previous secondary literature
          and editions. The four volumes were published by Universal Edition of Vienna between 1913
          and 1921.</p>
        <p>The motivation for this edition was to discredit the 19th-century editions, not only of
          these works but of those of the German and Austrian classical composers in general,
          against which Schenker had for many years polemicized; to show that with the exception of
          fingerings little or no editorial intervention was usually required — i.e. that
          Beethoven's orthography, when correctly understood and explained, provided all that was
          needed for understanding a work's structure and performing it according to his wishes; and
          ultimately to reveal the processes of mind of a supreme "master" of musical composition —
          to uncover the workings of genius. </p>
        <p> Because these volumes were prepared for the most part during World War I, they served
          also as a principal vehicle for Schenker's German nationalist feelings, and his intense
          antipathy toward the nations of the West, and this polemical stratum of the work relates
          directly to the leading article "Von der Sendung des deutschen Genies," in the first issue
          of <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title> (1921), and his Preface to <title level="m"
            >Kontrapunkt 2</title> (1922).</p>
        <p>The five volumes of the work, which were to have been published one per year (contract:
          OC 52/494, August 25, 1912) but for the impact of the war upon both Schenker's research
          and the commerce of publishing, were: <listBibl>
            <bibl>
              <ref cRef="ea-op109"><title level="m">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven ... op.
                  109</title> (1913)</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
              <ref cRef="ea-op110"><title level="m">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven ... op.
                  110</title> (1914)</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
              <ref cRef="ea-op111"><title level="m">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven ... op.
                  111</title> (1916)</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
              <ref cRef="ea-op101"><title level="m">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven ... op.
                  101</title> (1921)</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
              <ref cRef="ea-op106"><title level="m">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven ... op.
                  106</title> (unpublished)</ref>
            </bibl>
          </listBibl></p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>New Edition</head>
        <p>A new edition was produced in four separate, smaller-format volumes in 1971–72 by <ref
            cRef="jonas_oswald">Oswald Jonas</ref>, pupil of Schenker and Hans Weisse. Jonas excised
          from Schenker's original all the polemical material and the entire discussion of the
          secondary literature, and also replaced Schenker's editions of the sonatas by Erwin Ratz's
          edition of 1945 with the effect that the scores contradict some of the textual argument in
          Schenker's elucidations. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>English Translation and Study</head>
        <p>An English translation of all four published volumes of the <title level="m"
            >Erläuterungsausgabe</title> by John Rothgeb is currently in progress (2010). A new
          study of Op. 106 ("Hammerklavier") by Nicholas Marston, amplifying Schenker's unpublished
          work on the sonata (in the Oster Collection, OC 65), is also in preparation. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Bent, Ian</author>, <title level="a">'That Bright New Light': Schenker,
              Universal Edition, and the Origins of the Erläuterung Series, 1901–1910,</title>
            <title level="j">Journal of the American Musicological Society</title> LVIII/1 (Spring
            2005), 69–138 </bibl>
          <bibl><author>Drabkin, William</author>, <title level="a">The New
            Erläuterungsausgabe,</title>
            <title level="j">Perspectives of New Music</title> 12 (1971–72), 319–30 </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Ian Bent</author> and <author>William Drabkin</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
