<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-001753">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Beethoven: Klaviersonaten</title>
        <title type="sub">Beethoven: Piano Sonatas</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="beethoven-klaviersonaten">Beethoven: Klaviersonaten</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>30/10/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Work</term>
          <term subtype="basename">beethoven-klaviersonaten</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>

  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Beethoven: Klaviersonaten</head>

      <div>

        <p>Complete edition of the Beethoven piano sonatas by Heinrich Schenker, published by
          Universal Edition of Vienna between 1921 and 1923. </p>

        <div>
          <p>UE's publicity of the time claimed that it was: <cit>
              <q>a new edition of the complete sonatas in which all the alterations and
                contaminations that are perpetuated in most other editions to the detriment of the
                content have been eliminated by reference to manuscripts, revised copies, and
                original editions, and so Schenker's edition presents <hi rend="bold">for the first
                  time a reproduction of the greatest musical creations faithful to the
                  originals</hi>.</q>
            </cit>
          </p>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>Publication History</head>
          <div>
            <head>First Edition</head>

            <p>The original edition was published first individually (UE 4010–4041) in 1921–23, with
              the collective title: <cit>
                <q>
                  <title level="m">L. van. Beethoven: Klaviersonaten: Nach den Autographen und
                    Erstdrucken rekonstruiert von Heinrich Schenker </title>
                </q>
              </cit>
              <cit>
                <q>
                  <title level="m">L. van Beethoven: Piano Sonatas, reconstructed from the autograph
                    manuscripts and first editions by Heinrich Schenker</title>. </q>
              </cit>
            </p>

            <p>In this edition, Schenker eschewed editorial phrase-markings, dynamic marks, etc.
              (all of which he deplored in the work of other editors, maintaining that Beethoven
              provided all such markings as were necessary), but did supply fingerings, and also
              "elucidations" (<hi rend="italic">Erläuterungen</hi>), i. e. explanatory comment. </p>

            <p>It was then published in four volumes (Vierbändige Gesamtausgabe) as follows: I: Opp.
              2, 7, 10 (UE 8a) — II: Opp. 13, 14, 22, 26, 27, 28 (UE 8b) — III: Opp. 31, 49, 53, 54,
              57 (UE 9a) — IV: Opp. 78, 81a, 90, 101, 106, 109, 110, 111 (UE 9b). (UE 8‒9 were
              originally assigned to their two-volume bound "Prachtausgabe" of the sonatas, and seem
              to have been re-used at this time, and again for the second edition, by Erwin Ratz.) </p>

            <p>Some sonatas were edited a second time by Schenker during the later 1920s, notable
              Op. 57 ("Appasasionata") and Op. 90. </p>

            <p>The draft contract for this work was dated March 23, 1920, the revised contract July
              10, 1920 (OC 52/447 and 448). This is one of two contracts (the other being that for
              the <ref cRef="entity-001758">
                <title level="j">Kleine Bibliothek</title>
              </ref>) that Schenker contested vigorously under advice from the attorney Leo
              Fischmann. The contract made provision for publication as a single volume,
              collectively in several volumes, and individually, and for each sonata to be supplied
              with an introduction. For each sonata, Schenker inspected directly or obtained
              photographs of all the autograph manuscripts and first editions that were known and
              available to him. </p>

          </div>

          <div>
            <head>Second Edition</head>

            <p>A second edition, with revisions by Erwin Ratz, was published by Universal Edition
              (UE 8–9) c. 1946–47 as part of the Wiener Urtext Ausgabe, with Foreword in German,
              French, and English, bearing the title: <cit>

                <q>
                  <title level="m">L. van Beethoven: Klaviersonaten, nach den Autographen und
                    Erstdrucken revidiert und mit Fingersätzen versehen von Heinrich Schenker. Neue
                    Ausgabe revidiert von Erwin Ratz</title>
                </q>
              </cit>
              <cit>
                <q><title level="m">L. van Beethoven: Piano Sonatas, revised according to the
                    autograph manuscripts and first editions and provided with fingerings by
                    Heinrich Schenker. New edition revised by Erwin Ratz</title>. </q>
              </cit>
            </p>

            <p>In this edition, Ratz modernized Schenker’s bar-numbering and, significantly, refined
              some of his editorial work in the light of primary sources that Schenker had
              undervalued or did not know. (It was this edition that was reprinted for Oswald
              Jonas’s revised edition of the <title level="m">Erläuterungsausgabe</title>, 1971–72,
              with the consequence that Schenker’s commentary and the musical text are often
              contradictory.) </p>
          </div>

          <div>
            <head>New Edition</head>

            <p>A two-volume reprint of Schenker’s original edition, with Foreword and additional
              textual notes by Carl Schachter, was published by Dover Books in New York in 1975 as
                <title level="m">Ludwig van Beethoven: Complete Piano Sonatas</title>. </p>
          </div>
        </div>

      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Ian Bent</author> and <author>William Drabkin</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
