<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-001724">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Harmonielehre</title>
        <title type="sub">Theory of Harmony</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="harmonielehre">Harmonielehre</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>30/10/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Work</term>
          <term subtype="basename">harmonielehre</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Harmonielehre</head>
      <div>
        <p>Volume I of Schenker's series of theoretical works entitled <title level="s">Neue
            Musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</title> (New Musical Theories and Fantasies), first
          published by J. G. Cotta of Stuttgart in 1906, and later published by Universal Edition of
          Vienna. </p>

        <p>With <title level="m">Harmonielehre</title>, Schenker laid the foundation of his entire
          theoretical construct. This is not to diminish the significance of his <title level="m">Beitrag zur Ornamentik</title> of 1903, in which ornamentation emerged as fundamental
          to his way of viewing music, and his indebtedness to C. P. E. Bach's <title level="m">Versuch</title> became clear. But it was in <title level="m">Harmonielehre</title> that
          he set forth for the first time the central concepts of <hi rend="italic">Stufe</hi>
          (harmonic scale-degree) and <hi rend="italic">Auskomponierung</hi> (literally
          "composing-out," i.e. elaboration), along with the notions of tonicization and
          chromaticization. It was also in <title level="m">Harmonielehre</title> that he began to
          distance himself from certain trends in contemporaneous music, and that his polemical vein
          began to show itself. </p>

        <div>
          <head>Publication History</head>
          <div>
            <head>First Edition</head>
            <p>Half-title-page:</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">NEUE</hi> | <hi rend="italic">MUSIKALISCHE THEORIEN </hi> | <hi rend="italic">UND PHANTASIEN </hi> | <hi rend="italic">VON</hi> | <hi rend="italic">EINEM KÜNSTLER</hi> | <hi rend="italic">ERSTER BAND: HARMONIELEHRE </hi> | [<hi rend="italic">publisher's device</hi>: MDCXL] | <hi rend="italic">STUTTGART UND
                BERLIN 1906 </hi> | <hi rend="italic">J. G. COTTA'SCHE BUCHHANDLUNG NACHFOLGER</hi></p>
            <p>Ttle-page:</p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">HARMONIELEHRE </hi> | <hi rend="italic">VON</hi> | <hi rend="italic">EINEM KÜNSTLER</hi> | [<hi rend="italic">publisher's device</hi>:
              MDCXL] | <hi rend="italic">STUTTGART UND BERLIN 1906 </hi> | <hi rend="italic">J. G.
                COTTA'SCHE BUCHHANDLUNG NACHFOLGER</hi></p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head> Chronology:</head>
            <p> Schenker's Foreword is undated, but was submitted on October 17, 1906. Having failed
              during 1905 to secure publication by Breitkopf &amp; Härtel of Leipzig, Universal
              Edition Vienna, and Max Brockhaus of Leipzig, and having initially been turned down by
                <ref cRef="entity-002405">J. G. Cotta of Stuttgart</ref>, Cotta were persuaded through
              the intervention of <ref cRef="entity-000150">Eugen d'Albert</ref> to take it on in
              their commission publishing house. Schenker dispatched the manuscript of the work to
              Cotta on November 22, 1905; the contract for the work stipulated a print-run of 1,100
              copies at a retail price of 35 Pfennigs per gathering, with Schenker earning 75% of
              the net receipts. The eventual volume price was 10 Marks. </p>
            <p> At first, Schenker planned to add an "Nachwort" (Afterword) of one gathering, but
              the latter assumed such large proportions that eventually in discussion with Cotta he
              opted to issue it as a separate publication. In the event, it was never published, and
              remained a typescript entitled "Über den Niedergang der Kompositionskunst: eine
              technisch-kritische Untersuchung" ("The Decline of the Art of Composition: A
              Technical-critical Study"). Proof-correcting began in the summer of 1905 and continued
              into 1906, and the book was published on November 10, 1906. Alphons von Rothschild
              paid the publishing and marketing costs of 4,300.30 Marks. </p>
            <p> In 1909, Schenker agreed, having by then submitted his <title level="m">Kontrapunkt
                1</title>, that the title-page of <title level="m">Harmonielehre</title> should at
              last bear his name, and for the remainder of the first edition new half-title and
              title-pages were supplied that substituted "HEINRICH SCHENKER" for "EINEM KÜNSTLER."
            </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head>Second Edition</head>
            <p><ref cRef="entity-002408">Universal Edition of Vienna</ref> agreed in 1920 to
              take over from Cotta the publication of the first edition of <title level="m">Kontrapunkt 2</title>, and with it also the stocks of <title level="m">Harmonielehre</title> and <title>Kontrapunkt 1</title>. A second edition of <title level="m">Harmonielehre</title> was published on February 21, 1921, in a print-run
              of 531 copies. A new edition was released in August 1978, and subsequent releases in
              1992 and 2003. </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head>English Translation</head>
            <p>After several attempts, dating back to c. 1930, to promote an English translation,
              that by Elisabeth Mann Borgese, from an edited and annotated text by <ref cRef="entity-000412">Oswald Jonas</ref>, was issued in 1954 by the University of
              Chicago Press, Chicago. </p>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Bibliography:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Wason, Robert W.</author>, <title level="a">From 'Harmonielehre' to
              'Harmony': Schenker's Theory of Harmony and Its Americanization,</title> in <title level="m">Essays from the Fourth International Schenker Symposium</title>, vol. I, ed.
              <editor>Allen Cadwallader</editor> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms Verlag, 2008), pp. 213–58 </bibl>
          <bibl><author>Drabkin, William</author>, <title level="a">Schenker's 'Decline': an
              Introduction,</title>
            <title level="j">Music Analysis</title> XXIV/1–2 (March–July 2005), 3–31 [German text,
            pp. 131–232; Eng. transl., pp. 33–129] </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Ian Bent</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
