<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-001720">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Phil. Em. Bach: Klavierwerke</title>
        <title type="sub">C. P. E. Bach: Keyboard Works</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="bach_cpe_klavierwerke">Bach, C. P. E.: Klavierwerke</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>31/10/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Work</term>
          <term subtype="basename">bach_cpe_klavierwerke</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Phil. Em. Bach: Klavierwerke</head>
      <div>
        <p>Edition by Schenker of fourteen selected keyboard works of <ref cRef="entity-000025">Carl
            Philipp Emmanuel Bach</ref>, published by Universal Edition (UE 548) in 1903. It is the
          first in the series of critical editions by Schenker that constitute a major part of the
          his output.</p>

        <p>The original title-page (OC Scores/1) reads: <cit>
            <q>[<hi rend="italic">in highly decorative engraved frame:</hi>] KLAVIERWERKE | VON |
              PHILIPP EMANUEL BACH. | — | NEUE | KRITISCHE AUSGABE | VON | HEINRICH SCHENKER. |
              „UNIVERSAL-EDITION“ | ACTIENGESELLSCHAFT | IN WIEN.</q>
          </cit></p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Publication History</head>
        <p>The edition was first published by Universal Edition as a single volume on February 10,
          1903, although in the literature it is conventionally dated "1902" ‒ presumably because
          the Preface is dated "November, 1902". It was initially published separately in three
          different languages: 500 copies in German, 250 in French, 250 in English. Only later were
          the three consolidated into a single tri-lingual edition. It was subsequently published as
          two half-volumes. A companion volume was published also in 1903 (conventionally dated
          1904), <title level="m"><rs key="entity-001721" type="work">Ein Beitrag zur
              Ornamentik</rs>: Als Einführung zu Ph. Em. Bachs Klavierwerken mitumfassend auch die
            Ornamentik Haydns Mozarts u. Beethovens etc</title> ("A Contribution to the Study of
          Ornamentation: As an Introduction to the Keyboard Works of C. P. E. Bach, encompassing
          also the Ornamentation of Haydn, Mozart, Beethoven, etc."), of which a second edition was
          published in 1908.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Nature of the Edition</head>
        <p>In the introduction to her translation of the <title level="m">Beitrag</title>, Hedi
          Siegel characterizes the edition thus: "It represents Schenker's first 'Urtext' edition;
          its text is the result of intensive study and insightful interpretation of the sources. It
          carefully preserves Bach's dynamic markings; the few suggested additional markings are
          always placed in parentheses. These editorial additions, as well as the presence of
          fingerings (with footnotes to indicate the original fingerings) point to the fact that
          Schenker intended this collection as a <hi rend="italic">performing</hi> edition. The
          explanatory footnotes are directed toward the performer; they deal with such items as
          disputed readings, dynamic markings, and rhythm, but by far the greatest number are
          concerned with the realization of embellishments." (<bibl><title level="j">The Music
              Forum</title>, iv (1976), 1‒2</bibl>)</p>

        <p>The edition comprises whole sonatas and separate movements, selected from C. P. E. Bach's
          collections of sonatas "für Kenner und Liebhaber" (for connoisseurs and amateurs). By
          selecting only these sonatas, which date from the last decade of Bach's life (1779‒87),
          and excluding sonatas from earlier collection, e.g. the "Prussian" Sonatas of c.1742, and
          the "Württemberg" Sonatas of 1744, Schenker presented only a small, unrepresentative
          portion of the composer's keyboard output.</p>
      </div>
    </body>


    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Ian Bent</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
