<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-001749">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</title> [Jahrbuch] (1925‒30) </title>
        <title type="sub">
          <title level="j">The Masterwork in Music</title> [Yearbook] (1925‒30) </title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="meisterwerk"><title level="j">Meisterwerk in der Musik</title>, <title
              level="j">Das</title></term>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Work</term>
          <term subtype="basename">meisterwerk</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>
        <title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</title> [Jahrbuch] (1925‒30) </head>
      <div>
        <p>Single-author, three-volume yearbook by Heinrich Schenker. — <title level="j">Das
            Meisterwerk in der Musik</title> was published by <ref cRef="entity-002627">Drei Masken
            Verlag</ref> of Munich between 1926 and 1931, the publication dates on its title pages
          being 1925, 1926, 1930.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>The Constituent Parts</head>
        <p><title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</title> was published in three yearbooks:<listBibl>
            <bibl><ref cRef="entity-001750"><title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</title>,
                vol. I (1925)</ref></bibl>

            <bibl><ref cRef="entity-001751"><title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</title>,
                vol. II (1926)</ref></bibl>

            <bibl><title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</title>, vol. III (1930)</bibl>
          </listBibl></p>

      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Genesis and Publication History</head>
        <p><title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</title> arose out of the controversy
          between Schenker and <ref cRef="entity-002408">Universal Edition</ref>, whose Director was
            <ref cRef="entity-000356">Emil Hertzka</ref>, which had begun in 1922 over alleged
          suppression of content from issue 2 of <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title> and came to a
          head in late 1924, extending throughout 1925. Already by late October 1924 Schenker was
          considering either Piper's Verlag or <ref cRef="entity-002627">Drei Masken Verlag</ref> of
          Munich as the new home for <title level="j">Tonwille</title> (letter to <ref
            cRef="entity-000913">Moriz Violin</ref>: OJ 6/7, [10]), and was in direct contact with
            <ref cRef="entity-000195">Alfred Einstein</ref> at Drei Masken Verlag by November 27 (OC
          54/2). </p>

        <p>Schenker had sought, if possible, a direct continuation of <title level="j">Der
            Tonwille</title> in that format and bearing the same title. After consideration, Drei
          Masken Verlag decided that a new title was essential (OC 54/5-7), and in the format of a
          yearbook, each volume "being of the same extent as what amounted previously to four
          quarterly issues, i.e. 15 gatherings" of <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>, the
          proposed title being <title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik – Ein Jahrbuch von H.
            Schenker</title> (OC 54/12, Jan 20, 1925). Their argument was that each volume would
          allow Schenker to prepare "material of greater scope," making each volume "larger and
          deeper." Drei Masken Verlag also sought a reduction in political content (OC 54/15, Jan
          24, 1925), which was largely honored by Schenker.</p>

        <p>The terms of the contract between Schenker and the publisher were discussed during
          February 1925 (OJ 54/20-22 and 25); the actual contract is not preserved with the
          correspondence. Schenker submitted the material for volume I on June 3, 1925 and proofs
          began to circulate in late November (OJ 54/142).</p>

        <p>Over the course of the seven years of contact with Drei Masken Verlag (1924‒31) there
          were periods of discord. Already by December 9, 1925 the publisher complained at the
          number of changes on the galley-proofs and warned Schenker that he would be charged a
          proportion of the correction costs (OC 54/48). On June 21, 1926, in the month in which
          volume I was published and Schenker dispatched all the materials for volume II, the
          publisher shocked Schenker by declaring itself unable to commit to undertaking the latter
          before it had gauged the commercial success of volume I (OC 54/88 and 95, Schenker's
          response OC 54/96-99). By early December legal proceedings were threatened (OC 54/109),
          and conflict was avoided only by the intervention of <ref cRef="entity-000164">Otto Erich
            Deutsch</ref> and undertakings by "a circle of pupils," Drei Masken Verlag finally
          agreeing to proceed with volume II (OC 54/119), <ref cRef="entity-003129">Mandruck</ref>
          of Vienna being entrusted with the printing. To speed up the production, improve the
          layout of the ever more complex musical artwork, and keep the correction costs to a
          minimum, <ref cRef="entity-000922">Otto Vrieslander</ref> prepared neat copies of many of
          the Urlinie graphs (OC 54/124, 129, 131–134, 140); he was not paid directly for this work
          by Schenker, but probably undertook it to honor an ongoing obligation to <ref
            cRef="entity-000380">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>, Schenker's wealthy pupil and benefactor
          and Vrieslander’s erstwhile employer.</p>

        <p>Having resumed work on a new monograph – on the "Eroica" Symphony – and mindful of the
          fact that <title level="m">Der freie Satz</title> had largely been abandoned since the
          beginning of the decade, Schenker had little time to pursue shorter analytical pieces
          except as part of the work he undertook for his pupils. As the "Eroica" monograph neared
          completion, a prestigious German publisher was sought with assistance from <ref
            cRef="entity-000268">Wilhelm Furtwängler</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-000866">Karl
            Straube</ref> (see diary entries between April 18 and May 20, 1930). This having been
          turned down by both <ref cRef="entity-002422">Peters</ref> and Breitkopf &amp; Härtel in
          Leipzig, after a two-year silence in the correspondence Schenker reverted to Drei Masken
          Verlag – thanks in part to the good relationship between Einstein and Deutsch – and the
          analysis of the symphony, together with its polemical introductory article, extensive
          text-critical notes, and the usual <title level="a">Miscellanea,</title> became <title
            level="j">Meisterwerk</title> volume III. To save music typography costs, Schenker
          engaged the services of <ref cRef="entity-000894">Georg Tomay</ref>, a Viennese engraver
          whose work he was able to supervise personally (correspondence: OC 54/195‒220; diary
          entries on this begin on May 24, 1930). The volume was published in mid-December 1930 (OC
          54/256).</p>
      </div>


      <div>
        <head>Types of Content</head>
        <p><title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</title>, like <title level="j">Der
            Tonwille</title>, carries three types of article: the analytical study of a single work
          or movement (which includes source studies and textual criticism, as well as performance
          and secondary literature, in a format that Schenker devised first for his monograph <ref
            cRef="entity-001731"><title level="m">Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie</title>)</ref>; the
          essay on a topic in theory or textual criticism; and the free assemblage of polemics,
          selected verbal quotations, and aphorisms under the title <title level="a"
            >Vermischtes</title> [Miscellanea]. There is, however, a progression across the three
          volumes: the number of analyses reduces from ten to four to one, the analyses themselves
          becoming longer; theory remains the same at four articles for volumes I and II, then
          disappears altogether from volume III; <title level="a">Vermischtes</title> remains
          constant, but volume III contains the additional sharply polemical article <title
            level="a">Rameau or Beethoven?</title>.</p>

        <p>Most prominent of all are two large-scale analyses of four-movement orchestral works:
          Mozart's G-minor Symphony (vol. II: 50 pages + 13 fold-out graphs) and Beethoven's
          "Eroica" Symphony (vol. III: 72 pages + 35 Urlinie pages + nine fold-out graphic figures).
          These analyses take their place within the sequence of four symphonic analyses and four
          sonata analyses that span Schenker's middle career: Beethoven's Ninth (1912) ‒ Beethoven's
          Sonatas Opp. 109 (1913), 110 (1914), 111 (1915), 101 (1920) ‒ Beethoven's Fifth (1921‒23;
          1927) ‒ Mozart's G minor (1926) ‒ Beethoven's Third (1930). And whereas the Fifth Symphony
          analysis had to be split across three issues of <title level="j">Tonwille</title>, the
          greater length of the <title level="j">Meisterwerk</title> yearbooks, precisely as Drei
          Masken Verlag had foreseen, permitted the last two analyses to be accommodated each within
          a single volume.</p>

        <p>Specific continuity between <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title> and <title level="j"
            >Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</title> is established by three elements: (1) the series
          of analyses of "short preludes" by J. S. Bach, five of which appeared in <title level="j"
            >Tonwille</title> 4‒5 and three in <title level="j">Meisterwerk</title> I (more
          generally: the continued presentation of short analyses of single keyboard pieces); (2)
          the republication of the ground-breaking theoretical article <title level="a"
            >Erläuterungen</title> [Elucidations] from <title level="j">Tonwille</title> 8/9 in
            <title level="j">Meisterwerk</title> I and II; and (3) the continued presence of the
            <title level="a">Vermischtes.</title></p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Design and Layout</head>
        <p>Drei Masken Verlag had previously produced two music journals: four volumes of the <title
            level="j">Sammelbände für vergleichende Musikwissenschaft</title> (1922‒23), edited by
          Carl Stumpf and E. M. von Hornbostel, and the <title level="j">Mozart-Jahrbuch</title>
          (1923‒29), edited by Hermann Abert. It was agreed in February 1925 that the <title
            level="j">Mozart-Jahrbuch</title> should serve as the design model for <title level="j"
            >Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</title> (OJ 54/23 and 25), the main divergence being the
          choice of typeface, for which Schenker requested Fraktur (i.e. German Gothic) rather than
          Antiqua (thus retaining the type style of <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>), to which
          request Drei Masken Verlag acquiesced.</p>

      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Bibliography</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>English translation: <editor>Drabkin, William</editor>, ed., <title level="j">The
              Masterwork in Music: A Yearbook</title> [team-translated] (Cambridge: Cambridge
            University Press, 1994–97)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Ian Bent</author> and <author>William Drabkin</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
