<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-001740">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>, Heft 1 (1921)</title>
        <title type="sub"><title level="j">The Will of the Tone</title>, issue 1 (1921)</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="tonwille1"><title level="j">Tonwille</title> 1</term>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Work</term>
          <term subtype="basename">tonwille1</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head><title level="j">
          <hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</hi>
        </title>, Heft 1 (1921)</head>
      <div>
        <p>The first issue of Schenker's periodical <ref cRef="entity-001739">
            <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>
          </ref> (1921–24).</p>
        <div>
          <head>Contents</head>
          <p>Issue 1, 56 pages in length, comprises a lead-article highly polemical in content (19
            pages), one short article on the theoretical topic of the Urlinie (5 pages), three
            articles each on a single work (11, 8 and 4 pages), of which the first is the first of a
            three-instalment study of Beethoven's Fifth Symphony, and "Miscellanea" (6 pages of
            regular type). </p>

          <p>"The Mission of German Genius" serves as a manifesto for the whole of <title level="j"
              >Der Tonwille</title>. It deals with impossibility of splitting culture from politics,
            i.e. Germany will inevitably rise through the greatness of German music. The origins of
            the article appear to lie in a plan, conceived early in 1913, to publish a "Vorrede"
            (Preface) to <ref cRef="entity-001733">
              <title level="m">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven</title>
            </ref>. On February 4, 1913, Schenker wrote to <ref cRef="entity-000356">Hertzka</ref>:
            "I plan to precede the work in its entirety with a Preface ('To the Younger
            Generation'!), which I am not yet enclosing. The 'Preface' should be printed only once
            […], before the text of <title level="m">Op. 109</title>" (WSLB 146). But by March 18 he
            had reconceptualized the item: "The more intensively I polish the 'Preface,' the more
            compelling does my conviction become that […] the 'Preface' must be given a more precise
            and more comprehensive application right from the start. If we want to publish the
              <title level="j">Pamphlets</title> under whatever title […]" (WSLB 149), the
            implication being that the 'Preface' might serve instead as the opening salvo to the
              <ref cRef="entity-001758">
              <title level="j">Little Library</title>
            </ref> – the planned series which later became <title level="j">Der
            Tonwille</title>.</p>

          <p>Some idea of what Schenker had in mind at that time may be revealed in an article
            entitled <title level="a">Das deutsche Genie in Kampf und Sieg,</title> which Schenker
            wrote in August 1914 and submitted to the <ref cRef="frankfurter_zeitung">
              <title level="j">Frankfurter Zeitung</title>
            </ref>, but which was rejected and has remained in manuscript (OJ 21/2). This article
            asserted that the French, Russians, and English lacked any capacity for genius; "only
            the German bears the distinguishing mark of genius." <title level="a">Die
              Sendung</title> in its final form still maintained this but, fueled by Schenker's
            anger at the German defeat in 1918 and the demeaning terms of the Versailles Treaty, it
            now turned also on Germany's enemies "from within" – communists, revolutionaries,
            pacifists, journalists, cosmopolitans, etc.</p>
          <p>The "Urlinie" article, which follows directly upon the first disclosure of the concept
            in <ref cRef="entity-001737">
              <title level="m">Die letzten fünf Sonaten … op. 101</title>
            </ref>, forms a bridge between <title level="a">Die Sendung</title> and the Beethoven
            Fifth Symphony analysis: that is, genius, as proclaimed in <title level="a"
              >Sendung,</title> manifests itself specially in music as Urlinie and synthesis, and
            the technical workings of these are demonstrated in the Fifth Symphony. The analysis of
            Schubert's song <title level="a">Ihr Bild</title> is a modern version of an essay
            written c. 1907 which remained in typescript. The article has fascinated generations of
            Schenker scholars. The <title level="a">Miscellanea</title> mirror closely the preceding
            material, arguing the malign effect of French culture on German culture through a
            Beethoven edition and Mozart's letters, and the French occupation of Austria.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Publication History</head>
          <p>Schenker handed in <title level="a">Die Sendung</title> (still called "Preface") to UE
            on November 10, 1920, and in mid-December was correcting galley-proofs of it. First
            signs of trouble came on December 30 in a letter from <ref cRef="entity-000356"
              >Hertzka</ref> asking for a meeting and continuing: "I have only just now read the
            proof of your article 'The Mission of German Genius' and urgently need to speak with you
            in this regard" (OC 52/561). When the meeting took place on January 5, 1921, Hertzka
            remarked: "the 'Preface' is 'holy,' 'magnificent,' but, registered in New York, he would
            not dare to present it to foreign readers" (diary, p. 2309). The plan to create a
            "fictitious publishing house" to distance UE from Schenker's opinions was hatched at
            that meeting.</p>
          <p>Schenker began studying the source materials for <title level="a">Beethoven's Fifth
              Symphony</title> in the Archive of the <ref cRef="entity-002430">Gesellschaft der
              Musikfreunde</ref> in February 1920; by mid-November he was drafting and dictating the
            article (having two conversations about the symphony with <ref cRef="entity-000268"
              >Furtwängler</ref>), and was correcting galley-proofs in January–February 1921.</p>
          <p>He began dictating <title level="a">Die Urlinie: Eine Vorbemerkung</title> in February
            1920; in March he was working on the study of the Bach Prelude, of which he received
            proofs of the engraved Urlinie graph and letterpress in the September. The Urlinie for
            the Schubert study seems to have been delivered in September 1920, the remainder of the
            article in November, and by later that month he had returned the proofs. </p>
          <p>Page-proofs were sent out in late April 1921 (OC 52/255), and Schenker must have given
            his imprimatur in early or mid-May. On May 25, <ref cRef="entity-000420">Alfred
              Kalmus</ref> asked for a few lines to be cut so as to contain the issue within
            four-and-a-half (16-page) gatherings (OC 52/260), after which it went to press, being
            released on June 13 (diary, p. 2354).</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Contents List</head>
          <listBibl>
            <bibl><title level="a">Von der Sendung des deutschen Genies</title> [The Mission of
              German Genius], 3–21 [I, pp. 3–20]</bibl>
            <bibl><title level="a">Die Urlinie: Eine Vorbemerkung</title> [The Urlinie: A
              Preliminary Remark], 22–26 [I, pp. 21–24]</bibl>
            <bibl><title level="a">Beethoven: V. Sinfonie</title> [Beethoven's Fifth Symphony],
              27–37 [I, pp. 25–33]</bibl>
            <bibl><title level="a">Joh. Seb. Bach: Wohltemperiertes Klavier, Band I, Präludium
                Es-Moll</title> [The E-flat Minor Prelude from Bach's <title level="m">Well-Tempered
                Clavier</title>, Book I], 38–45 [I, pp. 34–40]</bibl>
            <bibl><title level="a">Franz Schubert: 'Ihr Bild' (Heine)</title> [Schubert's "Ihr Bild"
              (Heine)], 46–49 [I, pp. 41–43]</bibl>
            <bibl><title level="a">Vermischtes</title> [Miscellanea], 50–55 [I, pp. 44–48]</bibl>
            <lb/>
            <bibl>Enclosure: Urlinie for Beethoven symphony</bibl>
            <bibl>Advertisement (at back): <title level="a">Heinr. Schenkers Werke</title> (p.
              56)</bibl>
          </listBibl>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Ian Bent</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
