<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-001751">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</title>, Band II (1926)</title>
        <title type="sub"><title level="j">The Masterwork in Music</title>, volume II (1926)</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="meisterwerk_II"><title level="j">Meisterwerk</title> II</term>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Work</term>
          <term subtype="basename">meisterwerk_II</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head><title level="j">
          <hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</hi>
        </title>, Band II (1926)</head>
      <div>
        <p>The second volume of Schenker's yearbook <ref cRef="entity-001749">
            <title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</title>
          </ref> (1925–30), the full title of which is: <listBibl>
            <bibl><title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik: ein Jahrbuch von Heinrich
                Schenker</title></bibl>
            <bibl><title level="j">The Masterwork in Music: a Yearbook by Heinrich
              Schenker</title></bibl>
          </listBibl>
        </p>
        <div>


          <head>Contents</head>
          <p>Volume II is like its predecessor in having 220 printed pages (16 gatherings: 224pp)
            but differs from it in comprising only nine articles, of which four are theoretical
            studies and four analytical, plus a new "Miscellanea."</p>

          <p>The contents of this second volume forge links back to the first (and further back to
              <ref cRef="entity-001739"><title level="j">Der Tonwille</title></ref>) and also
            forward to the third. Besides the continuity established by the reprinting of <title
              level="a">Elucidations</title> and the extension of the <title level="a"
              >Miscellanea</title> series (which concludes in vol. III, thus spanning 1921 to 1930),
            the analysis of the Bach cello movement rounds off a self-contained group of three
            studies of Bach solo string works; and <title level="a">Further Considerations of the
              Urlinie</title> forms a sequel to that in volume I. Most importantly, the 50-page
            study of Mozart's G-minor Symphony links back to the 71-page study of Beethoven's Fifth
            Symphony serialized in <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title> and forward to the latter's
            reissue as a <ref cRef="entity-001760">monograph</ref> in 1927 and to the 72-page study
            of Beethoven's Third Symphony in <ref cRef="entity-001752"><title level="j">Meisterwerk
                III</title></ref>.</p>

          <p>The analysis of Reger's <title>Variations and Fugue, Op. 81</title> turns Schenker's
            analytical motivation on its head: rather than demonstrating compositional mastery and
            the secret workings of genius it exposes poor technique and formal confusion. In its
            polemical purpose it allies itself with the <title level="a">Miscellanea,</title> and
            also with the final part of <title level="a">Further Considerations,</title> which
            presents a diatribe against <ref cRef="entity-000798">Schoenberg</ref> and an analytical
            critique of Stravinsky's <title>Piano Concerto</title> as "bad, inartistic and
            unmusical." The second and third articles form a pair: <title level="a">On Organicism in
              Sonata Form</title> and <title level="a">The Organic Nature of Fugue.</title> Both
            demolish a conventional view ‒ the 19th-century reading of sonata form as organic, and
            the 18th/19th-century view of fugue as a succession of phases and technical devices ‒
            and replace them with a single concept of <hi rend="italic">coherence</hi> that stems
            from the prolongation of the primary tone (<hi rend="italic">Kopfton</hi>) and the
            inter-related unfoldings of linear progressions (<hi rend="italic">Züge</hi>); and each
            does this not by abstraction but by analysis, especially that of the C-minor Fugue from
            the <title level="m">Well-tempered Clavier</title> Book I in the latter article.</p>
        </div>
        <div>


          <head>Production Chronology</head>
          <p>Several of the articles in this volume have their beginnings in the latter part of 1924
            (even before the contents of volume I were started). Schenker worked on Haydn's <title
              level="m">Creation</title> in mid-August 1924, returning to it between July 31 and
            August 15, 1925, and finishing the work in May 1926. Likewise, he had got far enough
            with Schubert waltzes ‒ analyzed in <title level="a">Further Considerations of the
              Urlinie</title> ‒ in October 1924 to write out a fair copy, then after a 17-month
            break consolidated the first part of the article in late March 1926, worked up each
            section separately in April, and completed it on May 23.</p>

          <p>Analytical work on Beethoven's <title>Piano Sonata, Op. 10, No. 2</title> ‒ destined
            for <title level="a">On Organicism in Sonata Form</title> ‒ was underway in mid-December
            1924, then after a year's hiatus the article (provisionally titled <title level="a">The
              Sonata and the Act of Improvisation</title>) was restarted on January 15‒17, 1926 and
            concluded between May 3 and 25. Analytical work on the C-minor Fugue for <title
              level="a">The Organic Nature of Fugue</title> began in late December 1924, resumed in
            late August 1925 and was picked up again in October, the secondary literature study
            conducted in November 1925 and January 1926, and the work completed in late May. The
            Reger counter-analysis was written concentratedly between March 19 and April 26, 1925,
            then lay fallow for a year until finishing touches were put in May 1926.</p>

          <p>The remaining three articles, on the other hand, were all confined to 1926. The study
            of the Bach cello movement and <title level="a">Miscellanea</title> were written in
            March, April, and May. Schenker worked on the Urlinie of the Sarabande from the Bach
            C-major Cello Suite on March 5, 1926 knowing that he and <ref cRef="entity-000951">Hans
              Weisse</ref> would be hearing Pablo Casals perform
            that suite at the Konzerthaus on March 12 ("I was afraid that Casals could [...]
            misinterpret Bach; I was all the more agreeably surprised to see that he had arrived at
            a synthesis by his own routes!"), and had produced a full draft by the 24th. The Mozart
            Symphony study occupied five-and-a-half months of intensive work, from January 2 to June
            10, 1926, the first movement finished on March 28, the Andante on June 3, the Minuet on
            June 7, and the Finale on June 9.</p>

          <p>The complete contents were packed up for delivery to <ref cRef="entity-002627">Drei
              Masken Verlag</ref> on June 11, 1926 ‒ the day that Schenker received his first
            published copy of <ref cRef="entity-001750"><title level="j">Meisterwerk
            I</title></ref>. In July the publisher put off the decision to go into production until
            the early Fall (OC 54/95), and again deferred the decision in December, at which point
            legal proceedings were mooted (OC 54/109). By mid-January 1927 Schenker spoke of seeking
            compensation for breach of contract (OC 54/116), and only the intervention of <ref
              cRef="entity-000164">Otto Erich Deutsch</ref> and an undertaking from "a circle of
            pupils ... to facilitate matters financially" made the publisher relent and agree to
            proceed to publication (OC 54/117). First galley-proofs started circulating about
            February 3, 1927 and correction of these was completed on April 19, though some
            correcting, perhaps of the engraving, was already occurring by around January 27 (OC
            54/126); second galleys circulated between May 2 and 24. First page-proofs were received
            between June 13 and July 18, Schenker correcting them while on vacation in <ref
              cRef="entity-002292">Galtür</ref>; final page-proofs arrived around August 20 and were
            mailed back on August 22 (OC 54/186) with Schenker's imprimatur. Bound complimentary
            copies were dispatched to Schenker on September 27, and the volume was released in the
            first or second week of October.</p>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>Bibliography</head>
          <listBibl>
            <bibl>English translation: <editor>Drabkin, William</editor>, ed., <title level="j">The
                Masterwork in Music: A Yearbook</title> [team-translated] (Cambridge: Cambridge
              University Press, 1994–97): vol. II (1996)</bibl>
          </listBibl>
        </div>


        <div>
          <head>Contents List</head>
          <listBibl>
            <bibl><title level="a">Fortsetzung der Urlinie-Betrachtungen</title> [Further
              Considerations of the Urlinie], 9‒42 [1‒22]</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Vom Organischen der Sonatenform</title> [On Organicism in Sonata
              Form], 43‒54 [23‒30]</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Das Organische der Fuge aufgezeigt an der I. C-Moll-Fuge aus dem
                Wohltemperierten Klavier von Joh. Seb. Bach</title> [The Organic Nature of Fugue as
              demonstrated in the C-minor Fugue from Bach's <title level="m">Well-Tempered
                Clavier</title>, Book I], 55‒95 [31‒54]</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Joh. Seb. Bach: Suite III C-Dur für Violoncello-Solo,
                Sarabande</title> [J. S. Bach: Suite III in C major for Solo Cello: Sarabande],
              97‒104 [55‒58]</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Mozart: Sinfonie G-Moll</title> [Mozart: Symphony in G minor],
              105‒57 [59‒96]</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Haydn: Die Schöpfung: Die Vorstellung des Chaos</title> [The
              Representation of Chaos from Haydn's <title level="m">Creation</title>], 159‒69
              [97‒105]</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Ein Gegenbeispiel: Max Reger, op. 81: Variationen und Fuge über
                ein Thema von Joh. Seb. Bach für Klavier</title> [A Counter-example: Max Reger's
              Variations and Fugue on a Theme by J. S. Bach, Op. 81, for piano], 171‒92
              [106‒17]</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Erläuterungen</title> [Elucidations], 193‒97 [118‒20]</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Vermischtes: Gedanken über die Kunst und ihre Zusammenhänge im
                Allgemeinen</title> [Miscellanea: Thoughts on Art and its Relationships to the
              General Scheme of Things], 199‒216 [121‒31]</bibl>

            <bibl>Advertisement for <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>, issues 1‒10</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Urlinientafeln und Figuren im Anhang</title> [Voice-leading
              Graphs and Music Examples in the Appendix]</bibl>


          </listBibl>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Ian Bent</author> and <author>William Drabkin</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
