<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-001731">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie</title>
        <title type="sub">Beethoven's Ninth Symphony</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="beethovens_neunte_si">Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>28/07/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Work</term>
          <term subtype="basename">beethovens_neunte_si</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie</head>

      <div>
        <p>Monograph by Schenker written in
          1910–12, and published by Universal Edition in 1912.</p>
        <p>The initial stimulus for the work was an invitation from the Vereinigung Wiener
          Musikreferenten (Union of Vienna Music Critics) to give a lecture on the topic of the
          Ninth symphony (OJ 14/44, September 30, 1910). This came to nothing, but Emil Hertzka of
          Universal Edition took up the idea of making this into a monograph. The contract for this
          monograph is dated November 6, 1910 (OC 52/431), the title ultimately being:</p>
        
        <p>
          <hi rend="italic">Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie: Eine Darstellung des musikalischen Inhaltes
            unter fortlaufender Berücksichtigung auch des Vortrages und der Literatur</hi>
        </p>
        <p>[Beethoven's Ninth Symphony: a portrayal of its musical content, with running commentary
        on performance and literature as well]</p>
        </div>
        
        <div>
          <head>Publication History</head>
        <p>The work was submitted to the publisher on May 18, 1911 (OJ 1/10, p. 126) , proof-reading
          began in late November 1911, the corrected work was sent to the printers, Breitkopf
          &amp; Härtel, Leipzig, for production on June 11, 1912 and was released on
          July 2, 1912 in a print-run of 1,000 copies, and a further 200 copies were printed and
          released on January 20, 1913. (Verlagsdruckbuch UE 3499) The publisher produced a second
          edition in 1969 (UE 26307). Between 1911 and 1914, Schenker and Universal Edition had
          plans to produce a full score of the symphony, initially to be incorporated into this
          volume, later to serve as a companion volume. For this, click on <ref cRef="entity-001732">Ninth Symphony Score</ref>.</p>
        
        <p>Schenker came to view this monograph as the second of a series of analytical works that
          he produced between 1910 and 1920, even extending it back to 1903, and distinguished by
          his own style of "elucidations" (<hi rend="italic">Erläuterungen</hi>) remarking:
        
          <cit><q>If only you think that UE is showing the principal fortresses of music, the
          <title level="m">Ninth Symphony</title>, the <title level="m">Chromatic Fantasy</title>, the last five sonatas (even
          C. P. E. Bach), in that bright new light that humanity will soon come to crave, then UE
          will henceforth secure superiority over all the publishing houses of Germany. (WSLB 120,
          June 9, 1912)</q></cit></p>
      </div>
    </body>  
    
      <back>
        <div>
          <head>Bibliography:</head>

        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Beethoven's Ninth Symphony: a Portrayal of its Musical Content, with
            Running Commentary on Performance and Literature as well</title>, transl. and ed. <editor>John
            Rothgeb</editor> (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1992)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        </div>
       <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Ian Bent</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
        </div>
      </back>


  </text>
</TEI>
