<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-001732">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Beethoven, Ninth Symphony Score</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="ninth_symphony_score">Ninth Symphony Score</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>10/12/2007</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Work</term>
          <term subtype="basename">ninth_symphony_score</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Beethoven, Ninth Symphony Score</head>
      <div>
        <p>Score, to be edited by Schenker according to the composer's autograph manuscript, and
          intended to accompany Schenker's monograph <ref cRef="entity-001731">
            <title>Beethoven's Neunte Sinfonie</title></ref>, the plan for which was eventually
          abandoned. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>History of the Proposal</head>
        <p>Sometime early in 1911, <ref cRef="entity-000356">Emil Hertzka</ref> evidently suggested
          that Schenker's monograph <title level="m">Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie</title> (Vienna: UE,
          1912) might incorporate a score of the symphony, thereby giving the resultant work the
          status of an "elucidatory edition" (<hi rend="italic">Erläuterungsausgabe</hi>) along
          the lines of Schenker's <title level="m">Chromatic Fantasy &amp; Fugue</title> (1910) and
          the later <title level="m">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven</title> (1913,
          1914, 1915, 1920). First mention of this in the UE correspondence appeared on June 21,
          1911 in an allusion to "the conducting score planned by you [i.e. Hertzka]" (WSLB 77). On
          March 7, 1912, Hertzka announced that he had negotiated with Eulenburg to use the plates
          of their pocket score (OC 52/432).</p>
        <p>The original plan was apparently to bind the score in with the monograph study, but on
          March 13, 1912, Schenker proposed an alternative marketing scheme:
          
          <cit><q>Perhaps it would be a good idea to separate the book from the score for
          ease of study; and let the price indicate only that the two can be had more cheaply if the
          items are purchased together than if they are purchased individually. </q></cit>(WSLB 100)</p>

        <p>Hertzka indicated willingness to adopt this plan on May 7, 1912 (OC 52/433). Schenker's
          monograph, without score, was subsequently released on or around July 2, 1912.</p>
        <p>Then, on November 12, 1913, Schenker, after advocating having the Berlin autograph
          manuscript of the Ninth Symphony photographed, introduced an additional element into the
          proposal:
          
          <cit><q>You had in any case the idea of publishing the score of the Ninth
          Symphony on the occasion of my book. How would it be, then, if the authentic score (edited
          by me) were to be provided? (WSLB 192)</q></cit></p>

        <p>Hertzka inferred from this that the Eulenburg plates would not then simply be reprinted,
          but would have to be modified according to Schenker's reading of the autograph, and that
          this would be "technically much more complicated" and might entail completely re-engraving
          the score (OC 52/440, December 12, 1913; OC 52/138, January 5, 1914). On January 7, 1914,
          Schenker went further, proposing that the contents of the four formal diagrams in his
          monograph (pp. 2, 136, 194, 244) be incorporated into the score in square brackets (WSLB
          199, though there is a hint of such a plan in an interlinear insertion as early as May 11,
          1912: WSLB 112). The plan seems never to have got further than this stage.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Ian Bent</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
