<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-002882">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Neue Urlinie-Ausgabe</title>
        <title type="sub">Urlinie Edition</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="urlinie_ausgabe">Urlinie-Ausgabe</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>31/10/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Work</term>
          <term subtype="basename">urlinie_ausgabe</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="entity-002882"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head><rs key="entity-002882" type="person">Urlinie-Ausgabe</rs></head>
      <div>
        <p>An edition of the Beethoven piano sonatas with Urlinie graphs, planned by Schenker and
          Hertzka in 1922 but never carried out. </p>
        <p>An "Urlinie-Ausgabe" of the Beethoven piano sonatas is not mentioned in Schenker's
          analytical essay on the first sonata, Op. 2, No. 1, in F minor, published in <title
            level="j">Tonwille</title> 2. The expression suggests the provision of analytical
          commentary, but all that Schenker promised here was "to give a textual report of my
          edition of the remaining sonatas, where possible" (p. 36; Eng. transl., vol. 1, p. 83). He
          goes on, however, to clarify his view of what editing a sonata entails: <cit>
            <q>This immediately brings up the last and most difficult questions of the given
              content, as well as of musical culture in general. As little as one may say of
              Beethoven himself that he was merely practicing musical philology when he sought the
              best notation, improved slurs, etc., just as little may the work of an editor in this
              matter be regarded as philology. It is rather of a purely artistic nature, and demands
              the full interest of all those who want to make the content of the work of art truly
              their own. (<bibl><title level="j">Tonwille</title> 2, 36–37; Eng. transl., vol. 1,
                p.83.</bibl>)</q>
          </cit> That is, for Schenker the distinction between understanding the content of a work
          (analysis) and making informed editorial decisions when confronted with textually
          discrepant sources for it (editorial technique simply did not exist). </p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Drabkin, William</author></bibl>

        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
