<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-001760">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Beethovens Fünfte Sinfonie (1925)</title>
        <title type="sub">Beethoven's Fifth Symphony (1925)</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="beethovens_funfte_si">Beethovens Fünfte Sinfonie</term>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt><sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc></fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Work</term>
          <term subtype="basename">beethovens_funfte_si</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Beethovens Fünfte Sinfonie (1925)</head>
      <div>
        <p>Monograph publication of Schenker's study of Beethoven's Fifth Symphony – the first of
          three large-scale symphonic studies written in the wake of his "discovery" of the Urlinie
          around 1920, the other two studies being those of Mozart's Symphony No. 40 in G minor
            (<title level="j">Meisterwerk II</title>, 1926), and Beethoven's "Eroica" Symphony
            (<title level="j">Meisterwerk III</title>, 1930).</p>
        <p>In the longer term, it was also the second of three studies of what Schenker seems to
          have regarded as Beethoven's most important orchestral works. In 1929, he wrote to his
          friend Moriz Violin: "I have completed a monograph on the "Eroica," adding as a marginal
          note: "to round things off: Ninth, Fifth, and Third symphonies!" (OJ 6/7, [41], Feb 27,
          1929). </p>
        <p>Schenker wrote his study of Beethoven's Fifth Symphony between 1920 and late 1923, and
          this was published first in three installments in <title level="j">Tonwille</title>
          <ref cRef="entity-001740">issue 1</ref> (1921), <ref cRef="entity-001744">issue 5</ref> (1923;
          actually Feb 1924), and <ref cRef="entity-001745">issue 6</ref> (1923; actually April 1924)
          over the fictitious imprint "Tonwille-Flugblätterverlag," and later together as a
          monograph over Universal Edition's own imprint [UE 7646]. </p>
      </div>
      
      <div>
        <head>Publication History</head>
        <p>The first approach by UE to discuss the possibility of monograph publication came on May
          5, 1924 (diary, OJ 3/6, p. 2662), and the monograph was publicized as early as August of
          that year (<title level="j">Tonwille</title>
          <ref cRef="entity-001746">issue 7 [=IV/1]</ref>). Schenker gave his imprimatur to the proofs
          on June 2, 1925 (WSLB 366), submitted a new abbreviations list in the August (OC
          52/791-792), and returned the proof of this on September 12 (OC 52/794; WSLB 367); the
          work went to press in mid-September and was released on October 12 (OC 52/525) at a price
          of 3 Marks (OC 5/526). </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Differences between serial and monograph publications</head>
        <p>The text and music examples of the three installments were left untouched in the
          monograph format; the only two new elements were the revised abbreviations list (to
          reflect the latest version of Schenker's bibliography) and pagination in a single
          sequence. The figures retained their original numbering, so ran in five separate
          sequences. It should be remembered that the entire publication process unfolded against
          the background of a catastrophic deterioration of relations between Schenker and UE. Had
          that not been so, Schenker might well have wanted to make structural alterations and some
          updating of content, but at this point he was anxious to see through publication of <title level="j">Tonwille</title> issue 10 and extricate himself from his obligations to
        UE.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Title-page</head>
        <p>For the separate installments, Schenker's title had been "Beethoven: V. Sinfonie," with
          "(Fortsetzung)" and "(Schluß)"; but for the monograph publication Schenker – or UE –
          appropriated the subtitle from the <ref cRef="entity-001731">Ninth Symphony</ref> monograph with the insertion "nach der
          Handschrift", thus linking the two publications retrospectively as if they formed part of
          a series:</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="italic">Beethovens Fünfte Sinfonie: eine Darstellung des musikalischen Inhaltes
            nach der Handschrift unter Berücksichtigung des Vortrages und der Literatur</hi>
        </p>
        <p>[Beethoven's Fifth Symphony: a portrayal of its musical content, based on the autograph
          manuscript, with commentary on performance and secondary literature]</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Ian Bent</author> and <author>William Drabkin</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
