<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-002882">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Urlinie-Ausgabe</title>
        <title type="sub">Urlinie Edition</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="urlinie_ausgabe">Urlinie-Ausgabe</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>31/10/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Work</term>
          <term subtype="basename">urlinie_ausgabe</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="entity-002882"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <body>
      <head>
        <rs key="entity-002882" type="person">Urlinie-Ausgabe</rs>
      </head>
      <div>
        <p>An edition of the Beethoven piano sonatas, each item accompanied by an Urlinie graph;
          scheme devised by Hertzka and Schenker in February 1922, but never carried out.</p>

      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Genesis of the idea</head>

        <p>Schenker submitted the Urlinie graphs of the Beethoven Sonata in F minor Op. 2, No. 1 and
          the Mozart Sonata in A minor K 310 to <ref cRef="entity-002408">Universal Edition</ref>
          for <ref cRef="entity-001741"><title level="j">Tonwille</title> 2</ref> in the Fall of
          1921 and January/February 1922 respectively. When engraved, each graph, encompassing the
          entire sonata, occupied only a single sheet 13" x 9½" (33 x 24.5 cms), double-sided,
          folded once. Once <ref cRef="entity-000356">Emil Hertzka</ref> saw proofs of these graphs,
          especially that of the Beethoven sonata covering four movements, he must have realized
          that an edition of a sonata complete with its Urlinie graph would give UE a "monopoly
          product." Thus the initiative for the Urlinie-Ausgabe came not from Schenker but from
          Hertkza. </p>

        <p>Previously, Hertzka had wanted Schenker to use his periodical <title level="j">Der
            Tonwille</title> in part as a parallel commentary to his complete edition of the <ref
            cRef="entity-001753">Beethoven piano sonatas</ref> currently in train (e.g. diary OC
          3/3, p. 2143); and indeed the article on Op. 2, No. 1 in <title level="j">Tonwille</title>
          2 did just that. However, on February 11, 1922, Hertzka wrote: <cit>
            <q>Do you think it feasible for us to squeeze into the new individual Beethoven
              editions, and possibly into each sonata within the bound volumes, a page containing
              the Urlinie of the work in question? Is that a task that could at all be accomplished
              within a relatively short space of time? Cannot your wife, or one of your advanced
              pupils produce a preliminary draft for you, to which you could just provide an expert
              appraisal and the finishing touches? (OC 52/451)</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>By this scheme, the editions of individual sonatas would include only their Urlinie
          graphs, whereas the four-volume edition would also supply an explanation of the graphs.
          The title "Schenkers Urlinie-Ausgabe" was coined. Schenker took the scheme seriously,
          writing a detailed response on February 23 (OC 1B/10-11). In this he volunteered to word
          an announcement and to float the term "Urlinie-Ausgabe" in the forthcoming <title
            level="j">Tonwille</title> issues, while at the same time inquiring about the logistics
          by which the seventeen sonatas already submitted, eleven of which were printed, without
          the new title or graphs would be handled, and disabusing Hertzka of the idea that his
          pupils were capable of providing first drafts of graphs. Hertzka replied that the Urlinien
          could be inserted into the existing stocks of the sonatas already printed (OC 52/452).
          Schenker's correspondence to UE at the time is not known to survive, but he evidently next
          asked about the economic workings of the plan, for on April 13 Hertzka went into some
          detail (OC 52/548); he also enclosed a draft supplementary agreement, to be appended to
          Schenker's contract for the Beethoven sonatas edition (April 10, 1920 ‒ OC 52/448), which
          states: <cit>
            <q>the so-called 'Urlinie Edition' of each sonata will appear alongside the revised
              edition now being published, In this way, each individual sonata will be supplemented
              by the Urlinie and the Preliminary Remark that will serve to elucidate the latter. (OC
              52/453)</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>Schenker's royalty was to be raised to reflect the increased work involved. The plan must
          have run into difficulties in May 1922, for <title level="j">Tonwille</title> 2, published
          on June 10, includes no announcement, nor does it usher in the term "Urlinie-Ausgabe." The
          most likely stumbling block was Hertzka's letter to Schenker on May 2 (OC
          52/564recto-565recto) refusing to publish Schenker's "Miscellanea" on grounds that <title
            level="j">Tonwille</title> 2 as a whole was overlength and that the article contained
          only political, not musical material. An inflammatory situation arose between the two men
          that must have put paid to the scheme. </p>

      </div>

      <div>
        <head>J. S. Bach, Kleine Präludien</head>

        <p>Later in 1922, Schenker reported to Moriz Violin: "I am proceeding with the Urlinie
          Edition of the Short Preludes by J. S. Bach (all eighteen pieces, quite exquisite)" (OJ
          6/7, [4], Dec 21, 1922), which suggests that he continued to take the concept of the
          Urlinie-Ausgabe seriously for some time.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>William Drabkin</author>, <author>Ian Bent</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
