<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-001729">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Instrumentations-Tabelle, [pseud.] Artur Niloff</title>
        <title type="sub">Instrumentation Table</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="instrumentations-tab">Instrumentations-Tabelle/Niloff</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>25/06/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Work</term>
          <term subtype="basename">instrumentations-tab</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Instrumentations-Tabelle, [pseud.] Artur Niloff </head>
      <div>
        <p>Wall chart of musical instruments, showing for each instrument its fundamental,
          overtones, range, sub-ranges, whole-and half stopping, notation, then an illustration and
          a repertory list, preceded by an introduction.</p>

        <p>The table measures 199 x 62 cms (78¼ x 24½ inches), and presents 83 instruments,
          including, in addition to the standard orchestral instruments, the saxophones, saxhorns,
          cornets, keyed bugles, flügelhorn, and opheiclide. It is perhaps the most popular and
          widely disseminated of all Schenker's published works, having sold in excess of 11,000
          copies by the mid-1990s.</p>

        <p>Perhaps the most significant aspect of the <title level="m">Table</title>, apart from its
          general pedagogical application, is the prominence with which it promotes the technical
          details of 18th-century instruments, notably the oboe d'amore (citing examples from J. S.
          Bach and R. Strauss), the natural horns and trumpets (citing Bach, Handel, Haydn, Mozart,
          and Beethoven).</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Author's name</head>
        <p>The work is published under the pseudonym "Artur Niloff." According to Federhofer, the
          pseudonym, sometimes spelled "Niiloff" or "Nijloff" in correspondence, is a partial
          anagram of the last name of Schenker's closest friend, Moriz Violin. The identity with
          Schenker was put beyond question in a letter from Schenker to August Halm of 1918 (DLA
          69.930/3): "H. Niloff, <hi rend="italic">i.e. I myself</hi>, manufactured this little
          trifle many, many years ago out of pity for his pupils and for the critics of the daily
          newspapers in Vienna, who […] have used English terms such as 'stopped' in their reviews,
          [and have] praised Sebastian Bach’s clarinets to all the Heavens." (italics added).
          Despite its authorship's having become known early in the work's history, the <title
            level="m">Table</title> has always been published under the pseudonym: unlike Schenker's
            <title level="m">Harmonielehre</title> (1906), which was published initially under a
          pseudonym and later under Schenker's name, the true authorial name still does not appear
          even in present-day editions. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Publication History</head>
        <p>Negotiations over the <title level="m">Table</title> were underway by September 11, 1906
          with <ref cRef="entity-000875">Joseph Stritzko</ref>, the director of <ref
            cRef="entity-002402">J. Eberle &amp; Co.</ref>, and involved the music publisher
          Doblinger. Details of the terms are shown in the diary entry OJ 1/5, p. 19, September 13,
          1906, when Stritzko wanted "possible and impossible trills" to be included. Schenker
          reported that the <hi rend="italic">Table</hi> went to the printers on April 6, 1906
          (ibid, p. 12), and it is unclear how much production work, if any, had been done when
          negotiations broke down shortly afterward over royalties.</p>
        <p><ref cRef="entity-002408">Universal Edition</ref> took over publication, releasing it
          first to schools with a small print-run in November 1908 (OC 52/28, November 11) to test
          the market, the Introduction signed "October 1908." This was Schenker's first UE
          publication under <ref cRef="entity-000356">Emil Hertzka</ref>, and was evidently
          successful ("300 copies sold within three weeks in Vienna alone", CA 96-98, May 6, 1909),
          since Hertzka issued a public first edition three months later. Apparently, French and
          English editions were announced in 1909 (ibid), but never materialized. For the 1909
          edition, Schenker supplied "supplementary notes" on instrument classification, production
          of overtones, instrument families, and transposition, but these proved too extensive for
          publication and were not included until the second edition (1912).</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Editions</head>
        <p>The editions produced before the World War II were as follows (some confusion exists as
          to the correct numbering of the editions; the two systems in use are shown below), with
          release date and print-run:</p>
        <xmt:uList>
          <item>"schools edn" (= 1st) : November 1908 : 500?</item>
          <item>1st (=2d) : February 6, 1909 : 2,000</item>
          <item>2d (= 3d) : May 7, 1912 (500)/August 23, 1912 : 1,500</item>
          <item>3d (= 4th) : September 3, 1917 : 1,000</item>
          <item>4th (= 5th) : November 9, 1920 : 1,000</item>
          <item>5th (= 6th) : January 10, 1922 : 1,000</item>
          <item>6th (= 7th) : October 25, 1925 : 1,000</item>
          <item>7th (= 8th) : January 22, 1928 : 1,000</item>
          <item>8th (= 9th) : January 11, 1933 : 1,000</item>
          <item>9th (= 10th) : July 23, 1937 : 1,000</item>
        </xmt:uList>

        <p/>
        <p>A letter of July 2, 1920 (OC 52/410), from the Book-keeping department of UE, corresponds
          with the first part of the above except that it speaks of an edition of 1,000 copies in
          1912, and a further edition of 1,000 copies "that was not produced until 1913 but had
          already been ordered in 1912."</p>

      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Bibliography:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>Universal Edition Verlagsdruckbücher (UE Archive, Vienna)</bibl>
          <bibl>Federhofer, Hellmut, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern und Briefen
              ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), p. 30</bibl>
          <bibl>Bent, Ian, <title level="a">'That Bright New Light': Schenker, Universal Edition,
              and the Origins of the Erläuterung Series, 1901-1910,</title>
            <title level="j">Journal of the American Musicological Society</title> 58/1 (2005),
            69-138, esp. 73, 83 [where Stritzko is wrongly identified with Hertzka]</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Ian Bent</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
