<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-001730">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Chromatische Fantasie und Fuge</title>
        <title type="sub">J. S. Bach, Chromatic Fantasy and Fugue</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="chromatische_fantasie">Chromatische Fantasie und Fuge</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>31/10/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Work</term>
          <term subtype="basename">chromatische_fantasie</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Chromatische Fantasie und Fuge</head>
      <div>
        <p>Edition by Schenker of J. S. Bach's <title level="m">Chromatic Fantasy and Fugue</title>
          in D minor, BWV 903, first published by <ref cRef="entity-002408">Universal Edition</ref>
          (UE 2540) in 1910.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Work Description</head>
        <p>The work is the second in the series of critical editions by Schenker that constitute a
          significant part of his output (leaving aside his publication of <ref cRef="entity-001722"
              ><title>Handel Organ Concertos</title></ref> in 1905, which was strictly speaking a
          set of arrangements). His descriptive commentary, itself a logical successor to his <ref
            cRef="entity-001721"><title level="m">Beitrag zur Ornamentik</title></ref> of 1903,
          contains elements of formal analysis, textual criticism, survey of previous editions,
          performance practice and performing technique, concluding with subsections on non legato,
          dynamics, and fingering, all of which seek to foster an understanding of the "true
          content" (<hi rend="italic">wahrer Inhalt</hi>) of the music. This commentary was the
          first to be characterized in its internal text as <hi rend="italic">Erläuterungen</hi>
          ("elucidations"), hence the first in his envisioned series of <title level="m"
            >Erläuterungsausgaben</title> ("elucidatory editions") ‒ albeit without the study of
          manuscript sources ‒ of which the <hi rend="italic">Erläuterungsausgabe</hi> of the late
          piano sonatas of Beethoven (1913‒20) was to prove the final and prime exemplar. The only
          other adoption of the genre was <ref cRef="entity-000922">Otto Vrieslander</ref>'s <title
            level="m">Kurze und leichte Clavierstücke: Neue kritische Ausgabe mit erläuterndem
            Nachwort</title> (Vienna: EU, 1914), which the cover presents as: <title level="m">Carl
            Philipp Emanuel Bach</title>[:] <title level="m">Kurze und leichte
          Clavierstücke</title>[:] <title level="m">Erläuterungsausgabe</title>.</p>

        <p>The original title-page (OC Scores/11) reads: <lb/>[<hi rend="italic">in decorative
            engraved frame, with lyre, female musicians, trees:</hi>] <cit>
            <q>CHROMATISCHE | FANTASIE UND FUGE | D MOLL | VON | JOH. SEB. BACH | KRITISCHE AUSGABE
              MIT ANHANG | VON | HEINRICH SCHENKER | PIANO SOLO | „UNIVERSAL-EDITION“ |
              AKTIENGESELLSCHAFT | WIEN — LEIPZIG | COPYRIGHT 1910 BY UNIVERSAL-EDITION.</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>(The first page of the score is headed "CHROMATISCHE PHANTASIE UND FUGE D MOLL," and the
          commentary (p. 19) employs the subheading "Chromatische Phantasie," in conformity with the
          spelling that he had previously adopted in the series-title of his main theoretical work:
          "NEUE MUSIKALISCHE THEORIEN UND PHANTASIEN.")</p>

        <p>The edition comprises, in all, fifty pages, of which the title-page and Foreword occupy
          two, the engraved musical text fourteen (with occasional asterisked footnotes), the
          letterpress text thirty, and the engraved appendix four pages.</p>

        <p>Since Schenker did not start recording details of the lessons he gave until 1912, it is
          impossible to gauge what role the <title level="m">Chromatic Fantasy and Fugue</title>
          played in his teaching in that period, except that in 1910 he wrote to his publisher:
          "Year in, year out, I go through it two or three times with my pupils ‒ it is undoubtedly
          one of the principal works of our repertory" (WSLB 57). A letter of 1909 describes the
          work as "a frequently (but as often as not badly) played concert piece," and in his early
          diary he reported adversely on a performance by <ref cRef="entity-000028">Wilhelm
            Backhaus</ref> that was "acoustical-mechanical" (diary, January 26, 1907). Surprisingly,
          in the period 1912 to 1914, he taught the work to only two of his pupils: briefly to <ref
            cRef="entity-000861">Mrs. Stirling</ref> and extensively to the highly gifted young <ref
            cRef="entity-000399">Felix Hupka</ref>.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>PUBLICATION HISTORY</head>
        <div>
          <head>First Edition</head>
          <p>Up to 1909, Schenker had produced an edition of <ref cRef="entity-001720"
                ><title>keyboard works of C. P. E. Bach</title></ref>, but none by that composer's
            father. On April 1, 1909 a meeting took place of Schenker and <ref cRef="entity-000356"
              >Emil Hertzka</ref>, in his account of which Hertzka recorded that <ref
              cRef="entity-002408">Universal Edition</ref> was prepared to pay for editions of
            specified works of Johann Sebastian Bach (none of which came to fruition), including the
            vaguely worded "Fantasy and Fugue" (OC 52/920). On June 23 Schenker requested a copy of
            the Steingräber edition of the <title level="m">Chromatic Fantasy and Fugue</title>,
            stating that he already owned those by the Bach Gesellschaft, Peters, Bülow and Busoni
            (WSLB 39 ‒ his copies of the Bach Gesellschaft and Röntgen editions survive as OC
            Scores/9 and 10, and the Peters edition [by Czerny, Griepenkerl, and Roitzsch] as OC
            68/21, pp. 20‒31). The next day Hertzka confirmed agreement "for an analytical edition"
            (a significant phrase!) "of Bach's <title level="m">Chromatic Fantasy and Fugue</title>"
            (OC 52/422).</p>

          <p>On September 20 Schenker declared the edition finished, stressing how attentiveness to
            "exact and minute detail" in the printing would be crucial. For the first time, he used
            the term <hi rend="italic">Erläuterungen</hi> (placing it in quotation-marks), in his
            exuberant declaration:<cit>
              <q> I say openly, with joy, and bursting with pride: it is ‒ far surpassing Spitta et
                al ‒ the first genuine monument to Bach: teachers, performers, composers, etc. will
                at last gain insight into this genius. In my opinion, promoted by you in your
                customary energetic fashion, the "Elucidations" should spread to the far corners of
                the earth! (WSLB 42).</q>
            </cit></p>

          <p>Schenker explained that the work was "too idiosyncratic" not to be described in all its
            details (WSLB 52). The contract was signed on October 17, 1909 (OC 52/423). UE was due to send
            Schenker's text and manuscript to the printers shortly after October 26 (OC 52/41), but
            there were problems at the printing works that in turned caused a delay in the engraving
            shop so great that, despite repeated complaints on Schenker's part, the first proofs did
            not reach him until June 3, 1910 (WSLB 61). These he returned corrected by June 20; the
            second proofs were available on July 28 (OC 52/54), and were returned by Schenker from
            his vacation address in the Tyrol by August 17 (OC 52/55). A further series of technical
            issues arose during September.</p>

          <p>The edition finally went to press on September 20, and UE took delivery of 500 copies
            on October 21, Schenker receiving the second installment of his honorarium on October 14
            (OC 52/425). It was favorably reviewed by <ref cRef="entity-000955">Egon Wellesz</ref>
            in <title level="j">Der Merker</title> the same month.</p>

          <p>Schenker claimed for his Introduction that: "no textbook on fugue up to now ‒ be it the
            oldest or the earliest ‒ has given within its pages such valuable information concerning
            fugue as does my edition" (WSLB 66/67, October 17, 1910). Two days later he insisted
            that all UE notices of the edition should include the word <hi rend="italic"
              >Erläuterungen</hi> (OC 52/426) (catalogues took several years to conform to this
            demand). </p>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>Revised Edition</head>
          <p>The work had to wait until 1969 to be re-issued, as part of Universal Edition's series
              <title>Wiener Urtext Ausgabe</title>. The title-page reads: <cit>
              <q>J. S. BACH | CHROMATISCHE PHANTASIE | UND FUGE | KRITISCHE AUSGABE VON HEINRICH
                SCHENKER | REVIDIERT VON OSWALD JONAS | UNIVERSAL EDITION</q>
            </cit>
          </p>

          <p>Schenker's wish for the word <hi rend="italic">Erläuterungen</hi> to be included thus
            remained unfulfilled. The pagination is identical, and Schenker's notational and verbal
            texts are unchanged save for a few typographical corrections. <ref cRef="entity-000412"
              >Jonas</ref> appended (p. 51) five supplementary footnotes (with footnote numbers
            inserted below the commentary at relevant points), one of which relates Schenker's
            harmonic interpretation of measures 33‒42 and 49‒68 of the Fantasy back to his <ref
              cRef="entity-001724"><title level="m">Harmonielehre</title></ref> (1906), another of
            which quotes the graphic analysis of the fugue subject presented as Figure 20,2 of <ref
              cRef="entity-001728"><title level="m">Der freie Satz</title></ref> (1935), and cross
            refers to a passing mention in <title level="a">Das Organische der Fuge</title> in <ref
              cRef="entity-001751"><title level="j">Meisterwerk</title> II</ref> (1926).</p>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>English Translation</head>
          <p>Hedi Siegel's English translation was published in 1984, the title-page at last
            incorporating the word <hi rend="italic">Erläuterungen</hi>, rendered as "Commentary": <cit>
              <q>J. S. BACH'S | CHROMATIC FANTASY | AND FUGUE | — | Critical Edition with Commentary
                | Heinrich Schenker | Translated and Edited by Hedi Siegel | [<hi rend="italic"
                  >publisher's emblem</hi>] | Longman | New York &amp; London</q>
            </cit>
          </p>

          <p>The work is published in book format rather than, as with the two German editions, that
            of sheet music (although the music is also provided in larger format in a slipcase). The
            notation has been left unchanged; footnotes to the score and words in the examples
            appear in English translation. The translator's Foreword is a penetrating
            characterization of the work, which takes into account sketches of the music made by
            Schenker, and also the numerous annotations on his personal copy (preserved now as OC
            68/2‒5 and Scores/11 respectively). Siegel provides twenty-seven pages of endnotes,
            which incorporate those of Schenker and Jonas, sometimes in amplified form, with a
            wealth of additional information on a wide variety of matters that renders this edition
            a piece of basic research in its own right.</p>

        </div>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Other Discussions by Schenker</head>
        <p>Only two of Schenker's other published works refer to the <title level="m">Chromatic
            Fantasy and Fugue</title>. The article <title level="a">Die Kunst der
            Improvisation,</title> in <ref cRef="entity-001750"><title level="j"
            >Meisterwerk</title></ref> I (1925), p. 21 points in a footnote to examples of motivic
          parallelism in measure 21‒22 and 31 of the Fantasy. <ref cRef="entity-001728"><title
              level="m">Der freie Satz</title></ref> (1935), §78 shows "the fundamental line's
          progressions and the two bass arpeggiations" of the Fugue's subject and demonstrates it in
          Figure 20,2; four other passages refer to this figure: in §170 (notes in the inner
          voices), §243 ("the implied bass formula"), §248 ("conflict of chromatic tones" in the
          foreground), and §260 ("stationary boundary tones"). The work is not discussed in those
          parts of the near-contemporary <ref cRef="entity-001757"><title level="m">Die Kunst des
              Vortrags</title></ref>, unpublished in German, that are published in English
          translation.</p>
      </div>
    </body>


    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources and Further Reading</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><editor>Siegel, Hedi</editor>, transl. and ed., <title level="a">A Contribution to
              the Study of Ornamentation [by] Heinrich Schenker,</title>
            <title level="j">The Music Forum</title>, vol. IV (1976), 1‒139, esp. 1‒5</bibl>

          <bibl><editor>Siegel, Hedi</editor>, transl. and ed., <title level="m">J. S. Bach's
              Chromatic Fantasy and Fugue: Critical Edition with Commentary</title> (New York:
            Longman, 1984)</bibl>

          <bibl>Rothstein, William R. [review of Siegel transl.], <title level="j">Music Theory
              Spectrum</title>, 7 (1985), 203‒07</bibl>

          <bibl>Rink, John S. [review of Siegel transl.], <title level="j">Music Analysis</title>
            7/2, (July 1988), 224‒31</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Schulenberg, David</author>, <title level="a">Expression and Authenticity in
              the Harpsichord Music of J. S. Bach,</title>
            <title level="j">Journal of Musicology</title>, 8/4 (1990), 449‒76</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Bent, Ian</author>, <title level="a">'That Bright New Light': Schenker,
              Universal Edition, and the Origins of the Erläuterung Series, 1901‒1910,</title>
            <title level="j">Journal of the American Musicological Society</title>, 58/1 (2005),
            69‒138</bibl>

          <bibl><editor>Rothgeb, John</editor>, transl. and ed., <title level="m">Beethoven's Last
              Piano Sonatas: An Edition with Elucidation, by Heinrich Schenker</title> (New York,
            Oxford University Press, 2015) [= <title level="m">Erläuterungsausgabe</title>]: vol. I
              <title level="m">Piano Sonata in E major, Op. 109</title>; vol. II <title level="m"
              >Piano Sonata in A-flat major, Op. 110</title>; vol. III <title level="m">Piano Sonata
              in C minor, Op. 111</title>; vol. IV <title level="m">Piano Sonata in A major, Op.
              101</title> and associated website <ref type="external"
              target="http://www.oup.com/us/beethovenslastpianosonatas"><title>Beethoven's Last
                Piano Sonatas</title></ref></bibl>

          <bibl>Communications from Hedi Siegel and William Drabkin</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <lb/>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
