<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-001754">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Mondscheinsonate</title>
        <title type="sub">"Moonlight" Sonata</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="mondscheinsonate">Mondscheinsonate</term>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Work</term>
          <term subtype="basename">mondscheinsonate</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <p>Facsimile edition, edited by Schenker, with introduction, of Beethoven, Piano Sonata in
          C# minor, Op. 27, No. 2 ("Moonlight"). </p>
        <p>The facsimile was published by Universal Edition in 1921, with publication number UE
          7000. In UE's <title level="m">Nummernverzeichnis</title>, it is subtitled "Luxusausgabe"
          ("Luxury edition"); an English edition was planned, with publication number UE 7000a. It
          was the first volume in a series edited by <ref cRef="entity-000164">Otto Erich
            Deutsch</ref>, the remainder of which can be seen listed below.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Publication History</head>
        <p><ref cRef="entity-000164">Otto Erich Deutsch</ref> had obtained Emil <ref
            cRef="entity-000356">Hertzka</ref>'s agreement at Universal Edition for a series
          informally titled "Connoisseur Prints" (<hi rend="italic">Liebhaberdrucke</hi>) by early
          January 1920, the facsimile of the "Moonlight" Sonata by Schenker being designated as the
          first volume in the series (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-10-3_5">OJ 10/3,
          [5]</ref>). The contract for the volume is dated December 16, 1920 (<ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OC-52-485">OC 52/485</ref>). Schenker handed over the
          materials for the volume to <ref cRef="entity-000356">Hertzka</ref> on July 2, 1921 (<ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OC-52-229">OC 52/229</ref>), and the volume was released in
          about November 1921 (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-10-3_25">OJ 10/3, [25]</ref>).
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Title Page</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">L. van Beethoven, Sonata op. 27, n. 2 (Die sogenannte
              Mondscheinsonate). Mit drei Skizzenblättern des Meisters, herausgegeben in
              Faksimile-Reproduktion von Heinrich Schenker</title>, Musikalische Seltenheiten:
            Wiener Liebhaberdrucke, gen. ed. Otto Erich Deutsch, vol. I (Vienna: UE, 1921) </bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">L van Beethoven, Sonata Op. 27, No. 2 (The so-called "Moonlight"
              Sonata), with three sketch leaves by the composer, edited in facsimile by Heinrich
              Schenker</title>, <title level="s">Viennese Collection of Musical Rarities: Book
              Lovers Edition</title>, comp. Otto Erich Deutsch, vol. I (Vienna: UE, 1921).</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Paul Bekker's review</head>
        <p>Among the reviews of this work was an unfavorable one in 1922 by the chief music critic
          of the <title level="j">Frankfurter Zeitung</title>, <ref cRef="entity-000057">Paul
            Bekker</ref>, author of a book on Beethoven (1911). In the "secondary literature"
          sections of the <title level="m">Erläuterungsausgabe</title> of late Beethoven sonatas
          (1913–20), Schenker had repeatedly criticized opinions expressed in that book; and for
          that on Op. 101 he wrote a lengthy rejoinder, which <ref cRef="entity-000356"
            >Hertzka</ref> suppressed at proof stage, to an article by Bekker entitled <title
            level="a">Criticism and Personality.</title></p>
        <p>After a brief history of facsimile production, enumerating the advantages of facsimiles,
          Bekker proceeded to give favorable coverage to two facsimile editions by Drei Masken
          Verlag, then continuing: <cit>
            <q>At the same time, Universal Edition of Vienna is publishing facsimile prints of
              Beethoven's C#-minor Sonata, Op. 27, and of three songs by Brahms, "Mainacht,"
              "Sapphische Ode," and "Nachtwandler." The technical execution of the reproduction
              here, too, is laudable, the external make-up is less auspiciously handled. For a
              start, I regret that it was considered appropriate to include the expression
              "Moonlight Sonata" in the title of the Beethoven work. Still more unwelcome with
              facsimile prints, in which each beholder seeks direct contact with the composer, is
              the effect of superfluous and sterile introductions by the editors: Kalbeck's prolixly
              turgid expatiations about Brahms just as much so as the ridiculous comments by
              Schenker on Beethoven’s autograph along with his "Urlinie." If such personal
              expectorations have to be published at all, then at least they are out of place in
              this context, and actually spoil the impression of such a publication.</q>
          </cit>
        </p>
        <p>Upon seeing this review, Schenker resurrected the suppressed rejoinder and recast it for
            <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title> issue 2, including a polemical response to the
          above criticism, remarking at one point: <cit>
            <q>Can one not see clearly how Bekker begrudges me my objectivity, only to denigrate it
              as a "personal expectoration" just for the sake of denigrating me? Pure vengeance,
              which only proves that he finds "personal expectoration" in matters of art – exactly
              as I do – insipid and iniquitous. Moreover, he appears to rely for support on the
              widely read <title level="j">Frankfurter Zeitung</title>, in whose services he is
              engaged. […] I can say boldly that I am stronger than Bekker and his paper – his
              shield – because I am engaged in services of the aristocracy of genius. […] And so he
              should learn to be modest; otherwise he should say wherein I have been factually
              incorrect in my criticism of him. […] </q>
          </cit></p>
        <p>However, <ref cRef="entity-000356">Hertzka</ref> refused to publish it in this form, too,
          this refusal contributing in part to the deferral of all "Miscellanea" from issue 2 to
          issue 3, and thus to the further deterioration of relations between Schenker and UE. The
          item remained unpublished in German.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Bibliography</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Bekker, Paul</author>, <title level="m">Beethoven</title> (Berlin: Schuster
            und Löffler, 1911, 2/1912) [copy in Schenker's private library at his death]</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Bekker, Paul</author>, <title level="a">Kritik und Persönlichkeit,</title>
            <title level="j">Frankfurter Zeitung</title> Nov 7, 1919 [preserved as OC
            12/1225]</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Bekker, Paul</author>, <title level="a">Musiker-Faksimiles,</title>
            <title level="j">Frankfurter Zeitung</title> April 25, 1922 [preserved as OC 2/p.
            60]</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Schenker, Heinrich</author>, <title level="a">Music Criticism</title>, in
              <title level="j">Der Tonwille: Pamphlets/Quarterly Publication in Witness …</title>,
            ed. <editor>William Drabkin</editor>, vol. II (New York: Oxford University Press, 2005),
            pp. 161–65 [not published in German]</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Musikalische Seltenheiten series</head>
        <p>[<hi rend="italic">Only the first six volumes are known certainly to be part of Deutsch's
            series, since these are listed in UE's advertisement for the series in</hi> Der Tonwille
            <hi rend="italic">Heft 3 (1922). The remainder are given here on the basis of their all
            being facsimile editions, and of the proximity of their UE numbers. Volume editors are
            known for only the first six, and publication dates only for the first two.</hi>]</p>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="s"><hi rend="bold">Musikalische Seltenheiten: Wiener
                Liebhaberdrucke</hi></title>, gen. ed. <editor>O. E. Deutsch</editor>: (<hi
              rend="bold">Viennese Collection of Musical Rarities: Book Lovers Edition</hi>, comp.
            Otto Erich Deutsch)</bibl>
          <lb/>
          <bibl>I: <title level="m">L. van Beethoven, Sonate op. 27 Nr 2 in Cis Moll</title>, ed.
              <editor>H. Schenker</editor> (UE 7000: 1921)</bibl>
          <bibl>II: <title level="m">Joseph Haydn, Zwölf schottische Volkslieder</title>, ed.
              <editor>E. Mandyczewski</editor>, German transls <editor>Hugo Engelbert
              Schwarz</editor> (UE 7001: 1921) (English edition: <title level="m">Twelve Scotch
              Popular Songs for one voice with the accompaniment of pianoforte, violin and
              violoncello</title>) [not facsimile]</bibl>
          <bibl>III: <title level="m">Johannes Brahms, Drei Lieder</title>, ed. <editor>M.
              Kalbeck</editor> (UE 7002)</bibl>
          <bibl>IV: <title level="m">Franz Schuberts fünf erste Lieder</title>, ed. <edition>O. E.
              Deutsch</edition> (UE 7003)</bibl>
          <bibl>V: <title level="m">Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart, Zwei Rondos</title>, ed. <editor>H.
              Gal</editor> (UE 7004)</bibl>
          <bibl>VI: <title level="m">Johann Sebastian Bach, Präludium und Fuge H moll für
              Orgel</title>, ed. G. Kinsky (UE 7005: 1923)</bibl>
          <bibl>VII: <title level="m">Richard Strauss, Tod und Verklärung</title> (UE 7008)</bibl>
          <bibl>VIII: <title level="m">J. S. Bach, Kaffeekantate</title> (UE 7009)</bibl>
          <bibl>IX: <title level="m">Mozart, Jupiter-Symphonie</title> (UE 7010)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Ian Bent</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
