<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-001750">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</title>, Band I (1925)</title>
        <title type="sub"><title level="j">The Masterwork in Music</title>, volume I (1926)</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="meisterwerk_I"><title level="j">Meisterwerk</title> I</term>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Work</term>
          <term subtype="basename">meisterwerk_I</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head><title level="j">
          <hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</hi>
        </title>, Band I (1925)</head>
      <div>
        <p>The first volume of Schenker's yearbook <ref cRef="entity-001749">
            <title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</title>
          </ref> (1925–30), the full title of which is: <listBibl>
            <bibl><title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik: ein Jahrbuch von Heinrich
                Schenker</title></bibl>
            <bibl><title level="j">The Masterwork in Music: a Yearbook by Heinrich
              Schenker</title></bibl>
          </listBibl>
        </p>
        <div>


          <head>Contents</head>
          <p>Volume I, 220 printed pages in length (16 gatherings: 224pp), comprises fifteen
            articles in all: ten short and analytical, three theoretical, one text-critical, and one
            polemical. Six of them have their roots in <ref cRef="entity-001739"><title level="j"
                >Der Tonwille</title></ref>: the three mini-analyses of short preludes by <ref
              cRef="entity-00027">J. S. Bach</ref> continue the series of five published in <title
              level="j">Tonwille</title> 4 and 5; <title level="a">Further Considerations of the
              Urlinie</title> follows on from articles in <ref cRef="entity-001740"><title level="j"
                >Tonwille</title> 1</ref> (<title level="a">The Urlinie: A Preliminary
              Remark</title>) and <ref cRef="entity-001741">2</ref> (<title level="a">Yet Another
              Word on the Urlinie</title>); the <title level="a">Elucidations</title> are actually a
            reprint of the article published in <ref cRef="entity-001747"><title level="j"
                >Tonwille</title> 8/9</ref>; and the <title level="a">Miscellanea</title> continues
            the series that has appeared in all but two issues. At the same time, three articles
            connect forward to <ref cRef="entity-001751"><title level="j">Meisterwerk</title>
              II</ref>: the two analyses of Bach solo violin movements are matched by one of a Bach
            solo cello movement in volume II, and <title level="a">Further Considerations"</title>
            has its own direct sequel with the same title in volume II, where also <title level="a"
              >Elucidations</title> was to be reprinted again.</p>
        </div>
        <div>


          <head>Production Chronology</head>
          <p>Work on the contents of this volume goes back to the fall of 1924. Schenker began
            drafting the three Bach short prelude analyses in that November, worked up the
            voice-leading graphs and music examples in December, finalizing all three articles in
            January 1925 with finishing touches in early June. The two Bach violin analyses were
            started in early January 1925, polished in February and finalized in late May. Schenker
            started work on the two <ref cRef="entity-000129">Chopin</ref> Etude analyses in
            mid-January 1925, polished them in mid‒late April, finalizing them at the end of May.
            The two <ref cRef="entity-000760">Scarlatti</ref> sonata items were started in early
            April and completed in late May. The Op. 110 piece took only seven days, April 28 to May
            4, 1925.</p>

          <p>The text-critical <title level="a">Abolish the Phrasing Slur</title> was written
            between late February and early June 1925. It was a response to an article by <ref
              cRef="entity-000209">Walter Engelsmann</ref>, which was itself preceded by an exchange
            of letters between Engelsmann and Schenker. The essay represents the most significant
            published "updating" of a Schenkerian analysis by Schenker himself: he also provides
            foreground graphs of extracts of the first movement (Figs. 7 and 12) and a complete
            middleground reduction of the Allegro molto (Fig. 8), things which were unthinkable back
            in 1914 when the <ref cRef="entity-001735"><title level="m"
              >Erläuterungsausgabe</title></ref> of the work was published.</p>

          <p>The two theoretical articles (other than the much earlier <title level="a"
              >Elucidations</title>) were produced in 1925. The first idea for <title level="a">The
              Art of Improvisation</title> occurred to Schenker on February 23, the work spreading
            over fourteen weeks to early June; it proceeded by sections, the <ref
              cRef="entity-001720">C. P. E. Bach</ref> materials in mid-March, the Handel preludes
            in late March, the "introduction and epilogue" in early April, the graphs polished in
            mid-May, with <ref cRef="entity-000771">Jeanette Schenker</ref> taking dictation and
            writing up drafts at various stages, eventually producing the fair copy, all being
            finished on June 2. Work on <title level="a">Further Considerations of the
              Urlinie</title> was underway before March 20, when Schenker dictated a rough version
            to Jeanette; work continued section by section throughout April, preparation of the <ref
              cRef="entity-000798">Schoenberg</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-002793">Stravinsky</ref>
            section in the final week of that month (all of this charted in his diary), and the
            final version was produced May 22‒24.</p>

          <p>Schenker first referred to the <title level="a">Miscellanea</title> in December 1924,
            but the main work occupied only nine days, May 9‒17.</p>

          <p>The whole manuscript was packed up on June 3, 1925 and delivered to <ref
              cRef="entity-002627">Drei Masken Verlag</ref>. Early in the following November, the
            publisher assigned the printing and engraving to <ref cRef="entity-002402"
              >Waldheim-Eberle</ref> (OC 54/42). (This was held up for a time because of the lack of
            "special characters" – i.e. careted numbers – in the engravers' type-set: OC 54/43.)
            Schenker began receiving galley-proofs of the letterpress around November 28 (OC 54/45),
            at which point he submitted the text of his Foreword (OC 54/48).</p>

          <p>He records returning corrected first galley-proofs between December 9 and 15. Second
            galleys circulated in January 1926 (OC 54/59, 60), proofs of the engraved work and small
            music examples (<hi rend="italic">Klischees</hi>) in February, first page-proofs were
            returned on March 1 (OC 54/67), and Schenker seems to have given his overall imprimatur
            in April (OC 54/75), although some revisions trickled on into May. One copy of the
            volume was finally delivered to Schenker on June 11 ‒ the very day on which he submitted
            the manuscript of volume II! <title level="j">Meisterwerk</title> I was apparently
            released on June 21 (diary and OC 54/90).</p>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>Bibliography</head>
          <listBibl>
            <bibl>English translation: <editor>Drabkin, William</editor>, ed., <title level="j">The
                Masterwork in Music: A Yearbook</title> [team-translated] (Cambridge: Cambridge
              University Press, 1994–97): vol. I (1994)</bibl>
          </listBibl>
        </div>


        <div>
          <head>Contents List</head>
          <listBibl>
            <bibl>Vorwort [Foreword], 7 [1]</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Die Kunst der Improvisation</title> [The Art of Improvisation],
              9‒40 [2‒19]</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Weg mit dem Phrasierungsbogen</title> [Abolish the Phrasing
              Slur], 41‒59 [20‒30]</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Joh. S. Bach: Sechs Sonaten für Violine. Sonata III,
                Largo</title> [J. S. Bach: Six Sonatas for Violin, Sonata No. 3, Largo], 61‒73
              [31‒38]</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Joh. S. Bach: Sechs Sonaten für Violine. Partita III [E-Dur],
                Präludio</title> [J. S. Bach: Six Sonatas for Violin, Partita No. 3 (E major),
              Prelude], 75‒98 [39‒53]</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Joh. S. Bach: Zwölf kleine Präludien, Nr. 6</title> [J. S. Bach:
              Twelve Short Preludes, No. 6], 99‒105 [54‒57]</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Joh. S. Bach: Zwölf kleine Präludien, Nr. 7</title> [J. S. Bach:
              Twelve Short Preludes, No. 7], 107‒13 [58‒61]</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Joh. S. Bach: Zwölf kleine Präludien, Nr. 12</title> [J. S. Bach:
              Twelve Short Preludes, No. 12], 115‒23 [62‒66]</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Domenico Scarlatti: Sonate für Klavier D-Moll</title> [Domenico
              Scarlatti: Keyboard Sonata in D minor], 125‒35 [67‒74]</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Domenico Scarlatti: Sonate für Klavier G-Dur</title> [Domenico
              Scarlatti: Keyboard Sonata in G major], 137‒44 [75‒80]</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Chopin: Etude Es-Moll op. 10, Nr. 6</title> [Chopin: Etude in E<g
                type="flat"/> minor, Op. 10, No. 6], 145‒59 [81‒89]</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Chopin: Etude Ges-Dur op. 10, Nr. 5</title> [Chopin: Etude in G<g
                type="flat"/> major, Op. 10, No. 5], 161‒73 [90‒98]</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Noch einmal zu Beethovens op. 110</title> [A Postscript to
              Beethoven's Opus 110], 175‒84 [99‒103]</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Fortsetzung der Urlinie-Betrachtungen</title> [Further
              Considerations of the Urlinie], 185‒200 [104‒111]</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Erläuterungen</title> [Elucidations], 201‒05 [112‒14]</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Vermischtes: Gedanken über die Kunst und ihre Zusammenhänge im
                Allgemeinen</title> [Miscellanea: Thoughts on Art and its Relationships to the
              General Scheme of Things], 207‒19 [115‒21]</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Anhang: Notenbeilagen</title> [Appendix: Supplement of Music
              Examples] (14 pages)</bibl>

            <bibl>Advertisement for <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>, issues 1‒10</bibl>
          </listBibl>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Ian Bent</author> and <author>William Drabkin</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
