<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-001755">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln / Five Analyses in Sketchform</title>
        <title type="sub">Five Graphic Music Analyses</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="funf_urlinie_tafeln">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>31/10/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Work</term>
          <term subtype="basename">funf_urlinie_tafeln</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln / Five Analyses in Sketchform</head>
      <div>
        <p>Collection of voice-leading graphs, on loose sheets of paper, by Heinrich Schenker and
          pupils under his supervision. They were published in 1932 by the <ref cRef="entity-002454"
            >David Mannes Music School</ref>, <ref cRef="entity-002873">New York</ref>, in
          conjunction with <ref cRef="entity-002408">Universal Edition</ref>, Vienna; the title-page
          and Foreword are however in both German and English, and the titles of the compositions
          and the (sparse) annotations to the graphs are exclusively in German.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Concept and Preparation</head>
        <p>The idea of a set of analyses without commentary probably arose during work on
          Beethoven’s "Eroica" Symphony in the late 1920s. By this time, Schenker's graphing
          notation had reached a point at which it was to remain largely unchanged over the last
          years of his life: the technique used for the "Eroica" (published as the <ref
            cRef="entity-001752"><title>third Meisterwerk yearbook</title></ref> in December 1930),
          for these five pieces, and for the music examples for <ref cRef="entity-001728"><title
              level="m">Der freie Satz</title></ref> (1935) is essentially the same. Within the
            <title level="m">Five Analyses in Sketchform</title>, however, Schenker adopts an
          earlier practice (abandoned for the "Eroica") of presenting the <term>Ursatz</term> and
          all the <term>middleground</term>
          <term>layer</term>s in vertical alignment on a single page, with only the necessarily
          longer <term>foreground</term>
          <term>graph</term>s printed separately, these covering as many as three very wide sheets
          of paper.</p>

        <p>The <title level="m">Five Analyses in Sketchform</title> grew out of Schenker's teaching,
          both privately and in his <ref cRef="entity-002499">weekly seminar</ref>s with <ref
            cRef="entity-000473">Trude Kral</ref>, <ref cRef="entity-002498">Greta Kraus</ref>, <ref
            cRef="entity-000754">Felix Salzer</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-000964">Manfred
            Willfort</ref> (see Salzer 1967, p. 18). Two analyses – one published here, one
          projected for a later series – also inform the project: <ref cRef="entity-000143"
            >Felix-Eberhard von Cube</ref>, who had studied with Schenker in the mid-1920s before
          taking up teaching in <ref cRef="entity-002621">Duisburg</ref> and later in <ref
            cRef="entity-002589">Hamburg</ref> (at <ref cRef="entity-000913">Moriz Violin</ref>'s
            <ref cRef="entity-002455">Schenker-Institut</ref>), produced graphs on his own
          initiative of the C major Prelude from Bach's <title level="m">Well-Tempered
            Clavier</title>, Book I (1930–31), and the first-movement theme of Beethoven's Piano
          Sonata Op. 26 (1933). Despite the collaborative nature of the venture, the final
          publication appeared solely over Schenker's name.</p>

        <p>Another of Schenker’s pupils, <ref cRef="entity-000201">Angi Elias</ref>, was also
          invited to take part: she made a fair copy of Cube's Bach analysis, for purposes of
          consultation at the seminar. But the autography for publication was carried out by <ref
            cRef="entity-000894">Georg Tomay</ref>, the Viennese draftsman whose extraordinary skill
          and meticulous attention to detail had greatly contributed to the quality of the "Eroica"
          graphs two years before.</p>

        <p> In abandoning a prose commentary, Schenker and his pupils were compelled to render their
          analyses very precisely, so as to demonstrate with utmost clarity the relationship of
          notes in a composition to each other (see Salzer 1967, p. 20). The graphs would then be
          able "to 'speak' even without text," as Schenker explained in an undated letter to Cube
            (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-7a_40">OJ 5/7a, [40]</ref>, written around
          October 29, 1931). This had two beneficial side-effects: (1) Schenker did not have to
          spend time refining any accompanying prose, something that had consumed a large portion of
          his time after drafting an essay; and (2) the new format eliminated the need – and the
          opportunity – for polemical verbal tirades against contemporary culture and society. A
          polemical tone is, however, discernible in the footnotes to the Chopin analyses.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Publication History</head>
        <p>The main work on the analyses took place in <ref cRef="entity-002499">Schenker's
            seminar</ref> during the 1931/32 teaching year (see Salzer 1967, p. 17). The graphs must
          have been close to completion by early spring, as Schenker was corresponding in April with
            <ref cRef="entity-000894">Tomay</ref> about the autography and with <ref
            cRef="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</ref> over terms of publication, and <ref
            cRef="entity-000894">Tomay</ref> sent Schenker the invoice for 229 shillings for his
          work (<hi rend="italic">Matritzen Zeichnungen</hi>) on June 21 (OC 54/350). The job of the
          printing was assigned to the Viennese firm of <ref cRef="entity-002402"
            >Waldheim-Eberle</ref>, for a print-run of 1,000 copies, the graphs being placed
          loose-leaf into a printed wrapper, at a total cost of 1,140 shillings (a duplicate invoice
          being send to the <ref cRef="entity-002454">Mannes School</ref> in September: OC 54/361).
          The unusually large landscape format was 34 x 27 cms (13½ x 10½ inches) when closed, with
          several of the fold-out graphs opening to double that width, and the two largest extending
          to 100 x 27 cms (39 x 10½ inches) ‒ the factor that accounted for the high cost of
          production.</p>

        <p>The <ref cRef="entity-002454">David Mannes School</ref> agreed to take responsibility for
          the production costs, on the understanding that it was assuming the role of publisher.
          However, Schenker was anxious not to allow a quintessentially "German" work to appear as
          an exclusively American product. (His diary for April 26, 1932 records that he had a long
          consultation with <ref cRef="entity-000164">Otto Erich Deutsch</ref> "concerning the
          publisher of the <hi rend="italic">Urlinie</hi> volume," i.e. a European distributor based
          in Austria or Germany.) The solution to this issue was for the 800 copies destined for the
          American market to be printed with the imprint "Published by the David Mannes Music
          School", and the remaining 200 copies, for the European market, with the imprint of "Für
          Europa: / Universal-Edition, Wien / U.E. 10.385."</p>

        <p>A complete draft of the Foreword had been ready by May 1, 1932; on one fair copy,
          Jeanette signed her husband's name "Heinrich Schenker / not Hans Weisse" (OC 54/381). The
          English translation was prepared by <ref cRef="entity-000951">Weisse</ref> (Schenker's
          diary, June 14 and 19, 1932) and the typescript for it survives as OC 54/382–384. The
          German and English were printed side-by-side on the reverse of the front cover. Both were
          post-dated "August 30, 1932," presumably to allow for packaging and transatlantic
          shipment. It was marketed in Austria for 1.80 Florins.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Content</head>
        <p>The choice of works could hardly be regarded as representative of the literature, not
          even of Schenker's limited concept of what constituted great music: two etudes by Chopin
          (Op. 10, Nos. 8 and 12), a chorale from Bach's <title level="m">St Matthew Passion</title>
          and the Prelude in C major, and the development section from one of Haydn's late E-flat
          major sonatas (Hoboken XVI:49), the last of these intended as a contribution to the
          composer's bicentennial year. (Throughout the early 1930s Schenker was thinking of writing
          a substantial essay on Haydn, but he got no further than amassing a sizeable portfolio of
          notes for it, preserved in OC File 49.)</p>

        <p>But they did have one feature in common: the composers' autographs of all five works were
          available for consultation at the <ref cRef="entity-002452">Photogram Archive</ref> in
          Vienna. This point is stressed in the Foreword, and the name of the Archive's benefactor,
            <ref cRef="entity-000380">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>, is duly mentioned.</p>

        <p>Although only one set of "analyses in sketchform" was published, Schenker projected a
          second and third such collection, comprising further analyses; these were to be mainly of
          keyboard music by Chopin, Beethoven, Handel, Bach and Brahms. His handwritten list, which
          is reproduced on pp. 18–19 of Salzer's 1967 edition, also includes Bach's Fifth
          Brandenburg Concerto and themes – one by Paganini, one attributed to Haydn – used by
          Brahms for two of his variation sets. Some of this material was at a sufficiently advanced
          stage to be included among the illustrations for <ref cRef="entity-001728"><title
              level="m">Der freie Satz</title></ref>, the completion of which was his principal
          concern during the last four, illness-plagued years of his life.</p>
      </div>


      <div>
        <head>Revised Edition</head>
        <p>In 1969, Dover Publications, Inc. of New York ‒ a company set up to republish
          out-of-print works no longer marketed by their original publishers ‒ reissued the work
          with the title <title level="m">Five Graphic Music Analyses (Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln)</title>.
          This omitted the German Foreword, added an introduction by <ref cRef="entity-000754">Felix
            Salzer</ref>, a glossary of German technical terms with English translations and in some
          cases explanations, and a contents list. The <ref cRef="entity-000894">Tomay</ref> graphs
          were left unchanged except for anglicized titles, occasional bracketed translations, and
          translated footnotes. The format was reduced to 11½ x 8¾ inches.</p>
      </div>

    </body>


    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Bibliography</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><editor>Felix Salzer</editor> (ed. and trans.), <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker:
              Five Graphic Music Analyses</title> (New York: Dover Books, 1969)</bibl>

          <bibl><author>William Drabkin</author>, <title level="a">A Lesson in Analysis from
              Heinrich Schenker: The C Major Prelude from Bach's Well-tempered Clavier, Book
              I,</title>
            <title level="j">Music Analysis</title> 4 (1985): 241–58</bibl>

          <bibl><author>William Drabkin</author>, <title level="a">Schenker, the Consonant Passing
              Note, and the First-Movement Theme of Beethoven’s Sonata Op. 26,</title>
            <title level="j">Music Analysis</title> 15 (1996): 149–189</bibl>

        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributors</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">William Drabkin</hi></author> and <author><hi rend="bold"
                >Ian Bent</hi></author> with assistance from <author><hi rend="bold">Hedi
                Siegel</hi></author> and <author><hi rend="bold">Marko
            Deisinger</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <lb/>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
