<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-001739">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>
        </title>
        <title type="sub">
          <title level="j">The Will of the Tone</title>
        </title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="tonwille"><title level="j">Tonwille</title>, <title level="j"
            >Der</title></term>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Work</term>
          <term subtype="basename">tonwille</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>
        <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>
      </head>
      <div>
        <p>Single-author periodical by Heinrich Schenker. <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title> was
          published between 1921 and 1924 inclusive, by <ref cRef="entity-002408">Universal
            Edition</ref> of Vienna under the fictitious imprint of Tonwille-Flugblätterverlag, and
          distributed by Albert J. Gutmann in Vienna and Friedrich Hofmeister in Lepzig.</p>
        <p>The Schopenhauerian keyword of the title – which we know was an afterthought – occurs
          only once in the pages of the journal: in the analysis of Beethoven Op. 2, No. 1 in <title
            level="j">Tonwille</title> 2: "only now are we able to feel the fiery will of the tone
            (<hi rend="italic">flammender Wille des Tones</hi>) E-flat in measure 22," i.e. the
          E-flat established in m. 22 (of the fourth movement) endures through the local modulations
          of the second subject to reassert itself in m. 40 and complete the three-note descent to C
          in m. 42. As Schenker says immediately after: "What long-distance hearing! (<hi
            rend="italic">Welch ein Fernhören!</hi>).</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>The Constituent Parts</head>
        <p><title level="j">Der Tonwille</title> was published in ten issues comprising nine
          physical publications:<listBibl>
            <bibl>
              <ref cRef="entity-001740"><title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>, issue 1</ref>
              (1921)</bibl>
            <bibl>
              <ref cRef="entity-001741"><title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>, issue 2</ref>
              (1922)</bibl>
            <bibl>
              <ref cRef="entity-001742"><title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>, issue 3</ref>
              (1922)</bibl>
            <bibl>
              <ref cRef="entity-001743"><title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>, issue 4</ref>
              (1923)</bibl>
            <bibl>
              <ref cRef="entity-001744"><title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>, issue 5</ref>
              (1923)</bibl>
            <bibl>
              <ref cRef="entity-001745"><title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>, issue 6 (1923)</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
              <ref cRef="entity-001746"><title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>, issue 7</ref> (= Year
              IV, issue 1) (Jan/March 1924)</bibl>
            <bibl>
              <ref cRef="entity-001747"><title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>, issue 8/9</ref> (=
              Year IV, issue 2/3) (April/Sept 1924)</bibl>
            <bibl>
              <ref cRef="entity-001748"><title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>, issue 10</ref> (=
              Year IV, issue 4) (Oct 1924)</bibl>
          </listBibl></p>

      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Genesis and Publication History</head>
        <p>The idea of <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title> emerged first in 1910 as an
          illustrative offshoot of Schenker's theoretical series <ref cRef="entity-001723">
            <title level="s">Neue Musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</title>
          </ref>. It was initially dubbed <hi rend="italic">Handbibliothek</hi> (pocket library),
          but during the course of the 1910s the title <ref cRef="entity-001758">
            <title level="j">Kleine Bibliothek</title>
          </ref> (Little Library) became firmly established in the minds of Schenker and UE along
          with the characterization <hi rend="italic">Flugblätter</hi>. The concept was of a series
          of pamphlets, issued from time to time rather than on a regular schedule, each issue (<hi
            rend="italic">Heft</hi>) to comprise two gatherings (i.e. 32 pages), a maximum of twelve
          issues to appear per year, the print-run to be initially 2,000 copies.</p>
        <p>The terms of the contract for the work (which went through several revisions: OC 52/223,
          March 17(?), 1920; OC 52/560, March 23, 1920; OC 52/517, July 10, 1920), were themselves
          contentious, and Schenker took advice from the <ref cRef="entity-002458">Association for
            the Protection of German Authors in Vienna</ref> in arguing his requirements. The title
          of the publication was changed seven months after the contract had been signed, at the
          suggestion of UE's director, <ref cRef="entity-000356">Emil Hertzka</ref> (OC 52/249-250,
          Feb 23, 1921). The arrangement of a fictitious imprint, designed to permit Schenker to
          publish opinions with which UE did not wish to associate itself, had been agreed at a
          meeting of Hertzka with Heinrich and Jeanette Schenker on January 5, 1921 (OJ 3/2, p.
          2309). The title eventually used for the first issue (1921) was: <cit>
            <q><title level="j">Der Tonwille: Flugblätter zum Zeugnis unwandelbarer Gesetze der
                Tonkunst einer neuen Jugend dargebracht von Heinrich Schenker</title><lb/> [The Will
              of the Tone: Pamphlets in Witness of the Immutable Laws of Music, Offered to a New
              Generation of Youth by Heinrich Schenker]</q>
          </cit>
        </p>
        <p>However, <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>'s mode of publication was changed in 1924
          from an occasional to a quarterly publication, the title adjusted to start <title
            level="j">Der Tonwille: Vierteljahrschrift: zum Zeugnis …</title> […Quarterly
          Publication in Witness…], and the imprint modified to Tonwille-Verlag. </p>

        <p>The ten issues of <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title> were republished in collected
          form in December 1927 as three annual volumes (<hi rend="italic">Jahrgänge</hi>), 1922 [=
          1921/22], 1923, 1924 (jointly numbered UE 9602a‒c), this time with the publisher's own
          imprint "Universal-Edition / Wien, <hi rend="italic">No. 9602 &amp;</hi> Leipzig" (italics
          = handwritten). Unchanged as to internal contents except for new covers, Hertzka described
          them as "adapted to <title level="j">Tonwille</title>'s continuation as <title level="j"
            >The Masterwork in Music</title>." (WSLB 391 = OC 52/844). Copies survive as OC Books
          and Pamphlets/18–20.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Controversy with Universal Edition</head>
        <p>From the submission of material for issue 2 of <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>
          onward, relations between Schenker and Universal Edition became steadily more acrimonious,
          Schenker harboring resentment at what he saw as Hertzka's "terroristic censorship" of his
          work, notably of his material attacking <ref cRef="entity-000057">Paul Bekker</ref> and
          his polemics against France and French culture. In late 1924 and 1925 Schenker threatened
          to take UE to court for alleged financial mismanagement of the publication, failure to
          provide adequate publicity and to honor standing subscriptions, printing only 800 rather
          than 2,000 copies, and restriction of his right to free speech. </p>
        <p>To counteract the alleged inadequate publicity, Schenker arranged for each of his pupils
          to distribute at least five copies of each issue, and at the initiative of <ref
            cRef="entity-000913">Moriz Violin</ref> and the generosity ($100) of the Hamburg
          industrialist <ref cRef="entity-000884">Max Temming</ref> copies were distributed to
          University music departments and research libraries, etc. Eventually, matters were placed
          in the hands of lawyers, a settlement being reached in December 1925 without the matter
          going to court. Well before this time, Schenker had discussed with the Munich publishing
          firms Piper Verlag and Drei Masken Verlag the possibility of their taking over the
          periodical, and this resulted in publication by Drei Masken Verlag of <title level="j">Das
            Meisterwerk in der Musik</title> (1925, 1926, 1930), which is in effect the continuation
          of <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Content</head>
        <p><title level="j">Der Tonwille</title> carries essentially three types of article: the
          analytical study of a single work or movement (which includes source studies and textual
          criticism, as well as performance and secondary literature); the short essay on a topic in
          Schenkerian theory or some aspect of music arising from it (e.g. listening, performance);
          and the free assemblage of polemics, selected verbal quotations, and aphorisms under the
          title <title level="a">Vermischtes</title> [Miscellanea]. It was the last of these that
          gave rise most of all to such contention with the publisher. Issue 1 begins with a long
          polemical article, <title level="a">Von der Sendung des deutschen Genies</title> [The
          Mission of German Genius], which sets the tone for the entire periodical and demonstrates
          the great impact that World War I and the Versailles Treaty had had on Schenker's
          thinking. This article, with its antagonism toward Latin and Anglo-Saxon nations,
          communists, the journalist profession, commerce, and international, cosmpolitan Jewry, had
          already aroused Hertzka's alarm with a view to foreign readerships.</p>
        <p>The longest analytical articles are that on Beethoven's Fifth Symphony, which is spread
          over three issues, and that on Brahms's Variations and Fugue on a Theme by Handel, Op. 24,
          which occupies the bulk of issues 8/9. The article on Beethoven's Fifth Symphony was
          issued together as a separate <ref cRef="entity-001760">monograph</ref> in 1925. These
          exemplary analyses belong to the line of Schenker's large-scale treatments of masterworks;
          they were to be followed by his monumental studies of Mozart's Symphony No. 40 in G minor
          and Beethoven's "Eroica" Symphony, published in <title level="j">Meisterwerk</title> II
          and III, respectively. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Bibliography</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>English translation: <title level="j">Der Tonwille: Pamphlets/Quarterly Publication
              in Witness of the Immutable Laws of Music, Offered to a New Generation of Youth
              …</title>, ed. William Drabkin (New York: Oxford University Press), vol. I (issues
            1–5) (2004), vol. II (issues 6–10) (2005) [The General Prefaces of these volumes give a
            more detailed account of the publication history and contents of the work]</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Clark, Suzannah</author>, <title level="a">The Politics of the Urlinie in
              Schenker's <hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Der freie
                Satz</hi>,</title>
            <title level="j">Journal of the Royal Musical Association</title>, cxxxii/1 (2007),
            141–64</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Lubben, Robert Joseph</author>, <title level="u">Analytic Practice and
              Ideology in Heinrich Schenker's <hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</hi></title> (PhD
            diss., Brandeis University, 1995) [includes translations of twelve essays]</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Lubben, Robert Joseph</author>, <title level="a">Schenker the Progressive:
              Analytic Practice in <hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</hi>,</title>
            <title level="j">Music Theory Spectrum</title> 15/1 (1993), 59–75 </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Ian Bent</author> and <author>William Drabkin</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
