<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-001737">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven ... op. 101</title>
        <title type="sub">The Last Five Sonatas of Beethoven ... Op. 101</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="ea-op101">Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 101</term>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Work</term>
          <term subtype="basename">ea-op101</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven ... op. 101</head>
      <div>
        <p>The fourth volume of Schenker's "<ref cRef="entity-001733">Erläuterungsausgabe</ref>,"
          published in 1921 and comprising Beethoven's Piano Sonata in A major, Op. 101 in his
          edition based on Beethoven's autograph manuscript, which was at that time in the
          possession of the music antiquarian dealer <ref cRef="entity-000454">Louis Koch</ref> and
          is now in the Beethovenhaus, Bonn, his "Vorwort" (Foreword), "Vorbemerkung zur Einführung"
          (Preliminary Remark to the Introduction), "Einführung" (Introduction—Schenker also
          informally called this section "Analyse"), and "Literatur" (Secondary Literature). It is
          published by <ref cRef="entity-002408">Universal Edition</ref>, Vienna.</p>

        <p>Schenker spoke of the fourth and fifth planned volumes of the Erläuterungsausgabe as "the
          last two colossuses, Opp. 101 and 106," explaining that he had left them until last
          "because of both their size and their internal difficulties" (WSLB 200, February 19,
          1914). In the event, he completed Op. 101 but not Op. 106. Wartime conditions having
          delayed both its completion and the publication, Op. 101 reflects significant developments
          in Schenker's thought, in particular in the introduction of the term "Urlinie" in its
          original sense of voice-leading reduction.</p>

        <p>Schenker worked long and hard on the Foreword to this volume as giving voice to his
          political feelings. Ultimately, the Foreword (not reproduced in the New Edition) was
          short, and the major thrust was transferred to the first issue of <title level="j">Der
            Tonwille</title> and the Foreword to <title level="m">Counterpoint 2</title>: </p>


        <q>
          <p><hi rend="bold">Foreword</hi></p>
          <p>Five years have passed since the appearance of Op. 111 in the <title level="m"
              >Elucidatory Edition</title>. Why the edition of Op. 101 had to suffer so significant
            a delay is not difficult to guess. </p>
          <p rend="inset-10">The present publication comes at the most severe of times, which not
            only Germany but the whole of mankind had to endure. In this world, brought to
            misfortune by an incompetent western democratic movement, the ozone of a spiritual
            prince, of an aristocrat, of a true German genius must arise – refreshed by this ozone,
            a new generation of Germans must defy the pernicious onslaught of the west. </p>
          <p>Let no one expect to gain access to Beethoven if he does not understand the meaning of
            "German" in the special and narrowest sense, and "genius" in the highest meaning of the
            word. </p>
          <p>Vienna, August 30, 1920 Heinrich Schenker</p></q>
        <lb/>



        <div>

          <head>Publication History</head>
          <div>
            <head>First Edition</head>
            <p>The original edition was published in 1921, with publication number UE 3974.</p>
            <p>Cover title-page: <hi rend="italic">BEETHOVEN-SCHENKER</hi> | <hi rend="italic"
                >ERLÄUTERUNGS-AUSGABE</hi> | <hi rend="italic">DER LETZTEN FÜNF SONATEN</hi> | <hi
                rend="italic">SONATE A DUR</hi> | <hi rend="italic">OP. 110.</hi></p>
            <p>Inner title-page: <hi rend="italic">DIE LETZTEN</hi> | <hi rend="italic">FÜNF
                SONATEN</hi> | <hi rend="italic">VON</hi> | <hi rend="italic">BEETHOVEN</hi> | — |
                <hi rend="italic">KRITISCHE AUSGABE</hi> | <hi rend="italic">MIT EINFÜHRUNG</hi> |
                <hi rend="italic">UND ERLÄUTERUNG</hi> | <hi rend="italic">VON</hi> | <hi
                rend="italic">HEINRICH SCHENKER</hi> | — | <hi rend="italic">PIANO SOLO</hi></p>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Chronology:</hi> Schenker's Foreword is dated August 30, 1920. He
              had submitted the musical text of the work in late July or early August 1920 (OC
              52/449), and the textual material on October 25, 1920 (OC 52/450). Schenker stipulated
              that this work should appear before the <ref cRef="entity-001740">first issue of
                  <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title></ref> because it presented his new graphic
              device of the Urlinie (diary, OJ 3/2, p. 2292). The edition went to press on May 29,
              1921, and 497 copies were delivered from the printer to the publisher on August 9,
              1921.</p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head>Second Edition</head>
            <p><hi rend="italic">Chronology:</hi> This edition went to press on February 27, 1928,
              and 496 copies were delivered from the printer to the publisher on March 31, 1928.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <head>New Edition</head>
            <p>Edited by <ref cRef="entity-000412">Oswald Jonas</ref>, and published in 1972, with
              publication number UE 26.301, this excises Schenker's polemical matter and commentary
              on the secondary literature, and replaces Schenker's edition with the 1945 revision by
              Erwin Ratz, with the effect that the scores contradict some of the textual argument in
              Schenker's elucidations.</p>
            <p>Cover title-page: <hi rend="italic">Beethoven</hi> | <hi rend="italic">Die letzten
                Sonaten</hi> | <hi rend="italic">SONATE A DUR OP. 101</hi> | <hi rend="italic"
                >Erläuterungsausgabe</hi> | <hi rend="italic">von HEINRICH SCHENKER</hi></p>
            <p>Inner title-page: <hi rend="italic">Beethoven</hi> | <hi rend="italic">Die letzten
                Sonaten</hi> | <hi rend="italic">SONATE A DUR OP. 101</hi> | <hi rend="italic"
                >Kritische Einführung und Erläuterung von</hi> | <hi rend="italic">HEINRICH
                SCHENKER</hi> | <hi rend="italic">herausgegeben von</hi> | <hi rend="italic">Oswald
                Jonas</hi></p>
            <lb/>

          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>English Translation and Study</head>
          <p>The recent English translation by John Rothgeb is likewise in four separate,
            small-format volumes and a website, of which this volume is:</p>

          <p><title level="m">Piano Sonata in A major, Op. 101</title>, <title level="s">Beethoven's
              Last Piano Sonatas: An Edition with Elucidation</title>, vol. IV, transl., ed. and
            annotated by John Rothgeb (New York: Oxford University Press, 2015)</p>

          <p>This edition follows the text of Schenker's original, thereby restoring all the
            material excised by Jonas in his 1972 edition. Explanatory and citational footnotes by
            Rothgeb incorporate some of the observations made by Jonas. Schenker's surveys of the
            secondary literature appear not in the print volumes but on the website. The score of
            the sonata appears neither in the print volume nor on the website.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>

      <div>
        <head>Source:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>Universal Edition Archive: Verlagsdruckbuch UE 3974</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Ian Bent</author> and <author>William Drabkin</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <lb/>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
