<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-001720">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Phil. Em. Bach: Klavierwerke</title>
        <title type="sub">C. P. E. Bach: Keyboard Works</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="bach_cpe_klavierwerke">Bach, C. P. E.: Klavierwerke</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>31/10/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Work</term>
          <term subtype="basename">bach_cpe_klavierwerke</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Phil. Em. Bach: Klavierwerke</head>
      <div>
        <p>Edition by Schenker of fourteen selected keyboard works of <ref cRef="entity-000025">Carl
            Philipp Emmanuel Bach</ref>, published by Universal Edition (UE 548) in 1903. It is the
          first in the series of critical editions by Schenker that constitute a major part of the
          his output.</p>

        <p>The original title-page (OC Scores/1) reads: <cit>
            <q>[<hi rend="italic">in highly decorative engraved frame:</hi>] KLAVIERWERKE | VON |
              PHILIPP EMANUEL BACH. | — | NEUE | KRITISCHE AUSGABE | VON | HEINRICH SCHENKER. |
              „UNIVERSAL-EDITION“ | ACTIENGESELLSCHAFT | IN WIEN.</q>
          </cit></p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Publication History</head>
        <p>The edition was first published by Universal Edition as a single volume on February 10,
          1903, although in the literature it is conventionally dated "1902" ‒ presumably because
          the Preface is dated "November, 1902". It was initially published separately in three
          different languages: 500 copies in German, 250 in French, 250 in English. Only later were
          the three consolidated into a single tri-lingual edition (probably with the 1910 print-run
          of 500). A companion volume was published also in 1903 (conventionally dated 1904), <title
            level="m"><ref cRef="entity-001721">Ein Beitrag zur Ornamentik</ref>: Als Einführung zu
            Ph. Em. Bachs Klavierwerken mitumfassend auch die Ornamentik Haydns Mozarts u.
            Beethovens etc</title> ("A Contribution to the Study of Ornamentation: As an
          Introduction to the Keyboard Works of C. P. E. Bach, encompassing also the Ornamentation
          of Haydn, Mozart, Beethoven, etc."), of which a second edition was published in 1908.</p>

        <p>Heavy demand continued for the edition of the keyboard works, and reissues of 500 copies
          were made in 1923, 1926 (when it was split into two volumes), 1930, 1934, and 1938, and
          even larger print-runs from 1952 onward, making a total of at least 10,000 copies of the
          work as a whole by the end of the century (Verlagsdruckbuch UE 548).</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Nature of the Edition</head>
        <p>In the introduction to her translation of the <title level="m">Beitrag</title>, Hedi
          Siegel characterizes the edition thus: "It represents Schenker's first 'Urtext' edition;
          its text is the result of intensive study and insightful interpretation of the sources. It
          carefully preserves Bach's dynamic markings; the few suggested additional markings are
          always placed in parentheses. These editorial additions, as well as the presence of
          fingerings (with footnotes to indicate the original fingerings) point to the fact that
          Schenker intended this collection as a <hi rend="italic">performing</hi> edition. The
          explanatory footnotes are directed toward the performer; they deal with such items as
          disputed readings, dynamic markings, and rhythm, but by far the greatest number are
          concerned with the realization of embellishments." (<bibl><title level="j">The Music
              Forum</title>, iv (1976), 1‒2</bibl>)</p>

        <p>The edition comprises whole sonatas and separate movements selected from C. P. E. Bach's
          collections of sonatas "für Kenner und Liebhaber" (for connoisseurs and amateurs). Such a
          publication, which comprises only works dating from the last decade of Bach's life
          (1779‒87) and excludes sonatas from earlier collections, e.g. the "Prussian" Sonatas of
          c.1742, and the "Württemberg" Sonatas of 1744, offers only a small, unrepresentative
          sample of the composer's prodigious keyboard output. In its time, however, it served as an
          alternative to existing selected editions, notably that of <ref cRef="entity-000110">Hans
            von Bülow</ref> (C. P. E. Bach, <title level="m">Sechs Klavier-Sonaten</title>,
          published by C. F. Peters in 1862), which Schenker was to criticize sharply a year after
          his own edition had appeared, in the <ref cRef="entity-001721"><title level="m">Beitrag
              zur Ornamentik</title></ref>.</p>
      </div>
    </body>


    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources and Further Reading</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><editor>Siegel, Hedi</editor>, transl. and ed., <title level="a">A Contribution to
              the Study of Ornamentation [by] Heinrich Schenker,</title>
            <title level="j">The Music Forum</title>, iv (1976), 1‒139</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Bent, Ian</author>, <title level="a">'That Bright New Light': Schenker,
              Universal Edition, and the Origins of the Erläuterung Series, 1901‒1910,</title>
            <title level="j">Journal of the American Musicological Society</title>, 58/1 (2005),
            esp. 71‒81</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Felix Salzer</author>, <title level="a">Über die Bedeutung der Ornamente in
              Philipp Emanuel Bachs Klavierwerken,</title>
            <title level="j">Zeitschrift für Musikwissenschaft</title>, 12/7 (April 1930), 398–418;
            Eng. transl. by <editor>Mark Stevens</editor> as <title level="a">The Significance of
              the Ornaments in Carl Philipp Emanuel Bach's Keyboard Works,</title>
            <title level="j">Theory and Practice</title>, 11 (1986), 15–42.</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Ernst Oster</author>, <title level="a">Vom Sinn des langen
              Vorschlags,</title>
            <title level="j">Der Dreiklang</title>, 6 (September 1937), 148‒57; Eng. transl. by
              <editor>Robert Kosovsky</editor> as <title level="a">On the meaning of the Long
              Appoggiatura,</title>
            <title level="j">Theory and Practice</title>, 7/1 (August 1982), 20–37.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributors</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author> with <author><hi rend="bold">William
                Drabkin</hi></author> and <author><hi rend="bold">Hedi Siegel</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <lb/>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
