<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-001752">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</title>, Band III (1930)</title>
        <title type="sub"><title level="j">The Masterwork in Music</title>, volume III
          (1930)</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="meisterwerk_III"><title level="j">Meisterwerk</title> III</term>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Work</term>
          <term subtype="basename">meisterwerk_III</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head><title level="j">
          <hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</hi>
        </title>, Band III (1930)</head>
      <div>
        <p>The third volume of Schenker's yearbook <ref cRef="entity-001749">
            <title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</title>
          </ref> (1925–30), the full title of which is: <listBibl>
            <bibl><title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik: ein Jahrbuch von Heinrich
                Schenker</title></bibl>
            <bibl><title level="j">The Masterwork in Music: a Yearbook by Heinrich
              Schenker</title></bibl>
          </listBibl>
        </p>
        <div>


          <head>CONTENTS</head>
          <p>Volume III differs markedly from its two predecessors in comprising only 122 pages of
            printed text and a conversely greater proportion of foreground graphs (<hi rend="italic"
              >Bilder</hi>), and also in the absence of music examples (<hi rend="italic"
              >Figuren</hi>) from the text, all such examples being printed on separate fold-out
            sheets and housed in an appendix and cued (as are the graphs) from the margins of the
            text.</p>

          <p>The volume's contents further extend the progression from <title level="j">Meisterwerk
              I</title> and <title level="j">II</title>: The number of articles is reduced to three:
            one sharply polemical piece, one analysis, and the customary "Vermischtes." The analysis
            article, on the "Eroica" Symphony, which is the centerpiece of the volume, extends over
            73 pages of text, of which the "Presentation of Content" occupies 55 pages,
            "Performance" seven pages, and "Secondary Literature" two pages, with an additional
            section on Beethoven's revised score and the original instrumental parts interpolated
            between the first and second sections.</p>

          <p>That <title level="j">Meisterwerk III</title> was an expedient vehicle for his "Eroica"
            Symphony essay rather than an intended continuation of the Yearbook, and that Schenker
            had always conceived the essay as a separate monograph, is explained in the next
            section. See also <ref cRef="entity-003288">Beethovens Dritter Sinfonie
              [monograph]</ref>. In the light of this, the first article and the "Vermischtes" can
            both be seen as subservient to the "Eroica" essay, both emphasizing genius over
            non-genius.</p>
        </div>
        <lb/>


        <div>
          <head>PRODUCTION CHRONOLOGY</head>
          <div>
            <head>The "Eroica" Project</head>
            <p>The preparation of a monograph on Beethoven's Third Symphony appears to have been
              made in two phases. Diary entries mention work "on the Eroica" between October 1923
              and February 1924, though this was far from being regular and systematic. A couple of
              years later, between November 1926 and February 1927, mention is made of the "Eroica"
              Variations for piano, particularly in connection with Schenker's pupil <ref
                cRef="entity-000107">Robert Brünauer</ref>. Near the start of the following teaching
              year, on November 14, 1927, Brünauer dropped a bombshell by noting that the
              neighbor-note a<g type="flat"/><hi rend="supralinear">2</hi> near the start of the
              first movement, which is reached via a <hi rend="italic">crescendo</hi> from g<hi
                rend="supralinear">2</hi>, becomes "the driving force in the entire work."</p>

            <p>This observation may have spurred Schenker to resume work on the symphony. Although
              diary entries on the symphony in 1928 are sparse, on September 23, 1928 he records
              "the new revision of the Eroica, and all earlier leaves destroyed." From this point
              until May 1930, the diary documents intensive work on the symphony and its companion
              essay, <title level="a">Rameau oder Beethoven?</title>.</p>
          </div>

          <div>
            <head>The search for a publisher</head>
            <p>By late 1928, Schenker was writing to his old adversary, <ref cRef="entity-000356"
                >Emil Hertzka</ref>, hoping to regain the favor of <ref cRef="entity-002408"
                >Universal Edition</ref> by offering the "Eroica" together with an <hi rend="italic"
                >Erläuterungsausgabe</hi> of the "Hammerklavier" Sonata and the long-awaited final
              volume of the <ref cRef="entity-001723"><title level="s">Neue Musikalische Theorien
                  und Phantasien</title></ref> (i.e. <title level="m">Der freie Satz</title>);
              Hertzka's initial reply was politely cautious; but when the matter was broached again,
              shortly before the summer holidays, he deferred making a decision once more – for
              another year – on economic grounds (Hertzka to Schenker, June 21, 1929): <cit>
                <q>The people who would certainly be interested in an "Eroica" monograph have no
                  money, and the people who have money are buying no sheet music, no books, and no
                  "Eroica" monograph.</q>
              </cit>
            </p>

            <p>Through the conductor <ref cRef="entity-000268">Wilhelm Furtwängler</ref> and his
              close friend, the organist <ref cRef="entity-000866">Karl Straube</ref>, appeals were
              made to two major publishing houses in Leipzig: <ref cRef="entity-002890">Breitkopf
                &amp; Härtel</ref>, and <ref cRef="entity-002422">C. F. Peters</ref>. Neither of
              these bore fruit: in a letter to Schenker of May 14, 1930, Straube reported with
              regret that Breitkopf was not interested in taking over the publication of Schenker's
              work, noting that "works devoted to musical issues are hardly sold"; a postscript
              dated May 16 reports a rejection from Peters (OC 54/218). </p>

            <p>Schenker's anxieties about finding a publisher for the "Eroica" met with sympathy
              from <ref cRef="entity-000913">Moriz Violin</ref>, who was always willing to do his
              utmost for his teacher's cause. Between November 1929 and January 1930 he tried to
              interest another Leipzig publisher (D. Rather) in the monograph, but repeated visits
              to their Hamburg offices drew a blank. Schenker thanked Violin for his efforts, and
              seemed more optimistic when he wrote to him in March (OJ 6/7, [47]): <cit>
                <q>I hope soon to be able to have the musical graphs (<hi rend="italic"
                    >Notenbilder</hi>) for the "Eroica" engraved by Waldheim &amp; Eberle, who can
                  do this best of all. About a publisher, I shall tell you at a later occasion.</q>
              </cit>
            </p>

            <p>What Schenker had in mind here was a revival of the (fictitious) "Tonwille Verlag"
              imprint from the early 1920s. He approached the Viennese printers <ref
                cRef="entity-002402">Waldheim-Eberle</ref> (OC 54/221), who had engraved the first
              two volumes of <title level="j">Meisterwerk</title> for <ref cRef="entity-002627">Drei
                Masken Verlag</ref>, in the hope that they would be willing to act as the
              "commission publisher" for the "Eroica." Waldheim-Eberle's initial reply was
              encouraging: they prepared a cost estimate for Schenker on February 13 (OC 54/221).
              But while they were prepared to take on the printing, they did not also want the
              additional responsibility of acting as a publisher, saying that this activity was not
              part of their business (March 22, 1930: OC 54/223). </p>

            <p>It was at this time that Schenker, somewhat in desperation, considered returning to
              Drei Masken Verlag. The "Eroica" study could appear as the third volume of <title
                level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</title> in name only, as it would be
              difficult to justify the term "Yearbook" for a work that would come out three years
              after its predecessor, and moreover one that focussed on a single composer, and on a
              single work. (The polemical <title level="a">Rameau oder Beethoven?</title>, far from
              being an independent essay, functioned as an introduction to the study; indeed, while
              working on it Schenker repeatedly refers to it as the "Vorwort" (Foreword) in diary
              entries from mid-May.) </p>

            <p><ref cRef="entity-000164">Otto Erich Deutsch</ref> had continued to support Schenker
              in the late 1920s – the two collaborated on a revised edition of the "Unfinished"
              Symphony in the Schubert year 1928 – and also remained on good terms with the music
              editors at Drei Masken Verlag. In May 1930, within days of Schenker receiving
              Straube's discouraging letter, Deutsch approached them with the proposal to take on
              the "Eroica" as volume III of the <title level="j">Meisterwerk</title> series. Deutsch
              received a favorable response on May 22, and spent the next several weeks discussing
              arrangements for the setting of the music examples and the printing of the work (OC
              54/224). He kept Schenker informed of all developments by forwarding the relevant
              correspondence, often adding postscripts and making recommendations on how to proceed.
              With Deutsch's continued assistance, the contract for <title level="j">Meisterwerk
                III</title> was signed in mid-July, and the manuscript was received by the
              publishers a week later (telegram from Drei Masken Verlag to Schenker, July 22, 1930:
              OC 54/229).</p>
          </div>

          <div>
            <head>Production</head>
            <p>Well before the agreement with <ref cRef="entity-002627">Drei Masken Verlag</ref> had
              been signed, Schenker was in close contact with the Viennese music calligrapher <ref
                cRef="entity-000894">Georg Tomay</ref>, and the two men struck up a cordial
              relationship which lasted from their first meeting (May 26, 1930), at which Schenker
              handed over to him all the music examples (<hi rend="italic">Figuren</hi>) and
              foreground graphs, until Tomay produced his final account in November (OC
              54/195‒217). Tomay's handwritten examples were then turned into blueprints (<hi
                rend="italic">Blaupausen</hi>) by the Viennese lithographic firm of Karl Piller.
              Thus the production of the music examples preceded that of the main text of <title
                level="j">Meisterwerk III</title>, for which Drei Masken enlisted the services of
              the Leipzig firm of C. G. Röder.</p>

            <p>Schenker made regular visits to Tomay's studio to correct the work-in-progress on the
              graphs; after he and <ref cRef="entity-000771">Jeanette</ref> left Vienna in late
              June, discussion continued by correspondence during the summer. These letters show
              that Tomay exercised extreme care with his work, noting inconsistencies in the
              original manuscript and offering advice on how to correct the prints (<hi
                rend="italic">Matrizen</hi>); he also seems to have enjoyed the collaboration,
              writing with an inimitable mixture of courtesy and enthusiasm: <cit>
                <q>As soon as I send you Urlinie matrices for your inspection, I shall, dear
                  Professor, also send you instructions for marking the corrections. These matrices
                  are not so awkward, and you, Professor, can mark up everything, however only with
                  a normal pencil: no ink, no colored pencils, and also no indelible pencils – but,
                  Professor, you are after all in <ref cRef="entity-002292">Galtür</ref> to rest,
                  and not to work; I shall also leave you now, dear Professor, in peace and send you
                  something for inspection only about two weeks from now.</q>
              </cit>
            </p>

            <p>Tomay's remarks about needing to rest and recuperate while on holiday were prophetic.
              The Schenkers were obliged to entertain more than their usual complement of visitors
              in Galtür, at a time when they were expected to read through and correct the whole of
              the galley-proofs and most of the page-proofs. Problems arose when the galleys were
              turned into page-proofs (the <hi rend="italic">Umbruch</hi>). Schenker had overlooked
              a number of errors that needed correcting, and further – costly – delays took place in
              October (Oct 8: OC 54/237). Decisions were needed, too, about the way in which the
              foreground graphs were to be bound and accommodated within the volume. All these
              problems, however, were discussed and resolved in the ensuing weeks, and on December
              17 <ref cRef="entity-002627">Drei Masken Verlag</ref> was able to inform Schenker that
              bound copies of <title level="j">Meisterwerk III</title> had arrived in their
              warehouses and were already being distributed (OC 54/256). Some copies had made their
              way to Berlin in time for <ref cRef="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</ref>'s lectures on
              Schenker's theory at the Central Institute for Education.</p>

            <p>Although the work was in print, Schenker was obliged to pay the production costs,
              which were reckoned at 2,957 marks (Nov 14, 1930: OC 54/249); this was revised
              upwards, to 3,041 marks (Dec 16, 1930: OC 54/254). He was given a period of three
              months (OC 54/253) to repay the debt, and on March 20 he settled part of it with a
              cash payment of 4,000 shillings. A long-awaited subvention of 3,000 marks from <ref
                cRef="entity-000268">Furtwängler</ref> did not arrive until June 1 (OC 54/278); this
              enabled Schenker to make a final payment of 1,173 shillings to Drei Masken Verlag
              three weeks later (OC 54/267–276). </p>
          </div>

        </div>

        <div>
          <head>Bibliography</head>
          <listBibl>
            <bibl>English translation: <editor>Drabkin, William</editor>, ed., <title level="j">The
                Masterwork in Music: A Yearbook</title> [team-translated] (Cambridge: Cambridge
              University Press, 1994–97): vol. III (1997)</bibl>
            <bibl><author>Bent, Ian</author>, <title level="a">Heinrich Schenker and Robert
                Brünauer: Relations with a Musical Industrialist,</title>
              <title level="m">Festschrift Hellmut Federhofer zum 100. Geburtstag</title>, ed.
                <editor>Axel Beer</editor> (Tutzing: Hans Schneider, 2011), pp. 25‒37.</bibl>
          </listBibl>
        </div>


        <div>
          <head>CONTENTS LIST</head>
          <listBibl>
            <bibl><title level="a">Rameau oder Beethoven? Erstarrung oder geistiges Leben in der
                Musik?</title> [Rameau or Beethoven? Creeping Paralysis or Spiritual Potency in
              Music?], 9‒22 [1‒9]</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Beethovens Dritte Sinfonie zum erstenmal in ihrem wahren Inhalt
                dargestellt</title> [Beethoven's Third Symphony described for the first time in its
              True Content], 25‒101 [10‒68]</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Vermischtes</title> [Miscellanea], 103‒121 [69‒79]</bibl>

            <bibl>35 Urlinie-Tafeln, arranged as a separate booklet of four "Bilder" (lit: pictures)
              corresponding to the four movements (1‒10; 11‒16; 17‒22; 23‒35) tucked into the back
              of the volume</bibl>

            <bibl>46 "Figuren" (music examples) grouped and arranged in nine fold-out sheets,
              numbered by movement (I.1‒7, II.1‒2, III.1‒4, IV.1‒2) at the back of the
              volume.</bibl>
          </listBibl>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Ian Bent</author> and <author>William Drabkin</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
