<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-003331">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Oktaven und Quinten u. A.</title>
        <title type="sub">Octaves and Fifths. etc.</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="oktaven_und_quinten">Oktaven und Quinten</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>31/10/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Work</term>
          <term subtype="basename">oktaven_und_quinten</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Oktaven und Quinten u. A.</head>

      <div>
        <p>A facsimile edition of <ref cRef="entity-000094">Brahms</ref>'s handwritten compilation
          of parallel (consecutive) octaves, fifths, and related progressions, in music from the
          16th to the 19th century, with commentary on some of the examples by Schenker, published
          by <ref cRef="entity-002408">Universal Edition</ref> of Vienna. Brahms's manuscript is
          preserved in the library of the <ref cRef="entity-002430">Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde in
            Vienna</ref>.</p>

        <p>The Brahms manuscript seems to have come to Schenker’s attention in October 1913. The
          lessonbook for December 18 states “<ref cRef="entity-003331">Weisse</ref> … brings the
          photographic reproductions of sketches for the Intermezzi by Brahms, as well as the
          collection of interesting passages,” and the diary for that date records: “Weisse brings
          Brahms’s ‘collection of interesting passages’; beyond all expectation, the master shows
          himself immersed in the most intensive work and effort in his research into voice-leading
          problems.” On the 29th and 30th of the month, Schenker shows “Brahms’s studies in Oktaven
          und Quinten” to two others of his pupils. It is therefore possible that <ref
            cRef="entity-003331">Hans Weisse</ref> drew this work to Schenker’s attention; or,
          perhaps more likely, that Schenker heard of it and asked Weisse to collect photographs of
          it. Schenker’s surprise at Brahms’s “most intensive work” is striking. It is remarkable
          that it took Schenker twenty years to produce the edition, at the time of the centenary of
          Brahms's birth.</p>
      </div>
    </body>


    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Bibliography</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Johannes Brahms</author>, <title level="m">Oktaven und Quinten u. A.</title>
            (Vienna: Universal Edition, 1933)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="a">Brahms's Study, Octaven u. Quinten u. A., with Schenker’s
              Commentary,</title> annotated translation by <editor>Paul Mast</editor>, <title
              level="j">The Music Forum</title>, V (1980), pp. 1‒196</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributors</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">William Drabkin</hi></author> and <author><hi rend="bold"
                >Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
