<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-001721">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Ein Beitrag zur Ornamentik</title>
        <title type="sub">A Contribution to the Study of Ornamentation</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="ornamentik_ein_beitrag_zur">Ornamentik, Ein Beitrag zur</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>31/10/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Work</term>
          <term subtype="basename">ornamentik_ein_beitrag_zur</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Ein Beitrag zur Ornamentik</head>
      <div>
        <p>Companion volume to Schenker's <ref cRef="entity-001720"><title level="m">Phil. Em. Bach:
              Klavierwerke</title></ref> of 1903, <title level="m">Ein Beitrag zur
            Ornamentik</title> was published first by <ref cRef="entity-002408">Universal
            Edition</ref> in 1903 (widely and incorrectly dated "1904"), and reissued in a revised
          and enlarged edition in 1908.</p>

        <p>Bearing the plate-number UE 812, its full title is: <cit>
            <q>[<hi rend="italic">in highly decorative engraved frame with harps and timbrel:</hi>]
              EIN BEITRAG | ZUR ORNAMENTIK. | ALS EINFÜHRUNG ZU | PH. EM. BACH’<hi rend="sup">S</hi>
              KLAVIERWERKEN, | MITUMFASSEND AUCH DIE ORNAMENTIK | HAYDNS MOZARTS U. BEETHOVENS ETC </q>
            <lb/>
            <lb/>
            <q>(A Contribution to the Study of Ornamentation: As an Introduction to the Keyboard
              Works of C. P. E. Bach encompassing also the Ornamentation of Haydn, Mozart,
              Beethoven, etc.)</q>
          </cit></p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contents</head>
        <p>The work is structured in two long sections, variously subdivided, and interspersed with
          music examples. In the synopsis below, the pages of the original and revised editions are
          given in parentheses separated by "/", to convey an impression of the degree of
          expansion.</p>

        <p><hi rend="bold">Introduction (Einführung)</hi> (pp. 3‒20 / 3‒23)<lb/> This is subdivided
          in both editions into six subsections covering Bach's keyboard style, the artistic basis
          of his embellishments, musical form, and performance of his works.</p>

        <p><hi rend="bold">The Embellishments (Die Manieren)</hi> (pp. 21‒42 / 24‒70)<lb/> The three
          subsections are divided into embellishment in C. P. E. Bach's own music (its psychology,
          its notation, its performance), then (collectively or separately) in those of Haydn,
          Mozart, and Beethoven. <list type="litany" rend="simple">
            <item>I. The Appoggiatura (Der Vorschlag) (pp. 22‒26 / 25‒34)</item>
            <item>II. The Trill (Triller) (pp. 26‒30 / 34‒44)</item>
            <item>III. The Turn (Der Doppelschlag) (pp. 30‒42 / 44‒70)</item>
          </list>
        </p>

        <p><hi rend="bold">Appendix (Anhang)</hi> (pp. 42‒43 / 71‒72)</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Publication History</head>

        <p><hi rend="bold">Original Edition</hi><lb/>Universal Edition's agreement to Schenker's
          editing of keyboard works by <ref cRef="entity-000025">C. P. E. Bach</ref> for its new
          series of "model editions" occurred in early March 1901 (OC 52/386). Schenker delivered
          the edited material to the publisher in late December of that year (OC 52/387), initially
          intending to preface it with an introduction. However, by the following July he proposed
          to UE that the introduction be published separately, presumably on grounds that it had
          become more extensive than expected. UE agreed to publish the introduction "in paperback"
            (<hi rend="italic">in Brochüren-Form</hi>) (OC 52/380, July 15, 1902), their intention
          being that the two should be published simultaneously (OC 52/6, August 26). In saying
          this, they identified the separate publication for the first time as "Ornamentik" as
          against "Einführung." Since Schenker continued to work on this document, UE eventually
          went ahead with printing the keyboard works, and this was released on February 10, 1903
          with the following brief prefatory statement: <cit>
            <q>The principles that have guided the editor of this edition of the keyboard works of
              C. P. E. Bach are set down in a special work that will appear shortly from Universal
              Edition under the title of "A Contribution to the Study of Ornamentation." / There the
              performer may seek information on anything here that at first might seem to him
              unusual or even strange.</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>The <title level="m">Beitrag zur Ornamentik</title> went to the printers on June 24,
          1903. Pre-publication copies were sent to Schenker on July 23 (OC 52/9); UE formally took
          possession of it from the printers the next day (Verlagsdruckbuch UE 812) in a print-run
          of 500 copies (matching the German print-run of the edition); and complimentary copies of
          the edition and its companion volume together were sent to selected people four days later
          (OC 52/10).</p>

        <p>It is noteworthy that, in a list of those to whom complimentary copies of the 1908
          revised edition should be sent, the first name after the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde
          Archive was that of <ref cRef="entity-000228">Jakob Fischer</ref>, with the comment "who
          was of great service in getting the first edition known."</p>

        <p><hi rend="bold">Revised Edition</hi><lb/> Five years later stocks of the original edition
          must have been running low, because on March 24, 1908, <ref cRef="entity-000356">Emil
            Hertzka</ref> wrote announcing that UE was "on the point of going into production with a
          new edition" (OC 52/383). Schenker responded the next day that he had some "small
          additions" and "glaring desiderata" (WSLB 1). Working into the night on his revisions
          (while also trying to finish <ref cRef="entity-001726"><title level="m"
              >Kontrapunkt</title> I</ref> for <ref cRef="entity-002405">Cotta</ref>), Schenker
          delivered the revised Part I on April 8 and the remainder on April 22 (diary, WSLB 3, 4).
          Having corrected three sets of proofs ("It is turning into such a practical hand-book for
          student and teacher," WSLB 5, May 21) Schenker gave his imprimatur on June 23. A print-run
          of 500 copies was delivered on August 24 (Verlagsdruckbuch UE 812), but an error came to
          light requiring an erratum slip, and release of the edition was delayed until late August
          and early September.</p>

        <p>As can be seen above, in its revision the work was expanded from 43 to 72 pages. The
          underlying structure was unchanged, but titles were introduced for the subsections, and
          the text largely retained verbatim, with occasional new paragraphs interpolated and
          several new music examples. The bulk of the expansion took place in the second section: a
          system of numbered paragraphs (§1, etc) being introduced within the existing subsections;
          many new music examples are interspersed among the text; many footnotes, some extremely
          long, are provided, and also brief marginal annotations. To this Schenker added a Foreword
          (dated "June 1908") in which he lauded <ref cRef="entity-000025">C. P. E. Bach</ref> as
          author of the <title level="m">Versuch über die wahre Art das Clavier zu spielen</title>
          and reminded the reader of the reverence that Haydn, Mozart and Beethoven had for its
          author.</p>

        <p>Demand for <title level="m">Ornamentik</title> continued after 1908, reissues of 300
          copies being made in each of 1914, 1921, 1926, 1930, and 1936, and even larger print-runs
          from 1954 onward, making a total of well over 4,000 copies before the end of the century
          (Verlagsdruckbuch UE 812).</p>
      </div>
    </body>


    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources and Further Reading</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><editor>Siegel, Hedi</editor>, transl. and ed., <title level="a">A Contribution to
              the Study of Ornamentation [by] Heinrich Schenker,</title>
            <title level="j">The Music Forum</title>, iv (1976), 1‒139</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Bent, Ian</author>, <title level="a">'That Bright New Light': Schenker,
              Universal Edition, and the Origins of the Erläuterung Series, 1901‒1910,</title>
            <title level="j">Journal of the American Musicological Society</title>, 58/1 (2005),
            esp. 71‒81</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Felix Salzer</author>, <title level="a">Über die Bedeutung der Ornamente in
              Philipp Emanuel Bachs Klavierwerken,</title>
            <title level="j">Zeitschrift für Musikwissenschaft</title>, 12/7 (April 1930), 398–418;
            Eng. transl. by <editor>Mark Stevens</editor> as <title level="a">The Significance of
              the Ornaments in Carl Philipp Emanuel Bach's Keyboard Works,</title>
            <title level="j">Theory and Practice</title>, 11 (1986), 15–42.</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Ernst Oster</author>, <title level="a">Vom Sinn des langen
              Vorschlags,</title>
            <title level="j">Der Dreiklang</title>, 6 (September 1937), 148‒57; Eng. transl. by
              <editor>Robert Kosovsky</editor> as <title level="a">On the meaning of the Long
              Appoggiatura,</title>
            <title level="j">Theory and Practice</title>, 7/1 (August 1982), 20–37.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributors</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author> with <author><hi rend="bold">Hedi
                Siegel</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <lb/>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
