<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-001733">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven (Erläuterungsausgabe)</title>
        <title type="sub">The Last Five Sonatas of Beethoven (Elucidatory Edition)</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="ea">Erläuterungsausgabe</term>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Work</term>
          <term subtype="basename">ea</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven (Erläuterungsausgabe)</head>
      <div>
        <p>Schenker's edition of four of the last five piano sonatas of Beethoven, published
          separately, and based in each case on surviving autograph manuscripts and early editions,
          and drawing on <ref cRef="entity-000636">Gustav Nottebohm</ref>'s publications and private
          notes. This edition is in each case accompanied by Schenker's elucidations (<hi
            rend="italic">Erläuterungen</hi>); these describe the sources, analyze structure and
          thematic content (with copious music examples, and in the case of Op. 101 Urlinien),
          provide detailed guidelines for performance, and encompass a survey of the previous
          secondary literature and editions. The four volumes were published by <ref
            cRef="entity-002408">Universal Edition</ref> of Vienna between 1913 and 1921.</p>

        <div>
          <head>First Edition</head>
          <p>The format of each volume is the same: <list type="simple">
              <item>— <hi rend="italic">Vorwort</hi>: a short, dated foreword</item>
              <item>— Schenker’s edition of the sonata</item>
              <item>— <hi rend="italic">Vorbemerkung zur Einführung</hi>: preliminary remarks, often
                polemical in character</item>
              <item>— <hi rend="italic">Einführung</hi>: an analysis of the sonata, section by
                section, along with detailed discussion of the autograph score, early editions, and,
                for Op. 110 and Op. 111, Beethoven's sketches</item>
              <item>— <hi rend="italic">Literatur</hi>: extracts from writings about the sonata by
                A. B. Marx, Wilhelm von Lenz, Willibald Nagel, Paul Bekker, and others, together
                with Schenker's dismissive remarks about them; for Op. 101, Schenker also quotes
                from and comments on Nottebohm's account of the sketches.</item>
            </list></p>

          <p>The motivation for this edition was to discredit the 19th-century editions, not only of
            these works but of those of the German and Austrian classical composers in general,
            against which Schenker had for many years polemicized; to show that with the exception
            of fingerings little or no editorial intervention was usually required ‒ i.e. that
            Beethoven's orthography, when correctly understood and explained, provided all that was
            needed for understanding a work's structure and performing it according to his wishes;
            and ultimately to reveal the processes of mind of a supreme "master" of musical
            composition ‒ to uncover the workings of genius.</p>

          <p>To underscore a novel approach to editing, which seeks to understand the composer's
            intentions through his orthography, Schenker planned to begin each volume with a
            "Vorrede," a general introduction to the series. This does not survive; and it is
            possible that Schenker was not intending to write it until he had received assurance
            from <ref cRef="entity-000356">Emil Hertzka</ref>, director of Universal Edition, that
            such an essay could be included. Hertzka, ever mindful of the negative impact that
            Schenker's polemical tone could have not only upon the project but also on his
            publishing house, evidently objected to the "Vorrede"; and it was abandoned shortly
            before the first volume (Op. 109) went into production. (Schenker sent Hertzka a revised
            version of the "Vorbemerkung zur Einführung" for Op. 109, to compensate for the loss of
            the "Vorrede.")</p>

          <p> Because these volumes were prepared for the most part during World War I, they served
            also as a principal vehicle for Schenker's German nationalist feelings, and his intense
            antipathy toward the nations of the West, and this polemical stratum of the work relates
            directly to the leading article <title level="a">Von der Sendung des deutschen
              Genies,</title> in the <ref cRef="entity-001740">first issue of <title level="j">Der
                Tonwille</title></ref> (1921), and his Preface to <ref cRef="entity-001727"><title
                level="m">Kontrapunkt</title> 2</ref> (1922). (Indeed, Schenker told Hertzka that
            his "Vorrede" was addressed to the "youth," i.e. a new generation of musicians; this
            word appears in the subtitle of the <ref cRef="entity-001739"><title level="j"
                >Tonwille</title></ref> pamphlets.)</p>

          <p>The five volumes of the work, which were to have been published one per year (contract:
            OC 52/494, August 25, 1912) but for the impact of the war upon both Schenker's research
            and the commerce of publishing, were: <listBibl>
              <bibl>
                <ref cRef="entity-001734"><title level="m">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven
                    ... op. 109</title> (1913)</ref>
              </bibl>
              <bibl>
                <ref cRef="entity-001735"><title level="m">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven
                    ... op. 110</title> (1914)</ref>
              </bibl>
              <bibl>
                <ref cRef="entity-001736"><title level="m">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven
                    ... op. 111</title> (1916)</ref>
              </bibl>
              <bibl>
                <ref cRef="entity-001737"><title level="m">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven
                    ... op. 101</title> (1921)</ref>
              </bibl>
              <bibl> Because he was unable to locate the autograph score of Op. 106 (the manuscript
                is presumed lost), Schenker did not complete the last number in the series, though
                he left voluminous notes on the sonata. (See under "English Translation and Study,"
                below.) </bibl>
            </listBibl></p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>New Edition</head>
        <p>A new edition was produced in four separate, smaller-format volumes in 1971–72 by <ref
            cRef="entity-000412">Oswald Jonas</ref>, pupil of Schenker and Hans Weisse. Jonas
          excised from Schenker's original all the polemical material and the entire discussion of
          the secondary literature, and also replaced Schenker's editions of the sonatas by Erwin
          Ratz's edition of 1945 with the effect that the scores contradict some of the textual
          argument in Schenker's elucidations. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>English Translation and Study</head>
        <p>The recent English translation by John Rothgeb is likewise in four separate, small-format
          volumes and a website: <lb/><lb/><bibl><title level="m">Beethoven's Last Piano Sonatas: An
              Edition with Elucidation</title>, transl., ed. and annotated by <editor>John
              Rothgeb</editor> (New York: Oxford University Press, 2015)</bibl>
          <listBibl>
            <bibl><title level="m">Piano Sonata in E major, Op. 109</title></bibl>
            <bibl><title level="m">Piano Sonata in A-flat major, Op. 110</title></bibl>
            <bibl><title level="m">Piano Sonata in C minor, Op. 111</title></bibl>
            <bibl><title level="m">Piano Sonata in A major, Op. 101</title></bibl>
            <bibl>http://www.oup.com/us/beethovenslastpianosonatas [secondary literature
              only]</bibl>
          </listBibl></p>

        <p>This edition follows the text of Schenker's original, thereby restoring all the material
          excised by Jonas in his 1970‒71 edition. Significantly, it incorporates numerous
          annotations made by Schenker in his personal copies of the volumes (now in the Oster
          Collection). There are, in addition, explanatory and citational footnotes by Rothgeb, some
          of which incorporate observations made by Jonas. Schenker's surveys of the secondary
          literature appear not in the print volumes but on the website. The scores of the sonatas,
          however, appear neither in the print volume nor on the website.</p>

        <p>Complementary to this edition is the study by Nicholas Marston of Schenker's unpublished
          draft texts and sketches (now in the Oster Collection, OC 65) concerning Op. 106:
          <lb/><lb/><bibl><author>Marston, Nicholas</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker and
              Beethoven's 'Hammerklavier' Sonata</title>, <title level="s">Royal Music Association
              Monographs</title> 23 (Farnham, Surrey: Ashgate, with the Royal Musical Association,
            1913)</bibl>.</p>

      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Bibliography</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Bent, Ian</author>, <title level="a">'That Bright New Light': Schenker,
              Universal Edition, and the Origins of the Erläuterung Series, 1901–1910,</title>
            <title level="j">Journal of the American Musicological Society</title> LVIII/1 (Spring
            2005), 69–138 </bibl>
          <bibl><author>Drabkin, William</author>, <title level="a">The New
              Erläuterungsausgabe,</title>
            <title level="j">Perspectives of New Music</title> 12 (1971–72), 319–30 </bibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Note:</hi> Much of the evidence for the genesis and publication
            history of this work is contained in the <hi rend="bold">correspondence</hi> between
            Schenker and Universal Edition and in Schenker's <hi rend="bold">diaries</hi> in the
            period 1913‒16 and 1919‒21. The <hi rend="bold">correspondence</hi> for January to July
            1913 is at present available on the old SDO website
            (http://mt-extra.ccnmtl.columbia.edu/cgi-bin/mt-search.cgi?tag=UE%20~%20HSchenker&amp;Template=schenker&amp;SearchResultDisplay=ascend&amp;limit=500&amp;blog_id=28),
            and will be transferred to the current website. The <hi rend="bold">diaries</hi> for
            1919‒21 are already on the current site, and those for 1913‒14 will appear there within
            the next two years from the time of writing (March 2016).</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Ian Bent</author> and <author>William Drabkin</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl><lb/>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
