<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OC 44/9 : 10-27-34 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Oswald Jonas, published here with kind permission.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> Permission to publish on this website granted by the heirs of Oswald Jonas, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1934-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-1938) - -Oster, Ernst (1938-c.1939)—New York Public Library (c.1939-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Oswald Jonas; Image: New York Public Library, New York; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 10/27/1934 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated October 27, 1934</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-10-02</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Acks OJ 5/18, 59 and 60; Hoboken has no reason to complain about his behaviour. —As a result of Hoboken's distribution of complimentary copies, J has received letters of appreciation. —Reacts critically to Willi Reich and his magazine 23.  —Describes plans for forthcoming events in Hamburg.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Jonas, Oswald; Schenker, Heinrich;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  Photogrammarchiv;  journal;  Hamburg;  Leipzig;  Berlin;  Köln;  Cologne;  Gieseking, Walter;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Ney, Elly;  23—eine Wiener Musikzeitschrift;  Reich, Willi;  Universal-Edition;  UE;  Handel;  Lichtenberg, Georg Christoph</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker dated October 27, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>27. Okt. 34.
Sehr veehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Zunächst meinen herzlichsten Dank für Ihre beiden freundlichen Briefe.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  OJ 5/18, 59 and 60, October 16 and 25, 1934.</tei:note>  Ihre Mitteilung im ersten Schreiben, daß Sie vom +Ehepaar+ Hob.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> wenig zustimmendes über mich gehört haben, bestätigt mir nun die Richtigkeit meiner Vermutung.  Schreiben ist dgl. wirklich vielleicht nicht geeignet und so will ich mir das Weitere auch aufsparen, wenn einmal wieder Gelegenheit zu mündlicher Aussprache da ist.  H. hat jedenfalls keine&lt;strike&gt;n&lt;/strike&gt; Ursache, sich über mein Betragen zu beklagen, da er mich grundlos belästigt und verdächtigt hat.  Das müßte er wohl verstehen.  Daß er jetzt mit dem Plan einer Archiv Zeitschrift<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  See OJ 12/6, [32], June 11, 1934, and 5/18, 59 and 60, October 16 and 25.</tei:note> herausrückt, mit dem ich ihm schon oft gekommen bin, ist vielleicht bezeichnend.  Nun, wird etwas daraus und benötigt er mich, so wird er sich ja an mich wenden.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Seine 200 Exempl. hat er seinerzeit zur Verfügung gestellt, um Persönlichkeiten, Bibliotheken und Lehranstalten zu beteiligen.  Es wird auch eine ganze Reihe teils sehr netter Dankschreiben eingetroffen.  (Hambg, Leipzig, Berlin, Köln etc, dann habe ich sehr nette Schreiben von Gieseking,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Walter Gieseking [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> den ich übrigens heute im Furtw.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Wilhelm Furtwängler [creat biogfile and link].</tei:note> Konzert gesprochen habe, und Elly Ney,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Elly Ney (1882–1968), German pianist, pupil of Leschetizky and Sauer in Vienna, noted as an interpreter of Beethoven, Chopin, and Brahms.  </tei:note> die mir auch für ihren heutigen Abend eine Karte geschickt hat.)</tei:p><tei:p>Gestern bekam ich von meinem Vetter die letzte Nummer des Käseblattes “23” – die Sie wahrscheinlich auch nun schon gesehen haben werden.  Voll dummen Zeugs und schmutziger Pöbeleien.  Wegen der Worte “Dr Jonas lügt bewußt” wird [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg. word</tei:hi>] Herr Reich<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Willi Reich (1898-1980), Austrian writer on music and biographer of Alban Berg, writer of monographs on Bartók, Berg, Schoenberg, and other topics.  He completed a dissertation on Martini at the University of Vienna in 1934, was a pupil of Berg 1927–35, and served as music critic for several newpapers in Vienna and abroad.  The journal referred to here, <tei:hi rend="italic">23—eine Wiener Musikzeitschrift</tei:hi>, which was edited by him (1932–37), criticised the Viennese musical world, and championed the Second Viennese School vigorously;  in the June 1933 issue, Reich criticized National Socialism.  </tei:note> jedenfalls wegen Ehrenbeleidigung zu verantworten haben.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  This objectionable statement read precisely: “. . . an dieser Stelle lügt Herr Dr. Jonas ganz bewußt” (“. . . at this point Dr. Jonas lies completely consciously”).  See Willi Reich, “Kant, Schenker, und der Nachläufer,” in <tei:hi rend="italic">23</tei:hi> 15-16 (1934), p. 32.  An account of this matter by Milton Babbitt (see “‘My Vienna Triangle at Washington Square’ Revised and Dilated,” in Stephen Peles, ed., <tei:hi rend="italic">The Collected Essays of Milton Babbitt</tei:hi> [Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2003], 466-487, is not quite accurate; according to Babbitt, the “critical imputation” at which Jonas took umbrage was that “Brahms was a source, a root (<tei:hi rend="italic">eine Wurzel</tei:hi>), of Schoenberg’s composition” [p. 477].  The imputation was, rather, the more serious calumny of Jonas’s having lied.  See also OJ 12/6, [39], September 28, 1934, especially note 2.)</tei:note> Mein Vetter<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Dr. Fritz Ungar, owner of Saturn-Verlag, the publisher of <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks: Eine Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers</tei:hi> (Vienna: Saturn-Verlag, 1934).  Cf. OJ 12/6, [13], [15], [37], and [43].</tei:note> wird sich übrigens der Klage anschließen.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Das Wiener Musikliteraturpack ist wohl so ziemlich das niedrigste von der Welt.  Herr Reich hat sogar teilweise sein Herz für Schenker entdeckt, mindestens für die wertvollen Originalausgaben.  Da dürfte das Pack wahrscheinlich ^sonst^ ein Veto der U.E. gefürchtet haben, die sich nicht gern das Geschäft mit den Beeth. Sonaten verderben lassen wird.</tei:p><tei:p>– Furtw. war auch zu mir heute rührend nett im Konzert und hat mich für nächste Woche eingeladen.  Daß er unter allem sehr leidet, ist sicher.  – Er gab&lt;strike&gt;e&lt;/strike&gt; u. a. ein wunderbares Concerto grosso von Händel mit Solo Violine und  Cello. –</tei:p><tei:p>Ich hoffe, daß in Hamburg jetzt etwas mehr zusammenkommt, 1-2 Kurse sollen jetzt eingerichtet werden und bei einer Pianistin Fromm-Michaels<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Apparently a Hamburg-based pianist.  OJ 12/6, [30], mentions a “Frau Michaels” for whom (or for whose class) Jonas might give a “course”; OJ 12/6, [39], September 28, 1934 refers to a “Frau Fromm” for whom he gave a lecture in Hamburg.  Probably Michaels, Fromm, and the Fromm-Michaels cited here are the same persion.</tei:note> (Violin<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Click on <ref cRef="violin_moriz">Moriz Violin</ref>.</tei:note> sehr gut bekannt) soll ich das nächste Mal einen Vortrag halten.  Ich denke, daß es nun doch gehen wird.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Jedenfalls lasse ich mich noch lange nicht unterkriegen!!! – Schön ist das Ihnen zugekommene Wort von Lichtenberg!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Georg Christoph Lichtenberg (1742-1799), German physicist and author.</tei:note>  Auch Folgendes, mir neues, fand ich unlängst:</tei:p><tei:p>“Wer eine Wissenschaft noch nicht so inne hat, daß der jeden Verstoß dagegen fühlt wie einen grammatikalischen Fehler in seiner Muttersprache, der hat noch viel zu lernen.”</tei:p><tei:p>Empfehlen Sie mich bitte Ihrer verehrten Frau Gemahlin und seien Sie ergebenst gegrußt
von Ihren stets dankbaren
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker dated October 27, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>October 27, 1934
Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>First my warmest thanks for your two cordial letters.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  The information in your first post, that you had heard little concurrence with me from the Hoboken<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> <tei:hi rend="italic">couple</tei:hi>, confirms the accuracy of my assumption.  The written word is perhaps not suited to such matters, and so I will save further discussion until we again have an opportunity to talk.  Hoboken has in any case no reason to complain about my behavior, since he has harassed me and accused me without cause.  He must have understood that.  That he now comes out with the plan for an archive journal,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> which I have often put before him, is perhaps indicative.  Well, if something comes of it and he needs me, then he will call on me.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> He had at the time made his  two hundred copies available in order to secure the participation of personalities, libraries, and academic institutions.  A whole series of thank-you messages, partly very nice, has been received.  ([From] Hamburg, Leipzig, Berlin, Cologne, etc.; and I have very nice letters from Gieseking,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> with whom I spoke, incidentally, at the Furtwängler<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> concert today, and from Elly Ney,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> who also sent me an invitation to her soirée this evening.)</tei:p><tei:p>Yesterday I received from my cousin the last issue of the rag <tei:hi rend="italic">23</tei:hi>— which you probably will also have seen.  Full of stupid trash and dirty skulduggery. Mr. Reich<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> will [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg. word</tei:hi>] have to answer for the words “Dr. Jonas lies consciously” on grounds of character assassination.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/>  My cousin,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> incidentally, will join in the suit.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> The Viennese music-literature gang is surely the lowest in the world.  Mr. Reich even partly opened his heart for Schenker, at least for the valuable original editions.  There the gang may probably have otherwise feared a veto by Universal-Edition, who would not take lightly the loss of business with the Beethoven sonatas.</tei:p><tei:p>Furtwängler was touchingly nice to me at the concert and has invited me for next week.  That he is hard pressed by everything is beyond doubt.  —He presented among other things a wonderful concerto grosso by Handel with solo violin and cello.</tei:p><tei:p>I hope that in Hamburg now a few more things will come together; one or two courses are now to be organized, and with a lady pianist Fromm-Michaels<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> (very well known to Violin<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/>) I will give a lecture next time.  I think it will now work out.  In any case I won’t let it get me down!</tei:p><tei:p>The Lichtenberg<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> quotation you came across is beautiful!  I also found the following recently, which is new to me:</tei:p><tei:p>“Anybody who is not yet so completely at one with a science that any infraction against it feels to him like a grammatical error in his mother tongue has much still to learn.”</tei:p><tei:p>Please commend me to your esteemed wife and be most humbly greeted
by your ever grateful
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>