<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OC 1A/pp. 27-29 : 9-25-13 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  In the public domain.
©  Transcription Ian Bent, 2007.
©  Translation Ian Bent, 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1913-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-1938) - -Oster, Ernst (1938-c.1939)—New York Public Library (c.1939-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: in the public domain; Image: New York Public Library; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 09/25/1913 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Newlov ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Carbon copy of handwritten letter from Schenker to Miss Newlov, dated September 25, 1913</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-11-01</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>S challenges the latest missive from Newlov and sets out proof, based on itemized letters in his possession, that she has consistently paid in arrears between 15th and 20th of the month, and that is not the practice of his pupils and is unacceptable.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Newlov, Fräulein;  Newlov, Frau;  fee;  honorarium; arrears;  Paneveggio;  Briefkasten;  letterbox;  carpenter;  Polish baron</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Carbon copy of handwritten letter from Schenker to Newlov, dated September 25, 1913</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in top margin:</tei:hi>]  Eine frdl. Antwort erbitte ich [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg. word</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>Verehrtes Frl. v. Newlov!</tei:p><tei:p>Über Ihre l.[ieben] Zeilen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  No letter from Newlov is recorded in the diary, and no letters from Newlov to S are known to survive.  </tei:note> bin ich sehr, sehr überrascht u. auch beleidigt.  Sie sollten mich, wie alle übrigen Schüler von mir, soweit kennen, um zu wissen, daß ich nicht ein schon bezahltes Honorar noch einmal verlang[e.]  Da Sie mir aber nicht glauben, so muß ich sagen, daß ich <tei:hi rend="italic">Beweise</tei:hi> für meine Behauptung <tei:hi rend="italic">in der Hand habe</tei:hi>.  Die Beweise sind <tei:hi rend="italic">Ihre eigenen Briefe</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  “Ihre eigenen Briefe” (your own letters): double-underlined.</tei:note> u. die <tei:hi rend="italic">Kopien der meinen</tei:hi>.  Es ist meine Art, strengste Ordnung in sämtlichen Briefen, Korrespondenzen, Ansichtskarten, Rechnungen, Sendungen, Rez[?] einzuhalten von sämtlichen Personen, die [mir] schreiben u. auch von sämtlichen Schülern.  Dehnt sich die Sammlung auf ungezählte Jahre aus, so daß ich an 20000 Briefe auf- <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> [bew]ahre.  So besitze ich also auch von Ihnen sämtliche <tei:hi rend="italic">Briefe, Zettel, Postanweistagen, kurz Alles</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  “Alles” (everything): double-underlined.  Despite this claim, in fact none of the letters from Newlov to S survive in the Oswald Jonas Memorial Collection, as would have been expected.</tei:note> was Sie mir, seitdem ich das Vergnügen habe, Sie zu kennen, <tei:hi rend="italic">geschrieben haben</tei:hi>.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich besitze einen Brief vom <tei:hi rend="italic">November</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  “November”: double-underlined.  </tei:note> des Jahres 1912,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  No letters from Newlov to S are known to survive.  This letter, which must predate November 15, 1912, s not recorded in S’s diary, but receipt of Newlov’s fee for October is recorded on November 21, 1912, with the remark that S will have to keep a careful eye on the dates in order to avoid forfeiting the fee for June (OJ 1/11, p. 282).  </tei:note> worin Sie um <tei:hi rend="italic">Entschulidgung bitten</tei:hi>, daß Sie noch das Honorar <tei:hi rend="italic">für Oktober</tei:hi> schulden, u. indem Sie bitten, bis nach <tei:hi rend="italic">dem 15^ten^ Nov</tei:hi>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  “dem 15^ten^ Nov“ (November 15): double-underlined.  </tei:note> zu <tei:hi rend="italic">warten</tei:hi>, dieses erste Honorar der Saison haben Sie also ^Mitte November^ <tei:hi rend="italic">für Oktober</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  “für Oktober” (October): double-underlined.  </tei:note> erlegt!  Und wenn ich auch Ihren Brief, den ich besitze, nicht wirklich hätte, so würde dennoch Jedermann verstehen, daß ein zwischen 15 u. 20 des Monats erlegtes Honorar niemals für den laufenden Monat, sondern offenbar verspätet für den früheren Monat erlegt wurde.</tei:p><tei:p>Diesen Zahlmodus haben Sie in den folgenden Monaten bis Juni beibehalten, wofür ich wieder allerhand Beweise habe.  Immer <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> zahlten Sie zwischen 15 u. 20, u. immer für den <tei:hi rend="italic">früheren</tei:hi> Monat.  Ich habe Schüler, die im Vorhinein zahlen, aber sie zahlen am 1^ten^ für den laufenden Monat;  ich habe Schüler, die im Nachhinein zahlen, aber sie zahlen am 1^ten^ fur den früheren Monat.  Sie allein genoßen, weil Sie darum baten, das Recht, <tei:hi rend="italic">im Nachhinein um 3 Wochen später</tei:hi> zu zahlen.</tei:p><tei:p>Folglich hat Ihr Honorar, das Sie [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg. word</tei:hi>] im Juni bezahlt haben, für <tei:hi rend="italic">Mai</tei:hi> gegolten, u. das Honorar für Juni habe ich eben nicht erhalten, weshalb ich es erbitte.  Im vorigen Jahr haben Sie mir einen kleinen Rest nach <tei:hi rend="italic">Paneveggio</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  S and Jeanette spent the summer months of 1912 in Paneveggio, a resort in the South Tyrol, departing Vienna on June 29, and arriving back in Vienna on September 5 (OJ 1/11, pp. 205, 224).</tei:note> geschickt, aber heuer<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  “heuer” (this year):  Austrian, Southern German, and Swiss usage.  </tei:note> blieb bis &lt;strike&gt;zur Stunde&lt;/strike&gt; ^heute^ der letzte Monat unbeglichen.</tei:p><tei:p>Übrigens irren Sie sich, wenn Sie meinen, daß Sie das Honorar im Juni nur in den Briefkasten geworfen haben.  Sie haben es mir vielmehr <tei:hi rend="italic">selbst</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">in die Hand</tei:hi> gegebe[n.] <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Sie erinnern sich ja, daß ich Ihnen schrieb, Sie sollten[?] das Honorar <tei:hi rend="italic">nicht in den Briefkasten</tei:hi> werfen, weil der Briefkasten nicht in Ordnung war.  Sie antworteten mir in einem Briefe, den ich <tei:hi rend="italic">natürlich habe</tei:hi>, daß Sie es <tei:hi rend="italic">nicht tun</tei:hi> werden.  Laut Rechnung des Tischlermeisters wurde der Briefkasten am <tei:hi rend="italic">19. Juni</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  “19. Juni” (June 19): double-underlined.  </tei:note> in Ordnung gebracht.  Nachher übergaben Sie mir das Honorar, <tei:hi rend="italic">persönlich</tei:hi>, eben das Honorar für <tei:hi rend="italic">Mai</tei:hi>.  Denn Sie haben <tei:hi rend="italic">laut Ihren eigenen Briefen</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">niemals</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">im Vorhinein</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  “niemals im Vorhinein” (never ... in advance): double-underlined.  </tei:note> gezahlt.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich glaube, daß dieses genügen muß, um die Wahrhaftigkeit meiner Forderung zu erweisen.  Mir wäre es peinlich, wenn Sie den Beweisen aus Ihrer eigenen Hand nicht glauben wollten.</tei:p><tei:p>Erst einmal, im Laufe der vielen, vielen Jahre meiner Lehrertätigkeit, ist mir <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> in einem solchen Fall – es handelte sich um einen polnischen Baron<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Polish baron: [identify].  </tei:note> – vorgekommen, daß ich die Hilfe eines Advokaten u.s.w. in Anspruch nehmen mußte.  Der Baron hat selbstverständlich sofort die Schuld beglichen u. mir einen 16 Seiten [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] langen Brief voll Dankes u. Zärtlichkeit geschickt.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich will hoffen, daß sich selbst auf all das oben dargestellte nun besinnen, u. einsehen, daß ich nichts Unrechtes fordere.</tei:p><tei:p>Darüber kann sich auch Ihre Frau <tei:hi rend="italic">Mama</tei:hi> ganz u. gar <tei:hi rend="italic">nicht</tei:hi> aufregen – was jeder Professor gerne bestätigen wird –, es ist ja aus ein Misverständnis Ihrerseits, u. Sie sollen <tei:hi rend="italic">auch diesen Brief ruhig Ihrer Frau <tei:hi rend="italic">Mama</tei:hi> zeigen</tei:hi>.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit besten Grüßen an Sie u. Ihre Frau <tei:hi rend="italic">Mama</tei:hi>
Ihr erg[e]b[ener]
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] H Schenker
25. September 1913</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Carbon copy of handwritten letter from Schenker to Newlov, dated September 25, 1913</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in top margin:</tei:hi>]  I request a kind response [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg. word</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>Esteemed Miss von Newlov,</tei:p><tei:p>I am very, very surprised, and indeed affronted, at your est’d missive.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  You ought, like all my other pupils, to be well enough acquainted with me to know that I never demand a fee that has already been paid.   Since, however, you do not believe me, I am bound to say that I <tei:hi rend="italic">have proof in my hands</tei:hi> for my assertion.  The proof consists of <tei:hi rend="italic">your own letters</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> and the <tei:hi rend="italic">copies of mine</tei:hi>.  It is my practise to maintain the most stringent order with all letters, correspondences, picture-postcards, accounts, dispatches, [and] reviews[?] from all the people who write to me, and also from all my pupils.  The collection extends back over innumerable years, so that I have close to 20,000 lettters <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> on file.  I therefore have in my possession all your <tei:hi rend="italic">letters, notes, postal order dates, in short everything</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> that you <tei:hi rend="italic">have written</tei:hi> to me since I have had the pleasure of your acquaintance.</tei:p><tei:p>I have in my possession a letter from <tei:hi rend="italic">November</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> of the year 1912<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> in which you <tei:hi rend="italic">apologize</tei:hi> for still owing the fee <tei:hi rend="italic">for October</tei:hi>, and in that you ask [to be allowed] to <tei:hi rend="italic">wait</tei:hi> until after <tei:hi rend="italic">November 15</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> you therefore paid this first fee of the season for <tei:hi rend="italic">October</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> ^in mid-November^!  And even if I were not actually to have your letter, as I do, in my possession, nevertheless, anybody would understand that a fee paid between the 15th and 20th of the month was never once for the current month but obviously in arrears for the previous month.</tei:p><tei:p>You persisted with this manner of payment in the months that followed, as far as June, and again I have a ample evidence to this effect.  Every time, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> you paid between the 15th and 20th, and every time for the <tei:hi rend="italic">previous</tei:hi> month.  I have pupils who pay in advance, but they pay on the 1st for the current month;  I have pupils who pay in arrears, but they pay on the 1st for the preceding month.   You are the only one who has enjoyed, because you asked for it, the right to pay <tei:hi rend="italic">in arrears, three weeks later</tei:hi>.</tei:p><tei:p>Consequently, the fee that you paid [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg. word</tei:hi>] in June was attributable to <tei:hi rend="italic">May</tei:hi>, and I have not yet received the fee for June, which is why I am asking for it. In the previous year you sent me a small amount of the remaining sum to Paneveggio,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> but this year<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> up to &lt;strike&gt;this minute&lt;/strike&gt; ^today^ the last month has remained unpaid.</tei:p><tei:p>Incidentally, you are in error in thinking that in June you merely put your fee in my letterbox.  Rather, you put it <tei:hi rend="italic">straight into my hand</tei:hi>.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> You surely recall that I wrote you that you should <tei:hi rend="italic">not</tei:hi> put it <tei:hi rend="italic">in the letterbox</tei:hi> because the letterbox was out of order.  You answered me in a letter—which I <tei:hi rend="italic">of course have</tei:hi>—that you would <tei:hi rend="italic">not do</tei:hi> so.  According to the carpenter’s account, the letterbox was repaired on <tei:hi rend="italic">June 19</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/>  After that, you handed me the fee <tei:hi rend="italic">in person</tei:hi>, but that was the fee for <tei:hi rend="italic">May</tei:hi>.  For you have <tei:hi rend="italic">never</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">according to your own letters</tei:hi>, paid <tei:hi rend="italic">in advance</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/></tei:p><tei:p>I think this should suffice to demonstrate the veracity of my demand.  I would find it embarrassing if you were unprepared to believe the proof in your own hand.</tei:p><tei:p>Only once before in the many, many years of my activity as a teacher <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> was I obliged in such a case—it concerned a Polish baron<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/>—to avail myself of the services of an attorney, etc.  The baron, needless to say, settled the debt immediately and sent me a sixteen-page letter full of thanks and endearment.</tei:p><tei:p>I hope that you will now recall for yourself all that I have laid out above, and appreciate that I am demanding nothing improper.</tei:p><tei:p>There is <tei:hi rend="italic">no</tei:hi> reason for your mother to be in the slightest upset over this—as any Professor will gladly confirm—it has in fact arisen out of a misunderstanding on your part, and you ought <tei:hi rend="italic">even to show this letter calmly to your mother</tei:hi>.</tei:p><tei:p>With best wishes to you and your mother,
Yours truly,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] H. Schenker
25. September 1913</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>