<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OC 12/15-17 : 5-6-24 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain; published with the permission of the heirs of August Halm, March 2006.
© Transcription Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
©  Translation Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Lee Rothfarb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2000, and is published with the permission of the heirs of August Halm, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1924-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-1938) - -Oster, Ernst (1938-c.1939)—New York Public Library (c.1939-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In public domain; Image: New York Public Library, New York; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 05/06/1924 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Halm ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated April 7/April 14/ May 6, 1924</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-07-26</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>H asks S to point out an instance of non-genius in his [H's] music;  asserts that foreground (=corporeality) has been neglected in favor of the background (=spirituality) in music;  defends Kurth against S's critical remarks in DLA
69.930/12 (April 3, 1924)? —  Suggests explanation for Bruckner classroom incident; will send parts of [A major] String Quartet and promises copy of Von Grenzen und Ländern. — Accepts offer of assistance with publication costs; comments on Reger.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Halm, August; Schenker, Heinrich;  non-genius;  Vordergrundmusik;  foreground music;  Hintergrund;  background;  Körperlichkeit;  corporeality;  das Geistige;  spirituality;  Gefühl;  feeling;  Beethoven;  Religiöses Gefühl;  religious feeling;  Bruckner;  Kurth, Ernst;  string quartet;  Von Grenzen und Ländern;  publication costs;  Urlinie;  Der Tonwille;  Op. 101;  Wyneken;  Hildesheim;  Reger</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker dated May 6, 1924</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>7. IV. 24.</tei:p><tei:p>Lieber u. verehrter Herr Professor!</tei:p><tei:p>So war das mit der Öffentlichkeit von mir nicht gemeint, daß die Leserschaft als Instanz gelten soll, sondern so, daß sie sehen soll, wie eine anständig geführte Fehde aussieht, in der ein Gegner auch mal gern Unrecht hat, d.h. dankbar ist wenn er bessere Einsicht bekennt.  Wenn Sie sich aber die Mühe machen, mir in einem Brief diese u. jene Stelle zu zeigen, wo ich ausrutschte, u. die Nichtgenialität meiner Musik <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> sich offenbart, so ist mirs auch so recht.  Es sind nicht viele Fälle nötig aufzuweisen, denn ich vermute von vornherein, daß mir das fehlt was Sie meinen, oder ich halte es doch für sehr möglich.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  No paragraph-break in the original.</tei:note>  “Vordergrundmusik” – ein guter Ausdruck, den ich, je nach Befund, wohl auch für meine Musik akzeptieren würde mit ^viel^ Bescheidenheit sowohl als mit ^etwas^ Stolz, d.h.:  ich glaube schon lang, daß das Vordergründliche oder Oberfläch&lt;strike&gt;lich&lt;/strike&gt;^ige^ über dem <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Hinter- u. Untergründlichen, oder die Körperlichkeit über dem Geistigen vernachlässigt worden ist.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">   Neither “vordergründlich” nor “oberflächig”—the latter very deliberately used (NB the crossed-out letters “liche” in order to produce “oberflächig “)—are proper German.  Correct would be “vordergründig” and “oberflächlich.”  Halm rejected the latter because of its negative connotation (superficial), and coins "oberflächig" to mean surface detail.  Similarly, Halm writes "vordergründlich" because "vordergründig" means superficial, simplistic.</tei:note>  Sie sagen dagegen:  alles ist nur ein Körper, u. darin liegt gerade die Genialiatät. Zugegeben:  aber darum doch noch nicht <tei:hi rend="italic">eo ipso</tei:hi> die Schönheit – die ist auch Etwas!  Unschöne Phsyiognomie, Körperteile sind biologisch ebenso ein Wunder wie schöne.  Gefühl:  werde ich keineswegs ausschalten, spreche aber, wie sichs gehört, nur privatim davon.  Die Erkenntnis, die Tatsachen aufzeigt, wird ja doch auch vom Gefühl geleitet.  Die Tatsachen präsentiert man dann in der Hoffnung, oder auf gut Glück, daß sie bei dem Leser ins <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Gefühl zurückleiten, dieses speisen.  Tatsachen: ich habe stets gesagt:  was ich über Beethovens Musik schreibe, halte ich für unwiederlegbar; dagegen bin ich stets gewärtig, daß noch andere Gewichte in die Wagschalen geworfen werden; das Steigen u. Sinken dieser ist nicht endgiltig.  Was Sie von Beethoven anführen, ist mir, fast alles, wertvoll, ich bewundere es, zum Teil beglückt es mich, so z.B. eben die in Ihrem letzten Brief angeführte Stelle.</tei:p><tei:p>Religiöses Gefühl gegenüber der Musik:  eben aus diesem heraus meine ich die Musik sei an sich geistig, u. man müßte sie nicht noch extra vergeistigen.  Die unmittelbare Erscheinung, der Vordergrund, ist mir deshalb so wichtig.  Bruckner hat die Unschuld wiedergewonnen (die Klassiker hatten’s zu eilig).  Seine Volltaktigkeit, seine Solidität (Anfang mit I,,) rechne ich ^ihm^ gerade zur Größe an.  Was Sie erzählen (von der Steigerung) -ist gewiß- ^scheint zuerst^ tief bedenklich, <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> macht micht aber nicht irre [<tei:hi rend="italic">written in the left margin, top to bottom:</tei:hi> Einfachste Erklärung:  Er schätzte Sie u. wollte Ihnen eine schöne Stelle zeigen u. tat dies unter ungeschicktem Vorwand.]  – ich sehe zuviel von Struktur u. Bewußtheit, Willen u.  Können – ich habe da doch wohl einen ordentlich gefüllten Sack voll Tatsachen herbeigeschleppt – u. könnte noch manche Bögen füllen.  Aber wäre es selbst so, daß es sich nur um “herrliche Musikbilder” handelte – das ist ^ja^ vor allem das, was uns nach den Klassikern nottat; Musik der reinen Gegenwart.  Aber wie gesagt, ich bestreite, daß es <tei:hi rend="italic">bloß</tei:hi> das ist, u. glaube das Gegenteil erwiesen zu haben.</tei:p><tei:p>Dr. Kurth,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Ernst Kurth [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> Ich denke, er sagt doch wohl einiges mehr als wie Sie es darstellen, u. dieses Mehr scheint mir wichtig.  Der “Stoß,” den Sie führten, hat mir also sein Bild nicht umgeworfen, aber <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> Sie dürfen keine Sorge haben, daß ich so was nicht aushielte.  Was mir einer umwerfen kann, das mag nur umfallen; sowohl meine eigene Musik als ihre Stützen u. Hilfen.  Es freut mich immer, wenn jemand meine Musik gefällt; beweise man mir, daß er nichts versteht, so ist mirs doch willkommen, ihm Freude zu bereiten. [<tei:hi rend="italic">written vertically in the left margin, top to bottom:</tei:hi> Es ist gewiß <tei:hi rend="italic">möglich</tei:hi>, daß jemand meine Musik gefällt, der wenig von Musik versteht, ja auch jemand, der diese meine Musik selbst nicht versteht.]  Schon lang, schon beim ersten Kennenlernen Ihrer Schriften, merkte ich den Unterschied; Sie sind viel mehr esoterisch als ich.</tei:p><tei:p>— Die Quartettstimmen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  The parts of H’s A-major String Quartet, as promised in OC 12/10–12, February 1–6, 1924.  S has agreed to receive them, DLA 69.930/12, April 3, 1924, and to comment on the work in a forthcoming letter.</tei:note> sende ich demnächst ab. Wenn Sie bei einer Probe zuhören, so beeinflussen Sie doch, so gut es geht, die Spieler, daß sie <tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> nicht hetzen.  Im allgemeinen finde ich, daß die Spieler stets schnelleres Tempo nehmen als ich es meine (Temperaments-Surrogat!).  Von Grenzen u. Ländern<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Halm, <tei:hi rend="italic">Von Grenzen und Ländern der Musik</tei:hi> (Munich: Georg Müller, 1916).  H mentions it in OC 12/10–12, February 1–6, 1924, and in DLA 69.930/12, April 3, 1924, S admits that he does not know it, and promises a copy of of his <tei:hi rend="italic">Erläuterungsausgabe</tei:hi> of Beethoven’s Op. 101 (1920) in return if H sends it (see below).</tei:note> will ich Ihnen durch den Verlag zusenden lassen.  <tei:hi rend="italic">Noch nicht</tei:hi> geschrieben haben Sie mir, was Sie von meiner <tei:hi rend="italic">Kammermusik</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">nicht haben</tei:hi>  (IV., V. Heft?).<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  “Noch nicht” “Kammermusik nicht haben”: underlining, also heavy sidelining, probably done by Schenker.</tei:note>  [<tei:hi rend="italic">written in the top margin, inverted:</tei:hi>  Am liebsten ließe ich Ihnen die Stimmen mit den andern Heften zusammen zusenden, also bitte schreiben Siebald darüber.]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  No paragraph-break in the original.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Einen Beitrag für Drucklegungen nehme ich, wenn Sie eine entsprechend[e] Stiftung, oder ähnl., zur Verfügung haben, gern an<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  In DLA 69.930/12, April 3, 1924, S writes: “It is not impossible that I could be able to send you a payment for your purposes.”  This seems a somewhat ungracious reply.</tei:note> – ich darf doch aus dem Angebot (wenn ein solches mal in betracht kommt) schließen, daß Sie m. Musik veröffentlicht wünschen, u. daß Ihnen nicht eine andere bekannt ist, die es nach Ihrem Urteil mehr <tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> verdient als meine.  Immerhin denke ich, Sie sollten in solchem Fall, wo Sie z.B. entschieden haben, etwas von <tei:hi rend="italic">Ihren</tei:hi> Schriften veröffentlichen, wo die Verleger versagen oder gar hindern (ich habe mit Bedauern u. aufrichtiger Teilnahme von Ihren Schwierigkeiten mit dieser Gesellschaft<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  This must be in response to S's remark in DLA 69.903/12, April 3, 1924: "wie schwelgen da die Sargen der Juden Hertzka, Kalmus u. Bruder usw!" (how the coffers of the Jews Hertzka, Kalmus and Bros, etc. bulge there!): S and his lawyer were threatening to go to the courts at this time with charges of breach of contract: see <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</tei:hi>, Eng. trans., vol. II (New York, Oxford University Press, 2005), General Preface, pp. v-xii.  </tei:note> gelesen u. kann mir wohl denken, daß Sie ^da^ nur eine kleine Vorhang-Spalte von einer sehr unsauberen Geschäftsbühne geöffnet haben.).  Es kann nicht anders sein, als daß Sie Ihre Schriften für die Musik für wichtiger halten als meine Musik, u. danach müßten Sie entscheiden u. handeln.  Das wäre nun doch wahrhaftig keine Eigensucht.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{9}</tei:hi> Sie schreiben, daß Sie mir wohl schon mitgeteilt hätten, “wie Bruckner mühsam die Figuren auf den Klang abgestimmt habe.”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  „wie Bruckner mühsam die Figuren auf den Klang abgestimmt habe“: S’s sentence in DLA 69.930/12 reads: “... darüber, wie [Bruckner] seine Figuren auf den Klang mit Mühe abstimmte, glaube ich Ihnen schon einmal geschrieben zu haben.“  (I believe I have already written to you [describing] with what labor [Bruckner] coordinated his figurations to harmony.).  </tei:note>  Das ist noch nicht geschehen, es wird mich sehr interessieren, sehr, u. ich bitte Sie, es mir zu schreiben [<tei:hi rend="italic">written vertically in the left margin, bottom to top:</tei:hi> Oder erwähnen Sie doch einmal Beispiele davon in einem Heft “Tonwille”.] auch wenn Sie nunmehr annehmen werden, daß ich mich von meinem Standpunkt dadurch nicht abbringen lasse.  Denn schließlich kommts doch auf das Resultat der Mühsal an; wie auch bei Beethoven, der mir in seinen Skizzen auch <tei:hi rend="bold">{10}</tei:hi> (14.IV.24) manchmal unerwartet ungeschickt erscheint.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  No paragraph-break in the original.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Zum Anfang zurück: ich halte es nach dem, was ich so beobachte (gelegentlich, denn ich studiere meine Sachen nicht so wie die andern), immerhin für <tei:hi rend="italic">möglich</tei:hi>, daß eine schöne Urlinie in ihnen nachgewiesen werden könnte, auch das Gegenteil mag möglich sein.  Mein wirkliches bewußtes Arbeiten (so wie der Maler Kompositionsstudien,, von dem Bild macht) betrifft hauptsächlich die Harmonik, das andere suche ich, bis ich etwas finde was mich zufriedenstellt – ohne so eingehende Arbeit wie beim <tei:hi rend="bold">{11}</tei:hi> Harmonischen.  Da ich aber auch hinsichtlich der Linie sehr empfindlich [<tei:hi rend="italic">written at the bottom of the page:</tei:hi> Sie sagen wohl, ich sei zu wenig empfindlich, zu wenig hellhörig – ich versuche nicht, Ihnen meine Meinung hierüber? aufzudrängen u. meine das jetzt rein praktisch:  ich bin tatsächlich empfindlich, ob ich nun falsch oder richtig empfinde.] gegen ungenügende Weiterführung bin, so vermute ich, daß irgend eine Synthese vorhanden sein muß, vielleicht die Urlinie, vielleicht eine unbekannte.</tei:p><tei:p>Vorgestern kam op. 101, nehmen Sie herzlichen Dank.</tei:p><tei:p>6.V.24</tei:p><tei:p>Eine Osterreise kam dazwischen: bei einer Jugendtagung in Hildesheim, die Dr. Wyneken leitete, waren 4 Abende meiner Musik gewidmet;</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{12}</tei:hi> vorher hatte ich mancherlei mit Vorbereitungen dazu zu tun.  Nun hätte ich ja manches noch zu sagen, aber der Brief soll nun endlich fort.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich sage Ihnen herzliche Grüße.</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr 
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] A. Halm</tei:p><tei:p>Reger:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  Max Reger’s music has been discussed already in OC 12/10–12, February 1–6, 1924, and in DLA 69.930/12, April 3, 1924.</tei:note>  Ich meine, gegen ihn ist soviel zu sagen (u. <tei:hi rend="italic">für</tei:hi> ihn hat meines Wissens keiner seiner Anhänger etwas Greifbares u. Habhaftes gesagt), daß es mir fast unnötig erscheint, daß Sie sich damit abgeben.  Das <tei:hi rend="italic">Bei</tei:hi>&lt;strike&gt;h&lt;/strike&gt;<tei:hi rend="italic">nahe</tei:hi> wäre interessanter, aufschlußreicher—ich verstehe, daß dieses Beinahe nach Ihren Einstellung gerade eine [<tei:hi rend="italic">written vertically in the left margin, top to bottom:</tei:hi> Wesens- also Riesen-Unterschied Distanz bedeuten muß.  [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr to:</tei:hi>] Wesens-Unterschied also Riesen-Distanz bedeuten muß.]</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker dated April 7, April 14, and May 6, 1924</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>April 7, 1924</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor,
 
I didn't mean it that way with the [debate in] public, that the readship should count as a court of appeal, but rather that it should see how a respectably conducted dispute looks in which an opponent is sometimes gladly in the wrong, i.e., is grateful when he admits better insight.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  However, If you take the trouble to show me in a letter one or another passage where I got off track and the lack of genius in my music <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> reveals itself, that’s all right with me too.   It is not necessary to point out many instances, for I suppose from the start that I lack what you mean, or I do consider it very possible.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/></tei:p><tei:p>“Foreground music”—a good expression which, depending on the findings, I would surely also accept for my music with ^much^ modesty as well as ^some^ pride.  That is, I have long since believed that the foreground, or surface, has been neglected at the expense of the <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> background and foundation, corporeality at the expense of spirituality.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  You counter:  everything is merely a body and therein lies the quality of genius.  Granted, but certainly not, therefore, on that account beauty.  That is something!   Unattractive physiognomy, body parts are biologically just as much a wonder as beautiful ones.  Feeling:  I won’t dismiss it by any means, but I talk about it only in private, as it should be.  Knowledge that demonstrates facts is surely also guided by feeling.  One presents facts in the hope, or relying on luck, that that they will guide the reader to <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> feelings, to relish them.  Regarding facts, I have always said:  I consider irrefutable what I write about Beethoven’s music.  On the other hand, I am constantly aware that yet other weights can be tossed onto the scales.  Their rise and fall is not definitive.  What you adduce about Beethoven is almost all valuable to me.  I admire it; in part, it elates me, for example precisely the passage you mentioned in your last letter.</tei:p><tei:p>Regarding religious feeling vis-à-vis music:  specifically on account of such feeling I think music is spiritual in itself, and one doesn’t have to spiritualize it yet further.  The immediate phenomenon, the foreground, is therefore so important to me.  Bruckner regained innocence (the classicists were too much in a hurry).  His metric fullness, his solidity (opening with tonic harmony) I accredit him as greatness.  What you say (about escalation) -is certainly- ^seems at first^ of deep concern <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> but does not confuse me [<tei:hi rend="italic">written in the left margin, top to bottom:</tei:hi>  Simplest explanation:  he respected you and wanted to show you a nice passage and did it under an awkward pretense.]  I see too much structure and intention, will and ability.  I have hauled out a fairly full bag of facts here, and could fill yet quite a few sheets of paper.  But even if it were just a matter of “wonderful musical images”—that is of course above all what was needed after the classicists; music purely of the present.  But as I said, I dispute that it is <tei:hi rend="italic">merely</tei:hi> that, and believe I have proved the opposite.</tei:p><tei:p>Regarding Dr. Kurth,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  I think he certainly said a bit more than how you present it, and that More seems important to me.  The “blow” that you struck has thus not overthrown his image for me.  But <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> you need not worry that I cannot abide such things.  What someone can overthrow for me may just fall over, my own music as well as your support and assistance.  I am always delighted when my music pleases someone.  If one were to prove to me that he understands nothing, it is for me a pleasure to bring him joy.  [<tei:hi rend="italic">written vertically in the left margin, top to bottom:</tei:hi>  It is certainly possible that my music pleases someone who understands little of music, even someone who does not understand my music in particular.]  For some time, already at my first acquaintance with your writings, I noticed the difference; you are much more esoteric than I am.</tei:p><tei:p>I will soon be sending you the quartet parts.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  If you listen in on a rehearsal, do try to influence the players, as far as you can, <tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> not to rush.  In general I find that players always take a faster tempo than I intend (surrogate for spiritedness!).  I will have <tei:hi rend="italic">Of Boundaries and Countries</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> sent to you by the publisher.  You <tei:hi rend="italic">have still not</tei:hi> written me what items of my <tei:hi rend="italic">chamber music</tei:hi> you do <tei:hi rend="italic">not have</tei:hi> (volume 4, 5?).<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> [<tei:hi rend="italic">written in the top margin, inverted:</tei:hi> Most preferably, I would have the parts sent together with the other volumes, so write me soon about it.]<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/></tei:p><tei:p>I will gladly accept a contribution for printing if you have an appropriate foundation at your disposal.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/>  I may conclude from the offer (if such comes under consideration at some point) that you wish to see my music published, and that you are familiar with no music other than mine that in your opinion <tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> deserves it.  Should you have decided, for example, I still think you should publish something from <tei:hi rend="italic">your</tei:hi> writings when publishers don’t come through or even stand in the way.  (I read about your difficulties with that bunch of people<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> with regret and sincere sympathy, and can readily imagine that you have opened only a small slit in the curtain on a very sullied commercial stage.)  It can be no other way than for you to consider your writings more important for music than my music, and you would have to make decisions and act accordingly.  In truth, that would truly not be egotism.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{9}</tei:hi> You write that you had already told me “how Bruckner laboriously coordinated the figurations with the harmony.”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/>  That has not yet occurred.  It would very much interest me, very much, and I ask that you write me about it, [<tei:hi rend="italic">written vertically in the left margin, bottom to top:</tei:hi> Or mention an example of it in a volume of <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</tei:hi>.] even if you will then assume that I will not be budged thereby from my viewpoint.  For ultimately it depends on the outcome of the labor; as with Beethoven, who also sometimes appears <tei:hi rend="bold">{10}</tei:hi> (April 14, 1924) unexpectedly awkward to me in his sketches.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/></tei:p><tei:p>Back to the beginning:  After what I have observed (occasionally, for I don’t study my pieces as I do others'), I still consider it <tei:hi rend="italic">possible</tei:hi> that a beautiful Urlinie could be demonstrated in them.  The opposite may also be possible.  My actual, conscious work (as the painter makes composition studies of a picture) mainly applies to harmony.  The remainder I search out until I find something that satisfies me—without such intensive work as with the <tei:hi rend="bold">{11}</tei:hi> harmony.  However, with respect to line, since I am also very sensitive [<tei:hi rend="italic">written at the bottom of the page:</tei:hi>  You say I am insufficiently sensitive, insufficiently aurally aware—I won’t try to impose my opinion on you on that point, and mean this now purely from a practical viewpoint:  I am indeed sensitive, whether I sense incorrectly or correctly,] to unsatisfactory continuation, I suspect, accordingly, that some kind of synthesis must exist, perhaps the Urlinie, perhaps an unknown type.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Op. 101</tei:hi> arrived the day before yesterday.  Cordial thanks.</tei:p><tei:p>May 6, 1924
An Easter trip intervened.  Four evenings were devoted to my music at a youth convention in Hildesheim that Dr. Wyneken directed; <tei:hi rend="bold">{12}</tei:hi> before that, I had various things to do with preparations.  I do now have other things to say, but the letter should finally be off.</tei:p><tei:p>I express to you cordial greetings.  
Yours, 
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] A. Halm.</tei:p><tei:p>Reger:<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/>  I mean, there is so much to say against him (and to my knowledge none of his devotees has said anything tangible or concrete <tei:hi rend="italic">for</tei:hi> him), that to me it almost seems unnecessary that you have to deal with it.  The <tei:hi rend="italic">Nearly</tei:hi> would be more interesting, enlightening.  I understand that according to your attitude this Nearly must mean a [<tei:hi rend="italic">written vertically in the left margin, top to bottom:</tei:hi> difference in nature, i.e. a huge gap.]</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>