<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OC 12/7&#226;&#128;&#147;9 : 11-10-23 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain; published with the permission of the heirs of August Halm, March 2006.
© Transcription Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Translation Lee Rothfarb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Lee Rothfarb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2000, and is published with the permission of the heirs of August Halm, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1923-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-1938) - -Oster, Ernst (1938-c.1939)—New York Public Library (c.1939-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: New York Public Library, New York; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Lee Rothfarb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 11/10/1923 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Halm ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated November 6-10, 1923</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-06-29</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>H has sent the published score of a string quartet to S. —Patronage has enabled him to publish three volumes of compositions; reports on current and past composition activities and publications. —Discusses what he has learned from Schenker's theories, and questions whether it would be a fault were Bruckner's symphonies not to contain the Urlinie; H's book on Bruckner's symphonies has gone into its second edition. —H suspects that S may not "agree with" his compositions, and asks whether S wishes to receives further scores. —H considers socialism a "historical necessity."

</dc:description><dc:subject>Halm, August; Schenker, Heinrich;  Wickersdorf;  Vienna;  Neumann, Frl;  string quartet;  Chamber Music;  Hausmusik; Freie Schulgemeinde;  Free School Community;  Kurth, Ernst;  Switzerland;  Leonhardt, Carl;  Berlin;  Midsummer Night's Dream;  Cymbeline;  Winter's Tale;  As You Like It;  Luserke, Martin;  Der Tonwille;  Bach, J. S.;  Prelude;  Bruckner;  Urlinie;  Beethoven;  Zwissler, I.;  serenades;  Prelude &amp; Fugue;  socialism</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker dated November 6-10, 1923</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>6./10. XI. 23.</tei:p><tei:p>Lieber und verehrter Herr Professor!</tei:p><tei:p>Ihre Karte<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  No postcard appears to survive from the immediately preceding period.  The previous surviving communication is the letter DLA 69.930/11, November 2, 1922.  This is presumably the “cordial postcard” referred to in OJ 11/35, 22, January 22, 1924, to which the present letter is said to have been an answer.</tei:note> hat mich sehr erfreut.  Eben in diesen Tagen gab ich einer nach Wien reisenden Wickersdorfer Erzieherin<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  “Erzieherin”: female teacher; see note 15, below.</tei:note> die neuerschiene Partitur eines Streichquartetts<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  String Quartet in A major, published in <tei:hi rend="italic">Chamber Music</tei:hi> 6 (Wolfenbüttel: Zwissler, 1923).</tei:note> ^für Sie^ mit [<tei:hi rend="italic">written vertically in the left margin:</tei:hi> die Partitur wird Ihnen dort zugestellt werden], die Stimmen sind noch nicht fertig gedruckt.  Ich hatte von Freunden einige “Edel”valuta  (wie der herrliche Name lautet) zum Zweck der Veröffentlichung von meiner Musik geschenkt erhalten u. konnte damit die Hefte 4-6 Kammermusik herausgeben.  Das ist jetzt zu Ende.  Geschenke zu <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> diesem Zweck nehme ich unbedenklich dankbar an; ich fasse aber die Absicht Ihres Konzerts<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Schenker’s “concert” [identify]</tei:note> anders auf, u. so, daß ich hier nicht in Betracht komme, denn ich gehöre zunächst nicht zu den notleidenden unter den Künstlern.</tei:p><tei:p>Bis jetzt haben wir hier in unserer Freien Schulgemeinde zwar oft Schwierigkeiten gehabt, sie aber immer, mehr oder weniger gut, immerhin doch überwinden können.  Unser Essen ist nahrhaft u. ausreichend, verhältnismäßig gesehen sehr gut; gefroren haben wir einigermaßen, aber erträglich, um unsere Heiz-Vorräte für den Winter zu sparen.  Die neusten Verwicklungen samt Geldsturz brachten uns in Sorgen, doch hoffen wir, daß wir durchhalten können.  Im Frühjahr will ich in der Schweiz einige Vorträge halten, Prof. Dr. E. Kurth in Bern, der viel auf meine Bücher und meine Musik hält, hat dafür geworben.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Ernst Kurth [create biogfile].  Numerous letters passed between back and forth between Halm and Kurth about a lecture or series of invited lectures on Bruckner, going back to as early December 1920, and then continuing through 1923 and even into early 1924.  However, the lectures never materialized.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Mein kleines Vermögen, <tei:hi rend="italic">c.</tei:hi> 30,000 Mark in Frieden, ist natürlich wertlos geworden; darüber mache ich mir nicht viele Gedanken.  Ich mache aber an meinen Arbeiten weiter solang ich kann.  Gegenwärtig bin ich an der Orchesterpartitur einer größeren Symphonie, die im Winter oder Herbst <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn19">  H is probably referring to the abortive Bierkeller Putsch, November 8, 1923, in which Hitler and his supporters interrupted a speech by Gustav von Kahr in the Burgerbraukeller in Munich to announce that “the national revolution” had begun and urge those present to carry the revolution to Berlin; a march of 3,000 Nazis the next day met with police resistence as a result of which Hitler was tried and sent to prison.</tei:note>24 in Stuttgart gespielt werden soll (ich habe den Entwurf dem dortigen Kapellmeister [Carl] Leonhardt im Sommer vorgespielt).<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Carl Leonhardt (1886-1969) was General Music Direktor of the Württemberg State Theater in Stuttgart, 1922-1937, and conducting teacher at the Stuttgart Musikhochschule up until 1945.  He was well known as a conductor of Wagner’s operas.  The inception of the symphony goes back to 1911, according to a letter Halm wrote to his future wife, Hilda Wyneken, on June 8 of that year.  The symphony remains unpublished.  A recording appeared in 2004 (Sterling CDS-1064-2).</tei:note>  Mein <tei:hi rend="italic">C</tei:hi>-dur Konzert und eine Overtüre war für ein Berliner Konzert vorgesehen, das aber anscheinend gar nicht oder vorläufig nicht zu stand kommt. –<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  S enters an emdash at this point, then writes continuously without paragraph-break.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ich habe für unsere Aufführungen von Schauspielen hier im Lauf der Zeit manche Musik geschrieben, die ich gern veröffentlichen möchte, mit kleiner Besatzung (Flöte, Streichquartett, Klavier), für geübte Schulorchester zugänglich; Sommernachtstraum, Wintermärchen, Cymbeline, <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Sturm (die Overtüre u. d. Zecherkanon zu “Was ihr wollt”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Midsummer Night’s Dream</tei:hi> (Wolfenbüttel: Zwissler, 1924); <tei:hi rend="italic">Cymbeline</tei:hi> (Augsburg: Bärenreiter, 1927); <tei:hi rend="italic">As You Like It</tei:hi> (ibid., 1927). </tei:note> erschienen schon lang in einem Heft der einstweilen eingegangenen “Freien Schulgemeinde”; ich vermute, daß ich Ihnen das seinerzeit zugesandt habe); dann noch ^Musik^ zu mehreren Stücken von [Martin] Luserke.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Martin Luserke (1880-1968), novelist and story writer, was a colleague of Halm’s at the Hermann Lietz Country Boarding School in Haubinda, and at Wickersdorf from its founding in 1906.</tei:note>  Ich glaube, daß ein Verleger damit nicht schlecht führe – ich will gar keinen Idealismus von den Verlegern erwarten; wenn sie mir mehr von ihrem Geschäft verstünden u. Instinkt u. Menschenkenntnis hätten, so wäre beiden Teilen geholfen. –<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  S enters an emdash at this point, then writes continuously without paragraph-break.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Von Ihren Heften “Tonwille” habe ich schon manches Gute gelernt u. ich danke Ihnen für diese Bereicherung meiner Erkenntniße u. Auffassung.  Am meisten <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> Eindruck machte mir, was Sie über das Cis[<tei:hi rend="italic">recte:</tei:hi> Fis]-dur Präludium Bachs sagen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  “Die Kunst zu hören” (The Art of Listening), <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</tei:hi> 3 (1922, actual publication date January 19, 1923), 22–25 (Eng. trans., I, 118–20) features the F#-major Prelude from the <tei:hi rend="italic">Well-Tempered Clavier</tei:hi>, Book I.</tei:note>  Ob diese Lehren auf mein Erfinden u. Gestalten Einfluß gewonnen haben, weiß ich nicht; ich glaube, man kann sich solches nicht so eigentlich vornehmen u. beschließen, auf diese Art zu denken.  Auch ließ ich es nicht gelten, davon die letzte Entscheidung herzunehmen.  Gesetzt, Bruckner habe die Urlinie nicht, so würde ich es zunächst offen lassen, ob das ein Fehler bzw. Mangel an seiner Musik -ist-, oder ob es die notwendige Kehrseite seiner Vorzüge ist – an die ich mich nach wie vor halten würde;<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">   Halm mentions the Urlinie in connection with Bruckner in <tei:hi rend="italic">Einführung in die Musik</tei:hi>, 75.</tei:note> das müßte ich dann erst untersuchen.  Überhaupt wären wir ja, glaube ich, in -manchem- <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> engerem aber wichtigem sachlichen Bezirk ausgesprochene Gegner, wenn wir nicht den gemeinsamen Haß gegen die Verlotterung fühlten (deren Größe mir gewiß durch Ihre Schriften erst im ganzen Maß klar geworden ist, vor allem durch Ihre Beethovenausgaben.). –<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  S enters an emdash at this point, then writes continuously without paragraph-break.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Neulich ^erst^ erfuhr ich, daß mein Buch über Bruckners Symphonie in der (an einigen Stellen verbesserten) Neuauflage im vergangenen Sommer richtig erschienen ist;<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  August Halm, <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Symphonie Anton Bruckners</tei:hi> (Munich: Georg Müller, 1914), of which a second edition had appeared in 1923.</tei:note> ich hatte schon gefürchtet, daß der Verlag die Ausgabe wegen der Teuerung sistiert haben könnte.  Liegt Ihnen daran, so lasse ichs Ihnen zusenden.  Ein Wort ^von Ihnen^ über meine Musik habe ich vermißt, aber ohne Ihnen des- <tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> halb etwa gram zu sein, da ich doch weiß wie viel Sie mit dringenden Arbeiten in Anspruch genommen sind.  Immerhin bekam ich mit der Zeit so etwas wie eine Ahnung, daß Sie wohl nicht recht mit diesen Sachen einverstanden sein möchten, was mir zwar leid wäre, mich Ihnen und Ihrem Schaffen aber keineswegs entfremden könnte.  Doch habe ich aus diesem Grund weitere Veröffentlichungen nicht an Sie gehen lassen, bis ich (etwa eine halbe Woche vor Eintreffen Ihrer Karte) das neugedruckte Streichquartett für Sie bestimmte u. Fräulein Neumann zur Reise mitgab;<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15">  Fräulein Neumann: a colleague at Wickersdorf.</tei:note> ich dachte, daß das Ihnen gefallen könnte.  Liegt Ihnen aber daran, auch die <tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> dazwischen liegenden Veröffentlichungen zu haben – ich meine, wenn Ihnen meine Musik, auch ohne daß Sie ihr ganz zustimmten, von einigem Wert ist—so schreiben Sie mir nun ein Wort, u. ich lasse sie Ihnen zugehen.  Die Stimmen zu d. neuen Streichquartett (es ist übrigens <tei:hi rend="italic">c.</tei:hi> 3-4-5 Jahre alt) sind noch nicht da.  Wollen Sie gern auch die Stimmen haben?  Das letzte was ich Ihnen senden ließ, war glaube ich Kammermusik II u. Hausmusik 18 (Streich-Trio, Part.).  Die Hausmusik ist eine Beilage zur “Musikantengilde,” <tei:hi rend="italic">verschiedene Autoren</tei:hi> darin.  Haben Sie meine Sonaten für Geige allein (Hausmusik 9/10)?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn16">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Chamber Music</tei:hi> 2–4 (Wolfenbüttel: Zwissler, 1922);  <tei:hi rend="italic">Hausmusik</tei:hi> 9–10, 18 (ibid., 1921, 1923).</tei:note>  Kallmeyer, der Inhaber des I. Zwisslerverlags, ist ein netter u. lieber Mensch, leider hat er <tei:hi rend="bold">{9}</tei:hi> nicht so viel Geld, daß er in dieser Zeit viel herausbringen könnte, sonst würde er gewiß mehr von mir verlegen.  Kammermusik IV bis VI ist ja, wie ich schon schrieb, durch Geschenke ermöglicht worden, wie auch die Lieder des Narren in Was ihr wollt.  Kammermusik II müßte eigentlich die Spieler der Streichinstrumente anziehen, da diese Suiten, wirkliche Duette mit Klavierbegleitung, den Streichern größeren Atem gestalten als der Stil der klassischen Klaviertrios im allgemeinen tut.  Das wäre doch, wenns schon die fertigen Virtuosen nicht in ihre Programme nehmen wollen, eine schöne Sache für Konzertprogramme der Musikschulen.  Vorigen Winter spielten wirs in Leipzig, dazu noch 3 Serenade für Streichtrio; dazwischen spielte ich die Präludium u. Fuge C-moll aus m. <tei:hi rend="bold">{10}</tei:hi> IV. Klavierheft. –<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn17">  S enters an emdash at this point, then writes continuously without paragraph-break.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Der Sozialismus muß kommen, ob man ihn liebt oder nicht, als geschichtliche Notwendigkeit, und wenn man sich gegen ihn stemmt, wird er nur giftiger kommen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn18">  See Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern</tei:hi>, p. 147, where it is mentioned that Schenker noted in a diary entry of November 13, 1923, that Halm believed socialism must come.</tei:note>  So scheint es mir.  Die Bayern richten Unheil an, ob sie siegen oder unterliegen oder sich zurückziehen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn19">  H is probably referring to the abortive Bierkeller Putsch, November 8, 1923, in which Hitler and his supporters interrupted a speech by Gustav von Kahr in the Burgerbraukeller in Munich to announce that “the national revolution” had begun and urge those present to carry the revolution to Berlin; a march of 3,000 Nazis the next day met with police resistence as a result of which Hitler was tried and sent to prison.</tei:note>  Wenn Deutschland auseinanderfallen <tei:hi rend="italic">will</tei:hi>, so existiert es schon nicht mehr, leimen kann man ein Volk nicht.</tei:p><tei:p>Herzlich grüßt Sie Ihr</tei:p><tei:p>[ _signed:) ] A. Halm</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker dated November 6-10, 1923</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>November 6-10, 1923</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor,</tei:p><tei:p>Your postcard very much delighted me.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  Just in recent days I gave a Wickersdorf teacher<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> traveling to Vienna a newly published score of a string quartet ^for you^ (the score will be delivered to you there)<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>; the printing of the parts is not yet finished.  I received from friends some "largesse” (as the grand-sounding term has it) as a gift for the purpose of publishing my music and with it was able to issue volumes 4-6 of <tei:hi rend="italic">Chamber Music</tei:hi>.  That is now done.  Gifts for <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> that purpose I accept without hesitation.  However, I view the intent of your concert<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> differently, such that I not be considered for it, for I do not belong to the needy among artists.</tei:p><tei:p>To be sure, up to now we often have had difficulties in our Free School Community, but in the end always have been able, more or less well, to overcome them.  Our food is nourishing and sufficient, quite good comparatively.  We were cold to some degree, but tolerable in order to save our heating reserves for the winter.  The newest complications together with plunging deflation caused us worry, but we hope that we can hold out.  In spring I am going to give a few lectures in Switzerland.  Professor Dr. Ernst Kurth in Bern, who holds my books and my music in high regard, has promoted it.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> My small assets, around 30,000 Marks in peace time, have of course become worthless.  I don’t worry about it much.  I will continue my projects as long as I can.  Currently, I am working on the orchestra score of a larger symphony, which is supposed to be performed in fall 1924 in Stuttgart (I played the sketch for resident conductor, [Carl] Leonhardt, in the summer).<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/>  My C-major concerto and an overture were planned for a concert in Berlin which, however, apparently will not, or for the time being, take place.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/></tei:p><tei:p>Over time, for our performances of plays here I have written some music which I would like to publish, with small instrumentation (flute, string quartet, piano), accessible for a trained orchestra.  <tei:hi rend="italic">Midsummer Night’s Dream</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Winter’s Tale</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Cymbeline</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Tempest</tei:hi> (the overture and the reveler’s canon from <tei:hi rend="italic">As You Like It</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> appeared some time ago in a volume of the now defunct <tei:hi rend="italic">Free School Community</tei:hi>; I assume that I sent them to you at the time).  And additionally ^music^ for several pieces by [Martin] Luserke.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/>  I think a publisher would not do badly with them—I don’t expect any idealism at all from publishers.  If they understood more about their business and had instinct and knowledge of human nature, both sides would be helped.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/></tei:p><tei:p>I have learned some good things from your volumes of <tei:hi rend="italic">Tonwille</tei:hi>, and I thank you for the enrichments of my knowledge and conception.  What you say about Bach’s C#[<tei:hi rend="italic">recte</tei:hi> F#]-major Prelude made the biggest <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> impression on me.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/>  I do not know whether these theories have achieved any influence on my compositional invention and design.  I believe one cannot actually adopt something like that and resolve to think in that manner.  Further, I would not hold as valid deriving a final decision from it.  Supposing that Bruckner does not possess the Urlinie, I would still leave open whether that is a fault, and accordingly a deficiency in his music, or whether it is the necessary obverse of his virtues—to which I would hold now as before.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/>  I would first have to investigate it.  In general, I believe we would be outright opponents in <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> narrower but important technical areas if we did not feel the common hate for the rack and ruin (whose dimension certainly first became clear to me in full measure through your writings, above all through your Beethoven editions.).<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/></tei:p><tei:p>^Only^ recently, I learned that my book on Bruckner's [treatment of the] symphony properly appeared in a new edition last summer (improved in certain places).<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/>  I had feared that the publisher could have suspended the edition because of inflation.  If you are interested, I will have it sent to you.  I am lacking some comment ^from you^ on my music, but without therefore being annoyed at you <tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> because I do know how much you are occupied with urgent projects.  Still, over time I have gotten something like a suspicion that you may not exactly be in agreement with these pieces, which would be a shame for me, to be sure, but could in no way alienate me from you and your work.  But for that reason I have not had further publications sent to you, until (about half a week before the arrival of your postcard) I gave Miss Neumann the newly printed string quartet to take with her on her trip.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn15"/>  I thought you might like it.  If you are interested in having the <tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> intervening publications—I mean, if my music is of some value to you, even if you do not completely agree with it—then just let me know and I will have them sent to you.  The parts to the new string quartet (it is, by the way, about three, four, or five years old) are not yet available.  Would you like to have the parts?  The last thing I had sent to you was, I believe, <tei:hi rend="italic">Chamber Music</tei:hi> volume 2 and <tei:hi rend="italic">Hausmusik</tei:hi> 18 (string trio, score).  The <tei:hi rend="italic">Hausmusik</tei:hi> is a supplement to the <tei:hi rend="italic">Musicians Guild</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">various authors</tei:hi> in it.  Do you have my sonatas for solo violin (<tei:hi rend="italic">Hausmusik</tei:hi> 9/10)?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn16"/>  Kallmeyer, the proprietor of I. Zwissler Publishing, is a nice and kind man.  Unfortunately, he <tei:hi rend="bold">{9}</tei:hi> does not have very much money such that he could publish a lot right now.  Otherwise he would certainly publish more by me.  As I already wrote, <tei:hi rend="italic">Chamber Music</tei:hi> 4–6 was made possible through gifts, as well as the songs of the fool in <tei:hi rend="italic">As you Like It</tei:hi>.  <tei:hi rend="italic">Chamber Music</tei:hi> 2 should actually attract string players because those suites, actually duets with piano accompaniment, allow larger gestures for strings than does the style of the classical piano trios in general.  Even if accomplished virtuosos do not want to include them in their programs, it would surely be fine material for concert programs of music schools.  Last winter we played it in Leipzig, as well as three Serenades for string trio.  In between, I played the Prelude and Fugue in C minor from my <tei:hi rend="bold">{10}</tei:hi> fourth volume of piano music.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn17"/></tei:p><tei:p>Socialism must come, whether we like it or not, as a historical necessity, and if we resist it, it will only come more toxically.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn18"/>  So it seems to me.  The Bavarians are wreaking havoc, whether they triumph or succumb or retreat.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn19"/>  If Germany <tei:hi rend="italic">wants</tei:hi> to come apart, then it already no longer exists.  One can’t glue together a nation.</tei:p><tei:p>With cordial greetings, 
Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] A. Halm</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>