<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="heinrich_schenker"
    xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Heinrich Schenker</title>
                <title type="sub">(1868–1935)</title>
                <title type="sub"/>
                <author/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>compiled by</resp>
                    <name>Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836
                        5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>This resource is publicly available and free at the point of access and it is
                        registered under a a <ref type="external"
                            target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">Creative Commons
                            license Attribution-Share Alike 3.0</ref>
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at
                http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/about/encoding/</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2009-08-06</date>
                <name>TL</name>
                <desc>Template Created</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date/>
                <name/>
                <desc/>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head>Heinrich Schenker</head>
            <div>
                <p><figure>
                        <head>Heinrich Schenker seated, c. 1919 (OJ 72/14, No. 6)</head>
                        <graphic url="B72F14_6.jpg" xmt:type="thumb-caption" rend="left-img"
                            width="150px" height="113px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <graphic url="B72F14_6.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img" width="800px"
                            height="600px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <figDesc>Photograph of Heinrich Schenker.</figDesc>
                    </figure></p>
                <p> In the realm of tonal music, Heinrich Schenker was the most penetratingly
                    original thinker of the 20th century. His way of hearing music, developed over a
                    forty-five year career, was embodied in a formalized theory and expressed
                    through a sophisticated method of music analysis by way of treatises,
                    monographs, articles, periodicals, and editions that have had an irrevocable
                    influence on the way the world thinks about music. He was first and foremost a
                        <hi rend="italic">musician</hi>. A pianist with professional experience,
                    possessing an exceptionally acute ear, he was a musician's theorist, a
                    musician's analyst: never concerned with dry mechanisms, Schenker worked always
                    with the impact of music on the ear and its effect on the human mind. Moreover,
                    his theory and method have been adopted by those examining medieval and
                    renaissance music, and even music that Schenker himself scorned: impressionist
                    and atonal music, jazz, popular music, and music of non-western traditions. </p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Early Life : 1868–1901</head>

                <p> Schenker was born on June 19, 1868 in Wisniowczyk (in Galicia), of a Jewish
                    family. At least two years younger than his educational cohort, he attended
                    Polish-language schools, first in Lemberg (now L'viv, grades 5-8) – in addition
                    studying piano with Karl Mikuli, an erstwhile pupil of Chopin – then in Brzežany
                    (grades 9-12). The curricula were rigorous in history, social science, and
                    especially in classical languages (Latin, Greek), but also required study of
                    Polish and, in the upper grades, German and its literature for students of
                    German-speaking households. In 1884, at age 16, Schenker graduated first in a
                    class of 35. His elder brother Wilhelm had graduated the same high school a year
                    earlier.</p>

                <p> Schenker moved to Vienna in 1884, where he studied law at the University of
                    Vienna from that year to 1888. He took a comprehensive curriculum of over thirty
                    courses, including jurisprudence, legal history, and methodology, earning his
                    doctorate in 1890. Echoes of Schenker's legal education resonate in his analytic
                    approach to music. He emerged with a legal cast of mind reflected in his
                    juridification and moralization of music as the "life of the tones." Schenker's
                    teachers included Georg Jellinek, whose reconciliation of order with liberty
                    foreshadows Schenker's synthesis of harmonic structure with contrapuntal freedom
                    via prolongation, and Robert Zimmermann, whose rational ethical aesthetics
                    foreshadow Schenker's equation of truth, beauty, and righteousness. Schenker’s
                    laws of music adjudicate the juristic dialectic between authority and autonomy
                    in a hierarchical community of tones embodied in his motto <hi rend="italic"
                        >semper idem sed non eodem modo</hi> ("always the same, but not in the same
                    way"). From 1887 to 1890 he was concurrently enrolled at the Vienna Conservatory
                    of Music, studying harmony and counterpoint with Anton Bruckner, piano with
                    Ernst Ludwig, and composition with Johann Nepomuk Fuchs.</p>

                <p> His father, a country doctor, died at the end of 1887, and in order to support
                    his family Heinrich embarked on the activity that would frame his entire career:
                    private piano teaching at home. Further income came from work as a music critic
                    between 1891 and 1901 for newpapers and journals in Vienna, Leipzig, and Berlin.
                    But during this time, Schenker saw himself primarily as a composer and pianist,
                    publishing small-scale compositions, which received performances between 1892
                    and 1903, and remaining active as an accompanist and conductor.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Theorist and Editor: the First Period : 1901–1911</head>

                <p><figure>
                        <head>Heinrich Schenker c. 1912 (OJ 72/14, No. 5 - Atelier Kosel)</head>
                        <graphic url="B72F14_2.jpg" xmt:type="thumb-caption" rend="left-img"
                            width="150px" height="113px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <graphic url="B72F14_2.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img" width="800px"
                            height="600px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <figDesc>Photograph of Heinrich Schenker.</figDesc>
                    </figure></p>
                <p>For Universal Edition, newly founded in Vienna in 1901, Schenker edited selected
                    keyboard works by C. P. E. Bach (1903) and later J. S. Bach's <title level="m"
                        >Chromatic Fantasy &amp; Fugue</title> (1910). These editions marked the
                    beginning of a life-long involvement with composers' autograph manuscripts,
                    copies, and early printed sources, the contents of which he sought to transmit
                    without editorial intervention, save for footnoted commentary. </p>

                <p> For the C. P. E. Bach edition he provided a companion guide to executing the
                    ornamentation, but with significant remarks on form and compositional process:
                        <title level="m">Ein Beitrag zur Ornamentik </title>(1903). This was based
                    in part on Bach's own treatise, <title level="m">Versuch über die wahre Art das
                        Clavier zu spielen</title> (1753, 1762), a work that was to permeate
                    Schenker's whole conceptual world as a theorist. Within the J. S. Bach edition
                    he supplied a detailed commentary termed "Erläuterungen" (elucidations): this
                    volume inaugurated a series of “Erläuterungsausgaben” by Universal Edition. </p>

                <p> The series on which Schenker's fame today largely rests, <title level="s">Neue
                        Musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</title> (New Musical Theories and
                    Fantasies), had its origins in an essay started in 1903 entitled <title
                        level="a">Das Tonsystem,</title> which evolved into the opening sections of
                    his <title level="m">Harmonielehre</title> (J. G. Cotta, 1906), in which work he
                    expounded the central concepts of <hi rend="italic">Stufe</hi> (harmonic
                    scale-degree) and <hi rend="italic">Auskomponierung</hi> (literally
                    "composing-out," i.e. elaboration), along with tonicization and
                    chromaticization. It was in <title level="m">Decline of the Art of
                        Composition</title>, planned as an afterword to <title level="m"
                        >Harmonielehre</title>, revised 1905–09 as a separate volume in the series
                    but ultimately unpublished, that Schenker first articulated his enduring polemic
                    against the 19th century (especially Berlioz and Wagner) for sweeping aside the
                    "immutable laws" of composition embodied in German composers of the classical
                    period, whose mastery of cyclic forms found continuity in the music of
                    Mendelssohn and, finally, Brahms. </p>

                <p> The second volume of the series, <title level="m">Kontrapunkt</title>, was
                    originally planned as a single volume, but split in order to facilitate
                    publication of the first half-volume ("Cantus Firmus and Two-voice
                    Counterpoint") in 1910 (Cotta), the second ("Counterpoint in Three and more
                    Voices; Bridges to Free Composition") being delayed by the war and eventually
                    published in 1922 (UE). While Schenker's exposition of the five species of
                    counterpoint from two to eight voices was based on that of Fux and his
                    successors, it was unique in considering the combining of tones in terms of the
                    "affects" that they produced, rather than mechanical formulations, and for
                    demonstrating how Fuxian counterpoint underpinned real pieces of music. <title
                        level="m">Harmonielehre</title> and <title level="m">Kontrapunkt</title> had
                    in common that they adopted a "psychological" point of view. Neither was a
                    textbook in the normal sense; each was more a training in how to hear music
                    properly. (Indeed, the original working title for the latter was "Psychologie
                    des Kontrapunkts.") </p>

                <p> In 1908, Schenker published with UE the work that sold more copies than any
                    other of his works, the <title level="m">Instrumentations-Tabelle</title>, under
                    the pseudonym of Artur Niloff: a wall-chart of musical instruments, showing for
                    each the fundamental, overtones, range, special features, with a picture and
                    repertory list. Around this time he also mapped out a theory of musical form
                    (1907) and he made a first draft of a book entitled <title level="m">Die Kunst
                        des Vortrags</title> (The Art of Performance, 1911); he returned to both
                    from time to time, intending quite late in life to finalize them, but neither
                    was published. </p>

                <p> Between 1901 and 1910, Schenker established working relationships with his two
                    principal publishers: UE and J. G. Cotta of Stuttgart. Begun harmoniously, both
                    relationships were at times troubled. That with UE became stormy within a year
                    of Emil Hertzka's taking up its directorship in 1907, and those troubles would
                    recur in ever-mounting waves, alternating with periods of relative calm, until a
                    breaking point was reached in 1925. The relationship between the two men was
                    complex, admiration and respect mingled with suspicion and exasperation. In his
                    personal life, Schenker became acquainted with Jeaneth Kornfeld, wife of his
                    friend Emil Kornfeld, around 1903. A relationship developed over seven years,
                    and in 1910 she left her husband to devote herself to helping Schenker in his
                    work. By late in 1911, she was taking down his extensive diaries in shorthand,
                    and by 1912 his lesson notes, writing up fair copies of both in exercise books.
                    She also took letters and wrote up drafts for Heinrich to correct and write fair
                    copies. </p>

            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Theorist and Editor: the Middle Years : 1912–25</head>

                <p>Work on the first half-volume of <title level="m">Kontrapunkt</title> and his J.
                    S. Bach edition complete, by June 1910 Schenker's mind turned toward an
                    analytical study of Beethoven's Ninth Symphony. At that time, <title level="m"
                        >Decline of the Art of Composition</title> was envisioned as volume III of
                        <title level="s">Neue Musikalische Theorien und Phantasies</title>, and
                    Schenker planned a <hi rend="italic">Handbibliothek</hi> (pocket library) of
                    short guides to individual works as an "appendix" to that volume, to be
                    published by Cotta and inaugurated by a study of Beethoven’s Ninth Symphony.
                    Each was to comprise a score plus "Erläuterungen," and this format was by 1913
                    embodied in the composite term "Erläuterungsausgabe" (elucidatory edition). The
                    handbook on the Ninth Symphony grew in size, and was published in 1912 by UE as
                    an independent monograph, without accompanying score; nevertheless, it
                    established the format for the future: analytical commentary—performance —survey
                    of secondary literature. </p>

                <p> The notebooks in which Schenker recorded the details of each lesson given in his
                    private piano studio survive from 1912 onwards, and these in conjunction with
                    his diaries afford a sense of what his life was like during the academic
                    "season," October to June. He taught Monday to Saturday inclusive, each lesson
                    of one hour. Students usually attended twice or three times a week, other
                    students coming once a week, a few on an occasional basis. Serious students took
                    not only piano technique and interpretation but also at least a year of
                    counterpoint, a year of thoroughbass, and a year of chorale writing, plus source
                    studies and editorial technique, and analytical method. It was a fully
                    integrated music education, unique in its time, designed to train up a new
                    generation of musicians for all walks of musical life in a mode of thought
                    wholly new yet deeply rooted in tradition. </p>

                <p> On a typical full day, rising early Schenker worked on his publications until 11
                    am, taught 11–1 pm, then with Jeanette went to a local restaurant or coffee
                    house for the day's main meal; thereafter lessons 2–4, a teatime break (<hi
                        rend="italic">Jause</hi>), perhaps a short walk, then a further lesson. The
                    evening might involve a concert, receiving or visiting friends, otherwise an
                    evening meal at home followed by further study, including dictation to Jeanette,
                    whose work might then go on into the early hours of the morning while he himself
                    also worked late. July to mid-September was spent in the mountains of the Tyrol
                    or the Salzkammergut, reading, hiking, playing piano, doing conceptual
                    groundwork for future publications, correcting proofs and, on occasion,
                    receiving visits from his keenest pupils. </p>

                <p> Schenker's next major undertaking concerned the last five Beethoven piano
                    sonatas, Opp. 101, 106, 109, 110, and 111, for each of which he planned a single
                    volume containing a Foreword, the complete score, a <title level="a">Preliminary
                        Remark to the Introduction,</title> the <title level="a"
                        >Introduction</title> itself (analysis, textual commentary, and
                    performance), and <title level="a">Secondary Literature</title> (NB the 1971–72
                    re-editions are heavily abridged, and in the 2015 translation, which is
                    complete, the secondary literature material is accessible only on the web). That
                    for Op. 106 was never produced, because the autograph manuscript could not be
                    found. The remainder of the series, entitled <title level="m">Die letzten fünf
                        Sonaten von Beethoven</title>, was published in 1913, 1914, 1915, then 1920.
                    Working much of the time under wartime conditions, Schenker consulted autograph
                    and printed sources, and notes by Nottebohm, available in Vienna, and obtained
                    photographs of sources from libraries and collectors in Germany and elsewhere,
                    meticulously collating his sources to determine Beethoven's ultimate intentions.
                    Schenker's antagonism toward what he dubs "hermeneuticist" analysts is at its
                    strongest in these texts, as is his campaign against misguided editors. The
                    delaying of <title level="m">Op. 101</title> was propitious in that Schenker had
                    meanwhile developed his concept of Urlinie (fundamental line) and could deploy
                    it publicly for the first time in that volume, using a modified form of standard
                    musical notation with small and large stemmed and unstemmed noteheads,
                    horizontal brackets and slurs, combined with thoroughbass figurings. </p>

                <p> His work on the last five sonatas then led to his producing UE's new edition of
                    the complete Beethoven sonatas between 1921 and 1923, each edited according to
                    the early sources. He also produced a facsimile edition of the "Moonlight"
                    Sonata in 1921 for series edited by Otto Erich Deutsch. </p>

                <p> Schenker continued to develop his "pocket library" plan throughout the 1910s,
                    renaming it <title level="m">Kleine Bibliothek</title> (Little Library); but by
                    the time it began publication it had mutated into a periodical, <title level="j"
                        >Der Tonwille</title>, each of its ten outwardly modest issues offering a
                    fiery admixture of theoretical articles, work analyses, and miscellaneous
                    comment. In practice, the first issue was released within a few days of the
                        <title level="m">Op. 101</title> in summer 1921, so that the latter's
                    Urlinie graphs complemented nicely the former's important article <title
                        level="a">The Urlinie: a Preliminary Remark.</title>
                    <title level="j">Tonwille</title> saw the gradual extension of these graphic
                    devices into a highly sophisticated system. It also contains some of Schenker's
                    most important studies of large-scale works, notably that of Beethoven's Fifth
                    Symphony (issued as a separate volume in 1925), and a series of short analyses,
                    of which those devoted to Bach’s short keyboard preludes have had a wide
                    pedagogical influence, and the term "Ursatz" (literally primal counterpoint) was
                    introduced at first isolatedly in issue 5 (1923). Schenker's reaction to World
                    War I, which had seeped into the late Beethoven sonata volumes, surfaced
                    violently in the first issue in his most polemical essay, <title level="a">The
                        Mission of German Genius,</title> with its reaction to the Versailles Treaty
                    and its diatribes against the romance and anglo-saxon nations and the world of
                    commerce, and his condemnation of what he saw as the artistic mediocrity of his
                    day. The political content of <title level="j">Tonwille</title> led Emil Hertzka
                    to suppress some of Schenker's material, and a slow build-up of animosity led to
                    impending court proceedings, an out-of-court settlement in December 1925, and a
                    severing of all communications. </p>

                <p> Between 1910 and 1919, Jeanette Kornfeld's petitions for a separation from her
                    husband (to which Heinrich brought his legal training to bear) met with solid
                    resistance from her husband and his lawyers. Only after the country's marriage
                    laws had been changed was a divorce finally granted, and Heinrich and Jeanette
                    were permitted to marry, on November 10, 1919. Even so, it was not until
                    November 1921 that they were able to unite their two households in an apartment
                    on the Keilgasse, Vienna III. Meanwhile, in 1914 Schenker had been diagnosed
                    with diabetes, a condition that affected his day-to-day life and, ultimately,
                    would claim it. </p>

            </div>

            <div>

                <head>Theorist and Editor: the Mature Years : 1926–35</head>
                <p><figure>
                        <head>Heinrich Schenker, 1927 (OJ 72/14, No. 10 - F.-E. von Cube)</head>
                        <graphic url="B72F14_10.jpg" xmt:type="thumb-caption" rend="left-img"
                            width="150px" height="113px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <graphic url="B72F14_10.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img" width="800px"
                            height="600px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <figDesc>Photograph of Heinrich Schenker.</figDesc>
                    </figure></p>
                <p> Already by the break with UE in 1925, Schenker had identified an alternative
                    publisher, Drei Masken Verlag of Munich, which refused to continue the existing
                    periodical and insisted on a new identity as <title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in
                        der Musik</title>, and publication as a "yearbook" (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Jahrbuch</hi>), each commensurate with the last four issues of <title
                        level="j">Tonwille</title>. Three yearbooks were produced, dated 1925, 1926,
                    and 1930, all modeled on a typical issue of <title level="j">Tonwille</title>,
                    with theoretical articles, analyses, and miscellany, but with the political
                    polemic subdued. <title level="j">Meisterwerk 1</title> most closely resembles
                    the <title level="j">Tonwille</title> pamphlets, being made up of twelve essays
                    of varying lengths; here the concept of Ursatz was now well defined, and many
                    other mature concepts, such as arpeggiation (<hi rend="italic">Brechung</hi>),
                    linear progression (<hi rend="italic">Zug</hi>) registral transfer (<hi
                        rend="italic">Höher</hi>- and <hi rend="italic">Tieferlegung</hi>), and
                    reaching-over (<hi rend="italic">Übergreifen</hi>), were widely deployed. <title
                        level="j">Meisterwerk 2</title> and <title level="j">Meisterwerk 3</title>
                    contain fewer, longer items, each offering one major analytical article on a
                    four-movement work: Mozart's Symphony No. 40, in G minor, and Beethoven's
                    "Eroica" Symphony, respectively, each retaining some vestiges of the earlier
                        <title level="m"> Erläuterungsausgabe</title> format. These two analyses
                    reveal the confidence with which Schenker now operated in the analytical mode,
                    and serve as the two most important full-length exemplars of his method. The
                    graphic techniques begun in <title level="m"> Op. 101</title> now reached
                    maturity in graphs printed on large, separate sheets of paper (exquisitely
                    engraved by Waldheim-Eberle of Vienna) displaying parallel horizontal layers
                    using extended multi-level beams and slurs to convey long-term time-spans and
                    tonal coherence, and dotted lines and slurs, special symbols and abbreviations
                    to show voice-leading and interaction between voices, inter-relations between
                    tones, and chordal function. </p>

                <p> November 1928 saw a tentative resumption of communications between Schenker and
                    Hertzka. In 1932, Schenker described how, after completion of the "Eroica"
                    Symphony graphs in <title level="m">Meisterwerk 3</title>, the "presentation in
                    graphic form" had been "developed to a point that makes an explanatory text
                    unnecessary." From fall 1931, Schenker conducted a seminar with four of his
                    students, each student assigned a composition on which to work, and from that
                    seminar emerged his <title level="m">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln / Five Analyses in
                        Sketchform</title>, published by the David Mannes Music School, New York
                    (where his pupil Hans Weisse was teaching), but engraved by Waldheim-Eberle with
                    UE as the European distributor. The works graphed were a J. S. Bach chorale, the
                    first prelude of the <title level="m">Well-tempered Clavier</title> Book I, a
                    section of a Haydn sonata movement, and two Chopin Etudes. (A second volume was
                    mooted but never materialized.) </p>

                <p> Schenker's work with photostat copies of sources prompted him to propose the
                    establishment of an archive of copies of "musical master manuscripts," available
                    for consultation by scholars. This took shape in 1927 as the Photogrammarchiv,
                    located in the Austrian National Library, with Schenker's pupil Anthony van
                    Hoboken as its archivist. By 1934, it already held over 30,000 pages, and it
                    continued to grow thereafter. In the Archive of the Gesellschaft der
                    Musikfreunde in Vienna there was a Brahms autograph manuscript that bore
                    testimony to the composer’s interest in contrapuntal technique and wide
                    knowledge of the musical respertory and history of theory, which recorded 140
                    instances of parallel fifths and octaves in music from the mid-16th to the
                    mid-19th century; some Brahms regarded as unacceptable, others as tolerable,
                    others as entirely acceptable. For many years, Schenker had had his students
                    study this manuscript, and in 1933 to mark the centenary of Brahms's birth he
                    published a facsimile of this eleven-page source with commentary. </p>

                <p>By the early 1930s, Schenker could rightly claim that his theories were being
                    disseminated within Europe by his students and disciples to their pupils. Such
                    were Moriz Violin and Felix-Eberhard von Cube in Hamburg, Otto Vrieslander in
                    Munich, and Reinhard Oppel at the prestigious Leipzig Conservatory. Schenker
                    took particular pride in the influence that his ideas had on Wilhelm
                    Furtwängler, hence on the latter's interpretations of works in the concert hall.
                    The first to teach his theories in a foreign language (and to quote him in an
                    English publication) was John Petrie Dunn at the University of Edinburgh, until
                    his tragic death in a road accident in 1931; the American organist Victor Vaughn
                    Lytle, who had studied with Hans Weisse in the late 1920s, took a theory
                    teaching post at Oberlin College, Ohio. In September 1931, Weisse left Vienna to
                    take up an appointment as theory and composition teacher at the David Mannes
                    Music School and Columbia University in New York City in September 1931, where
                    he attracted a wide circle of admiring pupils and laid the foundations of
                    American Schenker pedagogy.</p>

                <p> The second half-volume of <title level="m">Kontrapunkt</title>, which had been
                    published in 1922, concluded with the <title level="a">Bridges to Free
                        Composition.</title> Even as late as 1920, however, <title level="m"
                        >Kontrapunkt</title> had been intended to include a section on free
                    composition, already drafted by summer 1917. However, 1917–20 being so
                    conceptually fertile a period, in which Urlinie and Ursatz were adumbrated, and
                    his subsequent redactions to this section being so extensive, Schenker decided
                    to abandon its inclusion in volume II/2 and envisioned a volume II/3 of <title
                        level="s">Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</title> entitled <title
                        level="m">Freier Satz</title>. But by 1925, after publication of <title
                        level="m">Op. 101</title> and the issues of <title level="j"
                        >Tonwille</title>, and with work on <title level="j">Meisterwerk 1</title>,
                    Schenker had reconceived this as volume III of the series, with the slightly
                    modified title of <title level="m">Der freie Satz</title>. For the next ten
                    years he worked on what became the summation of his mature theory, cast into
                    three main parts, <title level="a">Background,</title>
                    <title level="a">Middleground,</title> and <title level="a">Foreground,</title>
                    each explicated systematically (as in volumes I and II) in sections, chapters,
                    and numbered paragraphs in the manner of an 18th-century treatise. The
                    "elemental driving force" (<hi rend="italic">Urkraft</hi>) of the entire edifice
                    was the Ursatz—in which Urlinie and <hi rend="italic">Bassbrechung</hi> (bass
                    arpeggiation) unite in counterpoint, representing respectively horizontal and
                    vertical forces, falling and rising lines, and embodying the first tones of the
                    harmonic spectrum. To the text, Schenker provided a companion volume of musical
                    graphs. Schenker died on January 14, 1935, not having corrected the proofs of
                        <title level="m">Der freie Satz</title>; this was seen through the press by
                    his widow and others.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Schenker's Legacy</head>
                <p><figure>
                        <head>Inscription on Schenker's grave (Iby-Jolande Varga)</head>
                        <graphic url="schenker_grab_stein_det2.jpg" xmt:type="thumb-caption"
                            rend="left-img" width="150px" height="113px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <graphic url="schenker_grab_stein_det2.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                            width="800px" height="600px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <figDesc>Inscription on Schenker's gravestone.</figDesc>
                    </figure></p>
                <p> Already in January 1930, the rise of the National Socialists in Germany had cast
                    its shadow on Schenker's life, putting beyond reach a prospective official
                    appointment in Berlin. Soon after his death, his students, his living legacy,
                    most of whom were Jewish, were scattered: many emigrated to the USA and
                    elsewhere, others remained and were deported (as was his own wife) to the camps.
                    The Schenker Institute established in Vienna a few months after his death was
                    closed down in 1938, as had been a similar institute in Hamburg in 1934. Copies
                    of his publications at UE were confiscated by the Gestapo, and he himself was
                    characterized grotesquely in the <title level="m">Lexikon der Juden in der
                        Musik</title> as "Chief representative of the abstract music theory of
                    Jewish philosophy that disavows the existence of a spiritual content in music
                    and limits itself to constructing tone rows from the correlation of individual
                    sonata movements in arbitrary combination, from which an 'Urlinie' is read." The
                    dissemination of his ideas was to come not from Europe but from the USA, through
                    his students Hans Weisse, Oswald Jonas, and Felix Salzer, and through their
                    students. The influence of Schenker's theories blossomed there in the 1950s and
                    1960s, and gradually extended back to Europe and to other parts of the world
                    during the later 20th century. </p>

            </div>
        </body>

        <back>
            <div>
                <head>Contributors:</head>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl><author>Ian Bent</author>, with <author>William Drabkin</author>,
                            <author>Wayne Alpern</author>, and <author>Lee Rothfarb</author></bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
