<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="major_collections"
    xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Major Collections</title>
                <title type="sub">Of Schenker's Papers and Other Materials</title>
                <author/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>compiled by</resp>
                    <name>Ian Bent</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836
                        5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>This resource is publicly available and free at the point of access and it is
                        registered under a <ref type="external"
                            target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">Creative Commons
                            license Attribution-Share Alike 3.0</ref>
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at
                http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/about/encoding/</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2009-08-06</date>
                <name>TL</name>
                <desc>Template Created</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date/>
                <name/>
                <desc/>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head>Major Collections</head>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p> Correspondence to and from Heinrich Schenker survives in about twenty
                    depositories, located in Austria, Australia, Germany, the Netherlands, and the
                    United States. Some items are held in national, civic, and university libraries
                    and archives, some in the files of commercial companies, some in private
                    possession, whether by the descendants of recipients, or by other persons into
                    whose hands they have subsequently come. There are undoubtedly
                    yet-to-be-identified caches of correspondence, and such caches, for which <hi
                        rend="italic">Schenker Documents Online</hi> actively searches, come to
                    light from time to time. Diaries and lessonbooks, to the contrary, survive each
                    in a single location. </p>
                <p> Of these depositories, <hi rend="italic">four</hi> stand out as holding the
                    largest quantities of material, and details of them and their locations are
                    given below. </p>
            </div>


            <div>
                <head>Background: 1935–42</head>
                <p> What happened after Heinrich Schenker's death on January 14, 1935 should,
                    however, first be briefly outlined here. Whereas most of his books and scores
                    were sold through the book trade, the huge mass of papers that Schenker left
                    behind, including drafts and fair copies of texts for publications (prospective
                    or actual), analyses and sketches of music, handwritten notes and memos (some
                    even on tram tickets and restaurant bills), drafts and file copies of
                    correspondence (sent or unsent), correspondence received, diaries, lessonbooks,
                    scrapbooks, miscellaneous other materials, and copies of his own publications,
                    were retained by his widow Jeanette, who sought over the next few years to
                    impose some organization on them. </p>
                <p> Between Heinrich's death and her own deportation to Theresienstadt (Terezin) in
                    1942, Jeanette gave or sold some of her husband's papers to friends and pupils;
                    thus Felix Salzer purchased part of the collection in 1936, Otto Vrieslander
                    re-acquired most of the letters he had written to Heinrich, and materials were
                    passed to Wilhelm Furtwängler. In particular and still more significantly,
                    Jeanette entrusted a large quantity of his working papers to Ernst Oster (a
                    pupil of Oswald Jonas), who then emigrated to the USA; these passed at his death
                    to the New York Public Library. </p>
                <p> The remainder of the papers and other materials, stored in a large trunk, she
                    entrusted to Erwin Ratz, a close friend who for some time succeeded in shielding
                    her from the Nazis. Ratz himself remained in Vienna throughout the war and kept
                    the trunk safe; then Oswald Jonas, a pupil of Schenker's who had emigrated to
                    the USA in 1938, returned to Vienna some time after the war and acquired the
                    trunk from Ratz. He shipped it back to the USA, where from 1965 to his death in
                    1978 he taught at the University of California at Riverside, to which he
                    bequeathed its contents. </p>
            </div>


            <div xml:id="OJ">
                <head>Riverside, California, USA : <lb/>University of California, Riverside, Special
                    Collections Library</head>
                <div>
                    <head>Oswald Jonas Memorial Collection</head>
                    <p>This collection of materials (c. 75,000 leaves) comprises Schenker's diaries,
                        the bulk of his correspondence, spanning 1888–1935, his theoretical,
                        critical, and analytical works and editions in manuscript, proof, and
                        published versions (many with annotations and corrections), scores, and his
                        own compositions. In addition to these, the collection also holds the papers
                        of Oswald Jonas himself, including correspondence, manuscript and published
                        works and other materials, the papers of Schenker's life-long friend Moriz
                        Violin (who had emigrated in 1939 and lived and worked in San Francisco),
                        including correspondence and memorabilia, and also other correspondence
                        acquired subsequently, and photographs and portraits of the Schenkers, their
                        family and circle of friends. A checklist of the materials has been
                        published and made online.</p>


                    <div>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl><editor>Lang, Robert</editor> &amp; <editor>Kunselman,
                                    JoAn</editor>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker, Oswald Jonas,
                                    Moriz Violin: A Checklist of Manuscripts and Other Papers in the
                                    Oswald Jonas Memorial Collection</title> (Berkeley, CA:
                                University of California Press, 1994)</bibl>
                            <lb/>
                            <bibl><editor>Lang, Robert</editor> &amp; Kunselman, JoAn, <ref
                                    target="http://www.oac.cdlib.org/findaid/ark:/13030/tf4j49n9zc"
                                    type="external">
                                    <title level="m">Guide to the Oswald Jonas Memorial
                                        Collection</title>
                                </ref> (online edition)</bibl>
                        </listBibl>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>


            <div xml:id="NYPL">
                <head>New York, USA : <lb/>New York Public Library, Performing Arts Library, Music
                    Division</head>
                <div xml:id="OC">
                    <head>Oster Collection</head>
                    <p>This collection of Schenker's materials, deposited at the New York Public
                        Library in 1979/80 after the death of Ernst Oster, includes correspondence
                        with the publishers Universal Edition of Vienna (939 items), Drei Masken
                        Verlag of Munich and Waldheim-Eberle of Vienna (384 items), and to and from
                        others, spanning his entire career. It also includes Schenker's lessonbooks
                        (1912–31) and lesson notes (1931/32), and his scrapbook preserving clippings
                        from newspapers and journals (1902–35). In addition, it contains many music
                        analyses and graphs (mostly organized by composer), preparatory manuscript
                        and typed materials for publications, including texts of unpublished works,
                        and a collection of books, pamphlets, and scores (many with annotations and
                        corrections). The collection was preserved and catalogued in 1988-90 with
                        funding from the National Endowment for the Humanities and a finding-list
                        published. The entire collection is available on microfilm. </p>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl><editor>Kosovsky, Robert</editor>, comp., <title level="m">The Oster
                                Collection: Papers of Heinrich Schenker: A Finding List</title> (New
                            York: New York Public Library, 1990)</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>

                <div xml:id="FS">
                    <head>Felix Salzer Papers</head>
                    <p>This collection, bequeathed to the Library in 2000, holds the papers of Felix
                        Salzer, a pupil of Schenker's who left Austria in 1939 and emigrated to the
                        USA the following year, taught at the David Mannes Music School and
                        subsequently also at Queen's College and the Graduate Center of the City
                        University of New York. The collection includes a portion of Schenker's
                        papers, notably the latter's notes on the J. S. Bach "Generalbaßbüchlein,"
                        his "Von der Stimmführung des Generalbasses," and his commentary on C. P. E.
                        Bach's <title level="m">Versuch über die wahre Art das Clavier zu
                            spielen</title>, and numerous analyses and sketches, including
                        preparatory materials for the projected second volume of <title level="m"
                            >Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln</title>. In addition, it holds Salzer's own
                        correspondence with many people, including twenty-seven items from Heinrich
                        Schenker, communications with Jeanette, and correspondence between Hans
                        Weisse and Schenker. The papers were catalogued in 2007, and the catalogue
                        published online. </p>
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl><editor>Koslovsky, John</editor>, ed., <ref
                                target="http://www.nypl.org/research/manuscripts/music/mussalze.xml#IDADWACC"
                                type="external">
                                <title level="m">Guide to the Felix Salzer Papers</title>
                            </ref> (online edition)</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                </div>
            </div>

            <div xml:id="WSLB">
                <head>Vienna, Austria : <lb/>Wienbibliothek im Rathhaus (formerly Wiener Stadt- und
                    Landesbibliothek)</head>
                <div xml:id="WSLB-Hds">
                    <head>Handschriftensammlung [Manuscript Collection]</head>
                    <p>This collection contains correspondence between Schenker and Otto Erich
                        Deutsch (24 items), Adalbert Franz Seligmann (17), Karl Weigl (4), Artaria
                        (1), and Johannes Brahms (1). There is no published catalogue.</p>
                </div>

                <div xml:id="WSLB-Mus">
                    <head>Musiksammlung [Music Collection]</head>
                    <p>This collection comprises 408 letters, mostly in Schenker's hand, to his
                        principal publisher, Universal Edition of Vienna, and thirty-five from
                        Universal Edition to Schenker, spanning 1908-31, on long loan from Universal
                        Edition since 1976. Regrettably, the letters from Schenker to UE are missing
                        for the years 1920–23 inclusive. There is no published catalogue. </p>
                    <p>There is also a small number of letters between Jeanette Schenker and
                        Universal Edition dating from after Heinrich's death, held at the company's
                        archive at its head office in Vienna. </p>
                </div>
            </div>

            <div xml:id="DLA">
                <head>Marbach, Germany : <lb/>Schiller Nationalmuseum/Deutsches Literaturarchiv:
                    Cotta-Archiv (Stiftung der Stuttgarter Zeitung)</head>
                <p>This archive holds correspondence from Schenker to his publisher J. G. Cotta of
                    Stuttgart, interleaved with carbon copies of letters from Cotta to himself,
                    spanning 1905–21 (179 items). There are also letters from Schenker to August
                    Halm in the Deutsches Literaturarchiv itself (16 items). There is no published
                    catalogue. </p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <p> For full list of the depositories of Schenker materials, with the sigla used by
                        <hi rend="italic">Schenker Documents Online</hi>, see <ref
                        cRef="abbreviations_sigla">Abbreviations and Sigla</ref>.</p>
                <p>The information contained in the above introduction and collection descriptions
                    is drawn from the sources already cited, and also from the following:</p>
                <listBibl>
                    <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker
                            nach Tagebüchern und Briefen in der Oswald Jonas Memorial Collection,
                            University of California, Riverside</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms,
                        1985)</bibl>

                    <bibl><author>Kosovsky, Robert</author>, <title level="a">Levels of
                            Understanding: An Introduction to Schenker's Nachlass,</title>
                        <title level="m">Schenker Studies 2</title>, ed. Carl Schachter &amp; Hedi
                        Siegel (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1999)</bibl>

                    <bibl><author>[Anon.]</author>, <title level="a">Der Nachlaß Heinrich
                            Schenkers,</title>
                        <title level="j">Der Dreiklang</title> i (April 1937), 17–22</bibl>
                </listBibl>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
