<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 14/14 : 12-6-25 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Under inquiry.
© Transcription Christoph Hust, 2006.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Christoph Hust 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1925-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: under inquiry; Image:  University of California, Riverside;  Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Christoph Hust.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 12/06/1925 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Schnabel ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Artur Schnabel to Schenker, dated December 6, 1925</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-034-26</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Acks letter;  divulges limited information about the nature of his contract with his publisher. 

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schnabel, Artur; Schenker, Heinrich;  contract;  terms;  dispute</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> 14 Wielandstrasse, Charlottenburg</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Artur Schnabel to Schenker, dated December 6, 1925</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>14 Wielandstrasse
Charlottenburg
6. Dez. 1925</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Herr Schenker,</tei:p><tei:p>verzeihen Sie, bitte, die durch meine Abwesenheit von Berlin verursachte Verzögerung dieses Schreibens.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  S's letter to Schnabel is not known to have survived.  Click on <ref cRef="schnabel_artur">Artur Schnabel</ref>.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Wie gern würde ich Ihnen ganze Auskunft auf Ihre Frage<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Presumably S had written to Schnabel inquiring the terms of his contract with his publisher, and seeking comparison with those of his own contracts. </tei:note> geben, aber ich fühle mich etwas begrenzt durch die Zusage an meinen Verleger,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Presumably Ullstein, Berlin.</tei:note> über Einzelheiten unseres Vertrags nichts mitzuteilen.</tei:p><tei:p>Einiges kann ich aber wohl sagen: der Vertrag ist ein Autorenvertrag, also: bis zum Ablauf der Schutzfrist bin ich am Verkauf von jedem Exemplar beteiligt.  Bei einigermassen befriedigendem Absatz wird bei Vertragsende der Herausgeberanteil eine Summe darstellen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  The mention of “the editor’s [not “author's”] share of the profits” strongly suggests that S was inquiring about Schnabel’s editions with commentary of Beethoven’s piano sonatas and the Diabelli Variations, currently being published by Ullstein in Berlin, 1924–27. </tei:note> hinter der die von Ihrem Verlag<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Universal Edition, Vienna.  </tei:note> für Ihre Arbeit errechnete jedenfalls sehr weit zurückbleibt.</tei:p><tei:p>Vorschuss oder festes Honorar wurde nicht bezahlt.  Im übrigen: Verlegerrücksicht auf fremdes Wohl dürfte etwa gleichzeitig mit dem Messias kommen.</tei:p><tei:p>Indem ich Ihnen für Ihren Streitfall<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  S was at the time in dispute with UE’s director, Emil Hertzka, over alleged breach of contract, interference with authorial control, and accounting malpractice.  The dispute had since September 1924 been conducted between attorneys for the conflicting parties, and in October 1925 a brief was prepared for the court of arbitration.  However, a deal was struck on December 10, and S received payments from UE from December 31 onward, S moving to Drei Masken Verlag of Munich.  For an account, see <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille: Pamphlets/Quarterly Publication ...</tei:hi>, ed. William Drabkin, vol. II (New York: Oxford University Press, 2005), pp. v–xii.  </tei:note> nun die beste Lösung wünsche, bin ich Ihr verehrungsvoll ergebener</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Artur Schnabel</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Artur Schnabel to Schenker, dated December 6, 1925</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>14 Wielandstrasse
Charlottenburg</tei:p><tei:p>December 6, 1925</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Mr. Schenker,</tei:p><tei:p>Please forgive me for the delay in writing this letter, which was due to my absence from Berlin.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Much as I would like to give you full information regarding your question,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> I feel myself somewhat constrained by the promise to my publisher<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> not to divulge any of the details of our contract.</tei:p><tei:p>However, I feel sure I can tell you a little:  the contract is an author contract; i.e., up to the expiry of the term of copyright I receive a portion of the sale of each copy.  If sales are reasonably satisfactory, the editor’s share of the profits<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> at the end of the contract will amount to a sum, of which at any rate the [sum] reckoned by your publisher<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> for your work will fall very far short.</tei:p><tei:p>No advance or fixed honorarium is paid.  All in all, we will have to wait from here to kingdom come before publishers show any considerateness toward the well-being of others.</tei:p><tei:p>With best wishes to you for your dispute,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> I remain</tei:p><tei:p>In great admiration
Yours truly,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Artur Schnabel</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>