<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OC 12/13-14 : 3-15/4-1-24 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain; published with the permission of the heirs of August Halm, March 2006.
© Transcription Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Translation Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Lee Rothfarb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2000, and is published with the permission of the heirs of August Halm, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1924-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-1938) - -Oster, Ernst (1938-c.1939)—New York Public Library (c.1939-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain, published here with kind permission, March 2006; Image: New York Public Library, New York; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Lee Rothfarb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 04/01/1924 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Halm ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated March 15 and April 1, 1924</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-07-23</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>H takes issue with S's remarks about Berlioz in Tonwille 5, and questions the value of adopting such "harsh language";  he finds similar weaknesses in Brahms's music; he believes there is something to be learned from Berlioz's melodic practice. —Thanks S for copy of Beethoven complete sonata edition, asks whether S would like the parts of his A-major Quartet.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Halm, August; Schenker, Heinrich;  Berlioz;  Mendelssohn;  Brahms;  Beethoven;  Fifth Symphony;  piano sonatas;  String Quartet;  Midsummer Night's Dream;  Winter's Tale</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated March 15 and April 1, 1924</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>15. III. 24</tei:p><tei:p>Lieber, verehrter Herr Professor!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich beginne meinen Brief mit einem Angriff bzw. mit Abwehr.  Was Sie in dem Heft 5 Tonwille über Berlioz schreiben,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  The remark appears near the end of “Beethoven: V. Sinfonie (Fortsetzung),” <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</tei:hi> Heft 5 (1923—actually published just before February 23, 1924, thus recently released), pp. 10–42, on pp.18–19 and  footnote (Eng. trans., vol. I, p. 189): “Berlioz, because he believed that the entire wonder of Beethoven’s effect (rather like Wagner) was contained in the simple triadic unfolding of his principal themes, felt himself induced to follow Beethoven in this respect;  which bestowed upon him no more than the most feeble, misconceived, unspeakably awkward and childish melodies.”  The footnote quotes Mendelssohn on Berlioz.</tei:note> will ich bei nächster Gelegenheit öffentlich abweisen, möchte aber doch zuerst u. zunächst persönlich meinem Empfinden Ausdruck geben, daß so abschätzige Verurteilung nicht ohne genaues Namhaftmachen des Gemeinten, oder, wenn Sie die gesamte Melodik von Berlioz meinen, ohne das ausdrücklich zu sagen, angängig ist;  Beispiele wären hier nötig, u. sie sollten <tei:hi rend="italic">besprochen</tei:hi>, das Verunglückte sollte <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> aufgezeigt werden.  Und auch dann ist zu erwägen, ob mit weniger heftigen Ausdrücken nicht dieselbe Klarheit geschaffen werden kann. Sie können mir glauben, daß ich bei Brahms manches albern finde, -könnte- wenn ich meiner natürlichen Abneigung gegen ihn nachgebe; öffentlich möchte ich das doch nicht tun, wenn es nicht unbedingt nötig ist—das ist es auch nicht, denn im ganzen sehe ich doch seine Lebensarbeit im Hintergrund.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Wenn Berlioz ungeschickt ist, ist mirs immer noch wohler zu mut als bei der leidigen Gewandtheit Mendelsohns.  Und von ^einem Teil^ meiner Melodik sage ich, daß das Beste von Berlioz stammt; ich glaube schon lang, daß ich der erste bin der gemerkt hat, daß man gerade in der Melodik von Berlioz lernen kann, u. ich will, wenn's zutrifft, stolz darauf sein.  Außerdem hat Berlioz so Einzigartiges, Unnachahmliches, daß ich ohne große Dankbarkeit gar nicht <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> an ihn denken kann.  Wo er mir schwach erscheint, vergesse ich -jenes- diese doch nicht; mein Urteil trübt sie ^aber^ nicht.</tei:p><tei:p>Im übrigen will ich gerade das was Sie über Beethovens V. Sÿmphonie in dieser Nummer schreiben, sobald ich kann, genauer durchnehmen, schon aus Gerechtigkeitsgefühl u. sozusagen zur eigenen Erziehung u. Prüfung, weil mir eben diese Sÿmphonie die fremdste, die eigentlich feindliche unter den Sÿmphonien Beethovens ist.  Die Klaviersonaten, 4 Bände, habe ich erhalten u. ich danke Ihnen sehr[,]|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  <tei:hi rend="italic">L. van Beethoven: Klaviersonaten, nach den Autographen und Erstdrucken rekonstruiert</tei:hi>, 4 vols, ed. H. Schenker (Vienna: UE, 1921–23).</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> daß Sie mir diese wertvolle Gabe haben zukommen lassen.  In Ihrem Brief<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  H is presumably referring to S’s next letter.</tei:note> hoffe ich nun bald Ihre Wünsche, meine Musik betreffend, zu finden.  Ich sende sie Ihnen besonders gern (auch wenn Sie nicht so gut über sie denken wie ich selbst).  Gegenwärtig ist meine Musik zum Sommernachtstraum beim Stechen, in den nächsten Tagen soll die zum Wintermärchen dazu kommen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Halm, <tei:hi rend="italic">Sommernachtstraum</tei:hi> and <tei:hi rend="italic">Wintermärchen</tei:hi>, published as part of <tei:hi rend="italic">Bühnenmusik I</tei:hi> (Wolfenbüttel: Zwissler, 1924).</tei:note> alle meine Schauspiel-Musiken sind für kleine Besatzung, d.h. für unser Schulorchester geschrieben.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit herzlichen Grüßen,
Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] A. Halm</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> Nicht wahr Sie schreiben mir auch, ob Sie die <tei:hi rend="italic">Stimmen</tei:hi> zu meinem A-dur-Quartett gern haben möchten.</tei:p><tei:p>Nachschrift 1. IV. 24.  Ja, schließlich soll man natürlich sagen was man für wahr hält, aber doch so, daß man damit was ausrichtet. Einem Anhänger von Berlioz (übrigens: gibt es denn davon so viele, daß eine Bekehrungszug notwendig, auch bei Ihrer Auffassung?) wird doch durch solche Werte nicht zu ruhiger Prüfung seines Standpunkts veranlaßt.</tei:p><tei:p>Wie gesagt, ich gebe diese u. jene Schwächen von Berlioz ohne weiteres zu.  Aber er ist mir eitel, selbstgefällig—ich finde diese Züge manchmal bei Brahms.  Und dann: ist so eine Melodie wie "Rosen brach ich nachts mir" [op. 94, no. 4]; "Holder klingt der Vogelsang" [op. 71, no. 5]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> Op. 94, No. 4 and Op. 71, No.5: both songs are in Dover, Series III (pp. 158 and 60, respectively).</tei:note> etwa weniger albern als die verunglückte Melodie von Berlioz?</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated March 15 and April 1, 1924</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>March 15, 1924</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor,</tei:p><tei:p>I will begin my letter on the offensive, that is on the defensive.  At the next opportunity I plan to refute what you write about Berlioz in volume 5 of <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> would like first and initially, however, to express personally my feeling that such derogatory condemnation is not permissible without specifying precisely what is meant or, if you mean the entirety of Berlioz’s melodic practice, without saying that explicitly.  Examples would be necessary here, and they should be <tei:hi rend="italic">discussed</tei:hi>, the failures should be <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> shown.  And even then one should consider whether the same clarity cannot be achieved with less harsh language.  You can believe that I find some silly things in Brahms if I give in to my natural disinclination toward him.  I would rather not do that publicly if it is not absolutely necessary—and it isn’t because I do see his life’s work in the background.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> If Berlioz is clumsy, it is nevertheless more to my liking than the tiresome fluency of Mendelssohn.  And of ^a part of^ my melodic practice I say that the best of it derives from Berlioz.  For some time, I believe that I am the first to have noticed that we can learn from Berlioz precisely in melodic practice and, if that is correct, I will be proud of it.  Moreover, in Berlioz there are such unique, inimitable elements that I cannot think <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> of him without immense gratitude.  Where he appears weak to me, I certainly do not forget those passages, ^but^ they do not tarnish my opinion.</tei:p><tei:p>Additionally, as soon as I can I especially want to study more carefully what you say about Beethoven’s Fifth Symphony in that issue, above all out of a sense of fairness and, so to speak, for my own education and assessment, because that symphony is for me the most alien, the inimical one among Beethoven’s symphonies.  I received the piano sonatas, four volumes, and very much thank you<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> that you arranged for this valuable gift to be sent to me.  In your letter<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> I hope soon to find your wishes with regard to my music.  I send it to you especially gladly (even if you don’t think as well of it as I do).  My music for <tei:hi rend="italic">A Midsummer Night’s Dream</tei:hi> is currently being typeset.  In the next few days the music for <tei:hi rend="italic">Winter’s Tale</tei:hi> is to follow.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  All of my theater music is written for small instrumentation, i.e. for our school orchestra.</tei:p><tei:p>With cordial greetings,
Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] A. Halm</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> You will also write me whether you would like to have the <tei:hi rend="italic">parts</tei:hi> for my A-major quartet, right?</tei:p><tei:p>P.S. April 1, 1924  You know, one should of course in the end say what one considers to be true, but in a way that communicates something by it.  Such ideals will not lead devotees of Berlioz (by the way, are there in fact so many of them that a wave of proselytizing is necessary, even with your view?) to quiet examination of their viewpoint.</tei:p><tei:p>As I said, without question I concede one and another weakness in Berlioz.  But to me he is vain, smug—I find these traits sometimes in Brahms.  And then, is a melody like “Rosen brach ich nachts mir” [op. 94, no. 4]; “Holder klingt der Vogelsang” [op. 71, no. 5]<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> perchance less silly than the failed melody of Berlioz?</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>