<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 12/31, [3] : 7-11-24 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Under investigation
© Transcription Ian Bent, 2006.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is presumed to be in the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1924-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 07/11/1924 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "DeutschS ~ HSchenker","Lamberg ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Typed letter from Lamberg to Schenker, dated July 11, 1924</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-09-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Acks OJ 5/24; S's right to exclusive determination of the Deutsch stipendia lapses with the dissolution of the Verein;  L recommends S to meet with Marx and seek a solution approximating Deutsch's intentions more closely than the agreement reach in court.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Lamberg, Ernst; Schenker, Heinrich;  Deutsch, Sofie; Sophie;  stipendium for musicians;  Verein zur Speisung und Bekleidung hungernder Schulkinder in Wien;  Association for Feeding and Clothing Hungry Schoolchildren in Vienna; Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst;  Academy for Music and Representational Art;  Vienna Conservatory;  Marx, Josef;  agreement</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Vienna I, Mahlerstrasse 14</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Galtür, Tyrol, Palnauntal</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Lamberg to Schenker, dated July 11, 1924</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>]
Rechtsanwalt
Dr. Ernst Lamberg
WIEN I.
MAHLERSTRASSE 14
(FRÜHERE MAXIMILIANSTRASSE)
<tei:hi rend="italic">_</tei:hi><tei:hi rend="italic">_</tei:hi><tei:hi rend="italic">_</tei:hi><tei:hi rend="italic">_</tei:hi>__
Telefon Nr. -XXXXX- 76333.  
Postsparkasse-Konto 173.736</tei:p><tei:p>Wien, am <tei:hi rend="italic">11. Juli</tei:hi> 192<tei:hi rend="italic">4</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">typed:</tei:hi>]
F 33/O.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Professor!</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr gesch. Schreiben vom 8.d.M. habe ich erhalten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  OJ 5/24, which is a draft, of the same date, of the letter sent.</tei:note>  Ich erlaube mir hiezu zu bemerken, dass die Rechtslage die ist, das <tei:hi rend="italic">nur</tei:hi> der Verein zur Speisung und Bekleidung hungernder Schulkinde<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="verein_zur_speisung">Verein zur Speisung und Bekleidung hungernder Schulkinder in Wien</ref>.</tei:note> verpflichtet war, Ihnen die Entscheidung über die Stipendien<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  The “stipends for impecuious skilled composers and composition pupils” endowed by Sofie Deutsch died January 7, 1917) in her will.  See in particular the letter OJ 12/52, January 12, 1917, from Fritz Mendel to S.</tei:note> zu überlassen.</tei:p><tei:p>Für den Fall der Auflösung des Vereines hat die Erblasserin keinerlei Verfügung getroffen und war daher eine Lösung zu suchen, die dem Willen der Erblasserin möglichst nahekommt.</tei:p><tei:p>Diese Lösung ist in dem Ihnen von mir mitgeteilten Gerichtsbeschlusse enthalten, wornach der Akademie 20,000.000 K mit dem Ersuchen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  “Ersuchen” underlined by hand, probably by S.</tei:note> zuzuwenden sind, die Stipendien auszuzahlen und Ihnen auf Lebenszeit die Entscheidung zu überlassen.</tei:p><tei:p>Dies ist geschehen und die Antwort der Akademie habe ich Ihnen mitgeteilt.</tei:p><tei:p>Es liegt daher nicht in meiner Macht und ist auch durchaus nicht meine Aufgabe, die Akademie zu einer Aenderung ihrer Stellungnahme zu veranlassen.  Wenn Sie der Meinung sind, dass die Akademie sich ihre Ternavorschläge nicht vorbehalten sollte, und so grossen Wert auf die alleinige <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Entscheidung legen, dann muss ich Sie bitten, sich hierüber mit der Akademie direkt ins Einvernehmen zu setzen.  Ich zweifle nicht, dass Sie in persönlicher Rücksprache mit Herrn Prof. Marx<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="marx_joseph">Joseph Marx</ref>.</tei:note> die Angelegenheit in einer beide Teile befriedigenden Weise austragen werden, wozu, da die nächste Stipendiumauszahlung erst am 5. Jänner 1925 zu erfolgen hat, nach Ihrer Rückkehr vom Urlaube sicherlich Zeit genug ist.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich zeichne mit vorzüglicher Hochachtung als
Ihr ergebener
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] D^r.^ Lamberg</tei:p><tei:p>Wolgeboren
Herrn Prof. Dr. Heinrich S c h e n k e r ,
Galtür in Tirol,
Palnauntal.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Lamberg to Schenker, dated July 11, 1924</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>]
Attorney
Dr. Ernst Lamberg
VIENNA I,
MAHLERSTRASSE 14,
(PREVIOUSLY MAXIMILIANSTRASSE)
<tei:hi rend="italic">_</tei:hi><tei:hi rend="italic">_</tei:hi><tei:hi rend="italic">_</tei:hi><tei:hi rend="italic">_</tei:hi>__
Telephone No. -XXXXX- 76333.  
Post Office Bank Account 173.736</tei:p><tei:p>Vienna, <tei:hi rend="italic">July 11,</tei:hi> 192<tei:hi rend="italic">4</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">typed:</tei:hi>]
F 33/O.</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor,</tei:p><tei:p>I am in receipt of your letter of the 8th inst.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  I take the liberty of observing that the legal position is that the Association for Feeding and Clothing Hungry Schoolchildre<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> <tei:hi rend="italic">alone</tei:hi> was obligated to leave the decision regarding the stipends<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> in your hands.</tei:p><tei:p>In the event of the Association’s dissolution, the deceased has made no provision of any sort, thus a solution needs to be sought that approximates as closely as possibly the wishes of the deceased.</tei:p><tei:p>This solution is contained in the court decision conveyed by me to you whereby the 20,000,000 Kroner are to be bestowed upon the Academy with the request<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> that it disburse the stipends and leave the choice in your hands for your lifetime.</tei:p><tei:p>This has happened, and the Academy’s decision has been communicated to you.</tei:p><tei:p>Accordingly, nothing lies in my power, and it is also absolutely not my job to induce the Academy to change its position.  If you are of the opinion that the Academy ought not to reserve its [right to produce a] slate of three candidates, and [if you] place such great value on the [right to] exclusive <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> decision, then I must ask you to come to terms directly with the Academy over this matter.  I do not doubt that in personal discussion with Professor Marx<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> you will settle the matter in a manner agreeable to both parties, for which there is surely enough time after your return from vacation, since the next stipendium disbursement has not to be made until January 5, 1925.</tei:p><tei:p>I remain wiith kind regards,
Yours truly,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ]  Dr. Lamberg</tei:p><tei:p>Professor Heinrich S c h e n k e r , Esq.,
Galtür, in the Tyrol,
Palnauntal.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>