<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 12/17, [5] : 6-18-24 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  Under inquiry
©  Transcription Michaela Searfoorce, 2008
©  Translation Michaela Searfoorce, 2008
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Michaela Searfoorce 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Under inquiry.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1924-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Under inquiry; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Michaela Searfoorce.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 06/18/1924 12:31:18 PM --><!-- MT Tags: "Komorn ~ H+JSchenker","Komorn ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Komorn to Heinrich Schenker, dated June 18, 1924</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-02-01</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Komorn expresses fullsome thanks to Schenker for what he has taught her in a single year.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Komorn, Maria; Schenker, Heinrich;  thanks;  lessons;  health;  synthesis;  Weisse, Hans</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Komorn to Heinrich Schenker, dated June 18, 1924</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Herr Professor!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary on June 20:  "Thanks [me] for the instruction, from the health point of view, too." (Von Frau Komorn (Br.):  dankt für den Unterrich auch vom Standpunkt der Hygiene) (OJ 3/6, pp. 2681-2682).  Komorn probably knew that June 19 was Schenker's birthday.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ich kann es <tei:hi rend="italic">doch</tei:hi> nicht über mich bringen, so ganz wortlos für eine lange Ferienzeit von Ihnen zu scheiden. Danken? - Nun, so albern werd' ich nicht sein, um mit wenigen hilflosen Worten all dem gerecht werden zu wollen, das ich künstlerisch von Ihnen zu empfangen das Glück hatte.  Doch werden Sie es mir hoffentlich gestatten, &lt;del&gt;xxx&lt;/del&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;Ihnen an Stelle&lt;/sup&gt; aller Gemeinplätze ein ganz Weniges über die Wandlung in Geist und Gemüt zu sagen, die, auf dem Boden künstlerischer Vermittlung ruhend, der persönliche Umgang mit [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] Ihnen im <tei:hi rend="italic">Ganzen</tei:hi> in mir bewirkt hat.</tei:p><tei:p>Dass es möglich ist, Gelassenheit, Nervenruhe dem Leben und der Kunst gegenüber zu erwerben, ohne dafür den Preis eines aus letzte Ende gelangten <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Daseins bezahlen zu müssen, also einen ganz kleinen Teil dieses köstlichsten Gutes noch für einen Rest [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] des Lebens nützen zu können, dass das möglich ist, hab' ich nicht gewusst.  Besser gesagt, dass es <tei:hi rend="italic">meiner</tei:hi> Veranlagung möglich ist.  Und obwohl ich sehr gut weiß, wie weit dieser Weg für mich noch ist, dass ich erst einen ganz kleinen, schüchternen Schritt getan habe, so darf ich wohl mit strengstem Gewissen auch jetzt schon sagen:  Ich bin in dem heurigen Jahre ein anderer Mensch geworden. Aus einem Leben voll ständiger Angst, voll fiebernder Unruhe im Größten und im Kleinsten ist - - noch lange kein Leben der besonnenen Ruhe, der seelischen Gefasstheit geworden, wie es mir als Ziel vorschwebt.  Dazu ist ja die Zeit noch viel zu kurz. Wohl aber ein Leben der Zuversicht, dass es einmal so werden könnte, dass es nicht notwendig ist, zu verzagen, solange &lt;del&gt;es&lt;/del&gt; Jemand lebt, dem die Macht gegeben ist, uns dazu zu helfen.</tei:p><tei:p>Und wenn ich jemals einer Bestätigung dessen bedurft hätte, dass der Mensch vom Künstler, die Kunst vom Leben nie und nimmer zu trennen ist, - keine schönere könnte es für mich geben als die kostbare Erfahrung, wie ich in Klavier-technischen Nöten zu Ihnen, verehrter Meister kam, um nach einem kurzen Studienjahr als ein <tei:hi rend="italic">geistig</tei:hi> und <tei:hi rend="italic">auch körperlich</tei:hi> Gesünderer der Welt und dem Leben gegenüberzustehen.  Ich weiß nicht, ob irgend Jemand so bald Sinn und Inbegriff der Schenkerschen „Synthese" zu erfassen vermag wie ich es am eigenen Leib u. Wesen vermochte:  dass ein richtiger Fingersatz, eine richtige Handhaltung &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;schließlich&lt;/sup&gt; eine richtige Einstellung zur Welt nach sich ziehen muss. Ihr Wort „Man kann Villen bauen zwischen 2 Sechzehnteln" verehrter Herr Professor, habe ich mir gut gemerkt und es hat mir schon viel genützt, auch außerhalb der Sechzehntel.  Dass aber eine solche Wirkung bloß <tei:hi rend="italic">Ihr</tei:hi> unvergleichliches, unerreichbares Eigentum ist, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> hätte doch Hans Weisse<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  (Click on) <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref> was Komorn's teacher before Schenker took her on in the fall of 1923.  He had been a student of Schenker between 1908 and 1919.  </tei:note> am besten wissen müssen, der so lange um Sie war.  Würde er ahnen, was er damit gerade <tei:hi rend="italic">mir</tei:hi> entziehen wollte, was gerade <tei:hi rend="italic">ich</tei:hi> mit meiner Unsicherheit dem Leben gegenüber, meinem ewigen Kampf um menschliche Ausgeglichenheit brauchte, es würde auch für <tei:hi rend="italic">ihn</tei:hi> einen großen innern Fortschritt bedeuten.</tei:p><tei:p>Für die unendliche Geduld und Güte, die Sie mir bewiesen, sag' ich Ihnen meinen bewundernden Dank und habe wirklich keinen tiefern Herzenswunsch als dass mir noch recht lange das Glück gegönnt sei, bei Ihnen arbeiten zu dürfen, damit ich einmal Ihre Mahnung „Gesundheit ist gut spielen" ganz verwirklichen könnte.</tei:p><tei:p>Ihnen, verehrter Herr Professor u. der verehrten gnädigen Frau nochmals recht glückliche Ferien<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  The Schenkers departed on June 28 for Galtür.  </tei:note> und die ergebensten Empfehlungen Ihrer dankbaren Schülerin</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Maria Komorn
18.6.24</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Komorn to Heinrich Schenker, dated June 18, 1924</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Most honored Professor,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>I <tei:hi rend="italic">really</tei:hi> cannot bring myself to part from you for a long holiday period in this way without saying something.  Thanks? -- Now, I will not be so silly as to try to do justice with a few feeble words to all that I have had the fortune to receive from you artistically.  However, I hope you will permit me to say &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;to you, instead of&lt;/sup&gt; platitudes, just a little about the change in mind and spirit, which, on a foundation of artistic mediation[?], my personal association with you has wrought in me <tei:hi rend="italic">overall</tei:hi>.</tei:p><tei:p>That it is possible to acquire composure, calmness of the nerves, in relation to life and art, without having to pay the price of <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> coming to the end of one's life, and so still to be able to use a tiny part of this most delicious of bounties for the small amount that is left of one's life, this I did not know--put better, [I did not know] that it was possible for <tei:hi rend="italic">my</tei:hi> state of mind.  And although I know full well how far I still have to go along this path, [and] that I have taken only a few very small, timid steps, even so, I can already say with firmest conviction:  During this past year, I have become a different person.  Coming from a life full of constant anxiety, full of feverish unrest even down to the smallest things, I am still far from achieving a life of peace and calm, of spiritual tranquillity,  which I envision as my goal.  The time has been too short for that.  However, it is not necessary to give up hope of a life of confidence, as it could one day be, so long as there is someone to whom the power is granted to help us toward that goal.</tei:p><tei:p>And if ever I needed confirmation that man can never be separated from artist, art from life, no more beautiful confirmation could be given me than the precious experience [that I had] when I came to you, honored master, in need of pianistic-technical help, in order to face the world and life after one short academic year as a <tei:hi rend="italic">mentally</tei:hi> and <tei:hi rend="italic">also physically</tei:hi> healthier person.  I do not know whether anyone has been able to absorb the sense and inner meaning of Schenkerian "synthesis" as quickly as I have into my own body and being:  that a correct fingering, a correct hand position must &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;ultimately&lt;/sup&gt; entail a correct attitude toward the world.  Honored Professor, I have marked well your saying "Mansions can be built between two sixteenth-notes," and it has already been of much use to me, even outside of the realm of sixteenth-notes.  But that such an impact belongs incomparably and unassailably to <tei:hi rend="italic">you</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Hans Weisse,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> who was around you for so long, must surely have known best.  Were he to suspect that what he tried by that means to draw out of <tei:hi rend="italic">me</tei:hi>, what <tei:hi rend="italic">I</tei:hi> myself needed, with my insecurity in relation to life, my eternal struggle for human balance, it would mean, even for <tei:hi rend="italic">him</tei:hi>, a great inner progress.</tei:p><tei:p>I offer you my admiring thanks for the endless patience and kindness that you show me.  I have truly no deeper, more heartfelt wish than to be granted the good fortune of being allowed to work with you for a very long time further, so that one day I might realize in full your cautionary saying "Health is playing well."</tei:p><tei:p>Once more, a very happy holiday, honored Professor, and your dear wife,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> and kindest regards, from your grateful student</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Maria Komorn
June 18, 1924</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>