<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OC 52/923 : 6-6-19 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  Universal Edition A.G., Wien.
©  Transcription Robert Kosovsky and Ian Bent, 2009
©  Translation Ian Bent, 2009
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2009.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>email from Aygün Lausch (Universal Edition) to Ian Bent, 2004-09-09, confirming UE's ownership of IPR and granting permission to post to pilot website.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1919-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-1938) - -Oster, Ernst (1938-c.1939) - -New York Public Library (c.1939-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Universal Edition, A.G.; Image: New York Public Library, New York; Transcription Robert Kosovsky and Ian Bent, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 06/06/1919 02:33:06 PM --><!-- MT Tags: "Hertzka ~ HSchenker","UE ~ H+JSchenker","UE ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Typed letter from Hertzka (UE) to Schenker, dated June 6, 1919</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-06-07</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Acknowledging receipt of WSLB 302, Hertzka cannot entertain early publication of Weisse's work but wishes to get to know it now.   - - He hopes to have work from Schenker's pen as soon as work for Cotta is finished.   - - He proposes that the Foreword to Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven ... op. 111 be omitted [in future] .

  </dc:description><dc:subject>Hertzka, Emil;  UE; Schenker, Heinrich;  Weisse, Hans;  publication;  Cotta;  Kleine Bibliothek;  Little Library;  Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven;  op. 111;  Vorwort;  Foreword</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Vienna I. Karlsplatz 6</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Vienna</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Hertzka (UE) to Schenker, dated June 6, 1919</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">typewriter ink badly smudged</tei:hi>]  
[<tei:hi rend="italic">UE letterhead</tei:hi>]
Wien I. Karlsplatz 6
[<tei:hi rend="italic">illegible</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>Wien, [<tei:hi rend="italic">typed:</tei:hi>] 6. Juni 1919.</tei:p><tei:p>Wohlgeboren [/] Herrn Prof. Heinrich S c h e n k e r
<tei:hi rend="italic">W i e n</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Professor!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Receipt of this letter is recorded at OJ 2/14, pp. 2078-2079, June 9, 1919:  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Nach längerer Abwesenheit nach Wien zurückgekehrt, finde ich Ihre gesch. Zuschrift vom 20. Mai<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Presumably = WSLB 302, May 18, 1919.  There is no diary record of a letter having been written to UE on May 20.  </tei:note> vor und ich bitte Sie zu entschuldigen, dass ich erst mit einer solchen Verzögerung auf dieselbe antworten komme.</tei:p><tei:p>So gerne ich auch infolge Ihrer warmen Empfehlung der Herausgabe der Arbeit Weisses nähertreten möchte, so schwer dürfte dies im gegenwärtigen Augenblick<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  "Im ... Augenblick" (at the present moment): underlined by Schenker.  </tei:note> sein, da wir noch immer an einer schrecklichen Papierknappheit leiden und die Herstellungskosten augenblicklich eine derartige Höhe erreicht haben, dass man nur das Allernotwendigste herausbringen kann.  Ich möchte aber jedenfalls die Arbeit des Herrn Weisses kennen lernen und vielleicht ergibt sich dann doch eine Möglichkeit, der Herausgabe näherzutreten.</tei:p><tei:p>Hoffentlich werden Sie selbst nun Ihre Arbeit für Cotta<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="cotta_j_g">J. G. Cotta</ref>.  </tei:note> bald beendigen können und ich werde die Freude haben, wieder etwas aus Ihrer Feder - ob es nun die längst projektierte "kleine Bibliothek"<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="kleine_bibliothek"><tei:hi rend="italic">Kleine Bibliothek</tei:hi></ref>.  </tei:note> ist oder sonst eine Arbeit - für unseren Verlag zu erhalten.  Die schreckliche Zeit wird ja auch vorübergehen und die <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Stadt Beethovens, Mozarts und Schuberts wird auch das überstehen.  Für das Umsetzen des Nationalgefühls in Geld, habe ich wenig Verständnis.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit den besten Grüssen
Ihr in aufrichtiger Hochschätzung
ergebener
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hertzka</tei:p><tei:p>N.S. 
Ich nehme an, dass Sie nichts dagegen haben, wenn das Vorwort zur letzterschienenen kritischen Ausgabe der Beethoven-Sonaten,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Schenker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven ... op. 111</tei:hi> (Vienna: UE, 1915), p. 3 (not included in the 1971 reprint).  </tei:note> das heute in keiner Weise mehr zeitgmäss ist, und der Weiterverbreitung des Heftes absolut hinderlich wäre, wegfällt.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Hertzka (UE) to Schenker, dated June 6, 1919</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">typewriter ink badly smudged</tei:hi>]  
[<tei:hi rend="italic">UE letterhead</tei:hi>]
Vienna I, Karlsplatz 6
[<tei:hi rend="italic">illegible</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>Vienna, [typed:] June 6, 1919</tei:p><tei:p>Prof. Heinrich S c h e n k e r,  Esq.
<tei:hi rend="italic">V i e n n a</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Back in Vienna after a long absence, I have your esteemed letter of May 20<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> before me and ask you to excuse my getting round to answering it only now, after so long a delay.</tei:p><tei:p>Greatly though I should like to give closer consideration, in light of your warm commendation, to publishing Weisse's work, this would be hard to achieve at the present moment,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> since we continue to suffer from a terrible scarcity of paper, and production costs have at this point reached such a pitch that we can publish only what is absolutely indispensable.  I should, however, at any rate like to become better acquainted with Mr. Weisse's work, then perhaps the possibility may yet arise of taking steps toward publication.</tei:p><tei:p>It is to be hoped that you yourself will now soon be able to finish off your work for Cotta,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> and I will have the pleasure once again of having something from your pen--be it the long-projected <tei:hi rend="italic">Little Library</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> or some other work--for our publishing house.  These dreadful times will surely pass, and the <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> city of Beethoven, Mozart, and Schubert will survive even that.  Of the translation of national feeling into money I have little knowledge.</tei:p><tei:p>With most cordial greetings,
and with kind regards,
Yours truly,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  Hertzka</tei:p><tei:p>P.S.  
I take it that you will have no objection if the Foreword to the most recently appeared critical edition of the Beethoven sonatas<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> is omitted, since it is no longer at all in keeping with the times and would be absolutely detrimental to the wider dissemination of the volume.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>