<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OC 52/507-508 : 12-19-19 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Universal Edition A.G., Wien.
© Transcription Ian Bent 2009.
©  Translation Ian Bent, 2009
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2009.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>email from Aygün Lausch (Universal Edition) to Ian Bent, 2004-09-09, confirming UE's ownership of IPR and granting permission to post to pilot website.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1919-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-1938) - -Oster, Ernst (1938-c.1939) - -New York Public Library (c.1939-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Universal Edition, A.G.; Image: New York Public Library, New York; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 12/19/1919 04:11:29 PM --><!-- MT Tags: "Hertzka ~ HSchenker","UE ~ H+JSchenker","UE ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Typed letter from Hertzka (UE) to Schenker, dated December 19, 1919</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-05-15</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Hertzka is pleased that Louis Koch has given his consent [for Op. 101];  suggests that UE obtain certain sources from the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde Archive on loan at the office for Schenker to work on;  offers a larger fee for Op. 101, and cautions Schenker about growing costs of photographic work.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Hertzka, Emil; UE; Schenker, Heinrich;  Beethoven;  Op. 101;  Koch, Louis;  Frankfurt;  Op. 106;  autographs;  Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde;  Archive;  loan;  Kleine Bibliothek;  Little Library;  Mandyczewski, Eusebius;  photography;  cost</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Vienna I, Karlsplatz 6</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Vienna</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Hertzka (UE) to Schenker, dated December 19, 1919</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">UE letterhead</tei:hi>]
[Wien] I, Karlsplatz 6
D/K/W
Wien [<tei:hi rend="italic">typed:</tei:hi>] 19. Dez. 1919.
Wohlgeboren [/] Herrn Prof. Dr. Heinrich S c h e n k e r
<tei:hi rend="italic">W i e n</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hochgeehrter Herr Doktor!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/1, p. 2195, December 23, 1919:  "Von Hertzka (Br.):  mahnt mich zur Vorsicht in Sachen der Photographie, macht sich erbötig, aus dem Archiv die gewünschten Stücke in sein Bureau bringen zu lassen, wo ich sie Sonntags durchstudieren könnte."  ("From Hertzka (letter):  urges caution on me in matters of photography, offers his help in having the desired pieces brought from the Archive to his office, where I could study them on a Sunday.")    </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Besten Dank für Ihre geschätzte Zuschrift vom 17. ds.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  = WSLB 310.  </tei:note>  aus welcher ich gerne ersehe, dass Sie nunmehr die Zusage des Herrn Koch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="koch_louis">Louis Koch</ref>.  </tei:note> aus Frankfurt wegen Opus 101<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Schenker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven ... op. 101</tei:hi> (Vienna: UE, 1920).  </tei:note> erhalten haben.  Ich werde, sobald ich im Jänner nach Frankfurt komme, mit Herrn Koch wegen der Frage der Faksimileausgabe sprechen.  Hoffentlich kann ich die Bilder bis dahin mit mir nehmen.  Wegen Opus 106<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Beethoven's Piano Sonata, Op. 106:  ultimately, because the autograph manuscript could not be located, this volume of <tei:hi rend="italic">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven</tei:hi> was never produced.  </tei:note> werde ich natürlich alles Erdenkliche versuchen, um den Autographen auf die Spur zu kommen.</tei:p><tei:p>Was nun das Archiv<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="gesellschaft_der_mus">Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde</ref>.  </tei:note> betrifft, so halte ich es schon für möglich, dass die Originalausgabe uns für kurze Zeit leihweise zur Verfügung gestellt wird, eventuell über einen Sonntag, so dass Sie dann leicht die Zeit hätten, sich mit derselben zu beschäftigen.  Wenn Ihnen also dieser Vorgang erwünscht ist, so bitte ich Sie, mir dies mitzuteilen, worauf ich mich sofort mit Mandyczewski<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="mandyczewski_eusebiu">Eusebius Mandyczewski</ref>.  </tei:note> in Verbindung setzen würde.  Vielleicht wird dann auch bezüglich der kleinen Bibliothek<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="kleine_bibliothek">Kleine Bibliothek</ref>.  </tei:note> ein ähnliches Auskunftsmittel getroffen werden können, damit Ihre Zeit nicht <tei:hi rend="bold">{2 = 508}</tei:hi> allzusehr in Anspruch genommen wird.  Es wäre auch unter Umständen denkbar, dass wir z.B. op. 106 Originalausgabe für unser Bureau über einen Sonntag geliehen bekommen, mit der Verpflichtung, dass das Exemplar nicht aus dem Hause kommt und dass Sie in diesem Falle Sonntag vormittag sich einige Stunden hier mit der Sache beschäftigen.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich möchte noch meiner Genugtuung Ausdruck geben, dass wir uns über die verschiedenen Fragen verständigt haben und glaube, dass Sie nunmehr keinen Grund haben, sich wegen der Grosszügigkeit der Universal-Edition zu sorgen[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>], nachdem ich Ihnen für op. 101, an Stelle der verträglich festgelegten 1200 Kronen 15000 [alt from 1500] Kronen bewilligt habe.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  "der Grosszügigkeit der" (the generosity of) and "verträglich ... bewilligt habe" (contractually ... Kronen):  underlined by Schenker, and "!" in the left-hand margin.  </tei:note> [<tei:hi rend="italic">in HS's hand:</tei:hi> im Jahre 1919]</tei:p><tei:p>Während unserer persönlichen Besprechung meinten Sie auch, dass wir die Kosten des Photographierens tragen sollten.  Ich möchte nun doch, ehe ich nach dieser Richtung hin eine bindende Verpflichtung eingehe, diese Kosten kennen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  "des Photographierens" (of the photographic work), "möchte nun doch" (I should like), and "diese Kosten kennen" (to know what these costs are):  underlined by Schenker, and "!" in the right-hand margin.  </tei:note> damit Ueberraschungen ausgeschlossen werden und ich darf Sie wohl bitten, da ich nicht weiss, in welcher Weise Sie mit Herrn Koch über die Sache verkehrt haben, sich zunächst doch über die erwachsenden Kosten für die Photographien zu informieren.  Man hat derzeit in Bezug auf Preisbildung schon derartige Ueberraschungen erlebt, dass Sie meine Vorsicht wahrscheinlich ganz verständlich finden werden.</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in HS's hand, in lower margin:</tei:hi>]  auf Bl III, nur Unterschrift (wegen einer Noten-Skizze weggenommen)</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Hertzka (UE) to Schenker, dated December 19, 1919</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">UE letterhead</tei:hi>]
[Vienna] I, Karlsplatz 6
D/K/W
Vienna [<tei:hi rend="italic">typed:</tei:hi>] Dec. 19, 1919.
Prof. Heinrich S c h e n k e r, Esq., 
<tei:hi rend="italic">V i e n n a</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Dr. [Schenker],<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Many thanks for your esteemed letter of the 17th inst.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>, from which I am happy to learn that you have received consent from Mr. Koch<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> in Frankfurt henceforth in respect of <tei:hi rend="italic">Op. 101</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  As soon as I get to Frankfurt in January, I will speak with Mr. Koch regarding the question of the facsimile edition.  Let us hope that I shall be able by then to bring the pictures back with me.  As regards Op. 106,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> I will of course try everything I can think of to track down the autographs.</tei:p><tei:p>Now as concerns the Archive,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> I think it quite possible that the original edition will be made available to us on loan for a short time, possibly over a Sunday, so that you would then have ample time to do what you need with it.  So if this procedure seems desirable to you, then please let me know, whereupon I would immediately be in touch with Mandyczewski.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>   Perhaps a similar way forward can also be found in connection with the <tei:hi rend="italic">Little Library</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> so that your time <tei:hi rend="bold">{2 = 508}</tei:hi> will not be unduly encroached upon.  It is even conceivable, should the need arise, that for example we might procure the original edition of Op. 106 on loan for our office over a Sunday, on the understanding that the copy not go beyond these four walls and that you in that case spend a few hours working on it here on a Sunday morning.</tei:p><tei:p>I should further like to express my gratification that we have come to agreement over the various matters, and I believe that you have henceforth no reason to harbor any doubts as to the generosity of Universal Edition, since for <tei:hi rend="italic">Op. 101</tei:hi> instead of the contractually set 1,200 Kronen I have granted you 15,000 [<tei:hi rend="italic">alt from</tei:hi> 1,500] Kronen.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/>  [<tei:hi rend="italic">in HS's hand:</tei:hi>  in the year 1919]</tei:p><tei:p>In the course of our face-to-face discussion you also expressed the opinion that we ought to bear the costs of the photographic work.  Before I enter into a binding commitment in this direction, I should first like to know what these costs are,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> so as to avoid any surprises.  And I should like to ask you, since I have no idea in what terms you have discussed this matter with Mr. Koch, first of all to gather information as to the growing costs for the photographs.  One has in one's time experienced some unpleasant surprises with respect to price setting, so you will perhaps find my caution quite understandable.</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in HS's hand, in lower margin:</tei:hi>]  on sheet 3, only [a] signature (removed on account of a notational sketch)</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>