<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OC 52/138 : 1-5-14 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Universal Edition A.G., Wien.
© Transcription Ian D. Bent 2004.
© Translation Ian D. Bent 2004.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian D. Bent 2004.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>email from Aygün Lausch (Universal Edition) to Ian Bent, 2004-09-09, confirming UE’s ownership of IPR and granting permission to post to pilot website.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1914-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-1938) - -Oster, Ernst (1938-c.1939)—New York Public Library (c.1939-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Universal Edition, A.G.; Image: New York Public Library, New York; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian D. Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 01/05/1914 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Hertzka ~ HSchenker","UE ~ H+JSchenker","UE ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Typed letter from Hertzka (UE) to Schenker, dated January 5,  1914</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2004-11-17</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>
</dc:description><dc:subject>Hertzka, Emil; UE; Schenker, Heinrich;  Kreuz-Zeitung; article; review; Kleine Flugschriften; Little Pamphlets; Beethoven; Ninth Symphony; score; Berlin; Leipzig; Eulenburg; meeting; coffee house</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Vienna I, Reichsrathsstraße 9</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Vienna</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Hertzka (UE) to Schenker, dated January 5, 1914</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">UE letterhead</tei:hi>]
Wien I, Reichsratsstrasse 9
W
Wien [<tei:hi rend="italic">typed:</tei:hi>] 5. Jänner 1914.</tei:p><tei:p>Wohlgeboren [/] Herrn Prof. Dr. Heinrich  S c h e n k e r
<tei:hi rend="italic">W i e n</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Herr Doktor !</tei:p><tei:p>In sofortiger Erledigung Ihrer gesch. Karte von gestern<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  = WSLB 197, January 4, 1914.  </tei:note> lasse ich mir sogleich das Exemplar der Berliner Kreuz-Zeitung vom 31./XII.  besorgen.  Wenn Sie mir inzwischen den Artikel auf einige Tage leihen könnten, ware ich Ihnen sehr verbunden.</tei:p><tei:p>Ueber Ihre Meldung, dass Vrieslanders Arbeit<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.  This refers to: <tei:hi rend="italic">Kurze und leichte Clavierstücke mit veränderten Reprisen und beigefügter Fingersetzung für Anfänger von Carl Philipp Emanuel Bach</tei:hi> [ ... ] <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue kritische Ausgabe mit erläuterndem Nachwort von Otto Vrieslander</tei:hi> (Vienna: UE, c1912 by Schuberthaus-Verlag Leipzig).</tei:note> sehr zufriedenstellend ausgefallen ist, habe ich mich sehr gefreut und ich bin auf die Sache schon sehr neugierig.</tei:p><tei:p>Die kleinen Flugschriften<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="kleine_bibliothek">Kleine Bibliothek</ref>.  </tei:note> wären allerdings sehr wichtig  und ich hoffe, es kommt zur Ausführung dieses schönen Planes.</tei:p><tei:p>Nächste Woche bin ich in Leipzig und Berlin.  In Leipzig werde ich die Möglichkeit haben, mit Eulenburg wegen der Beethoven IX.-Partitur zu unterhandeln und wenn möglich, mir die Platten für eine Ausgabe (nach dem Faksimile) zu sichern.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="ninth_symphony_score">Ninth Symphony score</ref>.  </tei:note>  Allerdings möchte ich noch von Ihnen gerne hören, ob es sicher ist, dass diese Platten in der Taschenpartitur-Ausgabe, selbstredend mit Retouchen und Aenderungen für die von Ihnen projektierte Ausgabe benütztbar sein werden. [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr from</tei:hi> wird.]  Vielleicht ist es doch möglich, dass wir uns im Laufe dieser Woche einmal,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  The day of writing is Monday; see WSLB 198, January 6, and OC 52/139 and WSLB 199, January 7, 1914 further on this planned meeting.</tei:note> wenn auch abends im Kaffeehaus, auf eine halbe Stunde noch sprechen können, damit <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> ich mir in der Angelegenheit der weiteren Herausgabe von Beethoven IX. Symphonie-Partitur vollkommen klar werde.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich stehe Ihnen jeden Abend zur Verfügung und begrüsse Sie in aufrichtiger Hochschätzung.</tei:p><tei:p>ergebenst
[<tei:hi rend="italic">stamp:</tei:hi>] Universal-Edition Actiongesellschaft  [<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Herztka</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Hertzka (UE) to Schenker, dated January 5, 1914</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">UE letterhead</tei:hi>]
Vienna I, Reichsratsstraße 9
W
Vienna [<tei:hi rend="italic">typed:</tei:hi>] January 5, 1914</tei:p><tei:p>Prof. Heinrich  S c h e n k e r, Esq.,
<tei:hi rend="italic">V i e n n a</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Honored Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>In prompt response to your esteemed postcard of yesterday,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> I will get hold of the issue of the Berlin <tei:hi rend="italic">Kreuz-Zeitung</tei:hi> for December 31 for myself right away.  If in the meanwhile you could lend me the article for a day or two, I should be greatly indebted to you.</tei:p><tei:p>I was delighted at your report that Vrieslander’s work<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> has turned out very satisfactorily, and am already highly curious about the matter.</tei:p><tei:p>The Little Pamphlets<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> would certainly be very important, and I hope that this excellent plan will come to fruition.</tei:p><tei:p>Next week, I am in Leipzig and Berlin.  In Leipzig, I shall have a chance to negotiate with Eulenburg over the score of Beethoven’s Ninth Symphony, and if possible secure for myself the plates for an edition (after[?] the facsimile).<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  I should certainly still[?] be glad to hear from you whether these plates, belonging to the miniature score edition, are sure to be usable, naturally with adjustments and alterations, for the edition that you have in mind.  Perhaps we can manage to have half an hour’s talk some time this week,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> possibly even one evening in the coffee house, so that <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> I can be perfectly clear in the matter of the further edition of the Beethoven Ninth Symphony score.</tei:p><tei:p>I am at your disposal any evening, and send you my very kind regards.</tei:p><tei:p>Yours truly,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">stamp:</tei:hi>] Universal Edition &amp; Co. [<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Herztka</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>