<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OC 52/559 : 3-5-18 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Universal Edition A.G., Wien.
© Transcription Ian D. Bent 2009.
© Translation Ian D. Bent 2009.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2009.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>email from Aygün Lausch (Universal Edition) to Ian Bent, 2004-09-09, confirming UE's ownership of IPR and granting permission to post to pilot website.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1918-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-1938) - -Oster, Ernst (1938-c.1939) - -New York Public Library (c.1939-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Universal Edition, A.G.; Image: New York Public Library, New York; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 03/05/1918 10:01:43 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Hertzka ~ HSchenker","UE ~ H+JSchenker","UE ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Typed letter from Hertzka (UE) to Schenker, dated March 5, 1918</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-02-27</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Hertzka will inquire about a review published in Lausanne;  has dispatched Op. 111 to Steglich and encloses invoice and payment order;  in light of Brest-Litovsk, he inquires about Kontrapunkt2 and the Kleine Bibibliothek.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Hertzka, Emil; UE; Schenker, Heinrich;  Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven;  The Last Five Sonatas of Beethoven;  Lausanne;  review;  Steglich, Rudolf;  Brest-Litovsk;  Kontrapunkt2;  Kleine Bibliothek;  Little Library</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Vienna I, Karlsplatz 6</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Vienna III, Reisnerstraße 38</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Hertzka (UE) to Schenker, dated March 5, 1918</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">UE letterhead</tei:hi>]
I, Karlsplatz 6
W  
Wien, [<tei:hi rend="italic">typed:</tei:hi>] 5. März 1918.</tei:p><tei:p>Wohlgeboren [/] Herrn Prof. Dr. Heinrich  S c h e n k e r
<tei:hi rend="italic">W i e n  III.</tei:hi>
Reisnerstr.  38</tei:p><tei:p>Hochgeehrter Herr Professor!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/10, p. 851, March 6:  "has dispatched <tei:hi rend="italic">Op. 111</tei:hi> to Steglich immediately, want[ed] however to spare me the burden, sends the payment order only because of my recent complaint (the amount has again risen as much as in the earlier cases--despite correction);  under the influence of the conclusion of the peace treaty with Russia inquires after the state of play with II/2 and the Little Library." (habe an Steglich op. 111 sofort abgeschickt, von einer Belastung aber absehen wollen, sende Erlagschein nur über meine Reklamation (der Betrag ist wieder so hoch gehalten wie in den früheren Fällen - trotz Berichtigung);  erkundigt sich unter dem Eindruck des Friedenschlusses mit Rußland nach dem Stand von II^2^ u. der „kl. Bibliothek".)  -- Schenker had perhaps complained about the amount of author's discount, and this may be why Hertzka encloses the invoice along with the payment order--indeed Schenker complains in this instance, in his reply, WSLB 296, March 8!    </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Auf Ihre geschätzte gestrige Karte erlaube ich mir mitzuteilen, dass mir von einer fransösischen Kritik Ihrer Beethoven-Ausgaben<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven ... op. 111</tei:hi> (Vienna: UE, 1915).  The review appeared in the G<tei:hi rend="italic">azette de Lausanne</tei:hi>;  no copy is apparently preserved in OJ or OC.  </tei:note> nichts bekannt ist.  Ich schreibe deswegen heute an unseren Vertreter in Lausanne, vielleicht weiss er etwas und lasse mir in diesem Falle die Kritik schicken.  Selbstverständlich erhalten Sie dieselbe dann sogleich.</tei:p><tei:p>An Dr. Steglich<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="steglich_rudolf">Rudolf Steglich</ref>.  Schenker had requested the sending of a copy of <tei:hi rend="italic">Op. 111</tei:hi> to him in WSLB 294, February 23.  </tei:note> ist Ihr Opus 111 sofort wunschgemäss expediert worden.  Ich wollte von einer Belastung absehen, aber nachdem Sie eine solche neuerlich reklamieren, erlaube ich mir, die Faktura mit Erlagschein beizulagen.</tei:p><tei:p>Der gestrige definitive Friedensschluss mit Russland<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="brestlitovsk">Brest-Litovsk</ref>.  </tei:note> und die meiner Ansicht nach unausbleibliche Wirkung auf die Gesamt-Situation geben mir Gelegenheit, an Friedens-Dispositionen zu denken und ich benütze daher meine heutigen Zeilen, um Ihnen die zwischen uns des öfteren ventilierte Frage der „kleinen musikalischen Bibiliothek"[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="kleine_bibliothek"><tei:hi rend="italic">Kleine Bibliothek</tei:hi></ref>.  "kl. ... Bibliothek" (Little ... Library) underlined in crayon by Schenker.    </tei:note> in Erinnerung zu bringen.  Ich denke, Sie sind inzwischen mit Ihrer Arbeit für Cotta<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="cotta_j_g">J. G. Cotta</ref>;  click on <ref cRef="kontrapunkt_2"><tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt2</tei:hi></ref>.  </tei:note> vollständig fertiggeworden und es würde mich herzlich freuen, wenn unsere Sache recht bald in ein definitives Stadium treten könnte.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Mit den verbindlichsten Empfehlungen
Ihr in Hochschätzung ergebener
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  Hertzka</tei:p><tei:p>1  Faktura
2  Erlagschein<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  These documents are not filed with the letter, so were presumably returned.  </tei:note></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Hertzka (UE) to Schenker, dated March 5, 1918</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">UE letterhead</tei:hi>]
[Vienna] I, Karlsplatz 6
W  							
Vienna, [<tei:hi rend="italic">typed:</tei:hi>] March 5, 1918</tei:p><tei:p>Professor Heinrich  S c h e n k e r, Esq.
<tei:hi rend="italic">Vienna III </tei:hi>
Reisnerstraße 38</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>In response to your valued postcard of yesterday, I take the liberty of informing you that I know nothing of any French review of your Beethoven edition.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  I am accordingly writing today to our representative in Lausanne;  perhaps he knows something and if so can have the review sent to me.  Needless to say, you will then receive it forthwith.</tei:p><tei:p>Your <tei:hi rend="italic">Op.111</tei:hi> has been dispatched to Dr. Steglich<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> immediately, at your request.  I was going to spare you the burden, but since you complained about one such recently I take the liberty of enclosing the invoice with payment order.</tei:p><tei:p>Yesterday's definitive conclusion of peace with Russia<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> and the inevitable effect it will, in my opinion, have on the overall situation, afford me the opportunity to think about peace-makings, so accordingly I am taking advantage of these lines of mine today to revive the question of the "Little Musical Library,"[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>]<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> so often broached between us.  I believe that in the meanwhile you have finalized your work for Cotta,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> and I should be delighted if our plan could swiftly be brought to a definitive stage.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> With warmest regards,
Yours most sincerely,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hertzka</tei:p><tei:p>1.  Invoice
2.  Payment order<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/></tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>