<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OC 52/446 : 1-14-20 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  Universal Edition A.G., Wien.
©  Transcription Ian Bent, 2009
©  Translation Ian Bent, 2009
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2009.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>email from Aygün Lausch (Universal Edition) to Ian Bent, 2004-09-09, confirming UE's ownership of IPR and granting permission to post to pilot website.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1920-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-1938) - -Oster, Ernst (1938-c.1939) - -New York Public Library (c.1939-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Universal Edition, A.G.; Image: New York Public Library, New York; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 01/14/1920 05:28:36 PM --><!-- MT Tags: "Hertzka ~ HSchenker","UE ~ H+JSchenker","UE ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Typed letter from Hertzka (UE) to Schenker, dated January 14, 1920</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-06-08</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Hertzka has not yet gone to Frankfurt.  - - He wants to publish the "Moonlight" Sonata in a series edited by Otto Erich Deutsch.  - - Would like to do new edition of complete Beethoven sonatas, but without wholesale reengraving.   - - Discusses financial arrangements for the latter, and for the Kleine Bibliothek.  - - Encloses the contract for Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven ... op. 101.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Hertzka, Emil; UE; Schenker, Heinrich;  Frankfurt;  Beethoven;  Moonlight Sonata;  facsimile edition;  Deutsch, Otto Erich;  Beethoven sonatas;  Kleine Bibliothek;  Little Library;  honorarium;  retail price;  Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven;  Op. 101</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Vienna I, Karlsplatz 6</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Vienna</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Hertzka (UE) to Schenker, dated January 14, 1920</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">typewriter ink smudged in places</tei:hi>]  
[<tei:hi rend="italic">UE letterhead</tei:hi>]
D/W</tei:p><tei:p>Wien I, Karlsplatz 6
Wien, [<tei:hi rend="italic">typed:</tei:hi>] 14. Januar 1920.</tei:p><tei:p>Wohlgeboren [/] Herrn Prof. Dr. Heinrich  S c h e n k e r
<tei:hi rend="italic">Wien</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Herr Professor!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/1, p. 2209, January 19, 1920:  "Von Hertzka (Br.):  gehe auf 20% vom Ladenpreis ein, auch auf das Honorar pro Seite der Ausgabe." ("From Hertzka (letter): agrees to 20% of the retail price, also to the honorarium per page for the edition.")  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Im Besitze Ihres Geschaetzten vom 9. ds.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  The letter from Schenker is not known to survive, but its writing is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/1, pp. 2203-2204:  "An Hertzka (Br.):  schlage für die „Kleine Bibliothek" 20% vom Ladenpreis vor, erkläre mich dagegen bereit, das Honorar für die Ausgabe per Seite zu berechnen u. meine Mitwirkung an den bibliophilen Stücken um ein Geringes zu gewähren." ("To Hertzka (letter): propose 20% of the retail price for the <tei:hi rend="italic">Little Library</tei:hi>, and in exchange declare myself willing to reckon the honorarium of the edition by the page, and to offer my cooperation in the bibliophile items for very little money.")  </tei:note> erlaube ich mir mitzuteilen, dass ich noch immer in Wien bin, da ich bei den derzeitigen, hoechst unsicheren Reiseverhaeltnissen und der Bayrischen Bahnsperre noch nicht weggekommen bin.  Sollten sich die Verhaeltnisse einigermassen bessern, so gedenke ich Samstag oder Sonntag nach Frankfurt<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Hertzka had agreed to pick up photographs from the collector Louis Koch in Frankfurt:  see WSLB 310, December 17, 1919. </tei:note> zu reisen.</tei:p><tei:p>Die Idee, von saemtlichen Beethoven-Sonaten bibliophile Ausgaben<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  "Beethoven ... Ausgaben":  underlined by Schenker.</tei:note> herauszubringen, kann derzeit noch nicht durchgeführt werden.  Die Mondscheinsonate<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  "Mondscheinsonate":  underlined by Schenker.  </tei:note> wollen wir aber jedenfalls machen und ist Herr Otto Erich Deutsch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="deutsch_otto_erich">Otto Erich Deutsch</ref>.   </tei:note> der Leiter dieser bibliophilen Ausgaben.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  The series <tei:hi rend="italic">Musikalische Seltenheiten: Wiener Liebhaberdrucke</tei:hi>, general editor Otto Erich Deutsch (Vienna: UE, 1921-23), in vol. 1 of which the facsimile of Beethoven's sonata Op. 27 No. 2 ("Moonlight": UE 7000) with three sketch leaves was presented by Schenker, and in vol. 4 five early songs of Schubert.  </tei:note>  Er hat es auch uebernommen, mit Ihnen die Vereinbarung bezueglich der Herausgabe zu treffen, so dass Sie zweifellos von ihm noch Naeheres hoeren werden.  Dass ich die saemtlichen Beethoven-Sonaten - vorausgesetzt, dass nicht ein vollstaendiger Neustich notwendig sein wird, denn an einen solchen ist augenblicklich ueberhaupt nicht zu denken, - sehr gerne in einer von Ihnen revidierten Ausgabe<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  <tei:hi rend="italic"> L. van Beethoven: Klaviersonaten nach den Autographen und Erstdrucken rekonstruiert von Heinrich Schenker</tei:hi>, 4 vols (Vienna: UE, 1921-23).  </tei:note> neu herausgeben moechte, habe ich schon erwaehnt.  Wenn wir das in Verbindung mit der kleinen Bibliothek<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="kleine_bibliothek"><tei:hi rend="italic">Kleine Bibliothek</tei:hi></ref>.   </tei:note> machen koennten, so waere mir das natuerlich sehr sympathisch und ich akzeptiere <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> fuer die kleine Bibliothek die von Ihnen genannte Beteiligung;  d.i. 20 % vom Ladenpreis.  Das Honorar fuer die Beethovenausgabe [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">[<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>] pro Seite</tei:hi> zu fixieren,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  "pro ... fixieren":  underlined by Schenker.  </tei:note> ist mir sehr angenehm, ich moechte Sie aber bitten, mir mitzuteilen, welches [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>] Sie in Anrechnung bringen wollen. - Was die Preise, die fuer die kleine Bibliothek in Betracht kommen, betrifft, so ist Ihre Berechnung heute illusorisch.  Die [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>]kosten schwanken von Tag zu Tag.  Nach den hiesigen Preisen müsste man pro 16 Seitenbogen in halbwegs anständiger[?] [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>]tung, einen Ladenpreis von 6[?] - 8 Kronen berechnen.</tei:p><tei:p>Gleichzeitig sende ich Ihnen den Vertrag ueber op. 101 und bitte, mir denselben mit Ihrer Unterschrift versehen, zu retournieren, worauf Sie die die erste Rate des ausbedungenen Honorars von K. 7,500.- erhalten.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit verbindlichsten Gruessen
Ihr ergebener
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hertzka</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Hertzka (UE) to Schenker, dated January 14, 1920</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">typewriter ink smudged in places</tei:hi>]  
[<tei:hi rend="italic">UE letterhead</tei:hi>]
D/W</tei:p><tei:p>Vienna I, Karlsplatz 6
Vienna, [<tei:hi rend="italic">typed:</tei:hi>] January 14, 1920</tei:p><tei:p>Prof. Heinrich  S c h e n k e r, Esq.,
<tei:hi rend="italic">Vienna</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>In receipt of your valued letter of the 9th inst,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> I take the liberty of informing you that I am still in Vienna because I have not yet been able to get away on account of the current highly uncertain conditions for travel and the Bavarian rail stoppage.  Should the conditions improve to some degree, I have in mind to travel to Frankfurt<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> on Saturday or Sunday.</tei:p><tei:p>The idea of publishing bibliophile editions of all the Beethoven sonatas<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> is still not achievable at the present time.  However, we want in any case to do the Moonlight Sonata<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>, and Mr. Otto Erich Deutsch<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> is the general editor of these bibliophile editions.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>  He has also undertaken to reach agreement with you regarding the edition, so you will no doubt be hearing more from him.  I have already mentioned that I should very much like to publish afresh the collected Beethoven sonatas in an edition by you,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> provided that a complete new engraving will not be necessary, since this is altogether out of the question at a time like the present.  If we could do this in conjunction with the <tei:hi rend="italic">Little Library</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> that would of course be highly congenial, and I accept <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> your apportionment, namely 20% of the retail price.  To fix the honorarium for the Beethoven edition at [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>] per page,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> is entirely agreeable to me;  I should just like to ask you which [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>] you want to bring into the equation. -- As concerns the prices under consideration for the <tei:hi rend="italic">Little Library</tei:hi>, your calculation is illusory these days.  The [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>] costs fluctuate from day to day.  In terms of today's prices, one would have in any halfway respectable [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>] to reckon on a retail price of 6[?]-8 Kronen per sixteen-page gathering.</tei:p><tei:p>I am sending you at the same time the contract for <tei:hi rend="italic">Op. 101</tei:hi> and ask you to return the same furnished with your signature, upon which you will receive the first tranche of the stipulated honorarium of 7,500 Kronen.</tei:p><tei:p>With most cordial greetings,
Yours truly,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hertzka</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>