<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OC 52/500 : 5-5-14 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Universal Edition A.G., Wien.
© Transcription Ian D. Bent 2004.
© Translation Ian D. Bent 2004.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian D. Bent 2005
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>email from Aygün Lausch (Universal Edition) to Ian Bent, 2004-09-09, confirming UE’s ownership of IPR and granting permission to post to pilot website.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1914-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-1938) - -Oster, Ernst (1938-c.1939)—New York Public Library (c.1939-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Universal Edition, A.G.; Image: New York Public Library, New York; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian D. Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 05/05/1914 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Hertzka ~ HSchenker","UE ~ H+JSchenker","UE ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Typed letter from Hertzka (UE) to Schenker, dated May 5, 1914</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2005-11-06</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>
[ LfS 110:] Acks WSLB 210 and MS; is pressing printers for galley-proofs. —[ LfS 111:] Authorizes payment of first half of honorarium. —[ LfS 101, 106:] Economic depression precludes H from reimbursing miscalculated cost over-runs; lays out alternative possibilities.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Hertzka, Emil; UE; Schenker, Heinrich;  Beethoven; Die letzten fünf Sonaten; Erläuterungsausgabe; Op. 110; Op. 111; Op. 101; Op 106; manuscript; galley-proofs; honorarium; economic depression</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN" /><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN" /></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Hertzka (UE) to Schenker, dated May 5, 1914</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">left</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
[UE letterhead]
[transcribe date]</tei:p><tei:p>W
Wohlgeboren [/] Herrn Prof. Dr. Heinrich   S c h e n k e r
<tei:hi rend="italic">W i e n</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Doktor !</tei:p><tei:p>Besten Dank für Ihre gesch. Zuschrift vom 2. ds.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  i.e. WSLB 210.</tei:note> sowie für das Manuskript<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  i.e. of the last part of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Op. 110</tei:hi>, published later in 1914.</tei:note>, das wir Ihnen nach Beendigung des Druckes sofort wieder zurückstellen werden.  Wir urgieren bei der Druckerei die Einsendung der letzten Fahnen, damit Sie in der Ihnen bequemsten Zeit die Korrektur zu Ende bringen können.</tei:p><tei:p>Da nunmehr vertragsmässig der Beginn der dritten Sonate<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  i.e. <tei:hi rend="italic">Op. 111</tei:hi>, published in 1915.</tei:note> erfolgt, lassen wir Ihnen gleichzeitig K 600.- anweisen. Was nun die Angelegenheit der letzten zwei Sonaten<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  i.e. <tei:hi rend="italic">Opp. 101</tei:hi> (published in 1920), <tei:hi rend="italic">106</tei:hi> (never completed).</tei:note> betrifft, so ist es mir nicht möglich, alles das, was ich Ihnen in dieser Sache zu sagen hätte, schriftlich mitzuteilen.  Stellen Sie sich vor, dass ich &lt;strike&gt;Ihnen&lt;/strike&gt; in einer stundenlangen Auseinandersetzung unseren Standpunkt verfochten hätte, der in Folgendem gipfelt:</tei:p><tei:p>Die in den letzten Jahre platzgegriffene grosse Depression zwingt uns für die nächste Zeit zu grösster Sparsamkeit.  Wir entsprechen in genauester Weise allen unseren Verpflichtungen, können aber darüber nicht hinausgehen.  Wir sehen es ein, dass. ^[ <tei:hi rend="italic">in margins:</tei:hi> ] von Musikern resp. Schriftstellern^ das ^Nicht-^ Einhalten von übernommenen Verpflichtungen in Bezug auf künstlerische oder wissenschaftliche Leistungen ganz anders aufgefasst <tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">right</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> und behandelt werden muss als &lt;strike&gt;das&lt;/strike&gt; ^auf anderen Gebieten^ in Bezug auf kommerzielle ^u. ähnliche^ Leistungen.  Wir können aber deshalb, weil Sie sich geirrt und eine Arbeit unterschätzt haben, nicht verhalten werden, daraus Konsequenzen zu ziehen die, weil nicht vorgesehen, mit unserer Budgetierung kollidieren müssen.</tei:p><tei:p>[§]Es ist selbstverständlich, dass wir Sie nicht zwingen &lt;strike&gt;können&lt;/strike&gt; ^würden^, Ihrer Lieferungsverpflichtung bzgl. der letzten zwei Sonaten zu dem vorgesehenen Betrag nachzukommen und wenn Sie uns erklären, dass Sie zu dem vereinbarten Betrag die Arbeit absolut nicht machen können, so gibt es nur zweierlei Möglichkeiten u.zw.: entweder Sie nennen uns Ihre neuen Bedingungen für die beiden letzten Sonaten und wir akzeptieren dieselben oder aber wir verzichten unter den erhöhten Bedingungen auf die Herausgabe insolange, bis uns wieder eine günstigere Konjunktur die Bewilligung erhöhter Bedingungen ermöglicht.  Ich glaube, dass dieser Standpunkt absolut korrekt ist und ich bitte Sie, sehr geehrter Herr Doktor<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  S reciprocates this device (which he perhaps considered patronizing) twice in WSLB 211 with "sehr geehrter Herr Direktor" in the body of his letter.</tei:note> mir entweder jetzt oder zu einem Ihnen entsprechend erscheinenden späteren Zeitpunkt mitzuteilen, welche Honorarerhöhung Sie für die Herausgabe der beiden letzten Sonaten beanspruchen.</tei:p><tei:p>Jedenfalls freue ich mich sehr, dass die Herausgabe von op. 111 die Sie nun vorhaben, für Sie eine viel leichtere Arbeit bedeutet als die bisherigen beiden Arbeiten und dass Sie da Ihre Kräfte ein wenig schonen können.</tei:p><tei:p>Ihren weiteren Mitteilungen mit Interesse entgegensehend, verbleibe ich mit verbindlichen Empfehlungen</tei:p><tei:p>in aufrichtigen Hochschätzung
ergebenst
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">stamp:</tei:hi> ] Universal-Edition Actiengesellschaft [ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Hertzka</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Hertzka (UE) to Schenker, dated May 5, 1914</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">left</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
[UE letterhead]
Vienna, May 5, 1914</tei:p><tei:p>W
Prof. Heinrich S c h e n k e r, Esq.
<tei:hi rend="italic">V i e n n a</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>Many thanks for your est'd letter of the 2nd inst.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> and also for the manuscript<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>, which we will return the moment the printing is finished.  We are pressing the printers to dispatch the last [batch of] galley-proofs, so that you can complete the corrections at the time most convenient for you.</tei:p><tei:p>Since according to the contract commencement of the third sonata<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> ensues at this point, we are arranging concurrently for 600 Kroner to be transferred to you.  Now as concerns the matter of the last two sonatas<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>, it is not possible for me to communicate in writing all that I would wish to say to you.  Imagine for yourself that I had had to defend our point of view &lt;strike&gt;to you&lt;/strike&gt; in an hour-long explanation that culminates in the following:</tei:p><tei:p>The stationary deep depression of recent years forces us to make the greatest economies for the foreseeable future.  We are meeting all our commitments in the most stringent manner, but cannot exceed these.  We appreciate that ^not^ stopping payments ^[ <tei:hi rend="italic">in margins:</tei:hi> ] to musicians or writers^ for obligations that have been undertaken in respect of artistic or scholarly activities must be viewed <tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">right</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> and handled in a quite different way from those ^in other areas^ in respect of commercial ^and similar^ activities.  However, we cannot, just because you have miscalculated and underestimated a task, be constrained from drawing conclusions which, because unforeseen, are bound to conflict with our budgeting.</tei:p><tei:p>[§]It goes without saying that we &lt;strike&gt;can&lt;/strike&gt; ^would^ not compel you to abide by your obligation to deliver in connection with the last two sonatas in return for the payment already made, and if you tell us that you absolutely cannot produce the work for the payment agreed, then there are only two possibilities, namely: either you stipulate to us your new conditions for the last two sonatas and we accept these, or else in view of those higher conditions we forego the edition until such time as more favorable economic conditions permit us once more to authorize higher terms.  I believe that the position we have adopted here is absolutely correct, and I ask you, dear Doctor,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> to let me know either now or at a later point in time that seems suitable to you, what increase in honorarium you demand for the edition of the last two sonatas.</tei:p><tei:p>In any case, I am very happy that the edition of <tei:hi rend="italic">Op. 111</tei:hi> with which you are now busy constitutes a much less arduous task than the two previous ones, and that you will be able to spare your energies on it somewhat.</tei:p><tei:p>Looking forward with interest to your further communications, I remain with sincere best wishes,</tei:p><tei:p>With kind regards,
Most truly yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">stamp:</tei:hi> ] Universal Edition &amp; Co. [ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Hertzka</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>