<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OC 52/409 : 4-12-20 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  Universal Edition A.G., Wien, published here with kind permission
©  Transcription Ian Bent, 2009
©  Translation Ian Bent, 2009
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2009.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>email from Aygün Lausch (Universal Edition) to Ian Bent, 2004-09-09, confirming UE's ownership of IPR and granting permission to post to pilot website.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1920-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-1938) - -Oster, Ernst (1938-c.1939) - -New York Public Library (c.1939-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Universal Edition, A.G.; Image: New York Public Library, New York; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 04/12/1920 11:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Hertzka ~ HSchenker","UE ~ H+JSchenker","UE ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Typed letter from Hertzka (UE) to Schenker, dated April 12, 1920</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-06-25</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Hertzka encloses the contracts for the Kleine Bibliothek and collected Beethoven sonatas, hoping that it will meet with approval.  - - He explains the rise in price of the Instrumentations-Tabelle.   

</dc:description><dc:subject>Hertzka, Emil; UE; Schenker, Heinrich;  contracts;  Kleine Bibliothek;  Little Library;  Beethoven sonatas;  legal representative;  Instrumentations-Tabelle;  Instrumenten-Tabelle;  Instrumenation Table;  Instruments Table;  paper price;  production costs;  retain price;  cost of living increase</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Vienna I, Karlsplatz 6</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Vienna</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Hertzka (UE) to Schenker, dated April 12, 1920</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">UE letterhead</tei:hi>]
Wien I. Karlsplatz 6
D/W/Br</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">stamp:</tei:hi>]  Lesen Sie die Musikblätter des Anbruch!
Wien, [<tei:hi rend="italic">typed:</tei:hi>] 12. April 1920.</tei:p><tei:p>Wohlgeboren [/] Herrn Prof. Dr. Heinrich S c h e n k e r ,
<tei:hi rend="italic">W i e n .</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hochverehrter, lieber Herr Professor!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  fn1.  Receipt of this letter and OC 52/408 are recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/1, p. 2227, April 14, 1920: "Von U.-E.:  Verträge u. Brief der Buchhaltung;  im Jahre 1917 seien 100 Kronen ausbezahlt worden, eine neue Auflage gehe im Druck."  ("From UE:  contracts and letter from the Accounts Department saying that in 1917 100 Kronen were paid;  a new edition is going to press.")</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Mitfolgend die beiden Verträge über die kleine Bibliothek und über die Beethovensonaten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  These contracts form part of OC 52/517 (<tei:hi rend="italic">Kleine Bibliothek</tei:hi>) and OC 52/448 (Beethoven sonatas);  these are both dated July 10, 1920, but the contract in each case is dated April 10, 1920.  </tei:note>  Dieselben entsprechen genau unserer mündlichen Verabredung<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> See OC 52/255, April 7, 1920, where the meeting is set for Friday April 9 at Café Vindobona.  </tei:note> und ich glaube, dass Ihr Herr Rechtsvertreter dieselben ebenfalls wird billigen können.  Ich hoffe, dass wir nun sehr bald auch formell zu einem Abschluss der Abmachung kommen und erlaube mir, nur zu bemerken, dass ich bereits wegen Sonate Op. 101 nach Paris habe schreiben lassen.</tei:p><tei:p>Was nun die Instrumentationstabelle oder besser gesagt, Instrumententabelle betrifft,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="instrumentations-tab"><tei:hi rend="italic">Instrumentations-Tabelle</tei:hi></ref>.  Hertzka has several times given the title as <tei:hi rend="italic">Instrumenten-Tabelle</tei:hi> in correspondence, but this never found its way on to the title-page or cover.  </tei:note> so ist mit Hinblick auf die enormen Anschaffungspreise der Ladenpreis vor einiger Zeit auf Mk. 2.- erhöht worden.  Wenn also Ihr Schüler er für die Tabelle 12.- Kronen bezahlt hat, so hat er sie noch recht billig eingekauft, denn der heutige Preis ist noch höher.  Wie Sie sich wohl erinnern können, war schon seinerzeit der Preis von M 1.- ein ausserordentlich niedriger und ist zum Zwecke der Popularisierung und Einführung der Tabelle beinahe ohne Gewinnmög- <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> lichkeit festgesetzt worden.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  "beinahe ohne Gewinnmög" ("virtually ... profit"): underlined in pencil by Schenker, and whole paragraph to this point single-sidelined by Schenker.  </tei:note>  Sie können sich denken, dass letz[...?] der Preis des Papieres auf das hundertfache gestiegen ist, und der Druck etwa auf das zehnfache, die Beibehaltung des ursprünglichen Ladenpreises trotz der Erhöhung &lt;del&gt;des&lt;/del&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;durch [EH]&lt;/sup&gt; Teuerungszuschlage&lt;del&gt;s&lt;/del&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;n&lt;/sup&gt; unmöglich war.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  "das hundertfache," "Druck," "zehnfache" ("one hundredfold," "printing," "tenfold"): underlined in pencil by Schenker.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Wegen der Verrechnung des Honorars für eine Neuauflage schreibt Ihnen die Buchhaltung direkt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  = OC 52/408, April 12, 1920.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ihr in warmer Verehrung ergebener 
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  Hertzka</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Hertzka (UE) to Schenker, dated April 12, 1920</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">UE letterhead</tei:hi>]
Vienna I, Karlsplatz 6
D/W/Br</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">stamped:</tei:hi>]  Read the <tei:hi rend="italic">Musikblätter des Anbruch</tei:hi>!
Vienna, [<tei:hi rend="italic">typed:</tei:hi>] April 12, 1920</tei:p><tei:p>Prof. Heinrich S c h e n k e r , Esq., 
<tei:hi rend="italic">V i e n n a .</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear, revered Professor,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Enclosed are the two contracts concerning the <tei:hi rend="italic">Little Library</tei:hi> and the Beethoven sonatas.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  These correspond exactly to our verbal rendezvous<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> and I believe that your legal representative will likewise be able to give his approval.  I hope that we will very soon formally reach completion on the letter of agreement, and I take the liberty of remarking that I have already had a letter written to Paris regarding Op. 101.</tei:p><tei:p>Now, as regards the <tei:hi rend="italic">Instrumentation Table</tei:hi>, or better put, <tei:hi rend="italic">Instruments Table</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> the retail price has for some time now been raised to 2 Marks to reflect the enormous acquisition costs.  Thus if your pupil has paid 12 Kronen for the <tei:hi rend="italic">Table</tei:hi>, then he has purchased it really cheaply, for the price today is higher than that.  As you will well remember, the price of 1 Mark was an extraordinarily low one already at that time, and was set virtually without any possibility of making a profit for purposes of popularizing and introducing the <tei:hi rend="italic">Table</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> You can imagine that recently[?] the price of paper has increased one hundredfold, and printing something like tenfold, to adhere to the original retail process despite the cost-of-living increases was impossible.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/></tei:p><tei:p>Our Accounts Department is writing to you directly regarding the calculation of the honorarium for a new edition.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/></tei:p><tei:p>Yours sincerely, In warm admiration,  
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  Hertzka</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>