<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OC 52/227 : 4-17-20 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  Universal Edition A.G., Wien, published here with kind permission
©  Transcription Ian Bent, 2009
©  Translation Ian Bent, 2009
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2009.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>deemed to be in the public domain. Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to Schenker Documents Online at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk .</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1920-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-1938) - -Oster, Ernst (1938-c.1939) - -New York Public Library (c.1939-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Fischmann, Leo; Image: New York Public Library, New York; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 04/17/1920 03:52:55 PM --><!-- MT Tags: "Fischmann ~ HSchenker","Hertzka ~ HSchenker","UE ~ H+JSchenker","UE ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Typed letter from Leo Fischmann to Schenker, dated April 17, 1920</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-06-29</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Fischmann sees two points still outstanding over the contracts for the Kleine Bibliothek and Beethoven sonatas, and advises him how to handle them.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Fischmann, Leo; Schenker, Heinrich;  UE;  Vertrag;  contract;  Kleine Bibliothek;  Little Library;  Beethoven sonatas;  negotiations;  honorarium</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Vienna X, Favoritenstraße 106</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Fischmann (UE) to Schenker, dated April 17, 1920</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>]
Rechtsanwalt
D^R.^ LEO FISCHMANN
Gerichtsdolmetsch für die französische Sprache
Wien, X. Favoritenstraße Nr. 106
Telephon 50.037</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">typed:</tei:hi>] Wien, den 17. April 1920.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Professor!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/1, p. 2228, April 20, 1920:  "Von D^r.^ Fischmann (Br.):  Hertzkas Verträge u. neue Vorschläge dazu;  empfiehlt auf die 10% Valuta-Zuschlag zu verzichten u. dafür lieber 1% bei den Sonaten einzutauschen;  im übrigen sei dies bloß eine Machtfrage."  ("From Dr. Fischmann (letter):  Hertzka's contracts and latest proposals enclosed;  recommends foregoing the 10% foreign-currency surcharge and exchanging it instead for 1% on the sonatas;  otherwise this is just a question of power.").  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ich bestätige den Inhalt Ihres werten Briefen vom 14. d.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Schenker's letter is not known to survive.  Writing of it is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/1, p. 2227:  "An D^r.^ Fischmann Brief."  (To Dr. Fischmann, letter.")  </tei:note> samt die beide Vertragsentwürfen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Presumably the contracts quoted in OC 52/517 and 448 (dated April 10, 1920).  </tei:note> die ich gleichzeitig zurückstelle.</tei:p><tei:p>Wie ich sehe, sind einige der von mir gewünschten Aenderungen aufgenommen worden.  Es bleiben noch zwei Punkte im wesentlichen, in welchen der Verlag nicht auf Ihre Bedingungen eingehen wollte.  Die eine ist die Bezahlung der ins Ausland verkauften Werke, es ist ohneweiters klar, dass die Zuschlagsbeteiligung von 10% bei der kleinen Bibliothek nicht dem weit höheren Nutzen des Verlegers entspricht, die aus dem Auslandszuschlag und der Valutadifferenz fliesst.</tei:p><tei:p>Uebrigens vermisse ich eine annähernd ähnliche Bestimmung in dem Sonatenvertrag, obgleich hier der Verkauf ins fremdsprachliche Ausland gewiss noch leichter ist.</tei:p><tei:p>Das weitere ist die fixe Honorierung der Sonaten, ich kann nicht einsehen, warum der Verlag nicht darauf eingeht, einfach statt 40 Pf. sagen wir 1% zu sagen, bei einer möglichen Preissteigerung sind Sie dann eben mibeteiligt, während Sie so in alle Ewigkeit 40Pf., bekommen, auch wenn der Band etwa nicht 45 M sondern 300 M kosten wird.</tei:p><tei:p>Im wesentlichen aber sind das, wie ich mir bereits erlaubt habe, Ihnen auseinanderzusetzen, Machtfragen und muss es Ihrer Beurteilung überlassen ^bleiben^ ob Sie etwa durch Beharren auf diesen Forderungen das Zustandekommen der Sonatenausgabe gefährden.  Vielleicht liesse sich die Sache so machen, dass Sie etwa auf die von uns ursprünglich gewünschte prozentuelle Honorierung der Auslandsexemplare verzichten, der Verlag aber Ihnen, die prozentuelle Honorierung der Sonaten zu 1 oder 1½% zugesteht, was mir mit Rücksicht auf die möglichen zukünftigen Preissteigerung, wie oben angeführt, sehr wünschenswert erscheint.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich verbleibe mit dem Ausdruck vorzüglicher Hochachtung
ergebenst
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Beilagen.</tei:hi>
Rekommandiert</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Fischmann (UE) to Schenker, dated April 17, 1920</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>]
Attorney
DR. LEO FISCHMANN
Legal  interpreter for the French language
Vienna X, Favoritenstraße Nr. 106
Telephon 50.037</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">typed:</tei:hi>] Vienna, April 17, 1920</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>I confirm the content of your esteemed letter of the 14th inst.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> together with the two contract drafts,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> which I am returning at the same time.</tei:p><tei:p>As I can see, several of the modifications that I wished for have been adopted.  In essence, two points still remain in which the publisher will not go along with your conditions.  One is the payment of the works sold in foreign countries.  It is perfectly clear that the share of the surcharge of 10% on the <tei:hi rend="italic">Little Library</tei:hi> does not correspond with the far higher profit of the publisher that flows from the foreign surcharge and the currency differential.</tei:p><tei:p>Incidentally, I do not see an approximately similar stipulation in the sonata contract, although here the sale to foreign countries is certainly lighter.</tei:p><tei:p>The other point is the fixed honorarium for the sonatas.  I cannot understand why the publisher does not go along with simply saying, let's say, "1%" rather than "40 Pfennigs."  In the event of a possible price rise, you are then given a share, whereas otherwise you get 40 Pfennigs in perpetuity, even if the volume were to cost perhaps not 45 Marks by 300 Marks.</tei:p><tei:p>In essence, however, these are, as I have already taken the liberty of explaining to you, questions of power, and I must leave to your judgement whether you might possibly endanger realization of the sonata edition by persisting with these demands.  Perhaps the matter might best be resolved by your foregoing the percentage-based honorarium for copies sold in foreign countries that we originally sought, but the publisher granting you a percentage-based honorarium of 1% or 1½% of the sonatas, which seems to me, as stated above, to be highly desirable with respect to the possible future rise in price.</tei:p><tei:p>I remain, with highest regards,
Yours most truly, 
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Enclosures</tei:hi>
Registered</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>