<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OC 52/493 : 6-8-12 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Universal Edition A.G., Wien, published here with kind permission, 2004.
© Transcription Ian Bent 2006.
© Translation Ian Bent 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>email from Aygün Lausch (Universal Edition) to Ian Bent, 2004-09-09, confirming UE's ownership of IPR and granting permission to post to pilot website.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1912-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-1938) - -Oster, Ernst (1938-c.1939) - -New York Public Library (c.1939-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Universal Edition, A.G.; Image: New York Public Library, New York; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 06/08/1912 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Hertzka ~ HSchenker","UE ~ H+JSchenker","UE ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Typed letter from Hertzka (UE) to Schenker, dated June 8, 1912</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-05-21</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>[Niloff; Instrumentations-Tabelle:] Acknowledges two letters;  the 100 Kroner is a royalty, not a present.   - -[Die letzten fünf Sonaten Beethovens:] Proposes settlement on honorarium basis.  - -Comments favorably on Hans Weisse.  - -Is he to approach Dr. Harpner or vice-versa?

</dc:description><dc:subject>Hertzka, Emil; UE; Schenker, Heinrich;  Niloff, Artur;  Instrumentations-Tabelle;  Table of Instrumentation;  payment;  present;  Beethoven;  Die letzten fünf Sonaten Beethovens;  Erläuterungsausgabe;  payment;  Weisse, Hans;  Harpner, Dr.;  Organisation producirender und reproducirender Künstler;  Organization of Creative and Performing Artists </dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Vienna I, Reichrathsstraße 9</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Vienna</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Hertzka (UE) to Schenker, dated June 8, 1912</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">UE letterhead</tei:hi>]
R
Wien, 8. Juni 1912.</tei:p><tei:p>Wohlgeboren [/] Herrn Dr. Heinrich Schenker
W i e n
 - - - - - - -</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich war in den letzten zwei Tagen durch Sitzungen und geschäftliche und private Abhaltungen so in Anspruch genommen, dass ich Ihre beiden gesch. Zuschriften vom 5. ds.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Presumably WSLB 118, June 4, and WSLB 119, June 5, 1912.  </tei:note> erst heute beantworten kann.</tei:p><tei:p>Vor allem die Zahlung für K 100.- für Niloff, Instrumentationstabelle<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="instrumentations-tab"><tei:hi rend="italic">Instrumentations-Tabelle</tei:hi></ref>.</tei:note> betreffend, bitte ich Sie vollkommen beruhigt zu sein: es handelt sich hier nicht um ein Geschenk, sondern um eine Ihnen vertragsmässig zukommende Tantième,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  „sondern .. Tantième" ("rather ... contract")  underlined by Schenker.  For the contract, see OC 52/421, June 30, 1908, which specifies "For any editions to be printed after the sale of the first 2,000 copies, you will [i.e. UE] remunerate me at the rate of 100.- Kroner per thousand ...."</tei:note> über die Ihnen die Buchhaltung Montag spezielle Aufklärung erteilen wird.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  OC 52/404, June 4, 1912.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Was nun die Frage der ^5^ Beethoven-Sonaten betrifft, so will ich Ihnen, nachdem Sie sich auf eine tantièmenweise Beteiligung nicht gerne einlassen möchten, folgenden weitestgehenden Vorschlag machen:</tei:p><tei:p>Sie liefern mir järhlich eine der fünf Sonaten und erhalten von mir für jede Sonate einen Betrag von K 1200.- also zusammen K 6000.-<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  "K 6000.-" underlined by Schenker.</tei:note>  Dieser Betrag soll in der Weise zahlbar sein, <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> dass Sie die Hälfte stets bei Inangriffnahme und die zweite Hälfte bei Ablieferung einer Sonate erhalten.  Ich hoffe, dass Ihnen diese Kombination entsprechen wird.  Es ist das Aeusserste was ich Ihnen bieten darf.  Ich wäre glücklich gewesen, wenn ich Ihre  Bedingungen hätte akzeptieren können, aber es ist leider nicht möglich, dies zu tun.</tei:p><tei:p>Herr Weisse,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.</tei:note> der vor einigen Tagen bei mir war ist ein reizender junger Mann und ich hoffe, dass wir zusammenkommen werden.</tei:p><tei:p>Aus Ihrer gesch. Zuschrift ersehe ich nicht genau, ob ich an Dr. Har^p^tner<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="harpner_dr">Dr. Harpner</ref>.</tei:note> in der bewussten Sache<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="organization_artists">Organisation ... Künstler"</ref>.</tei:note> herantreten soll oder ob er an mich herantreten wird.  Ich bitte auch hierüber mir Ihre frdl. Aeusserung zukommen zu lassen.</tei:p><tei:p>In der Hoffnung, dass wir in allen Dingen werden zu einer befriedigenden Verständigung gelangen können, verbleibe ich mit den besten Grüssen Ihr in aufrichtiger Hochschätzung</tei:p><tei:p>ergebener
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Hertzka</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Hertzka (UE) to Schenker, dated June 8, 1912</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">UE letterhead</tei:hi>]
R
Vienna, June 8, 1912.</tei:p><tei:p>Dr. Heinrich Schenker, Esq.
V i e n n a
- - - - - - - - - - -</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>Over the past two days I have been so taken up with meetings and business and private engagements that am I able only today to answer your two est'd letters of the 5th inst.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Above all, as regards the payment of 100.- Kroner for Niloff, <tei:hi rend="italic">Table of Instrumentation</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> please be entirely reassured:  there is no question of this being a present;  rather [it is] a royalty due to you by terms of your contract,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> on which the book-keeping department was giving you special clarification on Monday.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/></tei:p><tei:p>Now, as concerns the ^five^ Beethoven sonatas, let me, since you are unwilling to entertain a royalty-based apportionment, put to you the following proposition, which goes as far as it can:</tei:p><tei:p>You supply me each year with one of the five sonatas, and receive from me for each sonata a sum of 1,200 Kroner, thus altogether 6,000 Kroner.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> This amount will be payable <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> such that for each sonata you will receive half upon embarking on the work and the other half upon delivery.  I hope that this formulation will meet with your agreement.  It is the utmost that I am in a position to offer you.  I should have been happy had I been able to accept your conditions, but it is unfortunately impossible to do this.</tei:p><tei:p>Mr Weisse,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> who was with me a few days ago, is a charming young man, and I hope we can reach an agreement.</tei:p><tei:p>I cannot quite tell from your est'd letter whether I am to approach Dr. Har^p^tner<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> in the matter in question,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> or whether he will approach me.  I should be grateful if you would kindly drop me a word on this.</tei:p><tei:p>In hoping that we will be able to reach a satisfactory understanding on all issues, I remain with best wishes, kindest regards,</tei:p><tei:p>Yours truly,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Hertzka</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>