<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OC B/136-138 : 3-20-30 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  Under inquiry
©  Transcription Ian Bent, 2008.
©  Translation Ian Bent, 2008.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish is being sought.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1930-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-1938) - -Oster, Ernst (1938-c.1939)—New York Public Library (c.1939-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Gerhard Albersheim; Image: New York Public Library, New York; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 03/20/1930 01:00:10 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Albersheim ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Albersheim to Schenker, dated March 20–21, 1930</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-10-07</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Albersheim returns the copy of his article annotated by Schenker and explains his improvements on their basis;  he discusses his prospective career and desire to promote Schenker's theory.  He is preparing for the state [teacher's] examination.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Albersheim, Gerhard;  Schenker, Heinrich;  article;  Der freie Satz;  Free Composition;  career;  Einstein, Alfred;  Staatsprüng;  state examination;  Albersheim, Erna</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Gerhard Albersheim to Schenker, dated March 20–21, 1930</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Wien, 20. III. 30.</tei:p><tei:p>Verehrter Meister,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary for March 22, 1930 (OJ 4/3, p. 3457), stating that it encloses a fair copy.  Schenker had handed the typescript back to Albersheim with annotations on March 12, requesting its return (OJ 4/3, p. 3452).  Schenker's subsequent letter to Albersheim informing him that he had sent the article off (to Einstein) is recorded in the diary for March 23 (OJ 4/3, p. 3457); the letter to Einstein recommending the article and enclosing it is recorded for the same date, and its dispatch recorded delivery for March 24 (OJ 4/3, p. 3458).    </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ich habe nun meinen Aufsatz<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  "Heinrich Schenker: Grundlagen und Bedeutung seines Werkes."  This article was submitted to the<tei:hi rend="italic"> Zeitschrift für Musikwissenschaft</tei:hi>, whose editor, Alfred Einstein, rejected it on March 28, 1930 (OC B/139).  It was eventually published in the <tei:hi rend="italic">Rheinische Musik- und Theater-Zeitung</tei:hi> 15–16 (Cologne, 1931), pp. 1–6.   A draft version is preserved as OB  B/112–134 with emendations by Albersheim and Schenker, and a clipping of the final publication in Schenker's scrapbook as OC 2/p.80.  </tei:note> auf Grund Ihrer Anmerkungen einer nochmaligen Bearbeitung unterzogen und teile Ihnen im Folgenden die Gesichtspunkte, die mich dabei leiteten, mit, um Ihnen womöglich eine nochmalige Lektüre zu ersparen.</tei:p><tei:p>Die kleineren stilistischen Umstellungen von Ihrer Hand glaubte ich ohne weiteres in den Text übernehmen zu dürfen.  Nicht aber ging das für Ihre den freien Satz betreffenden Formulierungen an, da ich mich unmöglich mit fremden Federn schmücken kann.  &lt;strike&gt;Dort&lt;/strike&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;An diesen 2 Stellen&lt;/sup&gt; fand ich den einfachen, auch stilistisch gut wirkenden Ausweg, Sie zu zitieren.</tei:p><tei:p>Einige andere Ihrer Anmmerkungen nahm ich zum Anlaß einer eigenen Neuformulierung, teils weil Ihr Stil zu unverkennbar war und uns jungeren Menschen nicht zukommt, an <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> einer &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;anderen&lt;/sup&gt; Stelle, weil ich mich nicht entschließen konnte, einen Gedanken diskussionslos zu opfern, der bei der Lektüre auch Ihren Beifall gefunden hatte.</tei:p><tei:p>Außerdem habe ich die absichtliche Einfachheit des Beispiels noch stärker betont und begründet, sowie einen Hinweis auf die Analysen von Ihrer Hand eingeschaltet. —</tei:p><tei:p>Ich betrachte diesen Aufsatz als den Anfang einer Wirksamkeit, in deren Ausübung ich mein Lebensziel erblicke, ohne heute schon zu wissen, ob sie sich auf ausübendem, (pädagogischem) unterrichtendem oder publizistischem Gebiet abspielen wird.  Mit dem gewählten Thema habe ich meine Visitenkarte ab[ge]geben und von Anfang an dokumentieren wollen, &lt;strike&gt;ich&lt;/strike&gt; in welcher Richtung ich zu wirken gedenke.  Außer dem Wunsche, dadurch der so nötigen – für die Menschheit nötigen – Verbreitung Ihrer Lehre zu dienen, lag mir auch an <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> der Feststellung der Priorität Ihrer Gedanken, weil diese mit der Zeit einen immer breiteren Raum in der Publizistik einnehmen werden und schon einnehmen.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich bin der Ansicht, daß eine monographische <tei:hi rend="italic">Darstellung</tei:hi> Ihrer Lehre a priori verfehlt ist, da niemand die Reinheit und Systematik Ihrer eignenen Darstellung erreichen könnte.  Arbeiten über Ihr Schaffen dürften sich daher meiner Meinung nach immer nur auf Spezialgebiete beschränken oder den Charakter von Einführungen in Ihr Werk haben.  Letzteres habe ich in der vorliegenden Arbeit in der knappsten Form versucht und mich dabei bemüht, persönlich ganz hinter die Sache zurückzutreten, wie Sie das auch bei meiner Vorlesung empfunden haben.  Wenn Sie nun auch nach den letzten Verbesserungen noch der Ansicht sind, daß in Einzelheiten <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> die Rechnung zwischen Thema und Darstellung nicht ganz aufgegangen ist, dürfte es sich wohl um den Rest der Individualität handeln, die bei einer Darstellung ursprünglich ganz persönlicher Gedanken aus fremder Feder wohl nie ganz zu vermeiden ist. —</tei:p><tei:p>Ich bin jetzt intensiv mit den Vorbereitungen auf die Staatsprüfung<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  The state examination resulting in a teaching qualification, with primary study piano.  Albersheim's taking of this exam has been under discussion for more than a year, as recorded in Schenker's diary.  </tei:note> beschäftigt.  Meine Frau<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Erna Eder, married 1929.  </tei:note> war deshalb so lieb, mir den Aufsatz abzuschreiben, wodurch ich viel Zeit sowie die Kosten einer nochmaligen Maschinendiktats erspart habe.</tei:p><tei:p>Das alte Exemplar mit Ihren Anmerkungen geht hiermit wunschgemäß in Ihren Besitz über.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  = OC B/112–134.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ich nehme an, daß sich Einstein<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="einstein_alfred">Alfred Einstein</ref>.  </tei:note> nach Einsendung des Aufsatzes an mich wenden wird, wobei ich ihm dann auch den Wunsch nach einen Anzahl Sonderdrucke eröffnen kann.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit besten Grüßen an Sie und Ihre verehrte Frau Gemahlin
Ihr ergebener
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  Gerhard Albersheim.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> P S. 21. III.</tei:p><tei:p>Vielen Dank für Ihre w. Karte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  This postcard is not known to survive.  Its sending is recorded in Schenker's diary for March 19, 1930 (OJ 4/3, p. 3455). </tei:note>  In der Tat wäre mir eine möglichst rasche Erledigung der Angelegenheit lieb.  Da Sie die Arbeit schon heute in Händen haben werden, brauchte ich wohl wegen der Aufsatzes Ihre kostbare Zeit am nächsten Mittwoch nicht mehr in Anspruch zu nehmen[.]   Schreiben Sie mir, wenn Sie auch so denken, also ganz ungeniert ab!  Wenn ich dagegen <tei:hi rend="italic">nichts</tei:hi> mehr von Ihnen hören sollte, komme ich um die vereinbarte Zeit.</tei:p><tei:p>Nochmals beste Grüßen
Ihr ergebener
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Gerhard Albersheim.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Gerhard Albersheim to Schenker, dated March 20–21, 1930</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Vienna, March 20, 1930</tei:p><tei:p>Revered master,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>On the basis of your annotations, I have now subjected my article<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> to a further reworking, and should like to tell you in what follows the considerations that guided me in that process so as, if possible, to spare your having to read it for a second time.</tei:p><tei:p>I felt able to incorporate into the text without further ado the smaller-scale stylistic modifications that you suggested.  That was not the case for your formulations relating to <tei:hi rend="italic">Free Composition</tei:hi>, since I find it impossible to take on[?] another person's style.  &lt;strike&gt;There,&lt;/strike&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;In these two passages,&lt;/sup&gt; I arrived at the simple and stylistically workable solution of quoting you directly.</tei:p><tei:p>One or two others of your annotations prompted me to devise my own new formulation, in part because your style was too unmistakeable and does not befit us younger people, [and] in <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> another passage, because I could not bring myself to offer an idea without discussion, which had actually met with your approval when you read it.</tei:p><tei:p>Additionally, I have emphasized and substantiated still more strongly the intentional simplicity of the example, while at the same time inserting a reference to your own analyses. —</tei:p><tei:p>I consider this article as the beginning of an activity the practice of which I look upon as my goal in life—without knowing at this early stage whether it will materialize in the realm of performance, (pedagogy) teaching, or journalism.  With this chosen topic I have presented my visiting card, and I want at the outset to betoken the direction in which I see myself working.  In addition to my wish to serve the dissemination of your theory, which is so necessary—so necessary for mankind—, I have set my heart also on <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> establishing the priority of your ideas, because these will in time occupy—and are already occupying—an ever greater place in journalism.</tei:p><tei:p>I am of the opinion that a monograph <tei:hi rend="italic">presentation</tei:hi> of your theory would be wrong <tei:hi rend="italic">a priori</tei:hi>, since no one  [else] can attain the purity and systematic nature of the way you present it yourself.  Publications about the work that you do ought always, in my view, to be limited just to specific issues, or to have the character of introductions to your work.  I have attemped the latter in the most succinct form in the present piece of work, and in so doing have been at pains to keep myself entirely out of the matter, as you yourself, too, have felt with my lecture.   If even now, after the last set of improvements, you are still of the opinion that <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> the balance between subject-matter and presentation has not been correctly struck at particular points, then it must surely be a matter of traces of a personality that in a presentation by another person of what were originally totally personal ideas can ultimately never be completely avoided. —</tei:p><tei:p>I am now intensely occupied with preparations for the state examination.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  My wife<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> was so kind as to transcribe the article, thereby saving me the loss of much time as well as the costs of dictating it again to a typist.</tei:p><tei:p>As you request, I herewith return the old copy to you with your annotations.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/></tei:p><tei:p>I assume that Einstein<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> will get back to me after submission of the article, at which point I can also put in a plea to him for a number of offprints.</tei:p><tei:p>With most cordial greetings to you and your esteemed wife,
Yours truly,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  Gerhard Albersheim.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> P. S. March 21</tei:p><tei:p>Many thanks for your kind postcard.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>  In actual fact, a settlement of the matter as quickly as possible would suit me better.  Since you will have the work in hand today, I would no longer need to call upon your precious time over the article next Wednesday.  Write to me canceling the arrangement, if you are of the same mind, without ceremony!  If on the other hand I hear <tei:hi rend="italic">nothing</tei:hi> more from you, I will come at the agreed time.</tei:p><tei:p>With cordial greetings once again,
Yours truly,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Gerhard Albersheim.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>