<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:FS 40/1, [21] : 3-25-34 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  Heirs of Felix Salzer, published here with kind permission
©  Transcription Hedi Siegel, 2008
©  Translation Hedi Siegel, 2008
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Hedi Siegel 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Salzer, Felix (1934-1986) - -the Felix Salzer estate (1986-2001) - -New York Public Library(2001 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Felix Salzer;  Image: New York Public Library; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Hedi Siegel.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 03/25/1934 12:44:27 PM --><!-- MT Tags: "Salzer ~ H+JSchenker","Salzer ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Salzer, dated March 25, 1934</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-12-19</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Schenker cancels the seminar for Friday March 30 on grounds of exhaustion;  wishes to read the manuscript of Salzer's forthcoming book;  reports on a long letter from Hans Weisse.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Salzer, Felix;  Easter;  Good Friday; lesson;  cancelation;  manuscript;  Weisse, Hans;  Kalmus, Alfred;  Herzta, Emil</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Vienna III, Keilgasse 8^XII^</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Vienna XIII, Maxingstraße 12</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Felix Salzer, dated March 25, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{envelope <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
H. <tei:hi rend="italic">D^r^ Felix Salzer</tei:hi>
Wien, XIII
Maxingstr. 12</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>]  || 3 WIEN 40 | 26. III. 34. 11 | <tei:hi rend="bold"> 4f</tei:hi> ||</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{envelope <tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed:</tei:hi>] WIEN, III., KEILGASSE 8^XII.^</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{letter}</tei:hi>
					25.3.34</tei:p><tei:p>Mein lieber D^r^ Salzer!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  The writing of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/7, p. 3900: "sage für Karfreitag ab, möchte seine Arbeit lesen - über den Brief von Weisse" ("I cancel for Good Friday [March 30], should like to read his work -- about the letter from Weisse").   </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Nur meinen von den Anstrengungen an den wirklich letzten Blättern u. Beispielen sehr hergenommenen Körper zu sanieren,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Of <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi> =  Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien, vol. III (Vienna: UE, 1935).</tei:note> will auch ich - beinahe wäre richtiger: muß auch ich -- von den „Osterferien" Gebrauch machen, wovon ich Sie schon heute unterrichte, um Ihnen rechtzeitig die Möglichkeit österlicher Dispositionen zu erleichtern.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  In 1934, Easter Sunday fell on April 1; Schenker, writing on the Sunday before the Easter weekend, is canceling the seminar session that would have taken place on Good Friday, March 30.</tei:note>  Daß ich noch in dieser Woche die „Form"<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  "Von der Form," the last chapter (Abschnitt) of <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi>.</tei:note> u. damit das Ganze abschließe, ist ausgemacht.  Schon ist Tomay<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  The engraver Georg Tomay, who was setting the examples for <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi>.  He had previously set the <tei:hi rend="italic">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln / Five Analyses in Sketchform</tei:hi> (New York: David Mannes Music School, 1932) and the extensive graphs for Schenker's essay on Beethoven's <tei:hi rend="italic">Eroica</tei:hi> Symphony in <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, vol. III (Munich: Drei Masken Verlag, 1930).</tei:note> in Sicht!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Wie verblieben wir bezüglich Ihres Manuskriptes?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Salzer was preparing what was to be his first book, <tei:hi rend="italic">Sinn und Wesen der abendländischen Mehrstimmigkeit</tei:hi> (Vienna: Saturn-Verlag, 1935). </tei:note>  Daß ich auf Ihren ersten Vorstoß in die wahre Musikgeschichte-Schreibung sehr gespannt bin, darf Sie nicht verwundern, d.h. lesen möchte ich gern.  Haben Sie aber Zutrauen, meinerseits wird gewiß nichts geschehen, was Sie in der Stimmung gegenüber den übermenschlich hohen Ziel schädigen könnte.  Wenn Sie die Blätter entbehren können, wollen Sie sie mir geben.   Sollen wir hiefür ein Datum ausmachen, oder wie sonst denken Sie sich diesen Akt?  Ich verspreche <tei:hi rend="italic">prestissimo</tei:hi> zu lesen, so daß ich keine Verzögerung verursache. Rede u. Antwort werde ich Ihnen unter 4 Augen stehen, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> einfach nur aus <tei:hi rend="italic">Discretion</tei:hi>, die zu solchen mysteriösen Dingen nun einmal gehört.</tei:p><tei:p>Vom l. Hans<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>. The six-page letter (OJ 15/16, [94]), sent from New York, is dated March 15, 1934.  Schenker's diary entry for March 24, 1934 (OJ 4/7, p. 3900) reports: "Von Weisse (Br.): lang; Aufschluß über die englische Ausgabe die ein "Dreh" von Kalmus war;  über Unangenehmes mit Schülern, versagen gegenüber seinen Kompositionen - schickt mir Kopien." ("From Weisse (letter):  long; information about the English edition which was a "trick" by Kalmus;  unpleasantness with students;  failure in regard to his compositions--is sending me copies.")</tei:note> empfing ich gestern einen sehr langen Brief.  Auch die neuen Kompositionen sind unterwegs.  Sie werden staunen zu hören, wie D^r.^ Kalmus<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="kalmus_alfred">Alfred Kalmus</ref>.  </tei:note> auch den l. Hans in der Angelegenheit der englischen Bd I-Ausgabe<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (Stuttgart: J. G. Cotta, 1906) = Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien, vol. I. The complex history of the work is discussed by Robert Wason in "From Harmonielehre to Harmony: Schenker's Theory of Harmony and its Americanization," in <tei:hi rend="italic">Schenker-Traditionen: Eine Wiener Schule der Musiktheorie und ihre internationale Verbreitung</tei:hi>, ed. Martin Eybl and Evelyn Fink-Mennel (Vienna: Böhlau Verlag, 2006), pp. 171-201;  expanded version in <tei:hi rend="italic">Essays from the Fourth International Schenker Symposium</tei:hi>, vol. I, ed. Allen Cadwallader (Hildesheim: Georg Olms Verlag, 2008), pp. 213-58.</tei:note> hereinzulegen versucht hat, der Macher „von's Tanze" war eben Kalmus, der so, so unschuldig bei mir tat. . . .  Der Neffe fällt nicht weit vom Onkel (Hertzka) usw.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Schenker is parodying the proverb "Der Apfel fällt nicht weit vom Stamm" or "Der Apfel fällt nicht weit vom Baum" ("The apple doesn't fall far from the tree"). Kalmus was Herztka's nephew;  he was the son of Erwine Fuchs (wife of Jacques Kalmus), the (step?)-sister of Hertzka's wife Jella (Fuchs). </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ein fröhliches Fest Ihnen u. Ihrer verehrten Gattin wünsche ich in unser[er] beiden Namen</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Felix Salzer, dated March 25, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{envelope <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
Dr. Felix Salzer
Vienna XIII,
Maxingstrasse 12</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>]  || 3 VIENNA 40 | 26. III. 34. 11 | <tei:hi rend="bold"> 4f</tei:hi> ||</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{envelope <tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
VIENNA III, KEILGASSE 8^XII.^</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{letter}</tei:hi>
March 25, 1934</tei:p><tei:p>My dear Dr. Salzer,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Only to allow my very exhausted body to recover from the strenuous work on what are truly the last pages and examples,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> I, too, want to--or it would perhaps be more correct to say:  I, too, must--take advantage of the "Easter holidays."  I am already informing you of this today, to make it easier for you to make Easter plans in time.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  I will most certainly finish the "form" [section]<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> and thus the entire work this week.  Tomay<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> is already in sight!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> What arrangements did we make regarding your manuscript?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/>  That I am very anxious to see your first attempt at true music-historical writing should not surprise you;  that is, I would very much like to read it.  Be assured, however, that of course nothing will be done on my part that could hinder you in the pursuit of a superhumanly lofty goal.  If you can spare the pages, please give them to me.  Should we fix a date for this or do you have some other idea?  I promise to read <tei:hi rend="italic">prestissimo</tei:hi> so I won't cause any delay. Our give-and-take will remain confidential, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> simply for the sake of discretion, which has to be part of such mysterious things.</tei:p><tei:p>I received a very long letter yesterday from dear Hans.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>   New compositions are also on their way.  You will be astonished to hear how Dr. Kalmus<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> has tried to draw dear Hans, too, into the business of the English edition of volume I;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/>  the producer "of the song and dance" was none other than Kalmus, who acted oh so innocent when he was with me. . .  The nephew doesn't fall far from the uncle (Hertzka), etc.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/></tei:p><tei:p>I wish you and your esteemed wife a happy holiday, in both our names.</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] H. Schenker</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>