<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 5/14, [1] : 6-29-12 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription Ian Bent, 2007.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1912-1934) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: in the public domain; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 06/29/1912 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde, dated June 29, 1912</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-06-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>S responds the the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde's invitation;  commenting on the reasons behind the proposal, and the style of lecture expected, he expresses his willingness, proposes a subject, and states his fee.

</dc:description><dc:subject> Schenker, Heinrich ; Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde;  lectures;  topics;  honorarium;  fee</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde, dated June 29, 1912</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>An die K.K. Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Although this letter is signed and dated, it may be a copy retained for the file, in which case the letter as delivered may have undergone editing.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Für die Ehre, die mir die sehr geehrte Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde daduch erweist, daß sie auch mich zur Erfüllung der neuen schönen Aufgabe mit heranzieht, erlaube ich mir meine herzlichsten dank <tei:hi rend="italic">abzustatten</tei:hi>.</tei:p><tei:p>Weitmehr noch als Ihre erste ruhmvolle Gründung scheint mir die gegenwärtige zweite, die so bedeutsam das zweite Jahrhundert Ihres Bestandes einleitet, die Erreichung dessen zu ermöglichen, was die Tonkunst meiner Meinung nach heute am dringendsten fordert, nämlich die größtmögliche Vertiefung der spezifisch-musikalischen Kenntnisse.</tei:p><tei:p>Zwar entnehme ich Ihrem geschätzten Schreiben nicht genau, ob die geplanten Vorträge den Charakter von Hochschulvorlesungen erhalten sollen;   doch wünschte ich vom Herzen, daß es so wäre, damit der durch die zahllosen Schulen verursachten Verflachung wirksam entgegengearbeitet werde.  Endlich <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> soll einmal auch dasjenige, worin sich <tei:hi rend="italic">besonders</tei:hi> das <tei:hi rend="italic">Genie</tei:hi> unserer großen Meister manifestiert, in die weitesten Kreise zu deren eigenstem Wohle getragen werden.  Das wäre meines Erachtens die idealste Art von „volkstümlichen Vorträgen.“</tei:p><tei:p>Hiermit will[?] ich freudigst meine Bereitwilligkeit ausgedrückt haben, mich Ihren Plänen zur Verfügung zu stellen.  Sehr gerne würde ich, um der neuen Institution freunde zu werben, über aus kunstpolitischen Gründen momentan aktuelle Themen aus dem Gebiete der Tonkunst vorlesen, so z.B. über ‚Gut u. schlecht in der Musik,“ oder über „die Unwandelbarkeit musikalischer Formen,“ über „die Technik in den <tei:hi rend="italic">Sinfonien</tei:hi> von <tei:hi rend="italic">Brahms</tei:hi>“ u. dgl.;  jedoch wäre es ratsam, mir zu gestatten, <tei:hi rend="italic">zur</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Einführung</tei:hi> Vorlesungen über „<tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi>“ zu halten.  Wer mich kennt, wird gerne bestätigen, daß ich damit durchaus nicht etwa für meine Theorien Propaganda machen möchte u. ich bitte auch die sehr geehrte Gesellschaft einem solchen Gedanken gar nicht erst Raum zu geben.  Vielmehr erscheint es mir unausführbar, Nachweise musikalischer Natur überhaupt zu führen um <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> meine Urteile vor Zuhörern zu begründen, die meiner Terminologie gar nicht folgen könnten.</tei:p><tei:p>Konkret gesprochen, frage ich die sehr geehrte Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde an, ob ihr <tei:hi rend="italic">zunächst</tei:hi> Vorlesungen über „Harmonielehre“ willkommen wären.  Für diesen Fall würde ich solche je 1-mal in der Woche halten, u. zw. so, daß ich eine Stunde den Ausführungen selbst widmen, woran sich eine <tei:hi rend="italic">Diskussion</tei:hi> von etwa 1/2-stundiger Dauer anschließen würde.</tei:p><tei:p>Was das Honorar anbelangt, würde ich für das Musikjahr (Oktober bis <tei:hi rend="italic">incl</tei:hi>. Juni) den Betrag von 3000 Fl = 6000 Kr. erbitten.</tei:p><tei:p>Einer gefälligen Entscheidung entgegensehend verharre ich</tei:p><tei:p>in ausgezeichneter Hochachtung
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] D^r.^ Heinrich Schenker
Wien, 29. Juni 1912</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde, dated June 29, 1912</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>To the  Imperial-Royal Society for the Friends of Music,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>I take the liberty of <tei:hi rend="italic">rendering</tei:hi> my most cordial thanks for the honor that the Society for the Friends of Music accords me by calling upon me to contribute to the fulfillment of the fine new task that it has set itself.</tei:p><tei:p>Far more even than your first glorious initiative [is] a second one belonging to the present day, one that so significantly ushers in the second century of your existence, [which] seems to me to be:  to make possible the attainment of that for which music in my judgment most pressingly cries out today, namely the greatest possible deepening of the specifically musical understanding.</tei:p><tei:p>To be sure, I cannot exactly tell from your est’d letter whether the planned lectures are intended have the character of highschool lectures.  I certainly would wish from the bottom of my heart that you will work effectively to counteract the lowering of intellectual standards that has been brought about through the countless schools.  At last, <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> that in which the <tei:hi rend="italic">genius</tei:hi> of our great masters is <tei:hi rend="italic">especially</tei:hi> manifested should for once be carried out into the farthest circles for their own good.  That would in my opinion be the most ideal type of “popular lectures.”</tei:p><tei:p>With this, I mean with greatest pleasure to have expressed my readiness to make myself available for your plans.  I should certainly have liked, in order to recruit friends to the new institution, to lecture on currently burning issues in the art-political arena, for example, on “Good and Bad in Music,” or on “The Immutability of Musical Forms,” [or] on “Technique in the Symphonies of Brahms,” or such like.  However, it would be advisable to permit myself to give lectures, <tei:hi rend="italic">by way of introduction</tei:hi>, on “<tei:hi rend="italic">Theory of Harmony</tei:hi>.”  Anybody who knows me will readily confirm that I would never for a moment wish to make propaganda out of this for my theories, and I beg the honored Society not to entertain any such thought.  What is more, it seems to me impracticable to introduce evidence of a <tei:hi rend="italic">musical</tei:hi> nature on <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> which to base my judgments in front of an audience that is entirely unable to follow my terminology.</tei:p><tei:p>Put in concrete terms, I ask the honored Society for the Friends of Music whether lectures on “Theory of Harmony” would be welcome to it <tei:hi rend="italic">in the first instance</tei:hi>.  If so, I would lecture once a week, devoting one hour to the lectures themselves, to which would be attached perhaps half an hour for <tei:hi rend="italic">discussion</tei:hi>.</tei:p><tei:p>As far as the fee is concerned, I should ask 3,000 Florins = 6,000 Kroner for the musical year (October to June inclusive).</tei:p><tei:p>In looking forward to a favorable decision, I remain,</tei:p><tei:p>With kind regards,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Dr. Heinrich Schenker
Vienna, June 29, 1912</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>