<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 5/6, [2] : 10-9/13-08 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Heinrich Schenker.
© Transcription Ian D. Bent 2005.
© Translation Ian D. Bent 2005.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian D. Bent 2005.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian D. Bent 2005.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> All reasonable steps have been taken to locate the heirs of Heinrich Schenker. Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:license> All reasonable steps have been taken to locate the heirs of Heinrich Schenker. Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1908-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:provenance>J.G. Cotta’sche Nachfolger/Stuttgarter Zeitung (1907-c.1954); Cotta-Archiv, Schiller-Nationalmuseum, Marbach a. N., Germany (c.1954-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian D. Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian D. Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 10/12/1908 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cotta ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten draft of letter from Schenker to Cotta, dated October 9/13, 1908</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2005-08-08</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>[ NMTP II = Kontrapunkt:] Acks OJ 12/27, [9] = CA 86 and accepts advice against splitting volume; writing out exercises for Section III is proving more laborious than expected; dropping Christmas deadline will allow more time, after which he will take a break. —[ NMTP III [=Niedergang ]:] If Kontrapunkt [Part I] can be released in March or April [1909], then will take a break before resuming vol. III.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Cotta, J. G.; NMTP; vol. II; Kontrapunkt; Counterpoint; exercises; deadline; Christmas; vol. III; Niedergang; Decline; holiday; Harmonielehre; Harmony; Bach, C. P. E.; Handel</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten draft of letter from Schenker to Cotta, undated; draft of CA 87, therefore between October 9 and October 13, 1908 inclusive</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr !</tei:p><tei:p>Ich beeile mich Ihnen herzlichst für Ihren liebenswürdigen Rat zu danken, dem ich mich ohneweiters füge.  Auch ist[?] es mir [ <tei:hi rend="italic">corr from</tei:hi> nicht?] selbst damit ruhiger. Es war nur das Drängen der Freunde, die an den Weihnachtstermin dachten, ^u.^ denen [ <tei:hi rend="italic">corr from</tei:hi> dem?] ich, gegen meine Gewohnheit, nachgegeben habe.</tei:p><tei:p>Und nur zur völligen Klarstellung, das Textliche des Werkes ist auch in den weiteren Abschnitten, sogar den kleinen Anfang eingeschlossen, fertiggestellt [ <tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi> ].  Nur die Aufgaben fehlen noch.  Nach der Erfahrung, die ich mit dem Eintragen von Aufgaben, in den Abschnitten 1 u. 2 gemacht habe, sah ich ein, daß ich sie in der weiteren Abschnitten nicht vor einem Monat hätte fertigstellen können, – so viel Zeit nimmt einfach das rein Mechanische des Notenschreibens in Anspruch, worin ich leider nicht vertreten werden kann, auch nicht will <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> (die Aufgaben werden, je später in das Werk hinein, desto notenreicher).  So lange ich also an den Weihnachtstermin dachte, mußte ich erkennen, daß das ganze Werk unmöglich zu beenden wäre vor Ende <tei:hi rend="italic">Oktober</tei:hi>, u. da entstand aber die Idee des Halbbandes.</tei:p><tei:p>Entfällt nun aber die Rücksicht auf den Termin, so wird es mir ein Leichtes sein, binnen der nächsten Wochen in Ruhe die Aufgaben der nächsten Abschnitt einzufügen.</tei:p><tei:p>Gleichwohl möchte ich bitten, daß sich Ihre Druckerei bald des Manuscriptes mit Fleiß annehmen möchte.  Denn ehe ich zum 3. Band, der <tei:hi rend="italic">Pointe</tei:hi> des ganzen [ <tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi> ] Werkes, aushole, muß [ <tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi> ] eine kleine Pause der Ruhe u. Sammlung für Frühling u. Sommer gewinnen, da ich seit ungefähr 7 bis 8 Jahren nicht dazu gekommen bin eine Ruhe zu genießen vor lauter – <tei:hi rend="italic">Bach</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Händel</tei:hi>,  (für die <tei:hi rend="italic">Universal-Edition</tei:hi> ), <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> u. <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Contrap</tei:hi>. u. Konzerten wohl.  Es wäre mir sehr lieb, wenn der Band spätestens vor März oder April herauskommen könnte.</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">no valediction</tei:hi> ]</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten draft of letter from Schenker to Cotta, undated; draft of CA 87, therefore between October 9 and October 13, 1908 inclusive</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Sir,</tei:p><tei:p>I hasten to thank you wholeheartedly for the kind advice, to which I acquiesce without more ado.  In fact, I am happier with it myself.  It was only pressure from friends, who thought in terms of the Christmas deadline, ^and^ to whom I, contary to custom, yielded.</tei:p><tei:p>And just to be completely clear:  the textual matter of the book is already finished, even that of the later sections, and even including the short beginning.  The only things still lacking are the exercises.  In the light of the experience that I had with entering exercises into Sections 1 and 2, I realized that I would not have been able to complete them for the later sections in less than a month—just the purely mechanical process of writing out the music alone takes up so much time, work which unfortunately I cannot assign to someone else, indeed, would not wish to <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> (the exercises get more notey the further one gets into the book!).   Thus as long as I was thinking in terms of the Christmas deadline, I was compelled to recognize that it would be impossible to finish the work in its entirety before the end of October, and from this arose the idea of the half-volume.</tei:p><tei:p>But if the prospect of the deadline is now dropped, then it will be a simple matter for me to enter the exercises into the next section in peace and quiet within the next few weeks.</tei:p><tei:p>Nevertheless, I should like to ask that your printers attend to the manuscript promptly and diligently.  For before I resume work on the third volume—the capstone of the whole work—I must have a short break to rest and recuperate over the Spring and Summer, since for something like 7 or 8 years now I have been unable to enjoy a break, just because of– Bach, Handel (for Universal Edition), <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmony</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> and <tei:hi rend="italic">Counterpoint</tei:hi>, and concerts.  It would be very nice for me if the volume could be released at the latest by March or April.</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">no valediction</tei:hi> ]</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>