<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OC 52/224 : 4-3-20 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  Universal Edition A.G., Wien, published here with kind permission
©  Transcription Ian Bent, 2009
©  Translation Ian Bent, 2009
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2009.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>deemed to be in the public domain. Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to Schenker Documents Online at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk .</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1920-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-1938) - -Oster, Ernst (1938-c.1939) - -New York Public Library (c.1939-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Fischmann, Leo; Image: New York Public Library, New York; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 04/03/1920 05:39:34 PM --><!-- MT Tags: "Fischmann ~ HSchenker","Hertzka ~ HSchenker","UE ~ H+JSchenker","UE ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Typed letter from Fischmann to Schenker, dated April 3, 1920</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-06-19</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Fischmann gives advice on Schenker's contracts for the Kleine Bibliothek and the collected Beethoven piano sonatas.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Fischmann, Leo; Schutzverband;  UE; Schenker, Heinrich;  Vertrag;  contract;  Kleine Bibliothek;  Little Library;  Beethoven sonatas;  Tantieme;  royalty</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Vienna X, Favoritenstraße 106</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Vienna III, Reisnerstraße 38</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Fischmann (UE) to Schenker, dated April 3, 1920</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>]
Rechtsanwalt
D^R.^ LEO FISCHMANN
Gerichtsdolmetsch für die französische Sprache
Wien, X. Favoritenstraße Nr. 106
Telephon 50.037</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">typed:</tei:hi>] Wien, den 3. April 1920.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Professor!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 3/1, p. 2225, April 5, 1920:  "Von Dr. Fischmann:  Verträge mit Bemerkungen zurück." (From Dr. Fischmann:  contracts with comments [received] back.")  This follows a meeting, OJ 3/1, p. 2224, March 31, 1920:  "Um ¼ 10^h^ zu D^r.^ Fischmann;  alles Material zur Kennzeichnung Hertzkas vorgelegt.  Im Grunde, meint er, sei keine Hilfe, außer im Prozesse, aber auch dann können falsche Bücher vorgelegt werden;  rat, die Niloff-Sache vorläufig auf sich beruhen zu lassen."  ("9:15 to Dr. Fischmann;  all the material for Hertzka's signature[?] shown to him.  Basically, he is of the opinion that it cannot be helped other than through a lawsuit, but even then false books can be submitted.[?]  He advises me to let the Niloff matter rest for the time being.").  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ich beehre mich, Ihnen im folgenden meine Bemerkungen zu den beiden Verlagsverträgen zu übermitteln.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  i. e. contracts relating to the <tei:hi rend="italic">Kleine Bibliothek</tei:hi> and the collected Beethoven piano sonatas.  The contracts commented on would appear to be OC 52/560 and 447 (dated March 23, 1920), and the results appear to be reflected in OC 52/517 and 448 (dated April 10, 1920).  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Der Vertrag bezüglich der "Kleinen Bibliothek" geht im wesentlichen in Ordnung.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich möchte nur folgendes vorschlagen, das in beide Verträge aufge-nommen werden soll.  "Erfolgt der Verkauf gegen fremde Valuta (keine deutschösterreichische Kronen [<tei:hi rend="italic">word del</tei:hi>]) so hat auch die diesbezügliche Verrechnung mit Ihnen in der entsprechenden Valuta zu erfolgen und Sie haben mir die entsprechenden Beträge, wenn ich deren Auszahlung zum Umrechnungskurse nicht wünsche, entweder in barem in der ausländischen Valuta oder durch Anweisung auf eine in Betracht kommende Bank im Ausland zu bezahlen."  Dieser Passus wäre dem § 4 anzuschliessen.</tei:p><tei:p>Im § 6 des Vertrages hat es zu heissen: "dann ist für diese Aufsätze die gleiche Tantième zu zahlen, welche dem Umfang ... entspricht."</tei:p><tei:p>§ 7) wäre besser einen Stichtag also 1.II. und 1.VIII. zu setzen.</tei:p><tei:p>§[ 8 ]  ist für Sie zu weit gefasst, da es sich ja um grössere musikwissenschaftliche Arbeiten handeln kann, für welche ein ausgesprochener Buchverlag in Betracht käme.  Ich würde vorschlagen, dass dieser § dadurch zu ergänzen wäre, dass nach den Worten "musikwissenschaftliche Ahbandlungen" die Worte eingeschaltet werden, "soferne sie nach dem Umfang und der Art in den Rahmen der "Kleinen Bibliothek" fallen" . .</tei:p><tei:p>Bei dem Sonatenbetrag hätte ich folgendes zu bemerken:</tei:p><tei:p>Der § 4 hätte derart zu lauten, dass Sie von dem Preise mit allen Teuerungszuschlägen, jedoch ohne Berücksichtigung des Sortimenterzuschlages eine Tantième von beispielsweise 2% erhalten.</tei:p><tei:p>Auch zu diesem § käme der Zusatz wegen der fremden Valuta.  Dann müsste der § 5 des anderen Vertrages vollinhaltlich aufgenommen werden[.]</tei:p><tei:p>Ich muss, sehr geehrter Herr Professor, es Ihnen überlassen, ob Sie die Verpflichtung des § 2 (Beigabe von Einfuhrungen) übernehmen kön- <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> nen, d.h. ob diese Arbeit mit etwa 2% Tantième bezahlt ist, und ob Sie damit auch für Ihre Barauslagen (Beschaffung von Kopien usw.) gedeckt sind.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich würde mir erlauben, Ihnen zu raten, mir vor dem definitiven Vertragsabschluss, also vor Unterfertigung der Verträge, die endgültige Entwürfe zu zeigen.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich zeichne mit dem Ausdruck vorzüglicher Hochachtung und Empfehlung an die gnädige Frau</tei:p><tei:p>ergebenst
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signature:</tei:hi>]  [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Beilagen.</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  See &lt;a href="../../../../contract/oc<tei:hi rend="italic">52560</tei:hi>3-23-20.html"&gt;OC 52/560&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="../../../../contract/oc<tei:hi rend="italic">52447</tei:hi>3-23-20.html"&gt;OC 52/447&lt;/a&gt;.</tei:note>
<tei:hi rend="italic">Rekommandiert.</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Herrn [/] Professor Dr. Heinrich  S c h e n k e r ,
<tei:hi rend="italic">Wien. III.</tei:hi>
Reisnerstrasse 38.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Fischmann (UE) to Schenker, dated April 3, 1920</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>]
Attorney
DR. LEO FISCHMANN
Legal  interpreter for the French language
Vienna X, Favoritenstraße No. 106
Telephone 50.037</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">typed:</tei:hi>] Vienna, April 3, 1920</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>I have the honor of submitting to you in what follows my remarks concerning the two contracts.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/></tei:p><tei:p>The contract relating to the <tei:hi rend="italic">Little Library</tei:hi> is essentially in good order.</tei:p><tei:p>I should just like to suggest the following to you, which should be applied to both contracts.  "If the sale takes place against foreign currency (not in German-Austrian Kronen), then the settlement with you in this connection has to take place in the corresponding currency, and you have to pay me the corresponding sums, if I do not wish them to be paid at the conversion rate, either in cash in the foreign currency or through transfer upon an appropriate bank in the foreign country."  This passage should be appended to §4.</tei:p><tei:p>In §6 of the contract, it has to read:  "then the same royalty is to be paid for these articles as ... corresponds to their size."</tei:p><tei:p>In §7 it would be better to set a date for engraving, thus February 1 and August 1.</tei:p><tei:p>§[8] is drafted too broadly for you, since it could be a matter of larger musicological works for which a specialist book publishing house might be deemed appropriate.  I would suggest that this clause be extended by inserting after the words "musicological essays" the words "insofar as they fall within the framework of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Little Library</tei:hi> in scope and type." . . .</tei:p><tei:p>As concerns the sonata contract, I would remark the following:</tei:p><tei:p>§4 ought to read in such a way that you receive a royalty of, for example, 2% of the price with all inflationary increases but without regard to the retail mark-up.</tei:p><tei:p>The addition regarding foreign currencies should be made to this clause, too.  In that case, §5 of the other contract should be taken up verbatim.</tei:p><tei:p>I must leave up to you, dear Professor, whether you can shoulder the obligation in §2 (supplying introductions), <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> i.e. whether this work is paid with perhaps a 2% royalty, and whether you are covered for your out-of-pocket expenses (procurement of photocopies, etc.).</tei:p><tei:p>I take the liberty of advising you to show the resultant drafts to me before finalizing, thus before signing, the contracts.</tei:p><tei:p>I remain, with expression of kind regards, and with regards to your lady wife,</tei:p><tei:p>Yours most truly,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signature:</tei:hi>] [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Enclosures.</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>
<tei:hi rend="italic">Registered mail.</tei:hi>
Professor Heinrich S c h e n k e r,
Vienna III,
Reisnerstraße 38</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>