<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OC 18/30 : 4-8-33 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  Under inquiry. 
©  Transcription Robert Wason, 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Robert Wason 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission being sought.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1933-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-1938) - -Oster, Ernst (1938-c.1939)—New York Public Library (c.1939-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Frederick Auslander; Image: New York Public Library; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Robert Wason.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 04/08/1933 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Auslander ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Typed letter in English from Auslander to Schenker, dated April 8, 1933</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-01-21</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Acknowledges with thanks [non-extant] letter from Schenker;  Auslander and Weisse consider it advisable to publish excerpts from Schenker's work in article form and proceed to publishing complete works later.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Auslander, Frederick;  Schenker, Heinrich;  translation</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> 8109–20th Ave., Brooklyn, N.Y.</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter in English from Auslander to Schenker, dated April 8, 1933</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>8109–20th Ave.
Brooklyn, N.Y.
April 8, 1933</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Dr. Schenker,</tei:p><tei:p>Permit me firstly to acknowledge receipt of your very kind and courteous letter.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  The letter is not known to survive.</tei:note>  I must, however, in the same breath, ask your leniency and graciousness in believing that it was not mere thoughtlessness and lack of consideration on my part in not responding any sooner. The fact is that Dr. Weisse,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.  </tei:note> who has been the soul of kindness and generosity, and I have been discussing up to date the advisability of my commencing work now or waiting a few months for better economic conditions on the outside or at least until that condensed version of your work has been fully prepared (as you mentioned in your letter).<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  This certainly refers to events of late 1932, when <ref cRef="marx_joseph">Joseph Marx</ref> suggested to Schenker that he have a "student edition" of his <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> made for use in the Vienna Conservatory, at which point Schenker contacted Vrieslander, and discussion between Schenker, Vrieslander and UE continued well into 1933 (OC 18/5-23). See R. Wason, "From Harmonielehre to Harmony ...," in Martin Eybl &amp; Evelyn Fink-Mennel, eds. <tei:hi rend="italic">Schenker-Traditionen: Eine Wiener Schule der Musiktheorie und ihre internationale Verbreitung</tei:hi> (Vienna: Böhlau Verlag, 2006), 155-201.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>The conclusion that Dr. Weisse and I have reached as to the best plan to follow, is to translate certain sections of your works, individually, and publish them if possible as separate articles in an accepted widely circulated Music magazine.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  No such translation articles were published.  It is interesting that Arthur Waldeck and Nathan Broder came to the same conclusion after Waldeck’s unsuccessful attempt to secure support for his translation of Schenker’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi>  (cf. OC 18/36 = NYma, [3]).  Given Hans Weisse’s involvement with both Auslander and Waldeck, one wonders if he recommended this course of action to both. </tei:note>  This would have the result of building up interest and demands for your works in this country, following which I could then translate your larger works in book form.</tei:p><tei:p>I sincerely regret that I have not <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> more definite news for you at this time, but I should like to give you my complete assurance that I shall not proceed one step without the advice, recommendation, and complete approval of Dr. Weisse.</tei:p><tei:p>It is my hope that this letter finds you enjoying the very best of health and well-being- and I look forward enthusiastically to the world-wide recognition of your work which your genius merits.</tei:p><tei:p>Very respectfully,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">unsigned:</tei:hi>]
Frederick E. Auslander<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Nothing is known about Auslander, though it has recently been asserted that he was twenty-two years old when he wrote to Schenker (David Carson Berry, “Hans Weisse and the Dawn of American Schenkerism,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Journal of Musicology</tei:hi> 20/1 (Winter, 2003): 104-56; see p. 152).</tei:note></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>