<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 36/62 : 1-9-49 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Oswald Jonas, published with kind permission
© Transcription Ian Bent 2008
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent, 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> Permission to publish on this website granted by the heirs of Oswald Jonas, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Jonas, Oswald (1949-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Oswald Jonas; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 01/09/1949 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ Chicago Sun-Times" --><dc:title>Carbon copy of typed letter from Oswald Jonas to the Chicago Sun-Times, dated January 9, 1949</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-06-01</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Jonas protests against a campaign to prevent Wilhelm Furtwängler from taking up an appointment with the Chicago Symphony Orchestra.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Jonas, Oswald; Chicago Sun-Times;  Berlin;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  France;  Ruhr;  America;  Nazis;  Hess, Myra;  Strauss, Richard</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> 1719 North Park Ave. Chicago </marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Carbon copy of typed letter from Oswald Jonas to the Editor of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Chicago Sun-Times</tei:hi>, Chicago, in English, dated January 9, 1949</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>January 9th, 1949
To the Editor of the "Sun-Times", Chicago, Ill.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Click on <ref cRef="chicago_suntimes">Chicago Sun-Times</ref>.</tei:note>
Dear Sir:</tei:p><tei:p>Being a musician, who had to leave Austria–Germany in 1938 and who has lived in Berlin until 1935, I would like to add a few words in connection with the appointment of Wilhelm Furtwängler.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Furtwängler had been offered an eight-week contract to conduct the Chicago Symphony Orchestra in August 1948.  Following protests allegedly by Arturo Toscanini, Jascha Heifetz, Vladimir Horowitz, Lotte Lehmann, Nathan Milstein, Gregor Piatigorsky, and Artur Rubinstein, subsequently joined by the American musicians' union, the Orchestra had asked Furtwängler to decline the offer.  He did not do so, but by January 1949 it became clear that the union would not allow Furtwängler to work.  (from Elisabeth Furtwängler, <tei:hi rend="italic">Über Wilhelm Furtwängler</tei:hi> (Wiesbaden: Brockhaus, 1979), pp. 138-9)</tei:note>  Does any[one] here know and realize the fact, how the French people,[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] who have fought and protested violently against the American decision on the Ruhr and certainly have any reason to "hate" the Nazis, have accepted and acclaimed F., when he appeared recently in Paris?  Furthermore how he was received in London, the city, which still shows the destruction inflicted by the brute force of the Nazis – and Myra Hess<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Dame Myra Hess (1890-1965), English pianist, who made her debut in 1907 under Sir Thomas Beecham in London.  Jonas's instancing of her in particular alludes to her iconic status in publicly defying the German bombing of London during World War II by playing daily lunchtime concerts at the National Gallery in London.  [identify relevant concert]</tei:note> was his soloist there!!  And here in America, where a rather mild treatment and matter of handling the Germans has taken place, we suddenly hear such an outcry about an eventual coming of F. here!  I must confess and I hardly can't help it, to get highly suspicious, whether there is not some other reason of some clique, who personally does not want him to come – because he is such an superior artist and musician!  To say, that Furtwängler should not be "allowed" to conduct Mozart or Beethoven, because he has no "character" is a quite ridiculous and dangerous statement;  especailly[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] as long as conductors in this country not hesitate to perform the works of R. Strauss. – I personally must say, that F. has acted towards myself always as a wonderful friend and has recommanded[sic] me inspite of all the Nazis, and I certainly remember all the remarks he has made to me about them – and certainly was not the only one in this respect. – Only those who have attended performances and rehearsals under Furtwängler's conducting, will  realize the great loss for this city and this country, if he would not come.</tei:p><tei:p>Oswald Jonas
[<tei:hi rend="italic">unsigned</tei:hi>]
1719 North Park Ave. Chicago 14</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>