<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 12/6, [15] : 9-5-32 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Oswald Jonas, reproduced here with kind permission.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> Permission to publish on this website granted by the heirs of Oswald Jonas, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1932-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Oswald Jonas; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 09/05/1932 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated September 5, 1932</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-06-06</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>[Jonas: Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks:] Encloses sample page-make-up by Saturn-Verlag, and asks S to send addresses for recipients of invitations [to subscribe].  Reports on his professional prospects and contacts in Berlin, and on reviewing.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Jonas, Oswald; Schenker, Heinrich;  Introduction;  Einführung;  Ungar, Fritz;  Saturn-Verlag;  addresses;  subscriptions;  Berlin;  lectures;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Roth, Hermann;  Violin, Moriz;  Einstein, Alfred;  reviews;  Das Meisterwerk in der Musik III</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Berlin</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated September 5, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Berlin 5. Sept. 32</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Aus beiliegendem Probedruck werden Sie ersehen, daß es nun doch Ernst mit meinem Absicht wird.</tei:p><tei:p>Der Direktor des in Wien bereits ziemlich angesehenen Verlags, D^r^ Fritz Ungar<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Fritz Ungar, director of the Saturn Verlag, which published Jonas’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks: Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers</tei:hi> in 1934.   He was involved in the earlier proposal for a monthly periodical centered on S’s theory, proposed in December 1927 and rejected by S.  </tei:note> ist ein Vetter von mir und wird sicher bei nur einigermaßen gegebenen Grundlage mein Interesse wahren.  Meine Bitte an Sie, sehr verehrter Herr Doktor, besteht nur darin, mir beziehungsweise Herrn D^r^ Ungar wenn irgend möglich Adressenmaterial zwecks Zusendung solcher Einladungen zukommen zu lassen.  Glauben Sie, daß darunter auch solche sein werden, die mehr als <tei:hi rend="italic">ein</tei:hi> Exemplar zum Gebrauch abnehmen würden, also auch ein übriges tun würden?  Bitte verzeihen Sie mir diese Belästigung und nehmen Sie mir Müheverursachung nicht übel.  Auch für sonstige Ratschläge wäre ich Ihnen sehr dankbar!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich bin nun wieder in Berlin – mein Kurs “Einführung in Schenker”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Jonas mentions this lecture in OJ 12/6, [14], August 30, 1932.</tei:note> findet seine Fortsetzung, im übrigen hoffe ich durch Arbeiten für Zeitschriften und Rundfunk mein vorläufiges Fortkommen zu <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> finden! Leicht wird es ja nicht sein.</tei:p><tei:p>Dr Furtwängler<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Wilhelm Furtwängler [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> habe ich noch nicht gesehn, ich schreibe ihm aber jetzt auch wegen des Buches.  Wissen Sie übrigens vielleicht auch die Adresse von Prof. H. Roth?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="roth_herman">Hermann Roth</ref>.</tei:note> Auch mit Violin<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="violin_moriz">Moriz Violin</ref>.</tei:note> will ich mich wieder in Verbindung setzen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Jonas inserts emdash here, then writes without line-break.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ich möchte Sie heute nicht weiter belästigen und verbleibe indes mit herzlichem Dank, besten Grüßen an Ihre werte Frau Gemahlin und Ihnen selbst</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr ganz ergebener
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p><tei:p>Von Dr Einstein<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="einstein_alfred">Alfred Einstein</ref>. </tei:note> bekam ich eine lange Reihe theoretischer Werke zur Besprechung.  Die Besprechung des Jahrbuches III<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi> III;  the review appeared in the <tei:hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für Neue Musik</tei:hi>, November 1932 (preserved in OC/p.88).</tei:note> erscheint im nächsten Heft.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated September 5, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Berlin, September 5, [19]32</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>From the enclosed offprint you will see that serious steps are now being taken regarding my plans.</tei:p><tei:p>The director of the press (which is already rather prominent in Vienna), Dr. Fritz Ungar,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> is a cousin of mine and will certainly look after my interests with only roughly stated guidelines.  My request to you, most  esteemed Doctor, is merely to send me or Dr. Ungar, if at all possible, address-material for the issuing of such invitations. Do you think that would include individuals who would take more than <tei:hi rend="italic">one</tei:hi> copy for their use, and thus would add an extra one?  Please excuse this bother, and take no offense at the imposition.  I would be grateful, too, for any further suggestions!</tei:p><tei:p>I am back in Berlin—my course “Introduction to Schenker”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> is being continued; for the rest, I hope to make a living for now through work for periodicals and radio! <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> It will by no means be easy.</tei:p><tei:p>I have not yet seen Dr. Furtwängler;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> I will now write him concerning the book. Do you know, by the way, the address of Prof. H. Roth?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  I want to get in touch again with Violin<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> as well.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/></tei:p><tei:p>I don’t want to bother you further today, and I remain, with hearty thanks, best greetings to your good wife and yourself,</tei:p><tei:p>Yours very sincerely,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ]Oswald Jonas</tei:p><tei:p>From Dr. Einstein<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> I received a long series of theoretical works for review.  The review of <tei:hi rend="italic">Jahrbuch</tei:hi> III<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> will appear in the next issue.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>