<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 12/6, [40] : 12-19-34 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Oswald Jonas, published here with kind permission.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> Permission to publish on this website granted by the heirs of Oswald Jonas, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1934-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Oswald Jonas; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 12/19/1934 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated December 19, 1934, with 2p typed enclosure</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-10-03</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>J encloses translation of English review of his book; comments desparingly. —Lawsuit against Willi Reich comes to court on December 22.  — J hopes to give lectures in Vienna. —Asks if S knows Carl Johann Perl. —Holiday good wishes.

 </dc:description><dc:subject>Jonas, Oswald; Schenker, Heinrich;  Monthly Musical Record;  Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks;  Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers;  Schoenberg;  Reich, Willi;  lawsuit;  court;  Vienna;  lectures;  Wolf, Hans;  Hamburg;  Klangauskomponierung;  composing-out of sonorities;  Auskomponierung;  composing-out;  Wiederholung;  repetition;  Perl, Carl Johann;  Das Meisterwerk in der Musik;  Masterwork in Music;  Jahrbuch III;  Yearbook III; Die Musik;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Christmas holidays</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated December 19, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>19. XII 34.
Sehr verehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Anbei sende ich Ihnen die Übersetzung eines in einer englischen Musikzeitschrift erschienen Kritik meines Buches.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  A review in <tei:hi rend="italic">Monthly Musical Record</tei:hi>, December 1934.  Click on &lt;a href="../../../../../review/monthly<tei:hi rend="italic">musical</tei:hi>reco.html"&gt;translated review&lt;/a&gt; of Jonas’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks: Eine Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers</tei:hi> (Vienna: Saturn-Verlag, 1934).  The typed translation of this review is filed with the letter.</tei:note>  Sie können daraus entnehmen, daß sich der Schwachsinn scheinbar in Permanenz etablieren will.  So armselig Dummes Zeug und Vorbeigerede und immer wieder – Schönberg.  Es scheint da wieder eine starke Konjunktion zu kommen für die Herrschaften, wahrscheinlich aus dem bedenklichen Trugschluß, daß alles, was verfolgt wird, schon deshalb unschuldig sein muß. – Ja, die Wahrheit ist zwar einfacher, aber schwerer, viel schwerer!</tei:p><tei:p>– Am 22. d. ist die Verhandlung gegen Willi Reich<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  See OC 44/9, October 27, 1934, and OJ 12/6, [39], November 28, 1934.</tei:note> – ich bin ja neugierig, was wir da wieder vorgetischt bekommen werden. –<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  S inserts an emdash and then continues writing without paragraph-break.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Wenn es mir nun irgendwie gelingt, bin ich im Sommer auf 1–2 Wochen in Wien und möchte dort gern <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> einige Vorträge halten, eventuell in Privatkreisen.  Ich habe schon an verschiedene Leute geschrieben, glaube aber, daß es nicht anders gehen wird, als mit “Kartenausgabe”, denn sonst versprechen die Leute zu kommen und lassen mich im letzten Moment sitzen.  Und ohne Ersatz der Kosten kann ich ja das leider nicht unternehmen.  Hans Wolf<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="wolf_hans">Hans Wolf</ref>.</tei:note> meinte, daß auf der Universität größeres Interesse dafür bestünde; vielleicht könnte ich dort Vorträge halten.  Und zwar vor allem über den Begriff der Klangauskomponierung.  Das erscheint mir heute das Allerwichtigste.  Bei zwei&lt;del&gt;t&lt;/del&gt; Vorträgen (so wie ich es jetzt in Hambg. gemacht habe) der +erste+ über Wiederholung im allgemeinen [der] +zweite+ über Auskomponierung als Wiederholung des Naturklanges “in der Zeit”, als +Stoff+ der Musik und Inhalt.</tei:p><tei:p>Damit erledigt sich alles gerade von “Theorien” akustischen, 12 Tönen und was sonst noch.  – Das wäre schön, wenn das in Wien einmal <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> zustandekäme, nur ist wie gesagt die Verläßlichkeit der meisten Menschen ja sehr zweifelhaft.</tei:p><tei:p>– Ich hoffe, sehr verehrter Herr Doktor, daß Sie sich gesundheitlich wohl fühlen und zufrieden sind.  Kennen Sie übrigens einen Herrn Carl Johann Perl<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Carl Johann Perl (1891–1979), Catholic musicologist, and translator of St. Augustine and other church fathers;  attended Guido Adler’s musicological seminar at the University, frequent reviewer for <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Musik</tei:hi>.  The review in question was “Heinrich Schenkers ‚Das Meisterwerk in der Musik,  Ein Jahrbuch, Bd. III’, <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Musik</tei:hi> 23/1 (1930/31) 672f, preserved on OC 2/p. 83. (<tei:hi rend="italic">Biographisch-Bibliographisches Kirchenlexikon</tei:hi> online: www.bautz.de/bbkl)</tei:note> (er hat über das III. Jahrb.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Schenker’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi> III (1930).</tei:note> In der Musik seinerzeit geschrieben)?  Ich bin seit sehr langer Zeit heute Abend wieder bei ihm eingeladen und hoffe, einiges Neues zu hören (auch über F.,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Wilhelm Furtwängler [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> von dem ich augenblicklich +nichts+ weiß!)</tei:p><tei:p>So will ich Ihnen und Ihrer verehrten Frau Gemahlin recht schöne Feiertage und alles Erdenklich Gute wünschen und bleibe mit den ergebensten Grüßen</tei:p><tei:p>stets
Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated December 19, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>December 19, 1934
Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>I send you herewith the translation of a review of my book published in an English music journal.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  You can see from it that the stupidity apparently aims to establish itself permanently.  Such miserably obtuse trash and irrelevancy, and always, again—Schoenberg.  Once again the powers seem to espy a strong conjunction, probably from the very dubious inference that anything that is assailed must for that very reason be innocent. —Well, the truth, though simpler, is more difficult, far more difficult!</tei:p><tei:p>The case against Willi Reich<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> comes up on the 22d—I am curious as to what fare will be served up there.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/></tei:p><tei:p>If at all possible I well be in Vienna for one or two weeks and would like to give <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> several lectures there, possibly in private circles.  I have already written to various people, but I think that it will work only with distribution of “tickets of admission,” otherwise people promise to come and then leave me in the lurch at the last moment.  And absent offset of the costs I unfortunately cannot undertake that.  Hans Wolf<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> thought there would be greater interest in this plan at the university; perhaps I could give lectures there.  Above all on the concept of composing-out of sonorities.  That seems to me today to be the most important topic.  In two lectures (which I have just given in Hamburg), the +first+ about repetition in general, the +second+ about composing-out as repetition of the chord of nature “through time,” as the +substance+ of music and its content.</tei:p><tei:p>That takes care of everything in the “theories,” acoustical, 12-tone, and whatever. —It would be lovely if that could happen in Vienna, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> but, as said, the reliability of most people is very dubious.</tei:p><tei:p>I hope, esteemed doctor, that you are feeling physically well and contented.  Do you, by the way, know a Mr. Carl Johann Perl<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> (he wrote about <tei:hi rend="italic">Yearbook</tei:hi> III<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> at the time in <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Musik</tei:hi>)?  I am invited, after a very long interim, to visit him again this evening and I hope to hear some news (including news of Furtwängler,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> of whom I know +nothing+ at the moment!)[.]</tei:p><tei:p>Thus I want to wish you and your good wife very happy holidays, and every imaginable boon, and remain, with most respectful greetings,</tei:p><tei:p>As ever,
Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>