<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 12/6, [22] : 5-9-33 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Oswald Jonas, published here with kind permission.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> Permission to publish on this website granted by the heirs of Oswald Jonas, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1933-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Oswald Jonas; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 05/09/1933 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated May 9, 1933</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-07-14</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>J acks OJ 5/18, 25; agreement having been reached on his Einführung, he hopes for fall publication; has read the two articles by S; sends recent article on Photogrammarchiv; will be in Vienna on 16th.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Jonas, Oswald; Schenker, Heinrich;  Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks;  Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers;  agreement;  publication;  Deutsche Zeitung;  Brahms;  Photogrammarchiv;  Vienna;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Brahms centenary</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated May 9, 1933</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>9. Mai 33</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Meinen herzlichsten Dank für Ihre freundliche Karte<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  OJ 5/18, 25. I thank Irene Schreier Scott for help with the transcription of this and a few other items.</tei:note> und “Mahnung zum Vorsicht.”  Ich hoffe nun doch, daß es jetzt zu einer endgültigen Einigung kommt und das Buch dann rechtzeitig im Herbst herauskommen kann.  Ihre beiden Artikel<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Schenker, „Erinnerung an Brahms,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Deutsche Zeitschrift</tei:hi> [prev. <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Kunstwart</tei:hi> ] 46 (May 1933), 475–82; „Was wird aus der Musik?“, <tei:hi rend="italic">Deutsche allgemeine Zeitung</tei:hi> (April 28, 1933) [= <tei:hi rend="italic">Basler National-Zeitung</tei:hi>, Sonntagsbeilage (May 28, 1933), 1].</tei:note> hatte ich selbstverständlich gelesen – ich kaufe Freitag stets die Dt. Ztg. wegen der Musikbeilage und Sie können sich meine Überraschung vorstellen, als ich Ihren Aufsatz sah (über die “Vorbemerkung” der Schriftleitung war ich weniger überrascht).</tei:p><tei:p>Köstlich finde ich das Wort von <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> von [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Brahms in dem andern Aufsatz ”Schauen Sie hinter den 8. Takt!”  Aber was nützt das alles – dgl. geht den Menschen eben nicht ein, sie können nicht, sie wollen nicht.  Und zu glauben, daß sie durch Schaden Klug werden, ist ein falsches Optimismus. –<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  S inserts emdash at this point, and continues writing without paragraph break.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ich erlaube mir, Ihnen den am 1. IV endlich erschienenen (am Boykotttag<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  April 1, 1933, the boycott of Jewish businesses.  It was the beginning of the severe restrictions on Jews in all areas of life.  Jews were not allowed on the street on this day, but, as the writer told me, “Mr. Jonas went out anyway” to pick up a copy of his new article.</tei:note>) Aufsatz über das Archiv<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  No copy appears to survive in OC or OJ: perhaps an earlier version of J's “The Photogram-Archives in Vienna,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Music &amp; Letters</tei:hi> (1934), 344–47. Click on <ref cRef="photogrammarchiv">Photogrammarchiv</ref>.</tei:note> “erweitert” verändert, zu übersenden.  Die Überschrift ist so sinnlos wie nicht von mir. – ich komme also am 16. auf eine Woche nach Wien und wäre Ihnen sehr dankbar, wenn Sie mir mitteilen wollten, wann ich Sie sehen dürfte.</tei:p><tei:p>Furtwängler<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Wilhelm Furtwängler [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> sprach ich noch vor seiner Abreise, ich war bei ihm und <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> wir unterhielten uns viel über Klavierspiel.  Über die “Pianisten”!</tei:p><tei:p>— Das Brahmsgetue am Sonntag<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Sunday May 7, 1933 was the exact centenary of Brahms’s birth.</tei:note> war wohl greulich – die Aufsätze in den verschiedenen Zeitungen, furchtbares Niveau!</tei:p><tei:p>Nochmals herzlichsten Dank und alles Gute Ihnen und Ihrer werten Frau Gemahlin.</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr ergebenster
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated May 9, 1933</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>May 9, [19]33</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor,
My warmest thanks for your cordial card<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> and “caution-alert”!  I hope, though, that now a final agreement can be reached and the book can then come out on time in the fall. Of course I read both of your articles<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>—I always buy the <tei:hi rend="italic">Deutsche Zeitung</tei:hi> on Friday for the music supplement, and you can imagine my surprise on seeing your essay (I was less surprised at the “prefatory remark” by the editors).</tei:p><tei:p>I found the utterance by <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Brahms in the other essay priceless: “Take a look at what happens after the eighth bar!” But what’s the use—people don’t understand that sort of thing, they can’t and don’t want to.  And to believe that they learn something through damage is a false optimism.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/></tei:p><tei:p>I take the liberty of  sending you the “expanded” modified essay on the Archive<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> which came out at last on April 1 (on boycott-day<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>). The epigraph is in equal measure nonsensical and not by me. —In a week, on the 16th, I’ll be coming to Vienna and would be very grateful if you would let me know when I might see you.</tei:p><tei:p>I visited Furtwängler<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> before his departure; I spent some time with him and <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> we talked a lot about piano-playing. About the “pianists”!</tei:p><tei:p>The Brahms to-do on Sunday<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> was simply dreadful—the essays in the various newspapers, horrible niveau!</tei:p><tei:p>Again, warmest thanks and all best wishes to you and your good wife.</tei:p><tei:p>Yours sincerely,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>