<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 12/6, [34] : 7-19-34 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Oswald Jonas, published here with kind permission.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> Permission to publish on this website granted by the heirs of Oswald Jonas, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1934-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Oswald Jonas; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 07/19/1934 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated July 19, 1934</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-09-04</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Acks two postcards, thanks S for his note [re Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks]; has heard nothing from Hoboken; Furtwängler is too busy to read the book now; J is going to Bayreuth.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Jonas, Oswald; Schenker, Heinrich;  Warnsdorf;  Varnsdorf;  Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks;  Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  Furwängler, Wilhelm;  Bayreuth;  errata list</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated July 19, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>19. Juli 1934.
Sehr verehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Ihre beiden, so liebenswürdigen Karten<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  The two postcards are obviously lost; the last postcard up to this point from Schenker to Jonas in our collection (OJ 5/18, 40) was written more than three months earlier.</tei:note> wurden mir bereits nach Warnsdorf in der C. S. R.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  The modern Czech Republic; Warnsdorf, now Varnsdorf, north of Prague, on the German border 30 miles ESE of Dresden.</tei:note> nachgesandt, wo ich seit 2 Wochen zur Erholung auf Besuch bei Bekannten bin.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich danke Ihnen tausendmal für Ihre freundliche Zeilen und hoffe nun, daß Sie durch die weitere Lektüre<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Further reading of Jonas’s recently published <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks: Eine Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers</tei:hi>.</tei:note> nicht enttäuscht sind; ich weiß aber leider nur zu gut, wo es überall noch fehlt. – Über meine Arbeiten, die ich nun vorhabe, kann ich leider noch garnichts sagen, da mir weder der Verleger auf meine Anfragen bezüglich Kosten etc. bis jetzt präzise geantwortet hat noch van Hoboken<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> bezüglich seiner Pläne – 2 Briefe und eine Karte sind seit Wochen (Monaten) ohne Antwort von ihm geblieben.  Ist er überhaupt in Garmisch?</tei:p><tei:p>Ihre Anfrage wegen Furtw.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Wilhelm Furtwängler [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> kann ich leider nicht so beantworten, wie es wünschenswert wäre.  Ich sehe natürlich ein, daß er in den letzten Monaten geistig wie physisch vollkommen überlastet war, aber schließlich geht das mit dem Buch schon seit etlichen Monaten: zum Schluß, nachdem ich ihn Wochen hindurch täglich – manchmal 3x &lt;strike&gt;)&lt;/strike&gt;|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Apparently a right parenthesis was written by mistake, and then overwritten with the matching m-dash.</tei:note> anrufen mußte – wollte er doch das Buch lesen, kann dann natürlich noch weniger – und so warte ich noch heute <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> auf irgendein Schreiben von ihm.  Ob es noch kommt, zweifle ich sehr, habe auch keine Lust, ihn noch und noch zu belästigen.</tei:p><tei:p>Samstag fahre ich nun nach Bayreuth – seltsamer Zufall, daß ich gerade in dieser Zeit zum ersten Mal im Leben dorthin komme.  Nun die jüngsten Ereignisse<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  J must be referring to the “night of the long knives”, June 30, 1934, when Ernst Röhm and other leaders of the SA (Stormtroopers), and Kurt von Schleicher and Otto Strasser, 400 in all, were shot by members of the SS.  </tei:note> werden dort der Festfreude Wahn heimlich auch einen kleinen Dämpfer aufgesetzt haben, was ja sicher nicht unvorteilhaft sein dürfte.</tei:p><tei:p>Wenn es nur irgendwie zu machen geht, werde ich mir erlauben auf der Reise nach Wien bei Ihnen vorzusprechen – ich hoffe sehr, daß es möglich sein wird.</tei:p><tei:p>Indes wünsche ich Ihnen sowie Ihrer verehrten Frau Gemahlin weiter die beste Erholung und verbleibe mit ergebensten Grüße</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr stets dankbarer
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p><tei:p>P.S. Leider sind trotz aller Sorgfalt und Mühe noch immer eine ganze Reihe Druckfehler stehen geblieben.  Es erscheint aber demnächst ein Fehlerverzeichnis.</tei:p><tei:p>Bis 27. erreicht mich Post: Bayreuth postlagernd</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated July 19, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>July 19, 1934
Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>Your two very kind postcards<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> have been forwarded to me in Warnsdorf in the C. S. R.,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> where I have been on vacation for the last two weeks visiting acquaintances.</tei:p><tei:p>I thank you so very much for your cordial note, and hope only that you will not be disappointed on reading further;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> I know only too well those places where it still falls short. —Concerning my works that I now have planned, I can unfortunately say nothing, since neither has my publisher as yet answered precisely my queries about costs, etc., nor has Hoboken<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> replied about his plans—two letters and a card remain unanswered for weeks (months) by him.  Is he in Garmisch at all?</tei:p><tei:p>Unfortunately I cannot answer your query about Furtwängler<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> as I would wish.  I understand, naturally, that in the last months he has been completely overloaded, both mentally and physically, but this matter with the book has gone on already for several months: in the end, after I had to call him daily—sometimes three times—<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> yes, he wanted to read the book, but now is naturally even less able to do so—and thus I wait still today <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> for any written message from him.  Whether it will still come I doubt very much, also don’t like to trouble him again and again.</tei:p><tei:p>Saturday I will go to Bayreuth—odd coincidence, that just in this time I go there for the first time in my life.  Now the latest events<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> will have put a little damper on the madness of the festivities, which may certainly not be disadvantageous.</tei:p><tei:p>If it can be arranged at all, I will permit myself on the trip to Vienna to call on you—I hope very much that it will be possible.</tei:p><tei:p>In the meantime I also wish you and your esteemed wife the best vacation and remain with most respectful greetings</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p><tei:p>P.S. Unfortunately, despite all effort and painstaking, a whole series of misprints remains.  But an errata list will be out shortly.</tei:p><tei:p>Until the 27th, mail will reach me at: general delivery, Bayreuth.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>