<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 12/6, [29] : 3-30-34 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Oswald Jonas, reproduced here with kind permission.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> Permission to publish on this website granted by the heirs of Oswald Jonas, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1934-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Oswald Jonas; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 03/30/1934 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated March 30, 1934</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-08-03</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Wishes the Schenkers a happy Easter. —Book expected out April 20: J wonders if it would be a good idea to ask Furtwängler for a letter for it.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Jonas, Oswald; Schenker, Heinrich;  Osterfest;  Easter holiday;  Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks;  Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Vienna;  Beethoven;  Coriolanus Overture;  letter;  eye condition</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  W 30 Bambergerstrasse 25</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated March 30, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>30. III 34.
[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>] Dr. OSWALD JONAS
W 30 Bambergerstr 25</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Zunächst möchte ich Ihnen sowie Ihrer verehrten Frau Gemahlin ein recht frohes Osterfest wünschen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Easter 1934 fell on April 1.</tei:note>  Ich hoffe, daß Sie die Tage recht ungetrübt und in frischer Gesundheit verbringen.</tei:p><tei:p>Von meinem Verleger kam ein Brief, daß das Buch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> Jonas’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks: Eine Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers</tei:hi> (Vienna: Saturn-Verlag, 1934).</tei:note> voraussichtlich am 20. April erscheint, was für mich sehr erfreulich.</tei:p><tei:p>Hob.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> schrieb mir, daß er am 3. in Wien und den Verleger sprechen möchte, dh. er <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> hat um seine Adresse gebeten.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr schön war das letzte Furtw.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Wilhelm Furtwängler [create biogfile and link].  </tei:note> Konzert am Montag – II, V Symph. Coriolan dasselbe Programm Freitg vorher unter ihm in Hambg habe ich gleichfalls gehört.  Er erzählte mir, daß er nach Wien führe nächste Woche und Sie sehen werde.</tei:p><tei:p>Er war in ziemlich verzweifelter Stimmung, ob sich indes wieder etwas geändert hat, weiß ich nicht.  Glauben Sie, daß es gut wäre, ihn um einen Brief für das Buch zu bitten, da wir vorhaben, dasselbe an Bibliotheken und Konserv. zu senden, was mit einem Begleitschreiben von ihm vielleicht wirkungsvoller wäre.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr dankbar wäre ich Ihnen, wenn Sie bei ihm für mich ein Wort einlegen <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> wollten.  – Ich selbst kann nie meine Situation so recht schildern, was soll ich auch antworten, wenn er mich fragt, wie es mir geht.  Da sage ich aber, ganz gut.  Er versteht wahrscheinlich nicht, daß mir mit 2 halbwegs anständig zahlenden Schülern mehr geholfen wäre als mit allem Fragen etc.  An eine Stellung ist jetzt auf keinen Fall zu denken. —</tei:p><tei:p>Wie geht es nun bei Ihnen?  Ist der Zustand der Augen erträglich?  Sehr gerne erführe ich etwas von Ihrem Befinden und  Ihrer Lage.  Ich hoffe, daß [Sie] mir mein langes Schweigen seit<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  This word appears in the script to be “dort.”  Given that the writer inadvertently omitted the subject “Sie,” we may assume that he was distracted and wrote the wrong word here.</tei:note> meinem vorigen Brief nicht übel genommen haben und es mich nicht entgelten lassen.</tei:p><tei:p>Nochmals alles Gute Ihnen und Ihrer werten Frau Gemahlin!</tei:p><tei:p>Mit ergebensten Grüßen
Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated March 30, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>March 30, 1934
[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>] Dr. OSWALD JONAS
W 30 Bambergerstr 25</tei:p><tei:p>Esteemed Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>First I would like to wish you and your esteemed wife a really happy Easter holiday.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> I hope that you pass the days without any aggravation and in the bloom of good health.</tei:p><tei:p>A letter came from my publisher to the effect that the book<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> should come out on April 20, which is very gratifying to me.</tei:p><tei:p>Van Hoboken<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> wrote me that he would be in Vienna on the 3rd and would like to speak with the publisher, that is, he <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> asked for his address.</tei:p><tei:p>The last Furtwängler<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> concert, on Monday, was very beautiful—[B’s] second and fourth symphonies, and the Coriolanus Overture.  I heard the same program the previous Friday under him in Hamburg as well.  He told me that he will travel to Vienna next week and will see you.</tei:p><tei:p>He was in a rather despondent mood; whether that has changed somewhat in the meantime I don’t know.  Do you think it would be good to ask him for a letter for the book,  since we plan to send it to libraries and conservatories, which would perhaps be more effective with an accompanying letter from him.</tei:p><tei:p>I would be very grateful to you if you <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> would put in a good word for me.  I myself can never describe my situation very well; what am I to answer when he asks how I am.  But I say: very well.  He probably doesn’t understand that I would benefit more from two halfway decent paying pupils than from all [his] questions etc.  There can be no thought just now of an [academic] appointment.</tei:p><tei:p>How are you doing?  Is your eye-condition tolerable?  I would be very glad for news of your health and your situation.  I hope that you do not take offense at my long silence since<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> my previous letter and won’t exact a penalty for it.</tei:p><tei:p>Once again, all good wishes to you and your good wife!</tei:p><tei:p>With sincerest greetings,
Your
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>