<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 12/6, [38] : 9-25-32 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> Permission to publish on this website granted by the heirs of Oswald Jonas, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1932-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Oswald Jonas; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 09/25/1932 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated September 25, [1932]</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-06-16</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Reports letter from Hoboken re subscriptions to his Einführung; also on publishing and broadcasting prospects.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Jonas, Oswald; Schenker, Heinrich;  Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks;  Eine Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  subscriptions;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Berlin;  Breithaupt; Die Musik;  Einstein, Alfred;  Grabner, Hermann;  Der lineare Satz;  Binenthal, Leopold;  radio;  Clavierbüchlein;  Photogrammarchiv;  Cäcilia;  Droucker, Sandra;  Oslo</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated September 25, [1932]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>25. IX.</tei:p><tei:p>Hochverehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich möchte Ihnen zunächst nun herzlich danken für Ihren lieben Brief,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  The letter 5/18, 14 rather than 5/18, 15, written the previous day and probably not yet received.</tei:note> die mich sehr, sehr gefreut hat!  Auch für die Mühe, die Sie sich mit der Zusammenstellung der Adressen gemacht haben innigen Dank! – Was Sie von Herrn Hob.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> schreiben, ist sehr betrüblich, für mich schon deshalb, weil er zu mir persönlich wirklich ungemein freundlich war; gerade gestern kam wieder ein Brief – eine Antwort wegen der “Einführung.”  Er fragt mich, wieviel schon subscribiert worden ist und wieviel <tei:hi rend="italic">notwendig</tei:hi> ist.  Ich vermute, daß er eben darüber orientiert sein will – ich schreibe ihm jedenfalls, was mein Vertrag mit dem Verlag enthält, daß 400 Exemplare notwendig sind.  Freilich über die Zahl der anherigen Subscribenten kann ich noch garnichts sagen.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich will auch Furtwängler<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Wilhelm Furtwängler [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> schreiben, der ist aber <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> noch nicht in Berlin. – Neulich war ich bei Breithaupt,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Perhaps Rudolf Maria Breithaupt (1873–1945), pupil of Liszt, piano professor at the Berlin Hochschule für Musik, author of <tei:hi rend="italic">Die natürliche Klavierthechnik. Die freie, rhythmisch-natürliche Bewegung (Automatik) des gesamtes Spielorganismus (Schulter, Arme, Hände, Finger) als Grundlage der "klavieristischen" Technik</tei:hi>  (Leipzig: Kahnt Nachf., 1905–1919).</tei:note> der mir alles mögliche versprach, vor allem bei der “Musik” – was aber nicht verhinderte, daß ich nach zwei Tagen beiliegenden Artikel von der Musik<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Possibly a response by Jonas to Walter Riezler, "Die Urlinie," in <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Musik</tei:hi> XXII/7 (April, 1930); see 5/18, 2 and 12/6, 16.</tei:note> zurückbekam.  Seltsam, da es eine Erwiderung auf einen doch erschienenen Aufsatz ist, aber das ist den Herren unbequem, sie sind auch so “mit Material überhäuft”!  (Über allem möglichen Quark nämlich!)</tei:p><tei:p>Von D^r^ Einstein<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="einstein_alfred">Alfred Einstein</ref>.</tei:note> bekam ich eine Anzahl Bücher zur Besprechung (darunter Grabner “Lineare Satz[”]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Hermann Grabner, <tei:hi rend="italic">Der lineare Satz; ein Lehrbuch des Kontrapunktes</tei:hi> (Stuttgart, 1930).</tei:note> und dgl. – eben auch ein entzückendes Chopin Buch, Dokumente von Binenthal<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Leopold Binental, <tei:hi rend="italic">Chopin: Dokumente und Erinnerungen aus seiner Heimatstadt</tei:hi> (Leipzig: Breitkopf u. Härtel, 1932).</tei:note> mit sehr hübschen unveröffentlichten Sachen, auch Facsimiles von Autographen!) Vielleicht freute es Sie, auch zu hören daß ich am 30. IX im Rundfunk einen Vortrag habe (Fantasien für Klavier) natürlich sehr populär, und einen [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] “Deutsche Welle” am 16. X. über das “Klavierbüchlein 1722”.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  The smaller “Clavierbüchlein vor Anna Magdalena Bach."  Cf. 12/6, [14].</tei:note>  In <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Berlin sind solche Dinge doch eher möglich als in Wien. Auch mein Kurs beginnt wieder am 1 Okt. im Konserv.  Ein Vortrag im Rundfunk über das “Archiv”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Click on <ref cRef="photogrammarchiv">Photogrammarchiv</ref>.</tei:note> ist so gut wie angenommen.  Haben Sie übrigens schon das Heft der “Cäcilia”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  See 12/6 [16] and [18].</tei:note> erhalten, das ich Ihnen zukommen ließ?  Darin ist ein Aufsatz über das Archiv, den eine Bekannte von mir ins Holländische übersetzt hat.</tei:p><tei:p>Meine Schülerin, Frau Sandra Droucker,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Sandra Droucker is found playing the Beethoven Piano Concerto No.4 with the Berlin Philharmonic in Oslo on March 27, 1913 (http://www.arbiterrecords.com/notes/140notes.html);  three Debussy pieces in a concert on January 27, 1914, in Norway (http://www.hf.uio.no/imv/forskning/forskningsprosjekter/norgesmusikk/bulletin/1/oversikt.html); the Brahms Piano Concerto No.2 with Furtwängler in Hamburg on March 13, 1914 (http://www.furtwangler.net/doc/WF06-22.doc), where she is described as “the piano teacher of Emperor Wilhelm II's daughter”; she recorded the Chopin G major Nocture, Op.37 for Welte Mignon piano rolls (http://www.usc.edu/libraries/archives/arc/findingaids/welte/176WelteRolls.pdf); is described as “piano teacher” in an ÖNB database (http://ezines.onb.ac.at:8080/moravec/pub/schr/1581.htm);and was author of <tei:hi rend="italic">Et blad av Oslos musikkhistorie</tei:hi> (1945).</tei:note> hält diese Woche in Oslo einen Vortrag über “Schenker”! – Daß Sie so gütig sein wollen, mir sachliche Ratschläge zu erteilen, nehme ich mit tausend Dank an. – Für heute begrüße ich Sie, Ihnen nochmals herzlichst dankend. Empfehlen Sie mich bitte Ihrer Frau Gemahlin!</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr ergebenster
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p><tei:p>Auf Vrieslander<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.</tei:note> bin ich sehr gespannt.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated September 25, [1932]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>September 25, [1932]</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>I want first of all to thank you most heartily for your gracious letter,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> which made me very, very happy!  Thank you too for your care in compiling the list of addresses!—What you write about Mr. Hoboken<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> is very disturbing, for me merely because he was really uncommonly friendly to me; just yesterday again a letter came—a reply about the “Introduction.”  He asks how many have already subscribed and how many are <tei:hi rend="italic">necessary</tei:hi>.  I presume that he wants orientation about exactly that.  I will write him in any event what my contract with the press stipulates, that 400 copies are necessary.  Of course, I can say nothing at all about the number of subscribers to date.</tei:p><tei:p>I want also to write Furtwängler,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> who is however <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> not yet in Berlin. —I was recently with Breithaupt,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> who promised me everything possible, above all at <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Musik</tei:hi>—which promise, however, did not avert the return, after two days, of the accompanying article from <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Musik</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  Strange, because it is a reply to an essay that <tei:hi rend="italic">was</tei:hi> published; but that is inconvenient for the gentlemen—they are “inundated with material”!  (With all manner of junk, to be exact!)</tei:p><tei:p>From Dr Einstein<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> I received a number of books for review (including Grabner, <tei:hi rend="italic">Der lineare Satz</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> and the like—also a captivating Chopin book, documents [edited] by Binenthal<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> with very beautiful unpublished things, also facsimiles of autographs!)  It may please you to hear as well that on September 30 I have a lecture on the radio (Fantasies for Piano), naturally very popular, and on October 16 a “German Broadcast” on the “Clavierbüchlein 1722.”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/>  In <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Berlin such things are more easily possible than in Vienna.  And my course begins again on October 1 at the Conservatory.  A radio lecture about the “Archive”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> is as good as accepted.  Have you, by the way, already received the volume of <tei:hi rend="italic">Cäcilia</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> that I had sent you?  It contains an essay about the Archive, which an acquaintance of mine translated into Dutch.</tei:p><tei:p>My pupil Frau Sandra Droucker<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> gives a lecture this week in Oslo on “Schenker”!—I thank you a thousandfold for your gracious willingness to give me professional advice.—For today I greet you with warmest thanks.  Do commend me to your wife!</tei:p><tei:p>Your most devoted,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ]Oswald Jonas</tei:p><tei:p>I am very much looking forward to the Vrieslander.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/></tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>