<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 12/6, [43] &amp; [44] : 3-9-35 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Oswald Jonas, published here with kind permission.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> Permission to publish on this website granted by the heirs of Oswald Jonas, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Oswald Jonas; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 03/09/1935 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ JSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Jonas to Jeanette Schenker, dated March 9, 1935</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-10-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>J thanks JS for opportunity to look at work [unspecified]; J, Salzer, and Saturn-Verlag wish to bring out a music journal in Schenker's memory: J requests access to unpublished materials; inquires whether JS has reached an understanding with Saturn-Verlag over aphorisms.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Jonas, Oswald; Schenker, Jeanette;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Goethe;  Eckermann, Johann Peter;  Salzer, Felix;  Saturn-Verlag;  Ungar, Fritz;  Der Dreiklang;  Bayreuther Blätter;  Czechoslovakia</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Berlin-Schmargendorf, Davoserstrasse 10a</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Vienna III, Keilgasse 8</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Jeanette Schenker, dated March 9, 1935</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">envelope</tei:hi> (= [44]) <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
Frau [/] Prof. Lina Schenker
Wien III
Keilgasse 8</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>]  || BERLIN W |  9 3 35 | 1-2 N | 9 G ||</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">envelope verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
D^r^ Oswald Jonas  B[er]lin-Schmargendorf
Davoserstr. 10a</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">letter</tei:hi> (= [43]}</tei:hi>
9. III 35</tei:p><tei:p>Hochverehrte gnädige Frau!</tei:p><tei:p>Noch möchte ich Ihnen danken für Ihr freundliches und ehrendes Vertrauen, das Sie mir entgegengebracht haben.  Was es für mich bedeutet, einen vorläufigen Einblick in dieses Werk<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Possibly proofs of <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi>.</tei:note> noch vor den andern gewonnen zu haben, werden Sie wohl am besten ermessen können.  Ich mußte in der letzten Zeit, d. h. ich möchte sagen, in den letzten Monaten, soviel an ein wunderbares Wort Goethes zu Eckermann<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Johann Peter Eckermann (1792–1854), German writer, assistant to Goethe toward the end of the latter’s life, and his literary executor and publisher of his posthumous works: <tei:hi rend="italic">Gespräche mit Goethe in den letzten Jahren seines Lebens, 1823–32</tei:hi> [“Conversations with Goethe in the Last Years of His Life, 1823–32”], 3 vol. (1836–48).</tei:note> denken: “Meine Sachen können nicht populär werden – sie sind nicht für die Menge gedacht und geschrieben, sondern für den Einzelnen, der ähnliches erstrebt.”  (Ungefähr so habe ich es <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> in Erinnerung.)  Und so wendet sich auch das Werk Schenkers an den Einzelnen, im Allgemeinen wirken wird es vielleicht langsamer, aber umso sicherer und dauerhafter, wie eben die Wahrheit nun wirken kann.  Es geht von solch einem Werk ein bestimmtes Fluidum aus, das sich der Zeit mitteilt, allmählich wirkt, ohne daß die Zeit selbst es ahnt und merkt.  Es genügt, daß die Einzelnen es weitertragen und wieder Kreise ziehen, die eben auch aus Einzelnen bestehen müßen [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] und gesucht werden müßen [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>].</tei:p><tei:p>– Falls Sie noch nichts durch D^r^ Salzer,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="salzer_felix">Felix Salzer</ref>.</tei:note> der Sie am vergangenen Sonntag zu besuchen wollte, erfahren haben, möchte ich Ihnen eine Mitteilung machen, die Sie sicherlich erfreuen dürfte.</tei:p><tei:p>Wir – Saturn-Verlag, D^r^ Salzer und ich – beabsichtigen eine Musikzeitschrift<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Dreiklang</tei:hi>, edited by Jonas and Salzer, consisting of nine issues (the last two bound as one) from April 1937 through February 1938.</tei:note> herauszugeben, deren vornehmste und wichtigste Aufgabe ist das Andenken Schenkers hochzuhalten und sein Werk zu deuten, es auch jenen zugänglich <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> zu machen, die erst eine Führung dazu bedürfen.  In diesem Zusammenhang möchte ich Sie auch fragen, ob Sie nicht geneigt wären, um manches von den vielen Kostbarkeiten, die noch nicht veröffentlicht sind, zu Publikation zu überlassen.  Es würde den Wert der Zeitschrift ungeheuer heben, ihr gleich von selbst das programmatische Rückgrat geben.  Dann wäre aber auch damit die notwendige Sichtung der vorhandenen Schätze verbunden und eine Vorbereitung für Buchform am ehesten gegeben.  Ich hoffe sehr, daß Sie unsere Bitte nicht abschlagen werden. –<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  S inserts an emdash, then continues writing without paragraph-break.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Haben Sie sich auch schon mit D^r^ Ungar<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Dr. Fritz Ungar, Jonas’s cousin and owner of Saturn-Verlag: see OJ 12/6, [13], July 14, 1932; OJ 12/6, [15], September 5, 1932; OJ 12/6, [37], August 23, 1934).</tei:note> (Saturn Verlag U 21008) ins Einvernehmen gesetzt wegen des Bandes Aphorismen?  – Das Heft der Bayreuther Blätter bringe ich Ihnen <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> nach Wien mit – ich werde mich gleich nach meiner Ankunft melden oder wollen Sie mir schon jetzt mitteilen, wann (^von^ Montag d 18. an) ich kommen darf?  Die Übersetzung des holländischen Artikels erhalten Sie direkt von der Übersetzerin, die sich in der Tschechoslovakei befindet.</tei:p><tei:p>Nochmals meinen innigsten Dank!</tei:p><tei:p>Mit ergebenstem Handkuß
Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p><tei:p>B[er]lin – Schmargendorf
Davoserstr. 10^a^</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Jeanette Schenker, dated March 9, 1935</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">envelope</tei:hi> (= [44]) <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
Frau Prof. Lina Schenker
Vienna III
Keilgasse 8</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>]  || BERLIN W |  9 3 35 | 1-2 N | 9 G ||</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">envelope verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
D^r^ Oswald Jonas  Berlin-Schmargendorf
Davoserstrasse 10a</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">letter</tei:hi> (= [43]}</tei:hi>
March 9, 1935</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Madam,</tei:p><tei:p>Again I would like to thank you for the cordial and ennobling confidence that you have shown me.  How much it means to me to have gained an advance look into this work<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> before the others you can best judge for yourself.  I have been obliged recently, or in recent months I should say, to think of a marvelous utterance of Goethe’s to Eckermann:<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> “my works cannot become popular—they are not conceived and written for the masses, but for that individual who seeks similar things.”  (Approximately thus, as I <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> remember.)  And Schenker’s work too speaks to the individual; its effectiveness on a broader scale will perhaps be slower, but all the more secure and lasting, which is the only way truth can make its mark.  Such a work exudes a certain atmosphere, which is imparted to the era, which makes its effect gradually, without the era’s having noticed or been aware of it.</tei:p><tei:p>In case you have not yet heard anything from Dr. Salzer,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> who wanted to visit you last Sunday, I would like to provide some information that should certainly please you.</tei:p><tei:p>We – Saturn-Verlag, Dr. Salzer, and I—intend to bring out a music journal<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> whose loftiest and most important task is to venerate Schenker’s memory and interpret his work, also to make it accessible <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> to those who need guidance in approaching it.  In this connection I want to ask you whether you would not be inclined to make available for publication a number of the many treasures that have not yet been published.  It would enormously enhance the value of the journal, would of itself virtually provide the programmatic backbone.  That, however, would entail the necessary viewing of the available treasures and would most readily provide a preparation for presentation in book-form.  I hope very much that you will not decline our request.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/></tei:p><tei:p>Have you already reached an understanding with Dr. Ungar<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> (Saturn-Verlag U 21008) concerning the aphorisms for the volume?  I will bring you <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> in Vienna the issue of <tei:hi rend="italic">Bayreuther Blätter</tei:hi>—I will notify you as soon as I arrive, or would you like to tell me now when (from Monday the 18th on) I may come by?  You will receive the translation of the Dutch article directly from the translator, who is now in Czechoslovakia.</tei:p><tei:p>Once again, my most heartfelt thanks!</tei:p><tei:p>With most respectful kiss on the hand,
Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p><tei:p>Berlin – Schmargendorf
Davoserstrasse 10^a^</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>