<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 12/6, [18] : 12-15-32 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain, reproduced with kind permission of the heirs of Jonas.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> Permission to publish on this website granted by the heirs of Oswald Jonas, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1932-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Oswald Jonas; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 12/15/1932 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated December 15, 1932</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-06-24</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Acks recent letter; comments on S's article in Der Kunstwart; reports conversation with Furtwängler; would like to write something on Handel-Brahms Saul; has heard nothing further from van Hoboken.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Jonas, Oswald; Schenker, Heinrich;  Selbstanzeige;  Der Kunstwart;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Kurth, Ernst;  Handel;  Brahms;  Saul;  Steglich, Rudoph;  Mendelssohn;  Einstein, Alfred;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  Cäcilia</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated December 15, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>15.XII 32</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Vielen Dank für Ihren lieben Brief.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Perhaps OJ 5/18, 17 (q.v.), whose date is uncertain but must fall between November 27, 1932, and the date of this letter.</tei:note>  Den “Kunstwart”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  “Eine Anzeige und eine Selbstanzeige,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Kunstwart</tei:hi> 46 (December 1932), 194–96.</tei:note> habe ich indes gelesen; die wenigen Zeilen in der “Selbstanzeige” haben mich wirklich erschüttert, weil sie so ganz kraß einem die Lage vor Augen bringen.  Freilich – die Wahrheit hat ja jederzeit ein kümmerliches Dasein gefristet und war stets unbeliebt, weil unbequem.  Auf breite Wirkung kann sie nicht berechnet sein.  Gerade bei dieser Lektüre hatte ich so stark das Bedürfnis, Ihnen meinen innigsten Dank für Ihr Werk auszusprechen und zu sagen, wie ich stets davon erfüllt bin, was Sie mir gegeben haben.</tei:p><tei:p>Gestern war ich bei D^r^ Furtwängler<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Wilhelm Furtwängler [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> – es war eine sehr schöne und genußreiche Stunde, in der wir uns über alles mögliche unterhielten – auch Kurth<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Ernst Kurth (1886-1946), music theorist, author of <tei:hi rend="italic">Grundlagen des linearen Kontrapunkts</tei:hi> (1917), <tei:hi rend="italic">Romantische Harmonik und ihre Krise in Wagners “Tristan”</tei:hi> (1920), <tei:hi rend="italic">Bruckner</tei:hi> (1925), <tei:hi rend="italic">Musikpsychologie</tei:hi> (1931).</tei:note> u. dgl.  Er gab mir den “Saul”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  See OJ 12/6, 11, note 8.</tei:note> mit, ich habe ihn natürlich erst ganz flüchtig durchgesehen, möchte Sie aber fragen, ob es außerdem eine ausgeschriebene Orgelstimme gibt. – Ich möchte nun gerne darüber etwas schreiben, vielleicht am besten für das Händel Jahrbuch, das D^r^ Steglich<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Rudolph Steglich (1886-1976), German musicologist, pupil of Hugo Riemann, editor of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Händel-Jahrbuch</tei:hi> 1928–33.</tei:note> herausgab und so im letzten Band von den Mendelssohn Bearbeitungen die Rede ist.  D^r^ Einstein<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="einstein_alfred">Alfred Einstein</ref>.</tei:note> muß ja sparsam sein mit Notenbeispielen.  Na, schön!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Von Hob.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> habe ich nichts weiteres gehört, ich warte also nun bis Anfang Jänner, bis er bei Ihnen gewesen ist.  So muß für ihn ja wirklich kein behagliches Gefühl sein, zu merken, daß man immer auf ihn rechnet. – Anbei sende ich Ihnen ein Exemplar der Besprechung<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">   Jonas’s review of Schenker’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi> III.</tei:note> – ich habe sie erst heute bekommen.  Nun wünsche ich Ihnen und Ihrer Frau Gemahlin noch recht, recht angenehme Feiertäge, volle Gesundheit und bleibe</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr stets dankbarer
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p><tei:p>Die Besprechung ist auch im Novemberheft der “Cäcilia”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Cf. OJ 12/6, [38] and [16].</tei:note> – holländisch übersetzt.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated December 15, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>December 15, [19]32</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>Thank you so much for your kind letter.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  I have meanwhile read [your article in] <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Kunstwart</tei:hi>;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> the few lines in the “autobiographical sketch” were truly moving, because they so vividly depict the situation.  Certainly—truth has always endured a tortured existence and was always unloved, because inconvenient.  It cannot be expected to exert a broad influence.  Just in reading this I felt so strongly the need to express my most profound gratitude to you for your work and to say how constantly I am filled with what you have given me.</tei:p><tei:p>Yesterday I spent some time with Dr. Furtwängler<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>—it was a very beautiful and satisfying visit, in which we discussed everything imaginable—including Kurth,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> etc.  He gave me Saul<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> to take along; I naturally looked through it at the outset only in the most cursory manner, but would like to ask you whether there is also a written-out organ part.  I would like to write something about it, perhaps best of all for the <tei:hi rend="italic">Handel-Jahrbuch</tei:hi>, which Dr. Steglich<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> edited and of which the latest issue includes discussion of the Mendelssohn arrangements. Dr. Einstein<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> has to be frugal with musical examples.  Fine!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> I have heard nothing further from van Hoboken,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> thus I’ll wait now until the beginning of January, until he has visited you.  It must be no comfortable feeling for him that everybody always depends on him.  I send you herewith a copy of the review<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/>—received only today.  Now I wish you and your wife very, very pleasant holidays, full of health, and I remain</tei:p><tei:p>Your ever grateful
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p><tei:p>[P. S.] The review is also in the November issue of <tei:hi rend="italic">Cäcilia</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/>—translated into Dutch.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>