<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 12/6, [13] : 7-14-32 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Oswald Jonas, reproduced here with kind permission.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> Permission to publish on this website granted by the heirs of Oswald Jonas, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1932-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Oswald Jonas; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 07/14/1932 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Typed letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated July 14, 1932</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-02-25</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>J reports on his visit to Berlin, where he failed to meet with Furtwängler. Discusses Brahms-Handel Saul and Beethoven Op. 109.  He has heard about the Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln from Hoboken and Salzer.  Discusses plans for publishing his Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerkes.  Has received books from Alfred Einstein. 

</dc:description><dc:subject>Jonas, Oswald; Schenker, Heinrich;  Vienna; Berlin; Furtwängler, Wilhelm; Brahms; Handel; Saul; Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde; National-Bibliothek; Kromer; Beethoven; Op. 109; Hoboken, Anthony van; Salzer, Felix; Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln; Five Graphic Analyses; Haydn; Bach, J. S.; Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerkes; publication; Jahrbuch; Yearbook; Meisterwerk in der Musik; Masterwork in Music; Harmonielehre; Theory of Harmony; Ungar, Dr.; Einstein, Alfred</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Vienna III Untere Weißgärberstr 3F</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated July 14, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>14. Juli 1932
Sehr verehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Seit einer Woche bin ich nun in Wien und arbeite im Photogrammarchiv.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Click on <ref cRef="photogrammarchiv">Photogrammarchiv</ref>.</tei:note> – In Berlin gab es nicht mehr viel Neues – trotz eifrigstem Telephonieren war eine Zusammenkunft mit Dr Furtwängler<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Wilhelm Furtwängler [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> nicht mehr möglich, er war nicht allzulange in Berlin und stets mit Probespielen beim Orchester überbeschäftigt.  So mußte unsere Zusammenkunft wegen des Brahms-Händel Saul<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Brahms’s arrangement for performance of Handel’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Saul</tei:hi> is among the autograph materials in the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde in Vienna.  Schenker had transcribed and edited this document, which he subsequently gave to Furtwängler (see 5/18, 9) who in turn made it available to Jonas (see 5/18, 21) for study and the writing of a commentary.</tei:note> für den September gelassen werden, was mir sehr leid tut, da ich ja gerne die Zeit jetzt im Sommer dazu benützt hätte; ich versuche es aber noch bei der Ges. d. Musikfreunde,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde [create biogfile and link]</tei:note> da die National-bibl.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  National-Bibliothek [create biogfile and link]</tei:note> ohnedies morgen gesperrt wird.  Herr Kromer<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Julius (Ritter von) Kromer (otherwise known as Julo von Kromer) of the Archive for Photographs of Musical Manuscripts of the Austrian National Library: his written communications to S are preserved as OJ 12/24 and OC 30/64, 119; 44/1; A/293.</tei:note> hat übrigens ein Exemplar <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> von op. 109 übergeben und ich soll Sie fragen, ob Sie es für sich haben möchten, andernfalls würde er es mir überlassen, da es ja sonst nicht weitergegeben werden darf.  Ich war vergangenen Montag neulich mit Herrn Hoboken<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> in Berlin zusammen, er erzählte mir viel von den Urlinietafeln,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Urlinietafeln</tei:hi>: i.e. the <tei:hi rend="italic">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln</tei:hi> (New York: David Mannes School, 1932).</tei:note> auch Dr Salzer<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">   Click on <ref cRef="salzer_felix">Felix Salzer</ref>.</tei:note> gab mir jetzt seine Ausarbeitungen von Haydn und Bach.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Haydn, Sonata in E-flat Major, Hob. 49, development; the Bach work could have been either the first Prelude from <tei:hi rend="italic">Well-Tempered Clavier</tei:hi> Book I or the chorale “Ich bin’s, ich sollte büssen” from the <tei:hi rend="italic">St. Matthew Passion</tei:hi> (probably the latter); these analyses, prepared under Schenker’s guidance, were published with others in <tei:hi rend="italic">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln</tei:hi> (New York: David Mannes School, 1932).</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Nun eine große Sache: ich habe schon im Frühjahr – glaube ich – in einem Brief angedeutet, daß ich mich mit einer “Einführung in die Lehre Sch.’s”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Jonas’s book <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Wesen des musikalsichen Kunstwerkes: Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers</tei:hi> (Vienna: Saturn Verlag, 1934).</tei:note> befasse – das ist nun indes greifbarer geworden, die Ferienmonate möchte ich vollends zur letzten Ausarbeitung benützen und habe auch mit meinem Vetter, der einen ziemlich angesehenen Verlag besitzt (Saturn Verlag) darüber gesprochen. (Vielleicht erinnern Sie sich, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> seinerzeit bei der Zeitschriftenfrage)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  This end-parenthesis, although not canceled, was premature; the parenthetical remark closes in the next line.</tei:note> war er auch dabei).  Dr. Ungar<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  The cousin mentioned in the preceding sentence.</tei:note> meint, daß der Subscriptionsweg für die Herausgabe das sicherste wäre und ich möchte Sie nun fragen, ob Sie irgend ein Adressenmaterial für solche Einladungen haben und es eventuell zur Verfügung stellen würden.  Das Buch soll für die bestimmt sein, denen das Jahrbuch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi> (Munich: Drei Masken Verlag, 1925, 1926, 1930).</tei:note> als Anfang zu schwierig ist, die Harmonielehre<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi>, i.e. that by Schenker (Vienna: UE, 1906).</tei:note> (die außerdem nicht zu haben ist) aber zu wenig des Eigentlichen bietet – für Lehrer, als erster Weg, dementsprechend nicht zu umfangreich – aber stets betonend, daß es sich hier um die <tei:hi rend="italic">Kunst</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn16">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Kunst</tei:hi> (art) double-underlined.</tei:note> vor allem handelt, also nicht etwas Nur-handwerkliches (wenn auch soviel Handwerkliches vorausgesetzt ist) und Absoluterlernbares.  Wenn es dem Buch nur gelänge, wieder einige zum näheren Befassen mit dem Werke <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> anzuregen, wäre sein Zweck vollkommen erfüllt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn17">  J inserts an emdash at this point and writes without paragraph break.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ich hoffe, Sie verbringen recht schön und in voller Gesundheit den Sommer, ebenso wie Ihre werte Frau Gemahlin.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn17">  J inserts an emdash at this point and writes without paragraph break.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Von Dr Einstein<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn18">  Click on <ref cRef="einstein_alfred">Alfred Einstein</ref>.</tei:note> kam heute ein großes Bücherpaket zur Besprechung.  Jahrbuch III<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn19">  i.e. a review by J of S's <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, vol.III, possibly in the <tei:hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für Musikwissenschaft</tei:hi>.</tei:note> erscheint im nächsten oder übernächsten Heft; ich möchte dann sofort auch über die Tafeln schreiben, wenn Sie erlauben!  Indes verbleibe ich mit der ergebensten Grüßen an Sie und Ihre Frau Gemahlin</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr stets dankbarer
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas
III Untere Weißgärberstr 3F</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated July 14, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>July 14, 1932
Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>I am now a week back in Vienna and working at the Photostat Archive.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> – In Berlin there was no longer very much news – despite most assiduous telephoning a conference with Dr. Furtwängler<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> was no longer possible; he was not too long in Berlin and was constantly overburdened with orchestra rehearsals. Thus our conference concerning Brahms-Handel <tei:hi rend="italic">Saul</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> had to be left for September, which I regret very much, since I would have liked to use the time now in summer for that purpose; but I will try again at the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> since the National Library<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> will in any case be closed tomorrow. Herr Kromer,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> incidentally, has provided a copy <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> of Op. 109 and I am to ask you whether you would like to have it for yourself; otherwise he would give it to me, since it  is not to be further passed on.  Last Monday I was again with Mr. Hoboken<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> in Berlin; he related much to me about the <tei:hi rend="italic">Urlinietafeln</tei:hi>;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> and Dr. Salzer<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> now gave me his final versions of Haydn and Bach.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/></tei:p><tei:p>Now an important matter: already in spring – I believe – I intimated in a letter that I might work on an <tei:hi rend="italic">Introduction to the Theory of Schenker</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> – that has meanwhile become more feasible; I would like to use the vacation months exclusively for the final completion and have also spoken about it with my cousin, who owns a quite reputable press (Saturn Verlag).  (Perhaps you recall <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> back then, in the periodical matter,)<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> he was also present.)  Dr. Ungar<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> thinks that the subscription-route would be the safest for the publication, and I would like to ask you whether you have any address material for such invitations and would possibly make it available for this purpose.  The book is intended for those for whom the <tei:hi rend="italic">Jahrbuch</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/> would be too difficult as a beginning, the <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn15"/> (which, besides, is unobtainable) on the other hand offers too little of the real substance – for teachers, as a first path, accordingly not too voluminous – but always emphasizing that here it is <tei:hi rend="italic">art</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn16"/> above all that is under consideration, thus not something purely skill-related (even if so much skill is presupposed) and absolutely learnable.  If the book succeeded only in motivating a few to closer study of the teaching, <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> its purpose would have been completely served.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn17"/></tei:p><tei:p>I hope that you are having a really pleasant summer in full health, and wish the same to your good wife.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn17"/></tei:p><tei:p>A large packet of books for review arrived today from Dr. Einstein.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn18"/>  <tei:hi rend="italic">Jahrbuch</tei:hi> III<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn19"/> appears in the next issue or the one after; I would then like to write immediately on the [<tei:hi rend="italic">Urlinie-</tei:hi>]<tei:hi rend="italic">Tafeln</tei:hi>, if you permit! Meanwhile I remain, with most sincere greetings to you and your wife,</tei:p><tei:p>Your ever grateful
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas
[Vienna] III Untere Weißgärberstr 3F</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>