<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 12/6, [11] : 3-24-32 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Oswald Jonas, published here with kind permission.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> Permission to publish on this website granted by the heirs of Oswald Jonas, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1932-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Oswald Jonas; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 03/24/1932 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Typed letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated March 24, 1932</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-05-06</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Acks receipt of letter and card.  Furtwängler will support publication of his essay in the Allgemeine Musikzeitung.  Reports on concert by Furtwängler, on four lectures by himself and the works discussed in them, and prospects for publication of his review of Meisterwerk III. Inquires as to feasibility of his plan for Furtwängler to perform Brahms's arrangement of Handel's Saul.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Jonas, Oswald; Schenker, Heinrich;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Schwers, Paul;  concert;  Haydn;  Beethoven;  Ravel;  Strauss, Richard;  Einstein, Alfred;  Zeitschrift für Musikwissenschaft;  Meisterwerk in der Musik III;  Masterwork in Music III;  Berliner Tagblatt;  lectures;  Vienna Conservatory;  Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst;  Academy of Music;  chorale;  harmonic theory;  Handel;  Saul;  Brahms;  arrangement;  Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde;  permission</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Berlin</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated March 24, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Berlin, den 24. März 1932</tei:p><tei:p>Hochverehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Meinen herzlichsten Dank für Ihren Brief und die Karte,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Probably OJ 5/18, 8, which appears not to survive.</tei:note> mit denen Sie mir eine große [Freude] bereitet haben.  Auch Dr. Furtwängler<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Wilhelm Furtwängler [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> hat der Aufsatz gefallen und mir im letzten Konzert nochmalige Unterstützung bei Schwers<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Paul Schwers, editor of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Allgemeine Musikzeitung</tei:hi>.</tei:note> zugesagt.  Im Konzert<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">   [research report of concert in diary]</tei:note> gab es eine wundervolle Aufführung von Haydn B-dur und Coriolan mit kaum überbietbaren Steigerungen.  Nach dem Ravel Klavierkonzert wirkte übrigens “Don Juan” von Strauß [ <tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi> ] geradezu erlösend!</tei:p><tei:p>Nun habe ich im Konservatorium drei Vorträge gehalten (bei den ersten beiden war auch Herr van Hoboken<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> anwesend), schwach besucht, aber darüber rege ich mich nicht mehr auf.  Ich besprach im ersten Bach kleinen Präludium C, in den weiteren Grundriß der c-moll Fuge, Thema und Beantwortung der Es-dur und als Beispiel schlechter Beantwortung Reger d-moll.  Sonaten: Haydn D, Mozart F-dur.  In einem nächsten kommt dann noch op. 106 und 109 und Brahms A-dur 100.  In meinem Kurs ist das kleine Präludium F Nr. 6<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Probably BWV 927.  J included a discussion of this piece with voice-leading graphs in an appendix of his edition of Schenker’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmony</tei:hi> (Chicago, 1954), 349-352.</tei:note> zur Besprechung.</tei:p><tei:p>Einstein<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="einstein_alfred">Alfred Einstein</ref>.</tei:note> hat genau vor einem Jahr die Besprechung des III. Jahrbuches<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi> III (1930);  The only review of this by J that survives as a clipping in S’s scrapbook (OC 2/p.88) is „Schenker, Heinrich.  Das Meisterwerk in der Musik.  Ein Jahrbuch.  Band III,“ <tei:hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für Neue Musik</tei:hi>, November 1932.</tei:note> bestellt und angenommen, sie aber bis heute nicht gebracht, allerdings zwei andere kleine Sachen.  Vielleicht besinnt er sich doch.  Bei einem Vortrag, den ich in einer Privatgesellschaft gehalten habe, hat er sich auf meine Einladung hin wegen Zeitmangel entschuldigt.  Seine Kritiken werden übrigens immer unangenehmer (Sie passen sich eben dem Milieu B. Tageblatt<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Of which Einstein was music critic from 1927 to 1933.</tei:note> an!).  Ich bin ja neugierig, wie er sich auf eine baldige Einsendung von mir (“Choral und Harmonielehre”) benehmen wird.</tei:p><tei:p>Nun habe ich eine Anfrage und Bitte: Ich möchte Dr. Furtwängler für nächstes Jahr vorschlagen, den “Saul” mit der Bearbeitung Brahms’<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Brahms’s arrangement for performance of Handel’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Saul</tei:hi> is among the autograph materials in the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde in Vienna.  Schenker had transcribed and edited this document, which he subsequently gave to Furtwängler (see 5/18, 9) who in turn made it available to Jonas (see OJ 5/18, 21) for study and the writing of a commentary.  See also OJ 12/6 [18] and [20], and OJ 5/18 11, 19, 22, and 24.</tei:note> zu bringen und <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> möchte die dazu notwendige Arbeit übernehmen.  Glauben Sie, daß ich die Erlaubnis dazu von der Ges. f. [ <tei:hi rend="italic">recte</tei:hi> d.] Musikfreunde bekommen würde und halten Sie die Absicht überhaupt für durchführbar?  Existieren ausser der Orgelstimme auch ergänzende Instrumentalstimmen?  Sehr dankbar wäre ich Ihnen da für einen Fingerzeig in dieser Angelegenheit.</tei:p><tei:p>Nun möchte ich nur noch Ihnen und Ihrer werten Frau Gemahlin recht angenehme Feiertage wünschen und bin Ihr</tei:p><tei:p>dankbarst ergebener
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated March 24, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Berlin, March 24, 1932</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>My warmest thanks for your letter and the card,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> with which you have given me great pleasure.  Dr. Furtwängler<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> too was pleased with the essay, and at the last concert assured me of full support again with Schwers.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  At the concert<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> there was a wonderful performance of the Haydn B-flat major and <tei:hi rend="italic">Coriolanus</tei:hi> with practically unsurpassable intensifications.  After the Ravel Piano Concerto, incidentally, Strauss’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Don Juan</tei:hi> was an absolute relief!</tei:p><tei:p>I have given three lectures at the Conservatory (Mr. van Hoboken<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> was also present at the first two), poorly attended, but I no longer get upset about that.  In the first I discussed the Bach Small Prelude in C, in the later ones the basic outline of the C-minor fugue, theme and answer in the E-flat major, and as example of a poor answer the Reger D-minor.  Sonatas: Haydn D major, Mozart F major.  In a forthcoming lecture Opp. 106 and 109 and the Brahms A-major Op. 100 will come up.  In my course the small prelude in F, No. 6,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> is being discussed.</tei:p><tei:p>Einstein<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> commissioned and accepted the review of the third <tei:hi rend="italic">Yearbook</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> just a year ago, but still hasn’t published it, although he has published two other small pieces.  Perhaps he is reconsidering.  Regarding a lecture that I held in a private gathering he made excuses in declining my invitation, citing lack of time.  His critiques are, incidentally, ever more unpleasant (they fit perfectly the milieu of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Berliner Tageblatt</tei:hi>!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/>).  I am really curious how he will react to a forthcoming submission from me (“Chorale and Harmonic Theory”).</tei:p><tei:p>Now I have a query and a request: I would like to suggest to Dr. Furtwängler for next year to perform <tei:hi rend="italic">Saul</tei:hi> with Brahms’s arrangement,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> and <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> would like to undertake the work necessary to that purpose.  Do you think that I would get the necessary permission from the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde, and do you consider the project at all feasible?  Are there also supplementary instrumental parts other than the organ part?  I would be most grateful for a clue in this matter.</tei:p><tei:p>Now I would like to wish you and your good wife very pleasant holidays, and remain</tei:p><tei:p>Most gratefully devoted
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>