<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 12/6, [17] : 11-27-32 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain, reproduced with kind permission of the heirs of Jonas.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> Permission to publish on this website granted by the heirs of Oswald Jonas, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1932-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Oswald Jonas; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 11/27/1932 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated November 27, 1932</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-06-23</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>J has received a preliminary refusal from van Hoboken [over subscriptions for Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks ], and seeks S's advice;  reports contact with Furtwängler;  comments on lectures given by Webern.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Jonas, Oswald; Schenker, Heinrich;  Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks;  Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  subscriptions;  Weisse, Hans;  print-run;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Schwers, Paul;  Webern, Anton von;  Die Musik;  Bach, C. P. E.;  Droucker, Sandra;  Hüglauer, Frau;  Vrieslander, Otto</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated November 27, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>27. XI 32</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Vor einigen Tagen erhielt ich von Herrn v. Hoboken<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>. On this topic, see OJ 5/18, 13, 14, and 15, OJ 12/6, [38] and [16], September 7, 23, 24 and 25, October 1, 1932.</tei:note> einen Brief mit einer vorläufigen Absage.  Er schrieb daß er gehofft hatte, es würden wenigstens die Hälfte der notwendigen Exemplare subscribiert werden; „dann hätte ich weitere Hilfe überlegt, so aber nicht.  Also warten wir ab.” – Indessen sind wohl noch einige Bestellungen eingegangen (von Dr Weisse<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.</tei:note> und seinem Kreis vorläufig 7) – im ganzen sind es nun 72.  Ja, was nun!  Entschuldigen Sie bitte, daß ich Sie damit so belästige.  Meinen Sie, ob es besser wäre, an meinen Verleger heranzutreten mit der Frage, ob er es nicht doch versuchen möchte, von der vorgesetzten Anzahl herunterzugehen – wenn v. Hoboken die Hälfte der ursprünglichen, also 200 auf sich nähme und dies Hob. mitzuteilen.  Oder das ganze auf eine andere Basis stellen und Hob. nur ein Darlehen für die Druckkosten zu ersuchen, das ihm je nach Eingang zurückgezahlt wird?  Und dies dann meinem Verleger vorzuschlagen? Hoffentlich gelingt es doch, dieses Hindernis zu beseitigen. –<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  J inserts an emdash at this point, then continues writing without paragraph-break.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Neulich in der Probe und gestern im Konzert sprach ich mit Dr Furtwängler,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Wilhelm Furtwängler [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> der mir von <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> seinem Zusammensein mit Ihnen erzählte.  Leider ist er ja hier derart umlagert (auch sehr beschäftigt) sodaß noch immer nicht das Zusammentreffen zustandegekommen ist, nächste Woche aber sehr wahrscheinlich.  Ich möchte ihn bitten, mir Empfehlungen an die bei ihm spielenden Solisten zu geben, vielleicht ergibt sich da eine Möglichkeit zu Theoriestunden. –<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  J inserts an emdash at this point, then continues writing without paragraph-break.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Haben Sie die neueste Frechheit im letzten Musikheft gelesen über die Vorträge, die Webern<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Anton von Webern.  The lecture-cycle, given in the home of Dr Rudolph Kurzmann, was “Composition with Twelve Tones”; it was the first of two series of lectures given in 1932 and 1933, and later transcribed and published by W. Reich as <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Weg zur neuen Musik</tei:hi> (Vienna, 1960).</tei:note> in einem “Wiener Bürgerhaus” gehalten hat.  Meinen die Menschen das alles wirklich im Ernst, was sie schreiben – sind sie so dumm?  Ich habe eine Entgegnung an Schwers<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Paul Schwers, editor of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Allgemeine Musikzeitung</tei:hi>.</tei:note> gesandt.  Augenblicklich bereite ich einen Vortrag im Rundfunk über Ph. Em. Bach vor (mit Frau Droucker<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Sandra Droucker is found playing the Beethoven Piano Concerto No.4 with the Berlin Philharmonic in Oslo on March 27, 1913 (http://www.arbiterrecords.com/notes/140notes.html); three Debussy pieces in a concert on January 27, 1914, in Norway (http://www.hf.uio.no/imv/forskning/forskningsprosjekter/norgesmusikk/bulletin/1/oversikt.html); the Brahms Piano Concerto No.2 with Furtwängler in Hamburg on March 13, 1914 (http://www.furtwangler.net/doc/WF06-22.doc), where she is described as “the piano teacher of Emperor Wilhelm II's daughter”; she recorded the Chopin G major Nocture, Op.37 for Welte Mignon piano rolls (http://www.usc.edu/libraries/archives/arc/findingaids/welte/176WelteRolls.pdf); is described as “piano teacher” in an ÖNB database (http://ezines.onb.ac.at:8080/moravec/pub/schr/1581.htm);and was author of <tei:hi rend="italic">Et blad av Oslos musikkhistorie</tei:hi> (1945). </tei:note> und Frau Hüglauer, einer Gesangsschülerin von Vrieslander<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.</tei:note>)[.]</tei:p><tei:p>Nun will ich Sie nicht länger belästigen.  Ich hoffe Sie im Vollbesitz Ihrer Gesundheit und bitte Sie, mich Ihrer Frau Gemahlin zu empfehlen.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit ergebensten Grüßen</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ]Oswald Jonas</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated November 27, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>November 27, [19]32</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>A few days ago I received from Mr. van Hoboken<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> a letter of preliminary refusal.  He wrote that he had hoped at least half of the necessary copies would be subscribed;  “then I would have considered additional aid, but not under the circumstances.  So we will have to wait.” —Meanwhile several further orders have probably arrived (thus far seven from Dr. Weisse<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> and his circle)—in all they now number 72.  Well, what next!  Forgive me, please, that I so burden you with this.  Do you think it would be better to approach my publisher with the question of whether he might try to reduce the planned number—if van Hoboken would agree to half of the original one, thus 200, and communicate this to Hoboken?  Or to set the whole matter on a different basis and seek from Hob. only a loan for the printing costs, for which he would be reimbursed gradually as the payments come in?  And then suggest this to my publisher?  It is to be hoped that this obstacle can be surmounted.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/></tei:p><tei:p>Recently in rehearsal and yesterday at the concert I spoke with Dr. Furtwängler,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> who spoke of <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> a visit with you.  Unfortunately he is so beleaguered here (and also very busy), so that it has not yet been possible to arrange a meeting; but very probably next week.  I would like to ask him to recommend me to the soloists performing with him; perhaps there may be a possibility for theory lessons.—<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/></tei:p><tei:p>Have you read the most recent impertinence in the latest issue of <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Musik</tei:hi> about the lectures that Webern<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> presented at a “Viennese residence.”  Do people actually take seriously what they write—are they so stupid?  I have sent a rebuttal to Schwers.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>  At the moment I’m preparing a lecture on the radio on C. P. E. Bach (with Mrs. Droucker<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> and Mrs. Hüglauer, a singing pupil of Vrieslander’s<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/>).</tei:p><tei:p>Now I’ll trouble you no further.  I hope you are in perfect health and bid you convey my greetings to your wife.</tei:p><tei:p>With sincerest greetings,</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ]Oswald Jonas</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>