<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/22, [2] : 6-21-12 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Permission to publish being applied for.
© Transcription Ian Bent, 2007.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish is being sought.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1912-1934) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 06/21/1912 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde ~ HSchenker","KrausE ~ HSchenker","Marchet ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Typed letter from the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde to Schenker, dated June 21, 1912</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-06-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Announces plans to institute a regular program of lectures, and invites S to participate by offering a lecture of lecture series.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde;  Schenker, Heinrich;  lecture series;  Musikverein;  Grosser Saal;  Kleiner Saal;  Mandyczewski, Eusebius;  Marchet, Gustav;  Kraus, Ernst</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde (Marchet, Kraus) to Schenker, dated June 21, 1912</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">italic (in text) = spaced type (Sperrdruck) in original</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">crest:</tei:hi> K. K. GESELLSCHAFT DER MUSIKFREUNDE IN WIEN]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Euer Hochwohlgeboren,</tei:hi> [/] Hochverehrter Herr !<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Schenker reports the substance of this letter to Hertzka (UE) in WSLB 124, June 27, 1921 and WSLB 129, August 6, 1912.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Die k.k. Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde beabsichtigt von Beginn der Saison 1912–1913 an teils für ihre Mitglieder, teils für andere Interessenten aus den Kreisen des gebildeten Mittelstandes zur grösstmöglichen Verbreitung musikalischer Bildung in Laienkreisen <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">volkstümliche Vorträge</tei:hi></tei:hi> im Musikvereinsgebäude<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  The Musikvereinsgebäude, built by the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde on the Karlplatz, was opened in 1870 and contained a concert hall, known as the “Großer Saal” (large hall) or “Goldener Saal” (golden hall), and a smaller recital hall (known today as the “Brahmssaal”).</tei:note> zu veranstalten.</tei:p><tei:p>Es kommen dabei sämtliche musikalischen Fachgebiete in Betracht.  Allein auch Themen, welche das Wesen der Musik nur streifen und ihren Schwerpunkt in anderen Kulturbezirken haben, wie z.B.:  in ethnographischen, historischen, literarischen Gebieten, sollen hier zur Verbreitung gelangen.  Ein Hauptgewicht würde auf die <tei:hi rend="italic">musikalische Illustration</tei:hi>, von hervorragenden Künstlern und auf erstklassigen Instrumenten ausgeführt, gelegt werden.  Auch sollen zum Zweck plastischer Anschaulichkeit nach Wunsch und Bedarf <tei:hi rend="italic">Skioptikonbilder</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Skiopticon (Sciopticon): a type of magic lantern whereby images recorded on glass were projected on to a wall.  It was developed in the 1850s and came into more common use from the 1870s.  </tei:note> in den Rahmen dieser Vorträge eingeführt werden.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Diese Vorträge können an Samstagen oder Sonntagen nachmittags, ferner an Sonntagen vormittags und manchesmal abends im kleinen, in vereinzelten Fällen auch im grossen Musikvereinssaal stattfinden, alle anderen Wochennachmittage können im Bedarfsfalle ebenfalls in Betracht kommen;  überhaupt <tei:hi rend="italic">ausgeschlossen</tei:hi> is nur die Zeit vom 8. – 20. Feber.  Die Vorführungen sollen höchstens anderthalb Stunden dauern und können sich über jedes beliebige Gebiet erstrecken.</tei:p><tei:p>Ueber Vorschlag ihres Archivdirektors Professors Dr. Eusebius <tei:hi rend="italic">Mandyczewski</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="mandyczewski_eusebiu">Eusebius Mandyczewski</ref>.</tei:note> erlaubt sich die Direktion der k.k. Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde Euer Hochwohlgeboren einzuladen, Ihre Persönlichkeit in den Dienst des Unternehmens zu stellen und sich an diesen Vorträgen beteiligen zu wollen.  Wir bemerken dabei ausdrücklich, dass dieselben nicht nur als ein Ereignis unserer nächsten Saison, sondern als eine auch für die Zukunft feststehende Institution gedacht sind.</tei:p><tei:p>Die Auswahl des Stoffes, des Termins, der Anzahl der Vorträge (auch Zyklen von mehreren derselben, die etwa ein gleiches Thema behandeln, sind in diesem Rahmen willkommen) bleiben völlig Ihrem Belieben anheimgestellt;  die Gesellschaft wird es sich angelegen sein lassen, jedem Ihrer <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Wünsche in Bezug auf musikalische oder bildnerische Behelfe in weitgehendstem Sinne Rechnung zu tragen, und ersucht Sie, hochverehrter Herr, dem neuen Unternehmen, das des regsten Interesses in Fach- und Laienkreisen sicher sein darf, Ihre wertvolle künstlerische Mithilfe leihen zu wollen.</tei:p><tei:p>Die Zahl der in der nächsten Saison stattfindenden Vorträge kann natürlich heute noch nicht genau festgestellt werden, wir wollen aber nach Massgabe der einlaufenden Anmeldungen besondere Wünsche tunlichst berücksichtigen und bitten Euer Hochwohlgeboren uns gütigst mitzuteilen, ob wir schon im kommenden Jahre oder vielleicht erst später auf Sie rechnen dürfen, für welches Vortragsthema Sie sich entscheiden werden und welche Modalitäten sich an Ihr Kommen knüpfen würden.  Eine freundliche Antwortzeile wäre uns baldigst erwünscht, denn wir wollen die Einteilung für das kommende Jahr jetzt schon treffen und binnen Kurzem mit der Publikation der beabsichtigten Vortragsreihe herausrücken.  Wir bitten Euer Hochwohlgeboren daher, sich gütigst bis zum 15. Juli d.J. schriftlich äussern zu wollen.</tei:p><tei:p>In der angenehmen Erwartung eines freundlichen <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> hoffentlich zusagenden Bescheides zeichnen [/] mit dem Ausdrucke besonderer Wertschätzung für die Direktion der k.k. Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde</tei:p><tei:p>|Der Präsident:|Der Vize-Präsident:|
|[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Marchet<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Dr. Gustav Marchet (1846-1916), specialist in agriculture, Minister for Culture and Education 1906-08, from c. 1907 involved in preparations for the Conservatory of the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde to become a state institution, in 1912 appointed Honorary President of the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde (also member of the commission of the Denkmäler der Tonkunst in Österreich 1911-16).  </tei:note>|[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] D^r^ Kraus<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Ernst Kraus (1867-), pupil of Schoenberg 1910–11, Vice-President of the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde by 1912, and in that position also in 1935.   He wrote three letters to S under the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde letterhead: the present letter, and OJ 12/20, [1] (June 17, 1925)  and [2]  (January 15, 1935, joint with Friedrich Dlabač).  </tei:note>|</tei:p><tei:p>Wien, 21. Juni 1912.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde (Marchet, Kraus) to Schenker, dated June 21, 1912</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">italic (in text) = spaced type (Sperrdruck) in original</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">crest:</tei:hi> IMPERIAL-ROYAL SOCIETY FOR THE FRIENDS OF MUSIC IN VIENNA]</tei:p><tei:p>Most honored Sir,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>From the beginning of the 1912/13 season on, the Imperial-Royal Society for the Friends of Music plans, in part for its members, in part for other interested persons belonging to the educated bourgeoisie, to organize <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">popular lectures</tei:hi></tei:hi>, to be held in the Musikverein Building,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> for the widest possible propagation of musical education among amateur circles.</tei:p><tei:p>All the specialist fields of music are intended to be included within these.  Even subjects that are only tangential to the essence of music, and that have their centre of gravity in other cultural realms, as for example ethnographical, historical, [and] literary fields, shall be included.  Particular stress would be laid on <tei:hi rend="italic">musical illustration</tei:hi>, performed by prominent artists and on first-rate instruments.  In order to achieve maximum graphic effect, <tei:hi rend="italic">magic lantern images</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> shall be made available as required in the context of these lectures.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> These lectures may take place on Saturday or Sunday afternoons, also on Sunday mornings and sometimes evenings, in the small hall, in isolated cases even the large hall, of the Musikverein.  All other afternoons of the week are likewise possible as required;  Only the period February 8–20 is entirely <tei:hi rend="italic">ruled out</tei:hi>.  The presentations are to last at most one-and-a-half hours, and may range over any topic at will.</tei:p><tei:p>At the suggestion of its Archive Director Professor Eusebius <tei:hi rend="italic">Mandyczewski</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>, the administration of the Imperial-Royal Society for the Friends of Music takes the liberty of inviting you, most honored Sir, to place yourself at the service of the undertaking and to participate in these lectures.  We should expressly point out that these lectures are being thought of not merely as an event of our coming season but rather as a permanent institution for the future.</tei:p><tei:p>The choice of topic, the date, [and] the number of lectures (cycles of several lectures dealing with the same topic are welcome within this context) are left entirely to your discretion.  The Society will make it its business to meet your every <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> wish to the fullest extent  in respect of musical or visual support, and asks you, my very dear Sir, to lend your valued artistic assistance to the new undertaking, which will surely be of the keenest interest to professional and amateur circles.</tei:p><tei:p>The number of lectures to take place next season cannot of course at this stage yet be precisely ascertained.   However, we want in the light of incoming enrollments to allow as far as possible for special requests, and ask you, honored Sir, most kindly to inform us whether we could count on you for the coming year or perhaps only for later, on which lecture topic you will settle, and what provisos would attach to your involvement. We should be grateful for a line from you in response as soon as possible, for we wish to finalize the arrangements for the coming year at this time and to come out shortly with the publication of the planned lecture series.  We therefore ask you, honored Sir, most kindly to give us an answer by July 15.</tei:p><tei:p>In looking forward eagerly to what <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> we hope will be an affirmative response from you, we sign, in expressing our special esteem, on behalf of the administration of the Imperial-Royal Society for the Friends of Music</tei:p><tei:p>|the President:|the Vice-President:|
|[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Marchet<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>|[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] D^r^ Kraus<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/>|</tei:p><tei:p>Vienna, June 21, 1912.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>