<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:Sbb 55 Nachl 13, [2] : 7-3-27 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Wilhelm Furtwängler, published with kind permission.
© Transcription Christoph Hust, 2008.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2008.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Christoph Hust, 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Furtwängler, Wilhelm (1927-19??) - -Staatsbibliothek, Berlin (19??-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: in the public domain;  Image: Staatsbibliothek, Berlin; Transcription, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Christoph Hust;  Translation Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 07/03/1927 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: &quot;Furtw&#195;&#164;ngler ~ H+JSchenker&quot;,&quot;Furtw&#195;&#164;ngler ~ HSchenker&quot; --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Furtwängler, dated July 3, 1927</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-03-10</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>With his new title, Schenker says, Furtwängler has surpassed the rank of Professor.   - -He draws Furtwängler's attention to Oppel's Mass.   - -He tells Furtwängler of van Hoboken's forthcoming visit, and tells him about Hoboken's valuable work.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich; Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Professor;  Oppel, Reinhard;  Kiel;  Leipzig;  Mass;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  library;  Erstdrucken;  first editions;  foundation;  manuscripts</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Galtür</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Furtwängler, dated July 3, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">names written in F's hand:</tei:hi>]  Curt.  [-]  Straube  [-]  Bt.
[<tei:hi rend="italic">typed:</tei:hi>] Heinrich Schenker</tei:p><tei:p>Verehrtester Herr D^r^ Furtwängler!</tei:p><tei:p>Vor nicht langer Zeit las ich in einem Berliner Blatt,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  No article of this description is preserved in Schenker's scrapbook (OC 2).  Schenker's record of this letter in his diary for July 3, 1927 (OC 3/9, p. 3084) reads:  "To Furtwängler (letter): I recommend Oppel's Mass, announce Hoboken:  I present him as a collector of first editions, as an institutor of manuscript photographic copies, and as my pupil" [An Furtwängler (Br.): empfehle die Messe von Oppel, kündige Hoboken an:  stelle ihn als Sammler vor von Erstdrucken, als Stifter der Handschriften-Nachbilder und als meinen Schüler].  </tei:note> daß sonderbarerweise gerade Sie den vielverliehenen Professor-Titel noch nicht führen. Nun haben Sie mit dem jüngsten Titel den „Professor", wie ich glaube, überholt,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> In 1927, Furtwängler was installed as conductor of the Vienna Philharmonic Orchestra, but perhaps Schenker had already heard that he was to become Generalmusikdirektor in Berlin in 1928, too.</tei:note> u. nun - was werden die Leute mit Ihnen anfangen? Weiter geht es ja nicht im Bereiche menschlicher Auszeichnungen . . .<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> Last three lines of this paragraph sidelined in right margin.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Zweck dieser Zeilen ist aber nicht, über die Unvollkommenheiten in der Technik der Auszeichnungen zu klagen, sondern Sie auf eine 4-stimmige Messe im alten Stil von Prof. <tei:hi rend="italic">Oppel</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="oppel_reinhard">Reinhard Oppel</ref>.   <tei:hi rend="italic">Messe für Vierstimmigen Chor</tei:hi>, Op 32, SATB a cappella (1926).</tei:note> (<tei:hi rend="italic">Kiel</tei:hi>, nun <tei:hi rend="italic">in <tei:hi rend="italic">Leipzig</tei:hi></tei:hi> wenn ich nicht irre) aufmerksam zu machen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Cf. Furtwängler's letter to Schenker of July 18, 1927: OJ 11/16, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="galtur">Galtür</ref>.  </tei:note>.  </tei:note>  Sollte H. Oppel Ihnen dieses Werk einschicken, so werfen Sie einen Blick darauf, das Werk wird es Ihnen lohnen. Prof. <tei:hi rend="italic">Opp</tei:hi>. versprach mich[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>], hier in <tei:hi rend="italic">Galtür</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="galtur">Galtür</ref>.  </tei:note> <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> zu besuchen, ein höchst charaktervoller Künstler u. Mensch.</tei:p><tei:p>Außerdem kündige ich Ihnen bei dieser Gelegenheit den Besuch des H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Anthony van Hoboken</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>. </tei:note> an, der in <tei:hi rend="italic">Sils-Maria</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="sils_maria">Sils Maria</ref>.  This was Hoboken's summer address that year: see letter from Schenker to Hoboken,  OJ 89/1, [1], July 3, 1927.  </tei:note> Platz nimmt. Trotz glänzendem Reichtum ein famoser Musiker mit Leib u. Seele - ich betreue ihn eben deshalb sehr gerne - hat er nicht nur das Verdienst eine allererstrangige Sammlung von <tei:hi rend="italic">Erstdrucken</tei:hi> geschaffen zu haben, sondern auch das historische Verdienst erworben einer <tei:hi rend="italic">Stiftung</tei:hi>, in der alle, alle <tei:hi rend="italic">Handschriften</tei:hi> der Großen in photographischen Abnahmen gesammelt werden,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="photogrammarchiv">Photogrammarchiv</ref>.  </tei:note> wodurch viele gerettet u. fast alle zur Feststellung einer richtigen Textvorlage benutzt werden können. Wenn Sie im Herbst oder Winter bei uns sind, sollten Sie H. <tei:hi rend="italic">v. Hobokens</tei:hi> Bibliothek einmal sehen - er wird Sie gewiß einladen -, dann komme auch ich hin u. <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> wir plauschen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  <tei:hi rend="italic">plauschen</tei:hi>:  Austrian dialect word for <tei:hi rend="italic">plaudern</tei:hi>.  </tei:note> in dem kunstgemütlichen Hause vielleicht so manches vergnügliche oder nützliche Wort.</tei:p><tei:p>Von mir u. meiner Frau<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Click on <ref cRef="schenker_jeanette">Jeanette Schenker</ref>. </tei:note> allerbeste Empfehlungen an Sie u. an Ihre Frau Gemalin</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Galtür,  3. Juli</tei:hi> 27
<tei:hi rend="italic">Tirol</tei:hi></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Furtwängler, dated July 3, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">names written in F's hand:</tei:hi>]  Curt[ius].  [-]  Straube  [-]  B[ee]t[hoven].
[<tei:hi rend="italic">typed:</tei:hi>] Heinrich Schenker</tei:p><tei:p>Most honored Dr. Furtwängler,</tei:p><tei:p>Not long ago, I read in a Berlin newspaper,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> that you, of all people, inexplicably, still did not hold the oft bestowed title of Professor.  Now, with your most recent title you have, in my opinion, surpassed that of Professor,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> and now--what will people do with you next?  There is no further to go in the realm of human distinctions . . .<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/></tei:p><tei:p>The purpose of these few lines is, however, not to lament the shortcomings of the system of awarding distinctions, but to draw to your attention a four-voice Mass in the olden style by Professor Oppel<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> (Kiel, now <tei:hi rend="italic">in Leipzig</tei:hi> if I am not mistaken).<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  If Mr. Oppel were to send you this work and you were to cast an eye over it, you would find the work rewarding.  Professor Oppel promised <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> to visit me here in Galtür<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/>--[he is] an artist and person of great character.</tei:p><tei:p>In addition, I should like to take this opportunity of apprising you of the visit of Mr. Anthony van Hoboken,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> who is staying in Sils-Maria.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/>  Despite his glittering wealth, [he is] heart and soul a splendid musician--for just that reason, I am very happy to give him my assistance--not only has he the merit of having created an utterly first-class collection of <tei:hi rend="italic">first editions</tei:hi>, but also history is greatly indebted to him for a <tei:hi rend="italic">foundation</tei:hi>, in which are being assembled absolutely all the <tei:hi rend="italic">manuscripts</tei:hi> of the great [composers] in photographic reproductions,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> by means of which many will be rescued, and almost all will be able to be used for establishing an accurate model text.  If you are going to be with us in the Fall or Winter, you ought to see Mr. van Hoboken's library some time--he will certainly invite you--, and then I will come along as well, and <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> we can perhaps have a good chinwag<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> about many delightful and useful matters in his artistically congenial house.</tei:p><tei:p>All the best to you and your wife from me and my wife,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/></tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  H. Schenker</tei:p><tei:p>Galtür,  July 3, 1927
Tyrol</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>