<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:Sbb 55 Nachl. 13, [1] : 4-19-30 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription Christoph Hust, 2006.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Christoph Hust &amp; Ian Bent 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Breitkopf &amp; Härtel (1930)—Straube, Karl (1930-19??)—Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin (19??-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: Special Staatsbibliothek zu Berlin; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Christoph Hust &amp; Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 04/19/1930 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: &quot;Breitkopf+H&#195;&#164;rtel ~ HSchenker&quot;,&quot;Hase ~ HSchenker&quot;,&quot;Straube ~ HSchenker&quot; --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Hellmuth von Hase (Breitkopf &amp; Härtel), evidently forwarded to Karl Straube, dated April 19, 1930</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-03-28</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>[ Meisterwerk III:] Refers to Peters Verlag's earlier invitation (1913) to edit ten selected Beethoven piano sonatas, and points now to his complete edition of the Beethoven sonatas.  Previous honoraria from UE prove his willingness to make sacrifices.  Offers B&amp;H "the book" [presumably Meisterwerk III ] gratis on condition of speedy publication.  Requests permission to write to Karl Straube direct.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Breitkopf &amp; Härtel;  Hase, Hellmuth von;  Straube, Karl;  Peters Verlag;  UE;  Beethoven sonatas;  Erläuterungsausgabe;  Die Neunte Sinfonie Beethovens;  Beethoven's Ninth Symphony;  honoraria;  German musicians;  Rameau;  Freie Satz, Der;  Free Composition;  Kunst des Vortrags, Die;  Art of Performance, The;  Eroica;  Hertzka, Emil;  Meisterwerk in der Musik, Der;  Masterwork in Music, The</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Hellmuth von Hase (Breitkopf &amp; Härtel), evidently forwarded to Karl Straube, dated April 19, 1930</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[Wien], 19. 4. 30</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Herr Doctor!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  This letter was evidently forwarded on to Straube from Breitkopf &amp; Härtel.  The original addressee must have been the proprietor and managing director of the firm at that time, Dr.( Juris) Hellmuth von Hase.  Around this time, Straube had edited several works for B&amp;H, including Heinrich Schütz’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Deutsches Magnificat</tei:hi> and Handel’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Solomon</tei:hi>, and he was also editor of the Neue Bach Gesellschaft, the volumes of which B&amp;H published. (Email communication from Matthias Otto, Archivist, B&amp;H, January 24, 2007) </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Vielen, herzlichsten Dank für Ihre Güte u. Mühe!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Unknown communication.</tei:note> Zuerst eine Aufklärung über <tei:hi rend="italic">Peters</tei:hi>.  Dieser Verlag erbat von mir vor Jahren eine Ausgabe von ausgewählten 10 Klaviersonaten <tei:hi rend="italic">Beeth</tei:hi>'s u. schrieb mir hierfür von vornherein vor: „in der Art von <tei:hi rend="italic">Straube</tei:hi>“.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="straube_karl">Karl Straube</ref>.   OJ 13/17, [3], September 10, 1913, Peters to Schenker: “ In this, the main thing for me would be to find an editor who on the one hand can bring to the edition a command of the pedagogical requirements of the practice, and on the other hand has something individual to say about Beethoven and his works, in the way that Straube in his new edition of Bach organ works does about Bach.”  (Hierbei wäre die Hauptsache für mich einen Herausgeber zu finden, der einerseits für die Revision die pädagogischen Anforderungen der Praxis beherrscht und andererseits über Beethoven und seine Werke etwas Eigenes zu sagen hat, in dem Sinne wie Straube in seiner neuen Ausgabe von Bach-Orgelwerke über Bach.)</tei:note>  Ich erwiderte, daß ich auf die +Handschriften zurückgehen+ -müsste- u. danach die Ausgabe des Verlages von +Grund aus neu+ machen müsste, daß ich dann auch lieber eine Gesammtausgabe durchführen wollte, daß die Einsammlung der Vorlagen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Vorlagen</tei:hi> : presumably S means “sources“ in general, here, rather than the technical term <tei:hi rend="italic">Stichvorlage</tei:hi>, i.e. the document from which the engraver worked.</tei:note> Zeit u. Geld fordern würde u. s. w.</tei:p><tei:p>Heute, da ich die G. A. nun wirklich ausgeführt habe,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  <tei:hi rend="italic">L. van Beethoven: Klaviersonaten, nach den Autographen und Erstdrucken rekonstruiert</tei:hi>, 4 vols (Vienna: UE, 1921–23).  </tei:note> mag ja <tei:hi rend="italic">Peters</tei:hi> sehen, wie +verschieden+ wir über die Frage urteilten! Das Honorar, das ich ansetzte, war das gleiche, <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> das in den Verhandlungen mit Hertzka<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Emil Hertzka: Director of UK 1907–32.</tei:note> zur Grundlage diente, das zuletzt freilich in Tantièmen geändert worden ist.  Aus jenem Grundmißverständnis hat also P., wie ich Prof. Straube's Brief entnehme,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Letter received by Schenker on April 18, 1930 (diary, OJ 4/3, p. 3468) stating that it was "almost out of the question that Breitkopf &amp; Härtel can take over the publication [<tei:hi rend="italic">Meisterwerk III</tei:hi>]" but that he would try.</tei:note> noch immer die Erinnerung an angeblich hohe Forderungen zurückbehalten, dazu kommt, daß P. damals sehr fest beleidigt war darüber, daß ich +seine+ Ausgabe für unrichtig erklärte.  Nein, nein, für die „IX“ Sinf.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie: eine Darstellung des musikalischen Inhaltes under fortlaufender Berücksichtigung auch des Vortrages und der Literatur</tei:hi> (Vienna: UE, 1912).  Honorarium:  OC 52/431, November 6, 1910, contract: „Für die Abtretung meines Urheberrechtes erhalte ich K 1000.– eintausend Kronen ...“ (In return for the assignment of my copyright I receive 1,000.– (one thousand) Kroner ...)</tei:note> erhielt ich 1000 Kr., für die Monographien op 109, 110, 101, 111 je 600 Kr,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Die letzten Fünf Sonaten von Beethoven: kritische Ausgabe mit Einführung und Erläuterung</tei:hi> (Vienna: UE), <tei:hi rend="italic">Op. 109</tei:hi> (1913), <tei:hi rend="italic">Op. 110</tei:hi> (1914), <tei:hi rend="italic">Op. 111</tei:hi> (1915), <tei:hi rend="italic">Op. 101</tei:hi> (1920).  Honorarium: OC 52/494, August 25, 1912, §II: „... ein Honorar von je K 1200.- für jede Sonate, die Hälfte d.i. K 600.- bei Inangriffnahme der Sonate und der Rest von K 600.- bei Ablieferung der letzten Korrektur-Abzüge zahlbar.“ (... an honorarium of 1,200 Kroner for each sonata, payable half, i.e. 600 Kroner, upon starting work on the sonata and the balance of 600 Kroner upon delivery of the final corrected proofs.)—as can be seen, Schenker understates the latter honorarium by 50%.</tei:note> sind das Honorare überhaupt??  Das würde kaum für die schriftlichen Kopistenarbeiten ausgereicht haben, zumal ich z. B. zur Gesamtausgabe u. den Monographien alle Vorlagen mit eigenem Gelde besorgt habe. Nein, nein, ich glaube, es findet sich nicht so bald Einer, der unter solchen Opfern wie ich sein Lebenswerk vollführt!</tei:p><tei:p>Hier wieder ein Beweis:  Ich bin bereit, das <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Buch +ohne Honorar+ zu überlassen, so sehr halte ich es für +höchste Zeit+, den +deutschen+ Musikern die Frage: „<tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Rameau</tei:hi></tei:hi> – oder <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven</tei:hi></tei:hi>? Erstarrung – oder Leben in der Musik“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Approximate title of the lead article (“Rameau oder Beethoven?  Erstarrung oder geistiges Leben in der Musik? (Rameau or Beethoven?  Creeping Paralysis or Spiritual Potency in Music?) in <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, vol. III (Munich: Drei Masken Verlag, 1930), pp. 11–24 (Eng. trans., vol. III, pp. 1–9), of which Schenker was probably handling the proofs at this time.  By “Buch” (book), S presumably therefore means <tei:hi rend="italic">Meisterwerk III</tei:hi> —relationships with Drei Masken Verlag may perhaps have been difficult at this point, and S casting about for an alternative publisher.  </tei:note> zur Entscheidung vorzulegen. Alle meine schwere Mühe schenke ich, nur für Eines müsste <tei:hi rend="italic">Br &amp; H.</tei:hi> gutstehen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  “gutstehen”: archaic for “gutsagen.”</tei:note> daß die Herausgabe unter <tei:hi rend="italic">keinen Vorwand verzögert werde</tei:hi>!  Ich habe vor mir den „freien Satz“,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue Musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:hi>, vol. III <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi> (Vienna: UE, 1935)</tei:note> die „Kunst des Vortrags“,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Kunst des Vortrags</tei:hi>, written in the Summer of 1911: diary entry, OJ 1/10, p. 135[b], July 1, 1911: „Inangriffnahme der Schrift: “Kunst des Vortrags.” (Started on the writing ‚The Art of Performance.’);  see also WSLB 78, July 23, 1911.  The work remained unfinished and unpublished in Schenker’s lifetime and survives as OJ 18/10, 19/6, 21/7–21, and 33/4, and  in compilation by Oswald Jonas as 57/2–5, comprising twelve chapters, taken down from dictation by Jeannette Kornfeld (later Schenker).  The work has been released in an edition that draws on later sources and omits some of the 1911 material, as <tei:hi rend="italic">The Art of Performance</tei:hi>, ed. Herribert Esser, Eng. trans. Irene Schreier Scott (New York: Oxford University Press, 2000).  See the review of this edition by David Gagné and Hedi Siegel, <tei:hi rend="italic">Music Theory Spectrum</tei:hi> 24 (2002), 135–41.  It is extraordinary that Schenker should still represent this as on-going nineteen years later!</tei:note> habe Schüler, also muß zumindest die „<tei:hi rend="italic">Eroica</tei:hi>“ fort,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  i.e. the analytical article “Beethovens Dritte Sinfonie zum erstenmal in ihrem wahren Inhalt dargestellt“ (Beethoven’s Third Symphony: its true content described for the first time) in <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi> (Munich: Drei Masken Verlag, 1930), pp. 29–101 and Urlinietafeln (Eng. trans., vol. III, pp. 10–115), the first three movements of which Schenker sent to the engraver Georg Tomay on July 24 and the fourth movement on July 26, 1930 (OC 54/203 and 204).  </tei:note> damit die Korrekturen beendet sind, ehe ich die letzten Arbeiten verrichte.  Nur +dieses Eine+ würde ich erbitten!  Schon Cotta<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15">  J. G. Cotta’sche Buchhandlung Nachfolger, Stuttgart, publisher of <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:hi>, I <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (1906), II/1 <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt I</tei:hi> (1910).  </tei:note> schrieb mir einmal, inmitten der Drucklegung (!), mein Werk sei ja zeitlos, folglich komme es auf dieses oder jenes Datum weniger an, als bei Werken vom Tage, desgleichen wartete mir Hertzka öfter mit „Ewigkeitswerken“ <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> auf, deren Herausgabe nicht so peinlich genau einzuhalten nötig wäre u. dgl.  Das muß diesmal aber vermieden werden, weil mein Sehvermögen sehr geschwächt ist, ich daher nicht Alles auf einmal bewältigen könnte.</tei:p><tei:p>Verzeihen Sie, verehrtester Herr Doctor, daß ich Ihnen eine so ausführliche Beichte schreibe.  Am liebsten würde ich Ihnen dadurch alle Mühe abnehmen, daß ich an Prof. <tei:hi rend="italic">Straube</tei:hi>, dem ich für seine Freundlichkeit herzlichst danke, selbst schreibe u. ihn frage, ob <tei:hi rend="italic">Br &amp; H.</tei:hi> zumindest die <tei:hi rend="italic">prompte Herausgabe auf sich nehmen wollten</tei:hi>?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn16">  [to which proposed edition is he referring?]</tei:note>  Ich würde mich der Verbindung sehr, sehr freuen, weil ich noch Pläne[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] für kleinere Arbeiten zum +Schulgebrauch+ habe, an denen schon Hertzka regsten Anteil nahm.  Darf ich Sie, den Vielgeplagten, entlassen u. an Prof. <tei:hi rend="italic">Straube</tei:hi> schreiben, oder genügt dieser Brief?  Und wie erfahre ich <tei:hi rend="italic">Br-H</tei:hi>'s Entscheidung? Vielen, vielen Dank, u. beste Ostergrüße!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn17">  Easter Sunday was April 20 in 1930.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ihr herzlichst ergeb.
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] <tei:hi rend="italic">H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Hellmuth von Hase (Breitkopf &amp; Härtel), evidently forwarded to Karl Straube, dated April 19, 1930</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>April 19, 1930</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Many and most cordial thanks for your kindness and the trouble you have gone to!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  First, some clarification regarding Peters.  The latter publishing house asked me years ago for an edition of ten selected piano sonatas of Beethoven, and stipulated for this from the outset [that it be] “in the manner of Straube.”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  I responded that I would have to +go back to the manscripts+ and, in accordance with them, make the publishing house’s edition +new from the ground up+, that I would then in fact prefer to carry it through as a complete edition, that the assembling of the copies<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> would demand time and money, etc.</tei:p><tei:p>Today, now that I have actually carried the complete edition through,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  Peters may see just how +differently+ we judge the question!  The honorarium that I quoted was that <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> which served as a basis for dealings with Hertzka,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> which was admittedly in the end changed to royalties.  Thus, from this basic misunderstanding, Peters, as I perceive from Prof. Straube’s letter,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> are still harboring the memory of allegedly high demands, and that is the reason why Peters were at that time greatly offended that I declared +their+ edition to be incorrect.  No, No.  For the <tei:hi rend="italic">Ninth Symphony</tei:hi> I received 1,000 Kroner,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> for the monographs on Opp. 109, 110, 101, [and] 111 each 600 Kroner.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/>  Are those honoraria at all?  That would hardly have sufficed to pay the work of copying by hand, particularly as for the complete edition and the monographs, for example, I took care of all the copies out of my own money.  No, no;  it is not, I think, so easy to find someone who accomplishes his life’s work, as I have, with such sacrifices!</tei:p><tei:p>Here is further proof:  I am willing <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> to hand over the book +for no honorarium+, so strongly do I feel that it is +high time+ to place before +German+ musicians the question “<tei:hi rend="italic">Rameau</tei:hi> or <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven</tei:hi>?  Creeping Paralysis or Potency in Music?“<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> for them to decide.  I will make a present of all my burdensome troubles;  Breitkopf &amp; Härtel would have only to be answerable for<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> one thing: that the edition not be +delayed+ on <tei:hi rend="italic">any pretext</tei:hi>!  I still have to finish <tei:hi rend="italic">Free Composition</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> [and] the „Art of Composition,“<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> I have pupils [to teach], thus must at least get ahead with the <tei:hi rend="italic">Eroica</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/> so that the proofs are out of the way before I tackle my last works.  I would ask only <tei:hi rend="italic">this one thing!</tei:hi>  Cotta<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn15"/> wrote me once in the midst of printing (!) that my work was in fact timeless, therefore it was less a matter of this or that date than of ephemeral works;  similarly Hertzka frequently offered my “eternal works,” <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> to whose publication date it was not necessary to adhere so terribly precisely, and so forth.  That must be avoided this time:  because my visual faculty is very much weakened, I could not accomplish everything all at the same time.</tei:p><tei:p>Forgive me, most honored Doctor, for writing you so lengthy a confession.  I would much prefer to spare you all the trouble by writing myself to Professor Straube, to whom I am most heartily grateful for his kindness, and ask him whether Breitkopf &amp; Härtel would at least +like to+ take on the <tei:hi rend="italic">prompt publication</tei:hi>?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn16"/>  I should rejoice very greatly at the association because I still have plans for shorter works for +educational use+, in which Hertzka has already taken a lively interest.  May I discharge you, the heavily-afflicted one, and write to Professor Straube, or is this letter sufficient?  And how shall I learn of Breitkopf &amp; Härtel’s decision?  Many, many thanks, and best greetings for Easter!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn17"/></tei:p><tei:p>Yours most sincerely,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H. Schenker</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>