<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 15/16, [28] : 12-7-16 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Hans Weisse, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2008.
© Translation Alison Hiley, 2008
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish granted by the heirs of Hans Weisse.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1916-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Hans Weisse; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin;  Translation: Alison Hiley</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 12/07/1916 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Weisse ~ H+JSchenker","Weisse ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated December 7, 1916</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-07-02</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Weisse writes of his spiritual emptiness, and looks forward to his forthcoming holiday from military service, when he can be with Schenker once again.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Weisse, Hans;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Brahms-Studien;  Brahms Studies;  war;  Gutherz, Frau</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated December 7, 1916</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Lieber Meister!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Receipt of this letter appears not to be recorded in Schenker's diary.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Wenn ich von Ihrer Aufforderung[,] nicht zu viel zu schreiben, gefolgt habe, so geschah es hauptsächlich aus der tiefen Depression[,] die ich über mein tatsächliches Nichtstuerdasein empfinde und die mich am liebsten all jene Fäden an meine geistige Vergangenheit zerreißen ließe, deren Erinnerung allein mich mit trüben und unerquicklichen Vorstellungen quält!  Dass es eine Zeit gegeben hat, in der, Geist und Herz, nicht unter fremden Joche zu stehen gezwungen waren, mag wohl nur<tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> für jene eine schmerzlich-bedeutsame Tatsache sein, die, früher gewohnt, alle Freiheiten des Geistes und der Seele zu geniessen, sich[?] und ihr Dasein nun in die engsten Grenzen gebannt [<tei:hi rend="italic">word deleted</tei:hi>] fühlen!  Wie lämend [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] es auch zu sehen mag – es ist doch alles jeglichen Inhaltes bar – !</tei:p><tei:p>So sehe ich denn mit Freuden jenen am 14. oder 15. Dezember beginnenden Tagen meines Urlaubs entgegen, die mir doch jene Güter und Wirkungskreise wiedergeben sollen, die tatsächlich verschüttet wurden!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich freue mich unendlich[,] Sie zu sehen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Weisse visited Schenker on December 16, 1916 at 10:30 a.m., during Miss Kahn's lesson: OJ 2/4, p. 544.    </tei:note> und habe [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] Ihnen sehr, sehr, viel Interessantes und Sie Interessierendes zu erzählen!</tei:p><tei:p>Was die in Verlust geratene Seite von Brahms <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Studienblättern<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Possibly Brahms’s handwritten compilation of consecutive fifths and octaves, which UE published under Schenker’s editorship in 1933 to mark the centennial of Brahms’s birth. </tei:note> anbelangt, ist es das Beste[,] Frau Gutherz<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Frau Gutherz: [create profile and link].</tei:note> läßt die fehlende Seite nochmals photographieren.  Sie dürfte sich deshalb noch mit Ihnen in Verbindung setzen.</tei:p><tei:p>Bis zum 15. also!  Und dann hoffe ich[,] Sie recht häufig zu sehen und von Ihnen[,] verehrter Meister, so viel Nahrung in meinen geistigen Proviantsack mitzubekommen, daß ich wieder getrost bis zum Ende dieses Krieges ausharren kann.</tei:p><tei:p>Ihnen und der lieben gnädigen – alles Herzliche von Ihrem alten getreuen</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hans.
7/XII 16.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated December 7, 1916</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear master,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>If I have risen to your challenge not to write too much, it has been mainly as a result of the deep depression that I am experiencing on account of my very real inactivity, which is trying its best to tear apart all those threads which connect to my intellectual past, the very memory of which torments me with troubled and unedifying ideas!  That there was once a time in which hearts and minds were not forced to submit to a foreign yoke may well only <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> be a painfully significant fact for those who were formerly accustomed to enjoy all the freedoms of mind and soul, but now feel themselves and their [very] existence banished to close confines [<tei:hi rend="italic">word deleted</tei:hi>]! However crippling this may seem—it has no substance whatsoever!</tei:p><tei:p>I thus view with delight my days of leave, due to start on the December 14 or 15;  they will surely restore that intellectual wealth and sphere of activity which have been truly buried!</tei:p><tei:p>I am looking forward immensely to seeing you<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> and have a very great deal to tell you which I know will be of interest!</tei:p><tei:p>As regards the page of Brahms’ <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Studies<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> which has gone missing, it is best for Frau Gutherz<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> to photograph it once more.  She should get in touch with you in that regard.</tei:p><tei:p>Until the 15th, then!  And then I hope to see you frequently and, honoured master, to absorb so much intellectual nourishment into my haversack that I shall be able to return comforted [to the field] and hold out until the end of this War.</tei:p><tei:p>Cordial greetings to you and your dear lady from your old and true friend</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hans.
December 7, 1916</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>