<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 15/16, [19] : 8-12-13 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Under inquiry.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2007.
© Translation  Alison Hiley 2008
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish is being sought.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1913-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Hans Weisse; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 08/12/1913 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Weisse ~ H+JSchenker","Weisse ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated August 12, 1913</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-02-03</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>On Schenker's advice, Weisse has been taking walks to gain composure in order to tackle difficult compositional problems; in the Fall, he will bring the draft of the newly composed first movement of his String Quintet for Schenker's guidance; he expects to finish laying out the Scherzo and Trio, but now has doubts about the Adagio, and contemplates replacing it. He sets out his travel plans prior to returning to Vienna. 

</dc:description><dc:subject>Weisse, Hans;  Schenker, Heinrich;  string quintet;  instrumentation;  Scherzo;  Trio;  Adagio;  Nürnberg;  Nuremberg;  Weimar;  Jena;  Leipzig;  Breslau;  Dahms, Walter;  review</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated August 12, 1913</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Liebster, verehrter Meister!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker’s diary for August 14, 1913 (OJ 1/13, p. 401).  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Sie wundern sich wohl über mein langes Stillschweigen und denken dabei an weiss Gott wie viel neu entstehende opera!  Dennoch aber befolge ich den zweiten Rat Ihres letzten so lieben Briefes[,]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Presumably the letter, which is not known to survive, that is recorded in Schenker’s diary as dispatched on July 9, 1913 (OJ 1/12, p. 379).  </tei:note> nämlich viel spazieren zu gehen[,] mehr als den die Arbeit betreffenden.  Ich habe nun 2 Wochen vollständig pausiert und will erst nächste Woche wieder fest dazuschauen.  Die Arbeit habe ich aber[,] und dies ist meiner Meinung nach das Beste[,] was geschehen könnte, gründlich kennengelernt[,] weil ich zur Einsicht gelangt bin, dass da endgül- <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> tigen Ziele und Resultate nicht im Handumdrehen gefasst und erreicht werden können.  Zum scheinbar leichtesten Gesellen [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte:</tei:hi> Leichtesten gesellen] sich die gleiche Ausdauer wie zu mühseligen Augenblicken:  Um diese Erfahrung reicher komme ich hin[,][?] begieriger als zuvor, genauer, consequenter als zuvor zu Ihnen zurück und freue mich aller kommenden geistigen Nahrung!  Den ersten Satz[,] der ganz neu componiert<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Weisse was working on a String Quintet, of which he was dissatisfied with the first movement.</tei:note> wird[,] wie auch den letzten hoffe ich in der Skizze fertig mitzubringen:  Unter ihrer [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte:</tei:hi> Ihrer] Aufsicht möchte ich im Herbste erst die Instrumentierung besorgen, weil damit das lästige Umarbeiten wegfällt, und zugleich auch viele Erfahrungen gewissermassen a priori gemacht werden können.  Das einzige Scherzo und Trio[,] das ich so gut noch wie voriges Jahr finde[,] soll ganz zu Ende geändert werden!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Meine Sorge aber bildet das Adagio:  Wieso ich mich im Vorjahre dazu hinreissen lassen konnte es gut, zu finden – einzig und allein, weil es nicht unmelodisch war?!  Wie in den Wüst, die Verlegenheit, die Unbeholfenheit der Synthese Licht und Geist bringen?  Schon der erste Gedanke mit seiner unglücklich – ungeheuer&lt;strike&gt;n&lt;/strike&gt;^lich^ angelegten[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] Liedform verursacht mir Schmerzen und Bitternisse!  Der zweite Gedanke, der mir melodisch gefällt[,] bedürfte eines besser passenden Vordersatzes!  Ob es doch nicht besser wäre[,] diesen Satz als Materielager für weitere Compositionen zu benützen und mit der Arbeit eines neuen Adagios zu beginnen?  Ich harre Ihrer Entschlüsse, ihrer Ratschläge:  nur habe ich das Eilen und Schnellmachenwollen über den Sommer verlernt und werde mich nicht genieren[,] nur das oberwähnte gut, statt einer fix und fertig gedrechselten aber schlechten Quintetts zu bringen!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Meine Pläne sind:  bis 15. September in diesem Neste, das ich heuer trotz schlechten Wetters von neuen lieb gewann zu bleiben und dan bis Ende eine Reise durch Deutschland zu unternehmen:  Nürnberg – Würzburg – Heidelberg – Frankfurt – Eisenach – Gota – Erfurt – Weimar – Jena – Leipzig – Breslau!  Etwaige Besorgungen würde ich mit grosser Freude von Ihnen entgegennehmen – und soweit’s in meiner Macht liegt ausführen!  Die Dahms’ Kritik<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="dahms_walter">Walter Dahms</ref>. Weisse refers to “Musikalische Arbeitungen,” signed “Ds,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue Preussische Kreuz-Zeitung</tei:hi> July 15, 1913 [review of Schenker’s edition of J. S. Bach’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Chromatic Fantasy &amp; Fugue</tei:hi>], a clipping of which is preserved in Schenker’s scrapbook, OC 2/p. 37.  </tei:note> fand ich flach und oberflächlich!  Derlei Dinge sind nicht für unsereines geschrieben!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich grüsse Sie allerinnigst, denke Ihrer viel und herzlich und freue mich heuer[,] mich ganz der Ihre nennen zu können.</tei:p><tei:p>Alles Liebe von Ihrem treuen
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hans.
12. Aug. 13.</tei:p><tei:p>Anbei das Häuschen in dem mein Arbeitszimmer ist.  Ein lieber Bauernstüblein!</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated August 12, 1913</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dearest, honored Master,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>You will be surprised at my long silence and be thinking that it must signify God knows how many newly created ‘opera’!  Yet nevertheless I am following the second piece of advice in your recent very kind letter<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> more than that which concerned work, namely taking lots of walks.  I have now had a break of two full weeks and do not intend to get back to it properly until next week.  However, I have become thoroughly acquainted with work and that is in my opinion the best thing that could have happened, because I have come to realize that final <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> goals and results cannot be grasped and attained in the twinkling of an eye.  Even that which seems the easiest thing can demand the same perseverance as times of trouble:  all the richer for this insight, I now return to you, hungrier than before, more exacting, more consistent than before, and I look forward to all the spiritual sustenance ahead!  I hope to bring the completed drafts of both the first movement (currently being composed afresh<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>) and the last one.  I should like to leave the instrumentation until the autumn, when I can tackle it under your supervision—the tiresome reworking will thus be avoided, and at the same time many things can be learned, so to speak, <tei:hi rend="italic">a priori</tei:hi>. The only Scherzo and Trio, which I still find as good as I did last year, will be changed last of all!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> The adagio causes me concern, however:  how could I have allowed myself to have considered it successful last year—purely and simply because it was not unmelodic?!  How is one to bring light and spirit to the jumble, the confusion, the unwieldiness of the synthesis?  Even the first idea, with its unfortunate—ridiculously contrived—song form, causes me pain and bitterness!  The second idea, which I like melodically, could do with a more suitable antecedent! Would it not be better to use this movement as a source of material for further compositions and start work on a new adagio?  I await your decisions, your advice, but over the summer I have forgotten how to hurry and make haste and it won’t bother me if all I can achieve is to effect the above well, rather than producing an elaborately ready-made, but inferior, Quintet!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> My plans are to stay until September 15 in this little place, which I’ve recently come to love despite the bad weather, and then to undertake a journey through Germany:  Nürnberg – Würzburg – Heidelberg – Frankfurt – Eisenach – Gota – Erfurt – Weimar – Jena – Leipzig – Breslau!  It would be a great pleasure to hear of anything I could do for you—and to carry it out to the best of my ability.  I found Dahms’ review<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> flat and superficial!  Such things are not written for the likes of us!</tei:p><tei:p>I send you most heartfelt greetings, think of you often and with affection and look forward to being able to devote all my time to you soon.</tei:p><tei:p>Loving greetings from
Yours faithfully, 
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hans.
August 12, 1913</tei:p><tei:p>I enclose a picture of the little house where my study is—a dear little country dwelling!</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>