<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 15/16, [3] : 1-13-12 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Under inquiry.
© Transcription Ian Bent and William Drabkin, 2007.
© Translation William Drabkin, 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish is being sought.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1912-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Hans Weisse; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin &amp; Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 01/13/1912 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Weisse ~ H+JSchenker","Weisse ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated January 13, 1912</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-09-28</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>W thanks S profusely for his helpful corrections to some short compositions, but at the same time feels discouraged that he will never progress much beyond the level of writing small pieces.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Weisse, Hans;  Schenker, Heinrich;  compositions</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - - </marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated January 13, 1912</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Verehrter Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Nun Sie sich mit meinen Kleinigkeiten<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> Evidently W had sent (or handed over at his previous lesson, January 10) to S some recent compositions. <tei:hi rend="italic">Kleinigkeiten</tei:hi> are short pieces (“bagatelles”), usually for solo piano; but in the course of the letter W uses the term, disparagingly, to mean music of short duration, which lacks the depth of vision needed to write in the larger forms.</tei:note> so viel Mühe gaben, und ihnen Ihren ganzen Feuereifer zugute kommen liessen, fühle ich mich genötigt, Ihnen aus tiefster Seele Dank zu sagen für all Ihre Plage und Mühe!  Und auch für jene Neuigkeiten, die ich dabei zu hören bekam, die mir unsre Kunst von einer ganz andren Seite her erschlossen;  ich habe vielleicht genau so stark wie Sie den Reiz des Feilens verspürt, die Freude an der Entdeckung kleiner und grosser Mangel und die Beseelung durch die Artikulierung!  Wie ich besonders früher das Wesen der Bögen unterschätzt habe, &lt;strike&gt;die&lt;/strike&gt; ihrer &lt;strike&gt;ferne&lt;/strike&gt; ^weithin^ reichenden Wirkung, und motivischer Wichtigkeit <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> nicht achtend!  Nun ist’s mir auf einmal klar geworden, dass ich meinen eigenen Themengebilden eigentlich doch immerhin mehr oder minder fremd war, ja sie sogar wie es meine Bogenführung ja bewies trotzdem sie mir nahestanden, verkannte!  Die richtige Erkenntnis und Wertung der Artikulierung nun hat mich in einen wahren Freudestaumel versetzt;  freilich, wenn dies allein noch lange nicht genügt, so habe ich doch die Empfindung[,] dass jetzt zwischen mir und dem was ich schreibe mehr Klarheit herrschen wird.  Naturgemäss knüpft sich an die Freude die Frage, woher mir Aufklärung über dieses Thema kam?</tei:p><tei:p>Und da muss ich Ihnen, liebster Meister[,] danken, ohne den ich früher ganz verkehrte und sinnlose Wege gegangen wäre.  Aber ich bin mir des Glückes, Ihr Schüler zu sein, <tei:hi rend="italic">vollständig bewusst</tei:hi>, und so <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> doch nicht mehr ganz wertlos!  Je mehr ich über die Feinheit Ihrer musikalischen Empfindung[,] über die Klarheit Ihres alles durchdringenden kritischen Auges staune, umso mehr fühle ich, dass ich in der Erreichung meines mir gesetzten Zieles nämlich alles mit solcher vornehmen Ruhe und Tiefe zu durchprüfen wie Sie, die höchste Befriedigung erreichen werde!  Aber diese Ungeduld, liebster Meister[,] diese jugendliche Ungeduld, die mich jeden Augenblick vor fremden Schweren entmutigt!!  Ganz konnte ich die Freude Ihres Lobes nicht auskosten, weil ich, wie von einem fixen Gedanken beherrscht, mir immer einbildete, dass mir nunmehr nichts mehr gelingen werde, und dass ich bei einem armseligen op. 2. stehen bleiben müsse und werde!</tei:p><tei:p>Vielleicht &lt;strike&gt;ist&lt;/strike&gt; ^trägt^ die Ungleichheit meines <tei:hi rend="bold">{4} </tei:hi>Wollens und Könnens Schuld an solchem Versagen&lt;strike&gt;s&lt;/strike&gt;!  Aber wenn sich meine kühnen Gedanken auf die Höhe von Trios, Quartetten und Symphonieen,[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] schwingen, so habe ich das Gefühl:  Diese Trauben werden ^mir^ <tei:hi rend="italic">immer</tei:hi> zu hoch häufen!  Als ob ich dieser Höhenluft nicht gewachsen, in die dumpfe Atmosphäre von allerhand Kleinigkeiten wieder hinab müsste!  Wieder Lieder und wieder Kleinigkeiten!  Offen gestanden!  Sie wachsen mir schon &lt;strike&gt;beim&lt;/strike&gt; ^zum^ Hals heraus!</tei:p><tei:p>Um ein tröstendes Wort will Sie also Ihr Schüler bitten, der sich einbildet[,] alles was Ihnen nahegeht und steht mit dem gleichen Interesse und der gleichen Liebe des Freundes zu betrachten und zu fühlen!</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hans</tei:p><tei:p>13. Jänner, 1912.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated January 13, 1912</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Honored Master,</tei:p><tei:p>As you have taken so much trouble over my trifles<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>, and brought the fullness of your fiery zeal to bear upon them, I feel obliged to thank you from the bottom of my heart for all your trouble and toil! And also for those new things that I gathered along the way, which showed me our art in an entirely new light; perhaps I have felt, just as keenly as you, the excitement of making fine adjustments [to my work], the joy in discovering shortcomings small and large, and the spiritedness that comes from marking the articulation! How, in particular, I undervalued the meaning of the slurs at an earlier time, failing to attend to their far-reaching effect and motivic importance! <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Now it has suddenly become clear to me that I was always more or less a stranger to my very own thematic constructions, indeed that I even did not recognize them, as my placement of slurs actually proved! The correct understanding and appreciation of articulation has now transported me into a true frenzy of joy; of course, even if this alone is far from satisfactory, I nonetheless have the feeling that greater clarity will prevail between myself and what I write. Naturally, with my joy comes the question: From whence came my enlightenment about this theme?</tei:p><tei:p>And there I must thank you, dear master, without whom I would certainly have taken entirely wrong and meaningless paths. But I am <tei:hi rend="italic">completely conscious</tei:hi> of the joy of being your pupil, and thus <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> indeed no longer entirely worthless! The more I marvel at the subtlety of your musical sensibility, at the clarity of your all-penetrating, critical eye, the more I feel that, in attaining the goal I have set myself, namely, the ability to check through everything with such admirable tranquility and profundity as you have, I shall achieve the greatest satisfaction. But this impatience, dearest master, this youthful impatience, which at every turn discourages me in the face of unknown difficulties!! I could not savor the joy of your praise to the full, because I always imagine, as if ruled by an <tei:hi rend="italic">idée fixe</tei:hi>, that now I shall no longer be successful at anything, and that I must and shall remain stuck at the level of a wretched opus 2!</tei:p><tei:p>Perhaps the inequality between <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> what I want to do and what I am able to do is to be blamed on such a failing! But if my keen ideas soar to the level of trios, quartets and symphonies, I have the feeling: these grapes will <tei:hi rend="italic">always</tei:hi> pile up beyond ^my^ reach! As if I have not grown sufficiently to breathe this rarified air, and must sink once more into the gloomy atmosphere of all sorts of trivial things! More songs, and more trivial pieces. I admit it: they are already growing around my neck!</tei:p><tei:p>Thus your pupil begs for a word of comfort from you; he imagines himself contemplating and feeling everything that is dear to you with the same interest, the same friendly love.</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hans</tei:p><tei:p>January 13, 1912</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>