<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 15/16, [34] : 2-26-18 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Hans Weisse, published with kind permission.
© Transcription by William Drabkin, 2008.
© Translation Alison Hiley, 2008.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin, 2009
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish granted by the heirs of Hans Weisse.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1918-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Hans Weisse; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin;  Translation: Alison Hiley</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 02/26/1918 02:58:21 PM --><!-- MT Tags: "Weisse ~ H+JSchenker","Weisse ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated February 26, 1918</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-03-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Weisse expresses his concerns about a proposed Festschrift in celebration of Schenker's fiftieth birthday, fearing that the work will be written largely by eminent people and journalists who have little knowledge of his teaching and so will not do justice to him as a theorist;   asks Schenker for his own opinion of the matter.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Weisse, Hans;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Vrieslander, Otto;  Festschrift;  Schoenberg, Arnold</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated February 26, 1918</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Lieber verehrter Meister!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> Receipt of this letter and Schenker's reaction is recorded at OJ 2/10, p. 847: February 28, 1918.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ich sende Ihnen beiliegend den Brief, den ich von Vrieslander<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.</tei:note> erhielt und gleichzeitig eine Abschrift meiner Antwort an ihn, bitte jedoch um die Rücksendung des ersteren.  Lieber, verehrter Meister, Sie verstehen gewiß meinen Standpunkt in dieser Angelegenheit, wenn Sie ihn nicht sogar teilen!  Aber, daß lauter so unbekannte Größen[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] und Journalisten eine Festschrift über Sie<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  A (proposed) book of musical studies, commemorating Schenker's fiftieth birthday.</tei:note> herausgeben - finde ich fast-„unstandesgemäß!"  Müßten Sie wohl erst darauf warten?  Ich weiß es aus eigener Erfahrung, ich beherrsche viel von Ihrer Lehre, aber doch sind ihre Wurzeln in mir nicht &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add HW--&gt;alle&lt;/sup&gt; so tief und fest gewachsen, daß ich lauter Wahrheiten und bis ins Letzte mit &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add HW--&gt;von&lt;/sup&gt; Ihren [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr from</tei:hi> Ihnen] übereinstimmende[n] Gedanken veröffentlichen könnte!  Wie erst die Herren, die doch eigentlich weniger in Kontakt mit Ihnen waren, als ich?</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Ich habe dabei wirklich ununterbrochen an das Festbuch Arnold Schönberg<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Weisse is probably thinking of the book <tei:hi rend="italic">Arnold Schönberg</tei:hi> (Munich:  R. Piper, 1912), comprising articles by Alban Berg, Wassily Kandinsky, and others.  Schoenberg's fiftieth birthday was commemorated in 1924, in a supplement to the <tei:hi rend="italic">Musikblätter des Anbruch</tei:hi>, one of UE's the house journals.</tei:note> gedacht! und wie lächerlich mich die Versammlung von Seiten seiner Schüler anmutete.  Was ich damals folgerte, war weiters, daß dem Unparteiischen jede solche mehr oder weniger objektive Darstellung von Menschen, im Brennpunkt der Begeisterung - als eine Art Clique&lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add HW--&gt;nwirtschaft&lt;/sup&gt; vorkommen müsse!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich bitte Sie[,] verehrter Meister[,] mich mit einem Worte aufzuklären, wie <tei:hi rend="italic">Sie</tei:hi> in dieser Angelegenheit denken?</tei:p><tei:p>Ich grüße Sie aufs Herzlichste und bin in Treuen
Ihr [<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hans</tei:p><tei:p>Meine besten Empfehlungen der lieber gnädigenFrau!
26/2 18.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated February 26, 1918</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear, honored master,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>I am enclosing the letter which I received from Vrieslander<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> and also a transcription of my response to him;  I would be grateful if you could return the former.  Dear, honored master, I am certain you will understand my point of view in this matter, even if you don't quite share it!  But I find it well nigh "unbefitting" that a collection of such unknown eminences and journalists should produce a Festschrift in your honor<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>.  Is this really what you were expecting?  I know from my own experience that whilst I have mastered much of your teaching, nonetheless none of it is rooted so deeply and firmly that I could publish utterly accurate truths which accorded in every degree with your thoughts!  How then could the gentlemen, who have in truth had less contact with you than I have, achieve this?</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi>Throughout I have not been able to stop thinking of the celebratory book for Arnold Schoenberg<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>!--and of how that collection made by his students struck me as ridiculous.  Furthermore, what I concluded then was that any such portrayal of people, whether more or less objective, must surely appear to the impartial in the heat of enthusiasm as a kind of cliquishness [<tei:hi rend="italic">alt from</tei:hi> clique].</tei:p><tei:p>Honored master, could you enlighten me briefly as to <tei:hi rend="italic">your</tei:hi> opinion on this matter?</tei:p><tei:p>I send you my most cordial and loyal greetings,	
Yours, [<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hans</tei:p><tei:p>My best regards to you dear lady!	
February 26, 1918</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>