<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 15/16, [25] : 4-7-16 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Hans Weisse, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2008.
© Translation Alison Hiley, 2008
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish granted by the heirs of Hans Weisse.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1916-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Hans Weisse; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin;  Translation: Alison Hiley</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 04/16/1916 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Weisse ~ H+JSchenker","Weisse ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated April 7, 1916</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-07-02</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Weisse acknowledges the receipt of the Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven … op. 111, praises its profundity and clarity but suggests that the political footnotes damage the dignity of the rest;  he hopes to meet Schenker the following Sunday. 

</dc:description><dc:subject>Weisse, Hans;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Op. 111</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated April 7, 1916</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Mein lieber, verehrter Meister!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary, OJ 2/1, p. 188, April 7, 1916.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Diese Woche las ich den 1. Satz von op. 111<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> Schenker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven … op. 111</tei:hi> (Vienna: UE, 1915). </tei:note> und möchte Ihnen nur mit einigen, wenigen militärisch-knappen (sowohl an Verstand als Gemüt) ^(darum eben militärischen[)]^ Worten sagen, wie gross und stark der Eindruck Ihrer Darstellung wieder auf mich gewirkt hat. Aber je mehr ich Sie verstehe, desto klarer und aut verständlicher wird mir die Kluft, die Sie von Jjenen trennt, zu denen Sie eigentlich sprechen:  aber es wird Ihnen niemals möglich werden können, Ihre Polemik als das durchzusetzen, was sie ist:  als Meilenstein gewissermassen auf der Strasse zur Wahrheit, der die Distanz zum höchsten Ideale des Kunstverständnisses von dem jetzigen und bisherigen Stande menschlichen kritischen Erkenntnisvermögens genau anzeigt!  Die Menschheit wird sie immer als ihren <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> unterbau[?] oder dgl. ansehen wollen.  Die Darstellung der Modulationspartie und des zweiten Gedankens, sowie die Bedeutung der Halben am Schlusse, war das, was mich am meisten faszinierte.  Auch die Vergrösserung in der Einleitung!  Kurz . . . . ich bin Ihnen nebst allem dankbar, neuerdings dankbar, für die wundervoll klaren, reinen Stunden dieses kritischen Genusses!  Soll ich ganz ehrlich sein, so stören Smich die politischen Fussnoten, insofern sie, Ausflüsse der gleichen Wahrheit gewiss, doch in die Schneeregion zwecklos-zweckvollster Ereignisse, etwas allzu Menschliches mit sich bringen und dadurch in einem bestimmten Gegensatze zu der adeligen Würde des Dargestellten stehen.  Es wird das Zeitlose, wie Sie so geistreich sagen[,] die “Modernität der Ewigkeit” doch zu sehr mit dem Zeitlichen in Verbindung gebracht und verblasst als Fussnote unter dem Texte – ich möchte fast sagen Zum [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte:</tei:hi> zum] Beigeschmacke des Gemeinplätzlichen!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich würde Sie gar zu gerne sehen, zumal ich Ihnen auch ein neues Lied vorzuspielen hätte und würde Sie <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> gerne um Verständigung in die Linke Wienzeile 36 bitten, ob ich Sie Sonntags gegen 10 Uhr auf eine Stunde besuchen könnte.</tei:p><tei:p>Vielleicht opfern Sie diese einem bald ins Feld abgehenden[,] daher egoistischen, doch herzlichst Sie und die liebe gnädige Frau grüssenden</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hans.
St. Pölten, 7. April 16.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated April 7, 1916</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>My dear, honored master,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>This week I read the first movement of <tei:hi rend="italic">Op.111</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> and wanted to tell you in just a few words, and with military conciseness (as regards both body and soul) ^(hence military[)]^, what a great and deep impression your analysis has made on me once more.  But the more I understand you, the more clearly and self-evidently I perceive the gulf which divides you from those whom you are in fact addressing:  and yet it will never become possible for you to enforce your polemic for what it [actually] is—it can be seen as a milestone on the road to truth, [one] which precisely indicates the distance to the highest ideal of artistic understanding, with man’s ability for critical insight, up to and including the present, as the starting point!  Humanity will always want to view your [polemic[?]] as its foundation[?] <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> or something similar.  What fascinated me most were the interpretation of the modulation and the second idea, as well as the significance of the half-notes at the end.  Also the augmentation in the introduction!  In short … quite apart from everything else for which I owe you thanks, renewed thanks are now due to you for the wonderfully pure, clear hours afforded by this critical delight!  If I were to be quite honest, the political footnotes trouble me, inasmuch as they are assuredly outpourings of the same truth, yet, in flowing into the snowy region of randomly expedient events, they bring with them something all too human and thereby appear somewhat in antithesis to the noble dignity of that which is represented.  The timeless, or, as you so brilliantly put it, the “modernity of eternity”, is then associated too directly with the temporal, and pales into insignificance as a footnote at the bottom of the text—I’m almost inclined to say, as an aftertaste of the commonplace!</tei:p><tei:p>I would be so happy to see you, especially since I also have a new song to play to you and would be grateful if you <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> could send word to Linke Wienzeile 36 to say whether I could visit you for an hour around 10 o’clock on Sunday.</tei:p><tei:p>Perhaps you can grant this to one who is soon to take the field, and who is therefore feeling egotistical, whilst sending you and your dear wife most heartfelt greetings</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hans.
St. Pölten, April 7, 1916</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>