<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 15/16, [27] : 8-3-16 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Hans Weisse, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2008.
© Translation Alison Hiley, 2008
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish granted by the heirs of Hans Weisse.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1916-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Hans Weisse; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin;  Translation: Alison Hiley</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 08/03/1916 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Weisse ~ H+JSchenker","Weisse ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated August 3, 1916</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-07-02</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Weisse, in a dispirited mood, apologizes for not writing sooner and hopes to give Schenker a more detailed account of his activities in military service.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Weisse, Hans;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Kontrapunkt II;  Counterpoint II;  Riemann, Hugo;  Specht, Richard;  Karpath, Ludwig;  Rasumovsky Quartet</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated August 3, 1916</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Liebster, verehrter Meister!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary, OJ 2/3, p. 266, August 7, 1916.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>So oft wollte ich noch daransetzen, Ihnen zu schreiben, aber immer und immer wieder kam etwas ganz Unwichtiges dazwischen, das mich nichts desto weniger davon abhielt.  Was ich empfand, als ich hörte, dass sie ihrer [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte:</tei:hi> Sie Ihrer] kostbaren Arbeit erhalten bleiben, können Sie sich ja vorstellen.  Nur hoffe ich in unser aller Interesse[,] dass wir II/2<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> The second volume of <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt</tei:hi>, publication of which has yet again been held up.  </tei:note> bereits im friedlichen Arbeitszimmer werden lesen können und nicht hier, wo doch immer der Geist abgelenkt wird.  Ich habe jetzt die Überzeugung gewonnen, dass ich, zurückgekommen, mit Generalbass nochmals werde anfangen müssen – und das wird keiner Wiederholung gleichen!   Ich beneide Sie nun[?] die Ungestörtheit[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] mit der sie [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte:</tei:hi> Sie] in gleicher Weise Natur wie Arbeit geniessen können;  mir geht’s obzwar nicht schlecht, in dieser Beziehung doch recht mässig, denn der geistige Kontakt vermag hier nur sehr spärliche Funken zu erzeugen:  der Mensch sammelt alle Überreste der hiesischen Natur, die sich in ihm vorfinden gewissermassen auf einem Punkt zusammen, und macht diesen zum Standpunkte seiner Lebensanschauung.  Rückwärts macht alles anderen Eindruck und man hat die Vorstellung einer Veränderung:  aber hier erkennt man das Unveränderte – von jeher Bestehende!  Was sollte auch ^einen [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte:</tei:hi> einen]^ Riemann[-,]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="riemann_hugo">Hugo Riemann</ref>.  </tei:note> <tei:hi rend="bold">{2} </tei:hi>Specht[-],<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Richard Specht (1870–1932), Viennese musicologist who championed the work of Mahler and Strauss, as well as of Brahms.   </tei:note> Karpath-typus<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Ludwig Karpath: [create profile and link].  </tei:note> Ursache zur Veränderung bieten?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Allusion is to the study of character features (Charakterkunde).  </tei:note>  Es giebt keine Hoffnungsberechtigung auf bessere, kommende Zeiten, bevor der Bazillus nicht gefunden ist, der jene Charakterköpfe aus dem vielköp^kantigen^ Profile der Menschheit aust ^abzehrt^!  Wenn man hie und da in eines der Rasumofsky Quartette untertaucht, so hat man die Empfindung, als gäbe es immer weiter Frieden auf der Welt, und der Krieg und die grosse Zeit wären die unwichtigsten Geschehnisse!</tei:p><tei:p>Anbei einen Aufsatz aus irgend einer säglichen-kläglichen Rundschau[,] die hier aufliegt.  Von meiner Beschäftigung denke ich hier in nächster Zeit Ihnen ein genaueres Bild zu geben!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich grüsse Sie, wie die liebe gnädige Frau aufs Allerherzlichste
und bin ganz Ihr getreuer
 [<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hans.
3. August. 16</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated August 3, 1916</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dearest, honored master,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>I have wanted to sit down to write to you so often but again and again something insignificant came in the way and kept me from doing so.  You can well imagine how I felt when I heard that you are continuing with  your valuable work.  I only hope that in all our interests we shall soon be able to read II/2<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> in a peaceful study and not here, where one’s mind is always distracted.  I am now convinced that once I return I shall have to start over again with basso continuo—and no revision will be equal to it!  I do envy you the tranquillity in which you can enjoy nature and work in equal measure, although things are not going badly for me, indeed in this respect they are middling, for intellectual discourse here is only able to generate very meagre sparks:  all that does remain of nature here is in some way gathered together in one place within men and that place becomes the source of their view of life.  Everything looks different over one’s shoulder and it seems as if things have changed: but here one sees that which has not changed—that which has existed from time immemorial! What can character types such as ^a^ Riemann,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> a Specht<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> or a Karpath<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> offer us as cause for change?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/>  There can be no justification for hoping for better times to come until the bacillus is found which ^causes emaciation^ in those distinctive features of the many^-sided^ profile of humanity!  If now and then one can lose oneself in a Rasumovsky Quartet, one has the feeling that there still is peace in the world, and that the War and These Important Times are the most insignificant of events!</tei:p><tei:p>I am enclosing an essay from some petty-pitiful chronicle which is available here.  I intend to give you a more exact idea here of how my time is spent very soon!</tei:p><tei:p>Most heartfelt greetings to yourself, and to your good lady,
I remain, yours ever,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hans.
August 3, 1916</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>