<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 15/16, [31] : 11-9-17 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Hans Weisse, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin 2008.
© Translation Alison Hiley, 2008
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin, 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish granted by the heirs of Hans Weisse.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1917-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Hans Weisse; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin;  Translation: Alison Hiley</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 11/09/1917 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Weisse ~ H+JSchenker","Weisse ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated November 9 1917</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-07-03</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Weisse has been studying Brahms and Mozart, and promises an analysis of Brahms, Intermezzo, Op. 119, No. 2 soon.  — Comments on the Italian and Russian campaigns.  — Has had a pamphlet by Walter Rathenau sent to Schenker.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Weisse, Hans;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Brahms;  Mozart;  Intermezzo;  Italian campaign;  Russia;  Rathenau, Walter</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated November 9, 1917</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Mein lieber teurer Meister!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> This is the first in a series of letters from Weisse to Schenker (OJ 15/16, [31] – [36]) written in Sütterlinschrift (perhaps to deceive the military censors?);  Weisse resumed writing in Lateinschrift in December 1918.  Receipt of this letter does not appear to be recorded in Schenker's diary, however, Schenker's reply is recorded on OJ 2/8, p. 794, November 11, 1917.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Wenn ich Ihnen so lange nicht geschrieben, so geschah’s hauptsächlich[,] weil meine Stimmung noch schlechter war, als ich je vermutet hatte, daß sie sein könnte.  Nun aber habe ich ein Klavier zu Hause, und verbringe meine Abende statt in der Offiziersmesse, mit Brahms, Mozart und fühle mich unbedingt wohler.  Insbesondere habe ich mein Augenmerk auf</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example:</tei:hi> Brahms, Intermezzo in E minor, Op. 119, No. 2, bar 1, right hand]</tei:p><tei:p>gerichtet, und habe vor[,] über dieses ganz einzigartige Stück[?] Ihnen demnächst, mein lieber Meister[,] eine Analyse einzuschicken. Also doch ein wenig Arbeit.  Auch möchte ich Ihnen den Fingersatz, nach dem ich es spiele, mitschicken!  Ich habe nun ernstlich Schritte eingeleitet, um auf 3–4 Monate ins Hinterland zu kommen und mein Doktorat zu absolvieren.   So wäre doch dem Kriege ein wenig abgewonnen – und wir leben doch in der Zeit der Kriegsgewinn[l]er!</tei:p><tei:p>Die italienische Niederlage ist eine recht kausal bedingte Tatsache und über alles erfreulich!  Auch die Zustände in Russland weisen wohl doch sehr deutlich nach dem Frieden!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Ich habe Ihnen, lieber Meister, Rathenaus Broschüre<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> Click on <ref cRef="rathenau_walter">Walter Rathenau</ref>.    The pamphlet does not survive in OC or OJ.  </tei:note> deshalb senden lassen, weil ich sie hier lesend, so recht für eine Manifestation des deutschen Geistes ansehe ^angesehen habe^, der, auch das Materiellste[?] mit einem allen Schwierigkeiten überwältigenden Idealismus und Glauben durchführt!  Ich denke, Sie dürften meiner Ansicht sein, und verstehe[n], weshalb ich das dringende Bedürfnis empfand, diese wenigen[?] und doch so inhaltsreichen Seiten in Ihren Händen zu wissen!  Schreiben Sie mir bitte ein Wort darüber!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich grüße Sie und die liebe gnädige Frau aufs Herzlichsteund bin in alter Treue und immer jünger werdender Dankbarkeit</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed</tei:hi>:] Hans.
9/XI. 17.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated November 9, 1917</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>My dear, valued master,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>If I have not written for so long it has been mainly because my mood has been even worse than I could ever have imagined it could be.  But now I have a piano in the house and instead of spending my evenings in the officers’ mess I spend them with Brahms and Mozart and feel undoubtedly better.  I have directed my attention in particular to</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example:</tei:hi> Brahms, Intermezzo in E minor, Op. 119, No. 2, bar 1, right hand]</tei:p><tei:p>and intend shortly to send you, my dear Master, an analysis of this quite unique piece.  A little work after all therefore.  I would also like to send you the fingering with which I’m playing it!  I have now initiated serious steps towards being transferred to the hinterland for three-to-four months in order to complete my doctorate.  Thus a little would be gained from the War—and after all we live in the age of war-profiteers!</tei:p><tei:p>The Italian defeat is surely nearly a fact and above all pleasing!  And the situation in Russia indeed points very definitely towards peace!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> I had Rathenau’s pamphlet<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> sent to you, dear Master, because, in reading it here, I found it to be a real manifestation of the German spirit, which imbues even the most materialistic with an idealism and belief which overcomes all difficulties!  I imagine you must share my point of view and will understand why I felt the urgent need to know that these pages, few in number but rich in content, were in your hands! Do please send me a word about them!</tei:p><tei:p>Most heartfelt greetings to you and your good lady wife.</tei:p><tei:p>Forever yours, and always freshly in your debt,</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hans.
November 9, 1917</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>