<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 15/16, [8] : 8-10-12 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Under inquiry.
© Transcription Ian Bent and William Drabkin, 2007.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin &amp; Ian Bent 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish is being sought.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1912-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Hans Weisse; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 08/10/1912 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Weisse ~ H+JSchenker","Weisse ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated August 10, 1912</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-10-07</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>W acks letter from S and looks forward to reading S's monograph Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie;  he is taking a break after completing two movements of his String Quintet, and will spend two weeks in Switzerland. W wishes to transfer from Violin to S for piano lessons.  Reports on Florence May's Brahms biography.   

</dc:description><dc:subject>Weisse, Hans;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie;  Beethoven's Ninth Symphony;  string quintet;  Spiegler;  Pontresina;  Switzerland;  Violin, Moriz;  piano lessons;  Brahms;  May, Florence;  Schumann, Clara;  Clementi;  Gradus ad Parnassum;  Mozart;  Meissner, Lorle</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated August 10, 1912</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Geliebter Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Für Ihren langen lieben Brief<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  The letter acknowledged here is not known to survive.  </tei:note> unendlichen Dank und für alles Lehrreiche darin!  Ihre IX.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  S’s monograph <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven’s Neunte Sinfonie</tei:hi> had just been published (Vienna: UE, 1912).</tei:note> wird mit solchem Fleiss und Eifer studiert[,] dass von einem „Lesen“ wohl die Rede nicht sein kann – taktweise und infolgedessen sehr langsam.  Immer mehr und mehr staune ich über die feinen, subtilen Zusammenhänge die Sie aufdecken, und die am Kunstwerke das begründen, was unbekannt und unbenannt die Überzeugung des Grossen erweckt, die der Laie aus seinen „Gefühl“ bezieht!</tei:p><tei:p>Nachdem die ersten 2 ^Quintett^ Sätze fertig waren beschloss ich ein wenig auszuruhen, konnte mich aber doch eines Scherzos nicht erwehren, das in mir rumort und dessen Trio einzig und allein noch fehlt, während das andere<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> The fourth movement of his String Quintet.</tei:note> schon ein wenig skizziert aus dem Halbdunkel tritt.  Nun wird die Arbeit doch durch eine Reise unterbrochen, die mich auf Besuch zu meinem einzigen, lieben Freunde Spiegler<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> Spiegler: [identify]</tei:note> nach Pontresina[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Pontresina: Alpine village and ski resort located in the Upper Engadin region of Switzerland.  </tei:note> in die Schweiz führt.  Am 16. August werde ich dort anlangen um eine Woche daselbst und eine zweite Woche auf einer kleinen Rundtour in fröhlicher Stimmung zu verleben.  Hernach wieder Ischl und neuerdings Ringkampf mit dem Quintett – so hoffe ich Ende September bei Ihnen mit der reinen Partitur erscheinen zu dürfen!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich habe jetzt mehr denn je das Verlangen nach jenem Klavierspiel das ich an Ihnen und Ihrer Schülerin bewunderte, und hoffe dass Professor Violin<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="violin_moriz">Moriz Violin</ref>: Violin was W’s piano teacher at the time.</tei:note> von mir genug hat!  Wahrlich nicht aus Undankbarkeit, das wissen Sie, Liebster, so gut wie &lt;strike&gt;ich&lt;/strike&gt; ^er^ selbst begreifen würde!  Könnten Sie nicht doch schonungsvoll ihn bedeuten?</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Was die Harmonielehrevorlesungen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7"> Probably the lectures he was due to take in the coming term at the University of Vienna given by Professor Guido Adler.  From 1914 onwards, S’s diaries include numerous summaries of  W’s reports of Adler’s lectures. </tei:note> betrifft zweifeln Sie doch gewiss!  Denken Sie an meine dummen Gesichter der ersten Stunden!  Und nun erst eine Masse!  Sind nicht doch Perlen vor die Säue geworfen?</tei:p><tei:p>Lese jetzt die Brahmsbiographie einer Engländerin Florence May<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Florence May (1845–1923), English pianist who studied with Clara Schumann and Brahms; author of the two-volume <tei:hi rend="italic">The Life of Johannes Brahms</tei:hi>, published in 1905.</tei:note> die in einem einleitenden Kapitel Interessantes über Äusserungen Brahms zu sagen weiss.  Klara Schumann<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Clara Schumann (1819–96), born Clara Wieck, married Robert Schumann in 1840, one of the greatest pianists of her age, who taught at the Leipzig Conservatory as well as privately.  </tei:note> übergab sie als Schülerin für kurze Zeit dem Meister;  ich zitiere einiges:</tei:p><tei:p>Sie erzählte B. von den Schwierigkeiten des Handmechanismus beim Klavierspielen:  Er antwortete:  „Ja das muss zuerst kommen“ und nachdem er eine Etüde aus Clementis Gradus ad Parnassum<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Muzio Clementi, <tei:hi rend="italic">Gradus ad Parnassum, or The Art of Playing on the Piano Forte</tei:hi> (1917-26), one of the staple works for pianists.</tei:note> von mir angehört hatte, begann er sofort meine Finger zu lockern und auszugleichen.  Denselben Tag fing er an[,] mich allmählich durch den ganzen Kursus technischer Ausbildungen zu führen indem er mir zeigte[,] wie ich am besten zur Erreichung meines Zieles an Arpeggien, Trillern[,] Doppelgriffen und Oktaven arbeiten sollte. — Er glaubte nicht, dass es nützlich für mich sei, die gewöhnlichen Fünffingerübungen zu machen, sondern zog es vor aus den Stücken oder Etüden, mit denen ich mich grade beschäftigte, Übungen zu bilden.  Eine schwierige Stelle bearbeitete er häufig indem er mich dieselbe nicht so wie sie geschrieben war, überliess sondern mit andern Akzenten und verschiedenen Figuren . . . .  — oder:</tei:p><tei:p>„Am Schlusse der ersten dieser beiden Mozartstunden sagte ich ihm: „Alles was Sie heute gesagt haben, <tei:hi rend="italic">ist mir ganz neu</tei:hi>.[“] (!) „<tei:hi rend="italic">Es steht alles da</tei:hi>“ erwiderte er, [„]<tei:hi rend="italic">auf die Noten deutend</tei:hi>![“]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Schade, das dieses Werk nicht mehr sachliche Äusserungen bringt.</tei:p><tei:p>Frau Lorle Meissner<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Mrs Lorle Meissner:  perhaps a singer whom S recommended over W’s previous suggestion of Julia Culp (OJ 15/16, [6], July 7) for W's <tei:hi rend="italic">Mädchenlieder</tei:hi>.  </tei:note> werde ich &lt;strike&gt;ba&lt;/strike&gt; also wegen der Lieder schreiben und danke ich Ihnen im Vorhinein dafür!</tei:p><tei:p>Vielleicht könnten Sie mir nach &lt;strike&gt;Pontresina&lt;/strike&gt; <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Pontresina Pension Collina</tei:hi></tei:hi> ein paar Zeilen schreiben!  Ich bin vom 16. August bis 22. incl. dort.  Es würde riesig freuen Ihren Sie innigst verehrenden und liebenden</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hans.
10. August 1912.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated August 10, 1912</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Beloved master,</tei:p><tei:p>Endless thanks for your long and precious letter<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> and for all the instructive things it contains!  Your <tei:hi rend="italic">Ninth Symphony</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> will be studied with such diligence and eagerness that “reading” won’t be the word for it—bar-by-bar, hence very slowly.  I am more and more astonished at the refined and subtle relationships that you uncover, and that establish for the art work that which awakes, unknown and unnamed, the conviction of greatness that the layman gets from his “gut feeling”!</tei:p><tei:p>Once the first two movements ^of my Quintet^ were finished, I resolved to take a short break.  However, I simply could not keep at bay a Scherzo that was rumbling around in my mind, only the Trio of which was still lacking, while the other movement,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> already partway sketched, was beginning to emerge from the shadows.  Now the work will have to be interrupted for a journey that will take me to visit my one and only dear friend Spiegler<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> in Pontresina<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> in Switzerland.  I shall arrive there on August 16 and spend one week there and a second week in cheerful spirits on a short tour.  After that, back to Ischl to wrestle anew with the Quintet.  So I hope to be able to appear at your place at the end of September with a fair copy of the score!</tei:p><tei:p>More than ever now I yearn for the piano playing that I admired in you and your lady pupil, and hope that Professor Violin<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> has had enough of me!  Genuinely not out of ingratitude—you know that, most beloved [master], as well as &lt;strike&gt;I&lt;/strike&gt; ^he^ himself would appreciate.  So could you not be merciful [to me] and take his place?</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> As concerns the harmonic theory lectures,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> you may well have misgivings!  Think of my stupid faces during the initial lessons!  And now for the first time, a crowd!  Are not pearls cast before swine?</tei:p><tei:p>Am currently reading a Brahms biography by an English woman, Florence May,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> who has interesting things to say in an introductory chapter about remarks that Brahms made.  Clara Schumann<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> passed her on as a pupil to Brahms for a short time.  Let me quote a few things:</tei:p><tei:p>She told Brahms of the difficulties she had with the mechanics of her hand while playing the piano.  He replied:  “Yes, that has to take priority” and after he had listened to me playing an etude from Clementi’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Gradus ad Parnassum</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> he immediately began to relax and equalize my fingers.  The same day, he began taking me gradually through the whole course of technical training, while showing me how best I should work to attain my goal by means of arpeggios, trills, two notes in each hand, and octaves. — He did not believe it profitable for me to play the customary five-finger exercises, but instead favored devising exercises direct from the pieces or etudes on which I was actually working.  He frequently rearranged a difficult passage by giving it to me not as it was written but with altered accentuation and different figurations . . .–or:</tei:p><tei:p>At the end of the first of these two Mozart lessons, I said to him: “Everything that you have said today <tei:hi rend="italic">is totally new to me</tei:hi>.”(!)  “<tei:hi rend="italic">It is all there</tei:hi>,” he responded, “<tei:hi rend="italic">in the notes themselves</tei:hi>!”</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> What a pity that this work does not pass on remarks that are more substantial.</tei:p><tei:p>So I will write to Mrs Lorle Meissner<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> regarding the songs:  thank you in advance for that!</tei:p><tei:p>Perhaps you could drop me a line to <tei:hi rend="italic">Pontresina, Pension Collina</tei:hi>.  I shall be there August 16 to 22 inclusive.  It would give me enormous pleasure.</tei:p><tei:p>Yours with deepest respect and love,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hans
August 10, 1912</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>