<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 15/16, [9] : 8-15-12 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Under inquiry.
© Transcription Ian Bent and William Drabkin, 2007.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin &amp; Ian Bent 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish is being sought.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1912-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Hans Weisse; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 08/15/1912 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Weisse ~ H+JSchenker","Weisse ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated August 15, 1912</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-10-08</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>W seeks advice on the structure of the Scherzo-Trio of his String Quintet.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Weisse, Hans;  Schenker, Heinrich;  München;  Munich;  Pontresina;  string quintet;  Scherzo;  Trio;  Mittelstück;  middle section;  Reprise;  reprise;  Tonart;  key;  modulieren;  modulate;  Coda;  Koda;  Stufenzug;  scale-degree succession;  Stufenwerk;  scale-degree structure;  Brünauer, Frau</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Hotel Bayerischer Hof, Munich</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated August 15, 1912</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>] Hotel Bayerischer Hof, München.
Haus allerersten Ranges.
Besitzer:  Gebrüder Volkhardt.
Lieber’s Code</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">handwritten:</tei:hi>]
Innigst geliebter Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Auf der Durchreise nach Pontresina<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> Pontresina: Alpine village and ski resort located in the Upper Engadin region of Switzerland.  </tei:note> stelle ich an Sie eine sehr dringende Frage mit der Bitte[,] Sie mir so schnell als möglich ebendahin <tei:hi rend="italic">Pension Collina</tei:hi> zu beantworten.</tei:p><tei:p>Mein Scherzo<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  The third movement of W’s String Quintet.</tei:note> ist, wenn auch noch nicht instrumentiert so doch fast fertig geworden, nur hat mir das Tonale des Trios einige Schwierigkeiten gemacht und zwar aus folgendem Grunde.</tei:p><tei:p>Das Scherzo in D dur moduliert im ersten Teile zur Dominante, es folgen Mittelstück, Reprise und eine C&lt;strike&gt;l&lt;/strike&gt;oda zur Beendigung des Scherzos.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Nun folgt das Trio, wie es mir am besten passen würde[,] in h moll mit einem Mittelstück seinerseits in fis dur.</tei:p><tei:p>Kann man nun ohne lange Umschweife zu machen nach Beendigung des Scherzos auf der Tonika nach einer Tuttipause in h moll mit dem Trio einsetzen.  <tei:hi rend="italic">Oder muss das Scherzo erst zum Trio hinausmodulieren</tei:hi>??  Wäre dies der Fall, so wäre die Consequenz, dass die Coda des Scherzos als Coda für das ganze Stück gelten könnte, weil sie ja nicht zweimal vorkäme.</tei:p><tei:p>Es ergeben[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] sich folgende Fälle:</tei:p><tei:p>1.)</tei:p><tei:p>|Scherzo|Trio|Reprise|
|||des|
|a :  b : a + coda|a b a|ganzen|
|||Scherzos.|</tei:p><tei:p>oder 2.)</tei:p><tei:p>|Scherzo|Trio|Scherzo|
|a : b : a1|a1 b a1|a b : a + Coda|
|......mod.|||</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Sie verstehen, was ich meine[,] teurer Meister?  Was tatsächlich mir als Endstück des Scherzos als kleine Koda gelten sollte, würde die Rolle eines wirklichen empfangen!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  In this sentence, W is making a distinction between a closing group (or codetta) in a sonata form, which follows the second group within the exposition (or recapitulation) , and a “true” coda, which concludes the form as a whole.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ich bitte Sie daher mir zu schreiben, ob das Scherzo zum Trio hinausmodulieren muss?</tei:p><tei:p>Einfacher wäre es freilich das Trio in D dur gleichfalls, wie das Scherzo zu bringen, nur muss ich aber bemerken dass das Scherzo bereits tonartlich stark zwischen D – und A – schwebt, und also im Trio derselbe Tonarten und Stufenzug recht ermattend und monoton wirken musste!</tei:p><tei:p>Trotz alledem, Liebster, bin ich überzeugt, dass sie Ihre Freude haben werden, wenn <tei:hi rend="italic">Sie</tei:hi> sehen was i<tei:hi rend="italic">ch</tei:hi> sehe, worauf ich mein Stufenwerk <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> lenke!  Immer heller wird im Hirne Ihres Sie innigst verehrenden und herzlichst grüssenden, in die eisige Schweiz reisenden</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hans.
15. August, 1912.
München.</tei:p><tei:p>Allein Anscheine nach hat Frau Brünauer<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  The wife or mother of <ref cRef="brunauer_dr">Robert Brünauer</ref>.</tei:note> meinem Vater<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Adolf Weisse (1856–1933), distinguished character actor and theater director, from 1902 Director of the Deutsches Volkstheater in Vienna.</tei:note> missfallen;  er engagiert sie nicht.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated August 15, 1912</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>] Hotel Bayerischer Hof, Munich.
Hotel of the highest caliber.
Proprietors:  the Volkhardt brothers.
Lieber’s[?] Code</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">handwritten:</tei:hi>]
Most deeply beloved master,</tei:p><tei:p>En route for Pontresina,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> let me put a very urgent question to you, with a request that you reply as soon as possible to the Pension Collina in that town.</tei:p><tei:p>My Scherzo,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> albeit not yet scored out, is almost finished except that the key-scheme of the Trio has given me some trouble, for the following reason.</tei:p><tei:p>The Scherzo, in D major, modulates to the dominant in the first section;  then come the middle section, reprise, and a coda to end off the Scherzo.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Now comes the Trio, and it would suit me best if it were in B minor with a middle section in F# major.</tei:p><tei:p>Now, is one allowed, without making a long digression after the end of the Scherzo on the tonic, to set off straightway in B minor with the Trio after a <tei:hi rend="italic">tutti</tei:hi> rest.  <tei:hi rend="italic">Or does the Scherzo have first to modulate  toward the Trio</tei:hi>??  If this were the case, then the consequence would be that the coda of the Scherzo could serve as the coda for the entire movement, because it would not in fact occur twice.</tei:p><tei:p>The two following cases arise:</tei:p><tei:p>1.)</tei:p><tei:p>|Scherzo|Trio|Reprise|
|||of the|
|a :  b : a + coda|a b a|whole|
|||Scherzo.|</tei:p><tei:p>oder 2.)</tei:p><tei:p>|Scherzo|Trio|Scherzo|
|a : b : a1|a1 b a1|a b : a + Coda|
|......mod.|||</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> You understand what I mean, dear master?  What is intended in fact to serve as the conclusion of the Scherzo, as a short coda, would take on the role of true [coda]!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/></tei:p><tei:p>Please will you write telling me whether the Scherzo must modulate into the Trio?</tei:p><tei:p>It would admittedly be simpler if the Trio were, just like the Scherzo, in D major.  But I must point out that the Scherzo already hovers strongly between the keys of D [major] and A [major];  therefore, the same keys and scale-degree succession in the Trio would inevitably give a really wearisome and monotonous effect!</tei:p><tei:p>In spite of all of this, dearest [master], I am convinced that you will be delighted when <tei:hi rend="italic">you</tei:hi> see what <tei:hi rend="italic">I</tei:hi> can see, [namely] how I <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> manage my scale-degree structure.  It all be comes clearer and clearer in the mind of yours truly, who sends you his deepest respect and most cordial greetings while traveling in icy Switzerland,</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hans
August 15, 1912
Munich</tei:p><tei:p>To all appearances, Mrs. Brünauer<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> has displeased my father;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  he won’t have anything to do with her.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>