<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 71/42 : 10-20-1893 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription William Pastille 2006.
© Translation William Pastille 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Pastille, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> In the public domain</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1893-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: in the public domain; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Footnotes, Commentary: William Pastille.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 10/20/1893 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Harden ~ HSchenker","WolffH ~ Harden" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter on printed letterhead from Hermann Wolff to Harden, with postscript annotation from Harden to Schenker, dated October 20, 1893</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-03-01</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Wolff encourages Harden to find him a collaborator for an article on music and concert life;  having read Schenker’s article on Bruckner, he praises Schenker for his clear and accurate understanding of Bruckner’s music. Harden commends Wollf’s praise to Schenker, and suggests that he write an article about “conductors.” 

</dc:description><dc:subject>Wolff, Hermann;  Harden, Maximilian; Schenker, Heinrich;  Bülow, Hans von;  Bruckner;  Richter, Hans;  Levi, Hermann</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Berlin W., Am Carlsbad 19</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter on printed letterhead from Hermann Wolff to Harden, with postscript annotation from Harden to Schenker, dated October 20, 1893</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">[= OJ 11/42, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Hermann Levi (1839–1900), German conductor.  </tei:note>, a photocopy of this letter]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead with handwritten date</tei:hi>]
Concert-Direction Hermann Wolff.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Hermann Wolff was a major concert promoter and artists’ agent in Berlin.  He also managed the Berlin Philharmonic starting in 1887.  </tei:note>
Berlin W., Am Carlsbad 19, Telegramm-Adresse: Musikwolff, Berlin</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">rule</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>Vertretung des <tei:hi rend="bold">Philharmonischen Orchesters, Stern’scher Gesangverein, Philharmonischer Chor in Berlin. [/] Châtelet Concerte in Paris (Ed. Colonne). Philharmon. Concerte in Kopenhagen (Joh. Svendsen). </tei:hi>
Vertreter für Europa von <tei:hi rend="bold">Abbey, Schoeffel &amp; Grau</tei:hi>, New-York.
Vertreter von <tei:hi rend="bold">Eugen d’Albert, Teresa d’Albert-Carreño, Hugo Becker,</tei:hi> Kammer-Virtuose, <tei:hi rend="bold">Felix Berber, Marie Berg,
Dr. Hans von Bülow, Carl Dierich,</tei:hi> Kammersänger, <tei:hi rend="bold">Felix Dreyschock, Jettka Finkenstein,</tei:hi> Kammersängerin, <tei:hi rend="bold">Hermann
Gausche, Heinrich Grahl, Charles Gregorowitsch, Eugen Gura, Carl</tei:hi> und <tei:hi rend="bold">Therese Halir, Arno Hilf,
Joseph Joachim, Amalie Joachim, Robert Kaufmann, Clotilde Kleeberg, Caecilie Kloppenburg, Elise Leutheusser,
Franz Litzinger,</tei:hi> Kämmersänger, <tei:hi rend="bold">Fritz Masback, Pauline Metzier,</tei:hi> Kämmersängerin, <tei:hi rend="bold">Fanny Moran-Olden,</tei:hi> Kammer-
sängerin, <tei:hi rend="bold">Lydia Müller, Johanna Nathan, Selma Nicklass-Kempner, Max Pauer, Amma Plüddemann, Clara Polscher,
Georg Ritter, Moriz Rosenthal, Nicolaus Rothmühl,</tei:hi> Hofopernsänger, <tei:hi rend="bold">Anton Rubinstein, Camille Saint-Saëns, Lillian
Sanderson, Max van de Sandt, Clara Schacht, Wally Schauseil, Marie Schmidt-Koehne, Betty Schwabe, Franz
Schwarz,</tei:hi> Kammersänger, <tei:hi rend="bold">Anton Sistermans, Joseph Silwinski, Alfred Sormann, Josef Staudigt, </tei:hi>Kammersänger,
<tei:hi rend="bold">Bernhard Stavenhagen, César Thomson, Julia Uzielli, Gabriele Wietrowetz, Florian Zajic, Raimund von Zur Mühlen</tei:hi> etc.
Vertreter von <tei:hi rend="bold">Marcella Sembrich, Alice Barbi,</tei:hi> K. K. Kammersängerinnen und <tei:hi rend="bold">Emil Götze,</tei:hi> Kgl. Kammersänger.</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">decorated rule</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>Telephon Amt VI, No. 797 [–] BERLIN W., am Carlsbad 19.I
Telegramm-Adr.: <tei:hi rend="italic">Musikwolff, Berlin</tei:hi> [–] [<tei:hi rend="italic">handwritten:</tei:hi>] 20 Octob</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit großem Interesse werde ich den Artikel über Bruckner lesen.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich habe schon oft die Idee gehabt, über das Musik- und Concertwesen einmal nöthige Aufklärungen zu geben, Vorurtheile  <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> zu beseitigen &amp; Wahrheit &amp; Klarheit zu schaffen.  Bülow<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="hans_von_bulow_18309">Hans Bülow</ref>.  </tei:note> hat mich oft dazu animirt, denn er pflegte Stunde[n]lang in meinem Beureau [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] zu sitzen, dem Getriebe zuzuschauen, Einblicke in den Mechanismus zu nehmen.</tei:p><tei:p>Aber mir fehlt Zeit, Ruhe, &amp; Geduld.  Vielleicht finden Sie den Geeigneten.  Nothwendig ist’s.  Ich stelle gern Alles Material zur Verfügung, gebe jede nötige Aufklärung &amp; gewähre dem von Ihnen designirten Schriftsteller gern Einsicht in Alles.  Hätten Sie Zeit, Sie wären der rechte Mann wir fänden auch Gelegenheit, uns öfter darüber auszusprechen.</tei:p><tei:p>Die Bedeutung eines solchen Artikels wäre zweifellos sehr groß.  Die Nothwendigkeit erscheint mir geradezu dringend.</tei:p><tei:p>Vielleicht finden Sie bald einmal Zeit mir ein Wort zu antworten.</tei:p><tei:p>Ergebenst
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hermann Wolff  W. S. G. U.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  = "Wenden Sie Gefälligst Um" = "Kindly turn the page over"  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Ich habe eben den Artikel über Bruckner<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  This was the article “Anton Bruckner,” which appeared in <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Zukunft</tei:hi> on October 21, 1893, and is reprinted in Hellmut Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker als Essayist und Kritiker</tei:hi> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms Verlag, 1990), pp. 57-61.</tei:note> gelesen.  <tei:hi rend="italic">Sans phrase</tei:hi> er ist gut u. richtig. Dr. <tei:hi rend="italic">H. S.</tei:hi> kennt die Partituren Bruckners wirklich genau.  Was er speciell über den Kontrapunktiker Bruckner sagt, ist treffend;  <tei:hi rend="italic">Sch</tei:hi> hat sich eben nicht blenden lassen, wie die Meisten, denen eine Scheingelehrsamkeit imponirt.  Ich kann Ihnen hier nicht auseinandersetzen, wie famos in dem Artikel das Wesen Br’scher Musik erkannt ist &amp; nur der, welcher weiß, wie undendlich schwer es ist, dies Wesen mit Worten zu characterisiren, kann voll beurtheilen, wie Dr. <tei:hi rend="italic">Sch</tei:hi> den Kern getroffen hat.</tei:p><tei:p>Besten Dank. 
Ihr
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] H. W.</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">Handwritten annotation from Harden to Schenker:</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>Könnten Sie nicht einmal über [„]Dirigenten“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  This suggestion led to the article “Konzertdirigenten,” which appeared in <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Zukunft</tei:hi> on April 14, 1884, and is reprinted in Hellmut Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker als Essayist und Kritiker</tei:hi> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms Verlag, 1990), pp. 75-82.  </tei:note> schreiben, Bülow,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="hans_von_bulow_18309">Hans Bülow</ref>.  </tei:note> Richter,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Hans Richter (1843–1916), Hungarian/Austrian conductor. </tei:note> Levi<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Hermann Levi (1839–1900), German conductor.  </tei:note> u.s.w. ??</tei:p><tei:p>Vielleicht interesssirt Sies!</tei:p><tei:p>Besten Gruß. 
Ihr erg.
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] H.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter on printed letterhead from Hermann Wolff to Harden, with postscript annotation from Harden to Schenker, dated October 20, 1893</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">[= OJ 11/42, <tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>, a photocopy of this letter]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead with handwritten date</tei:hi>]
Hermann Wolff<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> Concert Management
Berlin W., Am Carlsbad 19, Telegraph-Address: Musikwolff, Berlin</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">rule</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>Agency of <tei:hi rend="bold">The Philharmonic Orchestra, the Stern Gesangverein, the Philharmonic Chorus in Berlin. [/] Châtelet Concerte in Paris (Ed. Colonne). Philharmon. Concerte in Kopenhagen (Joh. Svendsen). </tei:hi>
European Agents for <tei:hi rend="bold">Abbey, Schoeffel &amp; Grau</tei:hi>, New-York.
Agents for <tei:hi rend="bold">Eugen d’Albert, Teresa d’Albert-Carreño, Hugo Becker,</tei:hi> Chamber Virtuoso, <tei:hi rend="bold">Felix Berber, Marie Berg,
Dr. Hans von Bülow, Carl Dierich,</tei:hi> Chamber Singer, <tei:hi rend="bold">Felix Dreyschock, Jettka Finkenstein,</tei:hi> Chamber Singer, <tei:hi rend="bold">Hermann
Gausche, Heinrich Grahl, Charles Gregorowitsch, Eugen Gura, Carl</tei:hi> and <tei:hi rend="bold">Therese Halir, Arno Hilf,
Joseph Joachim, Amalie Joachim, Robert Kaufmann, Clotilde Kleeberg, Caecilie Kloppenburg, Elise Leutheusser,
Franz Litzinger,</tei:hi> Chamber Singer, <tei:hi rend="bold">Fritz Masback, Pauline Metzier,</tei:hi> Chamber Singer, <tei:hi rend="bold">Fanny Moran-Olden,</tei:hi> Chamber Singer, <tei:hi rend="bold">Lydia Müller, Johanna Nathan, Selma Nicklass-Kempner, Max Pauer, Amma Plüddemann, Clara Polscher,
Georg Ritter, Moriz Rosenthal, Nicolaus Rothmühl,</tei:hi> Court Opera Singer, <tei:hi rend="bold">Anton Rubinstein, Camille Saint-Saëns, Lillian
Sanderson, Max van de Sandt, Clara Schacht, Wally Schauseil, Marie Schmidt-Koehne, Betty Schwabe, Franz
Schwarz,</tei:hi> Chamber Singer, <tei:hi rend="bold">Anton Sistermans, Joseph Silwinski, Alfred Sormann, Josef Staudigt, </tei:hi> Chamber Singer,
<tei:hi rend="bold">Bernhard Stavenhagen, César Thomson, Julia Uzielli, Gabriele Wietrowetz, Florian Zajic, Raimund von Zur Mühlen</tei:hi> etc.
Agents for <tei:hi rend="bold">Marcella Sembrich, Alice Barbi,</tei:hi> K. K. Chamber Singers and <tei:hi rend="bold">Emil Götze,</tei:hi> Royal Chamber Singer.</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">decorated rule</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>Telephone Office VI, No. 797 [–] BERLIN W., am Carlsbad 19.I
Telegraph Addr.: Musikwolff, Berlin [–] [<tei:hi rend="italic">handwritten:</tei:hi>] 20 Octob</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Sir,</tei:p><tei:p>I will read the article on Bruckner with great interest.</tei:p><tei:p>Quite often I’ve had the notion to set down some needful explanations about music and concert life, <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> to eliminate prejudices and produce accuracy and clarity.  Bülow<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> often urged me to do so, for he used to spend hours sitting in my office watching the commotion and observing the workings.</tei:p><tei:p>But I don’t have the time, leisure, or patience. Perhaps you will find the appropriate person.  It’s imperative. I will make all materials available, provide all necessary explanations, and allow the writer chosen by you to inspect everything.  If you had time, you would be the right man and we would find the opportunity to exchange our opinions about it from time to time.</tei:p><tei:p>The significance of such an article would undoubtedly be very great.  The need for it seems nearly critical to me.</tei:p><tei:p>Perhaps you will find time sometime soon to send me a brief reply.</tei:p><tei:p>Yours truly,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hermann Wolff  K. T. P. O.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> I’ve just read the article on Bruckner.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> Without any exaggeration, it is good and accurate. Dr. H. S. has an exceptionally precise knowledge of Bruckner’s scores. In particular, what he says about Bruckner as a contrapuntalist is on the mark; Schenker hasn’t let himself be blinded like  most people, who are impressed by the appearance of erudition. I cannot explain here how splendidly the essence of Bruckner’s music is revealed in the article and only a person who knows how infinitely difficult it is to describe this essence in words can accurately gauge how close Dr. Schenker has gotten to the root of the matter.</tei:p><tei:p>Sincere thanks,
Yours,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] H. W.</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">handwritten annotation from Harden to Schenker:</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>Couldn’t you write sometime about “Conductors,”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> Bülow,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> Richter,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> Levi<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> etc.??</tei:p><tei:p>Perhaps this will interest you!</tei:p><tei:p>Sincere greetings,
Your faithful
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] H.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>