<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:NYma, [4] : 3-9-36 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  In the public domain.
©  Transcription Robert Wason, 2007.
©  Translation Robert Wason, 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Robert Wason 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Waldeck, Arthur (1936-19??) - -[intermediate provenance unknown] - - Arthur Waldeck Collection, Scherman Music Library, The New School, New York (19?? - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Jeanette Schenker;  Image: Arthur Waldeck Collection, Scherman Music Library, The New School, New York; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Robert Wason.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 03/09/1936 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Broder ~ JSchenker","Waldeck ~ H+JSchenker","Waldeck ~ JSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Jeanette Schenker to Arthur Waldeck and Nathan Broder, dated March 9, 1936</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-01-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>JS acks receipt of article by Waldeck and Broder, and thanks them;  she reports on the establishment of the Schenker-Institut in Vienna.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Jeanette;  Waldeck, Arthur;  Broder, Nathan;  article;  Schenker-Institut, Vienna</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Vienna</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> </marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jeanette Schenker to Arthur Waldeck and Nathan Broder, dated March 9, 1936</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrte Herren,</tei:p><tei:p>Nehmen Sie meinen verbindlichsten Dank für die Uebersendung Ihres Artikels, vor allem aber für den umfänglichen Artikel selbst,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Arthur Waldeck &amp; Nathan Broder “Musical Synthesis as Expounded by Heinrich Schenker,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Musical Mercury</tei:hi> 2/4 (1935): 56–64: a copy, along with a two-page typescript summary in German, both catalogued among Jonas’s personal  teaching materials, survives as OJ 58/22.  The cataloguing appears to be correct, since the article is a negative photocopy, not a “presentation copy” from the mid 1930s.  Most likely, the presentation copy is lost.  In any case, there can be no doubt of the identity of the article to which Mrs. Schenker refers: Waldeck and Broder start their work by citing the only three articles in English that they know of (agreeing with modern bibliographers), and all others are by single authors.  Furthermore, the authors write that Schenker himself has recommended Jonas’s book to them (“Musical Synthesis,” p. 57; c.f., OJ 5/44 [4], above). </tei:note> der eben bei einem Uebersetzer ist, weil mein Englisch noch nicht auf der erforderlichen Stufe ist.</tei:p><tei:p>Jedenfalls ist es so, wie Sie im letzten Absatz es zusammengefaßt haben:  Weiteste Musikerkreise müssen für die Ideen Schenkers, für den Begriff Schenker gewonnen werden<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> Mrs. Schenker likely refers to the last <tei:hi rend="italic">two</tei:hi> paragraphs of the article, which read:  “Even if Schenker had stopped short of the basic line, his works would be of incalculable value to the musician.  For even the earliest books are full of flashes of the keenest insight into the nature of the music in hand. And while it is difficult to trace the course of the basic line, few difficulties are offered by the smaller spans; and it is these, as has been said, that constitute the most important means for gaining inner coherence. / ‘<tei:hi rend="italic">Der Freie Satz</tei:hi>’ presents a systematic exposition of Schenker’s technique. We have not attempted to summarize all of that technique. We have not even exhausted the subject of the span.  We have tried only to give the reader an indication of the nature of Schenker’s work.  If the reader’s interest and curiosity have been aroused, our goal has been attained.” (“Musical Synthesis,” p. 64)</tei:note> u. ich wünsche Ihnen, daß Ihr Aufsatz kräftigstes Echo finde!</tei:p><tei:p>Es dürfte Sie interessiren zu erfahren, daß das Wiener Schenker-Institut<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> The Schenker-Institut opened a few months after Schenker’s death in the Neues Wiener Konservatorium (which has remained “Konservatorium der Stadt Wien” to the present day), and lasted until October, 1938.  Oswald Jonas, Moritz Violin and Felix Salzer were all involved in its founding.  See the contemporaneous announcement of its opening (Carl Bamberger, “Das Schenker-Institut am Neuen Wiener Konservatorium,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Musikblättter des Anbruch</tei:hi> 18/1 (1936), pp. 7–8), and Evelyn Fink-Mennel’s recent discussion of the pedagogy of Schenkerian theory and analysis in Vienna (“Das Schenker-Institut und der Lehrgang für Tonsatz nach Heinrich Schenker:  Zur Wiener Schenker-Tradition,” in <tei:hi rend="italic">Schenker-Traditionen</tei:hi>, ed. Martin Eybl &amp; Evelyn Fink-Mennel (Vienna: Böhlau Verlag, 2006), pp.  155–68).</tei:note> sich <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> ganz schön einführt u. die Schülerzahl, wenn man die kunstfeindlichen Verhältnisse bedenkt, ziemlich befriedigend ist.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich danke Ihnen auch herzlich für Ihre guten Wünsche – ich trauere wie am ersten Tag nach dem Ableben um den gütigen, großen Menschen u. Künstler, dem Gattin, Freundin u. Gehilfin zu sein mir ein gütiges Geschick vergönnt hatte.</tei:p><tei:p>Beste Empfehlungen von
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Frau Dr. Heinrich Schenker</tei:p><tei:p>Wien, den 9. März 1936</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jeanette Schenker to Arthur Waldeck and Nathan Broder, dated March 9, 1936</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Gentlemen,</tei:p><tei:p>[Please] accept my most sincere thanks for sending your article, and above all, for the extensive article itself,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> which is presently with a translator, since my English is not yet at the necessary level.</tei:p><tei:p>In any case, it is just as you have summarized the matter in the last paragraph:  musical circles far and wide must be won over to Schenker’s ideas, and to the very idea of Schenker[‘s work].<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  I hope that your article finds strong response.</tei:p><tei:p>It may interest you to know that the Vienna Schenker-Institute<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> has started up smoothly, and the number of students—when one considers the anti-artistic situation—is reasonably satisfactory.</tei:p><tei:p>I also thank you cordially for your good wishes.  I mourn just as on the first day after the passing of that good and great man and artist;  a gracious destiny has permitted me to be wife, friend and helper to him.</tei:p><tei:p>With best regards,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Frau Dr. Heinrich Schenker</tei:p><tei:p>Vienna, March 9, 1936</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>