<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:NYma, [2] : 11-8-32 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  In the public domain.
©  Transcription Ian Bent, 2007.
©  Translation Robert Wason, 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Robert Wason &amp; Ian Bent 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Waldeck, Arthur (1932-19??) - -[intermediate provenance unknown] - -Arthur Waldeck Collection, Scherman Music Library, The New School, New York (19?? - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker;  Image: Arthur Waldeck Collection, Scherman Music Library, The New School, New York; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Robert Wason &amp; Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 11/08/1932 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Waldeck ~ H+JSchenker","Waldeck ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Waldeck, dated November 8, 1932</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-01-09</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>S sets out conditions for a translation of his Harmonielehre by W; asks if W knows Weisse, Lytle, and others; informs him of Dunn and his translation of S's Kontrapunkt.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich; Waldeck, Arthur; Universal Edition; copyright;  David Mannes School; Weisse, Hans; Lytle, Victor Vaughn; Oberlin College; Dunn, John Petrie; Edinburgh; Kontrapunkt; Counterpoint; Harmonielehre; Theory of Harmony;  Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst;  Vienna Conservatory</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Waldeck, in Jeanette Schenker’s hand,  dated November 8, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">The draft of this fair copy is</tei:hi> OJ 5/44, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Schenker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (Stuttgart: J. G. Cotta, 1906) = <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:hi>, vol. I.  </tei:note>]</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Waldeck!</tei:p><tei:p>Endlich bin ich in der Lage, Ihnen die gewünschte Auskunft geben zu können.   Unbewandert in urheberrechtlichen Fragen habe ich mich an meinen Verlag<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  UE, Vienna.  The firm’s Director, Emil Hertzka, had died on May 9, 1932;  S presumably turned to one of the three men who replaced him: Dr. Alfred Kalmus, Hugo Winter, or possibly Hans Heinsheimer.   </tei:note> gewendet u. wiederhole hier, was er zu dieser Angelegenheit erklärte.  Ich würde Ihnen die Uebersetzungsrechte der „Harmonielehre”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Schenker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (Stuttgart: J. G. Cotta, 1906) = <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:hi>, vol. I.  </tei:note> für die englische Sprache unter folgenden Bedingungen überlassen:</tei:p><tei:p><!-- bq. --> 1.) Bezahlung einer Ladenpreis-Tantieme: 10% des amerikanischen bezw. englischen Ladenpreises garantiert mit einer Tantieme für 1000 Exemplare.  Da ich annehme, daß der Ladenpreis für Amerika <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> zwischen 3 u. 4 Dollars festgesetzt werden wird, so wäre bei Abschluß des Vertrages ein Betrag von 300 bis 400 Dollars an mich zu entrichten.  Die Verrechnung für alle verkauften Exemplare hätte halbjährig im Monat Jänner u. Juli zu erfolgen.</tei:p><tei:p><!-- bq. --> 2.) Vor Drucklegung ersuche ich um Uebermittlung einer Uebersetzungsprobe, etwa 20–30 Seiten, u. nach Druck um fünf Belegexemplare.</tei:p><tei:p><!-- bq. --> 3.) Auf den Exemplaren hat der Vermerk  „Mit Genehmigung des Autors [<tei:hi rend="italic">deletion</tei:hi>] bezw. des Original-Verlags Universal-Edition A.G. Wien”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  The sole publisher of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (1906) had been J. G. Cotta of Stuttgart, although Cotta ceded the continuation of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:hi> to UE in 1921 (OJ 9/31, [46] and [47], February 5 and 21, 1921;  CA 194–195, February 21, 1921), canceling their contract with Schenker and forwarding all stocks-in-hand of <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> and the first volume of <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt</tei:hi> to UE.  </tei:note> aufgedruckt zu werden.  Die Eintragung des amerikanischen Copyrights soll nach Möglichkeit in <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> meinem Namen erfolgen.</tei:p><tei:p><!-- bq. --> 4.) Die Berechtigung gilt für den Vertrieb in allen englischsprechenden Ländern, die Verrechnung soll in U. S. A. in Dollars, für die andern englisch sprechenden Länder in englischen Pfund erfolgen.  Bei Einsendung der Uebersetzungsprobe bitte ich um Bekanntgabe des Verlages.</tei:p><tei:p>Sind Sie vielleicht in Verbindung mit der David Mannes School in New York<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  David Mannes School, New York [create profile and link].  </tei:note> u. kennen Sie meinen Schüler Dr. Hans Weisse,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.  </tei:note> der dort lehrt?  Kennen Sie vielleicht Prof. Lytle<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="lytle_victor_vaughn">Victor Vaughn Lytle</ref>.  </tei:note> in Oberlin, Ohio,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Oberlin College, Ohio [create profile and link].  </tei:note> der auch meine Theorien vorträgt?  Und die anderen Lehrer in New York, die sich mir angeschlossen haben?</tei:p><tei:p>An der Universität in Edinburgh<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  University of Edinburgh, Scotland;  the Reid Professor of Music from 1914 to 1940 was Donald Francis Tovey.  </tei:note> <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> hat der in England sehr geschätzte Prof. John Petri Dunn (†)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="dunn_john_petrie">John Petrie Dunn</ref>.  </tei:note> meinen Kontrapunkt Bd. I<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt</tei:hi>, vol. 1 (Stuttgart: J. G. Cotta, 1910) = <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:hi>, vol.  II/1.  Dunn translated only <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt</tei:hi>, vol. 2 (Vienna: UE, 1922); see David Carson Berry, <tei:hi rend="italic">A Topical Guide to Schenkerian Literature</tei:hi> (Hillsdale, NY: Pendragon, 2004), p. 448.</tei:note> übersetzt, allerdings nur für seinen Gebrauch an der Universität.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit Freuden würde ich es begrüßen, wenn Sie sich zur Uebersetzung der Harmonielehre<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Schenker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (Stuttgart: J. G. Cotta, 1906) = <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:hi>, vol. I.  </tei:note> entschließen könnten.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit ausgezeichneter Hochachtung
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  H Schenker</tei:p><tei:p>Wien, 8. Nov. 1932</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in HS’s hand:</tei:hi>]
Dieser Tage [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] erreichte mich die Mitteilung, daß die Harmonielehre<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Schenker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (Stuttgart: J. G. Cotta, 1906) = <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:hi>, vol. I.  </tei:note> von mir obligater Lehrstoff an unserer Musikakademie<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  The Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst, from 1924 the Hochschule für Musik und darstellende Kunst, i.e. the Vienna Conservatory.  [create profile and link].  </tei:note> wird, was nun auch für Sie nicht ohne Interesse sein dürfte.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Waldeck, in Jeanette Schenker’s hand,  dated November 8, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">The draft of this fair copy is</tei:hi> OJ 5/44, <tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>]</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Mr. Waldeck,</tei:p><tei:p>At last I am in a position to give you the desired information.  Unfamiliar with questions of copyright law, I turned to my publisher,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> and repeat here what he explained in this regard.  I would give you the translation rights of <tei:hi rend="italic">Theory of Harmony</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> under the following conditions:</tei:p><tei:p><!-- bq. --> 1.) Payment of a royalty on the retail price: 10% of the American or English retail price, guaranteed by a royalty payment for 1,000 copies.  Since I assume that the American retail price will be set at <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> between 3 and 4 dollars, a payment of 300 to 400 dollars is to be sent to me upon completion of the contract.  The accounting for all copies sold is to be settled on a half-year basis in the months of January and July.</tei:p><tei:p><!-- bq. --> 2.) Before printing, I request submission of a translation sample of 20-30 pages, and after printing, five proof copies.</tei:p><tei:p><!-- bq. --> 3.) The notice,  “With Permission of the Author and of the Original Publisher, Universal Edition, &amp; Co., Vienna”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> must be printed on every copy.  The American copyright is to be entered <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> in my name, if possible.</tei:p><tei:p><!-- bq. --> 4.) The permission is valid for sales in all English-speaking countries;  the payment for U. S. sales is to be in dollars, and in English pounds for all other English-speaking countries. Please inform me of the name of the publisher when you send the sample translation.</tei:p><tei:p>Are you perhaps in contact with the David Mannes School in New York<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>, and do you know my student, Dr. Hans Weisse<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>, who teaches there?  Do you perhaps know Prof. Lytle<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> in Oberlin, Ohio<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>, who also teaches my theories?  And [do you know] the other teachers in New York who have adopted my ideas?</tei:p><tei:p>At the University of Edinburgh,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Prof. John Petrie Dunn (†),<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> who is well-regarded in England, has translated my <tei:hi rend="italic">Counterpoint</tei:hi>, vol. I<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/>, though only for his own use at the University.</tei:p><tei:p>I would be most happy if you should decide to translate my <tei:hi rend="italic">Theory of Harmony</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/></tei:p><tei:p>Most respectfully,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] H. Schenker</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in HS’s hand:</tei:hi>]
I was recently informed that my <tei:hi rend="italic">Theory of Harmony</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> has been made a required text at our Academy of Music, <tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> which may not be without interest to you.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>