<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 5/18, 41 : 4-23-34 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Oswald Jonas (1934-1978)—Special Collections, University of California, Riverside (1978-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: Special Collections, University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 04/23/1934 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated April 23, 1934</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-09-01</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Der Freie Satz is completed. S is pleased that Hoboken has come round;  gives Weisse's address; S has ordered five copies of J's book;  reports that Salzer has completed a new book;  questions J about his new plan, but welcomes it; Oppel may not realize that S is a Jew.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Jonas, Oswald;  Der freie Satz;  Free Composition;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  recommendation;  Weisse, Hans;  New York;  Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks; Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers;   Salzer, Felix;  Saturn-Verlag;  Sinn und Wesen der abendländischen Mehrstimmigkeit;  Goos;  Oppel, Reinhard;  Jew</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated April 23, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>23.4.34</tei:p><tei:p>Geehrter, lieber Herr <tei:hi rend="italic">D^r^ Jonas</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>Vorigen Freitag habe ich das letzte Notenbeispiel eingetragen u. damit ist der “fr. S”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi>: <tei:hi rend="italic">NMTP</tei:hi> III, published UE, 1935.  Cf. OJ 5/18 35, January 9, 1934, and 37, March 19, 1934.</tei:note> abgeschlossen.  Letzte Durchsicht u. Drucklegung werden mir u. meiner Frau noch genug zu tun geben!</tei:p><tei:p>Daß <tei:hi rend="italic">v. H.</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> Ihnen zuletzt doch entgegen[ge]kommen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  See OJ 12/6, [31], April 15, 1934, to which this letter is the reply.</tei:note> ist, freut mich sehr, es ist ein gutes Zeichen, doppelt hoch zu werten, da er sich nun entschlossen hat, bei uns in Wien zu bleiben u. zu – <tei:hi rend="italic">bauen</tei:hi>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Cf. OJ 5/18, 13, September 7, 1932.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Furtw.’s<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Wilhelm Furtwängler [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> Empfehlung wird von grosser Durchschlagskraft sein, schon daß er überhaupt <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> mittut, kommt dem Verfasser zugute, besonders unter den ^Musik-^Händen von heute.  Er hat mir telephonisch den Besuch für später angekündigt.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Weisse</tei:hi>’s<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.</tei:note>  Adresse lautet:</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">1 W 64th New-York U.S.A.</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Er schickte mir neulich eine neue Klv-Vl. Sonate ein, die ich noch zu lesen habe.</tei:p><tei:p>Vergessen Sie die von mir erbetenen 5 <tei:hi rend="italic">Ex.</tei:hi> nicht, ich weiß heute nicht mehr, ob ich sie beim Verlag bestellt habe oder nicht.  Genügt es, daß ich Sie bitte, den Verlag hierüber zu informieren, oder muß ich an den Verlag schreiben?</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">D^r^ Salzer</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="salzer_felix">Felix Salzer</ref>.</tei:note> hat kürzlich eine musikhistorische <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Arbeit<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Subsequently published as <tei:hi rend="italic">Sinn und Wesen der abendländischen Mehrstimmigkeit</tei:hi> (Vienna: Saturn Verlag, 1935).</tei:note> vollendet, die er mir demnächst zeigen wird; er trägt sich mit dem Plan diese Arbeit, versteht sich auf eigene Kosten, dem Saturn-Verlag zu übergeben, worin ich ^ihn^ sehr unterstützt habe.  Das schlägt ja auch in Ihren Plan ein, es wäre der Sammelpunkt des Verlages ein Zeichen der Einheit.</tei:p><tei:p>Noch verstehe ich Sie nicht recht: gedenken Sie ^auch^ <tei:hi rend="italic">Notentexte</tei:hi> erscheinen zu lassen, ist das möglich, um so billigen Preis Musik u. Einführung herzustellen u. zu verbreiten?  Unter allen Umständen begrüßte ich die Idee auf das Wärmste, so oder so <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> ist die Zeit meiner Ansicht nach längst reif, aus meinen Anregungen u. Leistungen, die Allen zugute[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] kommen, auch bares Geld (Geld ist zu wenig gesagt) zu gewinnen.  Seit jeher sprach ich diese Überlegung aus, für naive Gemüter drückte ich es ländlich-sittlich mit den Worten aus: “Ich bin eine gute Kuh, die viel u. gute Milch gibt, da die werden die Menschen gern darauf greifen.”</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Goos</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  See also OJ 12/6, [31], April 15, 1934;  Goos was a pupil of Reinhard Oppel; in July 1933, S had written to Oppel asking whether he might write to Goos (Oppel F57, July 28, 1933).  ).  Already on April 27, 1933, Oppel had reported to S that Goos himself teaches S's theory, and that he had assembled a "Schenker week" for presentation on the radio.  In other correspondence, it appears to have been considered expedient that Goos not learn that S was Jewish.</tei:note> ist Schüler von <tei:hi rend="italic">Oppel</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Rheinhard Oppel [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> (<tei:hi rend="italic">Leipzig</tei:hi>) u. hat von diesem über alle Worte trefflichen Menschen eine ungewöhnliche Verehrung übernommen.  Er hat eine <tei:hi rend="italic">Schule</tei:hi> u. lehrt -doch- dort <tei:hi rend="italic">Schenker</tei:hi>; er ist uns sehr, sehr <tei:hi rend="italic">gierig</tei:hi> u. dürfte keine Ahnung haben, daß ich Jude bin: seine Schule feiert <tei:hi rend="italic">Schenker</tei:hi>-“Feste,” das wäre denn doch nicht möglich, wüßte er, was Sie wissen.</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">upper margin, inverted:</tei:hi> ]
Nun glaube ich Alles beantwortet zu haben – halt, <tei:hi rend="italic">H.</tei:hi> ist schon wieder auf Reisen – u. grüße Sie in unser Beider Namen auf das Beste</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr  
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] <tei:hi rend="italic">H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated April 23, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>April 23, 1934</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Dr. Jonas,</tei:p><tei:p>Last Friday I entered the last musical example, and thereby <tei:hi rend="italic">Free Composition</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> is completed.  Final review and printing will still give my wife and me plenty to do!</tei:p><tei:p>It pleases me greatly that Hoboken<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> has finally come round<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>; it is a good sign, to be valued doubly as he has now decided to stay here in Vienna and—to <tei:hi rend="italic">build</tei:hi> here!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/></tei:p><tei:p>Furtwängler’s<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> recommendation will be  greatly effective; the very fact that he cooperates at all benefits the author, especially among the musical powers of the present day.  He notified me by telephone of his coming visit.</tei:p><tei:p>Weisse’s<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> address is:</tei:p><tei:p>1 W 64th [St.], New-York, U.S.A.</tei:p><tei:p>He recently sent me a new piano-violin sonata, which I have still to read.</tei:p><tei:p>Don’t forget the five copies I requested; I don’t know any more whether I ordered them from the publisher or not.  Is it sufficient that I ask you to relay this to the publisher, or must I write to the publisher myself?</tei:p><tei:p>Dr. Salzer<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> has just completed a music-historical work,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> which he will show me presently; he plans, naturally at his own expense, to send this work to Saturn-Verlag, which I have strongly supported.  That fits well with your plan; the focal point of the publisher would be a sign of unity.</tei:p><tei:p>I still don’t understand you fully: are you thinking of having <tei:hi rend="italic">musical text</tei:hi> published as well?  Is it possible, for such a low price, to present and distribute music and commentary together?  In any case I would greet the idea most warmly; one way or another, in my opinion, the time is ripe to realize some hard cash (“cash” is not saying enough) from my efforts and achievements, which benefit everything.  I have expressed this conviction all along; for naive souls I put it in rustic terms with the words “I am a good cow that gives good milk and much of it; people will want to lap it up.”</tei:p><tei:p>Goos<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> is a student of Oppel<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> (Leipzig) and has developed, thanks to that indescribably excellent human, an extraordinary reverence.  He has a <tei:hi rend="italic">school</tei:hi> and teaches Schenker there; he is very, very <tei:hi rend="italic">hungry</tei:hi> for us and may have no notion that I am a Jew: his school celebrates Schenker “festivals,” which would not be possible if he knew what you know.</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">upside down at top of page:</tei:hi>]
Now I think I have answered everything—no, wait, Hoboken is traveling again—and I greet you most warmly on the part of both of us.</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H. Schenker</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>