<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 5/18, 17 : Nov/Dec 1931 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Oswald Jonas (1932-1978)—Special Collections, University of California, Riverside (1978-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: Special Collections, University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 12/01/1932 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, incorrectly dated by recipient as September 1932; actual date ?c.December 1, 1932</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-06-19</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Discusses likely sales for J's Das Wesen, and will himself help promote the book; warns J against Hoboken.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Jonas, Oswald;  Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks;   Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers;  subscriptions; sales;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  Berg, Frl.;  Hertzka, Emil;  Universal Edition;  UE;  Marx, Josef;  textbook;  Stöhr, Richard;  Harmonielehre;  Einstein, Alfred</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, incorrectly dated by recipient as September 1932; actual date ?c.December 1, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in hand of recipient:</tei:hi>] Sept 32<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  This date is incorrect; the letter is clearly a reply to 12/6, [17], of November 27, 1932.  I thank Hellmut Federhofer for help with the transcription of this and a few other items.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Geehrter, lieber Herr D^r^ <tei:hi rend="italic">Jonas</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>Kein Zweifel ist mir, daß das Buch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Jonas’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks: Eine Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers</tei:hi> (Vienna: Saturn-Verlag, 1934).</tei:note> mehr gekauft würde, als die Subscription heute beträgt.  Das ewige <tei:hi rend="italic">Hysteron Proteron</tei:hi>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  “The later [becomes] the earlier.”</tei:note>   Bei den Meisten ist nur Trägheit im Spiele, sie sagen sich, sie “werden ja . . . .”</tei:p><tei:p>Wegen <tei:hi rend="italic">v. Hob</tei:hi>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> ist guter Rat teuer.  Vielleicht kommt er Anfang Jänner nach Wien (2 Stunden der Woche hat er ja noch immer bestellt), u. erklärt <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> sich dann näher. Vorläufig sehe ich nur die Lust “hinauszuschieben u. zu überlegen.”  Nun es kommt nicht so sehr auf Ihre Vorschläge an, – beide sind möglich u. gut: das Heruntersetzen der <tei:hi rend="italic">Exempl</tei:hi>., wie das Darlehen – sondern auf die <tei:hi rend="italic">Stimmung <tei:hi rend="italic">Hob</tei:hi>’s</tei:hi>. Er macht jetzt eine wirkliche Kur durch, Frl. Boy<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Cf. OJ 5/18, 13.</tei:note> heiratet er doch nicht, ob das Alles etwas ihm bedeutet u. wieviel, wird kein Mensch beurteilen können, er ist unentzifferbar “dekadent.”   Also kann ich Ihnen <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> wieder nur äusserste Vorsicht empfehlen, wie ich sie auch selbst ihm gegenüber wahre, er lauert förmlich auf den leisesten Fehltritt . .  Denn in Einem hat er Recht: Meine Sache müßte eine deutsche, nationale Wiedergeburts-Angelegenheit sein, ^dürfte^ nicht auf zwei Augen eines Ausländers stehen.  Was kostete <tei:hi rend="italic">Hertzka</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Emil Hertzka, Director of UE from 1907 to his death in 1932. [create biogfile and link]</tei:note> die <tei:hi rend="italic">Propaganda</tei:hi> für die Zerstörer, was lassen sich[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] die Verlage ^u. Ministerien^ noch heute kosten, die verlorene Sache zu halten, nur gerade der “Meister”kurs in der Musik sollte von den Ärmsten u. Unorganisierten allein <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> getragen werden?! Schon nur mit 20. bis 25.000 Sch. wäre ja allen Nöten der Grippe geholfen, die sich die Rettung der Musik-Substanz heute angelegen sein lassen!</tei:p><tei:p>Marx<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on: <ref cRef="marx_joseph">Joseph Marx</ref>.</tei:note> ist für 2 Monate nach der Türkei gegangen.  Die “<tei:hi rend="italic">U.E.</tei:hi>” wird sich wahrscheinlich überlegen, das “Lehrbuch”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Probably the proposed “school-edition” of Schenker’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi>; see OJ 5/18, 22 and 24.</tei:note> zu finanzieren, wenn es nur für die ”Kompositions”klasse, nicht ^allgemein^ statt der Hml. von Stöhr<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Richard Stöhr, <tei:hi rend="italic">Praktischer Leitfaden der Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (Vienna: UE, 1909), UE 2013.</tei:note> in Verwendung kommen sollte.</tei:p><tei:p>Kurz: ich luge nach Subscribenten aus, nach Mäzenen, mache Wege, schriebe, posaune, ein andermal über das Ergebnis.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  i.e., about Jonas’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks</tei:hi>.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Hat Einstein<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Click on <ref cRef="einstein_alfred">Alfred Einstein</ref>.</tei:note> endlich etwas gebracht?</tei:p><tei:p>Mit bestem Gruß    
Ihr  
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, incorrectly dated by recipient as September 1932; actual date ?c.December 1, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in hand of recipient:</tei:hi>] Sept 32<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Dr. Jonas,</tei:p><tei:p>I have no doubt that the book<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> would be purchased more than the subscriptions add up to at present.  The eternal <tei:hi rend="italic">Hysteron Proteron</tei:hi>!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  With most people it is only a product of laziness; they say they “will get around to it . . .”</tei:p><tei:p>Regarding v. Hoboken,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> good news is hard to come by.  Perhaps he will come to Vienna at the beginning of  January (he has registered for two lessons per week) and tell us <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> more.  For now I see only the wish to “postpone and to think about it.”  Now it is not so much a question of your suggestions—both are possible and good: the reduction of the number of copies, as well as the loan—but rather of <tei:hi rend="italic">Hoboken’s frame of mind</tei:hi>.  He is now going through a real cure; but he will not marry Miss Boy,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> although all of that has some meaning for him, and just how much, no mortal will be able to judge—he is indecipherably “decadent.”  Thus I can <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> again only advise you to use most extreme caution, as even I myself observe in dealing with him; he literally lurks in wait for the slightest misstep.  For in one thing he is right: my cause would have to be a German, national rebirth-event, ^it could^ not depend on two eyes of a foreigner.  How much has it cost Hertzka<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> to propagandize for the destructors, how much do the publishers^and ministries^ have to pay to prop up the lost cause, and just the “masters” course in music is supposed to be <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> borne by the poorest and the disorganized?!  With only about 20-25,000 schillings all symptoms would be remedied of the affliction that would be the concern of the rescue of musical substance today!</tei:p><tei:p>Marx<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> has gone to Turkey for two months.  Universal Edition will probably decide to finance the “textbook”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> if it is to be used only for the “composition” class, not ^generally^ in place of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> by Stöhr.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/></tei:p><tei:p>In a word: I will seek out subscribers, patrons, open avenues, write, and advertize about the product<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> at another time.</tei:p><tei:p>Has Einstein<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> finally published anything?</tei:p><tei:p>With best greeting,
Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H. Schenker</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>