<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 5/18, 23 : 2-7-33 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Oswald Jonas (1933-1978)—Special Collections, University of California, Riverside (1978-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: Special Collections, University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 02/07/1933 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated February 7, 1933</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-06-30</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>S returns four essays with praise.  Salzer is informed that the price for J's Einführung has been set too high; S advises caution with Hoboken.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Jonas, Oswald;  Aufsätze;  essays;  Berlin;  Vienna;  Salzer, Felix;  Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks;  Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  Ungar, Fritz;  UE;  Drei Masken Verlag;  Meisterwerk in der Musik;  Masterwork in Music;  Jahrbuch;  Yearbook;  Brahms;  Simrock</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated February 7, 1933</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Geehrter, lieber Herr D^r^ <tei:hi rend="italic">Jonas</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>Mit bestem Dank stelle ich Ihnen die 4 Aufsätze zurück.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Enclosed with OJ 12/6, [19], January 28, 1933.</tei:note>  Ich kann mir heute wohl ersparen, Ihre treffenden Darstellungen zu loben u. dgl. Jedenfalls haben Sie Recht darauf, daß Sie in <tei:hi rend="italic">Berlin</tei:hi> viel mehr Möglichkeiten haben als in Wien.  Wo könnten Sie das alles in Wien unterbringen, wo fänden Sie 4 Schüler eines <tei:hi rend="italic">Bertrams</tei:hi>?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Cf. OJ 12/6, [19] and [30], January 28, 1933 and March 16, 1934.</tei:note>  Die Selbstanbetung, das Selbst-Genie der <tei:hi rend="italic">Wiener</tei:hi> schafft unübersteigliche Geistes-Zellschranken.</tei:p><tei:p>Nun aber ein sehr Wichtiges: D^r^ <tei:hi rend="italic">Salzer</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on: <ref cRef="salzer_felix">Felix Salzer</ref></tei:note> sagte mir in der letzten Stunde, da ich von Ihnen sprach, er sei von unterrichteter Seite informiert worden, der Preis Ihrer “Einf.” sei zu hoch angesetzt oder ä[hnliches].  <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Ich verstehe nichts davon, bin daher immer betrogen worden, möchte -ich- Ihnen aber  ^u.^ Ihrem Vetter<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Dr. Fritz Ungar, proprietor of Saturn-Verlag.  Cf. OJ 12/6, [13], [15], [37], and [43].</tei:note> empfehlen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  "empfehlen": originally written before the three preceding words, then inserted by an arrow into the position given here.</tei:note> wegen <tei:hi rend="italic">Hob</tei:hi>’s<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> eine besonders vorsichtige Haltung in Ihrem Interesse einzunehmen.  Wer davon so wie ich unterrichtet ist, wie <tei:hi rend="italic">Hob</tei:hi>. immer Gespenster von Übervorteilung sucht, wie er tückigsten Haß empfindet, wenn er eine findet, müß Sie warnen: denn genau so wie D^r^ <tei:hi rend="italic">Salzer</tei:hi> plötzlich ^von^ irgendwoher eine Auskunft obiger Art erhält, kann ja auch <tei:hi rend="italic">Hob</tei:hi>. eine ähnliche erhalten.  (Übrigens hat er mir so etwas schon einmal sehr, sehr zart angedeutet).  Also Vorsicht, Vorsicht!</tei:p><tei:p>Soeben erleb&lt;strike&gt;e&lt;/strike&gt;^te ich, daß die “<tei:hi rend="italic">U.E.</tei:hi>” für sich 70^o^ beansprüchte, sich schliesslich mit 50^o^ begnügt, natürlich ist es kaufmännischer, bei höherem Preis die Investition in kürzerer Zeit heranzukriegen, aber <tei:hi rend="italic">Hob</tei:hi>. muß vorsichtig behandelt werden.  Haben ^nicht^ die 3 M[asken] für Jb  I, II,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Schenker’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi> I and II (Munich: Drei Masken Verlag, 1925, 1926).</tei:note> den Preis von 18 S angesetzt, es geht aber auch um 10 S. (III. Jb.) das war auch die ewige Klage von <tei:hi rend="italic">Brahms</tei:hi> gegen Simrock, der zu hohe Preise machte.  Beste [<tei:hi rend="italic">upside down in top margin:</tei:hi> Grüße und Wünsche von uns Beiden</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr  
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] <tei:hi rend="italic">H Schenker</tei:hi>]
7.II.33</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated February 7, 1933</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Dr. Jonas,</tei:p><tei:p>With many thanks I return the four essays<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> to you.  I can spare myself the time today to praise your excellent presentations etc.  In any case you are right that in Berlin you have many more possibilities than in Vienna.  Where could you accomplish all of that in Vienna—where would you find four students of a Bertram?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  The self-adulation, the egotism of the Viennese poses insurmountable narrowness of mind.</tei:p><tei:p>But here is something very important: Dr. Salzer<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> told me in the last lesson, as I spoke of you, that he had been advised by an informed source that the price of your <tei:hi rend="italic">Introduction</tei:hi> was set too high or some such thing. <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> I don’t understand anything about that, have therefore always been deceived, but would like to recommend<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> to you and your cousin<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> that in your interest particular caution be used in dealing with Hoboken.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/>  Anybody who, like me, is instructed in how Hoboken always looks for phantoms of cupidity, and how he perceives the most deceitful hatred when he finds one, would have to warn you: because just as Dr. Salzer suddenly, from wherever, gets information of the foregoing sort, Hoboken too can get similar information.  (Incidentally, he once already hinted as much to me in a very, very delicate way.)  Thus, caution, caution!</tei:p><tei:p>I have just learned that UE requires 70% for itself, but is in the end satisfied with 50%; naturally it is better commercial strategy to recoup the investment in a shorter time with a higher price, but Hoboken must be handled carefully.  Didn’t Drei-Masken Verlag set the price of the first and second Jahrbuch<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> at 18 S., but 10 S. is alright too (third Jahrbuch).  That was Brahms’s continual complaint about Simrock, that he set the prices too high.  Best [<tei:hi rend="italic">upside down in top margin:</tei:hi>  greetings and wishes from both of us,</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H. Schenker]
February 2, 1933</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>