<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 5/18, 9 : 4-9-32 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Oswald Jonas (1932-1978)—Special Collections, University of California, Riverside (1978-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: Special Collections, University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 04/09/1932 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated April 9, 1932</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-05-08</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>S has presented Furtwängler with a copy of Brahms's preparation of Handel's Saul, and has told him of J's plan for F. to perform it and asked him to give J access to the score.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Jonas, Oswald;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Handel;  Saul;  Elias, Angelika;  Angi;  articulation;  dynamics;  continuo;  Mandyczewsky, Eusebius;  Löwe, Ferdinand;  Schalk, Franz;  score;  plan;  Posemuckel;  Einstein, Alfred</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Vienna</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated April 9, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Wien, 9 April [/] 1932</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr <tei:hi rend="italic">D^r^ Jonas</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>Gestern war D^r^ Furtwängler<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Wilhelm Furtwängler [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> bei mir u. ich übergab ihm die Kopie der <tei:hi rend="italic">Brahms</tei:hi>’schen Saul-Einrichtung,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  See OJ 12/6, 11.</tei:note> versteht sich, die einzige Kopie, zum Geschenk, zur Erinnerung und Anregung.  D^r^ F. wird reiches Material darin finden u. ich habe die Genugtuung, das Werk zu <tei:hi rend="italic">retten</tei:hi>!  Frl. <tei:hi rend="italic">Elias</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="elias_angelika">Angelika Elias</ref>.</tei:note> hat 3 Monate lang unter ^ <tei:hi rend="italic">meiner</tei:hi> ^ <tei:hi rend="italic">strengsten</tei:hi> [ <tei:hi rend="italic">corr. from</tei:hi> strengster] <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrolle</tei:hi> die Kopie “diplomatisch getreu” besorgt, das will -aber- in meinem Falle <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> sagen, daß ich für die Lesart (das oft sehr schwierigen Schreiben mit Bleistift) in aller Form gutstehe.  Alles ist sogar topographisch genau nachgebildet.</tei:p><tei:p>Vieles habe ich D^r^ F. zeigen können, die schönsten der Artikulation, Dynamisierung, des <tei:hi rend="italic">continuo</tei:hi>, usw.  Nun sprach ich von Ihrer Absicht<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  See OJ 12/6, 11.</tei:note> u. bat ihn, Ihnen den Einblick in die Part. zu gewähren.</tei:p><tei:p>Die Stimmen könnte ich nicht einsehen, denn schon zu viel schien es mir, wenn ich das Original – hinter dem Rücken D^r^ <tei:hi rend="italic">Mandyczewsky’s</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="mandyczewski_eusebiu">Eusebius Mandyczewski</ref>.</tei:note> der ^es^ mir aus Neid [ <tei:hi rend="italic">corr. from</tei:hi> aus Neid mir] verweigert hatte – 3 Monate zu Haus behielt!  Die Stimmen liegen <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> zu Tiefst, in den Kellern.  Auch dürfte D^r^ F. Recht damit haben, daß die Stimmen längst nicht mehr im Zustand <tei:hi rend="italic">de dato</tei:hi> Brahms sind, die andere Dirigenten (wie üblich) gewiß ihre Eintragungen haben machen lassen, zumal sie für[ <tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi> ] die[ <tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi> ] Stimmen des Meisters kein Verständnis aufbrachten, wie mir gegenüber <tei:hi rend="italic">Löwe</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="lowe_ferdinand">Ferdinand Löwe</ref>.</tei:note> u. <tei:hi rend="italic">Schalk</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="schalk_franz">Franz Schalk</ref>. </tei:note> es ausdrücklich erklärt haben.  Es erforderte vielleicht ein Viertel Leben, all diesen Dingen nachzugehen.  Wo Generationen sündigen in Unverstand u. Zerstörung ist ein schweres Versäumnis oft nicht mehr -einzuholen- ^gutzumachen^!</tei:p><tei:p>Wohl aber wäre es möglich, daß Sie [ <tei:hi rend="italic">alt. from</tei:hi> die] die Arbeit von Br’s nach Einsicht- <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> nahme der Part. (u. ^nun^ auch auf Einwilligung H D^r^ F.) in einem, zwei Aufsätzen würdigen u. des Meisters Mühen u. Sorgen, seinerzeit an ein Dummvolk vergeudet, ^zum 1. Male^ würdigen u. dem Lohn zuführen.  Doch suchen Sie sich erst der Zeitung zu <tei:hi rend="italic">vergewissern</tei:hi>, bevor Sie die Arbeit in Angriff nehmen!  Das rate ich Ihnen gut!  Denn das kleinste Notizschen aus Posemuckel<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  (Am.) from out in the sticks; (Eng.) from the back of beyond.</tei:note> steht dem Herzen der Schriftleiter näher als das ganze Lebenswerk eines Br., dieses als Kunst wahrhaft künstlerisch betrachtet.  So z.B. wird D^r^ Einst.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="einstein_alfred">Alfred Einstein</ref>.</tei:note> lieber Aufsätze über altbyzanti^ni^sche Trotteleien annehmen als einen über die Einrichtung des Saul von Br.  Beste Grüße von mir u. meiner Frau</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr  [ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] <tei:hi rend="italic">H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated April 9, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Vienna, April 9 1932</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Dr. Jonas,</tei:p><tei:p>Yesterday Dr. Furtwängler<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> was with me and I gave him the copy of Brahms’s preparation of <tei:hi rend="italic">Saul</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> the only copy, of course, as a present, in recognition and as an incentive.  Dr. Furtwängler will find abundant material in it, and I have the satisfaction of <tei:hi rend="italic">rescuing</tei:hi> the work!  Miss Elias<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> has toiled for three months under <tei:hi rend="italic">^my^ strictest control</tei:hi> to produce a “diplomatically accurate” copy, which -however- in my case <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> means that I will vouch for the reading (of the often very difficult script with pencil) in every way.  Everything is reproduced even with topographical accuracy.</tei:p><tei:p>I was able to show Dr. F. many things, the most beautiful aspects of the articulation, dynamicization, the continuo, etc.  Then I spoke of your plan<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> and asked him to grant you access to the score.</tei:p><tei:p>I could not examine the parts, because it already seemed too much to me that I kept the original—behind the back of Dr. Mandyczewsky,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> who had, out of envy, refused—at home for three months!  The parts are <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> at the very bottom, in the cellars.  And Dr. Furtwängler may be right that the parts have long since not been in the condition that they were in Brahms’s time, the other conductors (as usual) have certainly had their insertions made, especially as they lacked understanding of the master’s parts, as Löwe<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> and Schalk<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> expressly told me.  It would take perhaps a quarter of a lifetime to follow up all these things.  Where generations sin in incomprehension and distortion, a severe negligence often can no longer be -compensated- ^remedied^!</tei:p><tei:p>But it may be possible for you, upon examining <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> the score (and ^now^ with the consent of Dr. Furtwängler), to appreciate and reward ^for the first time^, in one or two essays, the effort and care of Brahms, squandered in its time on a stupid populace.  But try first of all to <tei:hi rend="italic">be certain of</tei:hi> the newspaper before you undertake the work!  That I advise you strongly!  Because the smallest news-item from Posemuckel<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> is dearer to the heart of the editors than the whole life-work of a Brahms, that work treated as art in a truly artist-like manner.  Thus, for example, Dr. Einstein<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> would rather accept essays on old Byzantine inanities than one on the preparation by Brahms of <tei:hi rend="italic">Saul</tei:hi>.   Best greetings from my wife and me.</tei:p><tei:p>Yours, [ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H. Schenker</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>