<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 5/18, 38 : 4-7-34 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Oswald Jonas (1934-1978)—Special Collections, University of California, Riverside (1978-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: Special Collections, University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 04/07/1934 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated April 7, 1934</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-08-29</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Further to OJ 5/18, 37, S reports his conversation with Hoboken, who praised Jonas's book, then asked S's opinion on how best to display the music examples.  S attempts diplomatically to explain Hoboken's pettiness.  —Furtwängler is in Vienna.  — S praises J's activities.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Jonas, Oswald;  Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks;  Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers;  Table of Contents;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  music examples;  cost;  wife;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Hamburg;  Berlin;  Vienna;  special academy</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated April 7, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>7.4.34
Geehrter, lieber Herr <tei:hi rend="italic">D^r^ Jonas</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>Meine Karte,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> OJ 5/18, 37, March 29, 1934, commenting on OJ 12/6, [30], March 16, 1934 and on the Table of Contents for Jonas’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks: Eine Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers</tei:hi> (Vienna: Saturn-Verlag, 1934).</tei:note> mit der ich fürs Erste Ihre Briefe u. den <tei:hi rend="italic">Index</tei:hi> beantwortete, dürfte doch wohl in Ihre Hände gelangt sein.  Ich wiederhole, daß mir Ihr <tei:hi rend="italic">Index</tei:hi> imponiert hat!  Im Übrigen glaubte ich Hob.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> abwarten zu sollen, um Ihnen die Auskunft zu geben.  Nun, gestern begab es sich erst, das er als Erster von Ihnen sprach, u. zw. <tei:hi rend="italic">äußerst lob</tei:hi>end sprach er sich über Ihre Arbeit aus, wozu ich dann noch meinen Sagen gab, den Eindruck des <tei:hi rend="italic">Index</tei:hi> schon allein hervor- <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> hob.  Dann rang sich ein “&lt;big&gt;&lt;big&gt;Aber&lt;/big&gt;&lt;/big&gt;” los, er fing mich (vielleicht auch nur, um sich zu zieren), was besser, billiger sei, die Beispiele im Text anzubringen oder?  Was es für eine Bewandtnis auf den Korrekturen habe? Usw.  Die Kleinigkeit, zumal nach dem Vortrag uneingeschränkten Lobes, verdraß mich sehr, beinahe hätte ich – worüber bei Gelegenheit später – aus dem Verdruß heraus etwas angestiftet.</tei:p><tei:p>Hob. hat, so glaube ich, nichts gegen Sie, er hat Sie immer geschätzt u. tut das auch heute noch – ein Anderes ist bei ihm freilich die Geldfrage.  Fast ist es so, daß er Niemandem verzeiht, der Geld von ihm erhält; obgleich Alle die Herren, die um ihn herum[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] hier sind, nicht so viel für ihre Leistungen an ihn in Anspruch nehmen, als die eine geschiedene Frau<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  See OJ 5/18, 13, dated September 7, 1932.</tei:note> in nur einem Jahre, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> bedauert er sich, wenn er zahlen soll.  Nicht reif zu einem vollen Talent, das etwas auf die Beine stellen kann, nicht reif zu einem vollen Mann, nicht reif zum wahren Liebhaber der Musik, zu einem wahren Mäzen, möchte er unter uns als ein uns gleicher, nahestehender gedeihen, u. wenn es nur auf Kosten unserer Leistungen u. Beiträge für sein Wohlergehen gienge, das schmeckte ihm so recht ins Herz hinein, da er keinen wahren Sinn für Andere hat.  Hiebei ziehe ich ab, daß er vermutlich ^von vielen Seiten^ sehr belästigt wird, nun, die Menschen, die ihm mehr geben, als er gibt, dürfte er aber nicht zu den lästigen zählen.  Was könnte dieser sonst so suggestible Mann für die Welt – mit Kleingeld!!! – leisten, wenn er Einsicht hätte!  Daß er Sie für “undankbar” hielte, <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> nehme ich nicht an, ein solches Motiv ist ihm sonst die äußerste Ausrede, wenn er einen Empfänger loswerden will, aber in dieser Verlegenheit ist er mit Ihnen noch lange nicht: das Buch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Jonas’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks: Eine Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers</tei:hi> (Vienna: Saturn-Verlag, 1934).</tei:note> schmeichelt ihm gar!  Sie dürfen also ruhig sein.  Ich freue mich sehr auf ihr Buch.</tei:p><tei:p>Furtw.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Wilhelm Furtwängler [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> ist hier, wer weiß, ob ich ihn zu sehen bekommen werde.</tei:p><tei:p>Ihre Verhältnisse kann ich mir schier nicht mehr vorstellen, diese Zureise nach Hamburg,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  See OJ 12/16, [30], March 16, 1934.</tei:note> der Aufenthalt in Berlin – ja, was könnte eben Hob für Verdienste sich erwerben, wenn er nur Alle in Wien durchorganisierte, als eine besondere Akademie usw.!</tei:p><tei:p>Beste Wünsche u. Grüße von uns Beiden</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr  
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] <tei:hi rend="italic">H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated April 7, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>April 7, 1934
Dear Dr. Jonas,</tei:p><tei:p>My postcard,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> with which I first responded to your letters and the Table of Contents, should have reached you.  I repeat that your Table impressed me!  For the rest, I thought I should wait on Hoboken<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> in order to give you the information.  Then, yesterday, it developed that he was first to speak of you, and indeed he expressed <tei:hi rend="italic">highest praise</tei:hi> for your work, whereupon I then made my speech, emphasizing only the impression made by the index. <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Then he let out with a “BUT”—he grasped me (perhaps only to play coy) asking what would be better, cheaper, to present the examples in the text or elsewhere?  What effect would that have on the proofs?  And so forth.  The pettiness, especially after the rehearsal of unrestricted praise, aggravated me greatly; out of aggravation I almost crossed swords with him (perhaps at a later opportunity).</tei:p><tei:p>Hoboken has, I believe, nothing against you; he has always valued you and does so still today—but with him the money-question is something else altogether.  It is almost as though he pardons nobody who gets money from him; although all of the gentlemen around him here do not take so much for their services to him as the divorced wife<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> in only one year, he <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> feels sorry for himself when he has to pay.  Not having matured as a talent capable of originating something, not matured as a complete man, not matured as a true lover of music, as a true patron, he would like to flourish among us as an equal, in the inner circle; and if he has to depend on our achievements and contributions for his well-being, that sits well enough within him, since he has no true sense for others.  Here I allow for the fact that he is presumably very burdened ^from many sides^, but, he should not count among the burdeners those who give him more than he gives.  What could this otherwise so suggestible man accomplish for the world—with small change!!!—if he had insight!  <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> I do not assume that he considered you “ungrateful”; such an implulse is generally the most transparent excuse for him when he wants to have done with a recipient, but he has long since not been in any such embarassment with you: the book<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> absolutely flatters him!  You may rest easy, then.  I am very happy with your book.</tei:p><tei:p>Furtwängler<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> is here; who knows whether I will get to see him.</tei:p><tei:p>Your doings are almost inconceivable to me, this journey to Hamburg,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> the sojourn in Berlin—indeed, what services a Hoboken could provide if only he organized everthing in Vienna, as a special academy etc.!</tei:p><tei:p>Best wishes and greetings from both of us.</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H. Schenker</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>