<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 5/18, 47 : 7-22-34 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Oswald Jonas (1934-1978)—Special Collections, University of California, Riverside (1978-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: Special Collections, University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 07/22/1934 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated July 22, 1934</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-09-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>S praises Jonas's book highly; gives Hoboken's current address; Furtwängler has written a recommendation for Moriz Violin, who is currently in Jerusalem; asks whether Vrieslander and Oppel are subscribers. —Comments on Bayreuth and Wagner.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Jonas, Oswald;  Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks;  Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers;  praise;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  Rotterdam;  Bergen am See;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Violin, Moriz;  Jerusalem;  Saturn Verlag;  Vrieslander, Otto;  Tessin;  Oppel, Reinhard;  Leipzig;  Bayreuth;  Wagner;  Löwe, Ferdinand;  Schalk, Franz;  Foll;  Brahms;  Gluck;  Haydn;  Mozart;  Beethoven</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Böckstein, Bad Gastein</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated July 22, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Böckstein
Bad Gastein
22. 7. 34</tei:p><tei:p>Geehrter, lieber Herr <tei:hi rend="italic">D^r^ Jonas</tei:hi>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  This document is apparently not in the Oswald Jonas Memorial Collection;  the photocopy of it was supplied to the transcriber by Oswald Jonas, and the current whereabouts of the original is unknown.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Und wieder<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  “Again” is an apparent reference to two earlier postcards from Schenker to Jonas that have become separated from the Oswald Jonas Memorial Collection and are not available for this project.  See 12/6, 34.</tei:note> das herzlichste Lob voran! Unerwartet tapfer, eindringend, überredend, glücklich in der Wahl u. Lösung der Beispiele, kurz: hätte ich auch 4 solcher Leser u. Könner wie Sie, dann hätten ^ich^ u. Sie bald weitere Hunderte u. die Musik würde wieder ihre Augen aufschlagen.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Hob</tei:hi>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> ist schon seit Ende April nicht mehr in Garmisch.  Er ist in ein kleines holländisches Bad (<tei:hi rend="italic">Bergen</tei:hi> am See) gegangen, seine Adresse ist aber:</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Rotterdam</tei:hi></tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="italic">p.a.G. van Aalen</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Gondsche Singel</tei:hi> 117 b</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Unter dieser Adresse erreicht ihm alle Post, wie er mir schrieb.</tei:p><tei:p>Trotzdem Ftw.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Wilhelm Furtwängler [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> mir hierher eine Empfehlung für den armen Prof. <tei:hi rend="italic">Violin</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="violin_moriz">Moriz Violin</ref>.</tei:note> der notgedrungen nach Jerusalem möchte, gern u. herzlich schrieb u. einsandte, glaub&lt;strike&gt;t&lt;/strike&gt;e<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  With a pen-stroke cancelling the “t,” Schenker converts the past-tense “glaubte” to the present “glaube.”</tei:note> ich an seine Verlässlichkeit doch nicht.  Eine gewisse begreifliche Unsicherheit des Urteils spielt vielleicht auch mit; daß ich das Buch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Jonas’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks: Eine Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers</tei:hi> (Vienna: Saturn-Verlag, 1934).</tei:note> nicht kannte, als er in Wien bei mir war, wußte er ja, also konnte ich davon auch nicht sprechen, heute aber meine Meinung ihm zu schreiben, um ihm sein Urteil leichter u. sicherer zu machen, dazu ist es ja wieder zu spät. <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Wollen Sie, bitte, den S. Verlag befragen, ob Otto <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Vrieslander</tei:hi></tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.</tei:note> u. Prof. <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Oppel</tei:hi></tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Rheinhard Oppel [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> sich unter den Subskribenten befinden, – sollte es <tei:hi rend="italic">nicht</tei:hi> der Fall sein, na, denn wissen wir ja den Grund, dann würde es sich sehr empfehlen, den beiden vielverdienten[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] Herren, die noch immer in unserer Sache leidenschaftlich wirken, “Rezensionsexemplare” zu senden.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">O. <tei:hi rend="italic">Vrieslander</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Locarno-Saldino</tei:hi> Villa
  Olga, Schweiz, Tessin.</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Prof. <tei:hi rend="italic">D^r^ Rhd. <tei:hi rend="italic">Oppel</tei:hi>, Leipzig</tei:hi>, Könneritzstr. 58^III^</tei:p><tei:p>Es wäre sehr schön u. nützlich, wenn ich Sie hier sprechen könnte, wie Sie eben können, <tei:hi rend="italic">ultra possumus</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  <tei:hi rend="italic">ultra possumus</tei:hi> : meaning ...</tei:note> usw.</tei:p><tei:p>In Bayreuth war ich nie.  In jungen Jahren reichten meine Mittel nicht hin, <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> dann sagten mir die Wagnerianer niemals zu, ausgenommen Musiker wie Löwe,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Click on <ref cRef="lowe_ferdinand">Ferdinand Löwe</ref>.</tei:note> Schalk,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Click on <ref cRef="schalk_franz">Franz Schalk</ref>.</tei:note> Foll<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13"> Ferdinand Foll (1867-1929), editor of Hugo Wolf songs, professional Lieder accompanist.  (Or possibly Leo Fall (1873-1925), theater conductor and composer of light operas.)</tei:note> u. ä., die gern auch <tei:hi rend="italic">Brahms</tei:hi>-Strahlen auf sich wirken ließen u. daraus den Vorteil besserer Umgangsformen zogen.  Ihnen brauche ich nicht zu sagen, daß Wagner größer ist als die Linie aller Wagnerianer, nur stand ^ihm^ die Diminution nicht zur Verfügung, aus dieser Verlegenheit erwuchs ihm das “Musikdrama” (nicht Musik, nicht Drama), ähnlich wie die gleiche Verlegenheit <tei:hi rend="italic">Gluck</tei:hi> zu seiner <tei:hi rend="italic">Renaissance</tei:hi> der <tei:hi rend="italic">Antike</tei:hi> drängte; <tei:hi rend="italic">Haydn</tei:hi> aber, <tei:hi rend="italic">Mozart</tei:hi> u. <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Brahms</tei:hi> etc. schrieben zu gleicher Zeit &lt;big&gt;Musik&lt;/big&gt;, wie <tei:hi rend="italic">sie</tei:hi> es brauchte.</tei:p><tei:p>Hoffentlich auf Wiedersehen!</tei:p><tei:p>Mit besten Grüßen von uns beiden
Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated July 22, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Böckstein
Bad Gastein
July 22, 1934</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Dr. Jonas,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>And again,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> first of all, heartiest praise!  Unexpectedly courageous, penetrating, convincing, felicitous in the choice and solution of the examples; in short: if I just had four such readers and able workers as you, then you and ^I^ would soon have hundreds more, and music would again open her eyes.</tei:p><tei:p>Hoboken<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> has no longer been in Garmisch since the end of April.  He went to a small Dutch spa (Bergen am See); his address is:</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Rotterdam</tei:hi>
p.a.G. van Aalen
<tei:hi rend="italic">Gondsche Singel</tei:hi> 117 b</tei:p><tei:p>All mail will reach him at this address, he wrote me.</tei:p><tei:p>Despite the fact that Furtwängler<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> gladly and cordially wrote and sent me a recommendation for poor Prof. Violin<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> who is obliged to go to Jerusalem, I am not convinced of his reliability.  A certain understandable insecurity of judgment may be partly responsible; that I did not know the book<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> when he was with me in Vienna he was well aware; therefore I could not speak about it.  To write him my opinion today, in order to make his assessment easier and more secure—well, it is too late for that. <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Will you please inquire of Saturn Verlag whether Otto <tei:hi rend="italic">Vrieslander</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> and Professor <tei:hi rend="italic">Oppel</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> are among the subscribers?  Should that <tei:hi rend="italic">not be the case</tei:hi>, well, then we know the reason, and it would be very advisable to send the two deserving gentlemen, who are still passionately active in our cause, “review copies.”</tei:p><tei:p>O. <tei:hi rend="italic">Vrieslander</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Locarno-Saldino</tei:hi> Villa
  Olga, Switzerland, Ticino.</tei:p><tei:p>Prof. Dr. Reinhard. <tei:hi rend="italic">Oppel</tei:hi>, Leipzig, Könneritzstrasse 58^III^</tei:p><tei:p>It would be very good and useful if I could speak with you here, any way you can arrange it, <tei:hi rend="italic">ultra possumus</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> etc.</tei:p><tei:p>I’ve never been in Bayreuth.  When I was young I didn’t have enough money; <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> and then I never cared for the Wagnerians, excepting musicians such as Löwe,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> Schalk,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> Foll<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> among others, who also liked to bask in the Brahmsian sunbeams, and thereby gained the advantage of better manners.  I need not tell you that Wagner is greater than the line of all Wagnerians, only diminution was not available ^to him^; because of this deficiency he had to take refuge in “music-drama” (not music, not drama) much as the same deficiency drove Gluck toward his renaissance of antiquity; but Haydn, Mozart and Beethoven, Brahms etc. at the same time wrote &lt;big&gt;music&lt;/big&gt; in a way suited to its <tei:hi rend="italic">own</tei:hi> needs.</tei:p><tei:p>Hoping to see you soon!</tei:p><tei:p>With best greetings from us both,
Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H. Schenker</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>