<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 5/18, 49 : 8-2-34 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Oswald Jonas (1934-1978)—Special Collections, University of California, Riverside (1978-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: Special Collections, University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 08/02/1934 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated August 2, 1934</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-09-19</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>S expresses heartfelt thanks to J for his book; their project is fundamentally one of "present-day Jewry." —An excerpt from freier Satz is to appear in Der Kunstwart.  —S has had to give up Willfort and Kraus because of their negligence regarding the planned Urlinie-Tafeln II.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Jonas, Oswald;  Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks;  Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers;  publishers;  patrons;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  Jewry;  Kalmus, Alfred;  Kunstwart, Die;  Deutsche Zeitschrift;  Freier Satz;  Free Composition;  Willfort, Manfred;  Kraus, Greta;  Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln;  Beethoven;  Mozart;  Chopin;  Salzer, Felix</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated August 2, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>2.8.34</tei:p><tei:p>Geehrter, lieber Herr <tei:hi rend="italic">D^r^ Jonas</tei:hi>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  This letter appears to have been mislaid at OJMC; the present edition is made from a photocopy supplied previously to the editor by J; the document number was assigned by J himself.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Nun will ich Ihnen meinen Dank<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  For Jonas’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks: Eine Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers</tei:hi> (Vienna: Saturn-Verlag, 1934).</tei:note> sozusagen <tei:hi rend="italic">in summa</tei:hi> u. in Form aussprechen! Für die schöne Liebe, Mühe, Sachlichkeit, treueste Hingabe an den Stoff.  Ich weiß keinen, der eine solche Leistung vollbracht hätte!</tei:p><tei:p>Nun steht Ihnen eine Welt von Stoffen offen, uns erscheint eben die Musikschöpfung <tei:hi rend="italic">neu</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">jung</tei:hi>, und da gibt es zu bestaunen, zu bejubeln wohl über unser Vermögen: uns -erscheint diese- ^geht es^ [<tei:hi rend="italic">deletion</tei:hi>] wie dem Bibelschreiber, der das erste Staunen über Gottes Schöpfung aussprach. <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Stünde uns nur Hilfe zu Gebote!  Verleger können nicht Mäzene sein,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Cf. “Niemals also ist der Verleger ein ‘Mäzen’ des Künstlers“ (Thus the publisher is never a "patron" of the artist), WSLB 113 : Schenker to Hertzka (UE), January 18, 1915.</tei:note> den Reichen, die es sein könnten, sagt sozusagen ein Vordergrundstück<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  A portmanteau of <tei:hi rend="italic">Vordergrund</tei:hi> (foreground) and <tei:hi rend="italic">Grundstück</tei:hi> (parcel of land, lot); likewise for the subsequent <tei:hi rend="italic">Hintergrundstück</tei:hi>.</tei:note> -des- besser zu denn unser Hintergrundstück, das an das Genie, an Gott, an Jenseitigkeiten rührt.  Die Erfahrung mit <tei:hi rend="italic">Hob</tei:hi>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> hat Ihnen wohl genug gesagt.  Nun erst was werden Sie aus der <tei:hi rend="italic">Aufnahme</tei:hi> Ihres Buches zu lernen haben!</tei:p><tei:p>Im Grunde wäre unsere Sache eine des heutigen Judentums als Rasse u. religiöser Gemeinschaft[.]  Einmal haben die Völker von den Juden gelernt: an Gott denken, dichten, warum sollten die Juden nicht umgekehrt von den anderen Völkern Musik lernen u. sie durch die Zeiten voran- <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> tragen, da die anderen Völker wohl für immer ihr gegenüber versagten?  Der Jude gesellte so zu seinem religiösen Monotheismus den Glauben auch an[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">eine</tei:hi> musikalische <tei:hi rend="italic">Ur</tei:hi>-Sache!  Aber wie bekehrt man die Juden dazu? Viel, viel wäre noch zu tun. —</tei:p><tei:p>Kalmus<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Alfred Kalmus [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> erwiderte mir, Ihr Verlag hätte für das Inserat zu viel gefordert, ihm wäre eben lieber gewesen, daß der Verlag ihm bezahlt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  See 12/6, [33].  Apparently Saturn-Verlag, Jonas’s publisher, had proposed that Universal Edition place an advertisement in Jonas’s forthcoming book and had been turned down.</tei:note> Der ehemalige “Kunstwart” (Deutsche Zeitschrift, München) bringt im Augustheft einen Aufsatz von mir, dem “fr. S.”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi> =  <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue Musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:hi> III.</tei:note> entnommen, der schon lange im Satz stand.</tei:p><tei:p>Erfüllen die Subskribenten ihre Pflicht?</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> H. Willfort u. Frl. Kraus<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Manfred Willfort and Greta Kraus: members of a group, elsewhere called the “seminar” by both Schenker and Jonas, including also Trude Krall and Felix Salzer; the published result of their studies had been <tei:hi rend="italic">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln</tei:hi> (New York: David Mannes Music School, 1932).</tei:note> habe ich doch aufgeben müssen, Sie haben das 2. Heft “Urlinie-Tafeln”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  A planned continuation of Schenker’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln</tei:hi> (New York: David Mannes Music School, 1932).  The volume was never published.  See Felix Salzer's Introduction to Schenker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Five Graphic Music Analyses</tei:hi> (New York: Dover Publications, 1969), pp. 17-21.</tei:note> (<tei:hi rend="italic">Beeth</tei:hi>. Son. cis^m^ [ganz],<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  The square brackets are in the original.</tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Moz. Fant dm, Chop. Et.</tei:hi> 10^III^ usw.) verraten, durch <tei:hi rend="italic">Unfleiß</tei:hi> im Stich gelassen, trotzdem oder gerade weil ich sie unentgeltlich lehrte!  Das Heft ist in 2 Jahren nicht fertig geworden, trotzdem ich die Hauptarbeit doch selbst leistete.  Ich hatte viel Verdruß mit ihnen (<tei:hi rend="italic">nicht</tei:hi> mit Dr. <tei:hi rend="italic">Salzer</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Click on <ref cRef="salzer_felix">Felix Salzer</ref>.</tei:note>).</tei:p><tei:p>Mit besten Grüßen an Sie von mir u. meiner Frau
Ihr  
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] <tei:hi rend="italic">H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated August 2, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>August 2, 1934</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Dr. Jonas,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Now I want to express my thanks to you<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> in the utmost and with all propriety, so to speak!  For the beautiful love, effort, objectivity, truest dedication to the material.  I know of no other who could have accomplished such a thing!</tei:p><tei:p>Now a world of materials stands open to you; the very musical creation appears <tei:hi rend="italic">new</tei:hi> to us, <tei:hi rend="italic">young</tei:hi>, and there we can but marvel, yea rejoice beyond our capability: we feel like the writer of the bible, who uttered the first astonishment over God’s creation.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> If only help were at our disposal!  Publishers cannot be patrons;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> the rich, who could be, are more impressed so to speak by a “foreground lot”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> than by our “background lot” which touches the genius, God, and transcendental things.  The experience with Hoboken<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> has probably taught you enough.  Now you’ll have plenty to learn from the <tei:hi rend="italic">reception</tei:hi> of your book!</tei:p><tei:p>Fundamentally our project is one of present-day Jewry as race and religious community.  There was a time when the peoples learned from the Jews: contemplate God, write poetry; why should the Jews not on the contrary learn music from the other peoples and propagate it through the ages, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> since the other peoples have probably abandoned it for good?  That way the Jew would join to his religious monotheism the belief in <tei:hi rend="italic">one</tei:hi> musical <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Ur</tei:hi>sache</tei:hi>!  But how does one motivate the Jews to do this?  Very, very much would remain to be done.</tei:p><tei:p>Kalmus<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> replied that your publisher has demanded too much for the advertisement; he would have preferred that the publisher pay him.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>  The former <tei:hi rend="italic">Kunstwart</tei:hi> (<tei:hi rend="italic">Deutsche Zeitschrift</tei:hi>, Munich) is publishing in the August issue an essay by me, extracted from <tei:hi rend="italic">Free Composition</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> which was already printed long ago.</tei:p><tei:p>Are the subscribers doing their duty?</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> I have had to give up Mr. Willfort and Miss Kraus;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> they have, by <tei:hi rend="italic">negligence</tei:hi>, betrayed the second volume of the “Urlinie-Tafeln”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> (Beethoven, Sonata in C-sharp Minor [complete],<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> Mozart Fantasy in D Minor, Chopin Etude Op. 10 No. 3 etc.), left it in the lurch, despite the fact (or precisely because) I taught them free of charge.  The volume has not been finished after two years, even though I did the primary work myself.  I had much aggravation with them (<tei:hi rend="italic">not</tei:hi> with Dr. Salzer<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/>).</tei:p><tei:p>With best greetings to you from my wife and me.
Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H. Schenker</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>