<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OC 1/23 : 3-17-17 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription Ian Bent, 2006.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1917-1935) - - Schenker, Jeanette (1935-1938) - -Oster, Ernst (1938-c.1939)—New York Public Library (c.1939-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Under investigation; Image: New York Public Library, New York; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 03/17/1917 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: &quot;DeutschS ~ HSchenker&quot;,&quot;T&#195;&#188;rkel ~ HSchenker&quot; --><dc:title>Handwritten draft letter from Schenker to Friedmann, dated March 17, 1917</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-09-21</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Encloses "talmudic" letter from Hugo Friedmann. —Assesses Fritz Mendl by comparison with other industrialists. —Speaks of his attitude to rich people.

</dc:description><dc:subject> Schenker, Heinrich;  Schenker, Jeanette; Türkel, Siegfried;  Friedmann, Hugo;  talmudic reasoning;  Jew;  stipend;  Deutsch, Sofie;  Sophie;  Mendl, Fritz;  Musikkapelle;  Damenkapelle;  German;  Riemann, Hugo;  Kretzschmar, Hermann;  Bülow, Hans von;  Austria;  Benedikt;  Korngold, Julius;  Rothberger, Alfred;  Scott, Walter;  Eisler;  timber merchant;  cloth merchant;  Neue Musikalische Theorien und Phantasien;  New Music Theories and Fantasies;  NMTP;  Kanzlei;  chancellry</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Draft letter, in JS’s hand, from Schenker to Türkel, dated March 17, 1917]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>(<tei:hi rend="italic">Dr. Türkel</tei:hi>)
17. III. 17</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Beiliegend ein heute eingelaufener Brief von Herrn D^r.^ Friedmann.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Hugo Friedmann: attorney involved with the estate of Sofie Deutsch, and to whom S had drafted a letter five days earlier (OC 1/19–20) and another three days earlier (OC 16/32v).  No letter from him to S prior to this date is known to have survived, but the letter in question was presumably in response to what resulted from those two drafts.</tei:note>  Nach dieser talmudistischen Erklärung (ich selbst bin Jude) gelangt man zu dem Schlusse, daß <tei:hi rend="italic">ich</tei:hi> das Stipendium<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  i.e. the stipend left to him by Sofie Deutsch in her will: see OJ 10/4, January 26, 1916; OJ 12/52, January 12, 1917.</tei:note> erst nach meinem Tode vergeben sollte.   Welche Wandlung nimmt doch die Sache seit jenem Brief des Herrn Kammerrates an mich,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Presumably OJ 12/52, January 12, 1917, from Fritz Mendl to S.</tei:note> der nichts von diesen Haarspaltereien wußte.  Und einmal nun wieder in diese Angelegenheit geworfen[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>], will ich, lediglich zu Ihrem privaten Gebrauche, in Würdigung gemeinsamer musikalischer Interessen nachträglich folgende drastische Erläuterung bieten: Den Herrn Kammerrat schätze ich bis zur Stunde als einen Mann, dem ich unter den vielen Industriellen, Bankdirektoren usw, die ich im Leben gesehen, am ehesten das Prädikat „genial“ zubillige.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Cf. S's first impression of Mendl, at Deutsch's house on December 21, 1906: "At the meal, a brother of the lady of the house, Mr. Fritz Mendl, turns out to be an excellent, clever fellow, and equallysuperb husband and father" (OJ 1/5, pp.  30-31).</tei:note>  Diese Ansicht lasse ich mir nicht einmal von ihm selbst -rauben- ^nehmen^.   Stellen Sie dagegen aber folgendes:  Eines Tages vor etwa 2–3 Jahren läßt er mich durch Fr. Deutsch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Sofie Deutsch, long-term pupil and benefactress of S, died January 5, 1917.</tei:note> fragen, ob ich nicht ein Mädchen bei einer Musikkapelle unterbringen <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> konnte?!  Ich u. eine Damenkapelle „sapiente sat[“].<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  <tei:hi rend="italic">sapiente sat</tei:hi>: Lat.: [define].</tei:note>  Hier liegt die Wurzel bloß.  So sieht der Herr Kammerrat einen Menschen dem nachgewiesenermaßen in Deutschland höherer Rang als Hugo Riemann, Hermann Kretzschmar, als Bülow usw. zugebilligt wird, dem der größte Teil der deutschen Jugend huldigt u. folgt, wovon man nur gerade in Oesterreich sehr wenig weiß, bloß weil ich einmal dem Herrn Benedikt<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Benedikt [identify].</tei:note> verraten habe, daß Korngold<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Julius Korngold (1860–1945), influential music critic.</tei:note> usw.  Herr Alfred Rothberger, Stephansplatz 9,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Alfred Rothberger [identify]</tei:note> erzählte mir einmal, daß er in London als Gast eines größten Tuchhändlers seinen Gastgeber nach dem Grab des Walther Scott befragte, worauf er die Gegenfrage bekam: „Ist das der Cheviothändler Scott?  Die Gastgeberin aber flötete: „Aber nein, das ist ja der Märchenerzähler.“  Im Hause I, Ehendorferstr. 2, großes, größtes Holzhandungshaus verkehrte ich 10–15 Jahre als Freund des Hauses.  Rasch habe ich mir für mein Teil gemerkt, daß Herr Eisler<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Herr Eisler: [identify]</tei:note> ein großes Holzgeschäft betreibt, aber umgekehrt fragte mich all die vielen Jahre her der <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> sonderbare Herr beim Schwarzen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  beim Schwarzen: [meaning?].  </tei:note> für welche Zeitung ich schreibe.  Bis ich endlich das Haus aufgab.  Ein gewisses Niveau der Betrachtung muß doch da sein.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  No paragraph break in the original at this point.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>In Ihrer Eigenschaft als Anwalt dürften Sie ebensogut als ich die Natur der Reichen kennen.  Nun bin ich glücklicherweise so beschaffen, daß ich ihnen nirgend den Vortritt lasse, am allerwenigsten, wenn sie auf Geld pochend Ansprüche stellen.  (Fr. Deutsch wußte davon ein Lied zu singen.)  Ins Gesicht sage ich es den reichen Leuten, daß die wahren Bettler u. Schmarotzer der Welt die Reichen sind u. werfen sich Millionäre in die Brust, so -g- sage ich: ich bin ein Milliardeur u. basta.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  “ ich bin ein Milliardeur u. basta“:  note S’s toying with other languages, probably to achieve an ironic edge:  French <tei:hi rend="italic">Milliardeur</tei:hi> (though the French word is actually <tei:hi rend="italic">Milliardaire</tei:hi>) and Italian <tei:hi rend="italic">basta</tei:hi>.  “Milliardeur” is also ambiguous: it could be translated “billionaire.”</tei:note>  In der Tat krümmten sich vor mir die Reichen, wenn es um ein paar Groschen ging, wie die elendesten Straßensammler, während mir ein Leichtes war, auf sein Geld u. alles zu verzichten, wenn er nur dieses betonte.  Auf diese Weise bitte ich Sie, sehr geehrter Herr Doktor, meine völlige Gleichgiltigkeit puncto<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  Note how S uses Latin words and phrases, <tei:hi rend="italic">sapiente sat</tei:hi> earlier, <tei:hi rend="italic">puncto</tei:hi> here;  he does this frequently to raise the tone of discourse or to overawe his correspondent;  in this case, it is more likely to be on the basis of one lawyer to another.  </tei:note> all der Beträge zu erklären;  ich folge Ihrem Rat, nichts <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> weiter.  Auch habe ich ja im Falle der Fr. D. wirklich ein Recht auf so manches.  Vergessen Sie bitte nicht, daß ich bei Cotta, Stuttgart, meine Neuen Theorien u. Phantasien im Jahre 1906 u. 1910 publiziert habe, auch ohne Akkreditiv u. Zusicherung usw.  Es ging, es wird gehen, weil es gehen [<tei:hi rend="italic">12 lines in HS’s hand, inverted, comprising a copy with variants of paragraph 1 of OJ 10/4, January 26, 1916, from Sofie Deutsch to S</tei:hi>] muß.  Ende März erscheine ich über Ihren Wunsch in Ihrer Kanzlei u. grüße Sie bis dahin aufs beste als Ihr sehr ergebener</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">unsigned</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>P.S.  Gleichzeitig danke ich Herrn Kammerrat für seine Freundlichkeit mit ein paar Zeilen an ihn selbst.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Draft letter, in JS’s hand, from Schenker to Türkel, dated March 17, 1917]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>(<tei:hi rend="italic">Dr. Türkel</tei:hi>)
March 17, 1917</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>Enclosed [is] a letter received today from Dr. Friedmann.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  On the basis of this Talmudic explanation (I myself am a Jew), one is led to the conclusion that <tei:hi rend="italic">I</tei:hi> should be able to grant the stipend<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> only after my death!  What a turn the matter has taken since the Chamber Counsellor’s<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> letter to me, which showed not a trace of this hair-splitting!  And now that I have once more been thrust into this affair, I will go further and offer you, purely for your own private use, the following drastic explanation in appreciation of [our?] common musical iterests.  I esteem the Chamber Counsellor up to the present moment as a man to whom I would, among the many industrialists, bank directors, etc. that I have encountered in the course of my life, soonest accord the attribute of “having a touch of genius.”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  I concede this opinion not solely on the basis of the man himself:  One day, some 2–3 years ago, he asked my through Mrs. Deutsch<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> whether I <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> could place a girl in a band?!  Me and a women’s band: <tei:hi rend="italic">sapiente sat</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/>  This is the root of the matter.  So the Chamber Counsellor sees a man to whom is evidently granted higher status in Germany than Hugo Riemann [or] Hermann Kretzschmar, than [Hans von] Bülow, etc, to whom the majority of the German new generation pays homage and whom it emulates, but of whom people in Austria itself know very little, all because I once divulged to Mr. Benedikt<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> that Korngold<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> etc., etc.   Mr. Alfred Rothberger, Stephansplatz 9,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> once told me that when in London as guest of a major cloth merchant he asked his host after the grave of Walter Scott, whereupon the counter-question came back: ‘Is that Scott the dealer in cheviot wool?”  However, his hostess said in a sugary voice: “Oh no, that is surely the fairytale-teller.”  For ten to fifteen years I frequented [Vienna] I, Ehendorferstraße 2, the house of a great—of the greatest—timber merchant, as a friend of the family.  I quickly made a mental note to myself that Mr. Eisler<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> ran a big timber business, but conversely in all those years the <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> remarkable gentleman asked me ......[?]<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> which newspaper I wrote for.  In the end, I gave up visiting the house.  A certain level of consideration has to exist.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/></tei:p><tei:p>In your capacity as an attorney, you must be as well acquainted as I am with the nature of rich people.  Now, happily I am constituted such that I do not under any circumstances give them precedence, least of all when they insistently make claims on money.  (Mrs. Deutsch knew a thing or two about that.)  I tell rich people to their faces that the true beggars and spongers of the world are the rich people, and when millionaires give themselves airs, I just say: I am a multi-millionaire and that’s enough!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/>  In actual fact, rich people squirmed before me when it was a matter of a couple of measly pennies, like the most wretched garbage collectors, whereas it was easy for me to forego his money and everything else when this is what he emphasized.  I beg you, dear Doctor, to explain my complete indifference in regard to<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/> all sums of money along these lines.  I follow your advice, but go no <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> further.  Moreover, in the case of Mrs. Deutsch I really do have a right to a great deal.  Please do not forget that I published my <tei:hi rend="italic">New Musical Theories and Fantasies</tei:hi> with Cotta of Stuttgart in 1906 and 1910 without any letter of credit or guarantee, etc.  It sufficed, it will suffice, because it has to suffice.  [<tei:hi rend="italic">12 lines in HS’s hand, inverted, comprising a copy with variants of paragraph 1 of OJ 10/4, January 26, 1916, from Sofie Deutsch to S</tei:hi>]    I shall appear in your chancellry as you request at the end of March, and remain until then with best wishes yours truly</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">unsigned</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>P. S. At the same time, I am writing a couple of lines direct to the Chamber Counsellor to thank him for his kindness.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>