<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 12/6, [36] : 8-6-34 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Oswald Jonas, published here with kind permission.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> Permission to publish on this website granted by the heirs of Oswald Jonas, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1934-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Oswald Jonas; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 08/06/1934 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated August 6, 1934</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-09-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Acks two postcards and letter OJ 5/18, 49. —Alludes to the Dolfuss assassination;  gives his reactions to Bayreuth (which he has just visited) and the Wagner cult. —Is seeing his publisher about the proposed commentary editions.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Jonas, Oswald; Schenker, Heinrich;  Vienna;  Bayreuth;  Ring;  Wagner;  Wahnfried;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  Saturn-Verlag;  Hefte;  commentary editions</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated August 6, [1934]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>6. August.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Herr Doktor!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  I am grateful to Lee Rothfarb for substantial advice on the translation of this letter.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Sie beschämen mich immer sehr durch Ihre wunderbaren Karten und vor allem den letzten Brief,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Including at least the card OJ 5/18, 48, July 29, 1934, and the letter OJ 5/18, 49, August 2, 1934.</tei:note> die mir aber eine Freude ohnegleichen bedeuten.  Alles andere wird daneben vollständig bedeutungslos.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich bin um eine Woche wieder in Wien, nachdem in Bayreuth auf die alarmierenden und verlogenen Nachrichten aus Wien<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  News of the assassination, on July 25, 1934, of Austrian Chancellor Engelbert Dollfuss.</tei:note> keine Ruhe mehr hatte und den “Ring” Ring sein ließ.  Diese ganze Atmosphäre dort war ja geradezu unbeschreiblich.  Ich konnte von dort nicht so schreiben, wie es mir <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> eigentlich am Herzen lag.  Ich hatte ja jetzt Zeit genug gehabt, die Psyche dieses Volkes und seiner “Bewegung” (Umbruch, Aufbruch - oder wie sie es schon nennen) kennen zu lernen, aber hier konnte man es sozusagen in Reinkultus betrachten.  Hauptmerkmal: Dummheit und Verlogenheit.  Beispiellose Kontraste zwischen Wort und Tat.  Blindwütiges Rennen ins Verderben, in finsterste Barbarei.  Ja, nichts schlimmeres auf der Welt als Ideenlosigkeit und noch schlimmer ebendieselbe mit dem aufgesteckten Schild einer “Idee”!  Ist Wagnerkult schon eine böse, barbarische Angelegenheit, aber nicht einmal dieser ehrlich, sondern <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> selbst der noch Vorwand einer weitaus schlimmeren.  Vor der Vorstellung, in den Pausen nachher – nicht Wagner war das Ziel, sondern  . . . . .  (wie der Teufel nicht zu Papier zu bringen!) Und die Fäden, die sich vom “Wahnfried”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Wagner’s home in Bayreuth.  The irony is that contrary to the state of peace suggested by its name,Wahnfried was anything but devoid of <tei:hi rend="italic">Wahn</tei:hi>, madness.</tei:note> zu diesem Wahn spinnen[.]  Ein schnurgerader Weg!  Alles stimmt!  Vor allem das Heidentum und die Maske.  Ein Abfall von Gott – beides.  Und die satanische Freude am Bösen, an der Zerstörung.  Der einzige Unterschied: der Grad des Können bei Wagner und der blutige Dilletantismus heute.</tei:p><tei:p>Nun aber bin ich hier und suche, ein wenig zu mir zu kommen.  Die furchtbare Verkrampfung in der ich draußen gelebt habe, jetzt kommt das erst so deutlich heraus <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> und äussert sich in einer ständigen Abspannung. Hoffentlich wird das bald besser, freilich der Gedanke, in Sept. da wieder hinaus – ich glaube, den Missionären muß es endlich zu Mute gewesen sein.</tei:p><tei:p>Hob.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> schrieb mir, daß er Sie in ca 10 Tagen besuchen würde und ob ich nicht auch kommen möchte.  Ja, das wäre freilich sehr schön, aber geht aus sehr einfachen Gründen leider nicht. – Heute komme ich mit meinem Verleger zusammen und hoffe schon mehr wegen der “Hefte”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  The commentary editions proposed by Jonas.  See OJ 12/6, [31], April 15, 1934.</tei:note> zu erfahren.</tei:p><tei:p>Nochmals Tausend Dank für all Ihre Freundlichkeit und ergebenste Grüße Ihnen sowie Ihren werten Frau Gemahlin.</tei:p><tei:p>stets Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated August 6, [1934]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>August 6[, 1934]</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>You always put me very much to shame by your wonderful cards and above all the last letter,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> which gives me a joy beyond measure.  Everything else is completely insignificant by comparison.</tei:p><tei:p>I am back in Vienna for a week, having had no peace in Bayreuth after the alarming and duplicitous reports from Vienna,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> and thus having skipped the <tei:hi rend="italic">Ring</tei:hi> cycle.  The whole atmosphere there was absolutely indescribable.  I could not write from there what was <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> really in my heart.  I had already had time enough to get acquainted with the psyche of this cadre and their “movement” (upheaval, revolution, or whatever they call it), but here one could observe it in unadulterated form.  Chief characteristic: stupidity and mendacity.  Unprecedented contrasts between word and deed.  Blind hurtling into ruin, into blackest barbarism.  Nothing’s worse in the world than complete lack of guiding idea, and still worse, that along with the fraudulent badge of an “idea”!  The Wagnerian cult is in itself an evil, barbaric business, only not even true to that, but instead, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> pretense of an even far murkier one. Before the performance, and in the subsequent intermissions—it was not Wagner that was the object [of conversation], but . . . . . (like the devil, not to be put on paper!)  And the threads that spin from “Wahnfried”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> to this madness.  An arrow-straight path!  It all fits!  Above all the heathenism and the pretense.  A cast-off from God, both of them.  And the satanic relish of the evil, of destruction.  The only difference: the degree of competence in Wagner and the bloody dilletantism today.</tei:p><tei:p>But now I am here and am trying to recover a little.  The horrible cramped condition in which I lived out there, now it really takes its toll <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> and manifests itself in a continual fatigue.  I hope it will soon be better; certainly the prospect of getting away again in September—I think the missionaries must have felt this way in the end.</tei:p><tei:p>Hoboken<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> wrote me that he will visit you in about 10 days and wonders whether I would not like to come too.  Yes, that would certainly be very nice, but for very simple reasons it is not possible.  Today I meet with my publisher and hope to learn more about the “issues.”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/></tei:p><tei:p>Many thanks again for all your amicability, and most respectful greetings to you and your good wife.</tei:p><tei:p>Yours always,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>