<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 12/6, [35] : 7-25-34 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Oswald Jonas, published here with kind permission.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> Permission to publish on this website granted by the heirs of Oswald Jonas, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1934-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Oswald Jonas; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 07/25/1934 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated July 25, 1934</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-09-06</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>J has changed his travel plans;  describes Bayreuth; sends corrigenda list for his Das Wesen;  Roth is working on continuo realizations of Handel.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Jonas, Oswald; Schenker, Heinrich;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  Garmisch;  Vienna visit;  Bayreuth;  Wagner;  exhibitions;  Genius at Work;  Parsifal;  Roller, Alfred;  Levi, Hermann;  Bockelmann, Rudolf;  Sachs, Hans;  corrigenda;  Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks;  Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers;  Vrieslander, Otto;  Oppel, Reinhard;  Roth, Hermann;  Hamburg;  Handel;  violin sonatas;  continuo realization;  Hamburger Nachrichten</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated July 25, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>25. Juli 34.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Tausend Dank für Ihren freundlichen Brief.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  OJ 5/18, 47, July 22, 1934.</tei:note>  Daß Hob.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> schon so lange nicht mehr in Garmisch ist, verwundert mich sehr.  Nun weiß ich garnicht, ob er überhaupt von mir die Post und – das Buch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Jonas’s just-published <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks: Eine Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers</tei:hi> (Vienna: Saturn-Verlag, 1934).</tei:note> bekommen hat.  Da er mir seinerzeit Garmisch als seine Sommerszene angegeben hat, hätte er mich wohl von dieser Änderung verständigen können.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich habe mich doch entschlossen, von hier direkt am Freitag abend nach Wien zu fahren.  Es tut mir sehr leid, daß auf die Art aus meinem Besuch bei Ihnen nichts wird.  Wann gedenken Sie nach Wien <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> zurückzukehren?</tei:p><tei:p>Bayreuth ist eine entzückende alte Stadt in der schönsten Umliegung – die musikalischen Aufführungen bleiben aber durchaus hinter dem Berliner Durchschnitt zurück.</tei:p><tei:p>Interessant in mancherlei Beziehung ist die Wagner Austellung[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] unter dem Titel ”Genie am Werk”.  In der Abteilung ”Kämpfer für Wagner” fehlt z. B. Hermann Levi.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Hermann Levi (1839-1900) conducted the first performance of <tei:hi rend="italic">Parsifal</tei:hi> to Wagner’s complete satisfaction.</tei:note>  Auch sonst gäbe es mancherlei zu sagen.  Übrigens ist “Parsifal” neu inszeniert mit manchen sehr schönen neuen Dekorationen von Roller(!).<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Alfred Roller (1864-1935), a Vienna-based designer (hence the exclamation mark).</tei:note> Wirklich großartig und ergreifend Bockelmann<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">    Rudolf Bockelmann (1892-1958), German baritone, at the time working at the Staatsoper in Berlin; noted especially for his singing of Wagnerian roles.</tei:note> als Hans Sachs.  Vieles an der Wirkung der Wagnerischen Musik ist mir übrigens hier klarer geworden.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Vielleicht daß das Zeitgeschehen da etwas nachhilft. —</tei:p><tei:p>Anbei übersende ich Ihnen ein Verzeichnis der Druckfehler, das demnächst gesetzt und nachgeliefert wird.  Wegen der Exemplare für Vrieslander<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.  See OJ 5/18, 47.</tei:note> u. Oppel<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Reinhard Oppel [create biogfile and link].  See OJ 5/18, 47.</tei:note> werde ich sofort in Wien fragen.  Ich hatte sie seinerzeit selbstverständlich auf die Liste gesetzt.  In Wien kann ich dann endlich auch wegen der Einführungshefte<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  The series of commentary-editions proposed by Jonas in OJ 12/6, 31, April 15, 1934.  See also OJ 5/18, 41, and 12/6, [36] and [37].</tei:note> sprechen.  Freilich daß Hob. so garnichts mehr hat hören lassen, erschwert die Sache.</tei:p><tei:p>— Übrigens fabelhaft ist hier das alte Opernhaus aus dem [Jahre] <tei:hi rend="italic">1743</tei:hi>, damals als das größte Theater Deutschlands mit unglaublichem Prank erbaut.  Das muß jedenfalls <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> eine theaterfreundige Welt gewesen sein, die verstanden hat, daß Schein und Illusion <tei:hi rend="italic">wesentlich</tei:hi> zum Theater gehören. – Haben Sie noch einmal etwas von H. Roth<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Click on <ref cRef="roth_herman">Hermann Roth</ref>.</tei:note> gehört?  Ich hatte ihn im Winter in Hamburg besucht – er arbeitete damals an der Continuoausarbeitung<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  This word is somewhat irregularly written, but there is little doubt as to the intent.</tei:note> der Händel Violin Sonaten.  Er ist Musikreferent der Hamburger Nachrichten und ich habe ihm jedenfalls ein Exemplar zukommen lassen.</tei:p><tei:p>Empfehlen Sie mich bitte Ihrer werten Frau Gemahlin.  Ich verbleibe,</tei:p><tei:p>In steter Verehrung
Ihr ergebenster
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated July 25, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>July 25, 1934</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>Thanks so much for your cordial letter.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  I am very surprised that Hoboken<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> has been gone from Garmisch for such a long time.  Now I have no idea whether he received mail from me and—the book.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  Since he told me at the time that Garmisch would be his summer locale, he could well have notified me of this change.</tei:p><tei:p>I have decided, however, to go directly from here to Vienna on Friday evening.  I am sorry that this way nothing will come of my visit with you.  When do you plan <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> to return to Vienna?</tei:p><tei:p>Bayreuth is a delightful old city in the most beautiful surroundings—the musical performances, however, are altogether inferior to the prevailing average in Berlin.</tei:p><tei:p>Interesting in many respects is the Wagner exhibition under the title “Genius at work.”  In the section “Champions of Wagner,” Hermann Levi,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> for example, is absent.  There would be much more to say besides.  Incidentally, <tei:hi rend="italic">Parsifal</tei:hi> has been newly staged with many very beautiful decorations by Roller(!).<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  Bockelmann<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> is truly magnificent and gripping as Hans Sachs.  Much about the effect of the Wagnerian music, incidentally, has become clearer to me here.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Perhaps the current events contribute to that somewhat. —</tei:p><tei:p>I send you herewith a list of the misprints, which now must be published and distributed.  I will ask right away in Vienna about the copies for Vrieslander<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> and Oppel.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/>  I had of course included them on the list at the time.  In Vienna too I can finally discuss the analytical publications.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/>  Admittedly, the fact that Hoboken writes nothing further at all makes the matter more difficult.</tei:p><tei:p>— Fabulous, by the way, is the old opera house here, from the year <tei:hi rend="italic">1743</tei:hi>, built with incredible splendor as the largest theater in Germany at the time.  It must in any case have been <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> a theater-friendly world, which understood that appearance and illusion belong <tei:hi rend="italic">essentially</tei:hi> to the theater. —Have you heard again from Hermann Roth?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/>  I had visited him in the winter in Hamburg—he was working then on the continuo realization<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> of the Handel violin sonatas.  He is music critic for the <tei:hi rend="italic">Hamburger Nachrichten</tei:hi>, and I have in any case had a copy sent him.</tei:p><tei:p>Please convey my regards to your good wife.  In enduring respect,</tei:p><tei:p>I remain
Your most indebted
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>