<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 12/6, [26] : 12-10-33 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Oswald Jonas, published here with kind permission.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> Permission to publish on this website granted by the heirs of Oswald Jonas, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1933-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Oswald Jonas; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 12/08/1933 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated December 10, 1933</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-07-28</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Asks how the music examples in Das Meisterwerk were printed, with respect to his Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks; in Riemann's Musiklexikon, ed. A. Einstein, Einstein's reference to Schenker appears under "Bach."

</dc:description><dc:subject>Jonas, Oswald; Schenker, Heinrich;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks;  Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers;  Jahrbuch;  Yearbook;  Meisterwerk in der Musik;  Masterwork in Music;  Harmonielehre;  Harmony;  Riemann's Lexikon;  Einstein, Alfred;  Bach, J. S.</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated December 10, 1933</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>10 Dez. 1933
Hochverehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Tausend Dank für Ihren liebenswürdigen Brief.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">    OJ 5/18, 31, December 8, 1933.</tei:note>  Umsomehr, da Sie mir darin von Ihren schlimmen Augen erzählen.  Sie haben aber schon viel Dienst gemacht in Ihrem Leben!  Ich wünsche Ihnen vom Herzen, daß das bald wieder vollkommen in Ordnung ist.</tei:p><tei:p>– An Hob.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> habe ich sofort geschrieben, wiewohl es mir nicht verständlich ist, daß er auf meinen ersten garnicht geantwortet hat. –<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  J inserts emdash, then continues without paragraph-break.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ich bin sehr froh, daß ich nun das größte<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  That is, the greatest part of the work on his <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks</tei:hi> (Vienna; Saturn-Verlag, 1934).</tei:note> hinter mir habe, der Rest ist nicht von Bedeutung.  Bezüglich des <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Druckes der Notenbeispiele herrscht noch keine vollkommene Klarheit.  Sind die Beispiele in Jahrbuch I, II<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Schenker’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, I and II (Munich: Drei-Masken-Verlag, 1925, 1926).</tei:note> gestochen oder Klischée?  Ersteres wäre nämlich wesentlich teurer, bei Klischées fürchte ich wieder, daß sie mehr Platz beanspruchen. Die Schwierigkeit in meinem Fall ist, daß ich es doch für ratsamer gehalten habe, die zu besprechenden Stellen auch “in natura” wiederzugeben (wie in der Harmonielehre<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Schenker’s <tei:hi rend="italic">NMTP</tei:hi> I (Stuttgart: J. G. Cotta, 1906).</tei:note>), sodaß noch außerdem eine erläuternde Figur notwendig ist.  Ich glaube, daß gerade der praktische Zweck, der mit dem Buch verfolgt wird, dies erfordert, weil sein Gebrauch erleichtert wird.  Ich <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> könnte nur dadurch nicht allzugroße Beispiele wählen, habe mir aber manchmal durch z. B. Noten | T.5 - 7 | Noten | u. s. w. geholfen.  Nun wenn das Buch Leser -auf- ^zu^ Ihren Werken hinführt und wenn sie dann ^bei^ deren Lekture nicht mehr auf fremde Begriffe stoßen, so erscheint mir der Zweck erfüllt.  Am meisten lag mir daran (bei den Zitaten aus der Harmonielehre vor allem) zu zeigen, wie die Lehre einheitlich gewachsen ist, wie die Begriffe im Keim schon in diesem ersten Werk zu finden sind (einmal “Verlängerung” für Prolongation!) u. s. w. – –</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Ja, wegen Lexikon: Sie scheinen die unsägliche Frechheit übersehen zu haben, die im Einstein lexikon<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  The revision by Alfred Einstein of <tei:hi rend="italic">Riemann’s Musiklexikon</tei:hi>, 9th-11th editions.  Click on <ref cRef="einstein_alfred">Alfred Einstein</ref>.</tei:note> nicht unter Schenker, wohl aber unter “Bach” stehen [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>].  Werkers Versuche<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Wilhelm Werker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Studien über Symmetrie im Bau der Fugen und die motivische Zusammengehörigkeit der Präludien und Fugen des Wohltemperierten Klaviers von Johann Sebastian Bach</tei:hi> (Leipzig, 1922).  Einstein had suggested a parallel between Werker’s attempt to find numerical relationships in Bach’s music and Schenker’s work.</tei:note> und die “Urlinie Skelettierungen Schenkers”!</tei:p><tei:p>Alles Gute Ihnen und Ihrer werten Frau Gemahlin! In dankbarster Verehrung</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p><tei:p>Haben Sie schon die neue Ausgabe der “Inventionen” von Landshoff<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Wilhelm Werker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Studien über Symmetrie im Bau der Fugen und die motivische Zusammengehörigkeit der Präludien und Fugen des Wohltemperierten Klaviers von Johann Sebastian Bach</tei:hi> (Leipzig, 1922).  Einstein had suggested a parallel between Werker’s attempt to find numerical relationships in Bach’s music and Schenker’s work.</tei:note> mit Rev. Ber.?</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated December 10, 1933</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>December 10, 1933
Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>Thank you so much for your cordial letter.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  All the more so as you report in it of your poor eyes.  But they have already given much service in your life!  I hope with all my heart that they will soon be perfectly restored.</tei:p><tei:p>I have written immediately to Hoboken,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> although it is not comprehensible to me that he has failed to answer my first letter.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/></tei:p><tei:p>I am very happy that I now have the greatest part<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> behind me; the remainder is not significant.  Complete <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> clarity regarding the printing of the musical examples has not yet been achieved.  Are the examples in <tei:hi rend="italic">Yearbooks</tei:hi> I and II<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> engraved or stereotype-plate? The former would be significantly more expensive, but with stereotypes, on the other hand, I fear that they would require more space.  The difficulty in my case is that I have considered it more advisable to reproduce the passages to be discussed “in natura” (as in <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/>), so that a further explanatory figure is needed. I believe that just the practical purpose that the book seeks to achieve requires this, because its use is [thereby] facilitated. For that very reason I was <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> not able to choose very large examples, but sometimes resorted to, for example, (music) “| bars 5-7 |” (music), etc.  If the book leads readers to your works, and if in reading them they no longer stumble on unfamiliar concepts, it seems to me that the purpose will have been fulfilled.   My main concern (above all in the extracts from <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi>) was to show how the teaching developed in a unified manner, how the concepts can be found in embryonic form already in this first work (even “Verlängerung” for Prolongation!) etc.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Yes, concerning “Lexicon”: you seem to have overlooked the unspeakable impudence that stands in the Einstein lexicon<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> not under “Schenker” but rather under “Bach.”  Werker’s attempts<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> and “Schenker’s Urlinie skeletonization”!</tei:p><tei:p>All good wishes to you and your good wife!  With most grateful respect,</tei:p><tei:p>Your
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p><tei:p>Do you have already the new edition of the “Inventions” by Landshoff<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> with critical report?</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>