<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 12/6, [10] : 3-3-32 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Oswald Jonas, reproduced here by kind permission.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish on this website granted by the heirs of Oswald Jonas, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1932-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Oswald Jonas; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 03/03/1932 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Typed letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated March 3, 1932</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-02-24</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Jonas reports on his course on Schenker's theory at the Stern Conservatorium, two forthcoming lectures, an article intended for publication, two radio talks and a radio recital; includes reference to his later textbook Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks.

</dc:description><dc:subject><!-- Enter subjects here --></dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Berlin</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated March 3, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Berlin, den 3. März 1932</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Mit großer Freude habe ich gehört, welchen Anteil Sie an meinen Bestrebungen hier in Berlin nehmen.  Wenn ich Ihnen nicht schon längst ausführlich geschrieben habe, so hängt das vor allem damit zusammen, daß das Resultat meiner Bemühungen größtenteils durch die katastrophale Mißgunst der Zeit in keinerlei Verhältnis zu diesen steht und daß der tägliche Kampf trotz des guten Willens Gutgesinnter einen in ständigem Atem hält.  Auch sind die Menschen selbst hier nicht mehr von jener absoluten Verläßlichkeit, wie man es früher gewohnt war - die Not hat sie eben auch schon ein wenig zermürbt.</tei:p><tei:p>Von meiner Tätigkeit haben Sie wahrscheinlich durch Herrn van Hoboken<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Anthony van Hoboken (1887-1983) [create biogfile].  Eminent musicologist and compiler of the standard <tei:hi rend="italic">Joseph Haydn: Thematisches-bibliographisches Werkverzeichnis</tei:hi> (3 vols.; Mainz: Schott’s Söhne, 1957-1978).  He was a pupil of Schenker’s and provided financial support for the publication of <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi>; at Schenker’s instigation, he founded the Archive for Photographs of Musical Manuscripts in the National Library at Vienna.</tei:note> gehört.  Das Schwierige an meinem Kurs „Einführung in die Lehre H. Schs.” ist der Umstand, daß er als Sonderkurs geht, d.h. von den Schülern des Konservatoriums extra bezahlt werden muß, eine fast unmögliche Sache in einer Zeit, wo die meisten um eine Ermäßigung des normalen Schulgeldes ansuchen müssen. Möglich daß nach Ostern hier eine Änderung geschaffen wird, jedenfalls bemühe ich mich in dieser Richtung.</tei:p><tei:p>Direktor Graener,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Paul Graener (1872–1944), German composer and conductor, who was from 1930 to 1934 Director of the Stern Conservatorium in Berlin.  In 1935, he replaced Richard Strauss as director of the composers’ division of the Reichsmusikkammer, a position he held until 1941.  (<tei:hi rend="italic">NGDM</tei:hi>2001)</tei:note> ein rührend guter Mensch, bemüht sich sehr für mich, aber es ist eben nicht alles von ihm abhängig.  Im übrigen hat er mir aufgetragen, Ihnen seine tiefste Verehrung auszudrücken.  Am 9. und 16. werde ich übrigens zwei Vorträge für die Lehrer halten.  (Den ersten: allgemeine Einführung in die Lehre vom Ursatz an Hand der Beiden ‚kleinen Präludien[’] in C; den zweiten unter dem Titel: „Geist der Form; Fuge und Sonate”).  Beiliegenden Aufsatz, den ich Ihnen zur gütigen Beurteilung ein- <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> sende, habe ich für die Allgemeine Musikzeitung bestimmt, an dessen Herausgeber, Paul Schwers, Dr. Furtwängler mir eine glänzende Empfehlung gegeben hat.  Es ist übrigens schon eine Umarbeitung, die erste Fassung war für die Leserschaft angeblich zu „schwer”!  Ja, der Inhalt der „führenden” Zeitschriften, das ist ein trauriges Kapitel.  Im Dezember habe ich im Rundfunk einen Vortrag über die „Wiederholung in der Musik” gehalten, ein weiterer über „Phantasien für Klavier” (Bach, Haydn, Beethoven) wird hoffentlich bald folgen.  (Übrigens spiele ich am 10. zum 100. Todestag Clementis am Rundfunk.)  Dies von mir für heute.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich hoffe, daß Sie sich voller Gesundheit erfreuen und sich rüstig und wohl fühlen.  Wie geht es Ihrer werten Frau Gemahlin? Macht Ihnen übrigens die Stunde mit den Weissezöglingen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Pupils of <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse.</ref>  This group, elsewhere called the "seminar" by both Schenker and Jonas, included Trude Kral, Greta Kraus, Felix Salzer, and Manfred Willfort; the published result of their studies was <tei:hi rend="italic">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln</tei:hi> (New York: David Mannes Music School, 1932).</tei:note> Freude?  Wenn es Ihre kostbare Zeit einmal erlaubt und Sie auch nur wenige Zeilen an mich richten würden, bedeutete es für mich eine innige Freude!  Indes verbleibe ich mit den besten Empfehlungen an Ihre werte Frau Gemahlin Ihr stets dankbarer</tei:p><tei:p>und ergebenster
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p><tei:p>Augenblicklich versuche ich mich an einem “Lehrbuch”,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  This is the first mention in the Jonas-Schenker correspondence of the work that would lead to Jonas's <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks: Eine Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers</tei:hi> (Vienna: Saturn-Verlag, 1934), the subtitle of which duplicates the title of the course about which Jonas speaks in paragraph 2.</tei:note> dessen Plan ich Ihnen gelegentlich vorlegen möchte.</tei:p><tei:p>Anbei 1 Aufsatz.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  The essay is not identified, and is not in the file containing this letter.</tei:note></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated March 3, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Berlin, March 3, 1932</tei:p><tei:p>Esteemed Herr Doctor!</tei:p><tei:p>I have heard with great pleasure of your interest in my endeavors here in Berlin.  If I have not written you in detail long before now, the reason is above all that, through the catastrophic malaise of the time, my efforts have for the most part produced no commensurate result, and the daily struggle, despite the good will of well-meaning people, makes one catch one’s breath.  And people here are themselves no longer so absolutely reliable as they used to be—privation has already worn them down somewhat.</tei:p><tei:p>You have probably heard of my activities through Herr van Hoboken.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  The difficulty with my course “Introduction to the Theory of Heinrich Schenker” is that it is held as a special course—i.e., one for which the students at the conservatory must pay extra, almost an impossibility at a time when most have to seek a reduction of the normal school fees.  Possibly a change will be made here after Easter -- at least I am working in that direction.</tei:p><tei:p>Director Graener,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> an affectingly good man, tries hard for me, but he does not have absolute say-so.  For the rest, he instructs me to convey his deepest respect to you.  On the 9th and 16th, incidentally, I will give two lectures for the faculty.  (The first: general introduction to the theory of the Ursatz with reference to the two “small preludes” in C; the second under the title: “Spirit of Form; Fugue and Sonata”).  The accompanying essay, which I send for your kind appraisal, is intended for the <tei:hi rend="italic">Allgemeine Musikzeitung</tei:hi>, to whose editor, Paul Schwers, Dr. Furtwängler provided me with a glowing recommendation.  It is, incidentally, already a revision; the first version was allegedly too “difficult” for the readership!  Ah, the contents of the “leading” periodicals—that’s a sad chapter.  In December I gave a radio lecture on “Repetition in Music,” and another on “Phantasies for Keyboard” (Bach, Haydn, Beethoven) will, I hope, follow soon.  (I play on the 10th, incidentally, on the radio for the 100th anniversary of Clementi’s death.)  So much for today.</tei:p><tei:p>I hope that you enjoy perfect health and feel vigorous and good.  How is your esteemed wife?  Did you, by the way, enjoy the lesson with the Weisse pupils?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  If your precious time permits and you would send me only a few lines, it would give me great pleasure!  Meanwhile I remain with best greetings to your good wife,</tei:p><tei:p>Your ever grateful and devoted
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p><tei:p>At the moment I am working on a “textbook,”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> whose outline I would like to show you at some point.</tei:p><tei:p>Enclosed: one essay<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/></tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>