<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 12/6, [31] : 4-15-34 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
©  Translation John Rothgeb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> Permission to publish on this website granted by the heirs of Oswald Jonas, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1934-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Oswald Jonas; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 04/15/1934 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated April 15, 1934</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-08-31</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Acks three communications;  Hoboken has increased subvention for Jonas's book; Furtwängler has agreed to write supporting letter.  —Proposes series of individual critical introductions to most frequently performed piano works and concertos.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Jonas, Oswald; Schenker, Heinrich; Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks;  Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  subvention;  support;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  concert tour;  Weisse, Hans;  Goos;  Neumünster;  Hamburg;  critical introductions;  piano works;  concertos</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated April 15, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>] Dr. OSWALD JONAS 
15. April 34</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Nun will ich Ihnen vor allem für Ihren gütigen Brief und die Karten<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  OJ 5/18, 38, April 7;  OJ 5/18, 39, April 10;  OJ 5/18, 40, April 11, 1934.</tei:note> danken.  Inzwischen habe ich von dem Verleger einen Brief bekommen, daß Hob.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> doch erhöht<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  i.e., has increased his support for Jonas’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks: Eine Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers</tei:hi> (Vienna: Saturn-Verlag, 1934).</tei:note> hat unter der Bedingung, daß der Preis der gleiche bleibt.  Nun über die Begleitumstände schreibe ich Ihnen noch, da ich selbst Hob geschrieben habe, worauf er noch nicht geantwortet hat.  (Bitte daher vorläufige Diskretion.)  Sie haben bis jetzt schon so viel von dem Buch gehört, daß ich fast fürchte, es könnte denn Ihren Erwartungen nicht entsprechen.  Zu vielem war leider der Raum zu gedrängt – auch mußte viel Raum den ersten Grunddingen gewidmet werden.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Furtw.</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Wilhelm Furtwängler [create biogfile and link].  Underscoring by the recipient, in magenta pencil.</tei:note> sprach ich noch Mittwoch im Konzert.  Er erzählte mir, daß in Wien seine Zeit zu knapp für einen Besuch war, und versprach mir, den Brief für das Buch zu schreiben.  Nur ist <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> er jetzt auf vierwochentlicher Konzertreise; ich habe zwar die Absicht, das Buch sofort nach Erscheinen ihm mit der wiederholten Bitte nachzusenden, eine Verzögerung wird es aber doch dadurch erleiden.  Denn für hiesige Biblioth. und Lehranstalten ist ein Begleitschreiben gerade von ihm unbedingt notwendig.  Wissen Sie vielleicht die Adresse von DrWeisse?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.</tei:note>  Er hat seinerzeit 7 Exempl. bestellt, weitere Bestellungen in Ansicht gestellt, hat aber keinen ausgefüllten Bestellschein eingewandt, noch sonst etwas.  Eine Bestellung von Goos,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  See also OJ 5/18, 41, April 23, 1934;  Goos was a pupil of Reinhard Oppel; in July 1933, S had written to Oppel asking whether he might write to Goos (Oppel F57, July 28, 1933). Already on April 27, 1933, Oppel had reported to S that Goos himself teaches S's theory, and that he had assembled a "Schenker week" for presentation on the radio.  In other correspondence Oppel commented that it was important to keep from Goos the fact that S was Jewish.</tei:note> Neumünster.  Ich glaube, daß diese Adresse von Ihnen stammt.  Was für eine Bewandtnis hat es mit diesen Leuten – vielleicht könnte ich mich mit ihnen in Verbindung setzen; Neumünster ist ja eine knappe Stunde von Hamburg.</tei:p><tei:p>Nun möchte ich Ihnen aber einen neuen Plan vorlegen, den ich gefaßt habe.  Hat das Buch nur einigermaßen Erfolg, so wäre <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> der Verlag leicht dazu zu gewinnen, zumal es sich um eine Sache handelt, die endlich auch weiteste Kreise interessieren und erfassen könnte.  Eine Reihe von Einführungen – zunächst 8-10 Hefte – in Klavierwerke (zunächst), die dann von Monat zu Monat fortgesetzt werden und mit der Zeit die häufigst gespielten Werke der Lit. umfassen könnte.  Jedem Heft (oder mindestens am Anfang) vorne eine kurzgefaßte “allgemeine” Einführung und Erläuterung, mit Erklärung der Termini.  Die Darstellung möglichst einfach, sehr auf das <tei:hi rend="italic">Praktische</tei:hi> gerichtet, mit Vortragsanweisungen etc.  Kein Heft stärker als 2-3 Bogen, Notenbeispiele auf Tafeln (zur Verbilligung) und sehr geringer Preis.  Ich glaube bestimmt, daß ein Großtel der klavierspielenden Welt danach greifen würde, das Verlangen nach ähnlichen ist indes bestimmt vorhanden.  An der Herausgabe könnten sich mehrere beteiligen – es wäre wieder ein schönes Zusammenarbeiten des Kreises (in der Öffentlichkeit) Hier ist es Usus, daß die Musikalienhändlern den bekannteren Leuten, die Neuer- <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> scheinungen ins Haus zur Ansicht senden – ich glaube, daß da große Möglichkeiten für so etwas wären.  Ich denke in einem Heft entweder ein größeres Werk&lt;strike&gt;e&lt;/strike&gt; oder 2 kleinere Sonaten oder mehrere Klavierstücke oder ein Konzert (besonders wichtig).  Ich stelle mir jedenfalls bereits einiges zusammen.  Erscheinen müßte es unbedingt Oktober.  Ich glaube, daß das Risiko so gering dabei wäre, daß nicht einmal eine besondere Finanzierung möglich<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Perhaps the German should have been “nötig,” necessary, rather than “möglich.”</tei:note> wäre.  Ein teures Buch kaufen sich die Leute nun einmal nicht – können es oft auch wirklich nicht, aber ein Heft zu -.60 eher, wenn der Inhalt sie reizt.  Es wäre das aber gleichzeitig das beste Werbemittel auch für die größeren Werke.  Ich bin neugierig, Ihre Ansicht darüber zu hören.  Ich habe bis jetzt noch niemand davon Mitteilung gemacht.</tei:p><tei:p>Für heute verbleibe ich mit allerergebensten Grüßen an Ihr werte Frau Gemahlin und Sie</tei:p><tei:p>stets Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p><tei:p>Heirs of Oswald Jonas, reproduced here with kind permission.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated April 15, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>] Dr. OSWALD JONAS 
April 15, 1934</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>Let me thank you first for your kind letter and the cards.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  In the meantime I have received a letter from the publisher to the effect that Hoboken<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> has offered more support<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> on the condition that the price remain the same.  I am writing you now about the attendant circumstances, as I have written Hoboken himself, which letter he has not yet answered. (Thus: discretion for the time being, please.) You have thus far heard so much about the book that I almost fear that it might not meet your expectations. For many things the available space was unfortunately too limited—and much space had to be devoted to the first foundational matters.</tei:p><tei:p>I spoke to <tei:hi rend="italic">Furtwangler</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> again on Wednesday at the concert. He told me that his time in Vienna was too short for a visit, and promised me to write the letter for the book. <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> But now he is on a four-week concert tour; it is my intention, however, to send him the book immediately on publication, with the repeated request to forward, although this will cause a delay. Because for local libraries and academies a cover-letter from him personally will be absolutely necessary. Do you perhaps know the address of Dr. Weisse?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> He ordered 7 copies earlier, and held out the prospect of additional orders, but has not sent in any filled-out order form or anything else. An order [arrived] from Goos,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> Neumünster. I believe that this address stems from you. What is the situation with these people—I could perhaps get in touch with them; Neumünster is barely an hour from Hamburg.</tei:p><tei:p>Now I would like to put before you a new plan that I have conceived. If the book has any success at all, it would be easy to get <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> the publisher interested in this, especially as it is a matter which could interest and appeal to the broadest circle. A series of critical introductions—at least 8-10 volumes—on piano works (at least), which are then continued from month to month and over time could encompass the most often performed works of the literature. Each volume to begin (or at least at the outset) with a concise "general" introduction and elucidation, with explanation of terms. The presentation as simple as possible, very much oriented toward the <tei:hi rend="italic">practical</tei:hi>, with performance instructions etc. No volume thicker than 2-3 fascicles, musical examples on plates (for reasons of economy) and at a very reasonable price. I definitely believe that a majority of the piano-playing public would buy it—there is certainly a demand for something of the sort. Several of us could participate in the editing—it would be a happy collaboration for the circle (in the public realm). The custom here is for music dealers to send <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> new publications to the homes of more well-known people on approval—I believe that there would be many possibilities for such a thing.  I think, in a given volume either a larger work or two smaller sonatas, or several piano pieces or a concerto (especially important).  In any case I am already assembling a few things.  It would absolutely have to come out in October.  I believe that the risk in such a venture would be so small, that not even a special underwriting would be possible.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>  People often don’t buy an expensive book—often can’t buy one—but are more likely to buy one for -.60 if the content appeals to them.  This would at the same time be the best publicity for the larger works as well.  I am curious to hear your opinion on this.  I have thus far communicated this to nobody.</tei:p><tei:p>For today I remain, with most highly respectful greetings to your good wife and yourself,</tei:p><tei:p>Ever yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>