<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 12/6, [32] : 6-11-34 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Oswald Jonas.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish on this website granted by the heirs of Oswald Jonas, March 2006</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1934-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Oswald Jonas; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 06/11/1934 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated June 11, 1934</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-02-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Reports progress on production of his Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks and its prospects.  Hopes still to give the Potsdam lecture arranged by Edwin Fischer. His article on Beethoven sketches for Zeitschrift für Musikwissenschaft is in press.  Refers to possible collaboration with Hoboken. Inquires as to S's Summer plans, and asks Brahms questions.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Jonas, Oswald; Schenker, Heinrich;  Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks; production; proofs; price; Furtwängler, Wilhelm; Fischer, Edwin; Postdam; Willfort, Manfred; Zeitschrift für Musikwissenschaft; Hoboken, Anthony van; Photogrammarchiv</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Berlin</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated June 11, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">printed:</tei:hi> ]Dr. OSWALD JONAS   [ <tei:hi rend="italic">handwritten:</tei:hi> ] Blin, den 11. Juni 34.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Entschuldigen Sie bitte mein langes Schweigen – meine Unschliessigkeit bezüglich meiner Pläne, vor allem ob ich hier bleiben soll oder nicht, ist die Hauptursache davon.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  At this point, J inserts an en-dash and continues on the same line.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Leider hat sich der Druck des Buches infolge einiger technischer Schwierigkeiten so verzögert, daß das Erscheinen nicht gerade zum günstigsten Zeitpunkt erfolgen wird.  Ich lese jetzt schon die letzten Druckkorrekturen mit den bereits eingesetzten Beispielen.  Alles geht immer sofort in die Druckerei und der 22. ist nun das endgültige Datum des Erscheinens.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  i.e. of his <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks: Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers</tei:hi> (Vienna: Saturn-Verlag, 1934).</tei:note>  Also jedenfalls gehen die Bücher noch im Omni hinaus und da ist doch noch Aussicht, daß es die Adressaten noch erreicht. <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Kauflust wird ja augenblicklich keine große sein – denke ich mir.  Aber im Herbst dann wird man ja doch schon etwas feststellen können.  Das Buch ist sehr [ <tei:hi rend="italic">corr. from</tei:hi> ja] billig!  (über 300 Seiten, 240 Notenbeispiele für M 5-!) Morgen soll ich Furtw.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Wilhelm Furtwängler [create biogfile]. Schenker recorded in his diary on June 10, 1934 the following report of a recent conversation with Furtwängler: “he praises Jonas most highly among all [my] students.”  Quoted in Hellmut Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker. Nach Tagebüchern und Briefen ...</tei:hi> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms Verlag, 1985), 130.</tei:note> anrufen, ich hoffe, daß er nicht wieder hinausschiebt und Schwierigkeiten macht, denn das ist nun einmal sehr wichtig.  Haben Sie ihn in Wien jetzt gesprochen?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  At this point, J inserts an en-dash and continues on the same line.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Vielleicht gelingt es mir doch, den Vortrag, den mir Edwin Fischer<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">   Click on <ref cRef="fischer_edwin">Edwin Fischer</ref>.</tei:note> für seinen Ausländerkurs in Potsdam zugesagt hat, halten zu können.  Ich soll morgen mit Fischer nochmals darüber sprechen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  See 12/6, [33].  At this point, J inserts an en-dash and continues on the same line.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Die neu orientierte Zeitschrift für Musikwiss. (jetzt Prof. Max Schneider<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Max Schneider (1875-1967), German musicologist.  The <tei:hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für Musikwissenschaft</tei:hi> was the principal organ of the Deutsche Musikgesellschaft, founded in 1918, and was edited by Alfred Einstein until he was removed in 1933 and Schneider took over.  </tei:note>) teilte mir vor einigen Tagen mit, daß mein Artikel (über Beethoven Skizzen) in die Setzerei gegangen <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> ist.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  The article was “Beethovens Skizzen und ihre Gestaltung zum Werk,” in <tei:hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für Musikwissenschaft</tei:hi> XVI/10 (October 1934).  </tei:note>  Also einige Möglichkeiten gibt es doch noch.  Hat Ihnen Hob.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> vielleicht eine Mitteilung davon gemacht, daß er eventuell an eine Zusammenarbeit mit mir denkt im Anschluß an meinem Plan der Erläuterungshefte<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  See 12/6, [31].</tei:note> (event. verbunden mit seinen beabsichtigten Publikationen aus dem Archiv<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Click on <ref cRef="photogrammarchiv">Photogrammarchiv</ref>. Plans were under discussion for a periodical to be issued by this Archiv.</tei:note>)[?] Bitte jedenfalls um Diskretion ihm gegen- über – man muß da ja so vorsichtig sein.  Das wäre freilich eine schöne Sache, wenn das zustande käme, denn mit den Stunden glaube ich nicht, daß es noch lange gehen wird.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  At this point, J inserts an en-dash and continues on the same line.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Willfort<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Manfred Willfort [create biogfile], a student of Schenker’s who had previously studied with Hans Weisse.</tei:note> ist hier, wie Sie wissen – wir sind oft beisammen und musizieren fleißig.  Wohin gedenken Sie im Sommer zu gehen und wie fühlen Sie sich gesundheitlich[?]  Ich hoffe zum allerbesten!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  At this point, J inserts an en-dash and continues on the same line.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Beiliegende Karte fand ich ihn einer Brahms Biographie reproduziert und finde leider nicht, worauf <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> sie sich bezieht.  Und in der op 110 auf der a^2^ – wollte Brahms es also nochmals angeschlagen wissen?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  See the response in 5/18, 43.</tei:note> Wissen Sie mir vielleicht da zu raten?</tei:p><tei:p>Empfehlen Sie mich bitte sehr Ihrer werten Frau Gemahlin.  Ich verbleibe mit den besten Grüßen und Wünschen für den Sommer</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr ganz ergebenster und
dankbarer
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated June 11, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">printed:</tei:hi> ] Dr. OSWALD JONAS    [ <tei:hi rend="italic">handwritten:</tei:hi> ] Berlin, June 11, 1934</tei:p><tei:p>Esteemed Herr Doctor!</tei:p><tei:p>Please excuse my long silence – my indecision regarding my plans, above all whether I should remain here or not, is the chief cause.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Unfortunately the printing of the book has been so delayed by several technical difficulties that publication will not come about at the most propitious time.  I am now reading the last proofs with examples already in place.  Everything goes immediately to the printer, and the 22nd is now the settled date of publication.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  Thus in any case the books go out by bus, and there is still the prospect that they will reach the addressees. <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> The market will not at present be very large, I think.  But we will know more in autumn.  The book is very inexpensive!  (More than 300 pages, 240 examples for 5 Marks!)  Tomorrow I should call Furtwängler;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  I hope that he will not delay again and make difficulties, because this time it is very important.  Have you spoken with him now in Vienna?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Perhaps it will still be possible for me to give the lecture that Edwin Fischer<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> had assigned me for his course in Potsdam for foreigners.  Tomorrow I should speak again with Fischer about it.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/></tei:p><tei:p>The re-oriented <tei:hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für Musikwissenschaft</tei:hi> (now Prof. Max Schneider<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/>) informed me a few days ago that my article (on Beethoven sketches) has gone to the typesetter.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Thus a few possibilities do still exist.  Has Hoboken<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> perhaps communicated that he is possibly considering a collaboration with me in connection with my plan for the explanatory publications<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> (possibly combined with his intended publication from the Archive<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/>)?  In any case please handle him with discretion – one must be so cautious.  It would certainly be a fine thing if that came about, because I don’t think it could continue long if supported only by lessons.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Willfort<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> is here, as you know—we are often together and diligently make music together.  Where do you plan to go in summer, and how do you feel as regards health?  I hope the very best!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>I found the enclosed card reproduced in a Brahms biography, and unfortunately cannot find what <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> it refers to.  And in Op. 110 at the a^2^ – does Brahms then want it re-attacked?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/>  Can you advise me on that?</tei:p><tei:p>Do please commend me to your good wife.  I remain, with best greetings and wishes for the summer,</tei:p><tei:p>Your devoted and 
grateful
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>