<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 12/6, [37] : 8-23-34 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Oswald Jonas, published here with kind permission.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> Permission to publish on this website granted by the heirs of Oswald Jonas, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1934-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Oswald Jonas; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 08/23/1934 01:01:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated August 23, 1934</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-09-22</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>J seeks advice on what to include in the first issue of the planned commentary editions;  distribution of his book is delayed until September;  J is correcting proofs of two articles.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Jonas, Oswald; Schenker, Heinrich;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  Ungar, Fritz;  commentary editions;  Chopin;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks;  Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers;   Grinzing;  Photogrammarchiv;  Zeitschrift für Musikwissenschaft</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated August 23, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>23. VIII 34</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Besten Dank für Ihre Zusendungen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  OJ 5/18, 51, August 18, 1934, with an unidentified card enclosed.</tei:note> und bitte wollen Sie die verursachte Mühe, an der ich vollkommen schuldlos bin, entschuldigen.</tei:p><tei:p>Ihre Nachricht bez. Herrn v. Hob<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> hat mich sehr interessiert.  Leider ist [er] mir bereits auf meine zweite Anfrage bezüglich seiner Pläne und wie er sich das mit Publikationen [vorstellt] bis heute jede Antwort schuldig geblieben.  Für mich peinlich, weil ich indes mit meinem Verleger hier doch die Sache wegen der “Einführungen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  The proposed commentary-editions; see OJ 12/6, [31].</tei:note> in Ordnung bringen will.  D^r^ Ungar<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Fritz Ungar, Jonas’s cousin and owner of Saturn-Verlag.</tei:note> hat sich entschlossen, Heft 1 in größerer Auflage auf seine Kosten herauszubringen und wir hoffen durch “Abonnements” die weitere Folge zu sichern.  Was soll im ersten Heft erscheinen.  Ich dachte vor allem an Chopin, wegen der Pianisten (op. 27 Des u. op 34 F<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Chopin Nocturne in D-flat, Op. 27 No. 1;  Waltz in F, Op. 34, No. 3.</tei:note>) – vielleicht kollidiert dies aber mit den Publ.-absichten Hob.?  Ich möchte auch [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr. from</tei:hi> auf] meine Ferienzeit nicht an eine Arbeit wenden, die nicht sofort für den Anfang nötig ist.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Oder halten Sie den Beginn mit Chopin für verfehlt?  An Furtw.,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Wilhelm Furtwängler [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> von dem ich garnichts mehr gehört hatte, habe ich geschrieben, daß die Versendung des Buches<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Jonas’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks: Eine Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers</tei:hi> (Vienna: Saturn-Verlag, 1934).</tei:note> also für Anfang Sept. aufgeschoben worden ist aus praktischen Gründen.  Darauf bekam ich ein gedruckte Karte, daß er mit wechseldender Adresse auf Reisen ist und im Herbst erst die Briefe beantworten wird.  Also eine vollkommene illusorische Angelegenheit.  Soll ich einfach aus seinem seinerzeitigen Empfehlungsschreiben einen Satz für die Buchschleife verwenden?  Für den Buchhandel in Deutschland halte ich das für absolut notwendig. – Hob. wollte ursprünglich Ende August hier sein, daß er erst am 5. 9. kommt, ist sehr schade.  Ich bin indes zu Besuch bei einem Freund in Grinzing – der ganze Sommer mitten in der Stadt ist zu unerfreulich (XIX Trummelhofgasse 4).</tei:p><tei:p>Weiter alles Gute Ihnen sowie Ihrer werten Frau Gemahlin.  Ihr
Dankbar ergebener
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p><tei:p>Ich habe bereits die Korrekturen für die engl. Übersetzung des Archiv Art.,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  “The Photogram-Archives in Vienna,” in <tei:hi rend="italic">Music and Letters</tei:hi> XV (1934) 344-347.  Click on <ref cRef="photogrammarchiv">Photogrammarchiv</ref>.</tei:note> sowie der Skizzen Art.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  “Beethovens Skizzen und ihre Gestaltung zum Werk,” in <tei:hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für Musikwissenschaft</tei:hi> XVI (1934), 449-459.</tei:note> für die Zeitschrift f. MusikW. bekommen.  Beide erscheinen im Septemberheft.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated August 23, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>August 23, [19]34</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>Thank you kindly for your mail,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> and please forgive the bother, of which I am entirely innocent.</tei:p><tei:p>Your news about Herr v. Hoboken<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> was most interesting.  Unfortunately my inquiry—the second already—about his plans and where he stands concerning publications, remains until now unanswered.  Unpleasant for me, because meanwhile I want to get the matter of the “introductions”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> settled here with my publisher.  Dr. Ungar<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> has decided to bring out vol. 1 in a larger printing at his own expense, and we hope to secure the continuation through “subscriptions.”  What should come out in the first issue.  I was thinking first of Chopin for the pianists (Op. 27 in D-flat and Op. 34 in F<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>)—but perhaps this would run afoul of Hob.’s publication intentions?  And, too, I would prefer not to devote my vacation time to work that is not necessary immediately for the beginning.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Or do you consider it a mistake to begin with Chopin? I have written Furtwängler,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> from whom I have heard nothing further, that the distribution of the book<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> has been postponed until beginning of September for practical reasons.  I then received a printed card, announcing that he is on the road with changes of address, and will answer the letters only in the fall.  Thus a completely illusory situation.  Shall I simply select a sentence from his earlier statement of recommendation for the dust-jacket?  I consider that absolutely necessary for the book trade in Germany. —Hoboken originally intended to be here at the end of August; it is a shame that he’ll not arrive until September 5.  Meanwhile I am visiting a friend in Grinzing—it is too unpleasant to remain in the city for the whole summer (XIX Trummelhofgasse 4).</tei:p><tei:p>Again, all good wishes to you and to your good wife.  Your
Gratefully respectful
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p><tei:p>I already have the proofs for the English translation of the Archive article,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> as well as for the sketches article for the <tei:hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für Musikwissenschaft</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/>  Both will come out in the September issue.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>