<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 12/6, [20] : 3-20-33 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Oswald Jonas, published here with kind permission.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> Permission to publish on this website granted by the heirs of Oswald Jonas, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1933-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Oswald Jonas; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 03/20/1933 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated March 20, 1933</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-07-01</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Van Hoboken is willing to advance 600 Mk for the Einführung; J inquires, in that regard, after the plan to reprint S's Harmonielehre, indicating that he had previously prepared a reformulation of that work for teaching purposes; alludes to introductory lectures to Furtwängler concerts, and the Handel-Brahms Saul project.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Jonas, Oswald; Schenker, Heinrich;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks;  Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers;  print-run;  advance;  Harmonielehre;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  concerts;  Ravag;  Vienna radio;  Brahms festival;  Einstein, Alfred;  Handel;  Brahms;  Saul</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated March 20, 1933</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>20 März 33</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Entschuldigen Sie bitte mein längeres Stillschweigen – es hatte verschiedene Gründe.  Vor allem wollte ich Ihnen doch schon etwas in der Buchangelegenheit<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  The situation regarding Jonas’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks.  Eine Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers</tei:hi> (Vienna: Saturn-Verlag, 1934).</tei:note> mitteilen können, eine Antwort von Hob.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> kam aber erst vor einigen Tagen.</tei:p><tei:p>Nachdem ich ihm die Antwort meines Verlegers mitgeteilt hatte, daß noch 200, allermindesten aber 150 Exempl. notwendig seien, schrieb er nun, daß er zu einer Ausgabe von 600 Mark bereit sei.  Es ist also endlich eine Basis und positive Antwort – die geringe Differenz wird sich sicherlich noch überbrücken lassen. Ich hoffe also, daß das Buch im Herbst und auch schon überall “wirken” kann.</tei:p><tei:p>Haben Sie indes wegen der Neuauflage der Harmonielehre<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Schenker’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (1906).</tei:note> etwas gehört?  Wie stellt sich die U.E.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Universal Edition, S's principal publisher from 1901 onward. [create biogfile and link]</tei:note> dazu?  Wenn keine Aussicht dazu besteht, da ja doch die Neuauflage einer starken Revision bedürfte, halten Sie es für zweckmäßig, meine „Einführung” so zu gestalten, daß sie <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> als vorläufiger Ersatz für die Harmonielehre stehen kann.  Bis zu einem gewissen Grade -ist- ^dürfte^ das ja auf jeden Fall nötig sein.  Ich selbst habe mir schon längst für Unterrichtswerke eine solche Neugestaltung der Harm. zurechtgelegt!  Wie weit <tei:hi rend="italic">soll</tei:hi> ich, wie weit <tei:hi rend="italic">darf</tei:hi> ich dies benutzen?  Sie können sich denken, verehrter Herr Doktor, daß mir <tei:hi rend="italic">Ihr</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  “Ihr”: double-underlined.</tei:note> Interesse und die Sache an erster Stelle steht.  Ich möchte Sie vielmals bitte[n], ^mir^ Ihre genaue Ansicht und Ihren Plan in dieser Richtung bald mitzuteilen.</tei:p><tei:p>– Die Absicht, Einführungsvorträge zu Furtw.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Wilhelm Furtwängler [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> Konzerten am Rundfunk zu halten, muß vorläufig infolge der veränderten Verhältnisse leider aufgeschoben sein – vielleicht gelingt es mir in Wien im Rahmen des Brahmsfestes bei der Ravag.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Radio Vienna.</tei:note>  Ich habe in diesem Sinn dahin geschrieben.  Eventuell auch wegen eines andern Vortrags (z. B. Archiv<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="photogrammarchiv">Photogrammarchiv</ref>.</tei:note>)</tei:p><tei:p>– Einen kurzen Aufsatz über “Saul”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Brahms’s arrangement for performance of Handel’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Saul</tei:hi> is among the autograph materials in the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde in Vienna.  Schenker had transcribed and edited this document (mentioning it to Jonas first on March 24, 1932: OJ 12/16, [11]), which he subsequently gave to Furtwängler (see OJ 5/18, 9) who in turn made it available to Jonas (see OJ 5/18, 21) for study and the writing of a commentary.  See also OJ 12/6 [18], and OJ 5/18 11, 19,22,  and 24.</tei:note> hat Dr Einstein<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Click on <ref cRef="einstein_alfred">Alfred Einstein</ref>.</tei:note> bei mir bestellt. – Nun heißt es <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> warten, wie sich alles weiter gestaltet.</tei:p><tei:p>Für heute verbleibe ich mit besten Empfehlungen an Ihre werte Frau Gemahlin und allen guten Wünschen</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr ergebenster
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated March 20, 1933</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>March 20, [19]33</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>Please forgive my long silence—there were various reasons for it.  Above all I wanted to be able already to tell you something about the book situation,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> but a reply from Hob.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> arrived only a few days ago.</tei:p><tei:p>After I relayed to him the response from my publisher that 200 copies, or at the very least 150, would be required, he wrote that he would be prepared to disbursement 600 Marks.  There is thus finally a basis and a positive answer—the small gap can certainly be bridged.  I hope therefore that the book can “get on it” in the fall, and do so everywhere right away.</tei:p><tei:p>Have you heard anything meanwhile about the reprint of <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi>?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  What is UE’s<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> position on that?  If none is contemplated, [e.g.] because the reprint would need a major revision, do you think it expedient to organize my “Einführung” in such a way that it can <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> serve as a temporary substitute for <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi>? To a certain extent that may in any case be needed.  I myself prepared such a reformulation of <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> for teaching purposes long ago!  How far <tei:hi rend="italic">should</tei:hi> I, how far <tei:hi rend="italic">may</tei:hi> I, use that?  You may imagine, esteemed Doctor, that <tei:hi rend="italic">your</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> interest and the subject matter are of primary concern to me.  I implore you to send ^me^ soon your precise opinion and your plan in this direction.</tei:p><tei:p>The project of presenting introductory lectures to the Furtwängler<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> concerts on the radio must for now, because of the altered circumstances, be postponed—perhaps it can be done in Vienna within the framework of the Brahms festival on the Ravag.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>  I have written them about this.  Also about the possibility of a different lecture (i.e. “Archive”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/>).</tei:p><tei:p>Dr Einstein<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> has commissioned a short essay by me on <tei:hi rend="italic">Saul</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> Now one must <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> wait to see how everything works out.</tei:p><tei:p>For today I remain, with warmest greetings to your good wife and with all good wishes,</tei:p><tei:p>Yours most sincerely,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>