<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 12/6, [33] : 6-29-34 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Oswald Jonas.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish on this website granted by the heirs of Oswald Jonas, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1934-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Oswald Jonas; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothbeg.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 06/29/1934 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Typed letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated June 29, 1934</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-02-04</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Acks OJ 5/18, 43; describes his summer travel plans; hopes to meet S in Vienna in August.  Reports state of play on his book, a proof copy of which Furtwängler is reading.  Reports on recent lecture, and prospect of another lecture.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Jonas, Oswald; Schenker, Heinrich; summer travel; Berlin; Czechoslovakia; Bayreuth; Furtwängler, Wilhelm; Vienna; Hoboken, Anthony van; Garmisch; Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks; proofs; wrapper; blurb; UE; Fischer, Edwin; Potsdam; Reger; dilletant; Eisner, Bruno; Mendessohn House; Schenker, Jeanette</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Berlin</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated June 29, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Blin, 29. VI 34</tei:p><tei:p>Hochverehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Tausend Dank für Ihren herzlichen Brief.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  i.e. OJ 5/18, 43, June 24, 1934.</tei:note> Innigst freue ich mich, daß Sie nun endlich zur gewünschten Ruhe und Erholung kommen. Ich selbst bleibe noch eine Woche in Berlin, fahre denn zu Bekannten in ^die^ Cechoslovakei — Ende Juli bin ich allen Voraussicht nach in Bayreuth, worüber Sie sicherlich erstaunt sein werden.  Ich soll dort für eine amerikanische Zeitung einen Bericht erstatten und Furtwängler<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Wilhelm Furtwängler [create biogfile].</tei:note> ist so freundlich, sich um Freikarten für mich zu bemühen.  August möchte ich gern in Wien sein.  Schön wäre das, wenn ich Sie auf der Fahrt dorthin besuchen könnte. – Von Hoboken<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> habe ich noch nichts wieder gehört; vor 4 Wochen schrieb ich ihm nach Amsterdam. <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Ob er wohl schon in Garmisch ist?</tei:p><tei:p>Nach neuerlichen Verzögerungen (es waren sogar nach der Klischierung in den Noten noch Korrekturen notwendig) soll das Buch am Montag versandtbereit sein.  Der Titel wurde geändert in “Das Wesen der musik. Kunstwerkes” Eine Einführung in die Lehre H. Sch.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  The closing quotation mark is premature and should be moved to the end of the sentence.</tei:note> Furtw. liest momentan einen Probeabzug — ich hoffe, daß er noch rechtzeitig mir den Brief geben kann, da er eventuell auch für die Schleife Verwendung finden soll.  An die Subskribenten wird das Buch jedenfalls sofort verschickt, eventuell noch ohne Schleife, da für sie ja eine Empfehlung nicht mehr nötig ist.  Ich warte jetzt die Vorschläge des Verlegers bezüglich der Einführungen in Heftform ab.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Jonas had put before Schenker and also his publisher the idea of a series of inexpensive commentary-editions of musical works, with editorial responsibility to be shared by members of Schenker's circle.  See 12/6, [31], April 15; 5/18, 41, April 23; 12/6, [32], June 11; 12/6, [36], August 6?; and 12/6, [37], August 23.</tei:note>  Übrigens wird die Annoncierung des Buches im Börsenblatt <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> und in den Zeitschriften erst im September erfolgen. – (Die U. E. hat ein Annonce Ihrer Werke abgelehnt!)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  J appears to have written the entire parenthesis in subsequent to starting the next paragraph; as a result, he had to squeeze "abgelehnt!)" ("declined")  in interlinearly below the line.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Mein Vortrag bei Edwin Fischer<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="fischer_edwin">Edwin Fischer</ref>.  See OJ 12/6, 32, which looks ahead to this lecture.</tei:note> ist also Dienstag glücklich von Stapel gegangen.  Es waren die meisten seiner Schüler, auch die Teilnehmer des Potsdamer Ausländerkurses (ca 30 Leute) da.  Der Abend war sehr angeregt.  Die Diskussion zwar auf den üblichen banalen Fragen (“haben die Leute das <tei:hi rend="italic">gewußt</tei:hi>”?  “Warum gilt es nicht auch für Reger etc” u. s. w. – na ja!) basiert — aber jedenfalls wurde doch bei vielen großes Interesse wachgerufen und das kann ja noch weiterwirken.  Im übrigen mache ich mir da schon lange keine Illusionen mehr – die Menschen sind in ihren künstlerischen Anschauungen doch zumeist auf dem Standpunkt kindlicher Dilletanten.  Der Abend endete sehr fröhlich bei Bowle, Grammophon und (wirklich sehr geschickten) Tanzimprovi- <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> - sationen auf 2 Klavieren.  – Vorgestern war ein Hauskonzert von Bruno Eisner<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Bruno Eisner [create biogfile].  Viennese-born pianist who, like Jonas, taught at the Stern Conservatory in Berlin.</tei:note> (den ich augenblicklich mit der Lehre bekannt mache) im Hause Mendelssohn, wo ich im Herbst hoffentlich auch einen Vortrag werde halten können.  Mindestens sind die Leute für mich sehr interessiert.  Wenn im Verein mit ^all^ dem sich dann auch für mich bessere Lebens- und Arbeitsbedingungen einstellen würden, wäre es jedenfalls sehr erfreulich.  Die Aussichten sind vorläufig nicht demnach.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich danke Ihnen sehr für Ihre lieben Wünsche und erwidere Sie auf das allerherzlichste.  Grüßen Sie sehr Ihre liebe Frau Gemahlin.</tei:p><tei:p>In steter Ergebenheit
Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated June 29, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Berlin, June 29, 1934</tei:p><tei:p>Esteemed Herr Doctor!</tei:p><tei:p>Many thanks for your warm letter.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  I take deepest pleasure that you now at last achieve the desired rest and rejuvenation.  I myself remain another week in Berlin, then travel to acquaintances in Czechoslovakia. – At the end of July I will in all likelihood be in Bayreuth, which will certainly surprise you.  There I am supposed to prepare a report for an American newspaper, and Furtwängler<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> is so kind as to arrange complimentary tickets for me.  In August I should like very much to be in Vienna.  It would be lovely if I could visit you on the trip there.  – I have heard nothing more from Hoboken;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> 4 weeks ago I wrote to him in Amsterdam.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Is he still in Garmisch?</tei:p><tei:p>After recent delays (corrections to the examples were necessary even after the plates were made) the book should be ready for distribution on Monday.  The title has been changed to <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks.  Eine Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  Furtwängler is currently reading a proof copy – I hope that he will be able to give me the letter in time, since it is possibly also to be used for the wrapper.  The subscribers will be sent the book immediately in any case, possibly even without wrapper, since no recommendation is needed for them.  I await the suggestions of the publisher regarding the introductory essays in installments.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  Incidentally the advertisement of the book will come out in the financial pages <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> and the journals only in September.  (Universal-Edition has declined an advertisement of your works!)<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/></tei:p><tei:p>My lecture for the Edwin Fischer<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> class was launched successfully on Tuesday.  Most of his students, and also the participants in the Potsdam course for foreigners (about 30 people) were there.  The evening was very energetic.  The discussion based naturally on the usual banal questions (“were the composers <tei:hi rend="italic">conscious</tei:hi> of that?” “Why doesn’t this apply also to Reger etc.” and so forth.  So fine!) – but in any case great interest was aroused in many, and that can have further repercussions.  For the rest I have long ceased to have any illusions – people in their artistic viewpoints are mostly at the level of childish dilletants.  The evening ended on a very cheerful note with punch, phonograph records, and (really very accomplished) dance-improvisations <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> with two pianos.  Day before yesterday there was a house-concert by Bruno Eisner<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> (to whom I am now introducing the theory) at the Mendelssohn House, where I hope also to be able to deliver a lecture in the fall.  At least the people are very interested in me.  It would be very gratifying in any case if, along with all of that, better living and working conditions would issue for me.  The initial prospects do not hold much promise of that.</tei:p><tei:p>I thank you very much for your kind wishes and reciprocate most warmly.  My greetings to your dear wife.</tei:p><tei:p>With unceasing respect,
Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>