<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 12/6, [5] : 11-28-30 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Oswald Jonas, reproduced here with kind permission.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> Permission to publish on this website granted by the heirs of Oswald Jonas, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1930-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Oswald Jonas; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 11/28/1930 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated November 28, 1930</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-04-21</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>J regrets any misunderstanding over his request for "a few lines of recommendation"; he had intended only to ask for "general lines," not recommendations to individuals.  J clarifies S's confusion over his Munich lecture, and points to his devotion to S's cause for fifteen years, stating what he considers to be the core of S's thought as he would publicly represent it.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Jonas, Oswald; Schenker, Heinrich;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm; Weisse, Hans; Munich; Berlin; recommendation; lecture; Auskomponierung; composing-out; horizontalization; tonal space</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated November 28, 1930</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>28. Nov 1930
Hochverehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Wenn mein Schreiben an Sie<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  i.e. OJ 12/6, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.</tei:note>, November 17, 1930.</tei:note> wirklich so undeutlich war, so bedauere ich dann auf das tiefste – irgendwie bewußt ist es mir heute nicht.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  S’s response is OJ 5/18, 2, November 26, 1930.</tei:note>  Zunächst hatte ich doch, so viel ich mich erinnere, um allgemeine, nicht an bestimmte Personen gerichtete Zeilen gebeten, die mich nichts anderes vorläufig als legitimieren sollten – für Furtwängler<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Wilhelm Furtwängler [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> selbst wären doch sicherlich auch solche von D^r^ Weisse<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.</tei:note> genügend gewesen, ganz abgesehn davon, daß mir selbstverständlich klar war, daß eine solche Inkommodation im jetzigen Zeitpunkt doch eine Unmöglichkeit und eine Unbescheidenheit gegenüber Furtwängler gewesen wäre.  Ich schrieb doch: vor allem bei F.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  These words are quoted from the letter under discussion, OJ12/6, [4].</tei:note> dh. doch nur, daß eine solche Legitimation von F. am ehesten anerkannt würde, aber doch nicht, daß sie ausschliesslich für ihn bestimmt wäre oder gar als persönliche Bitte an ihn gedacht war; denn das war mir unbedingt klar, daß ein Weg von mir zu Furtwängler jetzt ein rein persönliches nur sein könnte (soweit es jedem unbenommen ist, ihn für sich zu interessieren) aber niemals jetzt unmittelbar von D^r^ Weisse oder Ihnen, verehrter Herr Doktor, unterstützt werden könnte.  Ich habe schon D^r^ Weisse geschrieben, wie mich gerade die Einsicht dieser Unmöglichkeit solange unnütz in München zurückgehalten hat trotz des Zuredens aller Bekannten, es doch lieber in Berlin zu versuchen, und noch lange, als ich sogar eines Zugangs zu Furtw. von befreundeter Münchner Seite sicher war – Dinge, die in Anbetracht meiner so schwierigen Lage doch nicht ganz außer acht gelassen werden sollten.</tei:p><tei:p>Völlig rätselhaft aber ist mir, warum Sie aus meiner Mitteilung, daß ich in München einen Vortrag gehalten habe, schließen, daß ich in Berlin nun auch reden möchte – das habe ich nun doch -auch- in meinem Brief auch nicht mit einem Wort angedeutet, wüßte auch nicht, wo ich dazu die Möglichkeit nehmen sollte, abgesehn davon daß ich augenblicklich gar keinen Sinn darin erkennen könnte.</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr Skeptizismus nun gegenüber dem “Inhalt meiner Vorträge” (es handelt sich übrigens nur um einen) – er mag mich auch schmerzlich berühren – begreiflich ist ^er^ mir natürlich, haben Sie doch Jahre hindurch von mir nichts Direktes mehr gehört, wenn ich auch annehmen konnte, daß D^r^ Weisse, der mir selbst (es -mir- ist mir nicht angenehm, von <tei:hi rend="italic">mir</tei:hi> sprechen zu müssen) schon soviel Anerkennendes, auch Schmeichelhaftes über mein Erkennen und Wissen in Ihrer Lehre<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  comma deleted at this point.</tei:note> gesagt hat, mich manchmal in diesem Sinn auch Ihnen gegenüber erwähnt hat.  Warum Sie da gerade von mir, der ich seit mehr als 15 Jahren Ihnen und Ihrer Sache <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> ergeben bin – mindestens mit viel Herz, annehmen, daß ich Ihnen nun doch in der Folge nicht zustimmen könnte, das muß ich wohl nun hinnehmen, wiewohl ich so gut wie nur eines weiß und es mir nie aus dem Sinn gekommen ist, daß in geistigen Dingen nur das Absolute Geltung haben kann und ^ich^ daher auch in der “Folge” zustimmen mußte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  The final word in the German text probably a writing error for “müßte.”</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Selbst wenn man in einem Vortrag vor Leuten, die doch zunächst in eine fremde Sache eingeführt und für sie gewonnen werden sollen, noch einfacher sein müßte und manches “Esoterische” für ein weiteres zuerst zurückbehalten müßte, wer könnte da auf ein Nichtzustimmen schließen – solange das absolut Künstlerische im Vordergrund steht, und das kann auf jeder Stufe gewahrt werden; das Absolute ist im Standpunkt – wenn bei der Mitteilung auch noch vieles ungesagt bleiben muß.  Und so konnte ich auch zuerst vor allem nur von dem sprechen, was mir zunächst als das Wichtigste (und auch als der fundamentale Unterschied zu jeder andern “Theorie”) erscheint: der Begriff der Auskomponierung, die Reproduktion des vertikalen (naturgegebenen) Klanges in die Zeit durch Horizontalisierung dem Verlauf der Musik in der Zeit entsprechend, woraus ^sich^ der neue und wahre Tonalitätsbegriff ableitet: Absteckung des Tonraumes (wodurch der Zeitverlauf gleichsam nun überwunden ist) – Wer könnte in einem Vortrag außer dem Wesentlichen schon <tei:hi rend="italic">alles</tei:hi> sagen?</tei:p><tei:p>Ich bitte Sie, verehrter Herr Doktor, mir all diese Erklärungen nicht übel nehmen zu wollen – gesagt mußte es doch sein – und bitte bewahren Sie mich im Andenken</tei:p><tei:p>als Ihren <tei:hi rend="italic">stets</tei:hi> ergebenen
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p><tei:p>Wollen Sie bitte auch meiner [ <tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi> ] Verehrung Ihrer werten Frau Gemahlin gegenüber ausdrücken.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated November 28, 1930</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>November 28, 1930
Dearr Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>If my letter to you<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> was really so unclear, then I am most deeply sorry—I am not in any way aware of it today.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  In the first place, I had, as I recall, requested general lines (not ones directed to particular individuals), which would serve me only as a preliminary legitimation—for Furtwängler<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> himself such recommendation from Dr. Weisse<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> would also have been sufficient, completely apart from the fact that it was undoubtedly clear to me that such an imposition at the present time would have been an impossibility and a presumption.  I wrote, however, “above all with Furtwängler”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> meaning only that such a legitimation would most readily be accepted as such by Furtwängler, but not that it would be intended exclusively for him or was conceived as nothing short of a personal request to him; because it was absolutely clear to me that a connection from me to Furtwängler now could be only a purely personal one (to the extent that anyone can take the liberty of applying to him), but could never at this time be directly supported by Dr. Weisse or by you, esteemed Doctor.  I have already written to Dr. Weisse about how precisely the realization of this impossibility has kept me unnecessarily in Munich so long, despite the urging of all acquaintances to try Berlin instead, and still a long time, even after I was assured of access to Furtwängler by Munich friends.—[These are] things which, in view of my very difficult situation, really should not be left out of consideration.</tei:p><tei:p>But it is a complete mystery to me how, from my statement that I gave a lecture in Munich, you infer that I would also like to speak in Berlin—<tei:hi rend="italic">that</tei:hi> I did not suggest with a single word of my letter, nor would I know where I could find the opportunity to, all of this aside from the fact that at the moment I can see no point at all in it.</tei:p><tei:p>Your scepticism concerning the “content of my lectures” (there was, incidentally, only one)—however much it may pain me—is naturally understandable: for years you have no longer heard anything direct from me, though I could assume that Dr. Weisse, who has told me personally (it is not pleasant to have to speak of <tei:hi rend="italic">myself</tei:hi>) so much of an approving, even flattering, nature about my understanding and knowledge of your theory, has occasionally mentioned me in this vein to you as well.  Why you assume that I, who <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> have been devoted to you and your cause for more than fifteen years, wholeheartedly at least, could later nevertheless fail to agree with you: to that I must now resign myself, although I know practically only one thing and have never lost sight of it, [namely] that in matters of the spirit only the absolute can have validity, and ^I^ therefore would be<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> obliged to agree “later” as well.</tei:p><tei:p>Even if, in a lecture for people who are to have an unfamiliar idea introduced in a way that wins their conviction, one has to simplify and reserve some “esoteric” matters for a later presentation, who could there infer a lack of agreement—so long as the absolute artistic stands in the foreground, and that can be ensured at every stage; the absolute is in the perspective—even if in the process of communication much must still remain unsaid.  And thus I could speak at first above all of that which appears to me at the outset as the most important idea (and as the fundamental contrast to every other “theory”): the concept of Auskomponierung, the reproduction of the vertical (naturally-given) chord in time through horizontalization corresponding to the playing-out of music through time, from which the new and true tonality-concept emerges: staking-out of the tonal space (which enables us to cope, so to speak, with the temporal succession)—who could present in a lecture, besides the most important matters, <tei:hi rend="italic">everything</tei:hi> at once?</tei:p><tei:p>I beg you, dear Doctor, not to take all of these explanations amiss; it had, in any case, to be said.  And please think always of me as</tei:p><tei:p>Your <tei:hi rend="italic">ever</tei:hi> grateful
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Oswald Jonas</tei:p><tei:p>Please convey my esteem also to your good wife.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>