<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 12/6, [39] : 11-28-34 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Oswald Jonas, published here with kind permission.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> Permission to publish on this website granted by the heirs of Oswald Jonas, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1934-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Oswald Jonas; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 11/28/1934 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Typed letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated November 28, 1934</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-10-03</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>J has agreed to let his publisher conduct a lawsuit against Willi Reich; he has written up the documentary evidence of the case and asks S to circulate it among his circle. —Reports his activities in Berlin. — Reports his dispute with the Jüdischer Verlag.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Jonas, Oswald; Schenker, Heinrich;  Reich, Willi;  Ungar, Fritz;  Saturn-Verlag;  Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks;  Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers;  Schwers, Paul;  Berg, Alban;  Lulu Suite;  Wolf, Hans;  Fromm, Mrs;  Jüdischer Verlag;  Jewish Press;  Jüdisches Lexicon;  Schoenberg;  Kastner, Rudolf</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Berlin</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated November 28, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Berlin, den 28.XI.1934
Sehr verehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Nach mancherlei Überlegung habe ich dem Drängen des Verlegers nachgegeben und ihm die Vollmacht zur Klage eingesandt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  I.e. lawsuit against Willi Reich and/or the journal <tei:hi rend="italic">23— eine Wiener Musikzeitschrift</tei:hi>: see OC 44/9, October 27, 1934.  The publisher was J’s cousin, Dr. Fritz Ungar, owner of Saturn-Verlag.  </tei:note>  Mein Zaudern kam aus der Erwägung, daß ich nicht in Wien und bei der Verhandlung nicht anwesend sein kann.  Herr Reich könnte aber dem Richter einen “Dreh” vormachen, dem der Anwalt aus Sachunkenntnis einfach nicht gewachsen wäre.  So habe ich mich entschlossen, beiliegendes “Opus”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Undoubtedly Oswald Jonas, “Vorläufer und Nachläufer. (Ein Dokumentarischer Nachweis)” (unpubd. manuscript, carbon copy preserved as OJ 38/52).  Willi Reich (see OC 44/9, October 27, 1934) had accused Jonas of lying in his assertion (in <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks</tei:hi>, p. 54) that Brahms had been represented by the Schoenberg partisans as a “predecessor” (<tei:hi rend="italic">Vorläufer</tei:hi>) of Schoenberg. “Vorläufer und Nachläufer. (Ein Dokumentarischer Nachweis)” provided documentary proof that Brahms had repeatedly been so represented (thus establishing Jonas’s veracity).  Click on <ref cRef="schoenberg_arnold">Arnold Schoenberg</ref>.</tei:note> zu verfassen, erstens um die Nötige Materialuntergrundlage für den Anwalt zu bieten, dann aber um die Herren so zu erledigen, wie es für Schwindler paßt: satirisch und sie zu entlarven.  Ob es Herr Schwers,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Paul Schwers, editor of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Allgemeine Musikzeitung</tei:hi>.</tei:note> den ich darum ersucht habe, bringen wird, weiß ich noch nicht.  Ich zweifle noch daran, wiewohl es ihm willkommen sein könnte in Anbetracht der der [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] bevorstehenden Aufführung der “Lulusuite” von Alban Berg!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Berg’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Symphonische Stücke aus der Oper “Lulu”</tei:hi> was given its première in Berlin on November 30, 1934 under Erich Kleiber—the latter’s last concert before resigning from his post at the Berlin Staatsoper on December 4 in protest against the Nazis’ embargo on works such as <tei:hi rend="italic">Lulu</tei:hi>.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Jedenfalls bitte ich Sie, verehrter Herr Doktor, die Blätter indes unter Ihren Kreis zirkulieren zu lassen, ein Exemplar auch Hans Wolf<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="wolf_hans">Hans Wolf</ref>.</tei:note> (dessen Adresse ich verlegt habe) zu geben.  Er soll es aber nicht gleich Herrn Reich unter die Nase halten – mindestens nicht vor der Verhandlung.  Vielleicht gibt der Verleger ein kleines Flugblatt heraus!  Halten Sie das für richtig.  Sonst werden die Herren ja immer frecher.</tei:p><tei:p>Neulich habe ich in Hamburg bei Frau Fromm<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Apparently a Hamburg-based pianist.  OJ 12/6, [30], March 16, 1934, mentions a “Frau Michaels” for whom (or for whose class) Jonas might give a “course”; OC 44/9, October 27, 1934, refers to a “Fromm-Michaels” for whom he is to give a lecture “next time.”  Probably Michaels, Fromm-Michaels, and the “Frau Fromm” cited here are the same persion.</tei:note> einen Vortrag gehalten – zunächst über die “Wiederholung”, das die Leute sich aber beschwert haben daß sie daraus noch zu wenig über den eigentlichen “Schenker” erfahren <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> haben, wird nun jedesmal bei meinem Aufenthalt dort fortgesetzt werden. Die Gemeinde wächst!</tei:p><tei:p>Wie geht es Ihnen gesundheitlich?  Sind Sie auch mit dem Fortschritt der Korrekturen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Proofs for <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi> ( <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:hi> III).</tei:note> zufrieden?</tei:p><tei:p>Ich hatte und habe hier leider eine böse Affäre mit dem Jüd. Verlag.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Jüdischer Verlag:  a publishing house founded in 1902 by Martin Buber and others to serve as a “central agency for the promotion of Jewish literature, art and scholarship.” Its publications included the <tei:hi rend="italic">Jüdisches Lexicon</tei:hi> (1927–30), for which Alfred Einstein had provided the musical component, including an article on Schenker (quoted derisorily in OJ 12/6, [27], December 18, 1933), the <tei:hi rend="italic">Babylonischer Talmud</tei:hi>, translated by L. Goldschmidt (1930–36), the <tei:hi rend="italic">Weltgeschichte des Jüdischen Volkes</tei:hi> by Simon Dobnow (1925–29), and works by Theodor Herzl, including <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Judenstaat</tei:hi> (1920).  The press was prohibited in 1938.  </tei:note>  Aus dem mir zugesandten Revisionsabzug entnahm ich, daß ohne mein Wissen und ohne meine Einwilligung von fremder Hand (ich kenne sie) ein Hymnus-abschnitt über Schönberg nebst anderen Veränderungen (auch in den Zeilen über Schenker) eingestreut worden war – unter meinem Namen.  Sie können sich meinen Schreck und meine Empörung vorstellen.  Zeitraubender Briefwechsel und Laufen zum Anwalt war die Folge.  Und das gerade in diesem Moment der “23” Geschichte!  Die Sache ist noch nicht zu Ende!  Aus einer Bemerkung im letzten Brief von Wolf an mich schloß ich, daß Herr Reich darüber bereits vom Täter, Herrn Rudolf Kastner,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Perhaps reference is to Rudolf Kastner (1906–57), lawyer; during World War II he was head of the Jewish Rescue and Relief Committee in Budapest, and served as a conduit between the Nazis and the Hungarian Jewish community.  Found guilty of Nazi collaboration in his trial in 1954–58, he was assassinated by a Holocaust survivor in Israel in 1957.</tei:note> der jetzt in Wien weilt, “informiert” worden ist.  Eine saubere Welt!!!</tei:p><tei:p>Mit ergebensten Grüßen an Sie sowie Ihre werte Frau Gemahlin
stets Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">unsigned</tei:hi> ]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  This letter appears to be a carbon copy of a missing original.</tei:note></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Jonas to Schenker, dated November 28, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Berlin, den September 28, 1934
Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>After much consideration I have yielded to the urging of the publisher and have authorized him to conduct the suit.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  My hesitation came from the reflection that I cannot be in Vienna and be present at the hearing.  Mr. Reich, however, could pull a “trick” on the judge, which the lawyer, through lack of technical understanding, simply wouldn’t be able to handle.    So I have decided to write up the enclosed “Opus”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> in order first to provide necessary material foundations for the lawyer, but then also to deal with the gentlemen in a way fitting for swindlers: satirically, and to expose them.  Whether Mr. Schwers,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> whom I have asked about it, will use the text I don’t yet know.  I have doubts about how welcome it will be to him in light of the forthcoming performance of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Lulu Suite</tei:hi> by Alban Berg!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/></tei:p><tei:p>In any event, Doctor, I ask you please to circulate the pages among your circle, and also to give a copy to Hans Wolf<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> (whose address I have misplaced).  But he shouldn’t immediately hold it under Herr Reich’s nose—at least not before the hearing.  Perhaps the publisher will bring out a small pamphlet!  Do you think that would be appropriate[?]  Otherwise the gentlemen will become ever more impudent.</tei:p><tei:p>Recently at Mrs. Fromm’s<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> in Hamburg I gave a lecture on “Repetition,” about which people complained that they learned from it too little about the real “Schenker.” <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> It will be continued each time I stay over there.  The circle grows!</tei:p><tei:p>How is your health?  Are you satisfied too with the progress of the proofreading?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/></tei:p><tei:p>I unfortunately had and still have here an unpleasant affair with the Jewish Press.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/>  I learned from the proof-copy sent me that, without my knowledge and permission, a section adulating Schoenberg was inserted in a foreign hand (I recognize it), as well as other alterations (even in the lines on Schenker)—under my name.  You can imagine my horror and outrage.  Time-consuming correspondence and trips to the lawyer were the result.  And this precisely at the moment of the <tei:hi rend="italic">23</tei:hi> episode!  The matter is not over yet!  From a comment in the last letter to me from Wolf I gathered that Mr. Reich has already been “informed” about it by the culprit, Mr. Rudolf Kastner,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> who is now staying in Vienna.  A sanitary world!</tei:p><tei:p>With most respecful greetings to you and to your good wife,
Yours as ever,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">unsigned</tei:hi> ]<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/></tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>