<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/31, [9] : 6-5-06 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Heinrich Schenker; reproduced here by kind permission of the Deutsches Literaturarchiv, Cotta-Archiv (Stiftung der Stuttgarter Zeitung), Marbach am Neckar.
© Transcription Ian D. Bent 2005.
© Translation Ian D. Bent 2005.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian D. Bent 2005
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission granted by the Cotta Archiv of the Schiller-Nationalmuseum/Deutsches Literaturarchiv, 07-20-05</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance> Schenker, Heinrich (1906-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In public domain; reproduced here by kind permission of the Deutsches Literaturarchiv, Cotta-Archiv (Stiftung der Stuttgarter Zeitung), Marbach am Neckar; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian D. Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 06/05/1906 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cotta ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cotta to Schenker, dated June 5, 1906</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2005-06-01</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>[NMTP I = Harmonielehre:] Acknowledges CA 27; advises against simultaneous publication of main work and Afterword; will try to accommodate Schenker's timetable for proofs.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cotta, J. G.; Schenker, Heinrich;  NMTP; Harmonielehre; Theory of Harmony;  Nachwort;  Afterword; separate publication; Part II; proofs; timing</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Stuttgart and Berlin</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Vienna IX [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>]</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cotta to Schenker, dated June 5, 1906</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="bold">= CA 28 = OJ 59/9, p.4</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> CA 28 = Cotta’s carbon copy; OJ 59/9 = Jonas’s transcription of excerpts of the Cotta correspondence.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">Cotta letterhead</tei:hi>]
STUTTGART, den [<tei:hi rend="italic">handwritten:</tei:hi>] 5. Juni. 1906.</tei:p><tei:p>Herrn <tei:hi rend="italic">Dr. Heinrich Schenker,  <tei:hi rend="italic">Wien IX.</tei:hi></tei:hi> [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr!</tei:p><tei:p>Ihrem gefl.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">   OJ 59/9 reads incorrectly as “Hier im” (Here in).</tei:note> Briefe vom 4. d. M.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  = CA 27.  </tei:note> für den wir bestens danken, entnehmen wir, daß Sie beabsichtigen, das Nachwort von dem Hauptwerk “Musikalische Theorien und Phantasieen” [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] zu trennen und unter besonderem Titel, etwa “Beethoven oder Wagner”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  “Beethoven or Wagner”: Schenker’s full putative title, given in CA 27, is [']"<tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven</tei:hi> oder <tei:hi rend="italic">Wagner</tei:hi>?“ ein Nachwort zu den <tei:hi rend="italic">M. Th. u. Ph.</tei:hi>’ (“Beethoven or Wagner?”: an Afterword to <tei:hi rend="italic">Musical Theories and Fantasies</tei:hi>). It was this that Schenker later entitled <tei:hi rend="italic">Über den Niedergang der Kompositionskunst,—eine technisch-kritische Untersuchung</tei:hi> (The Decline of the Art of Composition–A Technical-Critical Inquiry), which remained unpublished, and survives in OC 31/pp.28–153 as a complete but untitled typescript, subsequently heavily reworked by Schenker.  For an edition with translation and Introduction by William Drabkin, see <tei:hi rend="italic">Music Analysis</tei:hi> XXIV/1–2 (March–July 2005), pp. 3–232.  </tei:note> erscheinen zu lassen.  Da Sie auf das Nachwort mit Rücksicht auf die Tendenz des Werkes ein großes Gewicht legen, so pflichten wir Ihrer Absicht bei; jedoch möchten wir dringend davon abraten, das Nachwort <tei:hi rend="italic">gleichzeitig</tei:hi> mit dem Hauptwerk erscheinen zu lassen, da nach unserer Überzeugung dies dem Absatz des Hautpwerkes nichts weniger als förderlich<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Original has “nothing less than advantageous”.</tei:note> ist.  Da- <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> gegen würde der Herausgabe des Nachwortes nach Verlauf etwa eines halben Jahres oder einer längeren Frist nach Erscheinen des Hauptwerkes nichts im Wege stehen.  Es ist die getrennte Erscheinungsweise der einzelnen Teile namentlich bei wissenschaftlichen Werken sehr gebräuchlich und hierbei trägt der später erscheinende Teil in der Regel zur Förderung des Absatzes des früheren Teiles bei indem er auf diesen erneut aufmerksam macht.</tei:p><tei:p>Ihrem Wunsche, die Notenbeispiele des zweiten Teiles bis Ende <tei:hi rend="italic">Juni</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  So that he can depart for his annual holiday in the South Tyrol at that time.  Cf. undated draft letter of 1905 or 1906, OJ 5/6, [2], stating that he wanted to keep the Spring and Summer clear for enjoying music.</tei:note> zur Korrektur zu erhalten, werden wir nach Möglichkeit gern nachkommen. Den Text einschließlich der in demselben enthaltenen Notenbeispiele hat die Druckerei bis Ende dieses Monats zu liefern zugesagt, die ohne Text (als Anhang)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Perhaps he means music examples that fall at the end of §-sections.  There is no “appendix” as such.</tei:note> beigegebenen Notenbeispiele werden dagegen erst Anfang <tei:hi rend="italic">Juli</tei:hi> im Satze fertig.  Jedenfalls werden wir unsererseits die Fertigstellung nach Kräften zu beschleunigen suchen.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit vorzüglicher Hochachtung
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] J. G. Cottasche Buchhandlung Nachf.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cotta to Schenker, dated June 5, 1906</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="bold">= CA 28 = OJ 59/9, p.4</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">Cotta letterhead</tei:hi>]
STUTTGART, [<tei:hi rend="italic">handwritten:</tei:hi>]June 5, 1906</tei:p><tei:p>Dr. Heinrich Schenker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Vienna IX.</tei:hi> [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Sir!</tei:p><tei:p>We are grateful for your est’d<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> letter of the 4th inst,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> from which we gather that you have in mind separating the Afterword from the main work, <tei:hi rend="italic">Musical Theories and Fantasies</tei:hi>, and publishing it under separate title, along the lines of “Beethoven or Wagner.”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> Since you lay great stress on the Afterword considering the views it expresses, we agree with your opinion.  However, we would strenuously advise you against releasing the Afterword and the main work simultaneously, since we are convinced that this is less than advantageous<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> to the sales of the main work.  Conversely, there would be nothing against publication of the Afterword perhaps six months or a longer period of time after the appearance of the main work.  The separate appearance of the individual parts is very common especially in scholarly works, and by this means the part appearing later as a rule helps promote the sales of the earlier part by renewing attention in it.</tei:p><tei:p>We will gladly comply as far as possible with your wish to receive the music examples of Part II for correction no later than the end of June.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> The printers have promised to supply text that includes music examples within it by the end of this month;  music examples that appear without text (as appendix),<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> on the other hand, will not be ready set until the beginning of July.  In any case, we will do everything in our power to speed up completion.</tei:p><tei:p>With kind regards,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Heirs of J. G. Cotta’s Bookdealership</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>