<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 8/3, [61] : 8-21-18 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  In the public domain
©  Transcription Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin, 2009
©  Translation Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin, 2009
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent &amp; William Drabmin 2009
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Violin, Moriz (1918-1956) - -Heirs of Moriz Violin (1956-197?) - -University of California, Riverside (197? - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker;  Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent and William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 08/21/1918 02:40:37 PM --><!-- MT Tags: "ViolinM ~ HSchenker","ViolinM+V ~ HSchenker","ViolinM+V+F ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten postcard from Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated August 21, 1918</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-05-01</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>The Schenker's went to Mariazell on the 16th for a work-free vacation.  - - Has had  difficulties with Wilhelm and Moriz Schenker.  - - Describes visit to Hupka in Kapuvár (Hungary).  - - Comments on Violin's forthcoming promotion to Lieutenant. 

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Violin, Moriz;  Schenker, Jeanette;  Durchbruch;  get-away;  Mariazell;  Tirol;  Tyrol;  Schenker, Wilhelm;  Schenker, Moriz;  Guttmann, Sophie;  Hupka, Felix;  Kapuvar;  Hungary;  Tiefebene;  lowland plains;  Wucher;  usury;  Schleichhandel;  black market</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Mariazell 135</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Marburg on the Drau, fHR. 106</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten postcard from Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated August 21, 1918</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
[Absender:]  <tei:hi rend="italic">D&lt;sup&gt;r&lt;/sup&gt; Heinrich Schenker, dzt.</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="italic">Mariazell, <tei:hi rend="italic">135</tei:hi></tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[An:] H. K.K. Fähnrich [/] <tei:hi rend="italic">Moriz Violin</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="italic">Marburg a/d Drau</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">fHR. 106,</tei:hi> Erl. Bett.</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>]  || MARIAZELL | 21.VIII.18 | <tei:hi rend="bold"> C </tei:hi> ||</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">for continuation of recto, see below</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
21. 8.
Fl!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Writing of this postcard is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/11, p. 938: "An Floriz (K.): Bericht über den Durchbruch nach M., über Kapuvar;  vermisse wegen der übrigen Verhältnisse auf eine mündliche Aussprache." ("To Floriz (postcard): report on the get-away to M[ariazell, via Kapuvár;  [I] miss, on account of all the other circumstances, a chance to talk face-to-face.").  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Am Freitag<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  i.e. August 16;  the journey is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/11, pp. 934-935.  </tei:note> haben wir den „Durchbruch" gewagt - nach Mariazell!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="mariazell">Mariazell</ref>.  </tei:note>  Zwar gab es nur sehr wenig heiße, unerträglich heiße Tage (so im Juli), aber das Übrige gieng über unsere Kraft.  Ich büßte im Juli allein 2 Kg. Gewicht ein, Lieliechen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="schenker_jeanette">Jeanette Schenker</ref>.  </tei:note> kam nicht aus mühsamster Arbeit, dazu Verdruß über die Brüder:  Wilhelm<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="schenker_wilhelm">Wilhelm Schenker</ref>.  </tei:note> beherbergt bei sich <tei:hi rend="italic">fremde</tei:hi> Personen als „Freundschaft", während ich, der bereit war, für uns zu zahlen, wie ich ja auch die wenigen Dinge die er sendet (meist voraus) bezahle, einen Weg betreten mußte, der <tei:hi rend="italic">über</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">unsere</tei:hi> Verhältnisse geht &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;u.&lt;/sup&gt; mir schwerste Opfer an Geld u. Arbeitsentgang auferlegt (so überflüssig!!).  Was ich mit Mozio<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="schenker_moriz">Moriz Schenker</ref>.  </tei:note> in einer Angelegenheit der Schwester<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="guttmann_sophie_nee">Sophie Guttmann</ref>.  </tei:note> erlebte, sei einer mündlichen Darsstellung vorbehalten.  Wir nahmen also Urlaub bei den obersten Wucher- u. Schleichhandelbehörden in Wien, u. giengen über vielfacher Empfehlung hierher - ohne Arbeit!! -, nur eines Urlaubes halber.  Die Preise sind höher als in Wien, mehr brauch ich nicht zu sagen. . . .   Bevor wir hierhergiengen, machten wir eine Stichprobe in <tei:hi rend="italic">Kapuvar</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="kapuvar">Kapuvár</ref>.  </tei:note> (Ungarn) bei <tei:hi rend="italic">Hupka</tei:hi>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="hupka_felix">Felix Hupka</ref>.  The visit is recorded in great detail in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/11, pp. 931-933.  </tei:note>  Es war märchenhaft die Fülle, die wir dort genoßen, aber die ungarische Tiefebene bedrückte uns zu sehr, u. dazu das Gefühl, <tei:hi rend="italic">Hupka</tei:hi> zu viel zuzumuten, obgleich wir sahen, wie überaus lieb u. gut  <tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> er Alles für uns tun.  Auch darüber mündlich.  Die Gegend hier ist sehr schön u. umschmeichelt uns - wär' nur das Wetter besser! -- mit Tiroler Assoziationen.  Wir treiben hier nur Lektüre, Müssiggang u. rasten, um Kraft für die kommende Zeit zu gewinnen. - daß du Leutnant wirst, ist mir so unbegreiflich, wie, daß du überhaupt Militärdienst tust!  Noch immer geht es mir nicht ein!  Wie geht es den deinen, Frau, u. Kinder im Speziellen?</tei:p><tei:p>Wir grüßen Euch Alle 2:4 
dein 
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">H</tei:hi></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten postcard from Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated August 21, 1918</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
[From:]  Dr. Heinrich Schenker,
c/o Mariazell, <tei:hi rend="italic">135</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[To:] Imperial-Royal Sub-Lieutenant Moriz Violin, 
Marburg on the Drau,
<tei:hi rend="italic">fHR. 106</tei:hi>,  Erl. Bett. [?]</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>]  || MARIAZELL | 21.VIII.18 | <tei:hi rend="bold"> C </tei:hi> ||</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">for continuation of recto, see below</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
August 21
Floriz,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>On Friday<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> we made our "get-away"--to Mariazell!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  True, we had only a very few hot, insufferably hot days (as in July), but it was the other things that got too much for us.  I lost two kilograms in July alone, Lieliechen<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> was for ever toiling away wearily, added to which was annoyance over my brothers:  Wilhelm<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> is putting up <tei:hi rend="italic">strangers</tei:hi> at his place as a "gesture of friendship," while I, who was prepared to pay for us, as indeed I always do pay for the few things that he sends (mostly in advance), had to walk a path that <tei:hi rend="italic">exceeded our</tei:hi> circumstances &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;and&lt;/sup&gt; inflicted upon me the severest sacrifice in loss of money and time (all so unnecessary!!).  What I went through with Mozio<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> in a matter concerning [our] sister<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> must wait to be told when we are together.  So we got our vacation through the highest officials in usury and the black market in Vienna, and made our way here on strong recommendation--work-free!!, just for the sake of getting a break.  The prices are higher than in Vienna;  I need say no more. . . .  Before coming here, we made a sortie to Kapuvár<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> (Hungary), to Hupka's<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> place.  The abundance that we enjoyed there was fabulous, but the Hungarian lowland plain depressed us exceedingly, and in addition we had the feeling we were expecting too much of Hupka, although we saw how extremely kind and good he was in <tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> everything that he did for us.  More about this, too, when we meet.  The area here is very beautiful, and is full of Tyrolean associations for us--if only the weather were better!  All that we are doing here is reading, lazing about, and resting, so as to gather strength for times to come.  -- That you are to be made a Lieutenant is inconceivable to me, as is the fact that you are doing military service at all!  I still just cannot grasp it!  How are you all keeping--your wife and children in particular?</tei:p><tei:p>We send you all our best wishes 2:4
Your
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] H[einrich]</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>