<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 8/3, [55] : 1-6-18 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  In the public domain
©  Transcription Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin, 2009
©  Translation Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin, 2009
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2009
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Violin, Moriz (1918-1956) - -Heirs of Moriz Violin (1956-197?) - -University of California, Riverside (197? - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker;  Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent and William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 01/06/1918 03:02:24 PM --><!-- MT Tags: "ViolinM+V ~ HSchenker","ViolinM+V+F ~ HSchenker","ViolinV ~ H+JSchenker","ViolinV ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten postcard from Schenker to Valerie Violin, dated January 6, 1918</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-04-22</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Schenker recounts explosion of gas oven and subsequent activities.  Jeanette has transferred things to her apartment and stayed up late to help.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Violin, Valerie;  Gasofen;  gas oven;  explosion;  health;  lessons;  Streichergasse</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Vienna III, Reisnerstraße 38</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Vienna XIII, Sechshauserstraße 126</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten postcard from Schenker to Valerie Violin, dated January 6, 1918</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
Absender: <tei:hi rend="italic">D^r^ Heinrich Schenker</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="italic">III, Reisnerstr. 38.</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[An:] <tei:hi rend="italic">Frau</tei:hi> [/] <tei:hi rend="italic">Prof Wally Violin</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="italic">XIII,</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="italic">Sechshauserstr. 126</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>]  || 10 WIEN 77 | 6. I. 18-3 | <tei:hi rend="bold"> 5b </tei:hi> ||</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">for continuation of recto, see below</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
Sonntag 10 ½^h^. Vm.
Liebe Frau <tei:hi rend="italic">Wally</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Writing of this postcard is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/10, p. 825:  "An Frau Wally (K.): können leider nicht kommen wegen eines Ofen-Zwischenfalles, meiner Erkältung usw."  ("To Wally (postcard): unfortunately we cannot come on account of an incident over the oven, my cold, etc.  ").  The communication from Valerie Violin to Schenker is not known to survive.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Die Wirklichkeit ist noch unerbittlicher, als jeglicher Voranschlag annehmen kann.  Da explodiert gestern 4 ½&lt;sup&gt;h&lt;/sup&gt; Nchm. meinGasofen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  This incident is recorded vividly in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/10, p. 825, January 5, 1918: </tei:note> u. ich muß sehen, daß er morgen zu den Stunden sich functioniert:  Lieliechen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="schenker_jeanette">Jeanette Schenker</ref>.  </tei:note> u. ich müssen also nach dem Frühstück zu mir, um Proben anzustellen, um sich zu überzeugen, ob ja oder nein.  Der Ofen bleibt bei „nein".  Lieliechen holt Holz u. Kartoffel aus meinem Keller zu sich in die Streichergasse<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Streichergasse 5:  Jeanette's apartment, a few minutes' walk from Heinrich's.  </tei:note>, um das Zimmer warm zu machen.  Denn . . . schon seit Monaten laboriere ich an irgend etwas rätselhaften därmlichen, das vermutlich auch Ursache meiner Abmagerung ist, u. vielleicht war es die Kälte im Zimmer, die ich gestern von 5-7&lt;sup&gt;h&lt;/sup&gt; während beider letzten Nachmittagsstunden zu ertragen hatte, - Frau Pairamall<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="pairamall_evelina">Evelina Pairamall</ref>. </tei:note> saß im Pelz, aber um die Füße mir einen Pelz zu wickeln geht schon darum nicht, weil ich überhaupt keinen habe -, die mir mehr also sonst zusetzte u. größere Opfer von mir forderte.  Ich habe es nicht gewagt, daraufhin, mich noch weiter den Fahrten hin u. her auszusetzen, den kalten Füßen, denen[?] in solchen Fällen immer diejenige „auf dem Fuße" folgt, was &lt;sup&gt;m&lt;/sup&gt;ich schon sehr irritiert.  Dienstag muß ich endlich doch den Arzt fragen, es geht so nicht weiter.  Was aber die höchste Ironie ist, Lielichen hat gestern <tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> hinter meinem Rücken bis 12&lt;sup&gt;h&lt;/sup&gt; Nachts geschrieben, um den heutigen Vormittag einzubringen, der ja unser fortlaufend ungestörter Arbeitstag sonst ist, - u. Alles fällt plötzlich (buchstäblich) ins - Wasser.  Da haben Sie es also!  Kann man also was vorausbestimmen?  Ich werde indessen froh sein, vom Arzt irgend welche gute Auskunft erhalten zu können.  Es ist schon zu dumm.  Viele Grüße von uns beide an Sie u. die Kleinchen!</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr 
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">HSch</tei:hi></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten postcard from Schenker to Valerie Violin, dated January 6, 1918</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
From: Dr. Heinrich Schenker
[Vienna] III, Reisnerstraße 38</tei:p><tei:p>[To:] Frau Prof. Wally Violin
[Vienna] XIII,
Sechshauserstraße 126</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>]  || 10 VIENNA 77 | 6. I. 18-3 | <tei:hi rend="bold"> 5b </tei:hi> ||</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">for continuation of recto, see below</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
Sunday, 10:30 a.m.  
Dear Wally,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>The reality is even grimmer than can possibly be imagined.  Because yesterday, at 4:30 in the afternoon, my gas oven exploded,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> I have to ensure that it is functioning in time for tomorrow's lessons.  So Lie-Liechen<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> and I have to come back to my place after breakfast to try it out, so in order to satisfy ourselves whether or not it is working.  The oven refuses to work.  Lie-Liechen is carrying wood and potatoes from my cellar to her place in the Streichergasse,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> in order to warm the room up.  For months now I have been afflicted with some mysterious trouble with my bowels, which may perhaps also be the cause of my weight-loss, and it was perhaps the coldness of the room, which I had to endure from 5 to 7 yesterday evening throughout my last two afternoon lessons (Mrs. Pairamall<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> sat with her fur coat on, but wrapping a fur around my feet was just not possible, because I just do not even own one), that plagued me worse than usual and demanded greater sacrifice from me.  I have not dared since then further to subject myself to the shuttling back and forth, [and] to the cold feet that inevitably ensue in such cases to those "on their feet," and that are already a source of irritation to me.  I really must now ask the doctor on Tuesday--things cannot go on like this.    But the supreme irony is that Lie-Liechen had stayed up writing until midnight <tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> unbeknownst to me to get things ready for this morning, which really is otherwise our regular, uninterrupted work day--and everything suddenly (literally) went wrong.  So now you know it all!  Is there anything one can predict?  Meanwhile, I shall be happy to receive some good news from my doctor.. It is all so exasperating.  Fond greetings from the two of us to you and the little ones.</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  H[einrich] Sch[enker]</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>