<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 5/16, [3] : 11-9-09 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Heinrich Schenker.
© Transcription Ian D. Bent 2006.
© Translation Ian D. Bent 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian D. Bent 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>All reasonable steps have been taken to locate the heirs of Heinrich Schenker.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Universal Edition Archive (1909-1976) - -on permanent loan to the Stadt- und Landesbibliothek Wien (1976-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker; Image: Universal Edition, A.G.; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian D. Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 11/09/1909 01:01:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Hertzka ~ HSchenker","UE ~ H+JSchenker","UE ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten draft of WSLB, Schenker to Hertzka (UE), dated November 9, 1909</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-01-28</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>[J. S. Bach: Chromatic Fantasy &amp; Fugue and Niloff: Instrumentations-Tabelle:] Draft of WSLB 47.  S is unavailable for a meeting with H and von Wöß because (a) work-time is too precious, (b) he suspects vW of seeking to impose unacceptable editorial "control" upon his work.  S asserts authorial priority, and defends quality of his work.  The principal topics are "virtuosos," natural and valve horns, and alterations to Beethoven. Compares UE unfavorably to Cotta.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Hertzka, Emil; UE;  Wöß, Josef Venantius von; Kontrapunkt; Counterpoint; Amsterdam; Paris; Vienna; editorial control; authorial priority; Beethoven; Fifth Symphony; original score; sketches; Eroica Symphony; Reinecke, Carl; Dalcroze, Emile Jacques-; Busoni, Ferruccio; Bach, J. S.; Chromatic Fantasy &amp; Fugue; Niloff; Instrumentations-Tabelle; Instrumentation Table; Berlin; Backhaus, Wilhelm; virtuoso; Berger, Alfred von; Cotta, J. G.; Schalk, Josef; Vienna Philharmonic Orchestra; honorarium; natural horn; valve horn; Hirschfeld, Robert; Retouche; Wagner; Kretzschmar, Hermann; Grove, George</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten draft of WSLB 47, Schenker to Hertzka (UE), dated November 9, 1909</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>S.G.H.D ! [/] 9. 11. 09.</tei:p><tei:p>Den Zahnartzt habe ich allerdings seit gestern hinter mir,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  See WSLB 45, October 27, and WSLB 46, October 30, where S uses inflammation of the periosteum as reason for being unavailable for a meeting, and OC 52/45, November 5, H's response.</tei:note> kann aber trotzdem Ihrem Wunsche nicht entsprechen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  i.e. those expressed in OC 52/45, November 5.</tei:note>  Erstens bin ich mitten in &lt;strike&gt;drängen&lt;/strike&gt; wichtigen Arbeiten, die keinen Aufschub zulassen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  S was evidently at galley-proof stage on his <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt</tei:hi> [I].</tei:note> und ich kann es als bestimmt voraussagen, daß ich vor Erscheinen des 1. ½ Bd. &lt;strike&gt;vom&lt;/strike&gt;[?] des <tei:hi rend="italic">Cp.</tei:hi> kaum überflüßige Exkursionen zu machen in der Lage sein werde.  Bis dahin ^wenigstens^ ersuche ich Sie daher, mich als einem Mitarbeiter zu betrachten, der irgendwo im Ausland &lt;strike&gt;wohnt&lt;/strike&gt;, z.B. in <tei:hi rend="italic">Amsterdam</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Paris</tei:hi> u.s.w. wohnt, u. somit nur <tei:hi rend="italic">brieflich</tei:hi> zu erreichen ist.  Ich weiß zwar, daß ich mich im Widerspruch mit der <tei:hi rend="italic">Wiener</tei:hi> Sinne befinde, wenn ich &lt;strike&gt;die zum&lt;/strike&gt; ^bisd...[del]^ &lt;strike&gt;Stunden&lt;/strike&gt; ^den^ Zeitverlust eines geistig arbeitenden Menschen eben so hoch einschätze, wie den irgend eines Beamten mit festen Bureaustunden, dennoch bitte ich Sie, sich endlich mit dieser[ <tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi> ] meiner <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> persönlichen Anschauung u. Praxis endlich befreunden zu wollen.</tei:p><tei:p>Aber selbst wenn dieses ^gewichtige^ Hindernis &lt;strike&gt;ernster Natur&lt;/strike&gt; nicht vorläge, würde ich mich noch immer bestimmt fühlen, aus Gründen, die vielleicht noch ernsterer Natur sind, die &lt;strike&gt;von Ihnen&lt;/strike&gt; gewünschte Konferenz mit Ihnen und Herren <tei:hi rend="italic">von Wess</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="woss_josef_venantius">Josef Venantius von Wöß.</ref>  S got the spelling right in the finished letter, WSLB 47.  </tei:note> höflich abzulehnen. Denn ich &lt;strike&gt;darum[?], daß Sie auf&lt;/strike&gt; ^schließe aus der Nichterfühlung^ meiner Bitte,  die "Kleinigkeiten"<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  This quotes from OC 52/40 41, October 26, which asks for a meeting, then says: "The <tei:hi rend="italic">Chromatic Fantasy &amp; Fugue</tei:hi> is finally about to go for printing, and we have a few details to discuss with you regarding it."  S's request appears in WSLB 46, October 30.</tei:note> brieflich zu präzisieren, &lt;strike&gt;dieses dennoch .. daß nun wieder&lt;/strike&gt;, daß nicht rein drucktechnische Angelegenheiten hier in Frage kommen, sondern ^wohl^ wieder, und zwar eben schon zum zweiten Mal, eine Kontrolle meiner Arbeit beabsichtigt wird.  Ich schätze persönlich Herrn von <tei:hi rend="italic">Wess</tei:hi> als einen der liebenswürdigsten und honnettesten Musiker, die ich kenne -- u. das will ^bei mir^ wahrhaftig viel sagen;-- aber &lt;strike&gt;nun xxlle&lt;/strike&gt; seinen Charakter in alle seine Kenntnisse in Ehren, kann ich &lt;strike&gt;doch&lt;/strike&gt; ^dennoch^ unmöglich &lt;strike&gt;zeigen same&lt;/strike&gt; zulassen, daß ihm statt mir als <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> dem <tei:hi rend="italic">Autor</tei:hi> die <tei:hi rend="italic">Priorität</tei:hi> der <tei:hi rend="italic">Correctur</tei:hi> zufalle.  Das wäre höchstens in dem Falle zulässig, wenn es sich um eine &lt;strike&gt;nicht von Ihnen&lt;/strike&gt; ^un^verlangte &lt;strike&gt;sondern von mir&lt;/strike&gt; angebotene Arbeit handelte, &lt;strike&gt;dies ist&lt;/strike&gt; ^was^ aber die beiden letzten Male nicht der Fall gewesen ist.  &lt;strike&gt;Ich decke ja schließlich meine Arbeit mit meinem Namen u es stünde ja Herrn von Wess frei, ^seine etwaigen^ entgegengesetzten Ansichten selbständig zu vertreten.&lt;/strike&gt;</tei:p><tei:p>Es kann sich ja schließlich nur um zweierlei handeln, entweder um einen etwaigen <tei:hi rend="italic">Lapsus</tei:hi>, oder um abweichende Absichten.  Ist das Erstere der Fall, dann habe ich ja als <tei:hi rend="italic">Autor</tei:hi> vor mir noch die <tei:hi rend="italic">Correctur</tei:hi>, die <tei:hi rend="italic">Revision</tei:hi> u die <tei:hi rend="italic">Superrevision</tei:hi>, sodaß mir bei der dreimaligen Durchsicht ein <tei:hi rend="italic">Lapsus</tei:hi> wohl kaum entgehen konnte.  Es dürfte auch Herrn von <tei:hi rend="italic">W.</tei:hi> bekannt sein, daß selbst das Hauptmotiv der fünften <tei:hi rend="italic">Symphonie</tei:hi> von <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven</tei:hi> noch in der <tei:hi rend="italic">Originalpartitur</tei:hi> (also nicht blos in den Skizzen!)  eine andere Gestalt aufweist als in der endgültigen Veröffentlichung.  Und <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> über die neuere Praxis Ihres Verlages wahrlich wundern.  Ich habe in der gegenwärtigen Arbeit mit Absicht und wohl[?] überlegt die Leistungen der bisherigen Herausgeber &lt;strike&gt;beleuchtet&lt;/strike&gt;, Revue passieren lassen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  i.e. his editing work on the <tei:hi rend="italic">Chromatic Fantasy &amp; Fugue</tei:hi>.  The editions collated are von Bülow (Bote &amp; Bock, 1859-65), Reinecke (Breitkopf und Härtel, 1871-83), Bischoff (Steingräber, 1880-88), Naumann/Bach-Gesellschaft (Breitkopf und Härtel, 1890), Ruthard (Peters, 1894), Röntgen (UE, c.1901), and Busoni (Simrock 1902).</tei:note> ebenso mit Absicht die Klavierspieler einer Kritik unterzogen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Presumably he means in his music criticisms, 1891-1901.  </tei:note> u selbst die weitestgehende Umständlichkeit ^steht^ &lt;strike&gt;kaum&lt;/strike&gt; kaum &lt;strike&gt;ausreichen, den&lt;/strike&gt; ^im richtigen Verhältnis zur^ Schwere der Versündigungen&lt;strike&gt;, die&lt;/strike&gt; an unseren Meistern &lt;strike&gt;täglich&lt;/strike&gt; b&lt;strike&gt;ezwungen wurden und noch&lt;/strike&gt; ^bypa....[del]^ &lt;strike&gt;werden&lt;/strike&gt;, in der Vergangenheit u &lt;strike&gt;in&lt;/strike&gt; der Gegenwart.  Wenn ich beispielsweise eine Lesart von <tei:hi rend="italic">Reinecke</tei:hi> zurückweise u hiefür - was die anderen Herausgeber zu machen nicht einmal fähig sind - die &lt;strike&gt;technischen&lt;/strike&gt; ^künstlerischen^ Gründe beigebe, so ^führt dies^ &lt;strike&gt;bildet das den Klavierspieler oder Componisten&lt;/strike&gt; jedermann, der das Heft in die Hand nimmt, &lt;strike&gt;ungleich&lt;/strike&gt; ungleich mehr &amp;#9484;zu&lt;strike&gt;m&lt;/strike&gt; dem  besprochenen Werk, [ <tei:hi rend="italic">from prev line</tei:hi> ] &amp;#9488;, als wenn zB. <tei:hi rend="italic">H. J dal Cros</tei:hi> die Phantasie tanzen ließe<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Emile Jacques-Dalcroze (1865-1950), Swiss music educationalist whose <tei:hi rend="italic">Méthode Jacques-Dalcroze</tei:hi> had recently been published (Paris, 1906-07), 3 vols, vol. I entitled "Rhythmic Gymnastics."</tei:note> oder Herr <tei:hi rend="italic">Busoni</tei:hi> [ <tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi> ] <tei:hi rend="italic">Sextenetuden</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="busoni_ferruccio">Ferruccio Busoni</ref>.  Unclear what is referred to.  The draft implies that these studies have nothing to do with the <tei:hi rend="italic">Chromatic Fantasy &amp; Fugue</tei:hi> ("mit der Sache nichts zu tun haben"), whereas the finished letter states explicitly "which has nothing to do with the <tei:hi rend="italic">Well-tempered Clavier</tei:hi>". Busoni's edition of the <tei:hi rend="italic">WTC</tei:hi>, done for Breitkopf und Härtel in 1894, was issued by UE in 1909.  UE also issued Busoni's <tei:hi rend="italic">Fantasia nach J. S. Bach</tei:hi> in 1909.  Busoni's arrangement of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Chromatic Fantasy &amp; Fugue</tei:hi> was not published until 1911.  </tei:note> ^, die mit der Sache nichts zu tun haben^ daneben schreibt, u ich wette, Sie haben gegen letztere keinen Einwand erhoben u ihn kaum aus <tei:hi rend="italic">Berlin</tei:hi> herzitiert.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> &lt;strike&gt;....  .... von Kritik der Virtuosen aber richtet sich gegen das mangelhafte Erfassen&lt;/strike&gt;</tei:p><tei:p>Was aber die Virtuosen anlangt, so richtet sich &lt;strike&gt;s&lt;/strike&gt; meine Kritik gegen ihr mangelhaftes Erfassen des geistigen Inhaltes eines <tei:hi rend="italic">Bach</tei:hi>schen Werkes und das damit zusammenhängende falsche Reproduzieren desselben ( o hätten Sie doch nur gestern zB. Herrn <tei:hi rend="italic">Backhaus</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Wilhelm Backhaus [create biogfile]</tei:note> gehört, wie er <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven</tei:hi> u <tei:hi rend="italic">Bach</tei:hi> maltraitiert, um sich erst bei <tei:hi rend="italic">Liszt</tei:hi> zurechtzufinden!); und meine Kritik geht keineswegs weiter als z.B. &lt;strike&gt;B&lt;/strike&gt; diejenige, die <tei:hi rend="italic">Alfred von Berger</tei:hi> in seiner Hand <tei:hi rend="italic">Dr</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">_</tei:hi><tei:hi rend="italic">_<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  S leaves details to be inserted (see finished letter).  Alfred  Maria Julius, Freiherr von Berger, <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Hamburgische Dramaturgie</tei:hi> (Ost. Rundschau,-d.M.), later published Vienna, 1910. </tei:note> &lt;strike&gt;gegen&lt;/strike&gt; selbst gegen die berühmtesten Schauspieler richtet.  Zwar verfolge ich dabei selbstverständlich in erster Linie die Restituirung des geistigen Wertes der Meisterwerke ( wie froh bin ich doch, daß mich mindestens </tei:hi>Cotta<tei:hi rend="italic"> nicht daran hindert!), indessen ist damit ja unzertrennlich verbunden auch die Hebung des materiellen Wertes dieser Stücke, was ja für Sie, wie ich dies schon mündlich hervorzuheben Geleg. hatte, von nicht zu unter- <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> schätzender Bedeutung ist. Wer wird zB. nach der Vorführung der Novität das </tei:hi>1. Phil. Concertes<tei:hi rend="italic"> (&lt;strike&gt;nämlich der Suite von Bach&lt;/strike&gt;) in der misverständlichen &lt;strike&gt;Vor&lt;/strike&gt; Auffassung </tei:hi>Schalks<tei:hi rend="italic">|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  The concert took place on November 14, 1909, at 12:30 pm, the program comprising: J.S.Bach: Suite in D major for three trumpets, timpani, three oboes, bassoon, and string orchestra (first performance in the Philharmonic Concerts), Mozart: Symphony in E flat, KV 543, Beethoven: Symphony No. 8 in F major.  Click on <ref cRef="schalk_franz">Franz Schalk</ref>.  [Thanks to the Vienna Philharmonic Society Archive Department for this information.]</tei:note> überhaupt noch Lust finden, dieses Werk zu kaufen ^erahrtest[?del]^, und doch steckt in dieser </tei:hi>Suite<tei:hi rend="italic"> von </tei:hi>Bach_, die &lt;strike&gt;xxxx&lt;/strike&gt; nun zum ersten Mal nach zwei Jahrhunderten aufgeführt wird, ^auch^ ein ganz ansehnlicher commerzieller Wert.  &lt;strike&gt;Den&lt;/strike&gt;</tei:p><tei:p>In allen diesen Dingen darf es von Hause aus keine Sentimentalität geben, und ich muß aus den angeführten und noch anderen Gründen selbst auf dem Tonfall beharren.  Ich decke ja <tei:hi rend="italic"> </tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic"> </tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic"> </tei:hi> bis <tei:hi rend="italic"> </tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic"> vertrete. </tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic"> </tei:hi><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  S leaves details to be inserted (see finished letter).</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ich kann vielleicht unter &lt;strike&gt;diese&lt;/strike&gt; den obwaltenden Umst.  froh sein, &lt;strike&gt;r..indem&lt;/strike&gt;[?] im Besitze mindestens des vertragsmäßigen Honorars &lt;strike&gt;f&lt;/strike&gt; zu sein, es hätte sich sonst vielleicht wiederholt, daß ich für eine bestellte Arbeit, weil sie nicht im Einklange ist mit den Ansichten der Leitung, einfach nicht entlohnt wurde.  Ich habe eben aus diesem Anlaß jenes Manuskr. nochmals durchgesehen, u finde mich <tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> veranlaßt, aufs Bestimmteste zu erklären, daß ich nur diese eigene Einleitung für &lt;strike&gt;der&lt;/strike&gt;[?] &lt;strike&gt;bestens&lt;/strike&gt;[?] den bestmöglichen u kürzesten Auszug einer Instrumentenlehre halte u daher auch niemals eine andere für meine [ <tei:hi rend="italic">corr to</tei:hi> jene?] Tabelle<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  There is some confusion here.  H wished to speak with S about the <tei:hi rend="italic">Chromatic Fantasy &amp; Fugue</tei:hi>.  It is not clear whether S has forgotten this, or is referring now to one of the "two most recent dealings" alluded to earlier.</tei:note> gestatten werde.  Sie vergessen, daß Sie nichts dagegen ^hatten^, in der Vorrede<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15">  The paragraph reads as follows:</tei:note> der dritten Absatz drucken zu lassen, &lt;strike&gt;ferner&lt;/strike&gt; und im Dienste dieses Absatzes &amp;#9484;trotzdem das  System es weder[?] gefordert hätte[ <tei:hi rend="italic">brought up from two lines below</tei:hi> ]&amp;#9488;&lt;strike&gt;s&lt;/strike&gt; neben das <tei:hi rend="italic">Naturhorn</tei:hi> das <tei:hi rend="italic">Ventilhorn</tei:hi> zu setzen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn16">  Nos. 27-9 are the natural horns in high Bb, high A, and high G, No.30 the natural horn in F, No.31 the valve-horn in F.  </tei:note> u doch haben Sie ^gerade xxxxx^ jene Anmerkung &lt;strike&gt;st&lt;/strike&gt; (mit Perldruck!), &lt;strike&gt;ab&lt;/strike&gt; die in diesem Absatz angekündigt war, mit den Worten kritisiert „ich hätte mich in Gedanken verloren".  Es wird Sie vielleicht interessieren zu erfahren, daß zw.[ <tei:hi rend="italic">corr from</tei:hi> zB.] <tei:hi rend="italic">Dr. Rob. Hirschfeld</tei:hi> nichts so sehr &lt;strike&gt;verwünscht&lt;/strike&gt; vermißt hat als die Klarstellung jenes Punktes, wo man mich eben - nicht zu Worte ließ.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn17">  Schenker had had words with Hirschfeld about the <tei:hi rend="italic">Instrumentation-Table</tei:hi>, e.g. diary, OJ 1/7, pp.92-93 ("speaks all the more harshly about details of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Table</tei:hi>").  Click on: <ref cRef="hirschfeld_robert">Robert Hirschfeld</ref>.</tei:note>  An die Adresse des Herrn <tei:hi rend="italic">Wess</tei:hi> aber, dessen Kritik mich eben um das Honorar für eine bestellte Arbeit gebracht,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn18">  S perhaps suspects that vW was behind H's rejection (OC 52/399-401, December 18, 1908) of the additional materials that S supplied for the <tei:hi rend="italic">Instrumentation-Table</tei:hi>--"commissioned" is too strong a work, but the material was certainly invited by H.</tei:note> möchte ich noch folgendes richten : das Thema worin ich mich angeblich <tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> "verloren" hatte, wurde bereits einmal von mir über Aufforderung des <tei:hi rend="italic">Dr Rob Hir</tei:hi>[<tei:hi rend="italic">schf</tei:hi>]<tei:hi rend="italic">elt</tei:hi> u. d. T. <tei:hi rend="italic">Beet Retouche</tei:hi> ^in einer^ &lt;strike&gt;als&lt;/strike&gt; Weihnachtsbeil.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn19">  Schenker, "Beethoven-'Retouche'", <tei:hi rend="italic">Wiener Abendpost (Beilage zur Wiener Zeitung)</tei:hi>, January 9, 1901, pp.6-7.  See Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker als Essayist und Kritiker ...</tei:hi>, pp.259-68.  Hirschfeld was music critic of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Wiener Abendpost</tei:hi>, so presumably "requested" it.  The article concerns Wagner's attitudes toward, and alterations of, Beethoven's orchestral use of instruments, dwelling especially on the horn part in the first movement of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Eroica</tei:hi> Symphony, and the notes available on the natural horn. </tei:note> ^und zwar über Auf^ zu behandelt, trotzdem ja das <tei:hi rend="italic">Orthodoxe Wagnertum</tei:hi> das Herren H allgemein bekannt ist, - ein Aufsatz der mehrfach zitiert wurde.  Außerdem möge es nur z. B. bei <tei:hi rend="italic">Kr.</tei:hi> S...  <tei:hi rend="italic">Grove</tei:hi>  S...<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn20">  S leaves the details to be filled in (see finished letter).</tei:note> nachsehen, u. er wird erfahren, daß Wagner die berühmte ^Horn^Stelle im 1. Satz der <tei:hi rend="italic">Eroica</tei:hi> so schwer wie nur irgend einer &lt;strike&gt;seix&lt;/strike&gt; der schlechtesten Kap. verkannte, eine materiell gr Korr. vorn., von der die Welt erst abgieng, nachdem die Skiz v B. unwiderleglich [ <tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi> ] das Gegentheil bewiesen haben.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich bitte also nochmals um briefliche Erört. der Kleinig u. zeichne Hochachtungs.</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">no signature</tei:hi>]</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten draft of WSLB 47, Schenker to Hertzka (UE), dated November 9, 1909</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>D. D.,</tei:p><tei:p>Since yesterday I have the dentist out of the way<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>; nevertheless, I cannot comply with your wishes.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  Firstly, I am in the throes of &lt;strike&gt;pressing&lt;/strike&gt; important tasks that will admit of no delay,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> and I can predict that before the first half-volume of <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt</tei:hi> appears I shall hardly be in a position to leave the house unnecessarily.  Accordingly, until then ^at least^ I ask you to think of me as if I were a colleague who lives abroad somewhere or other, e.g. in Amsterdam, Paris, etc., and can consequently be reached only <tei:hi rend="italic">by letter</tei:hi>.  I realize, to be sure, that I am at odds with the Viennese frame of mind in considering &lt;strike&gt;the xxxxx hours&lt;/strike&gt; loss of time on the part of a person who works with the mind as great as that on the part of any official with fixed office hours, nevertheless I beg you finally please to reconcile yourself to this <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> personal outlook and practice of mine.</tei:p><tei:p>But even if this were not a ^weighty^ obstacle &lt;strike&gt;serious in nature&lt;/strike&gt; in our way, I would still not budge in declining the meeting that you and Mr. von Weß<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> wish to have with me, and this on grounds that are perhaps even more serious in nature.  For &lt;strike&gt;the fact that you&lt;/strike&gt;, from ^the fact that^ my request to have the "details"<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> set out in a letter ^has not been fulfilled^, &lt;strike&gt;but that once again&lt;/strike&gt; I ^deduce^ that this is not about purely technical printing issues but ^rather^--and this is the second time this has happened--that you are trying to exert control over the work that I do.  I personally respect Mr. von Weß as one of the nicest and most honest musicians that I know--and ^coming from me^ that is really saying a lot--; however, &lt;strike&gt;now xxx&lt;/strike&gt; with all due respect to his character and his wealth of knowledge, I &lt;strike&gt;certainly&lt;/strike&gt; cannot, ^even so,^ possibly &lt;strike&gt;show&lt;/strike&gt; allow priority over proof-correcting to fall to him rather than to me <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> as the author.  That would be acceptable only in the case of a piece of work &lt;strike&gt;not&lt;/strike&gt; ^un^solicited &lt;strike&gt;by him&lt;/strike&gt;, &lt;strike&gt;but&lt;/strike&gt; freely offered &lt;strike&gt;by me&lt;/strike&gt;, &lt;strike&gt;this was&lt;/strike&gt; ^which was^ not the case in the last two instances.  &lt;strike&gt;I after all protect my work with my name, and Mr. von Weß is entirely at liberty to represent ^any^ contrary views ^that he may have^ independently.&lt;/strike&gt;</tei:p><tei:p>It can after all be only one of two things: either some kind of slip, or a difference of opinion.  Were it the former, then as author I have to hand the [first] proofs, the revised proofs, [and] the final set of proofs, so a slip could hardly have escaped me in my three passes through them.  Mr. von Weß must surely be aware that the <tei:hi rend="italic">main</tei:hi> motive (!!) of Beethoven's Fifth Symphony even as late as the original score (not merely in the sketches, that is!) takes a different form from that in the final publication.  And <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> [I] am truly astonished at your publishing house's more recent practice. In my present work, I have &lt;strike&gt;illuminated&lt;/strike&gt; reviewed the products of previous editors meticulously<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> and judiciously, have subjected pianists to a critique of equal meticulousness,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> and even the wordiest [of these critiques] ^is^ hardly &lt;strike&gt;is commensurate with&lt;/strike&gt; ^proportionate to^ the gravity of the sins &lt;strike&gt;that were and still are committed every day&lt;/strike&gt; against our masters in the past and present.  If, for example, I reject a reading by Reinecke, and supply the &lt;strike&gt;technical&lt;/strike&gt; ^artistic^ reasons for this--something that the other editors are incapable of doing--then ^this guides^ &lt;strike&gt;it teaches the pianist or composer&lt;/strike&gt; anyone who picks up my volume through the work under discussion vastly more than when, for example, Mr. J.-Dalcroze has people dance to the [<tei:hi rend="italic">Chromatic</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">Fantasy</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> or Mr. Busoni writes <tei:hi rend="italic">Studies in Sixths</tei:hi> to it<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> ^which has nothing to do with the matter^, and I wager you have not raised any objection to the latter and have hardly summoned him back from Berlin.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> But as regards the virtuosos, my critique is aimed at their deficient grasp of the intellectual content of a work by Bach and the false representation of it that they give as a result (oh, if only you had, for example, heard yesterday how Mr. Backhaus<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> maltreats Beethoven and Bach, finding his way only when he reaches Liszt!).  Nor does my critique go any further than, e.g., that of Alfred von Berger for his part[?] Dr. <tei:hi rend="italic"> </tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic"> </tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> directed against the most famous actors.  To be sure, I am of course by that means working first and foremost toward the restoration of the spiritual value of our masterworks (how very happy I am that at least Cotta puts no obstacles to this in my way!);  inseparable from this also, however,  is the raising of the material value of these pieces, and for you this is, as I already had occasion to point out in conversation, certainly not of <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> inconsiderable significance.  For example, after the presentation of the novelty of the first Philharmonic concert &lt;strike&gt;(i.e. the Suite by Bach)&lt;/strike&gt; in Schalk's misleading interpretation,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> who will still have the slightest desire to purchase this work?  And yet on this Suite by Bach, performed now for the first time after two centuries, a handsome commercial value is actually to be placed.</tei:p><tei:p>In all these things there has to be no shred of sentimentality, and I must myself, for reasons already given, and others as well, persist in my own idiom.  I defend <tei:hi rend="italic"> </tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic"> </tei:hi> until <tei:hi rend="italic"> </tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic"> </tei:hi> represents.  <tei:hi rend="italic"> </tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic"> </tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/></tei:p><tei:p>Under &lt;strike&gt;these&lt;/strike&gt; prevailing circumstances, I can perhaps at least be thankful that I am in possession of the honorarium agreed in my contract;  if not, it might perhaps have been reiterated that I would simply not be remunerated for a piece of commissioned work, because it is not in accordance with the views of the management.  For this reason, I have just gone through that manuscript once again, and find myself <tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> compelled to declare in no uncertain terms that I consider this particular introduction to be the best possible and most concise outline of a theory of instruments, and will accordingly never entertain another for &lt;strike&gt;my&lt;/strike&gt; that <tei:hi rend="italic">Table</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/> You are forgetting that you ^had^ no objection to printing the 3rd paragraph of the Foreword,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn15"/> &lt;strike&gt;furthermore&lt;/strike&gt; and in keeping with this paragraph, despite the fact that the system would not [?] have called for the valve horn to be placed next to the natural horn,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn16"/> and yet that is the ^very^ comment (in small type!), communicated in this paragraph, that you criticized with the words that "I had got confused."  It may perhaps interest you to learn, for example, that Dr. Robert Hirschfeld &lt;strike&gt;wishes for&lt;/strike&gt; misses nothing so much as the clarification of that point, where I was not even allowed--to put it into words!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn17"/> But I should also like to draw the following to the attention of Mr. von Weß, whose criticism in fact deprived me of my honorarium for a commissioned task:<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn18"/>  the theme in which I have allegedly "got confused" has already been discussed by me years ago at the request of Dr. Robert Hirschfeld under the title "'Alterations' of Beethoven" &lt;strike&gt;as&lt;/strike&gt; ^in a^ Christmas supplement,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn19"/> ^and, what is more, at the request^ --despite the fact that Mr. H's ultra-orthodox Wagnerianism is widely known,--an article that has been cited many times since then. Moreover, one need only take a look at, for example, Kretzschmar, p. ..., Grove, p. ...<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn20"/> to discover that Wagner made a substantial correction to the famous ^horn^ passage in the first movement of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Eroica</tei:hi> as flagrant as any of the worst of Kapellmeisters could have committed, and which the world did not abandon until the sketches by Beethoven gave incontrovertible evidence to the contrary!</tei:p><tei:p>So once again I ask you for an account of your details in writing, and I remain with kind regards ...</tei:p><tei:p>[no signature]</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>