<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 5/24 : 7-8-24 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription Ian Bent, 2006.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1924-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 07/08/1924 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "DeutschS ~ HSchenker","Lamberg ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten draft letter, in Jeanette's hand, from Schenker to Lamberg, dated July 8, 1924</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-09-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>The devolvement of the stipends for musicians upon the Academy [i.e. Vienna Conservatory] is against the will and intentions of Mrs. Deutsch.  S asks that the Academy be instructed to wait until his death before taking control of the awarding of the stipends, and in the meanwhile to pass the interest [on the endowment] into his hands without restriction for him to administer.  

</dc:description><dc:subject> Schenker, Heinrich;  Schenker, Jeanette; Galtür;  Lamberg, Ernst;  Deutsch, Sofie;  Sophie;  stipends;  musicians;  composers;  Mendl, Fritz,  Türkel, Dr.;  Friedman, Dr.;  Marx, Josef;  Hofrat;  Director;  Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst;  Academy for Music and Representational Art;  Vienna Conservatory;  Berlin Centrale;  Wunsch, H.;  Hausegger;  Mendelssohn, Arnold;  Verein zur Speisung und Bekleidung hungernder Schulkinder in Wien;  Association for Feeding and Clothing Hungry Schoolchildren in Vienna;   interest</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Galtür, Tyrol</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten draft letter, in Jeanette Schenker’s hand, from Schenker to Lamberg, dated July 8, 1924</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">An D^r.^ Lamberg – Galtür, den 8. Juli 1924.</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  The reply, OJ 12/31, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Fritz Mendl; Sofie Deutsch’s brother, Austrian industrialist.</tei:note>, July 11, acknowledges S's "letter of the 8th inst"; thus, clearly, the finished letter—which is not known to survive—was drawn up the same day. This first line is double-underlined.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ihr geschätztes Schreiben vom 1. VII.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  OJ 12/32, [2], July 1, 1924.</tei:note> hat mich in Galtür erreicht, wo aber die Post weniger flüßig ist als in Wien.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich nehme in dieser Frage einen andern Standpunkt ein.  Nicht ein einziges Mal seit den Tagen, da sie erörtert wurde, also seit Fritz Mendls,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Fritz Mendl; Sofie Deutsch’s brother, Austrian industrialist.</tei:note> Dr. Türkels,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Siegfried Türkel, attorney and barrister in Vienna, with whom S had considerable correspondence 1917–20 (OC 1/34; 1/23, 10/6; 16/27–28, 30–31, 33, 36–37, 38, 39–40; 38/146), and  who sent a contract to S in 1918 (OJ 14/40).  </tei:note> Dr. Friedmans<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Hugo Friedmann, attorney in Vienna, with who S had correspondence in 1917 and 1920 (OC 1/19–20; 16/32; 32/27). (JS writes the name with a single “n”.)</tei:note> Tagen u. auch nicht von Ihnen u. dem Hofrat<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Hofrat Joseph Marx, Director of the Vienna Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst 1922–25, Rector 1925–27.  Click on <ref cRef="marx_joseph">Joseph Marx</ref>.</tei:note> hörte ich je den Gedanken einer Beschränkung in der Ausübung der von mir zu übernehmenden Pflicht.  Und das allein trifft den Sinn der Erblasserin, den sie im Testament ausgesprochen hat, längst aber auch schon mündlich oft u. oft auszudrücken pflegte.  Im Gefühl, daß sie ein <tei:hi rend="italic">beträchtliches</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Stipendium</tei:hi> hinterläßt – daß es so völlig anders kommen sollte, ahnte sie nicht, sonst hätte sie das Testament anders abgefaßt – dachte sie durchaus nicht an ein sozusagen locales Stipendium, gebunden an eine Akademie<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  S is alluding in particular to the Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst, i.e. the Vienna Conservatory of Music.  </tei:note> oder sonst welche Schule, sondern an Künstler in der ganzen Welt, denen aus irgend einem Grunde beizuspringen wäre, mögen sie auch schon Namen u. Ehre tragen. (Z.B. wurden die zwei Millionen Kronen, die ich zum Geschenk darbot, von der Berliner Centrale<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Berliner Centrale:  presumably the Deutsche Reichsbank (1876–1945), the German central bank, which controlled the Mark, and which set up the Reichsmark in August 1924 in response to hyperinflation.  </tei:note> dem <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Sinfoniker H. Wunsch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  H. Wunsch:  perhaps Hermann Wunsch (1884–1954), German composer who studied at the Berlin Hochschule für Musik and later taught there, composed six symphonies, chamber operas, and works in other genres.  He wrote two letters to S, including biographical article on himself, in 1924 (OJ 15/31).  </tei:note> in Berlin übergeben, für den sich Hausegger<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Hausegger:  presumably Siegmund von Hausegger (1872–1948), Austrian conductor and composer, and who was from 1922 President of the Munich Academy of Musical Art; composer of operas, symphonic poems, Lieder, etc., and wrote books.    </tei:note> so sehr einsetzt.  Von vielen Seiten werde ich auf den alten Arnold Mendelssohn<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Arnold Mendelssohn (1855–1933), composer and essayist who rejected romanticism and advocated a purer, polyphonic musical style based on J. S. Bach and Schütz. ( <tei:hi rend="italic">NGDM2</tei:hi> ).  It is unclear what S is referring to here.</tei:note> aufmerksam gemacht usw. ) An ähnliche Fälle dachte Frau Deutsch, im Vertrauen auf das beträchtliche Geld u. meine Gerechtigkeit u. Verantwortlichkeit.)</tei:p><tei:p>So wenig lag ihr die übliche Art des Stipendiums im Sinn, daß sie doch ausdrücklich im Testament erklärte, das Stipendium^geld^ habe nach meinen Ableben <tei:hi rend="italic">dem</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Verein</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Click on <ref cRef="verein_zur_speisung">Verein zur Speisung und Bekleidung hungernder Schulkinder in Wien</ref>.</tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">anheim</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">zu</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">fallen</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>Haben zwar die Dinge nun einmal einen anderen Verlauf genommen, hat sich der Verein aufgelöst, so sehe ich noch immer den Grund nicht ein, weshalb der Erblasserin auch der letzte Rest von Pietät verringert [verweigert?] werden müßte vom Verein, von Ihnen, der Akademie u. mir.  Ich meine:  Der Akademie müßte es willkommen sein, die gebotene Pietät mit etwas Geduld zu vereinen, sie kommt zu dem Stipendium ja nicht gerade über Wunsch der Erblasserin, doch nur durch Zufall u. sollte diesen durch Dank ehren.  Wenn es auch so ist, daß mein Werk – wir sind unter uns – alle Akademien der Welt überleben wird, so wird doch körperlich die Akademie mich über- <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> leben, u. so findet sie wahrlich noch Zeit, Zeit, Zeit genug, des Stipendiums nach ihrem Ermessen zu walten.  Aber so lange ich lebe sollte sie es sich zu einer Ehrensache machen, den Wunsch der Erblasserin zu erfüllen, umso mehr, als sie gesonnen ist, das Stipendium mit ihrem Namen zu schmücken.  Demnach bitte ich Sie, Herrn D^r.^ Marx<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Hofrat Joseph Marx, Director of the Vienna Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst 1922–25, Rector 1925–27.  Click on <ref cRef="marx_joseph">Joseph Marx</ref>.</tei:note> (den ich persönlich nicht kenne) dies alles mitzuteilen u. bei ihm den Wunsch der Erblasserin durchzusetzen, was Ihnen gewiß nicht schwer fallen kann.  Ich habe gegen D^r.^ Marx gewiß nichts, auch nicht gegen die Akademie, aber der Fall liegt zunächst anders.  Die Akademie hat Zeit.</tei:p><tei:p>In diesem Sinne bitte ich Sie auch die Akademie zu beauftragen, daß sie mir die Zinsen rechtzeitig zur Verfügung stellt, damit ich das Kleingeld geheim dorthin lenken kann, wo ein bereits erworbenes Verdienst irgendwie schwer gekränkt wird.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit ausgezeichneter Hochachtung</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">unsigned</tei:hi> ]</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten draft letter, in Jeanette Schenker’s hand, from Schenker to Lamberg, dated July 8, 1924</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">To Dr. Lamberg – Galtür, Jul8,  1924.</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Your esteemed letter of July 1<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> has reached me in Galtür, where the postal service is less fluid that in Vienna.</tei:p><tei:p>I adopt a different standpoint on this question.  Not once since the days in which it was first discussed, hence not since the time of Fritz Mendl,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>, Dr. Türkel,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>, and Dr. Friedmann<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>, nor even of you yourself or the Hofrat<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/>, have I ever heard the idea of limiting the discharge of the duty that I was to undertake.  What the deceased enunciated in her will alone captures her intention, but long before then she had also been accustomed to expressing [it] again and again by word of mouth.  In bequeathing a <tei:hi rend="italic">considerable stipend</tei:hi>—never did she dream that something so utterly different might arise, otherwise she would have drafted her will differently—she was not for a moment thinking of a so-to-speak local stipend linked to an academy<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> or school of some sort but of artists anywhere in the world, to whom assistance was to be brought for any reason whatsoever, even if they were already known and regarded.  (For example, the two million Kroner that I offered as a present were handed over by the Berlin Central<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> to the <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> symphonic composer H. Wunsch<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> in Berlin for whom Hausegger<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> strove so very hard.  In many ways I am reminded of old Arnold Mendelssohn<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/>, etc.  Mrs. Deutsch had in mind similar cases in placing reliance on the considerable sum of money and my impartiality and sense of responsibility.</tei:p><tei:p>So far from her mind was the customary type of stipend that she expressly explained in her will that the stipend ^money^ was to <tei:hi rend="italic">revert to the Association</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> after my death.</tei:p><tei:p>Even though, to be sure, things have now taken a different path, even though the Association has gone into dissolution, I really still cannot see why the last vestiges of the deceased’s piety need be whittled away [denied?] by the Association, by you, by the Academy, or by me.  What I mean is:  the Academy ought to welcome the opportunity to exhibit a little patience in absorbing the piety offered;  it is coming into the stipend in no way directly at the wish of the deceased, but only by accident, and it ought to honor this with gratitude.  Even if it is the case that my work—just between ourselves—will outlive all the academies in the world, nonetheless physically the Academy will outlive me, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> so it really still has time, ample time, to take control of the stipend at its own discretion.  However, so long as I live the Academy should make it a matter of honor to fullfil the wishes of the deceased, all the more so since it has in mind to adorn the stipendium with her name.  Accordingly, I beg you to impart all this to Dr. Marx<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> (whom I do not know personally) and get over to him the wishes of the deceased, which surely cannot strike him as severe.  I have absolutely nothing against Dr. Marx, nor against the Academy either.  But for the time being the situation is another matter altogether.  The Academy has time.</tei:p><tei:p>In the same spirit, I ask you also to instruct the Academy to place the interest at my disposal in good time, so that I can distribute the money discretely to where merit already gained has in some way been severely incapacitated.</tei:p><tei:p>With kind regards,</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">unsigned</tei:hi> ]</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>