<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 5/5 : 8-12-27 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription Christoph Hust, 2007.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Christoph Hust &amp; Ian Bent 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1927-1934) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: in public domain; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Christoph Hust &amp; Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 08/12/1927 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Albersheim ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Incomplete draft of letter from Schenker to Josef Albersheim, in JS's hand with emendations by HS, dated August 12, 1927</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-06-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Acks OJ 9/5, [2]: S provides integrated instruction;  if GA were to receive comparable instruction elsewhere it would require several teachers and cause JA higher costs;  adverse comments on other unnamed "prominent persons";  S's pupils voluntarily raise their fees as Austrian currency loses its value;  advises continuing for a further year.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Albersheim, Josef;  Albersheim, Gerhard;  Prominenten;  prominent people;  instruction;  honorarium;  tuition;  fee;  currency;  inflation;  Schilling;  Dollar;  Hupka, Felix;  Hupka sister;  patronage;  accommodation</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Incomplete draft of letter from Schenker to Josef Albersheim, in JS's hand with emendations by HS, dated August 12, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Galtür <tei:hi rend="italic">12. 8. 27</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Sanitätsrat!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  This letter was dictated and drafted in the morning of August 12, and S wrote the fair copy later in the day:  see diary entry OJ 3/9, pp. 3099-3100.  At least two pages of the draft are missing from the folder.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>In Erwiderung Ihres frdl. Briefes vom 8. VIII aus Sulden<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  OJ 9/5, [2].</tei:note> will ich hiermit die Angelegenheit klarlegen.</tei:p><tei:p>Gesetzt den Fall, daß auch ich aus Mangel an entsprechenden Kenntnissen es -wie die- ^nach den^ sogen. Prominenten -hielte- ^halten müsste^ u. ^wie sie^ nur ^für[?]^ -in- einer Disciplin unterw&lt;strike&gt;eisen&lt;/strike&gt;iese -würde-, -müßte- ^so würde^ Ihr Herr Sohn die ^seine?^ Ausbildung in d. anderen ^übrigen^ Fächern bei anderen Prominenten ^zu^ suchen ^haben^, wenn er -seinen- ^den^ Wissensdurst, der ihm &lt;sup&gt;eigent[lich] [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg word</tei:hi>] so sehr&lt;/sup&gt; zur Ehre gereicht, befriedigen wollte. Dann -aber- würden die drei oder vier Prominenten, die Herrn G. zu betreuen hätten, ohne Zweifel Ihnen mehr Kosten verursachen, als der persönlich u. sachlich zusammengefaßte Un- <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> terricht bei mir, davon abgesehen, daß er an Kenntnissen nichts gewänne - was Herr G. heute sehr wohl zu beurteilen vermag.  Mein Gewissen u. &lt;strike&gt;m&lt;/strike&gt;Meine Kenntnisse [<tei:hi rend="italic">invert order</tei:hi>] verbieten mir ^aber^, mich in der Art jener Prominenten zu betragen, die ohne -mehr Worte zu verlieren- ^etwas -zu- lehren zu können^, einfach hohe Honorare den Schülern abnehmen -u. sie lediglich auf die- ^u. ihnen daher nur übrig lassen, sich entweder^ snobistische&lt;strike&gt;n&lt;/strike&gt;r [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg word</tei:hi>] ^zu erfreuen[?]^ -besten Fächern/Fällen- ^oder^ -gestatten-, ^die ersten kleinen Geschäftchen^ mit dem Namen des Lehrers ^zu machen^ &lt;strike&gt;Geschäfte zu machen.&lt;/strike&gt;</tei:p><tei:p>&lt;strike&gt;Schon Ddaraus allein können Sie entnehmen &lt;sup&gt;Sie, s. g. H. A.&lt;/sup&gt;, daß ich meinen Schüler&lt;/strike&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;strike&gt;schon&lt;/strike&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;strike&gt;grundsätzlich &lt;sup&gt;in materieller Hinsicht&lt;/sup&gt; entgegen kommen würde,&lt;/strike&gt; W&lt;strike&gt;w&lt;/strike&gt;enn ich &lt;strike&gt;ohne jede Prestige-Sucht&lt;/strike&gt; ^nur zum Unterschied von den ganz u. [?gar?] Promin.^ &lt;sup&gt;&lt;strike&gt;in Sachen d. Honorars&lt;/strike&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; die &lt;sup&gt;auch&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;strike&gt;schon&lt;/strike&gt; physisch ^so^ anstrengende Last eines vo&lt;strike&gt;m&lt;/strike&gt;n &lt;strike&gt;Gesichtspunkt&lt;/strike&gt; <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> höchster -Einheit- ^Einheit^ getragenen Unterrichts in sämtlichen Fächern auf mich nehme gleichwohl aber ^ohne jede Prestige-Sucht^ das Honorar niedriger halte, als selbst Lehrer unteren Ranges, ^liegt nicht schon darin viel Entgegenkommen?^ Meine langjährigen Schüler wissen mir auch Dank dafür u. be[s]tätigen ihn in der Form, daß sie die Honorare <tei:hi rend="italic">freiwillig</tei:hi> erhöhen, sobald die Kaufkraft unserer Währung sich vermindert.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  [note on inflation in the 1920s]</tei:note> So haben denn auch meine Schüler &lt;strike&gt;schon im Vorjahr&lt;/strike&gt;, mit Rücksicht darauf, daß in den Jahren 1924-26 unser Schilling - trotz politischer Sanierung - um nahezu 25% sich verschlechtert hat^te^, ^das Honorar schon für 1926^ von selbst hinaufgesetzt. (Waren doch die ungefähr 35 Sch. in Wahrheit nur so wenig wert, daß kein halbwegs ernst zu neh- <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> mender Lehrer ^sie^ um so geringes Honorar unterrichte&lt;strike&gt;n&lt;/strike&gt;t &lt;strike&gt;würde&lt;/strike&gt; ^hätte^&lt;strike&gt;)&lt;/strike&gt;. Nur eben Herrn G. u. der Schwester des Kapellmeisters Hupka<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  [Hupka's sister--identify]</tei:note> blieb ich mit den 5 Dollar&lt;strike&gt;s&lt;/strike&gt; im Worte weil ich im Mai mich daran gebunden hatte, ohne zu ahnen, was die Zukunft bringt.)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  HS inserts paragraph-sign into existing run-on text.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Nun &lt;strike&gt;waren&lt;/strike&gt; ^sind^ es wiederum meine Schüler ^gewesen^, die am Ausgang der letzten Saison mich für die künftige, 27/28, auf 50 Sch. hinaufgesetzt haben in Hinblick auf die weitere Verschlechterung unseres Geldes. &lt;strike&gt;Es ist ihnen dabei&lt;/strike&gt; ^Sie sind sich, um es zu wiederholen^ &lt;strike&gt;sehr wohl&lt;/strike&gt; bewußt, daß ich auch damit noch hinter dem Honorar mittlerer Lehrer zurückstehe u. -sie- wissen mir Dank für dieses [Entgegenkommen[?]]</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">missing</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> Er hätte zu mir eben schon früher kommen sollen oder sich mit einer längeren Studienzeit begnügen müssen. Gerade seine Tüchtigkeit, sein rasches Aufnehmen, &lt;strike&gt;be-&lt;/strike&gt; erfordern eher ein Mehr als ein Weniger.</tei:p><tei:p>Es würde sich also empfehlen, ihm das Opfer dieses einen Jahres noch zu bringen - ich tue gewiß das Äußerste - oder, falls es Ihnen doch unmöglich fiele, es vielleicht bei 2 Stunden der Woche bewenden zu lassen, obwohl ich daran festhalte, daß in diesem Falle der Verlust an Kenntnissen ganz außer Verhältnis wäre zu dem sehr bescheidenen Gewinn an Geld. Endlich bitte ich Sie, mir Ihre Entscheidung bis 9. IX. zukommen zu lassen.</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">missing</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> [...] Entgegenkommen, das einem Mäzenatentum ähnlich sieht, auf das ich ^u. Gerhard^ &lt;strike&gt;eigentlich&lt;/strike&gt; kein Recht haben. &lt;strike&gt;(&lt;/strike&gt;Inzwischen sind die Ende Juni vereinbarten 50 Sch. per Stunde &lt;strike&gt;wieder&lt;/strike&gt; im Werte zurückgegangen u. wer kann wissen, was das kommende Jahr an ähnlichen Ueberraschungen ^noch^ bringen wird.)</tei:p><tei:p>Demnach würde ich Sie bitten es bei dem Entgegenkommen, das ich schon im Vorjahr geübt u. auch in der kommenden Saison zu üben mich gern bereitfinde,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Cf. Gerhard Albersheim's letter to Schenker from September 5, 1928 (OJ 9/5, [3]), indicating that Schenker had raised his price again for 1928/29.</tei:note> bewenden zu lassen, - ein weiteres wäre ^wahrlich^ schlecht angebracht. Ich u. Herr G haben viel Mühe, in den zu zählenden Stunden eine unendliche neue Welt unterzubringen.</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="bold">{9}</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">missing--if any</tei:hi>]</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Incomplete draft of letter from Schenker to Josef Albersheim, in JS's hand with emendations by HS, dated August 12, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Galtür <tei:hi rend="italic">August 12, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear senior health official,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>In response to your kind letter of August 8 from Sulden<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>, I will set the matter out clearly here.</tei:p><tei:p>Imagining that even I, for want of relevant knowledge, &lt;strike&gt;were to do as the&lt;/strike&gt; ^were to have to do as the^ so-called prominent people do, and ^like them^ &lt;strike&gt;have to&lt;/strike&gt; give instruction in only one discipline, ^then^ your son would ^have to^ seek  the ^his?^ education in the ^remaining^ subjects from other prominent people, if he wanted to satisfy his thirst for knowledge, which ^genuinely^ does him ^such very great^ credit.  In that case, the three or four prominent people who would have to take care of Gerhard would without doubt cause you higher costs than instruction from me, which is tailor-made to the person and consolidated as to content, <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> quite apart from the fact that he would gain nothing in knowledge--as Gerhard is already very well able to judge [for himself].  My knowledge and my conscience forbid me ^, however,^ from conducting myself in the manner of those prominent people, who without &lt;strike&gt;more ado&lt;/strike&gt; ^being able to teach something^ simply extract high fees from their pupils, ^and merely after that leave it to them either to enjoy^ [their] snobbish [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg word</tei:hi>] ^or to make their petty little careers^ with the name of the teacher.</tei:p><tei:p>&lt;strike&gt;From this alone, you &lt;sup&gt;,my very dear Mr. Albersheim,&lt;/sup&gt; can understand that I would &lt;sup&gt;already&lt;/sup&gt; in principle accommodate my pupils &lt;sup&gt;on the financial front&lt;/sup&gt;  if&lt;/strike&gt; If I &lt;strike&gt;without any yearning for prestige&lt;/strike&gt; ^only to distinguish [myself] from the utterly prominent people^ &lt;sup&gt;&lt;strike&gt;in the matter of the fee&lt;/strike&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; take upon myself the ^even^ physically ^so^ strenuous burden of a [mode of] instruction <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> conducted with highest ^integration^ of all the subject-areas and yet, however, ^without any yearning for prestige^ keep the fee lower than [that of] even teachers of lower caliber, ^there is not much room left for accommodation?^  Those who have been my pupils for many years even know to thank me for that and corroborate it by <tei:hi rend="italic">voluntarily</tei:hi> raising their fees as soon as the purchasing power of our currency declines.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  Thus it is that my pupils, &lt;strike&gt;already last year,&lt;/strike&gt; with regard for the fact that in the years 1924-26 our Schilling--despite political rehabilitation--had worsened by 25%, ^already increased their fee for 1926^.  (Indeed, my about thirty-five pupils in reality amounted to so little that no teacher worth taking halfway seriously <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> ^would have^ taught ^them^ for so tiny a fee.  In fact, I kept only Gerhard and the sister of Kapellmeister Hupka<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> at 5 dollars because I had committed myself in writing to that in the May without suspecting what the future held in store.)<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/></tei:p><tei:p>Now, once again it &lt;strike&gt;was&lt;/strike&gt; ^has been^ my pupils who at the close of the teaching year have raised me to 50 Schillings for the forthcoming year, 1927/28, with an eye to the further worsening of our currency.  &lt;strike&gt;They are very well&lt;/strike&gt; &lt;sup&gt;They are aware--just to reiterate it--&lt;/sup&gt; that I am actually still well behind the fee of middle-rank teachers and know to thank me for this [accommodation[?]] ...</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">missing</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> He should have come to me earlier than he did, or will have to content himself with a longer period of study.  Precisely his capability, his quickness of uptake, require more, rather than less.</tei:p><tei:p>Thus it would be advisable to make the sacrifice for him for this one further year--I will surely do my utmost--or, if that proves absolutely impossible for you, perhaps to leave it at two lessons per week, although I maintain that in this event his desire for knowledge would be completely out of proportion to the very modest gain in money.  Finally, I ask you to let me have your verdict by September 9.</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">missing</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> [...] accommodation, which resembles an act of patronage, to which I ^and Gerhard^ &lt;strike&gt;really&lt;/strike&gt; have no right.  &lt;strike&gt;(&lt;/strike&gt;In the meantime, the 50 Schillings per lesson agreed at the end of June has &lt;strike&gt;again&lt;/strike&gt; declined in value, and who can tell what comparable surprises the coming year ^still^ holds in store.)</tei:p><tei:p>Consequently, I would ask you to leave it at the accommodation that I already implemented last year<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> and am very willing to implement also in the coming teaching year, --any further [accommodation] would ^truly^ be ill-advised.  Gerhard and I have our work cut out to pack into the number of lessons that we have an infinite new world.</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="bold">{9}</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">missing--if any</tei:hi>]</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>