<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:CA 1-2 : 11-8-05 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Heinrich Schenker; reproduced here by kind permission of the Deutsches Literaturarchiv, Cotta-Archiv (Stiftung der Stuttgarter Zeitung), Marbach am Neckar.
© Transcription Ian D. Bent 2005.
© Translation Ian D. Bent 2005.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian D. Bent 2005.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> All reasonable steps have been taken to locate the heirs of Heinrich Schenker. Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>J.G. Cotta’sche Nachfolger/Stuttgarter Zeitung (1905-c1954), Cotta-Archiv, Schiller-Nationalmuseum, Marbach a. N., Germany (c.1954-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian D. Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 11/08/1905 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cotta ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cotta, dated November 8, 1905</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2005-05-18</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>[ NMTP I [Harmonielehre]:] Schenker proposes publication in Cotta's commission-publishing house;  explains anonymity and choice of Cotta;  notes critical attacks on Bruckner, [R.] Strauss, and Reger;  refers to vol. II.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Cotta, J. G.; NMTP; vol. I; vol. II; Harmonielehre; Theory of Harmony;  Kontrapunkt; Counterpoint;  publication; Kommissionsverlag; commission publishing house; anonymity; polemics; criticism; Goldbaum, Wilhelm; Bruckner, Anton; Strauss, Richard; Reger, Max; Meisterschaft; modernism; dilettantism; Bach, C. P. E.; Klavierwerke; Beitrag zur Ornamentik;  Contribution to Ornamentation;  Simrock; Breitkopf &amp; Härtel; Weinberger; UE</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Vienna III, Reisnerstraße 38</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> </marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cotta, dated November 8, 1905</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in another hand:</tei:hi>]  
Schenker
[<tei:hi rend="italic">in Schenker's hand:</tei:hi>]
Wien, 8. Nov. 1905</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr!</tei:p><tei:p>Indem ich mich auf H. D&lt;sup&gt;r.&lt;/sup&gt; <tei:hi rend="italic">Wilhelm Goldbaum</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Dr. Wilhelm Goldbaum: unknown outside this context:  he is mentioned twice in Schenker's diary, OJ 1/5, pp. 20, 22, helping Schenker with the title and final chapter of <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi>.  </tei:note> berufe, der zu jeder Auskunft über meine <tei:hi rend="italic">Person</tei:hi> u. mein künstlerisches Wirken sich bereit hält, erlaube ich mir Ihnen folgenden Antrag zu stellen :</tei:p><tei:p>Ich habe ein Buch unter dem Titel : "Neue musikalische Theorien u. Phantasien von einem Künstler“ geschrieben u. würde es mir zur Ehre anrechnen, wenn Sie dieses in Ihrem sehr gesch. Verlag <tei:hi rend="italic">in <tei:hi rend="italic">Commission</tei:hi></tei:hi> zu übernehmen die Liebenswürdigkeit haben wollten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  A commission-publishing house was an arrangement whereby the work was undertaken by the publisher and full accounts were rendered to the author, and upon receiving bills the author would advance the necessary sums, or—as in the case of Schenker—call on his patron to do so.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Vorerst die Erklärung der <tei:hi rend="italic">Anonymität</tei:hi>.  Eine auf Bestellung der hiesigen „<tei:hi rend="italic">Universal-Edition</tei:hi>“ veröffentlichte kritische <tei:hi rend="italic">Ph. Em. Bach</tei:hi>-Ausgabe,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Klavierwerke von Philipp Emanual Bach: Neue kritische Ausgabe von Heinrich Schenker</tei:hi>, UE 548 (Vienna: UE, [1903]).</tei:note> der ich ein Buch “Beitrag zur <tei:hi rend="italic">Ornamentik</tei:hi>“ beigegeben habe,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Ein Beitrag zur Ornamentik. Als Einführung zu Ph. Em. Bach’s Klavierwerken, umfassend auch die Ornamentik Haydns, Mozarts u. Beethovens etc von Heinrich Schenker</tei:hi>, UE 812 (Vienna: UE, [1903]; 2nd edn 1908).</tei:note> <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> hatte einen solchen Erfolg bei der Presse u. dem <tei:hi rend="italic">Publikum</tei:hi>, daß sich, nach einer lieben alten Gewohnheit der Menschen, plötzlich Vorurteile gegen meine kompositorische Tätigkeit &lt;strike&gt;ge&lt;/strike&gt; laut zu machen versucht haben, trotz den Erfolgen der Aufführungen, u. trotzdem Firmen wie <tei:hi rend="italic">Simrock</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Br. &amp; Härtel</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Weinberger</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">etc</tei:hi>. meine Sachen druckten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  In the late 1890s and early 1900s, Schenker established himself as a composer of piano, solo vocal, choral, and vocal/orchestral works, many of which were given public performances; of these, some eight were published, e.g. <tei:hi rend="italic">Fünf Klavierstücke</tei:hi>, Op.4 (Leipzig: Breitkopf u. Härtel, 1898), <tei:hi rend="italic">Ländler für Pianoforte</tei:hi>, Op.10 (Berlin: Simrock, 1899), <tei:hi rend="italic">Syrische Tänze für Pianofort zu 4 Händen</tei:hi> (Vienna: Weinberger, [1899]).  </tei:note>  Um den künftigen Arbeiten nicht zu schaden, entschied ich mich zur vorläufigen <tei:hi rend="italic">Anomymität</tei:hi>.</tei:p><tei:p>Außerdem enthält das Buch, das ein <tei:hi rend="italic">Lehrbuch</tei:hi> der Harmonie ist,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6"> Eventually published as <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">NMTP</tei:hi> vol. I (Stuttgart: J. G. Cotta’sche Nachfolger, 1906). </tei:note> u. als solches einen in kleine § geteilten, fortlaufenden wissenschaftlichen <tei:hi rend="italic">Text</tei:hi> bringt, in einigen Anmerkungen gegen den modernen <tei:hi rend="italic">Dilletantismus</tei:hi> ziemlich starke <tei:hi rend="italic">Pointen</tei:hi>, so z. B. gegen die angebliche “Meisterschaft“ eines <tei:hi rend="italic">Bruckner</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Strauss</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Reger etc</tei:hi>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  See in particular <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi>, pp.220–23, fn.1 (Reger); 273–77, 376–78 (Bruckner); 291–93, fn.1, 299–304 (Strauss).</tei:note>  Es sind aber auch diese <tei:hi rend="italic">Pointen</tei:hi> mit <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Gründen theoretischer Natur motivirt, keineswegs blos in <tei:hi rend="italic">journalistischer</tei:hi> Weise behauptet.  Nun lag es mir daran, die Wirkung dieser Waffen abzuwarten, in aller Ruhe, um in der Abfassung des IIten Bandes, einer „<tei:hi rend="italic">Psychologie</tei:hi> u. <tei:hi rend="italic">Kritik</tei:hi> des <tei:hi rend="italic">Contrapunctes</tei:hi> &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;auf neuer Grundlage&lt;/sup&gt;“ nicht gestört zu werden.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Eventually published as <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt</tei:hi>, Parts 1 and 2, <tei:hi rend="italic">NMTP</tei:hi>, vol.II/1 <tei:hi rend="italic">Cantus Firmus und Zweistimmiger Satz</tei:hi> (Stuttgart: J. G. Cotta’sche Nachfolger, 1910), vol.II/2 <tei:hi rend="italic">Drei- und Mehrstimmiger Satz; Übergänge zum freien Satz</tei:hi> (Vienna: UE, 1922).  We may assume that the dust has by this time settled, since in the final paragraph Schenker declares himself in a hurry to see the book out.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Eben wegen dieser Angriffe empfahl es sich aber zugleich, einen neutralen Verlag zu wählen, der nicht <tei:hi rend="italic">Bruckner</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Strauss</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">etc.</tei:hi> gedruckt hat.  In diesem Sinne wurde ich nun[?] hier, wo das Buch – trotz allen Geheimnissen – von Fachleuten, u. Anhängern u. Schülern mit größter Spannung, wie es H. <tei:hi rend="italic">D&lt;sup&gt;r.&lt;/sup&gt; Goldbaum</tei:hi> ja bestätigen mag, erwartet wird, dahin beraten, daß ich mich mit der Bitte um dem <tei:hi rend="italic">Comissions</tei:hi>verlag an Sie wende.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi>Ich tue es hiemit, u. bitte zugleich, mit einem principiellen Bescheid zunächst zukommen lassen zu wollen.</tei:p><tei:p>Wollten Sie auch darauf Rücksicht nehmen, daß ich mit dem Erscheinen des Buches ziemlich eilig habe, so  wäre ich für diese Leibenswürdigkeit sehr zu Dank verpflichtet.</tei:p><tei:p>In ausgez. Hochachtung
zeichne
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">Dr. Heinrich Schenker</tei:hi>
III <tei:hi rend="italic">Reisner</tei:hi>strasse 38</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cotta, dated November 8, 1905</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in another hand:</tei:hi>]  
Schenker
[<tei:hi rend="italic">in Schenker's hand:</tei:hi>]
Vienna, November 8, 1905</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Sir,</tei:p><tei:p>Dr. Wilhelm Goldbaum<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> has agreed to provide any information regarding me personally or my work as an artist.  In referring [you] to him, I take the liberty of putting the following proposal to you:</tei:p><tei:p>I have written a book entitled <tei:hi rend="italic">New Musical Theories and Fantasies, by an Artist</tei:hi>, and should be greatly honored if you would do me the favor of accepting this in your highly est’d <tei:hi rend="italic">commission</tei:hi>-publishing house.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/></tei:p><tei:p>First let me explain the anonymity.  A critical edition of C. P. E. Bach,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> published by order of Universal Edition here, to which I have written a supplementary book, <tei:hi rend="italic">A Contribution to Ornamentation</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> has had such success with the press and the public that, in accordance with an long-standing human foible, hostile opinions have suddenly been expressed about my work as a composer, despite the successes of the performances, and despite the fact that firms such as Simrock, Breitkopf &amp; Härtel, Weinberger, etc. have published my works.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  So as not to jeopardize my future work, I elected to assume anonymity for the time being.</tei:p><tei:p>Moreover, as a harmony <tei:hi rend="italic">textbook</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> with a continuously reasoned scholarly text subdivided into short paragraphs, my book includes some commentary sections containing quite robust criticisms of modern dilettantism, for example of the alleged “mastery” of Bruckner, Strauss, Reger, etc.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> These criticisms, however, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> far from being merely asserted in journalistic fashion, are bolstered by arguments theoretical in nature.  Now, it was important to me to let the dust from these attacks settle, in order not to be disturbed while writing vol. II, a <tei:hi rend="italic">Psychology and Critique of Counterpoint</tei:hi> &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;<tei:hi rend="italic">based on new principles</tei:hi>&lt;/sup&gt;.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/></tei:p><tei:p>At the same time, precisely in view of these attacks, it seemed advisable to select a neutral publishing house that had not printed Bruckner, Strauss, etc.  It is for this reason that I was advised here—where the book, despite all the secrecy, is awaited with great excitement by specialists, disciples, and pupils, as Dr. Goldbaum can certainly attest—to the effect that I should turn to you with a request for [inclusion in] your commission-publishing house.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> This I do herewith, asking you at the same time in the first place to let me have an answer in principle.</tei:p><tei:p>I should be greatly indebted if you would be so kind as to bear in mind that I am anxious to see the book in print as soon as possible.</tei:p><tei:p>With kind regards,
I remain,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  Dr. Heinrich Schenker
Vienna III, Reisnerstrasse 38</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>