<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:CA 5-6 : 11-22-05 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Heinrich Schenker; reproduced here by kind permission of the Deutsches Literaturarchiv, Cotta-Archiv (Stiftung der Stuttgarter Zeitung), Marbach am Neckar.
© Transcription Ian D. Bent 2005.
© Translation Ian D. Bent 2005.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian D. Bent 2005.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> All reasonable steps have been taken to locate the heirs of Heinrich Schenker. Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>J.G. Cotta’sche Nachfolger/Stuttgarter Zeitung (1905-c1954), Cotta-Archiv, Schiller-Nationalmuseum, Marbach a. N., Germany (c.1954-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian D. Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 11/22/1905 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cotta ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cotta, dated November 22, 1905</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2005-05-23</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>[NMTP I = Harmonielehre:]  Implicitly acknowledges OJ 9/31, [3], and submits MS. Has retained Afterword for further drafting. Asks that the MS not be shown to too many specialists, and specifically not Hugo Riemann or a Riemann follower. Asks for quick decision.  Encloses Table of Contents typewritten.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Cotta, J. G.; NMTP; vol.1; Harmonielehre; Theory of Harmony;  publication; Afterword; Nachwort; cyclical technique; commission-publishing house; Kommissionsverlag; Riemann, Hugo; Riemannian; intellectual theft</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">s:</tei:hi>  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cotta, dated November 22, 1905</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr!</tei:p><tei:p>Über die angenehme neue Wendung sehr erfreut, erlaube ich mir hiemit das Manuskript zu Ihrer Einsicht einzusenden.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  See OJ 9/31, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  i.e. presumably Cotta’s commission-publishing house.</tei:note>, November 15, for Cotta’s change of heart in the light of a letter of recommendation received on Schenker’s behalf from Eugen d’Albert.  Schenker had initially proposed the publication to Cotta on November 8 (CA 1-2), and received a rejection from them on November 9 (OJ 9/31, [1]).</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ich habe nur das Nachwort hier zurückbehalten, um es einer zweiten <tei:hi rend="italic">Redaction</tei:hi> zu unterziehen: es ist etwa einen Druckbogen stark, u. beschäftigt sich mit der leider verloren gegangenen cyklischen Technik unserer großen Meister.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  This Afterword was not included in the eventual publication of <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi>.  It was dropped after it became too long (see OJ 9/31, [8], May 31, 1906), at which point Schenker expressed the intention of publishing it separately under a title “along the lines of ‘Beethoven or Wagner’.”  It is mentioned in the Foreword to <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (p.VII, trans. xxvi) and given the predictive title of <tei:hi rend="italic">Über den Niedergang der Kompositionskunst,—eine technisch-kritische Untersuchung</tei:hi> (The Decline of the Art of Composition–A Technical-Critical Inquiry).  The work was never published, but survives in a typescript draft with Schenker’s corrections as OC 31/28–153.  There is no evidence in the latter of there having been a one-gathering-length version.  For an edition with translation and Introduction, by William Drabkin, see <tei:hi rend="italic">Music Analysis</tei:hi>, XXIV/1–2 (March–July 2005), pp. 3–232.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Wenn ich nunmehr eine Bitte äußern darf, so wäre es diese: nicht allzuviel Fachleute [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] das <tei:hi rend="italic">Manuscript</tei:hi> einsehen zu <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> lassen.  Handelt es sich doch um die <tei:hi rend="italic">Priorität</tei:hi> der Idee, die ich eben durch die <tei:hi rend="italic">Commission</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  i.e. presumably Cotta’s commission-publishing house.</tei:note> so gut als möglich geschützt wissen möchte.  Insbesondere [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] befürchte ich jeden <tei:hi rend="italic">Contact</tei:hi> mit <tei:hi rend="italic">Prof. Dr. Riemann</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="riemann_hugo">Hugo Riemann</ref>.  </tei:note> oder einem „<tei:hi rend="italic">Riemannianer</tei:hi>,“ – gerade &lt;strike&gt;die&lt;/strike&gt; gegen Musik-Mathematik, wie sie <tei:hi rend="italic">Riemann</tei:hi> vertritt, wendet sich demonstrativ mein Buch, u. doch hat Niemand mehr Lust, alles Neue [...?] auf sich zu beziehen [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>], nur von sich abzuleiten als eben <tei:hi rend="italic">Prof. Riemann</tei:hi>.  Er beherrscht heute den Markt, auf dem er Niemandem mehr ein Plätzchen gönnt.</tei:p><tei:p>Lassen Sie mich, bitte, auf Ihre Entscheidung nicht allzulange warten.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Der Inhalt des Buches ist in einem Schreibmaschine–<tei:hi rend="italic">Exemplar extra</tei:hi> beigegeben, damit die Übersicht über die § u. die Marginalrubriken (wie sie auch gedruckt werden) erleichtert ist.</tei:p><tei:p>In ausgez. Hochachtung
ergeb.
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">H. Schenker</tei:hi>
Wien, 22. Novemb. 1905.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cotta, dated November 22, 1905</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Sir,</tei:p><tei:p>I am delighted at the latest welcome turn of events, and take the liberty of submitting to you herewith my manuscript for your inspection.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>The only thing I have retained is the Afterword so that I can give it a second reworking.  It is about one gathering long, and deals with the cyclical technique—regrettably now lost—of our great masters.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/></tei:p><tei:p>If I may at this point express one wish, it is that you not let too many specialists examine my manuscript.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> The issue is really one of the priority of my idea, which I should like to be sure is safeguarded as completely as possible through the commission.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  In particular, I fear lest Professor Riemann<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> or any “Riemannian” might get his hands on it.  It is precisely against “musical mathematics” as represented by Riemann that my book is expressly directed.  There is no one in the world more eager than Professor Riemann to appropriate to himself every new idea, only to present it as his own.[??]  He currently commands the marketplace, and no longer allows anyone even a small patch.</tei:p><tei:p>Please do not keep me waiting too long for your decision.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> I am also enclosing the Table of Contents of the book in a typewritten copy, so as to facilitate control of the paragraphs and marginal subheadings (and how they are printed).</tei:p><tei:p>With kind regards,
Yours,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H. Schenker
Vienna, November 22, 1905.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>