<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:CA 76 : 4-24-08 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Heinrich Schenker, with the permission of the Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach, Cotta-Archiv (Stiftung der Stuttgarter Zeitung), Marbach am Neckar.
© Transcription Ian D. Bent 2005
© Translation Ian D. Bent 2005.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian D. Bent 2005.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> All reasonable steps have been taken to locate the heirs of Heinrich Schenker. Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>J.G. Cotta’sche Nachfolger/Stuttgarter Zeitung (1908-c.1954); Cotta-Archiv, Schiller-Nationalmuseum, Marbach a. N., Germany (c.1954-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker; reproduced here by kind permission of the Deutsches Literaturarchiv, Cotta-Archiv (Stiftung der Stuttgarter Zeitung), Marbach am Neckar; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian D. Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 04/24/1908 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cotta ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cotta, dated April 24, 1908</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2005-08-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>[ NMTP I = Harmonielehre:] Complimentary copy to Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde (Mandyczewski); —[ NMTP II = Kontrapunkt:] Work has been delayed by production of 2nd edn of Beitrag zur Ornamentik, and will resume in a few days; would excerpts appearing in Beethoven-Jahrbuch damage vol. II's chances?

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Cotta, J. G.; NMTP; vol. I; Harmonielehre; Harmony; Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde; Mandyczewski, Eusebius; vol. II; Kontrapunkt; Counterpoint; Frimmel, Theodor; Beethoven-Jahrbuch; Müller, G; Munich; excerpts; essay; Beethoven; Fifth Symphony; UE; Beitrag zur Ornamentik; Ornamentation; 2nd edn; revision; proofs</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cotta, dated April 24, 1908</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">not in Schenker’s hand:</tei:hi> ]  Schenker</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">in Schenker’s hand:</tei:hi> ]
Wien, 24. 4. 08</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr !</tei:p><tei:p>Wollen Sie die Freundlichkeit haben, ein Exemplar meiner “Th. u. Ph.“ auf meine Rechnung an das „<tei:hi rend="italic">Archiv der Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde</tei:hi>“ <tei:hi rend="italic">in <tei:hi rend="italic">Wien</tei:hi></tei:hi> zu senden, dessen Archivar, H. Dr. Mandyczewsky mich darum ersucht hat.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  S made precisely the same request to UE on August 19, 1908, for a copy of <tei:hi rend="italic">A Contribution to the Study of Ornamentation</tei:hi>: WSLB 14.  Click on <ref cRef="mandyczewski_eusebiu">Eusebius Mandyczewski</ref>.</tei:note> – Wenn ich bis jetzt das <tei:hi rend="italic">Manuscript</tei:hi> des „<tei:hi rend="italic">Contrapunktes</tei:hi>“ noch nicht eingesandt habe, so hat dies [ <tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi> ] darin seinen Grund, daß ich plötzlich alle meine Zeit u. Kraft einer  II. Auflage eines in der hiesigen „<tei:hi rend="italic">Universal-Edition</tei:hi>“  vor nicht langer Zeit erschienenen Werkchens ( „Beitrag zur <tei:hi rend="italic">Ornamentik</tei:hi>“ ) zur Verfügung stellen mußte, u. die Veranstaltung eben der II. Auflage durchaus keine Verzögerung erleiden durfte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> This statement accords entirely with the facts.  The first edition of <tei:hi rend="italic">Ornamentik</tei:hi> was published on July 24, 1903, the second edition on August 24, 1908.  The demand for revisions to the work came from Hertzka out of the blue and on a tight schedule on March 24, 1908 (OC 52/383), S agreed on the following day (WSLB 1), and diary entries (OJ 1/5, p.89) report gruelling work during the first week of April; the work went to press on April 8 (Verlagsdruckbuch UE 812.), at which point S reports a nervous condition resulting from the work; after that, S was occupied with proof correcting from mid-April to June 23 (WSLB 9).</tei:note>  In wenigen Tagen kehre ich zum „<tei:hi rend="italic">Cp.</tei:hi>“ zurück, wo nur die letzten Bogen zu revidieren sind.</tei:p><tei:p>Nur nun eine Bitte um Ihren Rath.  H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Dr. Th. v. Frimmel</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="frimmel_theodor">Theodor Frimmel</ref>.</tei:note> bat mich mehrmals dringend um &lt;strike&gt;xxx&lt;/strike&gt; ^einem^ ersten eröffnenden Aufsatz des II. Jahrganges seines „<tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven</tei:hi>-Jahrbuches“ (Verlag, G. <tei:hi rend="italic">Müller</tei:hi>, München).  Für eben diesen Jahrgang <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> bereitet <tei:hi rend="italic">Dr. Frimmel</tei:hi> selbst sehr umfassende Auszüge aus meinem 1. Band.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  See CA 75, February 8, for the first reference to this project.</tei:note>  Ich schlug dem genannten Herausgeber, der
als <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven</tei:hi>-Forscher vielleicht auch Ihnen bekannt sein dürfte, einen Aufsatz über den Anfang der <tei:hi rend="italic">V. Symphonie</tei:hi> von <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven</tei:hi> ^vor^, der im 2. Band meiner „<tei:hi rend="italic">Th. u. Ph.</tei:hi>“ im Rahmen eines <tei:hi rend="italic">contrapunktischen Problems</tei:hi> seinen bestimmten Platz bereits seit langem inne hat.  Nun, kann dieses dem 2. Bande irgend schaden?  Oder ist es am Ende von Vorteil, wenn ein Abschnitt aus einem demnächst erscheinenden größeren Werke in einem so regardierten Jahrbuch, wie es das frimmel’sche ist wiedergegeben wird?</tei:p><tei:p>Besten Dank im Vorhinein<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  <tei:hi rend="italic">im Vorhinein</tei:hi>: an Austrian expression.</tei:note> für alle Mühewaltung.
Mit ausgezeichneter Hochachtung
Ir ergb.
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H Schenker</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cotta, dated April 24, 1908</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">not in Schenker’s hand:</tei:hi> ]  Schenker</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">in Schenker’s hand:</tei:hi> ]
Vienna, April 24, 1908</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Sir,</tei:p><tei:p>Would you be so kind as to send a copy of my <tei:hi rend="italic">Theories and Fantasies</tei:hi>, to be charged to my account, to the <tei:hi rend="italic">Archive of the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde</tei:hi> in <tei:hi rend="italic">Vienna</tei:hi>. The Keeper of that Archive, Dr. Mandyczewski, has asked me for one.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  —The reason why I have not yet submitted the manuscript of my <tei:hi rend="italic">Counterpoint</tei:hi> is that I was obliged suddenly to put all my time and energy into a second edition of a booklet ( <tei:hi rend="italic">A Contribution to the Study of Ornamentation</tei:hi> ) that appeared not long ago from Universal Edition here, and the preparation of this second edition brooked absolutely no delay.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  I shall get back to <tei:hi rend="italic">Counterpoint</tei:hi> again in a few days’ time; all that is left is to revise the final gatherings.</tei:p><tei:p>Now just to ask your advice.  Dr. Theodor von Frimmel<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> has several times insistently asked me for a first, opening essay for the second annual volume of his <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven-Jahrbuch</tei:hi> (published by G. Müller of Munich).  For this volume, <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Dr. Frimmel himself is preparing a very wide-ranging selection of excerpts from my vol. I.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  I proposed to the editor, Dr. Frimmel, who may perhaps be familiar to you as a Beethoven scholar, an essay on the opening of the Fifth Symphony of Beethoven that has long had its designated place in vol. II of my <tei:hi rend="italic">Theories and Fantasies</tei:hi> in the context of a contrapuntal problem.  Could this in any way damage the chances of vol. II?  Or is it ultimately an advantage if a selection from a soon-to-appear larger work is presented in an annual periodical as highly regarded as that of Frimmel?</tei:p><tei:p>With many thanks in anticipation<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> for any trouble this may put you to.
With kind regards,
Yours truly,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H. Schenker</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>