<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="clearances"
    xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Clearances</title>
                <title type="sub">Permissions and Clearances to Publish obtained by <hi
                        rend="italic">Schenker Documents Online</hi></title>
                <title type="sub"/>
                <author/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>compiled by</resp>
                    <name>Ian Bent</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836
                        5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>This resource is publicly available and free at the point of access and it is
                        registered under a a <ref type="external"
                            target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">Creative Commons
                            license Attribution-Share Alike 3.0</ref>
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at
                http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/about/encoding/</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2009-08-06</date>
                <name>TL</name>
                <desc>Template Created</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date/>
                <name/>
                <desc/>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head>Clearances</head>

            <div>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Schenker Documents Online</hi> seeks constantly to clarify its
                    position under Intellectual Property Rights law before it, under normal
                    circumstances, publishes any document. As a result, for some classes of document
                    it holds written permission from heirs of the author or their representatives,
                    for other classes of document it has established that those documents are in the
                    public domain, and for still other classes of document it is currently seeking
                    permission or clearance. The two lists given below show the current state of
                    affairs.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Permissions and Clearances Obtained</head>
                <p>The following are permissions granted by heirs of the author or their
                    representatives, and clearances established that material is in the public
                    domain:</p>
                <div>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst</hi> — granted by
                        the Leiterin des Archivs, Dr. Lynne Heller, January 17, 2009</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Albersheim, Gerhard and Josef</hi> — granted by principal
                        heir, Anne Albersheim Andrews, August 19, 2013</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">J. G. Cotta'sche Buchhandlung Nachfolger</hi> — material in
                        public domain; permission to publish letters written by Schenker to Cotta
                        and carbon copies of letters written by Cotta to Schenker held in the
                        Cotta-Archiv (Stiftung der Stuttgarter Zeitung) of the
                        Schiller-Nationalmuseum/Deutsche Literaturarchiv granted by the latter, July
                        20, 2005</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Cube, Felix von</hi> — granted by the principal heir,
                        Claus-Eberhard von Cube, January 16, 2005</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Dahms, Walter</hi> — granted by principal heir, his grand
                        daugther, Cristina Texeio Coelho, August 12, 2009</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Deutsch, Otto Erich</hi> — granted by the principal heir,
                        grand daughter, Lady Elisabeth Schiemann, February 12, 2008 </p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Drei Masken Verlag, Munich</hi> — material deemed to be in
                        the public domain in light of communication from the current Drei Masken
                        Verlag of Munich, February 10, 2010, stating that it neither holds the
                        rights itself nor knows which other publisher might hold them; its archives
                        were destroyed during World War II</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Einstein, Alfred</hi> — no surviving relatives could be found
                        after all reasonable efforts; the materials are deemed to be in the public
                        domain.</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Furtwängler, Wilhelm</hi> — granted by the principal heir,
                        Elisabeth Furtwängler, February 26, 2006</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Grunsky, Karl</hi> — granted by principal heir, grandson, Dr.
                        Konrad Grunsky, March 8, 2007 </p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Halm, August</hi> — granted by the principal heir, Eberhard
                        Halm, March 20, 2006; permission to publish the letters written by Schenker
                        to Halm and held in the Schiller-Nationalmuseum/Deutsche Literaturarchiv
                        granted by the latter, March 2, 2006</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Hammer, Victor</hi> — granted by the Executor of the will of
                        Carolyn Reading Hammer, wife of Victor Hammer, W. Gay Reading, October 14,
                        2013</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Harden, Maximilian</hi> — material in the public domain
                        (confirmed by VG WORT, December 7, 2006)</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Hindemith, Paul</hi> — granted by the representatives of the
                        heirs of Paul Hindemith, the Hindemith Institut, Frankfurt-am-Main, February
                        2, 2010</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Hoboken, Anthony van</hi> — granted by the son and heir,
                        Anthony van Hoboken, jnr., February 13, 2007</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Jonas, Oswald</hi> — granted by the sole heir, Professor
                        Irene Schreier Scott, March 6, 2006</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Kopfermann, Albert</hi> — material in the public domain
                        (confirmed by VG WORT, December 7, 2006)</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Lafite, Carl</hi> — granted by the grand daughter and heir,
                        Dr. Marion Diederichs-Lafite, March 29, 2009</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Edition Peters Leipzig</hi> — granted by the company, May 19,
                        2009</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Roentgen, Julius</hi> — material in public domain; letters
                        published with the permission of the Netherlands Music Institute</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Rothschild, Baron Albert von</hi> — granted by his
                        descendant, Mrs. Bettina Looram, via the Archivist of the The Rothschild
                        Archive, April 10, 2008 </p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Rothschild, Baron Alphons von</hi> — granted by his daughter,
                        Mrs. Bettina Looram, via the Archivist of the The Rothschild Archive, April
                        10, 2008 </p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Salzer, Felix</hi> — granted by the legal representatives of
                        the estate of Hedwig Salzer, December 21, 2004</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Schoenberg, Arnold</hi> — granted by his son, Lawrence
                        Schoenberg, January 6, 2011</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Universal Edition</hi> — publication of all correspondence by
                        Universal Edition and its employees to Heinrich &amp; Jeanette Schenker
                        granted by the Board of Directors of Universal Edition AG, Vienna, December
                        6, 2010</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Violin, Moriz &amp; Valerie</hi> — granted by the principal
                        heir, Mrs. Eva Violin-Windsor, June 25 and October 18, 2006</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Waechter, Eberhard Baron von</hi> — granted by his
                        descendant, Franz Waechter, July 7, 2010</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Waldeck, Arthur</hi> — granted by the grand daughter, Erika
                        S. Waldeck, January 31, 2008</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Weinberger, Josef &amp; Co.</hi> — granted by Sean Gray on
                        behalf of Weinberger Books, London, September 24, 2004</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Weisse, Hans</hi> — granted by the daughter, Susanna Parker,
                        grand daughter, Bronwyn Cooper, and grandson, Andrew Parker, May 26, 2008 </p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Wolf, Hans</hi> — granted by the sole heir, sister, Elsbeth
                        Pfeiffer, December 3, 2006</p>
                    <p><hi rend="bold">Zuckerkandl, Viktor (Victor)</hi> — granted by the nephew,
                        Professor Emile Zuckerkandl, April 14, 2007</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Permissions and Clearances Sought</head>
                <p>Permissions currently being sought are as follows:</p>
                <p>Bahr, Hermann</p>
                <p>Bienenfeld, Elsa</p>
                <p>Colbert, Carl &amp; Tony</p>
                <p>Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde Wien and its officials</p>
                <p>Hupka, Felix</p>
                <p>Karpath, Ludwig</p>
                <p>Marx, Josef</p>
                <p>Rosenthal, Moriz</p>
                <p>Seligmann, Adalbert</p>
                <p>Steglich, Rudolf</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
