<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ethical_statement"
    xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Ethical Statement</title>
                <title type="sub"/>
                <author/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>compiled by</resp>
                    <name>Ian Bent</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
        <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
        <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>This resource is publicly available and free at the point of access and it is
                        registered under a a <ref type="external"
                            target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">Creative Commons
                            license Attribution-Share Alike 3.0</ref>
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at
                http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/about/encoding/</p>
        </encodingDesc>

        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2009-08-06</date>

                <name>TL</name>

                <desc>Template Created</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date/>
                <name/>
                <desc/>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>

        <body>

            <head>Ethical Statement</head>

            <div>
                <p>Preparation and publication of Schenker's correspondence, diaries, lessonbooks
                    and other documents should in no way be construed as a tacit endorsement by any
                    of its contributors of the political, social, cultural, or racial views that may
                    be expressed in those documents. The materials have been made available as a
                    resource for research purposes only, not as a platform for particular
                    ideologies.</p>

                <p><hi rend="italic">Schenker Documents Online</hi> respects the intellectual
                    property of authors and editors, and the material property of libraries,
                    archives and individuals. It identifies the descendants of the originators of
                    all documents, and obtains written permission from them to publish those
                    documents, or alternatively establishes that those documents are in the public
                    domain. <hi rend="italic">SDO</hi> stamps each document with a statement of all rights held in that
                    document, or asserts that the IPR is in the public domain. <hi rend="italic"
                    >SDO</hi> does not knowingly infringe any copyright, and it provides an email
                    address to which any persons who consider they have a claim on a document may
                    present that claim. </p>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
