<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="project_history"
    xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Project History</title>
                <title type="sub"/>
                <author/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>compiled by</resp>
                    <name>Ian Bent</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836
                        5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>This resource is publicly available and free at the point of access and it is
                        registered under a a <ref type="external"
                            target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">Creative Commons
                            license Attribution-Share Alike 3.0</ref>
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at
                http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/about/encoding/</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2009-08-06</date>
                <name>TL</name>
                <desc>Template Created</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date/>
                <name/>
                <desc/>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head>Project History</head>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>It was the writing by Ian Bent and William Drabkin of the General Preface to the
                    English translation of <title level="m">Der Tonwille</title> (New York: Oxford
                    University Press, 2004–2005), entailing as it did examining much of Schenker's
                    correspondence with Universal Edition and the attorneys involved in the
                    potential court proceeding between the two contending parties, that gave the
                    initial impetus to what is now <hi rend="italic">Schenker Documents Online</hi>.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Phase 1 : <hi rend="italic">Schenker Correspondence Project</hi> :
                    2003–2007</head>
                <p>An independent web-based project entitled <hi rend="italic">The Schenker
                        Correspondence Project</hi>, the purpose of which was to publish all
                    Schenker's correspondence in a scholarly, digital edition, was launched in 2003.
                    This was co-ordinated from the UK by Professors Ian Bent and William Drabkin,
                    the editing done by a small international team of scholars, the data held on the
                    servers of Columbia University in the City of New York using the webblog
                    software package MovableType, with a linked website on the server of the
                    University of Cambridge Faculty of Music, for both of which invaluable technical
                    support was provided by those institutions. The first document went up on the
                    site on June 12, 2004. </p>
                <p>2003–2007 marked phase 1 of the project, and served as a pilot for an eventually
                    larger, more comprehensive undertaking; it was almost entirely unfunded. The
                    years 1900–1912 formed the primary focus of Schenker's correspondence for phase
                    1, emphasis being placed on Schenker's two principal publishers, Universal
                    Edition and J. G. Cotta—although correspondence from later years (Angi Elias,
                    August Halm, Maximilian Harden, Oswald Jonas, Felix-Eberhard von Cube, Viktor
                    Zuckerkandl, and others) was also published. Some 500 items of correspondence
                    were posted to the web during this phase. </p>
            </div>


            <div>
                <head>Phase 2 : <hi rend="italic">Schenker Documents Online</hi> : 2007–2010</head>
                <p>So important did Schenker's diaries prove to be in corroborating his
                    correspondence that for phase 2, spanning 2007–2010, the scope of the project
                    was expanded to include both Schenker's diaries and his lessonbooks, with the
                    aim of providing the end-user with fluid movement among the three categories of
                    documents. In 2007, the project was retitled <hi rend="italic">Schenker
                        Documents Online</hi> (<hi rend="italic">SDO</hi>). Funding was obtained
                    from the Leverhulme Trust in the UK for three years specifically to design and
                    deliver a new web environment using XML encoding and following TEI guidelines:
                    the design work was carried out at the Centre for Computing in the Humanities at
                    King's College London, on whose servers the project would in future be
                    maintained. For phase 2, the focus shifted to the eight-year period 1918–25, one
                    which saw the emergence of Urlinie and Ursatz and the beginnings of layered
                    voice-leading analysis, and in which the outcome of World War I and ensuing
                    economic stringency had a major impact on Schenker's thinking. Correspondence
                    with Universal Edition again occupied a central place, along with other
                    correspondence streams (Guido Adler, Wilhelm Furtwängler, Anthony van Hoboken,
                    the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde, Felix Salzer, Moriz Violin, Hans Weisse, and
                    others).</p>

                <p>For phase 2, <hi rend="italic">Schenker Documents Online</hi> entered into
                    collaboration with a team of scholars working at the Universität für Musik und
                    Darstellende Kunst in Vienna, who transcribed and translated Schenker's diaries
                    for 1918–25 <hi rend="italic">in extenso</hi>, delivering XML-encoded files for
                    publication on <hi rend="italic">SDO</hi>. This work was funded for three years
                    by the Austrian Fonds zur Förderung der wissenschaftlichen Forschung (FWF).
                    Funds were provided by other British trusts for the supply of document scans and
                    for other purposes. The new web environment was released in its first version in
                    September 2009. </p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Phase 3 : <hi rend="italic">SDO</hi> : 2011–2014</head>
                <p>Phase 3 focussed primarily on the period October 1925 to September 1930, the
                    period in which Schenker arrived at the final formulation of his theory, and
                    resumed work on <title level="m">Der freie Satz</title>. Emphasis was placed on
                    Schenker's correspondence with the third of his three main publishing houses,
                    Drei Masken Verlag of Munich, with the engravers Waldheim-Eberle of Vienna, and
                    with those involved in their publication of <title level="m">Das Meisterwerk in
                        der Musik</title> (Otto Erich Deutsch, Alfred Einstein, and others) as well
                    as that with Universal Edition, the content of which interlocks with that of
                    DMV; and also on the diaries for 1925‒30, and the lessonbooks for the seasons
                    1925/26 to 1929/30 (the latter, however, was not carried out). This phase was
                    funded by a large grant from the Arts &amp; Humanities Research Council of Great
                    Britain. During this phase, some transfer of correspondence from the Columbia
                    site was carried out, and some editing of new material outside the 1925‒30
                    framework (e.g. Walter Dahms, Viktor Hammer).</p>

                <p>For phase 3, <hi rend="italic">Schenker Documents Online</hi> was based at the
                    Department of Music of the University of Southampton in collaboration with the
                    Department of Digital Humanities of University of London King's College. The
                    Principal Investigator was William Drabkin, Co-Investigators were Paul Spence
                    and Andrea Reiter, with post-doctorate fellows Marko Deisinger and David
                    Bretherton and PhD candidates Kirstie Hewlett and Georg Burgstaller. As part of
                    the AHRC project plan, SDO published <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker:
                        Selected Correspondence</title>, edited by Ian Bent, David Bretherton and
                    William Drabkin and published by The Boydell Press of Woodbridge, Suffolk. This
                    568-page volume presents some 450 letters in English translation, organized into
                    six sections devoted to aspects of his professional life, with extensive
                    introductory materials and supporting commentary.</p>

                <p>In March 2013 the members of the phase 3 project team presented papers at a
                    special Schenker Documents panel at the Fifth International Schenker Symposium,
                    hosted by the Mannes College; these were published in the journal <title
                        level="j">Music Analysis</title>, vol. 34, No. 2, "Special Issue on Schenker
                    Documents" (July 2015).</p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Phase 4 : 2014‒2017</head>
                <p>Phase 4 comprised two main initiatives. First, the team of scholars in Vienna
                    which completed the transcribing and translating of Schenker's diaries 1918‒30
                    during phases 2 and 3 now extended that series to Schenker's death in January
                    1935. The team's work, headed by Martin Eybl, was funded as in phase 2 by the
                    FWF. Transcription was by Marko Deisinger, translation by William Drabkin (with
                    annotations by both), editorial work by Kirstie Hewlett, and XML encoding by Iby
                    Jolande-Varga.</p>

                <p>Second, much of the correspondence encoded during phase 1 and the early part of
                    phase 2 in MovableType on the Columbia University website (which finally went
                    offline around the end of this period) was re-edited and XML encoded on the main
                    site. The largest collections were those with Universal Edition, Josef
                    Weinberger, and J.G. Cotta, encompassing 1901 to 1909, but important collections
                    with numerous private persons, for example Felix-Eberhard von Cube, Wilhelm
                    Furtwängler, August Halm, Oswald Jonas, and Julius Röntgen, were re-edited and
                    encoded on the present site.</p>

            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Phase 5 : 2018-2022</head>
                <p>Phase 5 comprised three projects. The first closed the remaining gaps in
                    Schenker's diaries: that from the beginning in 1896 to 1911 was transcribed,
                    translated, and encoded by Ian Bent; separately, and funded yet again by the
                    FWF, that from 1912 to September 1917 was produced by the team of scholars in
                    Vienna with William Drabkin and Kirstie Hewlett, which also produced the
                    separate political diary that Schenker created between November 1918 and June
                    1919. Thus, after fourteen years, the online presentation of the entire diary
                    series from 1896 to 1935 was finally accomplished, giving access to an
                    unprecedented body of information on Schenker's career, works, teaching, private
                    life, contacts with family, friends, and colleagues, and dealings with the
                    outside world.</p>

                <p>The second project was to make significant inroads into Schenker's lessonbooks,
                    which are rich in information on Schenker's teaching methods and his dealings
                    with his pupils. Those presented for the first time were January-March 1912 (the
                    first lessonbook) and 1913/14 to 1920/21. These yield a continuous sequence from
                    October 1913 to June 1921 plus 1923/24, edited and translated by Ian Bent, Alan
                    Dodson and Sigrun Heinzelmann, the original transcriptions being by Robert
                    Kosovsky, who must be credited with laying the foundation for this entire
                    project. </p>

                <p>The third project concerned correspondence, and included that with Universal
                    Edition for 1910 and 1911, the completion of the surviving correspondence with
                    all of Schenker’s pupils (c.700 items), and Karl Grunsky, members of the Brahms
                    circle Ernst Rudorff and Eugen d’Albert, Violin/Schoenberg, and parts of those
                    with Hermann Rinn, editor of <title level="j">Der Kunstwart</title>, Victor
                    Hammer, Moriz Violin, and Josef Marx.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>The future</head>
                <p>. . .</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
