<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="project_history"
    xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Project History</title>
                <title type="sub"/>
                <author/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>compiled by</resp>
                    <name>Ian Bent</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836
                        5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>This resource is publicly available and free at the point of access and it is
                        registered under a a <ref type="external"
                            target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">Creative Commons
                            license Attribution-Share Alike 3.0</ref>
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at
                http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/about/encoding/</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2009-08-06</date>
                <name>TL</name>
                <desc>Template Created</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date/>
                <name/>
                <desc/>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head>Project History</head>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>It was the writing by Ian Bent and William Drabkin of the General Preface to the
                    English translation of <title level="m">Der Tonwille</title> (New York: Oxford
                    University Press, 2004–2005), entailing as it did examining much of Schenker's
                    correspondence with Universal Edition and the attorneys involved in the
                    potential court proceeding between the two contending parties, that gave the
                    initial impetus to what is now <hi rend="italic">Schenker Documents Online</hi>.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Phase 1 : <hi rend="italic">Schenker Correspondence Project</hi> :
                    2003–2007</head>
                <p>An independent web-based project entitled <hi rend="italic">The Schenker
                        Correspondence Project</hi>, the purpose of which was to publish all
                    Schenker's correspondence in a scholarly, digital edition, was launched in 2003.
                    This was co-ordinated from the UK by Professors Ian Bent and William Drabkin,
                    the editing done by a small international team of scholars, the data held on the
                    servers of Columbia University in the City of New York using the webblog
                    software package MovableType, with a linked website on the server of the
                    University of Cambridge Faculty of Music, for both of which invaluable technical
                    support was provided by those institutions. </p>
                <p>2003–2007 marked phase 1 of the project, and served as a pilot for an eventually
                    larger, more comprehensive undertaking; it was almost entirely unfunded. The
                    years 1900–1912 formed the primary focus of Schenker's correspondence for phase
                    1, emphasis being placed on Schenker's two principal publishers, Universal
                    Edition and J. G. Cotta—although correspondence from later years (Angi Elias,
                    August Halm, Maximilian Harden, Oswald Jonas, Felix-Eberhard von Cube, Viktor
                    Zuckerkandl, and others) was also published. Some 500 items of correspondence
                    were posted to the web during this phase. </p>
            </div>


            <div>
                <head>Phase 2 : <hi rend="italic">Schenker Documents Online</hi> : 2007–2010</head>
                <p>So important did Schenker's diaries prove to be in corroborating his
                    correspondence that for phase 2, spanning 2007–2010, the scope of the project
                    was expanded to include both Schenker's diaries and his lessonbooks, with the
                    aim of providing the end-user with fluid movement among the three categories of
                    documents. In 2007, the project was retitled <hi rend="italic">Schenker
                        Documents Online</hi> (<hi rend="italic">SDO</hi>). Funding was obtained
                    from the Leverhulme Trust in the UK for three years specifically to design and
                    deliver a new web environment using XML encoding and following TEI guidelines:
                    the design work was carried out at the Centre for Computing in the Humanities at
                    King's College London, on whose servers the project would in future be
                    maintained. For phase 2, the focus shifted to the eight-year period 1918–25, one
                    which saw the emergence of Urlinie and Ursatz and the beginnings of layered
                    voice-leading analysis, and in which the outcome of World War I and ensuing
                    economic stringency had a major impact on Schenker's thinking. Correspondence
                    with Universal Edition again occupied a central place, along with other
                    correspondence streams (Guido Adler, Wilhelm Furtwängler, Anthony van Hoboken,
                    the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde, Felix Salzer, Moriz Violin, Hans Weisse, and
                    others).</p>

                <p>For phase 2, <hi rend="italic">Schenker Documents Online</hi> entered into
                    collaboration with a team of scholars working at the Universität für Musik und
                    Darstellende Kunst in Vienna, who transcribed and translated Schenker's diaries
                    for 1918–25 <hi rend="italic">in extenso</hi>, delivering XML-encoded files for
                    publication on <hi rend="italic">SDO</hi>. This work was funded for three years
                    by the Austrian Fonds zur Förderung der wissenschaftlichen Forschung (FWF).
                    Funds were provided by other British trusts for the supply of document scans and
                    for other purposes. The new web environment was released in its first version in
                    September 2009. </p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Phase 3 : <hi rend="italic">SDO</hi> : 2011–2013</head>
                <p>Phase 3, running throughout 2011–2013, focusses primarily on the period October
                    1925 to September 1930, the period in which Schenker arrived at the final
                    formulation of his theory. Emphasis is placed on Schenker's correspondence with
                    the third of his three main publishing houses, Drei Masken Verlag of Munich,
                    with the engravers Waldheim-Eberle of Vienna, and with those involved in their
                    publication of <title level="m">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</title> (Otto Erich
                    Deutsch, Alfred Einstein, and others) as well as that with Universal Edition,
                    the content of which interlocks with that of DMV; and also on the diaries for
                    1925‒30 and the lessonbooks for the seasons 1925/26 to 1929/30. This phase is
                    funded by the Arts &amp; Humanities Research Council of Great Britain. During
                    this phase, some transfer of correspondence from the Columbia site is being
                    carried out, and some editing of new material outside the 1925‒30 framework
                    (e.g. Walter Dahms, Viktor Hammer).</p>

                <p>For Phase 3, <hi rend="italic">Schenker Documents Online</hi> is based at the
                    Department of Music of the University of Southampton in collaboration with the
                    Department of Digital Humanities of University of London King's College. The
                    Principal Investigator is Professor William Drabkin.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Longer-term Plans</head>
                <p>There are plans also to cover the final period of Schenker's life, 1930–35, and
                    longer-term plans to revert to the early and mid-career periods, extending back
                    to the late 1880s. </p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Policy Matters</head>
                <p>Without exception, from the beginning to the present day, all transcribing,
                    translating, and interpreting of documents contributed to <hi rend="italic"
                        >SDO</hi> by scholars in the USA, UK, and Europe, has been done entirely out
                    of the goodwill of those scholars, without payment of any sort. (For further
                    details, see <ref cRef="contributing_scholars">"Contributing
                    Scholars."</ref>)</p>

                <p>A vital part of the work of <hi rend="italic">SDO</hi> from the outset has been
                    the obtaining of permission from the holders of intellectual copyright to
                    publish documents to the web. To date, there have been no refusals, and no
                    limitations have been placed on <hi rend="italic">SDO</hi> by the descendants
                    and representatives of the authors of these materials, who have shown only
                    cooperation and generosity to the project. (For further details, see <ref
                        cRef="clearances">"Clearances."</ref>)</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
