<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="project_aims"
    xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Project Aims</title>
                <title type="sub"/>
                <author/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>compiled by</resp>
                    <name>Ian Bent</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836
                        5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>This resource is publicly available and free at the point of access and it is
                        registered under a a <ref type="external"
                            target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">Creative Commons
                            license Attribution-Share Alike 3.0</ref>
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at
                http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/about/encoding/</p>
        </encodingDesc>

        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2009-08-06</date>
                <name>TL</name>
                <desc>Template Created</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date/>
                <name/>
                <desc/>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>

        <body>

            <head>Project Aims</head>

            <div>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Schenker Documents Online</hi> aims:-</p>

                <p><xmt:uList>

                        <item>to increase insight into the <hi rend="italic">life and mind</hi> of
                            Heinrich Schenker, and by so doing to foster a fuller understanding of
                            his career, works, and the intellectual development that they
                            represent;</item>

                        <item>to stimulate biographical, historical, and socio-cultural study of
                            Schenker, his circle of pupils, friends, and associates.</item>
                    </xmt:uList></p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <p><hi rend="italic">SDO</hi>'s objectives in carrying out these aims are:
                        <xmt:oList rend="arabic">
                        <item>to provide a scholarly, critical edition of all Schenker's known
                            surviving correspondence (two-way), diaries, and lessonbooks, a task
                            that entails the production of a diplomatic transcription, English
                            translation, physical description, and supporting commentary for each
                            document; </item>

                        <item>to identify the intellectual rights holders of documents and to obtain
                            permission from them to publish, or to establish that the material in
                            question is in the public domain, or failing that to make all reasonable
                            efforts to locate rights holders and to provide the means by which any
                            claim upon any material can be made; </item>

                        <item>to publish this edition to the web, with free worldwide access, at no
                            charge to the end-user; </item>

                        <item>to provide supporting documentation in the form of online "profiles,"
                            i.e. encyclopedia-like entries on persons, institutions, works, and
                            places named in the published materials; </item>

                        <item>to seek out hitherto untraced caches of correspondence and other
                            private materials relating to Schenker's circle, and bring them to
                            publication; </item>

                        <item>to provide librarians and archivists with information to help them
                            catalog their holdings of Schenker materials; and to provide private
                            owners with information about the materials in their possession, and
                            where appropriate to encourage them to place those materials in a
                            publicly accessible library or archive;</item>

                        <item>to raise awareness of the correspondence, diaries, and lessonbooks as
                            a rich repository of information concerning not only Schenker and his
                            circle, hence the history of music theory, but also Viennese musical
                            culture, institutions and politics, cultural conservatism in the
                            modernist age, Jewish life in Austrian society, and other fields of
                            endeavor; </item>

                        <item>to stimulate the use of these materials for research purposes, by
                            presenting conference papers and organizing round tables, issuing
                            periodic progress reports, publishing articles and monographs, the
                            latter including the paper publication of a volume of selected
                            correspondence(published by The Boydell Press in 2014), diary and
                            lessonbook entries; </item>

                        <item>to provide a working model for other, future web-based correspondence
                            collections, in any field.</item>
                    </xmt:oList>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
