<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/31, [1] : 1-6-38 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  Heirs of Sophie Guttmann, permission being sought
©  Transcription Ian Bent, 2008
©  Translation Ian Bent, 2008
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent, 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Under inquiry.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Jeanette (1938-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Sophie Guttmann, under inquiry; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 01/06/1938 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "GuttmannS ~ H+JSchenker","GuttmannS ~ JSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Sophie Guttmann to Jeanette Schenker, dated January 6, 1938</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-07-14</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>On her 40th wedding anniversary, Sophie reports news of herself and her family, and asks how Jeanette is.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Guttmann, Sophie; Schenker, Jeanette;  Sereth;  Guttmann, Salo;  Dorna Watra;  Vienna;  Guttmann, Hans;  Guttmann, Frieda;  Guttmann, Julian;  Goldschäger, Dr.;  Czernowitz;  Cernauti;  Hilde;  Edith;  Schenker, Wilhelm</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Sereth</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Sophie Guttmann to Jeanette Schenker, dated January 6, 1938</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{envelope <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
Wohlg. Frau [/] Dr. Lilli Schenker
<tei:hi rend="italic">Wien</tei:hi>
I Reichsratsstrasse 7
III/19</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in Jeanette Schenker's hand:</tei:hi>]
Antw. [/] 22. III. 38 ohne Antwort [/] noch einmal gesschr. am 20. Nov. 38</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>]  || SIRET | 8 JAN 938 ||</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{envelope <tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
Sophie Guttmann
Siret
Roumaine</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{letter}</tei:hi>
Sireth<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Click on <ref cRef="sereth">Sereth</ref>.</tei:note> am 6. I 938</tei:p><tei:p>Meine liebste Lilli!</tei:p><tei:p>Heute an unserem 40ten Hochzeitstage mache mir das grosse Vergnügen dir zu schreiben.</tei:p><tei:p>Denke dir was die Ursache meines so langen Stillschweigens war:  ich erhielt seinerzeit deinen eingeschriebenen Brief aus der Schweiz, daraufhin bin ich mit meinem Mann<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  i. e. (click on) <ref cRef="guttmann_salo_dr_hus">Salo Guttmann</ref>.  </tei:note> nach Dorna<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="dornawatra">Dorna Watra</ref>.</tei:note> für einen ganzen Monat fort.  Ich traute mich nicht mehr allein zu fahren, dann musste auch mein Alter Moorbäder nehmen, wegen der starken Rückenschmerzen im vorigen Winter.  In aller Eile vergass ich zuhause deinen Brief samt Adresse.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Du bist nach Wien wahrscheinlich im September gegangen und wo hätte ich deine Adresse nehmen sollen?  Wie ich mich gekränkt habe, kann dir <tei:hi rend="italic">kaum</tei:hi> schildern.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich wusste nicht was da mit Hans<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="guttmann_hans">Hans Guttmann</ref>.  </tei:note> vorgekommen ist, bis du mir nicht schriebst.  Er war nach 4 Jahren im Juni 8 Tage bei uns, erzählte nur meiner Frieda.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="guttmann_frieda_daug">Frieda Guttmann</ref>.  </tei:note>  Ja, meine Teuere, wo soll er Geld nehmen, wenn er eine[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] solch' pretensiöse Frau<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Wife of Hans Guttmann: [identify].  </tei:note> hat?  Denke dir, sie wurde an Gallensteinen operirt, bald nach der schweren Operation fuhren sie nach Paris, im feinsten Hotel u. s. w. wohnten sie, von dort ist sie mit einer <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> bekannten Familie nach Wien gefahren, er, der blöde fuhr allein nachhause.  Sie blieb 3 Wochen [bei] uns, wegen Anschaffungen.  Zuhause angelangt fuhr sie an's Meer, u. s. w.  Es wäre sehr viel zu erzählen – – Also woher soll der gute Narr Geld nehmen?  Das ist unerhört! – –  Er hat sich bei mir so wohlgefühlt, wie ein kleines Kind bei der Mutter.  – Er hat dazu beigetragen, dass mein Mann mit mir fährt, Julko<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="guttmann_julian_julk">Julian Guttmann</ref>.  </tei:note> macht mir doch järlich zum Geburtstag ein Geschenk die Badereise. – Nun habe her...ges[?] nicht, wie deine Adresse zu erfahren, wir haben doch Niemanden in Wien. – Durch D^r.^ Goldschläger, den kennst du ja[,] erfuhr ich, aber wie <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> lange wartete ich.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  No paragraph-break in original.  Dr. Goldschläger:  an attorney.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Also meine Liebste, sei mir nicht böse und schreibe bald, was du machst, wie du dich fühlst u. s. w. Mir gebt's nicht schlecht, leide hie <tei:hi rend="italic">u</tei:hi> da an Schwindelanfällen, was nur natürlich ist;  das Alter will sich nicht verleugnen lassen.  Julko sorgt für uns, es fehlt uns an gar nichts.  Gott gebe er soll es weiter tun <tei:hi rend="italic">können</tei:hi>.  Du hörst ja Radio – – – – Meine Kinder in Czer.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Sophie's children were Hans, Frieda, and Julko.  Sophie is perhaps referring to Frieda and her husband Oskar, who were living in Czernowitz (Cernauti).  </tei:note> sind gottlob gesund, geschäftlich sind sie nicht besonders dran.  Die Mädel<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Perhaps the children of Frieda and Oskar:  Hilde and Edith,  i.e. Sophie's grandchildren.  </tei:note> sind reizend, die grosse ist in der IIIten Klasse, die Kleine im Kindergarten. – Mein Alter<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Mein Alter:  presumably her husband, Salo, though we know that his eyesight was bad already in 1934 (A/289).  (Since Sophie was at least 71 by the time of this letter, it can hardly be her father.)</tei:note> schaut nicht schlecht aus, Hauptsache, dass er gut sieht. – Was macht der Wilhelm?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Click on <ref cRef="schenker_wilhelm">Wilhelm Schenker</ref>.  </tei:note>  Hast du etwas vom Gelde bei der Nachlassenschaft bekommen?  Nun bitte, bitte <tei:hi rend="italic">schreibe mir</tei:hi>.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit tausend herzlichsten Küssen 
verbleibe deine treue
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Sophie</tei:p><tei:p>Von meinem Alten viele Grüsse</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Sophie Guttmann to Jeanette Schenker, dated January 6, 1938</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{envelope <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
Dr. Lilli Schenker
<tei:hi rend="italic">Vienna</tei:hi> I,
Reichsratsstrasse 7
III/19</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in Jeanette Schenker's hand:</tei:hi>]
Reply: March 22, 1938 unanswered wrote yet again on November 20, 1938</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>]  || SIRET | 8 JAN 938 ||</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{envelope <tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
Sophie Guttmann
Siret
Rumania</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{letter}</tei:hi>
Sireth<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>, January 6, 1938</tei:p><tei:p>My dearest Lilli,</tei:p><tei:p>Today, on our 40th wedding anniversary, I am giving myself the great treat of writing to you.</tei:p><tei:p>Just imagine why I have been silent for so long:  some time ago, I received your letter, written from Switzerland, immediately after which I went off with my husband<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> to Dorna<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> for a whole month.  I no longer feel up to traveling alone, then I had to take my husband's mud baths because of the acute back pains [he suffered] last winter.  In all of the hurry, I forgot to pick up from the house the letter containing your address.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> You probably went to Vienna in September, and where was I to get your address from?  You can <tei:hi rend="italic">scarcely</tei:hi> imagine how concerned I was.</tei:p><tei:p>I didn't know what's been going on with Hans<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> there, since you didn't write to me.  After four years, he was with us for a week in June, [but] he let on only to my Frieda.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  Yes, my dear, where is he to get money, with a wife<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> who puts on so many airs and graces?  Just imagine:  she was operated on for gallstones;  soon after the major operation she traveled to Paris, she stayed in the finest hotel, etc.;  from there, she traveled with a <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> family that she knew to Vienna;  he, the imbecile, went home alone.  She stayed [with] us for three weeks, to make some purchases.  Having got home, she went off to the coast, etc.  It was a long story . . .  So where is the silly fool to get money?  It's a scandal!  . . .  He was so contended when he was with me, like a child with its mother.  He contributed to my husband going with me:  every year on my birthday, Julko<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> gives me a trip to the spa as a present.  – By then I had no idea how to get hold of your address;  we have no one at all in Vienna.  – I got [it] through Dr. Goldschläger, whom I expect you know, but I had to wait such a <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> long time [for it].<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/></tei:p><tei:p>Oh well, my dearest, don't be cross with me, and write soon to tell me what you are up to, how you are feeling, etc.  Things are not bad with me;  unfortunately, from time to time I get dizzy spells, but that is only natural.  Old age takes its toll.   Julko looks after us;  we lack for absolutely nothing.  Pray God he will be <tei:hi rend="italic">able</tei:hi> to continue doing so.  You hear the radio, I expect. . . .  My children in Czernowit<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> are in good health, thank God;  they're not doing particularly well in business. The little girls<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> are charming;  the big one is in the third grade, the little one in kindergarten.  – My old man<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> isn't in bad shape;  the main thing is that he sees well.  –  What is Wilhelm<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> up to?  Have you received any of the money from the estate?  Now:  please, please <tei:hi rend="italic">write to me</tei:hi>.  I remain</tei:p><tei:p>with a thousand heartfelt kisses,
yours truly,  
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Sophie</tei:p><tei:p>Warm greetings from my old man.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>