<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="conditions_of_use"
    xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Conditions of Use</title>
                <title type="sub"/>
                <author/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>compiled by</resp>
                    <name>CompilerFirstName CompilerSurname</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
        <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
        <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>This resource is publicly available and free at the point of access and it is
                        registered under a a <ref type="external"
                            target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">Creative Commons
                            license Attribution-Share Alike 3.0</ref>
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at
                http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/about/encoding/</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2009-08-06</date>
                <name>TL</name>
                <desc>Template Created</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date/>
                <name/>
                <desc/>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>

        <body>

            <head>Conditions of Use</head>
            <div>
                <div>

                    <p><hi rend="italic">Schenker Documents Online</hi> delineates three levels of
                        copyright as applying to materials in its digital edition:</p>
                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>1. Intellectual Property Rights</head>

                    <p><hi rend="italic">SDO</hi> and all its contributors acknowledge their
                        obligation to obtain in writing from the originator of a document to be
                        edited, or from the heir(s) or representative(s) of that originator,
                        permission to publish the document on the web. It places a statement of that
                        permission at the foot of each document, in some such form as:</p>

                    <p>© Heirs of Hans Weisse, published with kind permission.</p>

                    <p>For a list of all permissions granted, cleared, or being sought, see <ref
                            cRef="clearances">"Clearances."</ref></p>

                    <p>Negotiation of these rights is constantly on-going, and is integral to the
                        work of the project. IPR are deemed for these purposes to apply up until
                        January 1 of the year following seventy years from the death of the
                        originator of the intellectual property. </p>

                    <p>Where <hi rend="italic">SDO</hi> has made a good-faith effort to locate heirs
                        or representatives of an originator and has been unsuccessful, it may
                        publish a document with some such copyright declaration as "Under inquiry."
                        In the case of all documents published, whether with permission or under
                        inquiry, it provides an email address to which anyone believing they may
                        have a claim to rights in a document may lodge that claim. </p>

                    <div>
                        <head>Reminder to User:</head>


                        <p>Most of the texts on this website are covered under intellectual property
                            rights law. For use of any material from <hi rend="italic">SDO</hi> that
                            you intend to publish beyond the provision of fair dealing, you are
                            responsible for obtaining clearance of IPR from the relevant rights
                            holder.</p>

                        <p>You may not use images that appear on <hi rend="italic">SDO</hi>. For
                            such images, you must apply to the image holder, sign a license
                            agreement with that holder, and pay the relevant fee. </p>
                    </div>

                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>2. Ownership Rights</head>

                    <p>SDO acknowledges for all physical documents the contents of which are edited
                        in its digital edition the rights of the owners of those documents, whether
                        archives, libraries, or private persons, to their physical property.
                        Accordingly, <hi rend="italic">SDO</hi> does not post images of documents to
                        the web without having first received permission to do so and paid any
                        license fees that may be due. </p>

                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>3. Editorial Rights</head>

                    <p><hi rend="italic">SDO</hi> asserts on behalf of its transcribers,
                        translators, and editors their copyright on all the work they supply to <hi
                            rend="italic">SDO</hi> and is published on its website. Rights to
                        transcriptions and translations are declared at the foot of each document,
                        in some such form as:</p>

                    <p>© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006</p>

                    <p>or:</p>

                    <p>© Translation William Drabkin 2008.</p>

                    <p>These rights are reinforced in the metadata of each document, and are claimed
                        there also for all footnotes and other editorial supporting commentary. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>

    </text>
</TEI>
