<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="editorial_conventions"
    xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Editorial Conventions</title>
                <title type="sub"/>
                <author/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>compiled by</resp>
                    <name>Ian Bent</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836
                        5454</addrLine>
                    <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>This resource is publicly available and free at the point of access and it is
                        registered under a a <ref type="external"
                            target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">Creative Commons
                            license Attribution-Share Alike 3.0</ref>
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at
                http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/about/encoding/</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2009-08-06</date>
                <name>TL</name>
                <desc>Template Created</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date/>
                <name/>
                <desc/>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Schenker Documents Online</hi> is a critical, scholarly digital
                    edition with translation and commentary. It aims to present documents as
                    faithfully as is possible within a digital environment, and to accompany them
                    with supporting information and a limited amount of scholarly interpretation by
                    way of traditional footnotes and links to "<ref cRef="profiles">profiles</ref>."
                </p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Quick Guide</head>
                <p>
                    <table rows="5" cols="2">
                        <row rend="demo">
                            <cell><hi rend="bold">{3}</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>page number</cell>
                        </row>

                        <row rend="demo">
                            <cell><hi rend="bold">{<hi rend="italic">recto</hi>}</hi>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>side of sheet or card (<hi rend="italic">recto</hi> or <hi
                                    rend="italic">verso</hi>)</cell>
                        </row>

                        <row rend="demo">
                            <cell><seg type="demo" subtype="editorial">[signed:]</seg>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>editorial note</cell>
                        </row>

                        <row rend="demo">
                            <cell>m<seg type="demo" subtype="editorial">[eines]</seg> E<seg
                                    type="demo" subtype="editorial">[rachtens]</seg></cell>
                            <cell>editorially supplied material (in green)</cell>
                        </row>

                        <row rend="demo">
                            <cell>von <seg type="demo" subtype="added">Bachs Prael. u.
                                Fuge</seg></cell>
                            <cell>authorial addition (in brown) inserted above line of text</cell>
                        </row>

                        <row rend="demo">
                            <cell>nach <seg type="demo" subtype="underline">seinen</seg>
                                Begriffen</cell>
                            <cell>authorial underlining</cell>
                        </row>

                        <row rend="demo">
                            <cell>ihres<seg type="demo" subtype="editorial">[corr]</seg>
                            </cell>
                            <cell>authorial correction, overwritten, where original text is
                                indecipherable</cell>
                        </row>

                        <row rend="demo">
                            <cell><seg type="demo" subtype="overwritten"><seg type="demo"
                                        subtype="undertext">unter</seg><seg type="demo"
                                        subtype="overtext">über</seg></seg></cell>
                            <cell>authorial overwriting - hover on "über" to see original text
                                underneath</cell>
                        </row>

                        <row rend="demo">
                            <cell>Viele Grüsse von Ihrem ergebenen, <seg type="demo"
                                    subtype="handshift" n="#OED"/>Deutsch </cell>
                            <cell>upward-pointing arrow marks where new handwriting (typing,
                                printing, stamping, etc.) starts - hover on arrow to see hand
                                attribution</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Documents: German</head>
                <p>In correspondence, the word "document" denotes a single item, such as a letter,
                    postcard, telegram, calling card, etc. In diaries and lessonbooks, the concept
                    of a document is less well-defined. In the case of diaries, it can be equated
                    with an entire library folder, such as OJ 3/1, comprising October 1, 1919 to
                    September 30, 1920. In the case of lessonbooks, it can be equated with a single
                    lessonbook, of which there are four of very variable length, thus e.g. OC 3/3,
                    comprising May 21, 1914 to June 1928. In the case of diaries and lessonbooks,
                    the "entry" is the operative unit, usually representing a day, in the case of
                    the diaries, and either a day or all the lessons for a given student in a given
                    period in the lessonbooks. </p>
                <div>
                    <head>Document Identifier (Correspondence)</head>
                    <p>Each document is assigned an individual identifier made up of its collection,
                        library, or archive siglum (assigned by <hi rend="italic">SDO</hi>) + its
                        box and folder number (assigned by the library) + its individual number or
                        letter (in square brackets if assigned by <hi rend="italic">SDO</hi>). Thus
                        "OJ 11/54, [9]" denotes the Oswald Jonas Memorial Collection (Riverside,
                        CA), box 11, folder 54, document 9. With the Oster Collection (New York
                        Public Library) we follow the library's cataloguing system, whereby each
                        loose sheet of paper is identified as an "item"; thus "OC 52/496" denotes
                        File 52, item 496. A document might be a single item, or it might comprise
                        two or more items (e. g. a letter running to several pages). (For a list of
                        library sigla, see <ref cRef="abbreviations_sigla">"Abbreviations and
                            Sigla."</ref>) </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Dating (Correspondence)</head>
                    <p>Where an internal date is given, this is taken to be the document's date and
                        is given in the document title—unless it can be proven wrong on internal or
                        external evidence, in which case the deduced dating is given in square
                        brackets in the title. Where an internal date is not given and the writing
                        of the document is recorded in the diary, the latter date is usually taken
                        to be the document's date; where neither of these is the case and a postmark
                        date is available, that is taken to be the document's date. Where diary and
                        postmark dates conflict, the diary normally takes precedence, however the
                        diary is not infallible (because often written up in arrears) whereas a
                        clear postmark is hard to contest. Where a letter is written over several
                        days with separate dates indicated, the last date is used for purposes of
                        the document title. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Layout (Correspondence, Diaries, Lessonbooks)</head>
                    <p>The edited text indicates all page-breaks (even when they occur in the middle
                        of a word), supplies editorial page numbers where no original numbers exist,
                        and with postcards, calling cards, etc., indicates <hi rend="italic"
                            >recto</hi> and <hi rend="italic">verso</hi>. These interventions are
                        given in bold type within curly brackets (e.g. <hi rend="bold">{2}</hi>; <hi
                            rend="bold">{<hi rend="italic">verso</hi>}</hi>). The text does not
                        indicate line-breaks. </p>
                    <p>In form-type documents (e.g. contracts; telegrams), printed matter is usually
                        given in Roman type, handwritten or typed entries are given in italics;
                        occasionally the reverse is adopted for clarity. In these and other tabular
                        documents, an attempt is made to render the tabulation, but the latter often
                        has to be broken up, and explanatory editorial comments guide the reader. </p>
                    <p>Printed letterheads are given in full where possible, with a preceding
                        editorial note "[printed letterhead:]". Precise layout and spacing are not
                        preserved. The wording of very long letterheads is curtailed, retaining the
                        main address but omitting such features as addresses in other cities and
                        countries, telephone and telegraph numbers, name of proprietor, etc. Any
                        pictorial matter in a letterhead is described rather than reproduced. </p>
                    <p>Certain standard features have been regularized. Thus, in postcards and some
                        letters, where the message continues on from the salutation ("Lieber Herr
                        …"), a line-break has been made; and likewise where the valediction (e.g.
                        "Mit vorz&#xFC;glicher Hochachtung …") runs on from the final paragraph.
                        Where a paragraph is so long as to make reading on-screen uncomfortable, a
                        paragraph-break has been inserted, and a footnote stating that the original
                        continued on without break. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Orthography (Correspondence, Diaries, Lessonbooks)</head>
                    <p>The German original text is rendered as close to a diplomatic transcription
                        as is compatible with the variable effects of browsers. The text presents
                        all the printed, typed, stamped, and/or handwritten matter of the original,
                        including deleted words and phrases, corrections, interlinear and inline
                        additions, overwritings, marginal annotations, underlinings, sidelinings,
                        and the presence of illegible elements. Wherever possible, authorship of
                        such emendations is indicated. — One exception to this arises in typed
                        material where mechanical mistypings have occurred and have either not been
                        noticed or have been corrected by overtyping or by handwritten insertion;
                        since the latter changes have been made by someone other than the originator
                        of the document, and are not part of the thought process of creating the
                        document, the changes have been adopted without indication, and mistypings
                        have been tacitly corrected. On the other hand, where those changes have
                        been made by the originator, the change itself has usually been presented.
                        Some of the spacing of typed matter, especially around commas and periods,
                        albeit in accordance with typing practice of the time, has been silently
                        modernized. </p>
                    <p>Where features in the original document cannot be conveyed succinctly within
                        the text, a footnote is used to explain the situation. Original punctuation
                        is preserved, with minimal addition of editorial punctuation only for
                        clarity of meaning. Original spellings are retained; where different from
                        present-day spelling, these often preserve archaic or regional spellings
                        that are of intrinsic interest; where spelling is manifestly incorrect, the
                        edition may on occasion supply "[<hi>sic</hi>]" or even "[<hi>recte</hi>
                        ...]." </p>
                    <p>Names of people, places, and organizations are given exactly as in the
                        original; the same is true for titles of books, plays, musical compositions,
                        and other works of art and literature. </p>
                    <p>In documents written in a mixture of Sütterlinschrift and Lateinschrift (as
                        in Heinrich Schenker's script post-1902), Sütterlinschrift is rendered in
                        Roman type, Lateinschrift in Italic type.</p>
                    <p>Editorial interventions are of two kinds: those amplifying the original text
                        are given in Roman type within square brackets (e.g. "i/W[estfalen]", where
                        "i/W" is deemed not self-explanatory), those extraneous to the original text
                        are given in italics within square brackets (e.g. "Ihres Briefes [<hi
                            rend="italic">word deleted</hi>],"). Material written in the margin and
                        cued to a specific point in the text is enclosed within square brackets,
                        with an editorial indication (e.g. "... machen, [<hi rend="italic">cued from
                            lower margin:</hi>] Auch Ihrem Archiv sei die Aufnahme der Abschrift
                        empfohlen als Ersatz der Handschrift![<hi>end cue</hi>] wieder …"</p>
                    <p>Hyphenation: in German script and printed matter, two words are coupled by
                        the sign "=" (e.g. "Urlinie=Tafel"). This has been rendered always with the
                        standard English hyphen ("-"); word-divisions over line-ends (hyphenation)
                        make use of a variety of different signs, all of which have been rendered
                        also with the hyphen. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Documents: English Translation</head>
                <div>
                    <head>Layout (Correspondence, Diaries, Lessonbooks) </head>
                    <p>as for German text. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Orthography</head>
                <p>Orthographical features of the original are mirrored as far as is feasible in the
                    English translation. The precise point of a page-break often cannot be indicated
                    because of differing word order: in such a case, the page-number is given late
                    rather than early. Present-day practice in punctuation is applied. Spelling and
                    word usage, as well as punctuation, follow American rather than British
                    conventions. Names of people, places, and organizations abbreviated in the
                    German original are extended, except where reasonable ambiguity exists (e.g.
                    where "B." might be Beethoven or Brahms). Titles abbreviated in the German
                    original are extended (e.g. "N. Fr. Pr." is rendered as "<hi rend="italic">Neue
                        Freie Presse</hi>"). </p>
                <p>Titles of books, plays, musical compositions, and other works of art and
                    literature, are translated where an English title is in wide circulation (e.g.
                        <hi rend="italic">A Midsummer Night's Dream</hi>), otherwise given in
                    German, and any abbreviations are extended. For musical compositions, the
                    conventions adopted are: generic titles (e. g. Symphony; Sonata; Concerto) in
                    Roman type with initial capitals, descriptive titles (e. g. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Syrische Tänze</hi>; <hi rend="italic">Salome</hi>) in Italic type. Generic
                    titles with descriptive elements are given with the latter in double-quotation
                    marks (e.g "Coriolanus" Overture; "Pastoral" Symphony). In a collection of
                    pieces (such as a song cycle or set of piano pieces), the overall title is given
                    in Italic type (e. g. <hi rend="italic">Winterreise</hi>; <hi rend="italic"
                        >Fantasiestücke</hi>), the component items (e.g. "Gute Nacht"; "Florestan")
                    in Roman type in double quotation-marks. </p>
                <p>Schenker's own publications are rendered in English in the translated text, and
                    usually extended when abbreviated in the original. However, Schenker's use of
                    "I", "II<hi rend="sup">1</hi>", "II<hi rend="sup">2</hi>", and "III" for the
                    volumes of his Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien are preserved as "I",
                    "II/1", "II/2", and "III". </p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Footnotes and Profiles</head>
                <p>Footnotes and profiles are written in English only. Titles are usually given in
                    the original language, and the orthographic rules outlined above for
                    translations usually apply. In general, quotations from letters, diaries, or
                    lessonbooks are given first in German in double quotation-marks, then in English
                    translation in parentheses and double quotation-marks. </p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Profiles</head>
                <p>Profiles are dictionary-like articles concerning persons, places, and
                    organizations of all types, also journals and newspapers, and Schenker's own
                    published works. They do not pretend to be encyclopedic in content, but rather
                    stress the relationship of that entity to Schenker and his circle. For further
                    information, and access, see <ref cRef="profiles">Profiles index</ref>. </p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Abbreviations and Sigla</head>
                <p>For a listing of general and bibliographical abbreviations, and library and
                    archive sigla, see <ref cRef="abbreviations_sigla">Abbreviations and
                    Sigla</ref></p>

            </div>


        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
