<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 5/11, [1], vsn 1 : 11-13-31 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain
© Transcription Christoph Hust, 2008.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2008.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Christoph Hust, 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1931-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935- c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker;  Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Christoph Hust.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 11/13/1931 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: &quot;Furtw&#195;&#164;ngler ~ H+JSchenker&quot;,&quot;Furtw&#195;&#164;ngler ~ HSchenker&quot; --><dc:title>Handwritten draft letter from Schenker to Furtwängler, in Jeanette Schenker’s hand, dated November 13, 1931</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-02-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Schenker thanks Furtwängler for his sympathy and reports on the condition of his eyes. —Reports on two lectures recently given by Hans Weisse;  encloses a review by Herman Roth, whom he praises, but whom he has chided for use of the word "abstraction."  —He is astonished at the simplistic view that some musicians have taken of the Ursatz;  he describes the logical relationship between background and foreground, and explains the roles of imagination, growth, and improvisational intuition in the composition process, comparing it to the misguided method of composing with motives.   —Referring to a recent article by Stravinsky, and articles published by Furtwängler, he writes about Wagner, and is dismissive of Verdi. —He identifies the cause of the current disintegration of the "community of tones," and outlines an educational program beginning in the earliest school years with 3rd-, 4th-, and octave-progressions.  —He draws an analogy between the Germans' failure to appreciate their past musical masters and the Jews' failure to understand the Bible, and outlines what Vienna should do to regain its artistic primacy;  in this, he deploys financial and banking metaphors. 

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich; Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Beethoven;  Eroica;  Weisse, Hans;  Roth, Herman;  Vienna;  Musikpädagogischer Verband;  Music Pedagogical Association;  Hamburg;  Pfohl, Ferdinand;  München;  Munich;  Hamburger Nachrichten;  abstraction;  Ursatz;  Urlinie;  Terz-Zug;  3rd-progression;  Quart-Zug;  4th-progression;  Oktav-Zug;  octave-progression;  Vordergrund;  foreground;  Hintergrund;  background;  Fantasie;  imagination;  improvisation;  motives;  Stravinsky;  Baseler National-Zeitung;  Neue Freie Presse;  Wagner;  Verdi;  Smetana;  Dvořák;  Werfel, Franz;  Mozart;  Huberman, Bronislaw;  Das Meisterwerk in der Musik;  The Masterwork in Music;  Handel;  J. S. Bach;  genius;  Moses;  Jews;  Bible;  Old Testament;  Jesus;  Plato;  modern music;  Kestenberg, Leo;  Schünemann, Georg;  Schreker, Franz;  Dussek;  Clementi;  Berlin;  Amstelbank;  Schoenberg;  Jöde, Fritz;  Geneva;  Basel;  Paris;  Bayreuth;  Salzburg;  </dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten draft letter from Schenker to Furtwängler, first version, in Jeanette Schenker’s hand, dated November 13, 1931</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">no address or salutation</tei:hi>]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  This letter-draft is preceded by a small folded piece of paper with the following inscription in Heinrich Schenker's hand:  "An Furtw. [/] Bf. vom 16–18/11 [/] 1931 [/] als Antw. auf [/] Bf. Furtw.'s vom 8/11/31" (To Furtwängler [/] letter from November 16–18, 1931 [/] as answer to [/] Furtwängler's letter of November 8, 1931").  There is no record in Schenker's diary of receipt of such a letter, nor is there any record of the drafting of the present letter (which one would expect with so long and carefully worded a document).  Moreover, Schenker attended a Philharmonic concert by Furtwängler on November 16, and reported on the interpretation.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Das Zeichen Ihrer &lt;strike&gt;freundlichen&lt;/strike&gt; Teilnahme<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Letter, OJ 11/16, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="hamburger_nachrichte">Hamburger Nachrichten</ref></tei:note>, November 8, 1931:  " I should very much like to have a word or two from you yourself about your health and such like things."  </tei:note> hat mich sehr erfreut. Ich bin im Sommer der &lt;strike&gt;strengen&lt;/strike&gt; Weisung der Aerzte gefolgt, die mir eine Schonung der Augen dringend nahelegten. Der Kampf um die „Eroica“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  The essay “Beethovens Dritte Sinfonie zum erstenmal in ihrem wahren Inhalt dargestellt,“ <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, vol. III (Munich: Drei Masken Verlag, 1930), pp. 25–101 and graphs, Eng. trans. by Derrick Puffett and Alfred Clayton in <tei:hi rend="italic">The Masterwork in Music</tei:hi>, vol. III (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1997), pp. 10–68 and graphs.  </tei:note> war meinerseits etwas zu heroisch geführt worden.  Kaum durfte ich etwas schreiben, kaum etwas lesen, u. so habe ich es denn auch wirklich fertiggebracht, diese für mich so schweren Entbehrungen zumindest durch die Wiederherstellung der Augen belohnt zu sehen. Noch immer aber ist Vorsicht am Platze, doch darf ich schon ausgreifen.</tei:p><tei:p>Die Erfolge Weisses<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>. </tei:note> übertreffen wirklich alle Erwartung. Vor seiner Abreise<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Presumably Weisse’s departure for New York in the early Fall, to teach at the Mannes Music School.  </tei:note> sprach er noch einmal in Wien im Musikpädagogischen Verband,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Österreichischer Musikpädagogischer Verband: [supply information].  [give date and title of lecture]    </tei:note> begeisterte die Zuhörer (vulgo Kollegen) <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi>	ohne sie freilich dorthin fortreissen zu können, wo er sie gern hätte haben mögen, auch in Hamburg sprach Weisse im Konzertsaal mit blendendem Erfolg.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  The lecture, given at the invitation of Moriz Violin on September 16, 1931, is reported in Weisse’s letter to Schenker of September 5, 1931 (OJ 15/16, [81]).  The title of the lecture was to be “Hörendes Schaffen – schaffendes Hören, Versuch einer Würdigung des Grundgedanken in H. Schenkers Werk“ (Hearing Creativity – Creative Hearing:  Attempt at an Appreciation of the Fundamental Thought of H. Schenker’s Work).  </tei:note>  Ich lege hier ein Referat von <tei:hi rend="italic">H. Roth</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="roth_herman">Herman Roth</ref>.  The article in question was presumably “Bekenntnis zu Heinrich Schenker,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Hamburger Nachrichten</tei:hi>, September 17, 1931, a clipping of which is preserved in Schenker’s scrapbook on OC 2/p. 84.  </tei:note> bei, weil ich mich zu erinnern glaube, daß Sie [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr from:</tei:hi> sie] R. von München her kennen u. auch um Sie wissen zu lassen, was Sie vielleicht interessieren könnte: ^daß^ R. &lt;strike&gt;ist&lt;/strike&gt; bei den „Hamburger Nachrichten“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="hamburger_nachrichte">Hamburger Nachrichten</ref></tei:note> an die Stelle von Pfohl<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Click on <ref cRef="pfohl_ferdinand">Ferdinand Pfohl</ref>. </tei:note> gekommen ist. Ich halte es R. sehr zugute, daß er nach so vieljähriger Pause sich wieder aktiv zu meiner Sache stellte. Ueber die Entgleisung zum Schluss des Aufsatzes, wo er von einer „Abstraktion“ spricht, habe ich ihm genau geschrieben. Es ist mir wirklich unerfindlich, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> wie Musiker mit den Beweisen meines gesund denkenden Kopfes in Händen mir eine so läppische Behauptung unterstellen können, alles Komponieren gehe vom Ursatz aus u. zwar so, daß man sich nur einen Urliniezug vorzunehmen braucht, u. ihn so lange diminuiere, bis man z. B. eine – „Eroica“ in der Hand hält! Das wäre wahrhaft eine [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Taschenspieler[ei], ins Gehirn einen Terzzug zu senken u. nach einigem Hin u. Her eine Sinfonie herauszunehmen (<tei:hi rend="italic">warum</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">zweimal</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">dasselbe</tei:hi>? <tei:hi rend="italic">Kürze</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">ist</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">des</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Witzes</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Würze</tei:hi>!)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  No paragraph break in original.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>So ist es nicht. Das Bild des Ursatzes u. der Schichten, das ich biete, hat in erster Linie eine logische Folge zum Inhalte vom Einfachsten <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> im Hintergrund, zum Buntesten im Vordergrund, die aber auch umgekehrt gelesen werden kann u. muß als eine Rückführung des Buntesten im Vordergrund zum Einfachsten im Hintergrund. Für die Wertung des Bildes als einer logischen Folge ist die Richtung völlig gleichgiltig. Schon dieser logische Zusammenhang bestätigt, daß darin offenbar im Vordergrund der Hintergrund enthalten sein muß, d. h. daß mit dem Vordergrund der Hintergrund immer mitgeht, der Hintergrund ist im Vordergrund gegenwärtig. Damit habe ich mich aber noch nicht darüber geäußert, wie eine Komposition nun wirklich zustandekommt. Das „Chronologische“ des <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> wirklichen Schaffens geht nicht am „logischen“ Bande so einher wie das so mißverstandene Bild zu sagen scheint. Die Fantasie des Komponisten entzündet sich geheimnisvoll an einer Tonfolge oder bei improvisatorischer Begabung an einem größeren Wurf; – dabei ist zunächst gleichgiltig, welche Tonfolge, welcher Wurf das ist, – entscheidend wird, daß, sobald nur ein Wachstum sich zu regen beginnt, das Werdende sich wie von selbst in eine gewisse „Logik“ fügt, die eben mein Bild festhält: Es ist, als komponirte sich ein Meisterwerk selbst in die Terz-, Quint- oder Oktavräume hinein!  Künstler der Sprache können [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr from:</tei:hi> kennen] diesen Vorgang aus ihrem Beruf bestätigen. Auch sie hantieren <tei:hi rend="bold">{6r}</tei:hi> mit einem gewissen Etwas, das den Vordergrund wachsen läßt in Uebereinstimmung mit einfachster Grundlegung. Dieses Gefühl ist keine „Abstraktion“, da es sich doch realiter in der Komposition äußert. Die angebliche Abstraktion ist eben so real wie der Vordergrund (Augartenquinten![?]) Geschichtlich erklärt sich das Unvermögen der Heutigen gerade dadurch, daß sie jenes Etwas eingebüßt haben, die kompositorische [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte:</tei:hi> improvisatorische?] Begabung ist ihnen abhanden gekommen, sie hat den Hauptteil der Arbeit geleitet, sie müssen sich auf Erfindung von „Motiven“ beschränken – die Meister wissen von Motiven nichts – u. so blieb ihnen nichts übrig, als diese Motive zu „verarbeiten“, sie wiederzukauen [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte:</tei:hi> wiederzukäuen?] in <tei:hi rend="bold">{7r}</tei:hi> Vergrößerung, Umkehrung u. dgl. öden Spässen.  Ueber der mechanischen Arbeit am Motiv verging der Blick in größere Zusammenhänge, wodurch zuletzt auch das Ohr für solche Zusammenhänge verloren ging auch dort, wo sie fertig vorliegen.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit diesen Bemerkungen sehen Sie mich im Anschluss an Ihrer Meinung, es sei mit der modernen Musik zuende (kennen Sie vielleicht den Aufsatz von Strawinsky in der Baseler National Zeitung 3. XI. 31?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Igor Stravinsky, “Moderne Musikauffassung,” <tei:hi rend="italic">National-Zeitung</tei:hi> (Basel), November 3, 1931, a clipping of which is preserved as OC C/205.  </tei:note>), u. da bin ich denn bei Ihren im Sommer u. Herbst in der N. Fr. Presse veröffentlichten Aufsätzen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  Wilhelm Furtwängler, [click on to view] &lt;a href="../../../../../article/furtwangler<tei:hi rend="italic">verkannt.html"&gt;“Der verkannte Wagner”&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="../../../../../article/furtwangler</tei:hi>lebenskr.html"&gt;“Die Lebenskraft der Musik,“&lt;/a&gt; Neue Freie Presse, November ?? and ??, 1931.  </tei:note>  Herzlichst freut mich, daß Sie sich doch entschlossen haben, Ihre Fahne hoch zu schwingen u. den verworrenen <tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> Musikern und Freunden der Musik Wege zu weisen. Ihr Ruf zu <tei:hi rend="italic">Wagner</tei:hi> ist wirklich zeitgemäß.  Was auch gegen diesen Riesengeist von der höheren Warte der großen Meister der Tonkunst aus gesagt werden kann u. gesagt werden muß –: es kommt gar nicht in Frage, wenn wir der heutigen Generation einschärfen, auch seinesgleichen hat es nur einmal gegeben, wird es nie wieder geben! An Wagner gemessen ist <tei:hi rend="italic">Verdi</tei:hi> – unter uns – ein völlig talentloser Musiker (im Jahrbuch III sprach ich ihm immerhin Talent zu<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, vol. III (Munich: Drei Masken Verlag, 1930), p. 108, Eng trans. by Ian Bent in <tei:hi rend="italic">The Masterwork in Music</tei:hi>, vol. III (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1997), p. 71: “Verdi was only a talent, since he has contributed absolutely nothing to genuine art, a fact that must be granted despite the Verdi renaissance from which we hear so obstreperously nowadays.”  </tei:note>). Ich kenne in seinem Gesamtwerk nicht 8 Takte, von denen ich irgend ein Aufhebens machen möchte, wie das bei Smetana, Dvořak u. a. Für den „Melodie“-Appetit von Werfel<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15">  Click on <ref cRef="werfel_franz">Franz Werfel</ref>.  </tei:note> u. Genossen reicht er gerade noch hin, aber nach unseren Meistern, <tei:hi rend="bold">{9}</tei:hi> namentlich nach Mozart in der Oper ist Verdi viel zu spät gekommen, um überhaupt noch auf eine Entwickelung der Musik einwirken zu können.  Was die frühesten Italiener schrieben, kam noch unseren Meistern zugute, Verdi aber hatte nichts mehr zu sagen.</tei:p><tei:p>Daß die Musikgemeinschaft – im Jhrb. III sprach ich von einer Tongemeinschaft<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn16">  Schenker is in error here.  He is referring to <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, vol. II (Munich: Drei Masken Verlag, 1926), p. 205, Eng. trans. by Ian Bent in <tei:hi rend="italic">The Masterwork in Music</tei:hi>, vol. II (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1996), p. 124, which speaks first of a “community of language” (Sprachgemeinschaft), then proceeds:  “We can speak, in the same sense, of a community of tones.  People belonging to the same community of tones attune to each others' musical discourse [<tei:hi rend="italic">Tonrede</tei:hi>] better than people of different communities of tones.  [...]  Despite belonging to a community of tones, the genius always does without the spiritual ambience that it provides.  [...] Though Germany's community of tones may crumble, the achievement of her great composers will endure.”  (translation modified)</tei:note> – in Auflösung begriffen ist, haben Sie (wie Hubermann<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn17">  Click on <ref cRef="huberman_bronislaw">Bronislaw Huberman</ref>.  </tei:note>) endlich in aller Oeffentlichkeit festgestellt, doch möchte ich die Ursache davon weniger im Rundfunk- u. Schallplattenwesen u. ä. suchen, als – ich weiß mich frei vom Leisten pro domo zu sprechen – in der nun 200 Jahre währenden Beziehungslosigkeit zur Produktion unserer grossen Meister.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn18">  Perhaps an oblique reference to Jean-Philippe Rameau‘s <tei:hi rend="italic">Traité de l’harmonie</tei:hi> (Paris: Ballard, 1722) (thus approximately two hundred years prior to 1931), about which Schenker had written an antagonistic article in <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, vol. III (Vienna: Drei Masken Verlag, 1930), pp. 11–24, Eng. trans. by Ian Bent in <tei:hi rend="italic">The Masterwork in Music</tei:hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1997), pp. 1–9.  </tei:note>  Rechnen Sie mit mir: Bis zur <tei:hi rend="bold">{10}</tei:hi> Heraufkunft von Händel, Bach brauchte es &lt;strike&gt;100&lt;/strike&gt; Jahrh. Musik! Unmöglich hätten diese beiden Musiker schon z. B. im 3. oder 4. Jhrh. unserer Zeitrechnung erscheinen können. Das Gefühl für die Züge u. ihre Praxis mußte erst erstarken, damit diese Genies ihnen die so große Diminutionslast aufladen konnten.</tei:p><tei:p>Dazu kam die erste Kraft des neuen Glaubens, dem man gar nicht genug mit ehrlichster Kunst dienen konnte! Heute aber! Da ist vor allem der schwere Irrtum, der allein schon wider jegliches Talent der heutigen Generation zeugt: diese hält nämlich ein Genie der Vergangenheit für einen verlorenen Posten der Geschichte, statt ^es^ als einen Wert auch für die Zukunft, als ein <tei:hi rend="italic">Ziel</tei:hi> zu verstehen.  Ein Religions-Genie wie Moses ist wahrhaftig nicht <tei:hi rend="bold">{11}</tei:hi> tot, wenn noch heute von ihm die Wirkung ausgeht, Millionen orthodoxer Juden gegen eine Welt zusammenzuhalten. Kein Zweifel, daß die Juden die Bibel gründlich mißverstehen – von diesem Mißverständnis wollte sie eben Jesus befreien – u. doch: <tei:hi rend="italic">Selbst der Irrtum</tei:hi>, durch den sie an Mose gekettet sind, geriet u. gerät ihnen zum Heile – so stark ist der Segen eines Genies!  Ist Jesus etwa überholbar?  Ist er nicht der Menschen Ziel auch in fernster Zukunft?  Ist Plato überholbar?  Was immer die Zeiten den Genies an Substrat nehmen mögen, es bleibt im Werk ein Göttliches übrig, das jeder Zeit spottet!  Von diesem Göttlichen ahnt die Welt nichts!  Mir ist kein Zweifel, daß den Deutschen <tei:hi rend="bold">{12}</tei:hi> in künftigen Jahrhunderten nichts übrigbleiben wird, als die großen Meister mit geradezu göttlichen Ehren zu pflegen, genau wie die Juden mit dem Alten Testament durch die Zeiten wandern.  Wie widerspricht dem aber das Treiben der Heutigen namentlich in den amerikanisierten Städten!  Von Jahr zu Jahr werden Genies ausgerufen, denen man gewaltsam dadurch Platz zu machen sucht, daß man die Alten als überholt ins Ausgedinge schickt – nun Sie wissen das alles ja auch – –</tei:p><tei:p>&lt;strike&gt;Die&lt;/strike&gt; Ich frage aber: was nun? da die „moderne“ Musik abgewirtschaftet hat?, bedarf erst recht einer gründlichen Erörterung. Wir haben u. werden bis auf weiteres ein Vacuum haben. Was soll u. darf in diesem Vacuum geschehen? Was jetzt geschieht, verbietet sich <tei:hi rend="bold">{13}</tei:hi> von selbst, d. h bald wird nichts mehr geschehen können – das bedeutet den völligen Untergang. Ist [es] nun eine in der Geschichte nicht dagewesene Schande, daß ein Volk von der Geniekraft der Deutschen binnen wenigen Jahren seine größten musikalischen Geister hinausgeworfen hat, so ist es eine noch größere Schande, daß selbst die große materielle Not das deutsche Volk noch immer nicht ahnen läßt, welche ungeheuer grosse Geldindustrie in den Meisterwerken steckt, die es sehr gut zuhilfe nehmen könnte. Ich wage zu behaupten, daß sämtliche Industrien der Welt der deutschen Genie-Industrie nicht gleichkommen; aber: man muß diese Industrie nach dem Verrat wieder sanieren, wie man die Banken saniert! Den „Kredit“, den deutsche <tei:hi rend="bold">{14}</tei:hi> Musik bisher in aller Welt genossen hat, darf doch das deutsche Volk nicht selbst untergraben.  Es hat die Pflicht, zur Größe seiner Werke zu stehen u. diese Währung mit allen Kräften zu stützen.  Kann das aber noch geschehen? Ich, u. vielleicht nur ich allein sage: Ja! Nur dürfen darüber nicht die Kestenberg,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn19">  Click on <ref cRef="kestenberg_leo">Leo Kestenberg</ref>.  </tei:note> Schünemann,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn20">  Click on <ref cRef="schunemann_georg">Georg Schünemann</ref>.  </tei:note> Schreker<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn21">  Click on <ref cRef="schreker_franz">Franz Schreker</ref>.  </tei:note> u. ähnliche Gelichter entscheiden, denn die wissen von Musik nichts, am allerwenigsten von der großen u. machen nur Geschäfte in „Organisation“!  Nichts wäre einfacher, als schon in den untersten Schulklassen mit dem Lesen von Terz-, Quart-, Oktavzügen zu beginnen u. so die Ohren an den kleinen Uebungen, den Dussek, Clementi u. a. auf Zusammenhänge zu spannen <tei:hi rend="bold">{15}</tei:hi> wie die Sprache auf grammatische Begriffe u. Zusammenhänge. Tausende Kinder, die der Musik verloren gehen, könnten ihr so gewonnen werden u. den neuen Humus<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn22">  Schenker uses the concept of “humus“ notably in “Von der Sendung des deutschen Genies,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</tei:hi>, Heft 1 (1921), pp. 3–21;  Eng. trans. by Ian Bent (New York: Oxford University Press, 2004), pp. 3–20.  </tei:note> bilden, den ja offenbar auch Sie suchen. Wäre Musik nicht eben diese ärmste u. am meisten mißverstandene aller Künste, vogelfrei für jedermann, glauben Sie, daß ich nicht schon längst vom Berliner oder Wiener Ministerium zu Rate gezogen worden wäre?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn23">  The allusion is to Kestenberg’s position as ministerial adviser in Berlin 1929–32.  </tei:note> Schließlich bin ich, wofür mein Lebenswerk zeugt, doch einer von den wenigen Morgans<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn24">  Presumably an allusion to John Pierpont Morgan, Jr. (1867–1943), American financier, son of the investment banker, art collector, philanthropist, and contributor to the New York Metropolitan Museum of Art John Pierpont Morgan, Sr. (1837–1913);  creator in 1924 of the Pierpont Morgan Library in New York in memory of his father and to house the latter’s library and collection, and philanthropist in his own right.  This is part of the larger financial metaphor that Schenker is creating in this section of the letter.  </tei:note> in der heutigen Musik – zieht man Morgan nicht zu Rate in allen Nöten? Warum ist Kestenberg zu feig, mich um Rat zu bitten, fürchtet er, daß ich ihm etwas zumute, was <tei:hi rend="bold">{16}</tei:hi> er nicht leisten könnte? Dann müßte er aber selbst helfen, um die Katastrophe zu verhüten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn25">  No paragraph break in the original.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Alle Praktiken, die den Banken aufhelfen, müßten auch für die Musik gelten. Den „Amstelbänklern“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn26">  The Amstel Bank was founded in the Netherlands in 1921.  It had ties to the Österreichische Credit-Anstalt, the bank founded by the Rothschild family.  </tei:note> muß schließlich das Handwerk gelegt werden! Also z. B. müßte man die Schönberg<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn27">  Click on <ref cRef="schoenberg_arnold">Arnold Schoenberg</ref>.</tei:note> u. Jöde<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn28">  Click on <ref cRef="jode_fritz">Fritz Jöde</ref>.  </tei:note> an die Luft setzen, sonst gibt es keine Sanierung. Und für Wien im besonderen wüßte ich eine glänzende Sanierung, ohne Genf, Basel, Paris.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn29">  The allusion of all three locations is perhaps to Stravinsky;  alternatively, Schenker might perhaps mean: Geneva = Stravinsky;  Basel = Paul Sacher?;  Paris = Debussy and others.  </tei:note> Ich habe den Plan schon oft vorgebracht: Statt sich, nur um ein Verkehrsgeschäft zu machen, verzweifelt des 138. Todestages, der 20. Wiederkehr des Tages an dem . . . usw. zu klam[m]ern, wäre es für das Geschäft viel ergiebiger, <tei:hi rend="bold">{17}</tei:hi> wenn Wien nach Bayreut[h]er Muster ein „Festspielhaus“ für seine Musik-Götter auferbaute, in dem alljährlich ein erlesenes, aus den besten Instrumentalisten gebildetes Orchester in <tei:hi rend="italic">kanonischer Weise</tei:hi> die großen Werke der Welt darböte. Einer wie Sie sollte die Reihe eröffnen u. für den Nachwuchs sorgen, so daß die Tradition in die Zeiten fortwirkte!  In aller Welt wüßte man: Nur in Wien könne man am besten die Meisterwerke hören!  Salzburg behielte seine eigene Note, die es dann gar nicht mehr zu verfälschen brauchte, weil Wien einen Teil der Aufgabe übernähme. Noch manchen anderen Weg gäbe es, die Musik zu sanieren!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{18r}</tei:hi> Haben Sie gehört, daß man z. B. einen gotischen Dom wegen geänderter Auffassung in religiösen oder baulichen Sachen in eine „moderne“ Kirche umbauen wollte? Noch zeugt jeder stolze got&lt;strike&gt;h&lt;/strike&gt;ische Dom für seine Zeit – u. auch noch uns für die heutige – mit welchem Rechte wagen sich Auffassungen ändernd, fälschend an die gotischen Dome in der Musik?! Alle Auffassungen sind entbehrlich.</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">private addition by Jeanette Schenker</tei:hi>]
Meiner Auffassung nach hätte ich das auch morgen schreiben können, statt heute bis in die späte Nacht</tei:p><tei:p>Deine Lie-Lie!
13. XI. 31</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten draft letter from Schenker to Furtwängler, first version, in Jeanette Schenker’s hand, dated November 13, 1931</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">no address or salutation</tei:hi>]<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Your gesture of &lt;strike&gt;kind&lt;/strike&gt; sympathy<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> gave me great pleasure.  This summer, I followed the &lt;strike&gt;strict&lt;/strike&gt; instructions of my doctors, who strongly urged me to give my eyes a rest.  The battle over the <tei:hi rend="italic">Eroica</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> had been waged rather too heroically on my part.  I was scarcely allowed to write anything, nor to read anything, and nevertheless I actually managed to see these privations, which were so severe for me, at least rewarded by the restoration of my eyesight.  There is still room for caution, but I may be able to get going again now.</tei:p><tei:p>Weisse’s<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> successes really do exceed all expectations.  Before his departure,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> he spoke once again at the Music Pedagogical Association<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> in Vienna [and] enthused his audience (aka colleagues), <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> admittedly without being able to carry them off as he would liked to be able to do.  Weisse also spoke in the concert hall in Hamburg with dazzling success.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>  I am enclosing with this a review by <tei:hi rend="italic">Herman Roth</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> because I seem to recall that you have been acquainted with Roth since Munich days, and also to let you know something that will perhaps interest you, namely ^that^ Roth has taken over Pfohl’s<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> place at the <tei:hi rend="italic">Hamburger Nachrichten</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/>  I very much give Roth credit that after a lull of so many years he has become active once again in my cause.  I have written to him specifically about the gaffe at the end of the article, where he speaks of an “abstraction.”  It is incomprehensible to me <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> how musicians with the examples of my right thinking available to them can attribute to me so ridiculous an assertion as that all composing should take the Ursatz as its point of departure, and that one need only get to work on an Urlinie progression and subject it to diminutions until, hey presto!, you finish up with, e.g., an <tei:hi rend="italic">Eroica</tei:hi>.  That really would be some conjuring trick:  to let a 3rd-progression sink into one’s brain, and after a bit of to’ing and fro’ing to take out a symphony!  (<tei:hi rend="italic">Why the same twice over</tei:hi>?  <tei:hi rend="italic">Brevity is the soul of wit</tei:hi>!)<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/></tei:p><tei:p>That is not the way it is.  The image of the Ursatz and its layers that I offer has first and foremost a logical progression to its content, proceeding from the simplest thing <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> in the background to the most colorful thing in the foreground, [a progression] which can and must, however, also be read in reverse as a regression from the most colorful in the foreground to the simplest in the background.  For the evaluation of the image as a logical progression, direction is wholly immaterial.  This logical continuity in itself verifies that the background must be manifestly contained within the foreground, i.e. the background proceeds always in tandem with the foreground, the background is present within the foreground.  In so doing, I have still not, however, expressed myself as to how a composition actually comes into being.  The “chronological dimension” of <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> actual creation does not run as completely in step with the “logical” progression as my image—so badly misunderstood!—seems to say.  The composer’s imagination is secretly set on fire by a tone progression or where there is a gift for improvisation by a sweeping intuitive move. In this process, it is at first immaterial which tone progression or which intuitive move it is:  the very moment a growth process gets underway, it is crucial that what is burgeoning submits itself, as of its own volition, to a certain “logic” that conforms precisely to my image:  It is as if a masterwork composed itself into the spaces of 3rd, 5th, or octave!  Artists who work with language can confirm this process from their own [artistic] realm.  They, too, operate <tei:hi rend="bold">{6r}</tei:hi> with a certain something that causes the foreground to grow in conformity with the simplest foundation?  This feeling is no “abstraction,” since on the contrary it expresses itself in tangible form in the composition.  This alleged abstraction is every bit as tangible as the foreground (.....[?] 5ths!).  Historically, the incapacity of today’s composers can be explained precisely in that they have lost that “something,” that the gift for composition [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte:</tei:hi> improvisation?] has forsaken them.  It was that which [in the past] presided over the most important part of the work;  they [i. e. today’s composers] must limit themselves to inventing “motives”—the masters know nothing of motives—and thus all that was left for them was to “fashion” these motives [and] to regurgitate them in <tei:hi rend="bold">{7r}</tei:hi> augmentations, inversions and suchlike barren tomfooleries.  Preoccupied with the mechanics of motive-building, they neglected to pay attention to the larger-scale connections, as a result of which ultimately the ear for such connections has become lost even when they are present and available for use.</tei:p><tei:p>With these remarks, you see me in accord with your opinion that all is up with modern music (are you perhaps familiar with the article by Stravinsky in the <tei:hi rend="italic">Baseler National Zeitung</tei:hi> of November 3, 1931?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/>), and thus with the articles that you published during the summer and fall in the <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue Freie Presse</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/>  It gladdens my heart that you have after all resolved to pin your colors to the mast and show confused <tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> musicians and friends the way of music.  Your call to <tei:hi rend="italic">Wagner</tei:hi> is really in keeping with the times.  What can and must be stated in criticism of this giant spirit from the loftier vantage-point of the great masters of music [is this]:  there is no question about it, if we impress upon the young people of today, that even in his own day it [i.e. Wagner’s work] was given only once and will never be given again.  Against Wagner is measured <tei:hi rend="italic">Verdi</tei:hi>—strictly between ourselves—a musician completely devoid of talent (in <tei:hi rend="italic">Yearbook III</tei:hi> I was still crediting him with talent<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/>).  I do not know eight measures in his entire output that I would ever like to make a fuss about—as I do in Smetana, Dvořák, and others.  Still today he barely satisfies the appetite for “melody” of Werfel<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn15"/> and his comrades, but after our masters, <tei:hi rend="bold">{9}</tei:hi> most particularly after Mozart in opera, Verdi came far too late to be able to have any effect on a development of the music.  What the earliest Italian composers wrote still benefitted our masters, whereas Verdi had nothing more to say.</tei:p><tei:p>You yourself (as also Hubermann<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn17"/>) have finally declared in the full blaze of publicity that the musical community—in <tei:hi rend="italic">Yearbook III</tei:hi> I spoke of a community of tones<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn16"/>—is in the process of disintegration;  but I should like to seek the cause of that, less in the nature of radio and recordings, and the like than—I know that I speak freely and from my own point of view—in the lack of relationship to the production of our great masters that has been going on now for 200 years.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn18"/>  Reckon it up with me:  &lt;strike&gt;100&lt;/strike&gt; Centuries of music were necessary before <tei:hi rend="bold">{10}</tei:hi> the emergence of Handel and Bach!  It would have been impossible for these two musicians to appear, for example, as early as the third or fourth century of our era.  The feeling for the linear progressions and their realization in practice had first to gain strength, in order that these geniuses could shoulder the burden of diminution, so very great as it was.</tei:p><tei:p>Thereafter, the new belief for the first time attained its full power—the belief to which people just could not pay sufficient service with the most noble art!  But today!  There, above all, there is the grievous error, which in itself alone testifies against any talent whatsoever on the part of today’s younger generation:  the latter considers a genius from the past as a long-lost entry in the leger of history instead of understanding it as something of value for the future, as a <tei:hi rend="italic">goal</tei:hi> to strive for.  A genius from the world of religion such as Moses is truly not <tei:hi rend="bold">{11}</tei:hi> dead when his effect on us is still felt today, holding together millions of orthodox Jews in the face of a whole world.  There is no doubt that the Jews fundamentally misunderstand the Bible—this is exactly the misunderstanding from which Jesus wanted to free them—and yet, <tei:hi rend="italic">the error itself</tei:hi>, through which they are chained to Moses, redounded—and still redounds—to their benefit:  That is how strong the blessing of a genius is!  Is it possible for Jesus to be surpassed?  Is he not the goal of all men, even into the remotest future?  Is it possible for Plato to be surpassed?  However much successive ages may take of these geniuses' substrate, there remains a godlike element in their work that disdains each age!  Of this godlike element the world has no inkling!  I am in no doubt whatsoever that there will be nothing left for Germans <tei:hi rend="bold">{12}</tei:hi> in future centuries to do other than to cherish the great masters with exactly that godlike honor with which the Jews wander through the ages with the Old Testament.  But how the pursuits of today’s [world] contradict that, especially in the Americanized cities!  From year to year, geniuses are proclaimed, for whom people furiously try to make room so that the old geniuses can be forced into retirement as superannuated. — But then, you know all this, too — —</tei:p><tei:p>But I ask :  What now?  Since “modern” music has been ruinously mismanaged?  More than ever, what is required is a fundamental discussion.  Until something is done about it, we have—and will continue to have—a vacuum.  What should happen in this vacuum?  What happens now is <tei:hi rend="bold">{13}</tei:hi> unthinkable; that is, nothing will soon be able to happen—and that spells total extinction.  If it is a shameful thing—something not present in history—that a people of the power of genius of the German people has discarded its greatest musical spirits in the space of a few years, then it is an even more shameful thing that even great material hardship still does not allow the German people to suspect what an extraordinarily large financial industry lies in the masterworks, from which it could very well derive help.  I dare to assert that all the industries in the world do not compare with the German industry of genius;  but after the betrayal, this industry must be recapitalized, just as banks are recapitalized!  It is imperative that the German people do not themselves undermine the “credit” that German <tei:hi rend="bold">{14}</tei:hi> music has hitherto enjoyed throughout the world.  They have the duty to stand up for the greatness of their works, and to support this currency with all its might.  But is there still any possibility of this happening?  I—and perhaps I alone—say: Yes!  Only it must not be the Kestenbergs,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn19"/> Schünemanns,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn20"/> Schrekers,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn21"/> and similar riffraff who make the decisions on this, for they know nothing about music, at least nothing about great [music], and merely make business deals in “organization.”  Nothing would be simpler than to begin as early as the lowest school classes with reading 3rd-, 4th-, and octave -progressions, and then to stretch the ear by examples of small exercises—Dussek, Clementi, and others—to [larger] connections, <tei:hi rend="bold">{15}</tei:hi> just as [is done] in language to grammatical concepts and connections.  Thousands of children, who are lost to music, could be won over to it in this way and form the new humus<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn22"/> that you, too, obviously seek.  If music were not simply the poorest and most misunderstood of all the arts, outlawed for everyone, do you not think that I might long ago have been called upon by the Berlin or Vienna Ministry as a consultant?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn23"/>  After all, I am, as my life’s work attests, one of the very few Morgans<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn24"/> in today’s music—does one not consult Morgans in all times of need?  Why is Kestenberg too cowardly to consult me;  is he afraid that I might demand something of him that <tei:hi rend="bold">{16}</tei:hi> he could not fulfill?  But then he himself would have to help in order to avert the catastrophe.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn25"/></tei:p><tei:p>All practices that help out the banks ought to be valid also for music.  A stop must at last be put to the “Amstelbank” people!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn26"/>  Thus, for example, the Schoenbergs<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn27"/> and Jödes<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn28"/> of this world would have to be given the sack, otherwise there will be no recapitalization.  And for Vienna in particular I would have in mind a glittering recapitalization, without Geneva, Basel, [or] Paris.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn29"/>  I have often put my plan forward in the past.  Instead of clinging desperately to the 138th death-date of so-and-so, the 20th anniversay of the such-and-such, etc., merely for business, it would be far more profitable <tei:hi rend="bold">{17}</tei:hi> if Vienna were to build a “Festival Playhouse” for its musical gods along the lines of Bayreuth in which, annually, a hand-picked orchestra made up of the best instrumentalists would present the great works of the world in <tei:hi rend="italic">canonical fashion</tei:hi>.  One such as youself ought to open the series and take care of its subsequent growth, so that the tradition would continue to be effective over time!   People throughout the world would then know:  only in Vienna can one hear the masterworks to best advantage!  Salzburg would retain its own particular character, which it would no longer ever need to falsify, because Vienna would be taking over part of the task.  There would still be many another way of cleaning up music!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{18r}</tei:hi> Have you heard that, for example, they wanted to convert a Gothic cathedral into a “modern” church because their interpretation of religious or architectural matters has changed?  Every proud Gothic cathedral stands as a witness for its own time—and us still for today’s, too.  What right do interpretations, changing, falsifying, have to tinker with the Gothic cathedrals of Music?!  All interpretations are dispensable.</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">private addition by Jeanette Schenker</tei:hi>]
According to my interpretation, I would have been able to do this tomorrow instead of today into the late hours.</tei:p><tei:p>Yours, Lie-Lie
November 13, 1931</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>