<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 5/11, [1], vsn 2 : 11-13-31 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain
© Transcription Christoph Hust, 2008.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2008.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Christoph Hust, 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1931-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935- c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker;  Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Christoph Hust;  Translation Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 11/13/1931 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: &quot;Furtw&#195;&#164;ngler ~ H+JSchenker&quot;,&quot;Furtw&#195;&#164;ngler ~ HSchenker&quot; --><dc:title>Draft letter from Schenker to Furtwängler, second version, dated November 13, 1931</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-04-06</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>[Material unique to vsn 2 italicized:] Schenker thanks Furtwängler for his sympathy and reports on the condition of his eyes. —Reports on two lectures recently given by Hans Weisse; encloses a review by Herman Roth, whom he praises, but whom he has chided for use of the word "abstraction." —He is astonished at the simplistic view that some musicians have taken of the Ursatz; he describes the logical relationship between background and foreground, and explains the roles of imagination, growth, and improvisational intuition in the composition process, comparing it to the misguided method of composing with motives. —Weisse has won over the faculty of the Mannes Conservatory in New York, and [George A.], who was teaching Schenker's theory earlier, has allied himself with Weisse; a Schenker Institute has been opened there. —Referring to a recent article by Stravinsky, and articles published by Furtwängler, he writes about Wagner, and is dismissive of Verdi. —He identifies the cause of the current disintegration of the "community of tones," and outlines an educational program beginning in the earliest school years with 3rd-, 4th-, and octave-progressions. —He draws an analogy between the Germans' failure to appreciate their past musical masters and the Jews' failure to understand the Bible, and outlines what Vienna should do to regain its artistic primacy; in this, he deploys financial and banking metaphors. —Musical calamities can be recapitalized only through music. —Asks Furtwängler to be in touch whenever he is in Vienna.   

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich; Furtwängler, Wilhelm; Beethoven; Eroica; Weisse, Hans; Roth, Herman; Vienna; Musikpädagogischer Verband; Music Pedagogical Association; Hamburg; Pfohl, Ferdinand; München; Munich; Hamburger Nachrichten; abstraction; Ursatz; Urlinie; Terz-Zug; 3rd-progression; Quart-Zug; 4th-progression; Quint-Zug;  5th progression;  Oktav-Zug; octave-progression; Vordergrund; foreground; Hintergrund; background; Fantasie; imagination; improvisation; motives; Mannes Conservatory;  Wedge, George A.;  Institute of Musical Art;  Schenker-Institut;  Schenker Institute;  Hamburg;  Stravinsky; Baseler National-Zeitung; Neue Freie Presse; Wagner; Verdi; Smetana; Dvořák; Leitmotiv;  Motiv;  Werfel, Franz; Mozart; Huberman, Bronislaw; Das Meisterwerk in der Musik; The Masterwork in Music; Handel; J. S. Bach; genius; Moses; Jews; Bible; Old Testament; Jesus; Plato; modern music; Dussek; Clementi; Berlin; Amstelbank; Morgan, John Pierpont; Geneva; Basel; Paris; Bayreuth; Salzburg;  Mozart; homeopathy;  Vienna</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten draft letter from Schenker to Furtwängler, second version, in Jeanette Schenker’s hand, dated November 13, 1931</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">no address or salutation</tei:hi>]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  This letter-draft is preceded by a small folded piece of paper with the following inscription in Heinrich Schenker's hand:  "An Furtw. [/] Bf. vom 16–18/11 [/] 1931 [/] als Antw. auf [/] Bf. Furtw.'s vom 8/11/31" (To Furtwängler [/] letter from November 16–18, 1931 [/] as answer to [/] Furtwängler's letter of November 8, 1931").  There is no record in Schenker's diary of receipt of such a letter, nor is there any record of the drafting of the present letter (which one would expect with so long and carefully worded a document).  Moreover, Schenker attended a Philharmonic concert by Furtwängler on November 16, and reported on the interpretation. </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Das Zeichen Ihrer Teilnahme<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Letter, OJ 11/16, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="roth_herman">Herman Roth</ref>.  The article in question was presumably “Bekenntnis zu Heinrich Schenker,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Hamburger Nachrichten</tei:hi>, September 17, 1931, a clipping of which is preserved in Schenker’s scrapbook on OC 2/p. 84.  </tei:note>, November 8, 1931:  " I should very much like to have a word or two from you yourself about your health and such like things."   </tei:note> hat mich sehr erfreut. Ich bin im Sommer der Weisung der Aerzte gefolgt, die mir eine Schonung der Augen streng abforderten. Mein Kampf um die „Eroica“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  The essay “Beethovens Dritte Sinfonie zum erstenmal in ihrem wahren Inhalt dargestellt,“ <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, vol. III (Munich: Drei Masken Verlag, 1930), pp. 25–101 and graphs, Eng. trans. by Derrick Puffett and Alfred Clayton in <tei:hi rend="italic">The Masterwork in Music</tei:hi>, vol. III (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1997), pp. 10–68 and graphs.  </tei:note> war meinerseits etwas zu heroisch geführt worden. zeitlich! Ich durfte nur sehr wenig schreiben u. lesen:  so schwer dies gerade mir fiel, der seit dem 13. Lebensjahr keine Arbeits-Pause kannte,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> i.e. since 1880/81.  </tei:note> ich hielt mich an das Verbot u. seh mich durch die Wiederherstellung der Augen zur Genüge belohnt. (Noch immer ist Vorsicht am Platze.)</tei:p><tei:p>Die Erfolge unseres l.[ieben] D^r^ Weisse<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.  </tei:note> übertreffen wirklich alle Erwartung.  Noch knapp vor seiner Abreise<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Presumably Weisse’s departure for New York in the early Fall of 1931.  </tei:note> sprach er einmal in Wien im „musikpädagogischen Verband“,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Österreichischer Musikpädagogischer Verband: [supply information].  [give date and title of lecture]    </tei:note> begeisterte die „Kollegen“ <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> ohne sie dorthin fortreissen zu können, wo er sie in ihrem eigenen Interesse gern hätte haben mögen. Mit blendendem Erfolg sprach dann Weisse auch in Hamburg im Konzerthaus.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  The lecture, given at the invitation of Moriz Violin on September 16, 1931,  is reported in Weisse’s letter to Schenker of September 5, 1931 (OJ 15/16, [81]).  The title of the lecture was to be “Hörendes Schaffen – schaffendes Hören, Versuch einer Würdigung des Grundgedanken in H. Schenkers Werk“ (Hearing Creativity – Creative Hearing:  Attempt at an Appreciation of the Fundamental Thought of H. Schenker’s Work).  </tei:note>  Zum Beweis des Erfolges in Hamburg lege ich hier das <tei:hi rend="italic">Referat</tei:hi> von <tei:hi rend="italic">H. Roth</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="roth_herman">Herman Roth</ref>.  The article in question was presumably “Bekenntnis zu Heinrich Schenker,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Hamburger Nachrichten</tei:hi>, September 17, 1931, a clipping of which is preserved in Schenker’s scrapbook on OC 2/p. 84.  </tei:note> bei, der bei den „Hamburger Nachrichten“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Click on <ref cRef="hamburger_nachrichte"><tei:hi rend="italic">Hamburger Nachrichten</tei:hi></ref>.</tei:note> an die Stelle von Prof. Dr. Pfohl<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Click on <ref cRef="pfohl_ferdinand">Ferdinand Pfohl</ref>. </tei:note> gekommen ist, weil ich mich zu erinnern glaube, daß Sie R. von München her kennen.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich halte es R. sehr zugute, daß er nach vieljähriger Pause sich wieder, wie ehedem, freundlich zu meiner Sache stellte. Nur die Entgleisung zum Schluss des Aufsatzes, wo auch er mißverstehend von einer „Abstraktion“ spricht, mußte ich richtig stellen in einem Briefe an ihn. Es ist mir wirklich unerfindlich, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> wie Musiker, die Beweise meines gesund denkenden Kopfes in Händen haben, mir eine solche „Abstraktion“ unterstellen können! Nie u. nirgend[s] habe ich gesagt, alles gute Komponieren gehe immer vom Ursatz u. seinem Terz-, Quint- oder Oktavzug aus, pflanze sich dann durch die Diminutionen der Schichten so lange fort, bis man z. B. eine neue – „Eroica“ in der Hand hält!  So ist es nicht. Das Bild des Ursatzes u. der Schichten, das ich biete, stellt nur die Logik im Zusammenhang eines Inhaltes dar, wobei es völlig gleichgiltig ist, ob die Betrachtung vom Einfachsten <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> im Hintergrund zum Buntesten im Vordergrund oder umgekehrt vom Buntesten im Vordergrund zum Einfachsten im Hintergrund sich bewegt.  Das sagt zugleich, daß im Vordergrund immer u. überall der Hintergrund gegenwärtig ist, d. h. daß  mit dem Vordergrund auch der Hintergrund mitgeht.</tei:p><tei:p>Ein Anderes aber ist das „Chronologische“ <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> im wirklichen Schaffen. Dieses geht a[n] jenem „logischen“ Bande durchaus nicht so einher wie das Bild den Mißverstehenden es zu sagen scheint. Die Fantasie des Komponisten entzündet sich vielmehr bei improvisatorischer Begabung  geheimnisvoll an[?] irgend einem Wurf;  dieser sei beliebig, wie er wolle, entscheidend ist nur, daß, sobald ein Wachstum sich zu regen beginnt, das Werdende sich in eben jene „Logik“ fügt, die mein das[?] Bild festhält: Es ist, als komponirte sich ein Meisterwerk in die Terz-, Quint- oder Oktavräume selbst hinein!  Künstler der Sprache können übrigens diesen Vorgang auch aus ihrem Schaffen bestätigen. Auch sie hantieren <tei:hi rend="bold">{6r}</tei:hi> mit einem gewissen Etwas, das den Vordergrund mit einfachster Grundlegung wachsen läßt. Dieses Gefühl ist nun gewiß keine „Abstraktion“, wenn es sich in der Komposition so real äußert.</tei:p><tei:p>Das Unvermögen der Heutigen zu einem wahren Meisterwerk erklärt sich geschichtlich gerade dadurch, daß sie jenes Etwas eingebüßt haben. Durch zunehmende Beteiligung, durch Betrieb, wie vor allem durch falschen Unterricht wurde das ehedem sehr gepflegte &lt;strike&gt;i&lt;/strike&gt;Improvisatorische abgetötet, [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from p. <tei:hi rend="bold">6v</tei:hi>:</tei:hi> das wie spielend die Hauptarbeit im Schaffen leistete u. dem Komponisten sozusagen die Mühe des Zusammenklaubens von Teilchen ersparte: notgedrungen beschränkte man sich daher in der Folge der Zeiten] auf Erfindung von kurzen „Motiven“ – die Meister wissen von Motiven solcher Art nichts – die man dann erst durch mechanische Wh. [Wiederholung] stre[ c ]kte, in Vergrößerung, Verkleinerung, Umkehrung usw. zu „verarbeiten“ sich bemühte.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{7r}</tei:hi> Ueber dieser öden Mechanik verlor sich der Blick für größere Zusammenhänge, im eigenen Schaffen wie leider auch für solche, die schon in den Meisterwerke[n] niedergelegt sind!</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from p. <tei:hi rend="bold">7v</tei:hi>:</tei:hi> Nun zurück zu Weisses Erfolgen.  In New-York gelang es ihm binnen Stunden die gesamte Lehrerschaft des Mannes-Konservatoriums<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Click on <ref cRef="mannes_music_school">Mannes School of Music</ref>.</tei:note> für sich u. meine Sache zu gewinnen:  alle Lehrer, voran der vorherige Theorie-Professor der Anstalt,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  Presumably Leopold Mannes, son of the Mannes School's co-founders, David and Clara Mannes.  </tei:note> arbeiten sich in regelmäßigen Stunden unter seiner Leitung in die neue Lehre ein.  Auch Mr Wedge,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  Click on <ref cRef="wedge_george_a">George A. Wedge</ref>.  </tei:note> der Leiter des „inst. for musical art,“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15">  Click on <ref cRef="institute_of_music_a">Institute of Musical Art</ref>.</tei:note>  der schon früher nach meinen Büchern lehrte, näherte sich ihm. Ich darf nun sagen, daß solcherart sich in <tei:hi rend="italic">U. S. A.</tei:hi> „Schenker-Institute“ aufgetan haben (als erstes ist das in Hamburg<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn16">  Hamburg: for the synopsis of the Schenker Institute c. 1933, click on <ref cRef="schenker_institute_h">Schenker Institute, Hamburg</ref>.  </tei:note> zur auf die Welt gekommen).]</tei:p><tei:p>Ihrer Meinung, es sei mit der „modernen“ Musik zuende pflichte ich bei (kennen Sie vielleicht den Aufsatz von Strawinsky in der Baseler National Zeitung 3. XI. 31?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn17">  Igor Stravinsky, “Moderne Musikauffassung,” <tei:hi rend="italic">National-Zeitung</tei:hi> (Basel), November 3, 1931, a clipping of which is preserved as OC C/205.  </tei:note>), u. da bin ich denn bei Ihren im Sommer u. Herbst in der N. Fr. Presse veröffentlichten Aufsätzen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn18">  Wilhelm Furtwängler, &lt;a href="../../../../../article/furtwangler<tei:hi rend="italic">verkannt.html"&gt;“Der verkannte Wagner”&lt;/a&gt; and “ &lt;a href="../../../../../article/furtwangler</tei:hi>lebenskr.html"&gt;Die Lebenskraft der Musik,“&lt;/a&gt; <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue Freie Presse</tei:hi>, November ?? and ??, 1931.  </tei:note> Herzlichst freut mich, daß Sie sich entschlossen haben, Ihre Fahne hoch zu schwingen u. den verworrenen <tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> Musikern und Freunden der Musik Wege zu weisen.</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr Ruf zu <tei:hi rend="italic">Wagner</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn18">  Wilhelm Furtwängler, &lt;a href="../../../../../article/furtwangler<tei:hi rend="italic">verkannt.html"&gt;“Der verkannte Wagner”&lt;/a&gt; and “ &lt;a href="../../../../../article/furtwangler</tei:hi>lebenskr.html"&gt;Die Lebenskraft der Musik,“&lt;/a&gt; <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue Freie Presse</tei:hi>, November ?? and ??, 1931.  </tei:note> ist wirklich zeitgemäß.  Gewiß darf u. muß auch gegen diesen Riesengeist von der höheren Warte der noch größeren Meister der instrumentalen Tonkunst aus dies im Ernst gesagt werden: daß „Leitmotiv“ = „Motiv“ s. ob.  [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from p. <tei:hi rend="bold">8v</tei:hi>:</tei:hi>  So z. B. kehren die Nachteile einer „Motiv“-Technik, s. o., auch bei seiner „Leitmotiv“-Technik wieder, sie arbeiten jeglicher Synthese entgegen, sogar der Synthese eines „Musikdrama“! (Fast dürfte man in Wagner's „Leitmotiven“ eine Vorausnahme der heute im Film so überschwenglich gebrauchten Einschaltungen von Erinnerungsbilder sehen.) Doch alles dies kommt] der heutigen Generation gegenüber gar nicht in Frage, denn auch Seinesgleichen hat es nur einmal gegeben, wird es nie wieder in Deutschland geben!</tei:p><tei:p>In <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Verdi's</tei:hi></tei:hi> Gesamtwerk wüßte ich nicht 8 Takte, von denen ein Aufhebens zu machen wäre, wie dies etwa bei Smetana, Dvořak u. a. immerhin möglich ist. Für den banalen „Melodie“-Appetit von Werfel<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn19">  Click on <ref cRef="werfel_franz">Franz Werfel</ref>.  </tei:note> u. Genossen reicht er gerade noch hin, nichts mehr.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{9}</tei:hi> Was die frühesten Italiener schrieben, konnte sogar noch unseren Meistern zugute kommen, Verdi dagegen ist ohne Kunstwert.</tei:p><tei:p>Daß die Musikgemeinschaft in Auflösung begriffen ist, haben Sie (wie auch Hubermann<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn20">  Click on <ref cRef="huberman_bronislaw">Bronislaw Huberman</ref>.  </tei:note>) endlich in aller Oeffentlichkeit festgestellt.  Auch haben Sie die Ursache davon, soweit sie im Rundfunk- u. Schallplattenwesen u. ä. zu suchen ist, ganz vortrefflich herausgearbeitet.</tei:p><tei:p>Eine noch wichtigere Ursache aber scheint mir in der nun 200 Jahre<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn21">  Perhaps an oblique reference to Jean-Philippe Rameau‘s <tei:hi rend="italic">Traité de l’harmonie</tei:hi> (Paris: Ballard, 1722) (thus approximately two hundred years prior to 1931), about which Schenker had written a antagonistic article in <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, vol. III (Vienna: Drei Masken Verlag, 1930), pp. 11–24, Eng. trans. by Ian Bent in <tei:hi rend="italic">The Masterwork in Music</tei:hi> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1997), pp. 1–9.  </tei:note> währenden allgemeinen Beziehungslosigkeit zur Produktion unserer grossen Meister zu liegen. Bis zur <tei:hi rend="bold">{10}</tei:hi> Heraufkunft eines Händel, Bach brauchte es Jahrhunderte Musik! Unmöglich hätten diese beiden Genies schon z. B. im 3. oder 4. Jhrh. unserer Zeitrechnung erscheinen können. Erst mußte in der Übung der Kunst das Gefühl für die Züge erstarken, damit sie ihnen die immer größere Diminutionsfracht aufladen konnten.  Dazu kam die erhebende Kraft des neuen Glaubens, dem man gar nicht genug mit ehrlichster Kunst dienen konnte!</tei:p><tei:p>Heute aber! Da ist vor allem der schwere Irrtum, der allein schon wider jegliches Talent der heutigen Generation zeugt: diese hält nämlich ein Genie der Vergangenheit grundsätzlich für einen verlorenen Posten der Geschichte, statt es als einen immer auch für die Zukunft giltigen Wert, als ein unwandelbares <tei:hi rend="italic">Ziel</tei:hi> zu verstehen.  Ein Religions-Genie wie Moses ist wahrhaftig nicht <tei:hi rend="bold">{11}</tei:hi> tot, wenn noch heute in seinem Namen Millionen orthodoxer Juden gegen eine Welt zusammenstehen. Kein Zweifel, daß die Juden ihre Bibel gründlich mißverstanden haben – von diesem Mißverständnis wollte sie eben Jesus befreien – u. doch: <tei:hi rend="italic">Selbst der Irrtum</tei:hi>, durch den sie an Mose gekettet waren u. sind, geriet u. gerät ihnen noch zum Heile – so stark ist der Segen eines Genies!  (Deswegen setzte ich hier dieses Beispiel an erster Stelle.)</tei:p><tei:p>Ist Jesus etwa überholbar? Bleibt er den Menschen nicht ein Ziel auch in fernster Zukunft?  Ist Plato überholbar? Was immer die Zeiten den Genies an Substrat nehmen mögen, in ihrem Werk bleibt ein Göttliches übrig, das jeder Zeit spottet! Von diesem göttlich Unzerstörbaren eben ahnt die Welt noch gar nichts! Mir ist kein Zweifel, daß den Deutschen <tei:hi rend="bold">{12}</tei:hi> in künftigen Jahrhunderten nichts übrigbleiben wird, als ihre großen Musik-Genies mit göttlichen Ehren zu pflegen, genau wie die Juden mit dem Alten Testament durch die Zeiten wandern. Wie widerspricht dem aber das Treiben der heutigen deutschen Welt namentlich in so devot amerikanisierenden Städten!  Von Jahr zu Jahr werden neue Genies ausgerufen, denen man dadurch Platz zu machen sucht, daß man die Alten als überholt erklärt u. gewaltsam ins Ausgedinge schickt – nun Sie wissen das alles ja auch – –</tei:p><tei:p>Unbeantwortet blieb bis heute aber die Frage: was nun?  Was soll u. darf, nachdem die „moderne“ Musik abgewirtschaftet hat, in dem Vacuum, dem ersten der Musikgeschichte überhaupt, geschehen?  <tei:hi rend="bold">{13}</tei:hi> Geschieht nichts – bald wird ja auch wirklich nichts mehr geschehen können –, so ist der völlige Untergang der Musik besiegelt.  Daß ein Volk von der Geniekraft der Deutschen binnen wenigen Jahren seine größten musikalischen Geister buchstäblich hinausgeworfen hat, ist umso unbegreiflicher, als es schon von seinem materiellen Instinkt aus (vom geistigen gar nicht zu sprechen) bei so großer materieller Not sich auf den beispiellosen <tei:hi rend="italic">Geldwert</tei:hi> der Meisterliteratur – u. Pflege hätte besinnen müssen!!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich wage zu behaupten, daß sämtliche Industrien der Welt der deutschen Genie-Industrie nicht gleichkommen. Weiß man das, so muß man auch diese Industrie wieder sanieren, wie man heute Banken u. allen Geldwert saniert! Den „Kredit“ – ich fahre fort, die Ausdrücke der Geldzeit anzupassen –, den deutsche <tei:hi rend="bold">{14}</tei:hi> Musik bisher in aller Welt genossen hat, darf doch nicht das deutsche Volk selbst untergraben.  Es hat die Pflicht, zur Größe jener Geist-Währung mit allen Kräften zu stehen.  Kann das aber noch geschehen? Ich sage: Ja! Nur dürfen darüber nicht die ? - Menschen entscheiden, die von all den Dingen nichts wissen.</tei:p><tei:p>So z. B. wäre nichts einfacher, als schon in den untersten Schulklassen mit dem Hören-Lehren von Terz-, Quart-, Oktavzügen in den Volksliedern, Choralmelodien, in den kleinen Uebungen, in Dussek, Clementi u. a. zu beginnen. Dies käme erst <tei:hi rend="bold">{15}</tei:hi> dem Verfahren gleich, wie in den Schulen die Sprache auf grammatische Begriffe u. Zusammenhänge gestellt wird. Tausende Kinder, die sonst der Musik verloren gehen, könnten ihr neu gewonnen werden u. den Kunst-Humus bilden<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn22">  Schenker uses the concept of “humus“ notably in “Von der Sendung des deutschen Genies,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</tei:hi>, Heft 1 (1921), pp. 3–21;  Eng. trans. by Ian Bent (New York: Oxford University Press, 2004), pp. 3–20. </tei:note> den Sie suchen. Wäre Musik nicht eben diese ärmste u. am meisten mißverstandene aller Künste, vogelfrei für jedermann, glauben Sie, daß ich nicht schon längst vom Berliner oder Wiener Ministerium zu Rate gezogen worden wäre? Schließlich bin ich, wofür mein Lebenswerk zeugt, doch einer von den wenigen Morgans<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn23">  Presumably an allusion to John Pierpont Morgan, Jr. (1867–1943), American financier, son of the investment banker, art collector, philanthropist, and contributor to the New York Metropolitan Museum of Art John Pierpont Morgan, Sr. (1837–1913);  creator in 1924 of the Pierpont Morgan Library in New York in memory of his father and to house the latter’s library and collection, and philanthropist in his own right.  This is part of the larger financial metaphor that Schenker is creating in this section of the letter.  </tei:note> in der heutigen Musik – zieht man Morgan nicht zu Rate in allen Nöten? Warum ist <tei:hi rend="italic">Der</tei:hi> oder Jener zu feig, mich um Rat zu fragen, fürchten sie, daß ich ihnen etwas zumute, was <tei:hi rend="bold">{16}</tei:hi> sie überschreitet?</tei:p><tei:p>Kurz: Alle Praktiken, mit denen man den Banken aufzuhelfen sucht, müßten auch für die Musik gelten. Den „Amstelbänklern“ müßte schließlich das Handwerk gelegt werden!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn24">  The Amstel Bank was founded in the Netherlands in 1921.  It had ties to the Österreichische Credit-Anstalt, the bank founded by the Rothschild family. </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Für Wien im besonderen wüßte ich eine glänzende Sanierung (auch ohne Genf, Basel, Paris<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn25">  The allusion of all three locations is perhaps to Stravinsky;  alternatively, Schenker might perhaps mean: Geneva = Stravinsky;  Basel = Paul Sacher?;  Paris = Debussy and others.  </tei:note>). Ich habe den Vorschlag schon oft vorgebracht (im Cons.,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn26">  i.e. the Vienna Conservatory, Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst.   </tei:note> vor Hammerschlag<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn27">  Perhaps János Hammerschlag (1885–1954), Hungarian composer, music critic, and pioneering early music specialist, who founded the chamber music ensemble Musik der Vergangenheit in 1923, and taught composition, music history and organ at the National Conservatory in Budapest.  </tei:note> u. A.): Statt sich verzweifelt z. B. an irgendeinen Todestag zu klammern, wäre es selbst für eine Fremdenverkehrsindustrie viel ergiebiger, <tei:hi rend="bold">{17}</tei:hi> wenn Wien nach Bayreut[h]er Muster ein „Festspielhaus“ für seine Musik-Götter auferbaute, in dem alljährlich ein erlesenes, aus den besten Instrumentalisten der Welt gebildetes Orchester in <tei:hi rend="italic">kanonischer Weise</tei:hi> ihre großen Schöpfungen darböte. Einer wie Sie sollte die Reihe eröffnen u. für den Nachwuchs sorgen, so daß die Tradition in die Zeiten fortwirkte!  In aller Welt wüßte man dann: Nur in Wien könne man die Meisterwerke am besten hören!  Salzburg behielte seine eigene Mozart-Note, die es dann gar nicht mehr zu verfälschen brauchte.</tei:p><tei:p>Und noch manchen anderen Weg gäbe es, die Musik zu sanieren!   [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from p. <tei:hi rend="bold">17v</tei:hi>:</tei:hi>  Ausgemacht ist nur: Wie die Geldkalamitäten wieder nur durch Geld saniert werden können, so eine Musikkalamität nur wieder nur durch Musik. (Homöopathische Kuren!). Kein Paneuropa, keine Politik, – nur die <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">restitutio in integrum</tei:hi></tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn28">  <tei:hi rend="italic">restitutio in integrum</tei:hi>:  legal term (shades of Schenker's legal training), the restoration of something to its previous (or original) condition, a principle of Roman Law enshrined in the <tei:hi rend="italic">Corpus Juris Civilis</tei:hi> (Justinian I, 529–34), one of the primary guiding principles behind the awarding of damages in common law negligence claims.   </tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">unser</tei:hi>[<tei:hi rend="italic">er</tei:hi>] großen Kunst kann helfen!]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{18}</tei:hi> Haben Sie gehört, daß man z. B. einen gotischen Dom wegen heute geänderter Auffassung in religiösen oder baulichen Sachen in eine „moderne“ Kirche umbauen wollte? Noch zeugt jeder stolze gotische Dom für die Vergangenheit wie nicht minder auch für die Gegenwart – mit welchem Rechte wagen sich Auffassungen ändernd, fälschend an die gotischen Dome in der Musik?!</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in Heinrich Schenker's hand:</tei:hi>]
Versäumen Sie mich nicht zu verständigen, wenn Sie einmal in Wien sind! Dann reden wir weiter über diesen Stoff.</tei:p><tei:p>Ihnen u Ihrer Fr. Gemahlin herzlichste Grüße von uns Beiden</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr 
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">H Sch</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn29">  The appended note from Jeanette Schenker has been omitted from this second version, but can seen at the end of the first version ("According to my interpretation, I would have been able to do this tomorrow instead of today into the late hours. [/] Yours, Lie-Lie").  </tei:note>
13. XI. 31</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten draft letter from Schenker to Furtwängler, second version, in Jeanette Schenker’s hand, dated November 13, 1931</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">no address or salutation</tei:hi>]<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Your gesture of sympathy<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> gave me great pleasure.  This summer, I followed the instructions of my doctors, who strenuously demanded that I give my eyes a rest.  My battle over the <tei:hi rend="italic">Eroica</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> had been waged rather too heroically on my part.  Insufficient time!  I was to do only very little writing and reading, no matter how hard this was for me, as someone who has experienced no let-up in work since my thirteenth year of life.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  I held myself to this injunction, and see myself amply rewarded by the restoration of my eyesight.  (There is still room for caution.)</tei:p><tei:p>Our dear Dr. Weisse’s<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> successes really do exceed all expectations.  Even just immediately before his departure,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> he spoke once at the Music Pedagogical Association<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> in Vienna [and] enthused his colleagues, <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> without being able to carry them off as he would have liked, for their own sakes, to be able to do.  Weisse then also spoke in the concert hall in Hamburg with dazzling success.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/>  As evidence of his success in Hamburg I am enclosing herewith a <tei:hi rend="italic">review</tei:hi> by <tei:hi rend="italic">Herman Roth</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> who has taken over Pfohl’s<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> place at the <tei:hi rend="italic">Hamburger Nachrichten</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> because I seem to recall that you have been acquainted with Roth since Munich days.</tei:p><tei:p>I very much give Roth credit that after a lull of so many years he has, as in former times, very agreeably become active once again in my cause.  Only the gaffe at the end of the article, where even he speaks erroneously of an “abstraction,” obliged me to write him a letter setting him straight.  It is really incomprehensible to me <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> how musicians with the examples of my right thinking available to them can attribute such "abstraction" to me!  Never and nowhere have I ever said that all good composing always takes the Ursatz and its 3rd-, 5th- or octave-progression as its point of departure, and that it then continues to propagate itself through the diminutions of the layers until, hey presto!, you finish up with, e.g., a new <tei:hi rend="italic">Eroica</tei:hi>!  That is not the way it is.  The image of the Ursatz and its layers that I offer has its logic only in the connection to a content, whereby it is completely immaterial whether one views it as moving from the simplest thing <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> in the background to the most colorful thing in the foreground, or conversely from the most colorful in the foreground to the simplest in the background.  That indicates at the same time that the background is present always and everywhere in the foreground, i.e. the background proceeds always in tandem with the foreground.</tei:p><tei:p>But the “chronological dimension” of <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> actual creation is quite another matter.  This absolutely does not comply with that “logical” progression as fully as the image in the mind of the person who has misunderstood it seems to say.  Rather, in the context of a gift for improvisation, the composer’s imagination is secretly set on fire by some kind of sweeping intuitive move.  The latter can be whatever he wishes;  the only crucial thing is that at the very moment a growth process gets underway, what is burgeoning submits itself to that selfsame “logic” that adheres to my image:  It is as if a masterwork composed itself into the spaces of 3rd, 5th, or octave!  Artists who work with language can also confirm this process from their own creative activity.  They, too, operate <tei:hi rend="bold">{6r}</tei:hi> with a certain something that causes the foreground to grow in conformity with the simplest foundation.  This feeling is definitively no "abstraction," if it expresses itself in tangible form in the composition.</tei:p><tei:p>The incapacity of today’s composers to [create] a true masterwork can be explained in historical terms precisely in that they have lost that "something."   Through increasing complicity, through commercialization, and above all through false teaching, the improvisatory impulse, hitherto greatly cherished, has been killed off, [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from p. <tei:hi rend="bold">6v</tei:hi>:</tei:hi>  [that impulse] which bears as if effortlessly the brunt of the work of creation, and spares the composer, so to speak, the labor of combining the small components.  Perforce, he confined himself accordingly within the temporal dimension] to inventing short "motives"—the master composers know nothing of this sort of motive—which he then for the first time extended  by means of mechancial repetition occupying himself with "fashioning" through augmentation, diminution, inversion, etc.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{7r}</tei:hi> With this dreary mechanical working, the eye for the larger-scale interconnections was lost, in his own creativity as sadly also for such [interconnections] that are inscribed in the masterworks!</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from p. <tei:hi rend="bold">7v</tei:hi>:</tei:hi> Now back to Weisse's successes.  In New York, he managed in no time at all to win over the entire teaching faculty of the Mannes Conservatory<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> to his way of thinking  and to my cause.  All the teachers, most notably the previous theory professor in the post,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> are familiarizing themselves with the new theory in regular lessons under his direction.  Even Mr. Wedge,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/> the Director of the Institute for Musical Art,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn15"/> who was teaching according to my books at an even earlier stage, has allied himself with him.   I venture now to say that a "Schenker Institute" like that in Hamburg<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn16"/> (which was the first of its kind in the world) has been opened in the U. S. A.</tei:p><tei:p>I endorse your opinion that all is up with modern music (are you perhaps familiar with the article by Stravinsky in the <tei:hi rend="italic">Baseler National Zeitung</tei:hi> of November 3, 1931?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn17"/>), and thus the articles that you published during the summer and fall in the <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue Freie Presse</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn18"/>  It gladdens my heart that you have after all resolved to pin your colors to the mast and show confused <tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> musicians and friends the way of music.</tei:p><tei:p>Your call to <tei:hi rend="italic">Wagner</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn18"/> is really in keeping with the times.  Certainly it ought to and must be stated in criticism of this giant spirit from the loftier vantage-point of the yet greater masters of instrumental music in all seriousness that "Leitmotive" = "motive," see above.  [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from p. <tei:hi rend="bold">8v</tei:hi>:</tei:hi> Thus, for example, the disadvantages of a motive-based technique (see above) recur also in his Leitmotive technique.  [Leitmotives] work counter to any synthesis, even the synthesis of a "music drama"!  (One might almost see in Wagner's Leitmotives an anticipation of the flashbacks used in film so copiously these days.]  But none of this enters the heads of today's generation, for even in his own day it [i.e. Wagner’s work] was given only once and will never be given again.</tei:p><tei:p>In <tei:hi rend="italic">Verdi's</tei:hi> entire output, I would not know eight measures that I would like to make a fuss about—just as continues to be possible perhaps in Smetana, Dvořák, and others.  Still today he barely satisfies the banal appetite for “melody” of Werfel<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn19"/> and his comrades. <tei:hi rend="bold">{9}</tei:hi>  What the earliest Italian composers wrote still benefitted even our masters, whereas Verdi is by contrast of no artistic value.</tei:p><tei:p>You yourself (as also Hubermann<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn20"/>) have finally declared in the full blaze of publicity that the musical community is in the process of disintegration.   You have also quite excellently adduced the cause of that, insofar as it is to be sought in the nature of radio and recordings.</tei:p><tei:p>But an even more important cause seems to me to lie in the lack of relationship to the production of our great masters that has been going on now for 200 years.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn21"/>  Centuries of music <tei:hi rend="bold">{10}</tei:hi> were required before the emergence of Handel and Bach!  It would have been impossible for these two geniuses to appear, for example, as early as the third or fourth century of our era.  The feeling for the linear progressions had first to gain strength in the practice of the art, in order that they could shoulder the even greater freights of diminution.  Thereafter, the new belief for the first time attained its edifying full power—the belief to which people just could not pay sufficient service with the most noble art!</tei:p><tei:p>But today!  There, above all, lies the grievous error, which in itself alone testifies against any talent whatsoever on the part of today’s younger generation:  the latter considers a genius from the past as fundamentally a long-lost entry in the leger of history instead of understanding it as something also enduringly valid for the future, as an immutable goal to strive for.  A genius from the world of religion such as Moses is truly not <tei:hi rend="bold">{11}</tei:hi> dead when still today in his name millions of orthodox Jews stand fast against a whole world.  There is no doubt that the Jews fundamentally misunderstand the Bible—this is exactly the misunderstanding from which Jesus wanted to free them—and yet, <tei:hi rend="italic">the error itself</tei:hi>, through which they are chained to Moses, redounded—and still redounds—to their benefit.  That is how strong the blessing of a genius is! (This is why I place this example first here.)</tei:p><tei:p>Is it possible for Jesus to be surpassed?  Does he not remain the goal of all men, even into the remotest future?  Is it possible for Plato to be surpassed?  However much successive ages may take of these geniuses' substrate, there remains in their work a godlike element that disdains each age!  Of this godlike indestructability the world has not the remotest inkling!  I am in no doubt whatsoever that there will be nothing left for Germans <tei:hi rend="bold">{12}</tei:hi> in future centuries to do other than to cherish the musical geniuses with exactly that godlike honor with which the Jews wander through the ages with the Old Testament.  But how the pursuits of today’s German world contradict that, especially in the so assiduously Americanized cities!  From year to year, new geniuses are proclaimed, for whom people try to make room so that the old geniuses can be declared superannuated and packed off into retirement. — But then, you know all this, too — —</tei:p><tei:p>What remains unanswered to this day, however, is the question:  What now?  What should and ought to happen now that “modern” music has been ruinously mismanaged, in the vacuum, the first such ever in the history of music?  <tei:hi rend="bold">{13}</tei:hi> If nothing happens—soon it will not be possible for anything to happen at all—the total extinction of music will be sealed.  That a people of the power of genius of the Germans has literally within the space of a few years discarded its greatest musical spirits is all the more inconceivable since it, out of material (to say nothing whatsoever of spiritual) instinct, [and] overtaken by such great material need, ought already to have contemplated the unparalleled <tei:hi rend="italic">monetary value</tei:hi> of the master-repertory – and cultivation!!</tei:p><tei:p>I dare to assert that all the industries in the world do not compare with the German industry of genius.  Once that is recognized, then this industy, too, must again be recapitalized, just as banks and other monetary values are being recapitalized today!    It is imperative that the German people do not themselves undermine the “credit”—I make progress in adapting to the expressions of the monetary era—which German <tei:hi rend="bold">{14}</tei:hi> music has enjoyed throughout the world up to now.  They have the duty to stand up with all their might for the greatness of that spiritual currency.  But is there still any possibility of this happening?  I say: Yes!  Only it must not be the ? — people who make the decisions on this, for they know nothing about these matters.</tei:p><tei:p>So, for example, nothing would be simpler than to begin as early as the lowest school classes with teaching and listening for 3rd-, 4th-, and octave -progressions in folksong, chorale melodies, in small exercises—Dussek, Clementi, and others.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{15}</tei:hi> This would equate with the method whereby language is taught in schools on the basis of grammatical concepts and relationships.   Thousands of children, who are otherwise lost to music, could be won over anew to it in this way and form the artistic humus that you, too, obviously seek.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn22"/>  If music were not simply the poorest and most misunderstood of all the arts, outlawed for everyone, do you not think that I might long ago have been called upon by the Berlin or Vienna Ministry as a consultant?  After all, I am, as my life’s work attests, one of the very few Morgans<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn23"/> in today’s music—does one not consult Morgans in all times of need?  Why is <tei:hi rend="italic">this</tei:hi> or that person too cowardly to seek advice from me;  are they afraid that I might demand something of them that <tei:hi rend="bold">{16}</tei:hi> they could not fulfill?</tei:p><tei:p>In short, all practices that seek to help out the banks ought to be valid also for music.  A stop must at last be put to the “Amstelbank” people!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn24"/></tei:p><tei:p>For Vienna in particular I would have in mind a glittering recapitalization, without Geneva, Basel, [or] Paris.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn25"/>  I have often put my suggestion forward in the past (in the Conservatory,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn26"/> before Hammerschlag<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn27"/> and others).  Instead of clinging desperately, for example, to some particular death-date, it would be far more profitable, even for the foreign tourist industry, <tei:hi rend="bold">{17r}</tei:hi> if Vienna were to build a “Festival Playhouse” for its musical gods along the lines of Bayreuth in which, annually, a hand-picked orchestra made up of the best instrumentalists in the world were to present their great works in <tei:hi rend="italic">canonical fashion</tei:hi>.  One such as youself ought to open the series and take care of its subsequent growth, so that the tradition would continue to be effective over time!   People throughout the world would then know:  only in Vienna can one hear the masterworks to best advantage!  Salzburg would retain its own particular Mozartian character, which it would no longer ever need to falsify, because Vienna would be taking over part of the task.</tei:p><tei:p>And there would still be many another way of recapitalizing music! [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from p. <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="bold">17v</tei:hi></tei:hi>:</tei:hi> what has to be made clear is this:  just as monetary calamities can be recapitalized only through money, so also a musical calamity can be recapitalized only through music.  (Homoepathic cures!)  No Pan-Europe, no politics—only the <tei:hi rend="italic">restitutio in integrum</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn28"/> of <tei:hi rend="italic">our</tei:hi> great art can help!]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{18} </tei:hi>Have you heard that, for example, people wanted to convert a Gothic cathedral into a “modern” church because today's interpretation of religious or architectural matters has changed?  Every proud Gothic cathedral stands as a witness for the past, and no less also for its own time.  What right do interpretations, changing, falsifying, have to tinker with the Gothic cathedrals of Music?!</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in Heinrich Schenker's hand:</tei:hi>]
Do not neglect to let me know whenever you are in Vienna!  Then we can talk more about this matteris.</tei:p><tei:p>Most cordial greetings from us both to you and your wife,</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  H. Sch.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn29"/>
November 13, 1931</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>