<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OC 30/122-124 : 7-8-28 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  In the public domain.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2007.
© Translation William Drabkin, 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1928-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-1938) - -Oster, Ernst (1938-c.1939)—New York Public Library (c.1939-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: in the public domain; Image: New York Public Library, New York; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 07/08/1928 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Dunn ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten copy or draft letter from Schenker to Dunn, in Jeanette Schenker's hand, dated July 8, 1928</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-05-08</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Thanks D for birthday greetings;  welcomes him as a fighter for his cause;  discusses relationship of strict counterpoint to free composition;  declares enthusiasm for D’s forthcoming book on orchestration.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Dunn, John Petrie;birthday greetings;  strenger Satz;  strict counterpoint;  freier Satz;  free composition;  music examples;  Wagner;  Bruckner;  Wolf, Hugo;  Brahms;  orchestration</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten copy or draft of letter from Schenker to Dunn, in Jeanette Schenker’s hand, dated July 8, 1928</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Galtür den 8.7.28<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> Jeanette left the date blank: the numbers “8.7.28” were filled in by S. </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Verehrter Herr Professor Dunn</tei:p><tei:p>Für die Aufmerksamkeit Ihrer liebervollen [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Erinnerung, namentlich aber für die Uebersendung Ihres Bildes sage ich Ihnen meinen wärmsten Dank.  Nun stehen Sie auch vor meinen Augen u. erfreuen mir das Herz als ein tapferer Mitkämpfer an der Front wider ein vielleicht hoffnungslos verlottertes Zeitalter.  Freilich, daß unser Kampf u. Sieg, der nicht ausbleiben kann, das Gesicht der späteren u. spätesten Geschlechter formen wird, gerade darüber hege ich nicht den mindesten Zweifel. [. <tei:hi rend="italic">changed to</tei:hi> ,] wir dürfen uns ihrer künftigen Freude schon heute schadlos halten gegenüber den in Dunkelheit Lebenden[,] wenn wir nicht Trost u. Freude in uns selbst fänden.</tei:p><tei:p>Was Sie mir von Ihrem Herrn Collegen erzählen zeigt den Sitz der Krankheit an:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> In his previous letter (OJ 10/13, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7"> In his previous letter, D had indicated that he and his wife were hoping to attend the Bayreuth Festival in the summer of 1929, and to make a side-trip to visit the Schenkers.</tei:note>, June 16, 1928), D had noted that his Edinburgh University students had to learn strict counterpoint from a pedantic colleague.  The music examples in S’s reply here correspond to those in D’s letter.</tei:note> Der Geist des strengen Satzes, der ehedem sehr leibhaftig [(]wenn auch theoretisch nicht ganz  bewußt) die Wirklichkeit der Komposition leitete, ist zu einem Schulgespenst geworden.  Man weiß nicht, ob der strenge Satz überhaupt lebt, man erkennt ihn weder im Hinter- noch im Vordergrund obgleich er überall zu sehen wäre als im ewig Unabänderliches über allen Veränderungen.  Doch gemach, der “Freie Satz” wird auch da <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Hilfe leisten.  Wie glücklich würde sich Ihr Herr College fühlen, ja fühlen müssen, wenn er begriffe, daß der freie Satz oft genug sich gleichsam hinter die ewig in sich ruhende Unschuld des strengen Satzes versteckt, um zu Zwecken einer besseren Auskomponierung so:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example</tei:hi>]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> Two-part counterpoint in whole notes: g^2^/g^1^ moving to e^2^/c^2^. (A treble clef is understood.)</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>zu setzen, statt</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example</tei:hi>]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> Two-part counterpoint in whole notes: g^2^/g^1^ moving to e^2^/c^2^/g^1^, with the lower g^1^s tied. (A treble clef is understood.)</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>unbekümmert darum, ob auch im ersten Falle das Ohr zur Annahme einer bloßen Umgehung des 6/4-Akkordes neigt.  Das ist ja der Sinn u. die Aufgabe des Kontrapunkts, einen Intervallenlauf wie jenseits von aller Deutung stellen.  Man stellt sich dumm[,] schreibt im Sinne des Kontrapunkts Intervall um Intervall u. tut vor sich selbst als wüßte man nicht, was ihre Folge bedeutet.  Aber diese schöne Verstellung schöpft man eben aus dem Kontrapunkt selbst, der zunächst jede Deutung ja wirklich ablehnt.  Für die Auskomponierung um wieviel bequemer ist doch die Folge 8–3. wobei die 8 wie die 3 wiederum reich u. wie selbständig ausgearbeitet werden können – u. darauf nur darauf kommt es ja an. –, als die steife 6/4-Summe, die die ehemalige 8 u. 3 in sich verschlingt.  Von diesem Tric[k] lebt ja alle Erzählungskunst unserer Meister: sie schreiben immer nur sozusagenen ihren <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Kontrapunkt[;]  unsere Sache ist es zu wissen, was er sagt, obgleich der Kontrapunkt tut, als täte er sonst gar nichts als Intervalle hervorbringen.</tei:p><tei:p>Das Werk[,] das Sie vorhaben,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> A treatise on orchestration; see D’s letter of June 16, 1928 (OJ 10/13, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7"> In his previous letter, D had indicated that he and his wife were hoping to attend the Bayreuth Festival in the summer of 1929, and to make a side-trip to visit the Schenkers.</tei:note>), and note 3.</tei:note> würde ich mit größter Freude begrüßen.  Der angedeutete Inhalt ist sehr reich u. treffend.  Zehn Jahre lang habe ich einem unserer namhaften Dirigenten<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6"> This is, almost certainly, Wilhelm Furtwängler.  S first met him nine years before, in 1919;  his diary entries record Furtwängler’s  championing of the music of Richard Strauss and Bruckner, and his “ignorance of sonata form” (see Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Nach Tagebüchern …</tei:hi> (1985), p. 116).</tei:note> gegenüber wiederholt, daß ja die Orchester-Behandlung der Heutigen abscheulich ist u. die klassische in gar nichts noch erreicht, geschweige übertrifft (trotz gegenteiligem Schein).  Er glaubte es nur nicht, da er zu Wagner, Bruckner und Hugo Wolf gehörend, meinen Beweisen sich nicht erschließen konnte.  Doch eines Tages – nach 10 Jahren – gestand er mir plötzlich bei einem gemeinsamen Mittagessen daß er sich glücklich fühlte[,] wenn er eine Brahms-Partitur zu dirigiren habe, den die neueren Partituren seien einfach unerträglich (Brahms galt als unfähiger Orchester-Schreiber).<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> A treatise on orchestration; see D’s letter of June 16, 1928 (OJ 10/13, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7"> In his previous letter, D had indicated that he and his wife were hoping to attend the Bayreuth Festival in the summer of 1929, and to make a side-trip to visit the Schenkers.</tei:note>), and note 3.</tei:note>  Für Sie arbeitet ebenfalls die Zeit: schreiben Sie das Buch u. wie der eine Dirigent in meinem Falle wird einmal die &lt;strike&gt;A&lt;/strike&gt;^a^usschlaggebende Musikerschaft ihre Irrtümer einsehen – also heraus.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit der Aussicht, die Sir mir u. meiner Frau bieten, ich meine die Aussicht eines Wiedersehens im Bayreuthjahr<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7"> In his previous letter, D had indicated that he and his wife were hoping to attend the Bayreuth Festival in the summer of 1929, and to make a side-trip to visit the Schenkers.</tei:note> haben Sie uns die größte Freude bereitet – wir werden Sie mahnen. Nun von Haus zu Haus allerbeste Grüße Ihr ergebenster   H S.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten copy or draft of letter from Schenker to Dunn, in Jeanette Schenker’s hand, dated July 8, 1928</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Galtür, July 8, 1928<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Esteemed Professor Dunn,</tei:p><tei:p>For your thoughtfulness in kind words of commemoration [of my 60th birthday], but especially for sending me your picture, I express my warmest thanks to you.  Now you stand before my eyes, too, and cheer my heart as a brave compatriot on the front against an age that has probably deteriorated beyond hope.  That our struggle and victory, which of course cannot fail, will change the face of future generations and beyond, of precisely this I harbour not the slightest doubt;  we may even today rejoice in their future happiness, in opposition to those who live today in darkness, even if we do not find comfort and joy in ourselves.</tei:p><tei:p>What you recount about your colleague points to the heart of the disease.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  The spirit of strict counterpoint, which in former times determined the reality of musical composition in a very substantial way (even if this was not fully understood, from a theoretical point of view), has become a ghost in the school. We do not know whether strict counterpoint is even alive: we recognize it neither in the background nor in the foreground [of today’s music], although it ought to be visible everywhere as something forever immutable in spite of all that changes.  But, have patience, <tei:hi rend="italic">Free Composition</tei:hi> will also <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> be of help here.  How happy your colleague would feel—would indeed have to feel—if he understood that free counterpoint often enough conceals itself, so to speak, behind the eternally blissful innocence of strict counterpoint for the sake of a better elaboration:  thus to give</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example</tei:hi>]<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/></tei:p><tei:p>rather than</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example</tei:hi>]<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>,</tei:p><tei:p>without worrying whether in the first case, too, the ear is inclined to perceive a merely roundabout expression of the 6/4-chord. This is indeed the meaning and the purpose of counterpoint: to present a succession of intervals as though it were disconnected from all interpretation. One pretends to be stupid, writing one interval after the next along the lines of [strict] counterpoint, and imagines that one does not know what their succession means.  But this beautiful pretence is something that is derived from counterpoint itself, which in fact truly refuses all interpretation.  For the elaboration, how much more convenient, in fact, is the succession 8–3, whereby the octave and the 3rd can both be treated independently and be subjected to rich elaboration—and this, and only this, is the point—in comparison with the rigidity of their summation as a 6/4-chord, which swallows up what was once an octave and a third.  This ploy is the source of the entire storytelling art of our masters:  they always write, so to speak, their <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> counterpoint, nothing more;  it is our job to find out what it is saying, although counterpoint behaves as if it did nothing else but generate intervals.</tei:p><tei:p>The work that you have in mind<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> is something that I would welcome with the greatest joy.  The content that you outlined is very rich and to the point.  For ten years I have been repeatedly telling one of our illustrious conductors<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> that the treatment of the orchestra by contemporary composers is abysmal, and in no way reaches the level of the classical masters, let alone exceeds it (in spite of appearances to the contrary).  He simply does not believe it since, being a champion of Wagner, Bruckner and Hugo Wolf, he cannot accept my reasoning.  But one day—after ten years had passed—he suddenly admitted to me, over lunch, that he felt happy when he had a score by Brahms to conduct, for the more recent scores were simply unbearable (Brahms used to be regarded as incapable of writing for the orchestra).  Moreover, time is on your side: get your book published and, as it happened with the one conductor in my case, the important people in the musical world will come to recognize their errors.</tei:p><tei:p>With the prospect that you offer me and my wife, by which I mean the prospect of a get-together in your Bayreuth year,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> you have provided us with the greatest pleasure. We shall urge you [to make good your intention].  And so, with the very best greetings from us to you, Your most devoted  H. S.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>