<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 6/6, [6] : 2-17-18 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  In the public domain
©  Transcription Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin, 2009
©  Translation Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin, 2009
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2009
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Violin, Moriz (1918-1956) - -Heirs of Moriz Violin (1956-197?) - -University of California, Riverside (197? - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker;  Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent and William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 02/17/1918 05:39:22 PM --><!-- MT Tags: "ViolinM ~ HSchenker","ViolinM+V ~ HSchenker","ViolinM+V+F ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated February 17, 1918</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-04-23</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Schenker warns Violin to expect a letter from Vrieslander concerning a contribution to a Festschrift for Schenker's 50th birthday, and then airs a number of grievances against Moriz and Valerie concerning jars of jam, Sunday visits, and insufficient food.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Violin, Moriz;  Vrieslander, Otto;  Festschrift;  birthday;  Hertzka, Emil;  Die letzten fünf Sonaten ... op. 101;  Beethoven;  Violin, Valerie;  Marmelade;  jam;  Violin, Fanny;  Kaffeehaus;  coffee-house;  Glattauer;  Schönbrunn;  Hauser, Friederike;  Popper, Frau;  Guttmann, Sophie</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated February 17, 1918</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Fl!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Writing of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/10, pp. 842-843, February 15, 1918:  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Dein Brief<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  = OJ 14/45, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10"> Violin did, in fact, write an essay in Schenker's honor:  Notebooks containing the twenty-page handwritten text of  "Zu Dr. Heinrich Schenker's 50ten Geburtstage" are among Violin's papers in the Oswald Jonas Memorial Library (OJ 70/53) and the "Schenker Scrapbook" in the Oster Collection (OC, File 2), at page 54.</tei:note>, February 5, 1918.  </tei:note> hat mich sehr überrascht, durch Tonfall u. Inhalt.  Ich will aber Ruhe bewahren u. der Reihe nach, was augenblicklich zu sagen nötig ist, sagen.</tei:p><tei:p>Vor Allem:  Vor wenigen Tagen kam mir von <tei:hi rend="italic">Vrieslander</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.  Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/10, p. 835, February 5, 1918: </tei:note> die <tei:hi rend="italic">Kopie</tei:hi> eines an <tei:hi rend="italic">Hertzka</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="hertzka_emil">Emil Hertzka</ref>.  </tei:note> gleichzeitig abgegangenen Briefes, worin diesem eine „Festschrift" zu meinem 50. Geburtstag (mit Bild),<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  A book of musical studies commemorating Schenker's fiftieth birthday: one of several projects proposed by Otto Vrieslander around this time that came to nothing.  Cf. Hans Weisse's letter of February 26, 1918 (IOJ 15/16, [34].  </tei:note> von verschiedenen Autoren geschrieben, angetragen wird.  Und schon gestern erhielt ich die ergänzende Mittteilung,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6"> Receipt is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/10, p. 841, February 15, 1918: " Von Vrieslander (K.): Hertzka habe „Ja" gesagt u. für die Anregung sogar gedankt; Mitwirkung von Schülern wäre ihm willkommen." ("From Vrieslander (postcard): Hertzka has said 'Yes' and even thanked [him] for the initiative;  contributions by pupils would be welcome to him.")  </tei:note> daß <tei:hi rend="italic">H.</tei:hi> überraschenderweise:  Ja gesagt hat, mit Dank für Anregung u.s.w.  In eben dieser Karte erkundigt sich <tei:hi rend="italic">Vr.</tei:hi> auch nach <tei:hi rend="italic">deiner</tei:hi> Adresse, die ich heute selbstverständlich auch zuschicke.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  This is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/10, p. 842, February 16, 1918:  " An Vrieslander (K.): danke für die auf sich genommene Mühe u. füge die Adressen von Weisse, Violin, Dahms bei." ("To Vrieslander (postcard): [I] thank [him] for the effort he has taken upon himself, and enclose the addresses of Weisse, Violin, [and] Dahms.").  From this can perhaps be deduced that the present letter was written across February 15-17.    </tei:note>  Er dürfte also auch dich um einen Beitrag angehen, was dich aber nicht hindern darf, nach deiner augenblicklichen <tei:hi rend="italic">Möglichkeit</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">allein</tei:hi> den  Entschluß zu fassen.  Nachdem die Sache hinter meinem Rücken geschehen, steht mir nicht zu, ein Urteil darüber abzugeben, was sich nur mehr um eine denkbare Anerkennung von im [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte</tei:hi> in] meinem Interesse getragener Mühen handeln kann.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Schenker recorded in his diary at OJ 2/10, p. 840, February 13, 1918: " An Vrieslander (Br.): danke für seine Absicht, erkläre aber skeptisch bleiben zu müssen u. verweise auf die jüngste Affaire mit Hertzka " ("To Vrieslander (letter): I thank [him] for his intentions, but declare that I must remain skeptical and notify him of the recent spot of bother with Hertzka [. . .]").  </tei:note>  Unter uns kann ich wohl aber sagen:  eben dieses Verlagsgeld hätte <tei:hi rend="italic">H.</tei:hi> lieber auf „op. 101"<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Schenker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven ... op. 101</tei:hi> (Vienna: UE, 1920).  </tei:note> draufschlagen sollen zu <tei:hi rend="italic">Ehren <tei:hi rend="italic">Beeth</tei:hi></tei:hi>'s u. Allen wäre damit doch ohne Zweifel mehr gedient, auch mir selbst.  Sage also flott:  Nein, wenn die Sache nach Nein liegt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10"> Violin did, in fact, write an essay in Schenker's honor:  Notebooks containing the twenty-page handwritten text of  "Zu Dr. Heinrich Schenker's 50ten Geburtstage" are among Violin's papers in the Oswald Jonas Memorial Library (OJ 70/53) and the "Schenker Scrapbook" in the Oster Collection (OC, File 2), at page 54.</tei:note>  So und nun zu deinem Schreiben:</tei:p><tei:p>Nicht nur aber in Ruhe will ich schreiben, sondern zum Voraus will ich ausdrück&lt;sup&gt;lich&lt;/sup&gt; <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> bitten, <tei:hi rend="italic">auch</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">mir</tei:hi> „das Vertrauen, Begreifen u. Verständnis"<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  "Begreifen u. Verständnis":  quoted from OJ 14/45, [10], February 5, 1918, paragraph 5.</tei:note> entgegenzubringen, das ich &lt;sup&gt;dir&lt;/sup&gt;, selbst ohne daß du mich darum erst ersucht [<tei:hi rend="italic">alt from</tei:hi> ersuchst] hättest, nach deinem eigenen Zeugnis entgegengebracht habe.</tei:p><tei:p>Ebenso bitte ich dich, auch mir das Recht auf „Eigenwürde"<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  "Eigenwürde": quoted from OJ 14/45, [??], February 15, 1918, paragraph 2.</tei:note> zuzugestehen, das du für dich in Anspruch nimmst.</tei:p><tei:p>Und damit du in Ruhe lesen kannst, schicke ich das <tei:hi rend="italic">Ergebnis</tei:hi> aus Freundlichkeit voraus u. sage:  du u. deine Frau sind beide etwas <tei:hi rend="italic">lässig</tei:hi> mir gegenüber, eine zwar harmlose Spielart von „Schlampigkeit," um deinen Ausdruck zu gebrauchen, die mir aber dennoch nahelegt, mir es nicht wieder bequem zu machen u. auf Euere Ein- oder besser <tei:hi rend="italic">Nach</tei:hi>sicht genauso zu rechnen, wie ich sie bisher mit einiger Verdrießlichkeit dennoch leistete.</tei:p><tei:p>Mir liegt es vollständig ferne, einen Keil zwischen dich u. deine Frau zu treiben, u. ich habe auch [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] in der Affäre Fanny<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  Click on <ref cRef="violin_fanny">Fanny Violin</ref>.</tei:note> seinerzeit zu genau gesehen, als daß ich etwas Anderes bezwecken könnte, als blos dir meine Haltung zu motivieren u., wie hier öfters wiederholt wurde, dein „Begreifen" selbst für den Fall in Anspruch zu nehmen, wenn dir das Gesagte nicht ganz angenehm &lt;del&gt;ist&lt;/del&gt; &lt;sup&gt;wäre&lt;/sup&gt; (Tragisch ist das Alles nach alldem je eben <tei:hi rend="italic">nicht</tei:hi>, wenn du siehst, daß ich <tei:hi rend="italic">blos dort</tei:hi> hinauswill, wo du selbst stehst, womit dir kein Unrecht geschehen kann).</tei:p><tei:p>Im Einzelnen bedarf dein Brief folgender einfacher Richtigstellungen:  1)  Was das „Thema" anlangt, so war deine Aufregung ganz kindisch.  Es bezieht sich das, auf unser beider Gespräch im Caféhaus.  Ich sagte dir damals (das letzte oder <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> vorletze Mal) - sehr oft sprach ich davon auch deiner Frau gegenüber, u. auch übrigens du selbst schreibst unter 21. XI:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  The item of November 21, [1917] is not known to survive. </tei:note> „So recht offen kann man doch nur mündlich reden", daß mir im Hinterlande es schwer fällt, dir oder den Anderen im Felde zu schreiben, da ich mit <tei:hi rend="italic">Boldrio</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15"> "Boldrio":  perhaps a legal expression.  </tei:note> nicht kommen kann, von Eueren Berufssorgen schweigen &lt;del&gt;muß&lt;/del&gt;, meine Freude besser unterdrücken muß (Freuden wollen mitgenossen, nicht blos gelesen werden) u.s.w.   2) daß deine Frau uns die Tasche ins Kaféhaus zu bringen die Freundlichkeit hatte, war ein weniger spontaner Akt, als du offenbar annimmst;  er hängt mit einem Briefe von mir<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn16">  Probably OJ 6/6, [5], December 30, 1917.  </tei:note> zusammen, in dem ich die Gründe darlegte, weshalb wir fürchten, nicht sobald hinauskommen zu können.  3)  Es freut mich, deinem Briefe zu entnehmen, daß du nicht mit einem Wort mich verdächtigst, ich hätte mit Glatt...<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn17">  Click on <ref cRef="glattauer">Glattauer</ref>.  </tei:note> etwa dich mir [<tei:hi rend="italic">alt from</tei:hi> mich] selbst gegenüber gemeint.</tei:p><tei:p>Was für Sinn hätte es aber, deine Beziehung <tei:hi rend="italic">zu Anderen</tei:hi> unter diesem Stichwort zu kritisieren?  Könnte so etwas Gegenstand einer Reklamation <tei:hi rend="italic">von</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">mir</tei:hi> zu <tei:hi rend="italic">dir</tei:hi> bilde?  Unsinn!  Bleibt also übrig, daß ich eben von mir selbst die unverdiente Rolle abtun will, auf die du auch selbst in einem beiläufigen Fragesatz zurückkommst.  In diesem Punkte will ich als dem Kernpunkte &lt;del&gt;will&lt;/del&gt; &lt;del&gt;ich&lt;/del&gt; lieber in Tatsachen sprechen, u. ganz offen, deiner erbetenen Nachsicht von vornherein sicher:</tei:p><tei:p>Ich habe mich bei dir draußen offen gestanden auf 20 Mal etwa 2 Mal wirklich satt essen können, was nach den so anstrengenden Stunden - du weißt ja selbst ein Lied davon, u. mein Lied ist wirklich kakaphoner - keine geringe Zumutung an mein Gehirn war.  Mit einem wirklich unbefangenen Wort:  „bitte, l. Frau Wally,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn18">  Click on <ref cRef="violin_valerie">Valerie Violin</ref>.   </tei:note> ich habe noch Hunger, ich muß noch essen," hätte ich sicher noch was gekriegt, aber es fiel mir das Wort schwer, wenn <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> ich Zeuge war, wie einmal deine eigene Aufregung, auch einmal übrigens der Frau Hauser<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn19">  Click on <ref cRef="hauser_friederike">Friederike Hauser</ref>. </tei:note> nichts zuwege brachte.  Eine Absicht liegt gewiß <tei:hi rend="italic">nicht</tei:hi> vor, das brauchst du mir nicht zu sagen, aber ich erwarte auch, daß du mir nicht den Hunger bestreitest, oder du es taktlos &lt;del&gt;sper&lt;/del&gt; findest, wenn ich davon spreche (Nachsicht!  Wie ich dir, so du mir! s. oben).</tei:p><tei:p>Nun schreibst du aber selbst, deine Frau wäre „geld<tei:hi rend="italic">schlampig</tei:hi>," - muß mich dann aber jenes Versäumnis <tei:hi rend="italic">nicht doppelt</tei:hi> schmerzen u. <tei:hi rend="italic">herabsetzen</tei:hi>: sollten in deinem Hause in Friedenszeiten 8-10 Kronen monatlich eine solche Rolle gespielt haben?  Unmöglich zu denken.</tei:p><tei:p>Oder: In allen, allen Jahren ist es <tei:hi rend="italic">niemals</tei:hi>, sage u. schreibe: niemals vorgekommen, daß wir je zuerst eine Anfrage, irgendeine Erkundigung aus Schönbr.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn20">  Click on <ref cRef="schonbrunn">Schönbrunn</ref>.   </tei:note> erhalten hätten.  Vielmehr waren es wir, die, obgleich älter - u. kannst es mir glauben, meistens doch <tei:hi rend="italic">viel</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">viel</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">beschäftigter</tei:hi> - den Faden fortzuspinnen hätten.  Bedenke ich, daß deine Frau nicht gerne schreibt - das sei ihr gewiß nicht übel genommen &lt;del&gt;werden&lt;/del&gt; -, so weiß ich doch aus so viel Einblick in Familien, daß sie doch zumindest einmal 4-5 Worte schon nur aus purem Gedenken zuerst an uns hätte richten können, wenn sie daran nur gedacht hätte.  (Eben das meine ich!)   Es ist vorgekommen, daß ich selbst einmal 3 Karten schreiben müßten, wo sie dann lachend ins Caféhaus trat u. sich mit den Worten rechtfertigte:  „Ich gebe zu, es war von mir eine arge Schweinerei."</tei:p><tei:p>Oder:  haben wir je Anspruch auf Sonntag Abend erhoben?  doch niemals, weil wir Euch bei Frau <tei:hi rend="italic">H.</tei:hi> wußten u. Euch beiden die Freude von Herzen gönnten.  Aber dann Sonntag Vormittag oder Nachmittag - meine einzige fortlaufende Arbeitszeit, die einzige Ausflugsmöglichkeit (im Kriege friedlich auch <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> mit Einkäufen belastet) habe ich aus purer Schonung des Sonntag Abends Euch doch zur Verfügung gestellt, wenn ich nicht anders hätte das Wiedersehen unmöglich machen wollen.</tei:p><tei:p>Alles wie du siehst Kleinigkeiten, die aber im Laufe der Jahre recht viel Unbequemlichkeiten verursachen.</tei:p><tei:p>Von hier aus fällt aber &lt;sup&gt;auch&lt;/sup&gt; auf die <tei:hi rend="italic">Marmeladengeschichte</tei:hi> ein ganz anderes Licht:  Ich bestreite durchaus nicht den Vorrang der Frau <tei:hi rend="italic">H.</tei:hi> u. jener Frau, der deine Frau verpflichtet ist<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn21">  A Frau Popper, cf. OJ 14/45, [10].  </tei:note> - es ist so, wie ich sage u. keine Ziererei -, aber <tei:hi rend="italic">du selbst</tei:hi> weiß es ja, der mir am 21. XI, mir völlig Ahnungslosem, Marmelade <tei:hi rend="italic">spontan</tei:hi> angetragen.  Dann höre ich von Euch beiden von 150-170 Kg, u. du sagst <tei:hi rend="italic">2 mal</tei:hi> mündlich aufs <tei:hi rend="italic">bestimmteste</tei:hi> die M. zu, u. zw. eine <tei:hi rend="italic">direkte</tei:hi> Sendung über deinen <tei:hi rend="italic">eigenen</tei:hi> Vorschlag.  Und nun frage ich dich:  ist es nicht herabsetztend [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] für mich, ganz ungeziemend, wenn ich schließlich von all der großen Gelegenheit, von deinen u. deine[ r ] Frau Versprechungen zunächst blos <tei:hi rend="italic">ein</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">kleines</tei:hi> Glas Marmelade davontrage?   Ihr brauchtet ja nichts zu sagen - ich maße mir aus Eigenem gewiß solcher Rechte nicht an -, aber tatet Ihrs (u. Augen wir haben doch auch, um zu sehen, Ohren um zu hören,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn22">  cf. <tei:hi rend="italic">Psalm</tei:hi> 115, vs. 4-6 "Sie haben Mäuler und reden nicht, sie haben Augen und sehen nicht, / sie haben Ohren und hören nicht,  sie haben Nasen und riechen nicht, / sie haben Hände und greifen nicht, Füße haben sie und gehen nicht, und kein Laut kommt aus ihrer Kehle." (Luther Bible)</tei:note> was Ihr selbst erzählt), so war es Euere Pflicht, Wort zu halten[.]   Und da schreibst du mir einen Bf. in solchem Tonfall?  Kommt dir „herauszuzahlen"?  Was ist denn das?</tei:p><tei:p>Die Konklusion lautet also:  (s. ob.) Ich muß desgleichen auch selbst tun lernen, u. rechne auf Nachsicht.  Es bleibe Alles beim <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> Alten, nur daß ich mirs ein wenig bequemer machen will, wie es die Zeit u. Umstände fordere.  Und das wirst du wohl begreifen.</tei:p><tei:p>Es ist selbstverständlich, daß ich keinerlei Geschenke solcher Art in einer Zeit wie der gegenwärtigen anzunehmen gesonnen bin - du wirst mich doch nicht zu solchen Kleinigkeiten notzüchtigen? -, um so weniger, als du schreibst: „das Meiste ist gekauft.  Wenn Wally manche <tei:hi rend="italic">geringe</tei:hi> Vorräte hat, so hat sie dieselben während meiner Abwesenheit in entsagungsvoller Lebensweise gesammelt."  Leider weiß ich nicht, <tei:hi rend="italic">wie</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">viel</tei:hi> Marillenmarmelade da war u. was der Inhalt der Tasche - ganz genau, wie wir es ja auch mit der <tei:hi rend="italic">Sophie</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn23">  Click on <ref cRef="guttmann_sophie_nee">Sophie Guttmann</ref>.  </tei:note> halten, haben wir sofort am l. I. die Gegenstände fixiert - an Kosten verursacht hat.  Bei Gelegenheit soll die Gesammte Rechnung mit herzlichsten Dank beglichen werden.</tei:p><tei:p>Nichts für ungut.  Ich habe mir wohl das Recht erworben, ganz offen zu sprechen u. du schuldest mir ganz bestimmt dasselbe, was ich dir an [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] Entgegenkommen, an Verständnis<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn24">  An echo of paragraph 3, which itself echoes Violin's previous letter.  </tei:note> geboten habe.</tei:p><tei:p>Viele Grüße von uns Beiden
Dein
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Heinrich
17. [<tei:hi rend="italic">smudge</tei:hi>] II. 1918</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated February 17, 1918</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Floriz,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Your letter<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> surprised me greatly in tone and content.  I will, however, maintain my composure and say, point by point, what needs to be said at this moment.</tei:p><tei:p>First of all:  a few days ago, I received from Vrieslander<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> a <tei:hi rend="italic">copy</tei:hi> of a letter sent simultaneously to Hertzka<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> proposing to him a "Festschrift" for my fiftieth birthday (with picture),<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> written by various authors.  Yesterday I received the additional information<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> that Hertzka has, astonishingly, said "Yes," with thanks for having taken the initiative, etc.  In this very same postcard, Vrieslander inquires after <tei:hi rend="italic">your</tei:hi> address, which I am of course sending to him today.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>  He will thus be approaching you yourself for a contribution, but this need not prevent you from making up your own mind <tei:hi rend="italic">solely</tei:hi> on the basis of your current <tei:hi rend="italic">commitments</tei:hi>.   Since the matter has ensued behind my back, it is not my place to pronounce a verdict on it, which can only take the form of due recognition of the effort that has been made on my behalf.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/>  Between you and me, though, let me say:  Hertzka would do better to throw the publishing house's money at <tei:hi rend="italic">Op. 101</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> to the <tei:hi rend="italic">greater glory of Beethoven</tei:hi>, and everybody would without question be better served by that--me too.  So just say a quick "No" if that is your inclination.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/>  And so, now on to your letter.</tei:p><tei:p>Not only do I want to maintain my composure while writing, but from the outset I will expressly <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> ask you to show <tei:hi rend="italic">me</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">too</tei:hi>, the  "the trust, sympathy, and understanding"<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> that I myself, by your own witness, showed &lt;sup&gt;you&lt;/sup&gt; without your having first asked it of me.</tei:p><tei:p>Likewise, I ask you to grant me the right to the "self-esteem"<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> that you invoke for yourself.</tei:p><tei:p>And so that you may read with composure, I will place the <tei:hi rend="italic">outcome</tei:hi> right up front, in the spirit of friendship, and say:  you and your wife are both somewhat <tei:hi rend="italic">lax</tei:hi> toward me, an admittedly harmless variety of "carelessness" (to use your own term), which nevertheless encourages me not to take the easy way out, and to count on your understanding, or better your <tei:hi rend="italic">forebearance</tei:hi>, every bit as much as I nevertheless, with some peevishness, previously rendered it [to you].</tei:p><tei:p>The last thing I want to do is drive a wedge between you and your wife, and I saw all too clearly also at the time of the Fanny affair<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> that there was nothing I could hope to achieve other than simply to explain my stance to you and, as has often been reiterated here, to take your "understanding" into consideration even in the case that what I have to say may not be altogether welcome to you. (After all, that is really <tei:hi rend="italic">not</tei:hi> all so very tragic if you see that I want to get away and be <tei:hi rend="italic">merely where</tei:hi> you are, so that no injustice can befall you.)</tei:p><tei:p>In matters of detail, your letter needs the following simple corrections:  (1) As far as "topic" is concerned, the way you got worked up was completely childish.  It goes back to the conversation the two of us had in the coffee-house.  I said to you then (the last or <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> previous time)-- I spoke about it very often to your wife also, and what's more, under [the date] November 21 you write:<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/> "To speak so frankly and openly is something that one can really only do face to face"--that it is hard for me away from the front line to write to you or others in the field since I cannot come with Boldrio,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn15"/> I must be silent about the professional troubles of the two of you [and] must better suppress my joy (joys need to be shared, not just read), etc.  (2) that your wife was so kind as to bring the bag to us in the coffee-house was less of a spontaneous act than you evidently suppose;  it relates to a letter from me<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn16"/> in which I explained the reasons why we feared we could not come out at that time.  (3) I am pleased to see from your letter that you do not for a moment suspect that, in using the name Glatt[auer],<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn17"/> I was referring to your relationship to me.</tei:p><tei:p>But what sense would there have been in criticizing your relationship <tei:hi rend="italic">to others</tei:hi> under this epithet?  Could such a thing constitute the subject of a claim <tei:hi rend="italic">by me against you</tei:hi>?  Sheer nonsense!  Hence it remains for me to undertake myself the relinquishment if the unwarranted role to which even you yourself return to, in a passing interrogative sentence.  On this point, I prefer as the central point to speak in facts, and quite openly, assured at the outset of the forebearance for which you ask:</tei:p><tei:p>I have freely admitted that, when at your place out there [in Schönbrunn?] that I can truly say that I have had enough to eat perhaps twice out of twenty times, which after such strenuous hours [of collaboration]--you have a song to sing about this, and my song is even louder--was no small affront to my brain.  Had I come out quite unabashedly with "Please, Wally<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn18"/> dear, I am still hungry, I need more to eat," I would certainly have got more;  but it was hard for me to say such a thing when <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> I was a witness to how once your own agitation, even once incidentally [that] of Mrs. Hauser,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn19"/> yielded no result. Nothing is intended, to be sure--you do not need to say that to me--but at the same time I expect you not to dispute my hunger, or that you find it tactless when I speak about it. (Forebearance!  Do unto me as I do unto you!  See above.)</tei:p><tei:p>But now you yourself write that your wife is "<tei:hi rend="italic">careless</tei:hi> with money,"-but must not that negligence be <tei:hi rend="italic">doubly</tei:hi> painful and <tei:hi rend="italic">disparaging</tei:hi> to me:  would not eight or ten Kronen a month have played a similar role in your household in times of peace?  An impossible thought.</tei:p><tei:p>Or:  in all the years that have gone by, we were <tei:hi rend="italic">never</tei:hi>--I repeat, never--the first to receive an inquiry, nor any kind of solicitation, from Schönbrunn.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn20"/>  Instead, it was we who, despite being older--and, believe me, mostly <tei:hi rend="italic">far, far busier</tei:hi> -- had to maintain the contact.  Aware as I am that your wife does not like writing--I certainly think no less of her for that --, nevertheless I know perfectly well from all that I have seen of families that she could at least have directed a few words to us first--purely out of thoughtfulness--if only it had crossed her mind.  (That's really what I think!)   There was an occasion when I myself once had to write three postcards, whereupon she came into the coffee-house laughing and justified herself with the words "I admit, it was really rotten of me."</tei:p><tei:p>Besides:  Have we ever laid claim to Sunday evening?  No, never, because we knew you were both at Mrs. Hauser's place, and did not in the least begrudge you both that pleasure.  But then, out of sheer preservation of [your] Sunday evening, I placed Sunday morning or afternoon--my one and only uninterrupted work time, [and] the only possibility for getting out (in wartime as well as peace, taken up <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> with shopping) at your disposal, if I were not otherwise to make it impossible for us to see each other again.</tei:p><tei:p>As you see, these are all trifling matters, but over the course of the years they give rise to a great many awkwardnesses.</tei:p><tei:p>But ^even^ the <tei:hi rend="italic">jam saga</tei:hi> at this point takes on a quite different aspect:  Not for a moment do I question the precedence of Mrs. Hauser or that other lady to whom your wife is obligated<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn21"/> -- it is just as I say, and no posturing --, but <tei:hi rend="italic">you yourself</tei:hi>, who on November 21 offered the jam <tei:hi rend="italic">spontaneously</tei:hi>, completely out of the blue, know it full well.  Then I hear from the two of you about 150-170 kilograms, and you yourself <tei:hi rend="italic">twice</tei:hi> to my face <tei:hi rend="italic">most emphatically</tei:hi> promise me the jam, what's more a <tei:hi rend="italic">direct</tei:hi> delivery at <tei:hi rend="italic">your</tei:hi> suggestion.  And now I ask you:  is it not disparaging for me, downright improper, when ultimately out of this big opportunity, after your wife's and your promises, all I come away with is <tei:hi rend="italic">one</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">measly</tei:hi> jar of jam?  There was no need for you to say anything at all--I certainly do not arrogate such rights to myself--, but you did do so (and we do have eyes to see with, ears to hear with,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn22"/> as you yourself say), so it was your duty to keep to your word.  And then you go and write me a letter in such a tone?  Is it time for you to "pay up"?  What is it, then?</tei:p><tei:p>The conclusion, thus, is:  (see above.)  I too must likewise learn to act, and I count on forebearance.  Let things remain as they were, <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> except that it will make me a little more comfortable as it demands time and [the right] conditions.  And that you will well appreciate.</tei:p><tei:p>It goes without saying that I am not prepared to accept any presents whatsoever of this kind in a time such as the present.--you will surely not violate me with such small items--all the less since you write: "most were purchased.  If Wally has many <tei:hi rend="italic">small</tei:hi> provisions, in her self-denying style of life she has accumulated them during my absence."  Unfortunately, I do not know <tei:hi rend="italic">how much</tei:hi> apricot jam there was, or how much the contents of the bag cost--in exact terms,  as we did with Sophie,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn23"/> too, settling matters right away on January 1--gave rise to costs.  The entire bill will then be settled with cordial thanks.</tei:p><tei:p>No hard feelings.  I have permitted myself to speak entirely frankly, and you owe me nothing less than what I have offered you by way of courtesy and understanding.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn24"/></tei:p><tei:p>Greetings from us both,
Yours,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  Heinrich</tei:p><tei:p>February 17 [<tei:hi rend="italic">smudge</tei:hi>], 1918</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>