<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:[OJ 6/6, [8] : 11-9-18 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  In the public domain
©  Transcription Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin, 2009
©  Translation Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin, 2009
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin 2009
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Violin, Moriz (1918-1956) - -Heirs of Moriz Violin (1956-197?) - -University of California, Riverside (197? - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker;  Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent and William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 11/09/1918 02:58:10 PM --><!-- MT Tags: "ViolinM ~ HSchenker","ViolinM+V ~ HSchenker","ViolinM+V+F ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated November 9, 1918</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-05-07</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Schenker reports news from Russia, Austria, Switzerland, and Poland, and comments on the current political situation.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Violin, Moriz;  Bezugschein;  purchasing voucher;  Russia;  Arbeiter-Zeitung;  Adler, Victor;  Renner, Karl;  Austria;  Switzerland;  Entente;  Germany;  America;  Poland;  Hungarians;  Wilson, Edith Bolling Gat;  Kaiser;  Emperor;  Junker</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter by Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated November 9, 1918</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Fl!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  The writing of this letter is not recorded in Schenker's diary for November 9 at OJ 2/12, p. 2012, the entry reading:  "Abdankung des Kaisers u. Kronprinzen. - Revolution in ganz Deutschland. - Maßlose Waffenstillstandsbedingungen.-  Czechen plündern in Deutsch-Böhmen." ("Abdication of the Emperor and Crown Princes. - Revolution throughout Germany. -- Unbridled conditions of cease-fire. - Czechs plunder German Bohemia.")  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Anbei das „beredete" Dokument, genannt Bezugsschein:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Bezugsschein: a voucher, issued during the War, to enable the civilian population to acquire goods without the exchange of money.</tei:note>  Und nun walte damit, vielmehr laß mit Erfolg walten.   („Gilt nur bis 9/XI": steht auf dem Schein).</tei:p><tei:p>Vom Tage registriere ich, weil ich schon dabei bin:</tei:p><tei:p>1)  In Rußland weinen bereits die Arbeiter, es gehe ihnen schlechter, wie vordem;  „was haben sie davon, daß sie Alles zu eigen haben, wann u.s.w.?"  Natürlich, jeder bleibt dort, wo er war, u. aus dem Arbeiter wird von selbst kein Unternehmen, geschweige etwas noch Höheres, Besseres.  Die „Arbeit,"<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="arbeiterzeitung"><tei:hi rend="italic">Arbeiterzeitung</tei:hi></ref>.  </tei:note> die stets Grüße hinübersandte („unseren Brüdern" maulte Adler,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="adler_victor">Victor Adler</ref>.  </tei:note> Renner<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="renner_karl">Karl Renner</ref>.  </tei:note>)  schweigt sich über die Katastrophe aus . . .<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  "Natürlich [...] aus . . ." (Naturally [...] catastrophe . . .): single side-lined to left by Schenker.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>2)  In Österr. geht Alles drunter, vor lauter „Selbstbuß[e]." - ein echt amerikanischer Sprengstoff war das.</tei:p><tei:p>3)  In der Schweiz weint man schon jetzt:  Amerika hat schwarze Listen durchgeführt u. <tei:hi rend="italic">zwingt</tei:hi> zu Handel.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  "zwingt" (compels): double-underlined by Schenker.  </tei:note>  Man war dort für die Entente<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  (Triple) Entente:  the alignment between Great Britain, France, and Russia agreed in 1907 as a counter force to the Triple Alliance of Germany, Austria-Hungary, and Italy.  </tei:note> („guter Ton") u. fürchtete Deutschlands Sieg.  <tei:hi rend="italic">Jetzt</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">bereut</tei:hi> man diese Gesinnung von gestern, weil Deutschl. stets an der Konkurrenz festhielt, aber die Gefahren u. Risiken trug, u. nicht Gewalt anwendete, von der billigeren Leistung abgesehen!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi>
4)  Polen hat seine Gemeinheit „selbstständig" etabliert<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  "etablieren": in using a French-derived verb, Schenker is further deriding the notion of Polish independence.</tei:note>, - von was befreit?  pah!  ihre Vorfahren u.s.w..  Bald &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;werden&lt;/sup&gt; auch sie weinen, nebst den Ungarn („eigene Armee" „los von Osterr." u.s.w.) u. ein europäischer Sklavenmarkt, betrieben von Amerika (Wilsons Frau<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Click on <ref cRef="wilson_edith_bolling">Edith Bolling Gat Wilson</ref>.  </tei:note> hat ein Versatzgeschäft gehabt) wird sich auftun, u. nur Deutschland wird den Kopf behalten, weil ihn der nicht verlieren kann, der ihn hat!</tei:p><tei:p>Ein großer Augenblick wurde versäumt, Deutschl. zum Schirmherren Europas u. der Welt zu bestellen!</tei:p><tei:p>Bald aber wird man für einen Kaiser, ja für einen Junker<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Junker:  lit. "young lord";  a member of the landed (as apart from aristocratic) nobility of Prussia.  Historically, Junkers constituted the landed nobility of Prussia, controlling the Prussian army and wielding great political influence over the Hohenzollern German Empire.  </tei:note> Phantasiepreise zahlen!  Der schlechteste Kaiser u. Junker ist mir lieber, als das ewig blöde Volk, das nur sich u. andere zerstört.</tei:p><tei:p>Dir, deiner Frau u. den Kleinen von uns viele Grüße    2 : 4
d[ein] 
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  <tei:hi rend="italic">H</tei:hi>
9. XI. 1918</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">left margin, sideways:</tei:hi>]
Wie unfähig sind doch die Kaufmenschen!  Jahreszinsen wahrzunehmen, ja, dazu reicht es aus, aber Folgen zu berechnen - - das nicht.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter by Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated November 9, 1918</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Floriz,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Enclosed is the document "under discussion", known as "purchasing voucher":<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  use it as you see fit or, rather, let someone else profit from it.   (It says on the slip "valid only to November 9").</tei:p><tei:p>As I am in the midst of [reading the news of] the day, I can report:</tei:p><tei:p>1)  In Russia, the workers are already shedding tears, saying things are worse for them now than in times past:  "What use is it to them that they own everything, when, etc.?"  Naturally, everyone is in exactly the same situation as they were before, and one cannot expect the worker to undertake anything of his own accord, to say nothing of aiming at something even higher, better.  The <tei:hi rend="italic">Arbeiter-Zeitung</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> which was constantly sending over greetings ("to our brothers," boasted Adler<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> and Renner<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>), remains silent about the catastrophe. . . .<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/></tei:p><tei:p>2)  In Austria, everything is going downhill through sheer "self-penance"--a genuinely American piece of dynamite.</tei:p><tei:p>3)  In Switzerland, people are already shedding tears now:  America has drawn up blacklists and <tei:hi rend="italic">compels</tei:hi> [others] to trade.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>  People there used to be in favor the Entente<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> (it struck the right note with them), and feared a German victory.  <tei:hi rend="italic">Now they regret</tei:hi> this attitude of yesterday, because Germany always remained competetive, and did so by bearing the dangers and taking the rists, not by using force--apart from manufacturing things more cheaply!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi>
4)  Poland has set itself up<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> in baseness "independently"--freed from what?  Bah! from its ancestors, etc.  Soon they, too, &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;will&lt;/sup&gt; shed tears, along with the Hungarians ("own army," "freed from Austria," etc); and a European slave market driven by America (Wilson's wife<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> owned a pawnshop) will be established, open up and only Germany will keep its head because anyone who has a head cannot lose it!</tei:p><tei:p>A great opportunity was missed, to appoint Germany as protector of Europe and the world!</tei:p><tei:p>Soon, however, people will pay fantastic prices for a [German] Emperor , indeed, for a Junker.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/>  To me, the worst Emperor and Junker is preferable to the eternally half-witted people, which only destroys itself and others!</tei:p><tei:p>Best wishes from us to you, your wife, and the children   2:4 
Your 
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] H[einrich]</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">left margin, sideways:</tei:hi>]
How incompetent the businessmen really are!  Taking advantage of the annual interest rates, yes, that is something they can manage; but reckoning the consequences - - of that they are incapable.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>