<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OC 1B/15 : 9-15-12 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain
© Transcription Ian Bent, 2007
© Translation Ian Bent, 2007
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish is being sought.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1912-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-1938) - -Oster, Ernst (1938-c.1939)—New York Public Library (c.1939-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: in the public domain; Image: New York Public Library; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 09/15/1912 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Colbert ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Carl Colbert, dated September 15, 1912</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-10-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>S sets out the contractual basis on which he gives lessons;  he does not give single lessons, only programs of instruction at a set monthly fee;  his teaching is increasingly in demand from Germany;  he asks that Mrs. Colbert abide by his stipulated conditions. 

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Colbert, Carl;  Colbert, Tony;  lessons;  fees;  honorarium;  conditions;  Lerchenfeld;  Ottakring;  Vienna;  Germany;  Grünfeld, Alfred;  Hupka, Felix;  Weisse, Hans;  München;  Munich</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten file copy of letter from Schenker to Carl Colbert, dated September 15, 1912</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Herr Kaiserlicher Rat!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  This letter is copied, in HS’s hand, into his copybook.  It is therefore possible that the letter as sent was modified in the final copy.  The wording of this letter closes mirrors that of the diary entry, OJ 1/10, p. 126, May 30, 1911, in places.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Prof. <tei:hi rend="italic">Violin</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="violin_moriz">Moriz Violin</ref>. </tei:note> überbrachte mir kürzlich Ihren Wunsch betreffs des Unterrichtes Ihrer Frau Gemalin.  Ich will ihm soviel als möglich <tei:hi rend="italic">entgegenkommen</tei:hi>, u. lege die <tei:hi rend="italic">Entscheidung</tei:hi> in <tei:hi rend="italic">Ihre</tei:hi> Hand.  Da die Sache ziemliche Schwierigkeiten hat, muß ich zu Ihrer Einfuhrung<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Einführung</tei:hi>: it is unclear to what this refers;  perhaps to the opening section of a letter from Carl Colbert to S.</tei:note> ausholen bezw. Einiges wiederholen.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich gebe aus <tei:hi rend="italic">Altruismus</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">keine</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Einzel</tei:hi>stunden obwohl solche einträglicher wären.  Ich halte es für einen Betrug ^des Lehrers^ am Schüler u. bei diesen für einen Selbstbetrug, wenn eine Einzelstunde gegeben u. genommen wird.  Berühmte Lehrer lassen sich für eine solche Stunde 25–50 <tei:hi rend="italic">fl</tei:hi> (!!) bezahlen, der Schüler nimmt 2–3 Stunden im Jahr (!), – u. da er eben <tei:hi rend="italic">noch</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Schüler</tei:hi> ist (sonst würde er ja des Unterrichtes nicht bedürfen), kann er, frage ich, in 2–3 Stunden Nützliches lernen?  Sicher nicht!  Ich zwinge daher meine Schüler zu einem regelmäßigen Unterricht u. <tei:hi rend="italic">ermäßige</tei:hi> mein Honorar ebenso entsprechend, daß der Schüler es leisten kann.  Am allerwenigsten sind es doch die sehr reichen Menschen, die soviel Sinn für Musik u. zugleich soviel Würdigung eines seriösen Unterrichtes haben, <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> daß sie sich den letzteren 8 x 25 fl. d.i. 200 fl. kosten ließen.  Folglich habe ich in Einsicht des Real-Möglichen für ^je^ 2 Stunden der Woche 80 fl. ^monatlich^, für je eine der Woche eben 40[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">fl.</tei:hi> festgesetzt.  Außerdem verbinde ich mit dieser Regelmäßigkeit des Unterrichtes eine [jetzt schon über Auftrag des musikpedagogischen Verbandes<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Österreichischer Musikpadagogischer Verband: [supply information]</tei:note> (dem ich natürlich fernstehe) von den letzten Lehrern für „hausbesorgerische“ (Lerchenfeld,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Lerchenfeld:  Alt-Lerchenfeld was one of the districts of central Vienna, now incorporated into Josefstadt, the 8th district.  </tei:note> Ottakring<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Ottakring: the 16th district, to the west of Vienna.  </tei:note>) <tei:hi rend="italic">gleichmäßig</tei:hi> adoptierte]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Square brackets in original.  </tei:note> Klausel, daß <tei:hi rend="italic">Feiertage</tei:hi> zu Günsten des Lehrers fallen, u. ebenso die von Schüler selbst abgesagten Stunden.  (Der Lehrer hat die von ihm abgesagten Stunden einzutragen).  Diese Klausel findet ihre Begründung darin, daß viele Monate 9 Stunden aufweisen u. es nur gerecht ist, wenn die Ausgleichung eintritt.  Außerdem haben von Haus aus einige Schüler die Nettigkeit, einen Feiertag auch für den Lehrer gelten lassen zu wollen.  So meine Praxis.</tei:p><tei:p>Nun schrieb ich neulich Ihrer Frau Gemalin, daß ich alle, alle Zeit besetzt habe.  Und dem[?] ist wirklich so.  Immer mehr überzeugen meine Werke das jüngste Deutschland, u. von dort melden sich unaufhörlich junge Leute, einige sogar mit ganz respektablem Namen, die nach Wien (auch mit Familie) kommen, um bei mir zu lernen.  Über diesem Erfolg freue ich <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> mich sehr u. ich habe <tei:hi rend="italic">im</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Interesse</tei:hi> der <tei:hi rend="italic">Kunst</tei:hi> alle Ursache, die Jugend in Deutschland den falschen Götzen abzuwenden.  Außerdem ist das Ausland dankbarer.  Ist <tei:hi rend="italic">Wien</tei:hi> nicht die Stadt, wo man bestenfalls – Grünfeld<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Grünfeld:  presumably Alfred Grünfeld (1852–1924), celebrated Viennese pianist, piano teacher, and composer, who settled in Vienna in 1873.  </tei:note> souteniert, aber Leute meines Schlages laut[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] liegen läßt?  Wo man, wenns Ernst wird, plötzlich Geldmangel spürt u. an Geldes statt am liebsten einen Mittags-, einen Abendtisch servieren möchte ? U. s. w.  Sie kennen die Schlampereien ebenso gut, wie ich.  Und nun komme ich zur Conclusion:</tei:p><tei:p>Da ich von den <tei:hi rend="italic">angestammten</tei:hi> Schülern u. Schülerinnen &lt;strike&gt;die&lt;/strike&gt; (8–9 Jahre)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Tony Colbert applied for lessons on December 5, 1906 (OJ 1/5, p. 28).  thus by choosing this limit S excludes her;  <tei:hi rend="italic">angestammt</tei:hi>: lit. “ancestral” or “heritage”;   it is unclear which of S’s pupils in 1912 qualified for this epithet:  most likely candidates are Frau Davydoff (first mentioned in the diary on April 4, 1906: OJ 1/5, p. 12),  Sofie Deutsch and Robert Brünauer (both mentioned in the diary as having lessons on October 10, 1906: OJ 1/5, p. 21).  </tei:note> Keinen opfern darf, auch nicht von denen, auf die ich, wie z. B. auf den jungen <tei:hi rend="italic">Hupka</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Felix Hupka, who was referred to S by Eugen d’Albert in June 1912 (OJ 1/11, p. 204), and studied theory and piano with him.  </tei:note> ^u. Weisse^<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.  </tei:note> im höheren Sinne etwas gebe, den Einen oder anderen wegschicken kann, zumal ich schon viel Mühe auf sie wandte, so könnte ich, um Ihrer Frau entgegenzukommen, einen Ausländer jüngsten Datums opfern.  Es ist mir ein Schmerz, dies zu tun, da ich es als moralische Pflicht empfinde, vor Allem der Jugend zu dienen, die selbst Dienst wirken soll.  Anbetracht dieses Schadens aber, den ich einem Schüler zufüge, werde ich Sie bitten, mich selbst nicht einen weiteren Schaden erleiden zu lassen.  Lassen Sie nicht mich das Opfer an Ihre Frau bringen, sondern bestimmen Sie sie, <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> die zuerst erwähnten Bedingungen einzuhalten!  Es wäre verwerflich sentimental, wenn ich bei so viel Nachfrage seitens seriöser junger Leute mich ^anderswo^ versagen wollte, um hier – Schaden zu erleiden.  Ihre Frau mag es bestätigen, daß ich in humaner Würdigung des herannahenden Alters ihr ein bestimmtes <tei:hi rend="italic">Programm</tei:hi> vorschlug u. daran mit glühendsten Eifer arbeitete.  Aber ich konnte nicht zugeben, daß sie diesen verkennt, unterschätzt, einem Andern (doch nicht minder Würdigen) den Platz wegnimmt, – mehr als 10 Schüler <tei:hi rend="italic">kann</tei:hi> ich nicht unterrichten! –, ohne selbst davon Gebrauch zu machen.  Sie darf nicht vergessen, daß ich meine Kraft jungen Leuten – schulde, heute dringender denn je, u. sie soll ihr Gewissen nicht mit der Unachtsamkeit belasten, selbst nicht zu kommen, dem Anderen nicht kommen zu lassen, u. so geistigen u. materiellen Schaden nach 2 Seiten hin zu stoßen, dem ein nur sehr kleiner Geldgewinn auf eigener Seite gegenübersteht.  Es ist mir angenehm, Ihnen Alles so genau u. seriös gesagt haben zu können u. harre Ihre Entscheidung umso drängender, als ^ich^ ja eventuell weiter nach München schleunigst schreiben müßte.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit besten Grüßen an Sie
u. Ihre Frau Gemalin verbleibe I[h]r
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] H Schenker</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten file copy of letter from Schenker to Carl Colbert, dated September 15, 1912</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Imperial Councillor,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Prof. Violin<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> conveyed to me briefly your wish concerning your wife’s program of instruction.  I wish to <tei:hi rend="italic">accommodate</tei:hi> it as far as possible, and I place the <tei:hi rend="italic">decision</tei:hi> in <tei:hi rend="italic">your </tei:hi>hands.  Since the matter entails considerable difficulties, I must defer to your instruction<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> and reiterate one or two things.</tei:p><tei:p>Out of <tei:hi rend="italic">altruism</tei:hi>, I give <tei:hi rend="italic">no</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">single</tei:hi> lessons, albeit such lessons would be more lucrative.  I consider it a betrayal ^by the teacher^ of the student, and of the latter a self-betrayal, if a single lesson is given and taken.  Famous teachers demand for such a lesson 25–50 Florins(!!), the pupil takes two or three lessons a year(!), – and since he <tei:hi rend="italic">still is just a pupil</tei:hi> (otherwise he would have no need of the instruction), can he, I ask, learn anything useful in two or three lessons?  Surely not!  For this reason, I require my pupils to take a regular program of instruction and <tei:hi rend="italic">reduce</tei:hi> my fee in just such a way that the pupil can afford it.  Least of all is it actually the very rich people who have so great a feeling for music and at the same time value so highly a serious program of instruction <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> that they can pay 8 x 25 Florins = 200 Florins for such a program.  Consequently, bearing in mind what (ordinary) people can actually afford to pay, I have fixed 80 Florins ^a month^ [as the rate] for two lessons each week, and likewise 40 Florins for one per week.  In addition, I combine with this regular pattern of instruction a clause, [now <tei:hi rend="italic">universally</tei:hi> adopted on the orders of the Music-Teachers’ Federation<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> (from which, naturally, I distance myself) by the latter teachers  as “what is needed for the household” (Lerchenfeld<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>, Ottakring<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/>)],<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> stating that <tei:hi rend="italic">holidays</tei:hi> fall in favor of the teacher, and likewise those lessons which the pupil himself cancels.  (The teacher is responsible for the lessons he cancels himself.)  This clause has as its basis that many months generate nine lessons, and it is only fair that some evening-out should occur.  Additionally, some of my pupils right from the beginning, out of the kindness of their hearts, wish their teacher to have the benefit of a holiday, too.  This is my practise.</tei:p><tei:p>So I wrote recently telling your wife that every single bit of my time is booked up.  And that is really the case.  Increasingly, my work is convincing the most recent generation of Germans, and young people, some even with respectable names, are constantly applying to move to Vienna (even bringing their families) to study with me.  I am delighted at this success, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> and have every reason, <tei:hi rend="italic">in the interests of the art</tei:hi>, to turn the youth of Germany away from false idols.  What’s more, people abroad are more appreciative.  Is Vienna not the city where people at best support Grünfeld<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/>, but merely leave men of my ilk to one side?  [The city] where people, when things get difficult and they suddenly feel the financial pinch, would, instead of [paying out] money, prefer to serve a mid-day [or] evening meal?  And so forth.  You know the slovenliness as well as I do.  And now I come to my conclusion:</tei:p><tei:p>Since I could not possibly sacrifice anyone of my <tei:hi rend="italic">longest-standing</tei:hi> pupils (8–9 years),<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> nor can I dismiss any of those such as the young Hupka<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> ^and Weisse^,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> to whom I give something of a  higher order, especially since I have already taken great pains with them, so, in order to accommodate your wife, I could sacrifice a foreigner whom I have taken on most recently.  It is painful for me to do this, since I take it as a moral duty above all to serve the young, who should themselves give service.  Considering this damage, however, that I would have to inflict on one student, I must ask you not to inflict further damage on me.  Do not make me perform the sacrifice for your wife;  rather, induce her to abide by <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> the conditions already set out!  It would be damnably maudlin[?] if, given so great a demand on the part of serious-minded young people, I were to deny myself ^in another direction^ so as to inflict damage here.  Your wife can confirm that in humane recognition of her approaching age I proposed to her a specific program, and worked on it ardently.  But I could not permit her to underrate, to undervalue this, [and] take the place from some (certainly no less worthy) other person,—I <tei:hi rend="italic">can</tei:hi>not teach more that ten pupils!—without herself making use of it.  She ought not to forget that I owe my strength to young people, more pressingly today than ever, and she ought not to burden her conscience with the negligence of failing to turn up herself, not letting the other person attend, and inflicting such spiritual and material damage on two sides, which is balanced by only a very small monetary gain on my own side.  I am glad to be able to say all this in such detail and so seriously to you, and await your verdict all the more pressingly since ^I^ would perhaps have had to write further urgently to Munich.</tei:p><tei:p>With best wishes to you and your wife,
I remain yours,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] H Schenker</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>