<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/30, [4] : 9-27-12 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain
© Transcription Ian Bent, 2007
© Translation Ian Bent, 2007
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish is being sought.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1912-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Tony Colbert; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 09/27/1912 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Colbert ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Tony Colbert to Schenker, dated September 27, 1912</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-10-16</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Refers to S's previous letter and her response by postcard;  she has drawn up a work-plan for the coming season, for S's approval.  PS: S has misundertstood her intentions.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Colbert, Tony;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Brahms;  Violin Sonata;  Beethoven;  Piano Sonata;  Op. 111;  Brioni Islands;  Brijuni Istlands;  Istria;  schedule;  Ninth Symphony;  Stirling, Mrs.;  Munich</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Hotel Brioni, Ischia</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Tony Colbert to Schenker, dated September 27, 1912</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>]
Hotel Brioni
(Brionische Inseln)
Istrien.
Telegramm-Adresse:
„Hoteldirektion Brioni“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  The Brioni (or Brijuni) Islands lie off the western coast of Istria, Croatia, in the Adriatic.  </tei:note>
<tei:hi rend="italic">_</tei:hi>__</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed:</tei:hi>] Brioni, [<tei:hi rend="italic">handwritten:</tei:hi>] 27. Sept. 1912</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Dr!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich hoffe, Sie haben meine pneumatischeKarte<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  S reports receipt of an item of correspondence from Mrs. C. on September 17 (OJ 1/11, p. 230), stating that “Mrs. Colbert accepts all [my] conditions ...”.  </tei:note> die ich 2 Stunden nach Empfang Ihres werten Schreiben<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Presumably the letter of which OC 1B/15, September 15, is S’s file copy, although that was addressed to her husband, not to her.  </tei:note> absandte – erhalten.  Ich bin unruhig wegen Ihres Stillschweigens[;]  habe Angst dass Sie sich’s anders überlegt haben oder an mich ganz vergessen haben.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich baute mir durch Ihre gütige Zusage meinen Arbeitsplan so schön auf freute mich riesig auf den Winter, auf die Stunden bei Ihnen.  Als erste Arbeit dachte ich mir die Violinsonate d moll von Brahms,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  “Brahms” underlined by S in crayon.  </tei:note> dann op. 111 Beethoven.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  “op. 111 Beethoven” underlined by S in crayon.  </tei:note>  Was meinen Sie dazu?  Ich unterwerfe mich aber selbstverständlich[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] meinem anderen <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Arbeitsplan wenn Sie es wünschen u. es für richtiger halten mit bescheid[en]eren Werken vorlieb zu nehmen.  Ich habe so ziemlich jeden Tag frei bis auf Montag wo ich absolut nicht kann.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Mrs. C. started lessons on a Friday (October 4), and thereafter on Thursdays.  In the Fall, she studied the Brahms Violin Sonata in D minor, Op. 108, Chopin Etude in A minor, Op. 25, No. 11, Beethoven Cello Sonata in C major, Op. 102, No. 1, Brahms Variations on a Theme of Paganini, Op. 35, and Beethoven Piano Trio in B-flat major (”Archduke”), Op. 97.   </tei:note>  Ich bin mit meinem Mann hier[,] der durch Aufregungen u. Überanstrengung sehr heruntergekommen ist u. der vor das Winter campagne ein wenig Erholung braucht die er aber leider nicht in dem Masse findet wie er sie braucht da meistens schlechtes Wetter ist.  Wir sind im Ganzen eine Woche aus u. ich bin Donnerstag<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  The letter was written on a Friday, so Mrs. C. is referring to October 3.  </tei:note> schon zu Hause.  Wir schwelgen im Genuss Ihres Werkes über die Neunte<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Schenker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie</tei:hi> (Vienna: UE, 1912), which had been released on July 2.  </tei:note> u. es ist eine wunderbare Einführung für mich.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Also ich bin in spannender Erwartung Ihrer guten Nachrichten.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit herzlichen Grüssen
Ihre getreuen[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>]
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Colbert</tei:p><tei:p>Herr Dr. missverstanden mich ganz u. gar als ich um die 2te Stunde des Fr. Stirling<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Mrs.  Stirling: another of S’s pupils at this time. </tei:note> [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg. word</tei:hi>].  Da doch 2 mal wöchentlich 160M. u. 1 mal 80M. kostet, habe ich keinen Moment an ersparen gedacht, sondern ich dachte wenn Sie diese Idee gutheissen, brauchten[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] Sie auch Ihrem Münchner<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Probably <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>, who did not take lessons.  </tei:note> nicht abzuschreiben, was Ihnen u. auch mir sehr unange[ne]hm ist.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Tony Colbert to Schenker, dated September 27, 1912</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>]
Hotel Brioni
(Brioni Islands)
Istria.
Telegram-Adress:
„Hoteldirektion Brioni“<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>
<tei:hi rend="italic">_</tei:hi>__</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed:</tei:hi>] Brioni, [<tei:hi rend="italic">handwritten:</tei:hi>] September 27, 1912</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>I hope you received my pneumatic card,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> which I sent off two hours after receiving your valued letter.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>    I am uneasy at your silence;  I am anxious lest you thought ill of it or have completely forgotten about me.</tei:p><tei:p>I drew up a work-plan for myself with your kind consent, so hugely did I enjoy myself over the winter at my lessons with you.  As the first work, I thought about the D minor Violin Sonata by Brahms,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> then Op. 111 by Beethoven.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  What do you think of that?  Naturally, however, I yield to my other <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> work-plan if you wish and think it better to make do with less ambitious works.  I have pretty well any day free other than Monday, which I absolutely cannot do.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/>  I am here with my husband, who is very run-down as a result of too much excitement and strain, and who needed a short respite before the winter campaign, but unfortunately did not get as much as he needed because of the mostly bad weather.  We are away for a whole week and I shall be back home on Thursday.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>  We are basking in the pleasure of your work on the Ninth,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> and it is a wonderful introduction for me.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> So I eagerly await good news from you.</tei:p><tei:p>With cordial good wishes,
Yours faithfully,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Colbert</tei:p><tei:p>You have misunderstood me completely, dear Doctor, as I [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg. word</tei:hi>] over Mrs. Stirling’s<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> second lesson.  Since twice a week costs 160 Marks and once [a week] 80 Marks, I did not think for a moment of saving money;  rather, I thought that if you approved of this idea, you would not need to write off your pupil from Munich,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> which would be very unpleasant for you as well as for me.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>