<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 5/16, [2] : 5-[5]-14 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Heinrich Schenker.
© Transcription Ian D. Bent 2005.
© Translation Ian D. Bent 2005.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian D. Bent 2005.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>All reasonable steps have been taken to locate the heirs of Heinrich Schenker.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Universal Edition Archive (1914-1976)—on permanent loan to the Stadt- und Landesbibliothek Wien (1976-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker; Image: Universal Edition, A.G.; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian D. Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 05/05/1914 01:12:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Hertzka ~ HSchenker","UE ~ H+JSchenker","UE ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten draft letter from Schenker to Emil Hertzka (UE), in Jeanette's hand, dated May [5], 1914</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-01-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>[ LfS 101, 106:] Draft for WSLB 211.  Argues for a higher honorarium for both on the grounds that (a) he has to employ and pay someone as copyist; (b) each LfS is really two autonomous volumes in one for which he has not hitherto be adequately recompensed; ( c) he forewent an offer from Peters in order to complete LfS, and is on that account out of pocket; (d) Op. 101 and 106 are projects of greater scope, requiring more work. Urges H to apply to Austrian Ministry of Education for a grant enabling S to drop two pupils and give the time to LfS. Has also to assemble evidence before publishing the Kleine Flugschriften. Rejects H's reference to economic depression and suggests Schoenberg publications might subsidize his.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Hertzka, Emil; UE;  draft; Beethoven; Die letzten fünf Sonaten; Erläuterungsausgabe; Op. 101; Op. 106; honorarium; increase; raise; Bach, J. S.;  Chromatic Fantasy &amp; Fugue; out-of-pocket expenses; reviews; Fifth Symphony; editions; monographs; New Testament; Latin; Sperlgasse; Kleine Flugschriften; Little Pamphlets; Chopin; Brahms; chamber music; symphonies; Lieder; songs; Peters; Schnabel, Artur; Flesch, Carl; economic depression; Simrock; Bohm; Brahms; Schoenberg; Mahler; profitability; pupils; roster; conditions of work; Ministry of Education; grant; subvention; subsidy</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Draft letter from Schenker to Hertzka (UE), dated May 1914</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">in Jeanette’s hand, with deletions, interlinear corrections and added sections all in Heinrich’s hand</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{1 <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">[top margin, in pencil:]</tei:hi> 1
<tei:hi rend="bold">[top margin, in red crayon:]</tei:hi> an Hertzka 1914 <tei:hi rend="italic">Mai</tei:hi> verändert u. gekürzt</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">[main body of text, in black ink:]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>In Erkenntnis, daß gerade &lt;strike&gt;so grandiose Werke wie&lt;/strike&gt; op. 101 u. 106 ^wegen jenes [deleted] des Umfanges u. der großen Schwierigkeiten^ einer längeren Vorbereitung bedürfen, beeile ich mich, auf Ihren sehr liebenswürdigen Brief, für den ich herzlich danke, Rede u. Antwort zu stehen.  &lt;strike&gt;Ich&lt;/strike&gt; wiederhole ^ich^ 1. &lt;strike&gt;w&lt;/strike&gt;<tei:hi rend="italic">W</tei:hi>as ich in allen meinen früheren Briefen wie ich hoffe überzeugend genug, zum Ausdruck gebracht habe, daß ^[illeg]^ die ganze Frage für mich nicht ^etwa^ eine ^verschleierte u.^ indirekte Honorar^erhöhungs^frage, sondern eine ^lediglich offene^ direkte Frage &lt;strike&gt;der&lt;/strike&gt; ^wirklicher^ Arbeitsmöglichkeit ist.</tei:p><tei:p>&lt;strike&gt;Sie werden mir doch, als&lt;/strike&gt; [ <tei:hi rend="italic">corr to</tei:hi> &lt;strike&gt;Als&lt;/strike&gt;] &lt;strike&gt;einem Menschen von Bildung, der&lt;/strike&gt; ^auch^ &lt;strike&gt;die schwierigsten Fragen der Musik besser als irgend jemand vor mir zu lösen xx weiß, die geringe&lt;/strike&gt; ^wohl bescheidene^ &lt;strike&gt;Kapazität zutrauen, zu verstehen, daß ich selbst mit erhöhtem Honorar nicht zu Kapital gelangen könnte.  Und deshalb allein war es mir ja bis heute&lt;/strike&gt; vollständig egal, welche Summe Sie mir auf den Tisch legten [ <tei:hi rend="italic">corr to</tei:hi> legen] ^wurde^ , u. &lt;strike&gt;wären diese auch zehn — oder zwanzigmal größer gewesen, so hatten sie noch immer kein Kapital ergehen.&lt;/strike&gt;  <tei:hi rend="bold">[Heinrich attempts to alter the above interlinearly, then writes out the new version on the <tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>: see below.]</tei:hi> Dieses war der Grund, weshalb ich gestatten ^vermögen^ konnte, daß ^ich^ eine Ausgabe u. eine dazugehörige Monographie, also zwei verschiedene Werke, die durchaus nicht in einem Bande u. überhaupt nicht zusammenzugehen brauchen, ohneweiters als ein Werk überließ.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  As was the case with his edition of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Chromatic Fantasy &amp; Fugue</tei:hi> of J. S. Bach (1910), and most recently with <tei:hi rend="italic">Die letzten fünf Sonaten ... Op. 109</tei:hi> (1913), which series is foremost in S’s mind in making this argument, whereas the issuing of his edition of C. P. E. Bach keyboard works (1903) as one item and its accompanying volume on embellishment, <tei:hi rend="italic">Ein Beitrag zur Ornamentik</tei:hi> (1903) as another, was a case of the contrary.</tei:note>  Und wenn ich bei Gelegenheit, z.B. gegen die Auslegung einer Arbeit als Revision protestierte,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Perhaps S has in mind the second edition (1908) of <tei:hi rend="italic">Ein Beitrag zur Ornamentik</tei:hi>, or maybe the Niloff <tei:hi rend="italic">Instrumentations-Tabelle</tei:hi>, first published in 1909, the second edition with extensive additional textual matter in 1912.</tei:note> so war es weniger um der 2–300 Kronen mehr, als um zu verhindern, daß eine so zukunfts-maßgebende Sache unter falschem Titel, wie z. B. die  „Chrom. Fant.“ in die Welt gehe.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">   His <tei:hi rend="italic">Chromatische Phantasie und Fuge D moll von Joh. Seb. Bach kritische Ausgabe mit Anhang von Heinrich Schenker</tei:hi> was issued on October 21, 1910.  It comprised the "Vorwort" (Foreword), the edition of the music, a "Vorbemerkung zur Einführung" (Preliminary Remark to the Introduction), the "Einführung" (Introduction), and an "Anhang" (Appendix).  It thus in many ways prefigured the structure of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Erläuterungsausgabe</tei:hi> (1913-20).  </tei:note>  Wie wenig ich den Geldstandpunkt regardierte, mögen Sie ja aus den Ihnen kürzlich zugeschickten Briefen entnommen haben, sowie aus der Tatsache,</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{1 <tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi> [Heinrich reworks beginning of previous paragraph]}</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>^Somit^ ist es mir auch heute &lt;strike&gt;also&lt;/strike&gt; ^noch^ ganz egal, welche Su[mme?] Sie mir auf d. Tisch legen wurden, kaum so wie bisher, aus dem sehr einfachen Grunde, weil kein Honorar begreift sein konnte, daß es eine nennenswerte Verschiebung eines Vermögensstandes bewirken &lt;strike&gt;könnte&lt;/strike&gt; wurde &lt;strike&gt;da Einsicht am daß .....  auf aus solchen Arbeiten&lt;/strike&gt; unmöglich &lt;strike&gt;Wohlstand&lt;/strike&gt;  ^Reichtum[?]^ ergeben[?] kann, was ja &lt;strike&gt;auch bisher der Grund meines Verhaltens gegenüber den „U.E.“&lt;/strike&gt;  Sie haben ja aus dieser[?] Einsicht sich auf Möglichkeit[?] &lt;strike&gt;Verxxxxxxx  verschafft&lt;/strike&gt; Nutzen sozusagen u. ich hatte nichts dagegen</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">[Text continues from the bottom of p.1 <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>, in Jeanette's hand]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> daß ich einen Herrn,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  <tei:hi rend="italic">einen Herrn</tei:hi>: this male designation does not have the ambiguity of WSLB 211’s "eine Person" at this point, and runs contrary to the sense in letters in earlier years that he employs a female pupil ( <tei:hi rend="italic">eine Schülerin</tei:hi> ) for such purposes.</tei:note> den ich noch außerdem bei den Blättern beschäftigte, mit 6 Kronen per Stunde honoriere, also genau das weggebe, was ich erhalte.  Ohne Hilfe aber wären die jeweilig zwei Werke, die ein Band vereinigt, absolut nicht auszuführen.  Ja schon die Baarauslagen allein haben bis heute 500 Kronen erreicht, für die sie allerdings 300 Kr. vorgeschossen haben.</tei:p><tei:p>Wie Sie aus all dem entnehmen, steht also meine Arbeit für die U.E. ausschließlich im Zeichen der Sache u. nicht eines Gewinnes! Und ich gestehe, daß ich es auch weiter so fortgetrieben hätte, wenn nicht, wie gesagt, der Körper ein sehr entschiedenes veto eingelegt hätte u. so muß es nun heissen : die Arbeitsbedingungen verbessern, ohne wieder auf Gewinn auszugehen, der ja überhaupt niemals zu erzielen möglich ist (wenn man Autor<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Autor</tei:hi>:  S often uses this word to mean “composer” but is clearly speaking as an author in this context.</tei:note> ist!).</tei:p><tei:p>Ich sagte schon oben, daß ich im Grunde (was auch drei Kritiken<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Presumably three reviews of "Die letzten fünf Sonaten ... Op. 109" (1913).  S’s scrapbook contains clippings of three reviews written in the weeks before this letter: [unsigned:] “Heinrich Schenker: Erläuterungsausgabe ... op. 109,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Rheinische Musik- und Theater-Zeitung</tei:hi>, February 28, 1914; Max Graf: “Beethoven–Schenker,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue Zeitschrift für Musik</tei:hi>, March 8, 1914; Hermann Wetzel: „Heinrich Schenker: Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven ...,“ <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Musik</tei:hi> XIII/12, March 15, 1914: OC 2/pp.39–40.</tei:note> bestätigen) je zwei Werke biete, die Ausgabe selbst u. eine Monographie, die füglich selbständig erscheinen könnte, ebenso wie die der V. Sinfonie<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  It is unclear to what S refers here; perhaps to a monograph intended for his new <tei:hi rend="italic">Kleine Bibliothek</tei:hi>, or <tei:hi rend="italic">Kleine Flugschriften</tei:hi>, and which eventually appeared serially in <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</tei:hi> 1, 5, and 6 (1921–23).</tei:note>.  Ich sehe auch die Möglichkeit, daß Sie nach Erscheinen sämtlicher 5 Werke<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  S is now talking of <tei:hi rend="italic">Die letzten fünf Sonaten</tei:hi>, of which one volume ( <tei:hi rend="italic">Op. 109</tei:hi> ) has so far appeared.  </tei:note> sowohl die fünf Sonaten, als auch die Monographien einzeln oder in Bandform auf den Markt bringen können.  Das doppelte Werk erfordert nun, wie Sie begreifen, doppelte Anstrengung u. dennoch halte ich, freilich gerade nur in Bezug auf die 5 letzten Sonaten, die wie Sie wissen als „das neue Testament“ in der Musik<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  S seems to be referring here to the sonatas themselves rather than to his elucidatory editions of (four of) them.</tei:note> gelten, an dieser Darstellung fest, um vorerst einwandfrei zu beweisen, daß — wenige Männer ausgenommen — <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Niemand die Musik unserer Meister so gehört hat, wie sie gehört werden sollte.  Ich biete damit für alle Zeiten ein einwandfreies Dokument der Musik der größten Meister, das man noch nach Jahrtausenden als Quelle vielleicht mehr sogar als den Test<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  “music”: S uses <tei:hi rend="italic">Text</tei:hi>, meaning the music in notational form.</tei:note> [ <tei:hi rend="italic">corr to</tei:hi> Text] selbst, benützen wird!  Schon heute wird Beethoven so gespielt, wie Wiener Kinder in den Unterklassen Latein sprechen; ebenso wie dies Latein in der Sperlgasse<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  The Kleine Sperlgaße is a street in the old Leopoldstadt center of Vienna. Elementary, high, and grammar schools (known as the “Sperlgymnasium”) exist today at Kleine Sperlgaße 2A &amp; 2C: “[In 1914/15, when the present school moved there], the “Sperl” had been located on the site ... since 1874....  From 1877 on the ‘Leopoldstädter Communalreal- und Obergymnasium’ was located there.  Up until 1938, the proportion of Jewish children was high.”  (http://www.sperlgymnasium.at/chronik.htm) The school was apparently attended by, among others, Sigmund Freud and Viktor Frankl.  (http://www.viktorfrankl.org/e/journalE_0301.html)  </tei:note> falsch u. erlogen ist, ebenso tot ist die Sprache, die auf dem Podium als eine lebendige Tonsprache ausgegeben wird.  Nach erbrachtem Beweis werde ich bei den Kleinen Flugschriften—4–5 per Jahr—durchaus keine Polemik mehr treiben, sondern nur von der Warte der bereits erreichten Erfolge den wahren Sachverhalt unserer Meisterwerke von Chopin, Brahms, u.s.w. in Kammermusik, Sinfonien, Liedern, u.s.f. der fernsten Nachwelt übermitteln. Man wird es einmal sehr dringend brauchen!</tei:p><tei:p>Daher mögen Sie sich erklären, weshalb ich leichten Herzens auf 12000–15000 Kr. von Peters verzichtete, der von mir einige Sonaten v. Beethoven mit Fußnoten versehen erbat.  Sicher hat mich Peters nicht verstanden, als ich ihm in ausführlicher Darstellung begreiflich zu machen suchte, daß ich mich lieber einer Anstrengung u. einem Beweis unterziehe, als al pari mit Artur Schnabel<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Click on: <ref cRef="schnabel_artur">Artur Schnabel</ref></tei:note> u. Carl Flesch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  Click on <ref cRef="flesch_carl">Carl Flesch</ref></tei:note> u.s.w. eine Ausgabe zu veranstalten, die nach weiteren 5–10 Jahren erst recht eine Neu-Ausgabe notwendig macht.  Mit Leichtig- <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> keit hätte ich tausendmal bessere u. reichlichere Fußnoten für die erbetenen Sonaten machen können, bei meiner Vertrautheit mit dem Stoff u. sogar in einem Jahre u. dennoch bin ich dem Antrag aus dem Wege gegangen!  Wie Sie sehen ist es mir um etwas mehr zu tun, als nun die paar Groschen, die mich doch auch wieder nicht in den Stand eines vermögenden Mannes setzen u. die ich daher ebenso gut entbehren kann.</tei:p><tei:p>Was Sie über eine Depression schreiben, mag ja sehr begründet sein; indessen kann nach einer wirtschaftlichen Depression sehr wohl noch ein Aufschwung kommen, nicht so leicht aber wirkliche Gesundheit nach exemplarischer<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  „full-scale“: S uses <tei:hi rend="italic">exemplarisch</tei:hi>, which normally means “exemplary,’ “model,” but can mean severe. Perhaps there is a possibility of word-play on <tei:hi rend="italic">Exemplar</tei:hi> (copy) in publishing. </tei:note> Zerstörung des Organismus.  Und schließlich, verzeihen Sie, wenn ich ein wenig mitkalkuliere, kann ich mir dem Verlag nicht ohne eine gewisse Rentabilität denken u. da fällt mir Simrock’s Antwort ein, die er Brahms gegeben hat, als dieser ihm Vorwürfe machte: „Du druckst schon wieder den Dreck“ (nämlich Bohm<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15">  Click on <ref cRef="bohm">Bohm</ref></tei:note>).  Simrock erwiderte: „Nein lieber Johannes, wenn ich den Dreck nicht drucken würde, könnte ich Dich nicht bezahlen.“  Auf unseren Fall angewendet möchte ich meinen, daß, wenn sich Schönbergs’,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn16">  Click on <ref cRef="schoenberg_arnold">Arnold Schoenberg</ref>..</tei:note> Mahler’s<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn17">  Click on <ref cRef="mahler_gustav">Gustav Mahler</ref>.</tei:note> Werke u.s.w.  als rentabel erweisen, warum sollte diese Rentabilität nicht dazu benutzt werden, um Arbeiten überhaupt zu ermöglichen, die noch rentabler sein könnten wenn nur erst der Verlag, deren unvergänglichen Wertes bewußt, sie in die englische, französische Sprache <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> übertragen u. allen Lehrern zugänglich machen würde.</tei:p><tei:p>Sind aber die oben genannten Werke nicht rentabel, dann wüßte ich wieder nicht, weshalb sie den <tei:hi rend="italic">Vorzug</tei:hi> verdienen sollten vor Arbeiten die über Mode u. Tag erhaben sind.  Kurz, wenn ich auch alle wirtschaftlichen Momente mitkalkuliere, ersehe ich nirgends einen Grund, weshalb für Beeth. oder andere ewige Meister zu geschehende Arbeiten auch nur aus dem Grunde mangelnder Rentabilität zurückgesetzt werden sollten.</tei:p><tei:p>So ist denn endlich Zeit, daß ich meine Arbeitsbedingungen nenne; &lt;strike&gt;S&lt;/strike&gt;sie lauten nach den gemachten Erfahrungen einfach so : Ich muß auf 2 Schüler verzichten können u. es blos bei einem Status von 10 Schülern bewenden lassen, wenn ich die Arbeit machen soll, wodurch ich 4 Stunden per Woche gewinnen würde, nebst dem weiteren Aufwand für dazu gehörigen &lt;strike&gt;Aufwand von&lt;/strike&gt; Correkturen der Schülerarbeiten u. s.f.  Wenn Ihnen dieser Gedanke unbequem sein sollte, — gesprächsweise meinten Sie einmal ausdrücklich, ich wäre dem Verlag nicht mehr ein so bequemer Autor! – bei 1000 Kr. für ein 450 S. starkes Werk, bei 1200 Kr. für Ausgabe u. Werk! — so mögen Sie bedenken, daß selbst in meinem gegenwärtigen Anbot noch immer ein Opfer zu erblicken ist, da ich mit einem Verzicht auf 2 Schüler zugleich ein Verzicht sozusagen auf eine Rente leiste, insofern, als Schüler die zu mir kommen <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> dauernd bleiben.  Zu jenem Verzicht auf 2 Schüler, der also gleichbedeutend ist mit einem Verzicht auf einen gesicherten Ertrag, entschlösse ich mich ja nur aus dem Grunde, weil ich eine ständige Cooperation mit Ihnen im Bezug auf die Flugschriften mir immerhin verspreche.  In diesem Sinne würde ich op. 101 u. 106, die aber in Summa, wie ich nicht oft genug betonen kann, 4 verschiedene  Arbeiten sind, nicht blos zwei, je 4000 Kr. per Werk erbitten (für op. 106 habe ich schon s.Z. von Ihnen ein Zugeständnis der Erhöhung erhalten, als ich sie nicht unter 2000 Kr. machen zu können[?] erklärte).  Ich wiederhole, daß es bei Leistungen geistiger Natur ja nicht anders gehen kann, als bei solchen physischer Natur : In beiden Fällen kann es nicht über die Leichen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn18">  the text has <tei:hi rend="italic">die Leichen</tei:hi>, lit. “the corpses”.</tei:note> desjenigen gehen, der die Arbeit leisten soll.  Was würde es Ihnen nützen, wenn ich mich bei der zweitnächsten Arbeit verbluten würde u. dann keinerlei Arbeit mehr verrichten könnte, wo mir doch meine Mission noch so furchtbar viel Arbeiten in die Feder drückt.</tei:p><tei:p>Und so komme ich endlich auf meinen ersten Vorschlag zurück, daß Sie sich an das Ministerium<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn19">  i.e. the Austrian Ministry of Education.</tei:note> um einen Beitrag wenden mögen.  Im Grunde ist ja der Schuldtragende eben das Ministerium selbst, das mir in meiner Heimat nicht die Arbeitsmöglichkeit verschafft, die sie überreichlich minder &lt;strike&gt;F&lt;/strike&gt;fähigen u. minder Bbedeutenden Musikern zubilligt.  Da ich zu stolz wäre, mich an ein Ministerium zu wenden, das mir gegenüber zu <tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> größtem Danke verpflichtet nicht einmal längst gebotene Dankesschuld abzutragen gelernt hat, so mögen vielleicht sie  selbst<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn20">  possibly “you yourself” ( <tei:hi rend="italic">Sie selbst</tei:hi> ).</tei:note> den Versuch machen, eine Subvention für die Herausgabe der letzten Kollosse<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn21">  i.e. <tei:hi rend="italic">Opp. 101</tei:hi> and <tei:hi rend="italic">106</tei:hi>.</tei:note> zu erwirken.  Unter allen Umständen hoffe ich aber, daß Sie, sehr!, mindestens das Hauptsächliche entnommen haben, daß es sich mir lediglich um die Arbeitsmöglichkeit. u. nicht um einen Gewinn zu tun ist</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">[no valediction or signature]</tei:hi></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Draft letter from Schenker to Hertzka (UE), dated May 1914</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">in Jeanette’s hand, with deletions, interlinear corrections and added sections in Heinrich’s hand</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{1 <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">[top margin, in pencil:]</tei:hi> 1
<tei:hi rend="bold">[top margin, in red crayon:]</tei:hi> to Hertzka <tei:hi rend="italic">May</tei:hi> 1914, altered and shortened</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">[main body of text, in black ink:]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>In recognition precisely that &lt;strike&gt;such grandiose works&lt;/strike&gt; as <tei:hi rend="italic">Opp. 101</tei:hi> and <tei:hi rend="italic">106</tei:hi>, ^on account of their scope and of their great difficulties^, will require longer preparation, I hasten to respond in detail to your kind letter, for which many thanks.  Let me reiterate that, as I have expressed in all my earlier letters—convincingly enough, I hope—for me the whole question is not ^some kind of^ a(n) ^veiled and^ oblique request for an ^increase in^ honorarium, but ^merely^ a ^frank,^ direct question as to the ^real^ possibility of work.</tei:p><tei:p>&lt;strike&gt;You will grant me, aAs an educated man who better than anyone before me knows how to solve the most difficult questions in music, the slight&lt;/strike&gt; ^rather modest^ &lt;strike&gt;capacity to understand that I could not become wealthy solely by means of an increased honorarium.  And for this reason alone it was until today&lt;/strike&gt; a matter of indifference to me what sum of money you laid on the table; &lt;strike&gt;and even if this were to have been ten or twenty times more , it would still never have made me a wealthy man.&lt;/strike&gt;  <tei:hi rend="bold">[Heinrich attempts to alter the above interlinearly, then writes out the new version on the <tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>: see below.]</tei:hi>  This was how I could have allowed it to happen that ^I^ submitted as a single work an edition and an accompanying monograph, hence two different works, which had no need whatsoever to go together in one volume, nor even to go together at all.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  And when, for example, I protested against the characterization of a work as a revised edition,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> it was less about the extra 200–300 Kroner than to prevent something that was so much a work of the future being published under a misleading title, as e.g. the <tei:hi rend="italic">Chromatic Fantasy</tei:hi> [ <tei:hi rend="italic">&amp; Fugue</tei:hi> ]<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>.  How little concerned I was with the monetary aspect you may well have inferred from the letters sent to you recently, as well as from the fact</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{1 <tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi> [Heinrich rewords beginning of previous paragraph]}</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Consequently[?] even today it is ^still^ a matter of total indifference to me what sum of money you would place on the table, scarcely less so than hitherto, for the very simple reason that no honorarium could be conceived[?] that &lt;strike&gt;could&lt;/strike&gt; would bring about an improvement in financial status worth speaking of, &lt;strike&gt;since inspection of, it would be&lt;/strike&gt; impossible &lt;strike&gt;for prosperity&lt;/strike&gt; ^riches^ to be produced &lt;strike&gt;from such works,&lt;/strike&gt; which [has been] &lt;strike&gt;up to now the reason for my behavior toward UE.&lt;/strike&gt;   You certainly have &lt;strike&gt;obtained&lt;/strike&gt; from this insight ...  possibility, profit so to speak, and I [would] have nothing against that</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">[Text continues from the bottom of p.1 <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>, in Jeanette's hand]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> that I am remunerating a man<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>, whom I still otherwise employ by the sheet, at 6 Kroner an hour, hence I give away precisely what I receive.  Without some help, however, the combining of two works into a single volume in times past absolutely would not wash [today].   Indeed, my out-of-pocket expenses alone have to date already reached 500 Kroner, for which you have, it is true, advanced 300 Kroner. 
 
As you will infer from all of this, my work for UE thus has been motivated exclusively by its intrinsic subject matter and not as a source of monetary gain.  And I admit that I would have gone on in the same vein had not, as I have said, the body imposed a highly emphatic veto, and so what is now at issue is: to improve working conditions without again seeking to make a profit, which is a completely unrealizable goal (if on is an author!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>).</tei:p><tei:p>I said earlier that (as three reviews<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> confirm) in essence I offer two separate works, the edition itself and a monograph, works that could with justice appear independently, just as that of the Fifth Symphony.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>  I can even see the possibility that, after the appearance all five works,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> you might market the five sonatas, and likewise the [five] monographs, singly or in single-volume form.  The double-barrelled work demands, as you can imagine, twice the exertion, and nevertheless, admittedly with reference specifically to the last five sonatas, which as you know qualify as the “New Testament” in music,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> I cling firmly to this mode of presentation in order first and foremost to prove beyond dispute that—few men excepted— <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> no one has yet heard the music of our masters as it should be heard.  With this I offer for all time an unassailable document of the music of our greatest masters, which will still be in use thousands of years from now as a source, perhaps more than the music<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> itself!  Beethoven is already performed as Viennese children in lower school speak Latin;  just as Latin is falsified and travestied in the Sperlgasse<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/>, so equally dead is the language that is given out on the podium as a living musical language.  When I have amassed my proof, I shall foreswear all polemics in the <tei:hi rend="italic">Little Pamphlets</tei:hi>—four-to-five a year—; instead, purely from the vantage-point of the successes that I have already achieved I shall bequeath to the farthest reaches of posterity the true content of our masterworks by Chopin, Brahms, and so forth in chamber music, symphonies, songs and so on.  Some day, people will be in desperate need of it!</tei:p><tei:p>So you might ask yourself why I cheerfully forewent 12,000–15,000 Kroner from Peters, who asked me for some Beethoven sonatas replete with footnotes.  Peters certainly did not understand me when I tried to make abundantly clear to him that I prefer to subject myself to hard work and the exaction of proof, rather than put together an edition on the level of Artur Schnabel,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> Carl Flesch<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> and others that will already require a new edition in five-to-ten years’ time.  I would have been able effortlessly <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> to have fashioned footnotes a thousand times better and more ample for the requested sonatas, given my intimate acquaintance with the material, and done it all within a year, and nevertheless I turned the proposal down.  As you can see, my concern is with rather more than a few measly pennies, which will come nowhere near making me a wealthy man of me, hence I can well do without them.</tei:p><tei:p>What you write about a depression is no doubt well-founded.  However, following an economic depression an upswing can still very easily take place, whereas it is not so easy for real health [to recover] following a full-scale<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/> destruction of the organism.  And finally, forgive me if I check your calculations a little;  I cannot imagine your publishing house without a certain profitability, and what springs to mind is the answer that Simrock gave to Brahms when the latter complained to him: “You keep printing muck (to wit, Bohm<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn15"/>)”.  Simrock retorted: “No, dear Johannes, were I not to print this muck, I could not pay you.”  Applied to our situation, I might suggest that if the works of Schoenberg,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn16"/> Mahler<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn17"/> and so on prove themselves profitable, why should not the latter profitability be used to make possible otherwise unviable works that, granted their imperishable value, could be still more profitable only if your publishing house were to <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> translate them into English [and] French and make them available to all teachers. 
 
Then again, if the above-mentioned works are not so profitable, I could not see why they should deserve priority over works that stand head-and-shoulders above fashion and time.  In short, even when I go through your calculations of all the economic factors, nowhere do I see any reason why works in progress for Beethoven or other eternal masters should be put back solely on grounds of poor profitability. 
  
At last, it is time for me to state my conditions for work.  They reflect my past experiences quite simply as follows:  If I am to do my work, I must be able to drop two pupils and settle merely for a status quo of ten pupils, through which I would be able to salvage four hours a week along with the further expenditure of time for correcting the student exercises associated with them, and so forth.  Should this idea be uncomfortable for you—in conversation you once specifically remarked that I would no longer be so comfortable an author for the your publishing house!—at 1,000 Kroner for a 450-page book, at 1,200 Kroner for edition and work!—bear in mind that even in my present proposition there is still an element of sacrifice, since giving up two pupils entails at the same time giving up, so to speak, a source of revenue, inasmuch as pupils who come to me <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> remain a long time.  I would only ever agree to giving up in that way two pupils, which thus equates with giving up an assured source of income, because I have committed myself to giving you my constant co-operation over the <tei:hi rend="italic">Little Pamphlets</tei:hi>.  With this in mind, for <tei:hi rend="italic">Opp. 101</tei:hi> and <tei:hi rend="italic">106</tei:hi>, which are <tei:hi rend="italic">in summa</tei:hi>, as I cannot often enough emphasize, four distinct works, not merely two, I would ask for 4,000 Kroner apiece (for <tei:hi rend="italic">Op. 106</tei:hi> I already obtained your agreement to an increase some time ago, explaining that I would be unable to edit it for less than 2,000 Kroner.)  Let me reiterate that where accomplishments intellectual in nature are concerned things cannot be any different from those that are physical in nature: in neither case can anything outlive the corpse<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn18"/> of him who is to accomplish the work.  What use would it be to you if my strength were to give out over the next task but one and I could then no longer accomplish any work, while there are still so formidably many works to come from my pen in fulfillment of my mission?</tei:p><tei:p>And so I come back finally to my initial proposal, that you might apply to the Ministry<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn19"/> for a grant.  Ultimately, the responsible party is surely the Ministry itself, which does not provide for me in my home country the possibility for work that they shell out in abundance to less capable and less significant musicians. Since I would be too proud to apply to the Ministry myself, which while owing me the greatest debt of gratitude has not once learned to honor its long overdue debt of gratitude, so they themselves<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn20"/> might now make an effort to effect a grant for the edition of the last two colossi<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn21"/>!  At all events, I hope, however, that you, dear [Director], have at least understood the principal thing, namely that it has to do solely with the possibility for work, and not with financial gain.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">[no valediction or signature]</tei:hi></tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>