<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 5/16, [4] : 12-25-08 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Heinrich Schenker.
© Transcription Ian D. Bent 2005.
© Translation Ian D. Bent 2005.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian D. Bent 2005.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>All reasonable steps have been taken to locate the heirs of Heinrich Schenker.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Universal Edition Archive (1908-1976)—on permanent loan to the Stadt- und Landesbibliothek Wien (1976-)</dcterms:provenance>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 12/25/1908 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Hertzka ~ HSchenker","UE ~ H+JSchenker","UE ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten draft letter from Schenker to Hertzka (UE) (unsent), dated December 25, 1908</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2005-03-31</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>[Niloff: Instrumentations-Tabelle:]  Acknowledges return of supplementary remarks; compares the content and price with those of editions of Goethe’s Faust.  Hertzka has forwarded letters from an Englishman.  Schenker answers his questions re: numbers on valve- and slide-instrument lines, omission of contrabass clarinet and heckelphone, and why no English or French music is included in the repertory listings.  Schenker asks how the heckelphone could be added to the Tabelle.  —Schenker answers criticisms by the reviewer in the [Wiener] Extrablatt.  Disparaging remarks about “the public.”

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Hertzka, Emil; UE;  Stritzko; Niloff; Instrumentations-Tabelle; Instrumentation Table;  supplement; Englishman; London; Mahillon, Victor; gourmand; public; reader; valve horn; trombone; valves; slide-positions; Goethe, Wolfgang; Faust; Fischer, Kuno; Jort; Düntzer, Heinrich; price; honorarium; contrabass clarinet; heckelphone; Strauss, Richard; Salome; France; England; military band instruments; music directors; repertory; Literatur; D'Indy; Massenet; Extrablatt; review; Lieder ohne Worte; Gevaert, François-Auguste; Berlioz, Hector; instrumentation; orchestration; Traité; Wöss, Josef Venantius von; </dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  —</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> — </marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten draft letter from Schenker to Hertzka (UE) (unsent), dated December 25, 1908</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="bold">See WSLB 33, January? 1?, 1909, for final version of this letter</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">Written in crayon in top-right corner:</tei:hi> ]  25/12 08</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Direktor !</tei:p><tei:p>Besten Dank für die Zusendung der 4<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  „4“ changed from „v“, presumably intending initially to write “vier”.</tei:note> §§ u. der Londoner Briefe. (Ich lese selbst Englisch nicht, eine Dame hat mir die Briefe vor einigen Tagen übersetzt, u. ich erwidere aus dem <tei:hi rend="italic">Gedächtnis</tei:hi> ! ) :</tei:p><tei:p>1)  H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Mahillon</tei:hi> giebt ein <tei:hi rend="italic">Vademecum de <tei:hi rend="italic">compositeur</tei:hi></tei:hi> (!), ich – gemäß der Einführung – wende mich an das <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Publikum</tei:hi></tei:hi> in der Hauptsache, u. in gewissen, wenigen Punkten nur an <tei:hi rend="italic">gourmands</tei:hi>, u. mehr als gewöhnlicher[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] K....tte[?]</tei:p><tei:p>2)  Die Ziffern bei den V. Hörnern u. Posaunen sind &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;ausdrücklich&lt;/sup&gt; <tei:hi rend="italic">oben</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> i.e.  in the key of symbols (“Zeichen“)  at the top of the Table: “Ziffern ohne Hornzeichen ... bedeuten bei Ventilinstrumenten die Ventile, bei Zuginstrumenten die Züge.” (Numbers without horn [stopping and half-stopping] signs in valve instruments denote valves, and in slide instruments positions.)</tei:note> als Ventile u. Züge erklärt worden.  Dieses hat Ihr [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] Engländer übersehen!</tei:p><tei:p>3)  <tei:hi rend="italic">Reclam</tei:hi> verkauft „Faust“ von <tei:hi rend="italic">Goethe</tei:hi> um 30–40 Kr u. legt nicht &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;noch&lt;/sup&gt; dazu Kommenten von Kuno Fischer,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> Kuno Fischer (1824–1907), writer on Spinoza, Kant, Hegel, Goethe, et al.: <tei:hi rend="italic">Goethes „Faust“</tei:hi>, 3rd edn, 4 vols (Stuttgart: J. G. Cotta, 1893); also <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Erklärung des goetheschen „Faust“, nach der Reihenfolge seiner Scenen</tei:hi>, 2 vols (Heidelberg: Carl Winter Universitätsverlag, c.1900), <tei:hi rend="italic">Goethe und Heidelberg</tei:hi>, 2nd edn (idem, 1900?), <tei:hi rend="italic">Goethes Iphigenie</tei:hi>, 2nd edn (idem, 1888?), <tei:hi rend="italic">Kritische Streifzüge wider die Unkritik</tei:hi> (idem, 1896), and other works.</tei:note> Jort<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Jort, or Jodl, or Dort, or Dorl ??</tei:note>, Düntzer<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> Heinrich Düntzer (1813–1901), writer on German literature and biographer of Goethe: <tei:hi rend="italic">Goethe als Dramatiker</tei:hi> (Leipzig: Engelmann, 1837); <tei:hi rend="italic">Goethe’s Prometheus und Pandora</tei:hi> (Leipzig: Dyk, 1850); <tei:hi rend="italic">Goethes Faust: erster und zweiter Teil</tei:hi> (Leipzig: E. Wartigs Verlag, 1887–89), et al.</tei:note> bei : der Käufer kauft auf eigene Verantwortung.  Will er mehr wissen, &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;z.B. über den II. Theil[,]&lt;/sup&gt; muß er andere Bändchen kaufen, u. wo diese seinem Wissensdrang nicht genügen, noch weitern.</tei:p><tei:p>So habe ich vorausgesetzt, daß der Leser mindestens Noten u. die Schlüssel beherrscht, etwas von der Naturscale gehört hat u.s.w.  Kann er dies nicht, so ist ihm um <tei:hi rend="italic">60 Kr</tei:hi>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  i.e. the originally agreed price.  Schenker had proposed that it be raised to 80 Kroner = 1 Florin (see WSLB 29, December 16). "60 Kr" double-underlined.</tei:note> nicht &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;auf einmal&lt;/sup&gt; zu helfen, weil um diesen Preis die Instrum. sammt Bildern, u. Klanglagen, u. Literaturbeispielen, u. allerhand <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Anregungen der Wißbegier (aber &lt;strike&gt;sich&lt;/strike&gt; um Schlüßel, Naturskale, Überblasen, sich erst zu bekümmern<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  In the accompanying text, which was not included until the 1912 edition, the natural scale and overblowing are explained with example in §2(a), and overblowing in greater detail in Comments I and III, with examples.  Treble and bass clefs, but not tenor and alto, are used in music examples, but are referred to only in passing, without explanation. </tei:note>) geboten zu haben, ein seltenes Geschenk des Autors ist, der selbst vom <tei:hi rend="italic">Publikum</tei:hi> nie je ein Geschenk gekriegt hat. 
 
4)  Kontrabaßklarinette fehlt; sie wird bei uns nicht gebraucht.</tei:p><tei:p>—<tei:hi rend="italic">Heckelphon</tei:hi> wurde um die Zeit, als + Stritzko<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8"> Click on <ref cRef="stritzko_joseph">Joseph Stritzko</ref>.</tei:note> die <tei:hi rend="italic">Tabelle</tei:hi> schon gedruckt[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] hat, noch nicht bekannt, da <tei:hi rend="italic">Strauss’ Salome</tei:hi> erst später kam.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Strauss's <tei:hi rend="italic">Salome</tei:hi> was first performed at the Dresden Court Opera on December 9, 1905, and at the Deutsches Volkstheater in Vienna on May 25, 1907.</tei:note>  Ich habe beider [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Instrumente nachträglich in § 3 ausdrücklich gedacht.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">   „So sind z. B. ... in der Familie der Oboe ... in jüngster Zeit Versuche mit einer Bariton-Oboe (Heckelphon) ...; der Klarinettenfamilie fehlt, um im praktischen Gebrauch wirklich komplett zu erscheinen, nur eine Kontrabaß-Klarinette ...“ (So, for example, ... in the oboe family [there have been] experiments most recently with a baritone oboe (heckelphone) ...;  all that is lacking in the clarinet family for it to be complete in practical terms is a contrabass clarinet ...“) The heckelphone’s place in the <tei:hi rend="italic">Tabelle</tei:hi> would have been between Nos. 10 and 11, and the contrabass clarinet’s between Nos. 19 and 20.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>5)  Da nicht England in der Musik tönengebend<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  or <tei:hi rend="italic">tonengebend</tei:hi> (unclear).</tei:note> ist, konnte ich nicht <tei:hi rend="italic">von Haus aus</tei:hi> die <tei:hi rend="italic">Tabelle</tei:hi> etwa für <tei:hi rend="italic">Engl.</tei:hi>, Frankreich setzen, am allerwenigsten für den Gebrauch dortiger mediocrer Kappelmeister.  Damit hängt es zusammen, daß ich mir einmal die bekannten Militär&lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;musik&lt;/sup&gt;stimmungen (B,—Es) u.zw. bei den <tei:hi rend="italic">Saxhörnern</tei:hi> regardiert, u. sonst mir literaturfähige Musik<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  The <tei:hi rend="italic">Tabelle</tei:hi> includes soprano (B flat = flügelhorn)), alto (E flat), tenor (B flat), bass (B flat = Euphonium), deep bass (E flat), and contrabass (low B flat = bombardon) saxhorns as Nos. 54-59.  There are no repertory citations for the saxhorns.</tei:note> (Militärkappelmeister machen keine Literatur!) anzuführen hatte.</tei:p><tei:p>6)  So erklärt es sich, daß ich nicht um einen <tei:hi rend="italic">Million Kronen</tei:hi>  den Namen <tei:hi rend="italic">d’Indy</tei:hi> oder <tei:hi rend="italic">Massenet</tei:hi>, (die nur Korporale unter den Komponisten sind) aufs Pagin<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  Doubtful reading: <tei:hi rend="italic">Pagina</tei:hi>, obsolete printer’s term for a page or folio sheet, is feminine.  Schenker’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Tabelle</tei:hi> measures 24.6” x 78” (63 x 198.1 cms), comprising two overlapped sheets, 24.6” x 39.25” (63 x 99.7), and 24.6” x 39.75” (63 x 101), which suggests that the latter are Double Royal (25" x 40") or Double Elephant (27" x 40") folios cut down. (Schenker does use <tei:hi rend="italic">Pagina</tei:hi> elsewhere, e.g. in his diary for August 29, 1906: "Ordnen aller Pagina, Arbeiten, Mscpte etc.", OJ 1/5, p.18.)</tei:note> gesetz hätte, dort, wo ich die großartigsten Instrumentalvisionen unserer größten Meister citiere.  <tei:hi rend="italic">D’Indy</tei:hi> u. <tei:hi rend="italic">Massenet</tei:hi> sind nicht in der Lage zu — kreieren, nur <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> größere Meister können es.  Ihr Engländer scheint kein <tei:hi rend="italic">gourmand</tei:hi> zu sein, ihm ist Zeitungsberümtheit auch Nachwelt zugleich.</tei:p><tei:p>7)  Der Esel vom <tei:hi rend="italic">Extrablatt</tei:hi> hat übersehen, daß ich, eben dies, was er wünscht, eine historische Skizze des Orchesters, in den Beispielen geboten habe.  Hier ist eine „Geschichte ohne Worte“ (um mich an die „Lieder ohne Worte“ anzulehnen), eine Geschichte, wie sich nicht bei <tei:hi rend="italic">Geväert</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14"> i.e. François-Auguste Gevaert, <tei:hi rend="italic">Traité général d’instrumentation</tei:hi> (Ghent &amp; Liège: Gevaert, 1863 = <tei:hi rend="italic">Nouveau traité</tei:hi>, 1885) and <tei:hi rend="italic">Cours méthodique d’orchestration</tei:hi> (Paris &amp; Brussels: Lemoine, 1890). </tei:note> nicht bei <tei:hi rend="italic">Berlioz</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15">  Hector Berlioz, <tei:hi rend="italic">Grand traité d’instrumentation et d’orchestration modernes</tei:hi> (Paris: ?, 1844); Berlioz-Strauss: Berlioz, <tei:hi rend="italic">Grand traité</tei:hi>, Ger. trans. A. Dörffel [1864], rev. R.Strauss: <tei:hi rend="italic">Instrumentationslehre</tei:hi> (Leipzig: Peters, [1904–05]).</tei:note> anzutreffen ist, u. für die allein, als das Ergebnis jahrelanger Studien, ich wohl das splendideste Honorar verdient hätte, — sie ist da, u. der Dummkopf <tei:hi rend="italic">erkennt sie einfach nicht</tei:hi>, (weil er nichts davon versteht, so lange Worte fehlen!), u. <tei:hi rend="italic">wünscht</tei:hi>&lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;(!)&lt;/sup&gt; erst eine Skizze.  Der Engländer ist nicht weit davon gefallen: die <tei:hi rend="italic">V. Symph. von Beeth.</tei:hi> kreiert zum 1mal das <tei:hi rend="italic">Piccolo</tei:hi> für die <tei:hi rend="italic">Symph.</tei:hi>, u. in einer nirgends mehr überbotenen genialen Weise.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn16">  This reflects a passage in the unpublished <tei:hi rend="italic">Niedergang der Kompositionskunst</tei:hi> (dating from the period c.1906–09)  in which Schenker extrapolates Beethoven’s reasons, as he sees them, for not introducing the piccolo until the last movement of the Fifth Symphony: OC 31/28–153, pp. 34–5.  An edition and translation by William Drabkin is available in <tei:hi rend="italic">Music Analysis</tei:hi> 24/1-2 (March-July 2005), 33-232.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>8)  Würde ich die Erklärung bei den Ventilen u. Zügen erklärt haben, würde der Käufer erst recht fragen: „Und wozu das? Und warum das?“  Würde ich auch darauf antworten, er hätte eine weitere Frage bereit, bis zur letzten Frage: „Wozu Gott die Musik erschaffen hat“?  Auch bei <tei:hi rend="italic">Gevaert</tei:hi> sind an 1000 Fragen noch nützlich, trotz[?] dem Preis von <tei:hi rend="italic">18 Fl</tei:hi>.! Zumal bei <tei:hi rend="italic">Berlioz</tei:hi>! <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Das <tei:hi rend="italic">Publikum</tei:hi> kann, wie ein Kind, ins Endlose fragen, aber  es geht nicht an, daß ich auch noch Anweisungen auf <tei:hi rend="italic">Privatstunden</tei:hi> ausstelle jedem Käufer der <tei:hi rend="italic">Tabelle</tei:hi>, vielleicht <tei:hi rend="italic">Theks</tei:hi>[?] u. <tei:hi rend="italic">Abonnements</tei:hi> zu den jahrlf. Konz. verteile, — Alles um 60 Kr !</tei:p><tei:p>Es folgt aus alle dem, daß ich Ihren Engländer für keinen besonders feinen Kopf halte.  Alles an seinem Platze !</tei:p><tei:p>Wie sollte aber <tei:hi rend="italic">Heckelphon</tei:hi> nachgetragen[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>][?] werden „ohne Umsturz“,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn17">  A reference to Hertzka’s letter of December 21, OC 52/31, regarding the Mahillon manual that Hertzka has sent Schenker: „Wenn Sie das eine oder andere in dem Werke finden, was  zur Komplettierung Ihrer Instrumental–Tabelle in der gegenwärtigen Form dienen kann, ohne dass wir einen Umsturz vorzunehmen haben, so wäre das ja immerhin ganz erwünscht.“ (If you find something or other in the work pertinent to the completion of your <tei:hi rend="italic">Instrumentations-Tabelle</tei:hi> in its present form, without our having an upheaval on our hands, that would be very welcome.)</tei:note> ohne Bild?  Ein paar abgerissene Worte machen sich läppisch aus, wenn sie nur auf ein Instrument zielen.  Entweder Alles oder gar nichts.</tei:p><tei:p>Vielleicht weiß H. <tei:hi rend="italic">v. Wöß</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn18"> Click on <ref cRef="woss_josef_venantius">Josef Venantius von Wöss</ref>.</tei:note> einen Ausweg „ohne Umsturz,“ der aber den Geschmack nicht beleidigt?</tei:p><tei:p>Daß eine solche Kleinigkeit so viel Zeit raubt, hätte ich nie gedacht!  Man soll dem <tei:hi rend="italic">Publikum</tei:hi> eben nichts — schenken, es will dann <tei:hi rend="italic">arrogant</tei:hi>enweise nur das paar Kreuzer Endloses, Endloses!</tei:p><tei:p>Mit ausgezeichneter Hochachtung
Ihr ergb
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  H Schenker</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten draft letter from Schenker to Hertzka (UE) (unsent), dated December 25, 1908</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="bold">See WSLB 33, January? 1?, 1909, for final version of this letter</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">Written in crayon in top-right corner:</tei:hi> ]  25/12 08</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Director,</tei:p><tei:p>Many thanks for sending my four<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> paragraphs and the London letters.  (I do not myself read English, [but] a lady translated the letters for me a few days ago, and I am replying <tei:hi rend="italic">from memory</tei:hi>!)</tei:p><tei:p>1)  Mr. Mahillon provides a <tei:hi rend="italic">Vademecum</tei:hi> for the <tei:hi rend="italic">composer</tei:hi>(!), I—in keeping with the Introduction—address myself primarily to the <tei:hi rend="italic">public</tei:hi>, and at a few particular points to <tei:hi rend="italic">gourmands</tei:hi>, and more than usual [...?].</tei:p><tei:p>2)  The numbers on the valve-horn and trombone lines are &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;expressly&lt;/sup&gt; explained <tei:hi rend="italic">above</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> as valves and slide-positions.</tei:p><tei:p>3)  Reclam sells Goethe’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Faust</tei:hi> for 30–40 Kroner and &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;still&lt;/sup&gt; does not include comments by Kuno Fischer,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> Jort[?]<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>, [or] Düntzer<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>: the buyer purchases on his own responsibility.  Should he want to know more, &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;e.g. about Part II,&lt;/sup&gt; he must purchase other volumes, and if these do not satisfy his desire for knowledge [he must purchase] still further ones.</tei:p><tei:p>Thus I have taken for granted that my reader has mastered at least notes and clefs, and has heard something of the natural scale, etc.  If he cannot do this, then for <tei:hi rend="italic">60 Kroner</tei:hi>!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> there is no way of helping him &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;immediately&lt;/sup&gt;, because to have offered the instruments at this price along with pictures, pitch-ranges, examples from the repertory, and a great many <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> stimulants to the thirst for knowledge (but first taking care for himself of clefs, the natural scale, [and] overblowing<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>) is a rare gift on the part of the author, who himself has never received a single gift from the public.</tei:p><tei:p>4)  The contrabass clarinet is lacking; it is not used by us.</tei:p><tei:p>—The heckelphone was still unknown at the time when Stritzko<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> printed the <tei:hi rend="italic">Table</tei:hi>, since Strauss’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Salome</tei:hi> came only later.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/>  I have subsequently referred explicitly to both instruments in paragraph 3.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/></tei:p><tei:p>5)  Since England is not creative in music,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> I was <tei:hi rend="italic">from the outset</tei:hi> unable to set the <tei:hi rend="italic">Table</tei:hi> up for England and France, at the very least for use by the mediocre music directors that exist there.  It is for that reason that I even took account of the keys known to me in which military &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;music&lt;/sup&gt; instruments are built (B flat, E flat), viz. in the case of the saxhorns, and otherwise[?] cited music worthy of the repertory.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> (Military band masters do not make repertory!)</tei:p><tei:p>6)  This explains why I would not for a million Kroner have included the names D’Indy or Massenet (who are mere foot soldiers among composers) on the folio sheet<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/>, in the very place where I cite the most sublime instrumental visions of our great masters.  D’Indy and Massenet are simply not up to creating—only <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> greater composers can do that.  Your Englishman appears to be no <tei:hi rend="italic">gourmand</tei:hi>;  to him, newspaper celebrity is synonymous with posthumous fame.</tei:p><tei:p>7) That idiot at the [<tei:hi rend="italic">Wiener</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">Extrablatt</tei:hi> has overlooked the fact that I have already provided in the examples precisely what he wants, namely a historical sketch of the orchestra.  Here you have a “History without Words” (if I may paraphrase “Songs without Words”), a history such as you will not find in Gevaert<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/> or in Berlioz,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn15"/> the fruit of long years of study, for which in its own right I ought assuredly to have earned the most magnificent honorarium.   It is right there, and the numskull <tei:hi rend="italic">simply does not recognize it</tei:hi> (because he cannot make head or tail of anything if it has no words!), and is still <tei:hi rend="italic">asking for</tei:hi>&lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;(!)&lt;/sup&gt; a sketch.  The Englishman is almost as bad as that: Beethoven’s Fifth Symphony makes the piccolo into a symphonic instrument for the first time and by a stroke of genius that has nowhere been surpassed.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn16"/></tei:p><tei:p>8)  Were I to elaborate on the explanation of the valves and slide positions, the purchaser would merely ask:  “And what is that for?” “And why is that so?”  And were I to answer those questions too, he would be ready with another question, and so on until we reached: “For what purpose did God create music?”  Even with the Gevaert, there are a thousand questions still to be asked, despite the price of 18 Florins!  Even more so with the Berlioz!  <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Exactly like a child, the public can go on asking questions to the end of time.  However, it is just not on for me to have to issue bits of advice in my own time as well to every purchaser of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Table</tei:hi>, [and] perhaps distribute tickets[?] and subscriptions to the season’s[?] concerts[?]—all for 60 Kronen!</tei:p><tei:p>From all of this you can see that I have no great opinion of your Englishman.  Everyone in his rightful place!</tei:p><tei:p>But how should we add the heckelphone “without causing an upheaval”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn17"/>, [and] without a picture?  A handful of isolated words look silly when aimed at only one instrument.  All or nothing.</tei:p><tei:p>Perhaps Mr. von Wöß<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn18"/> can think of a solution "without upheaval“ which does not offend good taste?</tei:p><tei:p>I would never have imagined that such a small thing could take up so much time!  One should never make a present of anything to the public.  It will only go on insolently [demanding] more and more small change!</tei:p><tei:p>With kind regards,
Yours truly,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  H. Schenker</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>