<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 36/19, [3] : 8-12-51 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Oswald Jonas, published here with kind permission.
© Transcription Christoph Hust 200l.
© Translation Ian Bent 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Christoph Hust, 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> Permission to publish on this website granted by the heirs of Oswald Jonas, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance> Jonas, Oswald (1951-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Oswald Jonas; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Christoph Hust &amp; Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 08/12/1951 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: &quot;Furtw&#195;&#164;ngler ~ Jonas&quot;,&quot;Jonas ~ Furtw&#195;&#164;ngler&quot; --><dc:title>Carbon copy of a typewritten letter from Jonas to Furtwängler, dated August 12, 1951</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-12-04</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>J thanks F for his kindness to his family while visiting Europe.  —He recounts the conditions under which he works, and the difficulty he has disseminating Schenker's theory;  he is convinced Schenker's works must be republished in German. —He has prepared an introduction and commentary to Harmonielehre and a book of Brahms documents, and has started a commentary on Der freie Satz.  —He has failed in his attempts to interest foundations in publishing the unpublished materials in Schenker's Nachlaß, and asks whether F can himself help.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Jonas, Oswald; Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Mozart;  Zauberflöte;  Magic Flute;  Weisse, Hans;  conditions of work;  republication;  translation;  Harmonielehre;  Theory of Harmony;  Brahms;  Der freie Satz;  Free Composition;  Nachlaß;  Guggenheim Foundation;  Fulbright Commission;  Library of Congress;  Sessions, Roger;  Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst;  Vienna Conservatory;  die Schweiz;  Switzerland;  Deutschland;  Germany;  Österreich;  Austria;  Wien;  Vienna</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> 1719 North Park Drive, Chicago 14, Ill.</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Carbon copy of typewritten letter from Oswald Jonas to Wilhelm Furtwängler, dated August 12, 1951, unsigned</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>12. August 1951
1719 North Park Av.
Chicago 14, Ill.</tei:p><tei:p>Lieber, sehr verehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Zunächst möchte ich Ihnen sehr herzlich für die freundliche Aufnahme danken, die Sie meiner Familie haben zuteil werden lassen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> It would appear that J’s family was traveling in Europe, and that F received them, while J remained in Chicago.  </tei:note> Ich bekam gerade einen begeisterten Brief mit einem Bericht über die "Zauberflöte"; die Aufführung war der Höhepunkt des Aufenthaltes in Europa. –<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  S inserts an emdash at this point, and continues writing without paragraph break.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Seit langer Zeit trage ich mich mit dem Gedanken, Ihnen etwas ausführlicher über die Verhältnisse hier zu schreiben, nicht zuletzt über die besonderen Schwierigkeiten, denen man hier begegnet.  Wenn ich nicht dieselbe Erfahrung gemacht habe wie seinerzeit Dr. Weisse<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.  </tei:note> – es mag dies mehr persönliche Gründe haben und weil ich mehr versucht habe, den Menschen hier Verständnis entgegen zubringen – und wenn ich auch eine große Anzahl von Freunden und ergebenen Schülern, besonders unter der Jugend, gefunden habe, das alles kann die Hauptschwierigkeit nicht beseitigen: der Lehre Schenkers jenen Platz zu sichern, der ihr in der heutigen Welt der Musik zukommt. Der Lehrplan, der vorgeschriebene, und damit verbunden die Eifersucht der Lehrer, die Schwierigkeit der Übersetzung, das alles sind Punkte, die nicht nur der mündlichen Verbreitung, sondern auch der Publikation im Wege stehen. So bin ich – besonders seit dem vergangenen Jahr – immer mehr zur Überzeugung gekommen, daß alle die Dinge zunächst wieder in deutscher Sprache herauszukommen haben – und wenn übersetzt, dann zunächst in England. –<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  S inserts an emdash at this point, and continues writing without paragraph break.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ich hatte <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Ihnen bereits in meinem vorigen Brief<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> OJ 36/19, [2], February 7, 1949.  </tei:note> angedeutet, daß ich eine Einleitung und einen Kommentar zu einem Neudruck der Harmonielehre ausgearbeitet habe, der sehr wahrscheinlich bei der U. E. herauskommen wird – wenn nicht, wie ich manchmal fürchte, wieder die übliche sabotage praktiziert werden wird und kein Druck von kompetenter Stelle ausgeübt wird.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  S’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi>, published by UE in 1906, was never reissued in German.  A condensed version was worked on by Otto Vrieslander between 1932 and 1938, for use at the Vienna Conservatory, but the war intervened.  Jonas’s desire for a second German edition of <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> came to nothing, but he did persuade UE to publish a second, revised edition by him of <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi> (1956) and a “new edition” of <tei:hi rend="italic">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven</tei:hi> (1971–72).  His introduction and commentary formed part of the English translation by Elisabeth Mann Borgese, published as <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmony</tei:hi> (Chicago: Chicago University Press, 1954).  </tei:note> Ferner arbeite ich an einem Brahms-Buch, bestehend aus nur dokumentarischem Material, das ich mit erlä[u]terndem und verbindendem Text versehe – es ist unter all diesen Briefstellen und Aussprüchen eine wahre Fundgrube für den lernenden und ausübenden Musiker.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  This book never reached publication.</tei:note> Ausserdem habe ich einen Kommentar zu dem "Freien Satz" in Angriff genommen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8"> This presumably follows on from J’s statement in OJ 36/19, [2], February 7, 1949, that he hoped to edit some items from Schenker’s surviving papers, then in the possession of Ernst Oster.  No such commentary every came to publication, only the Foreword to his second, revised edition of <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi> (Vienna: UE, 1956), vol. I, pp. 11–13, Eng. trans. (New York &amp; London: Longman, 1979), vol. I, pp. xv–xvi, in which he briefly described the sketches and draft among S’s papers, and claimed to have rectified some of the shortcomings of the 1935 first edition.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Der eigentliche Hauptpunkt aber ist: Schenkers Nachlass. Ein früherer Schüler von mir, Ernst Oster,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9"> Click on <ref cRef="oster_ernst">Ernst Oster</ref>.  </tei:note> ein sehr gediegener und ernster Musiker, hat einen Großteil des Nachlasses nach Amerika gerettet. Ich glaube, daß Sie seinerzeit ein Verzeichnis (38 Seiten!!)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10"> Two carbon copies of a typed list, prepared by <ref cRef="schenker_jeanette">Jeanette Schenker</ref>, dated “7.XI.1935,” with additions dated “14. I. 1936,” comprising twenty-nine pages, and a further annotated partial copy, all three with annotations by <ref cRef="oster_ernst">Ernst Oster</ref>, are preserved in the Oster Collection at the New York Public Library, and are reproduced on reel 1 of the microfilm of this collection.  How this list, which was presumably available to J, related to that allegedly in F’s hands, is unknown.  </tei:note> durch Frau Schenker<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Click on <ref cRef="schenker_jeanette">Jeanette Schenker</ref>.  </tei:note>bekommen haben; da sind druckfertige Ausgaben, Analysen und vor allem eine Menge Material (Vortragslehre!!!), das bearbeitet und druckfertig gemacht werden muß. Das ist freilich eine Arbeit die unter den obwaltenden Umständen auch bei übermenschlicher Anstrengung nicht ohne Hilfe geleistet werden kann.  Ich habe wiederholt verschiedene Foundations zu interessieren versucht (Guggenheim, sogar Fulbright – hatte glänzende Empfehlungen von der Library of Congress, wo meine Arbeit wirklich sehr geschätzt wird), habe Roger Sessions,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Roger H. Sessions (1896–1985).</tei:note> der an der Lehre Schenkers mehr interessiert ist, interpolliert – er ist momentan in Zürich – – alles vergebens. Für diese Dinge ist kein Geld da und keine <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Möglichkeit. Unbeschadet der Tatsache, daß auf diese Weise ein wichtiges Kulturgut verloren geht – ein Kulturgut, das in unserer Zeit der Verwirrung &lt;strike&gt;von doppelter Bedeutung&lt;/strike&gt;|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  This phrase is not deleted on the carbon copy, but is assumed to have been on the finished letter (which is not known to survive).</tei:note> für den Wiederaufbau der Musik von höchster Bedeutung wäre. In Wien habe ich noch eine kleine Anzahl begeisterter Schüler – aber Begeisterung allein kann es in diesem Fall nicht machen – sie sind Lehrer an der Akademie<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  The Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst, i.e. the Vienna Conservatory.  </tei:note> und müssen arbeiten, um den notwendigen Unterhalt zu haben.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich habe vieles versucht, vieles überlegt, ehe ich zu [dem] Entschluß gekommen bin, Ihnen über all das zu schreiben.  Ich tue es vor allem aus einem Pflichtgefühl der großen Sache gegenüber, wenn ich Sie frage, ob Sie irgendeine Möglichkeit der Hilfe sehen, ob Sie selbst in irgendeiner Form helfen könnten. Wäre es durch Ihre Befürwortung möglich, für ein Jahr einen Platz, eine Stelle in der Schweiz, in Deutschland oder in Österreich zu finden, wo ich, ohne mit Lehrtätigkeit überbelastet zu sein, wenigstens den Hauptteil des Projektes ausarbeiten könnte – die Leute in Wien würden, soweit es in ihren Kräften steht, mit Freude mitarbeiten und helfen. – Dann aber auch Verlagshäuser zu interessieren – eventuell auch für die oben beschriebene Arbeit, die so gut wie fertig ist. (Brahms etc.)</tei:p><tei:p>Verehrter Herr Doktor, Sie kennen mich lange genug, um zu wissen und mir zu glauben, daß ich diesen Brief nicht schreiben würde, wenn ich nicht von der absoluten Notwendigkeit desselben überzeugt wäre. Was immer Sie in Erwägung ziehen mögen[,] seien Sie stets meiner größten Verehrung und Dankbarkeit versichert!</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">unsigned</tei:hi>]</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Carbon copy of typewritten letter from Oswald Jonas to Wilhelm Furtwängler, dated August 12, 1951, unsigned</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>August 12, 1951
1719 North Park Av.
Chicago 14, Ill.</tei:p><tei:p>Dear, highly esteemed Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>First I should like to thank you most cordially for the kind reception that you granted my family.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  I have just received an enthusiastic letter with a report of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Magic Flute</tei:hi>;  the performance was the highpoint of the[ir] European stay. —<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/></tei:p><tei:p>I have for a long time now been intending to write to you in greater detail about the conditions here, not least about the particular difficulties that one encounters here.  If I have not had the same experience as Dr. Weisse at an earlier time<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>—and this may be more for personal reasons and because I have tried harder to reach an understanding with the people here—and if, too, I have acquired a large number of friends and devoted students, especially among the younger generation, all of this cannot mask the principal difficulty:  securing for Schenker’s theory the place that befits it in the world of music today.  The syllabus that is prescribed, and along with that the jealousy of the teachers, the difficulty of translation—these are all obstacles that stand in the way not only of dissemination by word of mouth but also of publication.  Thus I have come—especially over the past year—ineluctably to the conviction that all the items must first be published again in German, and if translated, then first in England. —<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/></tei:p><tei:p>I already <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> intimated to you in my previous letter<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> that I have prepared an introduction and a commentary to a new edition of [Schenker’s] <tei:hi rend="italic">Theory of Harmony</tei:hi> that will very likely be published by UE—just so long as people do not, as I often fear they may, again sabotage it in the customary fashion such that no pressure will be exerted by any competent authority.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/>  Furthermore, I am working on a Brahms book comprising only documentary material, for which I have provided explanatory and accompanying text—among all these sayings and passages quoted from letters there is a veritable treasure-trove for music students and practising musicians.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>  In addition, I have embarked upon a commentary to <tei:hi rend="italic">Free Composition</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/></tei:p><tei:p>The really essential thing, however, is Schenker’s surviving papers.  An erstwhile pupil of mine, Ernst Oster,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> a very sound and serious-minded musician, has rescued the majority of the surviving papers and brought them to America.  I gather that you received, some time ago, a list (38 pages!!)<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> from Mrs. Schenker;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/>  among these are editions and analyses that are ready for publication, and above all a host of material (theory of performance!!!) that must be worked on and prepared for publication.  This, it must be admitted, is a task that cannot be accomplished under the prevailing circumstances, even with superhuman exertion, without help.  I have repeatedly tried to interest various foundations (Guggenheim, even Fulbright—I had glowing recommendations from the Library of Congress, where my work is really highly regarded), I involved Roger Sessions,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> who is more interested in Schenker’s theory—he is currently in Zurich:  all in vain.  For these things there is no money and no <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> prospect.  Irrespective of the fact that in this way an important cultural asset is going to waste—a cultural asset that would in these times of bewilderment be of the greatest significance for the rebuilding of music.  In Vienna, I have a small number of enthusiastic pupils;  but enthusiasm alone is not enough in this case: they are teachers at the Academy<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/> and and have to work in order to have the necessary subsistence.</tei:p><tei:p>I have tried many things, have pondered many things, before reaching the decision to write about all of this to you.  It is above all out of a sense of duty toward the great cause that I now ask you whether you see any possibility whatsoever for help, whether you could yourself provide help in any form.  If it were possible through your advocacy to find a post, a position in Switzerland, in Germany or in Austria for a year where I could, without being overburdened with teaching duties, at least work out the bulk of the project, the people in Vienna would, so far as it were in their power, gladly collaborate and help. — But then [I would try] also to interest publishing houses, possibly even for the work described above, which is as good as ready.  (Brahms, etc.)</tei:p><tei:p>Esteemed Doctor, you have been acquainted with me long enough to know and to believe me [when I say] that I would not write this letter were I not convinced of its absolute necessity.  Whatever you might contemplate, be assured of my constant greatest admiration and gratitude!</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">unsigned</tei:hi>]</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>