<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/35, 2 : 1-27-17 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Translation Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Lee A. Rothfarb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2000, and is published with the agreement of the heirs of August Halm 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1917-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Lee Rothfarb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 01/27/1917 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Halm ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated January 27, 1917</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-03-03</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Discusses plans for his Piano Method (Klavierschule), which he intends to submit to UE.  Publication of his article on this has been delayed. Describes other works ready for publication, and his current wartime post. 

</dc:description><dc:subject>Halm, August; Schenker, Heinrich;  Klavierschule; piano method; Das neue Österreich; New Austria; Wächter, Baron Eberhard von; article; Hausmusik; serenade; suite; teacher training institute</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Stuttgart, Lehenstraße 21</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated January 27, 1917</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>27.I.17</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Professor,</tei:p><tei:p>Mein Klaviersatz ist mit meinen musikalischen Bedürfnissen zusammen gewachsen, infolgedessen mehr von der Klavierauszugstechnik bestimmt worden.  Ich danke Ihnen aber für Ihre diesbezüglichen Ausführungen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Federhofer transcribes the first sentence of this letter in Heinrich Schenker:  <tei:hi rend="italic">Nach Tagebüchern und Briefen</tei:hi>, 135.  The letter to which H replies appears not to have survived.</tei:note> — Meine Klavierschule denke ich mir zunächst nur in etwa 5-7 Druckbögen;<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Halm’s piano method (<tei:hi rend="italic">Klavierübung</tei:hi>) embraces three volumes: vol. 1, Stuttgart, Zumsteeg, 1918; vol. 2, ed. Willi Apel (a former Wickersdorf student of Halm), 1932; vol. 3 (unpublished).</tei:note> ich könnte mich darüber nur ziemlich ausführlich erklären u. bedauere daher doppelt die Verzögerung, die mein Aufsatz darüber erleidet, den Sie wahrscheinlich immer nocht nicht erhalten haben.  Ich schrieb an den musikalischen Schriftleiter der Zeischrift “Das neue Österreich” (existiert sie noch?) Herrn Baron von Wächter,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Wächter, Baron Eberhard von [create biogfile]</tei:note> seit langem vergeblich, hernach an die Chefredaktion—gleichermaßen ohne <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Antwort zu erhalten, so daß ich fürchte, die Zeitschrift hat &lt;strike&gt;sich&lt;/strike&gt; ihr Erscheinen unterbrochen u. meine Arbeit liegt irgendwo in einem verschlossenen Büro.  Nach einiger Zeit werde ich ja auch ein druckfertiges Manuskript meiner Klavierschule haben, das ich dann der Univ.-Edition vorlegen kann.  Nimmt sie dann überhaupt gegenwärtig neue Sachen an?  Ich hätte eine Serenade (Streichtrio, für Schul- u. Hausmusik geeignet) druckfertig,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Probably refers to one of Halm’s three serenades for string trio (G major, C major, G major), published in volumes 11 and 12 in Bärenreiter’s series of Halm’s chamber music, first published in <tei:hi rend="italic">Hausmusik</tei:hi>, ed. Fritz Jöde, vols. 4-5 (Wolfenbüttel, 1919). </tei:note> bald auch eine &lt;strike&gt;Sonate&lt;/strike&gt; &lt;strike&gt;bzw.&lt;/strike&gt; Suite f. Viol. u. Cello mit Klavierbegleitung (gleichfalls für Liebhaber u. Schüler gedacht).<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Probably refers to one of Halm’s three suites for piano trio (D major, C major, B minor), published in volumes 2 and 3 in Bärenreiter’s series of Halm’s chamber music (Kassel, Bärenreiter, 1922), the first of which appeared as supplement in the <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue Musikzeitung</tei:hi> 40 (1919).</tei:note>  Ich unterrichte seit Kriegsausbruch an einem Lehrerseminar als Hilfslehrer u. habe meine &lt;strike&gt;wenige&lt;/strike&gt; Freizeit zum größten Teil solchen Bedürfnissen gewidmet.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  During World War I, Halm taught as adjunct faculty at a teaching training institute in Esslingen, just outside of Stuttgart (Protestant Teacher’s College, Evangelische Lehrerbildungsanstalt) from 1914 to 1918.</tei:note>  Mit hochachtungsvollem Gruß</tei:p><tei:p>Stuttgart		[signed:] A. Halm
Lehenstr. 21</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated January 27, 1917</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>January 27, 1917</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor!</tei:p><tei:p>My compositional style for piano is fused with my musical requirements, consequently more determined by techniques of piano arrangements.  However, I thank you for your comments in this regard.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  Initially, I imagine my piano method in only 5-7 gatherings;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> I could only explain rather extensively and regret doubly, therefore, the delay that my essay on the topic has experienced, which you probably still have not received.  Some time ago, I wrote in vain to the editor of the periodical <tei:hi rend="italic">Das neue Österreich</tei:hi> (does it still exist?), Baron von Wächter,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> and thereafter to the office of the editor in chief—similarly without <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> receiving an answer.  I fear, therefore, that the appearance of the periodical has been interrupted, and my work is lying somewhere in a locked office.  After a time I will of course also have a manuscript of my piano method ready for print which I can present to Universal Edition.  Are they even currently accepting new things?  I could have a serenade (string trio, suitable for school and domestic music-making) ready for print,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> and soon a &lt;strike&gt;sonata, or rather&lt;/strike&gt; suite for violin and cello with piano accompaniment (also conceived for amateurs and students).<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  Since war broke out, I am teaching at a teacher training institute as adjunct faculty and for the most part have devoted my &lt;strike&gt;scant&lt;/strike&gt; free time to such necessities.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> With respectful greetings</tei:p><tei:p>Stuttgart  [ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] August Halm
Lehen Street 21</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>