<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/35, 23 : 4-6/15-25 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain; published with the permission of the heirs of August Halm, March 2006.
© Transcription Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Translation Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Lee Rothfarb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2000, and is published with the permission of the heirs of August Halm, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1925-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Lee Rothfarb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 04/15/1925 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Halm ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated April 6/15, 1925</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>H explains why he has not written before; wishes S luck with move from UE to Drei-Masken-Verlag; reports events at Freie Schulgemeinde.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Halm, August; Schenker, Heinrich;  A major Symphony;  performance;  Leonhardt;  Stuttgart;  Freie Schulgemeinde;  Free School Community;  Jüst;  Pollak</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated April 6/15, 1925</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>6/15.IV.25</tei:p><tei:p>Lieber u. verehrter Herr Professor!</tei:p><tei:p>Es ist mir immer wieder leid gewesen, daß ich Ihnen nicht schrieb.  Die Zeit bis zu den Osterferien war in mancher Hinsicht ungünstig dafür; eine der Behinderungen aber war erfreulich:  ich hatte die Aufführung meiner A dur-Sÿmphonie vorzubereiten, d.h. die Stimmen dazu zu schreiben.  Am 23. war die Aufführung; Leonhardt in Stuttgart dirigierte sie sehr gut, u. ich hatte, wenn auch schon in den vorhergehenden Proben, die größte Freude an dieser meiner Musik u. ihrem Klang.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  No paragraph-break at this point; but, from the slight gap, and the change of writing, this would appear to be the point at which H resumed the letter on April 15, after a nine-day break.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Zu Ihrer Übersiedlung in den neuen Verlag<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Schenker moved from Universal Edition to Drei-Masken-Verlag of Munich in 1925, and published with them the three volumes of <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi> (1925, 1926, 1930).</tei:note> wünsche ich Ihnen u. Ihren Lesern alles Gute; mögen die unnötigen zeit^raubenden^ u. nervenaufreibenden Schwierigkeiten nun alle wegfallen u. nur die sachlich notwendige Mühe, der man sich ja gern unterzieht, übrig bleiben!   Sie dürfen nicht denken, daß mir <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> das Schicksal Ihrer Arbeit nicht am Herzen liegt, weil ich lang nicht schrieb.  Ich hatte bewegte Zeit:  Meine Pflichten in der Freien Schulgemeinde hatten sich stark vermehrt u. außerdem war eine Übergangszeit mit mancherlei Kämpfen, die wir nun wohl als endgültig beseitigt ansehen dürfen; eine Gruppe von Lehrern hat hier eine Neugründung an der Nordsee auf der Insel Jüst vorbereitet u. ist nun zu Ostern abgezogen.  Die Trennung sollte in kamaradschaftlicher Gesinnung vor sich gehen; trotzdem war es eine starke Belastung unseres Gemeinschaftslebens.  Die wenige freie Zeit mußte ich dazu verwenden, die Stimmen einer Sÿmphonie auszuschreiben, die Professor Leonhardt in Stuttgart—ja das schrieb ich ja schon, wie ich eben sehe.  Dann kam noch ein Jugendtagung in Halle, von der ich gestern zurückkehrte.  Hat sich Professor Pollak einstweilen ein- [<tei:hi rend="italic">remainder cut off</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">written vertically in the left margin, top to bottom:</tei:hi>
Herzlichen Gruß von Ihrem</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] A. Halm]</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated April 6/15, 1925</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>April 6/15, 1925
Dear Professor,</tei:p><tei:p>I regret time and again that I have not written you.  The period up until Easter was in various regards inconvenient for it.  One of the obstacles was heartening.  I had to prepare for the performance of my A-major symphony, i.e. to write out the parts for it.  The performance was on the 23rd.  Leonhardt in Stuttgart conducted it very well, and I had the greatest joy from the music and its sound, even in the preceding rehearsals.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>I wish you and your readers the best on your move to the new publisher.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  May unnecessary, time^-consuming^ and nerve-wracking difficulties all vanish now, and only the substantively necessary effort remain!  You should not think that <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> the fate of your work is not on my mind because I have not written in so long.  I had a busy time.  My obligations in the Free School Community had increased considerably, and furthermore there was a transitional period with various conflicts that we may now view as definitively eliminated.  A group of teachers had prepared for establishing a new school on the North Sea island of Jüst, and withdrew at Easter.  The separation was supposed to take place with a collegial  attitude.  Despite that, it was a heavy burden on our communal life.  I had to use the little free time to write out the parts of a symphony that professor Leonhardt in Stuttgart—oh, I wrote that already as I now see.  Then, there was a youth conference in Halle, from which I returned yesterday.  Did Professor Pollak [<tei:hi rend="italic">remainder cut off</tei:hi>] in the meantime</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">written vertically in the left margin, top to bottom:</tei:hi> Cordial greetings from Your</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] A. Halm]</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>