<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/35, 1 : 1-4-17 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Translation Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Lee A. Rothfarb, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2000, and is published with the agreement of the heirs of August Halm 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1917-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Lee Rothbarb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 01/04/1917 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Halm ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated January 4, 1917</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-03-03</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>In response to a letter from S, H has sent him a recent piano volume, encloses a brochure on his violin method, and reports on others of his publications, released and forthcoming.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Halm, August; Schenker, Heinrich; Klavierheft; piano volume; Neues Österreich; New Austria; Wächter, Baron Eberhard von; Harmersdorf; Vienna; Kontrapunkt; Counterpoint; Von Zwei Kulturen der Musik; Of Two Cultures of Music; Von Grenzen u. Ländern der Musik; Of Borders and Countries of Music; Violinübung; Violin Method; Kretzschmar, Hermann; Bekker, Paul</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated January 4, 1917</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Professor!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich danke Ihnen für Ihren freundlichen Brief.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  The letter from S to which this replies appears not to survive.</tei:note>  Einstweilen werden Sie vermutlich mein V. Klavierheft<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Halm’s piano compositions appeared in five volumes, published by Zumsteeg (Stuttgart): vol. 1 (1911); vol. 2 (1914); vol. 3 (1914), vol. 4 (1911), vol. 5 (Bagatelles, no date).</tei:note> erhalten haben.  Gewinnt es Ihre Zuneigung, so sende ich Ihnen gern noch mehr von meinen Sachen.—Den erwähnten Aufsatz über Klavierunterricht gab ich Auftrag, Ihnen zu senden, falls er nicht schon im Satz ist.  Er sollte längst im “Neuen Österreich” erscheinen u. wird immer hingehalten.  Baron Eberhard von Wächter<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Baron Eberhard von Wächter [create biogfile].</tei:note> in Harmersdorf [?] bei Wien hat ihn als Redakteur dieser Zeitschrift angenommen;<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  A town called Harmersdorf lies roughly 50 miles west of Vienna.</tei:note> seit langem bin ich ohne Nachricht; die letzterhaltene lautete auf Setzermangel.  Ich hoffe, das Erscheinen Ihres “Kontrapunkts,” das ich schon im voraus <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> freudig begrüße, möge nicht durch solche Kalamitäten verzögert werden!</tei:p><tei:p>Sie Schreiben von “meinem Buch”; ich nehme an, daß es mein erstes ist:  “Von 2 Kulturen der Musik”.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Halm, <tei:hi rend="italic">Von zwei Kulturen der Musik</tei:hi> (Munich:  Müller, 1913).</tei:note>  Ist Ihnen das jüngste: “Von Grenzen u. Ländern der Musik” (Gesammelte Aufsätze) bekannt?  Ich möchte Sie auf den Aufsatz: “Rhythmik u. Vortragsdynamik” S. 155-161 aufmerksam machen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Halm, <tei:hi rend="italic">Von Grenzen und Ländern der Musik: gesammelte Aufsätze</tei:hi> (Munich: Müller, 1916).</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Mit vorzüglicher Hochachtung
begrüße ich Sie.
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] August Halm</tei:p><tei:p>Ich erlaube mir, einen Prospekt meiner Violinschule beizulegen, den Sie vielleicht gern lesen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7"> Halm’s violin method (<tei:hi rend="italic">Violinübung</tei:hi>) embraces three volumes:  vol. 1, Stuttgart: Zumsteeg, 1916; vol. 2 (unpublished); vol. 3, Kassel: Bärenreiter, 1930.</tei:note>  Ich glaube, der ganze Jammer, gegen den Sie zu feld ziehen, ruht auf dem heutigen Unterrichtswesen. <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Die Kretzschmar<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Hermann Kretzschmar [create biogfile]</tei:note> u. Bekker<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Paul Bekker [create biogfile]</tei:note> usw. hätten sich doch nicht als Musikschriftsteller auftun können, wenn das Publikum nicht zur Rat- u. Urteilslosigkeit erzogen worden.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10"> Halm is rephrasing here from something he wrote in an essay years before, “Von der Faustischen Krankheit” (1912), in <tei:hi rend="italic">Von Form und Sinn der Musik</tei:hi>, ed. Siegfried Schmalzriedt (Wiesbaden: Breitkopf und Härtel, 1978), 75-76: “Not what Bekker or Kretzschmar … or others sometimes think in their weak moments is of consequence, but rather what they are permitted to write, the lack of understanding people had in order patiently to read what they said … what we allowed to pass, what we allowed to grow and overgrow.  Such mushrooms sprout from ground that is fertilized with non-cultivation [<tei:hi rend="italic">Unbildung</tei:hi>], undergrown with non-belief, which has gone to seed and is under poor care.  Just a little more knowledge of music, a little more belief in it, and light and sun would never even have let the worms breed.  May the art journalist for whom the most important artistic things are silent change careers and maybe try talking about something else” ( “Denn nicht was die Bekker oder Kretzschmar … oder andere irgend einmal in ihren schwachen Stunden denken, ist von Belang, sondern was sie so schreiben durften, was man geduldig zu lesen den Unverstand hatte … Was man vielmehr gehen, sich gehen, was man wachsen und wuchern ließ.  Zeugen doch solche Pilze von einem Boden, der mit Unbildung gedüngt, mit Unglauben unterwachsen, der verkommen und von schlechten Händen bestellt ist.  Nur etwas mehr Wissen von Musik, etwas mehr Glauben an sie: und Licht und Sonne hätten die Maden gar nicht aufkommen lassen.  Der Kunstschriftsteller, dem die wichtigsten künstlerischen Dinge stumm sind, möge seinen Beruf wechseln und immerhin vielleicht über anderes zu reden versuchen”).  Federhofer transcribes the last section of this letter, from “Ich glaube, der ganze Jammer” to the end, in <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker:  Nach Tagebüchern und Briefen</tei:hi>, p. 135.</tei:note>
4.I.17.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated January 4, 1917</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor,</tei:p><tei:p>Thank you for your friendly letter.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  In the interim you will presumably have received my fifth piano volume.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  If you are sympathetic toward it, I will gladly send you more of my things.—I requested that the aforementioned essay on piano instruction be sent to you, in case it has not already been typeset.  It was supposed to appear some time ago in <tei:hi rend="italic">Neues Österreich</tei:hi> and is continually delayed.  As editor of that periodical, Baron Eberhard von Wächter<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> in Harmersdorf [?], near Vienna, accepted it;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> I have been without news for some time; the last news indicated a shortage of typesetters.  I hope that the appearance of your <tei:hi rend="italic">Counterpoint</tei:hi>, which I <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> eagerly anticipate, may not be delayed by such calamities!</tei:p><tei:p>You write of “my book”; I assume you mean my first one: <tei:hi rend="italic">Of Two Cultures of Music</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  Are you familiar with the newest one:  <tei:hi rend="italic">Of Borders and Countries of Music</tei:hi> (collected essays)?  I would like to direct to your attention the essay “Rhythm and Performance Dynamics,” pages 155-161.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/></tei:p><tei:p>With kind regards,
I send greetings,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] August Halm</tei:p><tei:p>I take the liberty of enclosing a brochure of my violin method, which you will perhaps care to read.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>  I believe the whole misery against which you take the field rests on the current educational system. <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> The Kretzschmars<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> and Bekkers,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> etc., could never have risen so far if the public were not reared to such helplessness and lack of judgment.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/>
January 4, 1917</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>