<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/35, 16 : 2-10-20 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain; published with the permission of the heirs of August Halm, March 2006.
© Transcription Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Translation Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Lee Rothfarb 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2000, and is published with the permission of the heirs of August Halm, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1920-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Lee Rothfarb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 02/10/1920 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Halm ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated February 10, 1920</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-04-10</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Acks 69.930/9 and return of contracts.  H is looking for a new publisher for his compositions, and wonders whether S would put in a good word to UE on his behalf, or whether S knows of a small press that might be suitable.  Wishes Furtwängler would perform something of his.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Halm, August; Schenker, Heinrich;  contracts; UE; recommendation; compositionswe; publisher; Furtwängler, Wilhelm</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Wickersdorf near Saalfeld/Saale</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated February 10, 1920</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>10.II.20
Wickersdorf bei Saalfeld/Saale (in Thüringen)</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Professor!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich bin auf etwa 7 Wochen (auch jetzt noch etwa 6) hier, wo ich mich noch immer in der Heimat fühle.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Halm returned at the end of December 1919 to teach at the Free School Community (Freie Schulgemeinde) at Wickersdorf, which he co-founded in 1906 with Paul Geheeb and close friend, colleague and, later, brother-in-law Gustav Wyneken (Halm married Wyneken’s younger sister, Hilda, in 1913).  Halm left his Wickersdorf post as music teacher when Wyneken was forced to resign as director of the school in spring of 1910 for various reasons, among them charges of homosexual activity with students.</tei:note>  Ihre Sendung mit meinen Verlags-Kontrakten habe ich richtig erhalten u. danke Ihnen auch für Ihren eingehenden Brief,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Presumably DLA 69.930/9, January 18, 1920.</tei:note> den ich beherzige u. öfters gelesen habe.  Erlauben Sie mir für jetzt eine geschäftliche Frage.  Von der gegenwärtig starken Unternehmungslust der Universaledition hörte ich kürzlich auch von anderer Seite.  Nun gehen manche meiner Kompositionen, d.h die Auflage, auf die Neige, z.B. meine Klaviersachen, u. ich suche auch für neues einen Verlag.  Das eigene Risiko u. das eigene geschäftliche Drum u. Dran habe ich beschlossen, nicht mehr auf mich zu nehmen u. ich möchte Sie fragen, ob Sie glauben, daß die Universaled. meine Sachen nimmt, u. ob Sie bereit wären, ihr dazu zu raten. (u. mir).  Sie sollen <tei:hi rend="italic">wirklich nicht mal Zeit damit verlieren</tei:hi>;<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  “wirklich ... verlieren” triple-underlined.</tei:note> aber <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> vielleicht bedarf es Ihrerseits nicht vieler Worte, um ihn dafür zu interessieren.  Näheres schreibe ich dann, wenn ich Ihre grundsätzliche Stellung zu der Frage kenne, die natürlich auch von der Ihnen einstweilen gewordenen Antwort des Verlags abhängt (wenn auch einer Neigung, dem Verlag m. Sachen anzuvertrauen).  Ich suche auch in Deutschland, aber wahrscheinl. nicht mit Erfolg.  Wissen Sie nicht einen kleinen, <tei:hi rend="italic">aufstrebenden</tei:hi> Verlag ^dort^, der noch eher mit den berechtigten Wünschen des Autors rechnet?—Ja: das noch:  die Buchstabentypen der Univ. Ed.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  UE made use of Jugendstil fonts and layout, cultivating a modern appearance.  These must have been unwelcome to S, as well.</tei:note> sind mir sehr unerwünscht u. fast ein Abhaltungsgrund.  Hoffentlich besteht sie nicht auf ihnen.—Wenn nur Furthwängler einmal was von mir aufführte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Beginning with this sentence (“Wenn Fürthwängler...”), Federhofer transcribes this letter in <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker: Nach Tagebüchern und Briefen</tei:hi>, 141. [create biogfile and link]</tei:note>  Ich war eigentlich überrascht, als Sie mir davon schrieben, daß er sich Ihnen gegenüber günstig über meine Sachen geäußert habe.  Als ich einmal bei ihm war, sprach er, zwar dies u. jenes anerkennend, im ganzen in einer für mich wenig hoffnungsvoller Weise.  Ich habe auch schlecht gespielt, wie es mir leicht passiert, wenn ich Widerstand spüre.  Meine Stellung zu den Verlegern wird natürlich durch die Zurückhaltung der Dirigenten auch nicht leichter.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit herzlichem Gruß  
Ihr 
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] A. Halm</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated February 10, 1920</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>February 10, 1920
Wickersdorf near Saalfeld/Saale (in Thuringia)</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor!</tei:p><tei:p>I have been here going on seven weeks (now still around six), where I still feel at home.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  I received your mailing with my publisher’s contracts and thank you for your detailed letter,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> which I take to heart and have frequently read.  Allow me a business question for the moment.  I recently heard from another quarter about the currently strong enterprising spirit of Universal Edition.  Some of my compositions, that is the edition, are beginning to decline, for example my piano pieces, and I am also looking for a publisher for new things.  I have resolved no longer to take upon myself the personal risk and all the personal odds and ends, and would like to ask you whether you believe Universal Edition would take on my pieces, and whether you would be prepared to advise them to do that   (and to so [advise] me).  You <tei:hi rend="italic">really should not spend too much time on this</tei:hi>;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> but <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> perhaps it would not require too many words from you in order to get him interested.  I will write further once I know your basic attitude on the matter, which of course also depends on the answer to you from the publisher (if also my inclination to entrust the publisher with my pieces).  I am looking in Germany but probably without success.  Do you not know a small, <tei:hi rend="italic">up-and-coming</tei:hi> publisher there which might sooner reckon with the justified wishes of the author?—Yes, this too:  the fonts of Universal Edition<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> are very undesirable to me and almost a reason to deter.  Hopefully, it will not insist on them.—If only Furtwängler would once perform something of mine.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  I was actually surprised when you wrote me that he spoke favorably to you about my pieces.  When I was once with him, he spoke, acknowledging this and that, on the whole in, for me, a less than hopeful manner.  I also played badly, as easily happens to me when I sense resistance.  Because of the reluctance of conductors, my position with publishers is of course not made any easier.</tei:p><tei:p>With warm greetings, 
Yours, 
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] A. Halm</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>