<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/35, 5 : 7-2-17 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Translation Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Lee A. Rothfarb 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2000, and is published with the agreement of the heirs of August Halm 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1917-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Lee Rothfarb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 07/02/1917 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Halm ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated July 2, 1917</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-03-06</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>[A] H's essay on piano instruction has been published.  H asks a question on editions of Beethoven variations; inquires after S's Kontrapunkt; hopes his review of LfS will appear in next issue of Die Freie Schulgemeinde. [B] Suggestions on library access and publishers, also honoraria and expenses. [C ] Advice on procuring a favorable contract.  News of performances of his own works.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Halm, August; Schenker, Heinrich; essay on piano instruction; Die Freie Schulgemeinde; Diederichs, Eugen; Jena; Beethoven; variations; Peters; LfS; Die letzten fünf Sonaten Beethovens; The Five Late Sonatas of Beethoven; Cotta, J. G.; Kontrapunkt; Counterpoint; Hofbibliothek; Archiv; paper factory; honorarium; contract; Müller, Georg; Busch, Fritz; concerto; Stuttgart; Ulm; Philharmonic Orchestra</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Eßlingen a. Neckar, Panoramstraße 11</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated July 2, 1917</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{A <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Eßlingen a. Neckar</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  double-underlined.</tei:note>  <tei:hi rend="italic">Panoramastr. 11</tei:hi>
					2. Juli.17
Sehr geehrter Herr Professor!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Federhofer mentions this letter in Heinrich Schenker: <tei:hi rend="italic">Nach Tagebüchern und Briefen</tei:hi>, 136, but does not provide any transcription.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Der Ihnen bekannte, einstweilen noch erweiterte Aufsatz über Klavierunterricht erschien in der Zeitschrift “Die Freie Schulgemeinde”, Juli-Nummer (Verl. <tei:hi rend="italic">Eugen Diederichs</tei:hi>, Jena).<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Refers to the letter from Halm to Schenker, dated January 4, 1917, which alludes to the essay “Bildender Klavierunterricht,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Freie Schulgemeinde</tei:hi> 7 (1917), 103-118, reprinted in Halm, <tei:hi rend="italic">Von Form und Sinn der Musik</tei:hi>, ed. Siegfried Schmalzriedt (Wiesbaden: Breifkopf und Härtel, 1978), 292-305.</tei:note>  Ich möchte nun die <tei:hi rend="italic">leichteren</tei:hi> Variationen Beethovens, die in der <tei:hi rend="italic">Peters</tei:hi> Ausgabe im <tei:hi rend="italic">II</tei:hi>. Heft kommen, mit in meine Klavierschule nehmen, in Auswahl natürlich.  Nun muß ich vermuten, nach Ihren Ausführungen in Ihrer Bethovenausgabe, daß auch die Variationen im Text -schadhaft geworden- ^beschädigt worden^ sind.—Und eine <tei:hi rend="bold">{A <tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> so eindringende Arbeit, wie Sie sie den späten Sonaten widmeten, wird an diesen kleinen Sachen noch nicht so bald getan werden.  Können u. wollen Sie mir nun mitteilen, welche Ausgabe Sie für die wenigst schlechte halten (auf eine gute wage ich also nicht zu hoffen), so wäre ich Ihnen sehr dankbar.  Bringt Cotta nun Ihren Kontrapunkt weiter heraus?  Die Verleger tun ja im allgemeinen jetzt nicht mehr mit.  Meine Bitte um ein Besprechungsexemplar hat Cotta nicht beachtet.—In unsere&lt;strike&gt;m&lt;/strike&gt;^r^ &lt;strike&gt;xxxx&lt;/strike&gt; Zeitschrift “Die Fr. Schulgem.” ha&lt;strike&gt;tt&lt;/strike&gt;^b^en wir zur Zeit viel dringend Aktuelles, ich hoffe aber, in der nächsten Nummer bringe ich endlich die Besprechung Ihrer Beethoven-Ausgabe, deren Verdienstlichkeit ich eindringlich verkünden will.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Refers to the letter from Halm to Schenker, dated January 4, 1917, which alludes to the essay “Bildender Klavierunterricht,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Freie Schulgemeinde</tei:hi> 7 (1917), 103-118, reprinted in Halm, <tei:hi rend="italic">Von Form und Sinn der Musik</tei:hi>, ed. Siegfried Schmalzriedt (Wiesbaden: Breifkopf und Härtel, 1978), 292-305.</tei:note> Mit vorzüglicher Hochachtung[.]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">   Halm’s review appeared as “Heinrich Schenker,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Freie Schulgemeinde</tei:hi> 8 (1917), 11-15; reprinted in <tei:hi rend="italic">Von Form und Sinn der Musik</tei:hi>, 271-274.</tei:note>  [ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] August Halm</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{B <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> Nachschrift:  Die Hofbibliothek u. das Archiv müßten Ihnen doch wohl besondere Stunden einräumen!  Haben Sie das schon versucht?  Wahrscheinlich könnte auch der Verlag da mitwirken, denn [...?] &lt;strike&gt;„artikel-&lt;/strike&gt; artikel” herzustellen, bei denen verhältnismäßig wenig Rohmaterial &lt;strike&gt;xxxx&lt;/strike&gt; ^investiert^ <tei:hi rend="bold">{B <tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> ist, muß doch der Staat jetzt begrüßen.  Übrigens wird der Verlag überdieß noch Teilhaber einer Papierfabrik sein, vermute ich.  Aber daß man auf Grund solcher Vorteile, eine eigene Druckerei, mehr Honorar herausschlagen kann, bezweifele ich, doch ists Versuchenswert.—Meine Serenaden sind das erste, bei dessen Druck ich keine Kosten habe u. sogar Honorar bezog<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  “Honorar bezog” ("received an honorarium")written vertically in right margin.</tei:note> (abgesehen von Zeitschriften).<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  “(abgesehen von Zeitschriften).” ("(apart from periodicals).") written upside-down in top margin.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{C <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> Bei Vorauszahlung ^Ihres^ -eines- Anteils an einer Auflage müssen Sie sich Nachzahlung sichern, für den Fall, daß der Verlag nachher den Preis erhöht.  Überhaupt sollten Sie einen Vertrag, wenn Sie sich nicht ganz sicher fühlen, ehe Sie ihn unterzeichnen, einem Rechtsanwalt vorlegen, der mit Preis- u. Verlagsgeschäften<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Originally written “ Preisgeschäften” then extended and re-ordered.</tei:note> gut vertraut ist (das sind nicht alle Anwälte).  Ein mir befreundeter Rechtsanwalt erklärte den Gg Müller<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Georg Müller: biog. not.</tei:note> Vertrag für ziemlich anständig (mit <tei:hi rend="bold">{C <tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>Ausnahme des §3).  In §2 ist [ein?] Widerspruch, der aber höchstens es zu meinem Gunsten ausgebeutet werden könnte.—Ich will heut nur aber diese Sache schreiben u. anderes aufsparen.  Nur noch mitteilen, daß Fritz Busch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Fritz Busch [create biogfile].</tei:note> in Stuttgart im <tei:hi rend="italic">nächsten</tei:hi> Winter ein großes Konzert (C dur) aufführen will;<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Halm means his <tei:hi rend="italic">Concerto in C Major for Large Orchestra with Obligato Piano</tei:hi> (Stuttgart: G.A. Zumsteeg, 1913), published under the auspices of the Society for the Publication of the Works of August Halm (Gesellschaft zur Veröffentlichung der Werke August Halms), founded in July 1910 at the instigation of Gustav Wyneken, Halm’s close friend, fellow teacher, and eventually brother-in-law when he married Wyneken’s sister, Hilda, in April 1913.</tei:note> am 12. <tei:hi rend="italic">April</tei:hi> dieses Jahres soll es in Ulm mit dem ^dort^ neugegründeten “Philharmonischen Orchester” aufgeführt werden—Ja noch eines:  Geht es, so bedienen Sie sich prozentuale Einnahmen aus anderen Ländern sichern, also eventuell haben Sie dann eine regelmäßige Quelle von Schweizer Franken!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  “Geht ... Franken!“ ("If ... francs!") written upside-down in top margin.</tei:note></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated July 2, 1917</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{A <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Eßlingen a. Neckar</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  <tei:hi rend="italic">Panoramastraße 11</tei:hi>
					July 2, 1917
Dear Professor!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/></tei:p><tei:p>The essay on piano instruction with which you are familiar, expanded in the meantime, appeared in the periodical <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Freie Schulgemeinde</tei:hi>, July issue (Eugen Diederichs Publishing, Jena).<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  I would like to incorporate the <tei:hi rend="italic">easier</tei:hi> Beethoven variations into my piano method, the ones that appear in volume <tei:hi rend="italic">2</tei:hi> of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Peters</tei:hi> edition—a selection naturally.  According to your comments in your Beethoven edition, I must presume that the variations have also -become defective- become corrupted.—And <tei:hi rend="bold">{A <tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> such thoroughgoing labor, as you devoted it to the late sonatas, will not so soon be applied to these small items.  If you can and want to tell me now which edition you consider the least bad (I do not even dare to hope for a good one), I would be very grateful to you.  Is Cotta going to further issue your <tei:hi rend="italic">Counterpoint</tei:hi>?  Publishers just no longer cooperate.  Cotta did not acknowledge my request for a review copy.  At the moment we ha&lt;strike&gt;d&lt;/strike&gt;^ve^ many urgent current items in our periodical <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Freie Schulgemeinde</tei:hi>, I hope, however, that in the next issue I will finally include the review of your Beethoven edition, whose worthiness I urgently want to announce.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  With kind regards, [ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] August Halm.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{B <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> P.S.  The Court Library and the archive should surely arrange special hours for you!  Have you tried that?  The publisher could probably cooperate in that effort, for producing articles for which relatively little raw material is invested <tei:hi rend="bold">{B <tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> should be welcomed by the state.  By the way, I presume, moreover, that the publisher will be a partner in a paper factory.  But I doubt that one can extract more honorarium on the basis of such advantages—their own printing firm—but it is worth a try.—My serenades are the first works for whose printing I had no expenses and even received an honorarium<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> (apart from periodicals).<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{C <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> In case of an advance on -a- your portion of an edition, you have to assure an additional payment in case the publisher raises the price afterward.  In general, if you do not feel sure, you should present a contract to an attorney who is well acquainted with price and publishing business<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> (not all attorneys are) before you sign it.  One attorney I am friends with declared the contract with Georg Müller<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> fairly decent (with the <tei:hi rend="bold">{C <tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> exception of paragraph 3).  In paragraph 2 there is a contradiction that at best could be exploited in my favor.—But today I only want to write about that matter and save other things.  Only to convey further that Fritz Busch<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> wants to perform my large concerto (C major) <tei:hi rend="italic">next</tei:hi> winter in Stuttgart;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> on April 12 of this year it is supposed to be performed in Ulm by the newly founded “Philharmonic Orchestra” there.—Oh yes, one other thing:  If it works, avail yourself of a percentage of the proceeds from other countries so that you potentially have a regular source of Swiss francs!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/></tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>