<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/35, 15 : 1-11-20 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain; published with the agreement of the heirs of August Halm 2006.
© Transcription Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Translation Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Lee Rothfarb 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2000, and is published with the agreement of the heirs of August Halm 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1920-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Lee Rothfarb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 01/11/1920 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Halm ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated January 11, 1920</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-04-09</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Expresses reservations about Kleine Bibliothek plan; wishes S might write history of music. —PS: Advises S to insure a regular income before moving to Germany.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Halm, August; Schenker, Heinrich;  Kleine Bibliothek; Little Library; Der Tonwille; UE; music history; cadence; sequence; emigration; Germany; income; earnings; percentage</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated January 11, 1920</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>11. I. 20.</tei:p><tei:p>Verehrter Herr Professor!</tei:p><tei:p>Zu Ihrem Brief<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  i.e. perhaps lost, since S’s most recent letter was DLA 69.930/8, October 27, 1919, and Halm has already written two letters since that date.</tei:note> könnte ich zunächst in Beziehung auf die geschäftliche Frage mich äußern.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Federhofer transcribes all of this letter except for the opening and the postscript in <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker:  Nach Tagebüchern und Briefen</tei:hi>, p. 140.</tei:note>  Daß Ihr Verleger nun einsieht, daß Sie zu Wort kommen müssen, oder daß er auch gut dabei fährt, wenn er Wichtiges u. Nachhaltiges bringt, freut mich sehr.  Der Gedanke der Kleinen Bibliothek aber nicht gleichermaßen[?], d.h.  nicht unbedingt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  The publisher is UE.  Schenker had orginally used the title “Kleine Bibliothek” for what became <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</tei:hi>.  Hellmut Federhofer transcribes a large section of Schenker’s reply of January 18, 1920 to Halm’s letter of January 11 in <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker: Nach Tagebüchern und Briefen</tei:hi>, pp. 141–142.</tei:note>  Ich meine, die typischen Analysen sollten genügen; eine ganze zweite Existenz der Kunstwerke in Analysen stelle ich immer ungern vor.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">   In the essay “Musik und Volk,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Von schwäbischer Scholle. Kalendar für schwäbische Literatur und Kunst</tei:hi> (Heilbronn: Eugen Salzer, 1922), p. 70, Halm spoke disparagingly—and with unwitting accuracy!—of a “proliferation of such analyses” that would “gradually form a large literature, so that at some point opposite the bookcase with masterworks another would stand with analyses of them.”</tei:note>  Von meinem Bedürfnis aus müßte ich wünschen, Sie schrieben die Musikgeschichte, für die wir bis jetzt kaum kümmerliche Surrogate haben, u. wenn das nicht möglich, da nach meinem Wissen oder Vermuten Wichtiges noch ganz unaufgeklärt ist (wer hat zuerst mit klarem Bewußtsein ihrer funktionellen Wirkung -eine- ^die^ Kadenz, <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> die Sequenz gebraucht?  Das kümmerte ja die Musikgeschichtenvefasser gar nicht!) einzelne Abschnitte von Musikgeschichte; was ich in Ihren Büchern nach dieser Richtung fand, erweckte mir sehr stark diesen Wunsch, den ich Ihnen hiemit vortragen will.  Der Verleger wird, denke ich, auch an das mit Mut hingehen.  (Ich selbst weiß viel zu wenig u. kann an dergleichen nicht denken, u. wer außer Ihnen sollte das können?)</tei:p><tei:p>Mit besten Grüßen u. Wünschen 
Ihr 
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] A. Halm</tei:p><tei:p>Es fiel mir noch ein, daß Sie schon um die Möglichkeit in ein anderes Land, sei es auch nur Deutschland, zu ziehen, sich zu wahren, sich anstatt einmaliger Abfindung mit österreich. Geld regelmäßige Einkünfte sichern sollten, u. zwar eben auch Prozent daraus, anderen Ländern fließenden Einnahmen in der betreffenden Währung u. mit Einberechnung des Verleger- (u. womöglich (?) Buchhändleraufschlags.[)]</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated January 11, 1920</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>January 11, 1920</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor!</tei:p><tei:p>In response to your letter,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> I could for the moment give my opinion regarding the business matter.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  I am very happy that your publisher now accepts that you must have a say, or that he will do well if he provides something important and lasting.  However[?], the idea of the “Little Library” likewise no, that is, not necessarily."<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  I mean typical analyses should suffice; only reluctantly do I imagine an entire second existence of works of art in analyses.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  Based on my needs, I would have to wish that you might write a history of music, for which up to now we barely have paltry surrogates; and if that is not possible, individual sections of music history, since things of importance are yet wholly unclarified according to my knowledge or supposition (who first employed -a- ^the^ cadence, <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> the sequence, with clear awareness of its functional effect?  That [question] does not occupy authors on music history at all!).  What I found in that direction in your books stirred in me very strongly the wish that I want to present to you here.  The publisher will approach it eagerly, I think.  (I know far too little and cannot consider something of that sort, and who other than you should be able to do it?)</tei:p><tei:p>With warm greetings and wishes,  
Yours, 
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] A. Halm</tei:p><tei:p>It occurs to me additionally, that if you follow through on the possibility of moving to another country, even if it is only Germany, you should assure yourself of regular proceeds instead of a one-time settlement in Austrian currency, and moreover also a percentage of earnings going to other countries, in the relevant currency, including publishers’ (and where possible (?)) the retailers’ mark-up.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>