<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="frankfurter_zeitung">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Frankfurter Zeitung</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="frankfurter_zeitung">Frankfurter Zeitung</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>16/06/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Title</term>
          <term subtype="basename">frankfurter_zeitung</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Frankfurter Zeitung</head>
      <div>
        <!-- BODY: -->
        <p><hi rend="bold">Frankfurter Zeitung,</hi> principal German newspaper.  Founded in 1856 as the <hi rend="italic">Frankfurter Gesch&#xE4;ftsbericht</hi> but known as the <hi rend="italic">Frankfurter Zeitung</hi> for most of its existence, 1866&#x2013;1943, the newspaper became a major  liberal forum for cultural and political opinion, and its contributors included a great many of Germany&#x2019;s leading 20th-century philosophers and novelists;  many of its columnists were forced to resign when the National Socialists came to power in 1933, and the newspaper&#x2019;s influence declined sharply during the last decade of its existence. (The <hi rend="italic">Frankfurter allgemeine Zeitung</hi> is generally considered to be its successor.)</p>
        <p>Prominent writers on music included Karl Holl, a Verdi scholar, and Paul Bekker, who was the chief music critic from 1911 to 1923.  Bekker&#x2019;s book <hi rend="italic">Beethoven</hi> (1911) provoked severe critical reactions from Schenker in the secondary literature sections of his analytical essays, and his articles on music criticism for the <hi rend="italic">Frankfurter Zeitung</hi> was the subject of an essay planned for <hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</hi>, issue 2 (1922) but withdrawn shortly before publication. (For an English translation of this, see <hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</hi>, vol. 2 ed William Drabkin [New York: Oxford University Press, 2005], pp. 161&#x2013;65.</p>
        <p>Clippings from the <hi rend="italic">Frankfurter Zeitung</hi> ranging from 1912 to 1931 are preserved in Schenker's scrapbook and file of clippings (OC 2; OC C), with articles on music written by Hermann Wetzel, Hugo Ganz, Paul Bekker, Karl Holl, Leo Kestenberg, Artur Bogen, B. Sekles, Bernhard Diebold,  Luigi Russolo, Erich Steinhard, Eugen d'Albert, Ludwig Rottenberg, and numerous articles on literary and other topics.</p>
        <!-- EXTENDED BODY: -->
        <!-- EXCERPT: -->
        <!-- KEYWORDS: -->
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
