<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="musikalisches_wochen">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>
          <hi rend="italic">Musikalisches Wochenblatt</hi>
        </title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="musikalisches_wochen">Musikalisches Wochenblatt</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>23/07/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Fritzsch ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Title</term>
          <term subtype="basename">musikalisches_wochen</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>
        <hi rend="italic">Musikalisches Wochenblatt</hi>
      </head>
      <div>
        <!-- BODY: -->
        <p><hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Musikalisches Wochenblatt</hi>,</hi>  weekly musical journal published in Leipzig, 1870&#x2013;1906, to which Schenker contributed six articles.</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="bold">The Journal and its Editors</hi>
        </p>
        <p>The <hi rend="italic">Musikalisches Wochenblatt</hi> began publication in January 1870 under the editorship of the music historian Oscar Paul.  The paper, aimed&#x2014;as its masthead declared&#x2014;at both &#x201C;Musicians and Enthusiasts&#x201D; (<hi rend="italic">f&#xFC;r Tonk&#xFC;nstler und Musikfreunde</hi>), featured a diverse array of articles, from reviews of concerts and new books and scores to essays on aesthetic questions and biographical portraits. Its appearance thus represented a conspicuous challenge to Leipzig&#x2019;s other musical weekly, the similar yet older and more widely read <hi rend="italic">Neue Zeitschrift f&#xFC;r Musik</hi>, with which it merged in October 1906, shortly after which its name disappeared from the masthead of the &#x201C;united&#x201D; (<hi rend="italic">vereinigte</hi>) weekly.</p>
        <p>Paul, who taught music history and theory at the University of Leipzig and piano at the Leipzig Conservatory, was most widely known for his <hi rend="italic">Lehrbuch der Harmonik</hi> (1880) and five-volume translation of Boethius&#x2019;s <hi rend="italic">De Musica</hi> (1872).  The range of essays published in the first issue of the <hi rend="italic">Musikalisches Wochenblatt</hi> reflected Paul&#x2019;s diversity of interests.  In his own lead article, &#x201C;Das musikalische Streben in der Gegenwart,&#x201D; Paul argued that present-day musicians can acquire a clear sense of the proper course for future advances only if they simultaneously endeavor to understand the musical innovations of previous eras and generations. Paul&#x2019;s essay was accompanied by Wilhelm Tappert&#x2019;s analytical study of the folk tune &#x201C;Aennchen von Tharau,&#x201D; a translation of an anonymous 16th-century treatise on mensural notation, and the first installment of a serialized analytical review of Brahms&#x2019;s <hi rend="italic">German Requiem</hi>.  Only three months after founding the <hi rend="italic">Wochenblatt</hi>, Paul retired from the editor&#x2019;s post, citing health concerns. He passed his duties on to Ernst Wilhelm Fritzsch, who would edit the journal for over three decades.</p>
        <p>Fritzsch, a Leipzig publisher, entrepreneur, and amateur musician, did not contribute any essays to the <hi rend="italic">Wochenblatt</hi>, but he did recruit some of the period&#x2019;s most prominent writers on music to write for it. These included Friedrich von Hausegger, Theodor Helm, Hugo Riemann, Richard Wallaschek, and even Richard Wagner.  At the time Fritzsch assumed Paul&#x2019;s duties, his publishing house was producing the first edition of Wagner&#x2019;s collected writings, and under his direction the <hi rend="italic">Wochenblatt</hi> took on a decidedly Wagnerian tone.  Several of Wagner&#x2019;s essays made their first appearance in the paper, and, in the years immediately following the composer&#x2019;s death in 1883, essays on Wagner, his writings, and his music came to dominate its pages.</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="bold"><hi rend="italic">Musikalisches Wochenblatt</hi> and Schenker</hi>
        </p>
        <p>In October 1891, Fritzsch&#x2019;s journal published Schenker&#x2019;s debut critical essay: his analytical review of Brahms&#x2019;s songs, Op. 107.  Over the course of the next four years, Schenker would publish five more articles, among them his most ambitious to date, in Fritzsch&#x2019;s paper.  These included his serialized analytical review of Brahms&#x2019;s choral pieces, Op. 104, which appeared on the front page of three consecutive issues in 1892, and his 1895 University of Vienna lecture, &#x201C;Der Geist der musikalischen Technik,&#x201D; which was subsequently reprinted, as a separate pamphlet, by Fritzsch&#x2019;s firm. The <hi rend="italic">Musikalisches Wochenblatt</hi> is the only specialist music journal to which Schenker contributed during this period.</p>
        <p>One letter survives from Fritzsch to Schenker under the journal's letterhead: OJ 11/11 (1892).</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="italic">Bibliography:</hi>
        </p>
        <p>Hellmut Federhofer, <hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker als Essayist und Kritiker &#x2026;</hi> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1990) [all six of Schenker's articles]</p>
        <p>Heinrich Schenker, "The Spirit of Musical Technique," trans. W. Pastille, <hi rend="italic">Theoria</hi> 3 (1988), 86&#x2013;104;  rev. edn. in N. Cook, <hi rend="italic">The Schenker Project</hi> (New York: Oxford University Press, 2007), pp. 319&#x2013;32</p>
        <p>Rast, Nicholas, "A Checklist of Essays and Reviews by Heinrich Schenker, <hi rend="italic">Music Analysis</hi> 7/2 (July 1988), 121&#x2013;3</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="italic">Sources:</hi>
        </p>
        <p>&#x201C;An unsere Leser!&#x201D; <hi rend="italic">Musikalisches Wochenblatt/Neue Zeitschrift f&#xFC;r Musik: Vereinigte Leipziger musikalische Wochenschriften</hi> (4 October 1906), 1</p>
        <p>Christa and Peter Jost, <hi rend="italic">Richard Wagner und sein Verleger Ernst Wilhelm Fritzsch</hi> (Tutzing: Hans Schneider, 1997)</p>
        <p>Oscar Paul, &#x201C;Das musikalische Streben in der Gegenwart,&#x201D; <hi rend="italic">Musikalisches Wochenblatt</hi> 1/1 (1870), 1&#x2013;3</p>
        <p>Hugo Riemann, <hi rend="italic">Musik-Lexikon</hi>, 4th ed. (Leipzig: Max Hesse, 1894), 796</p>
        <p><hi rend="italic">Author:</hi>  Kevin Karnes</p>
        <!-- EXTENDED BODY: -->
        <!-- EXCERPT: -->
        <!-- KEYWORDS: -->
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
