<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="schutzverband_deutsc">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Schutzverband deutscher Schriftsteller in Wien (Association for the Protection of German Authors in Vienna)</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="schutzverband_deutsc">Schutzverband deutscher Schriftsteller in Wien</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>10/06/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Fischmann ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">Schutzverband ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Organization</term>
          <term subtype="basename">schutzverband_deutsc</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Schutzverband deutscher Schriftsteller in Wien (Association for the Protection of German Authors in Vienna)</head>
      <div>
        <!-- BODY: -->
        <p><hi rend="bold">Schutzverband deutscher Schriftsteller in Wien (Association for the Protection of German Authors in Vienna),</hi> founded in Germany in 1909 as a type of trade union for authors, the parent organization, the Schutzverband deutscher Schriftsteller (SDS), first tried to establish a Vienna branch in 1916 with Engelbert Pernerstorfer as chairman.   Among the members of the board at the time were Hugo von Hoffmannsthal, Raoul Auernheimer, Franz Karl Ginzkey, Karl Glossy, and Anton Wildgans.  But the association did not get off the ground and it was re-established in early 1920 as the Schutzverband deutscher Schriftsteller in &#xD6;sterreich (Austria).  A branch also existed in Switzerland.</p>
        <p>The SDS was banned by the Nazis in 1935 and replaced by the Reichsverband Deutscher Schriftsteller (Imperial Association of German Authors) (DSV), then restored after World War II as the Deutsche Schriftstellerverband  in 1950.</p>
        <p>Schenker joined the Schutzverband in 1920, writing to Ginzkey on January 16, paying the subscription of 30 Kronen on February 14, sending the draft contract for the <ref cRef="kleine_bibliothek"><hi rend="italic">Kleine Bibliothek</hi></ref> on February 15, and exchanging letters with the organization's legal adviser <ref cRef="fischmann_leo">Dr. Leo Fischmann</ref> in February-April 1920 (Schenker's diary pp. 2208, 2214; OC 52/218, 222, 224, 227).  In the September and December he was again in contact with the organization.</p>
        <p><hi rend="italic">Source:</hi><hi rend="italic">A History of Austrian Literature 1918-2000</hi>, eds. Katrin Maria Kohl and Ritchie Robertson (Rochester, NY: Camden House, 2006), p. 83.</p>
        <p><hi rend="italic">Contributor:</hi>  Marko Deisinger</p>
        <!-- EXTENDED BODY: -->
        <!-- EXCERPT: -->
        <!-- KEYWORDS: -->
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
