<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/54, [2] : 5-29-25 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Anthony van Hoboken, published here with kind permission.  
© Transcribed John Rothgeb, 2007.
© Translated John Rothgeb, 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish granted by the heirs of Anthony van Hoboken February 3, 2007.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1925-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Anthony van Hoboken; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 05/29/1925 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Hoboken ~ H+JSchenker","Hoboken ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Hoboken to Schenker, dated May 29, 1925</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-12-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>H wishes to become a pupil of S;  he has studied S's theoretical works under Vrieslander, and describes his progress so far;  outlines previous education in piano and music theory at the Hoch Conservatory [Frankfurt], and activity as composer and conductor; after breaking his shoulder, he neglected his musical studies;  outlines the areas he wishes to study with S;  if accepted, he would take up residence in Vienna.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Hoboken, Anthony van;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Panzaun;  Vrieslander, Otto;  counterpoint;  Rotterdam;  Hoch Conservatory;  Knorr, Iwan;  München;  Munich;  wife;  Generalbass;  thoroughbass;  harmonic analysis;  formal analysis;  score reading;  piano;  Vienna</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Paris, 45 Quai Bourbon, IV^e^</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Hoboken to Schenker, dated May 29, 1925</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{envelope <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
Recommandé
Herrn Professor Heinrich Schenker
Wien III
Keilgasse 8 (oder 9?)
Autriche</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>]  || [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>] | 10 45 / 30 -5 / 25 | A.DE POINTOISE ||</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{envelope <tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
Exp.
A. v. Hoboken
45 Quai Bourbon
Paris IV
[<tei:hi rend="italic">wax seal</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{letter}</tei:hi>
Paris, 29. V. 25
45 Quai Bourbon, IV^me^ arr</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Herr Professor,</tei:p><tei:p>Seit einiger Zeit, besonders aber seit dem letzten Sommer, als ich im Paznaun<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Paznaun: ski resort in the western Tyrol, containing the towns of Galtür (at which the Schenkers regularly spent the summer months), Ischgl, Kappl, and See.  </tei:note> einige Tage in Ihrer Gesellschaft verbringen durfte wobei ich einen tiefen Eindruck von Ihrer Persönlichkeit gewann, hege ich den grossen Wunsch, mich für einige Zeit unter Ihrer musikalischen Führung zu stellen.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich habe bereits früher, vor meiner Weltreise, nach Ihren theoretischen Werken studiert unter Leitung von Otto Vrieslander,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.  </tei:note> bin jedoch dabei nicht über den Zweistimmigen Satz hinausgekommen weil ich mich der Sache niemals ganz gewidmet habe und stets Vielerlei nebenbei am Kopfe hatte.  Ich bin überhaupt technisch nicht so weit wie ich es in meinem Alter sein müsste und wie Sie es sicher von Ihren angehenden Schülern voraussetzen.  Insbesondere gilt dies von meinem Klavierspiel, und das hat seine verschiedene[n] Ursachen.  Erstens war ich früher nie durchdrungen von der ungeheueren Arbeit die dem künstlerischen Können zugrunde liegt.  In den Handelskreisen, in denen ich aufgewachsen bin, versteht man unter Arbeit <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> eben etwas ganz anderes. Ohne die Umgebung, aus der ich stamme, zu nahe treten zu wollen, möchte ich davon betonen[,] dass man dort, besonders in meiner amusikalischen Vaterstadt Rotterdam, die Ansicht huldigt, das Musikstudium sei eigentlich keine Lebensaufgabe für Bemittelten sondern mehr etwas, welches sie nebenbei treiben sollten.</tei:p><tei:p>Als ich dann mit 22 Jahren am Hochschen Conservatorium<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Hoch Conservatory, Frankfurt, founded 1878.  </tei:note> zu Frankfurt ^a^/Main aufgenommen wurde hatte sich dass [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Missverhältnis zwischen meinem musikalischen Auffassungsvermögen und meiner technischen Ausdrucksmöglichkeiten schon so weit herangebildet, dass ich wohl Theorie-Fortschritte machte, besonders unter Leitung Iwann Knorr’s,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="knorr_iwan">Iwan Knorr</ref>.  </tei:note> dem ich viele gute Ratschläge verdanke, mein Klavierspiel aber unter einem Lehrer, der für die erste[n] Gehversuche 13[- ] bis 15[-]jähriger angestellt war, völlig vernachlässigt wurde.</tei:p><tei:p>Das Studium am Conservatorium unterbrach ich dann, als ich aus Rotterdam den Auftrag erhielt, für eine Dillettanten-Aufführung durch Schülern der Realschule, der[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] ich früher angehört hatte, melodramatische Musik zu einem holländischen Drama zu schreiben.  Ich habe dieses mit vielem Vergnügen gemacht, die Sache auch selber dirigiert, alles zur vollen Zufriedenheit einiger dortigen [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Fachleute, kann aber das Ganze nicht als eine ernste Leistung betrachten.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich ging danach ans Conservatorium zurück, wo ein anderer Klavierlehrer mir &lt;strike&gt;ub&lt;/strike&gt; mehr über Arm- und Hand-<tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> bewegungen beim Klavierspiel beibrachte, wofür ich sehr empfänglich war.  Ich erlitt aber kurz drauf einen Unfall wobei ich die &lt;strike&gt;R&lt;/strike&gt; rechte Schulter ausrenkte; es kam der Krieg und einige andere beikommende Umstände veranlassten mich, nach München zu ziehen wo ich mich bald mit allem anderen mehr beschäftigen sollte als mit der Musik, bis ich dort Vrieslander<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.  </tei:note> kennen lernte und später meine jetzige Frau heiratete.  Ich bin nun weit davon entfernt, jemandem die Schuld an meine Vernachlässigungen in die Schuhe schieben zu wollen.  Die Tatsache ist nun mal, dass ich nie ernstlich gearbeitet habe&lt;strike&gt;n&lt;/strike&gt;, meine Technik und meine Kenntnisse daher sehr unvollkommen zu nennen sind.</tei:p><tei:p>Als ich mich nun während der letzten Jahre auf der Weltreise befand, wo es mir nicht, oder beinahe nicht möglich war mich mit der Musik zu befassen, ist mir die Notwendigkeit immer klarer geworden, mich endlich ernstlich dem Studium zu widmen.  Vrieslander,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.  </tei:note> mit wem ich sehr befreundet bin und mit dem ich diese Angelegenheit auch besprach, meinte, dass meine musikalische Begabung hierzu völlig ausreichend sei und ermutigt durch dieses Urteil bitte ich Sie anbei, mich ab nächster Saison als Ihr Schüler aufzunehmen.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich möchte Kontrapunkt und Generalbass studieren, sowie Harmonie- und Formanalyse und Partiturlesen[.]  <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Dabei möchte ich mein Klavierspiel weiter ausbilden und womöglich auch die Orgel erlernen.  Doch weiss ich nicht, ob Sie diese beiden letzten Fächer selber zu unterrichten pflegen oder einem anderen Lehrer dafür zu empfehlen gewohnt sind.  Ich möchte es in diesen Fächern soweit bringen, dass ich für die Zukunft eine beste Grundlage für die weitere Pflege der Musik besitze, und sogar noch weiter, falls sich herausstellen sollte, dass meine Fähigkeiten und meine Zeit hierzu ausreichen.  Meine Zeit, weil ich immerhin bereits 38 Jahre alt bin und meine Fähigkeiten als ich mir die Schwierigkeit nicht verhehlen darf, nach einem Leben von relativem Nichtstun auf einmal die Konzentrierteste musikalische Arbeit zu leisten.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich sehe Ihre Antwort mit begreiflicher Spannung entgegen und bitte Sie, falls diese günstig ausfallen sollte[,] mir zugleich Ihre Bedingungen sowie der Anfang Ihrer Kurse mitteilen zu wollen. Ich werde dann in Wien eine Wohnung suchen, möbiliert oder unmöbiliert, wo ich mit meiner Frau leben kann und in der ich bis spätestens 15 Oktober fertig installiert werde sein können.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit den besten Empfehlungen, auch seitens meiner Frau, an Ihrer Frau Gemahlin und Ihnen selber bin ich, mit vorzüglicher Hochachtung</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr sehr ergebener
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] AvHoboken</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Hoboken to Schenker, dated May 29, 1925</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{envelope <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
Registered
Professor Heinrich Schenker
Vienna III
Keilgasse 8 (oder 9?)
Austria</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>]  || [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>] | 10 45 / 30 -5 / 25 | A.DE POINTOISE ||</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{envelope <tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
Exp[ress]
A. v. Hoboken
45 Quai Bourbon
Paris IV
[<tei:hi rend="italic">wax seal</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{letter}</tei:hi>
Paris, May 29, 1925
45 Quai Bourbon, Fourth Arrondissment</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor,</tei:p><tei:p>For some time, but especially since last summer when I was privileged to spend several days in your company in the Paznaun<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> and gained a deep impression of your personality, it has been my strong wish to place myself for a time under your musical guidance.</tei:p><tei:p>Even earlier, before my world tour, I studied according to your theoretical works under the supervision of Otto Vrieslander,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> but have not progressed beyond two-voice counterpoint, because I have never completely devoted myself to the study and always had many other matters on my mind.  I am not at all so technically advanced as I would have to be at my age and as you certainly expect of your beginning pupils.  In particular this applies to my piano playing, and there are several reasons for that.  In the first place, I previously had never fully appreciated the enormous work involved in artistic ability.  In the trade circles, in which I grew up, what is meant by work is <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> something completely different.  Without going into too much detail about the environment from which I come, I might emphasize that there, especially in my a-musical father-city of Rotterdam, the commonly held view is that music study is really no proper mission in life for people of means, but more a thing to be pursued on the side.</tei:p><tei:p>Then when at age 22 I was accepted into the Hoch Conservatory<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> the incongruence between my musical comprehension and my technical expressive capabilities had already burgeoned to the extent that although I made progress in theory, especially under the guidance of Iwan Knorr,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> to whom I am indebted for much good advice, my piano playing, under the instruction of a teacher who had been taken on for the first attempts of 13- to 15-year-olds, was completely neglected.</tei:p><tei:p>I then interrupted study at the conservatory when I received the commission, from Rotterdam, to write melodramatic music for an amateur performance by students at the public school of a Dutch play.  I did this with much pleasure and also conducted the piece myself, all to the complete satisfaction of several experts who were present, but I cannot regard the whole experience as a serious accomplishment.</tei:p><tei:p>Afterward I returned to the conservatory, where a different piano teacher gave me a better understanding of arm and hand movements <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> in piano playing, to which I was very receptive.  A short time later, however, I suffered an accident in which I dislocated my right schoulder; the war came, and other interfering circumstances obliged me to move to Munich, where I soon was to occupy myself more with everything else but music, until I met Vrieslander<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> there and later married my present wife.  Now, I am far from wanting to blame anybody for my negligences.  The actual fact is that I have never worked at it seriously; my technique and my knowledge are therefore to be considered very incomplete.</tei:p><tei:p>As I was on world tour during the last years, where it was impossible, or nearly so, to concern myself with music, the necessity of finally devoting myself in a serious way to its study has become ever clearer to me.  Vrieslander,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> with whom I have become close friends and have also discussed this matter, thought my musical aptitude fully adequate for such work; and, encouraged by this appraisal, I request herewith that you accept me as your pupil beginning next season.</tei:p><tei:p>I would like to study counterpoint and thoroughbass, as well as harmonic and formal analysis, and score reading.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> At the same time I would like to advance my piano playing, and if possible also learn the organ.  But I don’t know whether it is your custom to teach these last two subjects yourself or normally refer them to another teacher.  I would like to advance in these areas so far as to possess the best foundation for the further cultivation of music, and even further if it should prove the case that my abilities and my time are adequate.  I say my time because anyway I am already 38 years old, and my abilities because I cannot conceal from myself the difficulty, after a life of relative idleness, of all at once taking on the most concentrated musical work.</tei:p><tei:p>I await your answer with understandable excitement and request, in case it should prove favorable, that you advise me of your conditions as well as the beginning date of your course.  I will then look for a residence in Vienna, furnished or unfurnished, where I can live with my wife and in which I hope to be able to be settled by October 15 at the latest.</tei:p><tei:p>With warmest felicitations, also from my wife, to your wife and yourself, I am, with deepest respect</tei:p><tei:p>Yours sincerely,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] A. v. Hoboken</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>