<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/54, [14] : 8-7-27 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Anthony van Hoboken, published here with kind permission.  
© Transcription John Rothgeb, 2008.
© Translation John Rothgeb, 2008.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish granted by the heirs of Anthony van Hoboken February 3, 2007.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1927-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Anthony van Hoboken; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 08/07/1927 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Hoboken ~ H+JSchenker","Hoboken ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Hoboken to Schenker, dated August 7, 1927</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-03-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Hoboken reports on recent travels, including the July 15, 1927 Vienna riots.  —He has made progress on his index of Haydn's works, and has purchased some Beethoven first editions.  —He hopes to meet Furtwängler soon, and has recently heard from Vrieslander.  —Asks Schenker to inscribe a copy of Meisterwerk2 to John Petrie Dunn. 

</dc:description><dc:subject>Hoboken, Anthony van;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Gmunden;  Salzkammergut;  Hallstadt;  Salzburg;  Vienna;  Justizpalast;  Palace of Justice;  riots;  Social Democrats;  Haydn;  index;  catalog;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Das Meisterwerk in der Musik;  The Masterwork in Music;  Dunn, John Petrie;  London;  Savoy Hotel;  Beethoven;  Deutsch, Otto Erich;  Vrieslander, Otto</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Giger's Hotel Waldhaus, Sils-Maria, Engadine</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from van Hoboken to Schenker, dated August 7, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>]
GIGER’S HÔTEL WALDHAUS
SILS-MARIA, ENGADINE</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">holograph:</tei:hi>]
7 August. 27</tei:p><tei:p>Lieber und verehrter Herr D^r^.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich fühle mich Ihnen tief verschuldet seit ich Ihren liebenswürdigen Brief vom 3t^en^ Juli<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  OJ 89/1, [1], July 3, 1927.</tei:note> bis jetzt noch mit keiner Silbe beantwortet habe.  Ich muss allerdings vorausschicken, dass derselbe mich erst am 18^ten^ Juli erreichte.  Ich fand ihm[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] an dem Tage in Gmunden vor als ich dorthin von einer Autofahrt durch das Salzkammergut (wobei ich auch das entzückende Hallstatt berührte und vier Tage in Salzburg verbrachte, mit meiner Frau) zurückkehrte.  Ich fuhr dann am gleichen Tage noch bis Linz weiter und am nächsten Tage nach Wien.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich kam also dort noch zeitig genug an <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> um den mustergültigen Ausbruch “proletarischer Freiheit” mitzuerleben, der sich da am 15^ten^ abgespielt hat.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Reference is to the Vienna riots of July 15, 1927, in which a mob set fire to the Palace of Justice (Justizpalast), with the loss of many of its records.  </tei:note>  Die Sozi’s<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Members of the Austrian Workers' Social Democratic Party (Sozialdemokratische Arbeiterpartei Österreichs (SDAPÖ)), who on July 15 formed demonstrations to protest against the judgment in early July in the Schattendorf trial.  </tei:note> waren empört, dass man auf eine Menge feuern liess, die den Justizpalast in Brand steckte!  Und so haben sie dann jetzt, als einziger positiver Gewinn aus den Unruhen, eine eigene Garde ins Leben gerufen der dagegen zu wachen hat, dass man in der Zukunft, wenn ähnliche “friedliche Demonstranter” z.B.:  die Universität oder/und das Parlament anzünden wollen, nicht mehr auf sie feuert!  Und die Regierung “bittet untertänigst” den Leitz,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Leitz: [identify]</tei:note> diese Wache doch nur . . . . u.s.w., u.s.w.  Was soll man zu so einer Unfähigkeit sagen?  Soll mann sich da noch wundern, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> wenn den Sozialdemokraten der Kamm schwillt?</tei:p><tei:p>Aber zur Sache.</tei:p><tei:p>Zu Hause fand ich natürlich allerhand Kleinigkeiten vor, die mich sehr in Anspruch nahmen.  Ich darf mich darüber nicht beklagen denn ich bin doch mit eigens während des Monats Juli in Wien geblieben um solcherlei abzutun damit es mich im Herbst nicht mehr stört.</tei:p><tei:p>Dazwischen habe ich jeden verfügbaren Augenblick dazu benützt, mein Haydn-Drucke zu registrieren und ich empfinde wenigstens die Genugtuung, damit so weit fertig geworden zu sein wie ich mir vorgenommen hatte d.h. alles steht in den Kästen, die Karthotek[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Karten sind <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> geschrieben, (daneben noch andere Kärtchen für meinen persönlichen Gebrauch in Hinblick auf das geplante chronologische Verzeichnis H’s Werke<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Van Hoboken's published catalog would not be completed until 36 years later: <tei:hi rend="italic">Joseph Haydn: Thematisch–Bibliographisches Werkverzeichnis</tei:hi> (Mainz: Schott, 1957–71): I: <tei:hi rend="italic">Instrumentalwerke</tei:hi>:  II: <tei:hi rend="italic">Vokalwerke</tei:hi>.  </tei:note>) bis auf die Lieder.</tei:p><tei:p>So verschob ich die Beantwortung Ihres Briefes [<tei:hi rend="italic">word deleted</tei:hi>], wozu ich mir doch Zeit nehmen wollte, immer länger hinaus, bis ich am 1^ten^ August von Wien fortfuhr ohne noch dazu gekommen zu sein.</tei:p><tei:p>Erst heute hole ich das nach und bitte Sie, hierüber nicht ungehalten zu sein.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit Furtwängler<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Wilhelm Furtwängler: [create profile and link].  The meeting took place during the week of August 21–27, 1927: see OJ 11/54, [15], August 28, 1927.  </tei:note> will ich mich dieser Tagen in Verbindung setzen und ihn fragen, wann mein Besuch ihm angenehm ist.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> Wenn das zweite <tei:hi rend="italic">Jahrbuch</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, vol. II (Munich: Drei Masken Verlag, 1926).  </tei:note> noch zeitig fertig würde, wäre das sehr schön.  Nur möchte ich Sie bitten, in dem Exemplar, welches ich Prof. Dunn<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="dunn_john_petrie">John Petrie Dunn</ref>.  </tei:note>  mitzubringen gedenke, ein Widmung an ihm hineinzuschreiben.  Die letzte Station, an dem das Buch mich erreichen kann, ist am 14^ten^ September im Savoy Hotel zu London.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich habe vergessen in meinem vorigen Brief den bedeutenden Kauf von Beethoven-Erstdrucke[n] zu erwähnen, den <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> ich kurz vor meiner Abreise gemacht habe.  Es handelt sich hierbei um 138 Stich Erstdrucke, die mir fehlten, dann noch viele Frühdrucke, die dort besser erhalten waren als meine Examplare.  Deutsch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="deutsch_otto_erich">Otto Erich Deutsch</ref>.  </tei:note> meint jetzt, dass meine Beethoven-Erstdruck Sammlung mit die bedeutendste ist ^sei^, welche existiert.</tei:p><tei:p>Von Vrieslander<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.  </tei:note> erhielt ich Nachricht.  Er beklagt sich sehr über die trockene Hitze in Neapal.</tei:p><tei:p>Hier ist es gerade das Gegenteil.  Neulich hatten wir sogar einen ganzen Tag Schnee.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit den besten Grüssen bin ich
Ihr sehr ergebener
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] AvHoboken.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from van Hoboken to Schenker, dated August 7, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>]
GIGER’S HÔTEL WALDHAUS
SILS-MARIA, ENGADINE</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">holograph:</tei:hi>]
August 7, 1927</tei:p><tei:p>Dear and esteemed Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>I feel very negligent where you are concerned, having thus far not sent a single syllable in answer to your gracious letter of July 3.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  I must say in advance that it reached me only on July 18.  I found it on the day in Gmunden when I returned there from an auto trip through the Salzkammergut (on which I also passed through the delightful Hallstadt and spent four days in Salzburg, with my wife).  I then traveled ahead on that same day to Linz, and on the next day to Vienna.</tei:p><tei:p>I thus arrived there in time <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> to endure the exemplary outbreak of “proletarian liberty,” which played out on the 15th.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  The Soci’s<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> were irate that somebody had let a crowd be fired upon who had set fire to the Palace of Justice!  And so today, as the single positive achievement of the unrest, they have brought about the establishment of a guard that is to see to it that in the future, when similar “peaceful demonstrators” for example try to set fire to the University and/or the Parliament, they will no longer be fired on!  And the government “most humbly asks” Leitz<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> only that this guarding activity . . . . etc. etc.  What is one supposed to say about such an incapacity?  Is it any wonder <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> that the Social Democrats get the big head?</tei:p><tei:p>But to the topic.</tei:p><tei:p>At home I naturally found all kinds of minutiae, which took a lot of time.  I can’t complain about it, because, among other reasons, I stayed during the month of July in Vienna in order to dispose of such things, so that I wouldn’t be bothered any more by them in the fall.</tei:p><tei:p>Meanwhile I have used every available moment to index my Haydn editions, and I feel at least the satisfaction of having progressed as far with that as I had planned—that is, everything is in the boxes, the index cards are <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> written (and other little cards too for my personal use in respect to the planned chronological catalog of Haydn’s works<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>), excepting those for the songs.</tei:p><tei:p>Thus I postponed replying to your letter (for which I did want to take time) longer and longer, until on August 1 I left Vienna without getting to it.</tei:p><tei:p>Only today I return to it and beg you not to be irritated about it.</tei:p><tei:p>I want in the coming days to get in touch with Furtwängler<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> and ask him when my visit would be convenient.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> If the second <tei:hi rend="italic">Yearbook</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> were to be ready on time, that would be very nice.  Now I would like to ask you to inscribe in the copy that I plan to take to Prof. Dunn<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> a dedication to him.  The last stop on which the book can reach me is on September 14 at the Savoy Hotel in London.</tei:p><tei:p>I forgot to mention in my previous letter the important purchase of Beethoven first editions, which <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> I made shortly before my departure.  It involves 138 engravings of first editions that I lacked, and then also many early editions, which were better preserved there than my copies. Deutsch<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> says now that my Beethoven first-edition collection ranks among the best that exist.</tei:p><tei:p>I received a report from Vrieslander.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/>  He complains bitterly about the dry heat in Naples.</tei:p><tei:p>Here it is exactly the opposite.  Recently we even had a whole day of snow.</tei:p><tei:p>With best greetings,
Yours most sincerely,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] A. v. Hoboken</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>