<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/54, [8] : 8-22-26 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Anthony van Hoboken, published here with kind permission.  
© Transcription John Rothgeb, 2008.
© Translation John Rothgeb, 2008.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish granted by the heirs of Anthony van Hoboken February 3, 2007.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1926-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Anthony van Hoboken; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 08/22/1926 12:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Hoboken ~ H+JSchenker","Hoboken ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from van Hoboken to Schenker dated August 22, 1926</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-01-21</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Hoboken will probably not now visit Schenker in Galtür;  explains his and his wife's departure from Munich and their subsequent travels to Bern, Naples, and Capri, and reports that his house in Vienna should be ready for occupancy on October 1. —Vrieslander and he are considering founding a music journal, and wish to discuss the idea with Schenker.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Hoboken, Anthony van;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Galtür;  München;  Munich;  Paznaun;  Vrieslander, Otto;  Vienna;  weather;  Bern;  Vatican;  Naples;  Capri; Casamicciola;  counterpoint;  Scirveco;  Sirocco;  Hiddigeigei;  journal;  Drei Masken Verlag;  Meisterwerk in der Musik;  Masterwork in Music;  Jahrbuch;  Yearbook;  Deutsch, Otto Erich</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Capri</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from van Hoboken to Schenker dated August 22, 1926</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Capri, 22 August 1926</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter lieber Herr Professor,</tei:p><tei:p>Nachdem es nun doch wohl ausgeschlossen ist, dass ich Sie noch in Galtür<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Click on <ref cRef="galtur">Galtür</ref>.  </tei:note> besuche, will ich doch wenigstens schriftlich etwas von mir hören lassen.  Wir gedenken nämlich nicht vor dem 6^ten^ September wieder in München zu sein und da vermute ich Sie sehen längst nicht mehr im Paznaun.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="paznaun">Paznaun</ref>.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Was die Ursache unseren[?<tei:hi rend="italic">recte</tei:hi> unseres] plötzlichen Abzug[s] aus München war, darüber hat Ihnen Vrieslander<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.  </tei:note> wohl geschrieben.  Es war das miserabele, unstete Wetter, das es mir nicht erlaubte, von heute auf morgen irgendwelche Pläne zu machen, geschweige denn einen Plan für eine lineare Auto-Tour.  Da wir nun auch der letzten Monaten in Wien kein übermässig erfreuliches Wetter gehabt hatten wollten wir, um uns wenigstens einige Wochen Sonnenschein zu verschaffen, dorthin, wo die Sonne garantiert scheint.  Und wie sie hier scheint.  Manchmal wurde es uns zuviel als wir nach den Baden am ganzen Körper verbrannt nach Hause kamen!</tei:p><tei:p>Zuerst waren wir drei Tage in Bern.  Wir kannten beide diese Stadt nicht, d.h. ich war einmal, in 1913, einen halben <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Tag dort gewesen.  Wir besichtigten Vieles, so viel sogar, dass es uns bald schwindlig wurde vor Katedralen [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>], Catacomben und römische Ruinen.  Es ist aber alles wohl sehr schön und interessant, doch müsste man Kunstgeschichte studiert haben.</tei:p><tei:p>Eins ist uns sehr aufgefallen: die Christliche Relegion [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>], die in unterirdischen Höhlen und mit bekehrten Sklaven angefangen hat und die sich schliesslich ein Monument wie die Peters-Kirche erbauen konnte.  Das kann man wohl ein Siegeszug nennen!  Doch wenn man dann ins Museum vom Vatican geht und sieht, wie diese selbe Religion von allen antiken Statuen, dem Apoll von Belvedere<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Apollo of the Belvedere:  Hellenistic statue (Roman copy: Vatican Museum) regarded as the quintessence of classical Greek art by late eighteenth-century German Hellenists.  Winckelmann gave this view a widely influential formulation in his <tei:hi rend="italic">Geschichte der Kunst des Alterthums</tei:hi> (1764).  </tei:note> nicht ausgeschlossen, Feigenblättchen an bestimmten Stellen mit Zement angebracht hat, dann fragt man sich doch unwillkürlich ab, ob dieser Sieg so unanfechtbar sei.</tei:p><tei:p>In Neapel trafen wir wieder mit Vrieslander,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.  </tei:note> der vorausgefahren war, zusammen.  Seine Frau und sein Sohn leben dort und schlagen sich mit einem Bagatell durchs Leben.  Ob es ihnen wirklich freut, möchte ich dahingestellt sein lassen.</tei:p><tei:p>Wir machten dann zu viert Ausflüge in der Umgebung auch nach Capri und endlich nach Ischia.  Dort wurde uns die Sache zu viel.  Casamicciola, wo die Vrieslanders voriges Jahr einige Monaten verbrachten, ist ein <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> sehr heisser Ort und ich konnte die Begeisterung, welche viele für den Ort hegen, nicht teilen.  Dann haben wir dort, wie ich zu Anfang meines Briefes schon erwähnte, einen halben Tag gebadet wobei mich die Sonne übel zugerichtet hat. Wovon ich mich zwei Tage nicht wohl fühlte.  Wir fuhren am selben Tag noch nach Neapel zurück, wo es tatsächlich etwas kühler ist, und entschlossen uns, das Herumreisen bei dieser Hitze aufzugeben.  Da es aber in München nach dem getreuen Wetterberichter meines Dieners immer noch trüb, kalt und regnerisch, oder regnerisch kalt und trübe war, entschieden wir uns für Capri und nahmen uns vor[,] einige Zeit hier fest zu bleiben.  Dies war mir insofern auch erwünscht, als ich nicht die ganze Ferienzeit ohne Arbeit verstreichen lassen möchte.  Nun habe ich hier Gelegenheit, nachmittags Kontrapunkt-Aufgaben<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Schenker had assigned Hoboken counterpoint exercises in his first season of lessons (1925/26), and the first lesson of the 1926/27 season (October 1, 1926) included “three-part counterpoint, fifth species,” which may have been the exercises in question (see lessonbooks 1925/26, 1926/27).  </tei:note> zu machen.  Mehr Arbeit habe ich nicht mit und das Klavier hier ist abominabel.</tei:p><tei:p>Morgens baden wir, schwimmen, Rudern und lassen uns von der Sonne trocknen.  Abends gehn wir dann früh ins Bett.  Der Ort und die Insel sind bezaubernd und geniessen nicht umsonst ihren Weltruf.  Kurgäste gibt es hier genug aber um diese Jahreszeit fast lauter Italiener da[?<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] es drolligerweise in Deutschland heisst, im <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Sommer sei es zu heiss für Capri.  Nichts ist weniger wahr.  Natürlich ist die Sonne sehr stark aber Abends weht immer ein kühler Wind.  Unangenehm schwül sind bloss die Tage, wo der Scirveco<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Sirocco?</tei:note> weht, ein Wind der vom Süden kommt und Wüstenhitze mit sich bringt, vielfach auch etwas Wolken und Regen.  Doch sind diese Tage nicht häufig, obwohl in diesem Sommer öfter wie sonst.  Viele Deutscher und Engländer leben hier ständig;  sie tun dies meist zu ganz besonderen Zwecken und haben eine entsprechende Gefolgschaft.  Das wirkt aber weiter nicht störend.  Das Hauptcafé heisst Hid[d]igeigei (nach Scheffel,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Joseph Victor von Scheffel (1826-1886), German author and poet.  The café Zum Kater Hiddigeigei on the Isle of Capri was named after The Tomcat Hiddigeigei from his epic poem <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Trompeter von Säkkingen</tei:hi> (1854).</tei:note>) ist aber trotzdem gut und angenehm.  So leben wir hier friedlich und angenehm[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] und wollen etwas[<tei:hi rend="italic">recte</tei:hi> etwa?] Anfang September wieder nach München zurück.  Die Nachrichten aus Wien lassen darauf hoffen, dass die Wohnung<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  See OJ 11/54, [4], also Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern ...</tei:hi> (1985), p. 154.</tei:note> am 1 Oktober bezogen werden kann.  Jedenfalls dränge ich auf die Fertigstellung meiner Musikraumes[,] doch sollte alles wider Erwarten eine Verzögerung erleiden so habe ich genügend kontrapunktisches Material, um die ersten Stunden damit zu füllen.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich höre mit Bedauern, dass Sie schlechtes Wetter haben.  Vielleicht klärt es sich gegen Ende des Monats doch noch auf.  Im September ist es ja meistens <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> schön in den Bergen.</tei:p><tei:p>Den Besuch, den ich und Vrieslander<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.  </tei:note> bei Ihnen vorhatten[,] hatte auch noch den Zweck, mit Ihnen über ein[en] Plan zu sprechen, der uns in München gekommen ist.  Es betrifft die Gründung irgendeiner Zeitschrift für Musik<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  This may be the precursor to <ref cRef="tonkunst_die">Die Tonkunst</ref>, although that was said to be the brainchild of Hans Weisse.  </tei:note> und die Idee kam mir, als ich hörte dass der Drei-Masken-Verlag wegen Ihr zweites Jahrbuch nun doch wieder Schwierigkeiten macht.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik II</tei:hi> (Munich: Drei Masken Verlag, 1926).  OC 54/95, July 9, 1926, from Drei Masken Verlag expressed concerns at the state of the book market, intended to maintain the high price, and would review the situation in September-October.  </tei:note>  Doch ist alles noch so vage, dass ich es vorziehe, hierüber nicht weiter mich schriftlich auseinanderzusetzen sondern damit zu warten, bis ich wieder in Wien sein werden.</tei:p><tei:p>Musikalisch weiss ich Ihnen nichts importantes zu berichten.  Hier höre ich natürlich nichts, bis auf Tanzmusik und, in Neapel, ab und zu einige jämmerlich falsch geblasene Militärmärsche und schlect gesungene Neapolitanische Canzone (die übrigens, wie mir einmal jemand, der Spanien bereist hatte, erzählte, viel stärker Spanisch als Italienisch beeinflusst sein sollen).  Die Bibliothek ruht auch, obwohl nicht ganz[,] und hin und wieder bekomme ich vom Herrn Deutsch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Click on <ref cRef="deutsch_otto_erich">Otto Erich Deutsch</ref>.  </tei:note> recht angenehme Briefe.  Ueber meine eigenen Tätigkeit berichtete ich schon.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> So komme ich dann allmählich zum[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] dem Schluss dieses Schreibens und muss ich[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] mich dabei ungelegentlich wegen der Schrift entschuldigen.  Ich habe ein[e] Feder, der mir nicht geläufig ist, &lt;strike&gt;Tinte&lt;/strike&gt; die Tinte ist zu dünn und das Löschblatt absorbiert nicht (daher der Klecks auf dem ersten Blatt), aber dafür blühen vor meinem Zimmer Orangen, Zitronen, Feigen und Reben und tröste ich mich mit dem Gedanken, dass Sie mein Geschreibsel <tei:hi rend="italic">doch</tei:hi> lesen können, trotz der Schrift.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich bitte Sie, mich Ihrer Frau Gemahlin zu empfehlen und seien Sie auch aufs herzlichste gegrüsst von Ihrem Schüler</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  AvHoboken</tei:p><tei:p>Meine Frau lässt auch ihre Grüsse an Ihnen beide übermitteln.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from van Hoboken to Schenker dated August 22, 1926</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Capri, 22 August 1926</tei:p><tei:p>Honored and dear Professor,</tei:p><tei:p>Now that it is probably out of the question that I should still visit you in Galtür<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> I want to send some news at least in written form.  We now plan not to be back in Munich before September 6, and thus I do not expect to see you again in the Paznaun.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/></tei:p><tei:p>Vrieslander<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> has probably written you about the reason for our sudden departure from Munich.  It was the miserable, unstable weather which prevented me from making any plans from one day to the next, to say nothing of a linear automobile tour.  As we have also had no exceedingly pleasant weather in Vienna in recent months, to give ourselves at least a few weeks of sunshine, we wanted to go where the sun is guaranteed to shine.  And how it shines here.  Sometimes it was too much for us, as we came home sunburned all over after swimming!</tei:p><tei:p>First of all we spent three days in Bern.  We were neither of us acquainted with this city; I was there once, in 1913, for half <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> a day.  We did much sight-seeing, even so much that we were soon giddy with all the cathedrals, catacombs, and Roman ruins.  But everything is certainly very beautiful and interesting, although one would have to have studied art history.</tei:p><tei:p>One thing was very notable for us: the Christian religion, which began in subterranean caves and with converted slaves and which ultimately was able to establish a monument like the St. Peter’s Church.  That can be called a stroke of victory!  But then when you go into the museum at the Vatican and see how this same religion has affixed fig leaves to all archaic statues in certain places with cement, the Apollo of the Belvedere<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> no exception, then one inevitably asks oneself whether this victory is so unassailable.</tei:p><tei:p>In Naples we again met Vrieslander,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> who had traveled on before.  His wife and his son live there, and manage to get by on practically nothing.  Whether they really enjoy it, I prefer not to question too closely.</tei:p><tei:p>Then the four of us made excursions into the surrounding area, also to Capri and finally to Ischia.  There it got to be too much for us.  Casamicciola, where the Vrieslanders spent several months last year, is a <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> very hot place, and I could not share the enthusiasm that many feel for the place.  Then, as I already mentioned at the beginning of my letter, we swam for a half day, during which the sun gave me a punishing.  After which I didn’t feel well for two days.  We returned to Naples on the same day, where it is actually somewhat cooler, and decided to forego driving around in this heat.  But since in Munich, according to the accurate weather forecaster of my servant, it was still cloudy, cold and rainy, or rainy, cold and cloudy, we decided to go to Capri and made plans to stay put here for a while.  One reason this was welcome to me is that I would not wish to let the whole vacation time pass without doing any work.  Now I have the opportunity here to do counterpoint exercises<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> in the afternoon.  I have no other work with me, and the piano here is abominable.</tei:p><tei:p>Mornings we sunbathe, swim, row, and dry ourselves in the sun.  Then evenings we go to bed early.  The place and the island are enchanting, and their world renown is well deserved.  There are plenty of spa-guests here, but around this season they are almost all Italians, since in Germany, amusingly, the word is that in Galtür<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> summer it is too hot on Capri.  Nothing is farther from the truth.  Naturally the sun is very strong, but in the evening there is always a cool breeze.  Only the days are unpleasantly muggy, when the Scirveco<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> blows, a wind that comes from the south and brings desert heat, and often some clouds and rain.  But these days are not frequent, although more often in summer than at other times.  Many Germans and English live here permanently; they do this for the most part for very special purposes and have a suitable following.  That however has no unpleasant repercussions.  The main café is named Hiddigeigei (after Scheffel<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>), but is good and pleasant in spite of that.  So we live here peacefully and pleasantly, and will return to Munich about the beginning of September.  The reports from Vienna hold out hope that the house<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> will be ready for occupancy on October 1.  In any case I am pushing for the completion of my music room; but if, contrary to expectation, things are delayed, I have enough contrapuntal material to fill up the first lessons.</tei:p><tei:p>I hear to my regret that you have bad weather.  But perhaps it will still clear up toward the end of the month.  In September the weather is usually <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> beautiful in the mountains.</tei:p><tei:p>The visit to you that I and Vrieslander<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> had planned had the purpose of discussing with you a plan that came to us in Munich.  It concerns the founding of some form of journal<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> for music, and the idea came to me when I heard that Drei-Masken Verlag now again makes difficulties concerning your second Yearbook.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/>  But everything is so vague that I prefer not to deal further with it here in writing but to wait with that until I am once again in Vienna.</tei:p><tei:p>Musically I know of nothing important to report to you.  Here naturally I hear nothing, except for dance music and, in Naples, now and then some kind of miserably tooted military marches and badly sung Neapolitan canzonas (which, incidentally, as I was told by somebody who had traveled in Spain, are supposed to be much more heavily Spanish-influenced than Italian).  The library is resting too, although not completely, and now and again I get very pleasant letters from Mr. Deutsch.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/>  About my own activity I have already reported.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> Thus I come gradually to the close of this letter, and must at this inopportune point beg pardon for the writing.  I have an unfamiliar pen, the ink is too thin and the blotter doesn’t absorb (thus the blot on the first page), but on the other hand there are oranges, lemons, figs and grapes blooming outside my room, and I comfort myself with the thought that you <tei:hi rend="italic">will</tei:hi> be able to read my scribbling, inspite of the writing.</tei:p><tei:p>Please commend me to your wife, and be most heartily greeted by your pupil,</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  A. v. Hoboken</tei:p><tei:p>My wife sends her greetings to you both.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>