<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/54, [18] : 9-18-27 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Anthony van Hoboken, published here with kind permission.  
© Transcription John Rothgeb, 2008.
© Translation John Rothgeb, 2008.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish granted by the heirs of Anthony van Hoboken February 3, 2007.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1927-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Anthony van Hoboken; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 09/18/1927 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Dunn ~ HSchenker","Hoboken ~ H+JSchenker","Hoboken ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Hoboken to Schenker, dated September 18, 1927</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-06-19</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Van Hoboken reports on his visit to John Petrie Dunn: his career, his grasp of Schenker's theory, his situation at Edinburgh University, his publications. — Tomorrow he is to visit C. S. Terry.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Hoboken, Anthony van;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Dunn, John Petrie;  Pauer, Max;  Lange, Samuel de;  Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven;  Beitrag zur Ornamentik;  Jahrbuch;  Meisterwerk in der Musik;  Tonwille;  Vrieslander, Otto;  Tovey, Donald Francis;  Scotland;  counterpoint;  Kahnt;  Leipzig;  Terry, Charles Sanford;  Switzerland;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  The Royal Hotel, 53 Princes Street, Edinburgh</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to van Hoboken, dated September 18, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>]
The Royal Hotel, Edinburgh.
Telegrams –
“Welcome, Edinburgh.”
53 Princes Street.
Telephone 23044
5 Lines</tei:p><tei:p>53 Princess Street.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">18 September</tei:hi> 192<tei:hi rend="italic">7</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter und lieber Herr Dr.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Receipt of this letter is reported in Schenker's diary, OJ 3/9, p. 3114, September 21, 1927.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Gestern habe ich also mit Herrn Dunn<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="dunn_john_petrie">John Petrie Dunn</ref>.</tei:note> zu abend gegessen.  Er ist ein breit und gesund aussehender Mann, dem man seine 49 Jahre ansieht.  Dabei sehr lebhaft.  Seine Frau, die auch mit war, ist viel jünger;  sie ist Deutsche, und war seine Schülerin als sie ihn heiratete.  Er hat s. Zt. in Stuttgart studiert;  Klavier bei Max Pauer<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="pauer_max_von">Max von Pauer</ref>.  </tei:note> und Theorie bei Samuel de Lange.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="lange_samuel_de_jnr">Samuel de Lange, jnr.</ref>.  </tei:note>  In 1914 hat er in Wien ein Concert gegeben wobei er eine sehr gute Presse gehabt haben soll.  Auf Ihre Werke ist er erst später gekommen und zwar über die Erläuterungsausgaben der letzten fünf Sonaten Beethoven’s,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Schenker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven, kritische Ausgabe, mit Einführung und Erläuterung</tei:hi> (Vienna: UE, 1913–20).  </tei:note> wo Sie ja Ihre <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> andere Werke immer zitieren.  Er hat sie nun nach und nach bestellt und kennt sie alle, vom “Beitrag zur Ornamentik”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Ein Beitrag zur Ornamentik</tei:hi> (Vienna: UE, [1903]).  </tei:note> bis zum Jahrbuch I.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Jahrbuch I</tei:hi> = <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, vol. I (Munich: Drei-Masken Verlag, 1925).  </tei:note> incl. den Tonwillen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</tei:hi> (Vienna: Flugblätterverlag [=UE], 1921–24).  </tei:note> wo er über das erste Heft wohl erstaunt gewesen sein mag, aber &lt;strike&gt;jetzt&lt;/strike&gt; heute die politischen Äusserungen zugunsten der musikalischen gerne vergessen hat.</tei:p><tei:p>Die Bekanntschaft mit Ihren Theorien war für ihm eine Offenbarung und er ist, neben Vrieslander,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.  </tei:note> der überzeugteste Anhänger derselben dem ich bis jetzt begegnet bin.  Er bekennt sich auch restlos dazu und tut das seinige, sie zu verbreiten.  Dieses “Seinige” ist aber leider etwas eingeschränkt.  Er ist nicht der Professor für Musik an der Universität; diese Stelle hat Herr Tovey<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Click on <ref cRef="tovey_donald_francis">Donald Francis Tovey</ref>.  </tei:note> inne, ein träumerischer, zerstreuter Musiker; ein “Irrlicht”, wie Dunn ihm [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte</tei:hi> ihn] nennt.  D. ist sein Assistent; er hat <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> aber &lt;strike&gt;H&lt;/strike&gt; hauptsächlichen Anteil am kontrapunktischen Unterricht und die Schüler halten zu ihm und damit zugleich zu Ihnen.  Solange aber Tovey die höheren Compositionsklasse leitet, kann Ihre Methode dort nicht zum vollen Entfaltung kommen, obwohl die Schüler am liebsten demnach unterrichtet werden würden.  Aber der Professor wird das nicht tun;  und, wenn er auch alle Ihre Schriften kennen würde und von der Richtigkeit derselben noch &lt;strike&gt;zu&lt;/strike&gt; so überzeugt wäre, nach D’s Beschreibung wäre er nicht imstande danach zu unterrichten.  Und ein Professor sitzt in Schotland[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] fester auf seinen <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Sitz als wie ein König auf seinen Thron.  Ein zweites Hinderniss ist, dass der Lehrer, welcher den Elementarunterricht hat, ein alter Pedant sein soll, der nach der alten Methode “Harmonie” Unterreicht erteilt u.s.w. [–] kurz: alles das tut, was Sie so richtig rügen.  So sitzt unser Mr. Dunn zwischen einem Esel und einem Entrückten und fällt den Samen, den er streut, zum grössten Teil auf felsigem Acker.</tei:p><tei:p>D. ist gänzlich unbemittelt und fristet sein weiteres Dasein mit Privat-Unterricht im Klavierspiel[.]  Er hat hierüber auch zwei Werkchen publiziert:</tei:p><tei:p>“Die Handführung beim Klavierspiel”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Geheimnis der Handführung beim Klavierspiel</tei:hi> (Leipzig: Kahnt, 1914).  </tei:note> und
“Die Ornamentik in den Werken F. Chopin’s”[.]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Ornamentation in the Works of Frederick Chopin</tei:hi> (London: Novello and Company, Ltd., [1921]).</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Letzteres, auf Englisch geschrieben, wird er mir verehren; das erstere, auf Deutsch bei Kahnt in Leipzig erschienen, werde ich mir bestellen.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> Aus einigen Gesprächen über dieses Thema gewann ich den Eindruck, dass er auf diesem Gebiet noch sehr viel von Ihnen zu lernen hätte.  Doch war das nur einer [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Eindruck, sowie ich Sie &lt;strike&gt;ich&lt;/strike&gt; bitte, diese ganze[n] Ausführungen ebenfalls als ersten Eindruck zu betrachten.</tei:p><tei:p>Heute gehe ich noch zu ihm zum Tee.  Morgen fahre ich von hier nach Aberdeen (das ist noch etwas näher am Nordpol wie Edinburgh) zum Besuch bei Dr. Terry,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  Click on <ref cRef="terry_charles_sanfor">Charles Sanford Terry</ref>.</tei:note> mit dem ich wegen das Archiv [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] verhandeln will. (Dunn war übrigens vom Archivplan sehr begeistert[.]) Ich bin froh, dass meine Reise nun endlich soweit gediehen ist, dass sich <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> meine musikalische[n] Pläne damit verbinden lassen.  In der Schweiz war ich diesmal nicht sehr glücklich obwohl ich mir gerne sagen lasse, dass der Aufenthalt auf &lt;strike&gt;diesen&lt;/strike&gt; jenen Höhen Körper und Geist sehr stärkt.</tei:p><tei:p>Furtwängler,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  Click on <ref cRef="furtwangler_wilhelm">Wilhelm Furtwängler</ref>.  </tei:note> der mir fest versprochen hatte, mich noch einmal zu sich einzuladen, hat nichts mehr von sich hören lassen obwohl ich ihm noch einmal begegnet bin und er dabei sein Versprechen wiederholt hat.  Ob er sich doch nicht für &lt;strike&gt;d&lt;/strike&gt;unsere Sache<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15">  Click on <ref cRef="photogrammarchiv">Photogrammarchiv</ref>.  </tei:note> interessiert?  Nun, es wird auch ohne ihm gehen.  Aber schade wäre es doch.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit den besten Empfehlung an Ihrer werten Frau Gemahlin bin ich, wie immer
Ihr sehr ergebener
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] AvHoboken</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to van Hoboken, dated September 18, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>]
The Royal Hotel, Edinburgh.
Telegrams –
“Welcome, Edinburgh.”
53 Princes Street.
Telephone 23044
5 Lines</tei:p><tei:p>53 Princess Street.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">18 September</tei:hi> 192<tei:hi rend="italic">7</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Dr. [Schenker],<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Yesterday, then, I joined Mr. Dunn<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> for dinner.  He is a sturdy and healthy-looking man who looks his age of 49.  Very vigorous too.  His wife, who was there too, is much younger;  she is German, and was his pupil when she married him.  He studied at the time in Stuttgart: piano with Max Pauer<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> and theory with Samuel de Lange.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  In 1914 he gave a concert in Vienna for which he is said to have had very good reviews.  He came to your works only later, and in fact by way of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Elucidatory Editions of the Last Five Sonatas of  Beethoven</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> where you do always <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> cite your other works.  He ordered them one by one and knows all of them, from the <tei:hi rend="italic">Contribution to Ornamentation</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> up to the first <tei:hi rend="italic">Yearbook</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> including the <tei:hi rend="italic">Tonwille</tei:hi> volumes.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/>  He may well have been astonished by the first issue, but today has been willing to overlook the political statements in favor of the musical ones.</tei:p><tei:p>Acquaintance with your theories was a revelation for him and he is, along with Vrieslander,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> the most thoroughly convinced disciple of them that I have met so far.  He is unswervingly faithful to them and does his part to disseminate them.  This “part” of his, however, is unfortunately somewhat limited.  He is not Professor of Music at the University; this position is occupied by Mr. Tovey,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> a dreamy, absent-minded musician;  a “will-o’-the-wisp” as Dunn calls him.  Dunn is his assistant; he has, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> however, primary responsibility for counterpoint instruction, and the students are loyal to him, and thus, at the same time, to you.  But so long as Tovey teaches the more advanced composition classes, your method cannot be fully applied there, although the students would prefer to be instructed according to it.  But the Professor will not do that;  and even if he knew all of your writings and were ever so convinced of their validity, according to Dunn’s description, he would not be in a position to teach accordingly.  And a Professor in Scotland sits more securely on his <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Chair than a king on his throne.  A second obstacle is that the teacher who has responsibility for the elementary instruction is said to be an old pedant, who dispenses instruction in “harmony” according to the old method, etc.—in short, does everything that you so rightly denounce.  Thus our Mr. Dunn sits between a jackass and a romantic, and drops the seed that he sows in large part on rocky plots.</tei:p><tei:p>Dunn is completely without means and gets by for the rest with the proceeds from private teaching of piano playing.  He has also published two small works on this topic:</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Usage of the Hand in Piano Playing</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> and 
<tei:hi rend="italic">Ornamentation in the Works of Frederick Chopin</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/></tei:p><tei:p>The latter, written in English, he will give me as a present;  the former, published in German by Kahnt in Leipzig, I will order.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> From several discussions on this theme I got the impression that in this area he still has very much to learn from you.  But that was only an impression, just as I request that you regard all of these reports likewise as first impression.</tei:p><tei:p>Today I join him again for tea.  Tomorrow I will go from here to Aberdeen (that is again somewhat closer to the North Pole than Edinburgh) for a visit with Dr. Terry,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> with whom I have business concerning the Archive.  (Dunn, incidentally, was very enthusiastic about the Archive plan.)  I am happy that my trip now has finally borne fruit to the extent that <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> my musical plans can be combined with it.  In Switzerland I was not very lucky this time, although I like to tell myself that the sojourn in those high elevations has strengthened body and spirit very much.</tei:p><tei:p>From Furtwängler,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/> who promised me faithfully to invite me again, I have heard nothing, although I met him once more, at which time he repeated his promise.  Is he not interested in our project?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn15"/>  Well, it will proceed without him too.  But it would be a shame.</tei:p><tei:p>With best wishes to your good wife, I am, as ever,
Yours most sincerely,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] A. v. Hoboken</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>