<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/54, [23] : 3-21-28 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Anthony van Hoboken, published here with kind permission.  
© Transcription John Rothgeb, 2009.
© Translation John Rothgeb, 2009.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb 2009
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish granted by the heirs of Anthony van Hoboken February 3, 2007.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1928-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Anthony van Hoboken; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 03/21/1928 02:25:47 PM --><!-- MT Tags: "Hoboken ~ H+JSchenker","Hoboken ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Hoboken to Schenker, dated March 21, 1928</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-06-26</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Hoboken has still made no progress of photographic work at the Paris Conservatory.  - - He will go to Rotterdam and Münster.  - - Speaks of the importance of his Archive work and contacts he has made.   Will probably go to a concert featuring music of Alban Berg.  - - He asks Schenker to intervene with O. E. Deutsch.  

 </dc:description><dc:subject>Hoboken, Anthony van;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Paris Conservatoire;  Rotterdam;  Münster;  Santini collection;  Paris;  Photogrammarchiv;  Steinhof;  Revue musicale;  Prunières, Henri;  Sorbonne;  Vrieslander, Otto;  Vienna;  Kunstgewerbeschule;  School of Industrial Art;  Berg, Alban;  Effenberger, Hans;  Sliwinsky, Jan;  Baker, Josephine;  Busoni, Ferruccio;  Deutsch, Otto Erich;  Schubert;  symphony;  sketches;  London;  Oxford University Press;  Schmid;  Österreichische Nationalbibliothek;  Austrian National Library</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Hotel Vouillemont, 15, Rue Boissy d'Anglais, Paris </marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Hoboken to Schenker, dated March 21, 1928</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>]
HOTEL VOUILLEMONT
15, Rue Boissy d'Anglais [<tei:hi rend="italic">etc.</tei:hi>]
Paris [<tei:hi rend="italic">etc.</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">handwritten:</tei:hi>]
21.III.28.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter und lieber Herr D^r.^<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/1, p. 3191, March 24:  " Von v. Hoboken (rec. Br. aus Paris):  er ist wegen eines Passus von Deutsch beunruhigt, der über eine Facsimilierung von Schubert-Skizzen spricht.  bittet mich D. einzuschärfen, daß Skizzen nicht zum Archiv gehören."  ("From van Hoboken (registered letter from Paris):  he is disturbed by a passage by Deutsch that speaks about the facsimile-ing of Schubert sketches.  He asks me to impress upon D. that sketches are not part of the Archive.")  However, some of the material in the latter part of this letter is recorded in the entry recording OJ 11/54, [22], March 11, 1928.   </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Nachdem ich Ihnen das letzte geschrieben habe, hat sich die hiesige Lage für mich um nichts geändert.  Das Ministerium hat auf meinem Brief bisher nicht geantwortet und auch der Direktion vom Conservatorium<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  The Paris Conservatoire.  </tei:note> keine weitere Anweisungen gegeben.  Ich habe, des Wartens müde, nun versucht, einige Herren, von denen ich annehmen konnte[,] dass sie mir helfen könnten, zu erreichen.  Aber die Folge davon ist, dass ich nun an so <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> vielen[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Leute verwiesen wurde die mir den richtigen Weg zeigen wollen (jeder zeigt natürlich einen anderen)[,] dass ich jetzt vollkommen wirr geworden bin.  Doch werden die nächsten Tage wohl noch etwas Klarheit schaffen.  Am Sonntag will ich nach Rotterdam fahren wo am Donnerstag einer meiner Neffen Hochzeit feiert.  Ich halte darauf, diese Feste beizuwohnen weil dort alle meine Geschwister zusammenkommen, was sich nun nicht allzuoft vortut.  Meine Frau kommt auch hin und von dort werden wir dann wohl direkt nach Wien kommen.  Ich habe allerdings noch einen Abstecher nach Münster i/W[estfalen] <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> vor, wo ich die &lt;del&gt;Aut&lt;/del&gt; Manuskript-Sammlung Santini<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="santini-sammlung">Santini-Sammlung</ref>.  </tei:note> besichtigen möchte.  Aber, da ich doch höchstwahrscheinlich wegen Verhandlungen im April oder Mai noch einmal nach Paris fahren werde, will ich nicht allzulang mehr von Wien fortbleiben weil dadurch mein musikalisches Studium bei Ihnen ziemlich illusorisch werden würde.  Und dies liegt mir sehr am Herzen obwohl ich davon überzeugt bin, dass die Arbeit welche ich für das Archiv verrichte, für die Nachwelt von grösserer Bedeutung sein wird als wie meine musikalische. Ich will auch, gestützt auf das Vertrauen welches Sie mir entgegenbringen (und das <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> ich nicht beschämen möchte) versuchen, von Zeit zu Zeit über Erfahrungen, in dem Archiv aufgetan, zu schreiben wobei ich für jede Hilfe Ihrerseits sehr dankbar wäre.</tei:p><tei:p>Bei meinem hiesigen Besuchen habe ich auch einen Herrn Steinhof<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Herr Steinhof:  see the comments two paragraphs later.  He and his wife are otherwise unknown.  He is not mentioned in Schenker's pre-1912 diaries.  </tei:note> kennengelernt dessen Frau Musikhistorikerin ist, in der Revue Musicale (von Prunières<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="prunieres_henry">Henri Prunières</ref>.  </tei:note>) schreibt und an der Sorbonne Vorträge hält.  Sie liest jetzt Ihre werke und will demnächst darüber sprechen.  Als ich ihr von Ihren bevorstehenden 60^ten^ Geburtstag sprach fasste sie gleich den Plan, aus diesem Anlass über Sie einen längeren Vortrag zu halten und bat mich um Material.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> Wie erfreulich ich es nun auch finde, wenn über Sie hier gesprochen würde, und wie sehr ich auch davon überzeugt bin, dass man auf die Dauer den[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr from</tei:hi> die] Menschen nicht verbieten kann, so zu sprechen wie sie (bezw.: ihre Zuhörer) es wollen[,] so [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr from</tei:hi> wollen.  So] möchte ich doch hier etwas Vorsicht walten lassen und mit Ihnen (und wohl auch mit Vrieslander,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.  </tei:note> der dann wohl in Wien sein wird) genau durchsprechen, welcher Art Material ich der Dame zur Verfügung <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> stellen werde.  Ihr &lt;del&gt;gegenüber&lt;/del&gt; habe ich mich natürlich ganz zur Verfügung gestellt und sie wird nach Wien kommen um mit mir zu sprechen.</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr Mann ist nämlich Wiener obwohl er fast sein ganzes Leben hier verbracht hat.  Seit drei Jahren kommt er wieder regelmässig nach Wien und unterrichtet an der Kunstgewerbeschule.  Er ist Architekt.  Er erzählte mir, dass er einmal beinahe Ihr Schüler geworden wäre.  Das war in 1905 aber durch einen Zufall ist nichts daraus geworden.</tei:p><tei:p>So habe ich hier auf einmal etwas erreicht, das ich gar nicht vorausgesehen hatte (und dessen Wert ich auch noch <tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> nicht prüfen kann) und es freut mich hier einige Beziehungen angeknüpft zu haben, wovon eine[?] auch nach Wien übergreift.  Sie wissen ja, wie gerne ich hier bin und diese Stadt regt mich immer wieder von neuem an durch ihre Lebendigkeit und Arbeitsamkeit.  Ich tue hier dann auch Dinge, die mir in Wien nicht einfallen würde.  So bin ich morgen zu einer Alban Berg<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Alban Berg: [create profile]</tei:note> Matinée eingeladen, wo er selbst sein Kompositionen aufführt und ich überlege mich ernstlich, ob ich nicht hingehen werde um mir dieses Zeug einmal anzuhören.  Ich verdanke diese Einladung einem Dr. Hans Effenberger,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="effenberger_hans">Hans Effenberger</ref>.  </tei:note> der auch mal ein Jahr lang Leiter der Musik- <tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> sammlung an der National-Bibliothek in Wien gewesen ist.  Er ist Pole, und seit sein Vaterland wieder selbständig ist nennt er sich Jan Sliwinsky und hält einen Buchladen und Bildergalerie "Au Sacre du Printemps" (nach dem Werk Stravinsky's) wo er auch nur wirres Zeug verkauft bezw. Ausstellt.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich meine, dass in einer grossen Stadt wie diese, wo es soviel Gutes gibt, solcherlei Episoden eben ungestört stattfinden können ohne dass sie ernste Menschen schaden und ich freue mich einmal so etwas beiwohnen zu können.  In Wien halte ich das für unmöglich besonders seit ich gelesen habe, dass man bei offenen Kirchentüren Messe &lt;del&gt;gegen&lt;/del&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;liest gegen&lt;/sup&gt; <tei:hi rend="bold">{9}</tei:hi> die Josefin Baker<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="baker_josephine">Josephine Baker</ref>.  </tei:note> (die ich gewiss nicht schätze; sie war noch so eine Episode und hat hier bereits abgetan; wer sie ernster nimmt, fällt selbst hinein).</tei:p><tei:p>Auch verkehre ich bein einem holländischen Musiker, so ich mich auf den Laufenden halte über die neueste Klangeffecten (die nennen es "Harmonieen") der französischen.  Er ist ein sehr feiner Mensch, Schüler Busoni's<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Click on <ref cRef="busoni_ferruccio">Ferruccio Busoni</ref>.  </tei:note> und wenn er mir so seine Sachen vorspielt, so meine ich immer, das bei einer[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] gut fundierten Stufengang, Bass- und[?] <tei:hi rend="bold">{10}</tei:hi> Stimmführung, manche von diese[n] Effekts sich gar nicht übel ausnehmen würden.  Aber daran fehlt es nun einmal und sie werden ersetzt durch schöne Worte, womit man seine Intentionen auszudrücken versucht.</tei:p><tei:p>Zuletzt noch eine Bitte, oder besser: ein Alarmruf.</tei:p><tei:p>In einem Brief von Deutsch,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Click on <ref cRef="deutsch_otto_erich">Otto Erich Deutsch</ref>.  </tei:note> den ich vor einigen Tagen erhielt, kommt folgender Passus vor:</tei:p><tei:p>"Zu London denke ich natürlich nicht daran, das Archiv mit den Aufnahmen der umfangreichen Skizzen zu Schuberts E-Symphonie<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Perhaps D. 729.  </tei:note> zu belasten.  Aber ich habe Hoffnung dass ein Wiener Verleger oder die Musikabteilung der Oxford-Presse <tei:hi rend="bold">{11}</tei:hi> in London, mit der ich in Fühlung bin, ein Faksimile danach oder einen Stich mit einem unterlegten Klavierauszug herausgibt (dieser Auszug, etwa von Schmid<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  Schmid ??</tei:note> hier gemacht, als letztes System)"   Was soll das heissen?  Meines Wissen[s] hat Schubert von dieser Symphonie nur die Melodieführung auf Papier geworfen und durchwegs ohne Angabe des Basses oder der Harmonie.  Mandyszewski,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  Click on <ref cRef="mandyczewski_eusebiu">Eusebius Mandyczeswki</ref>.  </tei:note> [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] der sie sich einmal abgeschrieben hat, könnte hierüber Auskunft geben.  Wie will Schmid hierzu einer[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Klavierauszug anfertigen?  &lt;del&gt;Wollen&lt;/del&gt; Ich fürchte daher, dass hier etwas geschiet was in schärfster[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Gegensatz zu &lt;del&gt;den&lt;/del&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;unsern&lt;/sup&gt; in dem Archiv verwirklichten Grundsätzen <tei:hi rend="bold">{12}</tei:hi> steht und ich bitte Sie, Deutsch hierüber zu befragen und ihm[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] nötigenfalls mit Ihrer ganzen Autorität von der Mitarbeit hieran abzuhalten.  Ich habe &lt;del&gt;ich&lt;/del&gt; ihm auch schon geschrieben, nur unbestimmter, da ich den richtigen Sachverhalt nicht kenne.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich bin ab Sonntag in Rotterdam, Weimar Hotel, wo ich meine Frau treffe die aus Berlin kommt von wo sie mir auch einige, sehr aufgeregte, Briefe schrieb.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit den besten Grüssen und Empfehlungen an Ihrer Frau Gemahlin bin ich, wie immer,</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr sehr ergebener 
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] AvHoboken</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Hoboken to Schenker, dated March 21, 1928</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>]
HOTEL VOUILLEMONT
15, Rue Boissy d'Anglais [<tei:hi rend="italic">etc.</tei:hi>]
Paris [<tei:hi rend="italic">etc.</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">handwritten:</tei:hi>]
March 21, 1928</tei:p><tei:p>Dear and esteemed Dr. Schenker,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Since I last wrote to you, the situation here has not changed at all.  The Ministry has not yet replied to my letter and the Administration of the Conservatory<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> has given no further instructions.  Tired of the wait, I have now attempted to reach several gentlemen I could assume would be able to help me.  But the result has been that I have been referred to so <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> many people who wanted to show me the correct way (each naturally shows me a different one) that I have now become completely confused.  But the coming days will probably bring some clarification.  On Sunday I will go to Rotterdam, where on Thursday one of my nephews is to be married.  I want to attend this celebration because all of my siblings will gather there, which doesn't happen so often.  My wife will come too, and from there we will come directly to Vienna.  I plan also a side-trip to Münster in Westfalia, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> where I want to view the Santini manuscript collection.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  But, since I most probably will go to Paris again in April or May on business, I don't want to remain away from Vienna too much longer, because otherwise my musical study with you would become rather illusory.  And this is very important to me, although I am convinced that the work I am doing for the Archive, for posterity, will be of greater significance than my musical work.  I want also, with the support of the confidence you have in me (and of which <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> I don't want to prove unworthy), to write from time to time about experiences provided by the Archive; in this I would be grateful for any help on your part.</tei:p><tei:p>In my visits locally I have also become acquainted with a Mr. Steinhof,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> whose wife is a music historian who publishes in the <tei:hi rend="italic">Revue Musicale</tei:hi> (Prunières<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>) and gives lectures at the Sorbonne.  She is now reading your works and will speak on them quite soon.  When I spoke with her about your approaching sixtieth birthday she immediately conceived the plan of giving a longer lecture and asked me for material.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> However gratifying I now find the prospect of your being discussed here, and however convinced I may be that in the long run people cannot be forbidden to speak in the way they (or: their audience) wish, I still would prefer to exercise some caution here and talk through completely with you (and perhaps also with Vrieslander,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> who may then be in Vienna) what kind of material I should make available to the lady.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> Naturally I have placed myself completely at her disposal, and she will come to Vienna to speak with me.</tei:p><tei:p>Her husband is in fact a Viennese, although he has spend almost his whole life here.  For three years he has again come regularly to Vienna and taught at the School of Industrial Art.  He is an architect.  He told me that he once almost became your pupil.  That was in 1905, but because of a coincidence, nothing came of it.</tei:p><tei:p>Thus I here achieved something that I had not at all foreseen (and whose value I can also <tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> not yet assess), and I am happy to have tied up several connections here, one of which also reaches over to Vienna.  You do know how I enjoy being here, and this city always reinvigorates me by its vitality and industriousness.  I do things here that would never occur to me in Vienna.  Thus tomorrow I am invited to an Alban Berg<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> matinée, where he will perform his own compositions, and I am seriously thinking about whether I may not actually attend in order to hear this trash for once.  I owe this invitation to a D^r.^ Hans Effenberger,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> who for a year has also been Director of the Music Collection <tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> at the National Library in Vienna.  He is a Pole, and since his fatherland is again independent, he calls himself Jan Sliwinsky, and runs a bookstore and picture gallery "Au Sacre du Printemps" (after Stravinsky's work), where he also sells and exhibits crazy trash.</tei:p><tei:p>I think that in a great city like this, where there are so many good things, episodes of this sort can take place undisturbed without any harm to serious people, and I am glad to be able to attend something of the sort.  In Vienna I think that impossible, especially since I have read that with church doors open they say mass against <tei:hi rend="bold">{9}</tei:hi> Josephine Baker<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> (whom I certainly don't admire;  she too was an episode of this kind and is already finished here;  anybody who takes her more seriously meets the same fate).</tei:p><tei:p>I also hobnob with a Dutch musician, to keep current on the newest sound-effects (they call them "harmonies") of the French.  He is a very fine man, a student of Busoni's,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> and when he plays me his pieces, I always think that with a well-founded scale-degree progression, bass and <tei:hi rend="bold">{10}</tei:hi> voice leading, some of these effects wouldn't be bad at all.  But those elements are missing, and they are substituted by pretty words that attempt to express intentions.</tei:p><tei:p>Finally a request, or better: a cry of alarm.</tei:p><tei:p>In a letter from Deutsch<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> that I received a few days ago, there is the following passage:</tei:p><tei:p>"In London I naturally have no plan to burden the Archive with the photographing of the extensive sketches for Schubert's Symphony in E.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/>  But I have the hope that a Vienna publisher or the Music Division of Oxford University Press <tei:hi rend="bold">{11}</tei:hi> in London, with which I am in contact, will issue a facsimile of them or an engraving with an underlaid piano reduction (this reduction perhaps made here by Schmid,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> as the last system)."  What is that supposed to mean?  To my knowledge, Schubert jotted down on paper only the melodic line of this symphony, without indication of the bass or the harmony.  Mandycewski,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/> who once made a copy of it for himself, would be able to provide information on this.  How will Schmidt make a piano reduction of this?  I fear, therefore, that something is afoot here which stands most sharply at odds with the principles that we have applied in the Archive, <tei:hi rend="bold">{12}</tei:hi> and I beg you to ask Deutsch about this, and to dissuade him, with your full authority if necessary, from collaboration on this.  I have already written him, but less emphatically, since I don't know the exact circumstances.</tei:p><tei:p>Starting Sunday I will be in Rotterdam, Weimar Hotel, where I will meet my wife, who will come from Berlin, from where she wrote me a few (quite apprehensive) letters.</tei:p><tei:p>With best greetings and regards to your wife, I am, as ever,</tei:p><tei:p>Yours most sincerely,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] A. v. Hoboken</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>