<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/54, [15] : 8-28-27 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Anthony van Hoboken, published here with kind permission.  
© Transcription John Rothgeb, 2008.
© Translation John Rothgeb, 2008.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish granted by the heirs of Anthony van Hoboken February 3, 2007.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1927-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Anthony van Hoboken; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 08/28/1927 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: &quot;Furtw&#195;&#164;ngler ~ H+JSchenker&quot;,&quot;Furtw&#195;&#164;ngler ~ HSchenker&quot;,&quot;Hoboken ~ H+JSchenker&quot;,&quot;Hoboken ~ HSchenker&quot; --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Hoboken to Schenker, dated August 28, 1927</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-05-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Hoboken reports on meeting with Furtwängler regarding the Photogrammarchiv, and expresses the hope that it will be possible to interest Furtwängler in performance according to the sources in the archive;  encloses the final version of the "Aufruf" for the archive, and discusses negotiations with the Austrian National Library and Ministry of Education.  — Comments on Oppel's plan to teach in Leipzig.  — Agrees to Schenker's lesson plan and fee for 1927/28.  — Describes his travel plans, which include meetings with Louis Koch in Frankurt, Ludwig Schiedermair in Bonn, contact with John Petrie Dunn in England, C. S. Terry in Scotland, and Maurice Cauchie in Paris, and photographing [of sources] at the [Paris] Conservatory.   

</dc:description><dc:subject>Hoboken, Anthony van;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Sils-Maria;  Engadine;  Photogrammarchiv;  Aufruf;  Appeal;  Vrieslander, Otto;  Weisse, Hans;  Oppel, Reinhard;  Leipzig;  Chopin;  manuscripts;  Haas, Robert;  Berg, Alban;  Schoenberg, Arnold;  lessons;  honorarium;  Ministry of Education;  Nationalbibliothek;  Vienna;  Bietz, Hofrat;  Rochlitzer, Dr.;  Krefeld;  Heuss, Alfred;  Deutsch, Otto Erich;  Beethoven;  Basel;  Frankfurt;  Rotterdam;  England;  Drei Masken Verlag;  Schiedermair, Ludwig;  Dunn, John Petrie;  Meisterwerk in der Musik;  Masterwork in Music;  Jahrbuch;  Yearbook;  Terry, Charles Sanford;  Aberdeen;  London;  Paris;  Cauchie, Maurice;  ConservatoryGaltür</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Giger's Hotel Waldhaus, Sils-Maria, Engadine</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from van Hoboken to Schenker dated August 28, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>GIGER’S HÔTEL WALDHAUS	
SILS-MARIA, ENGADINE</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">handwritten:</tei:hi>] 	28.VIII.’27
						
Sehr verehrter und lieber Herr D^r.^<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary as (click on) &lt;a href="../../../../../diary/oj<tei:hi rend="italic">39</tei:hi>p<tei:hi rend="italic">3106</tei:hi>83027.html"&gt;OJ 3/9, p. 3106&lt;/a&gt;, August 30, 1927.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ich war also vorige Woche bei Herrn Furtwängler<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Wilhelm Furtwängler: [create profile and link].  </tei:note> zum Tee.  Wir haben uns vorher eine kurze Weile unterhalten doch es war keineswegs &lt;strike&gt;ein&lt;/strike&gt; kein eingehenderes Gespräch welches wir führten[.]  Wir streiften die Gegenstände nur.  Ich erzählte ihm natürlich vom Archiv[.]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  i. e. the <ref cRef="photogrammarchiv">Photogrammarchiv</ref>, recently established by Hoboken at the instigation of Schenker and about to be publicly launched.   </tei:note>  Ob es ihm sehr interssierte, vermag ich nicht einmal zu sagen, um so weniger, ob er eines Tages die Resultate in der Praxis umsetzen wird.  Es ist auch schwer <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> jetzt schon zu entscheiden, wo wir noch gar keine Vorlagen haben.  Im Laufe des Winters, wenn wir ihm an Hand von Aufnahmen Abweichungen gegenüber den Ausgaben werden zeigen können, ist m. E. der Moment, ihm zu Aufführungen nach den Vorlagen des Archivs zu bewegen, viel günstiger wie jetzt.  Aber es hat mich gefreut, seine Bekanntschaft gemacht zu haben.  Er machte auf mich einen ruhigen und sympathischen Eindruck.  Wir sprachen noch über Vrieslander<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.  </tei:note> und Weisse<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.  </tei:note> und natürlich viel über Sie.</tei:p><tei:p>Ein[e] Frage regte er an, die mir wichtig scheint: er meinte, ob die Meister <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> während der Correctur ihrer Erst-Ausgaben, nicht noch Änderungen und Verbesserungen darin getroffen hätten, die sie nicht mehr in [das] MS. eingetragen hätten.  Die Frage ist sehr verfänglich und kann auch bestimmt in vielen Fällen (Chopin!) &lt;strike&gt;nich&lt;/strike&gt; zustimmend beantwortet werden.  Dennoch scheinen mir die MSS. wichtiger zu [sein] als wie die Erstdrucke, weil diese doch auch viele Fehler &lt;strike&gt;ert&lt;/strike&gt; enthalten.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich werde nun noch einmal, diesmal mit meiner Frau, zu Herrn F. zum Abendessen geladen werden.  Dann werde ich gleich mit ihm besprechen, wann er einmal zu uns in Wien kommen <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> kann.</tei:p><tei:p>Der Plan Prof. Oppel’s,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Reinhard Oppel: [create profile and link].  </tei:note> in Leipzig nach Ihrem System zu unterrichten, ist sehr erfreulich.  Nun mag man gespannt sein, wie die Schüler darauf reagieren.  Denn die Hindemith’sche, Alban- und Schönberg’sche u.s.w. u.s.w., Methode der Composition, wobei man weder auf vertikale, noch auf horizontale Combinationen oder Stellungen Rücksicht zu nehmen braucht, wobei man sozusagen nur seine persönliche Ansicht (ob man eine hat oder nicht) über die Musik zusammencomponiert, ist natürlich wesentlich leichter als wie Ihre.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> Mit der Aenderung Ihrer Honorar-Angelegenheit<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Presumably the fee for the 1927/28 season of study with Schenker.  </tei:note> bin ich ganz einverstanden und werde Ihnen Ende September 1/3 des für 1927/28 verschuldeten Betrages, also 13 Wochen à 4 Stunden zu 50 Schilling, macht 2600..  Schilling überweisen und den Restlichen Teil Anfang Sommer, vorausgesetzt dass Sie damit einverstanden sind.</tei:p><tei:p>Über den Vortrag mit der National-Bibliothek kann ich immer noch kein Definitivum berichte.  Das Unterrichts-Ministerium hat allerhand daran corrigiert[.]   <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> So darf z.B. nicht von einer “Stiftung” die Rede sein, da alle Stiftungen im Lande Wien unter der Supervision des Gemeinderates stehen und wir dies tunlichst vermeiden wollen.  Es soll jetzt, glaube ich, “Widmung” heissen.  Auch will das U. M. dem Vertreter der N. B. Kuratorium nur eine beratende Stimme zugestehen (was mir natürlich, falls Dr. Haas<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="haas_robert">Robert Haas</ref>.  </tei:note> einmal durch jemand anderes ersetzt wird&lt;strike&gt;)&lt;/strike&gt; nur angenehm sein kann.)  Aber die Finanzprokuratur will nun die neue Fassung nicht unterfertigen solange der Hofrat Bietz<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Hofrat Bietz: [identify]</tei:note> sich nicht zu den Aenderungen geäussert hat.  Er <tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> wird sie jedoch genehmigen müssen, da doch das Unterrichts-M. seine vorgesetzte Behörde ist, aber er war noch nicht vom Urlaub zurück und so konnte ich den Vertrag nicht mehr vor meiner Abreise unterschreiben.  Dr. Rochlitzer<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Dr. Rochlitzer: [identify]</tei:note> wird das nun während meiner Abwesenheit tun.  Indessen nehme ich an, das alles perfekt ist und handle entsprechend, da ich keine Zeit zum Warten mehr habe.</tei:p><tei:p>So sende ich Ihnen einliegend die letzte Fassung des “Aufrufes”.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Click on <ref cRef="aufruf_november_1927">Aufruf</ref>.  </tei:note>  Der neu hinzugekommene letzte Satz vom zweiten Abschnitt, Seite 1, ist zurückzuführen auf einer[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Rede[?], welche Hans <tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> Pfitzner auf einer Sonderversammlung anlässlich der 57[.] Tonkünstlerfest in Crefeld gehalten hat.  Welcher Erfolg er damit geerntet hat können Sie u. m. sehen an der Kritik des Dr. Alfred Heuss,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Alfred Heuss: perhaps the music critic and writer on music Alfred Valentin Heuss (1877-1934), who was at the time the chief editor of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für Musik</tei:hi>, whose interests lay in early music and Classical and Romantic music, and who saw contemporary music as "ungerman."  (<tei:hi rend="italic">Wikipedia</tei:hi> (2008)</tei:note> die ich Ihnen ebenfalls mitschicke (Ich brauche sie dann nicht mehr).  Die Fussnote 1 soll an der bezeichnete Stelle auf Seite 3 in den Text eingeschoben werden.  Herr Deutsch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  Click on <ref cRef="deutsch_otto_erich">Otto Erich Deutsch</ref>.</tei:note> hielt sie für wichtig.  Die Fussnote 2, Beethoven betreffend, soll als Fussnote aufgenommen werden wenn Prof. Schiedermair<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  Click on <ref cRef="schiedermair_ludwig">Ludwig Schiedermair</ref>.  </tei:note> damit einverstanden ist.  Ich habe ihm auch eine Abschrift geschickt <tei:hi rend="bold">{9}</tei:hi> und ihm um eine Unterredung gebeten am 9^n^ September.  Sollte ihm den Tag und die von mir &lt;strike&gt;erwo&lt;/strike&gt; vorgeschlagene Stunde passen so wäre mein Reiseplan für September folgender: Ab hier am 4^ten^, einen Tag in Basel, am 6^ten^ nach Frankfurt zum Besuche Herrn Koch’s.  Zwei Tage dort.  Am 9^ten^ morgens nach Bonn, dort Begegnung mit Prof. Sch. und am gleichen Tag weiter nach Rotterdam;  am 13^ten^ nach England.  Dort will ich mich dann bei Prof. Dunn<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15">  Click on <ref cRef="dunn_john_petrie">John Petrie Dunn</ref>.  </tei:note> anmelden.  Sehr gerne hätte ich <tei:hi rend="bold">{10}</tei:hi> das neue Jahrbuch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn16">  Jahrbuch, i.e. <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, vol. II (Munich: Drei Masken Verlag, 1926).  </tei:note> mitgebracht.  Besteht die Aussicht, dass die “Drei Masken” (<tei:hi rend="italic">Eine</tei:hi> Maske genügte wirklich für diesen Verlag) das Buch bis dahin fertig hat?  In Schottland will ich auch noch, auf Empfehlung von Dr. Haas, ein[en] Herrn Prof. Terry<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn17">  Click on <ref cRef="terry_charles_sanfor">Charles Sanford Terry</ref>.  </tei:note> in Aberdeen besuchen.  Der soll sich sehr viel mit Bach-Handschriften befasst haben und auch sicher den Standort manches wichtigen MS. wissen sodass mir ein Besuch dort sehr wichtig vorkomt.  Ich will dann noch einige Zeit in London verbringen und von dort nach Paris.  Ich habe auch dort die Verbindung mit Herrn Cauchie,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn18">  Click on <ref cRef="cauchie_maurice">Maurice Cauchie</ref>.  </tei:note> der sich sehr für das <tei:hi rend="bold">{11}</tei:hi> Unternehmen interessiert und dem ich bitten will, die Übersetzung des Aufrufes ins Franzözische zu besorgen (die Englische ist schon fertig).</tei:p><tei:p>Ich will dann am dortigen Conservatorium das Verzeichniss der MSS. vervollständigen, das ich im Mai angefangen habe.  Auch will ich versuchen, Aufnahmen machen zu lassen.  Doch sehe ich, wenn ich auf Photostat-Aufnamen bestehe, Schwierigkeiten voraus[,] da die beiden dort akkreditierten Photografen mit Platten arbeiten.  Das Conservatorium öffnet am 3^ten^ Oktober; ich will mir für alles 14 Tage Zeit nehmen[,] <tei:hi rend="bold">{12}</tei:hi> werde also am 15^ten^ Oct. von Paris nach Wien fahren und somit hoffe ich am Dienstag den 18^ten^ zum ersten Male in Ihrer[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Stunde zu kommen.  Ein schöner Plan, nicht wahr?  Nur bin ich neugierig ob was dazwischen kommt.</tei:p><tei:p>Hier ist der Aufenthalt sehr schön und die Luft herrlich; besonders wenn man aus der Tiefe Berichten über tropischen Temperaturen erhält.  Ich nehme an, dass es in Galtür ebenso schönes Wetter ist.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit besten Grüssen, ebenfalls an Ihre Frau Gemahlin, wobei sich meine Frau anschliesst, bin ich,</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr sehr ergebener
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] AvHoboken</tei:p><tei:p>PS. Wollen Sie den Aufruf bitte direkt an Dr. Haas, (Mus. Samml. der Nat. Bibl., Augustinerbastei 6) senden</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from van Hoboken to Schenker dated August 28, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>GIGER’S HÔTEL WALDHAUS	
SILS-MARIA, ENGADINE</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">handwritten:</tei:hi>] August 28, 1927</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>I was, then, to tea with Mr. Furtwängler<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> last week.  We spoke for a short while beforehand, but what we had was by no means a more detailed discussion.  We only touched on the matters.  I naturally told him about the Archive.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  Whether it interested him very much, I cannot even say, and even less whether he will one day put the results into practice.  It is difficult <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> to decide this early, when we still have no source-examples.  In the course of the winter, when we will be able to show him with reference to reproductions how the editions deviate, will in my opinion be a far more propitious moment than now to urge him toward performances according to the sources in the Archive.  But it was gratifying to meet him.  He impressed me as relaxed and congenial.  We spoke also about Vrieslander<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> and Weisse,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> and naturally quite a lot about you.</tei:p><tei:p>He asked me one question that seems important: he wondered whether the masters, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> during correction of their first editions, did not at that point make further modifications and improvements which they would not have entered in the manuscript.  The question is very complex and can in many cases (Chopin!) even be answered affirmatively.  Still, the manuscripts seem to me more important than the first editions, because the latter also include many errors.</tei:p><tei:p>I am now invited once more, this time with my wife, to join Mr. F. for dinner.  Then I will immediately speak with him about when he <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> can visit us in Vienna.</tei:p><tei:p>Prof. Oppel’s<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> plan to teach in Leipzig according to your system is most welcome.  Now it will be of interest to see how the students react.  Because the Hindemith method of composition, and that of Alban- and Schoen-berg etc. etc., in which one need take neither vertical nor horizontal combinations or situations into consideration, and one only synthesizes one’s personal opinion (if such exists) about music, is of course substantially easier than yours.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> I am completely amenable concerning the matter of your fee,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> and will remit to you at the end of September one third of the amount owed for 1927/28, thus 13 weeks of four lessons each at 50 schillings making 2,600 schillings, and the remainder at the beginning of summer, assuming that to be satisfactory to you.</tei:p><tei:p>Concerning the presentation at the National Library, I still can report nothing definitive.  The Ministry of Education has made all manner of corrections to it.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> Thus, for example, one may not speak of a “foundation,” since all foundations in the Vienna province stand under supervision of the regional authority, and we want to avoid this if possible.  Now, I think, it is to be called “dedication.”  And the Ministry of Education also wants to give the representive of the National Library’s Curatory only an advisory vote (which, in case Dr. Haas<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> should at some point be replaced by somebody else, can only be welcome to me).  But now the financial officer will not sign the draft until Hofrat Bietz<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> has commented on the changes.  He <tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> will however have to approve them, as the Ministry of Education is after all his superior authority, but the Minister was not yet back from vacation, and so I was no longer able to sign the contract before my departure.  Dr. Rochlitzer<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> will now do that during my absence.  However, I assume that all is in order and proceed accordingly, as I have no more time for waiting.</tei:p><tei:p>And so I send you herewith the final version of the “Appeal.”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/>  The newly added last sentence in the second section, page 1, goes back to a talk that Hans <tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> Pfitzner gave at a special conference on the occasion of the 57th Composers’ Festival in Krefeld.  How much success he realized by it you can see from the critique of Dr. Alfred Heuss,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> which I also enclose (I do not need it returned).  Footnote 1 is to be inserted at the marked place on page 3 in the text.  Mr. Deutsch<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> considered it important.  Footnoote 2, concerning Beethoven, is to be included as a footnote provided that Prof. Schiedermair<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/> is agreeable.  I have also sent him a copy <tei:hi rend="bold">{9}</tei:hi> and requested a meeting on September 9.  Should the date and the time I have suggested be suitable to him, my travel-plan for September then would be as follows: depart here on the 4th, one day in Basel, to Frankfurt on the 6th to visit Mr. Koch. Two days there.  On the morning of the 9th to Bonn, there a meeting with Prof. Schiedermair, and on to Rotterdam on the same day; on the 13th to England.  There I will be in touch with Prof. Dunn.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn15"/>  I would very much have liked <tei:hi rend="bold">{10}</tei:hi> to take along the new <tei:hi rend="italic">Yearbook</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn16"/>  Is there a chance that “Drei Masken” (<tei:hi rend="italic">one</tei:hi> mask would really be enough for this publisher) could have the book ready by then?  In Scotland I will also, on the recommendation of Dr. Haas, visit a Prof. Terry<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn17"/> in Aberdeen.  He is said to have done much work with Bach manuscripts and also certainly to know the location of many important manuscripts, so that a visit there seems to me very important.  Then I will spend some time in London and go from there to Paris.  There I am also in touch  with Mr. Cauchie,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn18"/> who is much interested in the <tei:hi rend="bold">{11}</tei:hi> project, and whom I will ask to made the translation of the Appeal into French (the English is already done).</tei:p><tei:p>Then, at the Conservatory, I will complete the inventory of the manuscripts that I began in May.  I also want to try to have photographs made.  But, if I insist on photostats, I forsee difficulties, as the two photographers accredited there work with plates.  The Conservatory opens on October 3;  I will allow myself two weeks for everything, <tei:hi rend="bold">{12}</tei:hi> will thus leave Paris for Vienna on October 15, and thus I hope to come to your lesson for the first time on Tuesday the 18th.  A nice plan, isn’t it?  I am just wondering what will interfere.</tei:p><tei:p>The stay here is very pleasant and the air is excellent, especially when one gets reports from down below about tropical temperatures.  I assume that the weather is equally nice in Galtür.</tei:p><tei:p>With best greetings, to your wife as well, in which I am joined by my wife, I am</tei:p><tei:p>Yours sincerely,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  A. v. Hoboken</tei:p><tei:p>P.S. Will you please send the Appeal directly to Dr Haas (Music Collection of the National Library, Augustinerbastei 6)?</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>