<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/54, [12] : 1-28-27 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Anthony van Hoboken, published here with kind permission.  
© Transcription John Rothgeb, 2008.
© Translation John Rothgeb, 2008.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish granted by the heirs of Anthony van Hoboken February 3, 2007.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1927-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Anthony van Hoboken; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 01/28/1927 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Hoboken ~ H+JSchenker","Hoboken ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from van Hoboken to Schenker, dated January 28, 1927</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-01-25</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Had to cancel visit to John Petrie Dunn because of illness; reports on library visits in London and Paris, discusses manuscripts and conditions for photography, purchases;  plans no further trips this season.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Hoboken, Anthony van;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Dunn, John Petrie;  Edinburgh;  British Museum;  London;  Kings of England;  Expert, Henry;  Paris;  Chopin;  Ballade;  Vienna;  Bach, J. S.;  Clavierübung;  Palestrina;  Purcell;  München;  Munich;  wife</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Savoy Hotel, London, WC2</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from van Hoboken to Schenker, dated January 28, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead, diagonally TL:</tei:hi>]
Gerrard 4343</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">TR:</tei:hi>]
Savoy Hotel,
London
W.C.2.</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">holograph:</tei:hi>]
28.I.27</tei:p><tei:p>Lieber Herr Professor,</tei:p><tei:p>Eines der Ziele meiner Reise habe ich nicht erreichen können: der Besuch bei Prof. Dunn<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Click on <ref cRef="dunn_john_petrie">John Petrie Dunn</ref>.  </tei:note> in Edinburgh musste ausfallen weil ich gestern mit Fieber zu Bett lag und daher am Abend nicht reisen konnte.  Dies war wohl sehr schade.  Ich hatte ihm geschrieben, und von ihm einen Brief zurück erhalten woraus ich sehen konnte[,] dass er nach wie vor einen grossen Anteil an Ihre Werken nimmt[.]  <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Ich werde ihn nun wohl diesen Sommer besuchen da ich dann wieder nach England will.  Ich kann hier Einführungen bekommen in verschiedene Privatsammlungen und möchte das nicht versäumen.</tei:p><tei:p>Im British Museum war ich.  Was es dort an wichtige MS. gibt ist aus dem Katalog zu ersehen.  Photografiert kann alles werden.  Über den Preis hierfür habe ich noch nicht unterhandelt.</tei:p><tei:p>Die Händel MS. sind Privatbesitz des Königs von England der sich alle Rechte, einschliesslich das zur Vervielfältigung, vorbehält.  Doch meinte <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> man, ich würde auch dort wohl die erforderliche Erlaubniss bekommen.  Ich kann sie aber nicht alle auf einmal aufnehmen!  Ausserdem erscheint von dieser Sammlung demnächst auch ein Katalog.</tei:p><tei:p>Am Dienstag treffe ich Herrn Expert<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="expert_henry">Henry Expert</ref>.  </tei:note> in Paris[.]  Ich hoffe dass es ^mir^ möglich sein wird wenigstens von der Chopin ballade<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Chopin, Ballade No. 2, in F major/A minor, Op. 38. See OJ 11/54, [6].</tei:note> ein paar Abzüge mitzubringen.  Das System von Photografien dort ist dasselbe wie in Wien und auch so billig[.]  In London bin ich dessen noch nicht so sicher.</tei:p><tei:p>Im übrigen habe ich hier manches gekauft.  So z. B. den vierten Theil der Clavierübung J. S. Bach’s in der Erstausgabe.  Ein ditto Messe von Palestrina und zwei Purcells.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Das Wetter ist zum Reisen nicht sehr verlockend und glaube ich, dass ich in dieser Jahreszeit möglichst keine Reise mehr unternehmen werde.  Besonders nicht in Städten wo die Grippe herrscht.  Es ist heute sehr stürmisch was die Ueberfahrt nach Frankreich morgen nicht sehr verlockend macht.  
	
Ueber die Münchener Besprechungen brauche ich Ihnen wohl nichts mehr zu schreiben;  sie werden alles wohl schon erfahren haben.</tei:p><tei:p>Indem ich Sie bitte, mir[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Ihrer Gattin bestens zu empfehlen bin ich</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr sehr ergebener
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] AvHoboken</tei:p><tei:p>Am Sonntag dem 6^ten^ Februar hoffe ich wieder
in Wien zu sein.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from van Hoboken to Schenker, dated January 28, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead, diagonally TL:</tei:hi>]
Gerrard 4343</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">TR:</tei:hi>]
Savoy Hotel,
London
W.C.2.</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">holograph:</tei:hi>]
January 28, 1927</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor,</tei:p><tei:p>One of the purposes of my journey could not be achieved: the visit to Prof. Dunn<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> in Edinburgh had to be canceled, because yesterday I was in bed with a fever and therefore could not travel in the evening.  This was certainly a great pity.  I had written him, and had received a letter of reply from him from which I could see that he still is greatly interested in your works.  I will probably visit him this summer as I want to return to England then.  Here I can obtain introductions to private collections, and I don’t want to fail to do that.</tei:p><tei:p>I have been to the British Museum.  Which important manuscripts are held there can be seen from the catalog.  Everything can be photographed.  I have not yet discussed the price for this.</tei:p><tei:p>The Handel manuscripts are private property of the King of England, who reserves all rights, including that of duplication.  But I am <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> told that I would probably also receive the necessary permission there.  I cannot, however, photograph all of them at one time!  Besides, a catalog of this collection is to appear soon.</tei:p><tei:p>On Tuesday I meet with Mr. Expert<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> in Paris.  I hope that it will be possible at least to bring home a few images of the Chopin Ballade.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  The system of photography there is the same as in Vienna and also just as cheap.  In London I am not so sure of that.</tei:p><tei:p>For the rest, I have purchased several things here.  For example, Part IV of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Clavierübung</tei:hi> of J.S. Bach in the first edition.  Likewise for a mass by Palestrina and two Purcell pieces.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> The weather is not very inviting for travel, and I believe that in this season if possible I will make no further trip.  Especially not to cities where the flu is prevalent.  Today it is very stormy, which does not make the crossing to France tomorrow very inviting.</tei:p><tei:p>I need not write you anything further about the Munich discussions; you will no doubt already have heard everything.</tei:p><tei:p>With a request that you remember me to your wife, I am,</tei:p><tei:p>Yours very truly,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] A. v. Hoboken</tei:p><tei:p>I hope to be back in Vienna on Sunday, February 6.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>