<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/54, [4] : 9-28-25 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Anthony van Hoboken, published here with kind permission.  
© Transcription John Rothgeb, 2008.
© Translation John Rothgeb, 2008.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish granted by the heirs of Anthony van Hoboken February 3, 2007.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1925-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Anthony van Hoboken; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 09/28/1925 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Hoboken ~ H+JSchenker","Hoboken ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Hoboken to Schenker, dated September 28, 1925</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-01-07</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>vH reports on his recent travels, describing the house that he has rented for a year in Vienna; he is to register in Vienna for nine months for study purposes;  vH thanks S for the plan of work he has sent, and will start lessons with S on October 13, 1925;  encloses $60 in advance monthly payment.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Hoboken, Anthony van;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Vienna;  Sankt Pölten;  Goldschmid, Hans;  Hohenlohe, Prince;  Vienna;  Cobenzl;  Sophienhöhe;  Gräf &amp; Stift;  Paris;  Galtür;  München;  Munich;  Kohn, Bernhard;  payment;  honorarium;  fee; wife</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Munich, Walhallastraße 1</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from van Hoboken to Schenker, dated September 28, 1925</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>]
ANTON van HOBOKEN
MÜNCHEN, WALHALLASTRASSE 1</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">holograph:</tei:hi>]
28. IX. ’25</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Dr.!</tei:p><tei:p>Vor einigen Wochen, vom 31 August bis zum 5^ten^ September war ich mit meiner Frau in Wien, und möchte ich Ihnen doch einen kleinen Bericht über diesem Besuch erstatten.</tei:p><tei:p>Wir sind nicht im Auto hingefahren sondern mit dem Schnellzug, der um 10 Abends eintreffen sollte, jedoch, infolge eines Machinendefektes kurz vor St. Pölten,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Sankt Pölten:  town 50 miles east of Vienna.  </tei:note> erst kurz vor 12 eintraf.  Am nächsten Tage begaben wir uns sofort zu dem Architekten Hans Goldschmid,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Hans Goldschmid:  [identify].  </tei:note> der die Wohnung vermittelt und mit ihm dann sogleich dorthin.  Wir waren einfach berauscht von der Wohnung und haben ihn sogleich auf die Dauer von einem Jahr gemietet.  Sie liegt am Heiligenkreuzerhof, direkt in der Nähe vom Fleischmarkt.  Man betritt sie durch ein kleines, etwas verwittertes Barock-steintor welches in einen kleinen von Bäumen und Wein bewachsenen Vorplatz führt.  Dann führt eine grosse und breite Stiege zum ersten Stock und zu der hölzernen, eingelegten Eingangstür der Wohnung.  Diese, sowie <tei:hi rend="italic">alle</tei:hi> übrigen Türen, sind alt, aus der Barockzeit, und zum Teil noch mit den alten <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Türschlössen versehen.  Überhaupt ist die ganze Wohnung und alle Möbel darin Barock.  Die Etage heisst „das Prälatenstöchl” und soll früher die Abt-Wohnung eines Stiftes gewesen sein.  Jetzt wird sie bewohnt vom Prinzen Hohenlohe<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Prince Hohenlohe: [identify] </tei:note> von dem wir wiederum möbliert gemietet haben.</tei:p><tei:p>Die Wohnung ist riesig gross.  Ausser dem unermesslichen Esssaal gibt es ein[en] noch grösseren Saal wo ich mich mit meinen Instrumenten häuslich niederlassen werde.  Ausserdem gibt es dann noch 4 Zimmer, ein Boudoir und ein Vorzimmer während Küche und Dienerschaftzimmer sich darunter im Parterre befinden.  &lt;strike&gt;Sie lieg&lt;/strike&gt; Die ganze Wohnung liegt sehr ruhig, da man den Heiligenkreuzerhof mit Fahrzeugen nur von einer Seite einfahren kann und es infolgedessen keinen Durchgangsverkehr dort gibt.</tei:p><tei:p>Wir freuen uns sehr darauf, die Wohnung zu bewohnen und hoffen, dass sich keine unüberwindliche[n] Beschwerden dabei einstellen werden, da man doch bei einer Besichtigung nicht alles übersehen kann, obwohl wir 3 bis 4 Mal dort waren.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Die uns übrigbleibende Zeit haben wir in Wien verbraucht wie das so für Fremden üblich ist.  Wir sind spazierengegangen an den Läden vorbei und waren Abends meistens zusammen mit einer Freundin meiner Frau.  Wir waren im Museum, im Theater, u.s.w.  Auch haben wir bei Gräf und Stift<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Gräf and Stift:  automobile manufacturer, founded 1904, Franz, Heinrich, and Carl Gräf, and Wilhelm Stift;  the Gräf brothers had built the first front-wheel drive car in 1898 and patented it in 1900.  Its main factory was located in Liesing, a district of Vienna.  The company also built buses and trucks.  (<tei:hi rend="italic">Wikipedia</tei:hi>)</tei:note> ein kleines Auto für meine Frau bestellt und dazu die nötigen Vorbesprechungen sowie auch eine Probefahrt auf dem Cobenzl<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Cobenzl:  perhaps Schloss Cobenzl, northwest of Vienna, between Grinzing and Klosterneuburg.  </tei:note> und der Sophienhöhe<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Sophienhöhe:  [identify]</tei:note> (so hiess es, glaub’ ich) gehabt.  Das war sehr schön.  Wir lernen jetzt beide Chauffieren und hoffen als gelernte Fahrer unser Eintritt in Wien zu machen.  (Vielleicht würde es sich empfehlen, dass die Wiener ihre Lebensversicherungen etwas erhöhen!  Doch so schlimm wird’s wohl nicht werden).</tei:p><tei:p>Am 5^ten^ sind wir nach Paris gefahren.</tei:p><tei:p>Doch habe ich noch etwas vergessen zu erwähnen[,] nähmlich meinen Besuch bei Dr. Siebenschein<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Dr. Siebenschein: [identify] </tei:note> bezw. sein Vertreter, Hofrat Stein.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Hofrat Stein:  [identify]  </tei:note>  Das Resultat dieser Besprechung ist, dass ich mich in Wien wie für einen vorübergehenden Aufenthalt von 9 Monaten anmelde zu Studienzwecke und mir wieter Entschliessungen bis später vorbehalte.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Paris haben wir wieder genossen wie immer.  Nur war noch gar kein Saison, und auf musikalischem wie auf theatralischem Gebiet noch nichts von Bedeutung las.</tei:p><tei:p>Seit dem 23ten sind wir nun wieder hier, und ich hatte diesen Brief schon soweit zusammengestellt als letzten Samstag Ihr Schreiben vom 25^ten^|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  No letter of this date from Schenker to Hoboken is known to survive.  </tei:note> eintraf.  Ich danke Ihnen für die Einteilung, welche ja für mich ganz besonders bequem ist.  Nur kann [ich] nicht schon am 3. X. in Wien sein.  Ich sprach diese Befürchtung bereits in Galltür[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Galtür: Tyrolean ski resort in the Paznaun Valley, 60 miles SW of Innsbruck, at which S regularly spent the summer months.  </tei:note> aus und sie hat sich bewahrheitet.  Ich habe hier noch allerhand zu erledigen.  So die Verpachtung meines Gartens, die noch nicht abgeschlossen ist und wobei die Hauptschwierigkeit darin besteht, dass mein verflossenen Gärtner die Wohnung nicht räumen will.  Denn die Veräusserung eines Geschäftes dessen Inhaber ich bin, u.s.w.  Nun kann ich natürlich wohl einfach abreisen, doch müsste ich dann alle diese[n] Sachen von Wien aus schriftlich erledigen oder doch am Ende noch einmal nach München zurück fahren.  Es scheint mir daher vorteilhafter, alles jetzt zu erledigen wenn auch mein Eintreffen in Wien sich dadurch verspätet.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> Immerhin hoffe ich um den 10^ten^ herum fertig zu sein und am Dienstag den 13^ten^ nachmittags halb 3 zu Ihnen zu kommen.  Allerdings werde ich dann noch kein Klavier haben.  Kohn<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Klavierhaus Bernhard Kohn, Vienna I, Himmerpfortgasse 20, piano dealer, supplier for Steinway, Blüthner, and Schweighofer,  founded 1856.  Kohn supplied Schenker with his Blüthner piano, and is known to have supplied pianos to Mahler, the Wittgenstein family, and others.  </tei:note> konnte mir auf einen Steinway keine Hoffnung geben und so habe ich mich entschlossen, einen von hier mitzunehmen und bei der Gelegenheit auch mein Bach-Klavier nach Wien zu schaffen.  Wie &lt;strike&gt;lange&lt;/strike&gt; ^viel Zeit^ die Reise dieser Instrumente in Anspruch nehmen wird ist mir noch nicht bekannt.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich erlaube mir, Ihnen einschliessend $60.- zu[zu]kommen als erste Zahlung, für den Monat October praenumerando, wie ausgemacht.  Ich leiste diese Zahlung in Amerikanischen Noten ohne zu wissen, ob Ihnen diese Form angenehm ist.  Sollten Sie eine andere Zahlungsform vorziehen, so bitte ich Sie, mir dieses gelegentlich mitzuteilen.  Ich kann mich nach jedem Ihrer Wünsche richten.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich bitte Sie, mich Ihrer Frau Gemahlin empfehlen zu wollen wobei sich meine Gattin gerne anschliesst.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit freundlichem Gruss bin ich
Ihr sehr ergebener
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] AvHoboken</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from van Hoboken to Schenker, dated September 28, 1925</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>]
ANTON van HOBOKEN
MUNICH, WALHALLASTRASSE 1</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">holograph:</tei:hi>]
September 28, 1925</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>A few weeks ago, from August 31 to September 5, I was in Vienna with my wife, and would just like to give you a brief report on this visit.</tei:p><tei:p>We traveled not by car but on the express train, which was supposed to arrive at 10 p.m., but because of a mechanical failure before St. Pölten,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> we did not arrive until shortly before 12.  The next day we immediately proceeded to the architect Hans Goldschmid,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> who served as agent for our housing, and from there, with him, directly to the latter.   We were simply enchanted with the place and immediately rented it for a term of one year.  It lies on the Heiligenkreutzerhof, quite close to Fleischmarkt.  You enter it through a small, somewhat weathered Baroque stone gate, which leads into a small forecourt grown up in trees and vines.  Then a large and broad stairway to the first level and to the wooden, inlaid entry-door to the residence.  This, like <tei:hi rend="italic">all</tei:hi> other doors, is old, from the Baroque period, and in part still fitted with the old <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> hardware.  The whole dwelling in general, and all the furniture in it, is Baroque.  This level is called “the prelate's floor,” and is said to have been previously the quarters of the Abbé of a cloister.  Now it is occupied by Prince Hohenlohe,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> from whom we in turn have rented it furnished.</tei:p><tei:p>The place is enormous.  Aside from the huge dining room there is a still larger room where I shall settle in with my instruments.  Then there are four more rooms, a boudoir and an anteroom, while the kitchen and servant quarters are below on the ground floor.  The whole place is very quiet, as one can enter the Heiligenkreuzerhof with vehicles only from one side, and consequently there is no through traffic.</tei:p><tei:p>We are very happy to move into the place and hope that no insuperable difficulties will arise, since not everything can be checked at a viewing, although we were there three or four times.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> The time we had left over in Vienna we occupied in the way usual for foreigners.  We went walking past the shops, and evenings were mostly in the company of a girlfriend of my wife.  We went to the museum, the theater, etc.  And we ordered from Gräf and Stift<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> a small auto for my wife, and had the necessary preliminary conference as well as a demonstration drive to the Cobenzl<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> and the Sophienhöhe<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> (so it is called, I believe).  That was very beautiful.  We are now both learning to drive, and hope to make our entrance into Vienna as skilled motorists.  (Perhaps it would be advisable for the Viennese to increase their life insurance somewhat!  But it probably won’t be that bad.)</tei:p><tei:p>On the fifth we traveled to Paris.</tei:p><tei:p>But I forgot to mention something, namely my visit to Dr. Siebenschein,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> or his agent, Hofrat Stein.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/>  The result of that conversation is that I’m to register in Vienna as though for a temporary stay of nine months for study purposes, and leave the way open to make further plans later.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> We enjoyed Paris as always.  Except that it was completely off season, and on both musical and theatrical fronts nothing of importance was happening.</tei:p><tei:p>We have been back here since the 23d, and I had this letter finished to this point when your mail of the 25th<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> arrived.  I thank you for the plan of work, which is indeed very convenient for me.  Except that I cannot be in Vienna as early as October 3.  I already expressed this misgiving in Galtür,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> and it has proven true.  I have all manner of things to take care of here.  Such as the lease of my garden, which is not yet definite, and in which the main difficulty consists in the fact that my previous gardner refuses to vacate the residence.  Then the disposal of a business of which I am the proprieter, etc.  Naturally, I could simply leave; but then I would have to attend to these matters in writing from Vienna, or, in the end, return once more to Munich.  It thus appears to me more advantageous to see to everything now, even though my arrival in Vienna is thereby delayed.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> Anyway, I hope to be ready on the 10th and to come to you on the afternoon of Tuesday the 13th at 2:30.  Then, to be sure, I will still have no piano.  Kohn<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> could not hold out hope for a Steinway, and thus I have decided to take one with me from here, and use the occasion to send my Bach keyboard to Vienna as well.  How much time the journey of these instruments will take is as yet unknown to me.</tei:p><tei:p>I take the liberty of enclosing $60 for you, as first payment in advance for the month of October, according to agreement.  I make this payment in American notes without knowing whether this form is acceptable to you.  Should you prefer a different form of payment, please notify me.  I can proceed in any way you wish.</tei:p><tei:p>Please be so kind as to convey my best wishes to your wife, a request in which my wife joins me.</tei:p><tei:p>With cordial greetings, I remain
Yours sincerely,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] A. v. Hoboken</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>