<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:DLA 69.930/1 : 7-8-17 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain; reproduced here with kind permission of the heirs of August Halm.
© Transcription Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Translation Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>August Halm (1917-19??)—Deutsches Literaturarchiv(19??-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain, published with the kind permission of the Deutsches Literaturarchiv; Image: Deutsches Literaturarchiv; Transcription Ian Bent and Lee Rothfarb, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary Lee Rothfarb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 07/08/1917 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Halm ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Halm, dated July 8, 1917</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-06-19</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Aks J's letter;  discusses relative merits of editions of Beethoven variations; looks forward to seeing J's review of Das Meisterwerk in der Musik vol. III;  S is putting the finishing touches to Kontrapunkt vol. 2.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Halm, August;  Vienna;  Tyrol;  Beethoven;  variations;  Peters;  Breitkopf &amp; Härtel;  Gesammtausgabe;  collected edition;  Diabelli Variations;  Eroica Variations;  fingerings;  Der Kunstwart;  Liebscher, Artur;  Bülow, Hans von;  Votta;  Kontrapunkt II</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Seefeld i. Tirol, Pension Wetterstein</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Halm, July 8, 1917</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Seefeld</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">i.</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Tirol</tei:hi>, Pension Wetterstein
8. Juli 1917</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Professor!</tei:p><tei:p>Ihre frdl. Zeilen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  i.e. OJ 11/35, 5, July 2, 1917.</tei:note> erreichten mich hier erst auf  Umwegen über Wien.  Desto kürzere Zeit dürfte aber meine Antwort beanspruchen, die ich postwendend abgehen lasse, u. ^die ja auch^ schon von Haus aus näheren Weg zu Ihnen hat.</tei:p><tei:p>Das II[.] <tei:hi rend="italic">Var.</tei:hi> Heft <tei:hi rend="italic">B.</tei:hi> bei <tei:hi rend="italic">Peters</tei:hi> ist,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  [note on edition] .  This is in response to Halm’s remark: „I would like to incorporate the easier Beethoven variations into my piano method, the ones that appear in volume 2 of the Peters edition—a selection naturally.” (OJ 11/35, 5, July 2, 1917).</tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">soweit</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">ich</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">mich</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">erinnere</tei:hi>, nicht gerade das schlechteste Stück Ausgabe u. mag dem vermutlichen <tei:hi rend="italic">Original</tei:hi> viel näher als die übrigen Stücke stehen.  Die <tei:hi rend="italic">Var.</tei:hi> dort gehören zu den wenigen [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte?</tei:hi> weniger „berühmten“ u. da ersparen sich die „berühmten“ Herausgeber ihre Mühe, was den Stücken nur umsobesser bekommt.  Bedenklich ist schon das I[.] <tei:hi rend="italic">Var.</tei:hi> Heft mitgenommen, wo die <tei:hi rend="italic">Diab</tei:hi>. u. <tei:hi rend="italic">Eroica-Var.</tei:hi> Platz gefunden haben.  Unter allen Umständen ziehe ich persönlich die <tei:hi rend="italic">Gesammt</tei:hi>-<tei:hi rend="italic">Ausg</tei:hi>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  i.e. the collected edition of Beethoven’s works by Breitkopf &amp; Härtel (Leipzig, 1862–65). The piano variations occuped vol. 17, of which S owned a copy (OC Scores/32).</tei:note> vor, die, wenn sie auch vor den tiefsten Angelegenheiten der Komposition u. Schreibart versagt, so doch sonst die allerwenigsten Zutaten u. Änderungen macht.  Zumal in jener <tei:hi rend="italic">Var.</tei:hi> möchte sich wohl zum größten Teile das <tei:hi rend="italic">Original</tei:hi> mit dem Nachbild der G. A. decken, obgleich ich nichts weniger als dazu aufgelegt bin, ihre wunderbare Kunst zu unterschätzen, die doch noch immer nicht übertroffen wurde.  Es würde mich interessieren, zu erfahren, auf welcher <tei:hi rend="italic">Var</tei:hi> Ihre Wahl gefallen ist.  Würden Sie denn dazu Finger- <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> sätze machen?  Da fällt mir ein, welch lohnende, schöne Aufgabe es wäre, z. B. sämmtliche Stellen aus sämmtlichen Werken <tei:hi rend="italic">B</tei:hi>’s in einem Heft zu vereinigen, die seine <tei:hi rend="italic">eigenen</tei:hi> Fingersätze tragen u. daraus <tei:hi rend="italic">Schlüsse</tei:hi> zu ziehen, die der Klaviertechnik unakademische Wege zu weisen vermöchten.</tei:p><tei:p>Ihre frdl. Besprechung meiner <tei:hi rend="italic">B.</tei:hi>’Ausgaben<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  August Halm, „Heinrich Schenker,“ <tei:hi rend="italic">Freie Schulgemeinde</tei:hi>, October 1, 1917; clipping preserved in S’s scrapbook, OC 2/p.53.</tei:note> erwarte ich mit größtem Interesse.  Kürzlich bekam ich eine zu Gesicht im „Kunstwart,“ gez. von A Liebscher,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Artur Liebscher, „Musikalische Urtextausgaben,“ <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Kunstwart</tei:hi>, April 1917 [re <tei:hi rend="italic">Die letzten fünf Sonaten Beethovens</tei:hi>]; clipping preserved in S’s scrapbook, OC 2/p.52.</tei:note> der mir bei so viel freundlicher Anerkennung nichts mehr u. nichts weniger unterschob, als daß ich <tei:hi rend="italic">Bülow</tei:hi> inferioren Instinkt vorwarf.  Wie oft habe ich doch aber betont, daß ich es nur <tei:hi rend="italic">an</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven</tei:hi></tei:hi> selbst geniessbar verstehe u. nicht an den Musikalischen sonst, u. welch gewaltigen Unterschied bedeutet das!  Ja, aber darum, weil von einem <tei:hi rend="italic">Bülow</tei:hi> zu <tei:hi rend="italic">Beeth.</tei:hi>  eine so übergroße Distanz ist, fordere ich, daß all die Übrigen nicht gar zu sehr hinter <tei:hi rend="italic">Bülow</tei:hi> zurückbleiben mögen.</tei:p><tei:p>An <tei:hi rend="italic">Cotta</tei:hi> [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte</tei:hi> UE] schreibe ich gleichzeitig,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  There is indeed a letter from S to UE, WSLB 288, of the same date, which reports that Halm is about to publish a review of <tei:hi rend="italic">Meisterwerk</tei:hi> vol. III, and asking for a copy to be sent to him when UE receives it, whereas there is no letter from S to Cotta from this period.</tei:note> daß er Ihnen unverzüglich ein Rezensionsex. zukommen lassen möge.  Unbegreiflich ist es mir ja dahin, daß er Ihnen nicht schon selbst eines schickte.  Der zweite <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrap.</tei:hi> Band wird bei <tei:hi rend="italic">Cotta</tei:hi> erscheinen, nur bin ich noch mit der Feile beschäftigt.  Schade, daß der Druck so lange dauert, Bd. I u. II^1^ haben ja 2 Jahre in Anspruch genommen.  Doch ich habe Geduld.  Sie bestens grüßend</tei:p><tei:p>Zeichne Ir sehr ergebener
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ]  <tei:hi rend="italic">H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Halm, July 8, 1917</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Seefeld in Tyrol</tei:hi>, Guesthouse Wetterstein
July 8, 1917</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor!</tei:p><tei:p>Your cordial missive<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> reached me here only circuitously by way of Vienna.  However, my reply, which I am sending right away, and ^which, in addition,^ has by nature a shorter path, may require all the shorter a time.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">So far as I recall</tei:hi>, volume II of the  Beethoven variations in the Peters edition<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> is not the worst edition and may be much closer to the supposed original than the others.  The variations therein are among the lesser “famous” ones, and in those cases the “famous” editors save themselves the trouble, which is all the better for the pieces.  Even the first volume of variations, where the <tei:hi rend="italic">Diabelli</tei:hi> and <tei:hi rend="italic">Eroica Variations</tei:hi> have been placed, is questionable.  Under all circumstances, I personally prefer the <tei:hi rend="italic">Collected Edition</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> which makes fewest additions and modifications, even if it fails with respect to the deepest issues of composition and notation.  Especially in that variation, the original is likely in large part to match the rendering in the Collected Edition, although I am nothing less than well disposed to underestimate its wonderful art, which surely has never been exceeded.  I would be interested to find out which variation you chose.  Would you provide <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> fingerings for it?  It occurs to me what a rewarding, pleasurable task it would be, for example, to bring together into one volume all passages from all of Beethoven’s works that have his <tei:hi rend="italic">own</tei:hi> fingerings, and to draw <tei:hi rend="italic">conclusions</tei:hi>, which could indicate unacademic paths for piano technique.</tei:p><tei:p>I look forward with greatest interest to your cordial review of my Beethoven editions.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  Recently I saw a review in <tei:hi rend="italic">Kunstwart</tei:hi>, signed by A. Liebscher,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> who with such genial acknowledgment attributed to me nothing other and nothing less than accusing Bülow of inferior instinct.  However, how often have I stressed that I understand it as enjoyable only with respect <tei:hi rend="italic">to Beethoven</tei:hi> himself and not to musical aspects generally, and what a tremendous difference that represents!  Yes, and because there is such a huge distance from a Bülow to Beethoven, I demand that all of the others may not fall too much behind Bülow.</tei:p><tei:p>I am writing to Cotta [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte</tei:hi> UE] at the same time<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> that he should send you a review copy without delay.  It is simply incomprehensible to me in that regard that he has not already sent you one on his own.  The second volume of <tei:hi rend="italic">Counterpoint</tei:hi> will appear with Cotta, but I am still putting the finishing touches [to it].  Too bad that the printing takes so long.  Volumes I and II^1^ have taken two years.  But I have patience.  Greeting you warmly,</tei:p><tei:p>Respectfully,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H. Schenker</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>