<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:DLA 69.930/10 : 9-25-22 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription Ian Bent &amp; Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Translation Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>August Halm (1922-1929)—Deutsches Literaturarchiv(19??-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain, published with the kind permission of the Deutsches Literaturarchiv; Image: Deutsches Literaturarchiv; Transcription Ian Bent &amp; Lee Rothfarb, 2006; Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary Lee Rothfarb, 2006.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 09/25/1922 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Halm ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Halm, dated September 25, 1922</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-10-27</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Acks OJ 11/35, 20 and composition; expects to be able to comment on H's Klavierübung in Tonwille 4; reports Leipzig University's decision not to appoint him; speculates on the impact of Kontrapunkt II and Der freie Satz;  public difficulty in accepting Urgesetze.  — Aristide Briand: The importance of being well-read on a topic before commenting in public: Schoenberg and Reger; newspapers.  — Maximilian Harden, although faithful to S, Harden had not mastered the topics on which he wrote.  — National Govenment: S's publishing plans, including The Future of Humanity: man's anthropomorphic thinking is a delusion, he needs to adapt to nature, to return to a primitive state, to abandon "development" and "progress" and return to primordial laws;  inferior man wants to "govern" (bowel wants to become brain); S deplores "artifice" (French) as against nature (German). — Things French: praises German superiority over French in its joy of work.  — Higher Plane: the German should not abase himself before the Frenchman.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Halm, August;  Tonwille, Der;  Straube, Karl;  Leipzig University;  Berlin Hochschule für Musik;  Scheidemann;  Kontrapunkt II;  Counterpoint II;  Der freie Satz;  Free Composition;  Briand, Aristide;  Vienna;  Berlin;  Frankfurt;  Reger, Max;  Schoenberg;  Harden, Maximilian;  Zukunft, Die;  Schoenberg, Arnold;  Schenker, Julia;  Schenker, Johann;  Schenker, Moritz;  Bahr, Hermann;  Masaryk, Tomás Garrigue;   Harding, Warren G.;  Ebert, Friedrich;  Wilson, Woodrow;  Volk;  Regierung;  government;  Niedergang der musikalischen Kunst, Über die;  Theorie der Form;   Rolland, Roman;  Bernstein, Eduard;  Barbusse, Henri;  Kautsky, Karl;  Wells, H. G.;  Bonsels;  France, Anatole;  Loti, Pierre;  Claudel, Paul;  Barrès, Maurice;  Rabelais;  Descartes;  Molière;  Racine;  Voltaire;  Hugo, Victor; Pasteur;  Bergson, Henri;  Kant;  Hegel;  Goethe;  Schiller;  Mozart;  Beethoven;  Nietzsche;   Einstein, Albert; Kraus, Karl;  Mahler, Gustav;  Copernicus;  Schuchard;  Schopenhauer;  Andrade, Francesco d';  Cailleux, André;  Curtius, O. E.;  Hofmüller;  Book of Genesis;  Nitti, Francesco Saverio;; Knotenpunkt;  nodal point;  Quartraum;  space of 4th;  </dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Halm, dated September 25, 1922]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">This edition conflates two texts,</tei:hi> DLA 69.930/10 <tei:hi rend="italic">and </tei:hi>OC 1/B 29–31<tei:hi rend="italic">, noting only the significant variants between the two.</tei:hi>  OC 1/B 29–31 <tei:hi rend="italic">is a fair copy of a presumed prior draft;  however, Schenker copied one large section of the draft out of order, and had to make a second fair copy in the correct order.</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>Lieber u. verehrter Herr Professor Halm!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Federhofer quotes several passages from this letter: <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern ...</tei:hi>, pp. 11, 146–47.  The editors wish to thank the following for help in elucidating parts of this highly problematic document:  Cornelia Becher, William Drabkin,  Hellmut Federhofer, Wolf Kittler, and Harmut Schick.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Für Ihren l. Brief besten Dank.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  OJ 11/35, 20, July 24, 1922, continued on August 19, 1922.</tei:note>  Inzwischen ist auch Ihr <tei:hi rend="italic">opus</tei:hi> angelangt, für das ich nicht minder herzlich danke.  Im 4. Heft des „Tonwille“ dürfte ich die erste Gelegenheit haben, Ihrer „Klavierübung“ zu gedenken (das 3. Heft ist schon im Druck)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Tonwille</tei:hi>, Heft 4, p. 25, fn = Eng. trans., vol. I, p. 164, n.18 (“Miscellanea”): “In his <tei:hi rend="italic">Klavierübung—Ein Lehrgang des Klavierspiels nach neuen Grundsätzen, zugleich erste Einführung in die Musik</tei:hi> [Keyboard practice: a course of instruction in keyboard playing according to new principles, together with an introduction to music] (Stuttgart: G. A. Zumsteeg, 1918–19), August Halm makes a fine attempt at enabling beginners to think musically, feel musically, and be spontaneous.  Let us hope that serious educators of the young will make every effort to use his book!”</tei:note> u. bis nur die Schwierigkeiten des Unterrichtsanfanges vorüber sind, will ich Ihr <tei:hi rend="italic">opus</tei:hi> durchstudieren u. Rechenschaft legen.  Und gleich beantworte ich Ihre letzte Frage nach dem Plan meiner Auswanderung.  Durch Prof. <tei:hi rend="italic">Straube</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  OC 1B 29–31: “Prof. <tei:hi rend="italic">Straube</tei:hi> (<tei:hi rend="italic">Leipzig</tei:hi>)”:  Click on <ref cRef="straube_karl">Karl Straube</ref>. </tei:note> brachte ich in Erfahrung, daß im Vorjahr die Universität <tei:hi rend="italic">Leipzig</tei:hi> an meine Berufung dachte, schließlich aber davon Abstand genommen in Erwägung, daß mir ein rein künstlerischer Wirkungskreis besser zusagt, als der mehr historisch gerichtete innerhalb der Universität.  Wie nett u. richtig eingefunden!  Ob es <tei:hi rend="italic">Straube</tei:hi>’s Bemühung gelingen wird, mich nach Leipzig oder <tei:hi rend="italic">Berlin</tei:hi> zu bringen, weiß ich nicht.  Einer Berufung auf die Hochschule <tei:hi rend="italic">Berlin</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Berlin Hochschule für Musik: [explain].</tei:note> steht, glaube ich,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  “, glaube ich,”: not in OC 1B 29–31.</tei:note> meine ausgesprochene antidemokratische Gesinnung entgegen.  „Handschellen für reaktionäre Burschen!“ dürfte das Musiker-Collegium mit <tei:hi rend="italic">Scheidemann</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Scheidemann  [create biogfile and line] Perhaps Philip Scheidemann (1865–1939), German social democratic leader, briefly first Chancellor of the new German Republic (1919).  </tei:note> sagen.</tei:p><tei:p>Ihre Anerkennung meines Gesamtwirkens im Ganzen u. Einzelnen schätze ich hoch.  Doch gestehe ich selbst, daß das Neue in II^2^ erst <tei:hi rend="italic">durch</tei:hi> II^3^<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  II^2^ = <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt</tei:hi> II (1922); II^3^ presumably = <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi>.  See Hedi Siegel, „When ‘Freier Satz’ was part of <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt</tei:hi>: a preliminary report,“ <tei:hi rend="italic">Schenker Studies 2</tei:hi> (Cambridge: CUP, 1999), 12–25.</tei:note> (den nächsten Band) sich klar auswirken kann, so die Begriffe Knotenpunkt<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  The term Knotenpunkt (nodal point) occurs in <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt</tei:hi> II (Vienna: Universal, 1922), 59 (<tei:hi rend="italic">Counterpoint</tei:hi>, vol. 2, trans. John Rothgeb and Jürgen Thym, ed. John Rothgeb [New York: Schirmer, 1987], 58).</tei:note>, Quartraum, und –Zug, 7<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  OC 1B 29–31:  “Sept”.</tei:note> als Dchg. u. als Vorhalt, Durchgangsgesetze überhaupt u.s.w.  Ich muß mich also in Geduld fassen u. alles Verkennen oder Misverstehen hin- <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> nehmen, wie es eben kommen mag.  Denn nichts fällt dem Menschen so schwer, als der Anblick von Urgesetzen.  Wer nicht eigene Kraft hat, zu ihnen vorzudringen, vermag auch nicht zu folgen, wenn ein Anderer ihm die Erscheinung in das Urgesetz auflöst; schon nur das Betrachten der Einzelerscheinung erschöpft seine ganze Kraft, geschweige daß er etwas erübrigte<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  “etwas erübrigt”: OC 1B 29–31 „davon noch übrig hätte“.</tei:note> für das Erfassen eines Urgesetztes, das ihm ein fremdes Geistiges bleibt, obgleich es in der Erscheinung auch sichtbaren Niederschlag hat.  Außerhalb der Kunst macht sich diese Unzulänglichkeit<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  „Unzulänglichkeit: OC 1B 29–31: “Unzulänglichmeit des Menschen”.</tei:note> nicht minder geltend:  auf den Gebieten der Kultur, <tei:hi rend="italic">Religion</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Politik</tei:hi> begegnen Sie ihr zu allen Zeiten; man scheitert schon an Einzelerscheinungen, entwickelt gleichwohl aber „Ideen,“ „Utopien,“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  OC 1B 29–31 adds “Fanatismen” at this point.</tei:note> die im selben Maße falsch sein müssen!</tei:p><tei:p>Und da bin ich schon bei dem Kern dieses Briefes, den ich, die letzten freien Tage ausnützend, etwas weiter zu fassen mich entschloß.  Ursprünglich hatte ich vor, das ganze Material, das ich auf dem Tische eigens aufgeschüttet habe, zu verwenden.  Ich sah aber die Unmöglichkeit ein u. bescheide mich, den Windungen Ihres Briefes folgend, blos Bemerkungen zu machen.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">[„Briand“]</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  In the first copy, OC 1/B 29–31, this series of headings, “Briand,” “Harden,”, “Volk,” “Französisches,” „höhere Ebene,“ may have been added subsequently in the space of the paragraph indentations.  Slightly modified they are paleographically incorporated into this final fair copy, extending out partway into the left margin.  Halm had mentioned Briand in OJ 11/35, 20, July 24, 1922, p.3.  Aristide Briand (1862–1932), French socialist leader, première and cabinet member of France at various times between 1902 and 1932.  He had been première during the War 1915–17, and became so again from January 1921 to January 1922.  He received the Nobel Peace Prize in 1926.</tei:note> Als ich vor vielen Jahren mit <tei:hi rend="italic">Schönberg</tei:hi>, den ich oft sah u. der mich geradezu liebte,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15">  Click on <ref cRef="schoenberg_arnold">Arnold Schoenberg</ref>.  This statement adds weight to the evidence that the two men met frequently between 1903 and 1910..</tei:note> über <tei:hi rend="italic">Reger</tei:hi> sprach, stieß ich auf unerklärlichen Widerstand.  Nach 1½ Stunden müssigsten Hin- u. Herredens schöpfte ich Verdacht u. frug: “Lieber <tei:hi rend="italic">Schönberg</tei:hi>, was kennen Sie eigentlich von <tei:hi rend="italic">Reger</tei:hi>?“, Nichts, nicht eine Note,“ bekam ich zur Antwort.  Da ließ ich meinen Unmut wilden Lauf . . .  Nun, <tei:hi rend="italic">Schönberg</tei:hi> bin ich nicht, – sowie ich z.B. über Bruckner, Strauss spreche, nachdem ich ihre +sämtlichen+ Werke nicht nur erworben, sondern auch genau gelesen u. in Konzerten oft<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn16">  OC 1B 29–31: „u. oft in öffentlichen Vorführungen“.  There is evidence in Schenker’s diary of his attendance at concerts with music by these two composers.  On Strauss, see also Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern ...</tei:hi> (Hildesheim: Olm, 1985), pp. 66, 122, 207, 256–7, 267; on Bruckner, see Federhofer, „Heinrich Schenkers Bruckner-Verständnis,“ <tei:hi rend="italic">Archiv für Musikwissenschaft</tei:hi> 39/3 (1982), 198–212. </tei:note> gehört habe, so treibe ich es auf jedem <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> anderen Gebiet.  Nicht eher spreche ich, bis ich nicht, wie<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn17">  OC 1B 29–31:  „ähnlich wie”.</tei:note> in der Musik, gleichsam die Urgesetze mir vergegenwärtigt habe.  Obgleich vollständig mittellos, von der Hand in den Mund lebend, habe ich in allen Kriegsjahren nicht weniger als 9 Tageszeitungen +aller Richtungen+ (des Auslands u. Inlands) +ins Haus+ bezogen, – wissen Sie noch einen auf dem Erdenrund, der ein solches Geldopfer zu bringen Mut gehabt hätte?  Dabei habe ich selbst den reichsten Schülern gegenüber auf jede angebotene Honorar-Erhöhung grundsätzlich verzichtet, um mich nicht mit einem Mehr-Geld zu beschmutzen, das mir, trotz zunehmender Teuerung, ein Verbrechen an den Kämpfern draußen erschien.  Über dem Vorrat, den ich in so vielen Blättern auftrat–dazu verschlang ich außer Hause Alles nur irgendwie Erreichbare<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn18">  OC 1B 29–31:  „Blättern erkannte–dazu verschlang ich auswärts Alles nur</tei:note>– verlor ich 30 Pfund an Körpergewicht;  ich litt unsäglich, ließ aber nicht ab, das Treiben der Demokraten, Sozialdemokraten, Nationalen, Pazifisten, Internationalisten in ihren Blättern zu verfolgen u. die wichtigsten Belege – aufzubewahren !  (Ich schätze sie auf viele, viele Tausend Stück.)  Im weiteren Verlaufe hatte ich mir Urteil genug z.B. über unsere „Arbeiter.Ztg“ (= Berliner „Vorwärts“)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn19">  OC 1B 29–31:  „z.B. über die hiesige „Arbeiterztg“ (gleichsam der Wiener „Vorwärts“)“.</tei:note> gebildet, um sie wegen ihres (aus Unreife) eckeln Betragens aus dem Hause<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn20">  OC 1B 29–31:  „aus meinem Zimmer“.</tei:note> zu entfernen, beziehe aber noch heute, wo ich mit dem Leben entsetzlich ringe, 3 große Tagesblätter, aus <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Wien</tei:hi></tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Berlin</tei:hi></tei:hi> u. <tei:hi rend="italic">Frankfurt</tei:hi>, die <tei:hi rend="italic">verschiedener</tei:hi> Richtung sind.  Wie oft mußte ich schon den Verlag ersuchen, mir bei den Quartalsbestellungen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn21">  OC 1B 29–31 inserts at this point: “für mich”.</tei:note> -mir- mit den unerschwinglichen MK<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn22">  “MK”: [explain].</tei:note> auszuhelfen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn23">  OC 1B 29–31:  “zu intervenieren”.</tei:note> u. lasse von dieser Gewissenhaftigkeit doch nicht ab!  Daß es eine innere, keine blos äußerliche ist, nehmen Sie nach alldem wohl selbst an. <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">„Harden“]</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn24">  Halm had mentioned Harden in OJ 11/35, 20, July 24, 1922, p.3.  Maximilian Harden (1861–1927), born Felix Ernst Witkowski (1861-1927), was one of the foremost political journalists in Wilhelmine Germany.  He founded the periodical <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Zukunft</tei:hi> (<tei:hi rend="italic">The Future</tei:hi>), which appeared from 1892-1923, to which Schenker contributed articles and reviews, and with whom he corresponded, 1892–95. [create biogfile and link]</tei:note>  In jüngsten Jahren noch, da ich Mutter, Schwester, jüngeren Brüder (den heute so undankbaren Milliardär)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn25">  Julia Schenker (1827?–1917), who bore four sons and two daughters: Marcus (died 1880), Rebecka (died 1889), Wilhelm (18..–at least 1935), Schifre, Heinrich, Moritz (1874–at least 1931); the “daughter” must therefore have been Schifre, and the“younger brother” Moritz, a banker who looked after S’s financial affairs, but who was later disgraced and bankrupted (Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern ...</tei:hi>, pp. 3–5, 137; OJMC <tei:hi rend="italic">Checklist of Manuscripts</tei:hi>).</tei:note> u. Nichte von Klavierstunden zu erhalten hatte, nahm ich den Antrag eines Wiener <tei:hi rend="italic">Harden</tei:hi>-Freundes, für ihn etwas zu schreiben, gern an.  Es waren das überhaupt meine ersten Versuche u. ich danke es H., daß er Mut hatte, sie zu veröffentlichen, denn die vielfachen Auswirkungen der Mitarbeit helfen immerhin eine bessere Zukunft<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn26">  “Zukunft”: clearly a word-play between his own (improved) future and the title of the journal, <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Zukunft</tei:hi>.  </tei:note> vorbereiten. Er bezeigte mir, ohne daß er etwas verstanden hätte, unbegrenztes, ja rührendes Vertrauen vom ersten Augenblick an, doch konnte ich diese Liebe nicht erwidern.  Ich sah bald, daß er keine Frage von Hand aus selbstständig beherrscht, folglich verurteilt ist, nach sachfremden unwesentlichen, sogar fremden Gesichtspunkten<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn27">  OC 1B 29–31 inserts “überhaupt” at this point.</tei:note> zu urteilen.  „Anders als die Anderen“ mußte unbewußt ihm Loh[n]ung werden, der er bis zur Stunde folgt.  Und doch war er gerade dadurch +genau+ +wie+ +die+ +Anderen+, die ihre Unselbstständigkeit (= Unzulänglichkeit) in derselben Art<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn28">  OC 1B 29–31: „(= Unmöglichkeit) in derselben Weise“.</tei:note>  vor sich selbst verbergen.  Er beschimpfte die Zeitungsherausgeber, die „Kulis“ als wäre ein Tagblatt ohne irdischen Schmutz überhaupt möglich – unser Karl Kraus ist ^genau^ so kindisch unreif –, hielt es aber selbst ganz anders.  Auch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn29">  OC 1B 29–31: „ganz u. gar nicht anders.  Selbst“.</tei:note> mir gegenüber scheute er sich nicht, öfter<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn30">  In OC 1B 29–31, Schenker copied the long section that follows, „Beinflussungen ... geistiges vorläuft”, in the wrong order, between “was noch sonst” (the end of p.2) and “an Erscheinungen” (the top of p.9).  This is why he was compelled to make a second fair copy from his presumed prior draft, to send to Halm.</tei:note> Beeinflussungen zu wagen, je nachdem er selbst<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn31">  OC 1B 29–31 inserts „von anderer Seite“ at this point.</tei:note> beeinflußt worden.  (Ich gab aber nicht nach.)  Ein pathetischerer H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Bahr</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn32">  Hermann Bahr (1863–1934), Austrian playwright and novelist, for whom Schenker worked and with whom he corresponded. [create biogfile and link to]</tei:note> ist er ^blos^ allezeit gewesen, ist mit Allem gegangen, was mir nach Minorität roch u.s.w. besonders abstoßend wirkte auf mich seine „Monarchen-Erziehung,“ die ihm Kerker eintrug.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn33"> In one of the first issues (December 31, 1892), Harden’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Zukunft</tei:hi> carried the essay “Monarchenerziehung,” which criticized monarchies for indulging in grand hunts, court festivals, and the like, instead of concerning themselves with the fatherland (“The peaceful time [of Bismarck] is gone, and with growing fear the nation asks how the German emperor will educate himself”).  For insulting the emperor in “Monarchenerziehung,” Harden was summoned to court on April 7, 1893, but no prison sentence resulted.  Years later, Harden was sentenced to a six-month prison term at the Weichselmünde fortress, near Danzig, beginning May, 1899, for anti-emperor opinions expressed in two articles, “Pudelmajestät” (<tei:hi rend="italic">Die Zukunft</tei:hi> 23, June 18, 1898) and “Grossvaters Uhr” (<tei:hi rend="italic">Die Zukunft</tei:hi> 24, Aug. 13, 1898).  On his release, Harden immediately resumed attacks on the monarchy with an article entitled "Kampf mit dem Drachen" (<tei:hi rend="italic">Die Zukunft</tei:hi> 32, Aug. 11, 1900).  Sabine Armbrecht, <tei:hi rend="italic">Verkannte Liebe:  Maximilian Hardens Haltung zu Deutschtum und Judentum</tei:hi>, Oldenburgische Beiträge zu jüdischen Studien, vol. 3 (Oldenburg:  Bibliotheks- und Informationssystem der Universität Oldenburg, 1999), 73-75.</tei:note>  Nicht nur fand ich den Aufsatz flegelhaft, sondern vor Allem +zu+ +billig+.  Hätte er nur, wie schon dazumal ich selbst, in das Leben der historischen Reichen Einblick gehabt (aus nächster Nähe), es wäre ihm nicht eingefallen, daß mehr „Erziehung“ zu suchen, als sich der Sachlage nach überhaupt erzielen läßt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn34">  OC 1B 29–31: „als sich nach der gegebenen Sachlage überhaupt erzielen läßt“.</tei:note>  Mit demselben Rechte müßte er die <tei:hi rend="italic">Masaryk</tei:hi><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn35">  Tomás Garrigue Masaryk (1850–1937), statesman, founder and first president of Czechoslovakia.  </tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Harding</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn36">  Warren G. Harding (1865–1923), President of the United States 1921–23.  </tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Ebert</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn37">  Friedrich Ebert (1871–1925), leader of the Social Democratic movement in Germany, President of the Weimar Republic 1921–25.  </tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Wilson</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn38">  Woodrow Wilson (1856–1924), President of the United States 1913–21, who took the US to war, was a leading force in the Versailles Treaty, and founder of the League of Nations, hence one of S’s bêtes noires!  In OC 1/B 29–31 S this list concludes with “Haimisch, Venizelos”: Eleuthérios Venizélos (1864–1936), leading Greek politician and statesman; Haimisch [identify].  </tei:note> u.s.w. beanstanden.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn39">  OC 1/B 29–31 adds „ja jeden Bauer, jeden Handwerker“ at this point.</tei:note>  Der Beruf, der Umfang der Geschäfte ziehen <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> da Grenzen, die nur in den seltensten Fällen einer zu überschreiten die Kraft hat.  Nicht einmal über die eigenen Güter, die irdischen, hat so einer Überblick: ein <tei:hi rend="italic">majordomus</tei:hi> muß täglich Vortrag halten, der den Besitzer nur<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn40">  „nur“: OC 1/B 29–31 reads „höchst”.</tei:note> langweilt.  Auf „Vorträge“ ist jeder Präsident angewiesen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn41">  OC 1/B 29–31 adds „auf Zeitungsmeldungen“ at this point.</tei:note> u. genau so ist es bei einem Kaiser, der nicht Alles zu wissen, Alles zu können braucht.  Ein arger Misbrauch H’s – wieder eine Mantelhängerei – war es, der mich veranlaßt hat, ihm – verzeihen Sie das<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn42">  OC 1/B 29–31 inserts „unschöne” (unpleasant) at this point.</tei:note> Wort – einer Fußtritt zu geben, trotz aller<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn43">  OC 1/B 29–31 inserts “persönlichen” at this point.</tei:note> Not.  Dazu kam noch die Einsicht, daß ich mich den Lesern gegenüber nicht so verständlich machen konnte, als ich auf andere Art es erhoffen dürfte.  Schon damals habe ich meine Theorien entworfen u. es drängte mich übermächtig, sie auszugestalten.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">„<tei:hi rend="italic">Volk</tei:hi>–<tei:hi rend="italic">Regierung</tei:hi>“]</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn44">  OC 1/B 29–31: “Volk”.  Halm had referred to “Volk” and “Regierung” on the same line in OJ 11/35, 20, July 24, 1922, p.2.  </tei:note> Es sei Ihnen verraten, daß ich für die Zeit nach dem Erscheinen des IV. Bd.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn45">  “IV. Band”: S is probably referring here to the last volume of Musikalische Theorien und Phantasien, roughly equating with <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi>, the third volume being, in his plans still at that time, the <tei:hi rend="italic">Über die Niedergang der musikalischen Kunst</tei:hi>.  </tei:note> u. der „Formenlehre“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn46">  “Formenlehre”: in his diary for July 16?, 1907, Schenker noted that he had had an idea for a “new theory of form.”  File 83 of the Oster Collection contains eleven folders of material for a theory of form never published.  Perhaps the implied volume III of <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:hi> is meant to be this volume.</tei:note> ein Werkchen plane, etwa „Zukunft der Menschheit“ betitelt:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn47">  OC 1/B 29–31:  „die Herausgabe eines Werkchen plane, dessen Titel etwa ‚“Zukunft der Menschen“ lauten wird“.</tei:note> Bis dahin wird das vollständige Werk der „Th. u. Ph.“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn48">  OC 1/B 29–31: „der Theorien“.</tei:note> den Beweis erbracht haben, daß es geradezu Pflicht eines Menschen ist, der Einblick in Urgesetze hat, wenn auch nur solche musikalischer Art, sich zu dieser Frage zu äußern: daß er dazu mehr Befugnis hat, als die vielen Minister, Parteiler, Philosophen u. Dichter,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn49">  OC 1/B 29–31: „als die vielen Politiker, Minister, Dichter, Philosophen“.</tei:note> die den Anblick von Urgesetzen ein genossen, steht fest.   Könnten Sie die ungeheuren Zurüstungen sehen, die schon seit Langem gemacht sind, Sie hielten es für Blendwerk!   Wer wie ich die Synthese eines Geniewerkes erfüllt u. in Worte gefaßt, darf sich an jene Aufgabe mit mehr Recht wagen, als die <tei:hi rend="italic">Rollands</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn50">  Romain Rolland (1866–1944), French novelist and writer, pacifist and activist against fascism.  </tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Barbusses</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn51">  Eduard Bernstein (1850–1932), German social democrat, Jewish, member of the Reichstag 1902–28, who pursued a revisionist brand of Marxism and was associated with Harden’s Die Zukunft.  </tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Bernstein</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn52">  Henri Barbusse (1873–1935), French novelist and poet, one of whose novels is <tei:hi rend="italic">Clarté</tei:hi> (1919), and who launched a journal of the same name (1919–27) and founded the movement <tei:hi rend="italic">Clarté</tei:hi> in 1919, emulated the Encyclopaedists and the spirit of the Enlightenment.  Schenker had excoriated the movement in his “The Mission of German Genius,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</tei:hi> 1 (1921), pp.14–15 (Eng. trans., vol. I, p.14) (see also DLA 69.930/11, November 2, 1922).  </tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Kautsky</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn53">  Karl Kautsky (1854–1938), German Marxist theorist and social democrat.  </tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Marx</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Engels</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Wells</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn54">   H. G. Wells (1866–1946), English novelist, perhaps S is referring to his <tei:hi rend="italic">The Outline of History</tei:hi> (1920).</tei:note> u.s.w.</tei:p><tei:p>Aus Hochschätzung für Sie, den ich als einen Mann ohne Tadel kenne, will ich hier einige Bekenntnisse ablegen, die, ich kann sagen, seit Kindheitstagen mit mir gehen.  Ich will sie nicht in der Sprache ausdrücken, die heute allen Unklaren eigen ist, sondern so natürlich als möglich, das Wort im heiligsten Sinne der Natur verstanden. <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi>
 
„<tei:hi rend="italic">Antropomorphes</tei:hi>,“ „<tei:hi rend="italic">Antropozentrisches</tei:hi>“ Denken ist mir<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn55">  OC 1/B 29–31: „ist mir Fremd“.</tei:note> eine Beleidigung der Natur, ein Größenwahn des Menschen.  „Heiligen Frieden in der Natur“ sieht der Mensch, wenn nur +er+ selbst die Arbeitsstätte verlassen u. z.B. einen Ausflug macht: die Natur raste mit ihm, meint er.  Auch Dichter fühlen so, u. doch finde ich es dichterischer, mich bescheiden vor dem Kampf zu neigen, der in der Natur auch während meiner Feierstunden rast.  Auch ich ihr Kampfobjekt, füge ich mich fürchtig u. dankbar, wie ein neuer <tei:hi rend="italic">Adam</tei:hi>, ein: so fühle ich mich glücklich.</tei:p><tei:p>Was Menschen sonst an jeder Jugend als „Entwicklung,“ „Fortschritt“ wahrzunehmen glauben, halte ich blos für +Reflex+ +körperlichen+ <tei:hi rend="italic">Wachstums</tei:hi>: lassen Sie dieses ein reifes Stadium erreichen, u. schon auch ist der Durchschnittsmensch da, mit seiner<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn56">  OC 1/B 29–31: Durchschnittsmench ausgeprägt, an seiner“.</tei:note> unüberschreitbaren Grenze.  Daß die Jugend selbst sich im „Fortschritt“ nährt, ist auf die gleiche Täuschung hinzuführen, die der Reisende hat, wenn er die Eisenbahn benützt: Die Landschaft +steht+, u. so steht auch der Kopf, während das +körperliche+ Wachstum ein geistiges +vorläuft+.</tei:p><tei:p>Der Mensch duftet nur aus dem Gehirn, stinkt aber aus dem Gedärm.  Das ist Wille der Natur, der das Genie wie der Trottel beugt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn57">: „beugt“: OC 1/B 29–31: „fügen“.</tei:note>  So auch ist es in der Gesammtmenschheit : sie duftet aus Einzelnen, die ihr Gehirn u. Auge sind, u. stinkt aus der Masse.  Das Schauerliche von heute ist, daß sich der Hintere herausgenommen hat, nicht mehr der Hintere sein zu wollen, als hinge es von seinem Trotz ab, u. nicht vielmehr davon, ob die Natur Gehirnnerven auch in den Hinteren einbaut, was sie dem Menschen zu gefallen doch niemals tun wird.  (Sie hat ihre Gründe.)  In Wiener Mundart ist: „ich bin nicht zu die Bücher“ <tei:hi rend="italic">stolzer</tei:hi> Ausdruck<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn58">  OC 1/B 29–31: „der Ausdruck von Lebensstolz“.</tei:note> eines Menschen, der sich den Gegenständen der Welt zuwendet, Bewußtsein u. Denken weder <tei:hi rend="italic">er</tei:hi>- noch <tei:hi rend="italic">ver</tei:hi>trägt.   Die selbe gilt von <tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> Völkern: durch geographischer Lage,  Klima, Geburt überhaupt sind manche „zu die Bücher,“ manche nicht.</tei:p><tei:p>Ein schauerliches Urgesetz ist: der Mensch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn59">  OC 1/B 29–31: „Ein furchtbares Menschen-Urgesetz ist: er“</tei:note> fühlt sich wohl, wenn er sich sein Gedärm erleichtert, hält sich aber die Nase zu u. schimpft, wenn sich ein Anderer das seine erleichtert!  Die Prolongationen dieses Urgesetztes sind +Inhalt+ +aller+ <tei:hi rend="italic">Menschenkämpfe</tei:hi>: Ein Diebsvolk – oder ^Diebs^Mensch, fühlt sich durch den Diebstahl erleichtert, schreit aber: „Unrecht, Gewalt,“ wenn ein Anderer stiehlt.  Jegliches Unrecht,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn60">  OC 1/B 29–31 inserts „jegliches Laster“ at this point.</tei:note> will Jeder selbst begehen – Gedärmerleichterung –, aber empfindlich bleibt er, wo er leiden soll „Ich sehe immer nur andern u. dich nur, wie du <tei:hi rend="italic">erscheinen willst</tei:hi>, aber nicht wie du bist“ (<tei:hi rend="italic">Bonsels</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn61">  Perhaps Waldemar Bonsels (1880–1953), writer of childrens books.</tei:note>), ist dennoch eine solche Art: dem sich ein Lastergestank Erleichternden noch damit hineinzuhelfen, daß man Erleichterung für Gehirnduft auslege, ist auch vergeblich. Gewissen, Reue, Einsicht hören auf, wo ein solcher Naturvolk vorliegt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn62">  “dem .. vorliegt”: OC 1/B 29–31: „dann ist er die Gedärmerleichterung, so vermag der Mensch niemals zu verstehen, was man ihm vorhalten.  Reue, Einsicht, Gewissen hören auf, wo ein solcher Naturakt vorliegt.  Dem sich ein Lastergestank Erleichternden noch damit hineinzuhelfen, daß man seine Erleichterung für Gehirnduft auslege, ist auch vergeblich.  </tei:note>  Man kommt um das Naturgesetz nicht herum, wie immer man sich dazu stelle.  In diesem Zusammenhange sei Ihres <tei:hi rend="italic">Briand</tei:hi> nun noch einmal gedacht:  +Nach+ Gedärmerleichterung ist auch der Franzose „vernünftig.“  (Nebenbei Br. ist ungebildet, daß er in offener Parlamentssitzung vom Konzil „<tei:hi rend="italic">de trente</tei:hi>“ sprach (Trient!?!), sprach, er [der Katholik!]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn63">  Square brackets in original.  Reference is presumably to the Council of Trent.</tei:note>  der heute vielgenannte <tei:hi rend="italic">Alain</tei:hi> spricht +zuerst+ – Gedärmerleichterung – von „einer Republik von jenseits des Rheins“, +hernach+ ist er wirklich trefflich.  (Hat so etwas aber Wert?)  <tei:hi rend="italic">Voltaire</tei:hi> schiebt in Getreide – Gedärmerleichterung –, ist im Übrigen “vernünftig” (nach Goethe, “ohne Tiefe”).  <tei:hi rend="italic">Anatole France</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn64">  Anatole France (1844–1924), French novelist, storteller, literary critic, and writer on many subjects, in later life supporter of the Communist party.  </tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Loti</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn65">  Pierre Loti (1850–1923), French naval officer and novelist. </tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Claudel</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn66">  Paul Claudel (1868–1955), French poet, playwright, for forty years a diplomat.</tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Rolland</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Barrés</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn67">  Maurice Barrès (1862–1923), French novelist, journalist, nationalist politician, anti-semitic and hater of Germany.  </tei:note> sind alle sehr „vernünftig“, aber <tei:hi rend="italic">nach</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn68"> Double underlining.</tei:note> Gedärmerleichterung.  Den Nobel-Preis auf der Hand schwört <tei:hi rend="italic">Anatole France</tei:hi> seine frühere Religion, den Kommunismus, ab.  <tei:hi rend="italic">Claudel</tei:hi> ergeht sich in Mysterien, aber seine – Kriegshetze ?  Und <tei:hi rend="italic">Loti</tei:hi>’s Haß ? Der Vizepräsident der Franz-Lig[u]e f. Menschenrechte, Prof. Basch (Paris)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn69">  Victor Basch (1863–1944), became President of the League for the Rights of Man in 1926; Hungarian-Jewish, naturalized Frenchman, anti-Fascist.</tei:note>, erzählt soeben in <tei:hi rend="italic">Berlin</tei:hi> u. <tei:hi rend="italic">Wien</tei:hi>,  <tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> die deutschen hätten binnen einem Jahrhundert 3 mal die Franzosen überfallen, so den <tei:hi rend="italic">Bonaparte</tei:hi> (!!), Napol. III, u. die Republik.  Was heißt das?  Der überfallende Franzose fühlt sich immer überfallen, <tei:hi rend="italic">der Überfall als Gedärmerleichterung tut ihm wohl</tei:hi>, u. er begreift nicht, weshalb  der Deutsche die Nase zuhält, oder besser zuhalten müßte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn70">  “Der Vizepräsident .. müßte.”: this passage, which replaces the cue “a)” in OC 1/B 29–31, was originally drafted as part of a P.S. to OC 1/B25–28, January 17, 1918 (cued “a]” there), which was not used in the final letter, DLA 69.930/2 of the same date, and subsequently incorporated into the present text.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Seitdem wir von der Natur abgewichen, nicht mehr auf Zweigen hüpfen u. von Gras oder dgl. uns nähren, dafür aber in die +Künstlichkeit+ +eines+ +Staates+ eingegangen, ist es ausgeschlossen, daß die Menschheit mit ihr ja fertig wird. Ginge es von einem <tei:hi rend="italic">Mozart</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven</tei:hi> ab, einen Staat nach seinem Gefühl für Urgesetze zu – komponieren, dann gienge es, aber die Masse weiß nicht einmal, daß es um eine Künstlichkeit geht, die als solche Fälschungen braucht, geschweige daß sie bei ihrer Unbegabung Mittel fände, zumal heute, wo schon Neger erklären, sie wollten sich selbst regieren, weil sie es auch schon treffe (!?).<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn71">  OC 1/B 29–31: „daß er um eine Widernatur geht, die ihre Fälschungen haben muß, geschweige daß sie bei ihrer Beschaffenheit Mittel fände, zumal heute, wo schon alle Neger erklären, sie wollen sich selbst regieren, weil sie es können (!?).“</tei:note>  Solange der Mensch den Größenwahn hat, Gott gar nach seinem Ebenbilde zu formen, ihn zu verleugnen, wenn er nicht zu gutem, bequemen [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte:</tei:hi> bequemem] Leben verhilft (Religion geht durch Magen-Feiertage), nach der Unsterblichkeit<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn72">  OC 1/B 29–31: „Unsterblichkeit der Sache“.</tei:note> verlangt, weil es ihm unerträglich ist, zu denken, er<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn73">  OC 1/B 29–31: „er, er, der Mensch“.</tei:note> könnte mal sein Ende haben, u. was noch sonst an Erscheinungen von Größenwahn gibt, wieder den Weg<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn74">  OC 1/B 29–31: „wird den Erdenwanze den Weg“</tei:note> zum Staat nicht finden, denn dieser heißt: Künstlichkeit, also Zwang<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn75">  OC 1/B 29–31 inserts „u. Arbeit” at this point.</tei:note> u. Fälschung.</tei:p><tei:p>Dazu kommt, daß jeder Mensch irgendwie betrügen +muß+.  Auch im Stoff liegt die Nötigung dazu.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn76">  OC 1/B 29–31 inserts „muß wieder wie im Menschen, der in die Gesellschaft eingestellt ist.“</tei:note>  Die ehrenhafteste Großkaufleute haben mir versichert: „Im Geschäft betrüge ich, aber außerhalb des Geschäftes lüge ich nie.“  Eine Welt von <tei:hi rend="italic">Spinozas</tei:hi> zu denken ist unerlaubt,  aber schon 1 <tei:hi rend="italic">Wilson</tei:hi>, unter Millionen <tei:hi rend="italic">Spinozas</tei:hi> würde den Bund beschmutzen u. sprengen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn77">  OC 1/B 29–31: „unter 12000000 <tei:hi rend="italic">Spinozas</tei:hi> wurde das Ideal sprengen.“</tei:note>  Es geht nicht, weil die Natur es gar nicht so haben will.  Sie hat dem menschlichen Körper dessen Organen <tei:hi rend="bold">{9}</tei:hi> Fallen gestellt, an denen er früher oder später zugrunde geht, so aber auch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn78">  OC 1/B 29–31: „fallen gestellt, an denen er früher oder später schließlich zugrunde geht, u. so auch“.</tei:note> dem Menschheitskörper.</tei:p><tei:p>Bin ich darum pessimistisch?  Sicher nicht.  Im Gegenteil.  Ich liebe u. verehre den Willen der Natur bis zum Äußersten meiner eigenen Vernichtung. – Ich glaube nur in die Auslese der Natur, u. nicht an eine ihr auf demokratisch abzutrotzende. –  Ich danke Gott, daß er meine hochlieben Eltern mit der Frommheit<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn79">  „Frommheit“: OC 1/B 29–31: „Licht“.</tei:note> ausgestattet hat, 12 Kinder zu zeugen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn80">  Schenker is usually said to have been one of five children, of which Schenker was the penultimate:  Federhofer: <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern ...</tei:hi> (Hildesheim: Olms, 1985), p.3.</tei:note> u. um sie alles Ungemach zu tragen.  Wenn mein Vater aus Mangel an Jugend,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn81">  “Wenn ... Jugend” OC 1/B 29–31: „Mein Vater war echt Frommen u. hätte sicher auf die neuzeitige „Parole“ nicht geforcht[?], auch wenn er sie gekannt hätte.  Denken Sie, wenn mein Vater“.</tei:note> dem Gedanken eines sehr berühmten Gelehrten, (den ich selbst gut kannte) eines Freundes von <tei:hi rend="italic">E. Mach</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn82">  Ernst Mach (1833–1916), Austrian physicist and philosopher.</tei:note> eines großen Entdeckers u. heilandsgütigen Menschen, gefolgt wäre, der von <tei:hi rend="italic">Voltaire</tei:hi> u. <tei:hi rend="italic">Marx</tei:hi> kommend forderte, der Stand sei auch berechtigt,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn83">  „kommend ... berechtigt: OC 1/B 29–31: „kommend die Grausamkeit forderte.  Der Stand sei nötigenfalls berechtigt“.</tei:note> Kinder zu töten, um der Lebenden willen, – ich wäre nicht am Leben,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn84">  „um der ... Leben”: OC 1/B 29–31: „um der Sicherstellung der Lebenden retten[?], – ich wäre vielleicht nicht am Leben“.</tei:note> da ich eins der mittleren Kinder war, u. dafür bliebe ein Abhub, der das Leben gar nicht verdient.  Wohin man nur mit einem Mitleid kommt, das doch wieder auf der anderen Seite zur eckelerregendsten +Grausamkeit+ ausarten <tei:hi rend="italic">muß</tei:hi>!  (Wir wissen es ja heute schon alle, alle, daß das Proletariat kein Mitleid kennt, sohin auch das Mitleid nicht verdient, das ihm gestern entgegengebracht wurde.  Gedärmerleichterungsfrage.) – Und als Unsterblichkeit der Sache fasse ich mein einmaliges Leben auf.  Nicht mit dem Ewigen um Zeit-Ewigkeit rettzuleben[?], fühle ich das Bedürfnis, ich fühle mich auch schon in der Spanne Zeit „unsterblich,“ als Teil des Ewigen, u. nicht anders als der Wurm, Vogel, Fisch, die ebenfalls seine Wunder sind.</tei:p><tei:p>Der Mensch ist so nicht schlecht, nicht gut, nur für die Künstliche Aufgabe unzulänglich, u. größenwahnsinnig vor Gott, Natur u. der Ewigkeit.  Trotz Kopernikus gibt er sein antropozentrisches Denken nicht auf u. stolzirt darüber, wie über einer Tuberkulose.  Er maßt sich an, der Natur ihre Hauptwaffe, <tei:hi rend="bold">{10}</tei:hi> die Vernichtung, zu entreißen, oder wenn sie schon sein muß, denkt er sie lieber dem Andern als sich zu.  Das Letztere muß ^auch^ bleiben : er +oder+ ich!  (Er +und+ ich ist schon Synthese, u. diese wird schon zu zweit nicht – Ehe, Freundschaft –, geschweige zu Millionen erreicht.)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn85">  Entire parenthesis not in OC 1/B 29–31.</tei:note>  Verteidige ich ^aber^ mit meinem Leben auch die Kunst, so habe ich alle Ursache, nicht zu weichen einem, der eine solche Aufgabe nicht hat.</tei:p><tei:p>Zwischen Volk u. Regierung vermag ich nicht zu unterscheiden.  Ist <tei:hi rend="italic">Ebert</tei:hi> nicht mehr „Volk“, seit er präsidiert,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn86">  “präsidiert”: OC 1/B 29–31: „regiert“.</tei:note> u. wird er wieder „Volk“, wenn er vom Amt zurückschritt?  Und in einem Staat, in dem Alle mit^re^gieren, als Wähler, Parlamentarier, Beamter u.s.w., gebe es nur eine Regierung<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn87">  OC 1/B 29–31 inserts „u. nirgend Volk” at this point.</tei:note>?  Wo ist denn aber dies ^“Volk“^ &lt;del&gt;letztere&lt;/del&gt;?  Hier liegt eine Irrtum<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn88">  OC 1/B 29–31: „Täuschung“.</tei:note> vor: jede Regierung +enttäuscht+, Tyrann, Oligarch, Kaiser, Präsident – muß doch jede Regierung auch +betrügen+, wie der Einzelmensch, es liegt in der Natur der Dinge so! – daher sucht man den Glückseligkeitswahn zunächst durch +Entgegensetzung+ von „Volk“ u. „Regierung“ noch irgendwie zu retten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn89">  „muß ... retten”: OC 1/B 29–31: „u. daher sonst man den Glückseligkeitswehe durch Entgegensetzung von Volk u. Regierung letztlich zu retten. Aber ^auch^ jede Regierung muß betrügen, wie der Einzelmensch, – es liegt in der Natur der Dinge so.“</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">„Französisches“]</tei:hi> Daher traue ich auch in Frankreich Volk u. Regierung nicht.  Das Volk selbst ist kleinlich, roh, nicht allzu begabt (weil maßlos<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn90">  “Französisches”: Halm had mentioned “französische Regierung,“ „französisches Volk,“ and „französische Kunst“  in OJ 11/35, 20, July 24, 1922, p.3;   „maßlos“ not in OC 1/B 29–31, and whole phrase not in parentheses.</tei:note> eitel).  Die Tat ist dort +immer+ eine – Gedärmerleichterung, nur huscht ihr Wort dort schöner darüber weg.  Sogar „<tei:hi rend="italic">die</tei:hi> Weise aus Frankfurt“ – so meine ich die Frkf. Ztg im Gegensatz zu Schopenhauer<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn91">  OC 1/B 29–31: „ich meine die „Fkf. Ztg.“</tei:note> – weiß schon ihren „ausgesprochenen klein-bürgerlichen Geist, der im kleinen Rentner seine vollendete Verkürzerung gefunden hat.“  Ein solches <tei:hi rend="italic">humus</tei:hi> taugt nicht viel, u. ich lobe mir die deutsche Arbeitsfreude:  der +Fleiß+ des deutschen Kaufmanns, Arbeiters sogar ist +derselbe+, der im deutschen Genie sich als „Schöpfung“ bewährt!   Die Westvölker treiben Handel, als daß sie arbeiteten;  sie verspotten den d. Fleiß, der etwa Genie-Vorzeichen ist.  Nicht allein Revision des <tei:hi rend="bold">{11}</tei:hi> Versailles „Vertrags“,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn92">  OC 1/B 29–31: „des Versailles Friedens“.</tei:note> eine Revision der Westvölker überhaupt täte not.   Auch die Weltgeschichte ist falsch geschrieben, nicht nur die Musikgeschichte. –  Der berühmte Philolog H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Schuchardt</tei:hi> hat gemeint: „Was hat es uns u. den andern genützt, daß wir in +ihrer+ Sprache zu ihnen geredet haben?  Damit sie uns kennen lernen, müssen +sie+ unsere Sprache erlernen.“  Dazu ist aber der Frankreicher nicht fähig u. daher wird eine Verständigung niemals gelungen, höchstens daß der deutsche zu jeder Gedärmerleichterung (um Diebstahl des Rheins,  Oberschlesiens u.s.w.) entzückt die Nase darbietet!  -Auch- Wollten  wir ^auch^ mit unserer besseren Art ein Beispiel geben, es hülfe nichts, denn der Franzose <tei:hi rend="italic">fühlt sich im Rechten</tei:hi> (s.o. Basch)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn93">  „(s.o. Basch)” not in OC 1/B 29–31.</tei:note> – das ist ja zugleich der tragischer Sinn der vielgenannten Gedärmerleichterung.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">„höhere Ebene“]</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">G. Mahler</tei:hi> schwärmte für so etwas (der er nämlich selbst der „Star,“ die Spitze war: auch Lenin schwärmt aus demselben Grund für die Ebene).  U. doch, hätte ich nicht z.B. d'Andrade<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn94">  Francesco d'Andrade (1859-1921), Portuguese baritone, lived in Berlin; Don Giovanni was his most celebrated role. — Halm had used the phrase “höhere Ebene” in OJ 11/35, 20, July 24, 1922, p.4.  </tei:note> als „Don Juan“ gehört, niemals hätte ich, trotz <tei:hi rend="italic">Mahler</tei:hi>, eine solche <tei:hi rend="italic">Mozart</tei:hi>-Vollendung für überhaupt ausführbar gehalten!  Und wie der Dramatiker nur auf die höchsten Punkte eines Menschenlebens, der Maler auf solche der Natur achtet, so achte auch ich auf Allem auf die höchsten Möglichkeiten, die allein dem Stand der Kunst anzeigen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn95">  “der Maler  ... anzeigen”: OC 1/B 29–31: „auch der Maler vor der Natur, genau so achte ich auf die höchste Möglichkeit, die allein dem Stand der Kunst anzeigt.“</tei:note>  Und wenn von Frankreich<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn96">  OC 1/B 29–31: „Frankreich (Gedärmerleichterung),“.</tei:note> die „moralische <tei:hi rend="italic">Führung</tei:hi>“ (<tei:hi rend="italic">Cailleux</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn97">  Perhaps André Cailleux, French geomorphologist.</tei:note>) beansprucht wird, von der geistigen nicht zu sprechen, bei so viel Ebene, wüßte ich nicht, weshalb Deutschland bei solchen Spitzen unter die Französische Ebene sich begeben soll.  H. Basch stellt entgegen: „<tei:hi rend="italic">Rabelais</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Descartes</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Molière</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Racine</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Voltaire</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">V. Hugo</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Pasteur</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Bergson</tei:hi>, / u. <tei:hi rend="italic">Kant</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Hegel</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Goethe</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Schiller</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Mozart</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Nietzsche</tei:hi> u. <tei:hi rend="italic">Einstein</tei:hi>,“ wahrlich man müsste ein <tei:hi rend="italic">O.E. Curtius</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn98">  O. E. Curtius: [identify]</tei:note> oder <tei:hi rend="italic">Hofmüller</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn99">  Hofmüller: [identify].</tei:note> sein (die vor <tei:hi rend="italic">Goethe</tei:hi> die Schätzung, aber niemals seine Distanzierung des Franzosentums anzunehmen befahigt sind), seiner <tei:hi rend="bold">{12}</tei:hi> muß man sein, um nicht zu -begreifen- ^sehen^, was man ^förmlich^ auf die Wege legen kann., Übrigens, dächte man auch so wie die deutschen Demokraten, dort die „Originalen“ hier (bei den Deutschen) blos die „Vertiefer“ – feine Geniekenner was? –, was nützte auch das?  Wie oft denn soll Deutschland Frankreichs „Überlegenheit“ bezahlen, mit Lande, Menschen?  Ist nicht schon genug Honorar entrichtet worden?  (Werde ich für +eine+ Stunde denn 2-, 3-, 4mal bezahlt?)  Wie lange, wie oft noch soll dieses Verhältnis andauern, wiederkehren?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn100">  „H. Basch ...  wiederkehren?”: this passage, which replaces the cue „b)“ in OC 1/B 29–31, was originally drafted as part of a P.S. to OC 1/B25–28, January 17, 1918 (cued “b]” there), which was not used in the final letter, DLA 69.930/2 of the same date, and subsequently incorporated into the present text.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Er +oder+ ich will die Natur! (Der Franzose fühlt’s, der Deutsche nicht.)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn101">  Parenthesis not in OC 1/B 29–31.</tei:note> International?  Übernational?  Als Lösung?  Gäbs wieder eine allgemeine Bindung, wie einstmals das Schriftentum, das Lateintum, dann gienge es eine +Weile vielleicht+.   Zu Gunsten der Idee ganz auslöschte: D. wäre dann als <tei:hi rend="italic">Nation</tei:hi> einfach nicht mehr da, aber darum +nicht+ schon das Internationale <tei:hi rend="italic">da</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich entsinne mich eines Bildchens in den „fliegenden Blättern“: der Tierfreund.  Stand da ein grundgutes Männchen u. geringster +freudig+ über einen — Flohbesuch auf dem Rücken.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn102">  “auf den Rücken” not in OC 1/B 29–31.</tei:note> So ein Tierfreund war u. bleibt Deutschland:  es grinst freudig über den Besuch von Wanzen, Flöhen u.s.w.;  als wäre Gottes Wort (s. T.I 1.28) “und füllet die Erde, u. machet sie euch untertan“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn103">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Genesis) [= I Moses], i.28: “God blessed them and said to them, ‘Be fruitful and increase in number; </tei:hi>fill the earth and subdue it._ Rule over the fish of the sea and the birds of the air and over every living creature that moves on the ground.”</tei:note> an diese Tierchen, u. nicht an die Menschen ergangen.  (Ein 70-Millionen Volk so feig, so erbärmlich !).–<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn104">  “Ein ... erbärmlich!”: this passage, which replaces the cue “c)” in OC 1/B 29–31, was originally drafted as part of a P.S. to OC 1/B25–28, January 17, 1918 (cued “c]” there), which was not used in the final letter, DLA 69.930/2 of the same date, and subsequently incorporated into the present text.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>So brauche ich nichts zurückzunehmen, wie es heute die Demokraten, Pazifisten, die auf dem Kongreß für Sozialpolitik, ja sogar die Unabhängigen tun müssen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn105">  OC 1/B 29–31: „Alle diese u. eheliche Gedanken haben mich da vor Enttäuschung bewahrt, u. so brauche ich nichts zurückzunehmen, zu bereuen, wie es heute die Demokraten, die Pazifisten, Lenin, die Professoren auf dem Kongreß für Sozialpolitik, die Unabhängigen tun müssen.  Wie 2 x 2 lag Alles zum Greifen klar seit Jahrtausenden u. Jahrhunderten.“</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ich lege Ihnen 3 Aufsätzte von <tei:hi rend="italic">Nitti</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn106">  Francesco Saverio Nitt (1868–1953), Italian statesman, Prime Minister 1919–20, served in parliament 1921–24.</tei:note> bei, der kein „Germaniak,“ kein „Alldeutscher,“ „Völkischer“ ist;  sie dürften Ihnen sonst kaum zugänglich sein.  Und daß ich Sie damit aus der Ruhe scheuche, wollen Sie mir zugute halten:  ich meine es gut, auch +ohne+ Sie bekehren zu wollen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn107">  OC 1/B 29–31: „Und daß ich Sie damit aus der Ruhe aufscheuche, wollen Sie gewiß mir zugute halten:  ich meine es gut, auch +ohne die Absicht+, Sie irgend zu bekehren.“</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Nun beste Grüße u. Wünsche für Herbst u. Winter
Ir
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] <tei:hi rend="italic">H Schenker</tei:hi>
25. Sept 1922</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Halm, dated September 25, 1922]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">This edition conflates two texts,</tei:hi> DLA 69.930/10 <tei:hi rend="italic">and </tei:hi>OC 1/B 29–31<tei:hi rend="italic">, noting only the significant variants between the two.</tei:hi>  OC 1/B 29–31 <tei:hi rend="italic">is a fair copy of a presumed prior draft;  however, Schenker copied one large section of the draft out of order, and had to make a second fair copy in the correct order.</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor Halm,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Many thanks for your first letter.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  Your opus has arrived in the meantime, for which I thank you no less cordially.  In issue 4 of <tei:hi rend="italic">Tonwille</tei:hi>, I may first have the opportunity to make mention of your <tei:hi rend="italic">Piano Method</tei:hi> (the third issue is already at the printer),<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> and only after the difficulties of the onset of lessons are past will I study your opus and give an accounting of it.  I will also now answer your last question about the plan for my immigration.  Through Prof. Straube<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> I found out that Leipzig University considered appointing me last year but ultimately refrained from doing it in consideration that a purely artistic environment suits me better than the more historically oriented one within the university.  How nicely and correctly determined!  I don’t know whether Straube’s efforts to bring me to Leipzig or Berlin will succeed.  I believe<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> my pronounced anti-democratic attitude militates against an appointment at the Berlin Hochschule.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  “Handcuffs for reactionary chaps!” might the musician’s collegium say with Scheidemann.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/></tei:p><tei:p>I value highly your acknowledgment of my cumulative work as a whole and individually.  However, I myself admit that the new material in the second volume of <tei:hi rend="italic">Counterpoint</tei:hi> will have its clear effect only +through+ the third<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> (the next volume), that is the concepts of nodal point,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> interval of a fourth, linear progression of a fourth, seventh<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> as passing tone and as suspension, laws of the passing tone in general, and so forth.  I have to conceptualize patiently and <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> accept all misapprehension and misunderstanding, however it may come.  For nothing is so difficult for people as the view of primordial laws.  Whoever lacks the strength to penetrate to them is incapable of following when someone else resolves a phenomenon into a primordial law.  Alone the contemplation of the individual phenomenon already exhausts their full strength, let alone anything remaining<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> for grasping a primordial law, which remains for them something intellectually alien even though it has a visible residue in the phenomenon.  In all periods, this insufficiency<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> makes itself known no less outside of art. You encounter it in the areas of culture, religion, politics.  People already break down with individual phenomena, but nevertheless develop “ideas,” “utopias”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> that must be false to the same extent!</tei:p><tei:p>And with that I come to the crux of this letter which, taking advantage of these last free days, I resolved to think about somewhat further.  Originally, I had planned to use all the material that I piled up on the table for the purpose.  But I accepted the impossibility and, following the course of your letter, content myself to merely make remarks.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">“Briand”]</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/> When years ago I spoke to Schoenberg—whom I saw often and who virtually loved me<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn15"/>—about Reger, I ran up against inexplicable resistance.  After an hour and a half of the most idle talk back and forth, I developed suspicion and asked:  “Dear Schönberg, what [music] do you actually know of Reger?”  I got the answer, “Nothing, not a note.”  At that point, I gave my displeasure free reign.  Now, Schönberg I am not,—just as I speak about Bruckner [and] Strauss, for example, after I have not only acquired but also closely read and often heard in concerts<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn16"/> their +complete+ works, I operate similarly in every <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> other field.  As<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn17"/> with music, I do not speak before I have envisioned, as it were, the primordial laws.  Even though totally without means, living from hand to mouth, during all the war years I had +home+ subscriptions to no fewer than nine daily newspapers +of all orientations+ (foreign and domestic).  Do you know another on the globe who would have had the boldness for such a monetary sacrifice?  While doing that, I declined out of principle every offer of a fee increase, even from the richest students, in order not to dirty myself with a More-Money mentality which, despite increasing inflation, seemed to me a crime against those struggling on the outside.  Because of a store of so many newspapers that I accumulated—I devoured outside of my home everything that was in any way attainable<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn18"/>—I lost 30 pounds in body weight.  I suffered unspeakably, but did not let up in following the activities of the democrats, social democrats, nationalists, pacifists, internationalists in their newspapers, and in saving the most important records!  (I estimate them at many, many thousand items.)  In the further course of time, I formed sufficient judgment, for example, about our “workers newspaper” (Berliner “Forward”)<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn19"/> in order to remove it from the house<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn20"/> because of its disgusting manner (owing to immaturity), but still today, as I struggle tremendously with life, I subscribe to three large daily papers, from <tei:hi rend="italic">Vienna</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Berlin</tei:hi>, and <tei:hi rend="italic">Frankfurt</tei:hi>, which are of +different+ orientations.  How often did I have to entreat the publisher to help me out<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn21"/> with the exorbitant MK[?]<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn22"/> regarding quarterly orders,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn23"/> and yet do not let up on that conscientiousness!  After all of this, you may certainly assume that it is an inner, not merely a superficial conscientiousness. <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">“Harden”]</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn24"/>  Already during my earliest years, because I had to support mother, sister, younger brother (today the so ungrateful billionaire)<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn25"/> and niece by giving piano lessons, I gladly accepted an offer from a Viennese friend of Harden to write something for him.  They were my very first attempts and I thank Harden for having the courage to publish them, for the multiple effects of the collaboration help in any case to prepare for a better future.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn26"/>  From the first moment, without having understood anything, he showed me boundless, even stirring trust.  However, I could not return that love.  I soon saw that he had mastered no issue independently, consequently is relegated to judge according to unrelated, insubstantial, even foreign viewpoints.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn27"/> “Being different than the others” had to be the reward, subconsciously, that he pursues up to the present.  And then again he was precisely for that reason +just like the others+ who conceal their lack of independence (= insufficiency) from themselves in the same manner.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn28"/>  He scolded the newspaper editors, the underlings as though a daily paper without mundane dirt were even possible—our Karl Kraus is ^just^ as childishly immature—but managed all together differently himself.  Even<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn29"/> with me he did not shy away from frequently<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn30"/> attempting to exert influences depending on how he himself<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn31"/> was influenced.  (But I did not yield.)  He has merely always been a pathetic H. Bahr,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn32"/> went along with everything that smelled of minority, etc.  His “Monarch’s Education,” which got him jail time, had an especially repulsive effect on me.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn33"/>  Not only did I find the essay boorish but above <tei:hi rend="italic">all too cheap</tei:hi>.  If only he had had insight (at close range) into the life of the historically rich, as even I did back then, it would not have occurred to him to seek more “education” than can be achieved according to circumstances generally.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn34"/>   He would have to object to Masaryk,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn35"/> Harding,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn36"/> Ebert,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn37"/> Wilson,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn38"/> etc., with the same authority.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn39"/> The profession, the scope of the dealings draw <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> boundaries which one has the strength to transgress only in the rarest cases.  Such a person does not even have an overview of his own goods, the mundane ones.  A majordomo has to give a daily report that only<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn40"/> bores the owner.  Every chairman depends on “reports,”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn41"/> and it is exactly the same with an emperor, who does not need to know everything, know how to do everything.  It was an awful misuse by Harden—again opportunism—which caused me—pardon the<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn42"/> expression—to give him a kick despite all<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn43"/> necessity.  Additionally there was the comprehension that I could not make myself as understandable to readers as I might have hoped in some other way.  Back then I drafted my theories and I felt the powerful urge to develop them.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">“<tei:hi rend="italic">People's Government</tei:hi>”]</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn44"/>  I will reveal to you that I am planning a little work entitled,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn47"/> perhaps, “Future of Humanity” for the time after the appearance of the fourth volume<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn45"/> and of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Theory of Form</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn46"/>  At that point, the complete work of “Theories and Fantasies”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn48"/> will have provided proof that it is the veritable obligation of a human being who has insight into primordial laws, even if only such of musical type, to speak out on that question.  That he has more authority to do it than the numerous ministers, party-liners, philosophers and poets<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn49"/> who have enjoyed a glimpse of primordial laws is certain.  Could you imagine the enormous preparations that have long since been made.  They would consider it illusion!  Whoever, like me, fulfills and formulates in words the synthesis of the work of genius may attempt such a task with more right than the Rollands,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn50"/> Barbusses,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn51"/> Bernstein,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn52"/> Kautsky,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn53"/> Marx, Engels, Wells,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn54"/> etc., of the world.</tei:p><tei:p>Out of respect for you, whom I know as a man without reproach, I want to make some admissions which, I can say, have followed me since childhood.  I do not want to express them in the language that is typical today for the unclear people, but rather as naturally as possible, the word understood in the most sacred sense of nature. <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>“Anthropomorphic”, “anthropocentric” thinking is an insult to me,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn55"/> humanity’s delusion of grandeur.  The human being sees “sacred peace in nature.” When +he+ alone, having left work, for example, goes on an outing, he thinks nature races along with him.  Poets, too, feel like that, yet I do find it more poetic to bow humbly before the struggle which in nature also races onward during my leisure time.  I, too, the object of nature’s struggle, adapt myself reverently and gratefully, like a new Adam.  In that way I feel happy.</tei:p><tei:p>What people otherwise believe they perceive as “development” and “progress” in every youth I take to be merely the <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">reflex</tei:hi> of bodily growth</tei:hi>.  Let that growth reach a mature stage, and the average person is there, with his<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn56"/> unexceedable limit.  That youth nourishes itself in “progress” is to be attributed to the same illusion that a traveler has when he takes the train.  The landscape stands still, and so too the head stands still while +bodily+ growth +precedes+ intellectual growth.</tei:p><tei:p>The human being smells good only from the brain, but stinks from the bowel.  That is the will of nature, to which genius bows, as does the nitwit.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn57"/>  It is like that in all humanity.  It smells good as individuals, which are its brain and eye, and stinks as a mass.  The horror of today is that the backside has decided no longer to want to be the backside, as though it depended on its defiance and no longer on whether nature installs brain nerves also into the backside, which it will certainly never do to please humankind. (It has its reasons.)  In Viennese, the idiom “I am not into books” is a +prideful+ expression<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn58"/> of a person who devotes himself to the material objects of the world, [but] neither <tei:hi rend="italic">en</tei:hi>dures nor <tei:hi rend="italic">ab</tei:hi>ides consciousness and thinking.  The same goes for <tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> nations: through geographical location, climate, birth, some are “into books,” some are not.</tei:p><tei:p>A nightmarish primordial law is, the human<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn59"/> being feels fine when it alleviates its bowels, holds his nose and scolds, however, when another alleviates his bowels!  The ramifications of this primordial law are the <tei:hi rend="italic">content of <tei:hi rend="italic">all</tei:hi> human conflicts</tei:hi>:  a thieving nation—or ^thieving^ person feels relieved through thievery, but screams “injustice, violence” when another steals.  Everyone wants to commit every injustice<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn60"/> themselves—bowel alleviation—but remains touchy wherever they are supposed to suffer “I only ever see others, and see you only as you <tei:hi rend="italic">want to appear</tei:hi>, but not how you are” (Bonsels<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn61"/>), is nevertheless such a type:  it is futile to help someone relieving himself of the stink of vice such that one construes the relief for the fragrance of the brain.  Conscience, regret, insight cease where such a primitive race exists.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn62"/>  One cannot get around natural law, whatever one’s attitude toward it may be.  In this context, your Briand may be mentioned again.  +After+ alleviating the bowels the Frenchman, too, is “reasonable.”  (By the way, Briand is uneducated in that he spoke of the Council “<tei:hi rend="italic">de trente</tei:hi>” (Trient!?!) in open parliament session, he [the catholic!]<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn63"/> the oft-mentioned Alain speaks <tei:hi rend="italic">first</tei:hi>—bowel alleviation—of “a republic beyond the Rhine,” <tei:hi rend="italic">afterward</tei:hi> he is truly outstanding.  (But does something of that sort have value?)  Voltaire profiteers in grain—bowel alleviation—is otherwise “reasonable” (according to Goethe, “without depth”).  Anatole France,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn64"/> Loti,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn65"/> Claudel,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn66"/> Rolland, Barrés<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn67"/> are all very „reasonable,“ but <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">after</tei:hi></tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn68"/> bowel alleviation.  With Nobel Prize in hand, Anatole France foreswears his former religion, communism.  Claudel indulges in mysteries, but his war baiting?  And Loti’s hate?  The Vice-President of the French League for Human Rights, Professor Basch (Paris)<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn69"/>, says just recently in Berlin and Vienna <tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> that the Germans attacked the French three times within one century, Bonaparte (!!), Napoleon III, and the republic.  What is the meaning of that?  The attacking Frenchman always feels attacked; <tei:hi rend="italic">the attack as bowel alleviation is good for him</tei:hi>, and he does not grasp why the German holds his nose, or, better, should hold his nose.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn70"/></tei:p><tei:p>Since we have deviated from nature, no longer hop around on branches and nourish ourselves on grass and the like, but instead have entered into the <tei:hi rend="italic">artifice of a state</tei:hi>, it is out of the question that humankind can come to terms with it.  If Mozart, Beethoven, were to compose a state according to his feeling for primordial laws, then it would work, but the mass does not even know that it is a matter of an artifice which, as such, needs falsifications, not to mention that in its lack of talent the mass would find means, particularly today, when even negroes proclaim that they want to govern themselves because they, too, can achieve it (!?).<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn71"/>  So long as the human being has the illusion of grandeur even to create God according to his image, to disavow Him when He fails to help in bringing about a good, comfortable life (religion works because of gastronomic festivals), when he demands immortality<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn72"/> because it is unbearable for him to think that he<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn73"/> could at some point meet his end, and whatever other manifestations there are of illusions of grandeur, once again not to find the path<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn74"/> to a state, for the state means artifice, thus coercion<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn75"/> and falsification.</tei:p><tei:p>On top of that comes the fact that every person +must+ somehow cheat.  The necessity for it also resides in the fabric<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn76"/>  The most honorable big-time merchants have assured me:  „I cheat in business, but outside of business I never lie.“  To imagine a world of Spinozas is disallowed, but even one Wilson among millions of Spinozas would sully and detonate the federation.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn77"/>  It will not work because nature simply will not have it that way.  It has laid <tei:hi rend="bold">{9}</tei:hi> snares for the human body, for its organs, on account of which it will founder sooner or later.  So too<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn78"/> for the body of humankind.</tei:p><tei:p>Am I therefore pessimistic?  Certainly not.  On the contrary.  I love and honor the will of nature to my dying day.  I believe only in the selection of nature and not in a selection defying nature on a democratic basis.  I thank God that He endowed my most beloved parents with the piety<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn79"/> to produce twelve children<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn80"/> and to sustain them under all adversity.  If out of lack of youth<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn81"/> my father had followed the ideas of a very famous scholar (whom I knew well myself), a friend of E. Mach,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn82"/> a great explorer and kindhearted man, who, descending from Voltaire and Marx, demanded that the standpoint of killing children for the sake of the living be also justified<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn83"/>—I would not be alive<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn84"/> since I was one of the middle children, and would thus have remained a piece of refuse that does not even merit life.  Where one ends up only with sympanthy that surely +must+ mutate, on the other hand, into the most disgust-evoking <tei:hi rend="italic">barbarity</tei:hi>!  (We all of us already know today that the proletariat knows no sympathy and so does not deserve the sympathy that would have been granted to it yesterday.  A matter of bowel alleviation.)  And I understand my one-time life as the immortality of the matter.  I feel the necessity not in order to salvage eternity for the eternal; I feel „immortal“ in the span of time, as a part of the eternal and nothing other than the worm, bird, fish, which likewise are wonders.</tei:p><tei:p>The human being is, then, not bad, not good, just inadequate for the artistic task, and suffering from delusions of grandeur before God, nature, and before eternity.  Despite Copernicus, he will not give up his anthropocentric thinking and is proud of it, as of tuberculosis.  He presumes to wrest from nature its chief weapon, <tei:hi rend="bold">{10}</tei:hi> death, or if death simply must be, he prefers to assign it to another rather than to himself.  The latter state of affairs must ^also^ remain: him +or+ me! (He +and+ I is already [an example of] synthesis, and that is not even achieved with pairs—marriage, friendship—not to mention with millions).<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn85"/>  If I also defend art with my life, however, then I have all cause not to yield to someone who does not have such a task.</tei:p><tei:p>I am not capable of distinguishing between folk and government.  Is Ebert no longer „folk“ since he is presiding,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn86"/> and does he become „folk“ again when he steps down from office?  And in a state in which all co-govern, as voters, parliamentarians, civil servants, etc., would there be just one government?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn87"/>  But where is, then, this ^“folk“^?  Herein lies an error.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn88"/>  Every government <tei:hi rend="italic">disappoints</tei:hi>, tyrant, oligarch, emperor, president,—every government must surely also <tei:hi rend="italic">betray</tei:hi>, just as [does] the individual person, it is in the nature of things!—thus people at first seek to rescue the illusion of happiness by +opposing+ „folk“ and „government.“<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn89"/></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">„Things French“]</tei:hi>  Consequently, in France, I do not even trust folk, and government.  The folk itself is petty, crude, not very talented (because exceedingly<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn90"/> vain).  There, the act is +always+ a—bowel alleviation, only their word [<tei:hi rend="italic">merde</tei:hi>] flits over it more felicitously.  Even „<tei:hi rend="italic">the</tei:hi> method from Frankfurt“—with that I mean the Frankfurt newspaper as opposed to Schopenhauer<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn91"/>—knows of its „decidedly petty bourgeois spirit, which has found its perfected reduction in the little retiree.“  Such humus is not worth much, and I praise the German joy in work: the +diligence+ of the German merchant, of the working man, is actually the <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">same</tei:hi></tei:hi> kind which proved itself as „creation“ in the German genius!  The western nations carry on commerce as though they were working.  They mock German diligence, which is perhaps an indicator of genius.  Not just revision of the <tei:hi rend="bold">{11}</tei:hi> Versailles „Treaty“<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn92"/> of the western nations in general would be necessary.  World history, too, is incorrectly written, not only music history.  The famous philologian H. Schuchardt thought, „What use was it to us and others that we spoke to them in +their+ language?  In order for them to acquaint themselves with us, +they+ have to learn our language.“  But the Frenchman is not capable of it, and consequently communication will never succeed, at most that the German, charmed, offers his nose to every bowel alleviation (for theft of the Rhine, of Upper Silesia, etc.)!  If we ^also^ wanted to provide an example with our better conduct, it would not help, for the Frenchman <tei:hi rend="italic">feels he is in the right</tei:hi> (see above, Basch)<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn93"/>.   That is at the same time the tragic sense of the oft-mentioned bowel alleviation.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">„higher plane“]</tei:hi>  G. Mahler raved on behalf of something like that (of which he himself was the „star,“ the peak.  Lenin, too, raved about the plane for the same reason.)   But assuredly, had I not, for example, heard d'Andrade<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn94"/> as „Don Juan,“ I would never have considered such perfection of Mozart even achievable, despite Mahler!  And just as the playwright pays attention only to the highest points of a human life, the painter to those of nature, so in everything I too pay attention to the highest possibilities, which alone exhibit the status of art.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn95"/>  And when, with so much [higher] plane, France<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn96"/> lays claim to „moral <tei:hi rend="italic">leadership</tei:hi>“ (Cailleux<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn97"/>), not to speak of intellectual leadership, I would not know why Germany with such peaks should place itself beneath the French plane.  Mr. Basch counters:  „Rabelais, Descartes, Molière, Racine, Voltaire, V. Hugo, Pasteur, Bergson,  and Kant, Hegel, Goethe, Schiller, Mozart, Beethoven, Nietzsche and Einstein,“ truly one would have to be an O.E. Curtius<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn98"/> or Hofmüller<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn99"/> (who prior to Goethe were capable of accepting the appreciation of French-hood but never his dissociation from it), <tei:hi rend="bold">{12}</tei:hi> would have to be him, in order not to ^see^ what one can ^formally^ put in motion.  By the way, if one were also to think like the German democrats, over there the „originals,“ here (by the Germans) merely the „deepen-ers“—fine experts on genius, eh?—what use would that be?  How often, then, should Germany pay for France’s „superiority,“ with territory, with human beings?  Hasn’t enough remuneration been paid already?  (Should I be paid two, three, four times for +one+ lesson?)  How long, how often yet should this relationship last, recur?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn100"/></tei:p><tei:p>He +or+ I want nature! (The Frenchman feels it, the German does not.)<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn101"/>  International?  Supernational?  As resolution?  If there were once again a general bond, as once in literature, in the world of Latin, then it might work for a <tei:hi rend="italic">while, perhaps</tei:hi>.  To the benefit of the idea completely extinguished.  Germany would then simply no longer be there as a nation, but consequently +not+ then the international there!</tei:p><tei:p>I recall a little picture in the „fliers“, the Animal Lover.  A wholly good little male was standing there and was of smallest +joy+ about a — flea visitation on his back.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn102"/>  Germany was and remains such an animal lover; it grins joyously about the visitation of bugs, fleas, etc., as though God’s word (<tei:hi rend="italic">Genesis</tei:hi> 1:28), „And fill the earth and subdue it“<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn103"/> were directed at these little animals and not at humanity.  (A nation of 70 million so cowardly, so pitiable!).<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn104"/></tei:p><tei:p>Thus I have to retract nothing, as must the democrats, pacifists, those in congress for social politics, indeed even the independents today.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn105"/></tei:p><tei:p>I am enclosing for you three essays by <tei:hi rend="italic">Nitti</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn106"/> who is not a „Germaniac,“ not a „Pan-German,“ not folkish.  They may otherwise scarcely be available to you.  And you should account to my credit that with them I rouse you from tranquility.  I mean it for the good, and +without+ converting you.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn107"/></tei:p><tei:p>Now warm greetings and wishes for fall and winter,
Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H. Schenker</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>