<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:DLA 69.930/9 : 1-18-20 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain; published with the permission of the Deutsches Literaturarchiv, March 2006.
© Transcription Ian D. Bent and Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Translation Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Lee Rothfarb 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>August Halm (1920-19??)—Deutsches Literaturarchiv(19??-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain, published with the kind permission of the Deutsches Literaturarchiv; Image: Deutsches Literaturarchiv; Transcription Ian D. Bent and Lee Rothfarb, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary Lee Rothfarb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 01/18/1920 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Halm ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Halm, dated January 18, 1920</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-04-18</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Acks OJ 11/35, 14 and 15, thanking H for the opportunity to see the two contracts, now enclosed.  S has been exploited by UE regarding LfS 101 and "The Little Library," and must now protect himself and extract better working conditions.  —Kontrapunkt2 will show the world that his Semper idem motto applies at every level from strict counterpoint through to free composition.  In a musical garden of Eden of genius, the rest of the world behaves like Adam and Eve. — Congratulates H on his successes and thanks him for his support.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Halm, August;  contracts; UE; exploitation; sacrifice; honoraria; dollar; Kroner; Mark; LfS 101; Erläuterungsausgabe; Kleine Bibliothek; Little Library; Der Tonwille; NMTP II/2; Kontrapunkt2; Counterpoint2; strict counterpoint; free composition; Eden, Garden of; Urgesetzte; promordial laws; piano lessons; working conditions; Furtwängler, Wilhelm; Vienna</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Halm, dated January 18, 1920</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Veehrter, lieber Herr Professor !</tei:p><tei:p>Vielen, vielen Dank für Ihren lieben Briefe u. die beiden Beilagen (die ich hier gleichzeitig beischließe).<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  i.e. OJ 11/35, 14 and 15, January 5 and 11, 1920.  The enclosures were two publishers’ contracts, for which H asked for return soon and by registered mail.   A large part of this letter is transcribed in Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker: Nach Tagüchern und Briefen</tei:hi>, pp.141–42.</tei:note>  Es war ein glücklicher Gedanke von Ihnen, die <tei:hi rend="italic">Original</tei:hi>-Dokumente beizulegen. Schon die optische Erfahrung war mir von Nutzen u. mußte es mir sein, wenn Sie bedenken, daß ich zeitlebens auf die Gegenleistung des Verlegers fast gar kein u. nur auf meine eigen[e] Leistung Gericht langte.  Ich wußte genau, daß der Verleger<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  i.e. UE.</tei:note> mich ausnützt, nicht etwa, daß er mich für einen jener Prostituierten des Intellekts gehalten hätte, die sich um jeden Preis gedruckt sehen wollen, sondern er hatte es sofort heraus, daß meine Opferfreudigkeit ihm Gelegenheit gebe, seine Vorteile überbestens zu wahren.  Und ich wieder gönnte ihm diese Kapitalistische Onanie, weil ich nur Eines wußte u. mußte, so gut als es noch geht, das <tei:hi rend="italic">Material</tei:hi> der Tonkunst, das Handwerk, die Stimmführung – im allerletzten Augenblick – zu retten.  Und auch noch heute suche ich keinen Vorteil, nur muß ich ^mich^ dagegen wahren, daß der auf der Basi[s] der Geldgier sich ins infinitum verlierende Verleger meine Arbeit schädige, wenn er sie schon nicht fördert.  Was sind ihm alle meine Pläne u. Arbeiten, die da noch ausge- <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> führt werden sollen, was meine Gesundheit als Voraussetzung einer Arbeitsmöglichkeit überhaupt, wenn er darüber den Genuß verlieren müßte<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  “verlieren müßte den Genuß” then marked for inversion.</tei:note>, für eine vorliegende Arbeit blos z.B. 1000, 1200 K bezahlen zu können.   So muß ich ^dann^ selbst das Kapital besser vertreten, als der Kapitalist es tut, u. um dem Verleger Zinsen u. Zinseszinsen einzutragen, muß ich, gegen seine eigene Unfähigkeit kämpfend, bessere Arbeitsbedingungen ertrotzen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  „working conditions“: S is speaking of his own circumstances, particularly the need to take on so many private piano students in order to sustain himself and his wife.  He has been pleading for more than a decade for a government subsidy, so that he could reduce the number of students and devote more time to his editing and theoretical work—a desire that he expresses below, on p.5.</tei:note> zumal heute, wo als in einer Epoche der <tei:hi rend="italic">Welteselei</tei:hi> bezeichnenderweise nur mehr der <tei:hi rend="italic">amerikanische</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Dollar</tei:hi> gilt, u. keine Krone, keine Mark mehr daneben.</tei:p><tei:p>Nun, für op.101, habe ich mich mit 15000 K (etwa = 5.000 MK) beschieden, daß der Verleger darauf eingegangen ist, hat sich nachträglich als eine Finte, als ein Köder erwiesen, denn an der „Kl. Bibl.“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  “Kleine Bibliothek”: one of the titles given by Schenker between c.1913 and 1921 for what became <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</tei:hi>; in fact the former appears as the title of the latter on the contract and was changed only at the last minute.</tei:note> gedachte er sich, sein kapitalistisches „Entgegenkommen“ abzubauen.  Aber auch auf 600 K per Bogen der „Kl. B.“ (bis 5000 <tei:hi rend="italic">Ex.</tei:hi>, dann noch einmal 600 K) wäre ich um der Sache willen schließlich eingegangen, wenn ich nicht Ursache gehabt hätte, mich als Ausbeutungsobjekt des Verlegers besser zu schützen.  Was hat denn der Zinsen<tei:hi rend="italic">fex</tei:hi> von einem Krank gewordenen Autor ?  Und so ist es -daxxx- ^in^ der geistigen Welt denn doch nicht, wie in der ungeistigen, wo der abtretende Eine durch einen beliebig Anderen ersetzt werden kann.  Die Angelegenheit ist noch nicht geordnet.  Der Verleger hat das Wort.</tei:p><tei:p>Was Sie zum Inhalt der „Kl. Bibl.“ äußern, hat mich tief bewegt.  Mir selbst ist, wie ich schon geschrieben zu haben glau- <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> be, das Wichtigste der II^2^-Halbband,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  i.e. <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt</tei:hi>, second half-volume (Vienna: UE, 1922).</tei:note> worin die Stimmführung des freien Satzes und ihrer <tei:hi rend="italic">völligen</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Identität</tei:hi> mit der des sog. strengen befunden und nachgewiesen wird.  „<tei:hi rend="italic">Semper idem, sed non eodem modo</tei:hi>“,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  “always the same but not in the same way,” Schenker’s motto, which appears on the title-pages of <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</tei:hi> and <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi>, among other places.  </tei:note> leuchtet in jeden Abschnitt hinein: dieselbe Mottofackel vom 3-stimmig[en] ^str.^ Satz ^ab^ über den 4- u. mehrstimmigen, über Mischungsgattungen zum freien Satz und hier wieder vor den Abschnitten über Stufen, Auskomponierung, Stimmführung, 5–5 bz. 8–8 Folgen, Durchgang, Synkope, Klaviersatz u. Abbreviationen, Generalbaß, Choral, u.s.w.  Lediglich um dieses Nachweises willen halte ich ja ein druckfertiges Material vom Umfang eines Bandes schon seit Jahren zurück;  denn, was ich von keinem Argument erwarte, erwarte ich von der rein äußerlichen Wirkung des Beisammenseins vom strengen u. freien Satz im Raume desselben Bandes.  Ihren <tei:hi rend="italic">Augen</tei:hi> werden es die Leser eher glauben, u. Alles ist gewonnen, wenn die Musiker ^mit mir^ zu den „Urmüttern“ hinabsteigen u. dort eine ewige, unzerstörtere Einheit erfahren, in deren Namen sie werden aufhören müssen, die Welten des str. u. fr. Satzes einander entgegenzustellen, von Regeln und Ausnahmen zu sprechen . . .</tei:p><tei:p>Nur aus dem Gefühl -scho- solcher Einheit schöpfen die Genies die Unendlichkeit u. Mannigfaltigkeit im Individuellen: Aber die übrige Welt?  Dieser muss auch das Individuelle sich verschliessen, wenn sie nicht irgendwie, u. sei es noch so leise, an das <tei:hi rend="italic">Mysterium</tei:hi> der Urgesetze anklopft.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Die Analysen waren u. sind mir, wie Sie daher begreifen, blos <tei:hi rend="italic">Beispiele</tei:hi> aus jenem Paradies der Einheit.  Und mit Ihnen teile ich im Innersten eine gewisse Unlust, die Musiker zu viel vom Baume der Erkenntnis essen zu lassen;  zumindest das Paradies der Kunst bleibe uns noch lange ein Paradies, wenn uns ein anderes verlorengegangen.  Bedenke ich aber, daß am Untergange unserer Kunst nichts so Schuld trägt, als das <tei:hi rend="italic">allzu</tei:hi> Adam- u. Eva-hafte der Menschheit, die sich im Eden unserer Größten gut gehen ließ, als der <tei:hi rend="italic">Bruch</tei:hi> im <tei:hi rend="italic">Musikorgan</tei:hi>, der die Einheit von Vertikalem u. Horizontalem nicht mehr aufkommen läßt, so drängt es mich unwillkürlich, mit noch, noch einem Beispiel nachzuhelfen . . . .   Wie glücklich könnte die Menschheit sich ausleben u. ihr Gottes-Ebenbildhaftes austragen, wenn sie nur von der Kontinuität der Geschlechter als einem so naheliegenden Analogon, das sie selbst absolviert, auf eine ähnliche Kontinuität im Geistigen ^zu^schließen wüßte, statt die Ewigkeit der Urgesetze mit der rastlosen Sucht nach neuen Anfängen zu beleidigen als angeblich Quellen neuer Urgesetze.  Noch gäbe es in der Welt unserer Genies Platz genug für tausend anderer, aber nein!, er findet die Kraft zum <tei:hi rend="italic">Anschluß</tei:hi> nicht.</tei:p><tei:p>Eine Musikgeschichte müßte vor Allem ja eben die <tei:hi rend="italic">Einheit</tei:hi> auch in den Genies aufzeigen;  sie zu schreiben, setzt aber voraus, daß die Einheit schon in den Urgesetzen, im Material vorerst nachge- <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> wiesen würde.  Die Voraussetzung zu erledigen, ist, wie Sie sehen, nun mein heißestes Bestreben, u. daß ich gerne dann auch das Schicksal der Urgesetze, wie es von den Künstlern im Laufe der Jahrhunderte erlebt wurde, darstellen möchte, wollen Sie mir glauben.  Wird mir das aber beschieden sein, in einer Welt, die nicht einmal mehr in den einfachsten Dingen sich zulänglich erweist, u. in eine zweite „ägyptische“ Finsternis geraten ist, gegen die die erste, reinste Sommerhelle gewesen?</tei:p><tei:p>Wäre ich nur von Stunden frei, ich getraute mir Alles zu !  Das Tragische ist ja, daß die Möglichkeit, ein blos der Arbeit gewidmetes Leben zu führen, an sich gegeben ist, sogar bis zu einem gewissen Grade <tei:hi rend="italic">leicht</tei:hi> gegeben ist, daß dennoch aber diejenigen versagen, die ^durch^ Gründe der Vernunft, des Anstandes, auch des Blutes <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> sich zu dem für sie mühelosen Geschäft wohl müßten bestimmen lassen.</tei:p><tei:p>Wir wollen sehen.</tei:p><tei:p>An Ihren Erfolgen nehme ich freudigsten Anteil.  Das Reine Ihrer Bestrebungen muß doch wohl Jedem, auch einem „sachlichen“ Gegner, – wüßte ein solcher nur ^aber^, wie gerade die Sachlichkeit für Sie spricht – Respekt abnötigen.  Mit Freuden hörte ich die Respektbezeugung von seiten Furtwänglers, der so oft in <tei:hi rend="italic">Wien</tei:hi> einkehrt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  „Mit ... hörte“ and “Respektbeugen ... eingekehrt“ underlined heavily in crayon.  Wilhelm Furtwängler [create biogfile and link].</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Nun sei Ihnen zum Beschlusse nochmals mein bester Dank für Ihre schöne Gesinnung ausgedrückt, ...[?] füge ich meine</tei:p><tei:p>herzlichsten Grüße
Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H Schenker
18. Jänner 1920</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Halm, dated January 18, 1920</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor!</tei:p><tei:p>Many, many thanks for your lovely letter and for the two enclosures (which I include here).<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  It was a fortunate idea of yours to enclose the original documents.  The visual experience in itself was useful to me and had to be if you consider that in my entire life I have achieved almost no justice in reciprocation from the publisher, and only on my own efforts.  I knew precisely that the publisher<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> was exploiting me, not that he would have taken me for one of those intellectuals who prostitute themselves, who want to see themselves in print at any price.  Rather, he figured out immediately that my willingness to be a victim would give him the opportunity optimally to guarantee his advantages.  And again I granted him this capitalistic onanism because I knew only one thing, and in the very last moment had to rescue the <tei:hi rend="italic">material</tei:hi> of music, the craftsmanship, the voice leading as much as was still possible.  And still today I seek no advantage.  But I must protect myself against the publisher (losing himself without end) damaging my work on the basis of greed if he does not promote it.  to To him, what are all my plans and projects that <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> ought to be carried out yet, what my health as the precondition for the possibility of work in general, if on account of it he loses pleasure<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> in being able to pay, for example, 1,000, 1,200 Kroner for a work at hand.  I ^therefore^ have to act myself on behalf of the capital, as does the capitalist, and in order to bring in interest and compound interest for the publisher, fighting against his incompetence, I have defiantly to extract better work conditions,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> particularly today, when in an era of <tei:hi rend="italic">world foolishness</tei:hi> only the <tei:hi rend="italic">American</tei:hi> dollar counts, no longer the Kroner, the Mark alongside of it.</tei:p><tei:p>So, for Op. 101 I satisfied myself with 15,000 Kroner (approximately 5,000 Marks).  That the publisher agreed to it turned out retrospectively to be a ruse, bait.  For with the “Little Library”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> he planned to reduce his capitalistic “accommodation.”  But even at 600 Kroner per sheet of the “Little Library (up to 5,000 copies, and then again 600 Kronen) I would have agreed in the end for the sake of the project, had I no reason to better protect myself as an object of the publisher’s exploitation.  What use is an author become ill to someone obsessed with interest?  And so it is -xxxx- ^in^ the intellectual world, for certainly not, as in the non-intellectual one, where one who withdraws can be replaced arbitrarily by another.  The matter is not yet arranged.  The publisher has the say.</tei:p><tei:p>What you say about the content of the “Little Library” stirred me deeply.  As I believe I have already written, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> the most important thing is the II/2 half-volume<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> in which the voice leading of free composition and its <tei:hi rend="italic">complete identity</tei:hi> with so-called strict counterpoint is discovered and demonstrated.  „<tei:hi rend="italic">Semper idem, sed non eodem modo</tei:hi>“<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> illuminates every section.  That same motto [applies] to three-voice ^strict^ counterpoint, through four and multi-voice counterpoint, through mixed species to free composition, and again in the sections on scale-steps, composing-out, voice leading, parallel fifths and octaves, passing tone, suspension, keyboard settings and reductions, figured bass, chorale, and so forth.  Solely for the sake of that verification have I held back for years material ready for publication in the scope of a book; for what I anticipate from no argument, I anticipate from the purely superficial effect of the juxtaposition of strict and free composition in the same volume.  Readers will sooner believe their <tei:hi rend="italic">eyes</tei:hi>, and all is won if musicians penetrate with me to the “primordial sources” and encounter an eternal, more indestructible unity in whose name they will have to cease setting the worlds of strict and free composition in opposition to one another, and speaking of rules and exceptions.</tei:p><tei:p>Only from the feeling of such unity do geniuses create the endlessness and diversity in the individual.  But the rest of the world?  From it, the individual must also close itself off if it [the world] does not somehow knock, if ever so gently, at the door of the mystery of primordial laws. <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Consequently, as you understand, analyses were and are for me merely <tei:hi rend="italic">examples</tei:hi> from that paradise of unity.  And with you I share most intimately a certain disinclination to allow musicians to eat too much from the tree of knowledge.  At least the paradise of art would long remain for us a paradise once another has been lost to us.  However, when I consider that nothing bears guilt for the decline of our art as much as the <tei:hi rend="italic">all too</tei:hi> Adam-and-Eve-like mentality of humanity, which fared well in the Eden of our greatest masters, as the <tei:hi rend="italic">breach</tei:hi> in the <tei:hi rend="italic">organ for music</tei:hi> that no longer permitted the unity of the vertical and horizontal to emerge, then I am involuntarily driven to assist with another and yet another example....  How blissfully could humanity live out its life and carry out the aspect of its divine image if it only knew how to draw the immediate analogy, fashioned by humanity itself, between the continuity of the races and a similar continuity in the intellectual dimension, instead of offending the eternity of primordial laws with the restless search for new starting points as ostensible sources of new primordial laws.  There would still be room enough in the world of our geniuses for a thousand others, but no!  He does not find the strength for <tei:hi rend="italic">contact</tei:hi>.</tei:p><tei:p>A history of music would above all have to show precisely the unity in the geniuses.  However, to write it presupposes that the <tei:hi rend="italic">unity</tei:hi> has first been verified <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> in the primordial laws, in the material.  The requirement to be fulfilled is, as you see, my most fervent aspiration, and you should believe that I would gladly like to show the destiny of the laws as it was experienced by artists over the course of the centuries.  However, will that be granted to me in a world that no longer even proves itself adequate in the simplest things, and is plunged into a second “Egyptian” darkness against which the first one was the clearest brightness of summer?</tei:p><tei:p>If I were only free from giving lessons, I would attempt anything!  The tragic thing is that the possibility of leading a life devoted solely to work actually exists, to a certain degree exists <tei:hi rend="italic">easily</tei:hi>, but that nevertheless those fail who because of reason, of integrity, also of bloodline <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> would surely have to allow themselves to be chosen for the, for them, effortless business.</tei:p><tei:p>We will see.</tei:p><tei:p>I share most joyfully in your successes.  The purity of your efforts must command respect from anyone, even from an “objective” opponent—^though^ if only such knew how objectivity speaks in your favor.  I happily read of the expressions of respect from Furtwängler, who so often comes to Vienna.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/></tei:p><tei:p>Once again, in closing let me express my sincere thanks for your wonderful attitude [and] add</tei:p><tei:p>My hearty greetings,
Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H. Schenker</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>