<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:DLA 69.930/3 : 2-7-18 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Translation Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>August Halm (1918-19??) - -Deutsches Literaturarchiv(19??-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain, published with the kind permission of the Deutsches Literaturarchiv; Image: Deutsches Literaturarchiv; Transcription Ian Bent and Lee Rothfarb, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary Lee Rothfarb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 02/07/1918 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Halm ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Halm, dated February 7, 1918</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-06-017</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Writes scathingly of UE's business practices; describes his counter-tactics, and his experiences over Niloff, Instrumentations-Tabelle.  He will read all of H's writings and asks for a reading-list.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Halm, August;  Universal Edition;  UE;  Hertzka, Emil;  business practices;  Kleine Bibliothek;  Little Library;  Hercules;  Niloff, Artur;  Instrumentations-Tabelle;  Instrumentation Table;  Bach, J. S.;  Harmonielehre;  Kontrapunkt;  New Austria;  Bruckner;  Von zwei Kulturen;  Volk;  Kant</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Halm, February 7, 1918</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Professor !</tei:p><tei:p>So peinlich es mir war, Sie auf meine Antwort<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  i.e. to OJ 11/35, 7, January 20 1918.</tei:note> bis heute warten zu lassen, so lohnend anderseits erwies ^sich^ mein Verfahren wider den Verleger u. das Resultat!  Es hat mich nämlich empört, daß er auch an Ihnen die Gemeinheit des Nichtantwortens verübte, wo er Ihnen ^gegenüber^ doch auch schon nach <tei:hi rend="italic">seinen</tei:hi> Begriffen Anerkennung zum Ausdruck hätte bringen sollen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  S is talking of UE here.  He sends a postcard to Hertzka on July 8, 1917 (WSLB 288) asking him to send Halm copies of his "Beethoven editions" for review in "his journal (Jena: Diederich)"; refers to Halm again on November 30 and December 6 (WSLB 290, 291); writes a letter on January 30, 1918 (WSLB 292) saying that Halm has written to UE requesting the Beethoven volumes but has received nothing, and asking that copies of <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie</tei:hi>, the keyboard works of C. P. E. Bach, the second edition of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Beitrag zur Ornamentik</tei:hi>, the arrangements of Handel organ concertos, and the Niloff, <tei:hi rend="italic">Instrumentations-Tabelle</tei:hi> be sent to Halm; and a postcard to UE on February 5. The language of these communications reflects S's remarks in the current letter.  Postcards from Hertzka to S exist for July 12, September 4, December 5, 1917, and February 5, 1918 (OC 52/ 200, 407, 202, 203).  No parallel correspondence with Cotta exists for this period of time (cf. remark in DLA 69.930/1, July 18, 1917).</tei:note>  Freilich konnte nur ich allein wissen, weshalb diesmal der Verleger scheinbar gar so unkaufmännisch, so wenig auf Rezension ??gicht[?] sich verhielt : nachdem er an recht vielen Bespielen bemerkt hat, daß ich <tei:hi rend="italic">durch ihn</tei:hi> auf meine eigene Rechnung (freilich etwas reduzierte) dies oder jenes von mir schicken lasse - ihm gegenüber halte ich mich <tei:hi rend="italic">so unabhängig</tei:hi>, daß ich Geschenke bezw. Gegengeschenke an <tei:hi rend="italic">Nicht</tei:hi>musiker eben selbst bezahle, statt ^hin^, was sonst üblich ist, einfach wie Rezensionsexemplare zu fordern -, dachte er bei sich, am Ende würde ich selbst auch die Kosten der Rez ex. an Sie auf mich nehmen, was ihm nun doppelten Vorteil (meiner u. Ihrerseits) eingebracht hätte.  Sie können sich denken, daß ein Kopf, wie der eines solchen Verlegers, außerstande ist zu begreifen, daß für unsereinen gar keine besondere Röntgenisierungskraft dazu gehört, sein Nutzenseelchen zu durchleuchten;  er kanns nicht fassen, daß ich seine Schlauheit zunächst doch <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> als Frucht einer bloßen Unfähigkeit erkenne, zwischen einem Ihnen vor allem zukommenden Rezensionsexemplar u. einem Gegengeschenk an einen <tei:hi rend="italic">Nicht</tei:hi>musikalischen zu unterscheiden. 
 
Um nun die Gemeinheit <tei:hi rend="italic">ad absurdum</tei:hi> zu führen u. zu strafen, griff ich sofort nach Erhalt Ihres l. Schreibens ein,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  probably OJ 11/35, 7, January 20, 1917.</tei:note> indem ich dem Verleger ein Briefchen schrieb.  Der arme Tropf hat aber auch dieses <tei:hi rend="italic">nicht</tei:hi> beantwortet, was ich schon zum voraus wissen konnte.  So habe ich dann endlich den Käfer, der sich todt stellen wollte, plötzlich anders gepackt u. ihn lebendig gemacht : ich schrieb ihm eine <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">recom.</tei:hi></tei:hi> Karte, so in meiner Art („ich vermisse u.s.w."), u. auf diesen derberen Griff hin lockerte sich sein Gehirn . .  Heute erhalte ich von ihm die Mitteilung, daß er an Sie alle meine anderen Arbeiten geschickt hat.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Postal receipt for return-receipt postcard from S: OC 52/204, February 5, 1918;  Hertzka to S: OC 52/203, February 5, 1918.</tei:note>  (Nebenbei will er von Ihnen einen Brief <tei:hi rend="italic">überhaupt nicht</tei:hi> erhalten haben (!! Lüge), der meinige soll ihn angeblich unrecht (!) u. auch "überbürdet" ^angetroffen haben^ .u. was[?] derlei Verlegeridiotismen mehr sind[?].  Das Ergötzlichste aber an der ganzen Sache ist, daß er zu mir im Ganzen eine <tei:hi rend="italic">sog.</tei:hi> gute Beziehung unterhält, u. mir sogar wegen der „Kl. Bibl."<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  "Kleine Bibliothek", i.e. what eventually became <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</tei:hi> (1921-24).</tei:note> ein Jahres<tei:hi rend="italic">anbot</tei:hi> machte!  Schade nur, daß das Herausoperieren von solchem kleinen "Nutz"forumkerle[?] kostbarste Zeit vergeudet!  Neugierig wäre ich, wie der selige Herakles mit - Verlegern fertig geworden wäre!  Ich  schwimme für die <tei:hi rend="italic">Keule</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>Zur Sendung selbst habe ich nur zu bemerken, daß H. Niloff,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="instrumentations-tab"><tei:hi rend="italic">Instrumentations-Tabelle</tei:hi></ref>.</tei:note> d.h. <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> ich selbst, diese Kleinigkeit aus Erbarmen für seine Schüler u. für die Kritiker der <tei:hi rend="italic">Tageszeitungen</tei:hi> in <tei:hi rend="italic">Wien</tei:hi>, vor vielen, vielen Jahren verfertigt hat, die - ich habe es selbst erlebt ! - <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">engl.</tei:hi></tei:hi> tirner[?] auch ^also^ „gestopft[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>]" in ihren Referaten bewendet haben, <tei:hi rend="italic">S. Bach</tei:hi>'s Klarinetten in alle Himmel hoben.  Zum Überfluß schenkte ich diese Kleinigkeit dem Verleger buchstäblich u. bedang mir nur aus, daß sie <tei:hi rend="italic">nicht teuerer</tei:hi> als mit 1 Kr. 20 verkauft werde.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  S prescribed a figure of 1.20 Kroner in dealings with Doblinger (presumably the recipient of the largesse referred to here), in a conversation on September 13, 1906 (diary, OJ 1/5, p.19), stipulating that he receive gratis scores of Mahler and Bruckner in return.  Nothing came of this negotiation.  UE's contract for Niloff  lays down that: "The <tei:hi rend="italic">Table</tei:hi> shall not have a shop price of more than 1.- Mk." (OC 52/421, June 30, 1908); but later, when S sought to expand the work and Hertzka resisted on cost grounds, S replied: "I do not think it immoderate of me to contend that this <tei:hi rend="italic">opus</tei:hi> ought now clearly to be sold for 80 Kroner, perhaps even for 1 Florin" (WSLB 29, December 16, 1908).</tei:note>  Sie wurde mehrfach übersetzt - mit der <tei:hi rend="italic">Harm.</tei:hi> u. <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrap.</tei:hi>lehre wird es wohl kaum hergehen -, in mehreren Aufl. ausgegeben.</tei:p><tei:p>Auf das, was ich in den Beilagen zum Heft der Zeitschrift gefunden, komme ich, bis ich nur II^2^ endgiltig abgeschlossen habe, noch zurück.  Das Heft des „Neuen <tei:hi rend="italic">Österr.</tei:hi>", von dem nur übrigens vorgestern ein Schüler von mir selbst erzählte, habe ich bestellt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Eberhard Freib. von Waechter, "Von Moderner Musik, modernen Musikern und moderner Musikkritik," <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Neue Österreich</tei:hi>, Heft 1, preserved in S's scrapbook, OC 2/p.54.</tei:note>  Von Ihnen besitze ich schon seit Langem, wie ich es schon geschrieben zu haben glaube, das Buch über Bruckner („Zwischen zwei Kulturen"<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  H's <tei:hi rend="italic">Von Zwei Kulturen der Musik</tei:hi> (Munich: Georg Müller, 1913) is <tei:hi rend="italic">not</tei:hi> a book about Bruckner; its two main sections are entitled "Concerning Form" (fugal form and its relationship to sonata form;  the spirit of sonata form) and "Concerning Language and Style" (rhythm and dynamics; symmetry; the art of thematicism), and much of the music discusses is drawn from J. S. Bach, Handel, Mozart, and Beethoven.</tei:note>), habe Sie sonst immer eifrig gelesen, was ich Sie nur fand.  Sie würden mich sehr verbinden, wenn Sie mir mit 2 Zeilen - schonen Sie bitte Ihre Zeit!  - zur Kenntnis brächten, auf  welche Arbeiten Sie selbst Wert legen u. ich schaffe Sie mir an, denn daß Sie Kosten tragen, wäre mir ein peinlicher Gedanke.</tei:p><tei:p>Bezüglich des „Volks"<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Topic raised by S in DLA 69.930/2, January 17, 1918, and referred to by H in OJ 11/35, 7, January 20, 1918, in connection with Kant.</tei:note> nur dieses : jedem Schüler gegenüber verfahre ich so, als wäre er zu höchstem, künstlerisch u. menschlich, berufen.  An mir selbst spare ich also durchaus nicht, u. so mündet <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> dieses Verfahren doch auch in den Gedanken Kant's, den Sie zitieren.  Gewissermaßen ist das „praktische Vernunft", - sie hebt aber die „reine" nicht auf, und vor dieser besteht das „Volk" mir leider in einem anderen, viel schlechteren Sinne, als man es heute auch nur ahnt, wobei ich unter Volk oben und unten der „Stände" verstehe.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit besten Grüßen an Sie
Ihr ergebener
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">H Schenker</tei:hi>
7. Februar 1918</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Halm, February 7, 1918</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor,</tei:p><tei:p>As distressing as it was for me to make you wait until today for my reply,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> my scheme against the publisher and the result, on the other hand, proved as rewarding!  I was outraged that he showed the snideness of not answering you when from <tei:hi rend="italic">his</tei:hi> perspective he certainly should have expressed to you his acknowledgment.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  Of course only I alone could know why the publisher apparently behaved in so unbusinesslike a manner this time, so little concerned[?] about reviews.   After he noticed, based on quite a few instances, that <tei:hi rend="italic">through him</tei:hi> I have this or that sent to me at my expense (somewhat discounted of course)--I conduct myself <tei:hi rend="italic">so independently</tei:hi> with respect to him that I just pay for the gifts and reciprocity gifts for <tei:hi rend="italic">non</tei:hi>-musicians myself, instead of ^[??]^ which is otherwise normal, just like requesting review copies--he thought to himself in the end that I would also take upon myself the cost of the review copies for you, which would have netted for him a double advantage (on my part and yours).  You can imagine that a mind like that of a publisher is incapable of grasping that for the likes of us no special X-ray power is required to illuminate his exploitative little soul.  He cannot grasp that I recognize his cleverness <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> as the product of a simple inability to distinguish between a review copy to which you are certainly entitled and a reciprocity gift for a <tei:hi rend="italic">non</tei:hi>-musician.</tei:p><tei:p>Now to take the snideness to absurdity in order to punish it, I immediately intervened after receiving your first letter<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> by writing a little letter to the publisher.  But the poor nitwit did <tei:hi rend="italic">not</tei:hi> answer that either, which I could have predicted.   So, I then finally grabbed hold of the insect, which wanted to play dead, in a different way and revived him.  I sent him a <tei:hi rend="italic">return-receipt</tei:hi> card in my style („I am lacking, etc."), and his brain loosened up owing to that crude means.  Today I receive from him the notification that he sent all my other works to you.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> (At the same time he asserts that he has <tei:hi rend="italic">not</tei:hi> received a letter from you <tei:hi rend="italic">at all</tei:hi>. (!! lie), and mine is ostensibly supposed ^to have struck him^ as unjustified (!) and also „overburdened," and whatever other such publisher's idiocies there are[?].  But the most amusing aspect of the whole thing is that on the whole he maintains a so-called good relationship with me, and in connection with the <tei:hi rend="italic">Little Library</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> even gave me a yearly <tei:hi rend="italic">deal</tei:hi>|! It is a shame, though, that the surgical removal of such a petty profit seeker[?] wastes most precious time.  I would be curious how the blessed Hercules would have fared with publishers !  I swim for the <tei:hi rend="italic">cudgel</tei:hi>! [?]</tei:p><tei:p>For the shipment itself, I remark only that H. Niloff<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> i.e. <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> I myself, manufactured this little trifle many, many years ago out of pity for his pupils and for the critics of the <tei:hi rend="italic">daily newspapers</tei:hi> in Vienna, who - I experienced it myself! - have used <tei:hi rend="italic">English</tei:hi> terms[?] such as "stopped"  in their reviews, [and have] praised Sebastian Bach's clarinets to all the Heavens.  In the deal, I made a gift of this trifle literally to the publisher and stipulated only that it be sold <tei:hi rend="italic">no more expensively</tei:hi> than 1 Kroner 20.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>  It was translated many times--it will hardly run the same with the <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmony</tei:hi> and <tei:hi rend="italic">Counterpoint</tei:hi> manuals--[and was] issued in several editions.</tei:p><tei:p>I will yet return to what I found in the supplements of the journal issue only after I have definitively concluded the second volume of <tei:hi rend="italic">Counterpoint</tei:hi>.  I have ordered the issue of <tei:hi rend="italic">New Austria</tei:hi>, about which a student told me only the day before yesterday.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/>  As I believe I have already written, I have owned your book on Bruckner (<tei:hi rend="italic">Between Two Cultures</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> ) for some time, [and] have always otherwise eagerly read whatever I found of yours.  You would put me much into your debt if with a couple of lines--safeguard your time!--you would bring to my attention which works you value, and I will purchase them.  For the idea of your bearing the cost would be distressing to me.</tei:p><tei:p>With regard to the „folk,"<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> just this:  I treat every student as though he were qualified to the highest level, artisitically and humanly.  I spare absolutely nothing when it comes to myself, and thus the process also <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> ends up in the idea of  Kant that you quote.  To a certain extent that is „practical reason"--but it does not suspend „pure" reason, and prior to that, for me the „folk" exists unfortunately in a different, much worse sense than people suspect today, where by folk I understand above and below the „social estates."</tei:p><tei:p>With best wishes to you,
Respectfully,
Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H. Schenker</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>