<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 15/15, [I] : 8-4-[12] --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  Under inquiry 
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2008.
© Translation William Drabkin, 2008
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish granted by the heirs of Hans Weisse.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1912-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Hans Weisse; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 08/04/1912 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Weisse ~ H+JSchenker","Weisse ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated August 4, [1914]</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-05-26</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Weisse reports: his Quintet is now finished;  he is in the midst of reading Schenker’s monograph on Beethoven’s Ninth Symphony;  repeats his request to have piano lessons with Schenker;  and asks his teacher’s advice concerning some songs of his that Lorle Meissner would be interested in singing.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Weisse, Hans;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Quintet;  Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie;  Beethoven's Ninth Symphony;  synthesis;  Bopp, Wilhelm;  Wiener, Karl von;  Violin, Moriz;  Meissner, Lorle;  Brünauer, Ida;  Salzburg</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated August 4 [1912]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Mein innig geliebter Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Vor allem Dank für Ihre letzte liebe Karte<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  The postcard is not known to survive.</tei:note> und die Nachricht, dass der zweite Satz meines Quintetts vollständig fertig ist und[,] wie ich glaube, zugleich das Beste ist[,] was ich bis jetzt gemacht habe!  Sehr tiefe Erfindung und gute Synthese.</tei:p><tei:p>Dann aber muss ich Ihnen auch sagen, wie sehr ^ich^ mich an der IX. ergötze, die ich Seite für Seite genauest studiere,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> From this remark one may deduce that this letter was written shortly after the publication of <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie</tei:hi> by Universal Edition;  copies of the book were dispatched on July 3, 1912.</tei:note> und die wie ich glaube der beste Beweis für die grandiose Lebenskraft Ihrer Theorie, Ihres Systems ist. —</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Was Ihre Lehrbücher <tei:hi rend="italic">in sich</tei:hi> trugen, in sich selbst aufbauten, entsteht neuerdings hier wie auszwingensdster[?] Notwendigkeit an der [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr from</tei:hi> dem] Kunstwerkanalyse.  Ihre einmal ausgesprochene Absicht[,] die Brücke zwischen Kunst und Theorie zu schlagen[,] wächst aus dem Bilde ins Wesenhafte!  <tei:hi rend="italic">Das</tei:hi> ist die idealste Brücke, die bisher einer gebaut hat, und welcher von den Blinden nicht Boden und Geländer zu ertasten vermag – hier helfen dann Götter selbst vergebens!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich habe nun den I. Satz der IX. in Angriff genommen und mit grösster Freude die Polemik gegen alle <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Maulhelden gelesen! Hier möchte ich Ihnen doch sagen, dass es mich gewundert hat, die Wiener–Bopp-Broschüre<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> Wiener-Bopp-Broschüre:  presumably the polemical pamphlet written by <ref cRef="violin_moriz">Moriz Violin</ref>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Zustände an der k. k. Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst: Ein offenes Wort über die Leiter der Anstalt Herren v. Wiener und Bopp</tei:hi> (Vienna: M. Violin, 1912) criticizing the sweeping changes—including compulsory staff redundancies and early retirements—at the Vienna Conservatory, instituted by its Director, <ref cRef="bopp_wilhelm">Wilhelm Bopp</ref>, and its President, <ref cRef="wiener_dr_karl_von">Karl von Wiener</ref>.</tei:note> nicht schärfer und wuchtiger drauf los hauen zu sehen!  Ich fürchte dass infolge dessen zu wenig Staub aufgewirbelt wurde und dass der arme Violin gar nicht auf seine Kosten gekommen ist!  Auch waren meines Erachtens nach zu wenig Fälle <tei:hi rend="italic">zitiert</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich frage mich nochmals wegen der Klavierstunden bei Ihnen an!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> Weisse had been having piano lessons with Moriz Violin, but was hoping that Schenker would teach him the piano, alongside theory and composition.</tei:note>  Für mich bedeutets ein unerhörtes Glück und ich brächte Ihnen dafür Lust und Eifer, Liebe und Fleiss entgegen.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Lorle Meissner</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> Lorle Meissner, a singer (probably a contralto, and probably based in Vienna). Her name appears on recital programmes in Berlin in the 1910s, and on a flyer listing concerts given at the Musikverein in Vienna in October–November 1921. (We do not know whether Meissner actually performed songs by Weisse;  a lieder recital of hers was scheduled for October 25, a week before the première of Weisse’s String Quartet in C, on November 3.  A copy of the flyer is preserved in OJ 15/15.)</tei:note> will Lieder von mir singen aber tiefere.  Wie wäre mit den Rücker[t] Lieder?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6"> Presumably songs already composed by Weisse, but for a high voice. Friedrich Rückert (1788–1866) was a German poet and scholar of Oriental languages;  his lyrics were among the most frequently set to music in the Romantic period and the early 20th century.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Morgen spielt Frau Ida Brünauer<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7"> Ida Brünauer: presumably a relation of the industrialist and Schenker’s long-standing pupil <ref cRef="brunauer_dr">Robert Brünauer</ref>.</tei:note> in Salzburg meinem Vater auf Engagement vor!</tei:p><tei:p>Nehmen Sie sich bitte meiner Liederbitte ein wenig an und lassen Sie bald von sich etwa hören (auch von Hertzka.)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8"> Weisse may may have been hoping that, through his teacher’s contact with <ref cRef="hertzka_emil">Emil Hertzka</ref>, Universal Edition might publish some of his music.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>In Liebe und Freundschaft
ganz Ihr</tei:p><tei:p>Ischl. 4. August.
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  Hans</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated August 4 [1912]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>My deeply beloved master,</tei:p><tei:p>First of all, I send my thanks for your last, lovely postcard,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> and also the news that the second movement of my Quintet is completely finished and, so I believe, the best work that I have written to date!  Very deep inventiveness, and good synthesis.</tei:p><tei:p>Secondly, I must also tell you how much I am captified by your book on the Ninth Symphony, which I am studying most carefully, page by page,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> and which I believe to be the best proof for the magnificent life-force of your theory, your system.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> What your theoretical works embraced <tei:hi rend="italic">in themselves</tei:hi> is reborn here, as though of the most convincing necessity for the analysis of works of art.  Your marked intention to bridge the gap between art and theory grows out of the picture into something significant!  <tei:hi rend="italic">That</tei:hi> is the most ideal bridge that has yet been built, and one whose floor and railings will be inaccessible to the blind—here the gods themselves will be powerless!</tei:p><tei:p>I have tackled the first movement of the Ninth and read with great joy the polemic against all <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> loudmouths!  Here I should like, however, to say that I was surprised that the Wiener–Bopp pamphlet<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> did not deal with them more sharply and forcefully!  I fear that, as a consequence, too little dirt will have been stirred up and that poor Violin will in no way be able to recoup his losses. Also, it is my opinion that too few examples were actually <tei:hi rend="italic">quoted</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>I ask once more about having piano lessons with you!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  For me, this would mean an unimaginable joy, for which I would bring to you my enthusiasm, determination, love, and industry.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Lorle Meissner</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> would like to sing Lieder of mine, but ones written for a low voice. What would you say to the Rücker[t]<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> songs?</tei:p><tei:p>Tomorrow, Mrs Ida Brünauer<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> is auditioning in Salzburg to my father, in the hope of getting a part!</tei:p><tei:p>Please consider my request regarding the songs, and let me hear something about you (and also about Herztka)<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> soon.</tei:p><tei:p>In love and friendship,
Yours truly,</tei:p><tei:p>Ischl, August 4.
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  Hans</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>