<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 15/16, [12] : 12-18-12 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Under inquiry.
© Transcription Ian Bent and William Drabkin, 2007.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish is being sought.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1912-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Hans Weisse; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 12/18/1912 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Weisse ~ H+JSchenker","Weisse ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated December 18, 1912</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-10-16</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>W expresses his misgivings at Vrieslander's plan to produce an abridgement of S's Harmonielehre, and his suspicions as to V's motives.  V is an egotist, and lacks altruism.  The author has first claim on publishing simplifications of his own work.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Weisse, Hans;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Vrieslander, Otto;  Harmonielehre;  Theory of Harmony;  Kontrapunkt;  Counterpoint;  Auszug;  abridgement;  popularization;  Handbuch;  handbook;  egotism;  altruism;  Kant;  Prolegomenon</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated December 18, 1912</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Liebster Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Sie kennen mich gut genug, um zu wissen, dass ich mich nie in Dinge menge, die mich nichts angehn.  Aber was den Fall des Herrn Vrieslander anbelangt, von dem Sie unlängst Erwähnung getan haben,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Evidently S had spoken to W of the <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Vrieslander</ref> matter in the previous day’s lesson.  W had lessons with S at this time on Tuesdays and Fridays (the letter is written on Wednesday):  the absence of any reference to the matter in the notes to that lesson is not surprising, since these notes were restricted to instructional and technical topics.  Records of Vrieslander’s lessons with S survive only between January 5 and March 5, 1912: it is not known how long before that period he had been taking lessons, though they may well have extended back at least to October 1911;  the first reference to Vrieslander in the diary is on January 19, 1912 (OJ 1/11, p. 198).  Of the diary entries prior to this letter, the pertinent one is probably a long entry dated September 30, 1912 (OJ 1/11, pp. 243–44) that begins "Vrieslander's psychology."  There is no record in the diary of any letter from S to W around this time (nor of receipt of the present letter).  </tei:note> so möchte ich Ihnen hiedoch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  <tei:hi rend="italic">hiedoch</tei:hi>: perhaps <tei:hi rend="italic">hiedurch</tei:hi>, “by this means,” is intended.</tei:note> einige Worte &lt;strike&gt;geben&lt;/strike&gt; sagen, und zwar berechtigte, weil ich, wenn schon nicht an Ihrem[<tei:hi rend="italic">recte</tei:hi> Ihrer] Person[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>], so doch an Ihrem Werke Interessent sein darf!  Die Tatsache die Sie mir berichteten, das[s] Vrieslander einen Auszug – eine „Populariesierung[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>]“ – aus Ihrem Werke vorbereitet,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  According to Robert Wason, <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Vrieslander</ref> produced three “lengthy commentaries” (72pp, 468pp, and 472pp, respectively) on S’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> between 1910 and 1925, and on October 11, 1915 wrote to S suggesting that a second edition of the work should be produced including “practical exercises and assignments” (which S resisted):  “From Harmonielehre to Harmony: Schenker’s Theory of Harmony and its Americanization,” in <tei:hi rend="italic">Schenker-Traditionen: Eine Wiener Schule der Musiktheorie und ihre internationale Verbreitung</tei:hi>, ed. Martin Eybl &amp; Evelyn Fink-Mennel (Vienna: Böhlau Verlag, 2006), pp. 171–201, esp. 181–82.   </tei:note> hat erst nach meinem Scheiden von Ihnen grosse Bedenken erregt, die ich Ihnen auch hier mitteilen möchte.</tei:p><tei:p>Vor allem muss man sich über das Vorgehen <tei:hi rend="italic">Vr.</tei:hi> klar sein, der, wenngleich er auch ein Jahr im Verkehre mit Ihnen einiges gewann,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  This may be the only evidence as to the extent of the prior association of the latter with S.  </tei:note> den Menschen <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> in sich durch Erkenntnis seiner Umgebung und der Verhältnisse, in die er hineingeboren ist nicht besserte [<tei:hi rend="italic">alt from</tei:hi> bessern konnte], weil er sonst an sich bemerken könnte, was das Um – und Auf des heutigen, armseligen sterilen Geistesleben geworden ist:  Die Ausbeutung fremden Kapitals – oder treffender gesagt Die Ausbeutung des Zinsen eines Kapitals.  Denn was heute geschrieben wird ist leider Gottes das Erfordernis einer Zeit, die dem Schaffenden wie dem Medium gleich wenig Fähigkeiten zu geben wusste [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte</tei:hi> weiss]:  Zwischen den Kunstwerken, die beschrieben werden und dem Publikum, das diese Beschreibungen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  W no doubt has in mind Hermann Kretzschmar, <tei:hi rend="italic">Führer durch den Konzertsaal</tei:hi> (Leipzig: Liebeskind, 1888–90, numerous later edns Breitkopf &amp; Härtel), of which S owned the first, two-vol. edn;  also George Grove, <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven and his Nine Symphonies</tei:hi> (London: Novello, [1896]), of which S owned the German translation, <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven und seine Neun Symphonien</tei:hi> (London: Hehemann, 1906); the program books written by S’s friend Robert Hirschfeld for the Vienna Philharmonic Society’s concerts, 1893–1913;  and other popular guides for concert- and opera-goers.</tei:note> verschlingt[,] liegt eine ungeheure Kluft:  Der Tod des Künstlers!  Er hat in seinem Werke eben eine Summe gehauft, die er &lt;strike&gt;eben&lt;/strike&gt; als Kapital fest umrissen der Welt uberliess; – aber das Fehlen der Erben hat es den Würmern ermöglicht aus blühendem Leben einen Kadaver zu machen, an dem jeder einzelne nagt, und &lt;strike&gt;das&lt;/strike&gt; ^die Nährung^ findet[,] die er sucht.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Die Würme[r ] aber zu verscheuchen geht ebensowenig an – als den Kadaver zum Leben zu erwecken.  Die geistige Luft, in der wir leben ist verseucht, von dem Pestgestanke nicht versorgter Leichen, die sich freilich gegen ihre Zernager nicht wehren konnten!</tei:p><tei:p>Was Vrieslanders Arbeit – sei sie gut oder schlecht – betrifft – so ist sie die Ausbeutung – und das ist es worauf ich hinaus will – einer Summe, die zum Kapitale noch nicht abgeschlossen wurde.  Sie haben – Gott sei Dank ihr [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte</tei:hi> Ihr] letztes Wort noch nicht gesprochen – und hiemit die Konsequenzen, die sich aus ihren [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte</tei:hi> Ihren] Prämissen und Schlüssen ergeben, selbst zu ziehen!!  (wie sie [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte</tei:hi> Sie] es ja auch vorhaben!)  Was sollte dieses Exzerptenbuch&lt;strike&gt;e&lt;/strike&gt; – und wem anders stünde es zu, wenn es sich darum handelte, eines zu machen – als wieder Ihnen selbst??</tei:p><tei:p>Der Prophet der einen Mittler duldet wird sich von der Menge, der er offenbart, durch diesen eher entfernen, abnähern.</tei:p><tei:p>Abgesehen von allem ist es notwendig und hat es je gute Früchte getragen, von der Quelle der <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Weisheit – Wasser in Abzugsflaschen zu exportieren^?^ Ist, der den Weg zur Quelle scheut, ihrer [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte</tei:hi> Ihrer] überhaupt wert?</tei:p><tei:p>Und zugegeben – dass das Entgegenkommen gegenüber all diesen geistigen Krückenträgern von Vorteil wäre, und zur Verbreitung beitrüge – so steht doch die Verdeutlichung eines scheinbar „zu schwierigen und komplizierten“ ^nur und nur^ dem <tei:hi rend="italic">Autor</tei:hi> zu.  <tei:hi rend="italic">Kant</tei:hi> selbst nur könnte und dürfte in den Prolegomenon die Erklärung und Vereinfachung der Kritik der reinen Vernunft geben.  Aus dem Munde eines andern hätte es gegen ihn eingenommen.</tei:p><tei:p>Wer könnte es dem Durchschnitte verargen, ja sogar wer [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr from</tei:hi> wegen] konnte [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte</tei:hi> könnte]  etwas anders von ihm erwarten als, dass dieser, nach dem man ihm in den Mund legte:  Schenkers Harmonielehre ist zu schwierig, vor dessen Kontrapunkt,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  This appears to refer to S’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> having been produced as vol. I of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:hi>, and <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt</tei:hi> as vol. II, a matter which is taken up by S in his correspondence with Vrieslander of October 1915.  </tei:note> (&lt;strike&gt;vor&lt;/strike&gt; ^dem gegen^über er ja a priori Angst hatte), zurückschrecken würde und auch auf dessen Verdeutlichung warten würde!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> Wenn aber auch dessen Verdeutlichung ihm in Aussicht gestellt &lt;strike&gt;würde&lt;/strike&gt; ^wäre^, würde hier nicht in aller Stille einbekannt<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  <tei:hi rend="italic">einbekennen</tei:hi>: Austrian usage for <tei:hi rend="italic">eingestehen</tei:hi>, to confess, admit, acknowledge.</tei:note> werden, dass Ihre Schreibweise, Ihre Ausdrucksweise, tatsächlich nicht geklärt &lt;strike&gt;ist&lt;/strike&gt; ^sei^:  und ^ist^ nicht das Gegenteil der Fall??  Die Verbreitung Ihres geistigen Eigentumes ist bereits vor sich gegangen[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] – wahrscheinlich zumeist auf unehrliche Weise.  Aber Sie sind Idealist genug, &lt;strike&gt;mit&lt;/strike&gt; auf die Verbreitung überhaupt, und auch auf die Art, wie sie vor sich geht, zu schauen.  Wenn hiemit Ihre „Gegner“ in Anbetracht jeglichen Fehlens einer Moral und eines Gewissens Ihren Namen zu verschweigen übersich&lt;strike&gt;te&lt;/strike&gt; brachten, so wäre im Falle eines Excerptenbuches dieses Vorgehen, sogar <tei:hi rend="italic">mit</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  <tei:hi rend="italic">mit</tei:hi>:  double-underlined.</tei:note> gutem Gewissen verbunden!  denn es hätte sich vor Ihrem eigenen Namen ein Zweiter gestellt, den zu verheimlichen kleine Gefahr und Notwendigkeit vorhanden wäre.</tei:p><tei:p>Jede Wahrheit aus zweiter Hand ist um einen Grad trüber – und kann umso leichter missverstanden und missdeutet werden!  Und hiemit <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> wären an dieses Unglücksbuch unfruchtbare und von unbefugter Seite geführte Kontroversen &lt;strike&gt;wird&lt;/strike&gt; geknüpt!</tei:p><tei:p>Wie gesagt nicht gegen die Idee eines „Handbuches“ habe ich Einwendungen sondern nur gegen die zweite Hand.  Denn Vrieslanders geistiges Schmarotzengesicht hat wie das aller seiner Kollegen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  It is unclear what is implied by Vrieslander’s “colleagues,” here.  [investigate]</tei:note> einen Januskopf:  Er <tei:hi rend="italic">scheint</tei:hi> zu geben, <tei:hi rend="italic">nur</tei:hi> in Wahrheit selbst nur zu nehmen, und zu profitieren.</tei:p><tei:p>Lässt einer, aber der seine beiden Hände frei hat, sich unter dem Vorwande, man gäbe ihm etwas hinein, in seine Tasche greifen?</tei:p><tei:p>Die Psychologie allein könnte Ihr Urteil in diesem Falle sofort erklären [<tei:hi rend="italic">alt from</tei:hi> verklären]: Sie haben an Vr. Ehrlichkeit schon lange gezweifelt, haben ihn als Egoisten erkannt, und werden doch nicht ^plötzlich^ eine altruistische Regung in ihm vermuten, die ihn derlei Dinge machen liesse, ohne selbst davon einen Vorteil zu haben?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  W places a question-mark at the end of this para., but there is no question to mark.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> Wenn es überhaupt so weit kommen sollte, dass er Ihnen sein „verdeutlichtes Handbuch“ vorlegen sollte, so bitte ich Sie, diesen Brief, der wahrlich ehrlich und im Interesse der Sache gemeint war, vorzunehmen und ihre [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte</tei:hi> Ihre] Billigung zur Herausgabe jenes erst zu geben, nachdem die treffende Widerlegungen meiner Einwände gefunden haben.</tei:p><tei:p>Herzlichst Ihr
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  Hans.
18. Dez. 1912.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated December 18, 1912</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dearest Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>You are well enough acquainted with me to know that I never meddle with things that do not concern me.  But when it comes to the matter of Mr. Vrieslander, of whom you recently made mention,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> I should like to say a few words to you here,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> [words that are] justified, moreover, because if not in your person I should be [seen as] having a vested interest in your work.  That, as you reported to me, Vrieslander is preparing an abridgment—a “popularization”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>—of your work has given me much pause for thought since left you, and I should like to convey those thoughts to you here.</tei:p><tei:p>First and foremost, we must be clear about the actions of <tei:hi rend="italic">Vrieslander</tei:hi>, who, even though he gained something by a year’s association with you,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> did [<tei:hi rend="italic">alt from</tei:hi> could] not improve the man himself <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> through cognizance of his environs and the circumstances into which he was born, because he could otherwise see for himself what the full extent of today’s impoverished, sterile spiritual life has become.  The exploitation of someone else’s capital—or better put, the exploitation of the interest on that capital.  For that which is written today is unfortunately the condition of an age that is able to confer as little competence on the creative artist as on the medium [in which he works]:  between works of art that are described and the public that devour these descriptions<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> there lies an enormous gulf:  the death of the artist!  What he has done in his work is precisely to heap up a sum that he entrusts to the world as well defined capital.  But the failings of his inheritors have made it possible for the worms to make out of blossoming life a cadaver at which each individual one of them gnaws and finds the ^nourishment^ that it seeks.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> But to get rid of the worms is just as difficult as bringing the cadaver back to life.  The spiritual air in which we live is contaminated by the pestilential stench of unattended corpses, who admittedly cannot defend themselves against those who gnaw at them!</tei:p><tei:p>As concerns Vrieslander’s work—be it good or bad—the exploitation—and that is what it amounts to—of a sum which has not yet been added into the capital.  You have—thanks be to God!—not yet spoken your final word, and therefore you have not yourself drawn the consequences that arise from your premisses and conclusions.  (As you indeed plan to do!)  What is this book of excerpts supposed to be, and who else should have a claim on writing it—if one is to be written at all—than, again, you yourself??</tei:p><tei:p>The prophet who tolerates a mediator will in so doing distance himself, sever himself from the crowd to which he makes his revelations.</tei:p><tei:p>Apart from everything [else], is it necessary, and has it ever been fruitful to draw liquid from the fountain of <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> wisdom and export it as bottled water^?^  Is he who shuns the path to the source at all worthy of you?</tei:p><tei:p>And granted, to make concession to all these intellectual cripples would be of advantage and might contribute to the dissemination [of the word];  however, the <tei:hi rend="italic">author</tei:hi> ^and he alone^  has sole claim on the explication of something allegedly “too difficult and complicated.”  Only <tei:hi rend="italic">Kant</tei:hi> himself could and was entitled to give in his Prolegomenon the explanation and simplification of the critique of pure reason.  From the mouth of anybody else it would have been to his detriment.</tei:p><tei:p>Who could blame the mediocre man—what’s more, who could expect anything else of him other than that, after the idea had been put into his head that Schenker’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Theory of Harmony</tei:hi> was too difficult, more so than his <tei:hi rend="italic">Counterpoint</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> (which he already dreaded), he would be scared off and would wait for the explication of it!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> However, even if the prospect of an explication of [the <tei:hi rend="italic">Theory of Harmony</tei:hi>] were to be held out to him, nobody would admit<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> to him covertly that it lacked any explanation of your style of writing [or] manner of expression:  and isn’t the contrary the case?  The dissemination of your intellectual property has already taken place—probably mostly in a disgraceful fashion.  But you are idealist enough to take care of the dissemination as a whole, and also of the way in which it is carried out.  If in this connection your “adversaries” were, out of a sheer lack of any ethics or conscience, to go so far as to suppress your name, they would do so in the case of a book of excerpts, even one made <tei:hi rend="italic">in</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> good faith!  For in place of your own name would have been put that of another, the concealment of which would present little danger, nor [would there be any] necessity [to include it].   
 
Any truth conveyed at second hand loses a degree in clarity and can all the more easily be misunderstood and misinterpreted!  And coupled to this <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> would be unfruitful controversies led by unauthorized sources that would overtake this ill-fated book.</tei:p><tei:p>As I have already said, I have no objections to the idea of a “handbook,” only to its second-hand nature.  For Vrieslander’s intellectual parasitism has, like that of all his colleagues,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> a janus face:  He <tei:hi rend="italic">appears</tei:hi> to give, <tei:hi rend="italic">only</tei:hi> in fact to take away and to profiteer.</tei:p><tei:p>But does someone who has his two hands free reach into his pocket under the pretext that someone else had put something in it?</tei:p><tei:p>Only psychology could give an instantaneous explanation of your verdict in this case:  you have long doubted Vrieslander’s honesty, you have recognized him for an egotist, and will certainly not ^suddenly^ expect to find a streak of altruism in him that causes him to do such things unless there is some advantage to be had from it.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> If it should ever come to such a pass that he presents you with his “explicated handbook,” I beg you to take up this letter, which is intended sincerely and honestly, and in the interests of the cause, and give your approval to the edition only after the relevant refutations have been given to my objections.</tei:p><tei:p>Most cordially yours,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  Hans.
December 18, 1912.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>