<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 15/16, [22] : 7-7-14 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© The heirs of Hans Weisse, published by kind permission.
© Transcription  William Drabkin, 2007.
© Translation  Alison Hiley 2008
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish granted by the heirs of Hans Weisse.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1914-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Hans Weisse; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 07/07/1914 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Weisse ~ H+JSchenker","Weisse ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated July 7, 1914</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-02-25</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Acknowledging a [non-extant] postcard from Schenker, Weisse reports that his health is now restored;  he is studying Brahms's Second Symphony and finding the second movement a puzzle. 
 
</dc:description><dc:subject>Weisse, Hans;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Brahms;  Second Symphony;  Richter, Jean Paul; Ischl, Bad</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Bad Ischl</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated July 7, 1914</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Liebster, verehrter Meister!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Receipt of this letter is noted in Schenker’s diary for July 9 (OJ 1/15, p. 611).  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Die Nachricht über mein Befinden habe ich solange zurückgehalten, weil ich die ganze Zeit meines hiesigen Aufenthaltes, in verschiedener Weise gepeinigt wurde, und erst jetzt anfange, mich gänzlich wiederherzustellen.  So wäre denn auch ohne Ihre liebe Karte,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  The postcard is not known to survive.  </tei:note> dieser Tage ein Brief an Sie abgeschickt worden, der[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] Ihnen mitteilen hätte sollen, dass ich die Übelstände, wie es den Anschein hat, gänzlich überwunden habe, und froh und frei in Gottes herrlicher Natur umherlaufe:  freilich gänzlich ruhend, und mich nur dem ^mir bislang^ unbekannten, &lt;strike&gt;nur&lt;/strike&gt; von Ihnen empfohlenen Jean Paul<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Jean Paul Richter [create profile].  </tei:note> anvertrauend.  Vielleicht geht es Ihnen auch so, lieber Meister – aber fern vom Klaviere, von lieblichen Synkopen- und Generalbass[-]Gedanken wird mir die Ruhe – gradezu eine Tätigkeit, die ich mit einem Aufwand von Kräften anstreben und gegen eventuelle Unvorsichtigkeiten schützen muss.  Dennoch konnte ich bereits bisher nicht verhindern, jeden Tag eine Stunde zu üben und ich <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> danke Ihnen für die Genüsse, die mir auf dem Klaviere bereits zu Gebote stehen:  von den kommenden gar nicht zu reden.  Momentan versenke ich mich nur[?] in die Brahms’sche II. Sinfonie, deren II. Satz noch manches Rätsel für mich hat, um dessen Lösung, falls ich mittlerweile nicht daraufkäme – ich Sie später nun bitten würde!</tei:p><tei:p>Das Wetter ist wundervoll und die Luft heuer ausnahmsweise so kräftig[,] dass vielleicht Ihre 2000m.  Ansprüche sich zufrieden geben würden!  Ich hoffe Sie, liebster Meister, bereits in diesen wenigen Tagen, ausgeruht und völlig genesen:  Letzten Endes war Ihr Zustand ja Gott sei Dank doch nur eine übermässige Ermattung!</tei:p><tei:p>Was ich Ihnen nebst allen Lieben und Innigen wünschen, wissen Sie, Liebster:  das Gedeihen der op. 111!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Schenker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven … op. 111</tei:hi> (Vienna: UE, 1915).  </tei:note>  Mögen Sie sie mit Leichtigkeit und ohne alle Aufregung der 110<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Schenker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven … op. 110</tei:hi> (Vienna: UE, 1914).  </tei:note> bezwingen!</tei:p><tei:p>Mit diesem frommen Wünsche grüsst und umarmt Sie aufs herzlichste Ihr gänzlich unproduktiver, getreuer</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hans.
7/7 14. Bad Ischl. <tei:hi rend="italic">Kaiser Ferdinandsplatz 4.</tei:hi></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated July 7, 1914</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Beloved, honored Master,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>I have refrained from sending my news for so long because I have been variously troubled for the entire duration of my stay here, and I am only just now beginning to recover fully.  So, even without your kind postcard,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> a letter would have found its way to you at this time and it would have informed you that I seem to have overcome all the ills completely and am going about freely and happily once more in God’s wondrous Nature, quite calmly to be sure, and in the sole company of Jean Paul<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>, whom you recommended to me and with whom I had not been ^previously^ familiar.  Perhaps you also find this, dear master, but, separated from a piano and from charming thoughts of syncopation and general bass, rest almost becomes an activity for which I must strive with all my strength and preserve against possible imprudence.  Nonetheless I couldn’t stop myself from practising for an hour each day and I <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> thank you for the pleasures which are at my disposal on the piano, let alone those which are still to come.  At the moment I’m immersing myself in Brahms’s Second Symphony, the second movement of which holds many a puzzle for me—if I don’t hit on the solutions myself meantime, I would request them from you later!</tei:p><tei:p>The weather recently has been wonderful and the air so exceptionally brisk that perhaps [even] your 2000 m. demands would be satisfied!  I hope, dear master, that these few days have left you already rested and fully recovered—thank God your condition was after all merely excessive fatigue!</tei:p><tei:p>In addition to all manner of heartfelt wishes, you know, dearest [master], that what I wish for you is the success of Op.111!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  May you vanquish it with ease, and without any of the excitement which accompanied Op.110!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/></tei:p><tei:p>With this wishful thinking come most heartfelt greetings and embraces from your utterly unproductive, but true friend,</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hans.
Tuesday, July 7, 1914 Bad Ischl. <tei:hi rend="italic">Kaiser Ferdinandsplatz 4.</tei:hi></tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>