<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 15/16, [36] : 9-30-18 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Hans Weisse, published with kind permission.
© Transcription by William Drabkin, 2008.
© Translation Alison Hiley, 2008.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin, 2009
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish granted by the heirs of Hans Weisse.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1918-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Hans Weisse; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin;  Translation: Alison Hiley</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 09/30/1918 04:19:35 PM --><!-- MT Tags: "Weisse ~ H+JSchenker","Weisse ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated September 30, 1918</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-03-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Still in military service, Weisse asks Schenker for advice regarding the interpretation of the ritardandos in the first movement of Beethoven's Eighth Symphony.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Weisse, Hans;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Wien;  Vienna;  Wagner, Richard;  Über das Dirigieren;   Beethoven;  Symphony No. 8;  tempo;  performance;  Bulgaria </dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated September 30, 1918</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Lieber, verehrter Meister!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/11, p. 2000.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ich hoffe, daß Sie meine Karte<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  No correspondence from Schenker to Weisse is known to survive.  </tei:note> erhalten haben und nur die Zeit bisher nicht gefunden haben, mir zu antworten.  Seit ich vom Wien zurück bin, wird est hier recht ruhig, ja nahezu idyllisch!  Seit heute wird's etwas lebendiger!  Offenbar bereiten sich die schon längst erwarteten größere Dinge vor.  Mir geht es sehr gut, lieber Meister, obzwar ich öfters mit von Hunger knurrenden Magen abends mich niederlege.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich las letzthin Wagners: Über das Dirigieren,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Wagner, <tei:hi rend="italic">Über das Dirigieren</tei:hi> (1869),  <tei:hi rend="italic">Gesammelte Schriften und Dichtungen</tei:hi>, vol. 8,  Eng. trans., vol. 4.  </tei:note> <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> eine trotz aller widerwärtigen Giftstacheln und des einseitigen Standpunktes doch insoferne gute Schrift, als sie die Modifikation des Tempos im Vortrage klassischer Werke für das Ausschlaggebende hält.  Schade nur, daß Wagner den Vortrag um eines gewissermaßen äußerlichen &lt;del&gt;Maßes&lt;/del&gt; Zweckes allein belebt wünscht, ihn aber doch nicht aus den letzten Quellen des Geistigen bezieht.</tei:p><tei:p>Hier eine Vortragsfrage: der 2. Gedanke des 1. Satzes der 8[.]  Symphonie erscheint zuerst in Adur<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  This should be "D major":  A major is the dominant that prepares the initial statement of the second subject.  </tei:note> dann erst in C, wohin er[,] wenn man so sagen dürfte[,] von altem Anfang hingehören wurde.  Das Ritardando bei</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example:</tei:hi> Beethoven, Symphony No. 8, I, measures 43-44, first violin]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> kennzeichnet den Übergang, bildet gewissermaßen eine Demarkationslinie für den tonalen Vorgang.  Nun in C erscheint an der reziproken Stelle das Ritardando [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] wieder bei</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example:</tei:hi> measure 51, first flute, of the same piece]</tei:p><tei:p>hier löst sich aber daraus durch Synthese das nächste Element des 2. Gedankengruppe los.  Ich frage nun[:] hat der Dirigent nicht die Verpflichtung[,] die  verschiedene Bedeutung dieser &lt;del&gt;Zei&lt;/del&gt; Vorschreibungen gleichen Namens im Vortrage zum Ausdruck zu bringen?</tei:p><tei:p>Verzeihen Sie, lieber Meister, wenn ich vielleicht dumme Frage - aber hier draußen gehen einem keine gescheiteren Dinge durch den Kopf! --</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Was sagen Sie zu Bulgarien!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> In the month in which Weisse is writing (September 1918) the Western alliance broke through Bulgaria's Macedonian front, forcing its ruler, Tsar Ferdinand, to accept a peace settlement.   He was persuaded by the Agrarian Party leadear, Alexander Stamboliyski, to abdicate in favour of his son and so avoid being over run by revolutionary forces.  </tei:note>  Es hat hier überall finstere Niedergeschlagenheit hervorgerufen!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich grüße Sie und die liebe gnädige Frau aufs Allerherzlichste in treuer Anhänglichkeit[.]  Ihr alter  
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hans
30/ix 18.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Weisse to Schenker, dated September 30, 1918</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear, honored master,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>I hope that you received my postcard<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> and just have not had time to reply to me in the interim.  Since I returned from Vienna, life here has become really peaceful, one could say idyllic!  Things appear to be happening today, however!  It seems that the long-awaited greater events are in preparation.  I am very well, dear master, although I often lie down of an evening with my stomach rumbling with hunger.</tei:p><tei:p>Recently I read Wagner's <tei:hi rend="italic">On Conducting</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> a text which has its merits, in that, for all its repulsive poison quills and the one-sided point of view, it does consider the modification of tempo in the performance of classical works to be the decisive factor.  It is a shame, therefore, that Wagner wishes to enliven performance purely for the sake of a &lt;del&gt;degree&lt;/del&gt; purpose which is to some extent external, rather than receiving this from an innermost spiritual source.</tei:p><tei:p>Now a question regarding performance: the second subject of the first movement of the Eighth Symphony seems at first to be in A major<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> and only thereafter in C, the key to which it belonged in the first place, so to speak.  The ritardando at</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example</tei:hi>: Beethoven, Symphony No. 8, I, measures 43-44, first violin]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> marks the transition, and forms in a certain sense a line of demarcation for the tonal procedure., Now in the key of C major, the ritardando appears again at the corresponding point:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example</tei:hi>: measure 51, first flute, of the same piece]</tei:p><tei:p>but now, through synthesis, the next element of the second subject group springs forth.  My question: should the conductor not be obliged, in performance, to give expression to the varied significance of similar directions?</tei:p><tei:p>Forgive me, dear master, if I [pose] what is perhaps a stupid question - but out here nothing clever runs through one's head! -</tei:p><tei:p>What do you think of Bulgaria!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> It has engendered nothing but a dark sense of depression here!</tei:p><tei:p>My most cordial best wishes to you and your dear lady in true devotion,
Your old,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hans
September 30, 1918</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>