<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:GdM Exh. 332, [4] : 9-20-12 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Carl Lafite, published here by kind permission
© Transcription Martin Eybl, 2009
© Translation Ian Bent, 2009
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Martin Eybl 2009
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish is being sought.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Gesellschaft der Musifreunde Archiv (1912 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde and Heirs of Carl Lafite; Image: Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde Archiv; Transcription, Commentary, Footnotes, Summary: Martin Eybl;  Translation: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 09/20/1912 11:51:36 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde ~ HSchenker","KrauseC ~ HSchenker","Lafite ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Carl Lafite to Schenker, dated September 20, 1912</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-04-06</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Lafite rejects Schenker's rebukes and regrets that because of the tone of Schenker's letter he is unable to pursue any further a year-long course that he had had in mind for the next season.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Lafite, Carl;  Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde;  Krause, Carl;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Vorträge;  lectures;  honorarium</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Vienna I, Giselusstraße 12; Vienna XX, Wallensteinstraße 1/1</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Vienna III, Reisnerstraße 38</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Carl Lafite to Schenker, dated September 20, 1912, but returned not accepted</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{envelope <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>]  Wien 23.IX.12</tei:p><tei:p>Hochwohlgeboren [/] Herrn <tei:hi rend="italic">Dr. Heinr. Schenker</tei:hi>
Musikschriftsteller
Wien [<tei:hi rend="italic">the remainder crossed through in red:</tei:hi>] III.
Reisnerstrasse 38
[<tei:hi rend="italic">noted in red ink:</tei:hi>] ret[ournieren] XX Aufg[abepostamt?]
[<tei:hi rend="italic">in a third hand:</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">nicht angenommen</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{envelope <tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
C. K. Wien XX.
Wallensteinstrasse N: 1/I.
[<tei:hi rend="italic">in Jeannette Kornfeld's hand:</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">Carl Krause</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> Click on <ref cRef="krause_carl">Carl Krause</ref>.  </tei:note>
[<tei:hi rend="italic">in Heinrich Schenker's hand:</tei:hi>] (Beamter der k.k. Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde)</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{letter}</tei:hi>
[<tei:hi rend="italic">letterhead of the k. k. Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde in Wien</tei:hi>]
<tei:hi rend="italic">Wien</tei:hi> 20/9 <tei:hi rend="italic">191</tei:hi>2.
<tei:hi rend="italic">I., Giselusstraße 12</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Geehrter Herr Doktor!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  According to Schenker's diary, a letter from Lafite reached Schenker on September 21, 1912, but was refused and returned.  The envelope in which it was sent does not survive.  The diary for September 21, 1912 (OJ 1/11, p. 232), reads:  "Gegen Abend trifft ein recom. Schreiben von Lafite ein;  dieses wird aber einfach nicht angenommen u. retournirt.  Vermutlich hat sich darin der Herr Generalsekretär von seiner Beleidigung erholen wollen.  Davon am selben Abend Mitteilung an Hertzka u. Floriz gemacht." ("Towards evening, a registered letter arrives from Lafite;  this is, however simply not accepted, and returned.  Presumably, it contains the General Secretary's attempt to get over his affront.  That same evening, [I] communicate it[s contents] to Hertzka and Floriz [=Moriz Violin].")  The same letter arrived two days later in a new envelope with the sender named as "C[arl] Krause" (diary, OJ 1/11, p. 237, September 29, 1912):  "Lafite steckt sich hinter einen Beamten, um die Annahme seiner mir zugedachten Beleidigung zu erzwingen;  aber auch wird retournirt."  ("Lafite hides behind an official in order to force me to accept the insult he intended for me, but this letter, too, is returned.").  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ich bedaure es, dass unsere Verhandlungen diese Wendung nehmen mussten;<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Lafite is referring to Schenker's letter of the same day, GdM Exh. 332, [3]. </tei:note>  umsomehr, als <tei:hi rend="italic">alle</tei:hi> anderen Herren, die in unserer "unfairen" Notiz<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  See OJ 11/22, [4], <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue Freie Presse</tei:hi>, September 15, 1912.  </tei:note> genannt waren, in liebenswürdigster und vornehmster Art auf unsere Wünsche und Bitten eingegangen sind, (der Briefwechsel mit all diesen Persönlichkeiten steht Ihnen zur eventuellen Einsichtnahme jederzeit zur Verfügung!) wol erkennend, dass unser neues Unternehmen noch völlig in den Kinderschuhen steckt und wir, in Zeit, Räumlichkeiten und Credit recht sehr behindert, vorerst probieren müssen, wie das ganze sich überhaupt anlassen wird. Ich habe das Missverständnis, das [<tei:hi rend="italic">illegible word, deleted</tei:hi>] ^unser^ erster, allgemein gehaltener Aufruf bei Ihnen offenbar erweckt hat, mit Beklommenheit bemerkt, schon damals; mit Bedauern aber den Tonfall Ihres heutigen Briefes zur Kenntnis genommen, der es mir unmöglich macht, bei einem günstigen Verlauf dieser Versuchsstationen gerade mit Ihnen, den von mir wol erkannten und nach Gebühr geschätzten Fachmann, in der nächsten Saison einen <tei:hi rend="italic">Jahreskurs</tei:hi> zu errichten - wovon ich vorgestern in der Direktion sprach.  Die Idee, dass wir Ihren Namen nur zur „Ausschmückung" missbraucht hätten, bitte ich Sie aber wieder einzupacken.  Gerade wir sind stolz darauf, ohne jede unsaubere Nebenabsicht unsere Geschäfte zu führen, und es ist sehr merkwürdig, dass wir gerade in dem Augenblick, da wir, so gut es eben gehen will, eine neue Einrichtung ins Leben rufen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  i.e. the proposed series of published popular lectures.  </tei:note> das mit der „Wiener Kunstpflege" an den Kopf bekommen.  Hier ist die Adresse tatsächlich verfehlt worden.  Was aber die Angelegenheit des „üblichen Honorarsatzes" anlangt, so können Sie sich jederzeit überzeugen, dass alle anderen Herren (eine Qualifikation vorzunehmen, wird eine etwas heikle Sache sein!) ohneweiters gerne drauf eingegangen sind.</tei:p><tei:p>Wie gesagt, schade! Es war gut gemeint, unsererseits.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich empfehle mich Ihnen
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Carl Lafite</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Carl Lafite to Schenker, dated September 20, 1912, but returned not accepted</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{envelope <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>]  Vienna, September  23, 1912</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Dr. Heinrich Schenker, Esq.,</tei:hi>
Writer on Music
Vienna [<tei:hi rend="italic">the remainder crossed through in red:</tei:hi>] III,
Reisnerstraße 38
[<tei:hi rend="italic">noted in red ink:</tei:hi>] return to 20th district [post office] 
[<tei:hi rend="italic">in a third hand:</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">not accepted</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{envelope <tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
C. K. Vienna XX,
Wallensteinstrasse N: 1/I.
[<tei:hi rend="italic">in Jeannette Kornfeld's hand:</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">C[arl] Krause</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>
[<tei:hi rend="italic">in Heinrich Schenker's hand:</tei:hi>] (Official of the Imperial-Royal Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde)</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{letter}</tei:hi>
[<tei:hi rend="italic">letterhead of the Imperial-Royal Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde in Wien</tei:hi>]
<tei:hi rend="italic">Vienna</tei:hi> September 20, <tei:hi rend="italic">191</tei:hi>2.
<tei:hi rend="italic">I., Giselusstraße 12</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Dr. [Schenker],<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/></tei:p><tei:p>I regret that our negotiations had to take this turn;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  the more so since <tei:hi rend="italic">all</tei:hi> the other gentlemen named in our "unsporting" newspaper notice<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> have consented in the most obliging and genteel manner to our wishes and requests (the correspondence with all these persons is available for your inspection if you wish at any time!), in full recognition that our new enterprise is still entirely in its infancy, and we,  severely restricted in time, premises, and funds, must for the time being wait and see just how the whole thing goes.  I already noted with apprehension at the time the misunderstanding that [<tei:hi rend="italic">illegible word, deleted</tei:hi>] ^our^ first appeal, which was couched in general terms, evidently created in your mind.  I note with regret, however, the tone of your letter of today, which will make it impossible for me, even granted a favorable outcome to these experimental efforts, to set up specifically for you--a specialist recognized by me and deservedly held in high regard--<tei:hi rend="italic">a year-long course</tei:hi> next season, about which I spoke to the board of directors the day before yesterday.  But I ask you to forget about the idea that we misused your name merely for purposes of "aggrandizement."  We in particular take pride in conducting our affairs without any underhand, ulterior motive, and it is quite astonishing that, at the very moment when, if all goes well, we launch a brand new initiative,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> we get thrown at us the blame for "Viennese cultivation of art."  To lay the blame at our door is entirely misplaced.  As regards the "customary honorarium," however, you can verify for youself at any time that all the other gentlemen (to take into account qualifications would be a ticklish matter!) have willingly and without more ado acquiesced to it.</tei:p><tei:p>As I have said, what a pity!  It was well-intentioned on our part.</tei:p><tei:p>I present my compliments to you,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Carl Lafite</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>