<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 89/1, [6] : 10-4-27 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.  
© Transcription John Rothgeb, 2008.
© Translation John Rothgeb, 2008.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Hoboken, Anthony van (1927-1983) - -Schneider, Hans(19??-2007) - -University of California, Riverside (2007 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker;  Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 10/04/1927 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Hoboken ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Hoboken, dated October 4, 1927</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-06-30</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Schenker thanks van Hoboken [for subventing Yearbook 2], while complaining at Drei-Masken Verlag's failure to send him his author's copies and its lack of honesty;  he praises Hoboken for his collection and service to mankind.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  Jahrbuch;  Yearbook;  Meisterwerk in der Musik;  Masterwork in Music;  Deutsch, Otto Erich;  Haas, Robert;  Frankfurt;  London;  Beethoven;  Widmung;  Dedication</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to van Hoboken, dated October 4, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Lieber Herr van Hoboken!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Writing of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary, OJ 4/1, p. 3117, October 4, 1927;  the letter is addressed to Paris.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Da ich selbst, obgleich Verfasser des “Jahrbuches,”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Yearbook</tei:hi>: <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, vol. II (Munich: Drei Masken Verlag, 1926).  </tei:note> bis zur Stunde <tei:hi rend="italic">kein</tei:hi> Exemplar vom Verlag erhalten habe, hätte ich unschuldigerweise mich in eine Schuld des Versäumnisses Ihnen gegenüber verstrickt.  So aber sah ich ein Exemplar schon am Freitag<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Apparently referring to September 30, 1927, the Friday preceding this letter of Tuesday, October 4.  Schenker must have visited van Hoboken’s house on that Friday while the latter was away.  See van Hoboken’s letter to Schenker OJ 11/54, [19], of September 29, 1927.</tei:note> bei Ihnen zu Hause, weiß seit gestern Ihre neue Adresse wie auch, daß auch Sie eine Ex. erhalten haben, u. so kann ich Ihnen nur vom Herzen, für das Opfer Ihrer Güte danken, mit der Sie der Sache gemäß einen großen Dienst erwiesen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Hoboken had subvented the printing costs of <tei:hi rend="italic">Meisterwerk II</tei:hi>.  </tei:note> u. mir persönlich einen Prozeß wider den Verlag erspart haben.  Vielen, vielen Dank.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Es kennzeichnet die Verlags-Schmiere, daß sie Sie sofort am Ärmel züpft: “Zahlen,”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  See OJ 11/54, [17], September 6, 1927.  </tei:note> sie, die sich sovieler Zeit- u. Geldhinterziehungen schuldig gemacht hat!  Selbst unser lieber Herr Deutsch,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="deutsch_otto_erich">Otto Erich Deutsch</ref>.  </tei:note> der wahre “Parsifal” in unserem Kreise, hat seinerzeit aus den Briefen des Verlags eine wiederholte wirkliche “Bestellung”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  See OJ 11/54, [17], September 6, and OJ 89/1, [5], September 13, 1927. Reference to Deutsch's communication probably relates to OJ 10/3, [68], September 13, 1927;  correspondence direct from Drei-Masken Verlag around this time is OC 54/183–188.  </tei:note> – so drückte er sich aus – entnommen, der Verlag hat es doch gewagt, die Bestellung abzuleugnen.  Mit Leichtigkeit könnte ich an der Hand meiner Fahnen beweisen, daß der Verlag bei der Verrechnung der Korrekturen Betrug übt, aber es hätte kein Ende damit.  Und als könnte sich der Verlag nicht den geringsten Luxus von Aufrichtigkeit leisten, führe ich an, daß er mich mit einer Karte vom <tei:hi rend="italic">30.9</tei:hi> verständigte: “Wir erhielten Ihre Karte von gestern, die sich mit der Sendung Ihrer gebundenen Freiexemplare <tei:hi rend="italic">kreuzte</tei:hi>”; das <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> nenne ich ein “Kreuzen,” wo noch am <tei:hi rend="italic">4.10</tei:hi> kein Ex. eingetroffen ist!  Nichts geht über die Robustheit der Verleger.  Da es ihnen nicht gelingt, die Quadratur des Zirkels zu lösen, die Kunstwerke auf den Stand von z. B. Lebensmitteln, Kleidern oder dgl. ^zu bringen^, die jeder Mensch kaufen muß, sind sie genötigt, um zu einer “anständigen” Verzinsung ihres Kapitals zu gelangen, tief unanständig zu werden, u. so verpesten sie die Sphäre der Kunst, die wahrlich reinere Menschen verdiente.  Freilich, heute sind Künstler u. Verleger einander wert . . .</tei:p><tei:p>Für alle Ihre Briefe besten dank.  Hoffentlich sind meine Briefe nach Frankfurt u. London in ihre Hände gelangt.</tei:p><tei:p>Über das Wachstum Ihrer Sammlung müßte ich kürzlich ordentlich staunen.  Einen Teil der Neuerwerbungen zu <tei:hi rend="italic">Beeth</tei:hi>. zeigte mir H. Deutsch, den Rest will <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> ich mit Ihrer Erlaubnis nachholen.</tei:p><tei:p>H. <tei:hi rend="italic">D^r^ Haas</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="haas_robert">Robert Haas</ref>.</tei:note> der wegen politischer Schiebereien kürzlich bei der Professoren-Avancement übergangen wurde, lud mich in sehr lieber Weise ein, Ihre “Widmung”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  See OJ 11/54, [15], September 28, 1927.  </tei:note> zu sehen.  Noch in dieser Weise soll es geschehen, ich freue mich wild darauf.</tei:p><tei:p>Und so haben Sie, ich möchte sagen, in heiterer, zwangloser Weise mit Ihrer Erstdruck- u. Photogramm-Sammlung eine Menge Verdienste um Kunst u. Menschen (gestatten Sie das Wortspiel) gesammelt, die Ihnen gewiß belohnt werden.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Vivat, crescat, floreat</tei:hi>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  "Let it live, grow, flourish!"</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ihnen u. Ihrer verehrten Frau Gemalin unser Beider beste Empfehlungen</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">HSchenker</tei:hi>
4. 10. 27</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to van Hoboken, dated October 4, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Mr. van Hoboken,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Having myself, although author of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Yearbook</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> thus far received <tei:hi rend="italic">no</tei:hi> copy from the publisher, I had guiltlessly become party to a guilt of omission where you are concerned.  But I saw a copy already on Friday<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> at your house, learned yesterday of your new address and also that you have a copy, and thus I can only thank you from the heart for the kindness with which you have rendered a great service to the cause<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> and have spared me personally the necessity of taking the press to court.  Many, many thanks.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> It is typical of the press-gang that they immediately tug at your sleeve: “pay!”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>—they, who have been so evasive about matters of time and money.  Even our dear Mr. Deutsch,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> the true “Parsifal” of our circle, at the time inferred from the letters of the press a repeated actual “order”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>—so he expressed himself—, but the press had the audacity to renege on the order.  I could easily demonstrate by my galley-sheets that the press committed fraud in billing the corrections, but that wouldn’t be the end of it.  And as though the press could not afford the slightest luxury of honesty, I might mention that it advised me with a postcard of <tei:hi rend="italic">September 30</tei:hi>:  “we received your card of yesterday, which <tei:hi rend="italic">crossed</tei:hi> in the mail with your bound complimentary copies”;  that’s <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> what I call “crossing” when not a single copy has arrived by <tei:hi rend="italic">October 4</tei:hi>!  There’s nothing to top the impudence of publishers.  Since they can’t manage to square the circle, to place works of art on the same footing as, for example, groceries, clothing and the like, which everybody has to buy, they are obliged, in order to achieve a “decent” return on their capital, to become profoundly “indecent,” and so they contaminate the sphere of Art, which truly would deserve better men.  Granted, today artists and publishers are equals . . .</tei:p><tei:p>Thank you so much for all of your letters.  I hope you received my letters to Frankfurt and London.</tei:p><tei:p>Just recently I really had to marvel at the growth of your collection.  A portion of the new acquisitions of Beethoven items were shown me by Mr. Deutsch;  I will see the rest later, <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> with your permission.</tei:p><tei:p>Dr. Haas,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> who by political machinations was recently passed over for professorial promotion, kindly invited me to see your “dedication.”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/>  So it is to happen in this way;  I am just delighted.</tei:p><tei:p>And thus you have, I might say, with your first-edition and photostat collection, quietly and naturally collected (permit me the play on words) a multitude of services to art and mankind that will surely be rewarded.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Vivat, crescat, floreat</tei:hi>!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/></tei:p><tei:p>Our best wishes to you and your dear wife,</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] H. Schenker
October 4, 1927</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>