<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker"
   xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
   xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
   xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../schema/schenker.xsd">

   <sdo:collectionDesc>
      <sdo:source>
         <sdo:correspondence shelfmark="WSLB-298"/>
      </sdo:source>

      <tei:handNotes>
         <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="minor">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
      </tei:handNotes>

      <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
         <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
         <tei:resp>Transcription, 2009</tei:resp>
         <tei:resp>Translation, 2009</tei:resp>
         <tei:resp>Footnotes, 2009</tei:resp>
         <tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp>
      </tei:respStmt>
      <tei:respStmt xml:id="TL">
         <tei:persName>Tamara Lopez</tei:persName>
         <tei:resp>XML Encoding Model</tei:resp>
      </tei:respStmt>
      <tei:revisionDesc>
         <tei:change when="2009-03-12" who="#TL">Template Generated</tei:change>
      </tei:revisionDesc>
   </sdo:collectionDesc>

   <sdo:record ID="r0001">

      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Hertzka (UE), dated April 17, 1918</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1918-04-17</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-07-21</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>Schenker returns the article by Maurice Kufferath and comments on it
            critically. -- Beethoven did give phrase-markings, thus Schenker advocates inserting
            fingering but not additional phrase-marks. -- Diatribe against Hans von Bülow's editions
            and those who have emulated him. </dc:description>
         <dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich; Hertzka, Emil; UE; Kufferath, Maurice; Kaiserbrief; Sixtus;
            Poincaré, Raymond; Beethoven; Bach, J. S.; Fidelio; Rosé, Arnold; Bülow, Hans von </dc:subject>
         <dc:format/>
         <marcrel:correspondent key="HS"/>
         <marcrel:recipient key="EH"/>
         <marcrel:recipient key="UE"/>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:transcription>
         <tei:opener rend="first">
            <tei:salute>Sehr geehrter Herr <tei:persName n="Emil Hertzka">Direktor</tei:persName>!</tei:salute>
            <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"> Writing of this letter is
               recorded at OJ 2/10, p. 877: "An Hertzka (Br.): stelle mit Dank den possierlichen
               Franzosen zurück; über eine gefälschte Stelle für 'schallende Ohrfeige' 'mit Recht
               verdiente Ohrfeige'; ein Wort über die Ausgaben: Beethoven sei phrasiert zur Welt
               gekommen; seine Phrasierung reiche überdies für alle Solisten, Quartett- Konzert- u.
               Operngesellschaften aus – nur sonderbarerweise nicht für Klavierspieler; das sei aber
               so gekommen, daß die Verleger, was schließlich verständlich ist, berühmte Pianisten
               um Fingersätze gebeten haben u. daß diese nun die Gelegenheit wahrgenommen, auch noch
               ihre Phrasierung auf Beethovens Kosten dreinzugeben. Wenn Bülows Ausgabe so lange
               vorgehalten hat – trotz falschem Text u. falschen Erläuterungen, wie müßte da erst
               eine Ausgabe mit richtigem Text u. richtigen Erläuterungen vorhalten. Jenseits von
               der Notwendigkeit der Verlage Herbstauslagen zu arrangieren – Güte sei ein
               Modeartikel für sich." ("To Hertzka (letter): return the comical nchman with
               thanks; about a spurious passage 'rightly deserved cuff on the ears' instead of
               'reeling cuff on the ears'; a word on the editions: Beethoven came into the world
               phrased; what is more, his phrasings suffice for all the soloists, quartet, concert
               and opera societies – though oddly enough not for pianists; this came about because
               publishers asked famous pianists for fingerings, which is after all understandable,
               and they then took the opportunity of imposing their phrasings at the expense of
               Beethoven. If Bülow's edition has served for so long – despite incorrect text and
               incorrect commentary, how long would an edition with correct text and correct
               commentary hold out. Beyond the publishers' need to arrange a fall display –
               benevolence is itself an article of fashion.") </tei:note>
         </tei:opener>

         <tei:p>Mit bestem Dank stelle ich anbei den possierlichen <tei:persName
               n="Maurice Kufferath">Franzosen</tei:persName><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02"
               type="editorial" place="foot">See WSLB 295, <!--Insert cRef--> March 3, and OC
               52/205, <!--Insert cRef--> April 10. </tei:note> zurück. Daß er dort, wo ich außer
            paar Zeilen Vorworts u. einer Fußnote<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
               place="foot">Of <tei:bibl><tei:author>Schenker</tei:author>, <tei:title level="m">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von
                     Beethoven … op. 111</tei:title> (Vienna: UE, 1915)</tei:bibl>. Schenker
               understates the case here; he engages in inflammatory polemics in the Foreword, in a
               long footnote on the sinking of the Lusitania (p. 80), in a still longer footnote
               about World War I (pp. 83–85), and in several other shorter footnotes, including an
               attack on <tei:persName>Debussy</tei:persName> (p. 69). The passage alluded to later
               in this paragraph occurs in paragraph 4 of the footnote on p. 80, of which his
               wording in this letter is a slight paraphrase: "[…] begriff er [the Anglo-American,
               i.e. Woodrow Wilson] doch auch die Ohrfeige der Lusitania-Torpedierung nur deshalb,
               weil sie so schallend war […]" ("he really understood the box around the ears of the
               torpedoing of the Lusitania only because it was so resounding […]"). Further to that
               footnote, see <tei:bibl><tei:author>William Pastille</tei:author>, <tei:title level="a">Aesthetic Education:
                     On the Origins of Schenker's Musical Politics</tei:title>, in <tei:title
                     level="m">Essays from the Fourth International Schenker Symposium</tei:title>,
                  ed. <tei:editor>Allen Cadwallader</tei:editor> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 2008), pp. 183–95, esp.
               184–86.</tei:bibl>
            </tei:note> eine umfangreiche Darstellung des Inhaltes biete, sich nur gerade mit jenen
            paar Zeilen beschäftigt, kann auch in Deutschland vorkommen u. kommt auch vor. Daß er
            aber an manchen Stellen mein <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Original</tei:hi> u. seine
            Ǘbersetzung anführt, damit nur die Leser an seiner Ehrlichkeit nicht zweifeln, u. doch
            an einer recht wichtigen Stelle &#8222;<tei:hi rend="underline">schallende</tei:hi>
            Ohrfeige&#8220; in &#8222;<tei:hi rend="lateinschr">
               <tei:foreign xml:lang="fre">un soufflet <tei:hi rend="underline"
                  >légitimement</tei:hi> appliqué</tei:foreign>
            </tei:hi>&#8220;<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">Phrase
               quoted from Kufferath review. </tei:note>
            <tei:hi rend="underline">umfälscht</tei:hi>, ist spezifisch französisch u. bestätigt,
            was ich schrieb, im kleinen nicht minder, wie die soeben enthüllte grobe, plumpe
            Fälschung des Kaiserbriefes<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot"
               >Kaiserbrief: a letter, written by the <tei:persName n="Wilhelm I, Kaiser">Austrian
                  Emperor Karl I</tei:persName> to the <tei:persName
                  n="Sixtus Ferdinand of Bourbon-Parma">Prince Ferdinand of
               Bourbon-Parma</tei:persName>, seeking peace negotiations and offering certain
               concessions. The letter was exposed in April 1918, and published by <tei:persName
                  n="Georges Clémenceau">Clémenceau</tei:persName>, leading to the resignation of
               Karl's foreign minister, <tei:persName n="Czernin">Ottokar Czernin</tei:persName>.
            </tei:note> (auf dem Wege von <tei:persName n="Sixtus Ferdinand of Bourbon-Parma"
            >Sixtus</tei:persName> zum <tei:persName n="Raymond Poncaré">
               <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Poincaré</tei:hi>
            </tei:persName>) im Großen. Ja, die Herren Franzosen sind Spezialisten in
            &#8222;Freiheiten,&#8220; nur sehe man: welche, – in der
            &#8222;Freiheit&#8220; <tei:del hand="#HS">auf</tei:del> der Fälschung, der
            Eroberungen des Rheins einer unmenschlichen Gefangenenbehandlung u. <tei:unclear
               reason="reading">lauter</tei:unclear> solchen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn06"
               type="editorial" place="foot">"u. … solchen": written in the line above after
               "Rheins," then marked to be transposed to this point. (There is clearly something
               wrong with this sentence.) </tei:note> anderen Freiheiten mehr. </tei:p>

         <tei:p rend="first">Zur Frage der Ausgaben ein Wort: Sie irren sich, wenn Sie glauben, daß
               <tei:persName n="Ludwig van Beethoven">
               <tei:hi rend="lateischr">Beeth.</tei:hi>
            </tei:persName> so unphrasiert auf die Welt gekommen ist, wie z.B. <tei:persName
               n="J. S. Bach">
               <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Bach S.</tei:hi>
            </tei:persName> Seine <tei:hi rend="underline">eigene</tei:hi>
            <tei:rs type="musical-term">Phrasierung</tei:rs> ist so genau, ja so übergenau, daß sie
            seit den ersten Tagen bis auf die heutigen noch allen Sologeigern, Quartett-, <tei:pb
               n="2"/> Orchester-, Operngesellschaften (<tei:hi rend="lateinschr"><tei:rs
                  type="work" n="Beethoven, Fidelio">Fidelio</tei:rs>, Messen etc</tei:hi>)
            ausgereicht u. Allen Köpfe u. Hände voll zu schaffen gemacht hat! Liegt es nicht also
            auf der Hand, daß die paar Bearbeiter<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial"
               place="foot">"Bearbeiter": Schenker means editors who "work on" their editions,
               inserting fingerings, performance instructions, phrase-markings, etc. On this, see OC
               52/205 : <!--Insert cRef--> April 10, 1918. </tei:note> aus Eitelkeit u. Frechheit sich putzig machen
            mit ihren &#8222;Phr<tei:hi rend="underline"
               >i</tei:hi>sierungen,&#8220;<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8" type="editorial"
               place="foot">"Phrisierungen", from "frisieren": literally "hairdressing" or
               "hair-styling" (from "Friseur", hairdresser), with the implication of fakery.
               Schenker is deploying a play on words between "Phrisierung" and "Phrasierung."
            </tei:note> die das volle Gegenteil von <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Beeth</tei:hi>’schen
               <tei:rs type="musical-term">Phr<tei:hi rend="underline">a</tei:hi>sierungen</tei:rs>
            sind? Die Verleger baten zuerst um <tei:rs type="musical-term">Fingersätze</tei:rs> –
               <tei:hi rend="underline">das</tei:hi> ist verständlich –, der Bearbeiter gab dann
            noch als <tei:unclear reason="reading">Zuwege</tei:unclear>, eine nicht einmal erbetene,
            auch <tei:hi rend="underline">seine</tei:hi>
            <tei:rs type="musical-term">Phrasierung</tei:rs>! Diese niederträchtige Protzerei ließ
            natürlich den zweiten, dritten Bearbeiter nicht ruhen, u. so phrisieren sie um die
            Wette, während, wie gesagt, <tei:persName n="Rosé, Arnold">
               <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Rosé</tei:hi>
            </tei:persName>, <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">etc.</tei:hi> noch immer nach der ersten
            Phrasierung spielen, u. doch wohl auch mit Erfolg. </tei:p>

         <tei:p rend="first">Also <tei:rs type="musical-term">Fingersätze</tei:rs>, ja, – nur aber
            die <tei:rs type="musical-term"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
            >Original</tei:hi>phrasierung</tei:rs>. </tei:p>

         <tei:p rend="first">Was die Erläuterung anbelangt, ist nur folgendes zu sagen: Wenn bei
            einer völlig <tei:add hand="#HS" place="interlinear-above">falschen</tei:add>
            Darstellung die Ausgabe von <tei:persName n="Hans von Bülow">
               <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Bülow</tei:hi>
            </tei:persName> so viele Jahrzehnte vorhielt, vorhält u. noch vorhalten wird, blos wegen
            der Erläuterungen, die ja auch falsch sind, wie müßte erst vorhalten eine Ausgabe, der
            Niemand falschen Text u. falsche Erläuterungen vorwerfen könnte?! Was hat ein solches
            Werk, das gleichsam über den Moden stünde, mit den Bedürfnissen der Verlage nach neuen
            Herbst-Auslagen zu tun? Gar nichts. Neben <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Bülow</tei:hi> kamen
            u. giengen ja <tei:pb n="3"/> so viel Mode-Bearbeiter, – er blieb, trug Geld ein u.
            trägt <tei:supplied resp="#IB" reason="cutoff">es</tei:supplied> noch. Güte ist ein
            ewiger Mode-Artikel für sich. — </tei:p>

         <tei:p rend="first">Leider kam der franz. Aufsatz in eine schmutzige Hand<tei:supplied
               resp="#IB" reason="cutoff">;</tei:supplied> ich brauche nicht erst zu sagen, daß es
            auch eine reiche Hand ge<tei:supplied resp="#IB" reason="cutoff">wesen</tei:supplied>,
            so bitte ich um Entschuldigung wegen des Zustandes, in dem <tei:supplied resp="#IB"
               reason="cutoff">ich</tei:supplied> Ihnen den Aufsatz zurückzustellen genötigt bin. </tei:p>

         <tei:closer rend="indent-50">
            <tei:salute><tei:gap reason="illegible" extent="2" unit="word"/> bestens dankend u.
               herzlichst grüßend <tei:lb/>Ihr sehr ergebener</tei:salute>
            <tei:signed>
               <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">H Schenker</tei:hi>
            </tei:signed>
            <tei:date>17. April 1918</tei:date>
         </tei:closer>
         <tei:closer>© In the public domain. </tei:closer>
      </tei:transcription>

      <tei:translation>
         <tei:opener rend="first">
            <tei:salute>Dear <tei:persName n="Emil Hertzka">Director</tei:persName>,</tei:salute>
            <tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/>
         </tei:opener>

         <tei:p>Herewith enclosed, I return the ridiculous <tei:persName n="Maurice Kufferath"
               >Frenchman</tei:persName><tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> with many
            thanks. Whereas I, aside from a few lines of Foreword and a footnote,<tei:ptr
               corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> offer a comprehensive presentation of the
            content, he concerns himself solely with just those few lines. This is something that
            can happen, and does happen, in Germany, too. But the way that in many places he quotes
            my original and his translation, such that his readers will not doubt his honesty, and
            indeed at one really important point renders "<tei:hi rend="underline"
            >resounding</tei:hi> box around the ears" <tei:hi rend="underline">falsely</tei:hi> as
            "<tei:foreign xml:lang="fre">un soufflet <tei:hi rend="underline">légitimement</tei:hi> appliqué</tei:foreign>",<tei:ptr
               corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/> is quintessentially French and confirms what
            I wrote, in small matters no less than in large, cf. the coarse, crude falsification of
            the Emperor's letter<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"/> recently exposed
            (en route from <tei:persName n="Sixtus Ferdinand of Bourbon-Parma">Sixtus</tei:persName>
            to <tei:persName n="Raymond Poncaré">Poincaré</tei:persName>). Yes, these French fellows
            are specialists in "freedoms"; one need only consider, in the "freedom" of
            falsification, in the conquests of the Rhine, in an inhumane treatment of prisoners, and
            other such<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/> freedoms. </tei:p>

         <tei:p>A word about the matter of editions: you are mistaken in believing that
               <tei:persName n="Ludwig van Beethoven">Beethoven</tei:persName> saw the light of day as unphrased as, e.g.,
               <tei:persName>J. S. Bach</tei:persName>. His <tei:hi rend="underline">own</tei:hi>
            phrasing is so precise, indeed so super-precise, that from early days up to the present
            day it has sufficed for all solo violinists, quartet ensembles, <tei:pb n="2"/>
            orchestral and opera companies (<tei:rs type="work">
               <tei:title level="m">Fidelio</tei:title>
            </tei:rs>, masses, etc.) and given everybody plenty to work with creatively. Is it not
            thus apparent that the few heavy-handed editors,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn07"
               type="footnote"/> out of vanity and impertinence, sully themselves with their "window
               dressing,"<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08" type="footnote"/> which is in total contrast
            to Beethoven’s <tei:rs type="musical-term">phrase indications</tei:rs>? At first,
            publishers asked for <tei:rs type="musical-term">fingerings</tei:rs>—<tei:hi
               rend="underline">that</tei:hi> is understandable—, then the heavy-handed editor threw
            in something else that had not been asked for, his <tei:hi rend="underline">own</tei:hi>
            <tei:rs type="musical-term">phrasing</tei:rs>! This low-minded ostentation naturally
            forced the hand of the next arranger, and then the next, and so they vied with each
            other in window-dressing, while, as has been said, <tei:persName n="Arnold Rosé"
            >Rosé</tei:persName>, etc. continue to play according to the first phrasing, what’s more
            with great success. </tei:p>

         <tei:p rend="first">So <tei:rs type="musical-term">fingerings</tei:rs>, yes, but only the
               <tei:rs type="musical-term">original phrase markings</tei:rs></tei:p>

         <tei:p rend="first">On the subject of elucidation, let me say just the following: if with a
            totally <tei:add hand="#HS" place="interlinear-above">false</tei:add> presentation, the
            edition of <tei:persName n="Hans von Bülow">von Bülow</tei:persName> has lasted so many
            decades, still lasts, and will continue to last, solely on account of its elucidations,
            which themselves are totally false, how long must an edition last that is irreproachable
            as to its musical text and its elucidations?! What has such a work that is, so to speak,
            above all fashion, to do with the requirements of publishers for their new autumn window
            displays? Nothing whatsoever. Alongside von Bülow, <tei:pb n="3"/> so many modish
            editors came and went; he has outlived them, raked in the shekels, and is still raking
            them in. Benevolence is itself an eternal article of fashion. — </tei:p>

         <tei:p rend="first">Unfortunately, the French article found its way into dirty hands. I
            hardly need say that they were wealthy hands, so I ask your forgiveness for the
            condition in which I am obliged to return the article to you. </tei:p>

         <tei:closer>
            <tei:salute><tei:gap reason="illegible" extent="2" unit="word"/> with best thanks and
               most cordial greetings, <tei:lb/>Yours very truly,</tei:salute>
            <tei:lb/>
            <tei:signed>H Schenker </tei:signed>
            <tei:date>17. April 1918</tei:date>
         </tei:closer>
      </tei:translation>

   </sdo:record>
</sdo:recordCollection>
