<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="kohn_bernhard">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Bernhard Kohn</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="kohn_bernhard">Kohn, Bernhard</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>19/07/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Company</term>
          <term subtype="basename">kohn_bernhard</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Bernhard Kohn</head>
      <div>
        <!-- BODY: -->
        <p><hi rend="bold">Bernhard Kohn,</hi> proprietor of the piano firm of Kohn, founded in 1856, and located at Himmelpfortgasse 20, Vienna I.  In 1886, he is recorded for the first time as a piano dealer, supplying pianos made by Steinway, Bl&#xFC;thner und Schweighofer.  Among its customers were Gustav Mahler and members of the Wittgenstein family.  In 1926, Kohn was a member of the Genossenschaft der Klavier-, Harmonium und Orgelbauer in Wien (Association of piano, harmonium, and organ manufacturers in Vienna).</p>
        <p>At the end of the 1920s, together with the piano maker Friedrich Karbach, Kohn took over the Austrian piano manufacturer Schweighofer. At the same time, a descendant of the Schweighofer family opened a parallel piano factory and built instruments under the Schweighofer name. To distinguish them, sometime after 1920  Kohn &amp; Karbach put the original Schweighofer inscription on their instruments and added the Karbach name on the soundboards. The Schweighofer (Kohn &amp; Karbach) company produced pianos until 1938 when it was closed because Kohn was Jewish.</p>
        <p>Schenker's diaries of 1914 and 1918 show that Schenker hired his piano from Kohn, and that he sometimes used one of the company's piano tuners.</p>
        <p>No correspondence between Kohn and Schenker is known to survive.</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="italic">Sources:</hi>
        </p>
        <p>Genossenschaft der Klavier-, Harmonium und Orgelbauer in Wien, <hi rend="italic">Mitgliederverzeichnis 1926 </hi>(Vienna 1926), p. 11.</p>
        <p>Allan Janik and Hans Veigl, <hi rend="italic">Wittgenstein in Wien. Ein biographischer Streifzug durch die Stadt und ihre Geschichte</hi> (Vienna, New York 1998), p. 108-110.</p>
        <p>Jens-Uwe Witter, <hi rend="italic">Das Klavier-Lexikon. Namen und Fabrikate aus dem Klavier-, Orgel- und Harmoniumbau sowie Handel und Service von 1788-2000</hi>, 2nd edn (Rothenburg ob der Tauber 2000), p. 399.</p>
        <p>&lt;a href="http://schweighofer.tripod.com/history.htm"&gt;Schweighofer website&lt;/a&gt;</p>
        <p><hi rend="italic">Contributor:</hi>  Marko Deisinger</p>
        <!-- EXTENDED BODY: -->
        <!-- EXCERPT: -->
        <!-- KEYWORDS: -->
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
