<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 12/31, [2] : 7-1-24 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Under investigation
© Transcription Ian Bent, 2006.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is presumed to be in the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1924-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 07/01/1924 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "DeutschS ~ HSchenker","Lamberg ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Typed letter from Lamberg to Schenker, dated July 1, 1924</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-09-08</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>The Verein zur Speisung und Bekleidung hungernder Schulkinder in Wien has decided to dissolve itself and to assign to the Vienna Academy [i.e. Conservatory] the amount assigned for the stipends for impecunious musicians;  The Academy has accepted the administration of the stipends, and agrees that the award of the stipends shall be in the gift of S.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Lamberg, Ernst; Schenker, Heinrich;  Deutsch, Sofie; Sophie;  will; testament;  Verein zur Speisung und Bekleidung hungernder Schulkinder in Wien;  Association for Feeding and Clothing Hungry Schoolchildren in Vienna;  Kolm, Betty:  Nienert, Anka;  Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst;  Academy for Music and Representational Art;  Vienna Conservatory;  Marx, Josef;  Sofie Deutsch-Musiker-Stipendium;  Sofie Deutsch Stipendium for Musicians</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Vienna I, Mahlerstrasse 14</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Vienna III, Keilgasse 8, Door 12</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Lamberg to Schenker, dated July 1, 1924</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>]
Rechtsanwalt
Dr. Ernst Lamberg
WIEN I.
MAHLERSTRASSE 14
(FRÜHERE MAXIMILIANSTRASSE)
<tei:hi rend="italic">_</tei:hi><tei:hi rend="italic">_</tei:hi><tei:hi rend="italic">_</tei:hi><tei:hi rend="italic">_</tei:hi>_
Telefon Nr. -XXXXX- 76333.  
Postsparkasse-Konto 173.736</tei:p><tei:p>Wien, am <tei:hi rend="italic">1. Juli</tei:hi> 192<tei:hi rend="italic">4</tei:hi>
[<tei:hi rend="italic">typed:</tei:hi>]
F 33/O.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Professor!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich beehre mich zur Kenntnis zu bringen, dass der Verein zur Speisung und Bekleidung hungernder Schulkinder in Wien<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> Click on <ref cRef="verein_zur_speisung">Verein zur  Speisung ...</ref>.</tei:note> in seiner letzten am 19. Mai l. J. stattgefunden Generalversammlung den Beschluss gefasst hat, sich aufzulösen.</tei:p><tei:p>Für diesen Fall ist auf Grund eines Gerichtsbeschlusses 1/4 des dem Verein aus der Verlassenschaft<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Verlassenschaft</tei:hi>: Austrian for <tei:hi rend="italic">Hinterlassenschaft</tei:hi>, estate, property.</tei:note> zugefallenen Kapitales der Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  i.e. the Vienna Conservatory of Music, which held this title from January 1, 1909.  </tei:note> mit dem Ersuchen zu übergeben, die Erträgnisse dieses Kapitales im Sinne des Testamentes der Frau Sophie[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Deutsch zu verwenden und bis zu Ihrem Ableben Ihnen die Entscheidung über die Stipendien zu überlassen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  The wording of this paragraph is close to the corresponding paragraph in OJ 12/31, [1], December 7, 1923.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Dem Verein ist aus der Verlassenschaft ein Betrag von K 74,000.000.– zugefallen.</tei:p><tei:p>Der Verein hat nun in der Generalversammlung vom 19. Mai den Beschluss gefasst, der Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst einen Betrag von K 20,000,000.– zuzuwenden.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich habe die Akademie von dieser Zuwendung verständigt und von derselben das nachstehende Schreiben erhalten: <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> „Die Direktion der Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst beehrt sich im Grunde der geschätzten Zuschrift des „Vereines zur Speisung und Bekleidung hungernder Schulkinder in Wien“ mitzuteilen, dass die Akademie bereit ist, den ihr nach der testamentarischen Verfügung der Frau Sophie[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Deutsch zufallenden Betrag von K 20,000,000.– als Stiftung zu übernehmen, diese Stiftung unter dem Namen: „Sophie[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Deutsch-Musiker-Stipendium“ zu führen und die Zinsenerträgnisse jährlich zu zwei gleichen Teilen an zwei mittellose tüchtige Komponisten oder ebensolche Kompositionsschüler<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  The wording of this clause follows exactly that of OJ 12/52, January 12, 1917, from Fritz Mendl to S, although the latter does not specificy two stipends; which itself presumably reproduces the wording of the will itself.</tei:note> zu verteilen, sowie bis zum Ableben des Herrn Dr. Heinrich Schenker demselben die Entscheidung über die Verleihung der Stipendien auf Grund von der Musikakademie ihm übermittelter Ternavorschläge für jedes Stipendium zu überlassen.  Der Direktor: Josef Marx m.p.“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="marx_joseph">Joseph Marx</ref>.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ich bitte also höflichst, sich wegen der Ihnen zustehenden Entscheidung rechtzeitig vor dem nächsten Todestage der Frau Sofie Deutsch (5. I.) mit der Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst ins Einvernehmen setzen zu wollen.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich zeichne mit dem Ausdrucke besonderer Hochachtung als
Ihr [/] sehr ergebener
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ]  Dr Lamberg</tei:p><tei:p>Wohlgeboren Herrn Prof. Dr. Heinrich Schenker,
Wien III., Keilgasse 8, Tür 12.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Lamberg to Schenker, dated July 1, 1924</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>]
Attorney
Dr. Ernst Lamberg,
VIENNA I,
MAHLERSTRASSE 14
(PREVIOUSLY MAXIMILIANSTRASSE)
<tei:hi rend="italic">_</tei:hi><tei:hi rend="italic">_</tei:hi><tei:hi rend="italic">_</tei:hi><tei:hi rend="italic">_</tei:hi>_
Telephone No. -XXXXX- 76333.  
Post Office Bank Account 173.736</tei:p><tei:p>Vienna, <tei:hi rend="italic">July 1,</tei:hi> 192<tei:hi rend="italic">4</tei:hi>
[<tei:hi rend="italic">typed:</tei:hi>]
F 33/O.</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor,</tei:p><tei:p>I have the honor of informing [you] that the Association for Feeding and Clothing Hungry Schoolchildren in Vienna<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> at its last General Meeting on May 19 of last year took the decision to dissolve itself.</tei:p><tei:p>Against this event, on the basis of a court order, a quarter of the capital assigned to the Association from out of the estate is to be given over to the Academy for Music and Representational Art<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> with the request that the yields of this capital be used in the spirit of Mrs. Sophie[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Deutsch’s will and the decision over the stipends be left to you for your lifetime.</tei:p><tei:p>The Asssociation is assigned a sum of 74,000,000 Kroner out of the estate.</tei:p><tei:p>The Association has now decided at its General Meeting of May 19 to bestow the sum of 20,000,000 Kroner on the Academy for Music and Representational Art.</tei:p><tei:p>I have notified the Academy of this bestowal and have received from the same the following letter:  <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> “The Directorate of the Academy for Music and Representational Art has the honor, on the basis of the esteemed letter of the Association for Feeding and Clothing Hungry Schoolchildren in Vienna, of announcing that the Academy is willing to take over the sum of 20,000,000 Kroner assigned to it under the testimentary provision of Mrs. Sophie[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Deutsch as endowment, to administer this endowment under the name “Sophie[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Deutsch Stipendium for Musicians” and to divide the monetary yields annually into two equal parts for two impecunious skilled composers and similarly qualified composition pupils<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> as well as for the lifetime of Dr. Heinrich Schenker the leave decision over the awarding of the stipends to him on the basis of slates of three candidates per stipend supplied to him by the Music Academy.  The Director: Josef Marx m.p.”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/></tei:p><tei:p>With greatest respect, I therefore request you kindly to come to agreement with the Academy for Music and Representational Art as concerns the decision asigned to you punctually before the next death-date of Mrs. Sofie Deutsch (January 5).</tei:p><tei:p>I remain with specially kind regards,
Yours very truly,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Dr. Lambert</tei:p><tei:p>Professor Heinrich Schenker,
Vienna III, Keilgasse 8, Door 12.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>