<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/35, 20 : 7-24-22 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain; published with the permission of the heirs of August Halm, March 2006.
© Transcription Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Translation Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Lee Rothfarb 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2000, and is published with the permission of the heirs of August Halm, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1922-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Lee Rothfarb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 07/24/1922 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Halm ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated July 24, 1922</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-06-06</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>H announces publication of his three suites for piano trio, and has arranged for two of them to be sent to S.  He thanks S for sending him Kontrapunkt II, and expresses admiration for the "power of the broad conception" of S's work.  He is distressed at S's attacks on other countries and glorification of Germany, and speaks with appreciation of French and Russian music.  He describes his new publisher.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Halm, August; Schenker, Heinrich;  Three Suites;  Kontrapunkt II;  Schulgemeinde;  England;  France;  Russia;  Italy;  Germany;  Smetana;  Harden, Maximilian;  Die Zukunft;  Schubert;  Ihr Bild;  Beethoven;  Hammerklavier sonata;  Grosse Fuge;  Kallmeyer, G.</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated July 24, 1922</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>24.VII.22</tei:p><tei:p>Lieber u. verehrter Herr Professor!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Federhofer transcribes this entire letter in <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker: Nach Tagebüchern und Briefen</tei:hi>, 143-146.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Oft denke ich an Sie, wenn ich wieder einmal etwas aus Wien lese (aber nicht nur dann), u. mache mir Gedanken darüber, wie es Ihnen gehen mag.  Aber wenn ich dann die Portosätze auf österreichischen Briefen sehe, denke ich wieder, daß man niemand zu einem irgendwie vermeidbaren Brief veranlassen soll.  (Was ja auch bei uns zutrifft).  Es freut mich sehr, daß ich ein neues Heft bei Ihnen anmelden kann: Von 3 Suiten für Geige, Cello u. Klavier werden zwei zusammen in einem Heft erscheinen, das Sie sofort nach Erscheinen von mir erhalten sollen; ich habe den Verleger schon gebeten, dies zu besorgen.  Ich hoffe, Sie werden es vor Weihnachten noch erhalten.  Die Fahnen sind definitive korrigiert.</tei:p><tei:p>19.VIII.22
Der Brief wurde nun doch nicht mehr vor meiner kleinen Ferienreise fertig.  Einstweilen erhielt ich Ihren Kontrapunkt II; ich danke Ihnen herzlich für Ihre wertvollen Gaben.  Je mehr ich mir bewußt bin, wie wenig planvoll mein Arbeiten im ganzen, (ich meine nicht im einzelnen Stück) gewesen ist, desto mehr bewundere ich die Kraft der großen Konzeption, u. in der Ausführung, der langen, höchst aktiven Geduld, von der Ihre einzelnen Werke, auch abgesehen von i&lt;strike&gt;I&lt;/strike&gt;hrem großen Einzelwert, Zeugnis geben.  Ich will mich ja damit nicht <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> deshalb tadeln oder es herabsetzen, daß ich zumeist eben den Zufall gepackt habe, u. Sie dürfen gewiß nicht denken, daß ich etwa in falscher Bescheidenheit einen Trost oder ein Lob ernten möchte; ich bin im grund nicht unzufrieden mit dem Gang meiner Arbeiten, u. jedenfalls ist er meiner Natur gemäß.  Aber der Anblick eines planvollen u. willensstarken, langen Atems fähigen Strategen ist mir um so wertvoller, -d- als ich eben, selber ganz anders bin; u. so sehr Sie gewiß fühlen, wie Ihre Werke im Entstehen u. dann im Erscheinen behindert u. verzögert wurden durch allerlei äußeren Zwang u. Verlegerdummheit, etwa auch Verlegertücke, so dürfen Sie doch sicher sein, daß Sie mit Ihrem Schaffen diesen vorbildlichen u. stärkenden Anblick in selten hohem Maß gewähren.</tei:p><tei:p>Unsere gelben Schulgemeinde-Hefte sind am Aufhören; eine Besprechung (kurz, etwas summarisch, wie es nicht anders geht) hoffe ich noch in die Abschiedsnummer zu bringen, die aber selbst nicht ganz gesichert ist.</tei:p><tei:p>Um der Wahrheit willen -de- muß ich Ihnen sagen, daß mir Ihre Angriffe auf England u. Konsorten u. Ihre Verherrlichung der Deutschen leid sind.  Zum ersteren:  ich finde es unrecht, daß man von Seiten unserer frühen Feinde (die zum teil in schnöder Weise die Feindschaft forgsetzen, gewiß!) uns als Volk für die zweifellos von unserer Regierung begangenen <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Fehler[?]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker:  Nach Tagebüchern und Briefen</tei:hi>, 144, inserts the word “Fehler” to make sense of the sentence.  The word does not appear in the letter.</tei:note> bestrafen wollte u. vollends, daß man zum teil damit kein Ende finden will.  Umgekehrt ist es dann auch nicht recht, wenn wir jetzt die französische Regierung (ich nenne sie als den derzeitigen Hauptfeind) als das französische <tei:hi rend="italic">Volk</tei:hi> ansieht.  Irgendwann und irgendwo muß man mit dem Völkerhaß aufhören, u. wenn das für die Besiegten u. tatsächlich Betrogenen viel schwerer ist als es für die Sieger sein sollte, so wollen wir, indem wir trotzdem damit anfangen, unsere bessere Qualität beweisen.  Und wir wurden und werden ja auch von eigener Seite her belogen oder getäuscht.  Lese ich einmal bei Harden (den ich gewiß nicht gern mag (übrigens erfreute ich mich an zwei Besprechungen von Ihnen, über Smetena u. italjenische [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Opernaufführungen in alten Zukunft-Nummern, die mir ein Kollege zu lesen gab)) etwa eine Rede von <tei:hi rend="italic">Briand</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Aristide Briand (1862-1932) served eleven times as the premiere of France, and won the Nobel Peace Prize in 1926, shared with Gustav Stresemann.</tei:note> im Wortlaut: wie anders, wie viel besonnener, mäßiger, gebildeter klingt sie als die Auszüge u. Berichte in den Tageszeitungen vermuten lassen!  Kurz, wenn man nicht den ganzen Tag verschiedenste, namentlich auch ausländische Zeitungen lesen kann, so weiß man ja viel zu wenig, -ein- ^als daß man^ ein für das Urteil grundlegendes Bild -zu- haben könnte.  Zum zweiten: ich schätze zwar den Geist u. die Leistungen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  “u. die Leistungen“ ("and the accomplishments“): words indicated by S to be moved to this point from immediately before “aber” (“but”).</tei:note> französischer Kunst viel mehr als Sie, will aber nicht bestreiten u. glaube es sogar, daß <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> die deutsche Musik obenan ist.  Das <tei:hi rend="italic">kann</tei:hi> einen Vorrang der Deutschen bedeuten, es kann aber auch sein, daß es auf Kosten der andern geschieht, wenn ein Genie in Deutschland entsteht.  So scheint es mir, wenn ich an die Russen denke, die mir als Volk musikalischer vorkommen als wie die Deutschen, die aber weniger hoch kommen, was ihre Genies anbetrifft.  Bei uns große Erhebungen aus tiefer Niederung (was freilich für das Mittelalter nicht so gelten mag); dort, u. wohl auch in Italien, die höhere Ebene.  Natürlich dürfen wir das praktisch nicht gelten lassen, d.h. wir dürfen nun nicht das Erziehungswerk preisgeben, müssen handeln “als ob.”  Und Sie betonen ja gewiß auch die Tatsache der deutschen Niederungen u. Sumpfgelände u. Nebellande rückhaltlos genug.  Aber der Beruf zur führenden Rolle geht <tei:hi rend="italic">für Deutschland</tei:hi> nicht aus der Tatsache der größeren Zahl der überlegenen Genies <tei:hi rend="italic">in</tei:hi> Deutschland hervor.</tei:p><tei:p>Zu Einzelnem:  Das Lied:  Ich stand in dunkeln Träumen zähle ich nicht zur guten Musik, u der Nachweis sowohl der Urlinie als auch vieler Feinheiten ist für mich noch kein Beweis, daß ich Unrecht habe.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">   Halm refers here to Schenker’s analysis of Schubert’s song „Ihr Bild“, No. 9 of <tei:hi rend="italic">Schwanengesang</tei:hi>, in <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</tei:hi> 1 (1921): 46-49</tei:note>  Aber das kann ich nun nicht näher ausführen.  Ähnlich geht es mir mit den späten Sonaten Beethovens Adur (auch As dur), die mich eben einfach (gefühlsmäßig) nicht ganz überzeugen.  Der <tei:hi rend="italic">Typus</tei:hi> der Beethovenschen Fuge steht mir sehr hoch; ihn erfüllt hat Beethoven, wie ich meine, nur in der Hammerklaviersonate, in der großen B dur Fuge <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> für Streichquartett, u. wahrscheinlich in dem Finale der späten D dur-Sonate für Cello u. Klavier.  Sicher haben Sie mir gerade auch in solchen Stücken, die mir innerlich fremd sind, die Augen für viele gute Züge geöffnet u. ich empfinde auch bei einzelner Gegnerschaft Dankbarkeit dafür.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Halm inserts an emdash at this points and continues writing without a paragraph break.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ihre Aufstellung dessen, was eine Musikgeschichte aufhellen müßte, kam einem Bedürfnis von mir entgegen; ich habe schon ähnliches versucht, aber fand nicht diese Vielzahl der Fragen u. nicht die Ordnung.  Noch eines:  was ich oben schrieb, gilt auch für die angekündigte Sendung, in anderer Weise:  ich nehme an, daß sie (d.h. meine Suiten) etwa gerade zu einer Zeit zu Ihnen kommen, wo Sie mitten in dringender Arbeit sind.  Dann lassen Sie sich nicht stören u. warten Sie ruhig u. beliebig lang mit dem Schreiben.  Daß es mir nicht gleichgültig ist, was Sie dazu sagen, geht ja gewiß deutlich aus meiner ganzen Stellung zu Ihnen hervor, daß ichs nicht zu versichern brauche, u. auch eine etwa weniger günstige Kritik w[ü]irde -ich- ^mir^ von Ihrer Seite kommend, als ein Zeichen der Teilnahme gelten.  Wir haben hier diese Musik öfters gespielt; sie gehört zum Kammermusikbestand unserer Schulgemeinde.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Halm inserts an emdash at this points and continues writing without a paragraph break.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Leider sind unsere Verleger nicht so gescheit wie die Universal-Edition, die offenbar merkt, daß Veröffentlichungen immerhin jetzt zu den sichereren u. besseren “Papieren” gehören.  Mein neuer Verlag, G. Kallmeyer, ist ein <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> lieber u. anständiger Mensch, hält auch viel von mir.  Leider nicht sehr kapitalkräftig, kann er nicht viel auf einmal riskieren, sonst würde er gleich mehr von mir veröffentlichen.  Aber ich habe nun doch nichts selbst zu riskieren, u. überhaupt keine geschäftlichen Mühen dabei.</tei:p><tei:p>Sie wollten früher nach Deutschland ziehen—haben Sie den Plan zurückgestellt oder ganz aufgegeben?  Wir sind an unserer Schule noch ziemlich gut daran, aber wie lang wir der Teuerungsnot stand halten werden, weiß niemand.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit herzlichen Grüßen und Wünschen</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] August Halm</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated July 24, 1922</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>July 24, 1922</tei:p><tei:p>Dear and honored Professor,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>I think of you often when I read something from Vienna (but not only then), and worry about how you might be doing.  But when I then look at the postage on Austrian letters, I think that one should not prompt anyone to an avoidable letter.  (Which of course also applies to us).  I am very happy that I can announce a new volume:  of three suites for violin, cello and piano two will appear together in one volume, which you should receive from me immediately after publication.  I have already asked the publisher to take care of this.  I hope you will receive it before Christmas.  The galley-proofs have been definitively corrected.</tei:p><tei:p>August 19, 1922
The letter was not ready after all before my little vacation trip.  In the meantime I received your <tei:hi rend="italic">Counterpoint</tei:hi>,  volume 2.  I thank you heartily for your valuable gift.  The more I am aware how little system there was in my works as a whole (I do not mean individually), the more I admire the power of broad conception and, in execution, of the extensive, highly active patience of which your individual works testify, even apart from their great value separately.  I do not want <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> to fault myself, accordingly, or detract from the fact that I mostly just seized on coincidence, and you should certainly not think that in false modesty I am fishing for consolation or a compliment.  In principle, I am not dissatisfied with the course of my works, and it is in any case according to my nature.  But the sight of a systematic and strong-willed strategist  capable of extended breadth is to me the more valuable, since I am simply completely different.  And as certain as you feel that your works were impeded and delayed in emerging and appearing by all kinds of external constraints and publishers’ stupidity, perhaps also publishers’ malice, you can certainly be sure that with your output you afford that exemplary and invigorating perspective to an uncommonly high degree.</tei:p><tei:p>Our yellow community school volumes are ceasing.  I hope to offer one review (short, somewhat summarily, as it will work no other way) in the farewell issue, which however is not all together assured.</tei:p><tei:p>In truth, I have to tell you that your attacks on England and supporters and your glorification of Germany are distressing to me.  First, I find it unjustified that from the perspective of our former enemies (who to some extent continue the enmity contemptuously, to be sure!) we are punished as a people for the undisputed <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> errors[?]<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> committed by our government, and moreover that there is to some extent no end to it.  Conversely, it is also not right when we now view the French government (I name it as the main enemy at the time) as the French <tei:hi rend="italic">people</tei:hi>.  At some point, somewhere, people have to stop this ethnic hate.  And if that should be much more difficult for the conquered and actually betrayed than for the conquerors, then we prove our better quality by starting nevertheless.  And we were and are lied to or misled from our own side.  When I read in Harden (whom I certainly do not like (I was pleased, by the way, by two reviews of yours, on Smetena and Italian opera performances in past issues of <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Zukunft</tei:hi> that a colleague gave me to read)), a speech by Briand<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> in original wording:  how different, how much more level-headed, more moderate, more educated it sounds than the excerpts and reports in daily newspapers allow to surmise.  In short, if one cannot read the most diverse newspapers all day, especially foreign ones, we know far too little to have a fundamental picture for judgment.  Second,  I do value the spirit and the accomplishments<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> of French art far more than you, but do not dispute, and even believe, that <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> German music is on top.  That <tei:hi rend="italic">can</tei:hi> mean pre-eminence for German music, but it can also be that it comes at the expense of other music when a genius arises in Germany.  So it seems to me, when I think of the Russians, who as a folk appear to me more musical than the Germans, but who do not rise as high with respect to their geniuses.  In our case, grand elevations from the lowland (which of course does not hold so much for the Middle Ages).  There, and probably also in Italy, the higher plateau.  Naturally, practically speaking we may not allow that validity, i.e. we may not sacrifice the educational enterprise, must carry on “as though.”  And surely you emphasize the fact of German lowlands and marsh lands and foggy regions without holding back.  But the calling to a leading role does not follow  <tei:hi rend="italic">for Germany</tei:hi> because of the greater number of superior geniuses <tei:hi rend="italic">in</tei:hi> Germany.</tei:p><tei:p>In particular:  I do not reckon the song “I Stood in Dark Dreams” as good music, and verification of the Urlinie as well as of many refinements is for me still no proof that I am wrong.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  But I can not expound more fully on that now.  For me it is similar with the late Beethoven sonatas in A major (also A-flat major), which just simply do not fully convince me (according to feeling).  The <tei:hi rend="italic">type</tei:hi> of Beethoven fugue ranks very high for me.  Beethoven fulfilled it, as I think, only in the Hammerklavier sonata, in the great B-flat-major fugue <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> for string quartet, and probably in the finale of the late D-major sonata for cello and piano.  Certainly, you have opened my eyes to many good features precisely in those pieces that are internally foreign to me, and I feel gratitude for that, even with some opposition.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/></tei:p><tei:p>Your statement of that which a history of music would have to illuminate accommodates a need of mine.  I have already tried something similar but did not identify that abundance of questions nor the order.  And something else:  what I wrote above goes for the announced mailing, in another way.  I assume that they (i.e. my suites) will reach you just about at the time when you are in the middle of urgent work.  Then do not disturb yourself, and wait as long as necessary with writing.  That I am not indifferent to what you say about them is surely clear from my whole attitude toward you so that I do not need to give assurances, and even a somewhat less favorable critique coming from your side would be for me a sign of a support.  We have frequently played the music here [in Wickersdorf]; it is part of the chamber-music collection of our school community.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/></tei:p><tei:p>Our publishers are unfortunately not so bright as Universal Edition, which apparently notices that publications are after all now among the safer and better “securities.”  My new publisher, G. Kallmeyer, is a <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> dear and decent man, and thinks highly of me.  Not very strong in capital, unfortunately, he cannot risk too much at one time, otherwise he would publish more from me right away.  But I really do not have anything to risk myself, and have no associated business troubles.</tei:p><tei:p>Earlier, you wanted to move to Germany.  Have you postponed the plan or given up all together?  At our school we are still getting along rather well, but how long we can hold up to the inflation hardship no one knows.  With cordial greetings and wishes,</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] August Halm</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>