<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 15/34, [2] : undated --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Viktor Zuckerkandl: permission to publish kindly granted by Professor Emile Zuckerkandl, April 2007.
© Transcription Christoph Hust, 2007.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Christoph Hust &amp; Ian Bent 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1914?-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Viktor Zuckerkandl; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Christoph Hust &amp; Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 08/01/1914 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Zuckerkandl ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Viktor Zuckerkandl to Heinrich Schenker, undated („Friday“; probably August 1914 or 1915)]</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-03-29</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Is still in Vienna; has passed officer examination and is waiting to go on active service. 

</dc:description><dc:subject>Zuckerkandl, Viktor;  Victor;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Vienna;  Kaderdienst;  active service;  Brünauer, Robert</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Viktor Zuckerkandl to Heinrich Schenker, undated („Friday“; probably August 1914 or 1915)]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>]
V. Z.
[<tei:hi rend="italic">two lines crossed out</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>Freitag.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  The letter is written between the end of July and the beginning of September, so most probably in August.  That Zuckerkandl is looking forward to going into battle could suggest that it dates from 1914 or 1915 at latest, as the initial enthusiasm at the outbreak of World War I stereotypically displayed in this letter soon ceased (cf. Zuckerkandl's letter OJ 15/34, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="brunauer_dr">Robert Brünauer</ref>.  Remark suggests that he was on active service at this time.</tei:note>).</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Herr Doctor!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich „wirke“ also noch in Wien.  Ende Juli hatte ich Offiziersprüfung, natürlich gut bestanden.  Jetzt mache ich den sogenannten Kaderdienst,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Kaderdienst</tei:hi> :  presumably some form of basic military training.</tei:note> der darin besteht daß ich einige saudumme Rekruten unausgesetzt anbrüllen muß.  Von der grenzenlosen Langweile dieser Beschäftigung können Sie sich gar keinen Begriff machen.   Da ich alles vertrage, nur Langweile nicht, bekommt mir das gar nicht.  Gott sei Dank wird diese Tätigkeit nicht allzulang dauern.  Im Lauf des September komme <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> ich ins Feld.  Vielleicht in der ersten, wahrscheinlich aber in der zweiten Hälfte.  Die Musik ruht jetzt gänzlich, ich habe gar keine Zeit.  Wenn ich einmal eine Stunde frei habe bin ich viel zu abgespannt zum Arbeiten.  Ich freu mich schon aufs Feld, das wird doch im Vergleich zu dieser trostlosen Zeit viel Abwechslung bieten.  Dr. Brünauer sehe ich öfters,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="brunauer_dr">Robert Brünauer</ref>.  Remark suggests that he was on active service at this time.</tei:note> er hat noch gar keine Aussicht hinaus zu kommen.  Vielleicht sind Sie so freundlich und schreiben mir ein paar Zeilen bevor Sie nach Wien kommen, damit ich Sie hier gleich aufsuchen kann.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  At this time, S would be on summer vacation in the Tyrol.  S's diary tells about Zuckerkandl's visit on November 30, 1914 (cf. Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Nach Tagebüchern ...</tei:hi> (1985), p. 183).</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ihr ergebener
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] V Zuckerkandl</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Viktor Zuckerkandl to Heinrich Schenker, undated („Friday“; probably August 1914 or 1915)]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>]
V. Z.
[<tei:hi rend="italic">two lines crossed out</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>Friday.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>I am still “functioning“ in Vienna.  I had my officer’s examination in late July—I passed comfortably, of course.  Now I am doing so-called “cadre service,”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> which consists in my having incessantly to bellow at a bunch of dim-witted recruits.  You can have absolutely no idea of the endless boredom of this activity.  Since I endure everything, except for the boredom, it doesn’t at all get me down.  Thank God that this activity will not last all that long.  Sometime in September, <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> I go into active service—maybe in the first half, but probably in the second half [of the month].  Music is completely in abeyance, now;  I have absolutely no time.  If ever I get a free hour, I am much too worn-out to do any work.  I am already looking forward to active service;  it will be a big relief by comparison with this miserable time.  I see Dr. Brünauer frequently;  he still has no prospect whatsoever of getting out.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>   Perhaps you would be so kind as to write me a few lines before you return to Vienna, so that I can pay you a visit right away.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/></tei:p><tei:p>Yours truly,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] V Zuckerkandl</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>