<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 10/18, [3] : 7-11-28 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription Michaela Rejack 2006.
© Translated Michael Rejack, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Michaela Rejack 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1928-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Michaela Rejack.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 07/11/1928 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Elias ~ H+JSchenker","Elias ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Elias to Schenker, dated July 11, 1928</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-06-10</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>E recounts her recent travels; is pleased with S's reaction to her graph of his piano piece Op.4, No.1; expresses concern that she does not produce as much work as he gives her to do; has visited two exhibitions.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Elias, Angelika; Elias, Angi; Schenker, Heinrich;  Schenker, Jeanette;  Vienna;  Vent;  Zell am See;  Ötztal;  Schenker Five Piano Pieces;  graph;  Portraitierung;  Darstellung; Galtür;  Stifter-Ausstellung;  Schubert exhibition;  Erlkönig;  autograph;  first edition;  Das Meisterwerk der Musik 2;  The Masterwork in Music 2</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Vent</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Elias to Schenker, dated July 11, 1928</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Vent<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Vent is a ski village in the foothills of the Wildspitze mountain, near to Obergurgl and Sölden, in the Ötztal region.</tei:note> ^11^/VII-28.
b/ Herrn Norbert Karlinger</tei:p><tei:p>Liebe Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Es gab in den letzten Wochen zu Hause noch so viel zu tun, daß ich doch erst am 7. <tei:hi rend="italic">Juli</tei:hi> Wien verlassen konnte. Ich fuhr vorerst mit meiner Prager Schwester nach Zell a/ See<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Zell a/See: Austrian lakeside town in the Prinzgau, in the Salzburg area, with a glacier behind it, making it a popular ski-resort.</tei:note> und verbrachte dort mit ihr und ihren Kindern 1½ Tagen. Von dort aus ging es zunächst nach <tei:hi rend="italic">Ötztal</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Ötztal: a valley and region of the Austrian Tyrol.</tei:note> wo ich ^im <tei:hi rend="italic">Ötztaler</tei:hi> Hof^ übernachtete.  Gestern abends kam ich endlich in Vent<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Vent is a ski village in the foothills of the Wildspitze mountain, near to Obergurgl and Sölden, in the Ötztal region.</tei:note> an und bin nun glücklich, in dieser herrlichen Gegend bleiben zu können.</tei:p><tei:p>Da ich hier nun einen Ruhepunkt gefunden <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> habe, ist es mein erstes, Ihnen zu sagen, wie sehr es mich freute zu hören, daß Sie mit meiner Arbeit an Ihrem op 4 N^o.^1<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Schenker, Fünf Klavierstücke, Op. 4, No. 1, Andante (Leipzig: Breitkopf &amp; Härtel, 1898).</tei:note> nicht unzufrieden waren. Es gibt mir dies weiteren Mut zum Vorwärtsschreiten und nimmt mir etwas von der steten Sorge, im Verhältnis zu dem, was Sie mir geben, viel zu wenig zu leisten. Wenn mir die <tei:hi rend="italic">Portrait</tei:hi>ierung<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  „<tei:hi rend="italic">Portrait</tei:hi>ierung“: lit. the painting of a portrait: stresses the visual nature of her analysis.</tei:note> Ihres op 4 N^o.^1 halbwegs gelungen ist, so habe ich ja[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] auch das Ihnen allein zu verdanken, da mir ohne Ihr Zutun das Verständnis für die[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] Werke unserer großen Meister und somit auch für Ihre Tonstücke versagt gewesen wäre.</tei:p><tei:p>Es wird mich freuen im <tei:hi rend="italic">Oktober</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  i.e. when E resumes lessons with S.</tei:note> zu erfahren, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> was Sie an meiner Darstellung noch auszusetzen hätten und dann die Möglichkeit zu haben[,] die verborgensten Feinheiten in Ihrem wundervollen Klavierstucke zu hören.</tei:p><tei:p>Sie werden wohl am 19. <tei:hi rend="italic">Juni</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  S’s 60th birthday.</tei:note> viel Gluckwünsche[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] aus aller Welt erhalten haben, die Ihnen, von wahren Freunden der Tonkunst stammend, die wissen[,] was sie Ihnen zu verdanken haben, mehr Freude gemacht haben dürften, als[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] jede öffentliche Feier.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Vrieslanders Monographie</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.</tei:note> muß ja nun auch schon -erschienen- ^in Ihren Händen^ sein. Ich würde sie gerne lesen und wäre Ihnen sehr erkenntlich, wenn Sie mir mitteilen wollten, wo und in welcher[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] Form sie erschienen ist.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Hoffentlich haben Sie und Ihre liebe Frau sich in Galtür bereits von den Mühen der letzten Wochen in Wien erholt.  Das Wetter dürfte ^auch bei Ihnen^ günstig gewesen sein, so hoffe ich daß Ihnen der Aufenthalt in Tirol in jeder Weise zusagt.</tei:p><tei:p>Für die Empfehlung der Stifter-Ausstellung<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Adalbert Stifter (1805-68), Austrian landscape painter and short-story writer.</tei:note> danke ich noch herzlichst. Es gelang mir noch vor meiner Abreise einen Sprung dorthin zu machen. Auch die <tei:hi rend="italic">Schubert</tei:hi>-Ausstellung<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  1928 was the anniversary of Schubert’s death.  </tei:note> habe ich (wenn auch nur flüchtig) gesehen.  Das weitaus interessanteste war dort eine Vorbeneinanderstellung[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Vorbeneinanderstellung[?]: the first three letters have been written then overwritten for correction.</tei:note> vom[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">Autograph</tei:hi> des Erlkönigs und der Erstausgabe. Welche Verschiedenheit der Vortragsbezeichnungen auf den allein sichtbaren ersten zwei Seiten!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich habe hier schöne Ruhe und beabsichtige viel[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] zu lesen. Vor allem aber will ich mich am Jahrbuch II erfreuen. 
 
Beste Wünsche für Ihren weiteren Aufenthalt und herzliche Grüsse Ihnen und Ihrer lieben Frau</tei:p><tei:p>von Ihrer 
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Angi Elias</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Elias to Schenker, dated July 11, 1928</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Vent,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> July 11, 1928
c/o Mr. Norbert Karlinger</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>There was still so much to do in recent weeks at home that I could not leave Vienna until the July 7. I travelled first—with my sister from Prague—to Zell am See<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> and spent a day-and-a-half there with her and her children. From there I went first to Ötztal,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> where I spent the night in the Ötztaler Hof. Yesterday evening I finally arrived in Vent<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> and am now happily able to remain in this marvelous area.</tei:p><tei:p>Since I have now found a resting place here <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi>, it is my first task to tell you how very happy I was to hear that you were not dissatisfied with my work on your Op. 4 No. 1.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> This gives me the extra courage to press on, and relieves me somewhat of the constant worry that I achieve far too little in proportion to what you give me. If my depiction<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> of your Op. 4 No. 1 has been halfway successful, I have you alone to thank for it, because without your support an understanding of the works of our great masters and therefore also of your compositions would have been denied me.</tei:p><tei:p>I will be glad to learn in October<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> what else you still have to criticize about my representation and then to have the possibility of hearing the most hidden subtleties in your wonderful piano piece.</tei:p><tei:p>On June 19,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> you will have received many congratulations from all and sundry, which—coming from true friends of music who know what they have to thank you for—should have given you more joy than any public celebration.</tei:p><tei:p>Vrieslander's monograph<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> must surely by now already -have been published- ^be in your hands^. I would love to read it, and should be very grateful to you if you would let me know where and in what form it has been published.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> I hope that you and your dear wife have already recovered in Galtür from the exertions of recent weeks in Vienna. The weather ^even where you are^ should have have been favorable, and I hope that your stay in Tyrol suits you in every way.</tei:p><tei:p>I thank you most cordially for the recommendation to the Stifter exhibition,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/>.  I was able to make a quick visit to it just before my departure.  I have also seen the Schubert exhibition,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> if only fleetingly. The most interesting thing by far was the juxtaposition<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Erlkönig</tei:hi> autograph and the first edition.  What a difference in the performance indications in the first two pages, which was all that was visible!</tei:p><tei:p>I am having a nice rest here and intend to read a lot.  But above all, I am going to enjoy Yearbook II.</tei:p><tei:p>Best wishes for the remainder of your stay, and cordial greetings to you and your dear wife</tei:p><tei:p>from your 
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Angi Elias</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>