<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 10/18, [5] : 6-17-33 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription Michaela Rejack 2006.
© Translated Michael Rejack, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Michaela Rejack 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1933-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Michaela Rejack.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 06/17/1933 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Elias ~ H+JSchenker","Elias ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Elias to Schenker, dated June 17, 1933</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-05-27</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>E send best wishes, expresses concern at S's absence from a concert, and reports on a recent visit from Robert Brünauer.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Elias, Angelika; Elias, Angi; Schenker, Heinrich;  greetings;  Schloss Reigersberg;  Vienna;  Bamberger, Carl;  Stephan, Paul;  Beckmesser;  Brünauer, Robert;  Haydn</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Vienna</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Elias to Schenker, dated June 17, 1933</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Wien, 17/VI-1933</tei:p><tei:p>Lieber Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Des 19. Juni<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  19th June:  The Schenkers have clearly already departed for their summer holidays in the Tyrol [verify from diary], and their vacation has begun; either June 19 marks some important event, or Elias herself is going to join them on that day. Her offer, later in the letter, to take care of anything they need from Vienna may reinforce the latter possibility.   </tei:note> freudigst und dankbarst gedenkend sende ich Ihnen meine aller-allerherzlichsten Glückwünsche.  Wollten sie doch nur alle in Erfüllung gehen, vor allem auch das Weltgeschehen und Weltgewissen sich so wandeln, daß <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Ihnen für das viele Glück, das Sie spendeten und immer wieder spenden auch die entsprechende Freude entgegengebracht würde!  Und könnte doch auch ich die Möglichkeit haben, meine Dankbarkeit „werktätig“ zu beweisen wie ich es so sehr ersehne!</tei:p><tei:p>Für Ihre lieben Zeilen <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> danke ich Ihnen vielmals.  Ich zögerte anfangs, Sie zu bemühen, war aber durch Ihr unerwartetes Fernbleiben vom Konzert so beunruhigt, daß ich doch nicht umhin konnte, Sie um eine Nachricht zu bitten.  Hoffentlich haben Sie und Ihre liebe Frau die Strapazen der <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Übersiedlung einstweilen schon überwunden und werden Sie nun auf Schloss Reigersberg<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> A monumental fortress atop a volcanic rock in Eastern Styria. The oldest castle complex was built there around 1100 A.D. It has been privately owned by the Liechtensteins since 1822. </tei:note> schöne, erholende Tage verbringen können.  Es würde mich herzlich freuen zu hören, daß Sie es in jeder Weise gut getroffen haben.  Sollten Sie noch irgend etwas aus Wien brauchen, so würde <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> ich es gern besorgen.</tei:p><tei:p>Hatten Sie bereits eine Nachricht von Dr. Guttmann<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Dr. Guttmann [identify]</tei:note> und auch von Violin<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="violin_moriz">Moriz Violin</ref>.</tei:note>?</tei:p><tei:p>Anbei sende ich Ihnen eine sehr erfreuliche Würdigung Bambergers<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="bamberger_carl">Carl Bamberger</ref>.</tei:note> von Paul Stefan<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Paul Stefan (1879–1943), Austrian writer on music, pupil of Schoenberg, editor of UE’s progressive journal <tei:hi rend="italic">Musikblätter des Anbruchs</tei:hi> (1921–38), co-founder of the ISCM in 1922, music critic and author of books on music. </tei:note>.  Die Besonderheit der Leistung hat dem gestrengen Beckmesser<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7"> Elias is implying that even the narrow-minded critic (likened to Beckmesser in Wagner’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Meistersinger</tei:hi> ) could recognize the performance’s qualities.</tei:note> sichtlich imponiert.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> Es wird Sie überraschen zu hören, daß gestern Dr. Brünauer<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="brunauer_dr">Robert Brünauer</ref>.</tei:note> bei mir auf Besuch war.  Er holte sich Ihren Aufsatz „Was wird aus der Musik,“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9"> Schenker, “Was wird aus der Musik?,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Basler National-Zeitung</tei:hi> [Sonntagsbeilage], May 28, 1933, p.1.</tei:note> den er sich nicht hatte verschaffen können, und bei dieser Gelegenheit spielten wir die Ddur-Sinfonie von Haydn, die Bamberger dirigiert  <tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> hatte. An Begeisterung fehlte es nicht.  Trotz all seiner Fehler hat Dr. Brünauer doch, wie Sie es mir ja immer sagten, eine echte, glühende Liebe zur Tonkunst.</tei:p><tei:p>Nun aber schliesse ich mit nochmaligen innigsten Glückwünschen von Mama, meinem Bruder und mir.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> Ihnen und Ihrer lieben Frau viele herzliche Grüsse von uns allen, besonders von</tei:p><tei:p>Ihrer 
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Angi Elias</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Elias to Schenker, dated June 17, 1933</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Vienna, June 17, 1933</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>With 19th June<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> most joyfully and thankfully in mind, I send you my most sincere good wishes.  May they only all come to fulfillment, above all that <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> world events and the conscience of the world might change in such a way that for as much happiness as you have dispensed, and continue always to dispense, a corresponding amount of joy might be brought back to you.  If only I, too, could have the chance to prove my gratitude in my work as I long to do so much!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Many thanks for your dear missive.  I hesitated initially to bother you, but I was so disturbed by your unexpected absence from the concert that I could not resist asking you for some news.  I hope you and your dear wife have in the meantime already overcome the strain <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> of the move and will now be able to spend pleasant relaxing days at Castle Reigersberg<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>.  It would sincerely please me to hear that everything has turned out well with you.  If you should need anything from Vienna, <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> I would be glad to take care of it.</tei:p><tei:p>Have you heard any news yet from Dr. Guttmann<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> and also from Violin<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>?</tei:p><tei:p>Enclosed I send you a very pleasing assessment of Bamberger<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> by Paul Stefan<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/>.  The remarkable quality of the achievement evidently impressed the severe Beckmesser<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> You will be surprised to hear that Dr. Brünauer<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> paid me a visit yesterday. He borrowed your article “What is Happening to Music?”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/>, which he had been unable to get for himself, and while he was here we played the D major Symphony by Haydn that Bamberger <tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> had directed. There was no lack of enthusiasm.  In spite of all his mistakes, Dr. Brünauer has, as you indeed always told me, a genuine, glowing love for music.</tei:p><tei:p>Now I will close with most heartfelt renewed best wishes from Mama, my brother and me.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> To you and your dear wife many sincere greetings from all of us, especially from</tei:p><tei:p>Your 
[signed:] Angi Elias</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>