<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 10/18, [15] : 2-27-38 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription Michaela Rejack 2006.
© Translation Michaela Rejack 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Michaela Rejack 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Jeanette (1938-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Michaela Rejack.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 02/27/1938 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Elias ~ H+JSchenker","Elias ~ JSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Elias to Jeanette Schenker, dated February 27, 1938</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-03-12</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Regrets that many teachers who admire S teach from non-Schenker textbooks;  is puzzled that JS has not received early volumes of Der Dreiklang; refers to Mengelberg's forthcoming broadcast performance of St. Matthew Passion;  conveys thanks from the Kahns, and sends best wishes.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Elias, Angelika; Elias, Angi; Schenker, Jeanette;  Gardone;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Thuille, Ludwig; Magister;  Gries-Bolzano;  Dreiklang, Der;  St. Matthew Passion;  Bach, J. S.;  Kahn, Marianne;  Kahn, Trude;  Pucki</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Vienna XIII, Nikolausgasse 1</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Gries-Bolzano, Guesthouse Regina, Italy</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Elias to Jeanette Schenker, dated February 27, 1938</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{envelope: <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
[An:] Wohlgeboren [/] Frau D^r.^ Heinrich Schenker
<tei:hi rend="italic">Gries–Bolzano</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  The postcard is not known to have survived: presumably the “picture postcard Gardone” named on the envelope.</tei:note>
Pensione Regina
<tei:hi rend="italic">Italien</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in another hand:</tei:hi>] Ansichtsk[arte] Gardone</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>]  || [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>] | [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>] 5–18 | [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>] ||</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{envelope: <tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
[Absender:] Angi Elias. Wien XIII, Nikolausgasse 1.</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>]  || BOL[ZANO] | [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>] | GRIES ||</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{letter}</tei:hi>
Wien, 27/II-38.</tei:p><tei:p>Liebe Frau Professor!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Elias writes this letter in the period between the Berchtesgaden agreement, February 12, and the annexation of Austria, March 12, 1938 without giving any sense of the threat then hanging over Vienna.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Herzlichen Dank für Ihre liebe Karte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  The postcard is not known to have survived: presumably the “picture postcard Gardone” named on the envelope.</tei:note> Es freute mich sehr zu hören, daß Sie die Fahrt gut verbrachten und auch angenehme, musikalische Reisegesellschaft hatten. Daß die Dame, die Sie kennen lernten nach Thuille<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Ludwig Thuille (1861–1907), Austrian composer, erstwhile professor at the Königliche Musikschule in Munich;  reference is to Rudolf Louis and Ludwig Thuille: <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (Stuttgart: Carl Grüninger Nachf., 1907, 2/1908, 3/1910, 10/1933).</tei:note> unterrichtet wurde <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> entspricht leider - leider, der üblichen Gepflogenheit.  So viele Lehrer bewundern und schätzen Schenker und greifen trotzdem aus Trägheit und auch aus Angst, der Schüler könnte sie durch eine, die Meisterwerke betreffende, Frage in Verlegenheit bringen, zu den alten Büchern zurück. Aber das wird auch noch einmal anders <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> werden!</tei:p><tei:p>Nun bin ich neugierig zu hören, ob Sie den netten alten Magister<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Magister: meaning unclear.</tei:note> wiedergesehen haben und mit welchen Schenker nahestehenden Menschen Sie ein freundlicher Zufall wieder zusammenführen wird.  Da der März vor der Türe steht werden wohl bald wärmere Tage kommen, da werden Sie <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> nicht mehr lange der einzige Gast in Ihrer Pension sein.  Es ist schade, daß Sie nicht etwas länger in Wien blieben, um gleichzeitig mit dem Frühling in Gries<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Gries–Bolzano: Gries–S. Quirino is a district of Bolzano, city in the Trentino–South Tyrol region;  since 1915, the region had been assigned to Italy.  </tei:note> einzutreffen. Immerhin muß[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] es auch in der kalten Jahreszeit in Gries sehr schön sein!</tei:p><tei:p>Wieso Ihnen die alten Hefte des „Dreiklang“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Dreiklang: Monatsschrift für Musik</tei:hi> (Vienna: Krystall-Verlag, 1937–38), ed. Oswald Jonas and Felix Salzer, of which issue 8/9 (November 1937/February 1938) was the last to be produced, Jonas emigrating to the United States in 1938 and Salzer soon after that. </tei:note> zugeschickt wurden, kann auch ich mir nicht <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> erklären. Die angekündigten Hefte 8 u. 9 erwarte ich täglich.</tei:p><tei:p>Mengelbergs Aufführung der Matthäus-Passion<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Mengelberg, (Josef) Willem (1871–1951), Dutch conductor, principally of the Amsterdam Concergebouw Orchestra, which he conducted for 50 years from 1895.  He was a specialist in performing Richard Strauss and Mahler, and an advocate of Schoenberg and Reger, but his annual Palm Sunday performances of the <tei:hi rend="italic">St. Matthew Passion</tei:hi>, which began in 1899, were famous.  </tei:note> wird Freitag den 4. März durch den Rundfunk übertragen, da werden Sie sie wohl auch in Gries hören.</tei:p><tei:p>Marianne und Trude Kahn<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="kahn_marianne">Marianne Kahn</ref>.</tei:note> danken vielmals für Ihre <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> lieben Grüße, die sie herzlichst erwidern.</tei:p><tei:p>Lassen Sie bald wieder hören, wie es Ihnen und der herzigen kleinen Pucki<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Pucki:  perhaps a dog?.</tei:note> geht. Ihnen weiterhin das Schönste für Ihren Aufenthalt wünschend grüßt Sie herzlichst.</tei:p><tei:p>Ihre
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Angi Elias</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Elias to Jeanette Schenker dated February 27, 1938</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{envelope: <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
[To:]  Frau Dr. Heinrich Schenker
<tei:hi rend="italic">Gries–Bolzano</tei:hi>
Guesthouse Regina
<tei:hi rend="italic">Italy</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in another hand:</tei:hi>] Picture postcard Gardone</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>]  || [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>] | [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>] 5–18 | [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>] ||</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{envelope: <tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
[From:] Angi Elias. Vienna XIII, Nikolausgasse 1.</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>]  || BOL[ZANO] | [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>] | GRIES ||</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{letter}</tei:hi>
Vienna, February 27, 1938</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Frau Professor,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Sincere thanks for your kind postcard.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  I was delighted to hear that you had a good journey and also pleasant musical travel companions.  That the lady with whom you became acquainted was taught according to Thuille<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> unfortunately corresponds with the usual practice. So many teachers admire and value Schenker and nevertheless resort to the old books, out of laziness and also out of fear that the student might embarrass them through a question concerning the masterpieces. But even this <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> will change once more!</tei:p><tei:p>Now I am curious to hear whether you have seen the nice old Master<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> again and which of the people who were close to Schenker you will again be brought into contact with by happy chance. Since March is almost upon us, warmer days will surely come soon, then you will <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> no longer be the only guest in the guest house.  It is a pity that you did not remain a little longer in Vienna so that your arrival in Gries<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> coincided with the coming of spring.  Nevertheless it must be very lovely in Gries during the cold season, too!</tei:p><tei:p>Why the early volumes of <tei:hi rend="italic">Dreiklang</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> were sent to you even I do not <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> understand.  I wait for the announced volumes 8 and 9 daily.</tei:p><tei:p>Mengelberg’s performance of <tei:hi rend="italic">St. Matthew Passion</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> will be broadcast on Friday, March 4th over the radio, you will probably also hear it there in Gries.</tei:p><tei:p>Marianne and Trude Kahn<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> thank you profusely for your <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> kind greetings, which they most sincerely reciprocate.</tei:p><tei:p>Send news again soon of how you and sweet little Pucki<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> are doing. Finally, wishing you all the best for your stay and most sincere greetings to you.</tei:p><tei:p>Yours 
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Angi Elias</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>