<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="correspondence_eg"
    xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Example of an item from Schenker's correspondence</title>
                <title type="sub"/>
                <author/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>compiled by</resp>
                    <name>Ian Bent</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
        <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
        <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>This resource is publicly available and free at the point of access and it is
                        registered under a a <ref type="external"
                            target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">Creative Commons
                            license Attribution-Share Alike 3.0</ref>
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at
                http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/about/encoding/</p>
        </encodingDesc>

        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-05-28</date>
                <name>PC</name>
                <desc>Template Created</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date/>
                <name/>
                <desc/>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>

        <body>

            <div>
                
                    <figure>
                        <graphic n="overviews_eg" url="correspondence_eg.jpg" xmt:type="thumb-caption" rend="left-img"
                            width="350px" height="534px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <graphic url="correspondence_eg.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img"
                            width="870px" height="1336px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                        <figDesc>Photograph of letter from Heinrich Schenker to Otto Erich Deutsch</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                
                <p><hi rend="bold">Letter from Schenker to Otto Erich Deutsch, May 15, 1930 (OJ 5/9,
                        [3])</hi></p>
                <p>Otto Erich Deutsch had by 1930 established himself as the leading authority on
                    Schubert and his music. He was also a book dealer in Vienna and the librarian of
                    a collection of manuscripts and early editions. Schenker ‒ no respecter of
                    persons! ‒ clearly held him in high regard. The two had been in correspondence
                    since 1913, Schenker had produced a volume for a series edited by Deutsch, and
                    the two had collaborated editorially.</p>
                <p>The letter shown here bespeaks cordiality between the two men: the informality of
                    the handwriting, absence of an address at the head of the letter, curtailed
                    signature "HSch," and the way the letter plunges into its subject without
                    preliminaries. It includes music notation, with simple analytical annotations
                    below. The whole letter is in Schenker's usual black-brown ink, except for the
                    reddish-brown crayon marking out the final paragraph, which may be Schenker's
                    way of drawing attention to the change of subject or Deutsch's way of marking
                    something that he needed to remember.</p>
                <p>To see the <hi rend="italic">Schenker Documents Online</hi> edition of this
                    letter, go to <ref target="/documents/correspondence/OJ-5-9_3.html">OJ 5/9,
                        [3]</ref></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
