<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="diaries"
    xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Diaries</title>
                <title type="sub"/>
                <author/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>compiled by</resp>
                    <name>Ian Bent</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
        <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
        <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>This resource is publicly available and free at the point of access and it is
                        registered under a a <ref type="external"
                            target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">Creative Commons
                            license Attribution-Share Alike 3.0</ref>
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at
                http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/about/encoding/</p>
        </encodingDesc>

        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2009-08-06</date>
                <name>TL</name>
                <desc>Template Created</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date/>
                <name/>
                <desc/>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>

        <body>

            <head>Diaries</head>

            <div>

                <p>Over a period of forty years, from 1896 to 1935, Schenker maintained meticulously
                    detailed diaries, a rich repository of information of all types. The diaries
                    before 1912 are written in Heinrich's own hand, on a variety of sizes and
                    formats of paper. After 1912 they were taken down, by dictation, in the hand of
                    his companion (later wife) Jeanette in a consistent format: 9 x 11½ inches (23 x
                    29 cms), 25 lines per page, in minute handwriting. In all, they comprise 3,970
                    pages.</p>

                <p>Abundant in biographical matter, they include information about Schenker's
                    family, the fine detail of every-day life, domestic arrangements, daily
                    appointments, professional schedules, meetings with friends (with summaries of
                    conversations), medical conditions, purchases, payment of bills, etc. The
                    reports of concerts, operas, plays, and exhibitions both attended and read about
                    in newspapers (with critical reactions), and (later in life) of the radio
                    programs and 78rpm recordings to which he listened, all these paint a vivid
                    portrait of Viennese cultural life and Schenker's ever-pungent response to it.
                    The diaries also chart the genesis and development of his published and
                    unpublished writings, his dealings with publishers, authorities, attorneys,
                    Viennese musical institutions and their officials, the performers and conductors
                    of his day, and the workings of his private piano teaching studio. </p>

                <p>Schenker took a keen interest in political and social matters. His reports (at
                    first and second hand) mirror the course of European history as it unfolds
                    through pre-war events, World War I, the inter-war years, and the rise of
                    Nazism—all viewed from his unrepentantly German-nationalist standpoint.
                    Paradoxically, he was a Jew who retained his allegiance to Judaism, and his
                    portrayals of Jews in an anti-semitic Vienna are of great social-historical
                    interest. He offers an "insider" account of the deprivations suffered by
                    Viennese in the later war years and subsequent period of hyper-inflation. At the
                    same time, he affords wonderful insights into the world of the Viennese
                    coffee-house, with its gatherings, chance encounters, debates, and hard-fought
                    negotiations. </p>

                <p>Between September 1914 and the end of the war, Schenker made numerous entries
                    about troop movements, battles, official diplomatic “notes” issued by various
                    governments (especially with regard to the sinking of the Lusitania in 1915),
                    newspaper articles, and the effect of the war on his own life and that of his
                    friends an pupils. Between late November 1918 and early June 1919, however, he
                    kept a separate, unnamed document in which he refers to all the newspaper
                    articles he read on the political situation in Europe in the aftermath of
                    Germany's surrender. During this period, then, there are usually two diary
                    entries, in separate manuscripts; to help readers distinguish between them, one
                    of these is specifically marked "Political Diary."</p>

            </div>




        </body>

    </text>
</TEI>
