<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="other_material"
    xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Latest Material</title>
                <title type="sub"/>
                <author/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>compiled by</resp>
                    <name>Ian Bent</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
        <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
        <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>This resource is publicly available and free at the point of access and it is
                        registered under a a <ref type="external"
                            target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">Creative Commons
                            license Attribution-Share Alike 3.0</ref>
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at
                http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/about/encoding/</p>
        </encodingDesc>

        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2009-08-06</date>
                <name>TL</name>
                <desc>Template Created</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date/>
                <name/>
                <desc/>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>

        <body>

            <head>Latest Material</head>

            <div>
                <head>CORRESPONDENCE</head>

                <p>13 letters from <hi rend="bold">Manfred Willfort</hi> to Schenker, and to
                    Jeanette after Heinrich's death, spanning 1931‒35, offer insights into the
                    workings and personal relationships of Schenker's Friday Seminar, and a hitherto
                    unknown episode in the attempted late revision of Schenker's <title level="m"
                        >Theory of Harmony</title>. — Of four items between <hi rend="bold">Moriz
                        and Valerie Violin</hi> and Schenker from late 1917, one gives new
                    information about Schenker's mother, Julia, and the behavior of Heinrich's
                    siblings toward her. These items are all new to <hi rend="italic">SDO</hi>.</p>

                <p>20 letters and postcards from <hi rend="bold">Josef Weinberger</hi> spanning 1898
                    to 1905 deal with publication by Weinberger's company of the <title level="m"
                        >Syrian Dances</title> in two versions, and show Weinberger as a director of
                    Universal Edition dealing with the <title level="m">C. P. E. Bach Keyboard
                        Works</title>, the <title level="m">Contribution to Ornamentation</title>,
                    the arrangements of <title>Handel Organ Concertos</title>, and the <title
                        level="m">Instrumentation Table</title>. We see Weinberger rejecting
                    Schenker's early offer to UE of his <title level="m">Theory of Harmony</title>.
                    — 35 letters between <hi rend="bold">Universal Edition</hi> and Schenker span
                    1901 to June 1908; in addition to the above-listed items, these are the opening
                    sallies of what was to become a fiery relationship between Schenker and UE's new
                    director, <hi rend="bold">Emil Hertzka</hi>. These items have moved from the
                    former <hi rend="italic">SDO</hi> site to the new.</p>

            </div>

            <div>
                <head>PROFILES</head>

                <p>Of major importance is the trio of new profiles, <title level="m">Carl Philipp
                        Emanuel Bach</title>; <title level="m">C. P. E. Bach: Klavierwerke</title>;
                    and <title level="m">Beitrag zur Ornamentation</title>, authored by William
                    Drabkin, Hedi Siegel, and Ian Bent. New also are the profile on Schenker's
                    arrangements of <title>Handel Organ Concertos</title> (1905), and an overhaul of
                    the series profile on the <title level="m">Erläuterungsausgabe</title>, and
                    individual profiles for Op. 109, Op. 110, Op. 111, and Op. 101. Other new
                    profiles portray August Artaria, Rudolf Maria Breithaupt, Franz Hardtmuth, and
                    Bernhard Herzmansky; the Doblinger Musikhaus; Gmunden, Richardgasse, Traungasse,
                    and a revision of Reisnerstraße to incorporate Nos 18 and 38. </p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>DIARIES</head>

                <p>The diaries for 1912 to 1914 are currently being transcribed and translated. They
                    should begin to be accessible on the site by the end of 2016. They cover the
                    publication of <title level="m">Beethoven's Ninth Symphony</title>, and the
                    writing and publication of the first two of <title level="m">The Last Five
                        Sonatas of Beethoven</title>. They also contain numerous mini-essays on
                    subjects such as wealth, commerce, and the place of women in society, as well as
                    Schenker's view of the war.</p>
            </div>
        </body>

    </text>
</TEI>
