<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="other_material"
    xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Latest Material</title>
                <title type="sub"/>
                <author/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>compiled by</resp>
                    <name>Ian Bent</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
        <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
        <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>This resource is publicly available and free at the point of access and it is
                        registered under a a <ref type="external"
                            target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">Creative Commons
                            license Attribution-Share Alike 3.0</ref>
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at
                http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/about/encoding/</p>
        </encodingDesc>

        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2009-08-06</date>
                <name>TL</name>
                <desc>Template Created</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date/>
                <name/>
                <desc/>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>

        <body>

            <head>Latest Material</head>

            <div>
                <head>OSWALD JONAS CORRESPONDENCE</head>

                <p>The 20-year-long exchanges between <ref cRef="entity-000412">Oswald Jonas</ref>
                    and Schenker ‒ spanning 1918 to 1938 ‒ constitute one of the most important
                    narratives among the Schenker correspondences. Jonas was Schenker's pupil
                    1918‒20, and thereafter studied with Hans Weisse. His value to Schenker
                    increased during the 1930s with the emergence of his book <title level="m">Das
                        Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks</title> (1934).</p>

                <p>The newly available material, covering 1932 to 1938, is dominated by the
                    preparation and publication of that book in parallel with Schenker's completion
                    of <title level="m">Der freie Satz</title>, and by the unpredictabilities of
                        <ref cRef="entity-000380">Anthony van Hoboken</ref> as the financial backer
                    of both works (something which arouses Schenker’s indignation).</p>

                <p>With the coming to power of the Nazis, Jonas's work in Berlin rapidly diminishes
                    from early 1933. One by one doors close on him as a Jew. His situation becomes
                    increasingly difficult, but his comments to Schenker are always so guarded that
                    one has to read between the lines.</p>

                <p>In two striking letters ‒ OJ 5/18, 33 and 49 (December 21, 1933 and August 2,
                    1934) ‒ Schenker makes far-reaching statements about his own Jewishness.</p>

                <p>Jonas's communications with Jeanette Schenker after Heinrich's death allude to
                    her giving him privileged access to Heinrich's unpublished papers, and to his
                    plans with Salzer to found the periodical <title level="j">Der
                    Dreiklang</title>.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>OTTO ERICH DEUTSCH CORRESPONDENCE</head>

                <p>The correspondence of the musicologist and bibliographer <ref
                        cRef="entity-000164">Otto Erich Deutsch</ref> and his wife Hannah to
                    Schenker and his wife Jeanette spans twenty-six years, from 1913 to 1939. The
                    subjects addressed in their exchanges vary widely and were substantive. Deutsch
                    was one of the relatively few professional people whom Schenker generally held
                    in high regard.</p>

                <p>The correspondence between Deutsch and Schenker in 1922 is primarily concerned
                    with Schenker’s fee for his facsimile edition of <ref cRef="entity-001754"
                        >Beethoven’s “Moonlight” Sonata</ref> (Vienna: UE, 1921), which was part of
                    the series “<title level="s">Musical Rarities: Viennese Connoisseur
                        Prints</title>,” of which Deutsch was general editor, and the hunt for other
                    suitable facsimile-edition subjects. Correspondence for 1923 is lost, but that
                    surviving from 1924 again revolves around financial matters. 1925 sees
                    discussion of Schenker’s contribution to a Schubert special issue of <title
                        level="j">Moderne Welt</title> (December 1, 1925), which Deutsch edited, and
                    during 1925‒26 there is an increasing number of references to social
                    gatherings.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>SCHENKER’S DIARIES JANUARY 1931 TO MAY 1934</head>

                <p>These years show, above all, a marked decline in Schenker’s health – he found it
                    necessary to consult a doctor frequently – and he tried reducing his workload in
                    order to concentrate as much as possible on <title level="m">Free
                        Composition</title>, the writing and proofreading of which is sometimes
                    recorded in meticulous detail. He had laid <title level="m">The Art of
                        Performance</title> aside in December 1930, but was still kept busy revising
                    his edition of the Beethoven sonatas, preparing the text for Brahms’s manuscript
                    study of consecutive fifths and octaves, working with students and engravers on
                    the <title level="m">Five Analyses in Sketchform</title>, and writing short
                    polemical essays for Hermann Rinn’s <title level="j">Der Kunstwart</title>
                    (later renamed the <title level="j">Deutsche Zeitschrift</title>).</p>

                <p>We also witness the fluctuating relationship with his pupil and principal
                    benefactor, <ref cRef="entity-000380">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>; his continued
                    collaboration with <ref cRef="entity-000164">Otto Erich Deutsch</ref>; and the
                    moments of elation bestowed upon him by the activity of a younger generation,
                    including <ref cRef="entity-000973">Hans Weisse</ref>, <ref cRef="entity-000412"
                        >Oswald Jonas</ref>, and <ref cRef="entity-000131">Israel Citkowitz</ref>.
                    Perhaps unsurprisingly, one observes an increase in expressions of spirituality,
                    as Schenker faces each new year "mit Gott", reads from the Old Testament while
                    on holiday, and conceives <title level="m">Free Composition</title> as a
                    religious offering.</p>
            </div>
        </body>

    </text>
</TEI>
