<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lessonbooks"
    xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Lessonbooks</title>
                <title type="sub"/>
                <author/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>compiled by</resp>
                    <name>Ian Bent</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
        <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
        <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>This resource is publicly available and free at the point of access and it is
                        registered under a a <ref type="external"
                            target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">Creative Commons
                            license Attribution-Share Alike 3.0</ref>
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at
                http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/about/encoding/</p>
        </encodingDesc>

        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2009-08-06</date>
                <name>TL</name>
                <desc>Template Created</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date/>
                <name/>
                <desc/>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>

        <body>

            <div>
                <head>Lessonbooks</head>

                <div>
                    <head>The nature of the lessonbooks</head>
                    <p>Over nearly 20 years, from 1912 to 1931, Schenker kept details of the piano
                        and theory lessons that he gave in his own apartment. Comprising 580 pages
                        in four bound volumes, these <hi rend="italic">Stundenbücher</hi> – written
                        by dictation in the hand of his companion (later wife) Jeanette, and
                        including many separate slips of paper ("lesson notes") in Heinrich's own
                        hand – record the musical works learned by each student, the features of
                        piano technique taught, the passages of his own theoretical works and those
                        of others – particularly in harmony, counterpoint, and thoroughbass –
                        assigned for reading and discussion, the written exercises done and graded,
                        the theoretical issues raised, the analyses conducted, and the studies made
                        of facsimiles of composers' autograph manuscripts and sketches and of early
                        printed editions. </p>
                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>Internal organization of the lessonbooks</head>
                    <p>There are two aspects of the organization of the lessonbooks that it is
                        important for users of this edition to understand. </p>

                    <div>
                        <head><hi rend="italic">Saison</hi></head>
                        <p>Each year of these lessonbooks mirrors Schenker's teaching year – what he
                            called his <hi rend="italic">Saison</hi> – by running from October 1 of
                            a given year to late June of the next year. In this online edition, such
                            a year is designated as e.g. "1917/18", thus covering from October 1,
                            1917 to c. June 21, 1918. </p>
                    </div>

                    <div>
                        <head>Ordering of contents</head>
                        <p>Schenker's method of organizing the contents of each <hi rend="italic"
                                >saison</hi> changed over the years. He adopted two essentially
                            different methods, with a transitional period from the former to the
                            latter, as follows. <lb/><lb/>
                            <hi rend="bold">19[11]/12 – 1914/15</hi> – arranged chronologically by
                            date, each date containing the lesson notes for the pupils of that day,
                            presumably in time order.<lb/><lb/>
                            <hi rend="bold">1915/16 – 1923/24</hi> – at first (1915/16), the <hi
                                rend="italic">saison</hi> divided into months, with pupils arranged
                            in alphabetical order within each month; then (1916/17 – 1919/20) the
                                <hi rend="italic">saison</hi> broken into two periods, with pupils
                            arranged alphabetically within each period; then (1921/22 – 1923/24)
                            presented as single <hi rend="italic">saisons</hi>, with pupils arranged
                            alphabetically, but with no dates at the beginning of entries.<lb/><lb/>
                            <hi rend="bold">1924/25 – 1930/31</hi> – arranged by pupil in
                            alphabetical order, the lessons for each pupil given in chronological
                            order, with lesson date at the beginning of each entry </p>
                    </div>

                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>The value of the lessonbooks</head>
                    <p>This information is significant not only in charting the progress of
                        individual pupils, but also for the insights that it offers into Schenker's
                        teaching methods, and the way in which those methods changed over the years.
                        Of great interest is the comparison of those methods with his unpublished
                        work <title level="m">Die Kunst des Vortrags</title> (The Art of
                        Performance: 1911 and later). Of potentially even greater interest is the
                        determination of the extent to which his teaching influenced the works he
                        published over the period 1912 to 1935, many of which contain detailed
                        remarks on performance of specific works. </p>

                    <p>Another field of study opened up by the lessonbooks is the comparison of his
                        "school" of teaching with those of other famous Viennese teachers of his
                        day, such as Theodor Leschetizky, Richard Robert, and Emil Sauer, through
                        their publications and editions, and the words of their pupils. </p>

                </div>
            </div>
        </body>

    </text>
</TEI>
