<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="lessonbooks_eg"
    xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Example of a page from Schenker's lessonbooks</title>
                <title type="sub"/>
                <author/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>compiled by</resp>
                    <name>Ian Bent</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
                <address>
        <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
        <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <p>This resource is publicly available and free at the point of access and it is
                        registered under a a <ref type="external"
                            target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">Creative Commons
                            license Attribution-Share Alike 3.0</ref>
                    </p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at
                http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/about/encoding/</p>
        </encodingDesc>

        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>2012-05-28</date>
                <name>PC</name>
                <desc>Template Created</desc>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date/>
                <name/>
                <desc/>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>

        <body>

            <div>

                <figure>
                    <graphic n="overviews_eg" url="lessonbooks_eg.jpg" xmt:type="thumb-caption"
                        rend="left-img" width="370px" height="537px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    <graphic url="lessonbooks_eg.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img" width="870px"
                        height="1336px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
                    <figDesc>Photograph of page from lessonbook</figDesc>
                </figure>

                <p><hi rend="bold">Lesson notes for Hans Weisse April 1 to June 3, 1924</hi></p>
                <p>Hans Weisse embarked on lessons in theory and composition with Schenker in 1908.
                    His instruction is recorded in the lessonbooks from 1912 to 1927. Schenker noted
                    down the content of Weisse's lessons in particular detail, sometimes including
                    music examples and voice-leading graphs. The richness of these notes suggests
                    that Weisse was a valued pupil (though Schenker often complained about him!) who
                    asked penetrating questions and raised serious musical issues.</p>
                <p>Jeanette Schenker's hand is upright, incisive, and clear ‒ a cursive hand unlike
                    the older German handwriting that Heinrich mostly used. She wrote on pages
                    scored with feint green lines. She left gaps for the musical notation, all of
                    which is in Schenker's hand. One can imagine Schenker instructing his wife in
                    how much space to leave while she was making the fair copy (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Reinschrift</hi>). The two worked closely together as a team ‒ more perhaps
                    than is generally realized.</p>
                <p>This page contains notes on the Beethoven Choral Fantasy, Chopin Polonaise in C
                    minor, C. P. E. Bach F-major Sonata, the Brahms <hi rend="italic">Song of
                        Destiny</hi>, and a Schubert Waltz. It shows that Weisse did homework prior
                    to lessons, and that he and Schenker worked on voice-leading graphs during the
                    lessons. Notable are Schenker's own markings in green and red crayon:
                    underlinings, but also a marginal annotation, and markings over one of the small
                    music examples</p>
                <p>To see the <hi rend="italic">Schenker Documents Online</hi> edition of this set
                    of lesson notes, go to <ref
                        target="/documents/lessonbooks/OC-3-3_1923/r0010.html">LB 23/24, p.14</ref>;
                    the page shown here begins about three-quarters of the way through the entry, at
                    "{14}aufgabe zur".</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
