<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [19] : 7-18-29 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2006.
© Translation by William Drabkin 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1929-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 07/18/1929 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated July 18, 1929</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-08-31</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Acks two postcards;  no word from Eric Voß;  reports on teaching activities;  reports on composing and sends two sonatas for S's comment.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  Voß, Erich;  Voss, Erich;  temperature;  weather;  Conservatory;  pupils;  theory classes;  sonatas;  Kahnt, C. F.;  Leipzig;  Hoffmann;  Weisse, Hans;  Oppel, Reinhard;  Berlin</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Duisburg, Rhineland, Pulverweg 41</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated July 18, 1929</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Duisburg/Rhld.
Pulverweg 41.
18.VII.29.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Vielen Dank für die beiden Karten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> i.e. vC 24 and 25, July 6 and 14.</tei:note> Von Herrn Voss<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Erich Voss: see OJ 9/34, [18], May 14, 1924;  vC 23, May 15; vC 24, July 6; vC 25, July 14, 1929.  Voss does not appear in S’s Lesson Books.</tei:note> habe ich seit seinem Brief nichts mehr vernommen.  Damals schien von finanziellen Schwierigkeiten noch nichts wahrnehmbar.  Inzwischen wird er – wie so viele – dem wirtschaftlichen “Aufbau” zum Opfer gefallen sein.  Ich hoffe, dass er trotzdem seinen Weg zu Ihnen finden wird. –</tei:p><tei:p>Hier ist inzwischen die saure Gurken Zeit ausgebrochen. Wir haben 38° im Schatten (soweit von Schatten überhaupt gesprochen werden kann) und man tut gut, jede körperliche Bewegung auf das notwendige Minimum zu beschränken.  Jede freie Stunde wird zur Flucht ins Strandbad benützt.  Für die Ernte das gegebene Wetter – mir persönlich wäre im Augenblick ein möglichst hartnäckiger Landregen mit etwas polarer Ventilation sympathischer. –</tei:p><tei:p>Das “Geschäft” ist auch im Sommerschlaf versunken.  Den ganzen Winter, bis jetzt war ich recht zufrieden.  Augenblicks ist wiedermal flaue Zeit. Wenn ich überhaupt wegfahren kann, wird es wohl nicht weit werden.  Momentan habe ich im Konservatorium 8 Schüler und drei Theorieklassen, privat nur drei Schüler. Getragen von der Hoffnung auf bessere Zeiten, kann man auch davon leben. –</tei:p><tei:p>Meine zweite Sonate ist jetzt endlich fertig. <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Ich habe einen neuen Schlusssatz ziemlich rasch komponiert.  Es ging wie von selbst, und ich glaube nicht dass er schlecht ist. Anbei sende ich Ihnen beide Sonaten; die erste kennen Sie ja, bis auf den langsamen Satz, und Teile des Rondos.  Die erste geht nach Leipzig zum C. F. Kahnt-Verlag, dessen Besitzer, Herr Hoffmann, nicht abgeneigt scheint, sie zu drucken. Erste Auflage natürlich ohne Honorar!  Die zweite möchte ich einem grösseren Verlag andrehen.  Ich wäre Ihnen <tei:hi rend="italic">sehr</tei:hi> dankbar für Rat- und Vorschläge, habe ich doch noch gar keine Verbindung zu solchen Leuten.  Wer hat denn Dr. Weisses und Prof. Oppels Sachen gedruckt?  Vielleicht könnte Ihre Begutachtung und die Duisburger Kritik (als Beweis der “Uraufführung”) doch einen Verleger bewegen[,] einen Versuch damit zu machen. –</tei:p><tei:p>Ich gehe schon wieder mit neuen Plänen schwanger, indes ist die Hitze zu gross um klare Gedanken zu krystallisieren.  Auf jedenfall habe ich jetzt nach der Vollendung zweier grösseren Sachen viel Mut und Lust für Weiteres. –</tei:p><tei:p>Durch meine Schwester öffnen sich neuerdings Perspektiven nach <tei:hi rend="italic">Berlin</tei:hi>.  Im Winter fahre ich hin, um die Lage zu sondieren. Bis dahin wird die hohe Protektion bearbeitet. –</tei:p><tei:p>Wenn ich von Leipzig Antwort habe, schreibe ich sofort.</tei:p><tei:p>Für heute viele herzliche Grüsse Ihnen und Ihrer Frau Gemahlin, und gute Erholung!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>;  Reinhard Oppel [create biogfile and link]. </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Felix v. Cube.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated July 18, 1929</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Duisburg, Rhineland
Pulverweg 41				 		
July 18, 1929</tei:p><tei:p>Most honoured master,</tei:p><tei:p>Many thanks for your two cards.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> Since receiving his letter, I have heard nothing more from Mr Voss.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> At the time I did not perceive any financial difficulties. In the mean time he, like so many others, has probably fallen victim to commercial “development”. I hope that he might, in spite of this, find his way to you.</tei:p><tei:p>Here, in the meantime, the quiet season is in full swing. The temperature is 38° in the shade (insofar as one as able to speak of shade at all), and one does well to restrict one’s bodily movements to the necessary minimum. Every free hour is used for the flight to the beach. It’s just the right weather for the harvest; personally, I would find a steady downpour, as persistent as possible, with a somwhat polar ventilation, more agreeable at the moment.</tei:p><tei:p>Business has also sunk into summer sleep. The entire winter, and up to now, I was entirely satisfied. At the moment it is again slack time. If I can get away at all, it will probably not be to a far-off place. At the moment I have eight pupils and three theory classes at the Conservatory, but only three private pupils. Sustained by the hope of better times, one can also live on this.</tei:p><tei:p>My second sonata is now, finally, complete. <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> I wrote a new finale rather quickly. It went almost automatically, and I do not believe that it is bad. I am sending you both sonatas herewith; you of course know the first one, apart from the slow movement and parts of the rondo. The first is being sent to the Leipzig publishing house of C. F. Kahnt, whose owner, Mr Hoffmann, does not seem disinclined to publish it: for the first impression, naturally, there will be no honorarium. For the second sonata, I would like to approach a larger publishing house. I would be <tei:hi rend="italic">very</tei:hi> grateful to you for advice and suggestions. Who, for instance, published Dr Weisse’s and Prof. Oppel’s things?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> Perhaps a reference from you, together with the Duisburg reviews (as evidence of the “premiere”) could indeed movate a publisher to have a go with it.</tei:p><tei:p>I am once again pregnant with new plans; at the moment the heat is too great to crystalize clear thoughts. In any event, now that two rather large sonatas are finished, I have a lot of courage and appetite for further things.</tei:p><tei:p>Through my sister, perspectives are lately emerging in <tei:hi rend="italic">Berlin</tei:hi>. I shall go there in the winter, to test the waters. Until then, I shall work on obtaining the patronage of important people.</tei:p><tei:p>As soon as I have an answer from Leipzig, I will write to you.</tei:p><tei:p>For today, many affectionate greetings to you and your wife, and best wishes for your recovery!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/></tei:p><tei:p>Your
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Felix von Cube</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>