<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [6] : 1-24-27 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2006.
© Translated by William Drabkin 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1927-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 01/24/1927 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated January 24, 1927</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-06-09</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Acks S's reply and corrections.  There will be no problem with his teacher's examination in May.  Reports on recent activities.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich; Duisburg Conservatory;  examination;  pupil;  Bach;  Chopin;  Schubert</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Duisburg, Rhineland, Mühlheimerstrasse 141/II</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated January 24, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Duisburg, Rhld.
Mühlheimerstr. 141/II.
24.I.27.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Besten Dank für Brief und Korrekturen!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> In his previous letter, OJ 9/34, [5], December 31, 1926, Cube sent Schenker an analysis with which he felt confident, asking for comments and corrections. Schenker’s reply does not survive, and we do not know what piece Cube had analysed; but it is clear from the tone of what follows here that he is somewhat embarrassed by the mistake he had made.</tei:note> Natürlich die Sept! Wie konnte ich das wieder überhören. Ob mich die Kürze des Stückes verleitet hat? Bis jetzt habe ich es immer nur soweit gebracht, nur auf diesem Felde ehrenvolle Blessuren zu holen. Wann werde ich es einmal zu einem bescheidenen Lorbeerblättchen bringen?</tei:p><tei:p>Am Conservatorium bin ich angestellt.  Das Lehrerexamen mach ich im Mai nach. Zur Prüfungskommission gehören drei mir bekannte Herren. Damit wird es keine Not weiter haben.  Eine meiner Schülerinnen – Seminaristin – ist erfreulich begabt. Alles andere – – “Holzwolle”.  Donnerstag spiele ich im öffentlichen Conservatoriumskonzert Bach, Chopin und Schubert.</tei:p><tei:p>Nebenbei lasse ich mich in Schulen und Gymnasien “aushängen” und versuche alles was Bezug auf unsern Beruf hat. Vielleicht werde ich demnächst auch Kritiker an einer Zeitung.</tei:p><tei:p>Alles von Wichtigkeit sollen Sie sofort erfahren. Einstweilen herzlichste Grüsse Ihnen und Ihrer Frau Gemahlin</tei:p><tei:p>von
Ihrem
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated January 24, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Duisburg, Rhineland
Mühlheimerstrasse 141/II
24 January 1927</tei:p><tei:p>Most honoured Master,</tei:p><tei:p>Best thanks for your letter and the corrections!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> The seventh, of course! How could I possibly have missed hearing it? Might I have been misled by the brevity of the piece? Until now, I have only ever gotten as far as sustaining honourable wounds on this field; when will I, for once, succeed in gaining a modest laurel leaf?</tei:p><tei:p>I have been appointed at the Conservatory. I will take the teacher’s examination in May. The examining committee comprises three gentlemen who are known to me; there will be no further problems with it.   One of my female pupils – a seminarist – is delightfully gifted. All the rest: “wood-shavings”.  On Thursday I am playing Bach, Chopin and Schubert in a public concert at the Conservatory.</tei:p><tei:p>In addition, I have been “hanging out” in schools and grammar schools, and try everything that is related to our profession. Perhaps I shall soon become a critic for a newspaper, too.</tei:p><tei:p>I shall report anything of importance to you immediately. For the time being, most affectionate greetings to you and your wife from</tei:p><tei:p>Your
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>