<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [31] : 5-8-32 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2008.
© Translation William Drabkin 2008.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1932-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 05/08/1932 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated May 8, 1932</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-06-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Cube sends Schenker an Urlinie graph of Schubert's song Der Dopplegänger, and offers an extended commentary.  — Describes his work and state of mind, and comments on working with Moriz Violin; he expresses fears for the Hamburg Schenker Institut. — He has just got married.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  Schubert;  Doppelgänger;  Urlinietafel;  Urlinie graph;  Quartzug;  fourth-progression;  Keimzelle;  germ-cell;  Ur-Satz;  Aussensatz;  outer voices;  Quintparallelen;  consecutive fifths;  Chroma;  chromatic note;  Ablauf;  course;  Grundton;  fundamental tone;  Brechung;  arpeggiation;  Dreiklang;  triad;  Abstieg;  descent;  Vordergrund;  foreground;  Violin, Moriz;  Violin, Karl;  Wien;  Vienna;  Gesellschaft Hamburger Tonkünstler;  Reichsverband deutscher Tonkünstler und Musiklehrer;  marriage</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Hamburg 37, Innocentiastrasse 11</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated May 8, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hamburg 37, Innocentiastraße 11.
8. V. 32.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter, lieber Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Heute schicke ich Ihnen meine erste, ganz selbstgefertigte “sprechende” Urlinietafel von Schubert’s “Doppelgänger”.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  A song from Schubert’s last collection, <tei:hi rend="italic">Schwanengesang</tei:hi>.  This was a work, and an analysis, that Cube held dear, for it is included among the graphic analyses in his <tei:hi rend="italic">Lehrbuch der musikalischen Kunstgesetzte</tei:hi>.  This graph is also reproduced (and discussed) in Hellmut Federhofer’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Akkord und Stimmführung in den musiktheoretischen Systemen von Hugo Riemann, Ernst Kurth und Heinrich Schenker</tei:hi> (Vienna: Österreichische Akademie der Wissenschaften, 1981), pp. 109–12), and again in David Neumeyer’s review of Federhofer’s book in the <tei:hi rend="italic">Journal of Music Theory</tei:hi>, 27 (1983), p. 104. </tei:note>  Ich glaube zu wissen, dass mir damit was Guts gelungen ist.  Eine prinzipielle Frage habe ich mit einer Portion Mut und Selbstvertrauen zu lösen gesucht.   Es mag falsch sein, aber ich weiss immerhin, dass es mehr eine Notationsfrage, denn ein Hörfehler ist. Ich meine die merkwürdige Verschiebung der diatonischen ~4 von ihrem, eigentlich durch den Bass vorgeschriebenen Platz.  Ich konnte mich nicht entschliessen, den Ablauf der Oberstimme[,] wie er in Fig. 4 und Fig. 5 dargestellt ist, auch auf den diatonischen Ursatz anzuwenden, wie ich umgekehrt in den obengenannten Figuren nicht schon das, mittlerweile in eine Mittelstimme abgewanderte eis^2^ als ~4 deklarieren wollte.  So habe ich versucht auszudrücken, wie die diatonische ~4 e^2^ infolge der “nachäffenden” Erhöhung der III zu eis^2^ wird, und nebennotenartig zu fis^2^ zurückgewendet werden muss, von wo aus das Ganze in zwei Quartzügen über dem orgelpunktartigen Fis des Basses, der ja eigentlich schon die ~3 d^2^ tragen sollte, zum Grundton<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Grundton</tei:hi>: normally a word meaning “root” (of a triad), but here used in the melodic sense of the starting tone of the scale (and goal-tone of the Urlinie), ~1.</tei:note> abläuft.  Die einzige “fremde Feder” in meiner Arbeit ist das “Nachäffen”, das Herr Dr. Weisse einmal mir gegenüber gesprächsweise erwähnt hat.  Ich fand es anschaulich genug um es in’s Bild aufzunehmen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  No paragraph break at this point in the original.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Nun will ich meine Gedankengänge kurz erläutern: Fig. 1.) a.) Die Keimzelle des Ur-Satzes.  b.) Einbeziehung unvollkommener Konsonanzen in den Aussensatz. c) Entstehung des, die Bassbrechung vom H zum Fis auskomponierenden Quart- <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Zuges H–A–G–Fis, die Quintparallelen von ~5 zu ~4 des Aussensatzes sind durch das zwischengeschaltete D der Brechung H-D-Fis paralysiert.  d.) Einbezieh[ung] der Chromen in den Aussensatz, und die dadurch bedingte Zurückwendung der chromatisierten ~4 zu nochmaligem Fis, mit eiligem Ablauf zum Grundton. Fig. 2.)  Aspekt des diatonischen Typus im vierstimmigen Satz.  Fig. 3.)  Der Färbungsprozess vierstimmig;  Stufen aus Dur bezogen, bei der #VII Erhöhung von 3 und 5; Zurückwendung der eis^2^ zum fis^2^ um dem natürlichen Aufwärtsdrang gegenüber einem zu harten Abwärtsschritt nachzugeben. Fig. 4.)  Das Spiel der Imitationen und Brechungen im Aussensatz.  Das eingeklammerte ais der Mittelstimme in Takt 8 würde durch Vollständigkeit der Dreiklänge die blosse Verstärkungswirkung der Oktaven in eine üble Parallelenwirkung verkehren.  Aus demselben Grunde bleibt in Takt 11 das a der Mittelstimme liegen, ohne sich an den Imitationen zu beteiligen.  Von Takt 43 an zeigt fis^1^ seinen Abstieg in die Mittelstimme, um einer fünften Stimme Platz zu machen, die die dritte Brechung zum Zweck des Hinaufgelangens zu fis^2^ übernimmt, da wegen der serieusen harmonischen Bewegung für das Spiel der Imitationen, die die erste und zweite Brechung trugen, kein Platz mehr ist.  Der Vordergrund, Fig. 5.), verdeutlicht die Einzelheiten. Fig. 6.) zeigt das “künstlerisch[e”] Gewissen in Bezug auf Vollständigkeit der motivischen Kombinationen.  Ich bin erklärlicherweise auf’s höchste gespannt, wie Sie diese meine jüngste Arbeit beurteilen werden! Mein persönliches Gefühl:  Die Schlei[er] werden immer dünner!  Meine heisseste Lebensfrage:  Wird für einzelne, wird für alle (mit der nötigen Voraussetzung) <tei:hi rend="italic">dieses</tei:hi> Hören erlernbar sein?   Wird sich ein Übergang vom “Schauen” zum “Wissen” vollziehen?</tei:p><tei:p>Neben meinem geistigen Leben geht das allgemeinleibliche seinen Gang. Noch verdiene ich Nahrung und Behausung. <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Weiter geht der Kampf um die Anerkennung.  Kleine Erfolge trösten über die allgemeine grosse Depression.  Fehler und Schlappen mache ich auch zuweilen, und komme mit Humor drüber weg.  Es muss so vieles noch gelernt werden!  Mit Violin<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="violin_moriz">Moriz Violin</ref>.  At this time, von Cube and Violin worked together at the Schenker Institut in Hamburg.  </tei:note> arbeite ich gerne zusammen.  Trotzdem der grosse Alters- und Wesensunterschied letzte Bindungen nicht zustandekommen lässt.  Auf Umwegen erfuhr ich, dass er eine Reise nach Wien beabsichtigt.  Mir sprach er nicht davon.  Ich fürchte etwas für den Bestand des Institutes.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  The Schenker Institut in Hamburg, established by Moriz Violin in 1931, at which von Cube taught theory.  </tei:note>  Ich habe in letzter Zeit oft den Eindruck, als ob er den Widerstand gegen seine Person als Widerstand gegen die Sache selbst überschätzt.  Ich spüre unsere Isoliertheit wie eine feine Fessel!  Ich bin im Begriffe den Versuch zu unternehmen, gewisse Gegensätze auszugleichen.  Vorsichtig natürlich!  Ich meine, dass manchesmal einer Sache mit ein wenig Geschmeidigkeit besser gedient ist, als mit dickem Kopf.  Vielleicht habe ich kein Recht so zu sprechen, Ich war selber ein wenig verkrampft in letzter Zeit.  Jetzt weiss ich, wo die Hemmung sitzt, und ich werde den Stier bei den Hörnern packen.  Das Nächste sind Vorträge in der Gesellschaft Hamburger Tonkünstler, und im “Reichsverband”.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Presumably the Hamburg chapter of the (click on) <ref cRef="reichsverband_deutsc">Reichsverband deutscher Tonkünstler und Musiklehrer</ref>.  </tei:note>  Ich werde in <tei:hi rend="italic">alle</tei:hi> Löwenhöhlen gehen!  Ich muss meinen Mangel an Initiative vor mir selber gut machen.  Im Übrigen habe ich mich, still und ohne Aufsehen, verehelicht.  Auch das war gut und notwendig.  Meine Frau ist ein guter Kamerad, und wir arbeiten beide schlicht und sachlich am Aufbau unseres Lebens.  Mein erster Vortrag in der GeHaTo hat ziemlich “eingeschlagen”; namentlich bei den Jüngeren.  Der Boden ist also bereitet. Karli<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Karl Violin, Moriz’s son, who had been seriously ill around the time that Cube arrived in Hamburg the previous year.  </tei:note> geht es recht gut! Was macht denn der “freie Satz”?  Mit den Besten Wünschen für Ihr und Ihrer Frau</tei:p><tei:p>Gemahlen Wohlbefinden bin ich stets</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr alter 
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Cube.</tei:p><tei:p>P. S.  Was hören Sie von Dr. Weisse,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.  </tei:note> und Dr. Jonas?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="jonas_oswald">Oswald Jonas</ref>.  </tei:note>  Rührt sich nichts in der Charlottenburger Hochschule?</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated May 8, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hamburg 37, Innocentiastrasse 11
May 8, 1932</tei:p><tei:p>Most honoured, dear master,</tei:p><tei:p>Today I am sending you my first entirely original “speaking” Urlinie graph, of Schubert’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Doppelgänger</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  I believe I can say that I have a certain measure of success with it. I have tried to find a solution to a question of principle with a measure of courage and faith in myself.  It may be incorrect, but I believe I am right in saying that this is more a matter of notation than an error in listening.  I am referring to the remarkable displacement of the diatonic ~4 from its proper place, as actually determined by the bass.  I could not bring myself to use the course of the upper voice as shown in Figs. 4–5 also on the diatonic Ursatz as, conversely, I did not want, in the above-named examples, to declare the e#^2^ that has moved into an inner voice already to be ~4. Thus I have attempted to emphasize how the diatonic ~4, e^2^, is transformed into an e#^2^ as a consequence of the “mimetic” raising of the III and must return in the manner of a neighbor-note to f#^2^, from which point the whole proceeds towards the fundamental tone<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> in two fourth-progressions above the pedal-point-like F# in the bass, which in fact ought to have already supported the ~3, d^2^. The only “foreign concept” in my work is that of “mimicry,” which Dr. Weisse once mentioned to me in conversation. I found it sufficiently vivid to incorporate it into the graph.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/></tei:p><tei:p>Now I should like to explain my thought processes briefly:  Fig. 1a) the germ-cell of the Ursatz;  b) the incorporation of imperfect consonances in the outer voices;  c) the origins of the fourth-progression <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> B-A-G-F#, which elaborates the bass arpeggiation from B to F#; the consecutive fifths in the outer voices from ~5 to ~4 are nullified by the D included in the arpeggiation B-D-F#;  d) incorporation of the chromatic notes in the outer voices, and, as a consequence, the return to the chromaticized ~4 to a further F#, with its hasty course to the fundamental tone.  Fig. 2:  Aspect of the diatonic model in four-part harmony.  Fig. 3:  The process of coloration, in four-part harmony; harmonic degrees shown in relation to [B] major; at #VII, the third and fifth are raised; return of e#^2^  to f#^2^, in order to stretch out an [otherwise] too abrupt descent in opposition to the natural upward impulse.  Fig. 4:  The play of imitations and arpeggiations in the outer voices.  The a# shown in parentheses in the middle voice at m. 8 would, by dint of the completeness of the triads, have changed the mere effect of octave doubling to an unsatisfactory succession of parallel intervals.  For the same reason, the a in the inner voice in m. 11 is stationary, without taking part in the imitations. From m. 43 onwards, f#^1^ shows its descent into the inner voice, in order to make room for a fifth voice, which takes over the third arepggiation with the purpose of  arriving at f#^2^ since, on account of the serious harmonic movement for the play of imitations, which had been taken by the first and second arpeggiations, there is no longer any place.  The foreground, Fig. 5, clarifies the details.  Fig. 6 shows the “artistic” conscience with respect to the completeness of the motivic combinations.  I am, as you will understand, most eager to know how you will judge my latest work!  My personal feeling: the veils are becoming ever thinner. The most burning question of my life: will some individuals—will everyone (with the required background)—be capable of learning <tei:hi rend="italic">this</tei:hi> manner of hearing? Will a transition from “seeing” to “knowing” be achieved?</tei:p><tei:p>Alongside my intellectual life, the general corporeal existence is running its course. I still earn enough for food and lodging. <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> The struggle for recognition goes on.  Small successes are a comfort in the midst of a general deep depression.  I also make mistakes and suffer setbacks from time to time, and pick myself up afterwards with good humor.  There is still so much to be learned!  I enjoy working with Violin<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>—in spite of the fact that the great differences between us in age and character do not allow the most intimate liaison to be made.  I heard off-hand that he plans to make a trip to Vienna.  He did not speak to me about it.  I am somewhat fearful for the survival of the Institute.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  I have often had the impression recently that he is overrating the opposition to himself, equating it with opposition to the cause itself.  I detect our isolation like a fine fetter.  I am on the point of undertaking the attempt to resolve certain conflicts.  With care, naturally!  What I mean is that a cause is often better served with a little give-and-take than with a thick head.  Perhaps I do not have the right to speak this way:  I was myself a little hemmed in recently.  Now I know where the tension lies, and I will grab the bull by the horns.  The next thing on the agenda are lectures in the Society of Hamburg Composers, and in the Reichsverband.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/>  I shall go into <tei:hi rend="italic">every</tei:hi> lion’s den!  I must myself make up for any lack of initiative around me.  In addition, I have got married , quietly and without sensation.  That, too, was a good, and necessary thing.  My wife is a good comrade; the two of us work smoothly and objectively at building a life together.  My first lecture in the Society caused something of a stir, particularly among the younger members.  The ground is, therefore, prepared.  Karli is in very good shape!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>  How are you getting on with <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi>?”</tei:p><tei:p>With best wishes, hoping [this letter] finds you and your wife well, I am as ever</tei:p><tei:p>Your old
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Cube</tei:p><tei:p>P.S.:   What do you hear from Dr. Weisse,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> und Dr. Jonas?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/>  Is there no activity at the music high school in Charlottenburg?</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>