<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [3] : 11-25-26 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2006.
© Translation by William Drabkin 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1926-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 11/25/1926 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated November 25, 1926</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-05-30</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>C asks for a letter of recommendation to be sent to the Provincial School Council.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  Provincial Schools Council; Sallmann;  reference;  letter of recommendation;  modern dances;  pupil;  Vienna;  Tantenhayn;  Mozart;  Glass Harmonica Quintet;  Radio Wien</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Kaiserswerth-Bockum, Rhineland, Villa Dahlmann</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated November 25, 1926</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Kaiserswerth-Bockum, Rhld.
Villa Dahlmann.
25.XI.26</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Zunächst eine freundliche Nachricht: Der Restbetrag von meines Vaters Verpflichtungen an Sie wird nun <tei:hi rend="italic">endlich</tei:hi> an Sie abgehen.  Es hat mich nicht geringe Mühe gekostet! – einerlei, wir wollen nicht mehr daran denken, zu viel Schönes möchte sonst getrübt werden. –</tei:p><tei:p>Zweitens habe ich etwas auf dem Herzen, einem in letzter Zeit etwas geplagten Herzen!</tei:p><tei:p>Vielleicht kennen Sie die neue Verordnung in Deutschland! – Drosselverordnung nennen sie die Musiker! – wonach man zur Ausübung seines Berufes eine staatliche Anerkennung haben muss. Mit dieser Sache machen mir jetzt die Conservatoriumsbonzen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> Cube had been given a junior post at the Rheinisches Musikseminar in Duisburg.</tei:note> das Herz schwer. Oh! – heiliger Bürokratius, das Zeitalter der kurzen Haare hat es nicht vermocht[,] den Beamtenzopf zu “fällen”.</tei:p><tei:p>Um diese Anerkennung habe ich mich beim Provinzial-Schulkollegium beworben, und zwar auf Grund eines guten Kilogramms Papier, enthaltend wohlgesetzten Contrapunkt, Generalbass, Lebenslauf, eine Sonate mit unvollendetem 4[.] Satz (den 3. habe ich inzwischen geschafft), Auszüge aus Ihren Büchern, Urlinien, Leumundszeugnis, Impfschein, Geburtsurkunde, Bauchumfang und Handschuhnummer.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> The last two items have, of course, been included in jest.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Noch eines fehlt aber, um das ich Sie hiermit dringend bitten möchte: Wollen Sie so gut sein, und mir eine Art Zeugnis ausstellen, enthaltend Angaben über Art und Weise, Intensität und Erfolg meiner Tätigkeit bei Ihnen, und geeignet, freundliche Gefühle im ver- <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> zopften Collegium zu erwecken? Ich wäre Ihnen sehr, sehr dankbar dafür! Nur müsste es am besten – rekommendiert Express! – postwendend an den Herrn</tei:p><tei:p>Oberschulrat <tei:hi rend="italic">Sallmann</tei:hi>.
Provinzial-Schul-Collegium, 
Abteilung für Schulmusik
<tei:hi rend="italic">Koblenz</tei:hi>, Rheinland</tei:p><tei:p>abgehen, damit es am 29. ds. spätestens dort ist, da die Konferenz bereits am 2. Dezember stattfindet. Entschuldigen Sie bitte das Tempo, ich habe es selbst so spät erfahren. Teilen Sie mir bitte Ihre Portoauslagen zur Rückerstattung mit!</tei:p><tei:p>Nebstbei habe ich einen “Auftrag” für 10–12 moderne Tänze für eine Revue oder so. Das wird was einbringen! –</tei:p><tei:p>Privat habe ich erst <tei:hi rend="italic">eine</tei:hi> Schülerin.  Das werden auch noch mehr werden.</tei:p><tei:p>Mein <tei:hi rend="italic">Radio</tei:hi> verbindet mich weiterhin mit Wien. Erst gestern “genoss” ich Freund Tautenhayn.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> E. Tautenhayn: may be the name of a radio presenter or concert promoter who appeared on the programs of the Viennese classical music station, Radio Wien. </tei:note> Das Glasharmonikaquintett von Mozart ist ja reizend!</tei:p><tei:p>Für heute also nur dieses, und besten Dank im Voraus für Ihre Bemühung!</tei:p><tei:p>Mit besten Grüssen an Sie und Ihre Frau Gemahlin
bin ich
Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated November 25, 1926</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Kaiserswerth-Bockum, Rhineland
Villa Dahlmann
November 25, 1926</tei:p><tei:p>Most honoured Master!</tei:p><tei:p>First, a welcome piece of news: the remainder of what my father owes you will now <tei:hi rend="italic">finally</tei:hi> be sent to you. This has cost me no little trouble—all the same, let us not think about it any more, otherwise too much that is beautiful might be spoiled.</tei:p><tei:p>Secondly, I have something weighing on my heart, a heart that has recently been somewhat troubled!</tei:p><tei:p>Perhaps you know the new ordinance in Germany—the “strangulation ordinance”, the musicians call it—according to which one needs official government recognition in order to practise one’s profession. The high priests of the Conservatory<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> are making things difficult for me with regard to this matter. Oh, St. Bureaucracy, the age of short hair has not succeeded in “chopping off” the pigtail of officialdom.</tei:p><tei:p>To obtain this recognition, I have applied to the provincial school council, and indeed on the basis of a good kilogram of paper containing well-composed counterpoint, thoroughbass, a curriculum vitae, a sonata with an incomplete fourth movement (I have, in the meantime, completed the third movement), extracts from your books, Urlinie graphs, a certificate of good conduct, a record of immunization, a birth certificate, and my waist measurement and glove size.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/></tei:p><tei:p>One thing is missing, about which I should like to ask you most urgently: would you be so kind as to set out a kind of reference containing information about the nature, intensity, and result of my studies with you, written in such a way as to arouse friendly impressions among the <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> bewigged councillors? I would be very, very grateful to you for it. But it must ideally be sent by return of post, registered express, to the</tei:p><tei:p>Hon. Senior Inspector of Schools <tei:hi rend="italic">Sallmann</tei:hi>,
Provincial School Council, 
Department of School Music, 
<tei:hi rend="italic">Koblenz</tei:hi>, Rhineland</tei:p><tei:p>in order to arrive at the latest on the 29th of the month, as the meeting takes place on December 2. Please excuse the haste; I myself found out about this at a very late stage. Please let me know your postage expenses, so that I can reimburse you!</tei:p><tei:p>By the way, I have an “assignment” for ten to twelve modern dance pieces for a revue or something like that. This will bring in some revenue!</tei:p><tei:p>On the private side, I have only <tei:hi rend="italic">one</tei:hi> student.  That will surely increase.</tei:p><tei:p>My <tei:hi rend="italic">radio</tei:hi> links me, moreover, with Vienna; only yesterday I “enjoyed” our friend Tautenhayn.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> Mozart’s Glass Harmonica Quintet<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> is simply enchanting!</tei:p><tei:p>That is all for today; my best thanks in advance for your efforts!</tei:p><tei:p>With best wishes to you and your wife,
I am,
Your
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>