<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [26] : 8-19-31 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin 2006.
© Translation William Drabkin 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1931-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 08/19/1931 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated August 19, 1931</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-07-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Informs S that Moriz Violin's son has been taken ill;  C sends S a copy of the Schenker Institute prospectus. 

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  Violin, Moriz;  Violin, Karl;  illness;  Schenker-Institut;  Schenker Institute;  prospectus;  Oppel, Reinhard</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Hamburg, Beneckestrasse 2</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated August 19, 1931</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hamburg, Beneckestr. 2, bei Alexander Schmidt.
29. VIII. 31.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter, lieber Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Heute kam Ihre Karte<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  This card is not known to survive..</tei:note> hier an, und ich beantworte sie kurz für Herrn Prof. Violin,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="violin_moriz">Moriz Violin</ref>.</tei:note> der im Moment keine Zeit hat, auch wird die Post in einer halben Stunde geschlossen. Violin hatte Ihnen vor einer Woche unseren Prospekt<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> For a later version of this document, click on <ref cRef="schenker_institute_h">Schenker-Institut, Hamburg: Prospectus</ref>.</tei:note> geschickt, der aber auf der Reise nach Galtür verloren gegangen zu sein scheint. Ein tragisches Geschick liess seinen Sohn<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">   Karl Violin, son of Moriz, whose illness is mentioned in several of Cube’s subsequent letters.</tei:note> mit neuer Krankheit darniederliegen, sodass er begreiflicherweise noch keine Ruhe fand, Ihnen ausführlich zu schreiben. Es scheint um Karli<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">   Karl Violin, son of Moriz, whose illness is mentioned in several of Cube’s subsequent letters.</tei:note> diesmal nicht gut zu stehen; er fiebert stark, und es wurde eine Blutprobe genommen, deren Analyse noch nicht beendet ist. Alles Nähere über Violins Unternehmen, dem ich micht Leib und Seele verschrieben habe, erfahren Sie aus dem – im Wesentlichen von meiner Wenigkeit verfassten – Prospekt, den ich Ihnen wiederum mitsende. –</tei:p><tei:p>Verzeihen Sie bitte für diesmal die Kürze meines Schreibens, ich werde in Bälde, ebenso wie Herr Prof. Violin, ausführlich von mir hören lassen. –</tei:p><tei:p>Einstweilen recht herzliche Grüsse an Sie, Ihre Frau Gemahlin, wie auch an Herrn Prof. Oppel<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> Reinhard Oppel, recently appointed Professor of Music Theory at the Leipzig Conservatory and staunch supported of Schenker’s teaching.  Oppel [create biogfile]</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>von Ihrem
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Cube.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated August 19, 1931</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hamburg, Beneckestrasse 2, c/o Alexander Schmidt
19 August 1931</tei:p><tei:p>Most honoured, dear master,</tei:p><tei:p>Today your card<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> arrived, and I shall answer it briefly on behalf of Prof. Violin,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> who has no time at the moment;  also, the post office will close in half an hour. Violin sent you our prospectus<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> a week ago, but it seems to have gone missing on the way to Galtür. A tragic fate has laid his son<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> low with a new illness, so that he could, understandably, find no time to write to you in detail. This time, things are not going well for Karli:<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> he has a high fever;  and a blood sample was taken, the analysis of which is not complete. All the details of Violin’s undertaking, to which I have pledged myself body and soul, you will learn from the prospectus (in essence, prepared by my humble self), which I am sending you again.</tei:p><tei:p>Please excuse the brevity of my writing this time;  you will hear from me, and from Prof. Violin, at length in the near future.</tei:p><tei:p>For the time being, most affectionate greetings to you and your wife, and also to Prof. Oppel,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> from</tei:p><tei:p>Your
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Cube</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>