<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [1] : 1-21-25 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2006.
© Translation by William Drabkin 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1925-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 05/29/1925 10:02:43 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated January 21, 1925</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-05-29</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>C has had to extend his holiday to take care of his father, who has been forced to abandon his second marriage under pressure from his firm.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  father;  catastrophe;  second marriage;  Schubert;  Gretchen am Spinnrade;  Vienna;  Brahms</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Duisburg</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated January 21, 1925</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[Letterhead of father’s architectural firm<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  The letter is written in Cube’s home town of Duisburg in northern Germany, on headed notepaper from his father’s architectural partnership. The printed heading, enclosed in a double box spanning the entire width of the page, reads as follows: “PROFESSOR Dr. ING. GUSTAV VON CUBE und ARTHUR BUCHLOH / ARCHITEKTEN B.D.A. / FERNSPRECHER NR. 3933 / DUISBURG a/RH. / A.E.G.-HAUS, SONNENWALL“, followed by names of banks in which the partnership had accounts, and an address for telegram.</tei:note>]</tei:p><tei:p>[den] 21. I. 1925.</tei:p><tei:p>Lieber Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Es haben sich hier malheureuse Dinge ereignet. Ich möchte Ihnen heute schon davon schreiben, obwohl ich noch ganz unter dem Druck der Ereignisse stehe, und mein Kopf mir nicht weniger verrückt ist, als dem armen Gretchen bei Schubert.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> A reference to Schubert’s early song, <tei:hi rend="italic">Gretchen am Spinnrade</tei:hi>, which had been the subject of a textual and analytical study a few years before, in the sixth issue of <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</tei:hi> (1923).</tei:note> Das Schicksal, wie so oft in der Gestalt einer weidlich bekannten, verlogenen und demoralisierten Gesellschaftsklasse, hat meinem Vater einen schlimmen Stoss versetzt. Er stand direct vor seiner Weiderheiratung mit einem Mädchen von ausserordentlichen Qualitäten, die[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] wie keine andere geeignet gewesen wäre, dem einsam gewordenen als lieber Kamerad zur Seite zu stehen. Ich lernte die junge Dame kennen und schätzen, und freute mich an dem Glück und der Zufriedenheit der beiden, bis gestern eine Katastrophe eintrat. Die obengenannte Gesellschaft wiedersetzte[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] sich der Verbindung, und – – drohte mit Boykott.</tei:p><tei:p>Was dies letztere für einen Geschäftsmann bedeutet, wissen Sie! Und alles, weil das Mädchen, das über jeden Tadel erhoben ist, trotzdem sie nicht den obersten Kreisen entstammt, sich ihr Brot bisher als Solotänzerin an einer grossen Rheinischen Opernbühne verdient hat, wie es <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> heute viele Mädchen mit der Schreibmaschine, oder den Nadel tun müssen. Und der Chef des Hauses von Cube darf keine “Tänzerin” heiraten, weil das den alten verkalkten Geheimratsgattinnen nicht passt. Man würde ihn verhungern lassen. Also – – – Trennung! Ich kann nicht wiedergeben, in welchem Zustand mein Vater sich befindet. Sicher wird er mit der Zeit ruhiger werde, vielleicht sogar vergessen.  Aber Sie werden verstehen, wenn ich Sie bitte darüber hinwegzusehen, wenn ich den kurz gedachten Urlaub so lange ausdehne. Ich kann meinen Vater jetzt nicht allein lassen.  Es mag immerhin in den Februar hinein dauren, bis ich wieder nach Wien fahre. Ich arbeite halt hier weiter an Brahms.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> Probably the Variations and Fugue on a theme of Handel, Op. 24, a favorite teaching piece of Schenker’s and the main article in a double issue (8/9) of <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</tei:hi> (1924).</tei:note> Und die Dollars – – die muss ich jetzt halt doch schicken.</tei:p><tei:p>Das sind wunderliche Dinge, die einem passieren können.  Hätte nicht gedacht, dass es <tei:hi rend="italic">so</tei:hi> schlechte Menschen gibt.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich freue mich sehr, Sie wieder zu sehen.  Bis dahin viele Grüsse Ihnen und Ihrer Frau Gemahlin von mir, und meinem Vater.</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated January 21, 1925</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[Letterhead of father’s architectural firm<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>]</tei:p><tei:p>January 21, 1925</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Master!</tei:p><tei:p>Terrible things have happened here. I want to write to you about them as early as today, even though I still remain under the weight of the events and my head is no less in turmoil than that of Schubert’s poor Gretchen.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> Fate, as it often [comes] in the shape of an only too well-known, mendacious and demoralized class of society, has dealt my father a painful blow. He was on the point of getting married for the second time, to a young lady of extraordinary qualities, who would have been suited like no other to stand as a dear companion to this lonely man. I became acquainted with the young woman and grew to treasure her, and I was rejoicing in the happiness and contentment of the pair – until yesterday’s catastrophe. The above-mentioned society stood in opposition to their bond – and threatened with a boycott.</tei:p><tei:p>What the latter means for a businessman is something you understand! And all this because the girl (who stands above all reproach) has, in spite of not coming from the highest social circles, earned a living as a solo dancer in a major Rhineland opera house, just as <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> today many girls must do with the typewriter or with needle and thread. And the head of the House of Cube may not marry any “dancer”, because this does not suit the old, calcified wives of the Privy Councillors. They would let him starve. Therefore – – – separation! I cannot convey the condition in which my father finds himself. To be sure, he will become quieter with the passage of time, and might even forget [the matter]. But you will understand stand if I ask you to excuse me for greatly extending what I had planned to be a short holiday. I cannot leave my father alone now. It may be well into February before I am able to return to Vienna. I shall just be working further on Brahms.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> And the money [we owe you] – – I suppose I shall have to send them to you now.</tei:p><tei:p>These are extraordinary things that can happen to someone. I would not have thought that there are people who are <tei:hi rend="italic">so</tei:hi> bad.</tei:p><tei:p>I am greatly looking forward to seeing you again. Until then, many greetings to you and your wife from me and my father.</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>