<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [20] : 1-2-30 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin 2006.
© Translation William Drabkin 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1930-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 01/02/1930 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated January 2, 1930</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-10-19</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Offers New Year greetings; reports on his current mood, on the Conservatory, his private teaching, and publication plans.  — Describes Urlinie of C-major Prelude from WTC I.  — Reports of compositional activity and reading.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  Christmas;  Conservatory;  Deutsche Tonkünstler-Zeitung;  Bach J. S.;  Wohltemperirtes Klavier;  Well-tempered Clavier;  Prelude;  Urlinie;  Terzraum;  Oktavzug;  Octave line;  Koppelung;coupling;  string quartet;  piano sonata;  Daqué, Edgar</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Duisburg, Rhineland, Pulverweg 41</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, January 2, 1930</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">upper left corner: stationery motif, crown above shield</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>Duisburg/Rhld.[,] Pulverweg 41.
2. I. 30.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Zuvor meine besten Grüsse und Wünsche zum neuen Jahre! Da est zugleich ein neues Decennium ist, erweitert man unwillkürlich den Zeitbegriff, und wird gewahr, wie wenig, und doch wieder wieviel des Unendlichen wieder einmal an einem vorbeigebraust ist. Man kommt sich vor, wie der Frosch im seichten Ufertümpel: Draussen zieht der grosse Strom vorbei, und man schielt etwas nach seinen Hinterbeinchen, ob sie’s wohl schaffen werden, da mitzukommen. –<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> The entire paragraph is written in neutral terms (with the German <tei:hi rend="italic">man</tei:hi> as the subject), but Cube is referring to himself, imagining his situation to be not so very different from other people’s.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Augenblicks ist mir etwas philosophisch zu Mute.  Ein wenig wird wohl auch die Weihnachtliche Überlastung von Magen und Gedärm daran schuld sein. Zum anderen aber ist es doch zur Zeit recht still um mich geworden. Offenbar sieht das Schicksal zuweilen auch Ruhepausen für seine Kinder vor.  Das mag ja sehr vorteilhaft für die Nerven sein, indess[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] beginne ich mich bereits zu beargwöhnen, ob nicht vielleicht meine Tatkraft sich dem <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> neuen Zustand anbequeme, um mich hinterlistigerweise faul und träge zu machen.  An sich habe ich mein Auskommen, und verdiene mir mein tägliches Schnitzel mit Häuptlsalat ohne Überanstrengung. Dazu gehört nicht viel, bei einiger Genügsamkeit.  Aber die  sichtbaren Stationen des Erfolges ziehen sich immer weiter auseinander.  So sinne ich dem eifrigst auf neue Aufgaben, an denen ich meine Kräfte erproben kann.  Das Konservatorium läuft jetzt wie eine gutgeölte Machine.  Der Privatunterricht bietet -m- etwas mehr in künstlerischer Hinsicht, aber es sind nur zwei von vielen, mit denen ich jene Sprache sprechen kann, die nun einmal für die Mehrzahl der Menschen Hieroglyphen bleibt.  Für die Tonkünstlerzeitung arbeite ich an einem Artikel “Urlinie und Klavierunterricht”, oder “Eine Stunde Bach” und habe dazu das erste C dur Praeludium aus dem Wohltemperierten genommen, und hoffentlich richtig gelesen:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> No paragraph-break in original.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Die Urlinie läuft im Terzraum e´´ d´´ c´´; die Stufen des Hintergundes sind I–V–I. Der V ist eine #IV vorgeschaltet, die in der Oberstimme den chromatischen Durchgang es´´ trägt. Die Ausfaltung zeigt einen Oktavzug e´´–e´, der ge- <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> wissermassen in zwei Tetrachord-artige Quartzüge aufgeteilt ist, die an ihren Enden die Betätigung der Stufen II–V (in Takt 10–11) und V–I (Takt 18–19) ermöglichen. Dadurch gerät die Stimmführung in eine tiefere Lage, und wird ganz am Schluss wieder mit Hilfe einer Figuration bei liegendem Bass in der gehörigen Höhe mit ~2 ~1 zu Ende geführt. Der Bass umschreibt mit Hilfe dreier C, nämlich c´, c, C, zwei Oktaven (Kopplung). Das, natürlich um in grossen Umrissen, habe ich herausgelesen. Daraus will ich zur Unterhaltung und Anleitung der Leser einen kleinen Schrieb machen, nicht ohne mich erkundigt zu haben, ob ich es Ihnen vor der Veröffentlichung schicken soll. –<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  The <tei:hi rend="italic">Deutsche Tonkünstler-Zeitung</tei:hi> did publish a letter of Cube’s in 1930, but the essay on Bach’s C major Prelude never materialized. Instead, Schenker went over the content of the analysis carefully with him (see letter, vC 28, January 12, 1930). Cube made a new voice-leading graph of the Prelude in October 1931, and again Schenker provided a critique (see letters OJ 9/34 [29] and vC 40). In the end, the final form of the voice-leading graph was published—under Schenker’s name, without acknowledgement of Cube’s involvement, and without verbal commentary—in the <tei:hi rend="italic">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln</tei:hi> of 1932. See William Drabkin, “A Lesson in Analysis from Heinrich Schenker”, <tei:hi rend="italic">Music Analysis</tei:hi> 4 (1985), pp. 241–258.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Komponierenderweise geht mir alles möglich durch den Kopf.  Am meisten Façon hat bis jetzt etwas für Streichquartett, was natürlich langwierige Spezialstudien und vieles Lesen und Hören im Gefolge hat.  Es sind doch – ach! – noch allzugrosse Lücken auszupolstern, und die Zeit schlüpft einem immerfort durch die Finger.  Vielleicht wird nächstens meine Sonate in As-Dur von einer Meisterschülerin im Konservatoriums- <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> konzert aufgeführt, das wäre dann mal wieder eine Kleinigkeit Wasser auf die ^Mühle der^ öffentlichen Meinung, die wir – aus Geschäftsgründen – nun einmal in Gang halten müssen.   Noch bin ich nicht soweit, dass die Kindlein zu mir kommen, vorläufig bin ich noch Aquisiteur, und bemüht, der Konkurrenz erfolgreich zuvorzukommen. –</tei:p><tei:p>Nebstbei lese ich die neuesten Philosophen, z. B. Edgar Daqué – “Natur und Seele”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> Edgar Daqué (1878-1945), German paleontologist and mystic philosopher.  He publications included <tei:hi rend="italic">Urwelt, Sage und Menschheit</tei:hi> (Munich, 1924), <tei:hi rend="italic">Natur und Seele</tei:hi> ( Munich, 1927), and <tei:hi rend="italic">Organische Morphologie und Palaeontologie</tei:hi> (1935).</tei:note> – und habe eine Neigung zum Billardspielen bei mir entdeckt.   Auch beginne ich langsam und Kiloweise stärker zu werden, was von vorteilhaftem Einfluss auf mein Wohlbefinden, und von nachteiligstem Einfluss auf meine Schneiderrechnungen ist.  Ausser unseren Kammermusikabenden habe ich als neuen “Sport” Jazzmusik auf zwei Flügeln angefangen; (Ich kanns halt nicht lassen!)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> In the parenthetical remark, Cube is probably alluding to Schenker’s well-known antipathy toward jazz, as expressed in the prefatory remarks to the essay on Mozart’s G minor Symphony (<tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, II, p. 107 (Eng. trans., II, p. 59), and the Miscellanea of <tei:hi rend="italic">Meisterwerk</tei:hi> III, p. 119 (Eng. trans., III, p.77: “Jazz stirs the bones, not the mind”).</tei:note>  Alles in allem bin ich so zufrieden, als mans in diesen Zeiten ohne Gefahr sein darf. –</tei:p><tei:p>Mit herzlichsten Grüssen Ihnen und Ihrer Frau Gemahlin bin ich</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, January 2, 1930</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">upper left corner: stationery motif, crown above shield</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>Duisburg, Rhineland, Pulverweg 41
January 2, 1930</tei:p><tei:p>Most honoured master,</tei:p><tei:p>First of all, my best greetings and wishes for the New Year.  As it is at the same time a new decade the concept of time is involuntarily extended and I become aware of how little, and yet how much, of the infinite has once again rushed passed me.  I imagine myself to be like the frog in the shallow pool by the river bank: outside the great current marches on, and I cast a furtive glance at my hind legs, wondering whether they will succeed in coming along with me.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>At the moment my mood is somewhat philosophical.  The overstraining of the stomach and gut at Christmas might well have something to do with this.  On the other hand, things have been quite peaceful around me.  Apparently, fate also furnishes occasional periods of rest for its children.  This may be very advantageous for my nerves; in the meantime I am already beginning to suspect that my energy is perhaps adjusting itself to the <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> new situation to make me lazy and indolent without my realizing it.  As things appear, I have my livelihood and am able to earn my daily schnitzel, with a bit of salad on the side, without overexerting myself.  That’s not too much of a task, if one is reasonably frugal.  But the visible stations of success are getting further and further apart. And so I think keenly about new assignments on which I can test my powers.  The Conservatory is running now like a well-oiled machine.  Private teaching offers somewhat more from an artistic point of view, but of the many there are only two with whom I can speak that language which, I am afraid, will remain hieroglyphics for the majority of people.  For the <tei:hi rend="italic">Deutsche Tonkünstler-Zeitung</tei:hi> I am working on an article “Urlinie and Piano Teaching” or “A Lesson with Bach,” and for this purpose I have chosen the first C major prelude from The <tei:hi rend="italic">Well-Tempered Clavier</tei:hi>. I hope I have read it correctly.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/></tei:p><tei:p>The Urlinie moves in the space of a third, e^2^–d^2^–c^1^; the harmonic degrees of the background are I–V–I. The V is preceded by a #IV, which supports the chromatic passing note e<tei:hi rend="italic">b</tei:hi>^2^ in the upper voice. The development [of harmonic degree I] shows an octave-progression, e^2^–e^1^, which <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> in a certain sense is divided into two tetrachord-like fourth-progressions, which enable the harmonic affirmation II[^#^]–V (in bars 10–11) and V–I (bars 18–19) at their end. By this means, the voice-leading arrives in a lower register; only at the very end, again with help from a figuration against a stationary bass, is brought to its conclusion in the appropriate high register with ~2 ~1. With the help of three Cs— namely c^1^, c and C— the bass encompasses two octaves (coupling).  That is what I have been able to read from the score, naturally in broad outline.  From this I would like to write a short piece, for the interest and benefit of the reader, though not without asking whether I should send it to you before I publish it.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/></tei:p><tei:p>With regard to composition, all sorts of things are going around in my head.  Until now, something for string quartet seems to be shaping up most of all; this naturally would have as a consequence long and strenuous special studies, and much reading and listening. There remain— alas!— all too large holes to fill up, and time is constantly slipping through my fingers.  Perhaps my [Piano] Sonata in A flat major will be performed by a master pupil at one of the next Conservatory <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> concert; that would be another small quantity of water passing through the mill of public opinion, which we must – for professional reasons – continue to keep in working order.  I have not reached the point that the little children come to me; at present I am still at the acquisitive stage and make an effort to keep ahead of the competition.</tei:p><tei:p>Alongside this, I read the latest philosophical works, for instance Edgar Daqué’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Nature and Soul</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> and have discovered within me an aptitude for billiards.  I’m also beginning to get stronger, slowly and by the kilogram, which has a beneficial effect on my general health and a detrimental effect on my tailoring costs.  Apart from our chamber music evenings, I have begun a new “sport”: jazz on two pianos. (I cannot help myself!)<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  All in all, I am as satisfied as one can safely expect to be in these times.
With most affectionate greetings to you and your wife, I am</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>