<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [11] : 4-24-28 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
© Translation by William Drabkin 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1928-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 04/24/1928 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated April 24, 1928</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-07-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>C describes difficulties with his colleagues, loss of pupils, and reactions to his lecture. —Scheuermann and Schmemann will put Schenker exhibits in their shop windows, items requested. —Inquires after Weisse journal plan.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  winter;  spring;  colleagues;  struggle;  pupils;  piano sonata;  lecture;  editions;  Scheuermann;  Duisburg;  Schmemann;  Essen;  exhibit;  Hammer, Victor;  Weisse, Hans;  journal;  Zeitschrift;  Monatsschrift</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Duisburg, Rhineland, Pulverweg 41 </marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated April 24, 1928</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">letterhead:</tei:hi>]  FELIX E. VON CUBE 
Duisburg./ Rhld.
Pulverweg 41. 
24.IV.28.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Auch dieser Winter wäre überstanden, und es will Frühling werden. Freilich einer, der sich mit dem Wienerischen nicht messen kann. Im Schatten der Hochöfen gedeihen keine Mandelbäumschen, und wo die Dampfhämmer poltern, da schweigen alle zarteren Töne. Aber wenn man ein bissel weiter geht, findet man auch hier ein paar schöne Plätzchen allwo man immer Beschaulichkeit pflegen kann. –</tei:p><tei:p>Der Kampf ums Dasein ist doch keine leere Phrase! Die lieben Kollegen merken langsam, dass ich nicht bloss gekommen bin, um ihnen guten Tag zu sagen.  So greifen sie zu bewährten Mittelchen, und machen mir die Arbeit sauer wo sie können. Nimmt man noch die schlechte Wirtschaftslage dazu, so ergiebt sich gerade kein sonderlich rosiges Bild. Ich habe Schüler verloren, und bin wieder soweit wie vor einem halben Jahr. Nun – es wird schon wieder besser werden. –</tei:p><tei:p>Meine Sonate ist natürlich nicht gespielt worden. Mann soll sich doch lieber nur auf sich selbst <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> verlassen! Die zweite nähert sich ihrer Vollendung.  Ich glaube, dass sie recht gut ist; dann werde ich beide im November einfach selbst spielen. Schluss. –</tei:p><tei:p>Angefangen haben die Kabalen nach meinem Vortrag. (Das Material ist zur Zeit noch in Düsseldorf, aber so bald ich es zurückbekomme, will ich es Ihnen schicken; es sind mehrere selbstverfertigte Analysen dabei.) Ich hatte eine audience von 50 Personen, darunter viele hiesige Lehrer, und eine Reihe Seminarschüler. An einer grossen Tafel habe ich über anderthalb Stunden mit farbigen Kreiden demonstriert. Erfolg: Dämmernde Erkenntnis benebst grosser Begeisterung bei der überwiegenden Minderheit,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> <tei:hi rend="italic">überwiegende Minderheit</tei:hi>: an ironic play on words, suggesting that only a small part of the audience showed much interest in Cube’s presentation.</tei:note> im anderen Lager mitleidiges Lächeln der in pädagogischen Ehren ergrauten Jochochsen; der Hauch aus dem Genieland hatte sie nicht erreicht. –</tei:p><tei:p>Ja, und erst die “Ausgabenfrage”! Du lieber Gott, da hatte ich schön ins Wespennest gestochen! Der ganze bissige Schwarm ist über mich hergefallen. Als Antwort habe ich meine “Tabelle der besten Ausgaben” im Theorielehrsaal angepickt, wie weiland Luther seine Thesen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Martin Luther posted his 95 Theses on the door of the Schlosskirche, Wittenberg, on October 31, 1517.</tei:note> Der Bahöl<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> <tei:hi rend="italic">Bahöl</tei:hi>: usually written <tei:hi rend="italic">Bahö</tei:hi>.</tei:note> geht also weiter. –</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Ein</tei:hi> gutes hat die ganze Sache gehabt, und vielleicht kann ich <tei:hi rend="italic">das</tei:hi> gute daraus machen: <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Die Direktion konnte nicht umhin, die Diskussion aufzunehmen; und so soll ich demnächst im Seminar über Urlinie und Ausgaben. Hoffentlich überlegt es sich der “Chef” nicht wieder.</tei:p><tei:p>Die Buchhandlungen Scheuermann in Duisburg und Schmemann in Essen machen also im Juni eine Sonder-Schaufensterausstellung.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> The idea of exhibiting Schenker’s work in local bookshops, on the occasion of his 60th birthday, is first suggested in OJ 9/34, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10"> Cube’s postscript replies to Schenker’s casual enquiry, in his previous letter, about whether Cube’s radio can pick up Vienna.</tei:note>, January 30, 1928.</tei:note> Ich wäre Ihnen sehr dankbar, wenn sie mir zwei Hammer-Radierungen vermitteln würden.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Victor Hammer [create biogfile and link].  Hammer made a mezzotint portrait of Schenker, dated 1926; and there is a bronze medallion on which this is inscribed.  The two survive as OJ 72/14, items 7 and 18.</tei:note> Möglicherweise könnten sie ja sogar hier verkauft werden.  Wir stellen Ihre sämtlichen Sachen aus. (Der “freie Satz[”] wird wohl noch nicht soweit sein?)</tei:p><tei:p>Gleichzeitig wäre es günstig, wenn wir schon ein paar Autographen mit publik machen könnten. Ist schon was fertig? Ich wollte mich schon an Hoboken<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> selbst wenden, indes habe ich keine Adresse von ihm. (Ist es wahr[,] wieder geschieden sein soll?)</tei:p><tei:p>Dann verfasse ich einen saftigen Zeitungsartikel<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7"> This newspaper article does not survive. Cube sent it to Schenker, who enjoyed reading it but noted that the connection between him and the Brahms circle (Brahms and Joachim) had been exaggerated. (See Schenker’s letter, vC 17, July 13, 1928.)</tei:note> – kurz, es wird eine richtige Campagne gemacht, ich freue mich schon!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Wie stehts mit Dr. Weisses Zeitschrift?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8"> Click on <ref cRef="tonkunst_die"><tei:hi rend="italic">Die Tonkunst</tei:hi></ref>.  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.</tei:note> Haben Sie Vrieslanders Artikel in der Tonkünstlerzeitung gelesen?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.  A one-page article by Vrieslander entitled “Heinrich Schenker,” written in connection with the publication of <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, vol. 2, appeared in the <tei:hi rend="italic">Deutscher Tonkünstler-Zeitung</tei:hi> (March 5, 1928); a copy of this is pasted into the Schenker Scrapbook (OC 2/p.76).</tei:note>
 
Mit herzlichen Grüssen
Ihnen und Ihrer Frau Gemahlin
Ihr [ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube.</tei:p><tei:p>PS:  Mein Fünfröhren-Rundfunk Ohr reicht auch 
bis Wien, das allerdings oft schlechter zu hören 
ist, als Madrid oder Petersburg.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10"> Cube’s postscript replies to Schenker’s casual enquiry, in his previous letter, about whether Cube’s radio can pick up Vienna.</tei:note></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated April 24, 1928</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">letterhead:</tei:hi>]  FELIX E. VON CUBE 
Duisburg, Rhineland
Pulverweg 41 
April 24, 1928</tei:p><tei:p>Most honoured master,</tei:p><tei:p>I seem have survived this winter, too, and spring has just about arrived. Not, of course, one that can be compared with the Viennese: in the shadow of the blast furnaces no almond trees thrive; and where the steam-hammers thunder, all tenderer sounds are silent. But if one walks a bit further on, one finds a few nice places where one can always pursue contemplation.</tei:p><tei:p>The struggle for existence is, however, no empty phrase! My dear colleagues are slowly recognizing that I have not come here merely to say “good day” to them. They take up their well-tested little tricks, and make my work as unpleasant as they possibly can. And if, further, one adds to this the bad state of the economy, then the picture that emerges is not an especially rosy one. I have lost pupils, and am back to where I was half a year ago. Well, things will get better again.</tei:p><tei:p>My sonata was, naturally, not performed. It is better to rely only on oneself! <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> The second sonata is approaching completion. I believe that it very good; when it is finished, I will simply play them both in November myself, and that will be it.</tei:p><tei:p>The intrigues began after my lecture. (The material is at present still in Düsseldorf, but as soon as I get it back I shall send it to you; it includes several analyses that I completed myself.) I had an audience of fifty persons, including many local teachers, and a fair number of seminar pupils. Standing at a large blackboard, I spent more than an hour and a half demonstrating with coloured chalk. The result: vague recognition alongside great enthusiasm among the vast minority;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> in the other camp, sympathetic smiles from the grayed oxen yoked to pedagogical honor. The breath from the land of genuis had not reached them.</tei:p><tei:p>Yes, and now the “matter of editions.” My God, I had stirred up a fine hornet's nest! The entire swarm fell upon me with their stings. By way of reply, I posted my “Table of the best editions” in the theory lecture room, as Luther did with his theses in days of yore.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> The saga<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> continues.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">One</tei:hi> good thing did come out of the entire affair, and perhaps I can make it <tei:hi rend="italic">the one</tei:hi> good thing to come out of it. <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> The administration had no choice but to continue the discussion, and so I am supposed to give a lecture on Urlinie and editions at the seminar in a short time. I hope that the “chef” will not reconsider this again.</tei:p><tei:p>The bookstores Scheuermann in Duisburg and Schmemann in Essen are putting on a special exhibit in their shop windows.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> I would be very grateful if you would let me use two Hammer engravings.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> Perhaps they could even be sold here. We will exhibit everything of yours. (I suppose that <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi> is not yet ready?)</tei:p><tei:p>At the same time it would be useful if we could include a few autograph [photostats] in the display. Is something ready yet? I wanted to contact Hoboken<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> myself, but find that I don’t have an address for him. (Is it true that he has divorced again?)</tei:p><tei:p>Then I shall write a meaty newspaper article:<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> in short, we shall make a proper campaign, to which I am already looking forward!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> How do things stand with Dr. Weisse’s journal?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> Did you read Vrieslander’s article in the society’s journal?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/>
	
With affectionate greetings to you and your wife,</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,  [ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube</tei:p><tei:p>P.S. My five-valved radio receiver can reach Vienna; but it is often more difficult to get good reception from there than from Madrid or St Petersburg.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/></tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>