<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [25] : 5-9-31 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin 2006.
© Translation William Drabkin 2006
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1931-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 05/09/1931 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated May 9, 1931</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-11-09</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>C describes his feelings and final dealings with the Conservatory in Duisburg, and preparations for work with Violin in Hamburg; he reports on his two best pupils, Erich Voss and Lieselotte Müller. 

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  Duisburg;  Conservatory;  Violin, Moriz;  Pentecost;  Düsseldorf;  Hamburg;  Eccarius;  Voss, Erich;  Müller, Lieselotte;  Berlin;  Frankfurt</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Duisburg, Gellerstraße 2</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated May 9, 1931</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Duisburg, Gellerstr. 2.
9.V.31.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Allgemach habe ich mich wieder in den – nun etwas veränderten Alltag hineingefunden.  Ich beginne bereits die Stadt Duisburg etwas wie aus der Entfernung zu betrachten, denn länger als etwa sieben oder acht Wochen werde ich nicht mehr hier sein.  Am 1. August trete ich in Hamburg bei Herrn Prof. Violin<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Click on <ref cRef="violin_moriz">Moriz Violin</ref>.</tei:note> an, um meinen Teil an den nötigen Vorarbeiten zu leisten.  Am 1. September geht es dann los.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  The Schenker Institute in Hamburg was due to open on September 1.</tei:note>  Vorher, in den Pfingstferien<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Pentecost Sunday was May 24 in 1931.</tei:note> gibt es noch eine kurze Besprechung in Hamburg, darnach ich meine Vorbereitungen treffe.  Dies werde ich sehr wahrscheinlich mit einem 3–4 wöchigen Erholungsaufenthalt in +Oberösterreich+ verbinden <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> (seit drei Jahren der erste Urlaub), wo ich bei Bekannten eingeladen bin.  Am Duisburger Konservatorium habe ich bereits gekündigt, wobei man mich zuvorkommenderweise von dem vertrags’chen Termin (Oktober) entbunden hat.   Einige Genugtuung bereitet mir die Tatsache, dass mein Posten nicht so leicht zu besetzen ist.  Gute Aussichten hat ein Anwärter aus Düsseldorf.  Sei dem wie ihm sei, ich habe im pädagogisch praktischen Sinne hier eine ganze Menge gelernt. –</tei:p><tei:p>Alle Welt hofiert mich jetzt.  Gerade die, die am grimmigsten gegen mich gewühlt haben, sind jetzt eitel Wohlwollen und Zuvorkommenheit.  Sie haben “schon immer” gesagt, das Schenker eine fabelhafte Sache sei, und sie hätten “gerade jetzt” sich entschlossen, ernsthaft an die Sache “ranzugehen”.  Zu schade, dass ich nun gerade wegfahre!  Mein “grosser” Konkurrent Eccarius<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Eccarius: identify.</tei:note> hat mir sogar das ver- <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> trauliche “Du” angeboten.  Es juckte mich in allen Eingeweiden zu sagen:  “Sie werden lachen, ich bleibe hier!” –</tei:p><tei:p>Der Herr Voss<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> Erich Voss had came into contact with Cube in Cologne, then went to Vienna in the hope of studying with Schenker but, unable to make ends meet, returned to north Germany.  See letters and postcards OJ 9/34, [18], May 14 and vC 23, May 15, 1929; vC24 and 25, July 6 and 14, and OJ 9/34, [19], July 18, 1929; vC 29, June 9, and OJ 9/34, [21], June 25, 1930)</tei:note> entwickelt eine prächtige Betriebsamkeit.  Er hält Kurse und Arbeitsgemeinschaften ab, gibt Stunden in Kontrapunkt, und geht jetzt in Dortmund aufs Seminar um einesteils sich aufs Staatsexamen vorzubereiten, andererseits um “Schenker-Zellen” zu bilden, wie er sich ausdrückt.  Er besitzt genügend Kenntnisse und überzeugende Redekunst, um Erfolge haben zu können.  Wir haben Harmonie, Stimmführung und manches andere gearbeitet, und er hat sich gut entwickelt, und wird der Sache sehr nützlich sein!  Leider ist er noch etwas von westfälischem, ja, beinahe holländischen Eigenschaften belastet, doch wird er diese schon noch ablegen lernen.  Ein vorzügliches Horosokop stelle ich meiner besten Schülerin Lieselotte Müller,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6"> Lieselotte Müller is not mentioned anywhere else in the Cube–Schenker correspondence.  His fondness for using Schenkerian terminology notwithstanding, it is not clear what Cube means by this.  (If Müller has the better musical mind, and in this sense more “fundamental,” then the expression should perhaps be reversed: Voss = Dreiklang, Müeller = Stufe)</tei:note> die schon beinahe unheimlich begabt ist.  Auch sie muss sich <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> zunächst die Staatsprüfung gefallen lassen, dann werde ich Himmel und Hölle in Bewegung setzen, um sie in Hamburg weiter unterrichten zu können.  Voss ist ein guter Arbeiter, die Müller aber verhält sich zu ihm wie ein Dreiklang zu einer Stufe.  Um diese beiden willen hat sich Duisburg schon gelohnt.  Schade, dass die Müller so sehr jung und noch ganz am Anfang ist! –</tei:p><tei:p>Die Ironie des Schicksals hat es gebracht, dass es mir nun ausgerechnet die letzten zwei Monate hier noch besonders dreckig gehen soll.  Mit Hamburg vor Augen ertrage ich es mit Humor, und lasse mich im Übrigen von allen Leuten zum Essen einladen.  À propos Geschäftslage:  Zwei Herren fahren von Berlin nach Frankfurt;  beide sprechen kein Wort.  Kurz vor Frankfurt seufzt der eine tief auf.  Darauf der andere: “Mir wollen Sie was erzählen?”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7"> Presumably, the punch-line indicates that things are so bad in Germany that two businessen cannot find anything to talk about even on a long train trip.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Einstweilen beste Grüsse Ihnen und Ihrer Frau Gemahlin, und sofort nach Pfingsten folgt genauer Bericht von</tei:p><tei:p>Ihrem
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated May 9, 1931</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Duisburg, Gellerstraße 2.
9 May 1931</tei:p><tei:p>Most honoured master,</tei:p><tei:p>Little by little I have found myself again in the—somewhat modified—pattern of daily life.  I am already beginning to view the city of Duisburg somewhat from a distance, for in about seven or eight weeks I shall no longer be here.  On the first of August I arrive in Hamburg at Prof. Violin’s,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> to accomplish my part of the necessary preliminary work.  On the first of September, things begin.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  Before that, during the Pentecost holidays,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> I have a short meeting in Hamburg;  then I shall get on with my preparations.  I will most probably combine this with a three-to-four-week period of relaxation in +Upper Austria+ <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> (my first holiday for three years), where I have an invitation from friends.  I have already given notice to the Duisburg Conservatory, whereby I have been courteously relieved of my obligations to the end of my contract (October).  The fact that my post will not be so easy to fill afforded me some satisfaction; a candidate from Düsseldorf has good prospects [to be appointed to it].  All things considered, I have learned quite a lot in a pedagogically practical sense.</tei:p><tei:p>Everyone is now courteous to me.  The very people who agitated most unpleasantly against me now show me vain goodwill and courtesy.  They have said “all along” that Schenker is a fabulous thing, and they were about to decide “precisely at this time” to “get going” with it.  What a pity that I am leaving at this very moment!  My “great” rival Eccarius<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> even offered to address me with the <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> intimate “Du”.  I had a feeling in my gut to want to say: “You shall laugh: I am staying here!”</tei:p><tei:p>Mr Voss<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> is developing a splendid enterprise.  He arranges courses and working groups, gives lessons in counterpoint, and is now going to the Seminar in Dortmund, partly to prepare for the state examination, partly to form “Schenker cells”, as he likes to call them.  He has enough knowledge and convincing oratorical skills to be successful.  We have worked on harmony, voice-leading and many other things, and he has developed well;  he will be very useful in the matter.  Unfortunately he is still encumbered by Westphalian—Dutch, one might almost say—qualities, but he will soon learn to cast these off.  I envisage an excellent future for my best pupil, Lieselotte Müller,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> who is already unusually talented.  She, too, must <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> first pass the state examination;  then I will move heaven and earth so that she can continue in Hamburg as a teacher.  Voss is a good worker;  but Müller is to him as a triad to a harmonic degree.  Just on account of these two, Duisburg was worth it.  A pity that Müller is so very young, and at the very beginning!</tei:p><tei:p>The irony of fate is that things will be particularly unpleasant for me during my last two months here.  With Hamburg ahead of me, I can bear it with good humour; and moreover I accept everyone’s invitation to dinner.  A propos of the economic situation:  Two gentlemen are travelling from Berlin to Frankfurt;  neither speaks a word.  Shortly before they are to arrive in Frankfurt, one of them sighs deeply.  The other replies: “Did you want to tell me something?”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/></tei:p><tei:p>For the time being, best wishes to you and your wife; and immediately after Pentecost you will get a more precise report from</tei:p><tei:p>Your
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>