<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [13] : 7-6-28 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2006.
© Translation by William Drabkin 2006
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1928-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 07/06/1928 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated July 6, 1928</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-07-16</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Cube reports on Scheuermann exhibit, and consequent interest and sales, encloses associated newspaper article; also on recent lecturing and composition activity.  He is unlikely to visit Schenker this year; recalls people at Galtür.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  exhibit;  Scheuermann;  Duisburg;  Der Tonwille;  Niloff, Artur;  Instrumentations-Tabelle;  Instrumentation Table;  Chopin;  Scherzo;  Beethoven;  Moonlight Sonata;  newspaper article;  Damrosch;  Dunn, John Petrie;  Köln;  Cologne;  NMTP;  Beitrag zur Ornamentik;  Contribution to Ornamentation;  Meisterwerk in der Musik;  Masterwork in Music;  Sallenthin, Dr.;  Bach, C. P. E.;  Versuch;  Photogrammarchiv;  Duisburg Conservatory;  Düsseldorf;  Hammer, Victor;  engraving;  Essen;  Galtür;  Türtscher family;  marmot</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Duisburg, Rhineland, Pulverweg 41</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated July 6, 1928</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">letterhead:</tei:hi>] FELIX E. VON CUBE 
Duisburg./ Rhld.
Pulverweg 41. 
6.VII.28.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Sicher war es unrecht von mir, solange mit Nachrichten zu zögern, indes lag in meiner Absicht, erst alle Auswirkungen der Sache abzuwarten, um einen umso vollständigeren Bericht abzufassen. Hier ist er:</tei:p><tei:p>Die Ausstellung lief gegen 14 Tage bei der besagten Buchhandlung Scheuermann.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Cube had arranged an exhibition of Schenker materials for the latter's 60th birthday in the store of Scheuermann, the leading music book dealer in Cube's home town of Duisburg, and also Schmemann in Essen: see vC 11, September 7, 1927;  OJ 9/34, [11], April 24, 1928; OJ 9/34, [12], May 24, 1928.</tei:note> Bis auf den "Tonwillen" war <tei:hi rend="italic">alles</tei:hi> von Ihnen mehrfach vertreten. In einem der grossen Schaufenster stand die Hammer-Radierung, umgeben von Büchern und Notenausgaben. (Die Nieloff-Tabelle fungierte zwei Tage als Gobelin<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  recte: Niloff:  click on <ref cRef="instrumentations-tab"><tei:hi rend="italic">Instrumentations-Tabelle</tei:hi></ref>.   <tei:hi rend="italic">Gobelin</tei:hi> = "woven tapestry": Cube is emphasizing the theatrical quality of the Schenker exhibit in Scheuermann's shop window, and the sheer size of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Tabelle</tei:hi>.</tei:note>). Ausserdem waren ständig einige Photogramme ausgestellt. Bei Chopin op.54, und Beethoven op.27/2 legten wir gute und schlechte Ausgaben zum Vergleich dazu.</tei:p><tei:p>Mein biographischer Artikel erschien in Duisburgs gelesenster Zeitung.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Presumably ""Heinrich Schenker," unknown newspaper, June 28, 1928 (clipping preserved OJ 58/3).</tei:note> Einige andere haben ihn ohne Angabe von Gründen abgelehnt. Dieser Artikel war mein erste Versuch dieser Art. Ich habe mich bemüht, das Richtige zu treffen. Hoffentlich findet er Ihre Billigung. Abzüge habe ich an mehrere "prominente" Leute geschickt, so auch an Damrosch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  The main members of the musical family of Damrosch, of whom the brothers Frank and Walter were born a few years before Schenker, had settled in American in the 1870s; Schenker is not known to have had any contact with them.</tei:note> <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> und J. P. Dunn.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="dunn_john_petrie">John Petrie Dunn</ref></tei:note> Zwei Rückäusserungen lege ich Ihne bei, mit der Bitte, sie mir wieder zugehen [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte:</tei:hi> zu geben] zu lassen. Köln werde ich allen Ernstes bearbeiten. Möglicherweise kann für mich was Gutes daraus entstehen. -</tei:p><tei:p>Von der Ausstellung wird hier viel gesprochen.  Es ist auch einiges verkauft worden. Meistens "Theorien" und Beethoven Sonaten. Die Stadtbibliothek hat für ihre Musikabteilung vorläufig die 9. u. 5. Sinfonie, den "Beitrag", die Sonaten, und die Jahrbücher angeschafft. Weiteres wird folgen. Der Direktor der Bücherei, Dr. Sallenthin, hat übrigens schöne Erstausgaben aus der Zeit von Haydn, Mozart und anderen. Auch die "zweyte Auflage" vom "Versuch", leider ohne die Probestücke. Da diese meistens fehlen, möchte ich anregen, diese Beilage zum "Versuch" in die Archivbestände<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="photogrammarchiv">Photogrammarchiv</ref>.</tei:note> aufzunehmen. Viele Bibliotheken würden sie wohl anschaffen. Besser in Faksimile, als garnicht. -</tei:p><tei:p>Als letzte Auswirkung vor den Ferien spreche ich im Seminar einen ganzen Vormittag über Ihre Theorien, über die Urlinie mit vielen Beispielen, und über die Ausgabenfrage. Die Zahl der Überzeugten ist noch gering, aber verlässlich - das liegt in der Natur der Sache. Am nächsten Dienstag werde ich dann wohl wieder etliche Seminaristen bekehren. -</tei:p><tei:p>In Düsseldorf war ich eingeladen[,] Vortrag zu halten. Es erschienen 10 Zuhörer.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  See OJ 9/34, [12], May 24, 1928: "I shall give my lecture now also in the Conservatory of the City of Düsseldorf, in front of what is expected to be a large audience."</tei:note> Da habe ich den Vortrag verschoben. Dem Veranstalter war es peinlich, aber er <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> versprach mir fürs nächstemal ein zahlreiches auditorium.</tei:p><tei:p>Hier ist ein grosser Komponistenwettbewerb ausgeschrieben, an dem ich mich mit zwei Sonaten beteiligen werde. An der zweiten fehlt noch einiges am letzten Satz, doch das wird wohl bis Oktober zum Ablieferungstermin fertig sein. -</tei:p><tei:p>Die zweite Radierung<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  by Victor Hammer [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> ist nicht benützt worden. Ich konnte mich der Essener Buchhandlung nicht genügend widmen. Soll ich sie Ihnen nach Galtür schicken, oder wünschen Sie eine andere Adresse? -</tei:p><tei:p>Ob ich diesen Sommer kommen kann ist mehr als fraglich. Es "kriselt" mal wieder in der Wirtschaft, was zur Folge hat, dass mir die Schüler in Scharen weglaufen. Aber sie werden schon wieder kommen. Ich werde aus Prinzip nicht billiger. Mein Tarif ist derzeit 10. Mark. -</tei:p><tei:p>Ich sende Ihnen also umso herzlichere Gedanken und Wünsche nach Galtür, und geselle mich im Geiste an Ihren Fenstertisch zu Luftbrot, Schlagobers und Riesenschnitzeln. Auch lasse ich Familie Türtscher bestens grüssen. Nicht zu vergessen den Hausdiener-Kapellmeister, und das zuckerlverzehrende Murmeltier.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">   Cube is reminiscing about his visit to Galtür the previous summer.</tei:note> -</tei:p><tei:p>Ihnen und Ihrer Frau Gemahlin alles Herzliche von</tei:p><tei:p>Ihrem
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated July 6, 1928</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">letterhead:</tei:hi>] FELIX E. VON CUBE 
Duisburg, Rhineland
Pulverweg 41
July 6, 1928.</tei:p><tei:p>Most honoured Master,</tei:p><tei:p>It was certainly wrong of me to delay with news for so long; but it had been my intention to wait for all the consequences of the matter, so that I could prepare an all the more complete report. Here it is.</tei:p><tei:p>The exhibition ran for two weeks at Scheurermann's bookshop,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> of which I spoke. Apart from <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">all</tei:hi> of your work was available in multiple copies. In the big shop window stood Hammer's engraving, surrounded by books and editions of music. (Niloff's <tei:hi rend="italic">Instrumentation Table</tei:hi> functioned for two days as backcloth.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>) In addition, a few photocopies of autograph manuscripts were on display at all times. For Chopin's Scherzo Op.54 and Beethoven's "Moonlight" Sonata we additionally placed good and bad editions side by side, for comparison.</tei:p><tei:p>My biographical article appeared in Duisburg's most widely read newspaper.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  (A few other papers turned it down, without giving reasons.) This article was my first essay of this kind. I made an effort to hit upon what was right. I hope it meets with your approval. I have sent copies to "prominent" people, thus also to Damrosch<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> and J. P. Dunn.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> I enclose two replies; please be so kind as to return them to me. I will work on the Cologne project with all seriousness; perhaps something good for me can come out of it.</tei:p><tei:p>There has been much talk her about the exhibition [of your work], and a few things have been sold: mainly the [<tei:hi rend="italic">Neue musikalische</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">Theorien</tei:hi> [<tei:hi rend="italic">und Phantasien</tei:hi>] and [your edition of the] Beethoven sonatas. The municipal library has, for the present, acquired the [monographs on] the ninth and fifth symphonies [of Beethoven], the <tei:hi rend="italic">Beitrag</tei:hi> [<tei:hi rend="italic">zur Ornamentik</tei:hi>], the sonata edition, and the [<tei:hi rend="italic">Meisterwerk</tei:hi>] yearbooks for its music section. More will follow. The director of the library, Dr. Sallenthin, has, moreover, beautiful first editions from the period of Haydn, Mozart, and others, and also the "second edition" of [Carl Philipp Emanuel Bach's] <tei:hi rend="italic">Versuch</tei:hi>, though unfortunately without the test pieces. Since these are missing from most copies, might I suggest that this supplement to the <tei:hi rend="italic">Versuch</tei:hi> be included in the holdings of the Archive.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> Better if as a photographic reproduction than not at all.</tei:p><tei:p>My last activity before the holidays, I shall speak at the Conservatory for an entire morning about your theories, about the Urlinie (with many examples), and about the question of editions. The number of converts is still limited, though reliable--that lies in the nature of the subject. The following Tuesday, I shall probably proselytize a few more conservatory students.</tei:p><tei:p>In Düsseldorf, I was invited to give a lecture. Ten listeners appeared.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> And so I postponed the lecturer. The organizer was disappointed by this, but he <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> promised me a sizeable audience the next time.</tei:p><tei:p>Here a big composers' competition has been announced, which I shall enter with two sonatas. There is still some things missing from the last movement of the second, but these will be finished by the October deadline.</tei:p><tei:p>The second engraving<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> was not used: I could not devote myself sufficiently to the bookshop in Essen. Shall I send it to you in Galtür, or would you prefer a different addess?</tei:p><tei:p>It is very unlikely that I shall be able to come this summer. Business is again in crisis, the consequence of which is that my pupils are leaving in droves. But they will come again. As a matter of principle, I am not lowering the rate for my lessons, which currently stands at 10 marks.</tei:p><tei:p>I therefore send you all the more heartfelt thoughts and wishes to Galtür, and will be present in spirit at your table by the window with <tei:hi rend="italic">Luftbrot</tei:hi>, whipped cream and gigantic cutlets. I also send my warmest greetings to the Türtscher family. Nor am I forgetting your servant-Kapellmeister, and the marmot who eats sweets.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/></tei:p><tei:p>To you and your wife, all affectionate feelings from</tei:p><tei:p>Your
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>