<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [8] : 5-28-27 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2006.
© Translation William Drabkin, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1927-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 05/28/1927 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated May 28, 1927</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-06-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>C reports on the state teaching examination, on which he was graded "satisfactory," deploring the way it was conducted. 

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  state teaching examination;  Richter, Ernst Friedrich;  Riemann, Hugo;  ear training;  theory;  sight reading;  thoroughbass;  Sodom; Geneva;  Siemens, Freiherr von;  compositions</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Duisburg, Rhineland, Mülheimerstrasse 141/II</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated May 28, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Duisburg./Rhld.
Mülheimerstr. 141/II. 	
28.V.27.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Das Staatsexamen ist bestanden.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> See C’s letters, OJ 9/34, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> Hugo Riemann (1849–1919), author of separate textbooks on harmony (1880; 1887; 1890; 1893; 1906), rhythmic structure (1883; 1884; 1890; 1903), counterpoint (1888), fugue (1890–94), and form (1889), a collective music theory manual (1902–13), manuals of analysis, a history of music theory, the principal musical dictionary of its time, and books on many other topics.  He was regarded by S and his disciples as the embodiment of the institutionalizing of (bad) music theory. </tei:note>,  November 25, 1926 ,and <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6"> C was sufficiently proud of this work to enter it in a competition, and dedicate it to his teacher. Schenker commented on it, and a second sonata, in his letter of August 10, 1929. For an extract from the sonata, see William Drabkin, “Felix-Eberhard von Cube and the North-German Tradition of Schenkerism,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Royal Musical Association</tei:hi> 111 (1985), especially pp. 205–7.</tei:note>, January 24, 1927.</tei:note>  Die Herren am grünen Tisch haben mich mit einem “genügend” vor der Welt diskreditiert, und sich damit ein nicht unbeträchtliches Armutszeugnis ausgestellt.</tei:p><tei:p>Das Gesamtergebnis war kläglich: Von dreissig Kandidaten (davon fünfundzwanzig Kandidatinnen) sind elf unterwegs ausgeschieden, sechs durchgefallen, fünf mit “gut” bedacht worden, (dieses[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] „Seminaristinnen”, von ihren Lehrern auf alle „Fragen” wohl vorbereitet!) und mit dem genügenden Rest soll ich mich auf eine Stufe gestellt fühlen? Ich finde das sehr humorvoll!</tei:p><tei:p>Doch fürchte ich, dass ich bei den Professoren lähmendes Befremden dadurch ausgelöst habe, dass ich in vielen Punkten, wo erstere nur keine oder “die” Antwort erwarteten, mir erlaubt habe, gänzlich anderer Meinung zu sein.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Solches ist Staatsverbrechen und Anarchie gegen die Majestät Richters<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Ernst Friedrich Richter (1808–79), leading teacher of music theory at the Leipzig Conservatory, author of widely-used textbooks on musical form (1851), harmony (1853), fugue (1859), and counterpoint (1872).  He was a regular object of S’s criticism.</tei:note> und Riemanns<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> Hugo Riemann (1849–1919), author of separate textbooks on harmony (1880; 1887; 1890; 1893; 1906), rhythmic structure (1883; 1884; 1890; 1903), counterpoint (1888), fugue (1890–94), and form (1889), a collective music theory manual (1902–13), manuals of analysis, a history of music theory, the principal musical dictionary of its time, and books on many other topics.  He was regarded by S and his disciples as the embodiment of the institutionalizing of (bad) music theory. </tei:note> und verstösst gegen die Institution des Kollektivwissens. Man hat mich also – da man mich als Ihren Schüler nicht wohl durchfallen lassen konnte – mit dem “genügend” bestraft. Angeblich, weil ich bei der Lehrprobe, zu der man mir ein neunjähriges Kind stellte, versagt hätte! Doch bin ich hierin auch anderer Meinung. Ich lehre aus meinem Wissen und Herzen, und nicht nach den staatlichen Normalvorschriften für Kretine. –</tei:p><tei:p>Das Zeugnis mit den Einzelwertungen ist noch nicht an mich gelangt; sobald es kommt, werde ich Ihnen meine Noten in den einzelnen Fächern mitteilen. –</tei:p><tei:p>Die ganze Handhabung der Prüfung ist von vorne bis hinten verfehlt. Ein Mensch mit Gewissen muss sich sagen, dass bei einer derartigen Examination das positive Können eines Musikers nicht einwandfrei festgestellt werden kann. Es fing an mit einer schriftlichen Arbeit: “Wie sind die produktiven Kräfte des Kindes im Unterricht anzuregen und zu verwerten”. Dann kam “Gehörbildung”. Sie <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> bestand im Wesentlichen im Nachschreiben atonaler, zusammenhangloser Tonfolgen und –Sprünge, sowie kleiner mehrstimmiger Sätze von 2–3 Takten. Dann “Theorie”, d.h. je ein Generalbässchen mit und ohne Oberstimme. Die praktische Prüfung bestand aus Vorspielen, analysieren (die Gesichter hätten Sie sehen sollen!), Ausführung blödsinniger Stufenfolgen, (letzteres besorgte ich in einer freien Phantasie, und alles war begeistert, und kein Schwein hat gemerkt, dass ich ganz andere Stufen durchlief – – was ich mich gefreut habe!) sowie aus der Unterrichtsprobe. Da kam ein winziges Kind mit sehr erschreckten Augen, und dem, das vor lauter Verlegenheit nicht aufzusehen wagte, sollte ich – ausgerechnet – “den” Dominantseptakkord “erklären”, obwohl das Kind kaum eine Ahnung von Dur und Moll hatte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> Nearly sixty years later, in his autobiographical essay of 1984, C recalls having to teach the seventh chord to “a frightfully shy nine-year-old girl who could barely read music.” </tei:note> Als man einsah, dass es nicht ging, musste ich “Vorder[ - ] und Nachsatz” lehren. Das gelang mit zärtlicher Überredung und vielen Vergleichen. Zum Schluss war ich ausserordenlich erbittert über diese idiotischen Massnahmen, und gegen die Herren nicht eben sehr freundlich. Ich werde alle meine Kräfte mobil machen, um, gegen diesen neuesten Auswuchs echt demokratischer Geistesunterjochung, im Sinne echten und freien Künstlertums energischst aufzutreten.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Aber wer ist sicher, dass er in diesem Sodom auch nur zehn Gerechte fände? –</tei:p><tei:p>Einliegend sende ich Ihnen ein interssantes Streiflicht von der Genfer Konferenz, das bezeigt, daß es doch noch Männer unter uns giebt, auf die man Hoffnungen setzen darf. (Freiherr v. Siemens).<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> Geneva conference, Freiherr Siemens [need details]</tei:note> Aber es sind ihrer zu wenige. –</tei:p><tei:p>Demnächst wird mein Kolleg für Theorie im Konservatorium eröffnet. Meine Klaviersonate<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6"> C was sufficiently proud of this work to enter it in a competition, and dedicate it to his teacher. Schenker commented on it, and a second sonata, in his letter of August 10, 1929. For an extract from the sonata, see William Drabkin, “Felix-Eberhard von Cube and the North-German Tradition of Schenkerism,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Royal Musical Association</tei:hi> 111 (1985), especially pp. 205–7.</tei:note> ist nahezu vollendet. Im September gedenke ich folgende Kompositionen aufführen zu lassen:</tei:p><tei:p>Thema mit Veränderungen, op. 1
Bagatelle, [/] Praeludium, [/] Tarantella, op. 2
Sonate As-Dur: Allegro, Scherzo, Adagio, Rondo, op.3.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6"> C was sufficiently proud of this work to enter it in a competition, and dedicate it to his teacher. Schenker commented on it, and a second sonata, in his letter of August 10, 1929. For an extract from the sonata, see William Drabkin, “Felix-Eberhard von Cube and the North-German Tradition of Schenkerism,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Royal Musical Association</tei:hi> 111 (1985), especially pp. 205–7.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Mit Freude unterziehe ich mich allen Mühen und meine gute Lebenslaune verlässt mich nie, aber das Hochkommen geht halt schwer und langsam. –</tei:p><tei:p>Zum Schluss: Es ist nicht ausgeschlossen, dass ich Sie in diesem Jahre noch besuche!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7"> Like many of Schenker’s advanced pupils and musical associates, C had an open invitation to visit him in the summer in the Tyrolean village of Galtür. C did, in fact, make the trip there in the summer of 1927.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Für diesmal Ihnen und Ihrer Frau Gemahlin herzlichste Grüsse von</tei:p><tei:p>Ihrem
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated May 28, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Duisburg, Rhineland
Mülheimerstrasse 141/II
May 28, 1927</tei:p><tei:p>Most honoured master,</tei:p><tei:p>The state examination has been passed.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> The men at the green table have discredited me before the world with a grade of “satisfactory,” and in consequence have issued themselves a certificate of a not inconsiderable degree of [intellectual] poverty.</tei:p><tei:p>The overall result was lamentable. Of the thirty candidates (of whom twenty-five were female), eleven dropped out along the way, six failed, five were judged as “good” (these “female seminarists,” who were probably prepared in advance by their teachers in all “questions”); and with the rest who were satisfactory, should I feel that we are all of the same level? I find that very humorous!</tei:p><tei:p>Yet I fear that I have alienated myself from the professors, to my disadvantage, since in many points where they expected no answer at all, or the obvious answer, I took the liberty of expressing a completely different opinion. <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> That is a state crime, and anarchy against the majesty of Richter<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> and Riemann<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>, which offends the institution of collective knowledge. So I was punished with “satisfactory”—as your pupil, I could certainly not have been allowed to fail—ostensibly on the grounds that, at the teaching trial at which a nine-year-old child was presented to me, I would have broken down! And yet in this, too, I am of a different opinion. I teach from what I know, and from the heart, and not according to the normal state regulations for cretins.</tei:p><tei:p>The certificate with breakdown of individual marks has not yet reached me; as soon as it arrives, I will give you my marks in the individual sections.</tei:p><tei:p>The entire conduct of the assessment was misguided from beginning to end. Anyone with a conscience would say to himself that, from such an examination paper, the positive ability of a musician could not be determined incontrovertibly. It began with a written essay: “How can one stimulate, and assess, the productive powers of the child in teaching?” This was followed by “aural training.” It <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> comprised mainly the writing out of incoherent atonal successions and leaps of tones, also short polyphonic phrases of two to three bars. Then “theory,” i.e. short thoroughbass exericises, one with and one without figures. The practical test comprised playing at sight, analysis (you should have seen their faces!), the realization of stupid chord progressions (this I dealt with in a free fantasia: all was inspired, and not one of the pigs noticed that I passed through entirely different harmonies – that pleased me!), and also the teaching test. A tiny child, with great fear in its eyes, came up; and to this child, who dared not look up from sheer embarrassment, I was supposed to “explain” <tei:hi rend="italic">the</tei:hi> chord of the dominant seventh, even though the child barely had an idea of major and minor.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> As it became clear that this was not working, I had to teach “antecedent and consequent phrases.” That succeeded with tender conviction and numerous analogies. At the end I was extremely embittered by these idiotic measures, and not even very friendly towards the examiners. I shall mobilize all my powers in order to confront this latest product of unadulterated democratic intellectual subjugation as energetically as possible, in the name of genuine and free artistry,. <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> But, in this Sodom, who can be certain of finding merely ten just men?</tei:p><tei:p>I am enclosing for you an interesting sidelight from the Geneva conference, which shows that there are indeed still men among us on whom we can set our hopes (Freiherr von Siemens).<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  But there are too few like them.</tei:p><tei:p>In a short time, my theory course will begin.  My piano sonata<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> is almost finished. In September I am thinking of having the following compositions performed:</tei:p><tei:p>Thema and Variations, Op.1
Bagatelle, Prelude and Tarantella, Op. 2
Sonata in A-flat major, Op.3, comprising Allegro, Scherzo, Adagio, Rondo<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/></tei:p><tei:p>I submit to all difficulties with joy, and my good humour never deserts me; but advancing in my career is proving rather difficult and will take a long time.</tei:p><tei:p>To conclude, it is not inconceivable that I shall still visit you this year!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/></tei:p><tei:p>For now, most cordial greetings to you and your wife from</tei:p><tei:p>Your
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>