<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [29] : 10-20-31 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin 2006.
© Translation William Drabkin 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1931-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 10/20/1931 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated October 20, 1931</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-07-12</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Encloses graph of  J. S. Bach, Wohltemperirtes Clavier, Book I, Prelude in C major and asks S's opinion of several aspects of his graphing. 

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  Bach, J. S.;  Wohltemperirtes Clavier;  Well-tempered Clavier;  prelude;  Terzraum;  third-progression;  Bassbrechung;  bass arpeggiation; Tieferlegung;  descending register transfer;  Parallelismen;  parallelisms;  Aufhaltung;  holding-over;  Terznebennotenbewegung;  Auswechslung;  exchange;  Oktavzug;  octave-progression;  Quartzug;  fourth-progression;  Lagenspiel;  play of registers;  Quartsprung;  Durchgang</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Hamburg, Beneckestrasse 2</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated October 20, 1931</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hamburg, Beneckestr. 2; bei Alexander Schmidt.
20. X. 31.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Anbei der angekündigte Leseversuch.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> In a letter written four days before (OJ 9/34, [28], October 16, 1931), C explained that a new graph of the Prelude in C major from Bach’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Well-Tempered Clavier</tei:hi>, Book 1, would soon be ready.  The graph is not with the letter, and is not known to survive.</tei:note>  Es liegt mir daran, den Abstand meiner seinerzeitigen und heutigen Hörfähigkeit und auch des Aufzeichnenkönnens festzustellen.  In der ersten Skizze<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> This is a graph dating from nearly two years before, and included in Cube’s letter, OJ 9/34, [20], January 2, 1930. The graph is not known to survive.</tei:note> waren der Terzraum, die Bassbrechung und die Tieferlegung – wenn auch schief ausgedrückt – enthalten.  Vom übrigen war nicht viel vorhanden.  Sie wiesen mich seinerzeit besonders auf die Parallelismen</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 1</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>hin, sowie auf 3–4–4–3 in den Schlusstakten.</tei:p><tei:p>Nun die Fragen:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> In fact, there is more in the way of explanation than “questions” in what follows: each layer of the graph is explained in some detail. There are, in fact, many more layers than the three that are used for the graph of the Prelude in the <tei:hi rend="italic">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln</tei:hi> (and for the graphs in Cube’s unpublished <tei:hi rend="italic">Lehrbuch der musikalischen Kunstgesetzte</tei:hi>).</tei:note> Ist bei a.) die ~2 schon über der II des Basses einzusetzen?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> In the piece itself, the definitive ~2 of the Urlinie, d^2^, arrives after the final C major has appeared in the bass;  Cube is asking whether this should be shown at the “highest” level in the analysis.</tei:note>  Bei b.) wird die Aufhaltung deutlich, die über dem f des Basses einen Vierklang der IV erzeugt. Die Auswechslung nahm ich an wegen</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 2</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>Bei c.) führe ich zunächst die Terznebennotenbewegungen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> That is, the 3–4–4–3 in mm. 1–4 and 32–35.</tei:note> und eine weitere Auswechslung, immer noch ohne die Tieferlegung und noch vierstimmig an, um erstere für sich benebst einigen Chromenparalellismen zu verdeutlichen. Bei d.) tritt der zweigeteilte Oktavzug und die Fünfstimmigkeit in ihre Rechte; bei 3–4–4–3 am Anfang und Schluss versuchte ich die Stimmenzedierung<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6"> “Stimmenzedierung”: literally the “yielding of the voices,” i.e. their gradual progression to the lower register in the course of the octave-progression in the bass.</tei:note> beim begleitenden Quartzug aufzuzeigen. Das Lagenspiel der Schlussbrechungen habe ich daher auch für e.) aufgespart.  e.) soll nur noch die Beseitigung der 8–8, und 5–5 zeigen, durch 6–5, 6–5 und Auswerfen der Mittelstimme, was wieder die Parallelismen zeugt. Die differierende Behandlung der Quarthälften des Oktavzuges sehe ich begründet bei den Anfängen, wo sich der Quartsprung e–a in einen ausgefüllten Terzraum b–cis–d wandelt. Ausserdem liegen die 6–5, 6–5 umgekehrt.</tei:p><tei:p>Die chromatischen Durchgänge rühren wohl von den Ur–Durchgängen bei e.) her. Ist dies alles einigermaassen vernünftig gelesen, oder habe ich ganz danebengehauen? Wie ist die Schreib-Art gewählt? Für eine neuerliche [<tei:hi rend="italic">most of penultimate line illegible</tei:hi>] verpflichtet! [?]</tei:p><tei:p>Mit herzlichsten
[<tei:hi rend="italic">end of valediction missing</tei:hi>]</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated October 20, 1931</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hamburg, Beneckestrasse 2, c/o Alexander Schmidt
20 October 1931</tei:p><tei:p>Most honoured master,</tei:p><tei:p>Enclosed is the attempted reading, as announced [in my previous letter].<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  What is of interest to me is determining the distance between my previous and my present capability of hearing, and also my ability in writing things up.  The first sketch<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> included the space of a third, the bass arpeggiation and the descending register transfer, even though this had still been clumsily expressed.  Of the rest, there was not much present.  You referred me at the time in particular to the parallelism [between a^2^–d^2^–g^2^ and a–d–g]:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 1</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>and also 3–4–4–3 in the [opening and] closing bars.</tei:p><tei:p>Now for the questions:<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  In a.), should I place the ~2 already above the II in the bass?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  In b.) the holding-over, which creates a seventh chord above F in the bass, is shown clearly. I assumed the exchange [of d^1^ for e^1^] on account of consecutive fifths:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 2</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>In c.), I introduce first of all the neighbor-note motions above the third<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>, and a further exchange, but still without the descending register transfer and still in four-part harmony, in order to clarify the former for itself, along with a few chromatic parallelisms.  At d.) the octave-progression, divided into two parts, and the five-part harmony come to the fore; at the  3–4–4–3 at the start and at the end, I attempted to show the yielding of the voices<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> above [each] accompanying fourth-progression. Thus I saved the play of registers in the final arpeggiations for e.).  e) is intended additionally to show merely the avoidance of consecutive fifths and octaves by means of 6–5, 6–5 and the throwing of the inner voice [into the highest/lowest voice], which additionally creates the parallelisms. The differing treatmeant of the two fourths that make up the octave progression is something I see as founded in the openings, where the leap of a fourth from e to a is transformed into a filled-in third-progression b-c#-d. In addition, the 6–5, 6–5 is reversed. 
 
The chromatic passing notes surely originate in the original passing notes shown in a.)  Does all this seem a more or less sensible reading? Or have I gone entirely wide of the mark? What do you think of my choice of notation? I would be indebted [to you] for a new [assessment of what I have done]</tei:p><tei:p>With most cordial [greetings to you and your wife,
Yours,
Cube]</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>