<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [4] 12-14-26 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2006.
© Translation by William Drabkin 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1926-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 12/14/1926 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated December 14, 1926</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-06-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>C was not given recognition, and has to take an examination for purposes of the appointment.  Sends Christmas greetings.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  appointment;  examination;  Sallmann, Dr.;  Koblenz;  lecture;  teaching methods;  Urlinie;  Christmas greetings</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Kaiserswerth-Bockum, Rhineland, Villa Dahlmann</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated December 14, 1926</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Kaiserswerth-Bockum, Rhld.
Villa Dahlmann.	
14.XII.26.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Haben Sie vielen Dank für Ihre Bemühungen in meiner Conservatoriums-Sache.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> See letters OJ 9/34 [3] and vC 5, an exchange of letters concerning a reference from Schenker in support of Cube’s appointment to the teaching staff of the Rheinisches Musikseminar in Düsseldorf.</tei:note> Die Anerkennung habe ich zwar nicht erhalten, indessen werde ich doch vermutlich angestellt werden, unter der Bedingung einer abzulegenden Prüfung. Diese wird von den mir schon bekannten Herren abgehalten, ist also nur eine Formalität.  Ausschlaggebend war, dass Dr. Sallmann ein Jugendfreund meines Vaters ist, was wir allerdings nicht wussten. Bei der Prüfung wird Rücksicht auf die verschiedenen “Methoden” genommen, und auch meine Tätigkeit im Conservatorium wird speziel Ihre Theorie, die <tei:hi rend="italic">Urlinie</tei:hi>! und Klaverspiel umfassen. Samstag halte ich den Direktoren der Anstalt Vortrag über diese Dinge, eine Art Vorprüfung, denn die Herren gehören gleichfalls zum Prüfungsausschuss.</tei:p><tei:p>Die stattliche “Anerkennung” wird nur an <tei:hi rend="italic">ältere</tei:hi> Herren verliehen, die man nicht gut mit einer Prüfung belästigen kann.  (Wäre es nicht trotzdem manchmal angebracht?)</tei:p><tei:p>Ich werde Ihnen fortlaufend über den Stand der Dinge berichten, und bin mit nochmaligem Dank und den besten Weihnachtswünchen Ihnen und Ihrer Frau Gemahlin.</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated December 14, 1926</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Kaiserswerth-Bockum, Rhineland
Villa Dahlmann
December 14, 1926</tei:p><tei:p>Most honoured Master!</tei:p><tei:p>Many thanks for your efforts regarding my conservatory matter.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> In fact, I did not get official recognition; in the meantime I expect, however, to be appointed, on condition that I pass an examination. This will be administered by men already known to me, and is thus merely a formality. It was crucial that Dr Sallman was a childhood friend of my father’s, something we did not actually know. The examination will take account of the various “Methods”, and also my employment at the conservatory will include, specially, your theory—the <tei:hi rend="italic">Urlinie</tei:hi>!—and piano playing. On Saturday I will give a lecture to the directors of the institute about these things, a kind of preliminary examination, for these men likewise belong to the board of examiners.</tei:p><tei:p>Official “recognition” is conferred only on <tei:hi rend="italic">older</tei:hi> men, whom one cannot, in fairness, burden with an examination. (Would this not, however, be appropriate in some instances?)</tei:p><tei:p>I shall give you a report about the state of things immediately; again with my thanks, and best Christmas greetings to you and your wife, I am</tei:p><tei:p>Your
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>