<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [23] : 2-10-31 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin 2006.
© Translation William Drabkin 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1931-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 02/10/1931 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated February 10, 1931</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-11-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>C acks issue of Der Kunstwart;  encloses a letter from Walter Braunfels responding to his plans to establish a Rhineland base for Schenkerian teaching at the Cologne Hochschule für Musik;  wonders whether Anthony van Hoboken might be approached for financial assistance on this, and if so how the approach should be made.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  Kunstwart, Der;  Köln;  Cologne;  Hochschule;  highschool;  Braunfels, Walter;  Rhineland;  base for Schenkerian teaching;  Berlin;  Kestenberg, Leo;  Essen;  Fokwangschule;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  financial assistance;  Weisse, Hans</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Duisburg, Rhineland, Kuhstrasse  23–25/^I.^</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated February 10, 1931</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Duisburg/Rheinland. Kuhstr. 23–25/^I.^
10.II.31.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Zunächst vielen Dank für die Übersendung des neuen “Kunstwart”,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> The January 1931 issue of <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Kunstwart</tei:hi>, vol. 44, No. 4, contained a notice of Schenker’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, vol. 3, by Otto Vrieslander.</tei:note> worüber ich gleich noch einiges zu erzählen haben werde. Vorher aber das Wichtigste.  Der einliegende Brief gibt Ihnen Aufschluss über die derzeitige Situation meiner Kölner Pläne.   Ich schrieb nämlich Braunfels<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> Walter Braunfels, professor of theory at the Cologne Hochschule für Musik, who had given support to Cube’s efforts to promote Schenkerian theory in northern Germany.</tei:note> einen seemeilenlangen Brief über die mehr und mehr in den Vordergrund pädagogischen Interesserückende Notwendigkeit der Schaffung einer staatlich sanktionierten Basis für Schenkerunterricht im Rheinlande;  die Fortschritte, die im Reich zu verzeichnen sind, wie auch die Tagung in Berlin wurden gebührend erwähnt.  Die Antwort Braunfels’, die eigentlich nur +einen+ triftigen, zeitlich bedingten Hinderungsgrund aufweist, kann zweierlei Bedeutung haben: eine reale und eine politische.   Real insofern, als die Finanzen der Hochschule tatsächlich besonders schlecht sind;  politisch wäre denkbar, dass auch Braunfels den unheilvollen Einfluss der “entfesselten Pädagogen” in Berlin (trotz Kestenberg!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> Leo Kestenberg (1882-1962), who taught at both the Stern Conservatory and the Klindworth-Scharwenka Conservatory in Berlin, and was appointed to the Ministry of Science, Art, and Education in 1918, rising to a high position in the division of Art.  His name frequently comes up in the correspondence as someone favorably disposed toward the dissemination of Schenker’s ideas by German educators.</tei:note>) fürchtet, und mit ausgezeichneter Höflichkeit das diplomatische Mittel des Abwartens einem Stich ins Wespennest vorzieht.  Ich persönlich halte jedoch die erstere Bedeutung für durchaus wahrscheinlich!</tei:p><tei:p>Um indes keine “Stimmführungsmöglichkeit” unversucht zu lassen, möchte ich Sie um Ihren Rat, möglicherweise sogar <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> um Ihre Fürsprache in der Angelegenheit bitten, die ich Ihnen im Folgenden unterbreiten will:</tei:p><tei:p>Die Schaffung geregelten Schenkerunterrichts an der Kölner Hochschule würde einen ganz erheblichen Schritt nach vorwärts bedeuten!  Würde Ihre Gedankenwelt doch den ganzen, bis jetzt ziemlich unbeleckten westlichen Provinzen erschlossen werden, und der Vorantritt der Hochschule manche andere Musikpflegestätte bei einiger Überredung zu änhnlichen Einrichtungen veranlassen.  Ich will hierbei der grossen Schwierigkeiten gedenken, die mir von den einfach unbelehrbaren Machthabern an der Essener Folkwangschule,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> The Folkwang-Schule in Werden, near Essen, was founded in 1927 as an interdisciplinary school devoted to music, dance and speech. In 1963 it gained the status of a Hochschule, and today there are four Folkwangs-Hochschulen in the Ruhrgebiet: Essen-Werden, Duisburg, Bochum and Dortmund.  Cube had gone there three years before in the hope of introducing Schenker’s approach (see letter OJ 9/34, [14], October 4, 1928), but he encountered mainly “folk-dancing and chorale singing” and made little headway with the young musicians there.</tei:note> sowie selbst in meinem eigenen Wirkungskreis bereitet wurden und noch werden!</tei:p><tei:p>Die Hochschule wäre an sich bereit, die Sache sofort anzupacken.  Ich warte nicht weit davon, bereit meine Kräfte an einem Orte anzuspannen, dessen Unternehmungen in weitestem Umkreis beachtet, besprochen und nachgeahmt werden.  Was zu dem vollständigen Dreiklang noch fehlt, ist eine – und noch dazu verhältnismässig geringe [–] Geldsumme, die die Einrichtung einer oder mehrerer Klassen für Harmonie, Kontrapunkt, Urlinie etc. ermöglichen könnte!</tei:p><tei:p>Es ist naheliegend, in diesem Zusammenhange an einen Mann zu denken, der in grossherzigster Weise die Lösung kultureller Aufgaben durch Beistellung von Mitteln ermöglicht hat, die gewiss erheblicher waren, als die zu obbesagtem Zwecke benötigen sein würden.  Glauben Sie, lieber Herr Professor, dass es aussichtsreich wäre, sich in dieser Angelegenheit <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> an Herrn Anthony van Hoboken<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.  Hoboken was a pupil of Schenker’s in the 1920s, one of his wealthiest patrons, and a keen supporter of some of his enterprises. In the end, he declined to support Cube’s initiative in Cologne;  Schenker devotes a whole letter vC 35, March 28, 1931, to Hoboken’s attitude towards the establishment of a Schenker base in Cologne.  </tei:note> zu wenden, und ihn zu bitten, diesem doch gewiss +nur+ nützlichen Vorhaben seinen Beistand zu gewähren?  Es würde sich wie gesagt um nicht viel Geld, und das auch nur auf ein bis zwei Jahre handeln, denn ich bin überzeugt, dass nach dieser Zeit, möglicherweise schon früher, ein ernsthaft aufgezogener Unterricht an der Hochschule von selbst obligatorisch würde, und seinen Platz im Etat des Schuldezernats erobern und behaupten könnte.</tei:p><tei:p>Es wäre da noch die Frage, ob ich mich selbst sofort an Herrn van Hoboken wenden soll, oder ob Sie selbst auf Grund meines und Braunfels’ Brief mit Herrn van Hoboken verhandeln möchten.  Möglicherweise könnte man sogar eine Einigung mit der Hochschule insofern anstreben, dass diese wenigstens einen +Teil+ der nötigen Mittel selbst dazugibt!  Meines Erachtens nach würde schon eine +prinzipielle+ Zusage Herrn van Hobokens genügen, um die Hochschule zu Zugeständnissen zu veranlassen.  Über die +Form+ einer eventuellen Beihilfe, ob Stiftung, Widmung oder rückzahlbares Darlehen, müssten natürlich auch erst direkte Verhandlungen mit der Hochschule Klarheit schaffen.  Ich selbst warte mit Schmerzen auf den Augenblick, der mir die Möglichkeit gibt, mich in der vordersten Kampflinie zu bewähren.  Obwohl ich noch viel schreiben wollte, muss ich jetzt schliessen.  Sehr bald berichte ich Ihnen von meinen sonstigen Erlebnissen, Meinungen und Versuche.  Für heute beste Grüsse Ihnen und Ihrer Frau Gemahlin, und ergebenste Empfehlungen an Herrn van Hoboken , auch an Dr. Weisse.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated February 10, 1931</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Duisburg, Rhineland, Kuhstrasse  23–25/^I.^
February 10, 1931</tei:p><tei:p>Most honoured master,</tei:p><tei:p>First of all, many thanks for forwarding the latest issue of <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Kunstwart</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> about which I shall presently have a few things to tell you. First of all, the most important matter.  The enclosed letter gives you information about the present state of my Cologne plans.  In fact I wrote a mile-long letter to Braunfels<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> about the necessity, which continues to make its way into the foreground of pedagogical interest, of establishing a state-sanctioned basis for Schenkerian teaching in the Rhineland.  The progress that has taken place in the country, and also the symposium in Berlin, were duly mentioned.  Braunfels’ answer, which actually raises only +one+ legitimate argument against it at the present time, can be understood as having two meanings:  a real one and a political one.  Real, in so far as the finances of the Hochschule are indeed particularly bad;  and politically one can imagine that even Braunfels fears the malevolent influence of the “chained pedagogues” in Berlin (in spite of Kestenberg!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>), and, with extraordinary politeness, prefers the diplomatic tactic of waiting to stirring a hornet’s nest.  Personally, I regard the first of these interpretations as highly probable!</tei:p><tei:p>So as to leave no voice-leading stone unturned, so to speak, might I in the meantime ask for your advice, possibly even your <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> good word in the matter that I shall amplify in the following way:</tei:p><tei:p>The creation of a regulated programme of Schenkerian instruction at the Cologne Hochschule would signify a truly palpable step forwards!  Your world of ideas would be made accessible to all the western provinces, which have hitherto been untouched.  And the involvement of the Hochschule might lead to other musical institutions being persuaded to set up similar programes.  I am thinking here of the great difficulties that have been created for me, and will continue to be created, by the authorities of the Folkwang School in Essen,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> who are simply unteachable, and those in my own sphere of influence!</tei:p><tei:p>The Hochschule ought to be in and of itself ready to get to work on the matter immediately.  I am waiting, not far away, to concentrate all my strength in a place whose undertakings will be regarded, talked about and imitated in the widest imaginable area. What is still missing from the complete triad is a sum of money—and, I might add, a relatively small sum—which would make possible the establishment of one or several classes in harmony, counterpoint, Urlinie, etc!</tei:p><tei:p>In this connection, one naturally thinks of a man who has, in the most generous way, enabled cultural projects to be realized by providing financial assistance that was certainly more substantial than the purposes described above would require.  Do you believe, my dear Professor, that there may be good reasons to approach <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Mr Anthony van Hoboken<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> in this instance, and to ask him to provide assistance for this plan, which can surely be +only+ a profitable one? As I said, it would not amount to a great deal of money, and only for one or two years; for I am convinced that by this time, perhaps even sooner, a seriously mounted program of studies at the Hochschule would of itself become obligatory, and could win and assert its place in the “balance sheet” of the school administration.</tei:p><tei:p>There is the further question as to whether I should write immediately to Mr. van Hoboken myself, or whether you would like to deal with him personally, on the basis of my letter and that of Braunfels. Possibly one could even strive for an agreement with the Hochschule, to the extent that it provides at least a +part+ of the necessary funds itself!  In my view, an agreement in +principle+ from Mr van Hoboken would be enough to persuade the Hochschule to make the necessary concessions.  Regarding the +form+ of the assistance—whether it is to be a trust fund, a grant, or a repayable loan—would naturally have to await direct negotiations with the Hochschule.  I myself wait in agony for the moment that gives me the opportunity to stand in the front-most line of battle.  Although I wanted to write yet more, I must close now.  Very soon I shall report to you about my other experiences, opinions and attempts. For today, best greetings to you and your wife, and most devoted regards to Mr van Hoboken, also to Dr Weisse.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/></tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>