<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [27] : 9-8-31 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Transcription William Drabkin 2006.
© Translation William Drabkin 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1931-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 09/08/1931 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated September 8, 1931</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-07-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Line drawing of Moriz Violin. —Reports on health of V's son;  discusses his relationship with Violin, and the prospects of the Schenker Institute in Hamburg;  C will be assisting at a lecture given by Hans Weisse.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  line drawing;  Violin, Moriz;  Violin, Karl;  sister;  Hamburg;  Salzburg;  Vienna;  Vogt, Friedrich;  Shylock;  Weisse, Hans;  Schenker-Institut;  Schenker Institute;  courses;  Frankfurter Zeitung;  Duisburg;  step-mother</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Hamburg, Beneckestrasse 2</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated September 8, 1931</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">left side: drawing of head of Moriz Violin, signed:</tei:hi> v. Cube. 31.]</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">right side: address to line 3 of para. 2</tei:hi>]
Hamburg, Beneckestr. 2, 
bei Alexander Schmidt.
8. IX. 31.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter, lieber Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Diesen Brief schicke ich Ihnen schon nach Wien. Von Violins<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> Click on <ref cRef="violin_moriz">Moriz Violin</ref>.</tei:note> Schwester, die augenblicklich in Hamburg weilt, erfuhr ich, dass Sie zurzeit in Salzburg seien, und demnächst nach Wien zurückfahren wollten;  anstatt Ihnen nachzureisen, soll Sie der Brief lieber in Wien erwarten. –</tei:p><tei:p>Nebenstehend habe ich versucht, Herrn Prof. Violin<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> Click on <ref cRef="violin_moriz">Moriz Violin</ref>.</tei:note> in karrikaturistichen Form, so wie Sein Äusseres sich meinem Linien-Sinn eingeprägt hat, darzustellen. Ich glaube, man kann ihn erkennen!  Es ist erfreulich, zu vermelden, dass seines Sohnes Befinden in letzter Zeit eine deutliche Besserung zeigt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  The illness of Moriz Violin’s son Karl (Karli) is mentioned in Cube’s previous letter of August 19, 1931 (OJ 9/34, [26]), and in Schenker’s postcard of August 24?, 1931 (vC 39).</tei:note>  Die Temperatur ist schon seit Tagen normal, und er sieht viel frischer und besser aus, fühlt sich auch bedeutend wohler.  Die Ärtzte urteilen noch sehr vorsichtig, zumal er ja auch immer noch unter der Einwirkung der Bekämpfungsmassnahmen steht, doch sind sie zufrieden schon allein mit der Tatsache, dass das Leiden offenbar eine bekämpfbare Form angenommen hat.  Der beinahe extatische Lebenswille, und die geradezu bewunderungswürdige Energie des lieben Jungen werden wohl einen Hauptanteil an der Besserung haben!  Ich wünsche Herrn Prof. Violin<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> Click on <ref cRef="violin_moriz">Moriz Violin</ref>.</tei:note> von ganzem Herzen, dass <tei:hi rend="italic">diese</tei:hi> Prüfung nun endlich zu Ende gehe!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> 	Andere Sorgen gibt es genug.  Die Verhältnisse haben immerhin in den letzten drei Monaten eine so gewaltige Änderung zum Schlechten erfahren, dass die Voraussetzungen für das “Schenker–Institut”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  For a later document describing this institute, see <ref cRef="schenker_institute_h">Schenker Institute, Hamburg: Prospectus</ref>.</tei:note> davon nicht unberührt bleiben konnten.  Materielle Ausfälle, unerquickliche Auseinandersetzungen mit dem früheren Konservatoriumsdirektor Vogt,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> According to Cube’s unpublished autobiographical essay <tei:hi rend="italic">Todeskampf oder Wiederauferstehung der Musik</tei:hi> (p. 77), Friedrich Vogt was the founder and proprietor of a music school at which Violin had been enagaged as a teacher.  When Violin left to set up the Schenker Institute, he took many of his pupils with him.</tei:note> Karli’s Erkrankung, Alles das ist viel, selbst für Violins kampferprobte Nerven.  Nun hat er auch noch mich dazubekommen.   Da die Familien[,] denen er mich zugedacht hatte, auch der Zeit zum Opfer gefallen sind, bin ich <tei:hi rend="italic">sein</tei:hi> Gast, bis meine Einnahmen mir eine eigene Lebenshaltung gestatten werden.  Das alles wirkt auch ein wenig hemmend auf mich selbst;  nicht etwa, das ich fürchtete ihm zur Last zu fallen [–] dazu sind unsere Wünsche zu gemeinsam, aber, dass ich noch so arg wenig für die Sache tun und leisten kann.  Ich habe erst eine Stunde, bekomme allerdings noch zwei dazu, und im Oktober sind wohl noch etliche Schüler fällig, die vorerst bei Vogt<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> According to Cube’s unpublished autobiographical essay <tei:hi rend="italic">Todeskampf oder Wiederauferstehung der Musik</tei:hi> (p. 77), Friedrich Vogt was the founder and proprietor of a music school at which Violin had been enagaged as a teacher.  When Violin left to set up the Schenker Institute, he took many of his pupils with him.</tei:note> bleiben müssen, da dieser Shylock auf seinem Pfunde besteht!  Wie es mit den Kursen wird, hängt noch an allen möglichen Voraussetzungen.  Wichtig und entscheidend ist vor Allem der Wiederhall, den der für den 16. Sept. angesetzte Vortrag: “Hörendes Schaffen – schaffendes Hören”, den Dr. Weisse auf der Durchreise nach Amerika hier halten wird, bei Fachleuten, Publikum und Presse erwecken wird.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> On his trip from Berlin to New York in September 1931, <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref> stopped in Hamburg and gave a lecture on Schenker’s teaching.</tei:note>  Die Sache ist ganz gross angelegt, und kostet sehr viel Geld.  Die grösste Konzertdirektion arrangiert den Vortrag unter ihrem Namen, lädt ein und inseriert in allen Zeitungen (auf Violins<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> Click on <ref cRef="violin_moriz">Moriz Violin</ref>.</tei:note> Kosten.)  Das “Schenker-Institut”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  For a later document describing this institute, see <ref cRef="schenker_institute_h">Schenker Institute, Hamburg: Prospectus</ref>.</tei:note> hält sich – scheinbar – aus taktischen Erwägungen abseits.  Es wäre schön, wenn wir gleichzeitig unsere Kurse inserieren könnten, aber aber dazu fehlt das Geld.  So muss die geladene Presse, worunter einige sind, die uns wohlgesinnt und im Übrigen “im Bilde” sind, soweit dies möglich ist, unsere Bestrebungen und die Mission des “Schenker-Institutes”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  For a later document describing this institute, see <ref cRef="schenker_institute_h">Schenker Institute, Hamburg: Prospectus</ref>.</tei:note> im redaktionellen Teil besprechen, was eben unter günstigen Umständen viel besser wirken kann, als Annoncen. Hat die gegenwärtige Zeit die Eröffnung des Institutes einerseits erst ermöglicht, muss man auch die grossen <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Nachteile dieser Zeit in Kauf nehmen. Immerhin sind wir guten Muts, und zuversichtlich.  Es wird sich schon einrichten!  Gesprochen wird schon aller Orten darüber.  Eine Anfrage kam aus Frankfurt(!), angeblich auf Grund einer Zeitungsnotiz!  Ich kann mir’s nur so erklären, dass ein Herr von der Frankfurter Zeitung, der mir befreundet ist, diese Notiz lanciert hat. –</tei:p><tei:p>Ich lebe mich ganz gut hier ein. Hamburg ist eine bezaubernd schöne Stadt mit einem bezaubernd scheusslichen Klima.  Die Säuglinge sollen hier schon mit Gummischuhen zur Welt kommen.  Leider konnte ich mir noch nicht viel sehenswertes betrachten. Zeit hatte ich genug;  aber die amerikanische Erscheinungsform der Zeit hat mein Portemonnaie noch allzuwenig belastet. –</tei:p><tei:p>Ich bin fast den ganzen Tag bei Violins,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> Click on <ref cRef="violin_moriz">Moriz Violin</ref>.</tei:note> übe Klavier, lese und schreibe. Am 16. assistiere ich Weisse<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> On his trip from Berlin to New York in September 1931, <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref> stopped in Hamburg and gave a lecture on Schenker’s teaching.</tei:note> am Flügel.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6"> According to a clipping from an unidentified Hamburg newspaper, preserved in the Schenker Scrapbook (OC 2/p.84: dated by Jeanette September 17, 1931), Cube did indeed assist <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Weisse</ref> at the piano at the lecture, both in a “Bach demonstration” and in a counter-example taken from Schoenberg’s Suite for Piano, Op. 25.  The highly favourable review of the event, written by another of Schenker’s former pupils (<ref cRef="roth_herman">Herman Roth</ref>) is said to have augmented the initial enrollment at the Schenker Institute (<tei:hi rend="italic">Todeskampf</tei:hi>, p. 78).</tei:note>  Abends trinke ich ein Glas hellen Bieres, und verfüge mich hierauf in meine Gemächer, bei den Eltern eines unserer jungen Lehrer.  Ich bin nur froh, dass ich mich in Duisburg, wie es mir noch gut ging, nicht verehelicht habe, das wäre jetzt ein schönes Débacle.  Meine Verlobte ist aber ein sehr verständiger Kamerad.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7"> Cube married Henriette Reich the following year.</tei:note>  Wenn das Trauerjahr vorbei ist,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8"> “Trauerjahr”: a reference to the suicide of Cube’s father Gustav earlier in the year.</tei:note> und ich nicht genug für zweie bei bescheidenen Ansprüche haben sollte, so wird sie eben mitarbeiten.  Wie viele müssen das heute! –</tei:p><tei:p>Von meiner verflossenen Stiefmutter höre ich nichts Gutes.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9"> After the death of his first wife, Gustav von Cube married a woman much younger than himself, by whom he had another child.  The engagement initially provoked a hostile reaction among his father’s friends and associates in Duisburg. (See OJ 9/34, [1], Cube’s letter of January 21, 1925.)</tei:note> Sie scheint ganz aus dem Geleise geworfen. Weiss der Himmel wie das enden wird. Ich kann ihr nicht helfen. Ein Glück, dass mein kleiner Bruder bei seiner Grossmutter untergeschlüpft ist. –</tei:p><tei:p>So ist es nun also.  Der Kampf geht weiter, und Regen wie Sonnenschein strömen in schöner Regelosigkeit auf uns hernieder, wie’s nun mal so der Brauch bei Stadt- und Weltchronik.  Mich soll’s nicht kümmern.  “Twingen lot ick mi nich, segg de Bur, da wollte he sick no ne Floh kratzen, wo he nich darankonnte”.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10"> An attempt to render in dialect “Zwingen lasse ich mich nicht, sagt der Bursche, da [=doch] wollte er noch einen Floh kratzen, wo er nicht darankonnte.” (“I will not be forced [I cannot be bothered],” said the boy, though he wanted to scratch another flea-[bite] where he could not reach: a variant of the proverb of the fox and the sour grapes.)</tei:note> –</tei:p><tei:p>Mit den herzlichsten Grüssen Ihnen und Ihrer Frau Gemahlin bin ich Ihr immergetreuer
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Cube.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated September 8, 1931</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">left side: drawing of head of Moriz Violin, signed:</tei:hi> v. Cube. 31.]</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">right side: address to line 3 of para. 2</tei:hi>]
Hamburg, Beneckestrasse 2, 
c/o Alexander Schmidt
September 8, 1931</tei:p><tei:p>Most honoured, dear master!</tei:p><tei:p>I am sending this letter to you directly to Vienna.  I learned from Violin’s<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> sister, who is staying at the moment in Hamburg, that you were now in Salzburg and were planning to return to Vienna soon.  Instead of following you, it is better that the letter await you in Vienna.</tei:p><tei:p>In the accompanying drawing, I have sought to portray Prof. Violin<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> in caricature, so far as his external appearance has made an impression on my sense of line.  I hope that he is recognizable.  It is a delight to report that his son shows clear signs of progress recently.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  His temperature has been normal for several days, and he looks much fresher and healthier, and is also feeling significantly better.  The doctors are very cautious with their prognosis, particularly as he remains under influence of treatments;  yet they are at the very least satisfied with the fact that his suffering has assumed a treatable form.  The almost extatic will to survive, and the veritably amazing energy of the dear boy will surely play a major part in his recovery!  I dearly wish for Prof. Violin,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> with all my heart, that <tei:hi rend="italic">this</tei:hi> trial will soon be over for good!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> We have enough other things to worry about.  The economic climate has continued to change so precipitously for the worse that the prospects for the “Schenker Institute”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> cannot remain unaffected.  Material shortages, disagreements with the previous head of the conservatory, Vogt,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> Karli’s illness:<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> all this is a great deal, even for Violin’s<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> well-tested nerves.  And now he has also me to cope with.  Since the families with whom he placed me have fallen victim to the times, I am <tei:hi rend="italic">his</tei:hi> guest until my income is sufficient to sustain my own livelihood.  This also has a somewhat hampering effect on myself;  not that I am afraid of becoming a burden on him—for that, our interests are too much alike—but rather that I can still be of such dreadfully little use to him, and achieve so little.  I have just one hour;  I expect to get two more, and in October a few pupils will come to me who must first remain with Vogt:<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> for this Shylock insists on his pound of flesh!  How the courses will go depends on all sorts of conditions.  What is important and crucial, above all, is the way in which professionals, audience and press will react to the lecture scheduled for September 16, “Creativity through Listening—Creative Listening,” which Dr Weisse will give here en route to America.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> The event has been advertised very widely, and will cost a lot of money.  The largest concert agency is arranging the lecture under its name, is taking care of the invitations, and is placing an advertisement in every newspaper, at Violin’s<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> expense. (The “Schenker Institute”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> will remain in the background, for tactical reasons.  It would be nice if, at the same time, we could advertise our courses;  but for this there is not enough money.)  Thus the invited press, among which are a few who are sympathetic to us and, moreover, “in the picture” will have to speak of our efforts, and the mission of the “Schenker Institute”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> in the editorial section, so far as this is possible; under favourable circumstances, this will indeed have a better effect than advertisements.  If the present time has, on the one hand, made possibly the opening of the Institute in the first place, one must also take <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> the disadvantages of the timing into the balance. At any rate, we are of good hope and circumspect.  Things will work out!  People are already talking about it everywhere. An enquiry came from Frankfurt(!), apparently on account of a notice in the newspaper! The only explanation that I can offer for this is that a journalist working for the <tei:hi rend="italic">Frankfurter Zeitung</tei:hi>, with whom I am on friendly terms, launched this notice.</tei:p><tei:p>I am thoroughly getting used to life here. Hamburg is a bewitchingly beautiful city, with a bewitchingly awful climate;  babies ought to be born already wearing their galoshes.  Unfortunately, I have not yet done much sight-seeing.  I had enough time, but the American manifestation of time has filled my wallet all too frugally.</tei:p><tei:p>I spend almost the whole day at Violin’s place,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> practising the piano, reading and writing.  On the 16th I shall assist Weisse<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> at the piano.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/>  In the evening I drink a glass of light beer, and walk here to my rooms, in the home of the parents of one of our young teachers.  I am only glad that I did not get married in Duisburg, where things were still going well for me: that would have been a pretty debacle now.  My fiancée is, however, a very understanding comrade.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>  If, when the year of mourning is over,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> I am not earning enough to keep two people with modest needs, she, too, will find a job. How many [married women] must do that today!</tei:p><tei:p>Of my poor stepmother, I hear nothing good.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/>  She appears to have come off the rails completely. Heaven knows how that will end. I cannot help her.  It’s a blessing that my little [step-]brother has found refuge with his grandmother.</tei:p><tei:p>That is the way things are now.  The struggle goes on; and rain and sunshine stream down on us with fine unpredictability, as now seems to be the custom in this city, and in the world at large.  I should not worry: “‘I will not force myself’, said the boy, yet he wanted to scratch another flea[-bite], where he could not reach.”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> –</tei:p><tei:p>With most affectionate greetings to you and your wife, I am 
your ever-faithful
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Cube</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>