<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 70/11, [1] : 4-3-31 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin 2006.
© Translation William Drabkin, 2006
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Violin, Moriz (1931-1956?) - -University of California, Riverside (1956? - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 04/03/1931 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ Violin" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Moriz Violin, dated April 3, 1931</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-11-08</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>C alludes to his father's recent suicide, and gives his acceptance in principle to Violin's proposal.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von;  Violin, Moriz;  Cube, Gustav von;  suicide;  Duisburg;  Berlin;  Köln;  Cologne;  Essen;  Schenker, Heinrich</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Duisburg, Rhineland, Düsseldorferstrasse 124</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Moriz Violin, dated April 3, 1931</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Duisburg/Rhld. Düsseldorferstr. 124.
Tel: 22261
3. IV. 31.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Violin!</tei:p><tei:p>Ihre Nachricht<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  OJ 70/2, March 31, 1931.</tei:note> erreichte mich in einem Augenblick, da sie mir beinahe als ein Symbol erscheinen muss.  Sie werden wohl inswischen erfahren oder gelesen haben, in wie grässlicher Weise mein guter Vater aus dem Leben geschieden ist.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Only weeks (or possibly days) before, Gustav von Cube, an architect by profession, had shot himself.</tei:note>  Ich beeile mich, trotz Allem was gerade jetzt um mich und in mir vorgeht, in einer Athempause Ihren Brief zu beantworten, schon um Ihnen herzlich zu danken, und Sie zu versichern, dass mir kein besserer Trost werden konnte, als dieser Hinweis zu neuen, schönen Aufgaben mitziehen!</tei:p><tei:p>Die Stadt Duisburg hat weder mir noch meinen Eltern viel Gutes gebracht.  Meine zweite Mutter und mein kleiner Bruder<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  After the death of his first wife, Gustav von Cube married a woman much younger than himself in 1926;  they had a baby boy a short time afterwards.</tei:note> werden sie schon bald ver- <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> lassen, um in Berlin mit Hilfe der Verwandten eine neue Existenz zu beginnen, denn mein Vater hat uns alle in bitterster Armut zurückgelassen.  Mich selbst bindet dann auch nichts mehr an Duisburg, wo ich mich in letzter Zeit nur noch ganz kümmerlich fortbringen konnte, ganz abgesehen von der Unmöglichkeit, im Sinne Schenkers auch nur einigermassen erspriesslich zu wirken.  Ich habe schon länger versucht[,] in Köln und namentlich in Essen neue Verbindungen anzuknüpfen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> In the summer of 1928, Cube made contact with a new school of music in Werden, near Essen, an experience he found “tragi-comic”; see his letter to Schenker, OJ 9/34, [14], October 4, 1928.  He had more success in Cologne over the next few years, and went so far as to ask Schenker’s help in petitioning Anthony van Hoboken for financial assistance to establish a permanent place for Schenkerian study at the Hochschule für Musik;  see in particular his letter OJ 9/34, [23], February 10, 1931, and Schenker’s reply vC 35, March 28, 1931.</tei:note> und werde auch vorläufig diese Beziehungen weiterpflegen, um meine Lage in etwa zu verbessern, selbstverständlich aber so, das ich mich in jedem Augenblick wieder lösen kann.  Auf jeden Fall ergreife ich mit tausend Freuden die mir gebotene Hand, und bitte Sie, meiner vollsten Hingabe an Ihr neues Werk versichert zu sein, dem ich alle meine Kräfte und Fähigkeiten nebst meiner Jugend und meinem Optimismus widmen will! Wie lange warte ich schon auf die Gelegenheit, mit in der vordersten Linie zu kämpfen, und ich bin so froh, dass <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Sie es mit mir versuchen wollen, und dass Schenker es gutgeheissen hat. –</tei:p><tei:p>Die Bedingungen erscheinen mir +sehr+ günstig, es muss ja bald überall besser sein, als hier in Duisburg.  Besonders die freie Station, worunter ja wohl Wohnung und Verpflegung zu verstehen ist, wirkt für den Anfang sehr beruhigend, und die Möglichkeit gleich mit einer Anzahl Schüler anfangen zu können klingt für einen an hiesige Verhältnisse gewöhnten fast märchenhaft!  +Drei Jahre+ habe ich hier gebraucht, um das Vertrauen der Duisburger Holzköpfe soweit zu erwerben, dass von einem “Schülerkreis” die Rede sein konnte.   Wat der Bur nich kennt, dat friätt he nich!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Presumably a north-German saying, written as if in dialect (translation partly worked out from context). </tei:note> Damit ist alles gesagt!</tei:p><tei:p>Lassen Sie mich bitte für heute mit meiner principiellen Zusage schliessen.  Es gibt in den nächsten Tagen so vieles zu sorgen und zu ordnen, dass ich weder mit meinem Schmerz noch mit meiner Freude zur Ruhe kommen kann.  In kurzer Zeit werde ich Ihnen <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> dann zu allen nötigen näheren Erörterungen zu Verfügung stehen.–</tei:p><tei:p>Einstweilen verbleibe ich mit erbensten Grüssen
Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Felix-E. von Cube.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Moriz Violin, dated April 3, 1931</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Duisburg, Rhineland, Düsseldorferstrasse 124.
Telephone: 22261
April 3, 1931</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Mr Violin,</tei:p><tei:p>Your news<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> reached me in a moment, as it had to appear to me almost as a symbol.  You will have heard, or read, in the meantime how my good father was parted from his life in such a dreadful way.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  I hasten, in spite of everything that is taking place around me and within me, to use a breathing space to answer your letter, to give you my heartfelt thanks now, and to assure you that there could be no better consolation than the prospect of joining in new, beautiful assignments!</tei:p><tei:p>The city of Duisburg brought neither me nor my parents much good.  My stepmother and my little [half-]brother<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> will soon <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> be leaving, in order to begin a new existence in Berlin with the help of relations, for my father has left us all behind in the bitterest poverty.  For myself as well, then, nothing ties me any longer to Duisburg, where recently I was able to make progress only with the greatest of difficulties, quite apart from the impossibility of making a fruitful contribution, however modestly, in a Schenkerian vein.  I have tried already for some time to create new connections in Cologne and in fact in Essen,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> and for the time being will pursue these relationships further, in order to improve my situation to some extent—but of course only in such a way that I can again untie myself at a moment’s notice.  In any event I shall grasp the hand offered to me with a thousand joys, and ask of you to be assured of my complete dedication to your new work, to which I want to dedicate all my powers and abilities together with my youth and my optimism!  How long have I already waited for the opportunity to fight in the front line, and I am so glad that <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> that you are willing to try it with me, and that Schenker has given it his blessing.</tei:p><tei:p>The conditions appear to me +very+ favorable;  indeed, it will undoubtedly soon be better anywhere than in Duisburg.  Especially the free accommodation, which I take to include an apartment with service, will have a very reassuring effect at the beginning;  and the possibility of being able to start already with a number of pupils sounds almost too good to be true to someone accustomed to today’s situation!  I needed +three years+ here in order to gain the confidence of Duisburg’s blockheads sufficiently to get any sort of “circle of pupils.”  “What you don’t know can bring you no joy!”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  That says it all!</tei:p><tei:p>Allow me to close for today with my acceptance in principle.  In the next few days I have so much to take care of, and to order, that I shall have time to give neither my pain nor my joy a moment’s peace.  In a short time, I shall then <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> be at your service for all necessary discussions of details.</tei:p><tei:p>In the meantime, I remain with my most devoted greetings
Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Felix-E. von Cube</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>