<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="conne_paul_de">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Paul de Conne (1874-1959)</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="conne_paul_de">Conne, Paul de</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>19/07/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">ConneDe ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">conne_paul_de</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Paul de Conne (1874-1959)</head>
      <div>
        <!-- BODY: -->
        <p><hi rend="bold">Paul de Conne (1874-1959),</hi> Russian concert pianist and piano teacher, pupil of Anton Rubinstein. From 1901 to 1915 he taught in the piano Ausbildungsklasse at the Akademie f&#xFC;r Musik und darstellende Kunst (=Vienna Conservatory--but according to Schenker (OJ 8/3, [67]), he tried to resume his teaching there in 1919, at the resignation of the President, Karl von Wiener). Among his students were Zbigniew Drzewiecki und Marie Emilie Freiin Bach (who dedicated her composition <hi rend="italic">Negroid</hi> to him in 1926). De Conne died in Vienna.</p>
        <p>First reference to De Conne in Schenker's diary is on December 17, 1906:</p>
        <p><!-- bq. --> Evening: concert [by] Paul de Conne:  good technique, now and again some beautiful playing.  But unfortunately, so to speak, physiologically immature;  boyish presentation of the pathos of Rubinstein (Sonata in A minor, Op. 100), too childishly wooden, under-declaimed, too simple, too hasty, without respite.  (diary OJ 1/5, p. 30).</p>
        <p>On January 13, 1911, at a concert in the B&#xF6;sendorfersaal, De Conne and Moriz Violin were the soloists in the first performance of C. P. E. Bach's Concerto in F major for two keyboards in Schenker's arrangement.  Schenker was present at this concert, and recorded his reactions in his diary (OJ 1/10, p. 125).</p>
        <p>From Schenker's diary for 1919, the two men were evidently personally acquainted by then.</p>
        <p>The only correspondence between De Conne and Schenker known to survive is one undated calling card (OJ 9/30a).</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="italic">Sources:</hi>
        </p>
        <p>Hellmut Federhofer, <hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker nach Tageb&#xFC;chern und Briefen...</hi> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), p. 19.</p>
        <p>Lynne Heller, "Vom Nebenfach zur Meisterschule: Klavierunterricht am Konservatorium f&#xFC;r Musik in Wien," in: <hi rend="italic">Studia Musicologica Academiae Scientiarum Hungaricae</hi> 42/1-2 (Franz Liszt and Advanced Musical Education in Europe: International Conference 2001), pp. 47-64.</p>
        <p>For correspondence between De Conne and Josef Marx, &lt;a href="http://www.musikerbriefe.at/briefe.asp?Nr=587"&gt;click here&lt;/a&gt;.</p>
        <p><hi rend="italic">Author:</hi>  Marko Deisinger</p>
        <!-- EXTENDED BODY: -->
        <!-- EXCERPT: -->
        <!-- KEYWORDS: -->
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
