<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="dahms_walter">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Dahms, Walter (born Berlin, June 9, 1887;  died 1973)</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="dahms_walter">Dahms, Walter</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>16/12/2005</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Dahms ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">dahms_walter</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Dahms, Walter (born Berlin, June 9, 1887;  died 1973)</head>
      <div>
        <!-- BODY: -->
        <p><hi rend="bold">Dahms, Walter (born Berlin, June 9, 1887;  died 1973).</hi>  German music critic and writer on music.</p>
        <p>Dahms was music critic of the <hi rend="italic">Kleines Journal</hi> (1912) and the <hi rend="italic">Neue Preussische Kreuz-Zeitung</hi>, and wrote for, among other publications, the <hi rend="italic">Ostdeutsche Rundschau</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">Allgemeine Musik-Zeitung</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">M&#xFC;nchner neueste Nachrichtungen</hi>, and the <hi rend="italic">Musikus-Almanach</hi>, at least between 1913 and 1928.</p>
        <p>The books that Dahms published during Schenker's lifetime, all of which were in Schenker's private library at his death, are:</p>
        <p><hi rend="italic">Schubert</hi> (Berlin &amp; Leipzig: Schuster &amp; Loeffler, 1912)
<hi rend="italic">Schumann</hi> (Berlin &amp; Leipzig: Schuster &amp; Loeffler, 1916)
<hi rend="italic">Mendelssohn</hi> (Berlin &amp; Leipzig: Schuster &amp; Loeffler, 1919)
<hi rend="italic">Die Offenbarung der Musik: Eine Apotheose Friedrich Nietzsches</hi> (Munich: Musarion, 1922)
<hi rend="italic">Musik des S&#xFC;dens</hi> (Stuttgart &amp; Berlin: Deutsche Verlags-Anstalt, 1923)
<hi rend="italic">Johann Sebastian Bach</hi> (Munich: Musarion, 1924)
<hi rend="italic">Chopin</hi> (Munich: Otto Halbreiter, 1924)</p>
        <p>Dahms moved to Lisbon in 1935, and continued to publish books there.</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="bold">Dahms and Schenker</hi>
        </p>
        <p>Dahms became one of Schenker's strongest supporters and advocates.  He first came to Schenker's attention in May 1913.  His review of Schenker's <hi rend="italic">Chromatic Fantasy &amp; Fugue</hi> edition (July 15, 1913) pleased the latter, several other reviews at that time drew attention to Schenker's ideas, and his review of <hi rend="italic">Die letzten f&#xFC;nf Sonaten ... op. 109</hi> &lt;a href="../../review/dahms<hi rend="italic">beethoven</hi>redi.html"&gt;"Beethoven redivivus"&lt;/a&gt;, December 31, 1913, and the cordial response from Schenker that it evoked, encouraged him in April 1914 to express the desire (reported in WSLB 202) to move from Berlin to Vienna in order to become a pupil of Schenker.  He did study briefly with Schenker's pupil <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref> (who was based in Munich) c.1919, but decided to discontinue this and sought Schenker's advice on further study.  Schenker regularly arranged for him to receive complimentary copies of his publications, from <hi rend="italic">Die letzten f&#xFC;nf Sonaten ... op. 109</hi> to <hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</hi>, vol. III (1930).  In 1918, he was involved with Vrieslander, Halm and <ref cRef="roth_herman">Herman Roth</ref> in an attempt to launch a Festschrift for Schenker's fiftieth birthday, through Universal Edition.</p>
        <p>Dahms was conservative in outlook, and applauded Schenker's uncompromising pronouncements on contemporary music and shared his German nationalist and anti-democratic political views (though he disagreed with him hotly over Germany's militarism).</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="bold">Correspondence</hi>
        </p>
        <p>105 items of correspondence survive from Dahms to Schenker in OJ 10/1 (1913 to 1931), and one letter from UE to Dahms with annotations by Schenker (OC 52/617, undated). No correspondence from Schenker to Dahms is known to survive. There are also many references to Dahms in Schenker's diary.  In addition, clippings of eight reviews by Dahms of Schenker's publications are preserved in Schenker's scrapbook (OC 2/pp. 38, 41-42, 49, 54, 61, 67, 72, 75).   Of these, two more general articles about Schenker are:</p>
        <p>"Heinrich Schenker:  zu seinem 50. Geburtstag am 19. Juni 1918,"  <hi rend="italic">Konservative Monatsschrift</hi>, June 1918, 647-49
"Heinrich Schenkers Pers&#xF6;nlichkeit," <hi rend="italic">Allgemeine Musik-Zeitung</hi>, Aug 3, 1923, 511-12</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="italic">Source:</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">Baker's1971</hi>
        </p>
        <!-- EXTENDED BODY: -->
        <!-- EXCERPT: -->
        <!-- KEYWORDS: -->
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
