<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="messchaert_johannes">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Johannes Messchaert (born Hoorn, Aug 22, 1857;  died Zurich, Sept 9, 1922)</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="messchaert_johannes">Messchaert, Johannes</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>14/11/2006</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Messchaert ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">messchaert_johannes</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Johannes Messchaert (born Hoorn, Aug 22, 1857;  died Zurich, Sept 9, 1922)</head>
      <div>
        <!-- BODY: -->
        <p><hi rend="bold">Johannes Messchaert (born Hoorn, Aug 22, 1857;  died Zurich, Sept 9, 1922),</hi> Dutch baritone.</p>
        <p>After studies in Cologne and Munich, Messchaert returned to Holland in 1881, where he taught at the Amsterdam Conservatory. A frequent collaborator with pianist <ref cRef="rontgen_julius">Julius R&#xF6;ntgen</ref>, Messchaert toured prolifically, establishing a reputation as one of Europe's most sought-after singers of Lieder and oratorio. He moved to Germany (Wiesbaden) in 1900, and thereafter held various conservatory appointments, ultimately attaining the post of professor at the Berlin Hochschule f&#xFC;r Musik.   Messchaert's interpretations were later set down in two volumes: F. Martiensen, ed., <hi rend="italic">Auswahl von Messchaerts Schubert-Repertoire, mit seinen Vortragsanweisungen</hi> (Mainz:  Schott, 1928).</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="bold">Messchaert and Schenker</hi>
        </p>
        <p>Schenker first reported, with great enthusiasm, on Messchaert's singing in the Berlin weekly <hi rend="italic">Die Zeit</hi> (1896; repr. in Federhofer 1990).  A mutually admiring relationship developed, and Messchaert engaged Schenker as his accompanist during a tour of the Habsburg Empire in January and February 1899 (schedule preserved as OJ 35/5, 48-49, 52-55).</p>
        <p>Schenker held Messchaert in the highest regard, as evinced in several of his published works, e.g.:</p>
        <p><hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt I</hi> (1910), p. 129, Eng. trans. pp. 91:</p>
        <p><!-- bq. --> "Why is he [the typical pianist of the day] not eager, like a violinist or singer who follows a good tradition (Joachim or Messchaert, for example) to rise to the full measure of Bach's art of expression?"</p>
        <p><hi rend="italic">Tonwille 6</hi> (1923), p. 41, Eng. trans. II, pp. 35-6:</p>
        <p><!-- bq. --> "Permit me, in this connection, to remember, alongside that great poet and great composer [Goethe and Schubert], the great singer Johannes Messchaert, recently deceased, who in his interpretation of "Meeresstille" achieved the corresponding effect by elongating the notes in so utterly peaceful a way that they sounded like messages emerging from the silence rather than notes issuing from the human breast.  Only at the word "ungeheurn" [immense] did any tone creep into the voice, swelling almost imperceptibly, as far as "ungeheure Weite" [immense distance], but pulling back immediataely.  The effect was to render the silence at the end all the more fearful and believable."</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="bold">Correspondence</hi>
        </p>
        <p>Correspondence from Messchaert to Schenker survives as OJ 12/54 (1896-1901: 11 items).  Other materials survive as OJ 35/5 (concert programs and tour itineraries), OJ 59/11, 70/27 (Messchaert/Violin correspondence), and 72/10 (portrait).</p>
        <p><hi rend="italic">Sources:</hi>
Federhofer, Hellmut, <hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker nach Tageb&#xFC;chern ...</hi> (Hildesheim: Olms, 1985), 18-19, 178-80
Federhofer, Hellmut, <hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker als Essayist und Kritiker ...</hi> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1990), 318-19
<hi rend="italic">NGDM2</hi>;  <hi rend="italic">MGG</hi></p>
        <p><hi rend="italic">Contributor:</hi> Ian Bent &amp; Kevin Karnes</p>
        <!-- EXTENDED BODY: -->
        <!-- EXCERPT: -->
        <!-- KEYWORDS: -->
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
