<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="paumgartner_berhard">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Bernhard Paumgartner (Hofrat Professor Dr.) (born Vienna, Nov 14, 1887;  died Salzburg, July 26,1971)</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="paumgartner_berhard">Paumgartner, Bernhard</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>19/07/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Paumgartner ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">paumgartner_berhard</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Bernhard Paumgartner (Hofrat Professor Dr.) (born Vienna, Nov 14, 1887;  died Salzburg, July 26,1971)</head>
      <div>
        <!-- BODY: -->
        <p><hi rend="bold">Bernhard Paumgartner (Hofrat Professor Dr.) (born Vienna, Nov 14, 1887;  died Salzburg, July 26,1971),</hi> Austrian conductor, composer, musicologist, and teacher.</p>
        <p>Paumgartner was assistant to Gustav Mahler at the 7th Salzburg Music Festival in 1906,  co-repetiteur under Bruno Walter at the Vienna Court Opera in 1911/12, conductor of the Vienna Tonk&#xFC;nstler-Orchester 1914-17, replaced Eusebius Mandyczewski as teacher (score-reading and song repertory) at the Akademie f&#xFC;r Musik und darstellende Kunst (=Vienna Conservatory) in 1915/16,  was head of the music-historical headquarters at the War Ministry 1916-18, Director of the Mozarteum in Salzburg 1917-38, from 1945 to 1959 its Director, and its President from 1953 on.</p>
        <p>Among others, Paumgartner was involved with Max Reinhardt in the founding of the Salzburg Festival, and from 1960 to 1971 President of its directorate.  From 1949, he was also a professor at the Vienna Akademie, teaching music theory and history.  His best-known pupil was Herbert von Karajan.</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="bold">Paumgartner and Schenker</hi>
        </p>
        <p>In 1914, Viktor Zuckerkandl introduced Paumgartner to Schenker, and in September 1914 Paumgartner reviewed Schenker's monograph <hi rend="italic">Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Heimgarten</hi>, a clipping of which is preserved in Schenker's scrapbook (OC 2/p. 45). Schenker reported the review enthusiastically to Emil Hertzka (UE), saying that he would like "to pay him this courtesy" (WSLB 227, September 24, 1914).</p>
        <p>Schenker reports in his diary that in spring 1919 he planned to spend the summer vacation in the Salzburg region.  After he experienced difficulty in obtaining authorization to travel, he wrote to Pamgartner as Director of the Mozarteum at the beginning of June, asking him to intervene on his behalf with the Salzburg regional government.</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="bold">Correspondence</hi>
        </p>
        <p>Only one letter, from Paumgartner to Schenker, is known to survive as OJ 13/15 (1915).  A file of "typed excerpts from Schenker's Tageb&#xFC;cher and from letters and reviews by Paumgartner," survives as OJ 59/13.</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="italic">Sources:</hi>
        </p>
        <p>Eva Maria Hois, "Paumgartner, Familie," in: <hi rend="italic">Oesterreichisches Musiklexikon</hi>, vol. 4, ed. Rudolf Flotzinger (Vienna 2005), pp. 1733-1734.</p>
        <p>Suppan, Wolfgang, "Viktor Zuckerkandl (1896-1965)," in Eybl, M. &amp; Fink-Mennel, E., eds.,  <hi rend="italic">Schenker-Traditionen:  Eine Wiener Scule der Musiktheorie und ihre internationale Verbreitung</hi> (Vienna: B&#xF6;hlau, 2006), p. 137</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="italic">Wikipedia</hi>
        </p>
        <p><hi rend="italic">Author:</hi> Marko Deisinger</p>
        <!-- EXTENDED BODY: -->
        <!-- EXCERPT: -->
        <!-- KEYWORDS: -->
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
