<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="riemann_hugo">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Hugo Riemann (born Sondershausen, July 18, 1849;  died Leipzig, July 10, 1919)</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="riemann_hugo">Riemann, Hugo</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>24/11/2007</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">RiemannH ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">riemann_hugo</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Hugo Riemann (born Sondershausen, July 18, 1849;  died Leipzig, July 10, 1919)</head>
      <div>
        <!-- BODY: -->
        <p><hi rend="bold">Hugo Riemann (born Sondershausen, July 18, 1849;  died Leipzig, July 10, 1919),</hi> leading German musicologist and music theorist, author of numerous books and articles on music history, practice, theory, aesthetics, philosophy, and cognition, and original author/editor of <hi rend="italic">Musik-Lexikon</hi> (Leipzig: 1882).</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="bold">Riemann and Schenker</hi>
        </p>
        <p>As early as 1905, Schenker was protective of the manuscript of his <hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</hi>, lest it fall into the hands of Riemann or his followers (CA 5-6).  Throughout his career, he regarded Riemann as his chief rival, embodying the antithesis of his own music theory, as well as being an odious force ("the most dangerous musical bacillus in Germany": CA 71, 1907; also OJ 15/16, [27], 1916).  Surprisingly, in 1913, he reported that Riemann "counts himself among my keenest admirers" (WSLB 146).  He accused Riemann of being "business-minded" in writing his numerous catechisms, and his "small" and "large" composition manuals (vC 14: 1928), and of spoon-feeding his readers rather than making them think for themselves (e.g. vC 21: 1928), such that it became one of Schenker's aims to free the youth of his day from Riemann's influence (vC 28: 1930).</p>
        <p>In his <hi rend="italic">Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie</hi>, he portrayed Riemann's interpretations as "false" (p. XXIV; Eng. trans., p. 17), and devoted much space in the "Secondary Literature" sections to pointing out  Riemann's impercipience and errors ("Beethoven's higher interests, aiming for the most perfect art of synthesis, he is unfortunately able neither to perceive in an artistically true manner nor to interpret correctly in theoretical terms.": p. 24/p. 48;  "Great heavens, what intellectual sloth!  Such a way to write about music!": p. 74/p. 88;  "It can be inferred [...] that Riemann has difficulty understanding composed-out larger complexes, and posits instead only smaller units [...]": p. 112/p. 119).</p>
        <p>Schenker returned to his harsh critiques of Riemann's theories and analyses in <hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</hi> (1921-24) and <hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</hi> (1925-30).  
  
<hi rend="bold">Correspondence</hi></p>
        <p>One item of correspondence between Schenker and Riemann is known to exist: OJ 13/23: the pro forma invitation to contribute autobiographical information to the <hi rend="italic">Musik-Lexikon</hi> (which Schenker refers to ironically as "being ushered into the Riemann Walhalla": WSLB 154).    The entry on Schenker appeared in the 10th edition of the <hi rend="italic">Lexikon</hi>, ed. Alfred Einstein (Berlin: Max Hesse, 1922), pp. 1135-36.</p>
        <!-- EXTENDED BODY: -->
        <!-- EXCERPT: -->
        <!-- KEYWORDS: -->
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
