<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="roth_herman">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Herman Roth (born Hornberg, Baden, Feb 15, 1882;  died Berlin, Feb 1, 1938)</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="roth_herman">Roth, Herman</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>16/12/2005</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Roth ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">roth_herman</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Herman Roth (born Hornberg, Baden, Feb 15, 1882;  died Berlin, Feb 1, 1938)</head>
      <div>
        <!-- BODY: -->
        <p><hi rend="bold">Herman Roth (born Hornberg, Baden, Feb 15, 1882;  died Berlin, Feb 1, 1938),</hi>  German writer on music.</p>
        <p>A pupil of Hugo Riemann (1905), he worked as a music critic in Leipzig (1907-10) and Munich (1910-20), taught at the Conservatory in Baden Baden (1921-24) and at the Hochschule f&#xFC;r Musik in Stuttgart (1925-35), then as a music critic in Hamburg (1932-35), settling finally in Berlin.</p>
        <p>His books include <hi rend="italic">Heinrich Kaspar Schmid</hi> (Munich, 1921), and <hi rend="italic">Elemente der Stimmf&#xFC;hrung</hi> (Stuttgart, 1926).  He also edited works by J. S. Bach, Handel and C. P. E. Bach and others, including the Schemelli songbook (copy as OJ 25/1, which has annotations in Heinrich's and Jeanette's hands), which Schenker used extensively for teaching purposes. He also translated opera libretti.</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="bold">Roth and Schenker</hi>
        </p>
        <p>Schenker and Roth (already a friend of Schenker's pupil Otto Vrieslander) evidently became acquainted in 1912.  Roth's work as a critic included remarks on <hi rend="italic">Die letzten f&#xFC;nf Sonaten von Beethoven ... op. 109</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</hi> in 1914 (both = OC 2/p. 38) and a later personal view of Schenker in 1931 (=OC 2/p. 84).</p>
        <p>In 1914, Schenker recommended Universal Edition to publish editions that Roth had produced of Handel cantatas, stating that Peters had already published a previous edition (see Bibliography, below), and that it was a highly professional piece of work (WSLB 202, April 1, 1914).  Schenker also praised Roth's edition of the J. S. Bach Passacaglia in C minor, seeing in it his own ideas.    There are many entries concerning Roth in Schenker's diary. 1932 saw a break in their good relations, apparently for personal reasons.</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="bold">Correspondence</hi>
        </p>
        <p>Correspondence from Roth to Schenker survives as OJ 13/30 (1912-33: 87 items) and OC 24/8 (1921: 1 item), and from Schenker to Roth as OJ 5/33 (1926: 1 item).</p>
        <p><hi rend="italic">Bibliography:</hi>
Bach, J. S.: <hi rend="italic">Magnificat</hi>, ed. K. Straube, piano/organ accomp. by H. Roth (Ed. No. 3392, not before 1906)
Bach, J. S.: <hi rend="italic">Lieder, 25 geistliche, aus dem Schemellischen Gesangbuch f&#xFC;r 1 Singstimme und basso continuo</hi>, piano/organ accomp. by H. Roth (Ed. No. 3392, pubd 1922) [copy as OJ 25/1, with annotations by Heinrich and Jeanette Schenker]
Bach, C. P. E.: <hi rend="italic">30 Geistliche Lieder f&#xFC;r eine Singstimme und Klavier</hi>, ed. H. Roth with detailed instructions as to ornamentation (Ed. No. 3748, pubd 1922)
Handel: <hi rend="italic">Ges&#xE4;nge f&#xFC;r eine Frauenstimme. Aus Opern und Oratorien ausgew&#xE4;hlt</hi>, ed. with keyboard accomp. by H. Roth (Ed. No. 3493, pubd 1916).</p>
        <p><hi rend="italic">Sources:</hi><hi rend="italic">Baker's1971</hi>
Federhofer, Hellmut, <hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker nach Tageb&#xFC;chern und Briefen ...</hi> (Hildesheim:  Georg Olms, 1985), pp. 196-98 <hi rend="italic">et passim</hi>
"Herman Max Johannes Roth," in Eybl, M. &amp; Fink-Mennel, E., <hi rend="italic">Schenker-Traditionen: Eine Wiener Schule der Musiktheorie und ihre internationale Verbreitung</hi> (Vienna: B&#xF6;hlau, 2006), p. 245
communications from John Rothgeb and C. F. Peters, Frankfurt/Main</p>
        <!-- EXTENDED BODY: -->
        <!-- EXCERPT: -->
        <!-- KEYWORDS: -->
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
