<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="schweitzer_albert">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Schweitzer, Albert (born Kayserberg, Alsace, Jan 14, 1875;  died Lambar&#xE9;n&#xE9;, Gabon, Sept 4, 1965)</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="schweitzer_albert">Schweitzer, Albert</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/01/2006</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">schweitzer_albert</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Schweitzer, Albert (born Kayserberg, Alsace, Jan 14, 1875;  died Lambar&#xE9;n&#xE9;, Gabon, Sept 4, 1965)</head>
      <div>
        <!-- BODY: -->
        <p><hi rend="bold">Schweitzer, Albert (born Kayserberg, Alsace, Jan 14, 1875;  died Lambar&#xE9;n&#xE9;, Gabon, Sept 4, 1965),</hi>  Alsatian organist, writer on music, especially that of J. S. Bach, also theologian, philosopher, and medical doctor.</p>
        <p>Schweitzer studied organ playing under Widor in Paris, and music theory under Heinrich Bellermann in Strasbourg.  He was a crucial figure in the new movement toward historical organ building in the early 20th century, with an important article presented to the IMG in 1909.  He spent much of his life from 1913 on at the missionary hospital that he founded in Lambar&#xE9;n&#xE9;, in Africa.  He was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize in 1952.</p>
        <p>His best-known book on music is <hi rend="italic">J. S. Bach, le musicien-po&#xE8;te</hi> (Leipzig, 1905); German translation, greatly enlarged, as <hi rend="italic">J. S. Bach</hi> (1908).  This work is much concerned with interpretation and issues of authentic performance.  Schweitzer also, with others, produced a complete edition of Bach's organ works (1912-14, 1954-67).</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="bold">Schweitzer and Schenker</hi>
        </p>
        <p>Schenker knew Schweitzer's book in the German translation from its publication in 1908 (a copy of the 1922 edition was in his private library at his death), and quoted from it not infrequently: in <hi rend="italic">Tonwille 5</hi>, p. 27 (Eng. trans., I, 165-66), in relation to Bach's practice of copying the works of other, lesser composers; in his own essay on the opening chorus of the <hi rend="italic">Matthew Passion</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Tonwille 10</hi> = IV/4, p. 10 (II, 133-34),  on the interpretation of that chorus; in his own essay on the Prelude to Bach's solo violin Partita No. 3 in E major in <hi rend="italic">Meisterwerk</hi>, vol. I, pp. 88-92 (Eng. trans., I, 48-50); and he mentions him in passing in <hi rend="italic">Meisterwerk</hi>, vol. III, p. 14 (III, 3).  In these passages he expresses agreement with much of what Schweitzer says, taking issue with him at the same time.  Schenker kept six newspaper clippings of articles about Schweitzer from between 1923 and 1928 (OC 12/20; C/3, 116, 500, 504, 505).</p>
        <p>There is no known correspondence between Schenker and Schweitzer.</p>
        <p><hi rend="italic">Sources:</hi><hi rend="italic">NGMD2</hi>;  <hi rend="italic">Baker's 1971</hi><hi rend="italic">Musik und Theater, enthaltend die Bibliothek des Herrn Dr. Heinrich Schenker, Wien</hi> (Vienna: Antiquariat Heinrich Hinterberger[, 1935])
Federhofer, Hellmut, <hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker nach Tageb&#xFC;chern und Briefen ...</hi> (Hildesheim:  Georg Olms, 1985)</p>
        <!-- EXTENDED BODY: -->
        <!-- EXCERPT: -->
        <!-- KEYWORDS: -->
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
