<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="vrieslander_otto">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Otto Vrieslander (born M&#xFC;nster, July 18, 1880;  died Tegna, Dec 16, 1950)</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="vrieslander_otto">Vrieslander, Otto</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>16/07/2006</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Vrieslander ~ H+JSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">Vrieslander ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">Vrieslander ~ JSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">vrieslander_otto</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Otto Vrieslander (born M&#xFC;nster, July 18, 1880;  died Tegna, Dec 16, 1950)</head>
      <div>
        <!-- BODY: -->
        <p><hi rend="bold">Otto Vrieslander (born M&#xFC;nster, July 18, 1880;  died Tegna, Dec 16, 1950),</hi>  German composer, teacher, pupil of Schenker's.</p>
        <p>Vrieslander studied piano and composition in D&#xFC;sseldorf 1891-1900, at the Cologne Conservatory 1909-02, and composition in Munich 1904-1911.  After brief study with Schenker in Vienna, he taught composition, piano, and theory in Ebersberg, nr. Munich 1912-24, then in Naples and Vienna.  From 1929, he lived in Switzerland.</p>
        <p>Vrieslander was a composer notably of Lieder (including a setting of poems from Giraud's <hi rend="italic">Pierrot lunaire</hi> in O. E. Hartleben's translation, dating from 1904  - eight years before Schoenberg's melodrama cycle:  both settings were commissioned by Albertine Zehme, but whereas Zehme performed Schoenberg's setting, she was dissatisfied by that of Vrieslander and never performed it).</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="bold">Vrieslander and Schenker</hi>
        </p>
        <p>Vrieslander was a pupil of Schenker only during the 1911/12 season: records survive only for January 5 to March 5, 1912, and Vrieslander took lessons twice a week (Mondays and Thursdays) between January 15 and February 29.  He remained in contact with Schenker for the rest of the latter's life as a member of the inner circle of long-time friends, former students, and supporters (others include, e.g., <ref cRef="brunauer_dr">Robert Br&#xFC;nauer</ref>, <ref cRef="dahms_walter">Walter Dahms</ref> (a pupil of Vrieslander), <ref cRef="roth_herman">Herman Roth</ref>, <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>, Viktor Zuckerkandl, and <ref cRef="oppel_reinhard">Reinhard Oppel</ref>).</p>
        <p>Vrieslander advocated several projects (all ultimately  abortive): in 1915, a second edition of Schenker's <hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</hi> (which he used in his own teaching, and on which he wrote three unpublished commentaries between 1910 and 1925 and compiled a list of typographical errors), and adding exercises and assignments (which Schenker resisted); in 1918, a Festschrift for Schenker's 50th birthday; in 1919-20, the founding of a Schenker Institute in Munich;  in 1921, with Hoboken, the publishing of inexpensive Urtext editions and a periodical;  in 1926-27, a Festschrift for Schenker's 60th birthday; in 1927-28 a monthly &lt;a href="http:../../profile/title/tonkunst_die.html"&gt;Schenker periodical&lt;/a&gt; planned by Weisse, Salzer, and Jonas; around 1927, a Schenker monograph-cum-anthology;  and in 1932 a student edition (<hi rend="italic">Schulausgabe</hi>) of <hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</hi> (of which he was then making a "concentrated" version) for use by Josef Marx at the Vienna Hochschule f&#xFC;r Musik (=Conservatory).  After Schenker's death, Jeanette Schenker wished Vrieslander to produce a new edition of the <hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</hi>, gave him Schenker's personal annotated copy for this purpose from which he copied out Schenker's numerous additions, and in 1938 signed a contract with him at UE for which he was paid an advance--but the annexation of Austria intervened.</p>
        <p>It was Vrieslander who recommended <ref cRef="roth_herman">Herman Roth</ref>, and <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref> to Schenker.  He also advised Hoboken in the building up of the latter's collection of first editions.  In 1920, Vrieslander served as intermediary with the publisher J. G. Cotta of Stuttgart by delivering the manuscript of <hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt2</hi> to them; and more importantly in 1924 as an intermediary with the Drei Masken Verlag of Munich in dealings that resulted in the publication of Schenker's <hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</hi> (1925, 1926, 1930), the proofs of which he assisted in correcting.</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="bold">Impact of Schenker on Vrieslander</hi>
        </p>
        <p>After encountering Schenker's <hi rend="italic">Hamonielehre</hi>, Vriselander underwent a sharp break with his previous compositional style (even destroying copies wherever possible), his new beginning occurring in 1916.  Schenker thought highly of Vrieslander's work from that time on, describing his Lieder as "the best since the death of [Hugo] Wolf," and "among the best that the Lieder repertory has to offer from the post-Brahms era."  Schenker states in 1917 that he commissioned a work from Vrieslander and subsequently paid him money from the stipend fund created by <ref cRef="deutsch_sofie">Sofie Deutsch</ref>.</p>
        <p>Under Schenker's influence, Vrieslander made a "critical edition with elucidatory appendix" (dedicated to Schenker) of <hi rend="italic">C. P. E. Bach's Kurze und leichte Clavierst&#xFC;cke: Neue kritische Ausgabe mit erl&#xE4;uterndem Nachwort</hi> [Short and easy keyboard pieces: new critical edition with elucidatory afterword] (Vienna: UE, 1914), which the cover title significantly characterized as: <hi rend="italic">Erl&#xE4;uterungsausgabe</hi> (elucidatory edition: the term that Schenker himself used for his publications on the late Beethoven piano sonatas); he also published the edition <hi rend="italic">C. P. E. Bach: Lieder und Ges&#xE4;nge</hi> (Munich: Drei Masken Verlag, 1922) and wrote the monograph <hi rend="italic">Carl Philipp Emanuel Bach</hi> (Munich: Piper, 1923), and  contributed the article "Carl Philipp Emanuel Bach als Theoretiker" to <hi rend="italic">Von neuer Musik</hi> (Cologne 1925) and <hi rend="italic">Ganymed</hi> iv (1922).  Vrieslander also wrote articles about Schenker and his work: <hi rend="italic">Musikbl&#xE4;tter des Anbruch</hi>, February/March 1923;  <hi rend="italic">Die Musik</hi>,xix/1 (October 1926), 33-38;  <hi rend="italic">Deutsche Tonk&#xFC;nstler-Zeitung</hi>, March 5, 1928;  and <hi rend="italic">Der Kunstwart</hi> xliii  (1930),  181-189.</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="bold">Correspondence</hi>
        </p>
        <p>The majority of the correspondence between Schenker and Vrieslander forms part of the Vrieslander Nachla&#xDF;, which is privately owned by Heribert Esser (the letters from Vrieslander to Schenker having been mostly returned by Jeanette Schenker).  There are 18 letters from Vrieslander to Schenker in the Oster Collection (OC 18/5-22 <hi rend="italic">passim</hi>; OC 54/11-140 <hi rend="italic">passim</hi> (Cotta-Verlag); OC 69/2-3: 1925-26, 1932-33); 2 letters from Schenker to Vrieslander and 12 from Otto and Helene Vrieslander to Schenker in the Jonas Collection (OJ 5/42 and OJ 15/4: 1912, 1917-20, 1935-39), and 5 from the Vrieslanders and Herman Roth to Schenker (OJ 13/30: undated); 1 from Vrieslander to Violin (OJ 70/43: 1912), 1 from Vrieslander to Robert Br&#xFC;nauer (OJ 71/37: undated), 1 from Hans Weisse to Vrieslander (OJ 71/40: [1918], concerning the 50th birthday Festschrift), and a portrait of Vrieslander and Roth (OJ 72/13).  The Vrieslander correspondence is an invaluable repository of biographical information about Schenker himself, his pupils, and contemporaries.</p>
        <p>Vrieslander's list of errors in, and his copy of a portion of Schenker's additions to, <hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</hi> survive as OJ 18/6; his three commentaries (72pp, 468pp, 472pp), are in the possession of Mr. Esser.</p>
        <p><hi rend="italic">Sources:</hi><hi rend="italic">Baker's1971</hi>;  <hi rend="italic">NGDM2</hi>
"Otto Vrieslander," in Eybl, M. &amp; Fink-Mennel, E., eds, <hi rend="italic">Schenker-Traditionen: Eine Wiener Schule der Musiktheorie und ihre internationale Verbreitung</hi> (Vienna: B&#xF6;hlau, 2006), pp. 246-47, also pp. 188-89, 196-99 <hi rend="italic">et passim</hi>
Oster Collection Finding List
Jonas Memorial Collection Checklist
R. Wason, "From <hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</hi> to <hi rend="italic">Harmony</hi>: Schenker's Theory of Harmony and its Americanization," Cadwallader, A., ed., <hi rend="italic">Essays from the  Fourth International Schenker Symposium</hi> (Hildesheim:  Georg Olms, 2008), pp. 213-58
personal communications from Heribert Esser
personal communication from Prof. Wason</p>
        <!-- EXTENDED BODY: -->
        <!-- EXCERPT: -->
        <!-- KEYWORDS: -->
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
