<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/16, [15] : 9-26-34 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Wilhelm Furtwängler, published with kind permission.
© Transcription Christoph Hust, 2008.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2008.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Christoph Hust, 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Heirs of Wilhelm Furtwängler, permission to publish granted on February 2, 2005.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1934-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935- c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Wilhelm Furtwängler;  Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Commentary, Footnotes: Christoph Hust; Translatio, Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 09/26/1934 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: &quot;Furtw&#195;&#164;ngler ~ H+JSchenker&quot;,&quot;Furtw&#195;&#164;ngler ~ HSchenker&quot; --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Furtwängler to Schenker, dated September 26, 1934</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-05-30</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Letter from Furtwängler;  apologies for not visiting Galtür in the summer;  he spent the vacation on his own work;  will be in Vienna and hopes to see Schenker;  he intends to write publicly about Schenker's work;  comments on current political situation.  —Finds Jonas's book excellent. 

</dc:description><dc:subject>Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Galtür;  Dolomites;  Poland;  Berlin;  Vienna;  visit;  politics;  Jonas, Oswald;  Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks;  Schenker, Jeanette</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Berlin W, Keitstraße 1</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Furtwängler to Schenker, dated September 26, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>26. IX. 1934  [—] Berlin W.  Keithstr. 1</tei:p><tei:p>Lieber verehrter Herr Schenker,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> Partially transcribed in Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern und Briefen</tei:hi> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), p. 131. Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary for &lt;a href="../../../../../diary/oj<tei:hi rend="italic">47</tei:hi>p<tei:hi rend="italic">3948</tei:hi>92934.html"&gt;OJ 4/7, p. 3948&lt;/a&gt;, September 29, 1934.   See also Schenker’s diary entry of October 4, 1934.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Statt meines Besuches in Galtür, den wir das letztemal als wir uns in Wien sahen, verabredeten, ist nun dieser Brief heute das erste, [<tei:hi rend="italic">words deleted</tei:hi>] das Sie von mir hören. Die Ereignisse waren ja derart, daß sie mir schon rein äußerlich eine Reise nach Österreich unmöglich machten. Ich war den Sommer über z. T. in den Dolomiten, z. T. in Polen – einer Einladung folgend – wo ich meine eigenen Arbeiten zu fördern hoffte,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> Furtwängler worked on a number of instrumental compositions at this time.</tei:note> und mich so sehr abschloß, daß ich nicht einmal mehr Zeitungen las.  Dieser schöne Zustand ist jetzt wieder dem Berliner Groß-Betrieb gewichen (der mir freilich noch niemals so problematisch – für mich persönlich – wie diesmal erschienen ist.)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Furtwängler is perhaps referring to the directorship of the Berlin Staatsoper, to which he was appointed in 1933, and from which he later resigned in protest over the banning of Hindemith's opera <tei:hi rend="italic">Mathis der Maler</tei:hi>, publishing two articles. "Hindemith soll geächtet werden," and "Der 'Fall Hindemith' geht weiter," <tei:hi rend="italic">Basler Nachrichten</tei:hi>, November 26 and 30, 1934. Both articles survive among Schenker's papers, OC 30/67–68.  </tei:note>  Nach Wien komme ich im Dezember zum ersten mal, (im Ganzen dreimal.), wo ich Sie zu <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> sehen hoffe. Ich werde Ihnen dann noch mündlich allerlei erzählen und erklären können, was ich jetzt nicht kann. U. a., warum ich bisher meine Absicht, mich öffentlich über Sie und Ihr Werk zu äußern, noch nicht verwirklicht habe. Die allgemeinen, d. h. politischen Lebensbedingungen sind für jemanden der so sehr der Kunst dient, wie ich, immer noch sehr unsicher und unklar. Das Buch von Jonas<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="schenker_jeanette">Jeanette Schenker</ref>.  </tei:note> finde ich indessen <tei:hi rend="italic">ausgezeichnet</tei:hi>, soweit ich nach flüchtiger Lektüre beurteilen kann, auch in seiner knappen, relativ leichtfaßlichen Form!</tei:p><tei:p>Wie geht <tei:hi rend="italic">es Ihnen sonst</tei:hi>? Bitte Ihre verehrte Frau[5] vielmals zu grüßen. Darf ich einmal hoffen, von Ihnen zu hören?</tei:p><tei:p>Herzlichst und verehrungsvollst
Ihr
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Wilhelm Furtwängler</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Furtwängler to Schenker, dated September 26, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>November 26, 1934  [—]  Berlin W.  Keithstraße 1</tei:p><tei:p>Dear, honored Mr.  Schenker,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>In lieu of my visit to Galtür, which we arranged last time we saw each other in Vienna, this letter today is the first that you have heard from me.  Events proved such as to make travel to Austria impossible for me in purely official terms.  I spent the summer partly in the Dolomites, partly in Poland—by invitation—, where I hoped to pursue my own work,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> and cut myself off so completely that I never so much as read the newspapers.  This happy state of affairs has now evaporated amidst the big Berlin goings-on (which have certainly never before been so problematic—for me personally—as it has seemed this time).<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  I am coming to Vienna in December for the first time (three times, in all), and I hope to <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> see you then.  I will then be able to recount and explain all sorts of things to you in person, which I cannot do now.   Among other things, why I have not thus far carry through my intention to express myself publicly about you and your work.  The general (i.e. political) conditions of life for someone who serves art as much as I do persist in being very uncertain and unclear.  Meanwhile, I find the book by Jonas<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> <tei:hi rend="italic">excellent</tei:hi>, so far as I can judge at a hasty reading, not least in its concise, relatively easy-to-grasp form!</tei:p><tei:p>How are things <tei:hi rend="italic">with you otherwise</tei:hi>?  Please give your esteemed wife[5] my cordial greetings.  May I hope to hear from you sometime?</tei:p><tei:p>Most cordially and in highest veneration,
Yours, 
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Wilhelm Furtwängler</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>