<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker"
   xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
   xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
   <!--OJ-01-10_1911-05May, 1911 -  ( Diary Series A box: 01 folder: 10 date: Jan 1, 1911–Dec 31, 1911 pages: 125-131, 131v, 131a, 132, 132a, 133, 133a, 134-135, 135a, 135b, 136-146, 146a, 147-152, 152a, 153, 153a, 153b, 154-161, 161a, 162-179, 162par-166par, 170-172, 173a-173b, 174-193, 194a, 194b, 195-197 )
                 
             -->
   <sdo:collectionDesc>
      <sdo:source>
         <!--Select an sdoID from the controlled list -->
         <sdo:diary sdoID="OJ-01-10_1911-05"/>
      </sdo:source>

      <tei:handNotes>
         <tei:handNote xml:id="HS-ink" scope="major">Heinrich Schenker's hand, in ink</tei:handNote>
         <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="major">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
      </tei:handNotes>
      <!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below -->
      <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
         <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
         <tei:resp>Transcription, 2019</tei:resp>
         <tei:resp>Translation, 2019</tei:resp>
         <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
         <tei:resp>Footnotes, 2019</tei:resp>
      </tei:respStmt>
      <tei:respStmt xml:id="TL">
         <tei:persName>Tamara Lopez</tei:persName>
         <tei:resp>XML Encoding Model</tei:resp>
      </tei:respStmt>
      <!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document -->
      <tei:revisionDesc>
         <tei:change when="2012-10-03" who="#IB">Template Generated</tei:change>
      </tei:revisionDesc>
   </sdo:collectionDesc>

   <sdo:record ID="r0001">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry, lessonbook entry or piece of correspondence. 
                         The   contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker May [c.10], 1911</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1911-05-10T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>The Date of Electronic Creation Goes Here:
            2019-01-24</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, </tei:hi><tei:pb n="128"/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in Jeanette Schenker's hand, with edits by
               Heinrich, final version only given here:</tei:note><tei:lb/>
            <tei:date when="1911-05-10">? <tei:supplied reason="clarity">c.10</tei:supplied>
               <tei:handShift new="#JS"/>Mai 1911 <tei:title><tei:hi rend="underline"
                     >Oedipus</tei:hi></tei:title>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000703"
                  >Reinhardt</tei:rs>sche Aufführung.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial"
                  place="foot"> Performances of Sophocles' <tei:title level="m">Oedipus
                     Rex</tei:title> by the Berlin German Theater under the direction of Max
                  Reinhardt, with "monumental decorations" by Alfred Roller, and in a translation by
                  Hugo von Hofmannsthal, took place in the Busch Circus building (a large circular
                  edifice with oriental entranceway, topped by a dome) in the Leopoldstadt, at 8
                  p.m. on May 5‒12 with Alexander Moissi as Oedipus, Else Heims as Jocasta, Eduard
                  von Winterstein as Creon, and Reinhardt himself as Tiresias. The drama was
                  performed without intermission. (The Busch Circus building, erected in 1892,
                  burned down in 1945.) The performances were announced in the May 4 and 5 issues of
                  the <tei:rs type="journal" key="entity-002559"><tei:title level="j">Neue freie
                        Presse</tei:title></tei:rs>, and a description and review appeared in the
                  May 6 issue, p. 12, an article by Reinhardt entitled <tei:title level="a">Meine
                     Inszenierung des „König Oedipus“</tei:title> in the May 7 issue, p. 14, and
                  further reference in the issue for May 10. — Despite the heading of Schenker's
                  essay, it is unclear whether this is a response to Reinhardt's production, a
                  reaction to his article, or simply Schenker's own thoughts about the
                  play.</tei:note></tei:date>
         </tei:opener>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0001-se01">Die Sage vielleicht als letzte Absage an die
            Blutschande aufzufassen, aehnlich, wie die Sage von Isaaks Opferung als die letzte
            Absage an Menschen-Opferung anzusehen ist. Ob daneben die Anerkennung der Moira erst nur
            als zweiter Gedanke zum Ausdruck kommt, bleibe darnach dahingestellt. Jedenfalls hat die
            Blutschande in der Oedipus-Sage, gleichviel was auch sonst noch mehr ihr zugrunde liegen
            mag, die gräßlichste Verkörperung gefunden, zu jeglicher Abschreckung wohl hinreichend.
            Die dramatische Technik (ähnlich wie bei <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000401"
               >Ibsen</tei:rs>) setzt hier am Ende ein, um den Anfang erst allmä<tei:supplied
               reason="omission">h</tei:supplied>lich zu suchen u. zu finden. Das Rückgewinnen der
            ersten, unseligen Ursache gestaltet sich technisch außerordentlich wirksam. Sehr
            bezeichnend u. von hoher dichterischer Erkenntnis: der Mann im König will die Schuld
            erforschen u. selbst auch noch dann, davon nicht lassen als ihm immer mehr u. mehr klar
            wird, daß er selbst der Schuldige; Nicht so aber Jokaste, die als Weib alles Forschen am
            liebsten sofort unterbinden möchte („Komm ins Haus“). (Hamlets Mutter im Vergleich)
               <tei:pb n="129"/> Von dieser sachlichen Technik indessen abgesehen, scheint mir
               <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006996">Sophokles</tei:rs>’ Drama am Mangel eines
            jeglichen weiteren Luxus der Poesie, der aber unentbehrlich ist, zu leiden. Noch ist
            darin nur erst das Notwendigste gesagt, was freilich zu jener Zeit nichts destoweniger
            schon zugleich die denkbar größte aestetische Freude bereiten mußte, zumal das Drama
            damals noch jung gewesen, darin außerdem eine durchaus bekannte Sage zur Reproduktion
            gelangte, endlich auch die Suggestion des Festspiels u.s.w. eine glückliche fördernde
            Rolle spielte. Ausgenommen so einige wenige Sentenzen, in deren Prägung sich der
            dichterische Sinn entlud, sind es außerdem doch nur mehr die Chöre, die, von ihrer
            dramatischen Funktion abgesehen, der Dichtkunst als solcher den schuldigen Tribut
            zollen. In den Chören allein waltet die Poesie um ihrer selbst willen. Doch, freilich,
            was wir heute als poetisches Bild ansehen, also die gesammte Götterwelt <tei:rs
               type="place" key="entity-002668">Griechenland</tei:rs>s, gerade dieses war dazumal
            weniger Bild denn Realität, u. wenn daher die Götterwelt, erst von uns selbst heute als
            Bild genommen, im dramatischen Gefüge doch nur wenig Bildhaftes sagt, ‒ man vergleiche
            dagegen die Bilderwelt eines <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000823"
               >Shakespeare</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000294">Goethe</tei:rs>,
               <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000784">Schiller</tei:rs>! ‒ so ist ohne weiters zu
            verstehen, wenn ich sage, daß auch trotz den Chören der Ertrag an wirklicher Poesie ein
            allzu bescheidener ist. Dadurch erklärt sich denn auch, weshalb das Drama, von der
            materiellen Wirkung des grau- <tei:pb n="130"/> samen Stoffes selbst abgesehen, keine
            große Wirkung mehr auszuüben vermag. So betrachtet stellt auch das <tei:rs type="person"
               key="entity-006996">Sophokleis</tei:rs>che Drama, trotz unleugbar meisterhafter
            Führung erst nur eine primitive Kunst (man denke z.B. an <tei:rs type="person"
               key="entity-002644">Palestrina</tei:rs>) dar. Würde man dieses allgemein erkennen, so
            könnte man unschwer aus dem Widerspruch heraustreten, der darin besteht, daß man
            einerseits in <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006996">Sophokles</tei:rs> Drama eine
            letzte Unnachahmlichkeit in allem u. jedem zu sehen geneigt ist, andererseits aber
            dennoch auch die Wirkungslosigkeit zugeben muß. Bleibt doch wahre Vollendung für alle
            Zeiten wirkungsvoll! (Der Einwand des Oedipus gegen Theiresias?). (vergl.
                  <tei:bibl><tei:author>Jean Paul</tei:author>, „<tei:title>Vorschule der
                  Aesthetik</tei:title>“ §21</tei:bibl>.)</tei:ab>

      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, </tei:hi><tei:pb n="128"/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">in Jeanette Schenker's hand, with edits by
               Heinrich, final version only given here:</tei:note><tei:lb/>
            <tei:date when="1911-05-10"><tei:handShift new="#JS"/>May ? <tei:supplied
                  reason="clarity">c.10</tei:supplied>, 1911 <tei:title level="m"><tei:hi
                     rend="underline">Oedipus</tei:hi></tei:title>, in <tei:rs type="person"
                  key="entity-000703">Reinhardt</tei:rs>'s Performance.<tei:ptr
                  corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:date>
         </tei:opener>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0001-se01">The myth is perhaps to be understood as the ultimate
            renunciation of incest, rather as the myth of Isaac's sacrifice is to be seen as the
            ultimate renunciation of human sacrifice. Whether at the same time the recognition of
            fate is expressed only as a secondary idea must remain an open question. At any rate, in
            the Oedipus myth, whatever else may also underlie it, incest has found its most hideous
            embodiment, amply sufficient to provide any deterrent. The dramatic technique (rather as
            is the case with <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000401">Ibsen</tei:rs>) is introduced
            here at the end in order to seek and to find the beginning only gradually. The
            uncovering of the primary ill-fated cause turns out to be technically extraordinarily
            effective. It is highly significant and showing great poetic understanding that the man
            within the king desires to get to the bottom of the guilt and not let go of it until it
            becomes ever clearer to him that he is himself the guilty party. Not so however Jocasta,
            who as a wife would prefer immediately to put a stop to all inquiry ("Come into the
            house") (cf. Hamlet's mother). <tei:pb n="129"/> Apart from this objective technique,
            however, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006996">Sophocles</tei:rs>' drama seems to me
            to suffer from a lack of any further poetic luxuriance, something which, however, is
            indispensable. But that is still only just to say what is the most essential, which
            admittedly in its own day nevertheless already must at the same time have afforded the
            greatest imaginable aesthetic joy, since drama at that time was still in its infancy
            and, in so doing, also succeeded in representing a thoroughly well-known myth; finally,
            the suggestion of a festival performance etc also played a happily productive role. With
            the exception of a very few sentences in the coining of which the poetic sense burst
            forth, it is otherwise really only the choruses that ‒ apart from their dramatic
            function ‒ pay due tribute to the art of poetry in its own right. Only in the choruses
            does poetry have free reign. But admittedly what we today regard as poetic metaphor ‒
            thus the entire world of the <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002668">Greek</tei:rs>
            gods ‒ precisely this was in those days less metaphor than reality; and if, accordingly,
            the world of the gods, which we nowadays perceive as metaphor, says only little that, in
            the dramatic context, is metaphorical (compare, against that, the metaphorical world of
            a <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000823">Shakespeare</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person"
               key="entity-000294">Goethe</tei:rs> or <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000784"
               >Schiller</tei:rs>!) then it is clearly self-evident if I say that even despite the
            choruses, the benefit in real poetic terms is something all too modest. This clarifies
            why it is that the drama, leaving aside the element {<tei:pb n="130"/> of cruelty
            itself, is no longer able to exert any great effect upon us. Seen from this point of
            view, even <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-006996">Sophocles</tei:rs>'s drama, despite
            its incontestably masterly thrust, presents ultimately only a primitive art form (think,
            for example, of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-002644">Palestrina</tei:rs>). Were
            this to be generally recognized, it would be possible easily to escape from the
            contradiction whereby on the one hand one is inclined to see in <tei:rs type="person"
               key="entity-006996">Sophocles</tei:rs>'s drama an ultimate inimitability in all its
            aspects, whereas on the other hand nevertheless one has to concede its inability to
            achieve its desired effect. True perfection however is effective for all times!
            (Oedipus's objection to Tiresias?) (cf. <tei:bibl><tei:author>Jean Paul</tei:author>,
                  <tei:title level="m">Introduction to Aesthetics</tei:title>,
            §21</tei:bibl>.)</tei:ab>

      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>


   <sdo:record ID="r0002">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry, lessonbook entry or piece of correspondence. 
                         The   contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker May 18, 1911</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1911-05-18T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>The Date of Electronic Creation Goes Here:
            2019-01-24</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, </tei:hi><tei:pb n="126"/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:fw type="header" rend="center"><tei:handShift new="#HS-ink"/><tei:date when="1911"
                  >1911</tei:date></tei:fw><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:date when="1911-05-02">18. 5.</tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0002-se01">Die <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001731"
                     ><tei:title><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Monographie</tei:hi> über die “<tei:hi
                     rend="lateinschr">IX. Symph.</tei:hi>“</tei:title></tei:rs> nach
            mehrmonatlicher Arbeit an „<tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408"><tei:hi
                  rend="lateinschr">U.E.</tei:hi></tei:rs>“ endlich abgeliefert.<tei:note
               xml:id="r0002-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">p. 131<tei:hi rend="italic"
                  >v</tei:hi> contains a series of pencil jottings-down of points for material on p.
               126. Relevant to this entry is: "18 Mai. IX. Symph abgel." ("May 18: Ninth Symphony
               handed over.").</tei:note> Erster u. größerer sachlich begründeter Vorstoß gegen
               <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000924"><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Rich.
                  Wagner</tei:hi></tei:rs> endlich in Erfüllung gegangen! Was man nun zu den Gründen
            sagen wird, die ich dort vorbrachte?<tei:note xml:id="r0002-fn02" type="editorial"
               place="foot">The main attacks on Wagner in <tei:title level="m">Beethovens Neunte
                  Sinfonie</tei:title> occur on pp. xxv‒xxvii, 45‒52, 109‒12; 153‒62, 181‒84;
               315‒19, 370‒75 (Eng. transl., pp. 18‒19, 67‒71, 116‒19; 152‒59, 174‒76; 279‒83,
               327‒30).</tei:note></tei:ab>

      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, </tei:hi><tei:pb n="126"/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:fw type="header" rend="center"><tei:handShift new="#HS-ink"/><tei:date when="1911"
                  >1911</tei:date></tei:fw><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:date when="1911-05-02">May 18</tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab corresp="r0002-se01">The <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001731"
                  ><tei:title>monograph on the Ninth Symphony</tei:title></tei:rs> finally delivered
            to <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002408">Universal Edition</tei:rs> after
            several months of work.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0002-fn01" type="footnote"/> First and
            weightier, more objectively based assault on <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000924"
               >Richard Wagner</tei:rs> finally brought to completion! What will people now say to
            the grounds that I have put forward there?<tei:ptr corresp="#r0002-fn02" type="footnote"
            /></tei:ab>

      </tei:div>
   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0003">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry, lessonbook entry or piece of correspondence. 
                         The   contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker May 30, 1911</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1911-05-30T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>The Date of Electronic Creation Goes Here:
            2019-01-24</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1911-05-30">30. 5.</tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0003-se01">Definitive Absage an <tei:rs type="person"
               key="entity-000137">Frau <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
               >Colbert</tei:hi></tei:rs>.<tei:note xml:id="r0003-fn01" type="editorial"
               place="foot">p. 131<tei:hi rend="italic">v</tei:hi> contains a series of pencil
               jottings-down of points for material on p. 126. Relevant to this entry is: "30 Mai
               Absage an Fr Colb." (May 30: Rejection <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
                  >sent</tei:supplied> to Mrs. Colbert."). The final remarks here may be in reaction
               to Colbert's undated letter <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-30_1">OJ 9/30,
                  [1]</tei:ref>.</tei:note> Alle meine Humanität reichte nicht hin, ihr das
            schmutzige Betteln um lumpige paar Gulden auszutreiben : ich dachte ihr ein <tei:hi
               rend="lateinschr">Program</tei:hi> zu, sorgte für Vermehrung ihrer Kenntnissen schon
            des herannahenden Alters halber, — sie aber starrte unablässig in das Geld, u. lieber,
            als Alles, was ich ihr klug u. human zugedacht, lieber, als alles Interesse für die
            Kunst, war ihr, eine Stunde zu umgehen, nur um sie nicht bezahlen zu müssen! Anders aber
            freilich lauten (nach Frauenart) ihre Briefe an mich : diese glühen von Liebe zur Musik,
            von Dankbarkeit für meine Führung! <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Volenti non fit
               injuria</tei:hi>! ..[<tei:note xml:id="r0003-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"
                  ><tei:hi rend="italic">Volenti non fit injuria</tei:hi>: Latin legal doctrine
               meaning that anyone who voluntarily takes a risk cannot make a claim for
               damages.</tei:note></tei:ab>

      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1911-05-30">May 30</tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab corresp="r0003-se01">Definitive rejection given to <tei:rs type="person"
               key="entity-000137">Mrs. Colbert</tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0003-fn01"
               type="footnote"/> All my humanity was not sufficient to cure her of her squalid
            begging for a measly few florins: I intended to prepare a program for her that would
            bring about an increase in her awareness of advancing age. ‒ But her mind was forever
            fixed on money, and rather than all that I ingeniously and humanely planned for her,
            rather than any interest in music, she preferred to dodge a lesson merely so as not to
            have to pay for it! Her letters to me on the other hand (typically of a woman) clearly
            say something else: they glow with her love for music, with gratitude for my guidance!
               <tei:hi rend="italic">Volenti non fit injuria</tei:hi>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0003-fn02"
               type="footnote"/></tei:ab>

      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>


   <sdo:record ID="r0004">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry, lessonbook entry or piece of correspondence. 
                         The   contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker May 30, 1911</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1911-05-30T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>The Date of Electronic Creation Goes Here:
            2019-01-24</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1911-05-30">30. 5.</tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0004-se01">Beginn des Nachfeilens am <tei:rs type="work"
               key="entity-001727"><tei:title>II<tei:hi rend="supralinear">2</tei:hi>
               Bd</tei:title></tei:rs>!<tei:note xml:id="r0004-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"
               >p. 131<tei:hi rend="italic">v</tei:hi> contains a series of pencil jottings-down of
               points for material on p. 126. Relevant to this entry is: "30 Mai Anfang des II
               Halbb." (May 30: Beginning of the second half-volume.").</tei:note></tei:ab>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0004-se02">— Nur die Genies bauen auf u. selbst auch noch
            dort, wo sie nur zu zerstören scheinen! Viele Menschenleben zerstörte ein <tei:rs
               type="person" key="entity-000075">Bisma<tei:supplied reason="spelling"
                  >c</tei:supplied>rk</tei:rs>, um das deutsche Reich zu gründen! Den anderen
            Menschen aber <tei:pb n="127"/> ist es allein vorbehalten, einander zu zerstören, ohne
            einander aufzubauen. So zerstört der Politiker den Staat, der Pfarrer die Religion, der
            Mann die Frau, die Frau den Mann, die Eltern ihre Kinder, die Kinder ihre Eltern, ein
            Freund den Freund, der Chef den Untergebenen u.s.w., u. doch ahnen sie selbst davon gar
            nichts u. schreien vielmehr über alle Dächer: Ein <tei:rs type="person"
               key="entity-000075">Bismarck</tei:rs>, ein <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000621"
                  ><tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Napoleon</tei:hi></tei:rs>, was haben diese Männer
            nicht Alles in der Welt zerstört! Nur die Zerstörung seitens der Großen nehmen sie wahr,
            obendrein doch auch nur, weil sie großen Formates ist u. daher in ihre trägen Augen von
            selbst springt!‒, Die Zerstörung seitens der Kleinen aber im Kleinen u. Alltäglichen ja,
            diese sehen sie ganz u. gar nicht. Nur vor Tugend u. wieder Tugend ‒ so kommt es ihnen
            nämlich selbst vor ‒ triefen die kleinen Wüteriche, während sie die aufbauende Kraft der
            großen Zerstörer nicht begreifen, ja, nicht einmal auch begreifen wollen!</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0004-se03">„<tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Timeo Danaos et
               dona ferentes</tei:hi>,“<tei:note xml:id="r0004-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"
               >"Beware Greeks bearing gifts" <tei:title level="m">Aeneid</tei:title>, II,
               49.</tei:note> doch was dir ein Durchschnittsmensch heute mit der rechten u. wie
            wenig obendrein ‒ giebt ‒, nimmt er dir morgen selbst wieder mit der linken Hand, wenn
            er eben nicht noch mehr nimmt, als er gegeben!</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0004-se04">Heil daher den großen Zerstörern u. ihnen
            allein, denn nur sie bauen die Menschheit auf.</tei:ab>

      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1911-05-30">May 30</tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab corresp="r0004-se01">I begin putting final touches to the <tei:rs type="work"
               key="entity-001727"><tei:title>second half-volume of volume
               II</tei:title></tei:rs>!<tei:ptr corresp="#r0004-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:ab>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0004-se02">— Only geniuses build, and even then only where they appear
            merely to destroy! A <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000075">Bismarck</tei:rs>
            destroyed the lives of many people in order to found the German empire! All that other
            people, however, <tei:pb n="127"/> can do is destroy each other without building each
            other up. Thus the politician destroys the state, the priest religion, husbands their
            wives, wives their husbands, parents their children, children their parents, friends
            their friends, bosses their underlings, and so forth. And yet they themselves are
            totally oblivious to any of this and instead cry out aloud: "A <tei:rs type="person"
               key="entity-000075">Bismarck</tei:rs>, a <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000621"
               >Napoleon</tei:rs>, what in all the world have these men <tei:hi rend="italic"
               >not</tei:hi> destroyed!" They discern only the destruction that great men do, what's
            more it is really only because it is on a large scale that it springs of its own accord
            before their dull eyes! Whereas the destruction in small and everyday matters that
            insignificant men perpetrate ‒ these things do not in the slightest register in their
            minds. The little hotheads exude virtue, and only virtue ‒ that's how they see it
            themselves ‒, whereas they do not grasp the constructive power of the great destroyers,
            indeed they have no desire whatsoever to grasp it! </tei:ab>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0004-se03"><tei:hi rend="italic">Timeo Danaos et dona
               ferentes</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0004-fn02" type="footnote"/> but what an
            average person gives you today with the right hand and how much less in addition ‒, he
            takes away from you the very next day again with the left, if indeed he doesn't take
            even more than he gave!"</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0004-se04">Hail, therefore, to the great destroyers and to them alone,
            for it is only they who build up mankind.</tei:ab>

      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

</sdo:recordCollection>
