<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker"
   xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
   xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
   <!--OJ-01-18_1915-07July, 1915 -  (Diary Series A box: 01 folder: 18 date: Apr 10–Aug 18, 1915, pages: 901-1000)-->
   <sdo:collectionDesc>
      <sdo:source>
         <!--Select an sdoID from the controlled list -->
         <sdo:diary sdoID="OJ-01-18_1915-07"/>
      </sdo:source>
      <!-- Most documents will be in the hand of Jeanette Schenker (with annotations in Heinrich's hand); add additional notes as needed to indicate
                     the presence of other hands-->
      <tei:handNotes>
         <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="minor">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
         <tei:handNote xml:id="JS" scope="major">Jeanette Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
         <tei:handNote xml:id="unknown">Unknown hand</tei:handNote>
      </tei:handNotes>
      <!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below -->
      <tei:respStmt xml:id="MD">
         <tei:persName>Marko Deisinger</tei:persName>
         <tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp>
         <tei:resp>Footnotes</tei:resp>
      </tei:respStmt>
      <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
         <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
         <tei:resp>English Translation</tei:resp>
         <tei:resp>footnotes</tei:resp>
      </tei:respStmt>
      <tei:respStmt xml:id="IJV">
         <tei:persName>Iby-Jolande Varga</tei:persName>
         <tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp>
      </tei:respStmt>
      <tei:respStmt xml:id="TL">
         <tei:persName>Tamara Lopez</tei:persName>
         <tei:resp>XML Encoding Model</tei:resp>
      </tei:respStmt>
      <!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document -->
      <tei:revisionDesc>
         <tei:change when="2012-01-19" who="#TL">Template Generated</tei:change>
      </tei:revisionDesc>
   </sdo:collectionDesc>
   
   <sdo:record ID="r0001">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 1, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-01T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-01">1. Juli 1915 </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0001-se01">Früh morgens, um als die ersten am Platze zu sein, fahren wir zur Polizei-Direktion wegen der Legitimationen. Beim Eingang aber bedeuten uns zwei Wachleute, daß wir zuvor noch eine Legitimation des Polizei-Kommissariats des III. Bezirks zu holen haben, die dann erst die Grundlage für die eigentliche, von der Polizei-Direktion auszufertigende Legitimation bilde. So haben wir auch bei dieser Gelegenheit wieder einmal das fatale Hochdeutsch unserer Behörden kennen gelernt, die in ihren Verordnungen kein Sterbenswörtchen von all’ den zu machenden Wegen verlauten ließen. Freilich bleibt uns nichts übrig, als den von <tei:pb n="970"/> Augenblick zu Augenblick wechselnden Spezialanweisungen der niederen Organe zu folgen. – Nachdem wir einen leider vergeblichen Versuch, im Militärbüro eine Auskunft zu holen, eingeschaltet hatten, fuhren wir zurück in den III. Bezirk ins Polizei-Kommissariat. Dort wurden wir zur Tür 5 gewiesen. Leider waren wir nicht mehr die ersten u. mußten uns auf ein qualvolles Warten gefasst machen. Immer mehr schwoll die Menge im kleinen engen Warteraum an; Beamte u. Diener gingen her u. hin – vielleicht war gerade dieses ihre einzige Beschäftigung – verweigerten aber den Parteien jedwede Auskunft. Desto ungehöriger u. übermütiger wirkte es, als plötzlich ein <tei:sic>ein</tei:sic> Beamter einen dem äußern Anschein nach wohlsituierten Herrn mit zwei Damen an allen Parteien vorüber ins betreffende Zimmer N.o 5 zum Schaden aller wartenden hineinbegleitete. Unerklärlich war uns vollends, weshalb die Erledigung der einzelnen Parteien gar so lange Zeit in Anspruch nahm. Und schon konnten wir den Schluss ziehen, daß, wenn es so fortginge, wohl kaum alle Parteien ihre Abfertigung erhalten könnten. Indessen regte sich lange noch keine Hilfe u. der von den Parteien erwartete zweite Beamte erschien noch lange nicht am Horizont. Da plötzlich – wir warteten schon ¾ Stunden – rief ein untersetzter Mann in den Warteraum hinein, es möchten alle, die nach <tei:rs key="entity-002483" type="place">Steiermark<!--[DPl Steiermark]--></tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-002344" type="place">Kärnten<!--[DPl Carinthia]--></tei:rs> u. s. w. reisen wollen, ihm folgen. Nun teilten sich die Parteien u. auch wir folgten jenem Beamten, der offenbar zur Aushilfe bestimmt war. Hier ging es aber drüber u. drunter; die Ordnung, die im früheren Warteraum stillschweigend beobachtet worden war, schien plötzlich gelockert u. um den Tisch herum gruppierten sich die Parteien ganz nach Belieben, so daß, wer am lautesten schrie, zuerst seine Legitimation erhielt. Als <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs> den Versuch machte, den Beamten auf die eingerissene Unordnung aufmerksam zu machen, erwiderte dieser gereizt, das gehe ihn nichts an, er helfe nur freiwillig u. werde sich von den Parteien nichts bieten lassen. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0001-se02"><tei:pb n="971"/> Endlich aber kamen doch auch wir dran u. nun konnten wir aus eigener Wahrnehmung begreifen, weshalb die Erledigung so lange Zeit beanspruchte. Eine ganz umständliche Aufnahme verschiedener Merkmale nebst Vorweisung von allerhand Legitimationen machte schon rein mechanisch den A<tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">c</tei:del><tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#HS">k</tei:add></tei:subst>t langwierig. Aber siehe, mitten in der Ausstellung der Anweisung bemerkte der Beamte, daß wir <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">ja</tei:add> im Grunde <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">ja</tei:del> <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">überhaupt</tei:add> keiner Legitimation bedürfen, da wir <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">ja</tei:del> nicht in<tei:add place="inline" hand="#HS">s</tei:add> <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">ein</tei:del> Kriegsgebiet<tei:supplied reason="syntax">,</tei:supplied> sondern in ein der Verordnung nach völlig freigegebenes Gebiet reisen wollen. – Mit der Anweisung nun <tei:subst><tei:del rend="overwritten" hand="#JS"><tei:gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" extent="7"/></tei:del><tei:add hand="#JS" place="superimposed">sollten</tei:add></tei:subst> wir noch einmal ins Büro Tür N.o 5 u. mit einer dort empfangenen Bestätigung zum Regierungsrat <tei:add place="inline" hand="#HS">(</tei:add>als Leiter des Kommissariates<tei:add place="inline" hand="#HS">)</tei:add>. Indessen kürzte ich den Weg ab, u. indem ich mir die Bemerkung des Beamten zunutze machte, daß wir keiner Legitimation bedürfen, zog ich vor, direkt zum Regierungsrat zu gehen u. ihn anzufragen. Dieser bestätigte nun, daß wir keinerlei speziellen Anweisung bedürfen, so daß wir ganz überflüssig all’ die Wege vom <tei:rs key="entity-002269" type="place">Westbahnhof<!--[DPl Westbahnhof]--></tei:rs> zur Polizei-Direktion, von dort zum Kommissariat gemacht haben. Die Hauptursache <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">aber</tei:add> all’ dieser in den Auskunft der Behörden <tei:sic>zutagetreten<tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">d</tei:del>en</tei:sic> Gegensätze ist die mangelnde Bestimmtheit <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">schon</tei:add> in den sogenannten Bestimmungen der <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">oberen</tei:add> Behörden. Schon die Verordnung ist aus dem Streben nach Hochdeutsch in sich unklar; kommen dazu dadurch veranlaßte mißverständliche Auffassungen der untergeordneten Organe, so erhält man das tolle Bild von widersprechendsten Angaben u. Forderungen, denen nun auch wir zum Opfer gefallen sind. Jedenfalls waren wir dem Schicksal dafür dankbar, daß es uns erspart blieb, noch weitere zwei Tage in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien<!--[DPl Wien]--></tei:rs> warten zu müssen (denn nach der Auskunft des Wachmannes <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">würde</tei:add> die endgiltige Ausfertigung einer solchen Reiselegitimation gewöhnlich zwei Tage <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">ge</tei:add>dauert <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">haben</tei:add>) u. frohen Herzens kehrten wir in den I. Bezirk zurück, um uns noch vor Tisch Auskunft im Militärbüro zu holen. Diesmal gelang uns die Unter- <tei:pb n="972"/> redung u. mehr als das, die Ergebnisse waren derart, daß sie uns befriedigen konnten. Der Inhaber des Büros zeigte sich gewandt u. orientiert u. gab mir schließlich den Rat, <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#JS">mir</tei:add> im Gemeindeamt eine Bescheinigung zu holen, wornach ich erst zur Nachmusterung wieder in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien<!--[DPl Vienna]--></tei:rs> zu erscheinen hätte. Er versicherte, dies sei üblich u. habe weiter nichts auf sich. Nun hatten wir endlich die Möglichkeit, den Sommer ungestört zu verbringen u. gerne stiegen wir in einen Einspänner, der uns aufs Gemeindeamt brachte. Aber alsogleich zerrann wieder unser Traum: Die Angabe des Büroinhabers erwies sich als falsch, da wider eine Musterungs-Anordnung solche legere Mittel absolut unzulässig sind u. nur eben viel stärkere Gründe im Spiel sein müssen, wenn der Stellungspflichtige das Recht auf eine Nachmusterung erwerben wollte. Doch konnte uns dies alles nichts mehr anhaben, da wir immerhin am Abend abzureisen in der Lage waren. – Während <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs> <tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">N</tei:del><tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#HS">n</tei:add></tei:subst>achmittags packte oder mindestens die letzten Zurüstungen traf, besorgte ich die Billetts u. genau um 6<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> abends stiegen wir in den Wagen ein. Auf dem <tei:rs key="entity-002269" type="place">Westbahnhofe<!--[DPl Westbahnhof]--></tei:rs> nahmen wir das Abendessen ein u. dann stiegen wir glücklich ins Coupé, wo wir des geringen Verkehrs halber günstige Ecksitze erreichen konnten. Wir sahen sogar die Möglichkeit, nachts auf den Bänken schlafen zu können.</tei:seg> 
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0001-se03">Kaum waren wir außerhalb des <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien<!--[DPl Wien]--></tei:rs>er Rayons, erschien ein Beamter, der sich nach unseren Legitimationen erkundigte. Also doch! So hatte der Regierungsrat Unrecht, der mir versicherte, daß ich keiner bedürfe. Da ich indessen in der Lage war, die Identität meiner Person durch viele andere Dokumente nachweisen zu können, hatten wir weiter keine Schwierigkeiten. Anerkennenswert war das liebenswürdige Verhalten des Beamten gegenüber <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs>, wie er den überhaupt die Legitimationsanweisung, die ich zu mir gesteckt, für voll gelten ließ, vielleicht eben darum, weil sie gegenüber all’ den übrigen Dokumenten schließlich überflüssig war. Nun fuhren wir unbehelligt weiter. Zu unserem Leidwesen passierte wir ja die uns so liebe Gegend leider bei völliger Dunkelheit, so daß es uns <tei:pb n="973"/> versagt blieb, aus dem ersten Ansturm der neuen Eindrücke jenen Anstoß des <tei:subst><tei:del rend="overwritten" hand="#JS"><tei:gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" extent="12"/></tei:del><tei:add hand="#JS" place="superimposed">Enthusiasmus</tei:add></tei:subst> zu schöpfen, der all die Jahre her unsere Reise nach <tei:rs key="entity-002334" type="place">Tirol<!--[DPl Tirol]--></tei:rs> sonst immer durchwirkte. – Frühmorgens trafen wir in <tei:rs key="entity-002304" type="place">Innsbruck<!--[DPl Innsbruck]--></tei:rs> ein, wo wir sehr viele Soldaten fanden. Nach kurzem Aufenthalt gieng es weiter. Vor <tei:rs key="entity-007711" type="place">Imst<!--[DPl Imst]--></tei:rs> harrte unser noch eine <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">weitere</tei:add> Ueberraschung: Wieder erschien ein Beamter, der uns nach unserer Legitimation frug u., anders als der erste, schien er <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">fürs Erste</tei:add> sich mit den Dokumenten <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">überhaupt</tei:add> nicht zufrieden geben zu wollen. Keinesfalls ließ er die Legitimationsanweisung gelten, die er vielmehr zu sich steckte, fand sich aber schließlich in die Situation u. gab uns nur die Belehrung, daß wir bei solchen Reisen uns allemal eines von der Polizei-Direktion ausgestellten &#8222;Passes&#8220; versichern möchten. Dieser Beamte schien strenger, aber die übliche Borniertheit hatte auch er tief im Gehirn sitzen, denn er kam darüber nicht hinweg, uns immer wieder anzuraten, einfach einen Pass &#8222;nach <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place">Deutschland<!--[DPl Germany]--></tei:rs>&#8220; oder der <tei:rs key="entity-002507" type="place">Schweiz<!--[DPl Switzerland]--></tei:rs> zu verlangen u. s. f. – keinesfalls schien er begreifen zu können, daß ich kaum einen Pass nach <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place">Deutschland<!--[DPl Germany]--></tei:rs> fordern würde, wenn ich keinen solchen brauche, wie eben in unserem Falle, da wir ja im Inland verbleiben <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">wollen</tei:add>. Der Beamte gefiel sich sehr in seiner Strenge, u. da wir seiner Eitelkeit schmeichelten, hatten wir auch ihn bald los.</tei:seg>
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0001-se04">Bei <tei:rs key="entity-007712" type="place">Flirsch<!--[DPl Flirsch]--></tei:rs> durchbrach die Sonne zum erstenmal die Wolken; es war, als hätte sie uns den ersten Gruß bis zu diesem Augenblicke aufgespart, um uns gewissermaßen zu sagen, sie sei in <tei:rs key="entity-002334" type="place">Tirol<!--[DPl Tirol]--></tei:rs> eine andere als in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien<!--[DPl Wien]--></tei:rs> u. wieder diejenige, die wir in <tei:rs key="entity-002334" type="place">Tirol<!--[DPl Tirol]--></tei:rs> so <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">sehr</tei:add> lieben u. verehren. – Auf der Reise fiel uns die große Menge Heu auf, die wir von Herzen der armen Bevölkerung gönnten.</tei:seg> 
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0001-se05">Im Hotel werden wir herzlich empfangen, so daß ich vermuten darf, daß selbst die im Meldezettel einbekannte Wahrheit keinerlei unangenehme Rückwirkung hatte. <tei:rs key="entity-000806" type="person">Schuler<!--[DPe Schuler, Walter]--></tei:rs> weist uns zwei prachtvolle Zimmer an, worin wir viel Licht u. Luft haben, so daß unserer Arbeit die bestmögliche Beflügelung gegeben ist. Walte nur Gott, <tei:pb n="974"/> daß mindestens nicht so bald eine Störung eintrete u. uns auch nur vorübergehend aus dem Paradiese jage. – Die Kost ist sowohl vortrefflich als überraschend reichlich, u. gilt der vom Hotelier geforderte Preis von 9 Kronen täglich mit auch für die Zimmer, so hätten wir alle Ursache, dem Schicksal für all die Güte zu danken. <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs> macht sich sofort ans <tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">a</tei:del><tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#HS">A</tei:add></tei:subst>uspacken, so daß wir am ersten Tage gleich im Genusse sämtlicher Voraussetzungen freier Bewegung sind. – Aus einem zufälligen Gespräch, das wir abends mit <tei:rs key="entity-000806" type="person">Schuler<!--[DPe Schuler, Walter]--></tei:rs> führten, entnehmen wir, daß die Behörden auch ihm viel Anlass zu begründeten Klagen gaben.</tei:seg> 
         </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-01">July 1, 1915. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0001-se01">Early in the morning, in order to be the first in line, we go to the police headquarters on account of the <tei:supplied reason="clarity">travel</tei:supplied> permits. At the entrance, however, two guards inform us that we first need to collect a further legitimation from the police station in district III, which will then become the basis of the actual permit which is to completed by the police authorities. Thus even on this occasion we have once again acquainted ourselves with the disastrous High German of our officials who, in their regulations, do not indicate a single word about all the steps that have to be taken. Admittedly, there is nothing left for us to do than <tei:pb n="970"/> to follow the special instructions of the lower authorities, which change from one moment to the next. – After first trying to acquire information at the military bureau, unfortunately to no avail, we went back to the police station in district III. There we were shown to door No. 5. Unfortunately we were no longer the first people, and we had to prepare ourselves for an agonizing wait. The crowd continued to swell in the small, narrow waiting room; officials and servants were going hither and thither – perhaps precisely this was their only occupation – but refused to give the parties concerned any information. Things became more unseemly and rowdy when, suddenly, an official escorted a gentleman, who looked well-off, and two ladies into room No. 5, to the detriment of everyone who had been waiting. We could not understand at all why it took such a very long time to deal with the individual cases. And already we were able to conclude that if things continued in that way, all of the parties concerned could surely not all be processed. Nonetheless, no further help was forthcoming for a long time, and the second official expected by the parties concerned did not appear on the scene. Then suddenly – we had already been waiting three quarters of an hour – a lower-ranking man called out in the waiting room: everyone who wanted to travel to <tei:rs key="entity-002483" type="place">Styria<!--[DPl Steiermark]--></tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-002344" type="place">Carinthia<!--[DPl Carinthia]--></tei:rs>, and so on should follow him. Now the parties divided up and we too followed that official, who had evidently been called upon to give assistance. But here things went helter-skelter; the order that had been tacitly observed in the previous waiting room suddenly seemed to be relaxed, and the parties grouped themselves around the table as they wished, so that whoever screamed loudest received his travel permit first. When <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs> attempted to make the official aware of the disorder that had broken out, he replied to her irritably that it wasn't his business; he was only volunteering his assistance and would not take any nonsense from the parties.</tei:seg> 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />          
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0001-se02"><tei:pb n="971"/> Finally, however, it was our turn; and now we could understand, from our own perception, why the processing took such a long time. A thoroughly laborious recording of various attributes, together with the production of all sorts of permits, made the business tiresome even from a purely mechanical point of view. But lo!, when he was in the midst of issuing the certificate, the official noted that we did not indeed any travel permit at all, as we did not want to travel into a war zone but rather to a freely accessible area. – We were now to take this certificate once more to the door of office no. 5 and, on receiving confirmation there, proceed to the councilor (as head of the police station). However, I shortened the path and, by making use of the official's remark to the effect that we did not need any travel permit, instead went directly to the councilor and question him. He confirmed now that we needed no special certificates at all, so that all the trips we had made from the <tei:rs key="entity-002269" type="place">Western Railway Station<!--[DPl Westbahnhof]--></tei:rs> to the police headquarters and from there to the police station were entirely unnecessary. The principal cause, however, of all these contradictions that came to light in the information provided by the authorities was the lack of precision even in the so-called regulations of the higher authorities. Already the regulation, in striving for High German, is in itself unclear; if this additionally results in ambiguous interpretations by the subordinate authorities, then one receives the confused picture of the most contradictory instructions and demands, to which we too have now fallen victim. In any event, we could thank the Fates for being spared having to wait two more days in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna<!--[DPl Wien]--></tei:rs> (for, according to the information of the guard, the final preparation of such travel permits would have taken two days); and, with cheerful hearts, we returned to district I in order to get information at the military bureau before lunchtime. This time we succeeded in getting an interview; <tei:pb n="972"/> and, more than that, the results were of a sort that could satisfy us. The official at the bureau proved knowledgeable and understanding, and in the event advised me to obtain from the district town hall a notification saying when I would be expected to appear in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna<!--[DPl Vienna]--></tei:rs> for the next army physical examination. He assured me that this was standard practice and no cause for concern. Now it was finally possible for us to pass the summer undisturbed; and we gladly boarded a one-horse carriage that took us to the town hall. But immediately our dream fell apart: the bureau official's instructions proved false: when confronted by a directive to take the physical examination, such easy measures are absolutely inadmissible, and much stronger reasons need to be produced if someone liable to enlistment is to be given the right to have the examination delayed. But we could no longer take any action over all this, as we were in any event ready to depart that evening. – While <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs> packed, or at least obtained the final provisions, I acquired the train tickets. And precisely at 6 o'clock in the evening, we got into the coach. We had supper at the <tei:rs key="entity-002269" type="place">Western Railway Station<!--[DPl Westbahnhof]--></tei:rs>, and then we finally boarded the train carriage; as it was, fortunately, a quiet time for traveling, we were able to find good corner seats. We even saw the possibility of being able to sleep at night on the benches.</tei:seg>
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0001-se03">Hardly had we left the district of <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna<!--[DPl Wien]--></tei:rs> than an officer appeared, asking us for our permits. So we needed them after all! Thus the government official was mistaken when he assured me that I did not need one. But as I was able to prove my identity by many other documents, we had no further difficulties. The officer's courteous behavior towards <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs> was noticeable: the way he fully accepted the travel certificate that I had with me, perhaps for the very reason that it was unnecessary in the light of all the other documents. Now we travelled on undisturbed. To our regret, we passed through the countryside we loved so much in complete darkness, so that we <tei:pb n="973"/> were prevented from conjuring that impulse of enthusiasm from the first rush of new impressions, which had otherwise always affected our trip to the <tei:rs key="entity-002334" type="place">Tyrol<!--[DPl Tirol]--></tei:rs> in all the years gone by. – In the early morning we arrived in <tei:rs key="entity-002304" type="place">Innsbruck<!--[DPl Innsbruck]--></tei:rs>, where we found a great number of soldiers. After a short stop, we moved on. Still another surprise awaited us before <tei:rs key="entity-007711" type="place">Imst<!--[DPl Imst]--></tei:rs>: another officer appeared, asking us about our permit; and, unlike the first, he seemed at first to show that he was entirely unhappy with the documentation. On no account would he accept the validity of the travel certificate, which he instead pocketed; but in the end he reconciled himself to the situation and only cautioned us against making such trips without always obtaining a "visa" from the police authority. This officer seemed stricter, but the usual narrow-mindedness was also deeply ingrained in him; for he could not refrain from reminding us over and over simply to request a visa "for <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place">Germany<!--[DPl Germany]--></tei:rs>" or <tei:rs key="entity-002507" type="place">Switzerland<!--[DPl Switzerland]--></tei:rs>, and so on. In no way could he understand that I would not require a visa for <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place">Germany<!--[DPl Germany]--></tei:rs> if I did not need one – which was precisely the case here, since we wanted to remain in our home country. The officer took great pleasure in his strictness; and as we pandered to his vanity, we were also soon free of him.</tei:seg>
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0001-se04">In <tei:rs key="entity-007712" type="place">Flirsch<!--[DPl Flirsch]--></tei:rs> the sun broke through the clouds for the first time; it was as if it had spared us its first greeting until this moment, in order to say to us in a certain way that it was a different sun in the <tei:rs key="entity-002334" type="place">Tyrol<!--[DPl Tirol]--></tei:rs> to the one in <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna<!--[DPl Wien]--></tei:rs>, and again the one which we so greatly loved and honored in the <tei:rs key="entity-002334" type="place">Tyrol<!--[DPl Tirol]--></tei:rs>. – On the trip, we were struck by the great quantity of hay, for which we were sincerely glad on behalf of the peasant population.</tei:seg>
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0001-se05">In the hotel we are greeted cordially, so that I may assume that the truth <tei:supplied reason="clarity">about our relationship</tei:supplied> acknowledged in our registration card had no adverse consequences at all. <tei:rs key="entity-000806" type="person">Schuler<!--[DPe Schuler, Walter]--></tei:rs> shows us two magnificent rooms, where we have much light and air, so that the best possible inspiration will be given to our work. Would to God <tei:pb n="974"/> that at least no disruption would soon occur, and drive us even only temporarily from this paradise. – The provisions are both excellent and surprisingly abundant; and since the price asked by the hotelier is 9 Kronen per day, including the rooms, we had every reason to thank Fate for all this goodness. <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs> begins immediately to unpack, so that on the first day we could enjoy all the prerequisites of free movement. – From a casual conversation that we had with <tei:rs key="entity-000806" type="person">Schuler<!--[DPe Schuler, Walter]--></tei:rs> in the evening, we learn that the authorities gave him, too, much cause for justified complaints.</tei:seg> 
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0002">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 2, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-02T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-02"><tei:supplied reason="clarity">July 2, 1915:</tei:supplied></tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0002-se01"><tei:supplied reason="clarity">no diary entry for this date</tei:supplied></tei:seg></tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-02"><tei:supplied reason="clarity">July 2, 1915:</tei:supplied></tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0002-se01"><tei:supplied reason="clarity">no diary entry for this date</tei:supplied></tei:seg></tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>
   
   <sdo:record ID="r0003">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 3, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-03T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>
      
      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-03">3. VII. 15 </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0003-se01">Blauer Himmel; schönstes Wetter, nach den heftigen Regengüssen doppelt wirksam, ladet sofort zum ersten Spaziergang ein. Auf allen Bergen ringsum Neuschnee, in Massen, wie ich sie hier in <tei:rs key="entity-002279" type="place">St. Anton<!--[DPl St. Anton am Arlberg]--></tei:rs> noch niemals beobachtet habe. Die ernste Gegend macht auch diesmal auf mich einen überaus charaktervollen starken Eindruck; <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs> aber gesteht, <tei:rs key="entity-002279" type="place">St. A.<!--[DPl St. Anton am Arlberg]--></tei:rs> nun eigentlich zum erstenmal ordentlich zu sehen. Sichtlich hat sich der Ort wirtschaftlich gehoben <tei:subst><tei:del rend="overwritten" hand="#JS"><tei:gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" extent="7"/></tei:del><tei:add hand="#JS" place="superimposed">seitdem</tei:add></tei:subst> wir <tei:sic>in</tei:sic> zum letztenmal gesehen haben; nicht nur sind die <tei:sic>ältern</tei:sic> Häuser vielfach u. geschmackvoll verbessert u. renoviert, sondern auch neue Villen sind erbaut worden, die bei aller Anspruchslosigkeit den Sinn fürs Schöne durchaus befriedigen. Nach dieser Richtung hin konnten wir also <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">überall</tei:del> Gefühle der Freude aufbringen, nur wurde uns diese anderseits dadurch stark beeinträchtigt, daß all die alten u. neuen Häuser fast ganz leer von Männern sind. Es fehlt sozusagen den Bergen u. Häusern an ihren berufenen Dolmetschen, u. gedenken wir der Ursache dieser Erscheinung, so haben wir allen Grund, unsere Freude etwas herabzusetzen. Frauen, Jünglinge u. Mädchen verrichten die Feldarbeiten u. wer nur irgend waffenfähig ist, trägt Waffen draußen im Felde. Hier, im Ort selbst, sehen wir nur Wachen u. wir erfahren, daß im Abstand von je 100m ein Soldat zur Sicherung der Bahnanlage Posten steht. –</tei:seg> 
		          </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0003-se02"><tei:pb n="975"/> Unser erster Ausflug gilt dem Arlberg<!--[DPl Arlberg]--> selbst; wir grüßen wieder die breite Straße, die so wundervollen <tei:sic>Ausblicke</tei:sic> auf <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">die</tei:del> Gletscher, in<tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">s</tei:del> <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#JS">die</tei:add> Täler bietet u. das Geheimnis besitzt, den Wanderer gar nicht ahnen zu lassen, daß er, wenn noch so bequem <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">u. lässig</tei:add> wandernd, dennoch <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">allmälich</tei:add> eine beträchtliche Höhe gewinnt. Im Walde hören wir noch den <tei:sic><tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">G</tei:del><tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#HS">K</tei:add></tei:subst>uckuk</tei:sic>; <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">u.</tei:del> Frühlingsblumen zieren den Weg. Wir begegnen einem Deutschen, der sich als Chemiker entpuppt u. einer Kur halber unseren Ort aufgesucht hat. Er erzählt, er habe sich im Laboratorium die Krankheit zugezogen, habe auch Sprengstoffe erfunden, die augenblicklich zur Verwendung gelangen, u. s. w. Ich glaubte ihm einen wesentlichen Dienst zu erweisen, wenn ich ihm die Küche unseres Hotels empfahl. – Wir gingen noch nicht <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">ganz</tei:add> bis auf den Pass u. begnügten uns <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">nur</tei:add> mit etwa halbem Wege. Wir taten dies aus Vorsicht u. weil wir mit Schlaf stark im Rückstande waren.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0003-se03">Karte an <tei:rs key="entity-000737" type="person">Roth<!--[DPe Roth, Herman]--></tei:rs> mit Angabe der neuen Adresse – an <tei:rs key="entity-000738" type="person">Rothberger<!--[DPe Rothberger, Alfred]--></tei:rs> (&#8222;Zwischenhändler der Luft&#8220;); Ansichtskarten an <tei:rs key="entity-000773" type="person">Mama<!--[DPe Schenker, Julia]--></tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Floriz<!--[DPe Violin, Moriz]--></tei:rs> u. <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">Wally<!--[DPe Violin, Valerie]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg> 
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> 
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0003-se04">Nachmittags wandern wir die Straße in entgegengesetzter Richtung u. landen im Bruckwaldele,
               <tei:note xml:id="r0003-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Bruckwaldele: possibly the name of a restaurant or inn.</tei:note>
               um dort den VI. Gesang der Odys<tei:add place="inline" hand="#HS">s</tei:add>ee
               <tei:note xml:id="r0003-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Book VI of The Odyssey recounts Odysseus's arrival in the land of the Phaeacians, where, on the beach, he first encounters the king's daughter Nausicaa, who is enchanted by the foreigner. There soon arises between them feelings of affection.</tei:note>
               fortzusetzen.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-03">July 3, 1915. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0003-se01">Blue sky, most beautiful weather, doubly effective after the heavy downpours, invite us immediately to take our first walk. New snow, all around on the mountains, in quantities that I have never previously seen here in <tei:rs key="entity-002279" type="place">St. Anton<!--[DPl St. Anton am Arlberg]--></tei:rs>. Even this time, the awesome landscape makes a thoroughly characterful, strong impression on me; <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs>, however, admits to seeing <tei:rs key="entity-002279" type="place">St. Anton<!--[DPl St. Anton am Arlberg]--></tei:rs> properly only for the first time now. The place has visibly prospered since the last time we saw it; not only have the older houses been improved and renovated in many respects, and with taste; new villas have also been built which, in spite of all modesty, thoroughly satisfy the sense of the beautiful. In this respect, we could summon up feelings of joy; on the other hand, we were strongly affected by the fact that all these old and new houses were almost completely empty of men. The hills and houses were, so to speak, bereft of their appointed interpreters; and when we consider the cause of this phenomenon, we have very reason to diminish our joy. Women, boys and girls organized the field work; and anyone who is just capable of bearing arms carries weapons outside in the field. Here, in the town itself, we see only guards; and we learn that soldiers are posted every 100 meters to secure the railroad system. –</tei:seg>
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0003-se02"><tei:pb n="975"/> Our first excursion is to the Arlberg<!--[DPl Arlberg]--> itself; we again greet the broad road, which offers such wonderful views over glaciers and into valleys, and which keeps the secret of not allowing the trekker even to have an inkling that, however casually and easily he walks, he nonetheless gradually gains significantly in altitude. In the forest we still hear the cuckoo, and spring flowers adorn the way. We encounter a German, who turns out to be a chemist who has come to our village for sake of a health cure. He tells us that he incurred his illness in the laboratory, that he has also invented explosives which are currently in use, and so on. I believe that I did him a significant favor by recommending the cuisine in our hotel – We did not go all the way to the pass, but satisfied ourselves with just half the distance. We did this for sake of caution, and because we were seriously in arrears of sleep.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0003-se03">Postcard to <tei:rs key="entity-000737" type="person">Roth<!--[DPe Roth, Herman]--></tei:rs> with details of our new address – to <tei:rs key="entity-000738" type="person">Rothberger<!--[DPe Rothberger, Alfred]--></tei:rs> ("the middleman of the air"); picture postcards to <tei:rs key="entity-000773" type="person">Mama<!--[DPe Schenker, Julia]--></tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Floriz<!--[DPe Violin, Moriz]--></tei:rs> and <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">Vally<!--[DPe Violin, Valerie]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg> 
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> 
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0003-se04">In the afternoon we walk along the road in the opposite direction and end up at the Bruckwaldele,<tei:ptr corresp="r0003-fn01" type="footnote"/>, where we continue reading Book VI of the Odyssey.<tei:ptr corresp="r0003-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0004">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 4, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-04T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-04">4. VII. 15 </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0004-se01">Ein reiner, zur Andacht stimmender Sommertag, dessen absolute Harmonie auch in Menschenseelen Harmonie<tei:add place="inline" hand="#HS">n</tei:add> auslöst. An solchen Tagen redet die Natur so eindringlich zum Menschen, daß er seiner selbst gleichsam vergisst u. sich in die Natur auflöst wie <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">der</tei:del> <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">ein</tei:add> Nebel, den die Sonne trinkt. Wir wandern vormittags nach <tei:rs key="entity-007713" type="place">St. Jakob<!--[DPl St. Jakob am Arlberg]--></tei:rs> u. widmen den Nachmittag neuerlich der Korrektur des <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title>Textes<!--[DW Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 111]--></tei:title></tei:rs> nach dem <tei:term>Aut.</tei:term>, die auch zuende gelangt.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0004-se02">Brief von <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Fl.<!--[DPe Violin, Moriz]--></tei:rs> über <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien<!--[DPl Wien]--></tei:rs>. Bei aller Vorsicht wahrlich unvorsichtig genug teilt er mir mit, daß selbst im Falle einer Tauglicherklärung sich vieles zu meinem Gunsten machen ließe.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0004-se03"><tei:pb n="976"/> Noch finden wir Muße zu einem Spaziergang in der Richtung des Ferwalltal<!--[DPl Verwalltal]-->es zur Stiegeneck-Kapelle<!--[DPl Stiegeneckkapelle]-->; <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">wir</tei:del> <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">u.</tei:add> sind freudig überrascht, den Weg in renoviertem Zustande zu finden; auch die Kapelle wurde verschönert u. <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">endlich</tei:add> unter<tei:add place="inline" hand="#HS">halb</tei:add> <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">der Kapelle</tei:del> <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">ihr</tei:add> ein neues <tei:rs key="entity-006278" type="person">Christus<!--[DPe Christ]--></tei:rs>bild errichtet. Freilich über allen Renovierungen u. Neuausschmückungen triumphiert die Schönheit der Natur, die, obgleich <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">sie</tei:del> sich allezeit treu bleib<tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">t</tei:del><tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#HS">end</tei:add></tei:subst>, in ihrer Art wohl auch Renovierungen erfährt. Ein neuer Frühling, ein neuer Sommer, welche Renovierung bedeutet das!</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-04">July 4, 1915. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0004-se01">A pure summer's day, attuned to devotion, whose absolute harmony releases harmonies among human souls. On such days, Nature speaks so powerfully to people that they forget themselves, so to speak, and dissolve into Nature like a mist that the sun imbibes. We take a walk in the morning to <tei:rs key="entity-007713" type="place">St. Jakob<!--[DPl St. Jakob am Arlberg]--></tei:rs> and devote ourselves again to the correction of the <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title level="m">score<!--[DW Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 111]--></tei:title></tei:rs> in accordance with the <tei:term>autograph</tei:term> manuscript, which we succeed in finishing.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0004-se02">Letter from <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Floriz<!--[DPe Violin, Moriz]--></tei:rs> about <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna<!--[DPl Wien]--></tei:rs>. In spite of all caution, he tells me, in truth without sufficient caution, that even in the event that I were declared fit <tei:supplied reason="clarity">for military service</tei:supplied>, there would be much in my favor.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0004-se03"><tei:pb n="976"/> We still find the energy for a walk in the direction of the Verwalltal<!--[DPl Verwalltal]--> to the Stiegeneck chapel<!--[DPl Stiegeneckkapelle]-->, and are pleasantly surprised to find that the path has been restored; the chapel, too, was beautified and, finally, a new image of <tei:rs key="entity-006278" type="person">Christ<!--[DPe Christ]--></tei:rs> was erected beneath it. Of course, all renovations and new adornments are trumped by the beauty of Nature which, although at all times remaining faithful to itself, also experiences renovations in its own way: a new spring, a new summer, that renovation signifies!</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0005">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 5, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-05T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-05">5. VII. 15 </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0005-se01">Nun zieht wieder die alte Ordnung ein <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#HS">,</tei:del> u. wir stehen um 5<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> morgens auf. Wir wandern auf den Pass. Auch dort finden wir Neues, obendrein Schönes <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#HS">,</tei:del> u. erfahren, der ehemalige Buchhalter unseres Gastwirtes habe dessen Nichte geheiratet u. das Hospiz in Pacht genommen. Die Räume sind auf das geschmackvollste eingerichtet u. so manches finden wir, das wir sonst noch nirgends angetroffen haben, z. B. auf den Bänken hölzerne Keile, auf denen Polster ruhen. Auf dem Wege pflückt <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs> Alpenrosen, die leider schon stark abgeblüht sind. Desto größere Freude macht uns eine Partie Enzian, die sich, <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">als wären sie</tei:del> <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">nach Art von</tei:add> Birkenstämme<tei:add place="inline" hand="#HS">n</tei:add>, gar zahlreich an derselben Stelle, sozusagen gesellschaftlich, <tei:subst><tei:del rend="overwritten" hand="#JS"><tei:gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" extent="16"/></tei:del><tei:add hand="#JS" place="superimposed">zusammengefunden</tei:add></tei:subst> haben. Von <tei:rs key="entity-007714" type="place">St. Christof<!--[DPl St. Christoph am Arlberg]--></tei:rs> Karte nach <tei:rs key="entity-002301" type="place">Kautzen<!--[DPl Kautzen]--></tei:rs>. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>         
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0005-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Nachmittags wird die Korrektur des <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title>Fingersatzes<!--[DW Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 111]--></tei:title></tei:rs> zuende geführt (4 Stunden!). Gegen Abend setzt ein starkes Gewitter mit Regen ein.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-05">July 5, 1915. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0005-se01">Now the old order returns, and we get up at 5 o'clock in the morning. We walk up to the pass. There we also find something new, moreover beautiful, and learn that our landlord's previous bookkeeper had married his niece and leased the mountain hostel. The rooms have been furnished most tastefully, and we find so many things that we have never encountered before. For example, wooden wedges on the benches, on which cushions are placed. Along the way, <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs> picks alpine roses, which are unfortunately already rather faded. A bunch of gentian gives us all the greater pleasure; these, in the manner of birch trunks, were found together in great quantities in the same place – socially, so to speak. From St. Christoph<!--[DPl St. Christoph am Arlberg]-->, a postcard sent to <tei:rs key="entity-002301" type="place">Kautzen<!--[DPl Kautzen]--></tei:rs>. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />  </tei:seg>        
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0005-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> In the afternoon, the corrections to the <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title level="m">fingering<!--[DW Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 111]--></tei:title></tei:rs> are completed (four hours!). Towards evening, a heavy thunderstorm with rain arrives.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0006">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 6, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-06T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-06">6. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0006-se01">Nachdem <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs> die schärfste Kontrolle ge<tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">führt</tei:del><tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">übt</tei:add></tei:subst> hat, konnten die <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title>Korrekturen<!--[DW Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 111]--></tei:title></tei:rs> als beendet angesehen werden u. ein schönes <tei:sic>Packet</tei:sic> wandert nach <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien<!--[DPl Wien]--></tei:rs>. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />   </tei:seg>       
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0006-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Wieder tritt ein schweres Gewitter auf, das uns an die Zimmer fesselt u. so die Tagebuch-Arbeit fördert.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-06">6. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0006-se01">After <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs> exercised the most severe control, the <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title level="m">corrections<!--[DW Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 111]--></tei:title></tei:rs> <tei:supplied reason="clarity">to the musical text</tei:supplied> could be regarded as finished; and a pretty package makes its way to <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna<!--[DPl Wien]--></tei:rs>. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />  </tei:seg>        
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0006-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Again a heavy storm arrives, which binds us to our rooms and thus facilitates work on the diary.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0007">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 7, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-07T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-07">7. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0007-se01">Früh wandere ich allein nach <tei:rs key="entity-007715" type="place">Pettneu<!--[DPl Pettneu am Arlberg]--></tei:rs>, da <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs> einer Schonung bedurfte. Aus Ne- <tei:pb n="977"/> beln klärt sich inzwischen eine wundervolle Stimmung, die wir zur Arbeit im Freien benützen. Gegen Abend Gewitter mit Regen u. Hagel. Eine harte Prüfung für die arme Landbevölkerung, die ihr Bestes tut, wenn sie der Natur blind ihren Fleiß anvertraut u. doch zuweilen, wie eben jetzt, gerade von ihr im Stiche gelassen wird. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>         
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0007-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Odyssee, VII. u. VIII. Gesang.
               <tei:note xml:id="r0007-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">The seventh and eighth books of The Odyssey tells of Odysseus's stay at the court of Alcinous, King of the Phaeacians and his wife Arete. Odysseus is able to win the favor of the king, who promises to escort him home to Ithaca.</tei:note>
               Ist es ein Widerspruch, wenn <tei:rs key="entity-006433" type="person">Homer<!--[DPe Homer]--></tei:rs> den Phäaken allerlei Tugenden nachrühmt, auch solche, die sie Fremden gegenüber betätigen, unter ihnen sich gleichwohl aber einer befindet, der Odysseus höhnt u. schmäht? Wirksam sind dagegen manche andern Züge; so <tei:subst><tei:del rend="overwritten" hand="#JS"><tei:gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" extent="10"/></tei:del><tei:add hand="#JS" place="superimposed">orientiert</tei:add></tei:subst> z. B. Pallas-Athene Odysseus über das Haus Alkinoos’ so genau, so daß er in Verfolgung seines Zieles von ganz wertvollen Behelfen sofort Gebrauch machen kann; oder wenn Arete an Odysseus plötzlich die Gewänder bemerkt, die ihr selbst ja sehr vertraut sind u. so Veranlassung hat, Odysseus zu fragen, woher er diese Gewänder erhalten habe, wodurch seine Erzählung begründet wird, u. s. w.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-07"></tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0007-se01">I take an early walk to <tei:rs key="entity-007715" type="place">Pettneu<!--[DPl Pettneu am Arlberg]--></tei:rs>, as <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs> needed a rest. <tei:pb n="977"/> In the meantime, a wonderful atmosphere breaks through the mists; we use this to work out of doors. Towards evening, thunderstorm with rain and hail. A difficult test for the poor countryfolk, who do their best when they blindly put their energies in Nature's trust and yet sometimes, as just now, are forsaken by it 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>        
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0007-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Odyssey, books VII and VIII.<tei:ptr corresp="r0007-fn01" type="footnote"/> Is it not a contradiction when <tei:rs key="entity-006433" type="person">Homer<!--[DPe Homer]--></tei:rs> praises the Phaeacians for all sort of virtues, which they practice with respect to foreigners, but among whom is nonetheless one who mocks and scorns Odysseus? Many other features are, however, effective; thus for example Pallas Athena describes to Odysseus the house of Alcinous in such detail that he is able immediately to make use of valuable aids in the pursuit of his mission; or when Arete suddenly notices the clothing worn by Odysseus, with which she is very well acquainted, which gives her occasion to ask Odysseus where he obtained this clothing, by which his narrative is provided with a foundation; and so on.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0008">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 8, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-08T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-08">8. VII. 15 </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0008-se01">Des morgens wolkenlose Bläue, ein Vergissmeinnicht-Ocean. Intensive Vorarbeit u. Durchsicht vorrätiger einschlägiger Notizen zur Literaturrubrik <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title>op.111<!--[DW Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 111]--></tei:title></tei:rs>. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />  </tei:seg>
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0008-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Nach dem zweiten Frühstück in die Rosanna-Schlucht<!--[DPl Rosannaschlucht]-->, zuerst lesend, dann blos äußeren Eindrücken ergeben. Inzwischen steigert sich die Schwüle bis zu unerträglichem Grade. Gegen 4<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> nachmittags bricht ein schweres Gewitter los – erstaunlich ist die Periodizität, die fast postalische Pünktlichkeit, mit der das Unwetter seit Tagen regelmäßig gegen 4<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> einsetzt. Diesmal war es vielleicht noch heftiger, als an den vor<tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">her</tei:del><tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#HS">an</tei:add></tei:subst>gegangenen Tagen, besonders drohend das Wolken-<tei:term>Pauken</tei:term><tei:term>konzert</tei:term>. Vor unseren Fenstern knickte der Sturm ein junges hoffungsvolles Bäumchen. Am Abend bessert sich das Wetter genau so, wie am vorhergegangenen Abend.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0008-se03">Die &#8222;<tei:rs key="entity-002537" type="journal"><tei:title>Frankfurter Ztg.<!--[DT Frankfurter Zeitung]--></tei:title></tei:rs>&#8220; ist in Unordnung geraten; vermutlich ist dabei die Unintelligenz der <tei:pb n="978"/> Postbeamten im Spiele.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-08">July 8, 1915. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0008-se01">In the morning, cloudless blue, an ocean of forget-me-nots. Intensive preliminary work and study of relevant, available notes for the section on the secondary literature on <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Op.111<!--[DW Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 111]--></tei:title></tei:rs>. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>         
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0008-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> After second breakfast, to the Rosanna ravine<!--[DPl Rosannaschlucht]-->, reading at first, then merely enveloped by external impressions. In the meantime, the humidity climbs to an unbearable level. Towards 4 o'clock in the afternoon, a heavy thunderstorm breaks out – what is astonishing is the periodicity, the almost post-office punctuality, with which the bad weather has for days regularly arrived around 4 o'clock. This time it was perhaps even more severe than on the previous days; the <tei:term>timpani</tei:term> <tei:term>concerto</tei:term> in the clouds was particularly menacing. In front of our windows, the storm bent a young, helpless sapling. The weather improves in the evening, exactly as it had the previous evening.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0008-se03">The <tei:rs key="entity-002537" type="journal"><tei:title level="j">Frankfurter Zeitung<!--[DT Frankfurter Zeitung]--></tei:title></tei:rs> in disarray; presumably the ignorance of the <tei:pb n="978"/> postal officers had something to do with this.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0009">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 9, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-09T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-09">9. VII. 15 </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0009-se01">Die uns gestern gewordene Mitteilung, daß das Gewitter bei <tei:rs key="entity-007715" type="place">Pettneu<!--[DPl Pettneu am Arlberg]--></tei:rs> einen Bahnschaden verursacht habe, lockt uns, diesen zu besichtigen. Des morgens ist der Charakter des Tages noch nicht entschieden; Nebel dampfen aus Wassern u. Wäldern, aus Schluchten u. Ritzen, ballen sich bald zu großen Massen um Berggipfel, die sie in die Mitte nehmen u. <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">blos</tei:add> wie Kohlköpfe hervorleuchten lassen, bald ziehen sie dünngeschichtet durch die Athmosphäre, <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">wie</tei:add> mit noch unbekanntem, unentschiedenem Ziel. Die Sonne ringt offensichtlich um ihre Autorität, doch ist’s vorerst noch fraglich, ob ihr diesmal die Bändigung der Nebel gelingen wird. Wir wandern durch das ganze Dorf <tei:rs key="entity-007715" type="place">Pettneu<!--[DPl Pettneu am Arlberg]--></tei:rs> u. werden nicht müde, uns an einzelnen Zügen zu erfreuen, die, aus alten Zeiten stammend, von geduldige<tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">m</tei:del><tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#HS">rem</tei:add></tei:subst> Fleiß <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">u.</tei:del> liebevollerer Versenkung zeugen, als sie heute in Dörfern u. bei Wohnhäusern solcher Art üblich sind. Hier entzückt uns ein prächtiger Giebel über einem Wirtshaus, hoch oben beinahe mit Wollust weit vorgelagert; dort ein künstlich gewundener Baumstamm als Stütze des Treppenaufganges, gewundene Fenstersäulchen, schön angebrachte Balkone, u. s. w. Auch hier ist <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">wie in <tei:rs key="entity-002279" type="place">St. Anton<!--[DPl St. Anton am Arlberg]--></tei:rs></tei:add> erfreulicherweise steigender Wohlstand zu bemerken, der sich sowohl in den neuen Wohnhäusern, als in den Renovierungen alter ausdrückt. Besonders erfreulichen Eindruck machen die vielen Brunnen, die, gut gebaut, von Frauen, Mädchen u. Kindern <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">allezeit förmlich</tei:add> umlagert sind. Wir treffen auch ziemlich viel<tei:add place="inline" hand="#HS">e</tei:add> Soldaten u. geraten mit einem ins Gespräch. Aus der <tei:rs key="entity-004095" type="place">Pressburg<!--[DPl Preßburg]--></tei:rs>er Gegend stammend gibt er sich für einen Slaven aus, der erst hier im Laufe von 1½ Monaten etwas Deutsch sprechen gelernt hat; das Ungarische kann er aber nicht. O, du armes <tei:rs key="entity-002506" type="place">Oesterreich<!--[DPl Austria]--></tei:rs>! Da er deutsche Zeitungen nicht lesen kann, <tei:subst><tei:del rend="overwritten" hand="#JS"><tei:gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" extent="9"/></tei:del><tei:add hand="#JS" place="superimposed">slavische</tei:add></tei:subst> aber nicht <tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">vorhanden sind</tei:del> <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">zu Gesicht bekommt</tei:add></tei:subst>, ist er auf Mitteilungen angewiesen, die ungarische Kameraden aus den ihnen zukommenden ungarischen Blättern hier schöpfen. Er focht, wie er erzählte, in <tei:rs key="entity-002355" type="place">Galizien<!--[DPl Galicia]--></tei:rs> u. machte den Rückzug in die <tei:rs key="entity-006677" type="place">Karpathen<!--[DPl Carpathian Mountains]--></tei:rs> mit, wo er auch verwundet wurde, weiß aber den Namen seines <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">eigenen</tei:add> Ober-Komman- <tei:pb n="979"/> danten nicht anzugeben, trotzdem er die Char<tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">ch</tei:del><tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#HS">g</tei:add></tei:subst>e eines Korporals hat.</tei:seg> 
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> 
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0009-se02">Im Orte hören wir auch von einem Hellseher aus <tei:rs key="entity-007713" type="place">St. Jakob<!--[DPl St. Jakob am Arlberg]--></tei:rs>, der, von Beruf Bahnarbeiter, an Gesichten – wie die Wirtin sagt – buchstäblich leidet, so daß er sich schwer dazu entschließt &#8222;zu erzählen&#8220;. Obgleich auch schon die Wirtin zu sagen wußte, daß an all den aus seinem Munde stammenden Aussprüchen durchaus nicht alles wahr ist, hat sie uns <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">gleichwohl</tei:add> als seinen neuesten Ausspruch mitgeteilt, daß eine große Ueberraschung für Monat August bevorstehe, u. daß schon Ende Oktober die ersten Gefangenen zurückkehren werden. Nun denn, die für August bevorstehende Ueberraschung scheint der wackere Hellseher aus dem &#8222;<tei:rs key="entity-007686" type="journal"><tei:title>Tiroler Anzeiger<!--[DT Allgemeiner Tiroler Anzeiger]--></tei:title></tei:rs>&#8220; einfach herausgelesen zu haben, wo sie schon gestern in der Form mitgeteilt wurde, daß der deutsche <tei:rs key="entity-000963" type="person">Kaiser<!--[DPe Wilhelm II, Kaiser]--></tei:rs> mündlich Herrn <tei:rs key="entity-006495" type="person">Ganghofer<!--[DPe Ganghofer, Ludwig]--></tei:rs> eine große Ueberraschung <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">mitteilte</tei:del> ankündigte.
               <tei:note xml:id="r0009-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:rs type="work"><tei:title level="a">Kaiser Wilhelm kündet eine Ueberrschaung,</tei:title></tei:rs> <tei:rs type="work"><tei:title level="j">Allgemeiner Tiroler Anzeiger</tei:title></tei:rs>, No. 310, July 7, 1915, evening edition, p. 1.</tei:bibl></tei:note></tei:seg> 
			         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0009-se03">Als wir auf dem Heimwege waren, schien es zuweilen, als käme ein Wind, der als kräftiger Büttel der Sonne die Macht hätte, die Nebel zu verjagen; aber schon da wir zuhause eintrafen merkten wir, daß auch heute, wie gestern u. vorgestern, der Regen das letzte Wort behalten werde. In der Tat brach das Unwetter, durch kurzen Donner eingeleitet, gegen ¾3<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> herein. Nun regnet es fort. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0009-se04">In der Veranda des Wirtshaus in <tei:rs key="entity-007715" type="place">Pettneu<!--[DPl Pettneu am Arlberg]--></tei:rs> sind unter Fresken die Worte zu lesen: 
            <tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:lg type="poem">
               <tei:lg type="stanza">
                  <tei:l>
                     Das Leben ist ein <tei:term>Orchester</tei:term>,
                  </tei:l><tei:lb/>
                  <tei:l>
                     Blase nur mit mein Bester;
                  </tei:l><tei:lb/>
                  <tei:l>
                     Und halte <tei:term>Takt</tei:term> in Spiel u. Rast,
                  </tei:l><tei:lb/>
                  <tei:l>
                     Wenn du auch nie ein <tei:term>Solo</tei:term> hast.
                  </tei:l><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
                  <tei:l>
                     Wer nicht liebt Wein u. Gesang
                  </tei:l><tei:lb/>
                  <tei:l>            
                     Verdient ein Weib sein Leben lang.
                  </tei:l><tei:lb/>
               </tei:lg>
            </tei:lg></tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0009-se05">Karte von Frau <tei:rs key="entity-000165" type="person">Deutsch<!--[DPe Deutsch, Sofie]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0009-se06"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Die &#8222;Frankfurter Ztg<!--[DT Frankfurter Zeitung]-->&#8220; noch immer voller Lücken.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0009-se07"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Odyssee, X. Gesang.
               <tei:note xml:id="r0009-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Book X of The Odyssey describes Odysseus's stay with King Aeolus and his failed attempt to get to his homeland with the king's help.</tei:note></tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:pb n="980"/>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-09">July 9, 1915. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0009-se01">The report from yesterday that the storm damaged the railroad at <tei:rs key="entity-007715" type="place">Pettneu<!--[DPl Pettneu am Arlberg]--></tei:rs> entices us to have a look. In the morning, the character of the day is not yet decided; mists created from waters and forests, from ravines and crevices, agglomerate quickly into great masses around the mountain peaks, which they seize in the middle and let them shine merely like cabbage heads; soon they pervade the atmosphere in thin layers, their goal as yet unknown, undecided. The sun struggles openly to assert its authority; but it is at first still questionable whether it will succeed in containing the mists. We walk through the entire village of <tei:rs key="entity-007715" type="place">Pettneu<!--[DPl Pettneu am Arlberg]--></tei:rs> and do not tire of taking pleasure in individual traits which, originating in times gone by, bear witness to a more patient diligence and tender contemplation than one customarily finds in village houses of this sort. Here we were delighted by a magnificent gable above an inn, set far above almost in ecstasy; elsewhere an artistically turned tree trunk, used to support the stepped entrance; turned window columns, beautifully attached balconies, and so on. Here too, as in <tei:rs key="entity-002279" type="place">St. Anton<!--[DPl St. Anton am Arlberg]--></tei:rs>, one can observe with pleasure a rising standard of living, which can be seen as much in the new homes as in the renovations of old ones. The many well-built fountains, at all times verily surrounded by women, girls and children, make a particularly pleasing impression. We also meet quite a few soldiers and fall into conversation with one of them. Coming from an area around <tei:rs key="entity-004095" type="place">Pressburg<!--[DPl Preßburg]--></tei:rs>, he says that he is a Slav who has learned to speak a bit of German in the space of a month and a half here; but he does not know any Hungarian. O, you poor <tei:rs key="entity-002506" type="place">Austria<!--[DPl Austria]--></tei:rs>! Since he cannot read German newspapers or get hold of any Slavic ones, he gets his information from what his Hungarian comrades get from the Hungarian newspapers available to them. He tells us that he fought in <tei:rs key="entity-002355" type="place">Galicia<!--[DPl Galicia]--></tei:rs> and joined the retreat in the <tei:rs key="entity-006677" type="place">Carpathian Mountains<!--[DPl Carpathian Mountains]--></tei:rs>, where he was also wounded; but he is unable to tell us the name of his own commanding officer, <tei:pb n="979"/> in spite of his having charge of a corporal. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />  </tei:seg>        
			   </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0009-se02">In the village we also hear about a clairvoyant from <tei:rs key="entity-007713" type="place">St. Jakob<!--[DPl St. Jakob am Arlberg]--></tei:rs> who, a railroad worker by profession, veritably suffers from visions – so the landlady says – so that he is determined, with difficulty, "to narrate." Although even the landlady was able to say that all the pronouncements coming from his mouth were by no means the whole truth, she nonetheless told us that, according to his latest pronouncement, a great surprise awaited us in the month of August, and that the first prisoners <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of war</tei:supplied> would be arriving home already by the end of October. Now, then, the imminent surprise in August seems to be something that the valiant clairvoyant had simply read in the <tei:rs key="entity-007686" type="journal"><tei:title>Tiroler Anzeiger<!--[DT Allgemeiner Tiroler Anzeiger]--></tei:title></tei:rs>, where he was officially informed that the German <tei:rs key="entity-000963" type="person">emperor<!--[DPe Wilhelm II, Kaiser]--></tei:rs> informed Mr. <tei:rs key="entity-006495" type="person">Ganghofer<!--[DPe Ganghofer, Ludwig]--></tei:rs> verbally of a great surprise.<tei:ptr corresp="r0009-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:seg>
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0009-se03">While we were on our way home, it occasionally seemed as if a wind came which, as the sun's powerful beadle, had the power to drive away the mists; but as soon as we arrived home, we observed that today, too, like yesterday and the day before, the rain had the last word. In fact, the bad weather, introduced by a short period of thunder, arrived towards 2:45. Now it is still raining. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0009-se04">In the porch of the inn in <tei:rs key="entity-007715" type="place">Pettneu<!--[DPl Pettneu am Arlberg]--></tei:rs>, beneath frescoes, the following words appear:
            <tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:lg type="poem">
               <tei:lg type="stanza">
                  <tei:l>            
                     Life is an <tei:term>orchestra</tei:term>,
                  </tei:l><tei:lb/>
                  <tei:l>            
                     Do join in, my friend;
                  </tei:l><tei:lb/>
                  <tei:l>
                     And keep the <tei:term>rhythm</tei:term> when playing and resting,
                  </tei:l><tei:lb/>
                  <tei:l>
                     Even if you never have a <tei:term>solo</tei:term>.
                  </tei:l><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
                  <tei:l>
                     Anyone who does not love wine and singing
                  </tei:l><tei:lb/>
                  <tei:l>
                     Deserves a wife for the whole of his life.
                  </tei:l><tei:lb/>
               </tei:lg>
            </tei:lg></tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0009-se05">Postcard from Mrs. <tei:rs key="entity-000165" type="person">Deutsch<!--[DPe Deutsch, Sofie]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0009-se06"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> The <tei:rs key="entity-002537" type="journal"><tei:title level="j">Frankfurter Zeitung<!--[DT Frankfurter Zeitung]--></tei:title></tei:rs> still full of gaps.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0009-se07"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Odyssey, book X.<tei:ptr corresp="r0009-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:pb n="980"/>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0010">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 10, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-10T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-10">10. VII. 15 </tei:date>Der Regen dauert den ganzen Tag an.  
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab> 
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0010-se01"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs> erhält von der <tei:rs key="entity-004173" type="organization">Steuerbehörde<!--[DIn Steuerbehörde]--></tei:rs> eine Aufforderung Dinge zu bekennen, die am besten <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">doch</tei:add> wohl der Steuerbehörde selbst bekannt sein müss<tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">t</tei:add>en, so z. B. von welcher Steuerbehörde sie im Vorjahr besteuert wurde?! Die<tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">selbe</tei:add> Behörde also, die es getan hat, fragt die Partei darnach, wer es getan hat …!</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0010-se02">Die zuletzt angeschaffte Klassen-Lotterienummer zieht ein Viertel von 120 Kronen. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />   </tei:seg>       
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0010-se03"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Antwort an die <tei:rs key="entity-004173" type="organization">Steuerbehörde<!--[DIn Steuerbehörde]--></tei:rs> <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">recom.</tei:add>.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0010-se04"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> An <tei:rs key="entity-000599" type="person">Mittelmann<!--[DPe Mittelmann, Aaron]--></tei:rs> 20 Kronen <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">recom.</tei:add> 
                  <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>         
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0010-se05"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Karte an <tei:rs key="entity-000773" type="person">Mama<!--[DPe Schenker, Julia]--></tei:rs> von <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0010-se06"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Recommandiertes Schreiben an das Post-Zeitungsamt mit Reklamation der verlorengegangenen Nummern <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">der <tei:rs key="entity-002537" type="journal"><tei:title>Frkf. Ztg<!--[DT Frankfurter Zeitung]--></tei:title></tei:rs></tei:add>. 
                  <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>         
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0010-se07"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Unser Hotelier rechnet anständigerweise, trotz so schönen Zimmern u. guter Verpflegung, den in diesen Zeitläuften wirklich bescheidenen Preis von 9 Kronen.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-10">July 10, 1915.</tei:date> The rain continues for the whole day.  
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0010-se01"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs> receives a request from the <tei:rs key="entity-004173" type="organization">tax authorities<!--[DIn Steuerbehörde]--></tei:rs> to acknowledge things that the tax authorities themselves must surely know best, thus for example from which tax authority she was taxed the previous year?! The same authority, then, that had done this asks the person concerned who had done it … !</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0010-se02">The most recently purchased lottery ticket wins a quarter of 120 Kronen. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>         
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0010-se03"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Reply to the <tei:rs key="entity-004173" type="organization">tax authorities<!--[DIn Steuerbehörde]--></tei:rs>, by registered letter.</tei:seg>  
               <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0010-se04"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> To <tei:rs key="entity-000599" type="person">Mittelmann<!--[DPe Mittelmann, Aaron]--></tei:rs>, 20 Kronen by registered letter. 
                  <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>         
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0010-se05"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Postcard to <tei:rs key="entity-000773" type="person">Mama<!--[DPe Schenker, Julia]--></tei:rs>, written by <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg>  
               <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0010-se06"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Registered letter to the postal news agency with claim for the lost issues of the <tei:rs key="entity-002537" type="journal"><tei:title level="j">Frankfurter Zeitung<!--[DT Frankfurter Zeitung]--></tei:title></tei:rs>. 
                  <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />  </tei:seg>        
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0010-se07"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Our hotelier calculates, in spite of such beautiful rooms and good provisions, the price of 9 Kronen, which is truly modest in these times.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0011">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 11, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-11T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-11">11. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0011-se01">Die Morgennebel verlieren sich allmälig, so daß wir endlich <tei:subst><tei:del rend="alternative" hand="#HS">in direkte</tei:del> <tei:add place="inline" hand="#HS">direkt in</tei:add></tei:subst> Beziehung zum Himmel treten können. Ein Wind<tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">stoß</tei:add> ruft uns zum Fenster förmlich hinein, ihm zu folgen; wir tun<tei:subst><tei:add place="inline" hand="#HS">’s</tei:add> <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">es</tei:del></tei:subst> u. wandern die Arlberg<!--[DPl Arlberg]-->straße hinauf. Majestätisch schaltet der Wind im Freien u. leitet uns – gleichsam ein Priester Gottes – zur tiefsten Andacht an.</tei:seg>
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0011-se02">Nachmittags wandern wir zum zweitenmal hinaus, immer noch vom Wind umstürmt, u. seiner Stimmung untertan. Dabei ergehen wir uns in den Schönheiten der <tei:rs key="entity-000294" type="person">Goethe<!--[DPe Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von]--></tei:rs>’schen &#8222;Sprüche in Prosa&#8220;, Kunst, I u. II,
               <tei:note xml:id="r0011-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl>Johann Wolfgang von Goethe, <tei:rs type="work"><tei:title level="s">Sprüche in Prosa</tei:title></tei:rs>, ed. Gustav von Loeper (= Goethe's Werke 19; Berlin: Gustav Hempel, 1870), pp. 137–146 (Kunst, Aphorismen, 1. und 2. Abteilung).</tei:bibl></tei:note>
               mit andächtiger Begierde lauschend, was das <tei:term>Genie</tei:term>, <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">sozusagen</tei:add> als heiliger Wind der Kultur, <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">zu uns</tei:del> spricht, um uns zum Höchsten emporzuführen.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0011-se03">Ob nicht auch der Wind für den menschlichen Kopf ähnliche Folgen zeitigt, wie das Meer? Wie hier die Seekrankheit Ausdruck gibt dem Gefühl der Unsicherheit des Bodens, ebenso scheint im Ocean des Windes der menschliche Kopf die Sicherheit der Stellung zu verlieren, wovon nun die beunruhigten Nerven in eigener Weise vermelden.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:pb n="981"/>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-11">11. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0011-se01">The morning mists gradually clear, so that we are finally able to come into direct contact with the sky. A gust of wind verily summons us to the window and asks us to follow it. We do this and walk up the Arlberg<!--[DPl Arlberg]--> Road. The wind switches direction majestically in the open air and leads us, almost like a priest of God, into deepest devotion.         </tei:seg>
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0011-se02">In the afternoon we take another walk, always buffeted by the wind and subject to its mood. Along the way we indulge in the beauties of <tei:rs key="entity-000294" type="person">Goethe<!--[DPe Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von]--></tei:rs>'s Maxims and Reflections on art, chapters 1 and 2,<tei:ptr corresp="r0011-fn01" type="footnote"/> listening with devotion to what the <tei:term>genius</tei:term>, as a kind of sacred wind of culture, is saying in order to lead us up to the highest point.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0011-se03">Does not the wind, like the sea, also bring about similar consequences for the human head? As seasickness gives expression to the feeling of the uncertainty of the ground, likewise the human head seems, in the ocean of the wind, to lose its secure orientation, something which our unsettled nerves now report in their own way.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:pb n="981"/>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0012">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 11, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-11T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-11">11. VII. 15 </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab> 
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0012-se01">Auf der Straße treffen wir auch die jüngsten Kinder <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">an,</tei:add> Feldgeräte tragend, ja sogar einen Dreijährigen, der, wie <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs> sagt, eine Heugabel &#8222;schultert&#8220;, <tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">D</tei:del><tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#HS">d</tei:add></tei:subst>as erste, <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">&#8222;jüngste</tei:add> Aufgebot<tei:add place="inline" hand="#HS">&#8220;</tei:add> der <tei:rs key="entity-002334" type="place">Tirol<!--[DPl Tirol]--></tei:rs>er (gegenüber dem in aller Welt gepriesenen &#8222;letzten&#8220;, das so oft von Malern verewigt wurde).</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0012-se02">Von Frau <tei:rs key="entity-000136" type="person">Colbert<!--[DPe Colbert, Toni]--></tei:rs> das Juni-Honorar erhalten, <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#HS">–</tei:del> wodurch mir viel Unannehmlichkeit erspart bleibt.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0012-se03"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> An den <tei:rs key="entity-002453" type="organization">Bankverein<!--[DIn Bankverein]--></tei:rs> 30 Kronen zur Bestreitung der 3. Ziehung.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0012-se04"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> An <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Fl.<!--[DPe Violin, Moriz]--></tei:rs>, den Lotterie-Gewinn meldend. </tei:seg>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0012-se05">Die Lusitania-Note <tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place">Deutschland<!--[DPl Germany]--></tei:rs>s an <tei:rs key="entity-002510" type="place">Amerika<!--[DPl America]--></tei:rs> scheint denn doch zu zahm.
               <tei:note xml:id="r0012-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:rs type="work"><tei:title level="a">Friedlicher Grundton in der deutschen Note. Der sichtbare Wunsch nach einem Ausgleich,</tei:title></tei:rs> <tei:rs type="work"><tei:title level="j">Neue Freie Presse</tei:title></tei:rs>, No. 18276, July 10, 1915, evening edition, p. 1. </tei:bibl>On 7 May 1915 a German submarine torpedoed and sank the RMS Lusitania, a British ocean liner en route from New York to Liverpool. While most of those lost in the sinking were British or Canadian, the loss of 128 Americans in the disaster outraged many in the USA. President Woodrow Wilson sent two official notes of protest to Germany in which he insisted the German government apologize for the sinking, compensate U.S. victims, and promise to avoid any similar occurrence in the future.</tei:note>
               Indessen mag die deutsche Regierung Gründe haben, weshalb sie, den frechen amerikanischen Ton ignorierend, immer wieder zur Waffe der Vornehmheit greift. Sehr geschickt schien mir die Waffe der <tei:add place="inline" hand="#HS">&#8222;</tei:add>Humanität<tei:supplied reason="syntax">&#8220;</tei:supplied> <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">verwendet</tei:add>, womit die Note die amerikanische aufs trefflichste parodiert. In der Tat gestaltet sich jene im Laufe des Krieges allmälig gleichsam zu einer Anrufung der Muse, wie in <tei:rs key="entity-006433" type="person">Homer<!--[DPe Homer]--></tei:rs>s Gedicht, aber mehr als eine poetische Wendung war sie tatsächlich ja niemals. So konnte sich auch die deutsche Note eine solche Anrufung der Muse leisten, um gewissermaßen zu sagen, daß <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">auch</tei:add> sie darin mit <tei:rs key="entity-002510" type="place">Amerika<!--[DPl America]--></tei:rs> ganz al pari stehe. Ob aber der amerikanische Krämer die Parodie begreifen wird, ist eher zu verneinen; denn wahrscheinlich begreift er die poetische Lüge nur, sofern er sie selbst ausspricht. Das erfreulichste Resultat der Note bleibt immerhin, daß auf den Unterseebootkrieg für keinen Fall verzichtet wird. Und so wird, fürchte ich, die viel angerufene Muse noch vielemale citiert werden können.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-11">July 11, 1915. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0012-se01">Along the road we also encounter the youngest children, carrying farm implements, among them even a three-year-old who, as <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs> says, "shoulders" a pitchfork. The first, "latest contingent" of <tei:rs key="entity-002334" type="place">Tyrol<!--[DPl Tirol]--></tei:rs>eans (as opposed to "last" in the whole world, which was so often immortalized by painters).</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0012-se02">From Mrs. <tei:rs key="entity-000136" type="person">Colbert<!--[DPe Colbert, Toni]--></tei:rs>, the lesson fee for June received, by which I am spared much unpleasantness</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0012-se03"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> To the <tei:rs key="entity-002453" type="organization">Bankverein<!--[DIn Bankverein]--></tei:rs>, 30 Kronen to match the third withdrawal.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0012-se04"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> To <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Floriz<!--[DPe Violin, Moriz]--></tei:rs>, reporting the lottery win. </tei:seg>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0012-se05"><tei:rs key="entity-002482" type="place">Germany<!--[DPl Germany]--></tei:rs>'s note to <tei:rs key="entity-002510" type="place">America<!--[DPl America]--></tei:rs> concerning the Lusitania seems in fact too tame.<tei:ptr corresp="r0012-fn01" type="footnote"/> Nonetheless the German government may have good reasons to ignore the defiant tone of voice of the Americans and stick to the weapon of politeness. The weapon of "humanity" seemed to be used very effectively, by which the American note is most trenchantly parodied. In fact, the former, in the course of the work, is gradually turning into a kind of invocation to the muse, as in <tei:rs key="entity-006433" type="person">Homer<!--[DPe Homer]--></tei:rs>'s epic, but it was never actually more than a poetic expression. Thus the German note, too, could permit itself such an appeal to the muse, in order somehow to say that in this respect they too are on a par with <tei:rs key="entity-002510" type="place">America<!--[DPl America]--></tei:rs>. It is rather unlikely, however, that the American businessman will understand the parody; for he probably understands the political lie only insofar as he himself utters it. The most gratifying result of the note still remains that the submarine warfare will on no circumstances be suspended. And so I fear that the much invoked muse will still be quoted many times.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0013">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 12, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-12T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-12">12. </tei:date>Noch immer starker Wind bei schönem Wetter.  
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0013-se01"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Von <tei:rs key="entity-000107" type="person">Brünauer<!--[DPe Brünauer, Robert]--></tei:rs> langt das Juni-Honorar an.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0013-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Karte von <tei:rs key="entity-000399" type="person">Hupka<!--[DPe Hupka, Felix]--></tei:rs> aus <tei:rs key="entity-007716" type="place">Heimburg<!--[DPl Heimburg]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0013-se03"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Brief an Frau <tei:rs key="entity-000136" type="person">Colbert<!--[DPe Colbert, Toni]--></tei:rs> mit Dank u. s. w.  </tei:seg>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0013-se04"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Karte an <tei:rs key="entity-007692" type="organization">Steinkeller<!--[DIn Steinkeller]--></tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-002310" type="place">Bozen<!--[DPl Bozen]--></tei:rs>, wegen Obstes.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0013-se05"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Ansichtskarte an <tei:rs key="entity-000773" type="person">Mama<!--[DPe Schenker, Julia]--></tei:rs>, Frau <tei:rs key="entity-000165" type="person">Deutsch<!--[DPe Deutsch, Sofie]--></tei:rs>, Frl. <tei:rs key="entity-000201" type="person">Elias<!--[DPe Elias, Angelika]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0013-se06"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Fortsetzung der &#8222;Sprüche in Prosa&#8220;, Kunst, III–IV.
               <tei:note xml:id="r0013-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl>Johann Wolfgang von Goethe, <tei:rs type="work"><tei:title level="s">Sprüche in Prosa</tei:title></tei:rs>, ed. Gustav von Loeper (= Goethe's Werke 19; Berlin: Gustav Hempel, 1870), pp. 147–152 (Kunst, Aphorismen, 3. und 4. Abteilung).</tei:bibl></tei:note></tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:pb n="982"/> 
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-12">12. </tei:date>Still a strong wind in fair weather.  
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0013-se01"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> From <tei:rs key="entity-000107" type="person">Brünauer<!--[DPe Brünauer, Robert]--></tei:rs>, the June lesson fee arrives.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0013-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Postcard from <tei:rs key="entity-000399" type="person">Hupka<!--[DPe Hupka, Felix]--></tei:rs> from <tei:rs key="entity-007716" type="place">Heimburg<!--[DPl Heimburg]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0013-se03"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Letter to Mrs. <tei:rs key="entity-000136" type="person">Colbert<!--[DPe Colbert, Toni]--></tei:rs> with thanks, etc.  </tei:seg>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0013-se04"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Postcard to <tei:rs key="entity-007692" type="organization">Steinkeller<!--[DIn Steinkeller]--></tei:rs> in <tei:rs key="entity-002310" type="place">Bozen<!--[DPl Bozen]--></tei:rs>, on account of fruit.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0013-se05"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Postcards to <tei:rs key="entity-000773" type="person">Mama<!--[DPe Schenker, Julia]--></tei:rs>, Mrs. <tei:rs key="entity-000165" type="person">Deutsch<!--[DPe Deutsch, Sofie]--></tei:rs>, Miss <tei:rs key="entity-000201" type="person">Elias<!--[DPe Elias, Angelika]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0013-se06"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Continuation of Maxims and Reflections on art, chapters 3–4.<tei:ptr corresp="r0013-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:pb n="982"/> 
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0014">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 13, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-13T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-13">13. VII. 15 </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0014-se01">Früh bei schönem Wetter ins Steißbachtal<!--[DPl Steißbachtal]--> <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#HS">,</tei:del> mit der Absicht<tei:supplied reason="syntax">,</tei:supplied> eventuell zur Galzig<!--[DPl Galzig]-->-Spitze zu gehen. Schon in der ersten Viertelstunde werden wir unmutig darüber, daß wir das Wasser aus dem Aug’ u. Ohr verlieren, während die Karte, wie wir glaubten, den Bach uns als steten Begleiter versprach. Je weiter wir von diesem abbiegen mußten, desto mehr gerieten wir auch in Besorgnis, ob wir nicht über einen überflüssigen Umweg allzu viel Zeit verlieren. Schließlich landeten wir doch auf den Weg zur Ulmerhütte<!--[DPl Ulmer Hütte]-->, ohne aber recht zu wissen, ob auch ins Steißbachtal<!--[DPl Steißbachtal]--> nur dieser Weg allein führe. Erkundigungen sagten immer wieder zugunsten des Weges aus, den wir <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">gerade</tei:add> giengen; sie konnten uns aber nicht beruhigen. Endlich kamen wir an eine Stelle, deren wir uns schon von früher her erinnerten u. <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">wir</tei:add> begannen  einzusehen, daß der Weg ins Steißbachtal<!--[DPl Steißbachtal]--> offenbar identisch ist mit dem zur Ulmerhütte u. daß es keinen andern gibt, der etwa entlang des Baches selbst führ<tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">t</tei:del><tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#HS">en</tei:add></tei:subst> <tei:add place="inline" hand="#HS">würde</tei:add>.</tei:seg> 
		          </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0014-se02">Wir überschritten ein kleines Schneefeld, in dessen Nähe wir noch den ersten Frühlingszauber schauen durften, um auf den Arlensattel<!--[DPl Arlensattel]--> zu kommen. Als wir aber nicht mehr weit davon waren, zogen plötzlich Wolken auf u. da schien es uns opportuner, den Rückweg abzutreten, zumal <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs> vorhatte, einige Geschenke des Frühlings mitzunehmen, Crocus, <tei:sic>Annemonen</tei:sic>, Primeln, Enzian, Dotterblumen, Knabenkraut, Glockenblumen u. verschiedene andere, unbekannte <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">Blumen</tei:add>. Während wir da<tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">ß</tei:del><tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#HS">s</tei:add></tei:subst> Frühstück – bereits in der Waldzone – aßen, gingen die ersten Regentropfen nieder, so daß wir uns unseres Entschlußes nur erfreuen konnten. Der Regen war indessen rücksichtsvoll genug u. ließ uns endlich heil nachhause kommen. Oberhalb <tei:rs key="entity-002279" type="place">St. Anton<!--[DPl St. Anton am Arlberg]--></tei:rs>, im sogenannten Moos, frugen wir wieder nach dem anderen Weg ins Steißbachtal<!--[DPl Steißbachtal]--> u. erhielten die Auskunft, es gäbe zwar einen solchen, doch sei er viel weniger gut als der sonst begangene. Außerdem lehrte uns ein Rückblick auf den zurückgelegten Weg, daß wir der Karte Unrecht getan u. wir begriffen, daß uns lediglich eine Erinnerung aus früherer Zeit täuschende Bilder vorgegaukelt, um derenthalb wir der Karte mißtrauten u. in der Folge in die eigentümliche Berg-Nervo- <tei:pb n="983"/> sität gerieten. Einige Bruchstücke der Erinnerung waren es insbesondere, die wir in falscher Weise zu einem Weg addierten, u. dies war der eigentliche Grund, weshalb wir gegen den gegenwärtig begangenen uns von Herzen auflehnten. Unter <tei:subst><tei:del rend="alternative" hand="#HS">anderem</tei:del> <tei:add place="inline" hand="#HS">anderen</tei:add></tei:subst> frugen wir einen kleinen Buben; anfangs scheu, trat er über <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs>s deutliche Aufforderung nahe zu uns heran, u. da konnten wir zwei wunderbare schwarze Augen bewundern, die im Gesicht wirkten, wie große Enziane in der Wiese.</tei:seg> 
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0014-se03">Nachmittags überrascht uns plötzlich Sturm, dem zwei Fensterscheiben in meinem Zimmer zum Opfer fallen. Der Sturm bringt nur kurzen Regen.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0014-se04"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Während des Abendessen melden sich vereinzelte Donner u. des nachts bemächtigt sich der Natur ein starker Aufruhr mit Donner u. starkem, dauernden Regen, so daß wir darüber nur wenig zum Schlaf kommen.</tei:seg>  
                  <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0014-se05"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Sprüche V.
                     <tei:note xml:id="r0014-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl>Johann Wolfgang von Goethe, <tei:rs type="work"><tei:title level="s">Sprüche in Prosa</tei:title></tei:rs>, ed. Gustav von Loeper (= Goethe's Werke 19; Berlin: Gustav Hempel, 1870), pp. 152–158 (Kunst, Aphorismen, 5. Abteilung)</tei:bibl>. Schenker had read chapters 3 and 4 the previous day (see diary entry for July 12, 1915).</tei:note>
                     <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />  </tei:seg>        
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0014-se06"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Notizen zu <tei:rs key="entity-000620" type="person">Nagel<!--[DPe Nagel, Wilibald]--></tei:rs> zuende.
               <tei:note xml:id="r0014-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">For the section on the secondary literature in Erläuterungsausgabe of Beethoven's <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title>Op. 111<!--[DW Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 111]--></tei:title></tei:rs> (Vienna: Universal Edition, 1916).</tei:note></tei:seg> 
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-13">July 13, 1915. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0014-se01">Early, in good weather, to the Steißbachtal<!--[DPl Steißbachtal]--> with the possible intention of going to the top of the Galzig<!--[DPl Galzig]-->. Even in the first quarter of an hour, we become uneasy about having lost the sight and sound of the water, whereas – so we believe – the map promised that the brook would be our constant companion. The further we must have turned away from it, the more we became concerned that we might be losing far too much time on an unnecessary detour. Yet in the end, we did land on the path to the Ulmerhütte<!--[DPl Ulmer Hütte]-->, but without quite knowing whether this was the only path that led into the Steißbachtal<!--[DPl Steißbachtal]-->. Enquiries always spoke in favor of the path that we had just taken; but they could not calm us. Finally we came to a place which we remembered from earlier times; and we began to realize that the path through the Steißbachtal<!--[DPl Steißbachtal]--> was evidently identical to the one to the Ulmerhütte and that there was no other path, say, that would have followed the course of the brook itself.</tei:seg>
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0014-se02">We crossed a small snow field, in whose vicinity we were still able to see the first magic of spring, in order to reach the Arlensattel<!--[DPl Arlensattel]-->. When we were not very far from it, clouds suddenly gathered; and it seemed more opportune for us to turn back, especially as <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs> was planning to take a few presents of spring with her: crocuses, anemones, primroses, gentians, buttercups, alpine orchids, bell flowers and various other unknown flowers. As we were eating our breakfast – already in the forested area – the first drops of rain began to fall, so that we could only be pleased with our decision. The rain was, however, sufficiently polite and we were in the end able to return home safe and sound. Above <tei:rs key="entity-002279" type="place">St. Anton<!--[DPl St. Anton am Arlberg]--></tei:rs>, in the so-called mossy area, we enquired again about the other path into the Steißbachtal<!--[DPl Steißbachtal]--> and received the information that there was indeed another, but it was not nearly as good as the one normally taken. Moreover, a retrospective view of the path we had taken taught us that we did the map an injustice; and we understood that simply a recollection from an earlier time led us to deceptive impressions, on account of which we mistrusted the map and consequently were subjected to that peculiar mountaineering nervousness. <tei:pb n="983"/> A few fragments of memory, in particular, we mistakenly added to a path; and this was the actual reason why we had revolted in our hearts against the one we took this time. Among others, we asked a small boy; at first shy, he approached us thanks to <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs>'s clear invitation; and we could admire two wonderful black eyes which adorned his face like great gentians in the meadow.</tei:seg> 
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0014-se03">In the afternoon, a sudden storm surprises us, to which two panes of glass in my room fall victim. The storm brings with it only brief rainfall.</tei:seg> 
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0014-se04"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> During supper, isolated thunderclaps are heard; and in the night a powerful impulse takes hold of Nature with thunder and heavy, persistent rain, so that we are able to get only a little sleep.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0014-se05"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Maxims and Reflections, chapter V.<tei:ptr corresp="r0014-fn01" type="footnote"/> 
                     <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />  </tei:seg>        </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0014-se06"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Notes on <tei:rs key="entity-000620" type="person">Nagel<!--[DPe Nagel, Wilibald]--></tei:rs> finished.<tei:ptr corresp="r0014-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:seg> 
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0015">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 14, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-14T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-14">14. VII. 15 </tei:date>Bedeckt u. regnerisch.  
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0015-se01"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Ein wenig Klavier gespielt.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0015-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Nachmittags heitert es sich auf, so daß wir einen kleinen Weg nach <tei:rs key="entity-007713" type="place">St. Jakob<!--[DPl St. Jakob am Arlberg]--></tei:rs> machen können.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0015-se03"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> &#8222;Sprüche in Prosa&#8220;, Kunst VI zuende.
               <tei:note xml:id="r0015-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl>Johann Wolfgang von Goethe, <tei:rs type="work"><tei:title level="s">Sprüche in Prosa</tei:title></tei:rs>, ed. Gustav von Loeper (= Goethe's Werke 19; Berlin: Gustav Hempel, 1870), pp. 158–166 (Kunst, Aphorismen, 6. Abteilung).</tei:bibl></tei:note></tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0015-se04">Natur bedeutet ewigen Fluss der Geschlechter, Individuen, Pflanzen u. s. w.; sie kennt keine Isolierung des Einzelindividuums. Es heißt daher der Natur widersprechen, wenn das Einzelne aus dem Fluß herausgegriffen, abgeschlossen, ausgeschnitten (Bild) wird. Dieses Geschäft besorgt die Kunst, die somit von vornherein künstlich ist. Dieses Verhältnis der Kunst zur Natur erfährt noch keine Verschiebung dadurch, daß die Kunst auf anderem als in der Natur möglichem Wege die Fortpflanzung des isolierten Einzelnen besorgt. Diese Fortpflanzung ist eine geistige, ein Ersatz für das verlorengegangenen Milieu der <tei:pb n="984"/> Natur u. bedeutet eine Verewigung selbst der Natur, der Landschaft u. s. f. – Gegen <tei:rs key="entity-000294" type="person">Goethe<!--[DPe Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von]--></tei:rs>s irrige Meinung bezüglich der Kunst.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0015-se05">Auf dem <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#JS">Weg?</tei:add> von <tei:rs key="entity-007713" type="place">St. Jakob<!--[DPl St. Jakob am Arlberg]--></tei:rs> sehen wir, wie auf einem Wägelchen ein Verwundeter ins Dorf gebracht wird u. knüpfen daran allerlei Gedanken des Mitleids, gewidmet dem Vaterland im Großen, der Familie im Kleinen u. dem armen Betroffenen. Nachträglich stellt sich heraus, daß der Soldat nicht etwa auf dem Schlachtfelde, sondern bei Ausübung des Sicherheitsdienstes in unserer Nähe eine Verletzung sich zugezogen habe. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />  </tei:seg>        
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0015-se06"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Abends wolkenlos u. kühl, <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">7</tei:del> zwischen 7 u. <tei:measure type="temperature" unit="celsius">8°</tei:measure>!</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0015-se07">Immer drohender wird die Frage, ob auch <tei:rs key="entity-005391" type="place">Rumänien<!--[DPl Romania]--></tei:rs> u. <tei:rs key="entity-002575" type="place">Bulgarien<!--[DPl Bulgaria]--></tei:rs> wider die Zentralmächte eingreifen werden!</tei:seg> 
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0015-se08">Karten von <tei:rs key="entity-000201" type="person">Elias<!--[DPe Elias, Angelika]--></tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse<!--[DPe Weisse, Hans]--></tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000319" type="person">Sophie<!--[DPe Guttmann, Sophie]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-14">July 14, 1915.</tei:date> Cloudy and rainy.  
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0015-se01"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> I play the piano a little.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0015-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> In the afternoon, the weather clears up, so that we can take a short walk to <tei:rs key="entity-007713" type="place">St. Jakob<!--[DPl St. Jakob am Arlberg]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0015-se03"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Maxims and Reflections, chapter 6, Art, finished.<tei:ptr corresp="r0015-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0015-se04">Nature means the perpetual flux of the generations, individuals, plants, and so on; it knows no isolation of the individual being. It is thus a contradiction against Nature if the individual is singled out from the flow, closed off, cut off (as a picture). This is the occupation of art, which is thus artificial from the outset. This relationship of art to Nature still does not encounter a postponement, since art takes care of the development of the isolated individual along other paths than those accessible to Nature. This development is an intellectual one, a substitute for the lost milieu of <tei:pb n="984"/> Nature, and signifies an immortalization even of Nature, of landscape, and so on. – This in opposition to <tei:rs key="entity-000294" type="person">Goethe<!--[DPe Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von]--></tei:rs>'s mistaken view of art.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0015-se05">On the way back from <tei:rs key="entity-007713" type="place">St. Jakob<!--[DPl St. Jakob am Arlberg]--></tei:rs>, we see that a wounded man is being brought to the village on a small wagon, and we attach all manner of sympathetic thoughts, dedicated to the fatherland in the large, to his family in the small, and to the poor person concerned. Subsequently we learn that the soldier received an injury not on the battlefield but in carrying out his security duty in our vicinity. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>         
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0015-se06"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> In the evening, cloudless and cool, between 7 and <tei:measure type="temperature" unit="celsius">8°</tei:measure>!</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0015-se07">The threat becomes ever greater that <tei:rs key="entity-005391" type="place">Rumania<!--[DPl Romania]--></tei:rs> and <tei:rs key="entity-002575" type="place">Bulgaria<!--[DPl Bulgaria]--></tei:rs> might take up arms against the Central Powers!</tei:seg> 
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0015-se08">Postcards from <tei:rs key="entity-000201" type="person">Elias<!--[DPe Elias, Angelika]--></tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000951" type="person">Weisse<!--[DPe Weisse, Hans]--></tei:rs>, <tei:rs key="entity-000319" type="person">Sophie<!--[DPe Guttmann, Sophie]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0016">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 15, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-15T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-15">15. VII. 15 </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0016-se01">Bei wolkenlosen Himmel nach <tei:rs key="entity-007713" type="place">St. Jakob<!--[DPl St. Jakob am Arlberg]--></tei:rs> (oberen Weg), dann bis <tei:rs key="entity-007715" type="place">Pettneu<!--[DPl Pettneu am Arlberg]--></tei:rs>, 4½ Stunden. Dazwischen Lektüre des <tei:rs key="entity-006433" type="person">Homer<!--[DPe Homer]--></tei:rs> eingestreut.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0016-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Auf dem Wege finden wir eine alleinstehende vollkommene Distel, sowie eine ebenfalls alleinstehende Lilie. Der Zauber der Vollkommenheit dieser Naturgeschöpfe ergreift uns u. wir lassen die Ergriffenheit walten, ohne vor der Natur etwaige Gesichtspunkte der Kunst in den Vordergrund zu schieben. Gewiss, wollte ein Maler dieser Gegenstände der Natur für Kunstzwecke habhaft werden, dann müßte er den eigenen Forderungen der Kunst gemäß alles dazu tun, um die Isolierung durchzuführen, <tei:pb n="985"/> schon aus dem Grunde, weil er außerstande wäre, den wahren Sachverhalt eines alleinstehenden Prachtexemplares auszudrücken. Wie könnte er denn eine so große Wiese aufrollen<tei:add place="inline" hand="#HS">,</tei:add> <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">nur</tei:del> <tei:subst><tei:del rend="alternative" hand="#HS">um</tei:del> <tei:add place="inline" hand="#HS">und</tei:add></tei:subst> <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">zu</tei:del> zeigen <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">wollen</tei:add>, daß die schöne Blume in ihrer Vollkommenheit hier sozusagen <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">nur</tei:add> Zufall gewesen, u. wozu sollte er es denn <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">auch</tei:add> <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">tun wollen</tei:del>, wenn sein <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">eigenes</tei:add> Geschäft gar nicht mit dem der Natur, <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">die</tei:add> solche Zufälle hervor<tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">zu</tei:del>bring<tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">en</tei:del><tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#HS">t</tei:add></tei:subst>, parallel läuft. Was im Fluss der Dinge allenfalls wie durch einen Plan bestimmt wird, kann in der Kunst, die den Fluß überhaupt nicht darzustellen vermag, ebensowenig <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">wie</tei:add> der dazu gehörende Zufall dar<tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">ge</tei:add>stell<tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">en</tei:del><tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#HS">t</tei:add></tei:subst> <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">werden</tei:add>. <tei:rs key="entity-000294" type="person">Goethe<!--[DPe Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von]--></tei:rs> befindet sich <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">daher</tei:add> im Irrtum, wenn er in den &#8222;Sprüchen in Prosa&#8220; Kunst (No. 752) meint: &#8222;Es steht manches Schöne isoliert in der Welt; doch der Geist ist es, der Verknüpfungen zu entdecken und dadurch Kunstwerke hervorzubringen hat. – Die Blume gewinnt erst ihren Reiz durch das Insekt, das ihr anhängt, durch den Thautropfen, der sie befeuchtet, durch das Gefäß, woraus sie allenfalls ihre letzte Nahrung zieht. Kein Busch, kein Baum, dem man nicht durch die Nachbarschaft eines Felsens, einer Quelle Bedeutung geben, durch eine mäßige, einfache Ferne <tei:sic>größern</tei:sic> Reiz verleihen könnte. So ist es mit menschlichen Figuren und so mit Thieren aller Art beschaffen.&#8220;
               <tei:note xml:id="r0016-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl>Johann Wolfgang von Goethe, <tei:rs type="work"><tei:title level="s">Sprüche in Prosa</tei:title></tei:rs>, ed. Gustav von Loeper (= Goethe's Werke 19; Berlin: Gustav Hempel, 1870), pp. 160–161 (Kunst, Aphorismen, 6. Abteilung).</tei:bibl></tei:note></tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0016-se03">Die Technik menschlichen Auges u. Sehens erklärt <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">uns</tei:add>, weshalb wir auch auf geistigem Gebiete eine Einheit des Gesichtspunktes anstreben: <tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">G</tei:del><tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#HS">g</tei:add></tei:subst>ewissermaßen vereinigen sich <tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">auch</tei:del> <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">auch</tei:add></tei:subst> auf einer geistigen Netzhaut geistige Linien in einem focus. <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">Dieses</tei:del> <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">Daher</tei:add> ist der menschliche Drang zur <tei:term>Synthese</tei:term>, <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">gleichsam</tei:add> ein<tei:add place="inline" hand="#HS">e</tei:add> organische<tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">s</tei:del> <tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">Bedürfnis</tei:del> <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">Funktion</tei:add></tei:subst>, wie die <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">Funktion</tei:del> des Sehens.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0016-se04">Antwort von <tei:rs key="entity-000738" type="person">Rothberger<!--[DPe Rothberger, Alfred]--></tei:rs> u. <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Floriz<!--[DPe Violin, Moriz]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0016-se05"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Gegen Abend Regen.  </tei:seg>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0016-se06"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Im Hotel taucht ein <tei:rs key="entity-000000" type="003995">Braunschweig<!--[DPl Braunschweig]--></tei:rs>er Professor auf, der zu unserem Erstaunen auch einige Orientierung in musikalischen Dingen zeigt. Freilich, was er da aus dem Musikleben in <tei:rs key="entity-000000" type="003995">Braunschweig<!--[DPl Braunschweig]--></tei:rs> erzählt, macht weder dieses noch den Erzähler interessant. Der bescheidene Horizont des Professors <tei:pb n="986"/> gestattet mir nicht, schärfer herauszutreten, u. ich lasse es daher nur bei einigen Andeutungen über meine Tätigkeit bewenden.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-15">July 15, 1915. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0016-se01">Under a cloudless sky, to <tei:rs key="entity-007713" type="place">St. Jakob<!--[DPl St. Jakob am Arlberg]--></tei:rs> (upper path), then as far as <tei:rs key="entity-007715" type="place">Pettneu<!--[DPl Pettneu am Arlberg]--></tei:rs>, 4½ hours. In between, reading of <tei:rs key="entity-006433" type="person">Homer<!--[DPe Homer]--></tei:rs> interspersed.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0016-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Along the way we find a single, fully grown thistle, likewise a single lily. The magic of the perfection of these creatures of Nature moves us, and we let the emotion take its course, without letting any possible points of view about art to push into the foreground to obscure Nature. For sure, if a painter wished to take possession of these things of Nature for artistic purposes, then he would have to do everything necessary with respect to the special requirements of art itself in order to get at the heart <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of its artistic qualities</tei:supplied>, <tei:pb n="985"/> for the very reason that he is not in a position to express the true facts of an splendid example in isolation. How could he, then, unfurl such a great meadow and want to show that the beautiful blower was, in its perfection, only a chance occurrence? And why should he do it anyway, when his own occupation does not run in parallel with Nature, which throws up such chance occurrences? That which, in the course of events, is at best determined by a plan can just as little be represented in art, which is utterly incapable of portraying that course. <tei:rs key="entity-000294" type="person">Goethe<!--[DPe Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von]--></tei:rs> is thus mistaken when, in his Maxims and Reflections (No. 752), he says: "There is much in the world that is beautiful in isolation: but it is the intellect whose purpose it is to discover the connections and thus produce works of art. – The flower gains its attractiveness only from the insect that clings to it, from the dewdrops that moisten it, by the vessel from which at best it gains its last nourishment. There is no bush, no tree to which one is unable to give meaning from the vicinity of a rock or stream, or to confer greater charm from a modest, simply distance. This applies to human figures, and to animals of every kind."<tei:ptr corresp="r0016-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0016-se03">The technique of the human eye, and of seeing, explains to us why we strive for a unified point of view even in intellectual fields: to a certain extent, intellectual lines combine in a focus on an intellectual retina. For this reason humans strive for <tei:term>synthesis</tei:term> almost as an organic function, like the function of sight.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0016-se04">Replies from <tei:rs key="entity-000738" type="person">Rothberger<!--[DPe Rothberger, Alfred]--></tei:rs> and <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Floriz<!--[DPe Violin, Moriz]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0016-se05"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Towards evening, rain.  </tei:seg>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0016-se06"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> In the hotel, a professor from <tei:rs key="entity-000000" type="003995">Braunschweig<!--[DPl Braunschweig]--></tei:rs> appears who, to our astonishment, shows some orientation in musical matters. Admittedly, what he says about musical life in <tei:rs key="entity-000000" type="003995">Braunschweig<!--[DPl Braunschweig]--></tei:rs> makes neither it, nor him, interesting. The professor's limited horizon <tei:pb n="986"/> prevents me from venturing more critically, and so I leave the matter with just a few remarks about my occupation.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0017">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 16, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-16T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-16">16. VII. 15 </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0017-se01">Des morgens ist das Wetter noch nicht ausgesprochen; daher wird zunächst <tei:rs key="entity-002743" type="person">Schindler<!--[DPe Schindler, Anton Felix]--></tei:rs> abgefertigt
               <tei:note xml:id="r0017-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">For his Erläuterungsausgabe of Beethoven's <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title>Op. 111<!--[DW Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 111]--></tei:title></tei:rs> (Vienna: Universal Edition, 1916).</tei:note>
               u. erst gegen ½11<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> begeben wir uns auf den Eugen-Weg<!--[DPl Erzherzog-Eugen-Weg]--> (bis ½1<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi>). 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>         
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0017-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Brief von <tei:rs key="entity-000136" type="person">Colbert<!--[DPe Colbert, Toni]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg>  
               <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0017-se03"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Brief von <tei:rs key="entity-000599" type="person">Mittelmann<!--[DPe Mittelmann, Aaron]--></tei:rs> mit Dank. 
                  <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>         
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0017-se04"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Da am Nachmittag das Wetter immer schöner, frischer u. anregender wurde, versuchen wir nächste u. allernächste Wege, z. B. die <tei:rs key="entity-007738" type="person">Cecconi<!--[DPe Ceconi, Giacomo]--></tei:rs>-Höhe unserem Bewußtsein aufs Neue einzuprägen u. so die Erinnerungsbilder zu korrigieren. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>         
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0017-se05"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Auf der Suche nach der Zeitung verlieren wir <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">auch</tei:del> einige Zeit.</tei:seg> 
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> 
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0017-se06"><tei:rs key="entity-002506" type="place">Oesterreich<!--[DPl Austria]--></tei:rs>s Note an <tei:rs key="entity-002510" type="place">Amerika<!--[DPl America]--></tei:rs>;
               <tei:note xml:id="r0017-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:rs type="work"><tei:title level="a">Eine Note der österreichisch-ungarischen Regierung an die Vereinigten Staaten. Gegen die Munitionslieferungen an England,</tei:title></tei:rs> <tei:rs type="work"><tei:title level="j">Neue Freie Presse</tei:title></tei:rs>, No. 18281, July 15, 1915, morning edition, pp. 2-3. </tei:bibl></tei:note>
               ganz vortrefflich im Tonfall. Aber freilich, die Torpedierung der &#8222;Lusitania&#8220;
               <tei:note xml:id="r0017-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">On 7 May 1915 a German submarine torpedoed and sank the RMS Lusitania, a British ocean liner en route from New York to Liverpool. While most of those lost in the sinking were British or Canadian, the loss of 128 Americans in the disaster outraged many in the USA. President Woodrow Wilson sent two official messages of protest to Germany in which he insisted the German government apologize for the sinking, compensate U.S. victims, and promise to avoid any similar occurrence in the future.</tei:note>
               war die wirksam<tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">ste</tei:del><tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#HS">ere</tei:add></tei:subst> Note, der einzige Tonfall, den ein englischer Krämer begreift.</tei:seg> 
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-16">July 16, 1915. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0017-se01">In the morning the weather is still not clear; for this reason, the first task is to complete <tei:rs key="entity-002743" type="person">Schindler<!--[DPe Schindler, Anton Felix]--></tei:rs>,<tei:ptr corresp="r0017-fn01" type="footnote"/> and only towards 10:30 do we take the Eugen-Weg<!--[DPl Erzherzog-Eugen-Weg]--> (until 12:30). 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>         
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0017-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Letter from <tei:rs key="entity-000136" type="person">Colbert<!--[DPe Colbert, Toni]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg>  
               <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0017-se03"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Letter from <tei:rs key="entity-000599" type="person">Mittelmann<!--[DPe Mittelmann, Aaron]--></tei:rs>, with thanks. 
                  <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>         
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0017-se04"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> As the weather in the afternoon is increasingly fair, fresh, and stimulating, we try paths that are close or very close by, for example to imprint anew the <tei:rs key="entity-007738" type="person">Ceconi<!--[DPe Ceconi, Giacomo]--></tei:rs> elevation on our conscience and thus to correct the images of it in our memory. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />  </tei:seg>        
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0017-se05"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> In search of the newspaper, we lose a bit of time.</tei:seg> 
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> 
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0017-se06"><tei:rs key="entity-002506" type="place">Austria<!--[DPl Austria]--></tei:rs>'s note to <tei:rs key="entity-002510" type="place">America<!--[DPl America]--></tei:rs>;<tei:ptr corresp="r0017-fn02" type="footnote"/> thoroughly excellent in tone. Admittedly, however, the torpedoing of the Lusitania<tei:ptr corresp="r0017-fn03" type="footnote"/> was the most effective note, the only tone of voice that the English businessman understands.</tei:seg> 
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0018">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 17, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-17T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-17">17. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0018-se01">Das schöne Wetter verlockt uns, die am <tei:rs key="entity-000576" type="person">Marx<!--[DPe Marx, Adolf Bernhard]--></tei:rs>-<tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title>Abschnitt<!--[DW Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 111]--></tei:title></tei:rs> zu beginnende Arbeit ins Freie zu verlegen u. obwohl uns gegenteilige Erfahrungen <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">bereits öfter</tei:add> zur Genüge gewarnt hatten, versuchen wir doch noch einmal ein passendes Plätzchen zu finden. Indessen hat uns schon der Tau jeden Aufenthalt im Freien, so weit unser Zweck in Frage kam, unmöglich gemacht u. wir kehren daher reuig in die <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">Laube der</tei:add> <tei:sic>Dependençe</tei:sic> zurück, wo nun die Arbeit ad <tei:rs key="entity-000576" type="person">Marx<!--[DPe Marx, Adolf Bernhard]--></tei:rs> beginnt. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>         
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0018-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Mittags setzt Regen ein, so daß ich nachmittags die Arbeit fortsetzen kann. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>         
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0018-se03"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Gegen Abend spiele ich wieder ein wenig Klavier u. freue mich zu bemerken, daß die Finger noch immer dem Geist willig gehorchen.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-17">17. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0018-se01">The fair weather entices us to relocate our initial work on the <tei:rs key="entity-000576" type="person">Marx<!--[DPe Marx, Adolf Bernhard]--></tei:rs> <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title level="m">section<!--[DW Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 111]--></tei:title></tei:rs> out of doors; and even though contrary experiences had warned us often enough, we still try to find a suitable place. However, the dew has made it impossible for us to make a stop outdoors, so far as our purpose is concerned; and we return with regret to the foliage of our residence, where the work on <tei:rs key="entity-000576" type="person">Marx<!--[DPe Marx, Adolf Bernhard]--></tei:rs> now begins. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>         
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0018-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> At midday it begins to rain, so that I am able to continue my work in the afternoon. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />  </tei:seg>        
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0018-se03"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Towards evening, I again play the piano a little; and I am pleased to note that my fingers are still always willing to obey my intellect.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0019">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 18, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-18T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-18">18. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0019-se01">Schwerer sonderbarer Traum: Zu Besuch bei <tei:rs key="entity-000738" type="person">Rothberger<!--[DPe Rothberger, Alfred]--></tei:rs>, der auf d<tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">ie</tei:del><tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#HS">er</tei:add></tei:subst> <tei:rs key="entity-004484" type="place">Hofburg<!--[DPl Hofburg]--></tei:rs>wand Schattenspiele zur Belustigung seiner abziehenden Gäste arrangiert, darunter ganz ergötzlich komische <tei:pb n="987"/> Figuren. Sodann Coulissenwechsel: Eine Façade, ebenfalls nach dem <tei:rs key="entity-004484" type="place">Hofburg<!--[DPl Hofburg]--></tei:rs>modell, zeigt im Mondlicht feinste<tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">n</tei:del> <tei:sic>architektonischen</tei:sic> <tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">Wert</tei:del> <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">Kostbarkeiten</tei:add></tei:subst>. Plötzlich, wie durch das Mondlicht geweckt, lächelt die Kaiserin aus Stein; <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">u.</tei:add> es lächeln <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">auch die</tei:add> Putti <tei:add place="inline" hand="#HS">(</tei:add>nach Art der <tei:rs key="entity-002659" type="person">Raphael<!--[DPe Raphael]--></tei:rs>ischen<tei:add place="inline" hand="#HS">)</tei:add> u. s. f. De<tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">r</tei:del><tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#HS">n</tei:add></tei:subst> Ausdruck des Lächelns <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">war</tei:del> <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">empfinde ich</tei:add> so innig <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">u. überzeugend</tei:add>, daß ich im Träume mich <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">von der Macht der Kunst verneige, ja</tei:add> bis zu Tränen gerührt zeige <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">über die Macht der Kunst</tei:del>.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0019-se02">Den ganzen Tag über Regen, Regen, so daß wir erst gegen Abend eine ¾-stündige Pause benutzen <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">können</tei:add>, um vor das Haus zu treten.</tei:seg>  
               <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0019-se03"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Neuschnee. 
                  <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>         
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0019-se04"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> <tei:rs key="entity-000576" type="person">Marx<!--[DPe Marx, Adolf Bernhard]--></tei:rs> zuende u. <tei:rs key="entity-000520" type="person">Lenz<!--[DPe Lenz, Wilhelm von]--></tei:rs> bis zur <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title>Arietta<!--[DW Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 111]--></tei:title></tei:rs>; wir arbeiten sogar abends nach Tisch.</tei:seg> 
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-18">18. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0019-se01">A serious, strange dream. A visit to <tei:rs key="entity-000738" type="person">Rothberger<!--[DPe Rothberger, Alfred]--></tei:rs>, who arranges a shadow pantomime on the walls of the <tei:rs key="entity-004484" type="place">Hofburg<!--[DPl Hofburg]--></tei:rs> for the amusement of his departing guests, among them thoroughly delightful comic <tei:pb n="987"/> characters. Then a change of scene: a façade, likewise modeled on the <tei:rs key="entity-004484" type="place">Hofburg<!--[DPl Hofburg]--></tei:rs>, reveals the finest architectonic treasures in the moonlight. Suddenly, as if awoken by the moonlight, the empress in stone smiles; and also the cherubs smile (in the manner of <tei:rs key="entity-002659" type="person">Raphael<!--[DPe Raphael]--></tei:rs>, etc.) The expression of the smiling I find so intimate and convincing that, in the dream, I bow down before the power of art, and even show myself moved to tears.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0019-se02">The whole day rain, rain, so that we are only able to take advantage of a three-quarter-hour break to walk around the house.</tei:seg>  
               <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0019-se03"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Fresh snow. 
                  <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0019-se04"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> <tei:rs key="entity-000576" type="person">Marx<!--[DPe Marx, Adolf Bernhard]--></tei:rs> finished, and <tei:rs key="entity-000520" type="person">Lenz<!--[DPe Lenz, Wilhelm von]--></tei:rs> as far as the <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title level="m">Arietta<!--[DW Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 111]--></tei:title></tei:rs>; we work even after the evening meal.</tei:seg> 
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0020">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 19, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-19T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-19">19. VII. 15 </tei:date>Neuschnee noch tiefer zum Tal; kühl, kein Regen.  
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0020-se01"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Gegen Mittag wird das Wetter immer klarer, bestimmter; wir wandern um ¼4<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> nach <tei:rs key="entity-007714" type="place">St. Christof<!--[DPl St. Christoph am Arlberg]--></tei:rs>, empfinden aber hernach u. besonders nachts seltsamerweise nervöse Störungen, die <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">uns</tei:add> umso unerklärlicher sind, als sie bei uns Beiden parallel laufen.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-19">July 19, 1915.</tei:date> Fresh snow even deeper in the valley; cool, no rain.  
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0020-se01"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Towards midday the weather becomes clearer and more stable. At 3:15 we walk to St. Christoph<!--[DPl St. Christoph am Arlberg]-->, but afterwards and especially in the night we strangely feel nervous disorders, which are all the more inexplicable as they run concurrently in the two of us.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0021">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 20, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-20T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-20">20. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0021-se01">Ein Tag, dessen Pracht wohl keine Feder, kein Pinsel, kein Film oder dgl. aus dem großen ewigen Album der Natur herausreißen <tei:subst><tei:del rend="alternative" hand="#HS">kann</tei:del> <tei:add place="inline" hand="#HS">könnte</tei:add></tei:subst>, um das Blatt der Nachwelt zu überliefern. Vor solcher Uebermacht der Zauber beugt sich der Mensch u. mündet demütig in den Fluss der Dinge, <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">nun</tei:add> auch selbst <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">wie</tei:del> <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">mit</tei:add> fortfließend. – Leider hält uns die Arbeit an <tei:rs key="entity-000620" type="person">Nagel<!--[DPe Nagel, Wilibald]--></tei:rs> u. <tei:rs key="entity-000057" type="person">Bekker<!--[DPe Bekker, Paul]--></tei:rs>
               <tei:note xml:id="r0021-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">For the Erläuterungsausgabe of Beethoven's <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title>Op. 111<!--[DW Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 111]--></tei:title></tei:rs> (Vienna: Universal Edition, 1916).</tei:note>
               im Tal zurück, was wir als ein schreiendes Mißverhältnis an persönliche<tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">n</tei:del><tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#HS">m</tei:add></tei:subst> Opfer<tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">n</tei:del> empfinden; <tei:subst><tei:del rend="alternative" hand="#HS">u.</tei:del> <tei:add place="inline" hand="#HS">nur</tei:add></tei:subst> verschaffen <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">wir</tei:add> uns dagegen <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">nur</tei:del> mindestens die bescheidene Genugtuung, die<tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">se</tei:del> <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">verdammten</tei:add> Blätter abschließen zu können.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0021-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Die Jause wird im neuerrichteten Caféhaus eingenommen; sodann zur Stockibrücke<!--[DPl Stockibrücke]-->, zur kleinen Kapelle bei <tei:rs key="entity-007717" type="place">Nasserein<!--[DPl Nasserein]--></tei:rs>, auf dem Weg zum Almejurjoch<!--[DPl Almajurjoch]--> nach <tei:rs key="entity-007713" type="place">St. Jakob<!--[DPl St. Jakob am Arlberg]--></tei:rs> u. auf dem oberen Weg zurück in unser <tei:rs key="entity-002279" type="place">Dorf<!--[DPl St. Anton am Arlberg]--></tei:rs>.  </tei:seg>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0021-se03"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Odyssee, XIII. Gesang.
               <tei:note xml:id="r0021-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Book 13 of The Odyssey recounts Odysseus's departure from the Phaeacians and arrival in his home town of Ithaca.</tei:note></tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-20">20. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0021-se01">A day whose magnificence surely no pen, no brush, no film or the like can tear out of the eternal album of Nature in order to transmit the page to posterity. Before such superior forces of magic, one must bow down, and humbly make one's way into the river of things, now themselves joining the flow. – Unfortunately we are kept in the valley by work on <tei:rs key="entity-000620" type="person">Nagel<!--[DPe Nagel, Wilibald]--></tei:rs> and <tei:rs key="entity-000057" type="person">Bekker<!--[DPe Bekker, Paul]--></tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="r0021-fn01" type="footnote"/>, something we feel as a screaming misalignment in personal sacrifice; we only create for ourselves the modest satisfaction of having been able to finish these damned pages.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0021-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> The afternoon snack is taken in the newly erected coffee house; afterwards to the Stockibrücke<!--[DPl Stockibrücke]-->, to the small chapel at <tei:rs key="entity-007717" type="place">Nasserein<!--[DPl Nasserein]--></tei:rs>, along the path to the Almajurjoch<!--[DPl Almajurjoch]--> to <tei:rs key="entity-007713" type="place">St. Jakob<!--[DPl St. Jakob am Arlberg]--></tei:rs> and returning along the high road to our <tei:rs key="entity-002279" type="place">village<!--[DPl St. Anton am Arlberg]--></tei:rs>.  </tei:seg>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0021-se03"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Odyssey, Book XIII.<tei:ptr corresp="r0021-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0022">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 21, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-21T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-21">21. </tei:date>Der Himmel etwas bedeckt, starker Wind; doch kommt es den ganzen Tag über nicht zu Regen. 
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0022-se01"><tei:pb n="988"/> Gegen ¾7<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> abends wird die Arbeit ganz fertig. Endlich!! Nun gilt es, den Aufenthalt in den Bergen, der wahrlich ein unvorhergesehenes Geschenk des Himmels ist, zu geniessen, um alle unsere Kräfte, sowohl die körperlichen wie geistigen, zu stärken.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-21">21.</tei:date> The sky somewhat overcast, and a strong wind; but there is no rain the whole day long.
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0022-se01"> <tei:pb n="988"/> Towards 6:45 in the evening, the work is completely finished. Finally!! Now it is a question of enjoying our stay in the mountains, which is truly an unimagined gift of Heaven, to strengthen all our powers, physical and intellectual alike.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0023">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. --> 
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 22, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-22T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-22">22. VII. 15 </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0023-se01">Scherzweise &#8222;erster Ferialtag&#8220; genannt, <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">u.</tei:add> in Wirklichkeit <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">auch</tei:add> &#8222;ferial&#8220;mäßig gelebt. Der Tag windet sich aus Nebeln allmählig schön heraus u. wir versuchen, uns neue kleine Wege zu erobern. Wir bleiben am rechten Ufer der Ros<tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">s</tei:del>anna<!--[DPl Rosanna]--> flussabwärts, geraten aber <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">des öftern</tei:del> <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">an mehreren Stellen</tei:add> in Verlegenheit wegen der Fortsetzung des Weges, so daß wir wieder, zum so u. so vielten male die Erfahrung machen, daß man mit in den Karten nicht <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">ausdrücklich</tei:add> vorgesehenen wegen einigermaßen vorsichtig umzugehen hat. Zurück per Bahn von <tei:rs key="entity-007713" type="place">St. Jakob<!--[DPl St. Jakob am Arlberg]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0023-se02">Briefe aus <tei:rs key="entity-002301" type="place">Kautzen<!--[DPl Kautzen]--></tei:rs> u. von <tei:rs key="entity-000201" type="person">Elias<!--[DPe Elias, Angelika]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0023-se03"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> An <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Floriz<!--[DPe Violin, Moriz]--></tei:rs>, enthaltend die Meldung über die abgeschlossene Arbeit.</tei:seg> 
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> 
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0023-se04">Die &#8222;<tei:rs key="entity-002545" type="journal"><tei:title>Zeit<!--[DT Zeit, Die]--></tei:title></tei:rs>&#8220; bringt die Kundmachung bezüglich der Musterung, die, wie es scheint, den Monat August mir noch durchaus nicht bedroht.
               <tei:note xml:id="r0023-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:rs type="work"><tei:title level="a">Die Musterung der 43- bis 50jährigen,</tei:title></tei:rs> <tei:rs type="work"><tei:title level="j">Die Zeit</tei:title></tei:rs> , No. 4605, July 21, 1915, 14<tei:hi rend="supralinear">th</tei:hi> year, evening edition, p. 2.</tei:bibl></tei:note>
            </tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0023-se05"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Nachmittags in der Hängematte.  </tei:seg>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0023-se06"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> <tei:rs key="entity-006433" type="person">Homer<!--[DPe Homer]--></tei:rs>, XIV. Gesang.
               <tei:note xml:id="r0023-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">In Book XIV of The Odyssey, Odysseus, having returned home to Ithaca, looks for the faithful Eumaeus, a pig farmer, who, without recognizing him, generously serves him wine and roasts and spends the night conversing with him.</tei:note>
            </tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0023-se07"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Bei wunderschönem Wetter machen wir uns auf den Eugen-Weg<!--[DPl Erzherzog-Eugen-Weg]-->, um &#8222;Wilhelm Meister&#8220;
               <tei:note xml:id="r0023-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl>Johann Wolfgang von Goethe, <tei:rs type="work"><tei:title level="m">Wilhelm Meisters Lehrjahre</tei:title></tei:rs> (Wilhelm Meister's Apprenticeship), first published in 1795–96 (Berlin: Johann Friedrich Unger).</tei:bibl></tei:note>
               (vom 2. Buch ab fortsetzend) zu lesen. Wir amüsieren uns fast kindisch <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">nebenbei</tei:add> damit, Kapitel um Kapitel auf verschiedenen Bänken zu lesen, wodurch wir gleichermaßen im Weg<tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">e</tei:del>, als auch im Roman fortkommen.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0023-se08">Im Hotel tauchen neue Gäste auf.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-22">July 22, 1915. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0023-se01">Jokingly called "first day of the holiday," and in reality, experienced in a "holiday" manner. The day is gradually transformed from mists to fine weather; and we seek to conquer small paths that are new to us. We stay on the right bank of the Rosanna<!--[DPl Rosanna]--> downstream, but in several places we get into difficulty about the continuation of the path, so that we discover, so and so many times, that one must proceed to some extent cautiously with the paths that are not explicitly marked on the maps. Return by train from <tei:rs key="entity-007713" type="place">St. Jakob<!--[DPl St. Jakob am Arlberg]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0023-se02">Letters from <tei:rs key="entity-002301" type="place">Kautzen<!--[DPl Kautzen]--></tei:rs> and from Miss <tei:rs key="entity-000201" type="person">Elias<!--[DPe Elias, Angelika]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0023-se03"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> To <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Floriz<!--[DPe Violin, Moriz]--></tei:rs>, including the report on the completed work.</tei:seg> 
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> 
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0023-se04"><tei:rs key="entity-002545" type="journal"><tei:title level="j">Die Zeit<!--[DT Zeit, Die]--></tei:title></tei:rs> publishes an announcement regarding the army medical examination which, it would appear, does not at all threaten me for the month of August.<tei:ptr corresp="r0023-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0023-se05"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> In the afternoon, in the hammock.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0023-se06"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> <tei:rs key="entity-006433" type="person">Homer<!--[DPe Homer]--></tei:rs>, Book XIV.<tei:ptr corresp="r0023-fn02" type="footnote"/>  </tei:seg>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0023-se07"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> In the most beautiful weather, we take the Eugen Path<!--[DPl Erzherzog-Eugen-Weg]-->, in order to read Wilhelm Meister<tei:ptr corresp="r0023-fn03" type="footnote"/> (continuing from Book 2). We amuse ourselves in an almost childish way, by reading each chapter on a different bench, so that we proceed along the path in the same way that we get through the novel.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0023-se08">New guests appear at the hotel.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0024">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 23, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-23T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-23">23.</tei:date> Wolkenloser Himmel. 
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0024-se01">Ins Steißbachtal<!--[DPl Steißbachtal]--> mit der Absicht, die 2. Serie der Blumen zu pflücken, die endlich nach <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien<!--[DPl Wien]--></tei:rs> hinausgehen sollen. Frühzeitig beim Schneefeld angelangt, erachten wir die Gelegenheit als günstig, um auf den Galzig<!--[DPl Galzig]--> zu gehen. Einige Minuten nach 11<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> waren <tei:pb n="989"/> wir auf der Spitze u. kehren, nachdem wir gefrühstückt hatten, auf dem Wege durchs Steißbachtal<!--[DPl Steißbachtal]--> zurück. Dort werden Blumen gepflückt. Um ¼2<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> sind wir im <tei:rs key="entity-002279" type="place">Dorfe<!--[DPl St. Anton am Arlberg]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0024-se02">Karte von Frau <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">Wally<!--[DPe Violin, Valerie]--></tei:rs>. </tei:seg>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0024-se03">Windstoß periodisch wiederkehrend gleichsam eine Wind-Schaufel.</tei:seg> 
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-23">23.</tei:date> Cloudless sky. 
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0024-se01">Into the Steißbach valley<!--[DPl Steißbachtal]--> with the intention of picking the second series of flowers, which should finally be dispatched to <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna<!--[DPl Wien]--></tei:rs>. Arriving early at the snow field, we consider that the conditions are favorable to go up the Galzig<!--[DPl Galzig]-->. A few minutes after 11 o'clock, <tei:pb n="989"/> we were at the summit and, after having breakfast, we returned through the valley of Steißbach<!--[DPl Steißbachtal]-->. There, flowers are picked. At 1:15 we were in the <tei:rs key="entity-002279" type="place">village<!--[DPl St. Anton am Arlberg]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0024-se02">Postcard from <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">Vally<!--[DPe Violin, Valerie]--></tei:rs>. </tei:seg>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0024-se03">Regularly returning gusts of winds are, so to speak, a wind-shovel.</tei:seg> 
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0025">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 24, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-24T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-24">24. VII. 15</tei:date> Nachtsüber Regen; erst im Laufe des Vormittags tritt Wasser-Ebbe ein. 
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0025-se01"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /><tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs> schickt Blumen an Frau <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">Wally<!--[DPe Violin, Valerie]--></tei:rs> in einem Karton; dazu eine Karte. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0025-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Karte an Frau <tei:rs key="entity-000136" type="person">Colbert<!--[DPe Colbert, Toni]--></tei:rs>, zur Genesung einige freundliche Worte.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0025-se03"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Brief nach <tei:rs key="entity-002301" type="place">Kautzen<!--[DPl Kautzen]--></tei:rs> mit Dank für Nachricht u. s. w.  </tei:seg>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0025-se04"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Brief an <tei:rs key="entity-000319" type="person">Sophie<!--[DPe Guttmann, Sophie]--></tei:rs> mit 10 Kronen für <tei:rs key="entity-000316" type="person">Hans<!--[DPe Guttmann, Hans]--></tei:rs> zu dessen Geburtstag.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0025-se05"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Karte an <tei:rs key="entity-000274" type="person">Gärtner<!--[DPe Gärtner, Eduard]--></tei:rs> als Lebenszeichen.  </tei:seg>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0025-se06"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Ein wenig Klavier gespielt.  </tei:seg>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0025-se07"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Brief von <tei:rs key="entity-000319" type="person">Sophie<!--[DPe Guttmann, Sophie]--></tei:rs> mit der Bitte um neuerliche Intervention bei <tei:rs key="entity-006472" type="person">Hofmokl<!--[DPe Hofmokl, Eugen]--></tei:rs> wegen <tei:rs key="entity-000318" type="person">Guttmann<!--[DPe Guttmann, Salo]--></tei:rs>s. 
            <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />  </tei:seg>        
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0025-se08"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Wir bleiben zuhause; <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs> beginnt die Kopi<tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">e</tei:del>atur. Dazwischen: <tei:rs key="entity-006433" type="person">Homer<!--[DPe Homer]--></tei:rs>, XV. Gesang;
               <tei:note xml:id="r0025-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Book XV of The Odyssey tells of the return of Odysseus's son Telemachus to Ithaca.</tei:note>
               <tei:rs key="entity-000294" type="person">Goethe<!--[DPe Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von]--></tei:rs>: &#8222;Unterhaltungen deutscher Ausgewanderter.&#8220;
               <tei:note xml:id="r0025-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:rs type="work"><tei:title level="m">Unterhaltungen deutscher Ausgewanderten</tei:title></tei:rs>: collection of novellas by Goethe, written 1794–95, first published by Cotta in Tübingen in 1795.</tei:bibl></tei:note>
            </tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0025-se09"> Die Reichen sagen: der Arme habe nichts zu verlieren. Damit sagen sie aber weniger <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#JS">etwa</tei:add>, daß sie zu verlieren hätten, sondern vielmehr, daß sie nichts zu gewinnen haben würden.</tei:seg> 
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0025-se10">Gegen Abend wieder Regen. </tei:seg>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-24">July 24, 1915.</tei:date> Rain overnight; only in the course of the morning does the water ebb away. 
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0025-se01"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /><tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs> sends flowers to <tei:rs key="entity-000914" type="person">Vally<!--[DPe Violin, Valerie]--></tei:rs> in a box; with it, a card. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />    </tei:seg>      </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0025-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Postcard to Mrs. <tei:rs key="entity-000136" type="person">Colbert<!--[DPe Colbert, Toni]--></tei:rs>, a few friendly words to wish her a recovery.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0025-se03"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Letter to <tei:rs key="entity-002301" type="place">Kautzen<!--[DPl Kautzen]--></tei:rs> with thanks for the news, and so on.  </tei:seg>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0025-se04"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Letter to <tei:rs key="entity-000319" type="person">Sophie<!--[DPe Guttmann, Sophie]--></tei:rs>, with 10 Kronen for <tei:rs key="entity-000316" type="person">Hans<!--[DPe Guttmann, Hans]--></tei:rs> on his birthday.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0025-se05"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Postcard to <tei:rs key="entity-000274" type="person">Gärtner<!--[DPe Gärtner, Eduard]--></tei:rs>, as a sign of life.  </tei:seg>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0025-se06"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> I played the piano a little.  </tei:seg>
                           <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0025-se07"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Letter from <tei:rs key="entity-000319" type="person">Sophie<!--[DPe Guttmann, Sophie]--></tei:rs> with the request for renewed intervention with <tei:rs key="entity-006472" type="person">Hofmokl<!--[DPe Hofmokl, Eugen]--></tei:rs> on behalf of <tei:rs key="entity-000318" type="person">Guttmann<!--[DPe Guttmann, Salo]--></tei:rs>. 
                              <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0025-se08"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> We stay home; <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs> begins the fair copy. In between: <tei:rs key="entity-006433" type="person">Homer<!--[DPe Homer]--></tei:rs>, Book 15;<tei:ptr corresp="r0025-fn01" type="footnote"/> <tei:rs key="entity-000294" type="person">Goethe<!--[DPe Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von]--></tei:rs>: "Conversations of German Refugees."<tei:ptr corresp="r0025-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0025-se09">The rich say: "Poor people have nothing to lose." With that, however, they say rather less than that they have something to lose, but rather much more that they would have nothing to gain.</tei:seg> 
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0025-se10">Towards evening, rain returns.</tei:seg> 
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0026">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 25, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-25T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-25">25.</tei:date> 
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0026-se01">Regnerisch u. Regen; des vormittags <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">ein wenig</tei:del> <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title>Correktur<!--[DW Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 111]--></tei:title></tei:rs> u. ein wenig Klavier getrieben. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />  </tei:seg>        
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0026-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> <tei:rs key="entity-006433" type="person">Homer<!--[DPe Homer]--></tei:rs>, XVI. Gesang.
               <tei:note xml:id="r0026-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Book XVI of The Odyssey recounts how Telemachus meets the Eumaeus, the pig farmer, and there finds his father Odysseus. Father and son then deliberate on how they should confront the eighty-eight freemen who have occupied his house and are courting his wife Penelope.</tei:note>
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>         
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0026-se03"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Karte von <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Floriz<!--[DPe Violin, Moriz]--></tei:rs> wegen der Musterung. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>         
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0026-se04"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Des Abends nach Tisch einige Schritte ins Freie gemacht, hernach arbeitet <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs> bis 11<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi>.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:pb n="990"/>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-25">25.</tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab> 
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0026-se01">Drizzle and rain; in the morning, <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title level="m">corrections<!--[DW Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 111]--></tei:title></tei:rs> and a bit of piano playing. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />  </tei:seg>        
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0026-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> <tei:rs key="entity-006433" type="person">Homer<!--[DPe Homer]--></tei:rs>, Book XVI.<tei:ptr corresp="r0026-fn01" type="footnote"/> 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />  </tei:seg>        
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0026-se03"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Postcard from <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Floriz<!--[DPe Violin, Moriz]--></tei:rs> regarding the medical examination. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />   </tei:seg>       
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0026-se04"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> After evening meal, a few steps taken outdoors; afterwards, <tei:rs key="entity-000771" type="person">Lie-Liechen<!--[DPe Schenker, Jeanette]--></tei:rs> works until 11 o'clock.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:pb n="990"/>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0027">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 25, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-25T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-25">25. VII. 15 </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab> 
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0027-se01">Zweite amerikanische Note!
               <tei:note xml:id="r0027-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:rs type="work"><tei:title level="a">Die amerikanische Note an Deutschland. Ablehnung der deutschen Vorschläge und ernste Sprache gegen Deutschland</tei:title></tei:rs> and <tei:rs type="work"><tei:title level="a">Die Antwort Amerikas auf die deutschen Note,</tei:title></tei:rs> <tei:rs type="work"><tei:title level="j">Neue Freie Presse</tei:title></tei:rs>, No. 18291, July 25, 1915, morning edition, p. 8.</tei:bibl> On 7 May 1915 a German submarine torpedoed and sank the RMS Lusitania, a British ocean liner en route from New York to Liverpool. While most of those lost in the sinking were British or Canadian, the loss of 128 Americans in the disaster outraged many in the USA. President Woodrow Wilson sent two official notes of protest to Germany in which he insisted the German government apologize for the sinking, compensate U.S. victims, and promise to avoid any similar occurrence in the future.</tei:note>
               Ueberaus frech im Ton, wie eben nur der anglo-amerikanische Typus sich zu äußern vermag.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0027-se02">&#8222;<tei:rs key="entity-002537" type="journal"><tei:title>Frankfurter Ztg.<!--[DT Frankfurter Zeitung]--></tei:title></tei:rs>&#8220; vom 25.: &#8222;Die Entwicklung zur Weltform&#8220; von <tei:rs key="entity-007739" type="person">Josef Rüder<!--[DPe Rieder, Josef]--></tei:rs>
               <tei:note xml:id="r0027-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl> Josef Rieder, <tei:rs type="work"><tei:title level="a">Die Entwicklung zur Weltform,</tei:title></tei:rs> <tei:rs type="work"><tei:title level="j">Frankfurter Zeitung und Handelsblatt</tei:title></tei:rs>, No. 204, July 25, 1915, 60<tei:hi rend="supralinear">th</tei:hi> year, first morning edition, pp. 1-2.</tei:bibl></tei:note>
               bringt einen sehr plausiblen, mir außerordentlich <tei:sic>sympatischen</tei:sic> Gedanken zur Darstellung, wornach bei gewissen Dingen eine definitive Form angenommen werden muß, die, wie der Autor behauptet, nicht mehr überschritten werden kann. Schade, daß er von demselben Gedanken nicht auch auf dem Gebiete der Kunst Gebrauch gemacht hat; liegt doch gerade hier der Gedanke, für den ich die meiste Vorliebe <tei:subst><tei:del rend="overwritten" hand="#JS"><tei:gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" extent="4"/></tei:del><tei:add hand="#JS" place="superimposed">hege</tei:add></tei:subst>.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0027-se03">Oberinspektor Stächelin<!--[DPe Stächelin]--> erzählt eine artige Geschichte von seinem <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">eigenen</tei:del> Knaben: Veränderter Verhältnisse halber mußte dieser, bis dahin Zögling der <tei:rs key="entity-007693" type="organization">stella mattutina<!--[DIn Stella Matutina]--></tei:rs> in <tei:rs key="entity-004327" type="place">Feldkirch<!--[DPl Feldkirch]--></tei:rs>, nach <tei:rs key="entity-002304" type="place">Innsbruck<!--[DPl Innsbruck]--></tei:rs> in die Realschule gebracht werden; hier ergab sich, daß der Junge gerade in Religion eine weniger gute Note erhielt. Der Vater begab sich zum Professor u. drückte ihm seine Verwunderung darüber aus, daß er nicht begreife, wie ein Zögling der <tei:rs key="entity-007693" type="organization">stella mattutina<!--[DIn Stella Matutina]--></tei:rs> in Religion zurückbleiben könnte. Drauf erwiderte der Professor: &#8222;Warum haben Sie denn nicht gleich gesagt, daß der Junge in <tei:rs key="entity-004327" type="place">Feldkirch<!--[DPl Feldkirch]--></tei:rs> war!&#8220;</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-25">July 25, 1915. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0027-se01">Second American note!<tei:ptr corresp="r0027-fn01" type="footnote"/> Thoroughly insolent in tone, as only the typical Anglo-American is capable of expressing himself.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0027-se02">The <tei:rs key="entity-002537" type="journal"><tei:title level="j">Frankfurter Zeitung<!--[DT Frankfurter Zeitung]--></tei:title></tei:rs> of the 25<tei:hi rend="supralinear">th</tei:hi>: "The Development Towards a World Order" by <tei:rs key="entity-007739" type="person">Josef Rüder<!--[DPe Rieder, Josef]--></tei:rs><tei:ptr corresp="r0027-fn02" type="footnote"/> presents a very plausible, for me extremely congenial thought, according to which certain things must take a definitive form, which, so the author maintains, can no longer be exceeded. A pity that he has not applied this same idea to the realm of art; for herein lies the very idea that I cherish most dearly.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0027-se03">Chief Inspector Stächelin<!--[DPe Stächelin]--> recounts a nice story about his child: on account of changed circumstances the boy, until then a pupil at the <tei:rs key="entity-007693" type="organization">Stella Matutina<!--[DIn Stella Matutina]--></tei:rs> in <tei:rs key="entity-004327" type="place">Feldkirch<!--[DPl Feldkirch]--></tei:rs>, had to be brought to the middle school in <tei:rs key="entity-002304" type="place">Innsbruck<!--[DPl Innsbruck]--></tei:rs>. Here it turned out that the boy received a lower grade in religion, of all subjects. The father went to the professor and expressed his astonishment: he could not understand how a pupil of the <tei:rs key="entity-007693" type="organization">Stella Matutina<!--[DIn Stella Matutina]--></tei:rs> could fall behind in religion. The professor replied, "Why did you not tell me in the first place that the boy had been in <tei:rs key="entity-004327" type="place">Feldkirch<!--[DPl Feldkirch]--></tei:rs>!"</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0028">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 26, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-26T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-26">26. </tei:date>Regen, mindestens regnerisch.  
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0028-se01"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Alle Monatsgelder sowie Zins nach <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien<!--[DPl Wien]--></tei:rs> u. <tei:rs key="entity-002301" type="place">Kautzen<!--[DPl Kautzen]--></tei:rs> geschickt.</tei:seg>
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0028-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Karte an <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Fl.<!--[DPe Violin, Moriz]--></tei:rs>, die jüngste amerikanische Note
               <tei:note xml:id="r0028-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">On 7 May 1915 a German submarine torpedoed and sank the RMS Lusitania, a British ocean liner en route from New York to Liverpool. While most of those lost in the sinking were British or Canadian, the loss of 128 Americans in the disaster outraged many in the USA. President Woodrow Wilson sent two official notes of protest to Germany in which he insisted the German government apologize for the sinking, compensate U.S. victims, and promise to avoid any similar occurrence in the future. His second verbal note was published in newspapers, see for example "Die amerikanische Note an Deutschland. Ablehnung der deutschen Vorschläge und ernste Sprache gegen Deutschland" and "Die Antwort Amerikas auf die deutschen Note," Neue Freie Presse, No. 18291, July 25, 1915, morning edition, p. 8.</tei:note>
               betreffend.</tei:seg>
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0028-se03"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Karte an <tei:rs key="entity-000319" type="person">Sophie<!--[DPe Guttmann, Sophie]--></tei:rs> mit Widerruf ihrer ohnehin absurden Bitte. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />  </tei:seg>        
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0028-se04"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Brot-Surrogate von <tei:rs key="entity-003859" type="place">Fritz<!--[DPl Fritz, August (Bäckerei)]--></tei:rs> <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">angelangt</tei:add>. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />   </tei:seg>       
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0028-se05"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> <tei:rs key="entity-002743" type="person">Schindler<!--[DPe Schindler, Anton Felix]--></tei:rs> zu Ende gebracht – Arbeit an <tei:rs key="entity-000576" type="person">Marx<!--[DPe Marx, Adolf Bernhard]--></tei:rs> begonnen;
               <tei:note xml:id="r0028-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">For his Erläuterungsausgabe of Beethoven's <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title>Op. 111<!--[DW Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 111]--></tei:title></tei:rs> (Vienna: Universal Edition, 1916).</tei:note>
               dazwischen des Vormittags ein wenig Klavier gespielt.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0028-se06"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> <tei:rs key="entity-006433" type="person">Homer<!--[DPe Homer]--></tei:rs>, XVII. Gesang.
               <tei:note xml:id="r0028-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Book XVII of The Odyssey, which Heinrich and Jeanette were reading together during the month of July.</tei:note></tei:seg>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0028-se07"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Gegen abend<tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">s</tei:del> Ausheiterung, nun die Straße hinab bis zur Haltestelle <tei:rs key="entity-007713" type="place">St. Jakob<!--[DPl St. Jakob am Arlberg]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:pb n="991"/>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-26">26.</tei:date> Rain, at least rainy weather.  
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0028-se01"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> All the money from the month, and interest, sent to <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna<!--[DPl Wien]--></tei:rs> and <tei:rs key="entity-002301" type="place">Kautzen<!--[DPl Kautzen]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg>
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0028-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Postcard to <tei:rs key="entity-000913" type="person">Floriz<!--[DPe Violin, Moriz]--></tei:rs> about the latest American message.<tei:ptr corresp="r0028-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:seg>
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0028-se03"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Postcard to <tei:rs key="entity-000319" type="person">Sophie<!--[DPe Guttmann, Sophie]--></tei:rs> with a rejection of her request, which is at any rate an absurd one. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />   </tei:seg>       
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0028-se04"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Bread substitutes arrive from <tei:rs key="entity-003859" type="place">Fritz<!--[DPl Fritz, August (Bäckerei)]--></tei:rs>. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />   </tei:seg>       
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0028-se05"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> <tei:rs key="entity-002743" type="person">Schindler<!--[DPe Schindler, Anton Felix]--></tei:rs> finished – Work on <tei:rs key="entity-000576" type="person">Marx<!--[DPe Marx, Adolf Bernhard]--></tei:rs> begun;<tei:ptr corresp="r0028-fn02" type="footnote"/> in between in the morning, the piano played a little.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0028-se06"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> <tei:rs key="entity-006433" type="person">Homer<!--[DPe Homer]--></tei:rs>, Book XVII.<tei:ptr corresp="r0028-fn03" type="footnote"/>  </tei:seg>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0028-se07"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Towards evening the weather clears up; we now walk down the road as far as the coach stop at <tei:rs key="entity-007713" type="place">St. Jakob<!--[DPl St. Jakob am Arlberg]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:pb n="991"/>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0029">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 26, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-26T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-26">26. VII. 15 </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab> 
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0029-se01">Glücklicherweise lassen sich die deutschen Zeitungen von <tei:rs key="entity-000966" type="person">Wilson<!--[DPe Wilson, Woodrow]--></tei:rs> keineswegs einschüchtern; vielmehr fordern sie, <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">u.</tei:add> womöglich noch energischer<tei:add place="inline" hand="#HS">,</tei:add> die Fortsetzung des U-Boot-Krieges!</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0029-se02">Ein oesterreichischer Minister bringt wieder einen Erlass <tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">w</tei:del><tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#HS">g</tei:add></tei:subst>egen Prei<tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">ß</tei:del><tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#HS">s</tei:add></tei:subst>treiberei zur Veröffentlichung.
               <tei:note xml:id="r0029-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:rs type="work"><tei:title level="a">Maßnahmen der Regierung zur Bekämpfung der Preistreibereien. Ein Erlaß des Ministers des Innern,</tei:title></tei:rs> <tei:rs type="work"><tei:title level="j">Neue Freie Presse</tei:title></tei:rs>, No. 18291, July 25, 1915, morning edition, pp. 17-18.</tei:bibl></tei:note>
               In demselben Maße aber, <tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">wie</tei:del><tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#HS">als</tei:add></tei:subst> er <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">in eben diesem Erlasse</tei:del> <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">darin</tei:add> gegen seine untergebenen Beamten selbst auftritt, sie ausdrücklich einer unzulässigen Parteilichkeit u. sonstiger Pflichtverletzungen schuldig erklärt, wirkt sein Auftreten nur umso verletzender u. frivoler. Der Minister hat Wandel zu schaffen u. nicht <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">blos</tei:add> Erlässe <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">aus <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Wien<!--[DPl Vienna]--></tei:rs> zu schreiben</tei:add>, denn dem Bürger, zumal wenn er Konsument ist, fehlt es <tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">sicher</tei:del> <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">ja eben</tei:add></tei:subst> an Macht, sich gerade <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">die</tei:del> <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">jene</tei:add> Macht zu <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">ver</tei:add>schaffen, die Amt des Ministers ist, <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">umsoweniger, als</tei:del> <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">wozu kommt, daß</tei:add> er sich gegenüber der Behörde schuld<tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">i</tei:add>g machen würde, wenn er ihr <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS"><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">nämlich</tei:del> die Gesetzesverletzung ins Gesicht <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">sagen wollte</tei:del> vorwerfen, also</tei:add> das sagen wollte, was <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">allein</tei:add> der Minister <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">ihr</tei:del> <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">zu</tei:add> sag<tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">t</tei:del><tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#HS">en</tei:add></tei:subst> <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">befugt ist</tei:add> (siehe Beilage).</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0029-se03">Auch die Sprache ist, dort angelangt <tei:del rend="overstrike" hand="#HS">,</tei:del> wo sie heute steht, als eine endlich selbständige Kunst aufzufassen, die, wie Musik vom Tanz, sich ähnlich vom Zweck los<tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">ge</tei:add>lös<tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">en</tei:del><tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#HS">t</tei:add></tei:subst> <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">konnte</tei:del> <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">hat</tei:add>. In ihren ersten Stadien mag sie zwar lediglich dem Zweck der gegenseitigen Verständigung als einer Notwendigkeit gedient haben, doch ist sie seither sozusagen zu <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">einer</tei:del> eigene<tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">n</tei:del><tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#HS">r</tei:add></tei:subst> Schönheit emporgewachsen, die sich <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">aber</tei:add> in der Ueberschreitung des <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">blos</tei:add> Notwendigen, also im gewissen Sinne in einem Luxus äußert.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-26">July 26, 1915. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0029-se01">Fortunately, the German newspapers are not in any way intimidated by <tei:rs key="entity-000966" type="person">Wilson<!--[DPe Wilson, Woodrow]--></tei:rs>; on the contrary, they demand the continuation of submarine warfare, and if possible even more vigorously!</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0029-se02">An Austrian minister issues another public statement about the raising of prices.<tei:ptr corresp="r0029-fn01" type="footnote"/> To the same extent, however, that he himself intervenes in opposition to his subordinate officers, explicitly declaring them guilty of an unacceptable partisanship and other derelictions of duty, his intervention has all the more damaging and frivolous effect. The minister must institute changes and not merely issue statements from <tei:rs key="entity-002484" type="place">Vienna<!--[DPl Vienna]--></tei:rs>; for the citizen, especially when he is a consumer, indeed lacks the power to create for himself that power which is the office of the minister. He would make himself guilty in the eyes of the authorities if he were to accuse them of law infringement to their faces, that is, to declare that which the minister alone is authorized to declare (see collection <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of clippings</tei:supplied>).</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0029-se03">Language, too, has arrived at the point today in which it should finally be regarded as an art in its own right, having detached itself from its function as music did from dance. In its initial phases, it may have simply served the necessary purpose of mutual understanding; but since then it has grown up, so to speak, into a beauty of his own. In exceeding what is merely necessary, however, it expresses itself to a certain extent, as a luxury.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0030">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 27, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-27T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-27">27. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0030-se01">Das Wetter bessert sich ein wenig; Spaziergang bis zum Waldhäusl<!--[DPl Waldhäusl]-->. Ein neues Grün der Wiesen entzückt uns.         </tei:seg>
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0030-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Magenverstimmung, <tei:subst><tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">d</tei:del><tei:add place="superimposed" hand="#HS">w</tei:add></tei:subst>eshalb Nachmittag zuhause.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-27">27. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0030-se01">The weather improves somewhat; a walk to the Waldhäusl<!--[DPl Waldhäusl]-->. A new green in the fields enchants us.          </tei:seg>
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0030-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Stomach ailment, on account of which we stay home in the afternoon.</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0031">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 28, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-28T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-28">28. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0031-se01"><tei:subst><tei:del rend="alternative" hand="#HS">Nachts über</tei:del> <tei:add place="inline" hand="#HS">Nachtsüber</tei:add></tei:subst> heftiger Regen, der <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">noch</tei:del> <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">sogar</tei:add> bis mittag <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">noch</tei:add> anhält; erst nachmittags wird es heiterer. Wir bleiben dennoch zuhause.</tei:seg> 
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:pb n="992"/> 
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-28">28. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0031-se01">Heavy rain over night, which persists even until noon; it brightens up only in the afternoon. Nonetheless we stay at home.</tei:seg> 
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:pb n="992"/> 
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0032">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 28, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-28T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-28">28. VII. 15 </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0032-se01"><tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title>Literaturrubrik<!--[DW Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 111]--></tei:title></tei:rs> fertiggestellt; die Arbeit an der <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title>Vorbemerkung<!--[DW Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 111]--></tei:title></tei:rs> beginnt.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0032-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> <tei:rs key="entity-006433" type="person">Homer<!--[DPe Homer]--></tei:rs>, XVIII. Gesang.
               <tei:note xml:id="r0032-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Book XVIII of The Odyssey, which Heinrich and Jeanette were reading together during the month of July.</tei:note></tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-28">July 28, 1915. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0032-se01">Section on the <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title level="m">secondary literature<!--[DW Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 111]--></tei:title></tei:rs> completed; work on the <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title level="m">preface<!--[DW Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 111]--></tei:title></tei:rs> begins.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0032-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> <tei:rs key="entity-006433" type="person">Homer<!--[DPe Homer]--></tei:rs>, Book XVIII.<tei:ptr corresp="r0032-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:seg> 
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0033">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 29, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-29T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-29">29. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0033-se01">Bedeckter Himmel ohne Regen. Zwischen 4 u. <tei:subst><tei:del rend="overwritten" hand="#JS"><tei:gap reason="illegible" unit="chars" extent="2"/></tei:del><tei:add hand="#JS" place="superimposed">7<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi> </tei:add></tei:subst> Spaziergang bis vor <tei:rs key="entity-007715" type="place">Pettneu<!--[DPl Pettneu am Arlberg]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0033-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> <tei:rs key="entity-006433" type="person">Homer<!--[DPe Homer]--></tei:rs>, XIX. Gesang.
               <tei:note xml:id="r0033-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Book XIX of The Odyssey, which Heinrich and Jeanette were reading together during the month of July.</tei:note></tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0033-se03">Allemal befindet sich <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">eine</tei:del> zarte Gesinnung im Nachteil, wenn sie sich als solche durchaus behaupten will; denn sie meidet es alsdann sich auszusprechen, <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">nur</tei:add> um eben nicht in Protzerei, weibliche Ziererei u. Zärtlichkeitsrenommisterei umzukippen. Wie kann sie aber unter solchen Umständen verstanden werden?</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-29">9. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0033-se01">Overcast sky, without rain. Between 4 and 7 o'clock, a walk towards <tei:rs key="entity-007715" type="place">Pettneu<!--[DPl Pettneu am Arlberg]--></tei:rs>.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0033-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> <tei:rs key="entity-006433" type="person">Homer<!--[DPe Homer]--></tei:rs>, Book XIX.<tei:ptr corresp="r0033-fn01" type="footnote"/></tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0033-se03">One always finds a tender sentiment in adversity, if it really wishes to assert itself as such; thereupon it avoids expressing itself, only so that it does not collapse into ostentation or feminine adornment, or by boasting of tenderness. But how can it be understood in such circumstances?</tei:seg>
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0034">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 30, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-30T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-30">30.</tei:date> Regen ohne Maß!  
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0034-se01"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> <tei:rs key="entity-000576" type="person">Marx<!--[DPe Marx, Adolf Bernhard]--></tei:rs> zuende, <tei:rs key="entity-000520" type="person">Lenz<!--[DPe Lenz, Wilhelm von]--></tei:rs>-<tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title>Teil<!--[DW Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 111]--></tei:title></tei:rs> begonnen.</tei:seg> 
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-30">30.</tei:date> Rain beyond measure!  
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0034-se01"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> <tei:rs key="entity-000576" type="person">Marx<!--[DPe Marx, Adolf Bernhard]--></tei:rs> finished, <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title level="m">section<!--[DW Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 111]--></tei:title></tei:rs> on <tei:rs key="entity-000520" type="person">Lenz<!--[DPe Lenz, Wilhelm von]--></tei:rs> begun.</tei:seg> 
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0035">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry. Contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker July 31, 1915</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1915-07-30T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2020-07-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description>A summary of the contents of the record (currently unused)</dc:description>
         <dc:subject>A list of subjects (currently unused)</dc:subject>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-31">31. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0035-se01">Bei schönem Wetter nach <tei:rs key="entity-007715" type="place">Pettneu<!--[DPl Pettneu am Arlberg]--></tei:rs>, zwischen 8–12<tei:hi rend="supralinear">h</tei:hi>.</tei:seg>  
               <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0035-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Feile bis <tei:rs key="entity-000620" type="person">Nagel<!--[DPe Nagel, Wilibald]--></tei:rs> gediehen.
                  <tei:note xml:id="r0034-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">For his Erläuterungsausgabe of Beethoven's <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title>Op. 111<!--[DW Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 111]--></tei:title></tei:rs> (Vienna: Universal Edition, 1916).</tei:note>
                  <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />  </tei:seg>        
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0035-se03"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Korrektur u. <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title>Stich<!--[DW Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 111]--></tei:title></tei:rs> in <tei:add place="interlinear-above" hand="#HS">einer</tei:add> durch <tei:del hand="#HS" rend="overstrike">eine</tei:del> ungewöhnliche Natur wundersam <tei:sic>gehobener</tei:sic> Stimmung auf dem Eugen-Weg<!--[DPl Erzherzog-Eugen-Weg]--> durchgesehen. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>         
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" xml:id="r0035-se04"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> <tei:rs key="entity-006654" type="place">Lublin<!--[DPl Lublin]--></tei:rs> gefallen!!
               <tei:note xml:id="r0034-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:rs type="work"><tei:title level="a">Besetzung von Lublin durch unsere Truppen,</tei:title></tei:rs> <tei:rs type="work"><tei:title level="j">Neue Freie Presse</tei:title></tei:rs>, No. 18297, July 31, 1915, morning edition, p. 1.</tei:bibl></tei:note></tei:seg> 
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>
      
      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:date when="1915-07-31">31. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0035-se01">In fair weather, to <tei:rs key="entity-007715" type="place">Pettneu<!--[DPl Pettneu am Arlberg]--></tei:rs> between 8 o'clock and noon.</tei:seg>  
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0035-se02"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Good progress on polishing as far as <tei:rs key="entity-000620" type="person">Nagel<!--[DPe Nagel, Wilibald]--></tei:rs>.<tei:ptr corresp="r0034-fn01" type="footnote"/> 
                  <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />  </tei:seg>        
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0035-se03"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> Corrections and <tei:rs key="entity-001736" type="work"><tei:title level="m">engraving<!--[DW Erläuterungsausgabe, Op. 111]--></tei:title></tei:rs> checked over along the Eugen-Weg<!--[DPl Erzherzog-Eugen-Weg]--> in an atmosphere that is wonderfully exalted by exceptional Nature. 
               <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> </tei:seg>         
         </tei:ab>
         <tei:ab>
            <tei:seg type="subentry" corresp="r0035-se04"><tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" /> <tei:rs key="entity-006654" type="place">Lublin<!--[DPl Lublin]--></tei:rs> has fallen!!<tei:ptr corresp="r0034-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:seg> 
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="inline em-dash" />
                     </tei:ab>
<tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk" />
         <tei:ab>
         </tei:ab>
      </tei:div>

   </sdo:record>

</sdo:recordCollection>
