<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker"
   xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
   xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
   <!--OJ-01-10_1911-10October, 1911 -  ( Diary Series A box: 01 folder: 10 date: Jan 1, 1911–Dec 31, 1911 pages: 125-131, 131v, 131a, 132, 132a, 133, 133a, 134-135, 135a, 135b, 136-146, 146a, 147-152, 152a, 153, 153a, 153b, 154-161, 161a, 162-179, 162par-166par, 170-172, 173a-173b, 174-193, 194a, 194b, 195-197 )
                 
             -->
   <sdo:collectionDesc>
      <sdo:source>
         <!--Select an sdoID from the controlled list -->
         <sdo:diary sdoID="OJ-01-10_1911-10"/>
      </sdo:source>

      <tei:handNotes>
         <tei:handNote xml:id="HS-ink" scope="major">Heinrich Schenker's hand, in ink</tei:handNote>
         <tei:handNote xml:id="HS-blue" scope="minor">Heinrich Schenker's hand, in blue
            crayon</tei:handNote>
         <tei:handNote xml:id="JK" scope="major">Jeanette Kornfeld's hand</tei:handNote>
      </tei:handNotes>
      <!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below -->
      <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
         <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
         <tei:resp>Transcription, 2019</tei:resp>
         <tei:resp>Translation, 2019</tei:resp>
         <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
         <tei:resp>Footnotes, 2019</tei:resp>
      </tei:respStmt>
      <tei:respStmt xml:id="TL">
         <tei:persName>Tamara Lopez</tei:persName>
         <tei:resp>XML Encoding Model</tei:resp>
      </tei:respStmt>

      <tei:revisionDesc>
         <tei:change when="2012-10-03" who="#IB">Template Generated</tei:change>
      </tei:revisionDesc>
   </sdo:collectionDesc>

   <sdo:record ID="r0001">
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker October 10, 1911</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1911-10-10T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-08-26</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description/>
         <dc:subject/>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, </tei:hi><tei:pb n="178"/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:fw type="header" rend="center"><tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:date when="1911"
                  >1911</tei:date></tei:fw><tei:lb/>
            <tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:date when="1911-10-10">10. Oktober.</tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0001-se01"><tei:handShift new="#JK"
               />Rechtsprechung<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">This may
               perhaps be Schenker's reaction to statements made and documents issued during
               Jeanette's current divorce court proceedings. See, for example, the letter to Moriz
               Violin, <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-6-5_4">OJ 6/5, [4]</tei:ref>, October
               5, 1911.</tei:note> ‒ nicht Wahrheitsprechung. Nicht um Wahrheit, sondern nur um
            Rechtsprechung geht es bei den offiziellen Gerichten; es ist daher zu bedauern, daß
            nicht den Dichtern,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">On the
               poet's role in society, cf. diary entries for July 21 and August 6, 1911.</tei:note>
            die allein die Wahrheit sprechen, die amtliche Gewalt verliehen ist, ihre Urteile zu
            vollstrecken bezw. vollstrecken zu lassen. Wie haben doch z.B. im Falle Calas u. <tei:rs
               type="person" key="entity-000174">Dreyfus</tei:rs> ein Voltaire u. Zola gerichtet;
            wie über Gretchen u. Faust ein <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000294">Göthe</tei:rs>!
            Wie anders, als die weltlichen Richter!</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0001-se02">Vielleicht ist alle <tei:hi rend="underline"
               >Freude</tei:hi> im letzten Grunde nur ein psychischer Reflex der
               Ideenassoziationen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"
               >Schenker's interest in the theory of the association of ideas goes back at least to
               c.1903 and the unpublished essay <tei:title level="m">Nur ein Gleichnis</tei:title>,
               also featuring large in the theoretical section of the <tei:title level="m"
                  >Harmonielehre</tei:title> (1906).</tei:note> die, wenn gleich mechanisch
            verlaufend, dennoch eine Art spontaner Tätigkeit des menschlichen Gehirns vorstellt. Je
            reicher die Assoziationen, auf welcher Basis immer, gedeihen, desto größer der Schein
            einer Tätigkeit, die man, im gewissem Sinne, auch schöpferisch zu nennen nicht anstehen
            darf. So ist es denn auch möglich, geradezu eine Scala der Freuden aufzustellen, wenn
            man sich entschließt im gegebenen Falle zu prüfen, ob der Gegenstand der Freude die
            Assoziationstätigkeit des Gehirns dauernd u. nachhaltig beeinflußt. Gehe ich z.B. in ein
            Varieté-Theater, so verdanke ich auch den Leistungen der Akrobaten oder dgl. Genuss,
            Freude u. Anregung, doch vermag das Gesehene, mindestens in mir, keine weiteren
            Assoziationen anzuregen, so daß der Genuss des Abends mit diesem selbst endet u. besten
            Falls als Erinnerungsskelett auf dem Friedhof meiner Vorstellungen eingereiht wird.
            Nehme ich dagegen z.B. ein Kunstwerk: wie strahlt dieses Beziehungen aus zu anderen
            Kunstwerken, zu anderen Menschen; wie überwindet es Tage, Monate u. Jahre, um die
            Assoziationen seines eignenen Schoßes zu verbinden mit solchen eines anderen. So erklärt
            es sich auch, weshalb körperliche Genüsse sogar Geschlechtsgenüsse, hinter geistigen
            Freuden an Fruchtbarkeit zurück- <tei:pb n="179"/> bleiben, sogar den Fall nicht
            ausgenommen, wo der Geschlechtsgenuß fruchtbar geworden u. einem neuen menschlichen
            Wesen das Leben eröffnet hat. Daher so wenig Erinnerung bei Nase, Gaumen, Magen, Genus ‒
            u. desto mehr beim Gehirn; ist doch schließlich die Erinnerung selbst Tätigkeit des
            Gehirns u. nicht der Sinne.</tei:ab>

      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, </tei:hi><tei:pb n="178"/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:fw type="header" rend="center"><tei:handShift new="#HS-ink"/><tei:date when="1911"
                  >1911</tei:date></tei:fw><tei:lb/>
            <tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:date when="1911-10-10">October 10</tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab corresp="r0001-se01"><tei:handShift new="#JK"/>Legal-speak<tei:ptr
               corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> ‒ not truth-speak. Official courts of justice
            are concerned not with truth but only with legal-speak; it is therefore to be regretted
            that it is not upon poets,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/> who alone
            speak the truth, that official power is conferred to enforce their judgments or have
            them enforced. How after all did, e.g. a Voltaire and Zola judge in the cases of Calas
            and <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000174">Dreyfus</tei:rs>; how did a <tei:rs
               type="person" key="entity-000294">Goethe</tei:rs> judge in the case of Gretchen and
            Faust? How otherwise than as global judges!</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0001-se02">Perhaps all <tei:hi rend="underline">joy</tei:hi> is in the
            last analysis only a psychich reflex of associations of ideas,<tei:ptr
               corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> which, albeit operating mechanically,
            nevertheless manifests itself as a sort of spontaneous activity on the part of the human
            brain. The more richly the associations ‒ on whatever basis ‒ flourish, the greater the
            semblance of an activity that one should not hesitate even to call, in a certain sense,
            creative. It then even becomes possible to posit a scale of <tei:supplied
               reason="clarity">degrees of</tei:supplied> joy, if one resolves in a given case to
            test whether the object of the joy influences the capacity of the brain to generate
            associations over a sustained and enduring period of time. If, for example, I go into a
            variety theater, I owe my pleasure, joy, and excitement to the accomplishments of the
            acrobats and the like; but what I have witnessed is not, at least in me, capable of
            engendering any further associations, such that the evening's pleasure ends at this, and
            is at best absorbed as a skeletal memory in the graveyard of my mental images. If, by
            contrast, I, for example, take a work of art: how this radiates out connections to other
            works of art and to other beings; how it transcends days, months and years in order to
            connect the associations of its own bosom to those of another! This explains also why
            bodily and sexual pleasures fall short of <tei:pb n="179"/> mental joys in fecundity,
            not even excepting the case in which sexual pleasure has become fruitful and instigates
            life in the form of a new human being. That is why memory has so little to do with the
            nose, the thumbs, the stomach, or the genus, and so much more to do with the brain;
            ultimately memory is really itself an activity of the brain and not of the
            senses.</tei:ab>

      </tei:div>
   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0002">
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker October 17, 1911</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1911-10-17T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-08-26</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description/>
         <dc:subject/>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, </tei:hi><tei:pb n="175"/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:fw type="header" rend="center"><tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:date when="1911"
                  >1911</tei:date></tei:fw><tei:lb/>
            <tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:date when="1911-10-17">17. Okt. </tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0002-se01"><tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:hi rend="bold"
               >Teuerungsrevolte in Wien, die ein Menschenopfer gefordert.</tei:hi><tei:lb/> In
            solch' schweren Krisen werden endlich auch Eingeständnisse laut, daß nicht, wie man bis
            dahin meinte, notwendige u. vernünftig begründete Wirkungen im wirtschaftlichen Leben zu
            Tage treten, die nur zufällig, ohne daß den Menschen irgendwie eine Schuld zugesprochen
            werden könnte, zu einer Teuerung führen, sondern daß ganz willkürliche verbrecherische
            Bosheit u. Gier im Spiele sind, die unter dem Deckmantel einer elenden völlig
            unzulänglichen Wissenschaft mutwillig von wirtschaftlichen Gesetzen sprechen, um Wucher
            treiben zu können. Wer noch eines Beweises dafür bedarf, daß nur der Menschen
            Bestialität, die über ihre Leerheit nicht hinwegzukommen weiß, die letzte Ursache der
            gegenwärtigen sozialen Uebel ist, wird sich ohnehin bald davon überzeugen, ganz einfach
            dadurch, daß die Teuerung eben wird revoziert werden müssen. Man trieb Wucher, solange
            man es duldete; er wird verschwinden, sobald man ihm entgegen tritt.Vor Jahrhunderten
            hielt man ja die Einrichtungen in Frankreich, Rußland doch ebenso für wirtschaftliche
            Notwendigkeiten u. wohin sind sie?</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, </tei:hi><tei:pb n="175"/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:fw type="header" rend="center"><tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:date when="1911"
                  >1911</tei:date></tei:fw><tei:lb/>
            <tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:date when="1911-10-17">October 17</tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab corresp="r0002-se01"><tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:hi rend="bold">Revolt in Vienna
               over price rises, which demands a human sacrifice</tei:hi><tei:lb/>In such severe
            crises as this, admissions at long last come to the surface that <tei:supplied
               reason="clarity">it was</tei:supplied> not, as had hitherto been claimed, necessary
            and rationally-based fluctuations in the world of commerce that come about, effects that
            ‒ only by accident, without guilt of any sort being attributable to any individuals ‒
            lead to an increase in prices; but instead that entirely random criminal wickedness and
            greed are at work which, under the cover of a wretched totally incompetent <tei:supplied
               reason="clarity">economic</tei:supplied> theory, maliciously speak of economic laws,
            in order to allow usury be practised. Anyone who still needs proof that it is only the
            bestiality of men, which does not know how to overcome its vacuity, that is the ultimate
            cause of the current social evil, will forthwith be persuaded quite simply that the
            price increase will just have to be withdrawn. Usury was practised as long as it was
            tolerated. It will vanish the moment it is confronted. Centuries ago the means did in
            fact exist in France and Russia, but equally for commercial emergencies, and where have
            they gone to?</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

      </tei:div>
   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0003">
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker October 18, 1911</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1911-10-18T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-08-26</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description/>
         <dc:subject/>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, </tei:hi><tei:pb n="175"/><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:date when="1911-10-18">18.</tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0003-se01"><tei:handShift new="#JK"/>Bei einem Neubau
            spielt sich folgendes ab: Ein Schwerfuhrwerker will eine übergroße Wagenladung vom Fleck
            bringen, während die vorgespannten Tiere sich als zu schwach erweisen. Da kommt ein
            anderer Schwerfuhrwerker dazu, um seinem Collegen vom Fach beizustehen. Er entfesselt
            gegenüber den armen Tieren eine so erschreckende Brutalität, daß die Passanten in
            stärkste Aufregung darüber versetzt werden. Zu Rede gestellt schreit er trotzig u. mit
            einem Tone, der auf einen Abgrund von Brutalität schließen läßt: „Wir müssen arbeiten.“
            Nachdem aber die Tiere trotz <tei:pb n="176"/> Peitschenhieben versagen, kommen die
            beiden Kutscher auf die Idee, das Erdreich um die Räder abzugraben. Nun geht das
            Fuhrwerk von statten.</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0003-se02">Welcher Unfug, der das Zeitalter getreu
            wiederspiegelt! Die von außen in den Kutscher hineingetragene, durch Organisation so
            gefährlich geförderte Ueberschätzung der Leistung, die aus ihm einen erbitterten Gegner
            der Menschheit macht. Die Verbitterung läßt er dann die armen Tiere entgelten. Wie
            bezeichnend diese Ausstrahlung der ersten Lüge!</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0003-se03">Einem Passanten gelingt es indessen einen
            Schutzmann aufzutreiben, den er eigens zur Tier-Tragödie herbei müht. Eben an diesen
            Schutzmann wende ich mich selbst, indem ich den Üebeltäter mit Fingern bezeichne, worauf
            ich aber vom Schutzmann folgende, für meine Heimat bezeichnende, charakteristische
            Antwort erhalte: „Ja, da bedaure ich, Herr Doktor; Sie wissen daß ich von einem anderen
            Raijan bin u. das ist nur meine Nebenbeschäftigung.“</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, </tei:hi><tei:pb n="175"/><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:date when="1911-10-18"><tei:supplied reason="dating"
                  >October</tei:supplied> 18</tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab corresp="r0003-se01"><tei:handShift new="#JK"/>The following takes place at a
            construction site: the driver of a heavy horse-drawn cart wishes to move an overweight
            waggonload from the spot, whereas the harnessed horses prove too weak. Another heavy
            horse-drawn carter turns up to assist his fellow driver. He attacks the poor animals
            with such shocking brutality that passers-by become extremely agitated by it. When
            accosted <tei:supplied reason="clarity">by them</tei:supplied>, he shouts defiantly and
            in a tone of voice that suggests an abyss of brutality: "We've <tei:hi rend="italic"
               >got</tei:hi> to work." However, after the animals, despite <tei:pb n="176"/> much
            whipping, refuse to budge, the two coachmen come up with the idea of levelling the
            ground around the wheels. Now the vehicle moves off.</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0003-se02">What nonesense, which faithfully reflects its own time! The
            overrating of achievement inculcated from outside into the coachdriver, and so dangerous
            promoted through organization, which makes of him an embittered enemy of society. He
            then inflicts that embitterment on the poor animals. How indicative this outward
            reverberation of the first lie!</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0003-se03">A passer-by succeeds meanwhile in getting hold of a policeman,
            whose attention he expressly draws to the tragedy of the animals. I myself turn to this
            same policeman in pointing the finger at the malefactor, whereupon, however, I receive
            from the policeman the following answer, characteristic for my home town: "Yes, but I
            regret to tell you, Doctor: I am from another region, and this is only a subsidiary
            responsibility for me."</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

      </tei:div>
   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0004">
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker October 20, 1911</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1911-10-20T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-08-26</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description/>
         <dc:subject/>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, </tei:hi><tei:pb n="176"/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:fw type="header" rend="center"><tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:date when="1911"
                  >1911</tei:date></tei:fw><tei:lb/>
            <tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:date when="1911-10-20">20./10</tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0004-se01"><tei:handShift new="#JK"/>Was die Menschen
            ihre Entwicklung nennen ist leere, emphatische Selbstbeschmeichlung, denn im Grunde ist,
            was ihr so erscheint, nur eine unendliche Serie von Undankbarkeiten wider die größten
            Geister. Sie tritt nur aus der einen in die andere u. glaubt sich zu entwickeln. Bevor
            sie die Lehren eines Moses verstanden, nahm sie die neuen eines Christus an; u. noch hat
            sie diese mißverstanden u. schon ist sie bei Luther angelangt; und nun will sie weiter,
            noch ehe sie den letzteren begriffen. Und so kommt es, daß während die früher genannten
            großen Menschen eines u. dasselbe meinten u. predigten, die übrige <tei:pb n="177"/>
            Menschheit sich, wie sie sagt, „entwickelt“! Welcher <tei:sic>Wiederspruch</tei:sic>
            zwischen dem Stationären jener u. der behaupteten angeblichen „Entwicklung“ der
            Menschheit!</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0004-se02">Niemals aber wird eine Annäherung stattfinden
            u. das Stationäre der großen Geister zugleich ein Stationäres der ganzen Menschheit
            werden.</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0004-se03">Den Aequator u. die übrigen Breite ‒ u.
            Längsgrade haben die Menschen in den Erdglobus eingezeichnet; ähnlich zeichnen sie in
            die Zeit <tei:hi rend="underline">Festtage</tei:hi> ein, ‒ ein imaginierter Notbehelf
            wohl in beiden Fallen. Kein Aequator drückt die Erde ‒ kein Festtag ritzt die Zeit. Man
            will dem Alltag den Festtag entgegenstellen? Da nützt es nichts, den Gegensatz blos
            durch den roten Kalenderstrich anzudeuten! Denn was Alltag heißt, liegt doch nur in den
            Menschen selbst, denen das Leben, wenn es kein fortlaufender Festtag ist, doch nur,
            trotz allen proklamirten Festtagen, ein ewiger Alltag bleibt.</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0004-se04">
            <tei:lg type="stanza">
               <tei:head><tei:handShift new="#HS-ink"/><tei:hi rend="bold">(nach dem
                     Englischen)</tei:hi></tei:head>
               <tei:lb/>
               <tei:l>Augenblicken die Stunde bereiten,</tei:l>
               <tei:lb/>
               <tei:l>Einzelgedanken des Werkes Pracht,</tei:l>
               <tei:lb/>
               <tei:l>Samenkörner der Baumwelt Herrlichkeiten,</tei:l>
               <tei:lb/>
               <tei:l>Wassertropfen des Stromes Macht.</tei:l>
               <tei:lb/>
               <tei:l>Bescheid'ne Liebesgaben den Himmel</tei:l>
               <tei:lb/>
               <tei:l>Zaubern in's ird'sche Lebensgetümmel.</tei:l>
               <tei:lb/>
            </tei:lg></tei:ab>

      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, </tei:hi><tei:pb n="176"/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:fw type="header" rend="center"><tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:date when="1911"
                  >1911</tei:date></tei:fw><tei:lb/>
            <tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:date when="1911-10-20">October 20</tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab corresp="r0004-se01"><tei:handShift new="#JK"/>What people call their development
            is empty, emphatic self-conceit, for at its root is, as it appears to itself, only an
            endless series of ingratitudes toward the great spirits. It has only to move from one to
            the next for it to believe itself to be developing. Before it has understood the
            teachings of a Moses it has adopted those of a Christ; and having still misunderstood
            the latter it has already moved on to Luther; and now it wants to go further before it
            has even grasped the last of these. And so it comes about that while the previously
            named great men proclaimed and preached one and the same thing, the remainder of <tei:pb
               n="177"/> mankind, as it says, "develops"! What a contradiction between the fixity of
            the latter and the alleged "development" of mankind!</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0004-se02">But there will never be a reconciliation, and the fixity of
            the great spirits at the same time <tei:supplied reason="clarity">will</tei:supplied>
            become a fixity of the whole of humanity.</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0004-se03">People have incised into the earth's globe the Equator and the
            other lines of latitude ‒ and longitude; they have likewise incised into the course of
            time <tei:hi rend="underline">holidays</tei:hi>, ‒ no doubt considering them to be a
            helpful device in each case. No Equator is imprinted on the earth's surface ‒ no holiday
            is scratched into the surface of time. Is the idea to differentiate the holiday from the
            everyday? There is no advantage in indicating the contrast merely by a red line on the
            calendar! For that which constitutes the everyday inheres solely in men themselves, for
            whom life, if it is not one long holiday, is and remains ‒ despite all the days
            proclaimed as holidays ‒ merely one eternal everyday.</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0004-se04">
            <tei:lg type="stanza">
               <tei:head><tei:handShift new="#HS-ink"/><tei:hi rend="bold">(from the
                     English)</tei:hi></tei:head>
               <tei:lb/>
               <tei:l>Instants make up the hour,</tei:l>
               <tei:lb/>
               <tei:l>Single thoughts the splendor of the work,</tei:l>
               <tei:lb/>
               <tei:l>Seedcorns the glories of the tree world,</tei:l>
               <tei:lb/>
               <tei:l>Waterdrops the might of the river.</tei:l>
               <tei:lb/>
               <tei:l>Modest gifts magically bring heaven</tei:l>
               <tei:lb/>
               <tei:l>Into the hurly-burly of earthly life.</tei:l>
               <tei:lb/>
            </tei:lg>
         </tei:ab>

      </tei:div>
   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0005">
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker October 22, 1911</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1911-10-22T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-08-26</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description/>
         <dc:subject/>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, </tei:hi><tei:pb n="179"/><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:date when="1911-10-22">22. Okt.</tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0005-se01"><tei:handShift new="#JK"/>Was nützt den
            Menschen all' ihre Fruchtbarkeit, wenn diese am Ende doch nur Unfruchtbares
            hervorbringt?</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0005-se02">Vom <tei:hi rend="underline">Lesen</tei:hi>.
            Es ist unbillig vom Leser eine Hingabe zu fordern, die ihn außer Stande setzen würde,
            das Buch auch mit Urteil zu lesen. Urteilslosigkeit u. Naivität dürfen nicht für
            dasselbe gehalten werden, da Naivität sehr wohl auch das Urteil in sich einschließen
            kann. Um dieses zu verstehen ist es nötig, das Wesen des Urteils zu erforschen.</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0005-se03">Der Stoff als Teil der unendlichen Welt steht
            mit dieser hoch über dem Menschen, der ihn aus der Unendlichkeit herausgreifen, u. in
            die Darstellung bannen will. Wie hoch steht nicht auch z.B. über einem <tei:rs
               type="person" key="entity-000294">Göthe</tei:rs> jenes Menschheitsproblem, das im
               <tei:title>Faust</tei:title> zur Lösung gelangen sollte. So wird denn schon der
            Autor, selbst der genialste, am Stoff gemessen, indem man auf Grund der Judizien, die
            der Stoff selbst entgegen bringt, darüber urteilt u. entscheidet, ob der Autor dem Stoff
            gerecht wurde, oder nicht. Eben dieses Geschäft bleibt auch dem Leser nicht erspart; er
            ist's ja, der den Stoff mindestens empfängt, wenn er ihn nicht selbst erzeugt u. auch
            ihm steht die Beziehung zum Stoff doch nicht minder offen, wie dem Autor. Und so kommt
            es, daß eigentlich beide, Dich- <tei:pb n="180"/> ter, wie Leser, sich dem Stoff
            hingeben, jeder freilich in seiner Art. Nicht also Hingabe an den Dichter fordere man
            vom Leser, sondern nur Hingabe an den Stoff. Nur im Falle der letzteren ist das höchste
            Ideal zu erreichen möglich, daß der Leser aus seiner eigenen Hingabe an den Stoff
            Naivität schöpft, um den Stoff in sich voll aufzunehmen u. zugleich soviel Urteil, um am
            Stoff gleichsam mit dem Autor mitschöpferisch, auch die Verfehlungen des Autors wider
            den Stoff, herausfinden u. verurteilen zu können.</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0005-se04">Währender Zeit ‒ während der Zeit . .
            lateinische Konstruktion.</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0005-se05"><tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:date
               when="1911-10-22">22. Okt. 1911</tei:date>.<tei:lb/><tei:title>Frankfurter
               Zeitung</tei:title><tei:lb/>Prof. Richard Meyer<tei:lb/>„Antworten sind immer
            provisorisch ‒ Fragen können ewig sein.</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0005-se06">Alle Erfinder sind arme Leute gewesen ‒ alle
            reichen Leute waren Erben.</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0005-se07">Es gibt ja so viele Arten von Unbildung, als
            es Arten von Bildung gibt. Wir wollen nicht leugnen, daß es auch eine spezifisch
            humanistische Unbildung gibt.</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0005-se08">Exakt nennen wir diejenige Forschung, die sich
            auf die methodisch zulässigen Fehler beschränkt.</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0005-se09">Auch der größte u. ergiebigste Landbesitz
            erregt nicht soviel Neid, wie ein verhältnismäßig geringeres Kapitalvermögen. Auch die
            umfänglichste Gelehrsamkeit können die unvermögenden noch verzeihen; aber
            Gedankenreichtum beleidigt jeden Proletarier.“</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, </tei:hi><tei:pb n="179"/><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:date when="1911-10-22">October 22</tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab corresp="r0005-se01"><tei:handShift new="#JK"/>What value to mankind is all its
            fruitfulness, when in the end the latter brings forth nothing by
            unfruitfulness?</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0005-se02">Concerning <tei:hi rend="underline">reading</tei:hi>. It is
            unfair to demand of the reader a level of dedication that leaves him incapable of
            reading the book also with judgement. Lack of judgement and naivety ought not to be
            considered the same, since naivety can perfectly well include also judgement. In order
            to understand this it is necessary to examine the very nature of judgement.</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0005-se03">The material, as part of the infinite world, stands high
            within this world above the head of man, who strives to identify it from within that
            infinitude and capture it by means of representation. How far above even a <tei:rs
               type="person" key="entity-000294">Goethe</tei:rs>, for example, hangs that human
            problem that was eventually to attain its solution in <tei:title level="m"
               >Faust</tei:title>? Thus the author, even the greatest of them, will be measured
            against the material, inasmuch as one will judge ‒ on the basis of indicators arising
            from the material itself ‒ and decide whether or not the author has done justice to the
            material. Nor is the reader spared this same business: it is indeed he who at least
            receives the material, even if he has not created it himself, and his relationship to
            the material is at least as apparent as the author's. And so it happens that in fact
            both ‒ poet <tei:pb n="180"/> and reader alike ‒ dedicate themselves to the material,
            each of course in his own way. It is therefore not dedication to the poet that is
            demanded of the reader but rather simply dedication to the material. Only in the case of
            the latter is the highest ideal attainable: that the reader, by dedicating himself to
            the material, creates a direct relationship in order fully to absorb the material and at
            the same time acquire sufficient judgement to, so to speak, become creative alongside
            the author and capable of seeking out even the author's failings vis-à-vis the material
            and condemning them.</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0005-se04">Enduring time ‒ during the time . . Latin
            construction.</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0005-se05"><tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:date when="1911-10-22">October
               22, 1911</tei:date><tei:lb/><tei:title level="j">Frankfurter
            Zeitung</tei:title><tei:lb/>Prof. Richard Meyer<tei:lb/>"Answers are always provisional
            ‒ questions can be eternal.</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0005-se06">All inventors have been reduced to poverty ‒ all rich people
            were inheritors.</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0005-se07">There are in truth as many types of uneducatedness as there
            are types of educatedness. Let us not deny that there exists also a specifically
            humanistic uneducatedness.</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0005-se08">We call 'exact' that kind of research that limits itself to
            methodically admissable errors.</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0005-se09">Even the largest and most lucrative piece of real estate does
            not arouse as much envy as a relatively small capital wealth. Those without any
            financial means can still excuse even the most all-encompassing erudition, but wealth of
            ideas offends every member of the proletariat."</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

      </tei:div>
   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0006">
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker October 25, 1911</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1911-10-25T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-08-26</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description/>
         <dc:subject/>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, </tei:hi><tei:pb n="186"/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:fw type="header" rend="center"><tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:date when="1911-11"
                  >November</tei:date></tei:fw><tei:lb/>
            <tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:date when="1911-10-25">25. Oktober</tei:date>
            (zurückdatiert.)</tei:opener>
         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0006-se01"><tei:handShift new="#JK"/>22000 Täfelchen aus
            Nineve u. Assuan harren der Entzifferung nach 3000 Jahren. Wie stramm doch die
               Nemesis<tei:note xml:id="r0006-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Nemesis: Greek
               goddess of retribution, the punisher of crime, or of arrogance toward the
               gods.</tei:note> ihres Amtes waltet: Der Menschheit, die sie nicht vor so und so viel
            Jahrhunderten ordentlich lesen wollte, ist es nicht erspart geblieben, sie jetzt unter
            größeren Schwierigkeiten lesen zu müssen!<tei:note xml:id="r0006-fn02" type="editorial"
               place="foot">Schenker may be referring to the landing of Italian troops in Libya on
               October 25 as part of the Italy-Turkish War of that month, which was heavily reported
               in the <tei:title level="j">Neue freie Presse</tei:title> that morning.</tei:note>
            Wahrhaftig, der Menschheit bleibt nichts Erspart.</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, </tei:hi><tei:pb n="186"/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:fw type="header" rend="center"><tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:date when="1911-11"
                  >November</tei:date></tei:fw><tei:lb/>
            <tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:date when="1911-10-25">October 25</tei:date> (back-dated) </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab corresp="r0006-se01"><tei:handShift new="#JK"/>After 3,000 years, 22,000 small
            tablets from Ninevah and Aswan still await their decipherment. How very strictly does
               Nemesis<tei:ptr corresp="#r0006-fn01" type="footnote"/> discharge her duties! Mankind
            ‒ who until however many centuries ago showed no interest in deciphering them accurately
            ‒ will now face even greater difficulties in doing so.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0006-fn02"
               type="footnote"/> In truth, nothing gets any easier for mankind.</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

      </tei:div>
   </sdo:record>

   <sdo:record ID="r0007">
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker October 30, 1911</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1911-10-30T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-08-26</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description/>
         <dc:subject/>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, </tei:hi><tei:pb n="181"/><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:date when="1911-10-30">30. Oktober.</tei:date><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="italic">This essay, in Jeanette
                  Kornfeld's hand, is corrected in blue crayon by Heinrich; final reading only given
                  here:</tei:hi></tei:note><tei:lb/>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0007-se01"><tei:handShift new="#JK"/>Schon zwei Wochen
            lang dauert der Angriff u. der Kampf eines Wiener Kunstschriftstellers, D<tei:hi
               rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Abels, wider den Generaldirektor der Kön: Museen in
               <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>, Exzellenz Bode.<tei:note
               xml:id="r0007-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Wilhelm (von) Bode (1845‒1929),
               German lawyer, art historian and museum curator. Starting as an assistant curator of
               sculpture in the Royal Museums of Berlin in 1872, he rose steadily through the ranks
               until he became General Director of the Royal Museums in 1905. Internationally
               respected and influential, he wrote extensively on art history, especially art of the
               Italian renaissance.</tei:note> Ersterer beschuldigt letzteren eines wissentlich
            falschen Gutachtens inbezug auf ein <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003466"
               >Rembrandt</tei:rs>bild u. läßt durchblicken, daß Bodes Praktiken auch in anderen
            Fällen der Kunst u. Kunstfreunden ungeheueren Schaden gebracht hat. Nun, daß Herr Bode
            falsche Gutachten abgibt, darf schon aus dem Grunde als ausgemacht gelten, weil er kein
            Impedimentum der Kennerschaft hat: wer sich so wenig auf Bilder versteht, wie er, hat es
            leichter als man glaubt, auch ein falsches Gutachten wissentlich abzugeben. Nur die
            Kennerschaft bedeutet Charakter, Nicht-Kennerschaft aber u. Charakterlosigkeit sind
            sicher Synonima. Die Aufregung der Welt über Bodes Charakterlosigkeit ist daher nur als
            eine Naivität zu belächeln.</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0007-se02">Weitaus interessanter aber ist die Art, wie
            ein Wiener Anwalt in den Prozess eingegriffen hat, mit Absicht seinem Mandanten D<tei:hi
               rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Abels einen Dienst erweisen wollte, gerade aber mit
            der vermeintlichen Dienstleistung die an sich vornehme u. reine Position des Clienten
            vor aller Welt verschlechtert hat. Mit dem üblichen, in den Schulsälen erworbenen
            Denkvermögen, dachte er auch auf dem Streit Bode's u. Abels um <tei:rs type="person"
               key="entity-003466">Rembrandt</tei:rs>werte den usuellen „Mahnbrief“ aplicieren zu
            müssen, den er ja schon unzählige male praktiziert hat, wenn er z.B. mehr oder minder
            große Schuldbeträge oder sonstige Einhaltung von Verträgen einforderte. Daß das
            Mahnbriefchen in der großen Welt nach einer „Erpressung“ riechen muß ‒ dieses
            vorauszusehen war der Anwalt unfähig. Und wahrscheinlich bis zur Stunde vermag er es
            vielleicht nicht zu begreifen, wie es möglich sei, daß ein korrekter anwaltschaftlicher
            Akt einer an sich <tei:unclear reason="original_unclear">gerechten</tei:unclear> u.
            würdigen Sache noch mehr Schaden verursacht, als Herrn Bode's Gutachten!</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0007-se03"><tei:pb n="182"/><tei:handShift new="#JK"
               /><tei:date when="1911-10-30">30. Oktober</tei:date><tei:lb/><tei:lb/><tei:note
               type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="italic">This essay, in Jeanette
                  Kornfeld's hand, is corrected in blue crayon by Heinrich; final reading only given
                  here:</tei:hi></tei:note><tei:lb/><tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:rs type="person"
               key="entity-000938">Wedekind</tei:rs> „<tei:title>Erdgeist</tei:title>“.<tei:note
               xml:id="r0007-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Wedekind's <tei:title level="m"
                  >Erdgeist</tei:title>, written in 1895 and first performed in 1898 in Leipzig, was
               being given in Vienna at the Residenzbühne, with Eveline Landing in the role of Lulu
               and Albert Steinrück as Dr. Schön. The run had begun on October 25 and had been
               extended to the end of the month (<tei:title level="j">Neue freie Presse</tei:title>,
               October 22, 24, 29, 1911; review of the production, October 26, p. 12, col. 2). It is
               unclear whether Schenker actually attended this production, or whether (as often) he
               is commenting after reading the text. Schenker had previously commented on Wedekind
               in his diary for April 30 (<tei:title level="m">Hidalla</tei:title>) and September 5
                  (<tei:title level="m">Frühlingserwachen</tei:title>), 1907. — Hellmut Federhofer
               prints Schenker's comments on <tei:title level="m">Erdgeist</tei:title> and
                  <tei:title level="m">Frühlingserwachen</tei:title> in full (<tei:bibl><tei:title
                     level="m">Henrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern und Briefen ...</tei:title>
                  (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), pp. 296‒98</tei:bibl>), and his remark that
                  <tei:title level="m">Frühlingserwachen</tei:title> was known to Schenker "nur
               durch Zeitungsberichte" may imply that he thought Schenker had seen the currently
               running performance.</tei:note> Das Dokument eines Autors, der hinter sein eigenes
            Wort nicht mehr sieht, sobald es nur das fünfte oder zehnte ist. Zugleich Dokument des
            allgemeinen Verfalls an Denk- u. Kunstnerven, also an Männlichkeit.</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0007-se04">Im Prolog will <tei:rs type="person"
               key="entity-000938">W.</tei:rs> dem Publikum als ein „Tier“ suggerieren; das Recht
            dazu steht ihm wohl frei, nur muß er als Dichter mit der Ausführung Wort halten.
            Freilich wirkt die Suggestion auf das <tei:sic>wiederstandslose</tei:sic> Publikum, das
            sich ihm bequemt, von vornherein in Lulu das Tier zu sehen; wer aber genauer zusieht
            findet, daß die vom Autor vorgebrachten Tatsachen eher für Lulu, als gegen sie sprechen.
            Man muß den Eindruck gewinnen, daß eigentlich nur der Chefredakteur D<tei:hi
               rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Schön eine männliche Lulu vorstellt, d.h.: was der
            Autor mit Absicht an der weiblichen zeigen wollte, ist ihm wider seine Absicht blos bei
            der männlichen gelungen. D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Schön hat sie
            aufgelesen, ausgebildet, zu seiner Geliebten gemacht u. sie dann um es drastisch
            auszudrücken je nach Bedarf seiner Zeitung, an andere Männer verheiratet, an deren Ehe
            er aber trotzdem noch partizipiert hat. Dieses ungeheuerliche Demoralisieren mag Lulu’s
            Instinkten vielleicht einmal bewußt u. <tei:sic>wiederwärtig</tei:sic> gewesen sein;
            aber in der Folge der längeren Zeit, hat der Schein eines Gewaltmenschen über die
            Wahrheit in Lulu’s Empfindung gesiegt. Doch freilich nur vorübergehend:‒ Der
            Gewaltmensch entpuppt sich als ein jämmerlich hilfloses Wesen u. damit gewinnt die
            ursprüngliche durch den Schein erstickte Empfindung neuerdings die Oberhand. Lulu weiß,
            wem sie gegenüber stand u. noch gegenüber steht u. verliert sich in eine Lebensweise,
            die ihre Enttäuschung u. Verbitterung immerhim rechtfertigt.</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0007-se05">Die Fehler des Autors liegen somit klar
            zutage: Meint er D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Schön als Gewaltmenschen oder
            nicht? Wenn als Gewaltmenschen, so ist die Jämmerlichkeit im Schluß des 3. Aktes ein
            technischer Widerspruch dagegen; <tei:pb n="183"/> wenn nicht als Gewaltmenschen, so ist
               D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Schön weil Urheber des Lulu-Schicksals, eben
            darum eine noch <tei:sic>wiederwärtigere</tei:sic> Erscheinung als Lulu.</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0007-se06">Ferner: Meint der Autor Lulu als Bestie oder
            nicht? Wenn als Bestie, so müßte ihr Schicksal mit ihr selbst, aus ihrem eigenen Blute
            u. nicht auf Grund der Urheberschaft des D<tei:hi rend="supralinear">r.</tei:hi> Schön
            über sie kommen. Wenn nicht als Bestie, so ist es ein Fehler des Autors, sie allein
            dennoch zum Mordbeil<tei:note xml:id="r0007-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:hi
                  rend="italic">Mordbeil</tei:hi>: obsolete: an axe with which to murder someone,
               either in battle, or by beheading; more generally: any type of murderous weapon. The
               word goes back to the middle ages. In <tei:title level="m">Erdgeist</tei:title>, Lulu
               was eventually murdered by Jack the Ripper, who killed his victims by cutting their
               throats then mutilating their corpses; but this reference is not to her final death,
               but to her treatment by several men. Or is Schenker saying that it is Lulu who
               becomes the "murder weapon" for several men?</tei:note> so vieler Männer zu machen.
            Kürzer ausgedrückt: Das Drama leidet an der Figur des D<tei:hi rend="supralinear"
               >r.</tei:hi> Schön, der im selben Maße als er Lulu moralisch entlastet, uns
            verhindert, die Bestie lediglich in Lulu zu sehen. Dieser Hauptfehler des Autors stammt
            aus seiner eigenen geringen Durchempfindung des Stoffes: er kennt ihn selbst nicht! Es
            ist daher überflüssig weitere moralische Bewertungen über diese u. jene Hauptperson,
            diese oder jene Nebenperson aufzustellen, wo der Autor selbst eine so mangelhafte
            Leistung vollbracht hat. Der Hauptfehler hat weitere Ausstrahlungen an Nebenfehlern u.
            wegen all’ dieser Fehler kann es niemandem gelingen, in die Nacht des Autors klarer
            hinein zu sehen, als er in ihr selbst sehen konnte.</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, </tei:hi><tei:pb n="181"/><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:date when="1911-10-30">October 30</tei:date><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="italic">This essay, in Jeanette
                  Kornfeld's hand, is corrected in blue crayon by Heinrich; final reading only given
                  here:</tei:hi></tei:note><tei:lb/>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab corresp="r0007-se01"><tei:handShift new="#JK"/>The attack and campaign by a
            Viennese writer on art, Dr. Abel, against the General Director of the Royal Museums in
               <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002501">Berlin</tei:rs>, His Excellence
               <tei:supplied reason="identity">Wilhelm</tei:supplied> Bode,<tei:ptr
               corresp="#r0007-fn01" type="footnote"/> has been going on already for two weeks. The
            former accuses the latter of giving a knowingly flawed opinion concerning a painting by
               <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-003466">Rembrandt</tei:rs>, and exposes Bode's
            methods as having caused enormous damage in other cases of art and art lovers. That Mr.
            Bode pronounces false opinions may readily be verified on the grounds that he has does
            not suffer the impediment of connoisseurship. Anyone who understands as little about
            paintings as he does finds it easier than one might think knowingly to pronounce a
            flawed opinion. Only connoisseurship denotes character; non-conoisseurship and
            characterlessness are, on the other hand, unquestionably synonyms. The flurry of
            interest in the world over Bode's characterlessness is accordingly to be smiled at as
            mere naivety.</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0007-se02">Far more interesting, though, is the way in which a Viennese
            attorney has intervened in the legal proceedings with the intention of wanting to
            provide a service to his client, Dr. Abel, but precisely with the supposed service he
            has worsened the standing of his client, in itself distinguished and unblemished, before
            all the world. With the customary powers of reasoning acquired in the lecture-halls of
            the schools, he thought he still had to submit the standard monitory letter in the
            litigation between Bode and Abel regarding the value of <tei:rs type="person"
               key="entity-003466">Rembrandt</tei:rs> that had been his normal practice countless
            times whenever he was, for example, calling in more or less large amounts of debt or
            other obligations on contracts. That to the world outside the monitory letter is bound
            to smack of "extortion" ‒ this the attorney was incapable of foreseeing. And apparently
            right up to the last moment he was perhaps unable to grasp how a correct action in an in
            itself <tei:unclear reason="reading">just</tei:unclear> and worthy matter on the part of
            an attorney might possibly cause more damage than Mr. Bode's opinion!</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0007-se03"><tei:pb n="182"/><tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:date
               when="1911-10-30">October 30</tei:date><tei:lb/><tei:lb/><tei:note type="editorial"
               place="inline"><tei:hi rend="italic">This essay, in Jeanette Kornfeld's hand, is
                  corrected in blue crayon by Heinrich; final reading only given
               here:</tei:hi></tei:note><tei:lb/><tei:handShift new="#JK"/><tei:rs type="person"
               key="entity-000938">Wedekind</tei:rs>
            <tei:title level="m">Earth Spirit</tei:title>.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0007-fn02"
               type="footnote"/> The document of an author who can see nothing further behind his
            own words as soon as they number five or ten. It is at the same time a document of the
            general decline in the ability to mentally control thought and art, thus in
            masculinity.</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0007-se04">In the Prolog, <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000938"
               >Wedekind</tei:rs> seeks to convey <tei:supplied reason="clarity">Lulu</tei:supplied>
            to the audience as an "animal"; he certainly has the right to do so, but he must, as
            playwright, stay true as the work develops. Admittedly, the suggestion acts upon his
            unresisting audience, making it acquiesce in seeing Lulu from the outset as the animal;
            but anyone who looks more closely finds that the facts brought forward by the author
            speak for rather than against her. The impression must prevail that actually only the
            newspaper chief editor, Dr. Schön, represents a male Lulu, i.e. that that which the
            playwright intentionally tried to show by means of the feminine has, contrary to his
            intention, succeeded merely through the male. Dr. Schön has picked her up, instructed
            her, made her his lover, and then (to express it in extreme form), always with his
            newspaper's needs in mind, marries her off to other men, in whose marriage he has
            nevertheless continued to involve himself. This atrocious demoralisation may perhaps at
            one time have been conscious and repulsive to Lulu's instincts; however, with the
            passage of time the semblance of an authority figure has triumphed over the truth in
            Lulu's perception. But really only in the short run:‒ The authority figure turns out to
            be a wretchedly helpless being, and with that her original perception, suppressed in the
            interim by this semblance, once more gains the upper hand. Lulu knows with whom she has
            been and still is dealing, and abandons herself to a mode of life that nevertheless
            justifies her disappointment and embitterment.</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0007-se05">The author's failings therefore come clearly into view: Does
            he intend Dr. Schön as an authority figure or not? If an authority figure, the
            wretchedness at the end of Act III is technically contradictory to that; <tei:pb n="183"
            /> if not as an authority figure, then is Dr. Schön, because he is the instigator of
            Lulu's fate, precisely for that reason an even more repulsive figure than Lulu.</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0007-se06">Furthermore: Does the author intend Lulu as a wild animal or
            not? If as a wild animal, then her fate ought to have derived from her inner self, from
            her own blood, and not at the instigation of Dr. Schön. If not as a wild animal, then it
            is an error on the part of the author to make her alone the butt<tei:ptr
               corresp="#r0007-fn03" type="footnote"/> of so many men. Put more briefly: the drama
            suffers from the figure of Dr. Schön who, to the same degree as he unburdens Lulu
            morally, prevents us from seeing the wild animal solely in Lulu. This prime error by the
            author stems from his own lack of a thorough understanding of the material: he doesn't
            himself know it! It is therefore superfluous to put forward further moral evaluations of
            this or that leading character, this or that minor charcter, when the author himself has
            produced so deficient a piece of work. The prime error has further reverberations out to
            lesser errors, and because of all these errors it is not possible for anyone to see any
            more clearly into the obfuscation of the author than he himself could see into
            it.</tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

      </tei:div>
   </sdo:record>




</sdo:recordCollection>
