<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker"
   xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
   xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
   <!--OJ-01-01_1897-09September, 1897 -  ( Diary Series A box: 01 folder: 01 date: Jan 1, 1897–Dec 31, 1897 pages: 1b, 2b, 3, 3b, 4)
                 
             -->
   <sdo:collectionDesc>
      <sdo:source>
         <!--Select an sdoID from the controlled list -->
         <sdo:diary sdoID="OJ-01-01_1897-09"/>
      </sdo:source>

      <tei:handNotes>
         <tei:handNote xml:id="HS" scope="sole">Heinrich Schenker's hand</tei:handNote>
      </tei:handNotes>

      <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
         <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
         <tei:resp>Transcription, 2017</tei:resp>
         <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2017</tei:resp>
      </tei:respStmt>

      <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD-AR">
         <tei:persName>William Drabkin &amp; Andrea Reiter</tei:persName>
         <tei:resp>Translation, 2017</tei:resp>
      </tei:respStmt>

      <tei:respStmt xml:id="TL">
         <tei:persName>Tamara Lopez</tei:persName>
         <tei:resp>XML Encoding Model</tei:resp>
      </tei:respStmt>
      <!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document -->
      <tei:revisionDesc>
         <tei:change when="2012-10-03" who="#IB">Template Generated</tei:change>
      </tei:revisionDesc>
   </sdo:collectionDesc>

   <sdo:record ID="r0001">
      <!--Use the itemDesc to group information about a single record, e.g. a single diary entry, lessonbook entry or piece of correspondence. 
                         The   contains a series of Dublin Core elements. -->
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker September 12, 1897</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1897-09-12T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2018-01-17</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description/>
         <dc:subject/>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">The text of these four paragraphs is heavily
               edited by Heinrich himself; only the final resultant text is given
            here</tei:note><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
         </tei:opener>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0001-se01"><tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, <tei:pb n="3"
               /></tei:hi><tei:lb/><tei:handShift new="#HS"/><tei:date when="1897-09-12">12.
               9.</tei:date>
            <tei:hi rend="underline">Hamlet</tei:hi>: Verliert den Glauben an das Weib: er begreift
            die eigene Mutter nicht, ebensowenig den Verrath <tei:hi rend="lateinschr"
               >Ophelien</tei:hi>’s. Welcher Schlag für ein junges, dem besten u. edelsten in der
            Welt zugewandten Herz, das Weib so plötzlich in seiner nackten Unmoral vor sich zu
            sehen. Trotz dem Verbot des Geistes macht sich seine Verbitterung gegen das Weib in der
            Szene mit der Mutter Luft, ‒ <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Ophel</tei:hi>. aber liebt er zu
            sehr, um sie noch einem Anderen zu gönnen, daher sein „Geh 'ins Kloster“. (Vielleicht
            auch <tei:hi rend="lateinschr">Egoismus</tei:hi>: mindestens auf dieser Art sollte sie
            ihm treu bleiben.)</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0001-se02"><tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, <tei:pb n="4"
               /></tei:hi><tei:lb/>(1897) Gehört indessen solche Enttäuschung am Weib zur Norm der
            Erlebnisse eines jeden starken, männlichen, also moralischen Charakters, so möchte das
            Genie des Dichters am meisten wohl doch in dem technischen Zug zu bewundern sein, womit
            das Rätsel der etwaigen Mitschuld der Mutter als solches vom wissenden Geist gleichwohl
            für immer verrammelt wird: „Schone deine Mutter“ wiederholt mahnend der Geist. Sagt er
            es etwa aus Ritterlichkeit u. aus Rücksicht, die der Gatte selbst noch im Jenseits der
            unmoralischen u. törichten Schwäche der Frau schulden zu müssen glaubt, oder nur damit
            auch der Sohn gegenüber der Mutter Ritterlichkeit zu üben lernen solle? Vielleicht ist
            es aber seine ewige Weisheit, (die zumal einem Geist so trefflich zu künden ansteht,)
            daß es nämlich zu nichts, zu gar nichts führe, wenn man mit dem Weib ringt, daß hiebei
            weder das Weib noch auch die Situation selbst dadurch ins Klarere rücken? (Vielleicht
            soll das Schmähen Hamlets in der Szene mit der Mutter unter anderm nur dieses beweisen?
            Ach! sie „sieht“ ja den Vater schon längst nicht mehr!)</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0001-se03">Daß Hamlet nicht gerne mordet, steht ja nur
            mit seiner Bildung im Zusammenhange. ‒ Doch kann u. will er deshalb allein seiner Moral
            die Genugtuung des Mordes durchaus nicht versagen, so heiß u. brennend ist ihm ihre
            Macht.</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0001-se04">Ein „spezifisch germanisches“ Stück? Gewiss in
            der Haltung der Technik, der Sprache u. der Bilder, dagegen gehört die Anekdote allen
            Zonen, allen Völkern an. Kann es nicht auch irgendwo anders, z.B. in Italien, einem
            jungen, gebildeten Studenten geben (vom Königsrang u.s.w. abgesehen), dem das Schicksal
            eine ähnliche Bürde aufladet? Dessen Mutter drei Monate nach des Vaters Tode dessen
            Bruder heiratet ‒ man munkelt von Gift, Mord ‒ u.s.w. Würde es dann der ital. Student
            anders mit der Vergeltung halten, als Hamlet? Sicher nicht. (vgl. der Fall meines
            Schülers <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000446">K. v. Klb</tei:rs>!)</tei:ab>

      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">The text of these four paragraphs is heavily
               edited by Heinrich himself; only the final resultant text is given
            here</tei:note><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
         </tei:opener>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0001-se01"><tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, <tei:pb n="3"
               /></tei:hi><tei:lb/><tei:handShift new="#HS"/><tei:date when="1897-09-12">September
               12</tei:date>. <tei:hi rend="underline">Hamlet</tei:hi>: loses his faith in women; he
            does not understand his own mother, no more so Ophelia's betrayal. What a setback for a
            young soul, inclined toward the best and noblest things in the world, so suddenly to see
            women before him in their naked immorality. Despite the ghost's injunction, his
            bitterness towards women comes to the fore in the scene with his mother. Ophelia,
            however, he loves too much to even let her be someone else's; thus his "Get thee to a
            nunnery." (Perhaps also <tei:supplied reason="clarity">a sign of</tei:supplied> egoism:
            at least in this way she ought to remain faithful to him.) </tei:ab>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0001-se02"><tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, <tei:pb n="4"/></tei:hi> (1897)
            If, however, such disappointment in women is part of the norm of experience among all
            strong, masculine – and thus moral – characters, then the poet's genius is perhaps most
            to be admired in the way the puzzle of the mother's possible complicity as such seems
            ever to be inaccessible to the knowing ghost. "Spare thy mother," the ghost repeatedly
            warns. Is he saying this out of chivalrousness and out of caution, which a husband –
            even from beyond the boundary of his wife's immoral and misguided weakness – believes he
            owes her? Or merely so that his son, too, learns to behave chivalrously towards his
            mother? Or is it perhaps his eternal wisdom (which it befits a ghost in particular to
            proclaim), namely that contending with the woman will get one nowhere, nowhere at all,
            that neither the woman nor the situation itself will thereby be made any clearer?
            (Perhaps Hamlet's abusive behavior in the scene with his mother proves only this? Ah,
            she has long since been unable to "see" his father!) </tei:ab>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0001-se03">That Hamlet is an unwilling murderer is indeed related only to
            his upbringing. Yet in spite of all his morality he cannot and will not for this reason
            alone deny himself the satisfaction of murder altogether, so hotly does its power burn
            within him.</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0001-se04">A "specifically Germanic" play? Most definitely in the
            approach to the construction of the plot, the language, and the imagery, and the scenic
            representation. On the other hand, the story belongs to all regions, to all peoples.
            Could there not even be some other place, for example in Italy, where a young, educated
            student (regardless of whether he is of princely rank etc.) upon whose shoulders fate
            has laid a similar burden? Whose mother marries his father's brother three years after
            his death – with rumors of poison, murder – and so on? Would the Italian student behave
            differently from Hamlet with regard to retribution? Surely not. (Compare the case of my
            pupil <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000446">Karl von Klobassa</tei:rs>!)</tei:ab>

      </tei:div>
   </sdo:record>



</sdo:recordCollection>
