<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker"
   xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
   xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">
   <!--OJ-01-10_1911-09September, 1911 -  ( Diary Series A box: 01 folder: 10 date: Jan 1, 1911–Dec 31, 1911 pages: 125-131, 131v, 131a, 132, 132a, 133, 133a, 134-135, 135a, 135b, 136-146, 146a, 147-152, 152a, 153, 153a, 153b, 154-161, 161a, 162-179, 162par-166par, 170-172, 173a-173b, 174-193, 194a, 194b, 195-197 )
                 
             -->
   <sdo:collectionDesc>
      <sdo:source>
         <!--Select an sdoID from the controlled list -->
         <sdo:diary sdoID="OJ-01-10_1911-09"/>
      </sdo:source>

      <tei:handNotes>
         <tei:handNote xml:id="HS-ink" scope="major">Heinrich Schenker's hand, in ink</tei:handNote>
         <tei:handNote xml:id="JK" scope="major">Jeanette Kornfeld's hand</tei:handNote>
         <tei:handNote xml:id="HS-pencil" scope="minor">Heinrich Schenker's hand, in
            pencil</tei:handNote>
      </tei:handNotes>
      <!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below -->
      <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
         <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
         <tei:resp>Transcription, 2019</tei:resp>
         <tei:resp>Translation, 2019</tei:resp>
         <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2019</tei:resp>
         <tei:resp>Footnotes, 2019</tei:resp>
      </tei:respStmt>
      <tei:respStmt xml:id="TL">
         <tei:persName>Tamara Lopez</tei:persName>
         <tei:resp>XML Encoding Model</tei:resp>
      </tei:respStmt>
      <!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document -->
      <tei:revisionDesc>
         <tei:change when="2012-10-03" who="#IB">Template Generated</tei:change>
      </tei:revisionDesc>
   </sdo:collectionDesc>

   <sdo:record ID="r0001">
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker September 1, 1911</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1911-09-01T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-08-19</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description/>
         <dc:subject/>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener/>
         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0001-se01"><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"
                  ><tei:hi rend="italic">See summary diary entry under September 10,
               1911</tei:hi></tei:note></tei:ab>

      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener/>
         <tei:ab corresp="r0001-se01"><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi
                  rend="italic">See summary diary entry under September 10,
            1911</tei:hi></tei:note></tei:ab>

      </tei:div>
   </sdo:record>


   <sdo:record ID="r0002">
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker September 2, 1911</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1911-09-02T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-08-19</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description/>
         <dc:subject/>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener/>
         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0002-se01"><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"
                  ><tei:hi rend="italic">See summary diary entry under September 10,
               1911</tei:hi></tei:note></tei:ab>

      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener/>
         <tei:ab corresp="r0002-se01"><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi
                  rend="italic">See summary diary entry under September 10,
            1911</tei:hi></tei:note></tei:ab>

      </tei:div>
   </sdo:record>


   <sdo:record ID="r0003">
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker September 10, 1911</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1911-09-10T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-08-19</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description/>
         <dc:subject/>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, </tei:hi><tei:pb n="169"/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:handShift next="#JK"/><tei:date when="1911-09-10">10. September.</tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0003-se01"><tei:handShift next="#JK"/><tei:date
               when="1911-08-31">Donnerstag, den 31. August</tei:date> verließen wir <tei:rs
               type="place" key="entity-002256">Sulden</tei:rs> u. traten die Heimreise an. Nachdem
            des morgens Gewitter die Luft abermals gereinigt hatten wir bei angenehmster Temperatur
            schöne Fahrt im offenen Wagen. Unterhalb Gomagoi,<tei:note xml:id="r0003-fn01"
               type="editorial" place="foot">Gomagoi: village (1,275m) 11km (6½ miles)
               north-northwest of Sulden. It lies in the Trafoi Valley at the point where the Sulden
               Valley branches off to the south-southeast toward Sulden. </tei:note> an der Stelle,
            wo der Bach 3 klm. Straße zerstört hat, gab es einen besonderen Anblick: Kleine Kinder,
            Buben u. Mädchen, Halberwachsene, Erwachsenen u. Greise standen mit Körben, sogenannten
            Kraxen bereit, den Reisenden ihr Gepäck abzunehmen, um es auf einem Umweg über den Berg
            weiter zu befördern. In den ersten Tagen nach der Katastrophe waren die Bauern rasch
            dabei, die Not der Reisenden auf unerhörteste Art zu bewuchern; nun hat die Behörde dem
            Raubliergelüste Einhalt geboten u. um mäßigen Lohn leisteten sie die nötigen Dienste.
            Von Spondinig<tei:note xml:id="r0003-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">Spondinig:
               village c. 8 km (= 5 miles) north-northeast of Gomagoi, and 60 km (= 37 miles)
               west-northwest of Bozen (Bolzano) (77 km = 48 miles by road).</tei:note> gieng es per
            Bahn nach <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002310">Bozen</tei:rs>. Nach langem
            Fernhalten von den Menschen brachte uns das erste Zusammentreffen mit den
            alltäglichsten, in ihrer Unzulänglichkeit unerschöpflichen Typen in Berührung. Da
            näherte sich einer, der seine Reisen förmlich nach Art u. Wunsch ihm völlig fremder
            Menschen sozusagen extemporierte u. gegenüber dem Schönsten u. Erhabensten der Natur es
            an Begeisterung nicht weiter brachte, als bis zu den Worten: „Ich freu’ mich d’rauf“,
            die seinen Lippen fast nur zu entschlüpfen schienen, als wäre er schlafend.</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0003-se02">Am nächsten Morgen <tei:note type="editorial"
               place="inline">September 1</tei:note> fuhren wir nach Klobenstein,<tei:note
               xml:id="r0003-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">Klobenstein: village 9 km (= 5½
               miles) northeast of Bozen (Bolzano) (15 km. = 9 miles by road).</tei:note> von wo wir
            besonders den Rosengarten samt Schlern<tei:note xml:id="r0003-fn04" type="editorial"
               place="foot">Rosengarten (2,981m): mountain in the Rosengartengruppe (range); Schlern
               (2,563m): mountain in the Schlerngruppe. Together the two ranges form the
               Schlern-Rosengarten-Gruppe, part of the Dolomites, east of Bozen (Bolzano),
               straddling the South Tyrol and Trentino. Since 1974 they form the Schlern-Rosengarten
               Nature Reserve.</tei:note> in plastischester Form sehen konnten. Die Fülle der Bilder
            machte, zumal bei schönster Luft, einen unvergeßlichen Eindruck u. bot nur zu deutlich
            einen willkommenen Kontrast zur Enge des Suldentals, das wir soeben verlassen. — Die
               Erdpyramiden<tei:note xml:id="r0003-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot">Erdpyramiden:
               2 km (= 1¼ miles) north of Klobenstein. Earth pyramids are natural phonemona
               particular to the South Tyrol. Formed usually from continuous alternation of periods
               of torrential rain and drought, they usually occur after a landslide (the original
               name, <tei:hi rend="italic">Lahntürme</tei:hi>, means literally landslide towers).
               Those of Klobenstein constitute one of three distinct groups on Ritten, a plateau
               above Bozen (Bolzano). For more information and pictures, see <tei:ref
                  type="external" target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earth_pyramids_of_Ritten"
                     ><tei:title level="a">Earth Pyramids of Ritten,</tei:title>
                  <tei:title level="m">wikipedia</tei:title></tei:ref>.</tei:note> hinter
            Klobenstein machen den Eindruck einer Capriole der Natur, wor- <tei:pb n="170"/> über
            man sonst zu lachen geneigt wäre, wenn nicht dahinter eben dieselben Gesetze stunden,
            die seit Ewigkeiten die Welt schaffen u. zerstören.</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0003-se03">Noch am Nachmittag des selben Tages fuhren
            wir, durch den Genuß des Vormittags eher erfrischt als abgespannt, auf den Mendelpaß.
            Von besonderem Zauber sind hier die Schlösser, die als gleichsam in Vergessenheit
            geratenen Petschafte aller Adelsgeschlechter in die ewig vorwärts lebende Natur Züge
            einer längst verrauschten Geschichte gewoben, die zu schön war, um ganz sterben zu
            können. Seither wurde die Erde freilich gerechter aufgeteilt, nur bekommt der Menschheit
            diese Gerechtigkeit sehr schlecht. Wo ehemals blos der eine Raubritter plünderte,
            raubrittern heute an die tausend Zwischenhändler.—</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0003-se04">Der Blick vom Mendelpaß bietet kaum viel
            Ergänzung zu dem vom Klobenstein aus Gesehenen; desto überraschender war das Schauspiel
            eines Alpenglühen, wie wir es in solcher Intensität noch nie u. nirgends gesehen
            haben.</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0003-se05">Den Eingang zur Pfarrkirche in <tei:rs
               type="place" key="entity-002310">Bozen</tei:rs> flankieren zwei Löwen, die auf ihrem
            Rücken Säulen tragen, doch so, daß die letzteren des eigenen Sockels gleichwohl nicht
            entbehren; ein sehr possierlicher Kunstscherz, der aber ernstlich zu bedenken gibt, daß
            nicht alles alte, blos weil es alt ist, wirklich ernst zu nehmen sei. Offenbar ist das
            ein Lapsus eines völlig ungeschulten, primitiven Plastikers, der auf eine sonderbare
            Weise neben Besseren zu Worte gekommen.</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0003-se06">Gegen abend des nächsten Tages <tei:note
               type="editorial" place="inline">September 2?</tei:note> fuhren wir nach Wien. Hier
            wurde sofort Wohnung gesucht u. gefunden<tei:note xml:id="r0003-fn06" type="editorial"
               place="foot">The search for an apartment for Jeanette, and the arrangements for the
               duration of that search, are illuminated by two letters from Heinrich Schenker and
               Jeanette Kornfeld to Moriz Violin: <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-6-5_1">OJ
                  6/5, [1]</tei:ref> and <tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-6-5_2">OJ 6/5,
                  [2]</tei:ref>, August 18 and 26, 1911. Further, OJ 8/1, [9], September 8, 1911,
               indicates that the initial apartment was in Reisnerstraße 27, but that after some
               kind of incident she quickly moved to Jaquingasse 1, 1st floor, apartment
               8.</tei:note> u. die abgelaufene Saison zur letzten Liquidierung gebracht. —</tei:ab>

      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, </tei:hi><tei:pb n="169"/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:handShift next="#JK"/><tei:date when="1911-09-10">September 10</tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab corresp="r0003-se01"><tei:handShift next="#JK"/>On <tei:date when="1911-08-31"
               >Thursday August 31</tei:date> we left <tei:rs type="place" key="entity-002256"
               >Sulden</tei:rs> and began our homeward journey. The air having again been cleared by
            the morning thunderstorm, we had a delightful journey in the open carriage in the most
            pleasant temperature. Below Gomagoi,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0003-fn01" type="footnote"/> at
            the place where the brook had destroyed three kilometers of road, was a remarkable
            sight: small children, babies and girls, youths, grown-ups and old men stood with
            baskets (so-called "Kraxen") ready to unload the travellers' luggage to transport it by
            a diversion over the mountain. In the first few days after the catastrophe, the peasants
            were quick off the mark to exploit the needs of the travellers in the most outrageous
            way. Now the authorities have put a stop to their avaricious appetites, and they
            provided the necessary services at a modest price. The journey continued by rail from
               Spondinig<tei:ptr corresp="#r0003-fn02" type="footnote"/> to <tei:rs type="place"
               key="entity-002310">Bozen</tei:rs>. After we had kept aloof from people <tei:supplied
               reason="clarity">around us</tei:supplied>, our first encounter brought us into
            contact with the most common types, tireless in their inadequacy. Then a man approached
               <tei:supplied reason="clarity">us</tei:supplied> who so to speak gave an improvised
            account of his travels verily on demand to people who were to him total strangers, and
            in the face of the most beautiful and sublime sights in Nature could not raise his
            enthusiasm beyond the words "I enjoy it", which seemed almost to slip out of his mouth
            as if he were asleep.</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0003-se02">Next morning <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"
               >September 1</tei:note> we journeyed to Klobenstein,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0003-fn03"
               type="footnote"/> from where we could see especially the Rosengarten with
               Schlern<tei:ptr corresp="#r0003-fn04" type="footnote"/> in its most three-dimensional
            form. The solidity of the images, especially in the purest air, made an unforgettable
            impression, and offered all too plainly a welcome contrast with the narrowness of the
            Sulden Valley, which we had just left behind. — The earth pyramids<tei:ptr
               corresp="#r0003-fn05" type="footnote"/> behind Klobenstein struck us as a caprice of
            Nature at which <tei:pb n="170"/> we would have been inclined to laugh were it not that
            what gave rise to them were the very laws that have created and destroyed the world
            since time immemorial.</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0003-se03">In the afternoon of the same day we travelled over the Mendel
            Pass, refreshed rather than fatigued thanks to the delights of the morning. Particularly
            magical here are the castles which, so to speak, as emblems of aristocratic lineages
            long passed into oblivion, have become woven into the eternally-proliferating fabric of
            Nature ‒ features of a history long lost sight of, but which was too beautiful to have
            perished altogether. Since then, the earth has of course been more justly apportioned,
            except that this justice accords with mankind very badly. Where in the old days it was
            only robber barons who plundered, today mercenary middlemen in their thousands commit
            daylight robbery.—</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0003-se04">The view from the Mendel Pass adds hardly anything more to
            what we have already seen on the way from Klobenstein. All the more surprising was the
            sight of an alpine glow such as we have at no time and nowhere else experienced in such
            intensity.</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0003-se05">Two lions flank the entry to the parish church in <tei:rs
               type="place" key="entity-002310">Bozen</tei:rs>. On their backs they carry pillars,
            but in such a way that the latter have not forgone their plinths ‒ a very droll artistic
            jest which, however, reminds us in all seriousness that not every old thing, merely
            because it is old, is to be taken wholly seriously. Clearly it is a lapse on the part of
            a totally untrained, primitive sculptor who in a curious way has found a voice alongside
            better artists.</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0003-se06">In the evening of the next day <tei:note type="editorial"
               place="inline">September 2?</tei:note> we travel to Vienna. Here an apartment was
            promptly sought, and found<tei:ptr corresp="#r0003-fn06" type="footnote"/> and the past
            teaching year finally put to rest.—</tei:ab>

      </tei:div>
   </sdo:record>


   <sdo:record ID="r0004">
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker September 12, 1911</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1911-09-12T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-08-19</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description/>
         <dc:subject/>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, </tei:hi><tei:pb n="171"/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:handShift next="#JK"/><tei:date when="1911-09-02">12. September.</tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0004-se01"><tei:handShift next="#JK"/>Floriz erlebt </tei:ab>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0004-se02"><tei:hi rend="bold"><tei:handShift next="#JK"
               />Vom Eheleben</tei:hi><tei:lb/><tei:handShift next="#JK"/>Im Grunde</tei:ab>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0004-se03">In der Regel </tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0004-se04"><tei:handShift next="#JK"/>Man wundert </tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, </tei:hi><tei:pb n="171"/><tei:lb/>
            <tei:handShift next="#JK"/><tei:date when="1911-09-02">September 12</tei:date>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab corresp="r0004-se01"><tei:handShift next="#JK"/>After a </tei:ab>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0004-se02"><tei:handShift next="#JK"/><tei:hi rend="bold">Married
               Life</tei:hi>
            <tei:lb/><tei:handShift next="#JK"/>In essence </tei:ab>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0004-se03">As a rule </tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0004-se04"><tei:handShift next="#JK"/>It is remarkable </tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

      </tei:div>
   </sdo:record>


   <sdo:record ID="r0005">
      <sdo:itemDesc>
         <dc:title>Diary entry by Schenker [September 24], 1911</dc:title>
         <dcterms:created>1911-09-24T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
         <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2019-08-19</dcterms:dateSubmitted>
         <dc:description/>
         <dc:subject/>
      </sdo:itemDesc>

      <tei:div type="transcription">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, </tei:hi><tei:pb n="173"/><tei:hi rend="bold">b</tei:hi><tei:lb/>
            <tei:dateline><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="italic">The
                     following two paragraphs are undated, and may belong to
                  October.</tei:hi></tei:note></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0005-se01"><tei:handShift next="#HS-ink"/>Tugenddirne </tei:ab>

         <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="italic">An entry between these two
               paragraphs, in Jeanette Kornfeld's hand, relates to November 12,
            1911</tei:hi></tei:note>
         <tei:lb/>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0005-se02"><tei:handShift next="#JK"/>Rechte Treue </tei:ab>

         <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">The following three-paragraph essay is undated,
            and may belong to October</tei:note>
         <tei:lb/>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0005-se03"><tei:pb n="174"/> Nicht zuletzt </tei:ab>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0005-se04">Alles läuft </tei:ab>

         <tei:ab type="sub-entry" xml:id="r0005-se05">Sinnig ist </tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

      </tei:div>

      <tei:div type="translation">
         <tei:opener>
            <tei:hi rend="bold">Ser. A, </tei:hi><tei:pb n="173"/><tei:hi rend="bold">b</tei:hi><tei:lb/>
            <tei:dateline><tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="italic">The
                     following two paragraphs are undated, and may belong to
                  October.</tei:hi></tei:note></tei:dateline><tei:lb/>
         </tei:opener>
         <tei:ab corresp="r0005-se01"><tei:handShift next="#HS-ink"/>Virtue prostitute </tei:ab>

         <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline"><tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:handShift next="#JK"
               />An entry between these two paragraphs, in Jeanette Kornfeld's hand, relates to
               November 12, 1911</tei:hi></tei:note>
         <tei:lb/>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0005-se02"><tei:handShift next="#JK"/>True loyalty </tei:ab>

         <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">The following three-paragraph essay is undated,
            and may belong to October</tei:note>
         <tei:lb/>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0005-se03"><tei:pb n="174"/> Not least </tei:ab>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0005-se04">Thus, as </tei:ab>

         <tei:ab corresp="r0005-se05">It is an </tei:ab>

         <tei:milestone unit="section" rend="block asterisk"/>

      </tei:div>
   </sdo:record>



</sdo:recordCollection>
