<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OC 16/29r, 28v, 27v : 3-10-17 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Under investigation.
© Transcription Ian Bent, 2006.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is presumed to be in the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1917-1935) - - Schenker, Jeanette (1935-1938) - -Oster, Ernst (1938-c.1939)—New York Public Library (c.1939-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Under investigation; Image: New York Public Library, New York; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 03/10/1917 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: &quot;DeutschS ~ HSchenker&quot;,&quot;T&#195;&#188;rkel ~ HSchenker&quot; --><dc:title>Typed letter from Türkel to Schenker, dated March 10, 1917</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-09-18</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Advises S re: claim for honorarium while explaining his own position, that of Fritz Mendl, and the stage the proving of the will of Sofie Deutsch has reached.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Türkel, Siegfried; Schenker, Heinrich;  Deutsch, Sofie; Sophie;  will;  estate;   Mendl, Fritz;  Kammerrat;  Chamber Counsellor;  honorarium;  pension;  Verein;  Futtermittelzentrale;  Association</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Vienna VII, Mariahilferstraße 26</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Türkel to Schenker, dated March 10, 1917</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>]
D^R^ SIEGFRIED TÜRKEL
HOF- UND GERICHTS-ADVOKAT
KANZLEI: VII. MARIAHILFERSTRASSE 26
EINGANG: VII. STIFTGASSE 1
[<tei:hi rend="italic">left:</tei:hi>] TELEPHON AUT. 35052 [<tei:hi rend="italic">right:</tei:hi>] POSTSPARK.-KTO. NR 104651</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">typed:</tei:hi>]
Wien, den 10. III. 17</tei:p><tei:p>T/N.  
<tei:hi rend="italic">Betr: Sofie Deutsch – Verl.</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Professor!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich bin entschieden dafür, dass Sie Ihre Honorarforderung anmelden.  Wie<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  “dass ... Wie”: underlined in crayon, presumably by S. </tei:note> ich mir bereits mitzuteilen erlaubt habe, bin ich sozusagen depossediert<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  „depossediert“: archaic word for „enteignet”: dispossessed, expropriated.</tei:note> und habe in der Verlassenschaft<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  “Verlassenschaft”: archaic term for “Hinterlassenschaft”; i.e. the estate of Sofie Deutsch, died January 5, 1917.</tei:note> fast nichts darein zu reden.  Der Testamentsvollstrecker hat nämlich nur die Erfüllung des Testamentes der Verstorbenen zu überwachen, hat aber auf die Abhandlung selbst sozusagen gar keinen Einfluss.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich kann entschieden die Gefahr, dass Ihnen die Rente erst ab Juni 1917 zugebilligt wird<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  “Ihnen ... word”: underlined in crayon, presumably by S.</tei:note> nicht leugnen.  Die Frage ist bis jetzt noch nicht zur Diskussion gekommen und dürfte auch solange die Inventur nicht beendet ist, nicht zur Diskussion kommen, da der Verein<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Verein: what is referred to here may be the <ref cRef="verein_zur_speisung">Verein zur Speisung und Bekleidung hungernder Schulkinder in Wien</ref>, or perhaps the bank association (Bankverein) with which Mrs. Deutsch dealt. </tei:note> noch keine Erbserklärung eingebracht hat, sich vielmehr zur Einbrungung derselben eine Ueberlegungsfrist vorbehalten hat.  Herr Kammerrat Mendl<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Fritz Mendl: Sofie Deutsch’s brother, leading Austrian industrialist.</tei:note> hat mit der Verlassenschaft persönlich gar nichts zu tun.  Ich führe für denselben das Amt des Testamentsvollstreckers und fällt es weder in meine noch in Herrn Kammerrat Mendls Kompetenz, Legate effectiv zur Auszahlung zu bringen.</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr gesch. Schreiben,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  No letter from S to T is known to survive prior to the date of this letter.</tei:note> veehrter [<tei:hi rend="italic">missing material: the remainder may be part of a different document</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="bold">{28v}</tei:hi> Sache an die Ankerbrotfabrik,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">   Ankerbrotfabrik: bakery founded in 1894 by brothers Heinrich and Fritz Mendl and employing by 1914 1,300 workers.  The firm was “aryanized” in 1938, but reverted to the previous owners in 1945.</tei:note> deren Kassier auch die privaten Geldangelegenheiten des Herrn Kammerrates Fritz Mendl führt und das verursachte immer einen Zeitverlust.  Herr Kammerrat ist, wie Herr Professor ja wissen werden, ^als^ Präsident der Futtermittelzentrale<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Futtermittelzentrale: Mendl writes his letters under the letterhead of this organization. </tei:note> entsetzlich in Anspruch genommen.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich weiss persönlich, wie sehr Herr Kammerrat Sie schätzt und liegt es Herrn Kammerrat gewiss ferne, Ihnen irgend welche Schwirgkeiten[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] zu berei- <tei:hi rend="bold">{27v}</tei:hi> ten.  In der Bankverein und Honorarangelegenheit würde ich Ihnen aber doch raten, wenn es auch nicht gleich geschieht, irgendwelche Schritte zu unternehmen, denn in juristischen Angelegenheiten kommt leider von selbst das Glück nicht.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich begrüsse Sie herzlichst
Ihr sehr ergebener:
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ]  <tei:hi rend="italic">Türkel</tei:hi></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Türkel to Schenker, dated March 10, 1917</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>]
D^R^ SIEGFRIED TÜRKEL
COURT AND IMPERIAL ADVOCATE
CHANCELLRY: VII. MARIAHILFERSTRASSE 26
ENTRANCE: VII. STIFTGASSE 1
[<tei:hi rend="italic">left:</tei:hi>] TELEPHONE AUST. 35052 [<tei:hi rend="italic">right:</tei:hi>] POST OFFICE BANK A/C NO. 104651</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">typed:</tei:hi>]
Vienna, March 10, 1917</tei:p><tei:p>T/N.
<tei:hi rend="italic">Re: Sofie Deutsch – Estate</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor,</tei:p><tei:p>I am definitely in favor of your putting forward a claim for your honorarium.  As<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> I have already taken the liberty of informing [you], I have been so to speak dispossessed<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> and have almost no say in the estate.  You see, the executor of the estate<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> has only to insure compliance with the terms of the deceased’s will, while having no influence at all over the carrying out of that compliance.
  
I certainly cannot deny the danger that the pension will not be granted to you until June 1917.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  The question has not yet come up for discussion and ought not to come up for discussion so long as the inventory has not been completed, since the Association<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> has not yet submitted an inheritance claim[?], let alone committed itself to[?] a period of deliberation for submitting the same.  Chamber Counsellor Mendl<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> has nothing whatsoever personally to do with the estate.  I take charge for him of the office of the executor of the will and it falls into neither my competence nor that of Chamber Counsellor Mendl actually to make payments of legacies.</tei:p><tei:p>You est’d letter,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>, dear [Professor] [<tei:hi rend="italic">material missing: the remainder may be part of a different document</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="bold">{28v}</tei:hi> matter to the Anchor Bakery,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> the cashier of which also takes care of the private financial affairs of Chamber Counsellor Fritz Mendl, and that always gives rise a time-delay.  The Chamber Counsellor, as the Professor will certainly know, is dreadfully in demand as the President of the Feedstuffs Headquarters.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/></tei:p><tei:p>I know from personal experience how very highly the Chamber Counsellor values you, and far be it from the Chamber Counsellor to make any kind of difficulties for you.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{27v}</tei:hi> In the matter of the bank association and the honorarium, I would however firmly advise you, if things do not happen immediately, to undertake certain steps, for in legal affairs, sadly, good fortune does not happen of its own accord.</tei:p><tei:p>With cordial greetings,
Yours very truly,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Türkel</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>