<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 14/45, [10] : 2-5-18 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  Heirs of Moriz Violin, published with kind permission
©  Transcription Ian Bent, 2009
©  Translation Ian Bent, 2009
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2009
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish granted by the heirs of Moriz Violin June 25, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1918-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Moriz Violin; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 02/05/1918 04:54:22 PM --><!-- MT Tags: "ViolinM ~ HSchenker","ViolinM+V ~ HSchenker","ViolinM+V+F ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Moriz Violin to Schenker, dated February 5, 1918</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-04-01</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Schenker, Violin alleges, has accused him of a dearth of subject matter in letter writing;  Violin defends himself on grounds that his life has been disrupted by military service and the impact of that on his physical and mental state.  He accuses Schenker of insensitivity, and treating him like his pupils.  He defends his wife for giving food to the Schenkers, and explains her motivation for so doing. 

</dc:description><dc:subject>Violin, Moriz;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Violin, Valerie;  Marmelade;  jam;  Militärdienst;  military service;  Brünauer, Robert;  Deutsch, Sofie;  Weisse, Hans;  Mittelmann, Aaron;  Glattauer;  Hauser, Friederike;  Popper, Frau;  prices;  Halm, August;  Hertzka, Emil;  Universal Edition;  Hauptmann;  captain;  Vienna</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">Marburg</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Moriz Violin to Schenker, dated February 5, 1918</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Marburg, February 5, 1918
cc
L. H.!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/10, p. 841, February 15, 1918:  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ich höre Dich sagen, „Floriz habe ich deutlich genug geschrieben.  Wenn er noch immer nicht versteht - - - -!"</tei:p><tei:p>Du hast mir ja so Manches geschrieben oder persönlich gesagt.  Meine große Neigung für Dich ließ mich immer schweigen.  Wenn ich Dir endlich nun doch Aufklärendes u. um Aufklärung Ersuchendes schreibe, so ist es wahrlich nicht Eitelkeit die mich reden macht, um nicht gar für dumm oder moralisch unreif gehalten zu werden, sondern das kategorische Gebot der Eigenwürde, die auch vor der größten Neigung u. Liebe nicht plötzlich Halt machen darf u. kann.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Ich werde meiner Absicht u. meiner Aufgabe am nächsten kommen, wenn ich Deine Karte<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  [check if postcard exists in OJ 8/3.]</tei:note> Zeile für Zeile beantworte.</tei:p><tei:p>-  -  -</tei:p><tei:p>Du willst mir in Form der Marmeladefrage<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  "Marmeladefrage":  the reference is to "<tei:hi rend="italic">one</tei:hi> jar of jam" (the underlining implying that more had been expected) that Valerie Violin gave Heinrich and Jeanette on January 13;  this is described in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/10, p. 828;  on January 21 (p. 831) Moriz Violin says that he is "unable to send the jam," and again on January 30 (p. 834), when Jeanette Schenker thanks Vally for two jars of jam, and inquires as to the cost of all three.   Later, on March 6 (diary, OJ 2/10, p. 852), Schenker refers in a letter to Vrieslander to the "Marmelade-Konflikt" ("conflict over jam").  Schenker was diabetic, and had known so since 1914, so the question arises as to whether this was jam for diabetics (in which case much harder to obtain) or regular jam for Jeanette's use.  -- Note that Violin employs (as his correspondent so often does) musical terminology when discussing a non-musical matter:: a "theme" on which to write something in the "form" of the jam issue.</tei:note> ein Schreibthema geben?!  Du glaubst, das[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] an einen Mangel bei mir?  Gerne zugegeben daß kein Thema in mir lebt!  Jedenfalls aber war ich mir dieses Ver- u. Behinderungsgrundes nicht bewusst.  Ich führe jetzt, wie Millionen Kriegsdienstler, ein grausames, tragisches Leben, das ich vielleicht im Gegensatz zu diesen, tragischer empfinde u. dem ich, vielleicht wieder im Gegensatz zu den Millionen Betroffenen, zu wenig physische u. psychische <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Energien entgegen zu setzen habe.  Ich wurde aus meinen Lebens[-] u. Strebensbahnen, in die ich so glücklich durch meine Heirat gelenkt wurde, durch den Kriegsdienst,  durch die ausgestandenen Todesfurchtsqualen, gerissen u. führe jetzt ein Pflichtleben, daß [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte:</tei:hi> das] mir nur lebenswert erscheint, wie es eben einem Menschen erscheinen muss, dem ^sich^ Frau u. Kinder als ein von Gott gegebener Schatz, der zu behüten u. zu pflegen ist, offenbaren [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>].  Wie das Schicksal mein Leben so grausam den Wechselwirkungen materieller, physischer u. psychischer Natur aussetzt, mich so schmerzlich in Ihnen herumzerrt, davon (von nichts Anderem hätte ich zu sagen gewünscht) <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> wollte ich dir, da ich <tei:hi rend="italic">Deine</tei:hi> Kämpfe genau kenne, in meiner großen Neigung nicht fortwährend etwas in's Ohr legen.  Ich wollte dich vor meinen Gemütsausbrüchen bewahren.</tei:p><tei:p>Der Du sonst so gut das Leben der Menschen hinter ihren eigenen Lebenskulissen kennst, beliebst diesmal in einer Tonart zu denken, die mir mit deiner sonstigen Beobachtungsgabe nicht stimmt (ich danke dankbarst, wie du mir einstens, bei wirklich dummen Lebenssünden, Begreifen u. Verständnis, im Gegensatz zu Anderen, entgegengebracht).  Du &lt;del&gt;wir&lt;/del&gt; ^wirfst^ mich mit Brünauers,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="brunauer_dr">Robert Brünauer</ref>.  </tei:note> Deutschs,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="deutsch_sofie">Sofie Deutsch</ref>.  </tei:note> Weißes<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.  </tei:note> etc. etc. in einem Topf. &lt;del&gt;wirfst&lt;/del&gt;  So weit bin ich dann doch nicht, daß Du, die auf jene angewendete Metode <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> bei mir nun praktiziert.  Oder ist es ein Wunsch von Dir, daß eine Freude, die ich oder Vally<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="violin_valerie">Valerie Violin</ref>.  </tei:note> Dir bereiten wollen, so ausgelegt wird, als wollten wir, indem wir sie dir bereiten, aus Dir einen Mittelmann<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="mittelmann_aaron">Aaron Mittelmann</ref>. </tei:note> oder Glattauer<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="glattauer">Glattauer</ref>.  </tei:note> machen?  Umgekehrt sollst Du deshalb aus uns auch keine Mittelmanns u. Glattauers machen.  Vally hat <tei:hi rend="italic">gar</tei:hi> keine Vorräte <tei:hi rend="italic">geschenkt</tei:hi> bekommen.  Wenn sie welche <tei:hi rend="italic">Geringe</tei:hi> hat, so hat sie dieselben, während meiner Abwesenheit, in entsagungsvoller Lebensweise gesammelt.</tei:p><tei:p>Sie hat sich eine entsetzliche, häusliche Arbeitslast, fremde Wohnungsgäste, aufgebürdet, wofür sie mitversorgt wird.  Vally entbehrt leider der <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> prosaischen „Fangarme",<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  "Fangarme" (tentacles):  i.e. perhaps, Wally does not have access to the black market.  </tei:note> dafür aber auch des Geldes.  Sie ist, ähnlich mir, geldschlampig in gutem Sinne u. findet ihr größtes Glück darin, mir damit Freude zu bereiten, indem sie jemand Anderem, von mir geschätztem (in diesem Falle Dir), eine Freude bereitet.  So hat sie spontan u. ohne mein Wissen, respektive meine Aufforderung, Dir in's Caféhaus die Kleinigkeiten gebracht,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  This incident is recorded in Schenker's diary for January 1, 1918 (OJ 2/10, p. 822): " Frau Wally kommt ins Caféhaus u. bringt: Aepfel, Slivowitz, Tee, Zucker, Hirse, Fleckeln, Zunge" ("Mrs. Wally comes to the coffee-house and brings apples, slivovitz, tea, sugar, millet, pasta[?], tongue").  </tei:note> hat keinen Preis angegeben, um offenbar den zarten Hauch ihrer guten Absicht nicht zu verscheuchen.  Sie sammelte mühsam für Frau Hauser,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Click on <ref cRef="hauser_friederike">Friederike Hauser</ref>.  </tei:note> die trotz ihres Geldes unversorgt ist, sie zeigte sich dankbar <tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> gegen [<tei:hi rend="italic">alt from</tei:hi> für] eine Frau Popper,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  Mrs Popper: unknown.  </tei:note> bei der sie als Mädchen wohnte, etc. etc.  Sie hat also bei <tei:hi rend="italic">Dir</tei:hi> nur eine vielfach angewendete Praxis &lt;del&gt;<tei:hi rend="italic">eigen</tei:hi>&lt;/del&gt; fortgesetzt u. es für nichts Bedeutendes gehalten.  Möglicherweise liegt darin, daß sie über ihre Verhältnisse gibt, nur Arroganz, gemeint hat sie es gut.</tei:p><tei:p>Bleibt mir nur übrig Deinen Standpunkt, Deine Auffassung zur Kenntnis zu nehmen.  Die Preise sind: (Ich hätte sie Dir keinesfalls verschwiegen) 2 Gläser Himbeere = 8 Kronen.  Von Marillen ist der Preis: 8 Kronen p. Klgr.  Ich weiß nicht wieviel im Glase war.  Ist aber <tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> leicht zu ermitteln.</tei:p><tei:p>Deine Geschichte:  „Halm<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  August Halm: [create profile and link].</tei:note> - Hertzka",<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15">  Click on <ref cRef="hertzka_emil">Emil Hertzka</ref>.  Schenker wrote to Hertzka on January 30, 1918 (WSLB 292), and again on February 5 (WSLB 293), that August Halm had written to UE requesting copies of works by Schenker other than <tei:hi rend="italic">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven</tei:hi> (especially <tei:hi rend="italic">Beitrag zur Ornamentik</tei:hi> and <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Neunte Sinfonie von Beethoven</tei:hi>), and that UE had ignored his request.  Halm's letter to Schenker reporting that is OJ 11/35, 7, January 20, 1918.  </tei:note> ist wohl sehr empörend.  Unverständlich ist, was er mit dieser Selbstbeschädigung erreichen will.</tei:p><tei:p>Herzl. grüßt Dich u. Frau Lielie
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  Floriz</tei:p><tei:p>Unser Herr Hauptmann nimmt diesen Brief aus Gefälligkeit nach Wien mit.  Er kommt so wenigstens sicher an.  Ich telephoniere nur  mit Wien.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Moriz Violin to Schenker, dated February 5, 1918</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Marburg 5 II 18</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Heinrich<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>I can hear you saying:  "I have written in plain enough terms to Floriz.  If he still does not understand even now - - - -!"</tei:p><tei:p>You have indeed said so much to me, in writing, or face to face.  My great predisposition toward you left me always silent.   If  now I do at last write something to you by way of clarification, and seeking clarification, then in truth it is not vanity that makes me talk so as not to be taken for completely stupid or morally immature;  it is rather the categorical command of my self-esteem, which, even in face of my very greatest predisposition and love [for you], neither may nor can suddenly stop me.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> I will come to my plan and my project next time, when I answer your postcard<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> line by line.</tei:p><tei:p>-  -  -</tei:p><tei:p>Under the guise of the jam question<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> you are trying to give me a topic to write about?!  You think that is something I lack?  I freely admit that my head is completely devoid of topics!  But at least I was not <tei:hi rend="italic">aware</tei:hi> of this handicap.  Like millions of other men on active service, I now lead a cruel, tragic life;  that I perhaps feel more tragic than these [men], and that I perhaps have too little physical and psychical <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> energy to put up resistance, by contrast with the millions of men affected [may well be the case].  I was uprooted from the paths of life and aspirations into which I had been so happily directed through my marriage, by active service, by the fear of death that I have endured, and I now lead a life of duty that seems to me only as worth living as it must appear to any man who contemplates a wife and children as a God-given treasure to be protected and cared for.  How cruelly fate exposes my life to buffettings of a material, physical, and psychical nature, how painfully [fate] savages me in [my dealings with] you.  Given my great predisposition [toward you], and knowing as well as I do the battles that <tei:hi rend="italic">you</tei:hi> have to fight, <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> I did not want continually to be bending your ear about all of this (I had nothing else of which I wished to talk).  I wanted to protect you from my emotional outbursts.</tei:p><tei:p>You who otherwise know so well the inner recesses of men's lives deign on this occasion to think in a manner that just does not fit with your gift for observation in others (I am deeply grateful for the way in which in times past, faced with the truly stupid sins that I have committed, you showed me sympathy and understanding as nobody else did).  You lump me together with the Brünauers,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> Deutschs,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> Weisses,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> and all the rest of them.  I will not stand for your practising <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> on me the method that you adopt with them.  Or is it your wish that a good deed that Vally<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> or I take pleasure in doing for you be interpreted as if in doing it we want to treat you as a Mittelmann<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> or a Glattauer<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/>?  Nor should you on that account make a Mittelmann or a Glattauer out of us.  Vally has received no provisions <tei:hi rend="italic">whatsoever</tei:hi> as a <tei:hi rend="italic">present</tei:hi>.  If she has some <tei:hi rend="italic">small items</tei:hi>, in her self-denying style of life she has accunulated them during my absence.</tei:p><tei:p>She has burdened herself with a terrible load of domestic work, unknown house guests, for whom she provides.  Unfortunately, Vally lacks the <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> prosaic "clutches,"<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> and money as well. Like me, she is careless with money, in the good sense of the expression, and takes her greatest pleasure in bringing happiness to me by doing a good deed for someone else whom I myself prize (in this case, you).  That is why, spontaneously, and without my knowledge or request, she came to the coffee house to bring you little things,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> indicating no price so as not to dispell the delicate atmosphere of her good intentions.  She painstakingly accumulated items for Mrs. Hauser,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> who despite her money is not looked after, she showed herself grateful <tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> toward a Mrs. Popper,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> in whose house she lived as a girl, etc., etc.  So when it came to <tei:hi rend="italic">you</tei:hi> she was only continuing to do something that she had often done as a matter of course, and thought nothing significant of it.  While it may be possible to read arrogance into her giving things away beyond her means, she nonetheless meant well.</tei:p><tei:p>All that remains is for me to acquiesce to your wishes.  The prices are (I had no intention of not telling you):  two jars of raspberries, 8 Kronen.  The price of apricots is 8 Kronen per kilogram.  I do not know how many there were in a jar, but it is <tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> easy to find that out.</tei:p><tei:p>Your tale about Halm<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/> and Hertzka<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn15"/> is indeed utterly disgraceful.  It is incomprehensible what he is trying to achieve by damaging himself in this way.</tei:p><tei:p>Cordial greetings to you and Mrs. Lie-Lie,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  Floriz</tei:p><tei:p>Our captain is taking this letter with him to Vienna out of the kindness of his heart.  That way, at least we can be sure it will reach you.  I telephone only with Vienna.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>