<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 12/38, [1] : 11-29-06 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  In the public domain.
©  Transcriptiontion Martin Eybl, 2007.
©  Translation Ian Bent, 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Martin Eybl &amp; Ian Bent, 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> deemed to be in the public domain</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1906-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: deemed to be in the public domain; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Martin Eybl; Translation, Footnotes, Commentary: Martin Eybl &amp; Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 11/29/1906 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: &quot;Illustrirtes Wiener Extrablatt ~ HSchenker&quot;,&quot;Liebst&#195;&#182;ckl ~ HSchenker&quot; --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Liebstöckl to Schenker, dated November 29, 1906</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-09-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Liebstöckl regrets having annoyed S with his remarks in the Illustrirtes Wiener Extrablatt, promises to write about it "conscientiously," and disclaims being a Reger adherent.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Liebstöckl; Schenker, Heinrich;  Illustrirtes Wiener Extrablatt;  Harmonielehre;  Theory of Harmony;  Bach, Johann Sebastian;  Reger, Max;  Adler, Guido;  Manzyczewski, Eusebius</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Vienna XI/1, Borggasse 31</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Hans Liebstöckl to Schenker, November 29, 1906, incompletely dated</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">Letterhead:</tei:hi> Illustrirtes Wiener Extrablatt]</tei:p><tei:p>Wien 29. November.</tei:p><tei:p>Lieber Künstler und Phantast!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> The salutation is a direct allusion to the title and series title of S’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:hi> (Musical Theories and Fantasies), I, and his anonymous signing of himself as “Von einem Künstler” (by an artist) in the first edition.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Es thut mir herzlich leid, daß ich zum Verräther an Ihnen geworden bin, in einem Augenblicke, da ich glaubte, Ihnen eine Annehmlichkeit zu bereiten<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  S’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (Stuttgart: Cotta, 1906) was released on November 10, 1906 (CA 54-55), and S asked for Liebstöckl to be sent a review copy on November 22 (CA 56).  Liebstöckl wrote about it in the <tei:hi rend="italic">Illustrirtes Wiener Extrablatt</tei:hi> for November 28, and S recorded his unfavorable reaction to Liebstöckl’s remarks in his diary the same day, evidently writing to Liebstöckl indignantly, to which the present letter is Liebstöckl’s response.  In a brief anonymous notice in the <tei:hi rend="italic">Illustrirtes Wiener Extrablatt</tei:hi> for 11-28-06 (p. 10), the author of the anonymously published <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> of Schenker is named: “From the house of the J. G. Cotta Bookdealership (Stuttgart and Berlin) the first volume of a work has just been published that bears the title “New Musical Theories and Fantasies by an Artist” and deals with the theory of harmony.  Of this work, expected to comprise four volumes, which makes an attempt to find new paths and to afford new insights into the essence of music, the author is the Viennese musician and writer about music, Dr. Heinrich Schenker.”  S recognized Liebstöckl as the initiator of this notice: see diary entry OJ 1/5, p. 27.  The preceding letter to Liebstöckl is not known to survive.</tei:note>.  Leider ist der Journalist in mir mitunter stärker als der taktvolle Mensch. Sie verstehen: da die Journalisten am liebsten das schreiben, was sie nicht wissen, reizt es Sie manchmal, aus der Rolle zu fallen; sie schreiben, was sie wissen.  Zudem hatte ich wirklich Freude, als ich Ihr Buch vor mir liegen sah, das von Außen so gar nicht revolutionär aussieht und ^sogar^ die heuchlerische &lt;strike&gt;Larve&lt;/strike&gt; Paragraphenlarve vornimmt, <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> damit man nur ja glaube, ein neuer Riemann wäre auferstanden, um unter uns zu wandeln.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> is written in numbered paragraphs lacking headings but with marginal rubrics, all within a systematic framework—an arrangement more characteristic of 18th-century and earlier treatises, and which was already somewhat archaic in the 19th century (Weber still used it in his <tei:hi rend="italic">Versuch einer geeordneten Theorie der Tonsezkunst</tei:hi> (Mainz: Schott, 1817–21), when it was gradually superseded by chapters with headed subdivisions (e.g. A. B. Marx).  Riemann used numbered paragraphs in those theory works intended for a skilled readership, e.g. <tei:hi rend="italic">Musikalische Dynamik und Agogik ...</tei:hi> (Hamburg: Rahter, 1884), <tei:hi rend="italic">Katechismus</tei:hi> [<tei:hi rend="italic">Grundriß</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">der Kompositionslehre</tei:hi> (Leipzig: Hesse, 1889), <tei:hi rend="italic">Vereinfachte Harmonielehre ...</tei:hi> (London: Augener; New York: Schirmer, 1903), although his paragraphs had emboldened headings rather than rubrics.  The overtone of biblical language (e.g. <tei:hi rend="italic">John</tei:hi>, xx.24: “Though the doors were locked, Jesus came and walked among them ...”) is blasphemous:  Riemann, or a Riemann follower, is equated with the risen Christ, and yet Schenker  is said to surmount and surpass this tradition.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ich plauderte also vor Freude. Nun bin ich fest in der Lektüre u. halte bei Seite 50. Hoffe auch, meinen Fauxpas gutzumachen und ^will^ gewissenhaft schreiben, sobald ich fertig bin.</tei:p><tei:p>Bewahren Sie mir, verehrter Künstler u. Phantast, Ihre Freundschaft und Ihr Wolwollen.  An dem der Großen, deren Namen Sie in Ihrem Buch anführen, lag mir immer sehr wenig.  Dachten Sie wirklich an „Bach für Reger“?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Modern composers, S maintains, exhibit a lack of scale-step progression, for which the opening of Reger’s Piano Quintet, Op. 64, is cited as a “deterrent example” (<tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi>, pp. 219–26;  the footnote concerning Reger is lacking in the English translation).  And Schenker invokes as “the model of a manner of composition truly sweeping in the utter boldness of its voice-leading and (even in fugues) securely based on scale-steps, those of Johann Sebastian Bach” (pp. 221-22).)</tei:note>  Bin ich ein Regerpfaffe? Nein, zum Kult hab’ ich niemals Talent gehabt. Bin auch <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> der Letzte, der nicht richtig zuhört, wenn Sie Argumente gegen Reger haben, an den mich nur eine gewisse innere Dankbarkeit für ^manche seiner^ Lieder knüpft.
 
Inzwischen bin ich Ihr
herzlich ergebener
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hans Liebstockl.</tei:p><tei:p>Famos ist Ihr Ausfall auf die Archivare u. Denkmälersammler! Invehitur in Adleros et Mandyczewskos!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  “It inveighs against people like Adler and Mandyczewski.  Guido Adler (1855–1941), the most influential musicologist in Vienna in S’s day, co-founder of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Vierteljahrsschrift für Musikwissenschaft</tei:hi> in 1884 and editor for ten years, directed the <tei:hi rend="italic">Denkmäler der Tonkunst in Österreich</tei:hi> 1893–1938, appointed full Professor of Musicology (Musikwissenschaftlicher Ordinarius) at Vienna University 1898–1927 and founder of the Music-historical Institute (Musikhistorisches Institut) in the University. He taught generations of musicologists and composers, including several of S’s own pupils, and is regarded by many as the “father” of modern musicology. S was at first on good terms with him, but an estrangement took place around 1913, fueled perhaps in part by Hans Weisse’s accounts of Adler’s seminars in 1914–15, which included the claim that Adler at first proscribed S’s publications from the library of the Seminar (Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Nach Tagebüchern ...</tei:hi>, p. 51). In 1916, S declined a place on the jury of the Rothschild Artists’ Foundation, probably because he did not wish to serve alongside Adler.  Click on <ref cRef="mandyczewski_eusebiu">Eusebius Mandyczewski</ref> (1857–1929) was archivist of the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde, Vienna collection 1887–1929.  Liebstöckl is referring to the footnote on p. 88 of the<tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi>, in which S criticizes the notion that „all old works are intrinsically good merely by virtue of their age, and deserve to be preserved and performed by us in extravagant fashion” (Eng. trans., p. 69, note 5).  </tei:note> Zu deutlich: es geht gegen die Trockenwönze!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6"> Trockenwönze:  meaning unclear;  die Wonze (plural: die Wonzen) is a ”trimmed beard“ or ”handlebar moustache“.</tei:note></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Hans Liebstöckl to Schenker, November 29, 1906, incompletely dated</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">Letterhead </tei:hi>Illustrirtes Wiener Extrablatt]</tei:p><tei:p>Vienna, November 29, [1906]</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Artist and Fantasist,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>I am truly sorry that I have become a traitor to you, just when I believed I was preparing something agreeable to you.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  Unfortunately, deep down the journalist in me is stronger than the diplomat.  You understand:  since journalists like best of all to write about that which they do not know, it often tempts them into dropping a clanger;  they write what they know.  Furthermore, I was genuinely delighted when I saw your book lying before me, looking outwardly so entirely unrevolutionary and ^even^ adopting the disembling guise of [numbered] paragraphs, <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> such as might actually lead one to believe that a new Riemann had risen from the dead to walk among us.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/></tei:p><tei:p>So I prattled for joy.  Now I am well stuck in to reading it and am on p. 50, and I am hoping to rectify my <tei:hi rend="italic">faux pas</tei:hi> and ^will^ write conscientiously as soon as I am ready to do so.</tei:p><tei:p>Maintain your friendship and goodwill toward me, my dear artist and fantasist.  I never was much interested in the goodwill of the great men you mention in your book.    Did you really think of “Bach for Reger”?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  Am I a Reger adherent?  No, I have never had any talent for the latest fashion.  Also, I am the last person <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> not to listen aright when you deploy arguments against Reger, to whom my sole attachment is a certain inherent gratitute for ^many of his^ Lieder.</tei:p><tei:p>In the meanwhile, I remain,
Cordially yours truly,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Hans Liebstöckl</tei:p><tei:p>Your attack on archivists and collectors is simply splendid!  Invehitur in Adleros et Mandyczewskos!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  Too clearly:  it goes against the grain[?]<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/>!</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>