<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/31, [2] : 11-24-38 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  Heirs of Sophie Guttmann, permission being sought
©  Transcription Ian Bent, 2008
©  Translation Ian Bent, 2008
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent, 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Under inquiry.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Jeanette (1938-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Sophie Guttmann, under inquiry; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 11/24/1938 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "GuttmannS ~ H+JSchenker","GuttmannS ~ JSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Sophie Guttmann to Jeanette Schenker, dated November 24, 1938</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-07-15</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Sophie replies to a [non-extant] letter from Jeanette, and reports on her recent movements and health, and on her brothers, her children and grandchildren.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Guttmann, Sophie; Schenker, Jeanette;  Guttmann, Salo;  Guttmann, Hans;  Guttmann, Frieda;  Guttmann, Julian;  Julko;  Guttmann, Salo;  Hilde;  Edith;  Oskar;  Sereth;  Dorna-Watra</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Siret, Rumainia</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Vienna IV, Schwindgasse 4/2</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Sophie Guttmann to Jeanette Schenker, dated November 24, 1938</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{envelope <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
Wohlgeboren [/] Frau D^r.^ Lie-Lie Schenker
in
<tei:hi rend="italic">Wien</tei:hi>
IV. Schwindgasse 4/2</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>]  || SIRET | 24 NOV 938 ||</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in Jeanette Schenker's hand:</tei:hi>]
Antw. [/] 22. I. 39</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{envelope <tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> [<tei:hi rend="italic">blank</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{letter}</tei:hi>
Siret<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Click on <ref cRef="sereth">Sereth</ref>.</tei:note> am 24. Nov. 938</tei:p><tei:p>Meine teuerste Schwägerin!</tei:p><tei:p>Kannst dir kaum vorstellen wie mich dein l. Brief<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  No letters from Jeanette to Sophie are known to survive.  We know from the envelope of OJ 11/31, [1] that Jeanette wrote to Sophie on March 22, 1938, and again on November 20.  </tei:note> überrascht hat!  Deine Schriftzüge nur zu sehen, diese Freude die du nur damit bereitet hast. – – natürlich hat mich der Inhalt sehr schmerzlich berührt. – Ich wähnte dich längst wieder bei deinem Bruder.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Jeanette's brothers were Victor, Paul, and Louis.  </tei:note>  – Ich habe seinerzeit deinen Brief unbeantwortet gelassen, mein Alter<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  i.e. her husband, (click on) <ref cRef="guttmann_salo_dr_hus">Salo Guttmann</ref>.  </tei:note> hat den vorigen ganzen Winter an furchtbaren Rückenschmerzen gelitten, im Frühjahr war es so arg, dass er gar nicht ausgehen konnte.</tei:p><tei:p>Nun kamen im Juni alle Kinder, man beschloss nach Dorna<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="dornawatra">Dorna-Watra</ref>.  </tei:note> zu fahren.  Frieda u. Kinder<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="guttmann_frieda_daug">Frieda Guttmann</ref>.  </tei:note> blieben bei uns und wir sind für einen Monat hingefahren.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Die Moorbäder kombinirt mit Kohlensäure haben ihm gut getan, er geht jetzt gottlob aus, hat sehr selten noch Schmerzen.  Auch mit den Augen geht's ihm gut.  Als wir fortfuhren, vergass ich deine Adresse mitzunehmen,  deine herrlichen Briefe halte ich wohlverwahrt, und meine Frieda hatte nicht den Schlüssel.  Als wir nachhause kamen, es war 18 September, war schon zu spät dir zu schreiben;  ich wandte mich an den Anwalt D^r.^ Goldschläger.  Kennst ihn doch?  er soll mir deine Adresse erwiren[?].  Er schickte mir von einem Auskunftsbüro deine Adresse: Reichsratsstrasse N^r^ 7, III Stock.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  This was the address to which she had previously sent OJ 11/31, [1].  </tei:note>  Ich schrieb sofort einen Brief hin, bis auf den heutigen Tag kein Antwort.  An wen konnte ich mich jetzt wenden?  Wahrscheinlich giebt es noch einen Schenker.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Meinen beiden Brüdern geht es jetzt am besten. – Dem l. Wilhelm<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="schenker_wilhelm">Wilhelm Schenker</ref>.  </tei:note> schreibe ich auch ein paar Zeilen, er hat ja sonst nie an uns gedacht.  –</tei:p><tei:p>Ja, der arme Heinrich, wenn er wüsste was du mitmachst!  Schau, dass du dir die Augen erhälst.  Ach wenn wir dir helfen könnten!</tei:p><tei:p>Der Oskar<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Oskar:  Frieda's husband.  </tei:note> hat stets gebeten, wir sollen Euch hernehmen!!  Meiner Frieda geht's jetzt so ziemlich, man kämpft geschäftlich, aber ihre Mäderl sind sehr herzig, mein grösstes Vergnügen auf der Welt sind diese Enkerl, und die hängen auch an ihrer Omama.  Julko<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Click on <ref cRef="guttmann_julian_julk">Julian Guttmann</ref>.  </tei:note> benimmt sich sehr, sehr schön.  Gott soll nur geben gute Zeiten – – –</tei:p><tei:p>Dem Hansi<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Click on <ref cRef="guttmann_hans">Hans Guttmann</ref>.  </tei:note> geht es auch gut, aber er hat eine sehr mondaine Frau, die sehr viel verbraucht.  Er hat ein reizendes Mäderl von 6 Jahren, <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> die wir leider nicht kennen.  Wir hätten hinfahren sollen, natürlich jetzt keine Rede mehr davon.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich halte mich noch stramm, aber meine Nerven – – – viele, viele schlaflose Nächte verbrachte ich – – – Gott möge helfen, wir sollen noch von dir gute Nachrichten bekommen. – Mein Alter lässt dir herzlichste Grüsse übersenden.</tei:p><tei:p>Dich küsst viel–vielmals
herzlichst
deine dich liebende
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  Sophie.</tei:p><tei:p>Wenn ich dir etwas Gutes schicken dürfte?</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Sophie Guttmann to Jeanette Schenker, dated November 24, 1938</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{envelope <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
Frau Dr. Lie-Lie Schenker
in
<tei:hi rend="italic">Vienna IV</tei:hi>,
Schwindgasse 4/2</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>]  || SIRET | 24 NOV 1938 ||</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in Jeanette Schenker's hand:</tei:hi>]
Reply: January 22, 1939</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{envelope <tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> [<tei:hi rend="italic">blank</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{letter}</tei:hi>
Siret,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> November 24, 1938</tei:p><tei:p>My dearest sister-in-law,</tei:p><tei:p>You can hardly imagine what a surpise your dear letter<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> gave me!  Just to see your handwriting, that alone gave me [such] pleasure.  Needless to say, I found its contents deeply distressing. – I fancied that you had long been back with your brother.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> – I left your letter unanswered at the time;  my old man<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> suffered terrible back pain the whole of last winter;  in the spring it was so bad he couldn't go out at all.</tei:p><tei:p>In June, all the children came;  it was decided [that we should] go to Dorna.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  Frieda and the children<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> stayed at our place, and we went off for a month.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> The mud baths combined with carbon-dioxide have done him good;  thank God, he now gets out, and only very occasionally has pain.  His eyes are all right, as well.  When we were leaving, I forgot to pick up your address;  I keep your splendid letters safely tucked away, and my Frieda didn't have the key.  By the time we got back home it was September 18;  it was already too late to write to you, so I resorted to Dr. Goldschläger, the attorney.  Do you know him at all?  He was to let me know[?] your address.  He sent me your address from an information bureau:  Reichsratsstrasse No. 7, 3rd floor.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>  I wrote a letter immediately, but up to today have not received a reply.  Who else could I turn to?  Probably there is still a Schenker.[??]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Everything is going swimmingly now with my two brothers. – I even drop a line to dear Wilhelm,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> otherwise he certainly never thinks of us.  –</tei:p><tei:p>Yes, poor Heinrich:  if only he knew what you have to put up with!   Make sure that you take care of your eyes.  Ah, if only we could help you!</tei:p><tei:p>Oskar<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> has been constantly asking why we don't bring you here!!  Things are going reasonably well with my Frieda, now;  the business is a struggle, but her little girls are real dears;  these grand-daughters are the greatest joy of my life, and they are even fond of their Grannie.  Julko<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> is getting on very, very well.  If only God would bring good times . . .</tei:p><tei:p>Things are well with Hansi,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> too, but he has an extremely fashion-conscious wife who is very, very extravagant.  He has a charming little girl of six, whom <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> alas we do not know.  We were going to go there, but of course that is out of the question now.</tei:p><tei:p>I still keep myself up-to-scratch, but my nerves . . . I have many, many a sleepless night . . .  God willing, we may yet get some good news from you. – My old man asks me to send his cordial greetings.</tei:p><tei:p>Many, many kisses,
Most sincerely,
Your loving
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  Sophie.</tei:p><tei:p>Is there anything you would like me to send you?</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>