<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:DLA 69.930/8 : 10-27-19 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain; published with kind permission of the Deutsches Literaturarchiv, 2006.
© Transcription Ian Bent &amp; Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Translation Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>August Halm (1919-19??)—Deutsches Literaturarchiv(19??-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain, published with the kind permission of the Deutsches Literaturarchiv; Image: Deutsches Literaturarchiv; Transcription Ian Bent &amp; Lee Rothfarb, 2006; Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary Lee Rothfarb, 2006.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 10/27/1919 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Halm ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Halm, dated October 27, 1919</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-06-22</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>
S writes of the deteriorating intellectual conditions in Germany and Austria
with respect to other nations, and of the devastating political and
psychological consequences.  S. praises H's Klavierübung for its
sensitivity to voice leading, and speaks of it as an antidote to the decline
of musical literacy.  He hopes to talk with H about these matters when he
moves to Germany.


</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Halm, August;  Germany;  Austria;  France;  America;  Italy;  Goethe;  Herder;  Schiller;  Lessing;  Bach;  Mozart;  Tristan;  Elektra;  Beethoven;  Bekker, Paul;  Klavierübung;  diminution;  Wagner;  Kontrapunkt II;  Counterpoint II</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN" /></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Halm, dated October 27, 1919</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">stamped:</tei:hi> ]
Aug. Halm
ESSLINGEN a.N.
Panorama 11</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">handwritten:</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Professor!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">   The whole of paragraphs 2-4, and paragraph 5 down to “zu unterhalten,” are transcribed by Federhofer in <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern ...</tei:hi>, pp. 139–40.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Es fällt einem wahrlich nicht leicht, in der deutsch-österreichischen Wüste sich heute auf die Oase des Geistigen zu retten.  Wie die gesammte Bevölkerung in unerhörter Weise brutalisiert wird, muß auch der Einzelne seine Tracht Prügel wegbekommen.  Gar ich leide unsagbar schwer unter der Erkenntnis, daß die Menschen hier keine Aussicht haben, mit sich <tei:hi rend="italic">ja</tei:hi> ins Reine zu kommen darüber, weshalb es so kommen mußte, so fortgeht.  Niemand weiß hier, was <tei:hi rend="italic">Amerika</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Frankr</tei:hi>., <tei:hi rend="italic">Engl</tei:hi>., <tei:hi rend="italic">Italien</tei:hi> sind, was bestenfalls sein Können oder Dürfen: mit jeder Stunde, fällt man tiefer in die Schande der Auslands-Prostitution, gibt besseres auf, um schlechteres einzutauschen, so in Politik, wie Kunst u. <tei:hi rend="italic">Literatur</tei:hi>.  Das ganze Geschlecht kann nicht sehen, nicht denken lernen, – so reicht es sich bitter, daß man auf die Zeugen, statt <tei:hi rend="italic">Goethe</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Herder</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Schiller</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Lessing</tei:hi>, statt <tei:hi rend="italic">Bach</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Mozart</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">etc</tei:hi>. zuerst <tei:hi rend="italic">Herzog</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Skovronek</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Skovronek ??</tei:note>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Rolland</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">A. France</tei:hi>, zuerst „<tei:hi rend="italic">Tristan</tei:hi>“ u. „<tei:hi rend="italic">Elektra</tei:hi>“ legt – u. 100 Jahre nach <tei:hi rend="italic">Beeth</tei:hi>. müssen wir <tei:hi rend="italic">Becker</tei:hi>s’<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  A reference to Paul Bekker (1882–1937), music critic of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Frankfurter Zeitung</tei:hi> and author of the book <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven</tei:hi> (1911), whose work S was already criticizing in <tei:hi rend="italic">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven</tei:hi> from 1913 on, and toward whom he exhibited deep antagonism by the time of <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</tei:hi> (1921–24).</tei:note> vor die Türe setzen, u. 200 Jahre nach <tei:hi rend="italic">Bach</tei:hi> müssen Sie eine „Klavierübung“ schreiben . .</tei:p><tei:p>Es macht Ihnen alle Ehre, wie Sie da den Tauben<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  „200 Jahre ... schreiben“: underlined in crayon, probably by recipient.</tei:note> die Ohren <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> öffnen, den Fingern gleichsam Verstand und Augen geben.  Diese schöne, echt deutsche Liebe zum Stoff, zum Schüler als Adepten der Kunst u. als – Menschen!  Wie drückt sich das alles in jeder Wendung der schönen Sprache ^aus^, die schon allein den Schüler heben muß, in der Führung jedes einzelnen Problems, das ihm vorgeführt wird.  Beinahe möchte ich glauben, daß Ihre „Klavierübung“ einem Selbstlerner mehr Segen bringen wird, als einem, der sich eines Lehrers bedient.  <tei:hi rend="italic">Ohne den Lehrern es zu verargen</tei:hi>, die ja mit dem Leben so schwer zu ringen haben, meine ich doch, daß mit der quantitativen Zunahme dieses Standes die qualitative Erleuchtung leider nicht gleichen Schritt halten kann, u. ich befürchte, daß Ihre schöne Arbeit, die ja beinahe alle -xxx- Mühe dem Lehrer abnimmt,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  “Es ... Tauben”: underlined in crayon, probably by recipient.</tei:note> gleichwohl das Gesetz der „Masse“ nicht werde überwinden können.  Sie haben aber Ihre Pflicht getan u. müssen es nun der Welt überlassen, ob sie folgen will oder nicht.</tei:p><tei:p>Was mir persönlich sehr zusagte, war die Art, wie Sie ständig die „Diminution“ im Auge behalten.  Dim hat uns auf die höchste Stufe gebracht, so muß man denn vor allem eben sie befragen, wenn man auf den Urkern kommen will.  Auch der Schüler, Kenner und Genießer muß denselben Weg zurücklegen, den der Komponist, den die Musik überhaupt gegangen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  „die ja ... abnimmt“ underlined in crayon, probably by recipient.</tei:note>
   
 Fremd aber, – Ihnen gegenüber spreche ich ganz frei u. will damit <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> unsere Beziehung nur ehren – ist mir der Grund geblieben, weshalb Sie in der Frage der Bogen-Artikulation nicht dem Original folgen, z.B. Mozart, A^d.^ Son., deren Thema ja: [<tei:hi rend="italic">mus.ex.<tei:hi rend="italic"></tei:hi>] beobachtet, und nicht: [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from top margin:</tei:hi>] so stehts auch nicht bei mir<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  “Was mir ... gegangen”: the first word of each line underlined in crayon, probably by recipient to emphasize entire paragraph.</tei:note> [<tei:hi rend="italic">mus.ex.</tei:hi>].  Als Schaffender müssen Sie wohl die Tücke der Artikulations-Frage am eigenen Leibe zu sehr erfahren haben, um nicht zu wissen, daß sie alle Musiker beunruhigt, u. peinigt.  Fürs Erste, ich meine: bis zur Lösung dieser Frage, dürfte die Treue zum </tei:hi>Original_ zumindest mit weniger Gefahren verbunden sein, u. es sollte meines Erachtens kein Schüler ein anderes Bild zunächst zu sehen bekommen, als der Autor selbst hinterlassen.</tei:p><tei:p>So treffend der Gedanke ist, den Schüler schon in diesem Stadium, z.B. zu <tei:hi rend="italic">Bach</tei:hi>’s ^ <tei:hi rend="italic">Prael</tei:hi>. u.^ Inventionen zu führen, u. so schön Sie auch zumeist, von Übung zu Übung wie von Assoziation zu Assoziation wandernd, sich an diese Kostbarkeiten heranpürschen, so wenig ratsam finde ich andererseits die Methode, an irgend einer Stelle selbst einzugreifen, u. die Stücke zu Ende zu führen.  Selbst bei jenen Komponisten, die, wie Sie, mit Recht das Kunstwerk auf die Stimmführung stellen, ist diese Kraft, da inzwischen ja die Wagner-Moräne niedergegangen ist, u. die Wege wieder neu gebaut werden sollen, noch nicht von der letzten Geschmeidigkeit, wie sie erforderlich wäre, um eine <tei:hi rend="italic">Bach</tei:hi>’sche Führung fortzusetzen.  Ich wüßte mir für <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> mein Teil nichts Anregenderes, als mich gerade mit Ihnen über dieses Stadium unserer gegenwärtigen Stimmführung mündlich zu unterhalten.  Was für Imponderabilien kämen da zur Erörterung, vielleicht weniger greifbar in Vortrag als schwingend vom Wunder Ihres Nervs zum Wunder -xxx- meines Nervs, u. dennoch von Beweiskraft auch das ungehörteste Begebnis, im Guten wie im minder Guten!</tei:p><tei:p>Nun, vielleicht kommt es evl auch zu einer solchen mündlichen Unterhaltung.  Denn ich will <tei:hi rend="italic">Wien</tei:hi> verlassen, um nach Deutschland zu ziehen.  Ich habe es wenigstens vor, u. habe die Empfindung, es sobald als möglich auszuführen ^zu sollen^, um Leben u. Arbeit zu retten.  Wäre ich doch nur schon mit II^2^ fertig, damit die anderen eigentlich schon fertigen Werke auch vorwärts kommen könnten!
 
Ich grüße Sie aufs herzlichste u. freue auch schon zum Voraus auf die Fortsetzung der „Klavierübung“[.]</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H Schenker
27. Okt. 1919</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">stamped:</tei:hi> ]
Aug. Halm
ESSLINGEN a.N.
Panorama 11</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Halm, dated October 27, 1919</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">stamped:</tei:hi> ]
Aug. Halm
ESSLINGEN o/ NAHE
Panorama 11</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">handwritten:</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>It is truly not easy today for someone in the German-Austrian desert to rescue themselves in an intellectual oasis.  The way that the entire population is being brutalized in unheard of manner, the individual must also take a beating.  Even I suffer unspeakably severely in the knowledge that people here have no prospect of <tei:hi rend="italic">really</tei:hi> coming to terms with themselves, which is why it had to turn out this way, and so continue.  No one here knows what America, France, England, Italy, are, what their ability or permissibility is in the best case.  With every hour, we fall deeper into the shame of prostitution by foreign countries, relinquish something better in exchange for something worse, in politics as in art and literature.  The entire race cannot learn to see, cannot learn to think—thus it turns out bitter that, instead of Goethe, Herder, Schiller, Lessing, intead of Bach, Mozart, etc., we put first Herzog, Skovronek<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>, Rolland, A. France, first <tei:hi rend="italic">Tristan</tei:hi> and <tei:hi rend="italic">Elektra</tei:hi>—and a hundred years after Beethoven we have to show the door to the Bekkers<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> of this world, and two hundred years after Bach you have to write a <tei:hi rend="italic">Piano Method</tei:hi>.</tei:p><tei:p>It is to your honor the way you open the ears of the deaf<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> with it, <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> the way you provide the fingers with understanding and eyes.  That beautiful, genuine German love of substance, of the pupil as connoisseur of art and as—human beings!  How all of that expresses itself in every turn of phrase of the beautiful language, which on its own must elevate the pupil, in the handling of each individual problem presented to him.  I almost would like to believe that your <tei:hi rend="italic">Piano Method</tei:hi> will afford the autodidact more blessing than someone who calls on a teacher.  <tei:hi rend="italic">Without blaming the teachers</tei:hi>, who struggle so arduously with life, I mean that the qualitative illumination unfortunately cannot keep pace with the quantitative increase of this condition, and I fear that your wonderful work, which relieves the teacher of practically all effort,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> will nevertheless not be able to overcome the law of the „mass.“  You have done your duty, however, and must now leave it to the world whether or not they follow.</tei:p><tei:p>What appealed to me personally was the way you always keep sight of „diminution.“  Diminution has brought us to the highest level, such that we must consult it above all when we want to arrive at the primordial kernel.  The pupil, too, the connoisseur and aficionado must therefore cover the same distance that the composer, that the music covered.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/></tei:p><tei:p>But—I speak completely freely to you and in doing so <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> want only to honor our relationship—the reason remains foreign to me why, on the question of phrase markings, you do not follow the original, e.g. Mozart, A-major sonata, whose theme of course:  [<tei:hi rend="italic">mus. ex.</tei:hi>] considered, and not: [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from top margin:</tei:hi>]  It is not like that in my case [<tei:hi rend="italic">mus. ex.</tei:hi>].  As a creative artist, you surely have experienced enough first hand the trickiness of the issue of articulation not to know that it disconcerts and distresses all musicians.  First of all, I say:  until that issue has been resolved, loyalty to the original has at least less dangers, and in my opinion no pupil should be initially shown a different picture than what the author himself specified.</tei:p><tei:p>As appropriate as the idea is to guide pupils toward Bach’s ^Preludes and^ Inventionen, for example, even at this stage, and as wonderfully as you usually sneak up on those treasures, moving from exercise to exercise as well as from association to association, as little advisable, on the other hand, do I find the method of intervening at some point and bringing the pieces to a conclusion.  Even in the case of those composers who, like you, rightly base an art work on voice-leading, that power has not yet reached ultimate elasticity, as would be necessary to continue the tradition of Bach, since in the meantime the Wagner avalanche has descended, and the paths should be rebuilt.  For my part, I would know <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> of nothing more exciting than to discuss in person with you in particular the status of our current voice-leading.  What sort of imponderables might then enter into the discussion, perhaps less tangible in verbalization than oscillating between the miracle of your neural system and the miracle of my neural system, and nevertheless with conclusiveness the most unimaginable events, in the positive as well as in the less positive!</tei:p><tei:p>So, perhaps it will come to such a face-to-face conversation.  For I want to leave Vienna in order to move to Germany.  At least I am so planning, and have the sense of needing to do it as soon as possible in order to save my life and work.  If only I were already done with the second volume of <tei:hi rend="italic">Counterpoint</tei:hi>, so that the other works, which are actually already completed, could move forward!</tei:p><tei:p>I send you cordial greetings and look forward in advance to the continuation of the „piano method.“</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H Schenker
October 27, 1919</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">stamped:</tei:hi> ]
Aug. Halm
ESSLINGEN o/ NAHE
Panorama 11</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>