<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:DLA 69.930/11 : 11-2-22 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription Ian Bent &amp; Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Translation Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>August Halm (1924-1929) - -Deutsches Literaturarchiv(19??-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain, published with the kind permission of the Deutsches Literaturarchiv; Image: Deutsches Literaturarchiv; Transcription Ian Bent &amp; Lee Rothfarb, 2006; Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary Lee Rothfarb, 2006.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 11/02/1922 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Halm ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Halm, dated November 2, 1922</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-10-08</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Acks receipt of two booklets on youth and the new republic, returns them, comments on them critically: idealistic Germans democrats desire maximal remuneration with minimal work; illustrates point by difficulties with maids in Schenker household; German democrats naively overestimate social and intellectual status of non-German commoners (French, British, American); S decries cosmopolitanism and those Germans who advocate individuality at the expense of society; S praises the fascists as countering communism and social leveling, compares Mussolini's Italy favorably with present-day Germany.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Halm, August;  Republik und Jugend;  Wirth, Joseph;  Russia;  France;  Russians;  French;  Thuringia;  Greek Kalends;  Slavs;  German democrat;  Umschichtung;  social reordering;  Vienna Philharmonic;  Vienna Opera House;  manufacturer;  capitalist;  Volk;  folk;  housemaid;  Voltaire;  Marx, Karl;  communism;  Communist Party;  food;  potatoes;  cold cuts;  Leipzig;  Kaiser Wilhelm II;  American banker;  Darine;  Lloyd George, David;  Brentano, Lujo;  Schenker, Jeanette;  Hertzka, Emil;  internationalist;  cosmopolitan;  Goethe;  Bach, J. S.;  Mozart;  Mendelssohn;  Beethoven;  Der Tonwille;  Shakespeare;  Richter, Jean-Paul;  Für-sich;  for-himself;  Schiller;  Racine;  Barbusse, Henri;  Clarté;  Oppel, Reinhard;  Kiel;  Kino;  cinema;  movies;  Austria;  Italy;  Mussolini;  fascists;  Dolchstoß;  stab in the back</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Halm, dated November 2, 1922</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Wien, 2 November 1922</tei:p><tei:p>Lieber verehrter Herr Professor Halm!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  This text is highly problematic, with many illegible or questionable words, and great difficulties of translation.  Thanks are due to William Drabkin for help in deciphering and translating it.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Mit bestem Dank sende ich die beiden Hefte „Rp. u. Jgd" zurück.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  The identity of the two pamphlets is unknown.  „Republik und Jugend" is the title of an aphorism by Novalis that reads „Republik ist das Fluidum deferens der Jugend. Wo junge Leute sind, ist Republik."</tei:note>  Ich kenne u. besitze derlei Stücke schon seit langem; sie erreichen immer das Gegenteil davon, was der Verfasser unter die Menschen bringen will.  Und alle sind sie heute überholt u. <tei:hi rend="italic">entlüftet</tei:hi><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  This must mean „entlüftet"`(deflated), even though there is a letter between „l" and „ü".</tei:note> durch den Vorstoß D^r^ Wirth's<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Presumably (Karl) Joseph Wirth (1879-1956), liberal German statesman, and chancellor during the Weimar Republic (1919-22).  On April 16, 1922, he and foreign minister Walther Rathenau negotiated the Treaty of Rapallo with the Soviet Union.  Rathenau was assassinated on June 24; a secret agreement was signed between Germany and the Soviet Union on July 29;  then Wirth resigned over the reparations question on November 14.  S writes this letter twelve days before the resignation.  </tei:note> u. der Reichsregierung, die durch ihre Veröffentlichungen vor der ganzen Welt erweisen, daß die Schuld durchaus nicht D. allein trifft, die von russischen u. franz.  „Fälschungen" ohne Schau sprechen.  Wenn schon die Jugend in Thür[in]g[en] politisiert werden muß, so wäre, unter dem Motto: Wahrheit ist nicht Haß, gerade von den Dingen +zuerst+ zu sprechen nötig gewesen, die der Verfasser <tei:hi rend="italic">ad calendas graecas</tei:hi> vertagt,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> " To the Greek Kalends":  Said by Emperor Augustus, in Suetonius, with the sense of "never". Kalends were part of the Roman calendar, not of the Greek, so the "Greek kalends" are "a date that will never happen."</tei:note> u. nicht vom Zusammenbruch u. Dolchstoß, der in zehnter Reihe steht.  In einer würdigeren Form hätte das Ministerium die Lage Deutschlands zwischen Franzosen, Eng., u. Slaven zum Bewußtsein bringen sollen, die Beschaffenheit dieser Völker, die das deutsche aus tiefsten Herzen hassen, die Notwendigkeit, den Taten des Hasses Widerstand zu leisten.  Aber der deutsche Demokrat denkt zuerst an sich, seine Stellung, u. verteidigt sie gegen „Umschichtung," obwohl er selbst nur durch eine Frucht[?]-Umschichtung emporgekommen ist; daher obige Hefte . . .</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Ich spreche so offen zu Ihnen, weil ich Sie als Aristokraten empfinde, mögen Sie auch selbst sich für einen Demokraten halten.  Ein Demokrat ist etwas völlig anderes als Sie.  Hier einige Kennzeichen.</tei:p><tei:p>Vor Allem ist er bestechlich.  Die Führergauner wissen ganz genau, was sie tun, wenn sie vor Allem die Löhne erhöhen u. Geld unter die Massen bringen, die käufliche Seele ist gleich mit Geld gewonnen!  Selbst ein geistig vorgeschrittener Philharmoniker, auch von Haus aus vermögend, war von der Partei begeistert, als sie die Löhne in der Oper hinaufsetzte, u. es gieng ihm nicht ein, daß das hinaufremunerierte Geld weniger wert wird („Inflation".)   Wenn das Geld die Menschenwürde ausmacht, warum verargt der Dem. dem Fabrikanten, Kapitalisten ihr Geld?  Und wie mißbraucht der Führer die unschuldige Seele[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] des „Volkes," wenn er die Gelderhöhung als gebührende Lohn anbietet: muß da nicht sein Opfer glauben, seine Arbeit sei allein die schöpferische?  Wo ohnehin der Mensch, je kleiner der ^er^ ist, von dem Wenigen, das er leistet, bis an den Rand voll ist, sich u. die Arbeit überschätzt, tritt noch von außen eine Partei, die dem Größenwahn ins Tollster fördert!  Was Wunder, daß der Dem. sich für den Alleskönner hält, der nur durch tausend „Wenn" ^sich^ verhindert fühlt: es ist der ewig verhinderte große Staatsmann, Dichter, Entdecker, Ingenieur usw. u. verlangt nach immer unser Geld, um zunächst einmal die ^angeblichen^ Hindernisse aus dem Wege zu räumen.  Und hier beginnt der Wucher, der Betrug.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Der Dem. haßt so seinen wahren Lebensinhalt, u. läßt sich zum Voraus für einen bezahlen, den er nur träumt.  Er fühlt sich, durch Geld verführt, zu höherem Berufen u. will die andere Arbeit nicht mehr leisten, u. so zerfällt er mit sich selbst.  Das Weib will nicht Kinder, denn sie möchte, - was? komponieren? dichten? entdecken? - sie weiß selbst nicht was, nur keine Kinder; sie träumt von Menschenwürde . . der Arbeiter will nicht arbeiten, was will er aber? - entdecken, dichten? nein, das kann er ja nicht, er will <tei:hi rend="italic">gut bezahlte Menschenwürde ohne Arbeit</tei:hi>.</tei:p><tei:p>Der Dem. hält „Umschichtung" für  Auslese; Menschenantlitz schon für Würde.  Er schämt sich seiner niedrigen Arbeit, begehrt aber Lohn ^immer^ für eine höchste.  Bei uns erscheint eine Hausgehilfin, u. verlangt den höchsten Lohn: wir gewähren diesen u. zuletzt fragt die Voltaire-Marx-Würdenträgerin: "muß ich auch kochen?" Eine andere Hausgehilfin schämt sich Brot"aufschnitt" zu essen, sie fürchtet ihre reine Würde etwas damit zu vergeben.  Eine dritte will keine Kartoffeln essen, bei uns nicht, wo meine Frau so wunderbar die Mahlzeiten bereitet, diesselbe Frau, die wie ich Kartoffel ißt u. noch überdies vollkommen gerüstet ^mir^ auch geistig zur Seite steht.  Eine vierte (aus <tei:hi rend="italic">Leipzig</tei:hi>) behauptet, Wilhelm II<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Wilhelm II (1859-1941): Emperor of Germany and King of Prussia 1888-1918, forced to abdicate in 1918, he took up residence in the Netherlands.  </tei:note> wäre ein Landstreicher geworden, wenn er nicht zufällig Kaiser gewesen wäre.  Arme Opfer vor gewissenlosen Schurken, Opfer, denen Arbeit wie Essen schon ganz vereckelt wurden.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Ein Demokr. ist der gerissene amerikanische Banquieur, der als „<tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Philantrop</tei:hi></tei:hi>" reist, der franz. Spitzbube, der den <tei:hi rend="italic">Rhein</tei:hi> stehlen geht (u. die Rheinländer so herabsetzt wie H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Darine</tei:hi>[?]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  „Herr Darine" [identify].</tei:note> z.B.), der englische „<tei:hi rend="italic">Liberale</tei:hi>",<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  English liberal": David Lloyd George (1863-1945), British prime minister 1916-22; "steal[ing] the Rhine": the 15-year inter-Allied occupation of the Rhineland and its bridgeheads, with a demilitarized zone and the possibility that the region might be occupied if the Germans failed to pay reparations (to all of which Lloyd George was a reluctant signatory), decreed by the Treaty of Versailles, 1919.</tei:note> den +Lujo Brentano+ (ein radikaler Sozialist!)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Lujo (= Ludwig Joseph) Brentano (1844-1931), German-Catholic intellectual and political economist, a Kathedersozialist (i.e. socialist who rejected the Marxian and Russian agendas) and founder of the Verein für Socialpolitik in 1873, who made a study of the English trade unions.</tei:note> beschuldigt, die[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] Mäntelchen von Lügen[,] Heuchelei um den Raubzug geschlagen zu haben.  Ein Demok. ist mein Verleger,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  "my publisher": Emil Hertzka: Director of Universal Edition 1907-32, from whom by this stage S was deeply estranged, leading to a complete break and threatened legal proceedings in 1925.</tei:note> trieft mir so von dem international. <tei:hi rend="italic">kosmop</tei:hi>. Fett, aber multipliziert in meiner u. meiner Frau Gegenwart mit 4 nachdem er, vor einer Sekunde, die 5 als den Schlüssel angegeben hat, fälscht den Absatz (erwiesen, [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg. word</tei:hi>]), usw., usw.</tei:p><tei:p>Wie ein Roß nach dem Huftritt an den Peiniger dennoch ein Roß bleibt, genau so bleibt die Masse Masse auch nach einem Revolutionshuftritt.  Der deutsche Dem. will die Masse „entmassen"?  Es entesle sich der Esel, entochse sich der Ochse zuvor, dann vielleicht.</tei:p><tei:p>All diese Lüge, dieser Betrug kam uns aus dem Westen.  Ein märchendichten-  der +Knabe+ <tei:hi rend="italic">Goethe</tei:hi>, ein komponierender <tei:hi rend="italic">Bach</tei:hi>, Mozart, Mendelssohn, Beeth, im Westen?  Nie gab es dort ein <tei:hi rend="italic">Wunder</tei:hi>, nie wird es Wunder geben.</tei:p><tei:p>Sie müssten aus Stein sein, wenn Sie nach der Lektüre des 3. Heftes <tei:hi rend="italic">Tonwille</tei:hi>,das einen Haydn bringt,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Schenker, „Haydn: Sonate Es-Dur," pp.3-21 (Eng. trans., vol. I, 99-117).</tei:note> nicht wie ich bis ins Innerste erschauern; fragen Sie sich dann ^ob^ so etwas im Westen möglich war, ist oder sein wird?</tei:p><tei:p>Aber während kein Franzose, Engl., Amerik. den deutschen für etwas mehr als eben einen deutschen nimmt, glaubt der deutsche in +jeden+ +Franzosen+ H. Voltaire zu sprechen, in jedem Droguisten, Tanzlehrer, Jour- <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> nalisten, in +jedem+ +Eng.+ H. Shakspeare selbst, in jedem Amerik.  H. Washington, u.s.f.  daher diese (J. Paul) Hausknechtsnatur.  Und dieses große, herrliche Volk begeht den Widerspruch, für jedes Individuum das „Fürsich" (<tei:hi rend="italic">Goethe</tei:hi>) anzustreben, ein solches „Fürsich" im Sinne eines Eigenseparaten, würdig in sich ruhenden Nation aber abzulehnen: der Einzelene soll individuell sein;  die Gesammtheit aber - keine Individualität!!  Dann die Auslandsfutterei ist nichts anderes als eine Minderung des „Fürsich", eine Zerstörung der Individualität.  Goethe, Schiller, die z.B. Racine, Voltaire ab^zu^lehnen ^wissen^, mögen ^auch^ bei deutschem "Fürsich" Früchte pflücken, wo sie wollen, aber das ganze Volk macht, das es nicht schöpferisch ist, den Kosmopolitismus zu Unrecht mit, auch mit Unverstand.<tei:hi rend="bold"> [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from lower margin:</tei:hi> </tei:hi> Wozu [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg. word</tei:hi>] auf einen Knochen[?] haben sich da kürzlich 3 oder 4 [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg. word</tei:hi>], u. Übersetzter auf Barbusse <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Barbusse, Henri (18732-1935), French novelist and poet, one of whose novels is <tei:hi rend="italic">Clarté</tei:hi> (1919), and who launched a journal of the same name (1919-27).  He founded the movement <tei:hi rend="italic">Clarté</tei:hi> in 1919, emulated the Encyclopaedists and the spirit of the Enlightenment.  Schenker had excoriated the <tei:hi rend="italic">Clarté</tei:hi> movement in his "The Mission of German Genius," <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</tei:hi> 1 (1921), pp.14-15 (Eng. trans., vol. I, p.14). </tei:note> gestützt, von dem ich nicht einen Satz noch wirklich geistvoll gefunden hatte.  Er spielt den[?] „[<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg. word</tei:hi>]" u. lockt die deutschen Gelder heraus.  <tei:hi rend="italic">Clarté</tei:hi> macht es ebenso.  Wir bezahlen die Kanonen, mit denen Frankreich den Krieg führt.]</tei:p><tei:p>Der deutsche Dem. sehnte sich nach Armut, nun hat er sie, u. mag begreifen, daß dem Einzelnen es geziemt,  Reichtümer abzulehnen, aber nicht einer Gesammtheit von 60 Mill., denn dann geht Alles zu Grunde.  Unser armer D^r.^ Oppel (Kiel)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  Click on <ref cRef="oppel_reinhard">Reinhard Oppel</ref>.</tei:note> muß bei zahllosen Stunden noch nur +Kino+ spielen!!  Und so tausend Beispiele.  Niemals aber wird es einem [„]Umschichtler" gelingen, auch nur soweit es zu bringen, wie[?] D^r^ Oppel es gebracht hat.</tei:p><tei:p>Daher lobe ich nur die Faszisten!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  To understand this astonishing and deeply ironic statement, we must remember that at this point Schenker considered Communism as the principal enemy and social evil, and saw the Fascists as the only force likely to overcome it.</tei:note> Weg mit der "Klasse" aus dem Fleisch der Nation, - gedacht,[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> getan, u. schon ^sind^ die Gaunerführer feig entflohen (sie sind ja uns nach Österr. gekommen) u. schon haben sich die Kommunistenverbände aufgelöst, u. schon sind die Arbeiter <tei:hi rend="italic">begeisterte Fascisten geworden</tei:hi>!  Das Volk jauchzt voll Stolz auf, - in der That Mussolinis Werk: [„]Ich bin Diener Euerer Majestät",  „Ich werde selbst ein Beispiel geben." sind wahrer Kaviar für das Volk, u. mehr als alles Demokratentreiben, das um Geduld fleht: "Warten Sie, wir sind in den Anfängen erst, in [ein] paar Generationen wird es besser werden."</tei:p><tei:p>Sagte Marx: die Religion ist Opium für die Völker,' sage ich: Demokr. ist Opium.</tei:p><tei:p>Deutschl. braucht Faszisten, die die Lüge der „Klasse" vertilgen, jener Fertig-Fresser, denen man Arbeit u. Gelegenheit verschafft, u. die  zum Lohn für dieses Schlaraffenleben Alles niedertrampeln.  Der gottverlassenste Habsburger hat mehr Kulturwert als die ganze „Lohnerhöhungsmaschinerie", wie der Führer der öst. Sozdem. selbst die Partei benannte.  Durch Geld geht es nicht.  Das ital. Volk lebt schöne Tage der Erhebung!  Und im deutschen Volk geht noch immer der Dolchstoß um!  Seelenmord um Seelenmord!  Was habe ich für Dokumente für den Dolchstoß seit +1915+ (!), geschweige 1917-1918!  [<tei:hi rend="italic">left margin, sideways:</tei:hi>  Nun Alles endgiltig an die Pflicht des Tages in so trüben Tagen!  Helfen Sie der deutschen  Jugend aus den Fängen des Westens, der „Klasse" - Vielen Dank u. beste Grüße Ihres</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H Schenker]</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Halm, dated November 2, 1922</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Vienna, November 2, 1922</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor Halm!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>With many thanks I am sending back the two booklets "Republic and Youth."<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  I have long since known and possessed such pieces.  They always achieve the opposite of what the author wants to get across to people.  All are outmoded and <tei:hi rend="italic">deflated</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> today by the initiative of D^r^ Wirth<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> and of the imperial government, who prove before the whole world by means of their publications that the fault does not apply to Germany alone, who speak without fanfare of Russian and French "falsifications."  If even the young in Thuringa has to be politicized, then under the motto "truth is not hate" it would have been necessary +first+ to speak precisely of those things that the author defers to the Greek Kalends,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> and not of the collapse and stab of the dagger, which is at the tail end.  The ministry should have brought Germany's situation among the French, English, and Slavs to awareness in a more dignified form, the nature of those nations that the Germans hate deep in their hearts, the necessity to put up resistance to the acts of hate.  But the German democrat thinks first of himself, of his position, and defends it against "social reordering," although he himself has risen to prominence only through a shifting of [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg. word</tei:hi>].  Therefore the aforementioned booklets.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> I speak to you so openly because I perceive you as an aristocrat, though you may consider yourself a democrat.  A democrat is something completely different than you.  Here, some characteristics.</tei:p><tei:p>He is above all bribable.  The leading crooks know absolutely precisely what they are doing when, above all, they raise wages and get money to the masses.  The purchasable soul is acquired instantly with money!  Even an intellectually advanced Philharmonic musician, well-to-do by background, was enthusiastic about the party when it raised salaries at the Opera House, and it didn't dawn on him that the money of increased remuneration will be worth less ("inflation").  If money is the substance of human dignity, why does the democrat hold it against the manufacturer, the capitalist?  And how the leader abuses the innocent soul of the "folk" when he offers the increased money as due wages.  Must not his victim believe his work alone is productive?  Where a person, the smaller he is, is full to the brim with that little bit that he accomplishes, overestimates himself and his labor, a party from the outside enters which escalates the delusion of grandeur to the worst madness!  What wonder that the democract considers himself someone capable of everything, who feels inhibited only by a thousand "if's."  It is the eternally obstructed great statesman, poet, discoverer, engineer, etc. and always demands our money in order to clear the ^ostensible^ hindrances out of the way.  And the profiteering, the deception begins there. <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> The democrat hates his true life's purpose so much and allows himself to be paid in advance for a purpose of which he merely dreams.  Seduced by money, he feels summoned to a higher calling and no longer wants to do the other labor, and so he falls apart.  The wife wants no children because she would like--what? to compose? write poetry? make discoveries?  She doesn't know herself what she wants to do, just no children.  She dreams of human dignity.   The worker doesn't want to work.  What does he want, though?  To make discoveries, to write poetry?  No, he certainly can't do that.  He wants <tei:hi rend="italic">well-paid human dignity without work</tei:hi>.</tei:p><tei:p>The democrat takes "regrouping" to be selection, human countenance simply to be dignity.  He is ashamed of his lowly labor, but ^always ^ desires a salary that is the highest possible.    A housemaid shows up at our home and demands the highest wage.  We grant it and in the end the Voltaire-Marx bearer of dignity asks:  "do I also have to cook?"  Another maid is ashamed to eat "cold cuts" with bread.  She is afraid of giving up something of her pristine dignity.  A third will eat no potatoes, not in our home, though my wife prepares such wonderful meals, the same wife who, like me, eats potatoes and moreover also stands fully equipped at ^my^ side intellectually.  A fourth (from Leipzig) claims that Wilhelm II<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> would have become a hobo if he were not coincidentally emperor.  Poor victims at the hands of unscrupulous scoundrels, victims whose work as well as meals have been made completely revolting.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> A democrat is the crafty American banker who travels as a "<tei:hi rend="italic">philanthropist</tei:hi>," the French rascal who goes out to steal the Rhine (and so demean the Rhinelanders, e.g. like H. Darine<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>), the English "liberal,"<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> whom <tei:hi rend="italic">Lujo Brentano</tei:hi> (a radical socialist!)<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> blames for having wrapped the robbery in a tissue of lies [and] hypocrisy. My publisher<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> is a democrat, he  oozes internationalist, cosmopolitan grease so much to my face, but in mine and my wife's presence [he] multiplies by four after he has given five as the factor a moment before, [thus] falsifies the sales (proven, [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg. word</tei:hi>]), etc., etc.</tei:p><tei:p>Just as a steed nevertheless remains a steed after kicking its tormentor, so too the masses remain the masses even after the kick of a revolution.  The German democrat wants to "de-mass" the masses?  If the donkey can de-donkey and the ox de-ox itself, then perhaps.</tei:p><tei:p>All of these lies, this deception, came to us from the west.  A fairytale-telling <tei:hi rend="italic">boy</tei:hi> Goethe, a composer <tei:hi rend="italic">Bach</tei:hi>, Mozart, Mendelssohn, Beethoven, in the west?  A <tei:hi rend="italic">miracle</tei:hi> never occurred there, never will there be miracles.</tei:p><tei:p>You would have to be made of stone if, like me, you don't shiver to the core after reading the third issue of <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</tei:hi>, which presents a [work by] Haydn.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/>  Do you ask yourself ^whether^ something like that was possible in the west, is or will be?</tei:p><tei:p>But while no Frenchman, Englishman [or] American takes a German for anything more than just a German, the German believes he's talking to Voltaire in <tei:hi rend="italic">every Frenchman</tei:hi>, every pharmacist, dance instructor, journalist, <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> with Mr. Shakespeare himself in <tei:hi rend="italic">every Englishman</tei:hi>, with Mr. Washington in every American, and so forth.  Hence this (Jean-Paul) house-servant mentality.  And this great, magnificent people commits the contradiction of striving toward a "For-himself" (Goethe) for every individual, but rejecting such a "For-himself" in the sense of a self-separated, enobled nation at peace with itself.  The individual person should be individualized, but the totality--not an individuality!!  Then the foreign fodder is nothing other than a diminishment of "For-himself," a destruction of individuality.  Goethe, Schiller, who knew to reject for example Racine, Voltaire, may ^also^ harvest fruit where they will with the German "for himself," but the entire people wrongly goes along with the cosmopolitanism because it is not creative, also in ignorance.<tei:hi rend="bold">  [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from lower margin:</tei:hi> </tei:hi> To which three or four [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg. word</tei:hi>] and translators recently with one accord based themselves on Barbusse,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> from whom I had not found a single intellectually stimulating sentence.  He plays the role of an "[<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg. word</tei:hi>]"and lures German money.  <tei:hi rend="italic">Clarté</tei:hi> does it the same way.  We pay for the canons with which France makes war.]</tei:p><tei:p>The German democrat longed for poverty.  .  Now, he has it and may grasp that it befits the individual to refuse riches, but not a totality of 60 million.  For them everything then goes down the drain.  Our poor Dr. Oppel (Kiel),<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> with countless private lessons, must yet play for <tei:hi rend="italic">movies</tei:hi>!!  And a thousand such examples.  But a "regrouper" will never succeed in getting even as far as Dr. Oppel.</tei:p><tei:p>Consequently, I praise only the facists!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/>  Get rid of "class" from the flesh of the nation--no sooner thought than <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> done, and the swindling [Italian] leaders ^have^ already fled like cowards (they have come to Austria, of course), and the communist federations have already been disbanded, and already the workers have <tei:hi rend="italic">become enthusiastic facists</tei:hi>!  The people rejoice full of pride, which is indeed Mussolini's doing.  "I am your majesty's obedient servant",  "I myself will set an example"--[such statements] are music to the ears of the people, and more than all the democrat bustle that appeals for patience.  "Wait, we are just at the beginning, in a few generations it will get better."</tei:p><tei:p>Marx said: "religion is the opium of the people."  I say democracy is opium.</tei:p><tei:p>Germany needs facists who will destroy the lie of "class," of those on-the-spot gluttons for whom we provide work and opporunity, and who as salary for this cushy life trample everything.  The most god-forsaken Habsburger has more cultural value than the entire wage-raising machinery, as the leader himself of the Austrian social democrats called the party.  It won't work by means of money.  The Italian people are living lovely days of elation!  And with the German people the knife in the back still goes on.  Murdering soul after soul!  The documents I have for the knife in the back since <tei:hi rend="italic">1915</tei:hi> (!), not to mention 1917-1918!  [<tei:hi rend="italic">left margin, sideways:</tei:hi> Everything now definitively toward the obligation of the day in such dismal days!  Help the German youth to get out of the claws of the west, of "class." --Many thanks and best wishes from Your</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H. Schenker]</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>