<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:DLA 69.930/15 : 7-11-27 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription Ian Bent &amp; Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Translation Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>August Halm (1927-1929)—Deutsches Literaturarchiv(19??-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain, published with the kind permission of the Deutsches Literaturarchiv; Image: Deutsches Literaturarchiv; Transcription Ian Bent &amp; Lee Rothfarb, 2006; Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary Lee Rothfarb, 2006.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 07/11/1927 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Halm ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Halm, dated July 11, 1927</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-10-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Thanking H for his Beethoven, he believes that their misunderstandings could be removed and hopes Der freie Satz will help bring that about;  gives order of publication for Meisterwerk II and Der freie Satz, and compares his "Das Organische der Fuge" with the work of others on Bach.  —S took no part in the Vienna Beethoven festival. —Describes his correspondence with Hindemith.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Halm, August;  Beethoven book;  Max Hesse Verlag;  Deutsche Buchgemeinschaft;  Der freie Satz;  Free Composition;  Das Meisterwerk in der Musik II;  Masterwork in Music II;  Jahrbuch II;  Yearbook II;  Der Tonwille;  Bach, J. S.;  Das Wohltemperirte Clavier;  Well-tempered Clavier;  Jöhde, Fritz;  Jöde, Fritz;  Werker, Wilhelm;  Graeser, Wolfgang;  Schoenberg;  Beethoven festival;  Rolland, Romain;  Casals, Pablo;  Herriot, Edouard;  General-Anzeiger für Bonn und Umgegend</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Galtür, Tirol</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Halm, dated July 11, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Galtür, Tirol
11. 7. 27</tei:p><tei:p>Verehrtester u. lieber Herr Professor Halm!</tei:p><tei:p>Hier, in Tirol, komme ich erst dazu, Ihnen für Ihren „<tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven</tei:hi>“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Halm, <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven</tei:hi> (Berlin: Max-Hesse-Verlag, 1927), presumably the book for which S thanked H briefly in DLA 69.930/14, January 22, 1927.</tei:note> herzlichst zu danken u. Ihnen zur Gewinnung von <tei:hi rend="italic">Hesse</tei:hi>’s Verlag u. der [Deutschen] Buchgemeinschaft<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  The Deutsche Buch-Gemeinschaft published Halm’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Einführung in die Musik</tei:hi> (1926).</tei:note> Glück zu wünschen: nun kann es Ihnen an einer Verbreitung Ihrer Gedanken nicht fehlen.</tei:p><tei:p>Auch Ihr Beethoven-Buch gibt mir Gelegenheit zu sagen, daß die zwischen uns beiden waltenden Misverständnisse sicher behebbar sind, daß es in einem gewissen Sinne schade ist, wenn wir nicht ganz zusammengehen.  Vielleicht schafft hierin der „freie Satz“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  S’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi>, published posthumously (Vienna: UE, 1935). On August 26, 1926, S remarked: “I am working on <tei:hi rend="italic">Free Composition</tei:hi> the last volume of the [<tei:hi rend="italic">New Musical</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">Theories</tei:hi> [<tei:hi rend="italic">and Fantasies</tei:hi>], which will bring together everything that is needed (vC 3, to von Cube);  on September 4, 1926: “my <tei:hi rend="italic">Free Composition</tei:hi> summons me” (vC4); On September 6, 1928: “This year I shall prepare <tei:hi rend="italic">Free Composition</tei:hi> for publication” (vC 18).</tei:note> einigen Wandel, der nun an die Reihe kommt.  Vorläufig kommt noch das <tei:hi rend="italic">Jb.II</tei:hi> (spätestens Oktober), womit ich den „Tonw.“ abschließe,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, vol. II (Munich: Drei-Masken-Verlag, 1926), released on September 30, 1927.  S saw this work as the continuation of <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</tei:hi> (Vienna: Tonwille-Flugblätterverlag [=UE], 1921–24) after relations with UE had broken down in 1925; however, Drei-Masken-Verlag insisted for marketing reasons on changing the title. </tei:note> um ganz Herr der Zeit u. meiner <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Arbeitskräfte zu sein.  Es fügt sich seltsam, daß mein <tei:hi rend="italic">Jb. II</tei:hi> die erste C-moll Fuge des “Wohlt. Kl.“ ebenfalls bringt u. zw. als Beleg für das Organische auch in der Fugenform.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  “Das Organische der Fuge aufgezeigt an der I. C-moll-Fuge aus dem Wohltemperierten Klavier von John. Seb. Bach,“ <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, vol. II, pp. 57–95 (Eng. trans., vol. II, pp. 31–54).  </tei:note>  Gegen <tei:hi rend="italic">Jöhde</tei:hi>’s,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Presumably Fritz Jöde (1887–1970), German music educator, author of <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Kunst Bachs</tei:hi> (1926) (not mentioned in “Das Organische der Fuge,” perhaps because the book was too recent to come to S’s attention in time for that article).</tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Werker</tei:hi>’s,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Wilhelm Werker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Studien über die Symmetrie im Bau der Fugen und die motivische Zusammengehörigkeit der Präludien und Fugen des „Wohtemperierten Klaviers“ von Johann Sebastian Bach</tei:hi> (Leipzig: Breitkopf &amp; Härtel, 1922), discussed in „Das Organische der Fuge,“ pp. 81–4 (Eng. trans., vol. II, pp. 45–7).</tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Graeser</tei:hi>’s<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Wolfgang Graeser, „Bachs ‚Kunst der Fuge’,“ <tei:hi rend="italic">Bach-Jahrbuch</tei:hi> 21 (1924), 1–104, and the supplementary volume 47 of the Bach-Gesellschaft edition, discussed in “Das Organische der Fuge,” p. 84 (Eng. trans., vol. II, pp. 47–8).</tei:note> Bach Unternehmungen dürfte die kleine Abhandlung zunächst vielleicht wenig ausrichten, aber wenn es einem Bach so schlecht mit diesen Unmenschen geht, warum sollte ich es besser haben wollen?  Noch vor 4–5 Jahren hätte ich einen solchen Bach-Verfall nicht anzunehmen gewagt, obwohl ich seit 30 Jahren auch i. meine Leser auf das Schlimmste gefaßt mache.</tei:p><tei:p>Nur wenn Schönberg eine Gegenäußerung wagt, würde ich ein kleines Schriftchen zur Aufrechterhaltung des in <tei:hi rend="italic">Jhb. II</tei:hi> gegen ihn Vorgebrachten herausgeben.  Sonst bleibe ich beim „fr. Satz“ u. setzte nun das Werk ohne Einschaltung bis ans Ende <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> fort.</tei:p><tei:p>An der <tei:hi rend="italic">Beeth.</tei:hi>feier in Wien<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9"> 1927, the centenary of Beethoven’s death, saw a major centennial festival and exhibition in Vienna.</tei:note> habe ich mich gar nicht beteiligt, sie war zu sehr auf <tei:hi rend="italic">Romain-Rolland</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Romain Rolland (1866–1944), French novelist, dramatist, Nobel Prize winner in 1915; occupied the first chair of music at the Sorbonne from 1903 on; writer on music, author of <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven</tei:hi> (Paris, 1903, 2nd edn 1927), <tei:hi rend="italic">La vie de Haendel</tei:hi> (Paris, 1906), <tei:hi rend="italic">Musiciens d’aujourd’hui</tei:hi> and <tei:hi rend="italic">Musiciens d’autrefois</tei:hi> (Paris, 1908), <tei:hi rend="italic">Goethe et Beethoven</tei:hi> (Paris: Editions du Sablier, 1930), and other works.  He was also a member of the Clarté group, much criticized by S, notably in “The Mission of German Genius,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</tei:hi> 1 (1924), pp. 14–15 (Eng. trans., vol. I, pp.14–15).  </tei:note>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Casals</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Pablo Casals (1876–1973), Catalan cellist, conductor, composer.</tei:note> usw. gestellt, um von Herriot<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Edouard Herriot (1872–1957), radical French politician, premiere of France three times between 1924 and 1932; writer on music, author of the popular biography <tei:hi rend="italic">La vie de Beethoven</tei:hi> (Paris, 1929).</tei:note> u. Kollegen nicht zu sprechen.  An Titeln u. hohen Auszeichnungen bin ich ausgewichen u. ich habe nur für den „General-Anzeiger für <tei:hi rend="italic">Bonn</tei:hi> u. Umgegend[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>]“ einen kleinen Aufsatz geschrieben unter dem Titel „B. u. seine Nachfahren.“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  “Beethoven und seine Nachfahren,” <tei:hi rend="italic">General-Anzeiger für Bonn und Umgegend</tei:hi>, special supplement “Zum 100. Todestage Beethovens,“ March 26, 1927, pp. 3–4 (clipping preserved as OJ 20/8; original MS in JS’s hand as OJ 17/3, dated “27.III.27”).</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Hindemith schrieb mir Gutgemeintes, ich erwiderte mit Gutgemeintem,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  Reference is to surviving letters OJ 11/51 (Hindemith to S, October 25, 1926), OJ 5/17 (S to Hindemith, November 12, 1926).  The exchange arose out of a remark in <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, vol. I (1925), p. 219 (“supposing Beethoven wrote music ‘today’ like Hindemith—well then, he would be bad, like him”), to which Hindemith responded by expressing admiration for S’s work, enclosing two of his quartet scores and claiming that S would find the Urlinie and confirmation of S’s theories in them, a contention that S rejected vigorously.  See Donald Johns, “’Aimez-vous Brahms?’: Ein Hindemith–Schenker-Briefwechsel,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Hindemith-Jahrbuch</tei:hi> 20 (1991), 141–51;  Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern ...</tei:hi> (1985), pp. 150–53.  </tei:note> nur – es geht jetzt in der Musik u. in der Musikliteratur zu, wie in einer echten <tei:hi rend="italic">Tragoedie</tei:hi>: ein Jeder will u. kann, wie er muß, Alle sind gegen Alle, Jeder gegen Jeden u. das gibt einen tragischen Ausgang: die Musik geht ab.</tei:p><tei:p>Desto besser für Sie, wenn Sie besseres <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> erwarten, ich bleibe dabei, daß man der[?] Tonkunst noch gar ^nicht^ in die Augen gesehen hat, obwohl sie sie so schön geöffnet hat.</tei:p><tei:p>Lassen Sie, bitte, bald von sich hören u. seien Sie aufs beste gegrüßt</tei:p><tei:p>von Ihrem
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] <tei:hi rend="italic">H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Halm, dated July 11, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Galtür, Tirol
11. 7. 27</tei:p><tei:p>Most revered Professor Halm,</tei:p><tei:p>Here in the Tirol I am only now getting around to thanking you cordially for your <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> and to wishing you luck on contracting with Hesse’s publishing house and with the [German] Book Society.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  Now you won’t lack for the dissemination of your ideas.</tei:p><tei:p>Your Beethoven book also gives me the opportunity to say that the misunderstandings prevailing between us can surely be removed, that in a certain sense it is a shame if we don’t join forces.  In that regard perhaps <tei:hi rend="italic">Free Composition</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> will bring about some change, whose turn it is now.  For the time being, <tei:hi rend="italic">Yearbook II</tei:hi> comes first (October at the latest), with which I finish off <tei:hi rend="italic">Tonwille</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> so that I can be master of [my] time and of my <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> capacity for work.  It just so happens that my <tei:hi rend="italic">Yearbook II</tei:hi> likewise includes the first C-minor fugue of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Well-tempered Clavier</tei:hi>, specifically as evidence for organicism also in fugue form.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  Contrary to Jöhde’s,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> Werker’s,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> [and] Graeser’s<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> undertakings with Bach, my brief essay may at first convey perhaps little.  But if Bach fares so badly with those brutes, why should I expect anything better?  Four-to-five years ago I would not have ventured to assume such a deterioration in the appreciation of Bach, although for 30 years I too have prepared my readers for the worst.</tei:p><tei:p>Only if Schönberg attempts a contrary remark would I publish a small essay to substantiate statements against him presented in <tei:hi rend="italic">Yearbook II</tei:hi>.  Otherwise I will stick to <tei:hi rend="italic">Free Composition</tei:hi> and will continue on that work up to its conclusion without interruption. <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>I did not take part at all in the Beethoven festival in Vienna<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/>.  It revolved too much around Romain-Rolland<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/>, Casals<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/>, etc., not to mention Herriot<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> and colleagues.  I sidestepped titles and elevated honors, and just wrote a little essay for the <tei:hi rend="italic">General Gazette for Bonn and Environs</tei:hi> entitled “Beethoven and his Descendants.”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/></tei:p><tei:p>Hindemith wrote me some well-intentioned words; I replied with something well-intentioned,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/> only:  events in music and in music literature are unfolding like a genuine tragedy.  Each wants and can do as he is compelled, all are against all, everyone against everyone else, and that will produce a tragic end:  music will go down the drain.</tei:p><tei:p>The better for you if you <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> expect anything better.  I stick with the view that people have ^not^ yet looked the art of music in the eye, although music has so wonderfully opened our eyes.</tei:p><tei:p>Let me hear from you soon, please, and accept best greetings</tei:p><tei:p>from your
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H. Schenker</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>