<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:CA 121&#226;&#128;&#147;122 : 9-10-10 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Universal Edition A.G., Wien.
© Transcription Ian D. Bent 2005.
© Translation Ian D. Bent 2005.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian D. Bent 2005.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> All reasonable steps have been taken to locate the heirs of Heinrich Schenker. Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>J.G. Cotta’sche Nachfolger/Stuttgarter Zeitung (1910-c.1954); Cotta-Archiv, Schiller-Nationalmuseum, Marbach a. N., Germany (c.1954-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian D. Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 09/10/1910 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cotta ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cotta, dated September 10, 1910</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2005-06-28</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>[ Handbibliothek:] Clarifies the proposal made in CA 118, August 19, 1910, and explains how it relates to other volumes of NMTP.  Suggests overall series title, and gives sample title for the first monograph, on Beethoven's Ninth Symphony.  Offers two letters from Ernst Rudorff. Discusses marketing and sales.  - -[ Kontrapunkt II_:]  Promises shortly.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Cotta, J. G.; Stuttgart; meeting; proposal; Handbibliothek; Reference Library;  Music-Repertory Appendix; NMTP; vol.1; Harmonielehre; Harmony; vol.2/1; Kontrapunkt I; Counterpoint I; vol.2/2; Kontrapunkt II; Counterpoint II;  vol.3; Niedgergang; Decline; monographs; marketing; pricing; title; Beethoven, Ludwig; Ninth Symphony; Rudorff, Ernst; Berlin; Hochschule für Musik; </dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cotta, dated September 10, 1910</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="bold">= OJ 5/6, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> Schenker had been planning to release his <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Niedergang der Kompositionskunst: eine technisch-kritische Untersuchung</tei:hi> (The Decline of the Art of Composition: a technical-critical Inquiry), originally intended as the <tei:hi rend="italic">Nachwort</tei:hi> (Afterword) to <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (CA 5–6, November 22, 1905), but which had expanded such that it was subsequently detached and scheduled to appear six months after <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (i.e. in May 1907: OJ 9/31, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  <tei:hi rend="italic">eben</tei:hi> (specifically) appears four words later in draft, before zu.</tei:note>, June 5, 1906) as a separate "supplementary publication" (<tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi>, p.VII, trans. p. xxvi), presumably in the form of a pamphlet or booklet.  S later reconceived it as vol. III of <tei:hi rend="italic">NMTP</tei:hi> (CA 68, September 13, 1907) and the "capstone" (<tei:hi rend="italic">Pointe</tei:hi>) of the entire work.  In 1908 he was still speaking of it in these terms (CA 87, October 13, 1908).  Here, he presents his <tei:hi rend="italic">Handbibliothek</tei:hi> as a direct extension of that work, which was never published.  Vol. III of -NMTP<tei:hi rend="italic"> ultimately became <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi>, published posthumously in 1935.  The </tei:hi>Niedergang<tei:hi rend="italic"> essay survives as an annotated typescript, OC 31/28-153, and an edition with translation and accompanying article by William Drabkin appears in </tei:hi>Music Analysis<tei:hi rend="italic"> 25/1-2 (March-July 2005).  The </tei:hi>Handbibliothek_ never materialized as such: the planned first booklet eventually became the much larger monograph</tei:note></tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  OJ 5/6, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> Schenker had been planning to release his <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Niedergang der Kompositionskunst: eine technisch-kritische Untersuchung</tei:hi> (The Decline of the Art of Composition: a technical-critical Inquiry), originally intended as the <tei:hi rend="italic">Nachwort</tei:hi> (Afterword) to <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (CA 5–6, November 22, 1905), but which had expanded such that it was subsequently detached and scheduled to appear six months after <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (i.e. in May 1907: OJ 9/31, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  <tei:hi rend="italic">eben</tei:hi> (specifically) appears four words later in draft, before zu.</tei:note>, June 5, 1906) as a separate "supplementary publication" (<tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi>, p.VII, trans. p. xxvi), presumably in the form of a pamphlet or booklet.  S later reconceived it as vol. III of <tei:hi rend="italic">NMTP</tei:hi> (CA 68, September 13, 1907) and the "capstone" (<tei:hi rend="italic">Pointe</tei:hi>) of the entire work.  In 1908 he was still speaking of it in these terms (CA 87, October 13, 1908).  Here, he presents his <tei:hi rend="italic">Handbibliothek</tei:hi> as a direct extension of that work, which was never published.  Vol. III of -NMTP<tei:hi rend="italic"> ultimately became <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi>, published posthumously in 1935.  The </tei:hi>Niedergang<tei:hi rend="italic"> essay survives as an annotated typescript, OC 31/28-153, and an edition with translation and accompanying article by William Drabkin appears in </tei:hi>Music Analysis<tei:hi rend="italic"> 25/1-2 (March-July 2005).  The </tei:hi>Handbibliothek_ never materialized as such: the planned first booklet eventually became the much larger monograph</tei:note> is a draft of the letter.  Since draft and final letter are relatively similar, I have conflated the two.  This transcription and translation presents the final version, and footnotes the variants in the draft.  At the head of the draft there appears, in Schenker’s hand: “an Cotta” (To Cotta).</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Wien, 10. 9. 1910</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr !</tei:p><tei:p>Im<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  <tei:hi rend="italic">In meinem</tei:hi> in draft.</tei:note> letzten Brief an Sie,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  CA 118, August 19, 1910, to which Cotta had replied discouragingly in OJ 9/31, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn26">  <tei:hi rend="italic">auch</tei:hi> not in draft.</tei:note>, August 1910.</tei:note> worin ich Sie um eine Unterredung in Stuttgart gebeten, mag ich vielleicht nicht genau meine Absicht ausgedrückt haben.  Jedenfalls ist der Titel: “Handbibliothek,” der nur im Augenblick ein Ziel, nicht der eigentliche.  Es handelt sich vielmehr um einen “<tei:hi rend="italic">Literaturanhang</tei:hi>” zu dem von mir bereits mehrfach in der Vorrede zu <tei:hi rend="italic">I</tei:hi> u. zu <tei:hi rend="italic">II/1</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> <tei:hi rend="italic">I/1</tei:hi> in draft.</tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">angekündigten</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">III Bd.</tei:hi> meiner “<tei:hi rend="italic">Th. u. Ph.</tei:hi>,” dem „Niedergang der Kompositionskunst.”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> Schenker had been planning to release his <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Niedergang der Kompositionskunst: eine technisch-kritische Untersuchung</tei:hi> (The Decline of the Art of Composition: a technical-critical Inquiry), originally intended as the <tei:hi rend="italic">Nachwort</tei:hi> (Afterword) to <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (CA 5–6, November 22, 1905), but which had expanded such that it was subsequently detached and scheduled to appear six months after <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (i.e. in May 1907: OJ 9/31, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  <tei:hi rend="italic">eben</tei:hi> (specifically) appears four words later in draft, before zu.</tei:note>, June 5, 1906) as a separate "supplementary publication" (<tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi>, p.VII, trans. p. xxvi), presumably in the form of a pamphlet or booklet.  S later reconceived it as vol. III of <tei:hi rend="italic">NMTP</tei:hi> (CA 68, September 13, 1907) and the "capstone" (<tei:hi rend="italic">Pointe</tei:hi>) of the entire work.  In 1908 he was still speaking of it in these terms (CA 87, October 13, 1908).  Here, he presents his <tei:hi rend="italic">Handbibliothek</tei:hi> as a direct extension of that work, which was never published.  Vol. III of -NMTP<tei:hi rend="italic"> ultimately became <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi>, published posthumously in 1935.  The </tei:hi>Niedergang<tei:hi rend="italic"> essay survives as an annotated typescript, OC 31/28-153, and an edition with translation and accompanying article by William Drabkin appears in </tei:hi>Music Analysis<tei:hi rend="italic"> 25/1-2 (March-July 2005).  The </tei:hi>Handbibliothek_ never materialized as such: the planned first booklet eventually became the much larger monograph</tei:note>  Folgerichtig ausgebaut müßte nämlich<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  <tei:hi rend="italic">nämlich</tei:hi> not in draft.</tei:note> letzterer innerhalb der theoretischen Erörterungen wohl<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  <tei:hi rend="italic">wohl</tei:hi> (certainly) not in draft.</tei:note> auch die wichtigsten Literaturbeispiele mit sich führen.  Da indessen dort die Beispiele eben nur in allzu knappen Grenzen gehalten werden müßten, wodurch aber die Beweiskraft meiner Lehren leider<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  <tei:hi rend="italic">leider</tei:hi> (unfortunately) not in draft.</tei:note> geschmälert würde, halte ich es für durchaus notwendig, ganz hervorragende Erscheinungen in Form eben<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  <tei:hi rend="italic">eben</tei:hi> (specifically) appears four words later in draft, before zu.</tei:note> eines selbstständigen Literaturanhanges zu <tei:hi rend="italic">Bd. III</tei:hi> in <tei:hi rend="italic">gesonderten Heften</tei:hi> herauszugeben.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  <tei:hi rend="italic">herauszugeben: erschienen zu lassen</tei:hi> in draft.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Der Generaltitel könnte etwa lauten:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Draft read: <tei:hi rend="italic">Jedes dieser Heftchen würde etwa mit den Generaltitel</tei:hi> [...]<tei:hi rend="italic">versehen, u. z. B.  mit: I “IX Symphonie von Beethoven” in Speziellen betitelt, ein solches Heftchen:</tei:hi> (Each of these booklets, given the overarching title of perhaps [...] would be individually titled, e.g., I. Ninth Symphony of Beethoven, each such booklet would also ...).</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> “Literaturanhang zum dritten, in Vorbereitung befindlichen Band der “<tei:hi rend="italic">N. m. Th. u. Ph.</tei:hi>” (so oder ähnlich)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Whole parenthesis not in draft.</tei:note> das einzelne Heftchen aber wurde eine Nummer tragen, wie z. B.</tei:p><tei:p>I.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven: IX Symphonie</tei:hi></tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Das Heftchen würde auch einzeln zu haben sein, was sowohl für die Verbreitung der Lehre, als auch in geschäftlicher Hinsicht von großem Vorteil wäre !</tei:p><tei:p>Anderseits stellen diese Bändchen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Bändchen</tei:hi>: in draft: <tei:hi rend="italic">Heftchen</tei:hi>.</tei:note> derart in sich<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  <tei:hi rend="italic">in sich</tei:hi> not in draft.</tei:note> abgeschlossene kleine <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Monographien</tei:hi></tei:hi> dar, daß sie wohl auch ohne Kenntnis des <tei:hi rend="italic">III. Bd.</tei:hi>, also auch <tei:hi rend="italic">vor</tei:hi> dessen Erscheinen mit Nutzen gelesen u. studiert<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15">  <tei:hi rend="italic">und studiert</tei:hi> (and studied) not in draft.</tei:note> werden können!  Zu einer vorzeitigen <tei:hi rend="italic">Publikation</tei:hi> bin ich außerdem bereits <tei:hi rend="italic">gezwungen </tei:hi>(!)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn16">  “(!)“ not in draft.</tei:note> durch die Haltung meiner<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn17">  Draft has <tei:hi rend="italic">eigenen</tei:hi> (own) at this point.</tei:note> Vorrede zu <tei:hi rend="italic">II/1</tei:hi>, die ich S. I–VIII nachzulesen bitte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn18">  S’s Foreword includes reference at the opening to a “decline”, stating: “I plan to discuss more precisely in a later volume the decline and its causes. ...,” and again “I will prove this, as promised earlier, in as much detail as possible on another occasion,” and later criticizes existing “concert guides, program books, and analyses” for failing to “come to grips with music in purely artistic terms.” (trans. John Rothgeb and Jürgen Thym, 1987,  Book I, pp.xvii, xviii, xxiv–xxv).  [NB provide original page-numbers]</tei:note>  Ich möchte dieser in ihrer Art wohl einzig dastehenden u.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn19"> <tei:hi rend="italic">in ihrer Art wohl einzig dastehenden u.</tei:hi> (totally unique) not in draft.</tei:note> unerbittlichen <tei:hi rend="italic">Anklage</tei:hi>—vielleicht interessiert es Sie, in diesem Zusammenhange zwei Zuschriften<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn20">  <tei:hi rend="italic">die Zuschrift</tei:hi> (the letter) in draft.</tei:note> des bekannten Professors u. <tei:hi rend="italic">Senators</tei:hi> der Kgl. Hochschule in <tei:hi rend="italic">Berlin</tei:hi>, H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Ernst Rudorff</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn21">  The Hochschule für Musik was founded in 1869, and was part of the Akademie der Künste.  Click on <ref cRef="rudorff_ernst">Ernst Rudorff</ref>.</tei:note> einzusehen—sobald als möglich entscheidende Beweise folgen <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> lassen, wodurch übrigens auch der Erfolg des <tei:hi rend="italic">II/1</tei:hi> in schöner Weise gestützt würde.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich schlage daher vor, Sie mögen mir Ihren geschätzten Verlag u. zw.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn22">  <tei:hi rend="italic">u. zwar</tei:hi> (and moreover) not in draft.</tei:note> wieder <tei:hi rend="italic">unter den für das Hauptwerk selbst vereinbarten Bedingungen</tei:hi> auch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn23">  <tei:hi rend="italic">auch</tei:hi> not in draft.</tei:note> für diese Heftchen, als <tei:hi rend="italic">organische Bestandteile</tei:hi> desselber,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn24">  <tei:hi rend="italic">organische</tei:hi> (organic) not in draft, and phrase not underlined.</tei:note> zur Verfügung stellen, so daß schon in diesem Winter als erstes die bereits fertig gebrachte “<tei:hi rend="italic">IX Symph. von Beethoven</tei:hi>“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn25"> <tei:hi rend="italic">von Beethoven</tei:hi> not in draft.</tei:note> (vielleicht das verkannteste Werk unserer Literatur!!) erscheinen könnte.  Dieses Bändchen sowohl, als auch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn26">  <tei:hi rend="italic">auch</tei:hi> not in draft.</tei:note> die nachfolgenden könnten dann selbstverständlich zu <tei:hi rend="italic">billigen</tei:hi> Preisen (weil einzeln)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn27">  <tei:hi rend="italic">weil</tei:hi> and parentheses not in draft, and einzeln underlined, thus reading: “could then of course be purchased <tei:hi rend="italic">individually</tei:hi> at <tei:hi rend="italic">low</tei:hi> prices.”</tei:note> verkauft werden. <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn28">  Significantly, S removed from the final version a discrete paragraph that appears in the draft at this point: „Vielleicht würde es Ihnen einmal passen, auch andere Mitarbeiter zu dieser Handbibliothek heranzuziehen!“ (Pehaps you might even care to involve other contributors in this Reference Library!)</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Das nun revidierte <tei:hi rend="italic">Mscpt</tei:hi> zu <tei:hi rend="italic">II/2</tei:hi> der „<tei:hi rend="italic">Th. u. Ph</tei:hi>.“ Sende ich alsbald nach !</tei:p><tei:p>In Erwartung einer baldigen höflichen Gegenäußerung zeichne ich</tei:p><tei:p>Hochachtungsvoll ergeben
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H Schenker
Wien, 10. 9. 1910</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cotta, dated September 10, 1910</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="bold">= OJ 5/6, <tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/></tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Vienna, September 10, 1910</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Sir,</tei:p><tei:p>In my<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> last letter to you,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> requesting a meeting in Stuttgart, I may perhaps not have expressed my intentions clearly.  At any rate, the title is: “Reference Library”, which is only provisional for now, not definitive.  It is, moreover, a “Music-Repertory Appendix” to vol. III of my <tei:hi rend="italic">New Musical Theories and Fantasies</tei:hi>, already <tei:hi rend="italic">announced</tei:hi> several times by me in the Foreword to vol. I and vol. II/1:<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> the <tei:hi rend="italic">Decline of the Art of Composition</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> Logically expanded, this<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> latter would certainly<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> have to include in the course of its theoretical discussions the most important examples from the repertory.  Since, however, the examples there [i.e. within <tei:hi rend="italic">Decline</tei:hi>] would have to be kept within all-too-tight limits, and since the force of my teachings would unfortunately<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> be severely restricted as a result, I consider it critically necessary {2} to publish<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> overwhelmingly convincing evidence in the form specifically<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> of an independent music-repertory appendix to vol. III in <tei:hi rend="italic">separate booklets</tei:hi>.</tei:p><tei:p>The overarching title could perhaps read:<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> “Music-Repertory Appendix to the third volume of the <tei:hi rend="italic">New Musical Theories and Fantasies</tei:hi>, currently in preparation.” (or something of the sort)</tei:p><tei:p>Each individual booklet would bear a number, as e.g.:</tei:p><tei:p>I.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven’s Ninth Symphony</tei:hi></tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>The booklet would also be obtainable singly, which would be of great advantage not only for the dissemination of my theory but also from the commercial point view.</tei:p><tei:p>On the other hand, these little booklets<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> amount to self-contained short <tei:hi rend="italic">monographs</tei:hi>, such that they can be profitably read and studied<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn15"/> without the slightest knowledge of vol. III, hence even <tei:hi rend="italic">before</tei:hi> the latter is out!  Indeed, I am already <tei:hi rend="italic">committed</tei:hi> (!)<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn16"/> that they should be published beforehand by the point of view put forward in my<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn17"/> Preface to II/1, of which I urge you to look up pp. I–VIII.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn18"/>  I should like to furnish conclusive evidence {3} as soon as possible corroborating this implacable and totally unique<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn19"/> charge—perhaps it might interest you in this connection to examine two letters<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn19"/> of Mr. Ernst Rudorff, the well-known Professor and Senator of the Royal High School [for Music] in Berlin.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn21"/> The success of vol. II/1 would, by the way, be very nicely reinforced by this evidence.</tei:p><tei:p>I therefore suggest that you might make your esteemed press available to me again for these little booklets, which are <tei:hi rend="italic">organic constituents</tei:hi> of that main work,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn24"/> and moreover<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn22"/> <tei:hi rend="italic">under the conditions agreed for that work</tei:hi> [i.e. <tei:hi rend="italic">NMTF</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">itself</tei:hi>, so that the “Beethoven’s<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn25"/> Ninth Symphony” (perhaps the most unappreciated work in our repertory!!), already completed, could appear as the first one as early as this Winter.  This booklet, as well as those that will follow, could then of course be purchased (because individually)<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn27"/> at <tei:hi rend="italic">low</tei:hi> prices.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn28"/></tei:p><tei:p>I shall be sending the newly revised manuscript for II/2 of <tei:hi rend="italic">Theories and Fantasies</tei:hi> shortly.</tei:p><tei:p>Looking forward to an early reply, I remain</tei:p><tei:p>Yours, with kind regards
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H. Schenker
Vienna, September 10, 1910</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>