<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 89/2, [4] : 3-16-28 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.  
© Transcription John Rothgeb, 2009.
© Translation John Rothgeb, 2009.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb 2009
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Hoboken, Anthony van (1928-1983) - -Schneider, Hans(19??-2007) - -University of California, Riverside (2007 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker;  Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 03/16/1928 09:23:16 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Hoboken ~ H+JSchenker","Hoboken ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Hoboken, dated March 16, 1928</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-06-24</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Schenker speaks of Hoboken's Photogrammarchiv as a "grand contribution," and of the work to be done there;  reports on a copy of Beethoven sonata, Op. 90, by Archduke Rudolph.    - - He will show Hoboken recent articles by Dahms and Vrieslander, and inquires about Hoboken's birthday.   - - Furtwängler may come to Vienna permanently.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  Photogrammarchiv;  illness;  Rudolph, Erzherzog;  Haas, Robert;  Beethoven;  Op.; 90;  Deutsch, Otto Erich;  Dahms, Walter;  Vrieslander, Otto;  Gebethner &amp; Wolff;  Chopin;  Graz;  Vienna;  Paris;  birthday;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Hoboken, dated March 16, 1928</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Lieber Herr van Hoboken!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Writing of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/1, p. 3183, March 16, 1928:  "An Hoboken (Br.):  "über die Aufsätze von Dahms u. Vrieslander;  über die Abschrift des Erzherzog Rudolf der Sonate op. 90;  über die Möglichkeit, durch das 1. Heft der Mitteilungen sich einen Weg zu Haunack[?] zu bahnen, falls Paris endgiltig versagen sollte (?)." [a question-mark above "versagen" and "sollte"] ("About the articles by Dahms and Vrieslander;  about the Erzherzog Rudolf's copy of the [Beethoven] Sonata Op. 90;  about the possibility the issue 1 of the communications to gain access to Haunack[?] in the event that Paris might ultimately refuse.")  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Erkrankung u. unerwartete Schwierigkeiten<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  See OJ 11/54, [22], March 11, 1928.  </tei:note> -- ein bischen[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] zu viel Störung für einen Mann, der im Begriffe ist, ein großes Gut<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  i. e. the (click on) <ref cRef="photogrammarchiv">Photogrammarchiv</ref>.  </tei:note> zu schenken.  Nun, von der Erkrankung scheinen Sie sich ganz erholt zu haben, hier sieht ja die Natur weise u. großzügig nach;  dagegen kommen die anderen Schwierigkeiten von den Menschen, die weniger weise u. großzügig sind als die Natur.  Und gar, wenn es sich um &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;ein&lt;/sup&gt; Hohes handelt, das ihnen nicht einleuchtet!  Sehen Sie, vor Kürzem war ich bei D^r^ <tei:hi rend="italic">Haas</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="haas_robert">Robert Haas</ref>.</tei:note> u. ließ mir dort ein Abschrift zeigen, die <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven</tei:hi>'s Schüler <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> der Erzherzog (u. Erzbischof) <tei:hi rend="italic">Rudolph</tei:hi> von der <tei:hi rend="italic">Sonate</tei:hi> op. 90 unmittelbar nach der Handschrift für sich selbst verfertigte<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  The first page of this copy is reproduced in <tei:hi rend="italic">Ludwig van Beethoven, Klaviersonate e-Moll op. 90, Faksimile des Autographs</tei:hi>, edited with commentary by Michael Ladenburger (Bonn: Beethoven-Haus, 1993), p. 36.</tei:note> - Sie müssen sich das Stück zeigen lassen, wie sauber, gewissenhaft, sinngebend, hoch in Liebe u. Ausführung! -, nur eine Abschrift ist es u. doch wies sie mir Wege, die die Orig. Ausg. nicht ahnen lässt.  Sollten wir &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;auch&lt;/sup&gt; nie zur Handschrift gelangen, getraute ich mich, nach dieser Abschrift allein ein Korrektur &lt;del&gt;der&lt;/del&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;meiner&lt;/sup&gt; Ausgabe zu machen, [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from lower margin:</tei:hi> Auch Ihrem Archiv sei die Aufnahme derAbschrift empfohlen als Ersatz der Handschrift!] wieder also ein Erlebnis, das praktisch die Dringlichkeit Ihrer Aufgabe zeigt.  Daher ist mir auch kein Zweifel, daß wir Beide uns auch zu Wort zu melden haben werden, um die wichtigsten Korrekturen anzuzeigen u. zu begründen - dann wird das Werk den <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Meister loben.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  No paragraph break in original.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Bis Sie nur Ihre Schwierigkeiten überwunden haben werden, werden Sie gewiß auch eine Form für solche Mitteilungen finden (D^r^ <tei:hi rend="italic">Haas</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Deutsch</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="deutsch_otto_erich">Otto Erich Deutsch</ref>.  </tei:note> halten Anregungen u. Pläne für Sie bereit), ich tue freudigst mit, u. vor Allem <tei:hi rend="italic">Sie</tei:hi> müssen die Feder gebrauchen, Sie sind 20 Jahre jünger als ich u. Sie sollen diese Kunst erben.  Ihr Ohr ist treffend, Sie schreiben sachlich, Űbung u. ich werden nachhelfen.  Wir dürfen uns um die Mitwelt nicht kümmern, müssen vielmehr große <tei:hi rend="italic">Toilette</tei:hi> für die Nachwelt machen.  Schließlich ist der Ruhm bei der Nachwelt, den Skeptiker verhöhnen, nicht schlechter als der bei der Mitwelt, genau genommen eher besser, viel, viel mehr.</tei:p><tei:p>Von <tei:hi rend="italic">Dahms</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="dahms_walter">Walter Dahms</ref>:  presumably "Das Meisterwerk in der Musik," <tei:hi rend="italic">Allgemeine Musikzeitung</tei:hi>, February 3, 1928, a copy of which is preserved in Schenker's scrapbook at OJ 2, p. 75.  </tei:note> u. Vrieslander<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>;  presumably "Heinrich Schenker," <tei:hi rend="italic">Deutsche Tonkünstler-Zeitung</tei:hi>, March 5, 1928, a copy of which is preserved in Schenker's scrapbook at OJ 2, p. 76.    </tei:note> sind inzwischen <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> zwei gewichtige Aufsätze eingelaufen, beide in <tei:hi rend="italic">Berlin</tei:hi> erschienen (am besten, ich zeige sie Ihnen in Wien, nicht?)</tei:p><tei:p>Wissen Sie schon, daß Sie inzwischen auch zum glücklichen Besitzer der <tei:hi rend="italic">Gebethner</tei:hi> &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;Gesammt&lt;/sup&gt; Ausgabe<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Chopin collected edition published by Gebethner &amp; Wolff (1/18??, 2/1882).  </tei:note> von <tei:hi rend="italic">Chopin</tei:hi> geworden sind?  H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Deutsch</tei:hi> fand sie in Graz.</tei:p><tei:p>Kommen Sie zum 23. nach Wien oder feieren Sie Ihren Geburtstag diesmal in <tei:hi rend="italic">Paris</tei:hi>?  Hier oder dort, Ich gedenke Ihrer mit aufrichtiger Freude!</tei:p><tei:p>Wir grüßen Sie Beide auf das herzlichste</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  <tei:hi rend="italic">HSchenker</tei:hi>
16.3.28</tei:p><tei:p>Furtwängler<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Click on <ref cRef="furtwangler_wilhelm">Wilhelm Furtwängler</ref>.  </tei:note> scheint in Wien Oper u. Konzert zu übernehmen, vielleicht ganz hier zu - bleiben.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Hoboken, dated March 16, 1928</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Mr. van Hoboken!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Illness and unexpected difficulties<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> -- a bit too much aggravation for a man who is about to make a grand contribution.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  Well, you seem to have recovered completely from the illness--nature takes care of this with wisdom and generosity --; but the other difficulties come from men, who are less wise and generous than nature.  And above all when it is a matter of &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;something&lt;/sup&gt; lofty that doesn't quite make sense to them!  Listen, just recently I visited Dr. Haas<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> and had them show me a copy that Beethoven's pupil <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> the Archduke (and Archbishop) Rudolph made for himself directly from the manuscript of the Sonata Op. 90<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> -- you must have them show you the item, how neat it is, scrupulous, communicative, excellent in devotion and execution!- -;  it is only a copy and yet it showed me things that could not be guessed from the original edition.  &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;Even&lt;/sup&gt; if we never get hold of the manuscript, I would confidently rely on this copy alone to make a revision of &lt;del&gt;the&lt;/del&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;my&lt;/sup&gt; edition [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from lower margin:</tei:hi> Inclusion of the copy in your Archive too, as a substitute for the manuscript, would be most advisable! ] -- yet another experience, then, that shows the practical urgency of your task.  Thus I also have no doubt that we both must speak out to list and demonstrate the most important corrections -- then the work will be a credit to the <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> master.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/></tei:p><tei:p>Once you have survived your difficulties, you too certainly will find a form for such communications (Dr. Haas, [Mr.] Deutsch<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> have suggestions and plans ready for you);  I will help with greatest pleasure, and above all <tei:hi rend="italic">you</tei:hi> must take up the pen;  you are twenty years younger than I and you have to become heir to this art.  Your ear is excellent, your writing is to the point;  practice will help you, as will I.  We must not worry about contemporaries, we must rather spruce ourselves up in grand style for posterity.  In the end, renown in posterity, which is derided by skeptics, is not worse than renown among contemporaries--in fact, it is instead better, and much, much more.</tei:p><tei:p>In the interim <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> two important essays have arrived, by Dahms<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> and Vrieslander,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> both published in Berlin (it's best if I show them to you in Vienna, don't you think?).</tei:p><tei:p>Did you know that also in the interim you have become the fortunate owner of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Gebethner </tei:hi>&lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;collected&lt;/sup&gt; edition of Chopin?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/>  Mr. Deutsch found it in Graz.</tei:p><tei:p>Will you come to Vienna on the 23d or celebrate your birthday in Paris this time?  Here or there, I will be thinking of you with true happiness!</tei:p><tei:p>Our warmest greetings to both,</tei:p><tei:p>Yours sincerely,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  H. Schenker
March 16, 1938</tei:p><tei:p>Furtwängler<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> apparently will take over opera and concert in Vienna, and may <tei:hi rend="italic">remain</tei:hi> here altogether.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>