<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:DLA 69.930/13 (Excpt) : 10-6-24 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription Ian Bent &amp; Lee Rothfarb 2006.
© Translation Lee Rothfarb &amp; Ian Bent, 2006.
 --><!-- 

 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 10/12/1924 02:01:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "DeutschS ~ HSchenker","MarxJ ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Halm, dated October 6, 1924 (Excerpt)</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted><!-- Enter date of submission here --></dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description /><dc:subject><!-- Enter subjects here --></dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN" /><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN" /></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Halm, dated October 6, 1924 (Excerpt)</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>. . .</tei:p><tei:p>(para. 2)
In der gewissen anderen Angelegenheit habe ich noch zu berichten:  Zu meiner Überraschung hat ^sich der Verein^, der eigentliche Erbe nach meiner langjährigen Schülerin, -sich- aufgelöst u. das gewisse Geld an die hiesige Akademie als Stiftung unter -dem- ^ihrem^ Namen übertragen mit dem ausdrücklichen Zusatz, daß ich bis an mein Lebensende allein über die Versendung zu entscheiden habe.  Entweder aber ließ es der Verein oder sein Anwalt an der nötigen Genauigkeit fehlen, kurz, es wurde mir ein Brief von Hofrat Marx, dem Direktor der Akademie, vorgelegt, worin er sich verpflichtet, mir jährlich einen <tei:hi rend="italic">Terna</tei:hi>-Vorschlag zu erstatten u. die endgültige Entscheidung zu überlassen.  Das ist gewiß nicht das, was die Erblasserin meinte.  Ich schrieb dem Anwalt aus Galtür, er aber verwies <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> mich auf eine persönliche Austragung mit Marx.  (Woraus ich schließen muß, daß letzterer in völliger Unschuld die Idee vom <tei:hi rend="italic">Terna</tei:hi>. Vorschlag hineinbrachte.)  Da augenblicklich der Direktor gewiß viel zu tun hat – erste Wochen eines neuen Schuljahres –, so will ich gegen Mitte oder Ende d. M. die Angelegenheit bereinigen.  Wenn er auf den Vorschlag verzichtet, dann verfüge ich allein über die Zinsen, ohne Jemand Rechenschaft zu legen (so war es gemeint).  Ich kann dann auch in Anbetracht dessen, daß der Wert des Geldes gesunken ist, an denselben Künstler mehrere Jahre hintereinander die Zinsen schicken, ohne daß dies Jemand zu wissen braucht. Überhaupt bestand die Erblasserin auf äußersten <tei:hi rend="italic">discretion</tei:hi>, da sie wußte, was ich vorhabe.  Das Ergebnis meiner Unterredung will ich dann mitteilen.</tei:p><tei:p>. . .</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Halm, dated October 6, 1924 (Excerpt)</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>. . .</tei:p><tei:p>(para. 2)
I have yet to report about a certain other matter. To my surprise, the ^Association^, the actual heir according to my student of many years, has been dissolved, and the specified money has been transferred to the local Academy as an endowment in ^her^ name with the explicit rider that I alone decide all disbursement until my death. However, either the Association or its attorney failed to provide the necessary precision. In short, a letter from Hofrat Marx, the Director of the Academy, was conveyed to me, in which he commits to provide me annually with a slate of three candidates, and to leave the final decision to me. That is surely not what the deceased intended. I wrote the attorney from Galtür, but he directed <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> me to negotiate personally with Marx. (From which I must conclude that the latter introduced the idea of a slate of three candidates in total innocence.) Since the Director surely has so much to do at the moment—first weeks of a new academic year—I will clear up the matter at the middle or end of the month. If he abandons the [idea of a] slate, then I alone have authority over the interest without having to be accountable to anyone (that is how it was intended). Then, considering that the value of the money has declined, I can send the interest to the same artist several years in a row, without anyone having to know it. The deceased insisted in general on extreme discretion, because she knew what I am planning. I will report the outcome of my meeting.</tei:p><tei:p>. . .</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>