<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 8/3, [59] : 5-13-18 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  In the public domain
©  Transcription Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin, 2009
©  Translation Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin, 2009
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin 2009
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Violin, Moriz (1918-1956) - -Heirs of Moriz Violin (1956-197?) - -University of California, Riverside (197? - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker;  Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent and William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 05/13/1918 12:45:30 PM --><!-- MT Tags: "ViolinM ~ HSchenker","ViolinM+V ~ HSchenker","ViolinM+V+F ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten postcard from Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated May 13, 1918</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-04-30</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Schenker thanks Violin for an address;  reports on planned visit to Wilhelm, and food promised by him and items sent by Hupka;  Heinrich and Jeanette expect to spend the summer in Vienna.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Violin, Moriz;  address;  Schenker, Wilhelm;  visit;  invitation;  foodstuffs;  Vienna;  Violin, Genovefa;  Violin, Karl</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Vienna III, Reisnerstraße 38</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Marburg on the Drau, Kokoschineggallee 6</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten postcard from Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated May 13, 1918</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
[Absender:] <tei:hi rend="italic">D&lt;sup&gt;r&lt;/sup&gt; Heinrich Schenker</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="italic">Wien, III, Reisnerstr. 38</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[An:] H [/] <tei:hi rend="italic">Violin Moriz</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="italic">Marburg a/d Drau</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="italic">Kokoschineggallee</tei:hi> [/] <tei:hi rend="italic">No. 6</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>]  || 3/3 WIEN [??] | 3.V.18 | <tei:hi rend="bold"> a </tei:hi> ||</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">for continuation of recto, see below</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
Fl!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Writing of this postcard is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/10, p. 890: "An Fl. (K.): danke für die Vermittlung;  habe nur gezögert, um auch das Resultat mitteilen zu können:  dieses sei leider negativ ausgefallen;  erwähne der Sendung von Hupka, der Absage von Wilhelm u. teile unsern Entschluß mit, in Wien zu bleiben. " ("To Floriz (postcard):  I thank [him] for passing on the information;  have only waited to let him know the result:  this time, unfortunately, it has proved negative;  mention of the package from Hupka being turned down by Wilhelm and let him know of our decision to remain in Vienna.").</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Für deine letzte Mitteilung besten Dank.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  this item of correspondence is not known to survive.  The most recently recorded receipt of a letter from Violin appears in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/10, p. 884, May 3, 1918:  "Von Fl. (K.): empfiehlt Pickern bei Marburg." ("From Floriz (postcard): recommends Pickern near Marburg.")  </tei:note> Ich habe sofort an die mir von dir bezeichnete Adresse eine Karte gerichtet, bin aber bis itzo keiner Antwort gewürdigt worden.  Eigens habe ich mit dem Dank für deine Mühe gezögert, weil ich noch das Resultat beifügen wollte: nun ist es ein negatives. - Von Wilhelm<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="schenker_wilhelm">Wilhelm Schenker</ref>.</tei:note> erhielten wir eine recht verlegene Absage trotz einer spontanen Einladung vor etlichen Wochen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Schenker's diary reports at OJ 2/10, p. 890, May 13, 1918:  "Brief von Wilhelm: ladet uns für Juni nach Dodis Rückkehr für paar Tage ein;  dies ginge, nur Sommergäste seien unwillkommen!." (Letter from Wilhelm: invites us for a few days in June, after Dodi's return;  all his means is that summer guests are unwelcome!") </tei:note>  (Ernst darf[?] eben nicht gemacht werden.) Dafür versprach er uns Eier u. Butter für die nächste Saison. Auch gut. 400 Kr. habe ich an ihn bereits <tei:hi rend="italic">à conto</tei:hi> dessen abgeschickt.  Kurioserweise erhielt ich von <tei:hi rend="italic">Hupka</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="hupka_felix">Felix Hupka</ref>.  </tei:note> eine sehr, sehr beträchtliche Ladung Butter, <tei:hi rend="italic">Milchbrod</tei:hi> (vom Umfang eines Auto-Rads), Pflaumen, Zucker <tei:hi rend="italic">etc</tei:hi>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  The advance letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/10, p. 884, May 3, 1918:  </tei:note> Das kam sehr überraschend. - Wir machen uns im Übrigen auf die Sommerfrische Wien gefaßt.  Noch frage ich hier u. dort an, <tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> um mir „am jüngsten Tag" Vorwürfe zu ersparen, habe aber keine Hoffnung.  Wo es allentfalls gienge, dort „gehen wir nicht hinein," wie das in der bekannten Anekdote von der Kirche heißt, u. „wo wir hineingiengen, dort ist nichts."<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Perhaps a reference to the parable of the wise and foolish virgins?:  <tei:hi rend="italic">Matthew</tei:hi> xxv.10: "Und als sie hingingen zu kaufen, kam der Bräutigam;  und die bereit waren, gingen mit ihm hinein zur Hochzeit, und die Tür wurde verschlossen." (Luther Bible) ("But while they were on their way to buy the oil, the bridegroom arrived.  The virgins who were ready went in with him to the wedding banquet.  And the door was shut.")  </tei:note>  Indessen es hat noch Zeit.  Dass Ihr alle wohl sind, ist schön und macht uns Freude.  Hoffentlich tut auch schon das Mädi<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="violin_genovefa">Genovefa Violin</ref>.    </tei:note> mit?  Wird bei Euch auch kroatisch gesprochen?  <tei:hi rend="italic">Karli</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  The Violins' son, <ref cRef="violin_karl">Karl Violin</ref>.  </tei:note> wäre es imstande, was?  So in Eile?</tei:p><tei:p>Viele Grüße Euch allen  
dein 
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] H u. Lielie.
13. Mai 1918</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten postcard from Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated May 13, 1918</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
[From:] Dr. Heinrich Schenker,
Vienna III, Reisnerstraße 38</tei:p><tei:p>[To:] Mr. Moriz Violin,
Marburg on the Drau, 
Kokoschineggallee 6</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>] || 3/3 VIENNA [??] | 3.V.18 | <tei:hi rend="bold"> a </tei:hi> ||</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">for continuation of recto, see below</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
Floriz,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Many thanks for your latest communication.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  I have sent a postcard off straight away to the address that you gave me, but have so far not been vouchsafed a reply.  I purposely delayed thanking you because I wanted to enclose the result:  now it is a negative.  -- We received a downright embarrased turn-down from Wilhelm,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> despite a spontaneous invitation a few weeks earlier.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  (Seriously, there is nothing to be made of it.[?])  In return, he promised us eggs and butter for next season.  That's good, too.  I have already sent him 400 Kronen on account for it.  Curiously, I received from Hupka<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> a very, very considerable consignment of butter, <tei:hi rend="italic">milk bread</tei:hi> (the size of an automobile wheel), plums, sugar, etc..<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/>  That came as a great surprise. -- By the way, we are steeling ourselves to spend the summer vacation in Vienna.  I am still asking around here and there, <tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> in order to spare myself reproaches "at the Judgment Day," but do not hold out any hope.  If the worst comes to the worst, we "will not enter in" there, as the well known anecdote from the church has it, and "where we did enter, there is nothing."<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>  Meanwhile, there I still time.  We are pleased to hear that you are all well.  I hope the little girl<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> is joining in now, as well?  Are you speaking Croatian to each other? Is Karli<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> up to that?  In such a hurry?</tei:p><tei:p>Heartfelt greetings to you all from 
Your
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  H[einrich] and Lielie.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>