<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 8/3, [57] : 4-7-18 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  In the public domain
©  Transcription Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin, 2009
©  Translation Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin, 2009
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin 2009
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Violin, Moriz (1918-1956) - -Heirs of Moriz Violin (1956-197?) - -University of California, Riverside (197? - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker;  Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent and William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 04/07/1918 11:51:27 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "ViolinM ~ HSchenker","ViolinM+V ~ HSchenker","ViolinM+V+F ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten postcard from Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated April 7, 1918</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-04-27</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Schenker has implemented the increase [in fee, for his pupils], and describes how intolerable life is in Vienna;  - - is trying with dificulty to book summer lodgings;  - - reports Weisse's declining of the invitation to contribute to the Schenker Festschrift;  - - he is working hard on his library. 

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Violin, Moriz;  fee increase;  shoes;  Kornfeld, Jeanette;  Dunkirk;  bowels;  Lembacher Inn;  Seefeld;  Kautzen;  Steinach-am-Brenner;  Weisse, Hans;  Vrieslander, Otto;  Adler, Guido;  library;  Freie Satz, Der;  Free Composition</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Wien III, Reisnerstraße 38</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> </marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten postcard from Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated April 7, 1918</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
[Absender:]  <tei:hi rend="italic">D&lt;sup&gt;r&lt;/sup&gt; Heinrich Schenker</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="italic">Wien, III., Reisnerstr. 38</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[An:]  H [/] Fähnrich <tei:hi rend="italic">Violin Moriz</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="italic">Marburg a/d Drau</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="italic">&lt;del&gt;Artilleriekaserne&lt;/del&gt;</tei:hi> ^[<tei:hi rend="italic">in pencil:</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Kokoschienegallee 6</tei:hi></tei:hi>^
<tei:hi rend="italic">&lt;del&gt;f. H. 106&lt;/del&gt;</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>]  || 3/3 [WIEN] | 8.[IV.18] | [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>] ||</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">for continuation of recto, see below</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
Fl.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  The writing of this postcard is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/10, p. 871: </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Besten Dank für deine letzten Erfreulichkeiten:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Violin's letter or postcard is not known to survive.  </tei:note>  das war eine gute Idee von Euch.  Hier wird es immer unerträglicher.  Die Erhöhung<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  i. e. notification to his students of the raising of his fees for the 1918/19 season.  </tei:note> habe ich nun glücklich durchgeführt - ohne Reibung, doch frägt sich, wie die Schüler ihr in der nächsten Saison standhalten werden, ob überhaupt -, doch Alles Geld mündet in den Wucher, der stündlich wächst.  Als Erstes gaben wir nicht weniger als 5 Paar Schuhe zur Besohlung u. bestellten ein neues Paar für Lieliechen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="schenker_jeanette">Jeanette Schenker</ref>.  </tei:note> woraus du nun nach den vergangenen Wintermonaten schließen magst, wie wir da „<tei:hi rend="italic">nicht</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">beschlagen</tei:hi>" gewesen sind.  Bei Kälte u. Nässe müßten wir so herumlaufen, u. dazu noch die unselige Neigung meines Darmes nach - wie sage ich es vor, nach „<tei:hi rend="italic">Dünn"nnn</tei:hi>kirchen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> "Dunn"nn" double-underlined by Schenker.  This is a complicated play on words. Schenker is alluding to Dunkirk (in German, "Dünkirchen"), a much fought-over coastal town in French Flanders (later, the site of a crucial battle in World War II). He has extended the "n" to emphasize weight-loss and other aspects of his bowel condition. (In colloquial German, "Dünnschiss" means "diarrhoea.")</tei:note> zu gehen! --<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Schenker inserts an emdash, then continutes without line-break.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Lembacher<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on the <ref cRef="lembacher">Lembacher</ref>.  </tei:note> gaunert[,] was ein Wiener nur kann u.s.w.  --<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Schenker inserts an emdash, then continutes without line-break.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Von Seefeld<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="seefeld">Seefeld</ref>.  Schenker is trying to secure lodgings for himself and Jeanette for their summer vacation in the Tyrol.  (By August 21, he was in Mariazell.)  </tei:note> kam eine Absage, so schrieb ich sofort nach Kautzen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Click on <ref cRef="kautzen">Kautzen</ref>.  </tei:note>    Noch will ich mit <tei:hi rend="italic">Steinach</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Click on <ref cRef="steinach_am_brenner">Steinach am Brenner</ref>. </tei:note> versuchen, von wo allerdings schon im vorigen Frühjahr eine Absage gekommen.  Lieber würde ich unter solchen Umständen noch in Wien bleiben, wenn es nicht so dringend sich empfehlen würde, meinem Lieliechen eine Pause zu gönnen.  Bald &lt;sup&gt;hätte&lt;/sup&gt; ich's vergessen:  Hans<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.  </tei:note> gab Vrieslander<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.  </tei:note> auf seinem langen <tei:hi rend="italic">zweiten</tei:hi> Brief <tei:hi rend="italic">eine</tei:hi> Zeile auf einer Postkarte zur Antwort:  „bedaure Ihrem Wunsche nicht entsprechen zu können, hochachtungsvoll"[.]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  Weisse's response to an invitation from Vrieslander to contribute to a Festschrift for Schenker on his fiftieth birthday.  It is unknown whether this survives.  </tei:note>  Vom ersten Augenblick, da mir der Sachverhalt bekannt wurde, habe ich angenommen <tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> (u. bleibe auch dabei), daß <tei:hi rend="italic">H.</tei:hi> sich die Reserve nur wegen <tei:hi rend="italic">Adler</tei:hi>'s<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15">  Click on <ref cRef="adler_guido">Guido Adler</ref>.  </tei:note> auferlegt, mit dem er sichs derzeit noch nicht verderben will (d.h. nicht vor dem erlangten Doctorat).  <tei:hi rend="italic">Vr.</tei:hi> ist über den Tonfall sehr empört, nun, da ist ja nichts zu machen.  --<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn16">  Schenker inserts an emdash, then continues without line-break.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Wir arbeiten höchst intensiv, um so viel als möglich vor Juli fertigzubringen an der Hand meiner Bibliothek,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn17">  Schenker was perhaps putting his library of scores into order because of the numerous music examples to be included in his Der freie Satz, by which he probably meant the second half-volume of his Kontrapunkt: (see <ref cRef="kontrapunkt_2"><tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt2</tei:hi></ref>), on a first draft of which he was working between 1917 and 1919.</tei:note> die ich unausgesetzt in Anspruch nehmen muß wegen der Unmenge von Beispielen des freien Satzes.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn18">  Der freie Satz (Free Composition): ultimately posthumously published under that title as vol. III of Neue Musikalische Theorien und Phantasien (Vienna:  UE, 1935), but in 1918 still considered part of <ref cRef="kontrapunkt_2"><tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt2</tei:hi></ref>.  </tei:note>  Du suchst, wir hoffen, abreisen zu können - möge es so kommen.</tei:p><tei:p>Euch allen beste Grüße von uns beiden 
dein
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">H</tei:hi>
7. April 1918</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten postcard from Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated April 7, 1918</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
[From:] Dr. Heinrich Schenker
Wien III, Reisnerstraße 38</tei:p><tei:p>[To:] Sub-Lieutenant Violin Moriz
Marburg on the Drau
&lt;del&gt;Artillery barracks&lt;/del&gt; &lt;sup&gt;[<tei:hi rend="italic">in pencil:</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">Kokoschienegallee 6</tei:hi>&lt;/sup&gt;
&lt;del&gt;f. H. 106&lt;/del&gt;</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>]  || 3/3 [VIENNA] | 8.[IV.18] | [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>] ||</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">or continuation of recto, see below</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
Floriz,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Many thanks for your latest bits of good news:<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  that was a good idea of yours.  Here, things get ever more unbearable.  Happily, I have now implemented the increase<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> -- without any friction, but the question remains how my pupils will withstand it during the coming season, or whether they will at all--all money is finding its way into usury, which grows by the hour.  The first thing we did was to take in no fewer than five pairs of shoes to be re-soled, and ordered a new pair for Lieliechen,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> from which you may deduce after the past winter months how "<tei:hi rend="italic">unshod</tei:hi>" we have gone.   We had to chase around so much in the cold and damp, and moreover to follow the unsavory dictates of my bowels to--how shall I put it?--to Dunnnnn-kirk<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>! --<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/></tei:p><tei:p>Lembacher<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> swindles [us] as only a Viennese can, etc..  --<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/></tei:p><tei:p>I received a rejection from Seefeld,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> so I wrote immediately to Kautzen.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/>  I will also try Steinach,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> though I was turned down there last spring.  Under such circumstances, I would prefer to remain in Vienna were it not so urgent to allow my Lieliechen to take a break.  Before I forget it:  Hans<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> sent Vrieslander,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> in reply to his <tei:hi rend="italic">second</tei:hi> long letter, <tei:hi rend="italic">one</tei:hi> line on a postcard:  "regret I am unable to accommodate your wishes, with kind regards."<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/>  From the very first moment I became aware of how matters stood, I assumed <tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> (and remain convinced) that Hans's reticence revolves solely around that of Adler,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn15"/> with whom he does not want to ruin his chances just now (i.e. not before he has obtained his doctorate).  Vrieslander is utterly furious at his tone, but nothing can be done about this. --<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn16"/></tei:p><tei:p>We are working at full stretch in order to have as much as possible of my library<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn17"/> ready by July;  I must  devote myself ceaselessly to it on account of the enormous number of music examples for <tei:hi rend="italic">Free Composition</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn18"/></tei:p><tei:p>We hope you are trying to get away--may it be so.</tei:p><tei:p>All best wishes to the two of you from both of us, 
your
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  H[einrich]
April 7, 1918</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>