<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 8/3, [56] : 1-31-18 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  In the public domain
©  Transcription Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin, 2009
©  Translation Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin, 2009
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2009
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Violin, Moriz (1918-1956) - -Heirs of Moriz Violin (1956-197?) - -University of California, Riverside (197? - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker;  Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent and William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 01/31/1918 03:47:58 PM --><!-- MT Tags: "ViolinM ~ H+JSchenker","ViolinM ~ HSchenker","ViolinM+V ~ HSchenker","ViolinM+V+F ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten postcard from Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated January 31, 1918</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-04-22</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Schenker inquires as to the price of a jar of jam that Valerie Violin brought him and lays down a "no presents" rule;  reports Halm's difficulties in obtaining copies of Schenker's works from UE.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Violin, Moriz;  Marmelade;  jam;  Kaffeehaus;  coffee-house;  Violin, Valerie;  Wally;  Mittelmann, Aaron;  Glattauer;  Halm, August;  Hertzka, Emil</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Vienna III, Reisnerstraße 38</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Marburg on the Drau, f.H.6, Artillery barracks</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten postcard from Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated January 31, 1918</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
[Absender:] <tei:hi rend="italic">D&lt;sup&gt;r&lt;/sup&gt; Heinrich Schenker</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="italic">Wien, III., Reisnerstr. 38</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[An:] H. [/] <tei:hi rend="italic">Fähnrich Violin Moriz</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="italic">Marburg</tei:hi> [<tei:hi rend="italic">added in pencil:</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">a/d Drau</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="italic">f.H.6.</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="italic">ArtillerieKaserne</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>]  || 10 WIEN 77 | 6. I. 18-3 | <tei:hi rend="bold"> 5b </tei:hi> ||</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">for continuation of recto, see below</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
Fl!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Writing of this postcard is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/10, p. 834, on the previous day, January 30, 1918:  "An Fl. (K.): erkundige mich nach den Kosten der drei Gläser; stehe auf dem Standpunkt, nicht unter 16000 Kronen Rente Geschenke anzunehmen, da ich Gott sei Dank noch sehr weit habe zu Mittelmann oder Glattauer; ersuche ihn bei dieser Gelegenheit, unser nicht zu vergessen."  ("To Floriz (postcard): I inquire as to the cost of the three jars;  I adopt the stance of not accepting presents from people with an income of less than 16,000 Kronen, since, thank God, I still have very far to go to Mittelmann and Glattauer;  I take the opportunity of begging him not to forget us. ").  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Schade, daß es nicht so gieng, wie wir es hofften!  Indessen sandte uns deine Frau<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="violin_valerie">Valerie Violin</ref>.  </tei:note> 2 große Gl., die gerade zur rechten Zeit erschienen.  Nun aber wußte sie gar nicht anzugeben, wie viel das erste Gl.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  The issue concerns jars of jam provided or promised by Valerie or Moriz Violin.  </tei:note> kostet, weshalb ich mich direkt an dich wende.  Schreibe mir also - wenigstens ein Thema - was 2 gr. + 1 kl. kosten, u. zw. sogleich, allsogleich, ja noch schneller.  Schon war es mir überaus peinlich, daß sozusagen aus <tei:hi rend="italic">technischen Gründen</tei:hi> nicht möglich war, den Gegenwert für einen schönen Tascheninhalt darzubringen, den uns deine Frau ins Cafëhaus Anfang des Monates<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  This incident is recorded in Schenker's diary for January 1, 1918 (OJ 2/10, p. 822): " Frau Wally kommt ins Caféhaus u. bringt: Aepfel, Slivowitz, Tee, Zucker, Hirse, Fleckeln, Zunge" ("Wally comes to the coffee-house and brings apples, slivovitz, tea, sugar, pasta, rolls, tongue").  </tei:note> selbst mitschleppte, aber ich begreife, daß sie für etwas, das ihr selbst geschenkt wurde, nichts annehmen wollte.  Diesmal liegt die Sache anders, u. da halte ich an meinem Grunden satz fest:  „Keine Geschenke unter 16.000 Kr. Rente!"  Hab' ich nicht recht?  Gott sei Dank, hab' ich doch noch sehr weit zu einem <tei:hi rend="italic">Mittelmann</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="mittelmann_aaron">Aaron Mittelmann</ref>.  The reference is presumably to obtaining goods on the black market.  </tei:note> oder <tei:hi rend="italic">Glattauer</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="glattauer">Glattauer</ref>.  </tei:note> d.h. es fehlen uns nur die gewissen <tei:hi rend="italic">Fangarme</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  "Fangarme":  presumably a reference to the black market, in which Mittelmann is known to have been involved.  </tei:note> um die Dinge zu erhaschen, aber bezahlen könnten wir sie schon.  Also heraus mit den paar Kronen.</tei:p><tei:p>Noch eine Kleinigkeit:  Halm<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  August Halm: [create profile and link].  This is Schenker's reaction to the postscript of a letter of January 20, 1918 from Halm (OJ 11/35, 7).    </tei:note> schrieb mir, daß er von Hertzka<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="hertzka_emil">Emil Hertzka</ref>.  </tei:note> meine übrigen Arbeiten als „Rezensionsexemplare" nicht erreichen kann!  Was sagst du dazu?  Ich <tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> drohte nun heute H.,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  = WSLB 292, January 30, 1918 (reported in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/10, p. 834, January 30.  </tei:note> daß ich selbst sie ihm bezahlen werde, doch nur zum alten Preise abzüglich u.s.w.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Schenker means minus the retail mark-up.  </tei:note>  Nun bin ich neugierig.  Womit man sich nur herumschlagen muß!  Solltest du aber gelegentlich zur Linderung aller Schmerzen etwas erhaschen, so denke gelegentlich auch an uns.  Also?  Viele Grüße von uns beiden.</tei:p><tei:p>Dein
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">H</tei:hi> 
31. Jänner 1918</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten postcard from Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated January 31, 1918</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
[From:] Dr. Heinrich Schenker
Vienna III, Reisnerstraße 38</tei:p><tei:p>[To:] Sub-Lieutenant Violin Moriz
Marburg [<tei:hi rend="italic">added in pencil:</tei:hi>] on the Drau
f.H.6.
Artillery barracks</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>]  || 10 VIENNA 77 | 6. I. 18-3 | <tei:hi rend="bold"> 5b </tei:hi> ||</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">for continuation of recto, see below</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
Floriz,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>A pity that it did not work out as we were hoping!  In the meantime, you wife<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> sent us two large jars, which appeared at just the right moment.  However, she was quite unable to tell me how much the first jar<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> cost, which is why I am turning to you directly.  So write telling me--at least one topic--what two large and one small [jars] cost, and do it right away, immediately, in fact even faster.  I found it embarrassing that, for <tei:hi rend="italic">technical reasons</tei:hi>, so to speak, it was not possible to offer the equivalent value of the lovely contents of the bag, which your wife went to the trouble of personally bringing to us at the coffee-house at the beginning of the month,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> but I can appreciate that she did not want to take anything for something that she herself had received as a present.  It is another matter this time, and I hold fast to my principle:  "No presents from anyone with an income of less than 16,000 Kroner!" Am I not right?  Thank God, I am still a long way from resorting to a Mittelmann<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> or Glattauer<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/>, which is to say, we lack only certain tentacles<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> to catch hold of things, but we can afford to pay for them.   So it is time for me to pay up!</tei:p><tei:p>One other trivial matter:  Halm<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> wrote telling me that he is unable to obtain my other publications from Hertzka<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> as "review copies."  What do you say to this?  I <tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> threatened Hertzka today<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> that I would pay him for them myself, but only at the old price, discounted by etc.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/>  Now I am curious [about his reply].  How hard we have to battle!  But if by any chance you should come up with a plan that might ease everyone's pain, then do think of us, too.  Any ideas?  Fond greetings from us both.</tei:p><tei:p>Your
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  H[einrich]
January 31, 1918</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>