<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-003296">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Wilna [lith: Vilnius]</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="wilna">Wilna [Vilnius]</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>28/04/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Place</term>
          <term subtype="basename">wilna</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Wilna [Lith: Vilnius]</head>
      <div>

        <p>City in north-eastern Europe, now the second largest city in Lithuania, but occupied by
          the Germans during much of World War I.</p>

        <p>A medieval city, Wilna was annexed to the Russian Empire in 1795 and remained so
          throughout the 19th century. Its population was part-Polish, part-Lithuanian, with some
          Russians, Belarusians, and Ukrainians, 41% being Jewish in 1897. From 1915 to 1918
          Lithuania was occupied by Germany, after which it was declared an indepent state in 1918;
          but after a period of rival claims it was annexed to Poland in 1922. In 1940 the whole of
          Lithuania was annexed by the Soviet Union. However, Vilnius was captured by the Germans in
          1941, its Jewish population being first gettoized then liquidated. Thereafter the country
          was absorbed into the Soviet Union until 1990 when it seceded and formed the Republic of
          Lithuania, of which Vilnius is now the second city.</p>

        <p>Schenker's correspondent <ref cRef="entity-000149">Walter Dahms</ref> while on military
          service was posted for a time in 1916 to "Wilna in the German administration" and put in
          charge of its libraries, archives, and museums. He wrote to Schenker from there,
          describing its climate as "swampy, with damp air" (OJ 10/1, [24]).</p>


      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
