<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-007490">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Theresienstadt [Terezín]</title>
        <title type="sub"/>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="theresienstadt_terezin">Theresienstadt [Terezín]</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>21/01/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Place</term>
          <term subtype="basename">theresienstadt_terezin</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Theresienstadt [Terezín]</head>
      <div>
        <p>Walled ghetto (or concentration camp), also transit camp to Auschwitz and other
          extermination camps 1941‒45, located in the town of Theresienstadt (Terezín) in northwest
          Bohemia.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Location</head>
        <p>Theresienstadt (Terezín) was a late-18th-century garrison town in northwest Bohemia,
          c.70km (43 miles) north of Prague and c.20km (12 miles) south of <ref cRef="entity-002248"
            >Aussig ((Ústí nad Labem)</ref>. From 1919 it was part of Czechoslovakia, but lay just
          inside the border of the predominantly German-speaking Sudetenland. It is situated on the
          Eger (Ohře) River just south of its confluence with the Elbe (Labe). It comprised a main
          fortress on the west bank, and a small fortress on the east side.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Ghetto</head>
        <p>After the German occupation of the Sudetenland in October 1938, then of the Czech lands
          (Bohemia, Moravia, Slovakia) in March 1939, the main fortress was adapted in 1941 as a
          ghetto to hold large numbers of Jews. These came initially from Prague and other parts of
          the Czech lands starting in November 1941, the small fortress becoming a Czech Gestapo
          prison. From June 1942, Jews were deported to the main fortress from Germany and Austria,
          including the Jews of Vienna, and from 1943 Jews from Holland and Denmark also. In all,
          150,000 Jews were sent to the ghetto, including 15,000 children. About 33,000 died in
          there, mostly of malnutrition and disease. When liberated by the Soviet army on May 8,
          1945, about 7,000 people were found, many of them ill or dying.</p>

        <p>The ghetto was used also to hold prominent members of Jewish communities and people in
          certain professions or possessing certain skills. The Nazis presented it as a "retirement
          settlement" for elderly Jews as part of their effort to conceal the extermination being
          conducted as the Final Solution. Despite the hideous, insanitary conditions in which the
          inmates were kept, the ghetto did have something of a cultural life with concerts,
          lectures, and other events. The Red Cross was once admitted to see in what "comfortable"
          conditions the Jews were living, the camp having been "beautified" for the occasion, and a
          documentary film was made for propaganda purposes. The ghetto was officially governed by
          Jewish self-administration, a "Council of Elders" making many of the decisions as to the
          running of the camp.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Transit Camp</head>
        <p>More than 88,000 Jews brought first to Theresienstadt were then deported to Auschwitz and
          other death camps. The number of survivors, from the ghetto itself and from those
          transported onward, is around 23,000.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Schenker Circle</head>
        <p>Since most of Schenker's pupils, friends, and associates were ‒ like Heinrich and
          Jeanette themselves ‒ Jewish, many of them were probably deported to Theresienstadt
          between 1942 and 1944. Heinrich died before the Anschluss, but <ref cRef="entity-000771"
            >Jeanette</ref>, on the other hand, persecuted by the Nazis from 1940 and reportedly
          rescued from them twice, was eventually deported from Vienna on transport IV/248, June 29,
          1942. Having survived in the ghetto for two-and-a-half years, she died there on January 8,
          1945. Her younger son, <ref cRef="entity-000468">Felix Kornfeld</ref>, was placed in
          Theresienstadt, where he encountered his mother (<ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-71-21a_2">OJ 71/21a, [2]</ref>), before being deported to Auschwitz, where he
          perished on September 29, 1944. <ref cRef="entity-000909">Fanny Violin</ref>, sister of
          Schenker's closest friend <ref cRef="entity-000913">Moriz Violin</ref>, was transported to
          Theresienstadt and deported to Auschwitz, where she perished in May 1944. Heinrich's
          amanuensis <ref cRef="entity-000599">Aron Mittelmann</ref> was deported to Theresienstadt
          on transport IV/9, No. 601, August 27-28, 1942 at the age of 85, and died on November 16
          of that year of <hi rend="italic">marasmus senilis</hi>. He lived in building L 504,
          section 1. The cellist <ref cRef="entity-000728">Eduard Rosé</ref>, admired by Schenker,
          died in the ghetto on January 24, 1943. Others of whom nothing is known after 1939 must
          also have been deported to Theresienstadt.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Today</head>
        <p>The concentration camp is now open to the public, with guided tours, and there is a
          Ghetto Museum and War Museum.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources/Bibliography</head>
        <p>
          <listBibl>
            <bibl><title level="m">wikipedia</title>
              <ref type="external" target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theresienstadt_Ghetto">
                <title level="a">Theresienstadt Ghetto</title></ref>; <ref type="external"
                target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terez%C3%ADn">Terezín</ref></bibl>
            <bibl><ref type="external"
                target="https://www.google.com/search?q=terezin+museum&amp;rlz=1C1CHBD_en-GBGB786GB786&amp;oq=terezin+museum&amp;aqs=chrome.0.69i59j0l7.2839j0j7&amp;sourceid=chrome&amp;ie=UTF-8"
                >Terezín Museum</ref></bibl>
            <bibl><author>Kluger, Ruth</author>, <title level="m">Landscapes of Memory: A Holocaust
                Girlhood Remembered</title> (New York: Feminist Press, 2001; London: Bloomsbury,
              2003), pp. 76-100</bibl>
            <bibl><author>Muller, Melissa</author> and <author>Piechocki, Reinhard</author>, <title
                level="m">Ein Garten Eden inmitten der Hölle</title> (Munich: Droemer Knauer, 2006),
              Eng. transl. <title level="m">A Garden of Eden in Hell ... The Life of Alice
                Herz-Sommer</title> (London: Pan Macmillan, 2007, pp. 123-42</bibl>
            <bibl><editor>Smith, Lyn</editor>, ed., <title level="m">Forgotten Voices of the
                Holocaust: A New History in the Words of the Men and Women who Survived</title>
              (London: Ebury Press and Imperial War Museum, 2005), p. 139 and <hi rend="italic"
                >passim</hi></bibl>
          </listBibl>
        </p>
      </div>


      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
