<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-004227">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Hadersdorf‒Weidlingau</title>
        <title type="sub">nr. Vienna</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="hadersdorf‒weidlingau">Hadersdorf‒Weidlingau</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>28/04/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Place</term>
          <term subtype="basename">hadersdorf‒weidlingau</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Hadersdorf‒Weidlingau</head>
      <div>

        <p>Two small towns c. 5½ miles (9 km) west-north-west of Vienna in the Vienna Woods,
          situated on opposite sides of the Wien River and the Western Railroad line to St. Pölten,
          c.2 miles (3 km) west of Hütteldorf and c.2½ miles (4 km) east of <ref
            cRef="entity-003216">Purkersdorf</ref>.</p>

        <p>Grieben's travel guide <title level="m">Vienna and its Environs</title> for 1913
          describes them and their surrounding features thus, much as Schenker must have known them: <cit>
            <q><hi rend="bold">Hadersdorf‒Weidlingau</hi>,the next station on the Western Railroad
              after Hütteldorf, is a much loved summer vacation resort (restaurants Fieldmarshall
              Loudon, At the Rehböckl, Rouland, Laye, and Audel. ‒ Railway Restaurant Josef
              Starnberger; restaurants Hullesch; Pisecker, and Karl Grosser). In the Hütteldorf
              direction [west] lies <hi rend="italic">Mariabrunn</hi>, a much visited place of
              pilgrimage. From the church in Mariabrunn on the northward-branching road can be
              reached <hi rend="italic">Hadersdorf</hi>, with its castle and park belonging to the
              Loudon family; in the park is the statue of the famous army commander. Continuing on
              this road leads in half an hour into the delightful valley of the same name northwest
              toward <hi rend="italic">Vorder-Hainbach</hi>; a quarter hour further on are the
              restaurants Reinwald, a good restaurant, and Josef Riedl. — <hi rend="italic"
                >Hinter-Hainbach</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Sofie Alp</hi> (Gasthof and Dairy)
              [one hour from here, the <hi rend="italic">Franz-Karl Viewpoint</hi>, 486 meters] lie
              [north] in a narrow wooded valley, in which the roadway leads into the idyllically
              situated small village of <hi rend="italic">Steinbach</hi>; the path in the valley
              itself leads [northwest] toward <hi rend="italic">Mauerbach</hi>. From here northward,
              the 495-meter-high <hi rend="italic">Tulbingerkogl</hi> (yellow-marked path) can
              comfortably be reached in one hour. On it is a look-out point, erected by the Austrian
              Mountaineering Association, from which a lovely vista opens up.</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>To the south of Weidlingau in Schenker's day lay the village of Auhof and the Imperial
          Zoo, and southwest lay <ref cRef="entity-003282">Baunzen</ref>.</p>

      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Hadersdorf‒Weidlingau and Schenker</head>
        <p>During the 1900s, 1910s and 1920s Schenker made many weekend excursions into the Vienna
          Woods, either on his own or with friends, and later with Jeanette. Taking the train either
          to Hütteldorf or to Hadersdorf‒Weidlingau, he would take his choice from among the many
          marked footpaths; and he recorded these walks in his diaries. From October 13, 1907 is
          recorded: "First excursion: Purkersdorf, Baunzen, Weidlingau (with the Pollaks)." A
          typical example from June 19, 1919 reads: <cit>
            <q>didn't leave until 9:30 to Hütteldorf, then to Weidlingau for lunch; ate very well,
              some dishes prepared just as in peacetime. — After lunch in Laudon Park, which we
              incidentally enter for the first time; it remains private property, just the open gate
              gave rise to the idea that it might possibly have recently been opened to the public.
              The Count's servant informed us to the contrary, but was kind enough to permit us to
              continue walking through the park. Through the woods first back to the Weidlingau
              train station and then, despite high heat, by foot to Hütteldorf, since the next train
              would have brought us there two hours later.</q>
          </cit></p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Source</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Griebens Reiseführer</title>: vol. 68, <title level="m">Wien und
              Umgebung 1923</title> (Berlin: Verlag von Griebens Reiseführern, 25th edn, 1923), pp.
            75‒76</bibl>
        </listBibl><lb/>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>

  </text>
</TEI>
