<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-002401">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Lemberg [Pol: L'wów; Ukr: L'viv]</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="lemberg">Lemberg</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>16/10/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Place</term>
          <term subtype="basename">lemberg</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Lemberg [Pol: L'wów; Ukr: L'viv]</head>
      <div>

        <p>City now in western Ukraine, on the Poltva River.</p>

        <p>From 1772 to 1918, Lemberg was the capital city of <ref cRef="entity-002355"
            >Galicia</ref>, a province of the Austro-Hungarian Empire lying to the north-east of the
          Kingdom of Hungary and bordering on Russia; it was governed from Vienna. After 1918,
          Lemberg was for a time an area of conflicting claims between Poland and the Ukraine, but
          became the third largest city in Poland. Absorbed into the Soviet Union after World War
          II, following the collapse of the Soviet Union it became part of the Ukraine.</p>

        <p>Lemberg was a multi-ethnic, multi-lingual community, primarily of Poles, Ruthenians, and
          Jews (27.7% of the population in 1900), of whom the Jews were expelled during the
          Holocaust, and the Poles were relocated by the Soviet Union after 1945.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Lemberg and Schenker</head>
        <p>Schenker was born in <ref cRef="entity-002333">Wisniowczyk</ref>, a village some 75 km
          (c. 47 miles) south-east of Lemberg, but attended the German-language Gymnasium [grammar
          school] in Lemberg, where he also studied piano with Chopin's pupil Karl Mikuli.</p>

        <p><ref cRef="entity-000878">Paula Szalit</ref>, briefly a pupil of Schenker in 1896–97, was
          born in 1885 and spent her early childhood in the town of Drohobycz, near Lemberg, and in
          1906 was appointed head of the advanced piano class at the Lemberg Conservatory. How long
          she remained in that position is unknown.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <head>Sources:</head>
      <div>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Wikipedia</title> ("L'viv"; "Galicia")</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Rozenblit, Marsha L.</author>, <title level="m">The Jews of Vienna,
              1867–1914</title> (Albany, NY: SUNY Press, 1983)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <listBibl>
          <head>Contributor</head>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>

  </text>
</TEI>
