<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-003102">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Tenants Harbor</title>
        <title type="sub">Maine, USA</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="tenants_harbor">Tenants Harbor</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>28/04/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Place</term>
          <term subtype="basename">tenants_harbor</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Tenants Harbor</head>
      <div>

        <p>One of several coastal villages making up the town of St. George, in Knox County, a
          peninsula in the southern part of the state of Maine, USA.</p>

        <p>Tenants Harbor, on the eastern side of the peninsula, looking out across islands to the
          Atlantic Ocean, is the commercial center of St George, an area in which fishing, canning,
          shipping, and formerly shipbuilding, were principal industries. From the 1880s onward it
          became increasingly a haven for artists and for summer visitors escaping the cities, and
          latterly for boating and water sports.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Tenants Harbor and Hans Weisse</head>
        <p><ref cRef="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</ref>, a pupil of Schenker's, emigrated with his
          family from Vienna to New York City in 1931, and from 1934 to at least 1938 (he died in
          1940) vacationed in the summers in a house in Tenants Harbor, which provided a refuge in
          which he could concentrate on his work as a composer. In his letter of June 2, 1934 (OC
          44/41), he gives a vivid description of the surroundings: <cit>
            <q>The Atlantic Ocean practically roars before our house, an old farmhouse. The coast is
              steep, comprising rocks that give the surf an unbelievably dramatic visual effect. But
              we also have, in places, beautiful sandy beaches, where the children will be able to
              enjoy themselves. The landscape is magnificent: meadows, forests ‒ inexpressible,
              indescribable beauty. And the air is spicy, like a farm high up in the Alps. It is an
              entirely unknown little place; our only neighbors are a few families with whom we have
              become friendly.</q>
          </cit></p>
      </div>

    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
