<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-002333">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Wisniowczyk</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="wisniowczyk">Wisniowczyk</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>20/10/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Place</term>
          <term subtype="basename">wisniowczyk</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Wisniowczyk</head>
      <div>

        <p>Village some 75 km (c. 47 miles) south-east of <ref cRef="entity-002401">Lemberg</ref> [L'viv)]
          in <ref cRef="entity-002355">Galicia</ref> (now in Western Ukraine).</p>
        </div>
        
        <div>
          <head>Wisniowczyk and the Schenker Family</head>
        <p>Schenker's parents lived in Wisniowcyk, where his father was a country doctor. Of
          their children, Markus and Rebekha (both of whom died young), Wilhelm, Schifre (Sophie),
          and Heinrich were born and brought up there, Moriz was born in Podhajce. Schenker
          described the family home thus:
        
        <cit><q>In our house there were many, many children, mainly boys. And whereas in
          other cases parents consider that, when there are a lot of girls, they should get them out
          of the house quickly, my parents were similarly exercised with the boys: off to their
          schools, and the sooner the better! Thus I was made out to be a year older than I really
          was, just so that I could advance to Lemberg. In this, the official records conspired with
          my parents' wishes. Similarly, later my parents made my sister out to be some ten years
          younger for purposes of marriage—in that, too, they succeeded! My father had
          originally married according to the Jewish rite; only much later were such marriages
          recognized also by the state. Later, when rectification was made, it was possible to
          adjust the official records to suit oneself. I know this because my parents told me so.
          (letter to Moriz Violin, OJ 6/7, [36], December 29, 1927)</q></cit></p>
        </div>
    </body>
    
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Source:</head>
        <listBibl>
            <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
            Tagebüchern und Briefe ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), p. 3</bibl>
</listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
