<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-002355">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Galicia</title>
        <title type="sub">[Ger.: Galizien]</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="galicia">Galicia</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>20/10/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Place</term>
          <term subtype="basename">galicia</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Galicia</head>
      <div>

        <p>Region of central Europe, annexed by Austria in 1772 in the first partition of Poland,
          and ruled directly from Vienna as part of the Austro-Hungarian Empire, heavily Germanized.
          Its principal cities were Lublin and Krakau to the west, Przemysl in the center, and
          Lemberg, Stanislau, and Ternopil to the east. From 1873 it was an autonomous province of
          the Austria-Hungary dual monarchy.</p>
        
        <p>During World War I, Galicia was heavily fought over by Russia and the Central Powers.
          Between 1918 and 1923, the region was in flux, the western part forming part of the
          Republic of Poland, the eastern part being claimed for Ukrainian independence, and briefly
          becoming a Soviet Socialist Republic in 1920 during the Polish–Soviet war. From
          1923 until 1939, the whole region belonged to Poland.</p>
        
        <p>Early in World War II, Galicia was split between Germany and Russia, but the German army
          occupied East Galicia in 1941, after which the Jewish population was largely annihiliated.
          Following the war, Galicia was split between Poland and Soviet Ukraine (since 1991 the
          independent Ukrainian state).</p>
        
        <p>Galicia was a multi-ethnic (primarily Poles, Ukrainians, Germans, and Jews),
          multi-lingual (predominantly German, Polish, Ruthenian, and Yiddish) society. Its Jewish
          population had long been subject to deprivations; and with the lifting of residential
          restrictions in 1848 large numbers began to migrate, many of them to Vienna (others to
          other European cities and the United States). Jews continued to migrate throughout the
          later 19th century, as impoverishment and anti-semitism steadily increased and they became
          subject to boycotts; in Vienna, most of them assimilated and acculturated into Germanic
          society as fully as possible, in many cases being baptized as Catholics or Protestants.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Galicia and Schenker</head>
        <p>Schenker's parents lived in Galicia, and brought up their children in part in Wisniowczyk
          (where Markus, Rebekha, Wilhelm, Schifre (Sophie), and Heinrich were born), in part in
          Podhajce (where Moriz was born). Heinrich Schenker attended primary school in Wisniowczyk
          and German Gymnasium (grammar school) in Lemberg [L'viv], later Brežany, then
          moved to Vienna in 1884 to study Law at Vienna University, remaining there for the rest of
          his life. With the death of his father in 1887, his mother migrated to Vienna, and was
          supported in part by him.</p>
        </div>
      </body>
        
      <back>
        <div>
          <head>Sources:</head>
      <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Wikipedia</title></bibl> 

        <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern und Briefen
            ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985)</bibl>
        <bibl><author>Rozenblatt, Marsha L.</author>, <title level="m">The Jews of Vienna 1867–1914</title> (Albany:
        SUNY Press, 1983)</bibl>
      </listBibl>
        </div>
      </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
