<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-002826">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Keilgasse</title>
        <title type="sub">Vienna</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="keilgasse">Keilgasse</term>
        </title>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Place</term>
          <term subtype="basename">keilgasse</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>23/05/2011</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Keilgasse</head>
      <div>

        <p>Since 1909, street in the 3rd district (Landstraße) of Vienna. </p>

        <p>The Keilgasse was formerly part of the Hohlweggasse. The name "Keilgasse" (literally
          "Wedge Street") was derived from the original shape of the street in the early 20th
          century. The street runs parallel with the <ref cRef="entity-00238">Fasangasse</ref> south
          of the latter's junction with the <ref cRef="entity-002336">Rennweg</ref> at the
          Fasanplatz. Only about 100 meters in length, it runs between the Gerlgasse and Hegergasse.
          The Botanical Garden of the University is located close by, on the opposite (west) side of
          the Fasangasse, and the <ref cRef="entity-002324">Aspang Bahnhof</ref> just north of the
          Keilgasse.</p>

        <p>In her diary for summer 1936, recording her journey to <ref cRef="entity-005845"
            >Chile</ref> and back, <ref cRef="entity-000771">Jeanette Schenker</ref> likens the
          sounds of her street in <ref cRef="entity-008467">Santiago</ref> to those of Keilgasse
          during the time that she and Heinrich lived there, 1921–35: “A cock crows morning and
          night, just as in the Keilgasse just before winter set in and people brought their
          chickens to the warmer city henhouses” (OJ 35/9, July 6).</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Keilgasse and Schenker</head>
        <p><figure>
            <head>1. Schenker's study-bedroom</head>
            <graphic url="B72F19_3.jpg" xmt:type="thumb-caption" rend="left-img" width="150px"
              height="113px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <graphic url="B72F19_3.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img" width="800px" height="600px"
              mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <figDesc>Photograph of Heinrich Schenker's study-bedroom in the Schenkers' apartment on
              Keilgasse</figDesc>
          </figure></p>
        <p>Heinrich and <ref cRef="entity-000771">Jeanette Schenker</ref> moved into Keilgasse 8 in
          May 1921 – their first home together since their marriage on November 10, 1919 – before
          which they had been living separately in the <ref cRef="entity-002277">Reisnerstraße</ref>
          and <ref cRef="entity-002257">Streichergasse</ref>, from which the Keilgasse was only a
          few minutes' walk – after an arduous fifteen-month search for accommodation. As he
          commented: <cit>
            <q>Now we are in our home. For the first time we can both betake ourselves to the same
              apartment, the same room, after so many years of being torn apart, a fulfillment which
              makes us all the happier because it has been so difficult to achieve. (diary, August
              31, 1921)</q>
          </cit></p>
        <p><figure>
            <head>2. Living room</head>
            <graphic url="B72F19_1.jpg" xmt:type="thumb-caption" rend="right-img" width="150px"
              height="113px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <graphic url="B72F19_1.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="right-img" width="800px"
              height="600px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <figDesc>Photograph of living room in the Schenkers' apartment on Keilgasse</figDesc>
          </figure></p>

        <p><figure>
            <head>3. Music room</head>
            <graphic url="B72F19_2.jpg" xmt:type="thumb-caption" rend="left-img" width="150px"
              height="113px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <graphic url="B72F19_2.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img" width="800px" height="600px"
              mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <figDesc>Photograph of music room in the Schenkers' apartment on Keilgasse</figDesc>
          </figure></p>

        <p>Their apartment was No. 12 (Tür 12), and they had procured the rental of it by May 7, and
          moved in about May 20. Heinrich described his room to <ref cRef="entity-000913">Moriz
            Violin</ref> in a letter of June 13, 1921 (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-6-7_1">OJ
            6/7, [1]</ref>), when it was still full of painters, cleaners, and electricians: <cit>
            <q>It [...] offers me all the conveniences I could possibly wish for. In my room there
              are no fewer than three desks, each for a specific purpose: one for the "Theory"
              volumes, another for the Beethoven edition, and the third <title level="j">Der
                Tonwille</title>. Lamps everywhere, and my own writing materials, so that all I have
              to do is summon the physical strength needed to bring this quantity of work to a
              conclusion.</q>
          </cit>
        </p>
        <p><figure>
            <head>4. Jeanette's bedroom</head>
            <graphic url="B72F19_4.jpg" xmt:type="thumb-caption" rend="right-img" width="150px"
              height="113px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <graphic url="B72F19_4.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="right-img" width="800px"
              height="600px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <figDesc>Photograph of Jeanette Schenker's bedroom in the Schenkers' apartment on
              Keilgasse</figDesc>
          </figure></p>

        <p>The diary for May and June 1921 provides much description of the apartment and its
          renovations. At the end of August, Schenker wrote: <cit>
            <q>our apartment fulfils all the requirements we could muster. It gives me and <ref
                cRef="entity-000771">Lie-Liechen</ref> the opportunity for work in comfort, for
              quietude, for pleasure; it has rooms and corners which, with the passing of time, will
              hopefully be carpeted with [our] blessings. (diary, August 31, 1921)</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>The couple lived there until Heinrich's death in January 1935. Thereafter, Jeanette seems
          to have remained only until November of the same year.</p>


      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Photographs</head>
        <p>Six photographs of the interior of the apartment (four of them taken by the Atelier
          Meroth, Rennweg 17) survive in the Oswald Jonas Memorial Collection as OJ 72/19, showing
          the living room, the music room, and Heinrich's study-bedroom.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Marko Deisinger</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Image rights</head>
        <list type="simple">
          <item>1. OJ 72/19, No. 3: used by permission of Special Collections &amp; Archives,
            University of California, Riverside, CA; original photographer: Atelier Meroth </item>

          <item>2. OJ 72/19, No. 1: used by permission of Special Collections &amp; Archives,
            University of California, Riverside, CA; original photographer: Atelier Meroth </item>

          <item>3. OJ 72/19, No. 2: used by permission of Special Collections &amp; Archives,
            University of California, Riverside, CA; original photographer: Atelier Meroth </item>

          <item>4. OJ 72/19, No. 4: used by permission of Special Collections &amp; Archives,
            University of California, Riverside, CA; original photographer: Atelier Meroth </item>

        </list>

      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
