<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-002873">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>New York City</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="new_york_city">New York City</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>21/01/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Place</term>
          <term subtype="basename">new_york_city</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>New York City</head>
      <div>

        <p>New York City has been the primary vehicle for the transmission of Heinrich Schenker's
          ideas into the United States from as early as c. 1925, initiated through the institutional
          and private teaching of, in particular, Hans Weisse, Felix Salzer, and Ernst Oster between
          1931 and the 1970s, and furthered through the issuing in English translation of the
          majority of Schenker's published and unpublished works by New York publishing houses,
          thereby disseminating Schenker's ideas to the broader English-speaking world.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Educational Institutions: to 1940</head>
        <p>Several institutions for the teaching of music at college level came into existence
          toward the end of the 19th century, including the New York College of Music (founded in
          1878, it absorbed the German Conservatory in 1920 and the American Conservatory in 1923),
          the National Conservatory of Music in America (1885, of which Dvořák was director 1892 to
          1895), and the Metropolitan Conservatory (1886).</p>

        <p>The Music Department of <ref cRef="entity-005886">Columbia University</ref> was founded
          in 1896. Further institutions were established in the early 20th century, most notably the
            <ref cRef="entity-002437">Institute of Musical Art</ref>, founded by Frank Damrosch in
          1905, and the <ref cRef="entity-002454">David Mannes Music School</ref>, founded by <ref
            cRef="entity-004633">David Mannes</ref> and his wife <ref cRef="entity-004634">Clara
            Damrosch</ref> in 1916. Also, the <ref cRef="entity-006977">Manhattan School of
            Music</ref> was founded in 1917. The Institute of Musical Art merged with the graduate
          music school of the Juilliard Music Foundation to form the Juilliard School of Music in
          1926. The New School for Social Research was founded in 1919, and in the 1920s broadened
          its curriculum to include subjects in the arts and humanities.</p>

        <p>It was in three of these newer institutions that the first signs of interest in the
          theories of Heinrich Schenker emerged. <ref cRef="entity-000939">George A. Wedge</ref> was
          a student at the <ref cRef="entity-002437">Institute of Musical Art</ref> before 1920, and
          later returned to teach there and serve as its dean. In 1925, the professional cellist
            <ref cRef="entity-000934">Gerald F. Warburg</ref> reported that Wedge was "lecturing on
          the Urlinie" and pioneering Schenker's theory. In the 1920s, Warburg, while in Vienna, had
          himself been a pupil of <ref cRef="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</ref>, and it is he who may
          have drawn the attention of <ref cRef="entity-004633">David Mannes</ref> and <ref
            cRef="entity-004634">Clara Damrosch</ref> to Weisse's work; at any event, Weisse taught
          at the <ref cRef="entity-002454">David Mannes Music School</ref> from the Fall of 1931 to
          his death in 1940, giving courses in music theory and composition influenced by Schenker's
          ideas. From 1932 to 1940, Weisse also gave courses and graduate seminars at <ref
            cRef="entity-005886">Columbia University</ref> in which he introduced significant
          numbers of people ("musicians, teachers, even concert artists") to Schenker's ideas. Among
          those whom Weisse influenced at those two institutions were <ref cRef="entity-000927"
            >Arthur Waldeck</ref> (who corresponded directly with Schenker in 1929‒34), <ref
            cRef="entity-000131">Israel Citkowitz</ref>, <ref cRef="entity-006978">Arthur
            Berger</ref>, <ref cRef="entity-006967">Adele T. Katz</ref>, <ref cRef="entity-006979"
            >Ruth Halle Rowen</ref>, and <ref cRef="entity-006980">William J. Mitchell</ref>,
          several of whom subsequently disseminated Schenker's ideas.</p>

        <p><ref cRef="entity-006967">Adele T. Katz</ref> taught courses on Wagner's music dramas at
          the New School for Social Research in 1932‒34 into which she may have introduced
          Schenkerian elements. She also taught a wide range of courses at the Rand School of Social
          Science between 1931 and 1940, the titles of some of which suggest that she adopted a
          Schenkerian perspective. She also taught at the Young Men's Hebrew Association and gave
          lectures at a number of other educational institutions and clubs in the 1930s through
          which she most likely propagated Schenker's ideas to a broader audience.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Educational Institutions: after 1940</head>
        <p>It was <ref cRef="entity-006967">Adele T. Katz</ref> who authored the first
          English-language book devoted to Schenker's theory and analytical method: <title level="m"
            >Challenge to Musical Tradition</title>, published in 1945, which both reflected her
          studies with <ref cRef="entity-000951">Weisse</ref> and arose out of her teaching in the
          1930s, and which had wide influence throughout the English-speaking world. She was
          appointed an instructor at <ref cRef="entity-005886">Columbia University</ref>'s Teachers
          College 1946‒51, where she explicitly taught "the Schenker approach" to analysis; and at
          the Studios of Music Education 1947‒69, where again her teaching was imbued with
          Schenker's ideas.</p>

        <p><ref cRef="entity-006980">William J. Mitchell</ref> (1906‒71) studied at the <ref
            cRef="entity-002437">Institute of Musical Art</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-005886"
            >Columbia University</ref>. After two years in Vienna during which he studied with <ref
            cRef="entity-000951">Weisse</ref> he returned to Columbia's Music Department, teaching
          there from 1932 to 1968 (latterly as chairman), using the Schenkerian approach in his
          theory and analysis courses, and concurrently lectured at <ref cRef="entity-002454"
            >Mannes</ref> (by then Mannes College) between 1957 and 1968. His <title level="m"
            >Elementary Harmony</title> (1939) was the first American textbook to draw explicitly on
          Schenker's ideas. He was founding co-editor with <ref cRef="entity-000754">Felix
            Salzer</ref> in 1967 of <ref cRef="entity-006981"><title level="j">The Music
              Forum</title></ref>, an occasional hardcover periodical published by Columbia
          University Press to which Schenker's "ideas, teachings, and theories" were central, and to
          which Mitchell contributed several major articles.</p>

        <p>Born in Vienna, <ref cRef="entity-000754">Felix Salzer</ref> (1904‒86) had been a pupil
          of <ref cRef="entity-000951">Weisse</ref> in the 1920s and after Weisse's emigration a
          member of Schenker's "<ref cRef="entity-002499">Friday seminar</ref>" from 1931 to 1934
          (the seminar the work of which resulted in the publication by the <ref
            cRef="entity-002454">David Mannes Music School</ref> of <ref cRef="entity-001755"><title
              level="m">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln / Five Analyses in Sketchform</title></ref> in 1932),
          and briefly a private Schenker pupil. He had received a doctorate in musicology from the
          University of Vienna in 1926 under the direction of <ref cRef="entity-000003">Guido
            Adler</ref>, and had in 1936 purchased part of Schenker's posthumous papers from the
          theorist's widow (ultimately bequeathed to the New York Public Library among the Felix
          Salzer Papers). He emigrated to the United States in 1939 and spent the remainder of his
          life in New York City. Salzer succeeded Weisse at Mannes in 1940 and taught there until
          1956, serving as Executive Director 1948 to 1955. During that time he established the
          "Techniques of Music" curriculum, based on Schenker's approach, for which Mannes became
          celebrated; and taught there again part-time from 1962 to 1981.</p>

        <p><ref cRef="entity-000754">Salzer</ref> published a book in English in 1952 that was to
          have an enormous impact not only throughout America but also in other English-speaking
          countries around the world. <title level="m">Structural Hearing: Tonal Coherence in
            Music</title>, which grew out of his teaching at <ref cRef="entity-002454">Mannes</ref>,
          presented a systematic and pedagogical approach to Schenker's theory and analytical method
          while eschewing its political and social components and polemical style. Salzer
          established English equivalents for Schenker's technical vocabulary and devised some new
          terminology (perhaps in part derived from <ref cRef="entity-000951">Weisse</ref> and <ref
            cRef="entity-006967">Adele T. Katz</ref>). Extending the repertory to which he deemed
          Schenkerian theory applicable, he included music of the middle ages and renaissance, as
          well as 20th-century music.</p>

        <p><ref cRef="entity-000649">Ernst Oster</ref> (1908‒77), born in Mannheim and educated in
          Hamburg, after studies with <ref cRef="entity-000412">Oswald Jonas</ref> in Berlin in the
          1930s moved to Vienna in 1935, where in 1938 Schenker's widow entrusted him with a large
          part of the theorist's papers (correspondence, unpublished sketches and draft materials,
          etc., eventually bequeathed to the New York Public Library as The Oster Collection). Oster
          emigrated to the United States in 1939, where he taught privately in New York. In the late
          1960s he taught briefly at Princeton University and began teaching at the New England
          Conservatory and, in the mid-1970s, at <ref cRef="entity-002454">Mannes</ref>. His pupils
          included Peter Serkin, Edward Laufer, <ref cRef="entity-006986">William Rothstein</ref>,
          and David Beach. Oster was angered by <ref cRef="entity-000754">Salzer</ref>'s <title
            level="m">Structural Hearing</title>, in part because he did not believe Schenker's
          approach should be applied to works outside the 18th‒19th-century canon. He advocated
          advancing Schenker’s cause by presenting his published works in well-informed
          translations, and contributed to this process by translating Schenker's final work, <ref
            cRef="entity-001728"><title level="m">Der freie Satz</title></ref>, published in 1979 as
            <title level="m">Free Composition</title>.</p>

        <p>Of the campuses of the City University of New York, that of <ref cRef="entity-006982"
            >Queens College</ref>, which established its music department in 1937, had the greatest
          impact on the spread of Schenker's ideas. New York-born <ref cRef="entity-006983">Saul
            Novack</ref> (1918‒98) taught there from 1952, was its chair 1961‒66, and Dean of Arts
          and Humanities 1978‒82, and was instrumental in the department's transformation to the
          Aaron Copland School of Music in 1982. The department's music theory curriculum
          incorporated Schenker's theory, and the School became a center for Schenkerian study and
          research with scholars such as Novack, <ref cRef="entity-000754">Felix Salzer</ref>, <ref
            cRef="entity-006984">Carl Schachter</ref>, <ref cRef="entity-006985">Charles
            Burkhart</ref>, and <ref cRef="entity-006986">William Rothstein</ref> on its faculty and
          also on that of the <ref cRef="entity-006987">CUNY Graduate Center</ref>, founded in the
          1960s. </p>

        <p>In the later 1930s, the New School for Social Research became a haven for Jewish German
          and Austrian scholars escaping the Nazi regime. One of these was <ref cRef="entity-000989"
            >Viktor Zuckerkandl</ref>, a Schenker correspondent, and pupil in 1914/15, who taught at
          the New School 1946‒48 before moving to St. John's College, Annapolis. His teaching, as
          evidenced in his publications, was imbued with Schenker's ideas and graphing methods.
          Other students and members of Schenker's circle who emigrated to New York include the
          conductors <ref cRef="entity-000034">Carl Bamberger</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-006147"
            >Paul Berl</ref>, who both taught at <ref cRef="entity-002454">Mannes</ref>, as did the
          clarinettist <ref cRef="entity-006148">Erich Simon</ref>. Also active in New York were
            <ref cRef="entity-000098">Paul Breisach</ref> (Schenker pupil 1913‒19), who conducted at
          the Metropolitan Opera House, and <ref cRef="entity-000473">Trude Kral</ref> (a member of
          Schenker's "<ref cRef="entity-002499">Friday seminar</ref>" in 1931/32), who was on the
          piano faculty of the Third Street Music School.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Publishers</head>
        <p>The role of New York's publishing houses in the dissemination of Schenker's ideas to the
          English-speaking world cannot be overstated. The New York publishing scene around 1930 was
          dominated by companies such as Simon and Schuster, Random House, Alfred A. Knopf, and the
          Viking Press, but there was a host of small, independent publishers as well.</p>

        <p>Publication of the first work by Schenker was undertaken by the <ref cRef="entity-002454"
            >David Mannes Music School</ref> itself: <ref cRef="entity-001755"><title level="m">Fünf
              Urlinie-Tafeln / Five Analyses in Sketchform</title></ref> (1932). The School
          published this in conjunction with <ref cRef="entity-002408">Universal Edition</ref> of
          Vienna. Every graph bears the imprint "Autographie Gg. Tomay Wien I" ‒ <ref
            cRef="entity-000894">Georg Tomay</ref>, the draftsman who had executed the graphs for
          Schenker's study of the "Eroica" Symphony in 1930. Universal Edition saw to the printing,
          and supplied Mannes with 80% of copies, retaining 20% for sales in Europe, an arrangement
          made possible by use of parallel, dual-language text for the one-page foreword and
          title-page, the graphs being solely in German.</p>

        <p>The first fully English-language book on Schenker's theories, <ref cRef="entity-006967"
            >Adele T. Katz</ref>'s <title level="m">Challenge to Musical Tradition</title> (1945),
          with over 400 pages and numerous music examples, was fortunate in being taken up by one of
          the major houses, Alfred A. Knopf. By contrast, the second, <ref cRef="entity-000754"
            >Felix Salzer</ref>'s <title level="m">Structural Hearing</title> (one volume of text,
          one of music examples) was issued by the small publishing house of Charles Boni in 1952.
          Boni had started in 1913 as a leftist bookshop in Greenwich Village frequented by writers
          and intellectuals, and launched a small publishing house, Albert &amp; Charles Boni, in
          1923, issuing modernist literary works (such as Upton Sinclair and Thornton Wilder). This
          eventually foundered in the Depression, but Charles Boni started publishing again after
          World War II.</p>

        <p>Columbia University Press embarked on <ref cRef="entity-006981"><title level="m">The
              Music Forum</title></ref> in 1967. The series, while not exclusively Schenkerian in
          content, served as a laboratory for Schenkerian ideas. It offered analyses of works in the
          traditional and non-traditional Schenkerian repertory, and studies of autograph sources
          and performance issues. It was the platform for translations of two analyses from
          Schenker's <ref cRef="entity-001749"><title level="j">Das Meisterwerk</title></ref>, and
          of two Schenker monographs: <ref cRef="entity-001721"><title level="m">Ein Beitrag zur
              Ornamentik</title></ref> (1903, rev. 1908) by <ref cRef="entity-006988">Hedi
            Siegel</ref> as <title level="m">A Contribution to the Study of Ornamentation</title> in
          1976, and <ref cRef="entity-003331"><title level="m">Oktaven u. Quinten u.
            A.</title></ref> (1933) by Paul Mast in 1980.</p>

        <p>Dover Publications Inc. of West Soho was founded in 1941 to reissue works no longer
          marketed by their initial publishers. In 1969, by which time it had a motley list of music
          titles and scores as well of long-playing records, the firm reissued <ref
            cRef="entity-001755"><title level="m">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln</title></ref> as <title
            level="m">Five Graphic Music Analyses</title>, omitting the German foreword, adding an
          introduction by <ref cRef="entity-000754">Salzer</ref> and a glossary of German terms,
          while leaving <ref cRef="entity-000894">Tomay</ref>'s graphs unchanged save for occasional
          bracketed translations and anglicized titles. It had reissued the two volumes of Salzer’s
            <title level="m">Structural Hearing</title> in 1962 (consolidated into one volume in
          1982). In 1975 the firm reissued Schenker's <ref cRef="entity-001753"><title>edition of
              Beethoven's Piano Sonatas</title></ref> (1921‒23), edited by <ref cRef="entity-006984"
            >Carl Schachter</ref>, and in 2016 it rescued from permanent out-of-print status the
          English translation by <ref cRef="entity-006989">William Drabkin</ref> and others of the
          three-volume <ref cRef="entity-001749"><title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der
              Musik</title></ref> (1925‒30), published in England by Cambridge University Press in
          1994‒97.</p>

        <p>It was the small house of Longman of West 44th Street that in 1979 undertook publishing
            <ref cRef="entity-000649">Oster</ref>'s translation of <ref cRef="entity-001728"><title
              level="m">Der freie Satz</title></ref> as <title level="m">Free Composition</title>
          (after rejection by several other publishers), issuing it in two hard-back volumes with
          slipcase. This edition, part of the Longman Music Series edited by Gerald Warfield,
          re-established many of the passages omitted by <ref cRef="entity-000412">Oswald
            Jonas</ref> in his 1956 second German edition of the work. (This translation was
          reprinted in 2001 by Pendragon of Hillsdale, in upstate New York.) Three years later,
          Longman issued <ref cRef="entity-006990">John Rothgeb</ref>'s English translation of <ref
            cRef="entity-000412">Jonas</ref>'s 1934 <title level="m">Das Wesen des musikalischen
            Kunstwerks</title> (2nd edn. 1972) as <title level="m">Introduction to the Theory of
            Heinrich Schenker</title>. (A further edition of this translation was issued by
          Musicalia Press of Ann Arbor, Michigan, in 2005.) In 1984 Longman published Schenker's
          critical edition of <ref cRef="entity-000027">J. S. Bach</ref>'s <ref cRef="entity-001730"
              ><title level="m">Chromatic Fantasy and Fugue</title></ref> in a translation by <ref
            cRef="entity-006988">Hedi Siegel</ref>.</p>

        <p>In 1987 Schirmer Books of New York, part of Macmillan, Inc., took on the two volumes of
          Schenker's <ref cRef="entity-001725"><title level="m">Kontrapunkt</title></ref> (1910,
          1922) translated by <ref cRef="entity-006990">John Rothgeb</ref> and Jürgen Thym as <title
            level="m">Counterpoint</title>.</p>

        <p>Oxford University Press's New York music division published Schenker's unfinished and
          fragmentary work <ref cRef="entity-001757"><title level="m">Die Kunst des
            Vortrags</title></ref> (1911‒30), edited by Heribert Esser and translated by Irene
          Schreier Scott as <title level="m">The Art of Performance</title>, in 2000, followed by
          the ten issues of <ref cRef="entity-001739"><title level="j">Der Tonwille</title></ref>
          (1921‒24) in translation by <ref cRef="entity-006989">William Drabkin</ref> and others in
          two volumes in 2004‒05; and the four volumes of <ref cRef="entity-001733"><title level="m"
              >Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven</title></ref> (1913‒20), also known as the
            <title level="m">Erläuterungsausgabe</title>, translated by <ref cRef="entity-006990"
            >John Rothgeb</ref> as <title level="m">Beethoven's Last Piano Sonatas</title> in four
          slim volumes with associated website in 2015.</p>

        <p>The only translations of autonomous publications by Schenker to be released by a
          publisher outside New York City were his <ref cRef="entity-001724"><title level="m"
              >Harmonielehre</title></ref> (1906), abridged and edited by <ref cRef="entity-000412"
            >Oswald Jonas</ref> and translated by Elisabeth Mann Borgese as <title level="m"
            >Harmony</title>, by Chicago University Press in 1954; his <ref cRef="entity-001731"
              ><title level="m">Beethovens neunte Sinfonie</title></ref> (1912) by <ref
            cRef="entity-006990">John Rothgeb</ref> as <title level="m">Beethoven's Ninth
            Symphony</title>, by Yale University Press in 1992; and his <ref cRef="entity-001749"
              ><title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</title></ref>, first issued in 1994‒97
          by Cambridge University Press, as referred to above.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Symposia</head>
        <p>In commemoration of the fiftieth anniversary of Schenker’s death, <ref
            cRef="entity-002454">Mannes</ref> hosted the first International Schenker Symposium in
          March of 1985 (see below, <title level="m">Schenker Studies</title>). At seven-year
          intervals, symposia were subsequently held at Mannes in March 1992 (see <title level="m"
            >Schenker Studies 2</title>), March 1999 (see <title level="m">Essays from the Third
            International Schenker Symposium</title>), March 2006 (see <title level="m">Essays from
            the Fourth International Schenker Symposium</title>, vols. I and II), and March 2013
          (see <title level="m">Essays from the Fifth International Schenker Symposium</title>,
          parts I and II, and <title level="j">Music Analysis</title>, Special Issue on Schenker
          Documents). The symposia were three-day events; scholars from Australia, Austria, Canada,
          Finland, France, Germany, Israel, Italy, the Netherlands, the United Kingdom, and the
          United States presented papers and participated in panel discussions. Topics covered a
          broad range of analytical, theoretical, and historical subjects. A memorable discussion,
            <ref cRef="entity-006991">Milton Babbitt</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-006992">Allen
            Forte</ref> in conversation with Joseph N. Straus, took place at the 2006 Symposium.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Music Societies</head>

        <p>The Music Theory Society of New York State (MTSNYS), founded in 1971, several years
          before the establishment of the national Society for Music Theory (SMT), has held about
          half of its annual meetings in the New York City area. Schenkerian theorists from the city
          have played an active role in the society, serving as officers and as editors of the
          Society's journal <title level="j">Theory and Practice</title>, reading papers at the
          annual meetings (<ref cRef="entity-000649">Ernst Oster</ref> gave a talk, <title level="a"
            >Words and Music in Schubert Lieder,</title> in 1975), and contributing to the journal.
          The early issues of <title level="j">Theory and Practice</title> were produced in New York
          City, from 1981 to 1990 in affiliation with the Ph.D. program in music at CUNY. A large
          proportion of the articles published in the journal have a Schenkerian focus.</p>

        <p>From 1962 to 1964 <ref cRef="entity-000754">Felix Salzer</ref> served as chairman of the
          Greater New York Chapter of the American Musicological Society (AMSGNC), founded in 1935,
          a year after the founding of the national AMS. Among the papers presented during Salzer's
          tenure was one read by <ref cRef="entity-006980">William J. Mitchell</ref>, <title
            level="a">Chord and Context in 18th-Century Theory</title> (published 1963 in the <title
            level="j">Journal of the American Musicological Society</title> 16/2), in which
          Schenkerian graphs demonstrated the application of thorough-bass theory to 20th-century
          examples. (Mitchell was a very active AMS member, serving as president from 1965 to 1966.)
          At the annual meeting of the AMS held in New York in 1949, Salzer had presented an
          important paper: <title level="a">Directed Motion: The Basic Factor of Musical
            Coherence,</title> which prefigured some of the ideas of <title level="m">Structural
            Hearing</title>. New York continued to be a venue for meetings of the national
          societies. A joint meeting of the AMS and SMT held in New York in 1995 included a keynote
          address, <title level="a">Reflections on Schenker,</title> by Charles Burkhart and a
          special session on Schenkerian approaches to rhythm featuring Frank Samarotto, Channan
          Willner, William Rothstein, and Carl Schachter.</p>
      </div>

    </body>



    <back>
      <div>
        <head>BIBLIOGRAPHY</head>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>History</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Babbitt, Milton</author>, <title level="a">My Vienna Triangle in Washington
              Square,</title> in <title level="m">Driven into Paradise: The Musical Migration from
              Nazi Germany to the United States</title>, ed. <editor>Reinhold Brinkmann</editor> and
              <editor>Christoph Wolff</editor> (Berkeley &amp; Los Angeles: University of California
            Press, 1999), pp. 33‒53; repr. <title level="m">The Collected Essays of Milton
              Babbitt</title>, ed. <editor>Stephen Peles</editor> et al (Princeton: Princeton
            University Press, 2003), pp. 467‒87</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Berry, David Carson</author>, <title level="a">The Role of Adele T. Katz in
              the Early Expansion of the New York 'Schenker School,'</title>
            <title level="j">Current Musicology</title> 74 (2002), 103‒51</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Berry, David Carson</author>, <title level="a">Hans Weisse and the Dawn of
              American Schenkerism,</title>
            <title level="j">Journal of Musicology</title> 20/1 (2003), 104‒56</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Berry, David Carson</author>, <title level="a">Schenkerian Theory in the
              United States: A Review of its Establishment and a Survey of Current Research
              Topics,</title>
            <title level="j">Zeitschrift der Gesellschaft für Musiktheorie</title>, 2/2‒3 (2005),
            101‒37</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Berry, David Carson</author>, <title level="a">Schenker's First
              'Americanization': George Wedge, the Institute of Musical Art, and the 'Appreciation
              Racket,'</title>
            <title level="a">Festschrift for Allen Forte, Part 3</title>, <title level="j"
              >Gamut</title> 4/1 (2011) <ref type="external"
              target="https://trace.tennessee.edu/gamut/vol4/iss1/7"
              >https://trace.tennessee.edu/gamut/vol4/iss1/7</ref></bibl>

          <bibl><author>Forte, Allen</author>, <title level="a">Schenkerians and Schoenbergians in
              America,</title>
            <title level="m">Schenker-Traditionen: eine Wiener Schule der Musiktheorie und ihre
              internationale Verbreitung</title>, ed. <editor>Martin Eybl</editor> &amp;
              <editor>Evelyn Fink-Mennel</editor> (Vienna: Böhlau Verlag, 2006), 83‒88</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Berry, David Carson</author>, <title level="a">Hans Weisse
              (1892‒1940),</title>
            <title level="m">Schenker-Traditionen</title>, pp. 91‒103</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Schachter, Carl</author>, <title level="a">Felix Salzer (1904‒1986),</title>
            <title level="m">Schenker-Traditionen</title>, pp. 105‒11</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Rothgeb, John</author>, <title level="a">Oswald Jonas (1897‒1978),</title>
            <title level="m">Schenker-Traditionen</title>, pp. 113‒20</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Rothstein, William</author>, <title level="a">Ernst Oster
              (1908‒1977),</title>
            <title level="m">Schenker-Traditionen</title>, pp. 121‒35</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Suppan, Wolfgang</author>, <title level="a">Viktor Zuckerkandl
              (1896‒1965),</title>
            <title level="m">Schenker-Traditionen</title>, pp. 137‒48</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Grünzweig, Werner</author>, <title level="a">Vom 'Schenkerismus' zum
              'Dahlhaus-Projekt': Einflüsse deutschprachiger Musiker und Musikwissenschaftler in den
              Vereinigten Staaten—Anfänge und Ausblick,</title>
            <title level="j">Österreichische Musik Zeitschrift</title> 3‒4 (1993), 161‒70</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Koslovsky, John</author>, <title level="m">From Sinn und Wesen to Structural
              Hearing: The Development of Felix Salzer's Ideas in Interwar Vienna and their
              Transmission in Postwar United States</title> (PhD dissertation, Eastman School of
            Music, 2009)</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Rothstein, William</author>, <title level="a">The Americanization of
              Heinrich Schenker,</title> in <title level="m">Schenker Studies</title>, ed.
              <editor>Hedi Siegel</editor> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1990), pp.
            193‒203</bibl>

          <bibl><title level="a">New York,</title>
            <title level="m">The New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians</title>, (1980)
              (<author>Irving Kolodin</author>, <author>Francis D. Perkins</author>, <author>Susan
              Thiemann Sommer</author>)</bibl>
        </listBibl>

      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Early Primary Sources</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>1931: <author>Lytle, Victor Vaughn</author>, <title level="a">Music Composition of
              the Present: An Analysis of the Trend of Composition based on the Proved Achievement
              of the Greatest Masters of Past Centuries,</title>
            <title level="j">The American Organist</title> 14/11 (Nov. 1931), 661‒66 <note
              type="editorial" place="inline">uses Schenkerian terms and graphing</note></bibl>

          <bibl>1932: <author>Kolodin, Irving</author>, <title level="a">Music,</title>
            <title level="j">Arts Weekly</title> 1, 51</bibl>

          <bibl>1932: <author>Schenker, Heinrich</author>, <title level="m">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln /
              Five Analyses in Sketchform</title> (New York: David Mannes School)</bibl>

          <bibl>1933: <author>Citkowitz, Israel</author>, <title level="a">The Role of Heinrich
              Schenker,</title>
            <title level="j">Modern Music</title> 11/1, 18‒23; repr. <title level="j">Theory and
              Practice</title> 10/1‒2 (1985), 15‒22</bibl>

          <bibl>1935: <author>Katz, Adele T.</author>, <title level="a">Heinrich Schenker's Method
              of Analysis,</title>
            <title level="j">Musical Quarterly</title> 21/3, 311‒29; repr. <title level="j">Theory
              and Practice</title> 10/1‒2 (1985),75‒95</bibl>

          <bibl>1935: <author>Waldeck, Arthur</author> and <author>Nathan Broder</author>, <title
              level="a">Musical Synthesis as Expounded by Heinrich Schenker,</title>
            <title level="j">Musical Mercury</title> 2/4, 56‒64; repr. <title level="j">Theory and
              Practice</title> 10/1‒2 (1985), 63‒73</bibl>

          <bibl>1936: <author>Katz, Adele T.</author>, <title level="a">Analysis or
              Synthesis?,</title>
            <title level="j">Musical Review</title>, 3‒5</bibl>

          <bibl>1936: <author>Weisse, Hans</author>, <title level="a">The Music Teacher's
              Dilemma,</title>
            <title level="j">Proceedings of the Music Teachers National Association</title>, 122‒37;
            repr. <title level="j">Theory and Practice</title> 10/1‒2 (1985), 25‒48</bibl>

          <bibl>1939: <author>Mitchell, William J.</author>, <title level="m">Elementary
              Harmony</title> (New York: Prentice-Hall)</bibl>

          <bibl>1945: <author>Katz, Adele T.</author>, <title level="m">Challenge to Musical
              Tradition: A New Concept of Tonality</title> (New York: Knopf)</bibl>

          <bibl>1946: <author>Mitchell, William J.</author>, <title level="a">Heinrich Schenker's
              Approach to Detail,</title>
            <title level="j">Musicology</title> 1/2, 117‒28; repr. <title level="j">Theory and
              Practice</title> 10/1‒2 (1985), 51‒62</bibl>

          <bibl>1952: <author>Salzer, Felix</author>, <title level="m">Structural Hearing: Tonal
              Coherence in Music</title> (New York: Charles Boni), 2 vols</bibl>

          <bibl>1959: <author>Katz, Adele T.</author> and <author>Ruth Halle Rowen</author>, <title
              level="m">Hearing—Gateway to Music</title> (Evanston, IL: Summy-Birchard)</bibl>

          <bibl>1959: <author>Zuckerkandl, Victor</author>, <title level="m">The Sense of
              Music</title> (Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press)</bibl>

          <bibl>1960: <author>Oster, Ernst</author>, <title level="a">Re: A New Concept of Tonality
              (?),</title>
            <title level="j">Journal of Music Theory</title>, vi/1, 85‒98 <note type="editorial"
              place="inline">responding to an article by Roy Travis of the previous
            year</note></bibl>

          <bibl>1969: <author>Salzer, Felix</author> and <author>Carl Schachter</author>, <title
              level="m">Counterpoint in Composition: The Study of Voice Leading</title> (New York:
            McGraw-Hill)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Symposium Publications</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>[1985] <title level="m">Schenker Studies</title>
            <note type="editorial" place="inline">Essays from the First International Schenker
              Symposium</note>, ed. <editor>Hedi Siegel</editor> (Cambridge: Cambridge University
            Press, 1990)</bibl>

          <bibl>[1992] <title level="m">Schenker Studies 2</title>
            <note type="editorial" place="inline">Essays from the Second International Schenker
              Symposium</note>, ed. <editor>Carl Schachter</editor> and <editor>Hedi Siegel</editor>
            (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1999)</bibl>

          <bibl>[1999] <title level="m">Essays from the Third International Schenker
              Symposium</title>, ed. <editor>Allen Cadwallader</editor> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms,
            2006)</bibl>

          <bibl>[2006] <title level="m">Essays from the Fourth International Schenker
              Symposium</title>, vol. 1, ed. <editor>Allen Cadwallader</editor>; vol. 2, ed.
              <editor>L. Poundie Burstein</editor>, <editor>Lynne Rogers</editor>, and <editor>Karen
              Bottge</editor> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 2008, 2013)</bibl>

          <bibl>[2013] <title level="m">Essays from the Fifth International Schenker
              Symposium</title>, ed. <editor>William M. Marvin</editor>, Part I, <title level="j"
              >Gamut</title> 7/1 (2014), <ref type="external"
              target="https://trace.tennessee.edu/gamut/vol7/iss1"
              >https://trace.tennessee.edu/gamut/vol7/iss1</ref>; Part II, <title level="j"
              >Gamut</title> 8/1 (2018), <ref type="external"
              target="https://trace.tennessee.edu/gamut/vol8/iss1"
              >https://trace.tennessee.edu/gamut/vol8/iss1</ref>; and <title level="j">Music
              Analysis</title> 34/2 (July 2015), <title level="a">Special Issue on Schenker
              Documents</title></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Collections of Schenker Papers</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">The Oster Collection: Papers of Heinrich Schenker: A Finding
              List</title>, comp. <editor>Robert Kosovsky</editor> (Music Division, The New York
            Public Library, 1990) <ref type="external" target="http://archives.nypl.org/mus/20057"
              >http://archives.nypl.org/mus/20057</ref></bibl>

          <bibl><title level="m">The Felix Salzer Papers</title>, comp. <editor>John
              Koslovsky</editor> (Music Division, The New York Public Library) <ref type="external"
              target="http://archives.nypl.org/mus/20415"
            >http://archives.nypl.org/mus/20415</ref></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>





      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author>, with assistance from <author><hi
                rend="bold">Hedi Siegel</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <lb/>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
