<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 13/27, [1] : 3-18-01 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  In the public domain.
©  Transcription  Kevin Karnes, 2006.
© Translation Kevin Karnes, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Kevin Karnes 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1901-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image:  University of California, Riverside;  Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Kevin Karnes.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 03/18/1901 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: &quot;R&#195;&#182;ntgen ~ HSchenker&quot; --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Röntgen to Schenker, dated March 18, 1901</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-11-15</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Acks NMI C 140 02, March 15, 1901;  agrees in principle to contribute to the Austrian collected edition to be published by Weinberger, but first asks questions about editorial policy; suggests some works he would be interested to edit.  — Apologizes for poor communication during his last visit to Vienna, and reports on Messchaert's health.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Röntgen, Julius; Schenker, Heinrich;  Weinberger, Josef;  collected edition;  fingering;  phrasing;  Cotta, J. G.;  Mozart;  Bach, J. S.;  Bülow, Hans von;  arrangement;  joke;  Messchaert, Johannes;  influenza;  Bach Festival;  Berlin;  Posa, Oscar</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Amsterdam</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Röntgen to Schenker, dated March 18, 1901</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Amsterdam, 18 März 1901.</tei:p><tei:p>Verehrtester Herr Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>Herzlichsten Dank zuerst für Ihren Brief<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  NMI C 140 02, March 15, 1901.  My thanks to Lee Rothfarb and Maximilian Aue for their help with a number of passages in this letter.</tei:note> und Ihre so freundlichen Gesinnungen, die ich sehr hochschätze!</tei:p><tei:p>Es wird mir eine Freude sein, etwas zu dem großen Unternehmen, von dem Sie mir schreiben, beizutragen. Im Princip sage ich also gerne: ja, möchte aber meine endgültige Entscheidung davon abhängen laßen, in welcher Art die Herausgabe gewünscht wird.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Daß nicht nur eine kritische Wiedergabe des Urtextes beabsichtigt ist, sehe ich schon aus Ihren Bemerkungen.  Wird die Ausgabe um nach allgemeinen Principien veranstalten oder bleibt jedem der verschieden[e]n[?] Herausgeber sein individueller Weg überlaßen?</tei:p><tei:p>Handelt es sich z. B. nur um eine Bezeichnung von Fingersatz, Phrasirung u. s. w. oder muß es eine +instruktive+ Ausgabe in der Art der Cottaischen sein.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  The firm of J. G. Cotta’sche Buchhandlung Nachfolger published a series, “Instruktive Ausgabe klassischer Klavierwerke,” the team of co-editors being listed as “Hans von Bülow, Imanuel von Faisst, Ignaz Lachner, Franz von Liszt.”  In 12 divisions, it included works by J. S. Bach (edited by Eugen d’Albert), Beethoven, Chopin, Clementi, Dussek, Field, Haydn, Hummel, Mendelssohn, Mozart, Schubert, and Weber.  (Information from the end-matter of Schenker’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (Stuttgart: Cotta, 1906, but in a later impression because it has the author’s name on the title-page)).  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Eine Arbeit in letzterem Sinne würde ich nicht gern übernehmen.  Eine andere Frage: soll die Ausgabe eine vollständige sein, d. h. alle <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Werke eines Componisten bringen oder könnte man sich auf eine Auswahl beschränken? z. B. einige der Mozartschen Claviersachen (außer den Sonaten), die Phantasien, Rondo amoll, Adagio hmoll und noch einige der kleineren, weniger bekannten Stücke?  Das schiene mir praktischer, als die ganze Maße zu bringen, in der doch Vieles nur historisches Intereße hat. Eine Auswahl Mozart’scher Clavierwerke würde mir eine lockende Aufgabe sein! Dann hatte ich gedacht an die 6 Bach’schen Clavier u. Violinsonaten, die nur in sehr unbrauchbaren populären Ausgaben erschienen sind. Die 6^t.^ Sonata ist <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> überhaupt noch nicht in der älteren Bearbeitung – die zwei wundervolle Adagios enthält – erschienen (nur in der großen Bach-Ausgabe).<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Missing period in original.  Referred to is <tei:hi rend="italic">J. S. Bach: Werke</tei:hi>, ed. Bach-Gesellschaft, 47 vols (Leipzig, 1851–99).</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ich wäre Ihnen sehr dankbar, wenn Sie mir also noch etwas Näheres über die Künstlerische[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] Operations-Basis des ganzen Unternehmens mittheilen wollten!</tei:p><tei:p>Zum Spaß schicke ich Ihnen einen Scherz mit, den ich mir vor Jahren mit Bülow geleistet habe.  Es ist die “Bearbeitung” eines Clavierstücks von mir für eine Bülowbegeisterte Schülerin, die sehr stark im “Nichttreffen” war.</tei:p><tei:p>Sie sehen daran, was Sie von mir als “Bearbeiter” zu fürchten haben!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> Gelegentlich schicken Sie mir das Ding wohl zurück, am Liebsten recht bald mit den Inventionen, auf die ich sehr gespannt bin!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich bedaure noch, daß ich bei meinem letzten Wiener Besuch in so schlechter Verfaßung war und deßhalb weniger von unsrem Zusammensein haben konnte.  Messchaert<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="messchaert_johannes">Johannes Messchaert</ref>.</tei:note> wurde leider von mir “influenzirt”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  A pun: Röntgen apparently “influenced” (<tei:hi rend="italic">influenzirt</tei:hi>) Messchaert by giving him influenza.</tei:note> und hat bis vor Kurzem damit zu thun gehabt: Jetzt ist er aber wohl und munter zum Bach-Fest in Berlin und am 26^t.^ haben wir hier Concert[e.]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Cut-off text at right margin.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> An Posas Violinsonate und neuen Liedern<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Oscar Posa (1873-1951), Austrian composer and conductor. An acquaintance of Schenker, Posa was a founding member of Schoenberg’s and Zemlinsky’s Vereinigung Schaffender Tonkünstler in 1904 (in which Schoenberg tried hard to persuade Schenker to be involved). It has been suggested that Posa, an otherwise obscure figure, might have penned the Society’s charter. (Joseph Auner, <tei:hi rend="italic">A Schoenberg Reader: Documents of a Life</tei:hi> (New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 2003), 42; Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebücher ...</tei:hi> (Hildesheim: Olms, 1985), 179;  Charlotte E. Erwin &amp; Bryan R. Simms, “Schoenberg’s Correspondence with Heinrich Schenker,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Journal of the Arnold Schoenberg Institute</tei:hi> 5 (1981), 23–43.)</tei:note> habe ich großen Genuß: sie[?] beschäftigen[<tei:hi rend="italic">alt from</tei:hi> beschäftigt] mich auf’s Intensiveste!</tei:p><tei:p>Für heute genug, ich schreibe in großer Eile.</tei:p><tei:p>Wollen Sie die Güte haben Herrn Weinberger<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Josef Weinberger (1855-1928), Viennese music publisher. Weinberger, who had run his own music publishing outfit since 1885, was principal shareholder in the cooperative publishing firm Universal Edition, established formally in June 1901. At the time of its founding, Universal Edition aimed—as expressed in an early catalogue—to publish “a comprehensive collection of model editions of all the works needed in schools and for private study covering all the various levels of piano, violin, and voice instruction; of classical compositions for piano, solo song, and chamber music; as well as four-hand transcriptions of all classical symphonies, quartets, overtures, etc.” Schenker sought to secure Röntgen’s collaboration in the latter endeavor in a letter of March 15, 1901 (NMI C 140-02). Schenker’s contact with Weinberger and his firm extends back to 1899; the latter published Schenker’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Syrische Tänze für Pianoforte zu 4 Händen</tei:hi> (Vienna: Josef Weinberger, n. d.). (Ian D. Bent, “‘That Bright, New Light’: Schenker, Universal Edition, and the Origins of the Erläuterung Series, 1901-1910,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Journal of the American Musicological Society</tei:hi> 58, no. 1 [2005], 71-75 [cited at p. 72]; Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern ...</tei:hi> (Hildesheim: Olms, 1985), 17, 189-92.)</tei:note> von meiner vorläufigen Zusage Mittheilung zu machen?</tei:p><tei:p>Ich hoffe dann bald Näheres zu hören, um dann hoffentlich etwas Bestimmtes sagen zu können.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit herzlichstem Gruß
Ihr
verehrungsvoll ergebener
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Julius Röntgen.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> Bitte um Discretion für den “Über-Bülow”!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  “Über-Bülow”: presumably the joke-piece described earlier.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>S[?].O.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Röntgen to Schenker, dated March 18, 1901</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Amsterdam, March 18, 1901.</tei:p><tei:p>Most honored Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>First of all, many thanks for your letter<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> and for so kindly sharing your views, which I value so highly!</tei:p><tei:p>It will be a pleasure to contribute something to the great undertaking about which you write. In principle, I happily say “yes,” but my final decision must depend upon what kind of edition is desired. <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> I already see from your remarks that a mere critical reproduction of the original text is not intended. Will the edition follow a set of general principles, or will each of the individual editors be left to follow his own path?</tei:p><tei:p>Is it a matter, e.g., of merely marking fingerings, phrasings, etc., or must this be an +instructive+ edition in the manner of Cotta’s?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/></tei:p><tei:p>I would not like to undertake a work in the latter sense. Another question: is this to be a complete edition, i.e., covering all <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> the works of a composer? Or could one limit oneself to a selection? E.g., some of Mozart’s piano works (apart from the sonatas), the Fantasies, A-minor Rondo, B-minor Adagio, and also some of the smaller, lesser-known pieces? That would seem more practical to me than bringing out the entire mass, in which there is much that is of only historical interest. A selection of Mozart’s piano works would be an enticing project for me! Then I thought about Bach’s six sonatas for piano and violin, which have appeared only in quite useless popular editions. The older version of the 6th sonata— <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> including the two wonderful adagios—has still not appeared, except in the big Bach-Ausgabe.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/></tei:p><tei:p>I would therefore be very grateful if you would tell me a bit more about the operative artistic foundation of the entire undertaking!</tei:p><tei:p>For fun, I’m sending you a joke that I played years ago with Bülow. It is an “arrangement” of one of my piano pieces for a Bülow-enthusiast female student, who was very good at “hitting the wrong notes.”</tei:p><tei:p>Here you will see what you have to fear from me as an “arranger”!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> Send the thing back to me sometime, preferably quite soon, along with the inventions, which I am eagerly awaiting!</tei:p><tei:p>I’m sorry that I was in such a bad state during my last visit to Vienna, and that I therefore made so little use of our time together. Unfortunately, Messchaert<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> was “influenza-ed”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> by me and had, until just recently, been dealing with that. But he is now fit as a fiddle at the Bach Festival in Berlin, and we have concerts here on the 26th.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> I’ve been thoroughly enjoying Posa’s violin sonata and new Lieder<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>—those have been occupying me most intensely!</tei:p><tei:p>Enough for today; I write in great haste.</tei:p><tei:p>Would you be kind enough to pass my provisional acceptance along to Herr Weinberger?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/></tei:p><tei:p>I hope to hear more of the details soon, and then, hopefully, to be able to say something more certain.</tei:p><tei:p>With best wishes, 
In great admiration,
Yours truly,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Julius Röntgen</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> Your discretion please regarding “Über-Bülow”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> (see above[?])!</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>