<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 13/27, [7] : 9-23-08 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain, reproduced with kind permission of the Nederlands Muziek Instituut.
© Transcription Kevin Karnes, 2007.
© Translation Kevin Karnes, 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Kevin Karnes 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1908-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image:  University of California, Riverside;  Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Kevin Karnes.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 09/23/1908 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: &quot;R&#195;&#182;ntgen ~ HSchenker&quot; --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Röntgen to Schenker, dated September 23, 1908</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-05-09</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Acks S's letter (non-extant) and thanks S for Beitrag zur Ornamentik, applauding its remarks on Riemann and von Bülow; raises (with music examples) the execution of appogiaturas comprising more than two notes. —Reports on his meeting with the singer Steiner. —Hopes to see S in the winter, and asks again after a suitable publisher for his piano quintet.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Röntgen, Julius; Schenker, Heinrich;  Beitrag zur Ornamentik;  Contribution to the Study of Ornamentation;  Riemann, Hugo;  Mannheimer Schule;  Mannheim school;  Bülow, Hans von;  Bach, C. P. E.;  Bach, J. S.;  Mozart;  Vorschlag;  appoggiatura;  Lebert, Sigmund;  Stark, Ludwig;  J. G. Cotta;  Steiner;  Anriessen, Willem;  Amsterdam Conservatory;  Prix d'excellence;  fugue;  improvisation;  Greef, Arthur de;  Vienna;  Zurich;  Röntgen, Engelbert;  Gutmann, Albert J.;  piano quintet</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Amsterdam</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Röntgen to Schenker, dated September 23, 1908</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Amsterdam, 23 Sept. 08
77, van Eeghenstraat.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Herr Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>Seit lange schon schulde ich Ihnen Antwort und Dank für Ihren Brief und für die “Ornamentik”,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  S’s letter is not known to have survived.  Schenker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Ein Beitrag zur Ornamentik</tei:hi> (Vienna: U.E., 1903, 2/1908), possibly the “new work” to which R referred in his letter of August 8, 1908 (OJ 13/27, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  There may be some confusion regarding terminology here. In <tei:hi rend="italic">Beitrag</tei:hi>, S uses R’s term—<tei:hi rend="italic">Vorschlag</tei:hi>—narrowly, to denote the appoggiatura.  The ornament shown in R’s example below, however, is what S would call an “ascending turn” (<tei:hi rend="italic">Doppelschlag von unten</tei:hi>) or “slide” (<tei:hi rend="italic">Schleifer</tei:hi>).  (See <tei:hi rend="italic">Beitrag</tei:hi> [2/1908], pp. 54-55; Eng. trans., pp. 107-108.)  S corrects R on this point, albeit obliquely, in his letter of October 3, 1908 (NMI [C 176-03]).</tei:note>). In a letter of October 3, 1908 (NMI [C 176-03]), S makes clear that it was the 2nd edn of <tei:hi rend="italic">Beitrag</tei:hi> that he sent. </tei:note> die ich mit größtem Intereße gelesen habe und noch weiter studiren werde.</tei:p><tei:p>Mir ist das Meiste darin aus der Seele gesprochen, besonders auch die allgemeineren Bemerkungen über den[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] neuesten Riemannschen Reclameartikel: “die Mannheimer- <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Schule”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Hugo Riemann, ed., <tei:hi rend="italic">Sinfonien des Pfalzbayerischen Schule (Mannheimer Schule)</tei:hi>, Denkmäler Deutscher Tonkunst, ser. 2: Denkmäler der Tonkunst in Bayern 3/1, 7/2, 8/2 (Leipzig: Breitkopf und Härtel, 1902-1907).  S dedicates much of his preface to the 2nd edn of <tei:hi rend="italic">Beitrag</tei:hi> to a critique of Riemann’s statements on behalf of the Mannheim symphonist Johann Stamitz (1717-57), whose contributions were, in Schenker’s view, far less significant than those of C. P. E. Bach.  S does not name Riemann as his target, but he makes the historian’s identity clear by referring to a critical edition of music by Stamitz and other “precursors” (<tei:hi rend="italic">Vorläufer</tei:hi>) of Bach published in the series “Denkmäler der Tonkunst in …” (Schenker’s ellipses). See <tei:hi rend="italic">Beitrag</tei:hi> (2/1908), p. 2; Eng. trans. (1976), pp. 12-13.</tei:note> und über ^die^ Bülow’schen Extravaganzen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  In his introduction to <tei:hi rend="italic">Beitrag</tei:hi>, S criticizes Hans von Bülow’s editorial practice as evinced in the latter’s edition of Bach’s piano sonatas (C. P. E. Bach, <tei:hi rend="italic">Sechs Klavier-Sonaten</tei:hi>, ed. Hans von Bülow [Leipzig: C. F. Peters, 1862]).  In the latter volume, as quoted in S’s book, Bülow likened his undertaking to preparing an “arrangement” (<tei:hi rend="italic">Bearbeitung</tei:hi>) of Bach’s scores for a modern audience. See Schenker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Beitrag</tei:hi> (2/1908), pp. 4-5; Eng. trans., pp. 16-19.</tei:note>  Ich freue mich nun sehr darauf Ihre Ph. Em. Bach-Ausgabe kennen zu lernen und bin sehr gespannt darauf.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  S’s edition of selected works by C. P. E. Bach was published as <tei:hi rend="italic">Klavierwerke von Philipp Emanuel Bach: Neue kritische Ausgabe von Heinrich Schenker</tei:hi> (Vienna: Universal Edition, [1903]; UE 458). R seems not to have realized that S’s edition had already been published; S corrects him on this point in a letter of October 3, 1908 (NMI [C 176-03]).</tei:note>  Nachdem ich Ihre Schrift gelesen habe, mußte ich mir mit einem Gefühl der Beschämung gestehen, daß ich den Philipp Emanuel eigentlich viel zu wenig kenne.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit der Ornamentik habe ich mich natürlich beschäftigt, da ja viele Fragen bei der Herausgabe des alten Bachs<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Beginning in 1902, R undertook extensive work for UE, editing many of J. S. Bach’s keyboard works. These include Bach’s Little Preludes and Fugues, Two- and Three-Part Inventions, French Suites, English Suites, Partitas, Italian Concerto, D-minor Concerto, and <tei:hi rend="italic">Chromatic Fantasy &amp; Fugue</tei:hi>.</tei:note> an mich herantraten.  Ich habe meine eigenen Ansichten über diese schwierige Materie, die ich so gerne einmal mündlich mit Ihnen bespräche.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Ich [<tei:hi rend="italic">deletion</tei:hi>] meine es läßt sich nicht Alles nach der starren Regel: “jede Verzierung wird von der darauf folgenden Note abgezogen” behandeln, besonders nicht bei den nach-Bachische[n] Componisten.  Der gute Geschmack muß doch auch mit sprechen dürfen[.]  Bülow geht mir darin viel zu weit. Schon bei Mozart finde ich es in vielen Fällen geschmackvoller, Vorschläge von mehr als zwei Noten vorher zu nehmen – wieviel zierlicher klingt doch:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">musical example</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>als</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">musical example</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>(siehe Lebert &amp; Stark Cottaausgabe[)]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  R refers S to Sigmund Lebert’s edn of Mozart’s A-minor Rondo, K. 511 (Edition Cotta, No. 389;  Stuttgart and Berlin: J. G. Cotta, 1892); he quotes from m. 1.  With Ludwig Stark, Lebert authored the widely distributed and influential <tei:hi rend="italic">Grosse theoretisch-praktische Klavierschule</tei:hi>, pubd by Cotta Verlag with four-part appx (1858, 23rd edn 1904 by Max Pauer).  </tei:note> <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> besonders wenn die Schüler die Verzierung noch mit einem Accent auf dis u. mit der nöthigen Steifheit (verführt durch die Art[?] der Notirung) spielen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  R may be referring to the grace-note notation of the ascending turn in Lebert’s edition.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Warum nun nicht solche Verzierungen als Verbindungsnötchen auffaßen und warum müßen sie immer der darauf folg. Note als Gewicht angehängt werden?</tei:p><tei:p>Jedenfalls kann ich nicht auf das Bülow’sche Dogma, das überhaupt keine Ausnahme der Regel zuläßt, schwören.</tei:p><tei:p>Doch genug hiervon, bis wir uns einmal sprechen.</tei:p><tei:p>Nur noch ein paar Worte über Herrn Steiner,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  See OJ 13/27, [6], August 8, 1908;  perhaps the Franz Steiner who corresponded with Schenker in 1908 and 1913 (OJ 14/34);  clearly a singer, and suggested by Schenker.</tei:note> deßen Bekanntschaft ich dieser Tage hier gemacht habe.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> Trotz des sympathischen Eindrucks, den mir seine Person und auch seine gesanglichen Leistungen gemacht haben, konnte ich seinem Wunsche, mit[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] ihm zu concertiren nicht entsprechen.  Er wird Ihnen meine Gründe mittheilen.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich kann nicht gut mit einem Debutanten auftreten u. habe das stets geweigert.</tei:p><tei:p>Herr Steiner hat aber die Reise doch nicht umsonst gemacht.  Ich habe ihm einen genialen jungen Mann empfohlen, den er auch für seine Concerte gewonnen hat.  Er kommt dieser Tage nach Wien, um mit Steiner die <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> Programme vorzubereiten und ich hoffe, daß Sie ihn kennen lernen werden.  Er heißt Willem Andrießen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Willem Andriessen (1887-1964), Dutch pianist and composer.  A student of R at the Amsterdam Conservatory, Andriessen went on to cultivate a significant career as a solo pianist and a staunch advocate of new music in the Netherlands. He was appointed to the piano faculty of the Conservatory in The Hague in 1910. (Jos Wouters and Ronald Vermeulen, “Willem Andriessen,” in <tei:hi rend="italic">NGDM2</tei:hi> [2001].)</tei:note> und hat vor kurzem hier in glänzender Weise den Prix d’excellence unsres Conservatoriums bekommen[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>].</tei:p><tei:p>Laßen Sie sich einmal von ihm ein[e] Fuge vor-improvisiren und Sie werden erstaunen!</tei:p><tei:p>Hier that er es vor dem versammelten Publicum über ein höchst raffinirtes Thema, das ihm Arthur de Greef<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Arthur de Greef (1862-1940), Belgian pianist and composer. A student of Liszt and Camille Saint-Saëns, De Greef was appointed professor of piano at the Brussels Conservatory in 1887. (Henri Vanhulst, “Arthur de Greef,” in <tei:hi rend="italic">NGDM2</tei:hi> [2001].)</tei:note> aufgab. –</tei:p><tei:p>Vielleicht werden wir uns noch diesen Winter in Wien sehen.  Ich möchte mit meinem Sohn, der jetzt Solocellist in Zürich ist,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Engelbert Röntgen (1886-1958), Dutch cellist. After studies in Amsterdam, Klengel, and Leipzig, Röntgen was appointed principal cellist in the Philharmonic Orchestras of Rostock and later Zürich, from which he moved in 1912 to serve as principal cellist of the Vienna Hofoper. (Rogier Starreveld, “Röntgen,” in <tei:hi rend="italic">NGDM2</tei:hi> [2001].) </tei:note> <tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> ein paar Concerte geben u. habe gerade an Gutmann<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  Albert J. Gutmann, agent and concert promoter.  Gutmann’s sometimes complicated relationship with R, S, and Johannes Messchaert is discussed in NMI C 176-01 and OJ 13/27, [4].</tei:note> darüber geschrieben.</tei:p><tei:p>Was mein Quintett betrifft, wäre ich Ihnen sehr dankbar, wenn Sie mir einen Verleger nennen könnten, mit dem ich mich in Verbindung setzen könnte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  Here R reminds S of his request—made in R’s letter of August 8, 1908 (OJ 13/27, [6])—for help in securing a Viennese publisher for his piano quintet, which had been awarded a prize by the Wiener Konzertverein. The identity of the quintet is unclear. The complete list of Röntgen’s compositions maintained by the Julius Röntgen Stichting in The Hague (www.juliusrontgen.nl/composities.html) includes only a single piano quintet upon which Röntgen seems likely to have been working around this time: an unpublished quintet for flute, clarinet, horn, oboe, and piano, reportedly completed in 1911.</tei:note>  Da das Stück in Wien preisgekrönt ist, hätte ich ganz gerne, daß es auch dort herauskäme.</tei:p><tei:p>Für heute genug u. nochmals Dank für den Bach[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15">  This may be a reference either to the <tei:hi rend="italic">Beitrag</tei:hi>, the central focus of which is the ornamentation of C. P. E. Bach’s keyboard ornamentation, or possibly to S’s edition of selected keyboard works of C. P. E. Bach;  or it may be a miswriting for “das Buch” (“the book”).</tei:note> – Ihr neues Werk hoffe ich recht bald kennen zu lernen.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit bestem Gruß
Ihr herzlich ergebener
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Julius Röntgen</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Röntgen to Schenker, dated September 23, 1908</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Amsterdam, 23 Sept. 08
77, van Eeghenstraat.</tei:p><tei:p>Very honored Herr Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>For a long time I have owed you a response and thanks for your letter and for <tei:hi rend="italic">Ornamentation</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> which I have read with the greatest interest and will study still further.</tei:p><tei:p>Most of its contents took the words right out of my mouth, especially the more general remarks about the newest thing advertised by Riemann, <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Mannheimer-</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Schule</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> and about Bülow’s extravagances.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  I am now really looking forward to becoming acquainted with your C. P. E. Bach edition, and am eagerly awaiting it.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  After I read your essay, I had to confess, with a feeling of shame, that I actually know Philipp Emanuel much too poorly.</tei:p><tei:p>I have, of course, been occupied with the subject of ornamentation myself, since many questions confronted me when editing the elder Bach.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> I have my own views about this difficult subject, which I would like very much to discuss with you sometime in person.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> I think that not everything can be handled by the inflexible rule, “every ornament is subtracted from the following note”—especially not in the case of composers after Bach. Good taste must also be permitted to play a role.  To me, Bülow goes much too far in this respect. Already with Mozart I find it more tasteful in many cases to take appoggiaturas of more than two notes from the preceding [time-unit].<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/>  How much more delicate does this sound:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">musical example</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>than</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">musical example</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>(see the Lebert &amp; Stark Cotta edition)<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> especially when the pupil plays the ornament with an accent on D sharp and with the necessary stiffness (encouraged by the type[?] of the notation).<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/></tei:p><tei:p>Why not regard such ornaments as little connecting notes, and why must they always be hung like a weight on the note that follows?</tei:p><tei:p>In any case, I cannot swear by Bülow’s dogma, which allows for no exceptions to the rule whatsoever.</tei:p><tei:p>But enough about this, until we speak someday.</tei:p><tei:p>Just a couple more words about Mr. Steiner,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> whose acquaintance I recently made here.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> In spite of the congenial impression that his personality and his vocal abilities have made upon me, I could not grant him his wish to perform in concert together. He will inform you of my reasons.</tei:p><tei:p>I really cannot perform well with someone making his debut, and I have always refused to do so.</tei:p><tei:p>But Mr. Steiner did not make the trip in vain. I recommended a brilliant young man to him, whom he has engaged for his concert.  He is coming soon to Vienna in order to <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> prepare the program with Steiner, and I hope that you will get to know him. His name is Willem Andriessen,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> and he recently received, in an outstanding way, our conservatory’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Prix d’excellence</tei:hi>.</tei:p><tei:p>Get him to improvise a fugue for you sometime, and you will be amazed!</tei:p><tei:p>He did that here before the assembled audience, on a highly cunning theme given to him by Arthur de Greef.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/></tei:p><tei:p>Perhaps we may yet see each other in Vienna this winter.  I want to give a couple of concerts with my son, who is presently solo cellist in Zurich,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> <tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> and I have written directly to Gutmann<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> about it.</tei:p><tei:p>Concerning my Quintet, I would be very thankful if you could give me the name of a publisher with whom I could get in touch.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/> Since the work was awarded a prize in Vienna, I would like very much for it to be published there as well.</tei:p><tei:p>Enough for today, and thanks once again for the Bach[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>]<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn15"/>. I hope to get to know your new work right soon.</tei:p><tei:p>With best wishes, 
Yours most truly,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Julius Röntgen</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>