<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 13/27, [2] : 4-22-01 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  In the public domain.
©  Transcription  Kevin Karnes, 2006.
© Translation Kevin Karnes, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Kevin Karnes 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1901-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image:  University of California, Riverside;  Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Kevin Karnes.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 04/22/1901 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: &quot;R&#195;&#182;ntgen ~ HSchenker&quot; --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Röntgen to Schenker, dated April 22, 1901</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-11-22</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>R comments on S's Zweistimmige Inventionen, Op. 5, and Sechs Lieder, Op. 3, promises to continue studying them, and will go through the Lieder with Messchaert.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Röntgen, Julius; Schenker, Heinrich;  Zweistimmige Inventionen;  Op. 5;  Sechs Lieder;  Op. 3;  Bach, J. S.;  Ausklang;  Wiegenlied;  Messchaert, Johannes</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Amsterdam</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Julius Röntgen to Schenker, dated April 22, 1901</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Amsterdam, 22 April 1901.</tei:p><tei:p>Verehrtester Herr Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>Endlich ein Wort des Dankes auf Ihre inhaltsreiche Sendung! Halten Sie die Verzögerung nicht für Gleichgültigkeit! Im Gegentheil: Ihre Lieder und vor Allem die Inventionen beschäftigen mich sehr, ich wollte Ihnen aber nicht eher schreiben, ehe ich in ein etwas intimerer Verhältniß zu den Sachen getreten war und das ist mir nicht sogleich gelungen.</tei:p><tei:p>Sie gehen in den Inventionen auf ziemlich verschlungenen Pfaden, auf denen Ihnen zu folgen nicht immer leicht fällt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Heinrich Schenker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Zweistimmige Inventionen</tei:hi>, Op. 5 (Leipzig: B&amp;H, 1901).</tei:note> Besonders liegt die rein +musikalische+ Essenz nicht immer <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> vor der Hand, während das Technische ja sogleich intereßirt und imponirt.  Am Meisten in dieser Beziehung zieht mich das Fismoll Stück an – bisjetzt aber mehr beim Lesen, als beim Spielen.  Klanglich scheint mir Vieles gewagt, obgleich Alles vollkommen logisch ist. Sie können getrost darauf schreiben: “eine deutliche Art darneben einen starken Vorschmack von der Komposition zu überkommen” – wie es Bach bei den Inventionen gethan hat.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Röntgen quotes, apparently to signal his approval of Schenker’s adherence to expectations associated with the genre, and without syntactic coherence, from Bach’s inscription on the title page of the fair copy of his <tei:hi rend="italic">Inventions and Sinfonias</tei:hi>, BWV 772-801 (1723). Bach’s inscription reads: “Upright Instruction wherein the lovers of the clavier, and especially those desirous of learning, are shown a clear way not alone to learn to play clearly in two voices but also, after further progress, to deal correctly and well with three <tei:hi rend="italic">obbligato</tei:hi> parts; furthermore, at the same time not alone to have good <tei:hi rend="italic">inventiones</tei:hi> [ideas] but to develop the same well and, above all, to arrive at a singing style in playing and at the same time to acquire a strong foretaste of composition.” (“Auffrichtige Anleitung, Wormit denen Liebhabern des <tei:hi rend="italic">Clavires</tei:hi>, besonders aber denen Lehrbegierigen, eine deütliche Art gezeiget wird, nicht alleine mit 2 Stimmen reine spielen zu lernen, sondern auch bey weiteren <tei:hi rend="italic">progreßen</tei:hi> mit dreyen <tei:hi rend="italic">obligaten Partien</tei:hi> richtig und wohl zu verfahren, anbey auch zugleich gute <tei:hi rend="italic">inventiones</tei:hi> nicht alleine zu bekommen, sondern auch selbige wohl durchzuführen, am allermeisten aber eine <tei:hi rend="italic">cantable</tei:hi> Art im Spielen zu erlangen, und darneben einen starcken Vorschmack von der <tei:hi rend="italic">Composition</tei:hi> zu überkommen.”) (<tei:hi rend="italic">Bach-Dokumente. Supplement zu Johann Sebastian Bach: Neue Ausgabe sämtlicher Werke</tei:hi>, ed. Werner Neumann and Hans-Joachim Schulze, vol. 1, <tei:hi rend="italic">Schriftstücke von der Hand Johann Sebastian Bachs</tei:hi> (Kassel: Bärenreiter, 1963), 220-21; facs. and trans. in <tei:hi rend="italic">The New Bach Reader: A Life of Johann Sebastian Bach in Letters and Documents</tei:hi>, ed. Hans T. David and Arthur Mendel, revised and enlarged by Christoph Wolff (New York: W. W. Norton, 1998), 97-98.)  My thanks to Stephen Crist for his help in identifying the source of R’s quotation.</tei:note> Dagegen scheint mir die “Gemüths-Ergötzung” etwas zurückzutreten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  “Gemüths-Ergötzung”: This term appears on the title pages of the first editions of Bach’s four volumes of <tei:hi rend="italic">Clavier-Übungen</tei:hi> (I: BWV 825–830 [1731]; II: BWV 831, 971 [1735]; III: BWV 552/1, 669–689, 802–805, 552/2 [1739]; IV: BWV 988 [c. 1742]). The spelling used by Röntgen, however, is found only in Bach’s second volume, containing the Italian Concerto (BWV 971) that Röntgen was then editing for UE. The title pages reads: “Second part of the Keyboard Practice, consisting of a Concerto after the Italian Taste and an Overture after the French Manner, for a harpsichord with two manuals. Composed for music lovers, to refresh their spirits, by Johann Sebastian Bach, Capellmeister to His Highness the Prince of Saxe-Weissenfels and <tei:hi rend="italic">Directore Chori Musici Lipsiensis</tei:hi>. Published by Christoph Weigel, Junior.” (“Zweyter Theil der Clavier Ubung bestehend in einem Concerto nach Italiœnischen Gusto und einer Overture nach Französischer Art, vor ein Clavicÿmbel mit zweÿen Manualen. Denen Liebhabern zur Gemüths-Ergötzung verfertiget. von Johann Sebastian Bach. Hochfürstl: Sœchßl: Weißenfelßl: Capellmeistern und Directore Chori Musici Lipsiensis. in Verlegung Christoph Weigel Junioris.”) (<tei:hi rend="italic">Bach-Dokumente</tei:hi>, vol. 1, 235; facs. and trans. <tei:hi rend="italic">in The New Bach Reader</tei:hi>, 167-68.)  My thanks to Stephen Crist for his help in identifying the source of R’s quotation.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Soweit bin ich +bisjetzt+ mit den Inventionen gekommen, vielleicht ändert sich mein Urtheil aber noch.  Ich werde jedenfalls oft zu den Stücken zurückkehren und ich freue <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> mich darauf später mehr mit Ihnen darüber zu reden!</tei:p><tei:p>Mit den Liedern habe ich mich noch nicht viel beschäftigen können, da ich gerade in den letzten Wochen sehr viel Anderes zu thun hatte. Die Bach-Ausgabe, die ich übernommen habe,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  The identity of the edition to which Röntgen refers is unclear. During this period, Röntgen’s editorial work for UE was extensive. His editions of Bach’s Little Preludes and Fugues, Two- and Three-Part Inventions, French Suites, English Suites, Partitas, Italian Concerto, D-minor Concerto, and <tei:hi rend="italic">Chromatic Fantasy &amp; Fugue</tei:hi> all appeared in 1902.</tei:note> beschäftigt mich in freien Stunden ganz und gar (zu dieser Thätigkeit paßten nun Ihre Inventionen +sehr+ gut[)] und Alles Andere mußte deßhalb zurücktreten.</tei:p><tei:p>“Ausklang” steht mir unter den Liedern obenan.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Schenker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Sechs Lieder für eine Singstimme mit Begleitung des Pianoforte</tei:hi>, Op. 3 (Leipzig: Breitkopf &amp; Härtel, [c. 1898]), No. 4.</tei:note> Der herrliche Text hat einen unmittelbaren Ausdruck in der Musik gefunden und das Lied muß eine tiefe Wirkung machen. Die anderen Lieder kommen mir zum Theil nicht so natürlich vor (das reizende Wiegenlied [<tei:hi rend="italic">in lower right corner:</tei:hi>] ausgenommen!)[.]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Schenker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Sechs Lieder</tei:hi>, Op. 3, No. 2.</tei:note>   <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Die Texte sind ja aber auch mehr geistreicher Art und interessant haben Sie +Alles+ illustrirt! Am Wenigsten sagt mir das letzte Lied zu – mir kommt’s hie und da etwas zu schwer für den leichtfertigen Text vor (gis-moll <tei:hi rend="italic">Episode</tei:hi>)[.] Doch, wie gesagt, ich muß noch besser eindringen und bitte Sie diese paar Worte nur als vorläufig anzusehen.</tei:p><tei:p>Messchaert kommt dieser Tage nach Amsterdam.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">   Click on <ref cRef="messchaert_johannes">Johannes Messchaert</ref>.</tei:note> Ich freue mich darauf die Lieder mit ihm durchzumachen und besonders auf den “Ausklang”.</tei:p><tei:p>Und nun nehmen Sie heute mit dieser zu kurzen Antwort auf Ihren so Vieles anregenden Brief vorlieb und nochmals für Alles herzlichen Dank[.]</tei:p><tei:p>Ihren Sie verehrenden
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Julius Röntgen.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Julius Röntgen to Schenker, dated April 22, 1901</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Amsterdam, April 22, 1901.</tei:p><tei:p>Most honored Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>At last a word of thanks for your letter, which was so rich in content!  Don’t mistake the delay for indifference!  To the contrary: your songs and, above all, inventions have occupied me intensely; but I did not want to write until I had developed a somewhat more intimate relationship with the material at hand, and that did not come immediately to me.</tei:p><tei:p>In the inventions you tread upon fairly twisted paths, and it is not always easy to follow you.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> In particular, the purely +musical+ essence is not always <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> readily apparent, even though the technical aspect is immediately interesting and impressive. In this respect, I’m drawn most strongly to the piece in F-sharp minor—but more, thus far, through reading it than through playing it. There is much that sounds quite daring to me, even though everything is entirely logical. On it, you can safely write, as Bach did on his inventions: “a clear way at the same time to acquire a strong foretaste of composition.”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> In contrast, “refreshing of the spirit” seems to take somewhat of a back seat.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/></tei:p><tei:p>Considering how well I have become acquainted with the inventions <tei:hi rend="italic">thus far</tei:hi>, it is possible that my opinion will change. In any case, I will return to the works frequently, and I look forward <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> to discussing them with you further in the future!</tei:p><tei:p>I have not yet spent a great deal of time with the Lieder, since I’ve had many other things to do in recent weeks. The Bach edition I took on<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> has occupied me during every free hour (for the latter purpose, your inventions are +very+ well suited!), and everything else had therefore to be pushed back.</tei:p><tei:p>To me, “Ausklang” stands out among the Lieder.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> The marvelous text has found immediate expression in the music, and the Lied must make a profound impression. The other Lieder seem a bit less natural to me (with the exception of the delightful “Wiegenlied”!).<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> But the texts are of a wittier sort, and you have illustrated +everything+ interestingly! The last Lied is least to my liking—it seems, to me, to be too heavy for the clever text in places (the G-sharp minor episode). As I said, however, I must probe them further and ask that you consider these few words as merely provisional.</tei:p><tei:p>Messchaert is coming to Amsterdam in a day or so.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> I’m looking forward to playing through the Lieder with him, especially “Ausklang.”</tei:p><tei:p>And now you must make do, for today, with this overly brief reply to your highly stimulating letter, and once again many thanks for everything,</tei:p><tei:p>Yours, in great admiration,</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Julius Röntgen.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>