<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 89/1, [4] : 9-6-27 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.  
© Transcription John Rothgeb, 2008.
© Translation John Rothgeb, 2008.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Hoboken, Anthony van (1927-1983) - -Schneider, Hans(19??-2007) - -University of California, Riverside (2007 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker;  Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 09/06/1927 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Hoboken ~ H+JSchenker","Hoboken ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Hoboken, dated September 6, 1927</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-06-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Schenker comments on Hoboken's Appeal [for the Photogrammarchiv], sets out what is necessary for correctly reading an autograph manuscript and understanding its relationship to the first edition, and rails against the tendency of performers, including Furtwängler, to think such matters trivial.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  nephew;  brother;  Galtür;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Aufruf;  Appeal;  manuscripts;  Kinsky, Georg;  Altmann, Wilhelm;  Bülow, Hans von;  Liszt;  Germany;  Violin, Moriz</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Vienna</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to van Hoboken dated September 6, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Wien, 6. 9. 27
Lieber Herr van Hoboken!</tei:p><tei:p>Durch den Besuch eines Neffen von mir sowie durch die Vorbereitungen zur Abreise u. zum Besuch bei meinem älteren Bruder<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Wilhelm Schenker: [create profile and link].  </tei:note> war ich in Galtür in den letzten Augusttagen verhindert, einiges zu Ihrem Besuch bei Furtwängler<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Wilhelm Furtwängler: [create profile and link].  </tei:note> zu bemerken.  Da ich gestern endlich heimgekehrt bin, war ich im Begriffe, das Vorgehabte heute nachzuholen, als Ihr zweiter lieber Brief (über Galtür) hierherkam.  Ich muß offen sprechen.</tei:p><tei:p>An einer Stelle Ihres schönen Aufrufs<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="aufruf_november_1927">Aufruf</ref>.</tei:note> sprechen Sie von der Bedeutung der Handschriften u. sagen, daß auch diejenigen, die sie einsehen, von ihrem Wert nicht sonderlich überzeugt sind, da ihnen die etwa angetroffenen[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] Divergenzen zu gering- <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> fügig erscheinen.  Einen Augenblick lang gelüstete es mich, Sie zu ermutigen, die volle Wahrheit auszusprechen, daß die Herausgeber u. Musiker so sagen können u. müssen, weil sie <tei:hi rend="italic">die Handschrift nicht zu lesen verstehen</tei:hi> im Einklange mit dem Gewollten. [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from lower margin:</tei:hi> Im nächsten Augenblick gewann der Gedanke doch Oberhand in mir, daß Sie in Ihrem “Aufruf” besser tun, etwas diskreter zu sprechen, wie Sie es eben getan haben.]  Die Sache steht so: erstens muß man die Komposition aus dem Innersten verstehen, zweitens muß man die Handschrift in ihrem Sinne lesen, drittens muß man die Unterschiede von Erstdruck u. Handschrift <tei:hi rend="italic">nach der Komp. zu werten wissen</tei:hi>, denn so gewiß es ist, daß der Komponist sich zuweilen im Erstdruck verbessert (was aber bei den Meistern <tei:hi rend="italic">sehr, sehr, sehr selten</tei:hi> vorkommt!), so geschiet es noch häufiger, daß (von solchen Verbesserungen abgesehen) die Handschrift noch lange nicht gut genug durch den Erstdruck wiedergegeben erscheint.  So &lt;strike&gt;galt&lt;/strike&gt; ^gilt^ es denn also, diesen Vorzug der Handschrift festzustellen, nicht nur die <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> groben Fehler des Erstdruckes zu berichtigen, sondern noch darüberhinaus alles das ins Licht zu stellen, was der Erstdruck <tei:hi rend="italic">wiederzugeben gar nicht den Versuch machte</tei:hi>.</tei:p><tei:p>Solange ich davon rede, höre ich (von den Historikern, von den Kinsky’s<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="kinsky_georg">Georg Kinsky</ref>.  </tei:note> u. Altmanns,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="altmann_wilhelm">Wilhelm Altmann</ref>.</tei:note> den Pianisten u. &lt;strike&gt;H&lt;/strike&gt; Dirigenten) das leicht hingeworfene Wort von der Geringfügigkeit aller dieser Dinge, von dem überragenden Wert des Erstdrucks – aber das sind alles Menschen, denen die Komp. vollständig unbekannt ist, daher auch die Handschrift trotz all ihren Zaubern des besonderen Ausdrucks nichts mehr bedeutet als ein Musealstück.</tei:p><tei:p>Und eben, daß zu diesen Menschen ehedem ein Bülow,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="hans_von_bulow_18309">Hans von Bülow</ref>.  </tei:note> Liszt u.s.w. ^gehörten^ u. heute ein Furtw. gehört[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>], <tei:hi rend="italic">das macht die Schande u. den Schaden aus</tei:hi>!  Nicht nur, daß die Wiedergabe in <tei:hi rend="italic">Text</tei:hi> u. Ausführung fehlerhaft, kindisch, kindlich, anfängerhaft <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> lautet, daß über dieser verlorensten Unwissenheit die Gefahr des Unterganges aller Handschriften als angeblich überflüssiger Dinge [droht], sodaß man allen Ernstes Ursache hat, sich <tei:hi rend="italic">der Händler</tei:hi> u. Liebhaber <tei:hi rend="italic">zu freuen</tei:hi>, die die Handschriften schon zum Zweck des Gewinns solange wie möglich am Leben erhalten.  Kürzer:  unser Furtw. versteht von alldem gar nichts;  wenn ihm nur per Abend 3-4000 Doll. u. im Deutschland sou[nd]soviel MK geboten wird, der Rest greift ihm nicht an’s Herz, leider auch nicht an’s Ohr!  Das ist es ja, unsere Ersten sind noch viel zu schlecht u. zu untauglich u. darum kam es so katastrophenhaft – ein Zufall ist das nicht, es ist die Folge von Ursachen.  Ist es nicht schauerlich, wenn ich sagen muß, ^daß^ mein Freund Prof. Violin<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="violin_moriz">Moriz Violin</ref>.  </tei:note> in Hamburg u. Sie besser hören (feiner meine ich) als unser F.?  Sehen Sie nur den <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> Lauf der Welt: Sie unterdrücken im Aufruf eigens die Schärfe, die geboten wäre, ich unterdrücke die Lust, Sie zur Schärfe zu veranlassen, wir tun uns einen Zwang an, aber die Bösewichte aus Unwissenheit tun sich gar keinen Zwang an u. nötigen uns, wie mich hier, die Schärfe nachzutragen.  Beim besten Willen:  es geht nicht ohne Schärfe, wenn man die Sache nicht verraten will;  man wird zur Schärfe <tei:hi rend="italic">durch die Menschen genötigt</tei:hi>, die Schaden stiften u. nicht rasten in der Zerstörung.  Wie gern <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> gäbe ich ^mich^ zahmer, aber das wäre Verrat.  Mit dem Schwert der Wahrheit u. des Zornes muß es gelingen u. es wird gelingen!</tei:p><tei:p>Viel Glück auf Ihren
Wegen u. beste
Grüße von uns Beiden
Ihr
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">HSchenker</tei:hi></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to van Hoboken dated September 6, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Vienna, September 6, 1927
Dear Mr. van Hoboken,</tei:p><tei:p>Through the visit of a nephew of mine and also through the preparations for departure and for a visit to my older brother,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> I was deterred in Galtür in the last days of August from commenting on a few points regarding your visit with Furtwängler.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  As I finally returned home yesterday, I had intended today to follow up on that intent when your second nice letter (via Galtür) arrived.  I must speak openly.</tei:p><tei:p>In one place in your excellent Appeal<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> you speak of the significance of the manuscripts and state that even those who examine them are not particularly convinced of their value, since various divergences encountered appear to them to be too trivial. <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> For a moment I felt inclined to encourage you to speak the complete truth, that the editors and musicians can and must say this because they <tei:hi rend="italic">do not know how to read the manuscript</tei:hi> in terms of what it means to express.  [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from lower margin:</tei:hi>  A moment later I reconsidered, and thought that you were better advised in your Appeal to speak somewhat more discreetly, just as you have in fact done.] The matter stands thus:  in the first place one must understand the composition down to the core; second, one must read the manuscript in the spirit of that core content;  and third, one must <tei:hi rend="italic">know how to evaluate</tei:hi> the differences between first edition and manuscript <tei:hi rend="italic">in relation to the composition</tei:hi>;  because however certain it is that the composer sometimes makes improvements in the first edition (which however happens <tei:hi rend="italic">very, very, very seldom</tei:hi> with the masters), a far more common occurrence is that (apart from such improvements) the manuscript is far from being well enough represented by the first edition.  What must be done, then, is to discover this advantage of the manuscript, not only in order to correct the <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> crude errors of the first edition, but also, above and beyond that, to shed light on all that the first edition <tei:hi rend="italic">does not even attempt to reproduce</tei:hi>.
 
As long as I am speaking of this, I hear (from the historians, from the Kinskys<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> and Altmanns,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> the pianists and conductors) the facile word about the triviality of all of these things, about the superior value of the first edition—but those are all people to whom the composition is completely unknown, and thus to whom the manuscript as well, despite all of its marvels of particular expression, signifies nothing more than a museum-piece.</tei:p><tei:p>And precisely that this group used to include a Bülow,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> Liszt, etc., and today includes a Furtwängler,—<tei:hi rend="italic">that completes the damage and the pity</tei:hi>!  Not only that the reproduction in text and performance sounds faulty, childlike, childish, amateurish, <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> and that because of this most irremediable ignorance the danger threatens of the destruction of all manuscripts as allegedly superfluous objects, so that one quite seriously has reason to <tei:hi rend="italic">celebrate the dealers</tei:hi> and music lovers, who keep the manuscripts just for the purpose of profit so long as possible.  More concisely:  our Furtwängler understands nothing of all that; when he is offered 3–4,000 dollars, and in Germany so and so many Marks per evening, the other things don’t go to his heart, and unfortunately also not to his ear!  That’s the problem, alright, our best people are still much too bad and too ill-suited, and therefore things got so catastrophic—that is no accident, it is the result of causes.  Is it not frightening that I have to say that my friend Prof. Violin<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> in Hamburg and you hear better (more accurately I mean) than our Furtwängler?  Just look at <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> how things go in the world:  you deliberately suppress in your Appeal the stridency that would be called for, I suppress the urge to recommend stridency to you, we restrain ourselves, but the scoundrels practice no restraint whatever, and they oblige us, oblige me here, to take a strident tone.  With the best of intentions: stridency cannot be suppressed without betrayal of the cause;  one is <tei:hi rend="italic">obliged to use strident language by the people</tei:hi> responsible for the damage and whose destructiveness knows no rest.  How I would <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> like to take a milder tone, but that would be betrayal.  With the sword of truth and of anger it must succeed and it will succeed!</tei:p><tei:p>Good luck on your quest and best greetings from us both,   
Yours,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] H. Schenker</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>