<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 89/1, [8] : 12-17-27 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.  
© Transcription John Rothgeb, 2008.
© Translation John Rothgeb, 2008.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Hoboken, Anthony van (1927-1983) - -Schneider, Hans(19??-2007) - -University of California, Riverside (2007 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker;  Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 12/17/1927 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Hoboken ~ H+JSchenker","Hoboken ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Hoboken, dated December 17, 1927</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-07-24</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Reply from Dr. Richtera has arrived, and Schenker encloses it;  Otto Erich Deutsch is invited to give a lecture about the damages. — Hoboken has had a letter from Alban Berg that may be intentionally ironic;  Schenker reflects on the spirit of the Photogrammarchiv.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  Photogrammarchiv;  Regierungsrat;  govenment counsel;  Richtera, Dr.;  Deutsch, Otto Erich;  Berg, Alban;  Schoenberg;  Joachim, Joseph;  Messchaert, Johannes</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to van Hoboken, dated December 17, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Lieber Herr van Hoboken!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Writing of this letter (sent express mail) is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/1, p. 3154.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Soeben trifft die Antwort der Regierungsrates Prof D^r^ Richtera<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Dr. Richtera: [identify]</tei:note> ein, sie liegt hier bei.  H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Deutsch</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="deutsch_otto_erich">Otto Erich Deutsch</ref>.  </tei:note> wird also gebeten werden um einen “<tei:hi rend="italic">richtigen Vortrag</tei:hi>”;<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Presumably a lecture on the Archiv für Photogramme musikalischer Meisterhandschriften.</tei:note> wegen der “Bebilderung” wird wohl ein Besprechung nötig sein, wenn damit gemeint ist, die Zuhörer optisch über die Schäden<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Probably the damage inflicted by printed editions on musical texts as they are presented in the autographs of masters.</tei:note> aufzuklären.  Da H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Deutsch</tei:hi> heute zu Ihnen kommt, so wollte ich Sie davon schon unterrichtet haben.  Mehr am Dienstag, habe sogleich (10-12^h^) zu tun.  Nur das Eine noch: H. A. <tei:hi rend="italic">Berg</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  i. e. Alban Berg.</tei:note> dürfte <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> in Anwandlung von <tei:hi rend="italic">Ironie</tei:hi> an Sie geschrieben haben, davon lernt man bei <tei:hi rend="italic">Schönberg</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="schoenberg_arnold">Arnold Schoenberg</ref>.</tei:note> mehr als [von der] Musik.  Sowie [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] Sie das Ziel des Archivs<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="photogrammarchiv">Photogrammarchiv</ref>.  </tei:note> umrissen haben, stellt es, wenn auch als jüristische Person, gleichsam einen großen Künstler vor, der sagt: Was ich, das Archiv, hier wieder&lt;strike&gt;gäbe&lt;/strike&gt;^gebe^, das allein ist die wahre Kunst.”  Das Archiv stellte geistig das vor, was wir bei Joachim,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Joseph Joachim: [create profile and link].  </tei:note> Mes[s]chaert<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Click on <ref cRef="messchaert_johannes">Johannes Messchaert</ref>.  </tei:note> gesehen haben, heute leider vermissen.  Das Archiv erreicht dieses hohe künstlerische u. menschliche Richteramt, ohne es eigentlich zu betonen, da es vor Allem die Schätze vor Untergang bewahren will.  H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Berg</tei:hi> begreift als bisher der Einzige, daß der “neuen Musik” durch das Archiv<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  That is, through its very existence.</tei:note> mittelbar ein <tei:hi rend="italic">Schaden an Ansehen</tei:hi> erwachsen würde u. daher <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> protestiert er leise.  Nicht uneben wäre es, ihm zu sagen, daß wir <tei:hi rend="italic">hoffen</tei:hi>, in <tei:hi rend="italic">100-200</tei:hi> Jahren werde sich ein <tei:hi rend="italic">neuer van Hoboken</tei:hi> finden, der die “neue Musik” von heute in ähnlicher Weise vor Untergang bewahren wird, f<tei:hi rend="italic">alls</tei:hi>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  The tacet continuation could probably be filled in as “(in case) new music has survived that long!”  "falls" (in case):  double-underlined by Schenker.  </tei:note> usw.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit bestem eiligstem Gruß  
Ihr
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  HSchenker
17.12.27</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to van Hoboken, dated December 17, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Mr. van Hoboken,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>The reply from the government counsel Prof. Dr. Richtera<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> has just arrived and is enclosed here.  Mr. Deutsch<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> is thus invited to give a “<tei:hi rend="italic">proper lecture</tei:hi>”;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> concerning the “illustration,” a discussion will probably be necessary, if what that means is to give the audience visual information about the damages.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  As Mr. Deutsch is visiting you today, I wanted to have informed you already.  More on Tuesday, right now (10:00-12:00) I have something to do.  Only one thing more: Mr. A. Berg<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> might have <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> written you in a fit of <tei:hi rend="italic">irony</tei:hi>—from Schoenberg<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> one learns more about that than [about] music.  As you have sketched the purpose of the Archive,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> it stands, if only as a juridical person, for a great artist who says:  only that which I, the Archive, here reproduce is the true art.”  The Archive in spirit represents what we have seen with Joachim,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> Messchaert,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> [etc.], but which regrettably is lacking today.  The Archive attains this high artistic and human judicial authority without actually emphasizing that it wants first of all to guard the treasures against decline.  Mr. Berg (thus far alone) understands that “new music” would indirectly suffer an <tei:hi rend="italic">injury to its reputation</tei:hi> through the Archive,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> and therefore he <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> gently protests.  It wouldn’t be a bad idea to tell him that we hope, in <tei:hi rend="italic">one or two hundred years</tei:hi>, that a <tei:hi rend="italic">new van Hoboken</tei:hi> will come along who will guard “new music” against decline -- <tei:hi rend="italic">in case</tei:hi> . . .!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> etc.</tei:p><tei:p>With best, hastiest greetings,
Yours,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  H. Schenker
December 17, 1927</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>