<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 89/1, [2] : 8-12-27 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.  
© Transcription John Rothgeb, 2008.
© Translation John Rothgeb, 2008.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Hoboken, Anthony van (1927-1983) - -Schneider, Hans(19??-2007) - -University of California, Riverside (2007 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker;  Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 08/12/1927 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Hoboken ~ H+JSchenker","Hoboken ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Hoboken, dated August 12, 1927</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-05-08</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Schenker acknowledges van Hoboken's letter, OJ 11/54, 14, dated August 7, 1927;  encloses seven articles;  responds regarding Haydn, Furtwängler, the "Appeal" for the Photogrammarchiv, an exhibition in Frankfurt, John Petrie Dunn, Reinhard Oppel, Das Meisterwerk in der Musik, vol. II, Otto Erich Deutsch,  and an honorarium;  and sends best wishes for the Hobokens' trip to Switzerland, reporting on von Cube.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  Jaray, Karl;  Vienna;  Haydn;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Germany;  Mozart;  Aufruf;  Appeal;  Photogrammarchiv;  Haas, Robert;  Deutsch, Otto Erich;  Radio Wien;  Richtera, Dr.;  Koch, Louis;  Frankfurt;  Ischgl;  Galtür;   Dunn, John Petrie;  Oppel, Reinhard;  Knorr, Iwan;  Meisterwerk in der Musik;  Masterwork in Music;  Waldheim-Eberle;  enclosures;  Noah;  Ark;  negro singers;  Strauss, Richard;  Pfitzner;  Schindler, Anton;  Nürnberg;  Nuremberg;  Schweiz;  Switzerland;  Cube, Felix-Eberhard von</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to van Hoboken dated August 12, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Lieber Herr van Hoboken!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  For relevant diary entries, see:  &lt;a href="../../../../../diary/oj<tei:hi rend="italic">39</tei:hi>p<tei:hi rend="italic">3099</tei:hi>81127.html"&gt;OJ 3/9, p. 3099, August 11, 1927&lt;/a&gt;;  -- &lt;a href="../../../../../diary/oj<tei:hi rend="italic">39</tei:hi>p<tei:hi rend="italic">3100</tei:hi>81227.html"&gt;OJ 3/9, p. 3100, August 12, 1927&lt;/a&gt;;  -- &lt;a href="../../../../../diary/oj<tei:hi rend="italic">39</tei:hi>p<tei:hi rend="italic">3100</tei:hi>81327.html"&gt;OJ 3/9, p. 3100, August 13, 1927&lt;/a&gt;.  As the diary shows, this letter was not finished until August 13, despite being dated August 12 below the signature.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Vielen Dank für Ihren lieben, so geduldig durchgehaltenen Brief,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  See OJ 11/54, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  Click on <ref cRef="galtur">Galtür</ref>.</tei:note>, dated August 7, 1927.</tei:note> dessen Genauigkeit mir, wie jede Genauigkeit, so viel Freude machten.  Ich hätte mich schon längst nach dem Befinden ihrer verehrten Frau Gemalin erkündigt, wenn mich nicht eine Karte des Architekten Jaray,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Perhaps Karl Járay (1878-1947), Viennese architect, member of the Jewish family Jeitteles, who designed several bank buildings, sanatoria, factories, and apartment buildings in Prague and elsewhere in Bohemia.  He belonged to the circle around Karl Kraus and Adolf Loos.   </tei:note> der sich in den ersten Julitagen nach Ihrer "gegenwärtigen Adresse" bei mir erkündigte, stutzig gemacht u. genötigt hätte, zu warten, bis Sie ein Lebenszeichen u. eine Adresse fanden.  Nun sehe ich, daß Sie den ersten Plan beibehielten u. daß Jaray's Anfrage in eine Zeit fiel, da Sie plangemäß fern von Wien weilten, was ich freilich nicht mehr so bestimmt wissen konnte.  (Ich habe J. dazumal doch auf Ihre Wiener Adresse verwiesen.)  Einmal unsicher geworden, unterließ ich mich zu erkundigen, <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> ob nicht die staatlich autorisierten Herren Einbrecher in Ihrem Wiener Heim etwas angestellt haben.  Angesichts Ihres richtigen Urteils über das Ereignis erspare ich mir mein schmerzliches Gefühl hier bloszulegen, wer weiß &lt;strike&gt;ich&lt;/strike&gt;, ob ich es werde aufbringen können, den so geschändeten Teil der Ringstrasse zu begehen oder zu befahren.</tei:p><tei:p>Und nun lassen Sie mich den Stichworten Ihres Schreibens folgen:  daß Sie in Ihrer so schönen Erstdrucksammlung <tei:hi rend="italic">Haydn</tei:hi> zu solchem Fortschritt verholfen haben, darf Ihnen eine ehrliche Genugtuung bereiten.  Wollte Gott, daß die glücklichen Zufälle Schritt hielten mit dem, was Sie anstreben,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  This refers not to van Hoboken's collection of first editions but to his search for manuscripts for the <ref cRef="photogrammarchiv">Photogrammarchiv</ref> project.</tei:note> was wir Alle <tei:hi rend="italic">Haydn</tei:hi> noch schulden - wo mögen nur seine Sachen stecken!  Die Musiker u. Laien, die sich mit ihrem Phrasenschwinden vor diese Sonne, diesen unheimlichen Dämon zu stellen wagen, haben nicht einmal so viel Anstand, ihm dafür zu danken, daß er ihnen Gelegenheit zu den Phrasen schenkt, die ^sie^ sich in solcher Fülle von <tei:hi rend="italic">Haydn</tei:hi>'s Vorgängern oder Zeitgenossen gewiß nicht holen könnten.  Kein Zweifel, daß <tei:hi rend="italic">Haydn</tei:hi>, der heute auf die spielenden Kinder gesunken ist, von den Kindern <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> einmal wieder zu den Erwachsenen steigen wird, wo im Grunde die seltensten u. erwachsensten Menschen zu ihm gehören.</tei:p><tei:p>Mein Brief an (D^r^) Furtwängler<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  This letter is not known to survive, but presumably replied to that from Furtwängler', OJ 11/16, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  This enclosure is not filed with the letter.</tei:note>, July 18, 1927, in which the latter said that he would be seeing Hoboken , who had recently written to him.    </tei:note> dürfte ihm lange nachgefahren sein, denn nachträglich erfuhr ich aus einer Zeitung, daß er gerade dazumal mit <tei:hi rend="italic">seinem</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Orchester</tei:hi> Abend um Abend (!) von Stadt zu Stadt (!) in Deutschland reiste.  Bis zur Stunde habe ich keine Zeile von ihm, was aber nicht ausschließt, daß er meinen Bf doch erhalten hat.  F. ist mal so, vielleicht spielt er sogar auf sich selbst, jedenfalls gehört er zu jenen Menschen, die, sich selbst täuschend, für bestimmt annehmen, daß man sie nur so u. immer nur so günstig sieht, als sie sich günstig sehen.  Beilage 1)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  This enclosure is not filed with the letter.</tei:note> zeigt eine treffende Entlarvung, aber F. ist sicherlich der letzte, der sie fassen kann - er wird auch darin nur ein Unrecht vermuten.  Gleichviel - der Versuch soll gemacht werden.  Wie schön wäre es, wenn er auf den Konzertzettel setzte z.B. <tei:hi rend="italic">Mozart</tei:hi>, Sinf. Gmoll, "nach den Erstdruck-Stimmen von André," (freilich auch danach richtig spielte)!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Ihren "Aufruf"<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="aufruf_november_1927">Aufruf</ref>.  </tei:note> sende ich gleichzeitig an D^r^ <tei:hi rend="italic">Haas</tei:hi>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="haas_robert">Robert Haas</ref>. </tei:note> Da ich ^ihn^ wieder lese, finde ich ihn sehr gut, wie am ersten Tage.  H. Deutsch'<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="deutsch_otto_erich">Otto Erich Deutsch</ref>.  </tei:note> Anregung zur Fußnote 1 finde ich <tei:hi rend="italic">treffend</tei:hi>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  The footnote refers to an agreement with the Beethoven Archive in Bonn not to duplicate photographic work on the Beethoven manuscripts.  </tei:note>  Wäre es nicht auch ratsam, daß H. Deutsch Ihren Aufruf im <tei:hi rend="italic">Radio Wien</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">zur</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Vorlesung</tei:hi> brächte, nötigenfalls einige Erläuterungen hinzufügte?  Der Weg zum Radio steht &lt;strike&gt;ja&lt;/strike&gt; H. D. ja immer offen, sonst könnte ich mit meiner Beziehung zum Prof. Dr <tei:hi rend="italic">Richtera</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Dr. Richtera: [identify].  </tei:note> dort nachhelfen.</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr Reiseplan nötigt mir alle Achtung ab.  Daß schön durchdachte, dem Ziel gelassen aber bestimmt Nachgehende, das liest sich schon angenehm u. lebt man auch angenehm mit.  Möge Ihnen <tei:hi rend="italic">Koch</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Click on <ref cRef="koch_louis">Louis Koch</ref>.  </tei:note> in Frkf. gewogen sein!  er hat gern schöne Dinge.  Die Ausstellung in Frkf. hat - u. ich lese die "Frkf. Zt." sehr genau - für mich wenigstens mehr den Geschmack einer soz. musik-<tei:hi rend="italic">ethnologischen</tei:hi> Ausstellung denn einer Ausstellung der Musik als wahrer Kunst.  Nach der Meinung der Frankfurter ist offenbar Alles "Kunst," was <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> in aller Welt gedudelt, gezupft, gebrüllt wird, - da hätten sehr wohl auch die Ischgler<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  Ischgl: [create profile and link-.  </tei:note> u. Galtürer<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  Click on <ref cRef="galtur">Galtür</ref>.</tei:note> Künstler hineingehört.  So demokratisch ist ^aber^ die Kunst nicht.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich komme zu Prof. <tei:hi rend="italic">Dunn</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15">  Click on <ref cRef="dunn_john_petrie">John Petrie Dunn</ref>.  </tei:note> den Sie ja auch auf dem Programm haben.  Da setzt ein Strauß von Űberraschungen ein:</tei:p><tei:p>Ende Juli besuchte mich hier Prof. D^r^ <tei:hi rend="italic">Oppel</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn16">  Click on <ref cRef="oppel_reinhard">Reinhard Oppel</ref>. </tei:note> aus Kiel.  Er ist nach <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Leipzig</tei:hi></tei:hi> für Theorie berufen worden, dort wird[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr from:</tei:hi> u. wird dort] ^er^ <tei:hi rend="italic">mein</tei:hi> System voll zur Anwendung bringen, Hm. Kp. Analysen usw.  Auch er ist Schüler von <tei:hi rend="italic">Knorr</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn17">  Click on <ref cRef="knorr_iwan">Iwan Knorr</ref>.  </tei:note> also ein Studienkollege von Ihnen, freilich ein älterer, da er 48 Jahre zählt.  Außerdem kennt er auch <tei:hi rend="italic">Dunn</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">sehr gut</tei:hi>, aus langjährigem persönlichem Verkehr; er rühmt ihm peinlichste Genauigkeit nach.  Prof. <tei:hi rend="italic">Oppel</tei:hi> wird mich Ende Dezember in Wien besuchen, vielleicht ergibt sich die Gelegenheit, daß auch Sie ihn kennen lernen.</tei:p><tei:p>Das Jahrbuch II,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn18">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Jahrbuch II</tei:hi>, i.e. <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, vol. II (Munich: Drei Masken Verlag, 1926).  </tei:note> das Sie Prof. <tei:hi rend="italic">D.</tei:hi> zu schenken so lieb im Sinn hatten, dürfte Ihnen zu dem angegebenen Termine kaum zur Verfügung stehen.  Am 25. <tei:hi rend="italic">6</tei:hi> sollte es mir <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> - noch in Wien - fertig vorliegen, dann brach (bis auf ^ein^ einziges Mal) ein großes Schweigen herein, - keine Bestätigung, keine Antworten - schließlich kam eine Zusage des allerletzten Umbruches für den 10. 8, aber auch dieses Datum brachte gar nichts ein.  Der Verlag - Ihr Witz von nur einer Maske<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn19">  This reference is anomalous in the present letter of August 12, 1927, for Hoboken's quip does not appear in the correspondence until his letter of August 28 (see OJ 11/54, [15]).  The possibility on the other hand that the letter may actually have preceded the present one, and that one of the letters is misdated, is ruled out by several other factors, such as the reference here to Oppel's plan to teach the Schenker approach in Leipzig, on which Hoboken comments in the August 28 letter.</tei:note> ist sehr gut - versicherte zuletzt, daß das Jahrb. noch im August ausgedrückt u. im September ausgegeben werden wird, ich glaube es aber nicht: wer weiß auch, was die Druckerei noch im "Anhang" anstellen wird.  O, wie steht diese Druckerei tief unter <tei:hi rend="italic">Waldheim &amp; Eberle</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn20">  Click on <ref cRef="waldheimeberle">Waldheim-Eberle</ref>.  </tei:note> in Wien in Hinsicht solcher Arbeiten!  Die Generalbaßziffer zB. 6 oder 5<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn21">  Both numbers have strokes, indicating raising of the respective intervals.</tei:note> ist nicht zu erreichen, immer heißt es [<tei:hi rend="italic">natural sign</tei:hi>] für [<tei:hi rend="italic">sharp sign</tei:hi>], u. alle Korrekturen führen nicht zum Ziel.  Sie hat keine Ordnung, sie weiß nie, wohin das oder jenes gehört.  Usw.  Sollte es doch wahr werden, was der Verlag mitteilt, denn erfahren Sie es ja ohnehin.</tei:p><tei:p>Und nun ein paar Worte zu den Beilagen, die ich ohneweiteres wegzuwerfen bitte:</tei:p><tei:p>Blg 2 u. 3 (die Aufsätze des Wiener u. Berliner Ordinarius)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn22">  These enclosures are not filed with the letter.  The authors are not identifiable from the given descriptions.  </tei:note> <tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> In Gedanken u. Ausdruck unfertig wie ein Schulaufsatz &lt;strike&gt;eines&lt;/strike&gt; von Knaben, die noch nicht mutieren.  Ich übertreibe nicht, richtiger:  ich untertreibe nicht.  Gott denkt, unsere Meister denken, aber diese Volksschulknaben - lenken!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn23">  A play on the saying "Der Mensch denkt, Gott lenkt" ("man proposes, God disposes"), based on <tei:hi rend="italic">Proverbs</tei:hi> 16: 9.  Schenker sardonically turns it around: God--and our masters--think, but the leading is done by these schoolboys.  </tei:note>  Welche Welt!  Nachgerade dürfen wir diesen ecklen[<tei:hi rend="italic">recte:</tei:hi> eklen] Sündern gegenüber uns wie der gerechte Noah denken, inmitten solcher Sintflut bauen wir eine Arche hoch oben auf dem Ararat, füllen sie mit Kostbarkeiten, die drauß eine neue Welt wiedererstehen machen sollen, - wir dürfen uns freuen, dann, eben auch wie Noah, werden wir einmal, bis nur die Sintflut vorbei ist, Wein u. Wein u. Wein trinken dürfen, jene Bösewichte aber hat die Sintflut verschlungen.</tei:p><tei:p>Blg. 4 u. 5 sprechen von Originalen, Urtexten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn24">  These enclosures, and the others mentioned in this paragraph, are not filed with the letter.  The diary indicates that there were seven enclosures in all.  </tei:note>  Der Rest der Beilagen sind sozusagen Heiterkeiten.  Die Notiz über die "schwarzen Sänger" bringt die Wahrheit an den Tag.  Der Musiker, der die Neger-Chöre gesetzt hat, wie Sie sie uns auf Ihrem Grammophon vorgeführt haben, ist heute <tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> als ein wahres Musik<tei:hi rend="italic">genie</tei:hi> zu bezeichnen, es würde lohnen, zu erfahren, wer das ist: er verdient einen ersten Platz unter den Musikern, jedenfalls vor Strauss u. Pfitzner.</tei:p><tei:p>Für Schindlers' Erstdruck<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn25">  Probably meaning the first edition of Anton Schindler, <tei:hi rend="italic">Biographie Ludwig van Beethovens</tei:hi> (Münster, 1840; 2/1845; 3/1860).  See OJ 89/1, [1], dated July 3, 1927.</tei:note> vielen Dank.  O, da habe ich Ihnen viel Wichtiges zu sagen, was aber nur am Klavier geschehen kann.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn26">  At least some of these many important remarks were published posthumously in Heinrich Schenker, "Ein Kommentar zu Schindler, Beethovens Spiel betreffend," <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Dreiklang</tei:hi> 8/9 (1937-38), pp. 190-199. See also Oswald Jonas, "Nachtrag zu Schenkers Aufsatz über Schindler," ibid., pp. 200-207.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>An H. Deutsch schrieb ich nach Nürnberg, wer weiß, ob er schon dort ist, ob ihn die Karte erreicht.</tei:p><tei:p>So.  Viel Vergnügen wünschen wir Ihnen u. Ihrer Frau Gemalin in der Schweiz, viel Erfolg Ihnen auf der Kunstreise!</tei:p><tei:p>Für Ihre frdl. Zustimmung in der Honorarfrage danke ich verbindlichst, auf [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte:</tei:hi> auch] für den Modus, den Sie beabsichtigen.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich u. meine Frau grüßen auf das herzlichste.</tei:p><tei:p>Der junge <tei:hi rend="italic">Cube</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn27">  Click on <ref cRef="cube_felixeberhard_v">Felix-Eberhard von Cube</ref>.  </tei:note> ist seit paar Tagen hier u. bleibt noch längere Zeit.</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] HSchenker
12.8.27</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to van Hoboken dated August 12, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Mr. van Hoboken,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Many thanks for your kind letter,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> so patiently perseverant, whose precision, like every instance of  precision, gave me such pleasure.  I would have inquired long ago as to the health of your wife except that a card from the architect Jaray,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> who had asked me in the first days of July for your "current address," made me suspicious and obliged me to wait until you showed some sign of life and found an address.  Now I see that you stayed with the first plan and that Jaray's inquiry came at a time when you were by design away from Vienna, which I admittedly could no longer remember so exactly.  (At the time, though, I referred Jaray to your Vienna address.)  Having become uncertain, I neglected to find out <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> whether the state-authorized vandals at your Vienna house have not done some mischief.  In view of your accurate assessment of the situation I shall forgo a rehearsal of my painful feelings; who knows whether I could manage to walk or drive through the so badly damaged section of the Ringstrasse.</tei:p><tei:p>And now let me take up the points of your letter in order:  you may take well-earned satisfaction in having so advanced Haydn's cause with your very beautiful collection of first editions.  Would God but grant that strokes of good luck kept pace with what you are striving for,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> which we all still owe Haydn--where on earth could his things be hiding!  The musicians and amateurs who dare to stand before this star, this extraordinary demon, with their empty phrases, have not even honor enough to thank him for providing them the occasion for phrases that they certainly would never be able to dream up in such abundance about Haydn's forerunners and contemporaries.  No doubt that Haydn, who today has sunk to the level of child-performers, will one day rise again from the children <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> to the adults, as basically the rarest and most adult people of all belong to his circle.</tei:p><tei:p>My letter to (Dr.) Furtwängler<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> may have followed him about for some time, for I subsequently learned from a newspaper that exactly at that time he was traveling with <tei:hi rend="italic">his orchestra</tei:hi> evening after evening (!) from city to city (!) in Germany.  Thus far I have no word from him, which, however, does not rule out the possibility that he received my letter.  That's how it is with F.; perhaps he even thinks quite highly of himself--in any case he is one of those people who self-deceptively take for granted that everybody views them just as favorably, and always just as favorably, as they view themselves.  Enclosure 1)<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> shows a put-down that is on target, but F. is certainly the last one who can understand it--he will only suppose an injustice there.  Nevertheless--the attempt must be made.  How lovely it would be if he put on the concert bill, for example, Mozart, Symphony in G minor, "after the first-edition parts from André" (and of course then played correctly)!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> I am just now sending your "Appeal"<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> to Dr. Haas.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/>  As I read it again, I find it very good, as I did the first time.  Mr. Deutsch's<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> suggestion in footnote 1 I find <tei:hi rend="italic">excellent</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/>  Would it not be advisable for Mr. Deutsch to <tei:hi rend="italic">read out</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">your</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Appeal on Radio Vienna</tei:hi>, and if necessary add a few amplifications?  Radio access is always open to Mr. Deutsch, otherwise I could also be of help there with my relationship to Prof. Dr. Richtera.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/></tei:p><tei:p>Your travel plan commands my full admiration.  The well thought-through quality, the unhurried but determined pursuit of the goal--it reads nicely and one is comfortable with it.  I hope Koch<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> in Frankfurt will be favorably disposed!  He likes nice things.  The exhibition in Frankfurt--and I read the <tei:hi rend="italic">Frankfurter</tei:hi> [<tei:hi rend="italic">Allgemeine</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">Zeitung</tei:hi> very carefully--has at least for me more the flavor of a music-<tei:hi rend="italic">ethnological</tei:hi> exhibition, so to speak, than of an exhibition of music as true art.  In the opinion of the Frankfurters, obviously everything is "art" which <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> is tootled, twanged, or grunted anywhere in the world--the artists of Ischgl<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> and Galtür<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/> too would very probably have been at home there.  Art, however, is not so democratic.</tei:p><tei:p>I come now to Prof. Dunn,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn15"/> whom you also have on the program.  Here a bouquet of surprises:</tei:p><tei:p>At the end of July Prof. Dr. Oppel<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn16"/> from Kiel visited me here.  He has been engaged at <tei:hi rend="italic">Leipzig</tei:hi> to teach theory, and there will implement my system completely--harmony, counterpoint, analysis etc.  He too is a pupil of <tei:hi rend="italic">Knorr</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn17"/> thus a student-colleague of yourself, although older, as he is 48.  Besides, he knows Dunn too <tei:hi rend="italic">very well</tei:hi>, from years-long personal association; he credits him with the most scrupulous accuracy.  Prof. Oppel will visit me at the end of December in Vienna; perhaps the opportunity will arise for you to meet him as well.</tei:p><tei:p>The second <tei:hi rend="italic">Yearbook</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn18"/> which you so kindly had planned to give him, can scarcely be available by the date you mentioned.  I was to receive, they said, a finished copy on <tei:hi rend="italic">June</tei:hi> 25 <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> -- still in Vienna--, then a great silence (with one single exception) set in--no confirmation, no replies--finally a promise of the final page-proofs for August 10, but this date too passed without any arrival.  The press--your quip about only one mask<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn19"/> is very good--assured me finally that the <tei:hi rend="italic">Yearbook</tei:hi> would still be printed in August and distributed in September, but I don't believe it: who knows what the press will still get up to in the "Appendix"?  Oh, how far behind this press is in comparison to Waldheim &amp; Eberle<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn20"/> in Vienna with repect to such works!  The thoroughbass figure 6 or 5,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn21"/> for example, is not available; [<tei:hi rend="italic">sharp sign</tei:hi>] always has to be represented as [<tei:hi rend="italic">natural sign</tei:hi>], and any corrections are made in vain.  They have no routine, they never know where this or that belongs.  Etc.  Should it be true, though, what the publisher tells me, then you will hear of it anyway.</tei:p><tei:p>And now a word or two about the enclosures, which you may immediately discard:</tei:p><tei:p>Enclosures 2 and 3 (the essays of the Vienna and of the Berlin Professor)<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn22"/> [are] <tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> unformed in thought and expression like a school-essay by pre-adolescent boys.  I do not overstate--or more correctly, I do not understate.  God thinks, our masters think, but these schoolboys--they lead!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn23"/>  Such a world.  We may think of these miserable sinners like the righteous Noah, in the midst of such a flood let us build an ark high up on Ararat, fill it with treasures, which are to make a new world arise--then we can be happy, just like Noah, until the flood is over, we may drink wine, wine, and more wine, but the flood has trapped those monsters.</tei:p><tei:p>Enclosures 4 and 5 concern originals, Urtexts.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn24"/>  The rest of the enclosures are, so to speak, frivolities.  The notice about the "black singers" shows the state of affairs today.  The musician who assembled the negro choruses that you played for us on your phonograph today <tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> has to be called a true music <tei:hi rend="italic">genius</tei:hi>; it would be worth while to know who that is: he deserves a first place among musicians, certainly ahead of Strauss and Pfitzner.</tei:p><tei:p>Many thanks for Schindler's first edition.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn25"/>  Ah, I have many important things to say to you on that, but it can be done only at the piano.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn26"/></tei:p><tei:p>I wrote to Mr. Deutsch in Nuremberg, but who knows whether he is already there, or whether the card reached him.</tei:p><tei:p>Well then.  We wish you and your wife a pleasant time in Switzerland, and much success to you on your art-journey!</tei:p><tei:p>Thank you so much for your agreement on the honorarium question, and also for the procedure that you intend to use.</tei:p><tei:p>Warmest greetings from me and my wife.</tei:p><tei:p>Young Cube<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn27"/> has been here a few days and will stay a while longer.</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] H. Schenker
August 12, 1927</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>