<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OC 1/34r : 2-24-18 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription Ian Bent, 2006.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1918-1935) - - Schenker, Jeanette (1935-1938) - -Oster, Ernst (1938-c.1939)—New York Public Library (c.1939-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Under investigation; Image: New York Public Library, New York; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 02/24/1918 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: &quot;DeutschS ~ HSchenker&quot;,&quot;T&#195;&#188;rkel ~ HSchenker&quot; --><dc:title>Handwritten draft letter from Schenker to Türkel, dated February 24, 1918</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-09-25</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Addresses legal obstructions regarding Sofie Deutsch's will, and threatens to go back on an earlier disclaimer if he continues to be deprived of the inheritance due to him; notifies Türkel that S has already paid out the first stipend, to Otto Vrieslander, and has promised the second and third to two composers (unnamed).  

</dc:description><dc:subject> Schenker, Heinrich;  Türkel, Siegfried;  Deutsch, Sofie;  Sophie;  Verzicht;  disclaimer;  Figdor, Frau;  legacy; honorarium;  stipend;  Rothschild, Alphons;  pension;  Mendl, Fritz;  Wiener Bank-Verein;  Vienna Bank Association;  Vrieslander, Otto;  Ebersberg;  München;  Munich;  Korngold, Julius;  Japan;  Berlin;  Vienna;  Friedmann, Hugo</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten draft letter, Schenker to Türkel, dated February 24, 1918</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>24. II. 1918
Sehr geehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Indem ich Ihnen bestens dafür danke, daß Sie mich des Weges zu Ihnen überhoben haben, der -wäre- mir heute ^ohnehin^ unausführbar ^gewesen war^ –, beeile ich mich, Ihnen postwendend<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Evidently S had received a communication from Türkel; none is known to have survived.</tei:note> den von mir schon am 1. 6. 1917 abgegebenen Verzicht hiemit -zum zweitenmal u. wieder auch schriftlich zu bestätigen- <tei:hi rend="italic">..........eln</tei:hi>[.]  Abgesehen davon, daß ich der Frau Figdor ^durchaus^ nicht im Wege stehen -will- ^mag^ (umsoweniger, als diese Dame Ihrer Mitteilung gemäß seinerzeit gegen das Akkreditiv keine Einwände ihrerseits erhob), will ich jeden Prozess <tei:hi rend="italic">vermeiden</tei:hi>, in dem ich unter Anführung von Zeugen den Nachweis dafür erbringen müßte, daß ich den Betrag des Akkreditivs -im gewissen Sinn- ^eigentlich^ schon mit meinen Leistungen vorausgegeben, u. durch das Versagen des Schriftstückes ^auch außerdem^ beträchtlichste Schaden – zumal mitten im Kriege – erlitt.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich würde, sehr geehrter Herr Doktor, den Verzicht -gewiß- ^wohl^ auch sonst wiederholt haben, auch wenn Sie [<tei:hi rend="italic">moved up from next line:</tei:hi> nicht in der Lage gewesen wären[,]] mir den günstigen Stand der Legatsfrage (allerdings unverbindlich) mitzuteilen.  [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from lower margin:</tei:hi> Nach all den gemachten Erfahrungen bin ich heute -nach mir- auf dieser Frd. Eröffnung gegenüber nur praktisch.]  Den Verzicht sprach ich -schon- seinerzeit ^eben schon^ aus den -oben- erwähnten Gründen aus;  muß -ich- ^mir^ aber freilich vorbehalten, darauf gelegentlich auch öffentlich zurückzukommen für den Fall, daß ich über den Gerüsten, <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> die mir die Erbschaft nach der Verewigten ^ganz oder teilweise^ zu schieben u. zu denen sie durch ihre ^große^ Schätzung meiner Leistung unschuldigste Veranlassung gegeben haben mag, noch weiteren Schaden leiden müssten.  Wie ich schon einmal lange, lange Schaden dadurch leiden mußte, daß man mir blos daraufhin, daß ich den jungen <tei:hi rend="italic">Baron Rothschild</tei:hi> unterwies, eine Rente aufdichtete, von der ich weder damals noch heute je eine Spur gesehen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  It is well known that Baron Alphons Rothschild paid the publication costs of S’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> and <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt I</tei:hi>.  Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern ...</tei:hi> (Hildesheim: Olms, 1985), does not mention a pension.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Bei dieser Gelegenheit erlaube ich mir, Ihnen auch mitzuteilen, daß ich am 5. Januar als dem Sterbetage der Frau Deutsch aus den Mitteln des mir ^seinerzeit^ durch den H. Kammerrat Mendl<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Fritz Mendl, Sofie Deutsch’s brother, leading Austrian industrialist.</tei:note> frdl. -zudienten- ^ausbezahlten^ Beilegates den <tei:hi rend="italic">ersten Betrag</tei:hi> durch den <tei:hi rend="italic">Wiener Bankverein</tei:hi> an H. <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Otto Vrieslander</tei:hi></tei:hi>, Tonkünstler in <tei:hi rend="italic">Ebersberg</tei:hi> b. München<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.</tei:note> zur Auszahlung gebracht habe.  Damit lüfte ich ^endlich^ das Geheimnis der Ursache, weshalb ich seinerzeit gerade auf diesem Legat mehr ^als^ auf meinem eigenem Honorar bestand: die “dritte Person,“ von der ich Ihnen seinerzeit <tei:hi rend="italic">sub rosa</tei:hi> schrieb, bin nämlich ich selbst.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Sofie Deutsch left S a legacy of 5,000 Kroner to support the printing costs of future publications, and a pension of 2,000 Kroner a year;  : see OC 12/52, January 12, 1917 (Mendel to S).</tei:note>  Gewissermaßen lag eine Notwehr der Ehre vor, nicht nur meiner eigenen, sondern auch ^die^ der Frau Deutsch wie des H. Kammerrates.  Sie erinnern sich, daß ich keine Lust hatte, die <tei:hi rend="italic">Stipendien</tei:hi>sache anzugehen, u. daß ich mich hiezu ^nur^ durch unendliches Zureden von des H. Kammerrats Seite wie von der Ihren bestimmen ließ.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  S’s doubts about the viability of the stipends are expressed in his letter to Hugo Friedmann, OC 1/19–20, March 12, 1917, in which he says that he has expressed these also to Fritz Mendel and Siegfried Türkel.</tei:note>  Angesichts des Schreibens des H. Kammerrats an mich, wie dann auch angesichts des Vorhaltens im Mündlichen hatte wohl ich am wenigsten Ursache, je am Zustandekommen der Sti- <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> pendien ^überhaupt^ zu zweifeln. Nun einmal aber in der Sache, verfügte ich über das <tei:hi rend="italic">Stipend</tei:hi>ialgeld so, wie es Frau Deutsch von mir erwarten konnte u. wohl auch erwartet hat: statt zweifelhafte[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] Produkte zu prämieren, <tei:hi rend="italic">bestellte</tei:hi> ich ^lieber^ bei -bei- zwei angesehenen Künstlern mir wichtig scheinende Arbeiten u. sagte einem dritten Künstler, dessen Namen Sie wohl oft genug in Korngold’s<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Julius Korngold (1860–1945), eminent Austrian music critic, Hanslick’s successor at the <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue Freie Presse</tei:hi>, conservative in outlook.</tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Feuilletons</tei:hi> nebst Zitaten aus seinen autoritativen Urteilen gefunden haben mögen, u. dem Frau Deutsch selbst für die Dauer ihrer Reise nach Japan ihre eigenen Stunden <tei:hi rend="italic">zu übergeben vorhatte</tei:hi>, (der auch Referent einer der angesehnsten Tagesblätter in <tei:hi rend="italic">Berlin</tei:hi> ist) aufs bestimmteste zu, ihm den Aufenthalt in Wien durch das Stiftungsgeld zu erleichtern, wo ich dann freilich den Unterricht selbst nur unentgeltlich erteilen wollte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  third composer: [identify].</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Diesen Herren gegenüber nannte ich ^nun^ <tei:hi rend="italic">mit</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Namen</tei:hi> die <tei:hi rend="italic">Quelle der</tei:hi> Bescherung – ich mußte es schon darum tun, weil ich nicht in den Verruf auch noch eines Geldmäzens kommen wollte, wo ich als Mäzen des Unterrichts ohnehin überbürdet bin.  Als die Zweifel auftauchten, war es zumindest vor <tei:hi rend="italic">diesen</tei:hi> drei Herren <tei:hi rend="italic">zu spät</tei:hi>, einzulenken oder zurückzutreten.  Ein anderes war dort, wo ich nach Fühlungnahme mit einzelnen Vorlagen mich gleichwohl auf keinen Autor, kein Werk noch festlegte.</tei:p><tei:p>Der Betrag leitete auf 1020 MK, auf den dritten Teil <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> jenes Legates[.]  Am nächsten 5. Jänner soll dann der nächste Musiker drankommen, u. endlich -am überreichsten-, als dritter, der <tei:hi rend="italic">Berliner</tei:hi> Künstler.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich konnte leider nicht anders, wie Sie es wohl auch selbst zugeben werden.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit besten Empfehlungen Ihr ergebener
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">unsigned</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>P. S. Sie werden mich ^sehr g. H D^ sehr verbinden, wenn Sie in Ihrem Zuschrift an Dr. Friedm.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Hugo Friedmann: attorney involved with the estate of Sofie Deutsch.</tei:note> den Verzicht <tei:hi rend="italic">auch von dem Tage</tei:hi> ^1. 6. 1917^ <tei:hi rend="italic">aus, d.......</tei:hi>, an dem ich ihm schrieb zum 1. Male gegeben habe – sofern dies nicht irgendwie wider Ihren Interessen streitet.  Mir läge an dieser Feststellung <tei:hi rend="italic">sehr viel</tei:hi> für jetzt sowohl als für später.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten draft letter, Schenker to Türkel, dated February 24, 1918</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>February 24, 1918
Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>In thanking you most warmly for having eased my access to you, which ^ had without that been^ impossible for me recently, I hasten by return post<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> herewith -for the second time and once again in written form to confirm- to <tei:hi rend="italic">.........</tei:hi>[?] the disclaimer already surrendered by me on June 1, 1917.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  Apart from the fact that I -will- ^may^ ^by no means^ stand in the way of Mrs. Figdor<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> (all the less so as in accordance with your communication the latter lady raised no objections at the time on her own part against the letter of credit), I will <tei:hi rend="italic">avoid</tei:hi> any legal proceeding that would have required my putting forward evidence by summoning witnesses [to show] that I have -in the strict sense- ^in fact^ already given the amount of the letter of credit in advance with my accomplishments, and [have] ^in addition also^ suffered the most considerable damage—what’s more, in the midst of the war—through the failure of the piece of writing.</tei:p><tei:p>I would, dear Doctor, -certainly- ^surely^ otherwise have repeated the disclaimer, even if you [<tei:hi rend="italic">moved up from the next line:</tei:hi> had not been in a position] to convey to me (at any rate without obligation) the favorable position on the legacy question.  [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from the lower margin:</tei:hi>  In the light of all the experiences I have had, I am today merely being practical as regards this kind granting of access.]  I gave my disclaimer purely for the reasons -already- then stated -above-;  but I must freely reserve ^to myself^ the right to go back on it, possibly even publicly, in the event that I were to have to suffer still further damage with respect to the frameworks[?] <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> that may deprive me ^in part or whole^ of the inheritance [due] to me in accordance with the deceased’s wishes, and to which she through her ^high^ valuation of my accomplishments may wholly unintentionally have given rise.  How once before I had to suffer damage for a long, long time as a result of the fact that a pension was conjured up[?] for me purely on the basis that I gave lessons to the young Baron Rothschild, a pension of which I neither then nor to this day have ever seen a penny.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/></tei:p><tei:p>I also take this opportunity to inform you that, on January 5, i.e. the death date of Mrs. Deutsch, I disbursed out of the resources of the part-legacy[?] kindly ^paid out^ to me ^at that time^ by Chamber Counsellor Mendl<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> the <tei:hi rend="italic">first</tei:hi> sum through the <tei:hi rend="italic">Vienna Bank Association</tei:hi> to Mr. <tei:hi rend="italic">Otto Vrieslander</tei:hi>, composer, of Ebersberg, nr. Munich.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/>  In so doing, I ^at long last^ lift the veil of secrecy from why I at the time insisted on precisely this legacy more ^than^ on my own honorarium: for it is I myself who am the “third person” of whom I wrote to you at the time <tei:hi rend="italic">sub rosa</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>  To a certain degree I had in mind a defense of honor, not only my own but also ^that^ of Mrs. Deutsch as well as of the Chamber Counsellor.  You will recall that I had no desire to take on the matter of the stipends, and that ^only^ through endless persuasion on the part of the Chamber Counsellor, as too from yourself, did I let myself be talked into it.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/>  Faced with the Chamber Counsellor’s letter to me, and then also faced with its being held up to me in conversation, I surely at least had cause to doubt ^altogether^ that the stipends would ever be viable.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> But once committed to the matter, I dispensed the stipend money in the manner in which Mrs. Deutsch had reason to expect me, and indeed did expect me, to do;  instead of awarding it to questionable products, I <tei:hi rend="italic">bestowed</tei:hi> it ^by preference^ upon two reputable composers whose works appeared to me important, and promised a third composer, whose name you may quite frequently have encountered in Korngold’s<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> feuilletons along with quotations from his authoritative opinions, and to whom Mrs. Deutsch herself <tei:hi rend="italic">had contemplated giving over</tei:hi> her own lesson[-hours] for the duration of her journey to Japan ([and] who is the critic for one of the most highly respected daily papers in Berlin), quite specifically that I would facilitate his stay in Vienna by means of money from the foundation, in which case I myself then fully intended to give him instruction free of charge.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/></tei:p><tei:p>^Now,^ I divulged to these gentlemen <tei:hi rend="italic">by name</tei:hi> the <tei:hi rend="italic">source</tei:hi> of the award—I had to do that because I did not want to get a bad name for myself [by appearing to be] a benefactor of money when I am in any case overburdened as a benefactor of instruction.  As the doubts arose, it was <tei:hi rend="italic">too late</tei:hi>, at least in the cases of <tei:hi rend="italic">these</tei:hi> three gentlemen, to deviate or to go back on the commitment.  It was a different matter in cases where after the initial approach to individual potential candidates I nevertheless did not commit myself to any one composer or any one work.</tei:p><tei:p>The sum amounted to 1,020 Marks, i.e. one third <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> of that legacy.  On January 5 next, the second musician should have his turn, and finally as the third the Berlin composer.</tei:p><tei:p>Unfortunately, I could not have done otherwise, as you yourself will admit.</tei:p><tei:p>With best wishes, Yours truly,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">unsigned</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>P. S. I should be greatly obliged to you, ^dear Doctor,^ if in your letter to Dr. Friedmann<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> you would  <tei:hi rend="italic">refer to</tei:hi>[?] my disclaimer <tei:hi rend="italic">also</tei:hi> [speak] <tei:hi rend="italic">of the day</tei:hi> ^June 1, 1917^ on which I wrote to him for the first time—so long as this does not conflict in any way with your interests.  <tei:hi rend="italic">A very great deal</tei:hi> for now as well as for later would hang[?] on this determination for me.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>