<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OC 1 B/35-40 : 6-10-19 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  In the public domain
©  Transcription Ian Bent, 2009
©  Translation Ian Bent, 2009
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2009.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Universal Edition Archive (1919-1976) - -on permanent loan to the Wienbibliothek im Rathhaus (1976-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: Universal Edition, A.G.; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 06/10/1919 05:22:45 PM --><!-- MT Tags: "Hertzka ~ HSchenker","UE ~ H+JSchenker","UE ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten draft letter from Schenker (in Jeanette's hand) to Hertzka (UE), undated [June 10, 1919]</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-05-09</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Schenker promises to send Hans Weisse to see Hertzka. In reacting unfavorably to Hertzka's suggestions that the Foreword to Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven ... op. 111 be discarded for its second edition, Schenker puts up a stout defense of his use of polemic in his writings, contending that art and all manifestations of human life are inextricably interconnected. He claims that his pronouncements on politics now will prove correct in the long run. His sole concern is with the truth; he is not interested in pandering to his readers.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Hertzka, Emil; UE;  Weisse, Hans;  Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven;  Vorwort;  Foreword;  Op. 111;  Kleine Bibliothek;  Little Library;  Beethoven sonatas;  Kontrapunkt2;  Counterpoint2;  polemics;   truth;  chauvinism;  England;  France;  Italy;  Serbia;  Czechoslovakia;  America;  Aristotle;  Lessing, Gotthold Ephraim;  Hamburgische Dramaturgie;  Lloyd-George, David;  Clemenceau, Georges;  Wilson, Woodrow;  Weingartner, Felix</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten draft letter from Schenker (in Jeanette's hand) to Hertzka (UE), undated [June 10,1919]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">This transcription gives only the first stage of the draft, i.e. that which Heinrich Schenker dictated to Jeanette.  His subsequent revisions of Jeanette's longhand copy, many of which are illegible, have not been included.  This draft should be compared with WSLB 303, the final version of the letter received by UE.</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{1 = 35r}</tei:hi>
[<tei:hi rend="italic">top left corner (Heinrich's hand:</tei:hi>]
[<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>]
Hertzka<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Drafting of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/14, p. 2079, June 10, 1919 (hence the date proposed here):  "An Hertzka (Br.): wegen des Vorwortes (liegt im Copierbuch)."  ("To Hertzka (letter): concerning the Foreword (is in the copybook).")  Dispatch of the letter in its final form (=WLSB 303) is recorded at OJ 2/14, p. 2080, June 13.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">Jeanette's hand:</tei:hi>]
Es dürfte wohl das Vernünftigste u. Kürzeste sein, wenn ich Ihnen den jungen Dr. mus.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.  </tei:note> (samt opus) zuschicke, was in Bälde geschehen wird.</tei:p><tei:p>Weitmehr aber als Ihre Klage über Papiernot u. erhöhte Kosten<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> in OJ 52/923, June 6, 1919.  </tei:note> hat mich Ihr mein op. 111|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Schenker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven ... op. 111</tei:hi> (Vienna: UE, 1915).  </tei:note> betreffendes P. S. erschreckt.  Meinerseits noch zu mehreren Arbeiten bereit, wie z.B. zur „Kleinen Bibliothek",<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="kleine_bibliothek">Kleine Bibliothek</ref>.  </tei:note> zum Abschluß der Sonatenserie,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  i. e. Schenker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven</tei:hi>, 4 vols (Vienna: UE, 1913, 1914, 1915, 1920).  </tei:note> ja sogar zu einer Ausgabe der Klaviersonaten von Beethoven,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  i. e. <tei:hi rend="italic">L. van Beethoven: Klaviersonaten nach den Autographen und Erstdrucken rekonstruiert von Heinrich Schenker</tei:hi>, 4 vols (Vienna: UE, 1921-23).  </tei:note> fühle ich mich nur schon in der Bereitschaft wie gelähmt wenn ich befürchten muß, daß auch nur nachträglich meine Gedankengänge irgendwelchen Interessen geopfert werden könnten!  Ich bin gewohnt so zu denken u. zu schreiben, wie der Stoff es fordert;  es kann mir also niemals widerfahren, daß ich etwas zu bereuen oder zu widerrufen hätte.  Auch dort, wo es für oberflächliche Betrachter den Anschein haben könnte, als hätte ich ein falsches oder ungerechtes Urteil abgegeben, braucht es eben nur der Zeit, damit man sich die Nachwelt von der Sicherheit meines Urteils überzeuge.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich erachte es nicht für des Lesers Sache, zu wissen, ob ich mit Recht oder Unrecht auch den Krieg in die Debatte <tei:hi rend="bold">{2 = 36r}</tei:hi> gezogen habe, denn meine Gründe gehen so ins Tiefe, daß er weder fürs erste noch fürs tausendste begreifen könnte, weshalb ich es getan.  Erst bis mein Gesamtwerk in Erscheinung getreten ist, wozu ich natürlich auch alle noch zu veröffentlichenden Arbeiten zähle, wird man vielleicht zu beurteilen vermögen, weshalb ich den Zusammenhang der Musik mit allen übrigen Lebensäußerungen so hoch veranschlagt habe.  Sie verstehen, daß mich aus eben diesem Grunde die augenblickliche Empfindung des Lesers gar nicht interessiert u. ich am allerwenigsten wohl geneigt wäre, seiner persönlichen oder nationalen Eitelkeit Rechnung zu tragen.  Es muß der Leser den Autor interessieren, nach dessen Werk er langt, um eine Belehrung zu empfangen, die er bis dahin nicht kannte:  Bin ich es, der ihn am besten belehrt, dann muß er sich darein fügen, wie ich ihn zur Wahrheit führe, u. sei sie ihm persönlich noch so unangenehm.  Oder aber er - lasse das Werk stehen u. gehe als Esel durch die Welt!  Selbst die Wahrheit verliert an Wucht, wenn man sie Allen u. Jedern nach ihrer niedern[?] Fasson mundgerecht machen will.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3 = 37r}</tei:hi> Ich treibe Wahrheit, aber nicht „Chauvinismus" u. wenn ich dem Deutschtum den höchsten Rang zugewiesen habe, so waren darin bis zum Kriege mit mir sogar unsere Feinde einig.  Im Laufe des Krieges wurden nur[?] die Feinde um eine Million Grade infamer, aber meine Wahrheit nicht um einen Grad „chauvinistischer".  Ich will noch damit gesagt haben zur Belehrung, nicht zur Beleidigung wenn ich zu verstehen gegeben habe, daß ein Beethoven bis ans Ende aller Zeiten niemals, niemals in England, Frankreich, Italien, Serbien, Czechien, geschweige denn in Amerika, dem letzten aller Kulturländer je verstanden werden könnten.  Denn schärfe ich so dem Leser die überhohe Bedeutung des Meisters ein, so erwirbt er die Fähigkeit von ihm zu lernen, widrigenfalls [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>] die Beethoven-Predigt bagatellisiert weil  er glaubt, es hätte andererswo ähnliche Köpfe wie Beethoven schon gegeben oder würde es demnächst gehen können.  Wie Sie sehen, mache ich es um den Scherz zu wagen mit meinen Arbeiten nur dem Verleger billig, aber niemals meinem Leser.  Ich dulde es niemals, daß der Leser von meinem Tische auf- {<tei:hi rend="bold">4 = 38r}</tei:hi> steht mit dem Gefühl er hätte dies alles schon früher gewußt, u. daß er soeben von mir beschenkt, auch mich richte.  Ich schreibe, wie gesagt, nicht für die Gegenwart, sondern - um es mit vollem Bewußtsein auszusprechen - für Jahrtausende, da man mich als allereinzige Quelle für die Blüte-Epoche der Musik zu schätzen wissen wird etwa wie z.B. Aristoteles als Quelle für griechisches Wesen.  Daher greife ich ins Volle der Zusammenhänge u. verschmähe es, des Lesers Eitelkeit zu ködern.  Uebrigens bin ich überzeugt, daß die absolute Rücksicht, die ich wider die Wahrheit übe der Weiterverbreitung des Werkes förderlicher ist, als es die Rücksicht gegenüber Lesern.  Es hat einem Lessing durchaus nicht geschadet, wenn in seiner vielgelesenen „Hamburgische Dramaturgie"<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Gotthold Ephraim Lessing, <tei:hi rend="italic">Hamburgische Dramaturgie</tei:hi> (1767), a treatise on poetry and drama, which can be seen as a new interpretation of Aristotle's theory of drama.  </tei:note> bis zum heutigen Tag z.B. der Satz: „wie englisch, wie unanständig" stehen geblieben ist u. die vielen Verspottungen der Franzosen, die doch wieder nicht als deutschen Chauvinismus von Lessing zu betrachten sind, sondern vielmehr als Wahrheit.  Und was lesen Sie sonst nicht alles bei allen unsern großen Meistern an Kritiken fremder Nationen so scharf als möglich!?  Was geht die Meister eine Rücksicht an <tei:hi rend="bold">{5 = 39r}</tei:hi> Haben sich je Franzosen ein Blatt vor den Mund genommen, um[?] auch nur eine Lüge in die Welt zu schleudern?</tei:p><tei:p>Und was speziell das Vorwort zu op. 111 anlangt, so steht doch die Sache so, daß selbst unsere Tagesblätter einen Sieg der Entente<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  (Triple) Entente:  the alignment between Great Britain, France, and Russia agreed in 1907 as a counter force to the Triple Alliance of Germany, Austria-Hungary, and Italy.  </tei:note> nur mit Gänsefüßchen anführen, d. h. ihn eben nicht für einen Sieg halten.  U. dies ist ja erst eine journalistenhafte Betrachtung.  Den Sieg aber von dem ich gesprochen, bezog sich ja nicht [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>] auf die Siege auf den Schlachtfeldern, die ja auch nicht wegzuleugnen sind, sondern auch noch auf andere höherer Art.  Und ob ich nun darin Recht habe, den Sieg der Deutschen prophezeit zu haben, überlasse ich nicht dem Leser im Jahre 1920 zu beurteilen, sondern erst dem vom Jahre 2000.  Habe ich denn nicht bezüglich Wilsons<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Click on <ref cRef="wilson_woodrow">Woodrow Wilson</ref>.  </tei:note> Recht behalten, u. bezüglich der Engländer?  Nun aber genug.  Ich bin also durchaus nicht [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>], nicht einverstanden, sondern bitte Sie ausdrücklich, die Ausgabe so stehen zu lassen, wie sie aus meiner Feder gekommen ist:  ich trage gern u. stolz die Verantwortung für jedes Wort, ja ich habe sogar vor, in den künftigen <tei:hi rend="bold">{6 = 40r}</tei:hi> Arbeiten mir Rechte zu nehmen, wie sie sich Menschen herausgenommen haben, denen es mit weniger als mir zugekommen ist, wozu ich eben auch die Wilson, Lloyd-George,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Click on <ref cRef="lloyd_george_david">David Lloyd-George</ref>.  </tei:note> Clemenceau<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Click on <ref cRef="clemenceau_georges">Georges Clemenceau</ref>.  </tei:note> rechne, einschließlich Weingartner<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  Click on <ref cRef="weingartner_felix">Felix Weingartner</ref>.  </tei:note> u. wie sie alle heißen mögen.  Musik ist ja - vergessen Sie es nicht, lieber Herr Direktor - keine Angelegenheit eines häuslichen oder öffentlichen Konzertes, einer Privatstunde, eines Konservatoriums, sondern eine eminent öffentliche Angelegenheit.</tei:p><tei:p>Uebrigens freut es mich, daß Sie so weit sind, eine II. Auflage veranstalten zu können, da ich mir sonst nicht zu erklären könnte, wie Sie das Vorwort vom Texte loslösen wollten.</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">unsigned, undated</tei:hi>]</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten draft letter from Schenker (in Jeanette's hand) to Hertzka (UE), undated [June 10,1919]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">This transcription gives only the first stage of the draft, i.e. that which Heinrich Schenker dictated to Jeanette.  His subsequent revisions of Jeanette's longhand copy, many of which are illegible, have not been included.  This draft should be compared with WSLB 303, the final version of the letter received by UE.</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{1 = 35r}</tei:hi>
[<tei:hi rend="italic">top left corner (Heinrich's hand:</tei:hi>]
[<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>]
Hertzka<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">Jeanette's hand:</tei:hi>
It would clearly be most sensible and efficacious if I were to send the young PhD (Mus.)<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> to you (together with his opus), and this I shall do forthwith.</tei:p><tei:p>However, your P.S. concerning my <tei:hi rend="italic">Op. 111</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> has given me a far bigger fright than your lament about scarcity of paper and increased costs.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  Prepared as I remain to contribute several works, such as for example the <tei:hi rend="italic">Little Library</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> the completion of the already begun sonata series,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> indeed even an edition of the Beethoven piano sonatas,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> I feel as if my legs had already been cut from under me in my preparedness on the purely theoretical front if I must fear that even my trains of thought could subsequently be sacrificed in the interests of something else.  I am accustomed to thinking and writing solely as the material itself demands.  That way, I should never live to regret or have to revoke something.  Even where to superficial observers it might appear as if I had pronounced a false or incorrect verdict, it will be only a matter of time before posterity will be convinced of the rectitude of my viewpoint.</tei:p><tei:p>I do not consider it a matter for my reader to know whether or not I am right or wrong in having drawn the war into my line of argument, <tei:hi rend="bold">{2 = 36r}</tei:hi> for my reasons run so deep that he could not possibly even begin to fathom why I had done it.  Only when my entire life's work has been completed (among which I of course count all those works yet to be published) will people perhaps be in a position to judge why I have rated so highly the organic relationship between music and all other manifestations of human life.  You must understand that, for this very reason, the feelings of the individual reader at this particular moment do not interest me in the slightest, and least of all would I be inclined to take account of his personal or national vanity.  The reader must interest himself in the author whose work he takes up, in order to assimilate a [body of] instruction of which until then he knew nothing.  If I am the only one who can best instruct him, then he must just submit to that by which I lead him toward the truth, however uncongenial he may personally find it.   Otherwise, let him drop the work, and go through life as an ass!  Even the truth loses weight if after their lower fashion they want to render it palatable to anybody and everybody.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3 = 37r}</tei:hi> I pursue truth, but never "chauvinism," and if I have accorded the highest status to Germanity, then even our enemies would have agreed with me on that up until the war.  In the course of the war, our enemies became a million times more infamous;  but my truth did not become one iota more "chauvinistic."  It was to instruct the reader and not to insult him that I gave him an understanding that a Beethoven could never, never, not until the end of time, have been understood in England, France, Italy, Serbia, Czechoslovakia, let alone America, the worst of all cultural lands.  For if I impress upon the reader the supreme importance of the master, he then acquires the ability to learn from him, failing which he belittles the Beethoven sermon because he believes that otherwise figures similar to Beethoven have already existed somewhere or would be able to exist in the near future.   As you can see, with my works--if I may venture a joke--I make things easy only for the publisher, never for my reader.  I never tolerate the reader getting up from my table <tei:hi rend="bold">{4 = 38r}</tei:hi> with the feeling that he already knew all of this and that albeit[?] it has just been presented by me, he is ahead of[?] even me.  As I have said, I do not write for the present time, but--to articulate it with full consciousness--for millenia, when people will learn to value me as the one and only source for the supreme epoch of music, rather like, for example, Aristotles as the source for the Greek way of life.  This is why I delve into the relationships [between art and life] in all their fullness, and repudiate all pandering to the reader's vanity.  Incidentally, I am convinced that the uncompromising approach that I practice in respect to the truth is more advantageous to the wide dissemination of my work than the approach that privileges readers.  It has done a Lessing not the slightest harm that, for example, the phrase "how English, how unseemly" has stood the test of time in his widely read <tei:hi rend="italic">Hamburg Dramaturgy</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> to the present day, and the many expressions of derision of the French, which are again not to be considered as German chauvinism by Lessing, but rather as the truth.  And what do you not read elsewhere in all our great masters by way of criticism of foreign nations [that is] as harsh as could possibly be?  So when did the masters ever hesitate?  Have Frenchmen ever minced matters <tei:hi rend="bold">{5 = 39r}</tei:hi> when spreading even just one lie far and wide?</tei:p><tei:p>And as specifically concerns the Foreword to <tei:hi rend="italic">Op. 111</tei:hi>, the situation is such that even our daily papers report a victory of the Entente<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> only within quotation-marks, i. e. they do not consider it to be a victory.  And this is merely the journalist's way of looking at it.  However, the victory about which I have spoken did not at all relate to victories upon battlefields (which can certainly not be denied), but to those of an even higher order of things.  And whether I was right to prophesy the victory of the Germans I leave not to the reader in the year 1920 to judge, but to that of the year 2000.  Have I not already been proved right regarding Wilson?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/>  But that's enough of that.  So I completely disagree;  instead, I ask you expressly to leave the edition exactly as it is, just as it came from my pen:  I stand by every word gladly and proudly, indeed I even intend in my future <tei:hi rend="bold">{6 = 40r}</tei:hi> works to take liberties just as other people have taken whom it befits even less than it does me, among whom I count even the Wilsons, Lloyd-Georges,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> Clemenceaus,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> including Weingartner,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> and whatever else their names may be.  Music is truly--and don't you forget it, dear Director--not the business of a domestic or public concert, of a the private lesson, of a conservatory, but a pre-eminent public business.</tei:p><tei:p>By the way, I am delighted that you have reached the point at which you can arrange for a second edition--I could see no other way to interpret the fact that in the very case of <tei:hi rend="italic">Op. 111</tei:hi> you were wanting to detach its Foreword from its text.</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">unsiged, undated</tei:hi>]</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>