<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 14/40[a] : 12-27-18 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Under inquiry.
© Transcription Ian Bent, 2006.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is presumed to be in the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1918-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 12/27/1918 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: &quot;DeutschS ~ HSchenker&quot;,&quot;T&#195;&#188;rkel ~ HSchenker&quot; --><dc:title>Typed letter from Türkel to Schenker, dated December 27, 1918</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-09-26</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Acks letter of December 25, 1918 [not surviving]; T distances himself from S's recent actions [over stipends];  S cannot count on restitution of money overspent;  these matters have nothing to do with T or the Deutsch estate. Encloses[?] copy of earlier "disclaimer" [= OJ 14/40[b]].

</dc:description><dc:subject>Türkel, Siegfried; Schenker, Heinrich;  Deutsch, Sofie; Sophie;  Mendl, Fritz;  stipends;  donations;  awards;  restitution;  Cession;  disclaimer</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Vienna VII, Mariahilferstrasse 26</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Vienna III</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Türkel to Schenker, dated December 27, 1918, with enclosed doc. = OJ 14/40[b]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>]
D^R^ SIEGFRIED TÜRKEL
HOF- UND GERICHTS-ADVOKAT
KANZLEI: VII. MARIAHILFERSTRASSE 26
EINGANG: VII. STIFTGASSE 1</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">left:</tei:hi>] TELEPHON AUT. 35052  [<tei:hi rend="italic">right:</tei:hi>] POSTSPARK.-KTO. NR 104651</tei:p><tei:p>Wien, 27, Dezember 1918.</tei:p><tei:p>T/K.
<tei:hi rend="italic">Betr.: S. Deutsch-Verl.</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Professor!</tei:p><tei:p>Im Besitze Ihres Schreibens vom 25/12.1918<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  No letter of this date from S to Türkel is known to survive; however, the substance of this letter corresponds in some ways to S’s draft letter of February 24, 1918, of which the final letter is not known to survive (if indeed it ever existed).</tei:note> erlaube ich mir zu bemerken, dass ich nicht recht verstehe, aus welchem Grunde Herr Professor<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Note the highly formalized and distancing language that Türkel adopts in this letter—especially the admixture of third- and second-person discourse (which has unavoidably been converted into second-person in translation)—which contrasts sharply with his previous communications to S.  The postscript is clearly an attempt to mitigate this distancing effect.</tei:note> mir diese Mitteilung machen.  Wenn Herr Professor aus eigenem[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] oder aus gesammelten Mitteln Spenden machen und Prämien verteilen, so ist das eine reine Privatsache von Ihnen, die mich als Ihren Vertreter eigentlich nicht interessieren darf.  Ich verstehe daher nicht, was Herr Professor damit meinen, wenn Sie davon sprechen, dass Sie auch heuer<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  <tei:hi rend="italic">heuer</tei:hi> : South German, Austrian, and Swiss usage.</tei:note> wie im Vorjahre der Verpflichtung, zu der Sie sich auf Grund der Ihnen gewordenen Mitteilungen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Presumably the letter (OJ 10/4, January 12, 1916) and word-of-mouth instructions (mentioned in OC 1/19–20, March 12, 1917, draft letter from S to Friedmann) given to S by Sofie Deutsch herself. </tei:note> berechtigt fühlen dürften, nachgekommen sind.  Auf Ersatz solcher, ohne irgendwelche Ermächtigung von Ihnen verausgabter Beträge dürfen Sie begreiflicherweise nicht rechnen.  Ich habe mir seinerzeit schon mündlich erlaubt, Herrn Professor darauf aufmerksam zu machen.  Ich habe Sie aufgeklärt, dass Sie keine Verpflichtung trifft und dass Sie daher auch keine <tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> Berechtigung haben, in fremdem Namen irgendwelche Zahlungen zu leisten und daher auch kein Recht auf irgendwelchen Rückersatz haben.</tei:p><tei:p>Unter diesen Umständen verstehe ich aber auch nicht, wozu Sie mich als Ihren Vertreter von diesen privaten Aktionen, die mit der Angelegenheit Deutsch und mit meiner Vertretung Ihrer Person nichts zu tun haben, verständigen.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich erlaube mir, dieses Schreiben an Sie deshalb zu richten, damit durch eine widerspruchslose Empfangnahme Ihres Briefes meinerseits in Ihnen nicht der Irrtum entstehe, dass Sie zu irgendwelchen Zahlungen heute verpflichtet oder berechtigt seien.  Selbstverständlich was Sie im eigenen Namen ohne Anspruch auf Rückersatz machen, ist Ihre Sache aber geht mich gar nichts an.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich begrüsse Sie
hochachtunsvoll
Ihr sehr ergebener:
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  <tei:hi rend="italic">Türkel</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>wohlgeboren Herrn [/] Prof. Dr. Heinrich Schenker,
<tei:hi rend="italic">Wien III.</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">handwritten in pencil above, to the right of, and below the address:</tei:hi>]
Lieber Hr Professor,
Ich bitte Sie diesen Brief nicht als Unfreundlichkeit aufzufassen.  Ich möchte aber gerne jedes Misverständnis vermeiden 
....gruß  Ihr Türkel</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">[<tei:hi rend="italic">Copy of typed document,</tei:hi> &lt;a href="../../../../disclaimer/oj<tei:hi rend="italic">1440b</tei:hi>060117.html"&gt;OJ 14/40[b]&lt;/a&gt;, <tei:hi rend="italic">probably enclosed with this letter</tei:hi>]</tei:hi></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter from Türkel to Schenker, dated December 27, 1918, with enclosed doc. = OJ 14/40[b]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead:</tei:hi>]
D^R^ SIEGFRIED TÜRKEL
IMPERIAL AND COURT ADVOCATE
CHANCELLRY: VII. MARIAHILFERSTRASSE 26
ENTRANCE: VII. STIFTGASSE 1</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">left:</tei:hi>] TELEPHONE AUSTR. 35052  [<tei:hi rend="italic">right:</tei:hi>] POST OFFICE BANK A/C NO. 104651</tei:p><tei:p>Vienna, December 27, 1918</tei:p><tei:p>T/K.
<tei:hi rend="italic">Re: S. Deutsch Estate</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor,</tei:p><tei:p>In receipt of your letter of December 25, 1918,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> I take the liberty of observing that I do not rightly understand for what reasons [you,] Professor[,]<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> give me this information.  If [you,] Professor[,] make donations and distribute awards out of your own or collective resources, then that is a purely private matter for yourself, which really ought to be of no interest to me as your representative.  I therefore do not understand what [you,] Professor[,] mean by saying that this year<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> as well as last year you have fulfilled the duty which you feel it your right [to carry out] on the basis of communications made to you.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  Needless to say, you ought not to count on restitution of such amounts as have been overspent by you without any authorization.  I took the liberty of drawing this to your attention in person, Professor, at the time.  I made clear to you that no obligation is placed on you, and accordingly that you also have no <tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> entitlement to make payments of any sort in another’s name and accordingly also have no right to restitution of any kind.</tei:p><tei:p>But under these circumstances I also do not understand why you notify me, as your representative, of these private actions, which have nothing to do with the Deutsch matter and with my representation of your person.</tei:p><tei:p>I take the liberty of addressing this letter to you so that, with a grasp of your letter on my part that is free of contradiction, the error may not be incurred on your part that you are obligated or entitled today to payments of any sort whatsoever.  It goes without saying that anything you do by way of restitution in your own name or capacity is your affair and has nothing to do with me.
	
With greetings,
and kind regards,
Yours very truly,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  Türkel</tei:p><tei:p>Professor Heinrich Schenker, Esq.,
<tei:hi rend="italic">Vienna III.</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">handwritten in pencil above, to the right of, and below the address:</tei:hi>]
Dear Professor,
I beg you not to construe this letter as an unfriendly act.  I should, however, like to avoid any misunderstanding.
... greeting, Yours, [ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Türkel</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">[<tei:hi rend="italic">Copy of typed document,</tei:hi> &lt;a href="../../../../disclaimer/oj<tei:hi rend="italic">1440b</tei:hi>060117.html"&gt;OJ 14/40[b]&lt;/a&gt;, <tei:hi rend="italic">probably enclosed with this letter</tei:hi>]</tei:hi></tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>