<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="instrumentations-tab">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Instrumentations-Tabelle (<hi rend="italic">Instrumentation Table</hi>), by Artur Niloff [<hi rend="italic">pseud.</hi> of Heinrich Schenker] (Universal Edition, 1908; UE 1999)</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="instrumentations-tab">Instrumentations-Tabelle/Niloff</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>25/06/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Work</term>
          <term subtype="basename">instrumentations-tab</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Instrumentations-Tabelle (<hi rend="italic">Instrumentation Table</hi>), by Artur Niloff [<hi rend="italic">pseud.</hi> of Heinrich Schenker] (Universal Edition, 1908; UE 1999)</head>
      <div>
        <!-- BODY: -->
        <p><hi rend="bold">Instrumentations-Tabelle (<hi rend="italic">Instrumentation Table</hi>), by Artur Niloff [<hi rend="italic">pseud.</hi> of Heinrich Schenker] (Universal Edition, 1908; UE 1999),</hi> wall chart of musical instruments, showing for each instrument its fundamental, overtones, range, sub-ranges, whole-and half stopping, notation, then an illustration and a repertory list, preceded by an introduction.  The table measures 199 x 62 cms (78&#xBC; x 24&#xBD; inches), and presents 83 instruments, including, in addition to the standard orchestral instruments, the saxophones, saxhorns, cornets, keyed bugles, fl&#xFC;gelhorn, and opheiclide.  It is perhaps the most popular and widely disseminated of all Schenker's published works, having sold in excess of 11,000 copies by the mid-1990s.</p>
        <p><hi rend="bold">Author's name</hi>
According to Federhofer, the pseudonym "Artur Niloff" (sometimes spelled "Niiloff" in correspondence), is a partial anagram of the last name of Schenker's closest friend, Moriz Violin.  Despite its authorship's having become known early in the work's history, the <hi rend="italic">Table</hi> has always been published under the pseudonym:  Schenker's name still does not appear in present-day editions.</p>
        <p><hi rend="bold">History of the work</hi>
Negotiations over the <hi rend="italic">Table</hi> were underway by September 11, 1906 with  <ref cRef="stritzko_joseph">Joseph Stritzko</ref>, the director of J. Eberle &amp; Co., and involved the music publisher Doblinger.   Details of the terms are shown in the diary entry OJ 1/5, p. 19, September 13, 1906, when Stritzko wanted "possible and impossible trills" to be included.  Schenker reported that the <hi rend="italic">Table</hi> went to the printers on April 6, 1906 (ibid, p. 12), and it is unclear how much production work, if any, had been done when negotiations broke down shortly afterward over royalties.</p>
        <p><ref cRef="universal_edition">Universal Edition</ref> took over publication, releasing it first to schools with a small print-run in November 1908 (OC 52/28, November 11) to test the market, the Introduction signed "October 1908."  This was Schenker's first UE publication under <ref cRef="hertzka_emil">Emil Hertzka</ref>, and was evidently successful ("300 copies sold within three weeks in Vienna alone", CA 96-98, May 6, 1909), since Hertzka issued a public first edition three months later.  Apparently, French and English editions were announced in 1909 (ibid), but never happened.  For the 1909 edition, Schenker supplied "supplementary notes" on instrument classification, production of overtones, instrument families, and transposition, but these proved too extensive for publication and were not included until the second edition (1912).</p>
        <p><hi rend="bold">Editions</hi>
The editions produced before the World War II were as follows (some confusion exists as to the correct numbering of the editions):</p>
        <p>| <hi rend="bold">edn</hi> | <hi rend="bold">date</hi> | <hi rend="bold">print-run</hi> |
| schools | November 1908 | 500? |
|1st | February 6, 1909 | 2,000 |
| 2d |  May 7/August 23, 1912 | 2,000 |
| 3d | September 3, 1917 | 1,000 |
| 4th | November 9, 1920 | 1,000 |
| 5th | January 10, 1922 | 1,000 |
| 6th | October 25, 1925 | 1,000 |
| 7th | January 22, 1928 | 1,000 |
| 8th | January 11, 1933 | 1,000 |
| 9th | July 23, 1937 | 1,000 |</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most significant aspect of the <hi rend="italic">Table</hi>, apart from its general pedagogical application, is the prominence with which it promotes the technical details of 18th-century instruments, notably the oboe d'amore (citing examples from J. S. Bach and R. Strauss),  the natural horns and trumpets (citing Bach, Handel, Haydn, Mozart, and Beethoven).</p>
        <p><hi rend="italic">Bibliography:</hi>
Universal Edition Verlagsdruckb&#xFC;cher (UE Archive, Vienna)</p>
        <p>Hellmut Federhofer, <hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker nach Tageb&#xFC;chern und Briefen ...</hi> (Hildesheim:  Georg Olms, 1985), p. 30</p>
        <p>Bent, Ian, "'That Bright New Light': Schenker, Universal Edition, and the Origins of the Erl&#xE4;uterung Series, 1901-1910," <hi rend="italic">Journal of the American Musicological Society</hi>  58/1 (2005), 69-138, esp. 73, 83 [where Stritzko is wrongly identified with Hertzka]</p>
        <p><hi rend="italic">Contributor:</hi>  Ian Bent</p>
        <!-- EXTENDED BODY: -->
        <!-- EXCERPT: -->
        <!-- KEYWORDS: -->
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
