<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="kleine_bibliothek">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>XXXXX</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="kleine_bibliothek">Kleine Bibliothek</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>29/11/2007</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Work</term>
          <term subtype="basename">kleine_bibliothek</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>XXXXX</head>
      <div>
        <!-- BODY: -->
        <!-- EXTENDED BODY: -->
        <!-- EXCERPT: -->
        <p><hi rend="bold">Kleine Bibliothek [Little Library]</hi>:  Schenker&#x2019;s planned series of small volumes, each containing an analysis of a single work or group of works, often referred to as his &#x201C;pamphlets&#x201D; (<hi rend="italic">Flugschriften</hi>) or "little pamphlets" (<hi rend="italic">kleine Flugschriften</hi>).  First public announcement of this plan appeared in the Vorrede (Preface) to Schenker&#x2019;s monograph <hi rend="italic">Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie</hi> (Vienna: UE), released on or just after July 2, 1912:</p>
        <p>If my labors on my principal work leave me sufficient time, I contemplate describing, in a newly founded &#x201C;Kleine Bibliothek,&#x201D; with brief and concise words those necessities that hold sway in other masterworks by our geniuses.  And I hope thereby to be able to offer more substantial contributions to the study of composition than are found in modern textbooks.  (p. XII; trans. John Rothgeb, p. 8)</p>
        <p>One of the earliest indications of items intended for analysis comes in a letter of March 18, 1913 to Emil Hertzka of UE:  &#x201C;If we want to publish the Pamphlets under whatever title&#x2014;and we do both want to do so&#x2014;(for the [<hi rend="italic">Little</hi>] <hi rend="italic">Library</hi> there would be, for example, <hi rend="italic">Mozart</hi>'s G minor Symphony, <hi rend="italic">Brahms</hi>'s First (or Fourth) Symphony, <hi rend="italic">Chopin</hi>, several Etudes (the most frequently played and the most difficult), <hi rend="italic">Schubert</hi>, a few <hi rend="italic">Lieder</hi>, etc., etc.) then we could&#x2014;and we really <hi rend="italic">should</hi>&#x2014;give all the things that I want to offer an attractive gateway&#x201D; (WSLB 149: March 18, 1913).  (This suggests that the <hi rend="italic">Little Library</hi> was a subset of the <hi rend="italic">Flugschriften</hi>.)  Schenker had in mind &#x201C;3&#x2013;4 [pamphlets] a year, 40&#x2013;50 pages long&#x201D; (WSLB 211: May 5, 1914).</p>
        <p>Schenker&#x2019;s retrospective statement in a letter to Hertzka dated January 18, 1915 not only adumbrates the intended content, and details the economics, but also exposes the strategic purpose behind the project at that time:</p>
        <p>In pursuance of my overall plan ... I therefore offered you a "<hi rend="italic">Little Library</hi>."  In this, the ultimate truth would be told about our masterworks, and all the Kretzschmars, Spittas, Jahns, etc. would be confronted.  Just as Breitkopf &amp; H&#xE4;rtel sells Kretzschmar's analyses both singly at 20 Pfennigs, and has itself carried the three-volume work [...] through to its <hi rend="italic">5th</hi> edition (!!) within the shortest possible space of time, likewise, I thought to myself, UE should offer for sale, for example, my presentations of the Chopin Etudes:</p>
        <p><!-- bq. --> a) <hi rend="italic">singly</hi> at a price of 20 h. [Heller]
b) <hi rend="italic">by set</hi>:   Op.10, Op.25, and
c) <hi rend="italic">complete</hi>:    [Op.10 + Op.25].</p>
        <p>Just imagine the same scheme applied to Brahms's <hi rend="italic">four symphonies</hi>, <hi rend="italic">chamber music</hi>, songs, choral odes, and <hi rend="italic">piano pieces</hi>, to Mozart, Beethoven (III, V, VI, VII, VIII), etc, etc, and UE would have been able to take the whole of Germany by storm with my analyses, whose <hi rend="italic">superiority</hi> over those of Kretzschmar would by now <hi rend="italic">already have been recognized</hi> even <hi rend="italic">by my enemies</hi>.  (WSLB 236, p. 8)</p>
        <p>Schenker also suggested that &#x201C;the analyses could [...] even be offered <hi rend="italic">to the public</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">concert hall</hi> (just as Breitkopf und H&#xE4;rtel do with Kretzschmar's load of crap)&#x201D; (WSLB 242: February 26, 1915).</p>
        <p>That Schenker was actively realizing his plan is shown by diary entries such as the following from October 10, 1913:</p>
        <p>Sketches to the Chopin Prelude in F# minor for the <hi rend="italic">Little Library</hi>.</p>
        <p>No analysis of this work was ever published, but a series of undated sketches survives as OC 32/103&#x2013;107 (with a calendar page from September 21&#x2013;27, 1913 used as scrap paper).</p>
        <p>The <hi rend="italic">Little Library</hi> plan was offered to UE, and also to Breitkopf &amp; H&#xE4;rtel, Peters Verlag (September 15, 1916), and J. G. Cotta (CA 168-169, March 25, 1920) but made no headway, presumably on account of wartime and post-war conditions.  The formal title proposed to Peters and Cotta was:</p>
        <p><hi rend="italic">Kleine Bibliothek</hi> / Bl&#xE4;tter zum Zeugnis unwandelbarer / Gesetze der Tonkunst / einer neuen Jugend dargebracht / von / Heinrich Schenker
(<hi rend="italic">Little Library</hi>: Leaves in Witness of the Immutable Laws of Music, Offered to a New Generation of Youth by Heinrich Schenker)</p>
        <p>The project emerged after the war in modified form as a series of somewhat larger &#x201C;issues&#x201D; (<hi rend="italic">Hefte</hi>), each containing several work-analyses (many previously envisioned for the <hi rend="italic">Little Library</hi>), alongside theoretical articles, but now&#x2014;fueled by Schenker&#x2019;s anger at the Versailles Treaty of 1919&#x2014;with prominently placed polemical statements, under a title that parallels that for the <hi rend="italic">Little Library</hi>:</p>
        <p><hi rend="bold">Der Tonwille</hi> / Flugbl&#xE4;tter / zum Zeugnis unwandelbarer Gesetze der Tonkunst / einer neuen Jugend dargebracht von / Heinrich Schenker
(<hi rend="bold">The Will of the Tone</hi>: Pamphlets in Witness of the Immutable Laws of Music, Offered to a New Generation of Youth by Heinrich Schenker)</p>
        <p>The utilitarian appearance of these pamphlets (published by UE, but under the fictitious imprint of the &#x201C;Tonwille-Flugschriftenverlag&#x201D;) preserves some of the spirit of &#x201C;dispatches from the front line&#x201D; of the original intended publication.</p>
        <!-- KEYWORDS: -->
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
