<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="kleine_bibliothek">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Kleine Bibliothek</title>
        <title type="sub">Little Library</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="kleine_bibliothek">Kleine Bibliothek</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>29/11/2007</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Work</term>
          <term subtype="basename">kleine_bibliothek</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Kleine Bibliothek</head>
      <div>
        <p>Planned series of small volumes, each containing an analysis of a single work or group of
          works, often referred to as "pamphlets" (<hi rend="italic">Flugschriften</hi>) or "little
          pamphlets" (<hi rend="italic">kleine Flugschriften</hi>).</p>
        <div>
          <head>History of the Project</head>
          <p>The project can be traced back to 1910, when Schenker envisioned a third (never
            published) volume of his <title level="s">Neue Musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</title> entitled <title
              level="m">Niedergang der Kompositionskunst</title> (Decline of the Art of
            Composition). As a supplement to that volume, he planned a series, initially dubbed <hi
              rend="italic">Handbibliothek</hi> (pocket library), of short guides to individual
            works, to be published by <ref cRef="cotta_j_g">J. G. Cotta</ref> and inaugurated by a
            study of Beethoven’s Ninth Symphony. The latter, the only item of the series to
            materialize, as the monograph <ref cRef="beethovens_neunte_si"><title level="m"
                >Beethoven's Neunte Sinfonie</title></ref> (Vienna: UE), released on or after July
            2, 1912, included in its Vorrede (Preface) the first public announcement of the series:
            
            <cit><q>If my labors on my principal work leave me sufficient time, I
            contemplate describing, in a newly founded "Little Library," with brief and concise
            words those necessities that hold sway in other masterworks by our geniuses. And I hope
            thereby to be able to offer more substantial contributions to the study of composition
            than are found in modern textbooks. (p. XII; trans. John Rothgeb, p. 8)</q></cit></p>
          
          <p>One of the earliest indications of items intended for analysis comes in a letter of
            March 18, 1913 to <ref cRef="hertzka_emil">Emil Hertzka</ref> of UE:
            
            <cit><q>If we want to publish the Pamphlets under whatever title&#x2014;and we
            do both want to do so&#x2014;(for the <hi rend="italic">Library</hi> there would be, for
            example, Mozart's G minor Symphony, Brahms's First (or Fourth) Symphony, Chopin, several
            Etudes (the most frequently played and the most difficult), Schubert, a few Lieder,
            etc., etc.) then we could&#x2014;and we really <hi rend="italic">should</hi>&#x2014;give
            all the things that I want to offer an attractive gateway&#x201D; (WSLB 149: March 18,
            1913).</q></cit></p>

          <p>This suggests that the <title level="m">Kleine Bibliothek</title> was a subset of the
              <hi rend="italic">Flugschriften</hi>. Schenker had in mind "3&#x2013;4 [pamphlets] a
            year, 40&#x2013;50 pages long" (WSLB 211: May 5, 1914).</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Contents of Series</head>
          <p>Schenker's retrospective statement in a letter to Hertzka dated January 18, 1915 (WSLB
            236) not only adumbrates the intended contents, and details the economics, but also
            exposes the strategic purpose behind the project at that time:</p>
            
            <p><cit><q>In pursuance of my overall plan ... I therefore offered you a "Little
            Library." In this, the ultimate truth would be told about our masterworks, and all the
            Kretzschmars, Spittas, Jahns, etc. would be confronted. Just as Breitkopf &amp;
            H&#xE4;rtel sells Kretzschmar's analyses both singly at 20 Pfennigs, and has itself
            carried the three-volume work [...] through to its 5th edition (!!) within the shortest
            possible space of time, likewise, I thought to myself, UE should offer for sale, for
            example, my presentations of the Chopin Etudes:</q></cit></p>
            
          <p><cit><q>a) singly at a price of 20 Heller</q></cit></p>
          <p><cit><q>b) by set: Op.10, Op.25, and </q></cit></p>
          <p><cit><q>c) complete: [Op.10 + Op.25].</q></cit></p>
          <p><cit><q>Just imagine the same scheme applied to Brahms's four symphonies, chamber music, songs,
            choral odes, and piano pieces, to Mozart, Beethoven (III, V, VI, VII, VIII), etc, etc,
            and UE would have been able to take the whole of Germany by storm with my analyses,
            whose superiority over those of Kretzschmar would by now already have been recognized
            even by my enemies. (WSLB 236, p. 8)</q></cit></p>

          <p>Schenker also suggested that "the analyses could [...] even be offered to the public in
            the concert hall (just as Breitkopf und H&#xE4;rtel do with Kretzschmar's load of crap)"
            (WSLB 242: February 26, 1915).</p>
          <p>That Schenker was actively realizing his plan is shown by diary entries such as the
            following from October 10, 1913:
            
            <cit><q>Sketches to the Chopin Prelude in F# minor for the <title level="m"
              >Little Library</title>.</q></cit></p>
          
          <p>No analysis of this work was ever published, but a series of undated sketches survives
            as OC 32/103&#x2013;107 (with a calendar page from September 21&#x2013;27, 1913 used as
            scrap paper).</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head><title level="m">Kleine Bibliothek</title> to <title level="m">Tonwille</title></head>
          <p>The <title level="m">Kleine Bibliothek</title> plan was offered to UE, and also to
            Breitkopf &amp; H&#xE4;rtel, Peters Verlag (September 15, 1916), and J. G. Cotta (CA
            168-169, March 25, 1920) but made no headway, presumably on account of wartime and
            post-war conditions. The formal title proposed to Peters and Cotta was:</p>
          <p>Kleine Bibliothek | Bl&#xE4;tter zum Zeugnis unwandelbarer | Gesetze der Tonkunst |
            einer neuen Jugend dargebracht | von | Heinrich Schenker</p>
          <p>Little Library | Leaves in Witness of the Immutable | Laws of Music | Offered to a New
            Generation of Youth | by | Heinrich Schenker</p>
          <p>The project emerged after the war in modified form as a series of somewhat larger
            "issues" (<hi rend="italic">Hefte</hi>), each containing several work-analyses (many
            previously envisioned for the <title level="m">Kleine Bibliothek</title>), alongside
            theoretical articles, but now&#x2014;fueled by Schenker's anger at the Versailles Treaty
            of 1919&#x2014;with prominently placed polemical statements, under a title that
            parallels that for the <title level="m">Kleine Bibliothek</title>:</p>
          <p><hi rend="bold">Der Tonwille</hi> | Flugbl&#xE4;tter | zum Zeugnis unwandelbarer
            Gesetze der Tonkunst | einer neuen Jugend dargebracht von | Heinrich Schenker</p>
          <p><hi rend="bold">The Will of the Tone</hi> | Pamphlets | in Witness of the Immutable
            Laws of Music | Offered to a New Generation of Youth by | Heinrich Schenker</p>
          <p>The utilitarian appearance of these pamphlets (published by UE, but under the
            fictitious imprint of the "Tonwille-Flugschriftenverlag") preserves some of the spirit
            of "dispatches from the front line" of the original intended publication.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Ian Bent</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
