<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [39] : 4-29-34 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2006.
© Translation William Drabkin, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1934-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 04/29/1934 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated April 29, 1934</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-10-09</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>C has broken his silence; believes he is defeated: encloses letter from his employer; will try to enlist Furtwängler's support.  He is known as "the" Schenkerian; others now avoid S's name to protect themselves. Does S know of any possibility for him and his family in Austria? —Encloses graph.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  employers;  dismissal;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Spengel, Prof.;  Kaufmann, Theodor;  Germany;  graph</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Hamburg 13, Mittelweg 126, Ia/^II.^</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated April 29, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hamburg 13, Mittelweg 126, Haus Ia/^II.^
29.IV.34</tei:p><tei:p>Lieber, hochverehrter Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich habe lange geschwiegen, denn ich musste schweigend kämpfen.  Nun bin ich, glaube ich, unterlegen.  Ich haben Ihnen und der Wahrheit die Treue gehalten, solange meine Kräfte reichten.  Nun fürchte ich, bricht das Unheil auch über mich herein.  Der beilegende Brief meiner derzeitigen Brotherren<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Brotherren</tei:hi> = employers, but literally “the gentlemen who provide bread”.</tei:note> erübrigt jeden Kommentar!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  This letter does not appear to have survived in either OJ or OC.</tei:note>  Ich werde nicht kampflos weichen.  In diesen Tagen versuche ich durch Furtwängler Unterstützung von oben her zu erhalten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Furtwängler [create biogfile and link] did write to Cube, around August 9, 1934. Cube copied this letter at the start of a very long letter to Schenker, dated October 4, 1934.</tei:note>  Doch glaube ich nicht sehr an Erfolg, da mein letzter Brief an ihm (mit Bitte um Empfehlungsschreiben) unbeantwortet blieb.  Ebenso erhoffe ich mir wenig Hilfe von alteingesessenen Verehrern Ihrer Lehre (Prof.  Spengel<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Professor Spengel: probably refers to to the composer Julius Heinrich Spengel (1853-1936); his personal papers are preserved at the Brahms Institute of the State Music Conservatory in Lübeck.</tei:note> und Th. Kaufmann<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Theodor Kaufmann (1892-1972) was a Hamburg-based pianist, teacher and composer, who had studied with Busoni in Berlin. The Piano Sonata No. 1, a large and difficult one-movement work that  was among the few compositions to survive the Allied bombing of Hamburg in 1943, has recently been recorded. For further biographical details, see:  http://www.romana-hamburg.de/Theodor%20Kaufmann.htm (accessed June 9, 2008).</tei:note>), da dieselben gegen jene, die es in der Hand haben, nichts vermögen.  Ich bin nun mal bekannt als “der” Schenkerianer, und habe alles auszubaden, wenngleich andere schon zwanzig Jahre vor mir hier dasselbe lehrten; ihnen wird man nichts tun, den sie haben sich gehütet[,] Ihren Namen zu nennen, als es brenzlich wurde! Ich hoffe immer noch, dass mein Fall nicht sÿmptomatisch für Deutschland ist, sondern eine lokale kleine Machtprobe einiger anonÿm (naturlich!) arbeitender “Kollegen”, die mich auf diese Weise erledigen, und sich damit noch Verdienste erwerben.  Furtwängler muss sich nun entscheiden!  Hic Rhodus, hic salta!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Hic Rhodus, hic salta</tei:hi>, a Latinized form of the punch-line of Aesop's fable of the athlete who boasted of feats he never actually performed: "Here is Rhodes, here is where you [must] jump." Cube is using it to imply that Furtwängler must summon his moral courage and publicly proclaim that Schenker, a Jew, has made an important contribution to German musical culture.</tei:note> Ich glaube das Ergebnis vorauszuwissen!  Und aus diesem Grunde frage ich erstmalig informatorisch bei Ihnen an, ob Sie für mich eine Mögligkeit sehen, mit meiner Familie (im August werden wir selbdritt sein) der sicheren Vernichtung zu entgehen?  A propos: Noch ist die Gafahr latent, doch muss ich beizeiten Vorkehrungen treffen. Inwieweit Verwandtenhilfe und Furtwänglers Macht in- (oder ausserhalb) des Reiches in Frage kommen, will ich Ihnen mitteilen, sobald ich sondiert habe.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  No paragraph-break in original.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Zur beiliegenden Tafel: Das letzte Dritteil gefällt mir selber noch nicht!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Probably a voice-leading graph of the D major prelude from Bach’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Well-Tempered Clavier</tei:hi>, Book 1. Schenker’s brief response (postcard of May 8, 1934) is followed by a letter from Cube (June 2, 1934) in which a revised Ursatz is written into the body of the text.</tei:note>  Aber ich wollte den Brief abschicken, und allzuweit werde ich wohl nicht vorbeigeschossen haben.  Auch plagt mich heute Rheumatismus[,] dass ich nicht viel schreiben kann.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  No paragraph-break in original.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Noch dies: Ich hatte vor einem halben Jahr eine Unterredung mit Furtwängler, in der er Sie sehr überzeugt verteidigte – allerdings unter vier Augen. –</tei:p><tei:p>Mit herzlichsten Grüssen von Haus zu Haus
Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube.</tei:p><tei:p>P.S. 1) mein Bekenntnis zum neuen Deutschland wird an sich dadurch nicht berührt! –<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  See Cube’s letter, OJ 9/34, [37], May 11, 1933, in which he proclaims his allegiance to the new Germany for the first time.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">sideways in left margin:</tei:hi>]
P.S. 2) Für einen etwaigen Domizilwechsel kommt nur etwas +ganz Sicheres+ wenn auch +noch so bescheiden+ in Frage!</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated April 29, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hamburg 13, Mittelweg 126, Ia/^II.^
April 29, 1934,</tei:p><tei:p>Dear, most honoured master!</tei:p><tei:p>I have remained silent for a long time, for I had to struggle in silence. Now I am, I believe, defeated. I remained faithful to you and to the truth, so long as my powers were sufficient. Now I fear that disaster will befall me, too. The enclosed letter from those who at present employ me<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> requires no explanation!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> I shall not give way without a struggle. In the next few days I shall seek to gain support from above, from Furtwängler.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>. Yet I have little expectation of success, as my last letter to him (with a request for a letter of recommendation) went unanswered. I can look forward to as little help from old established admirers of your theory (Professor Spengel<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> and Theodor Kaufmann<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>), since they can do nothing against those who are in power. I am now generally known as <tei:hi rend="italic">the</tei:hi> Schenkerian and have to take the consequences for all of that, even though others were teaching the same thing twenty years before me; nothing will happen to them, because they have protected themselves by not mentioning your name when things began to heat up. I am still always hopeful that my case is not symptomatic for Germany, but rather a small, local test of power on the part of a few “colleagues” who are working anonymously (naturally!) to bring me down in this way and thereby gain some merits. Furtwängler must now make up his mind! <tei:hi rend="italic">Hic Rhodus, hic salta!</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> I believe that I can predict the result. And for this reason I am asking you for the first time for information as to whether you see a possibility in your vicinity for me and my family (in August there will be three of us), to avoid certain destruction. A propos: The danger is still only latent, yet I must take precautions in good time. The extent to which the help of relatives and Furtwängler’s power inside (or outside) the state will be useful is something I shall let you know as soon as I have taken soundings.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/></tei:p><tei:p>Regarding the enclosed graph: I am myself still not satisfied with the last third,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> but I wanted to send the letter, and I don’t believe I am so far off the mark. Also, rheumatism is plaguing me today, so I cannot write much.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/></tei:p><tei:p>Just one other thing: half a year ago I had a talk with Furtwängler in which he defended you with great conviction, at any rate privately.</tei:p><tei:p>Cordial greetings from my family to yours.
Your
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube</tei:p><tei:p>P.S. 1) My faith in the new Germany has not in itself been affected by this!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">sideways in left margin:</tei:hi>]
P.S. 2) For a possible change of domicile, only something +quite definite+ will do, even if it is <tei:hi rend="italic">only very modest</tei:hi>!</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>