<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [21] : 6-25-30 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin 2006.
© Translation William Drabkin, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1930-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 06/25/1930 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated June 25, 1930</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-10-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Acks vC 29 and offers mitigation for Vrieslander's non-acquaintance with the Urlinie (to which C has just introduced new violin teachers).  — Reports on Erich Voß, and on concert plans at Conservatory. — Reports on his teaching. — Threat of financial difficulties; he has offered his services to the Hochschule für Musik in Berlin.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  Vrieslander, Otto;  Urlinie;  Das Meisterwerk in der Musik;  Masterwork in Music;  Guttmann, Otto;  Voß, Erich;  Voss, Erich;  fathers;  Conservatory;  Hochschule für Musik, Berlin;  Charlottenburg;  Schreker, Franz;  Variations;  sonatas;  Beethoven;  teaching;  Duisburg</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Duisburg</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated June 25, 1930</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">upper left corner: stationery motif comprising crown above shield</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>Duisburg, den 25.VI. 30.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Zuvor vielen Dank für Ihren Brief, und den Artikel von Vrieslander.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> Probably Vrieslander “Heinrich Schenker,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Kunstwart</tei:hi> XLIII (June 1930), pp. 181–89.  Jeanette made a note of this essay in Schenker’s Scrapbook,OC2/p. 80);  the article survives, part-photocopy, in OJ 58/21.  Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.</tei:note> Wenn Vrieslander der Urlinie noch nicht in dem Maasse nahegekommen ist, wie Sie es wünschen würden, so mag es meines Erachtens nach darin begründet sein, das er von niedersächsisch schwerbeugsamer Art ist, somit sich dem stärkeren Neuen nicht geschmeidig beugt, sondern, vielleicht in unbewussten Widerstand, versucht, einiges seiner eigenen, etwas dogmatischen Persönlichkeit mit in den neuen Zustand hinüberzuretten, durch welchen frommen Selbstbetrug natürlich die Erkenntnisfähigkeit getrübt wird.  Doch fürchte ich nicht, das die Leser des Artikels sich von solch subtilen Erwägungen leiten lassen werden; denn – ist Vrieslander immerhin schon im nächsten An- <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> [<tei:hi rend="italic">pasted in upper left corner: published</tei:hi> &lt;a href="../../../../../review/guttmannmeisterwerk.html"&gt;Review of “ Das Meisterwerk”</tei:hi>&lt;/a&gt;] ziehungsbereich der Urlinie, so bewegen sich seine Leser immer noch in Siriusfernen[,] wie Figura zeigt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> An arrow in the text points to a &lt;a href="../../../../../review/guttmannmeisterwerk.html"&gt;Review of <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>&lt;/a&gt;, which has been pasted on to the page.  Beneath the review, Cube has indicated the source as the <tei:hi rend="italic">Deutsche Tonkünstlerzeitung</tei:hi>, volume 11.  It is clear from the text of the review, given below, that the reviewer had the first two volumes of <tei:hi rend="italic">Meisterwerk</tei:hi> to hand. </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Herr Voss ist inzwischen bei mir “eingekehrt”.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> Erich Voss, a young musician who encountered Schenker’s theories through Cube’s visit to Cologne, and who went to Vienna in the hopes of studying with Schenker: see also OJ 9/34, [18], May 14, 1929; vC 23, May 15; vC 24, July 6, 1929;  vC 25, July 14; OJ 9/34, [19], July 18, 1929.  Voss does not appear in S’s Lesson Books.</tei:note>  Er ist eben auch ein Opfer derVerhältnisse, und muss nun in der Nähe suchen, was ihm anfänglich in die Ferne zog.  Soviel ich herausbekommen habe, spielen da auch Differenzen mit seinem Vater eine Rolle.   (Oh, diese Väter!)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> Cube is alluding to the difficulties he had with his own father, especially concerning lessons with Schenker in Vienna.</tei:note>  Ich wollte Ihnen schon früher Mitteilung gemacht haben, schob aber den Brief mit dem Termin eines Konzertes immer weiter hinaus.  Nun ist der Brief im Entstehen, das Konzert ist aber endgültig auf den Herbst verlegt worden.  Es handelt sich um einen Abend der “Hauskomponisten” des Konservatoriums, von diesem als Schülerabend veranstaltet. Ich stehe <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> auf dem Programm mit meinen Variationen, sowie beiden Sonaten.  Die entstehenden Hohlräume werden (konzessionsweise) mit Liedern meiner Komponierkollegen ausgefüllt; (auf dass einen jeden ein Strahl der Publikumssonne treffe[.)]  Es ist so unerträglich im Schatten zu bleiben.  Dabei werde ich nie gefragt, wenn mal die ander[en] was veranstalten.  Nach dem Motto:  Der eigene Hund macht keinen Lärm – – er bellt blos.  Das ganze Konzert wird von Schülern bestritten [–] gute Könner, es wird viel Reiz haben, – und ich eine Menge Arbeit vorher. –</tei:p><tei:p>Eine unserer frischgebackenen Geigenlehrerinnen bat mich, mit ihr Beethovensonaten zu spielen.  Ich nahm an, und die Gelegenheit wahr, ihr auf den Urliniezahn zu fühlen.  Am dritten Abend kam die Erleuchtung über sie, und allbereits stürmt sie mit den üblichen, viel zu grossen Schritten ins neue Land hinein.  Ich will abwarten, wie lange die Begeisterung vorhält, ehe ich registrier[e:] Wieder eine Seele gerettet! – <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Mit der Oberklasse mach ich jetzt auch strengen Satz und leichte Analysen.  Im Seminar wird es jetzt Mode, an meinen Vorlesungen teilzunehmen.  Die Hörer mehren sich – zu meiner Freude;  (ob auch zu der der Seminartheoristen bleibt dahingestellt.) –</tei:p><tei:p>Im Allgemeinen leide ich zur Zeit an den Auswirkungen unserer fabelhaften Finanzreformen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> In the late spring of 1930 the government of Heinrich Brüning, Chancellor of the Weimar Republic, was unsuccessful in gaining a majority vote in the Reichstag for a financial reform bill designed to curb unemployment and the steep rise in unemployment insurance payouts.  Article 48 was invoked, allowing the bill to be passed without a parliamentary vote, but in July 1930 the Reichstag voted to invalidate it anyway.  (The consequent political turmoil led to the dissolution of the Reichstag and the call for new elections, at which the National-Socialists and Communists made great gains at the expense of the more moderate parties.)</tei:note>  Noch habe ich ein Dach überm Kopf und satt zu essen.  Aber manche kleine Bequemlichkeit ist schon dem Pleitegeier zum Opfer gefallen.  Ich hätte nichts dagegen, gelegentlich Duisburg wegzukommen.  Neulich habe ich – mit Protektion – meine Dienste der Charlottenburger Hochschule (Direktion Schreker)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6"> This is the Hochschule für Musik in Berlin, where the composer Franz Schreker was the director.</tei:note> angeboten, aber noch keine Antwort bekommen.  Sollten Sie in Wien mal was erfahren, wäre ich Ihnen für einen Wink dankbar.  Duisburg ist gut genug als Sprungbrett, aber es bietet keine anderen Entwicklungsmöglichkeiten, als auf das Ableben seiner Vordermänner zu warten.</tei:p><tei:p>Für heute beste Grüsse Ihnen und Ihrer Frau Gemahlin, auch den Türtschers,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7"> Acquaintances of the Schenkers in Galtür, mentioned in Cube’s letter OJ 9/34, [13], July 6, 1928.</tei:note> von</tei:p><tei:p>Ihrem
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated June 25, 1930</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">upper left corner: stationery motif comprising crown above shield</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>Duisburg, June 25, 1930</tei:p><tei:p>Most honoured master,</tei:p><tei:p>To begin with, many thanks for your letter, and for Vrieslander’s article.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  If Vrieslander is not as intimate in matters concerning the Urlinie as you would have hoped, then I believe this might be based on the fact that he is a rather inflexible Lower Saxon type and thus does not bow gracefully before that which is new and stronger; rather, and perhaps with an opposition of which he is unconscious, he tries to salvage things by incorporating something of his own, somewhat dogmatic personality in the new situation, through which pious self-deception his power of understanding naturally becomes blurred.  But I do not fear that the readers of his article will be misled by such subtle considerations; for even if Vrieslander is already in the nearest <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> [<tei:hi rend="italic">pasted in upper left corner: published</tei:hi> &lt;a href="../../../../../review/guttmannmeisterwerk.html"&gt;Review of “ Das Meisterwerk”</tei:hi>&lt;/a&gt;] field of gravitational pull to the Urlinie, his readers are still as distant as Sirius, as the attached illustration shows.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/></tei:p><tei:p>Mr Voss has, in the meantime, “returned.”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  He, too, is a victim of the economic situation, and must now seek at close hand that which initially directed him afar. So far as I have been able to make out, disagreements with his father also played a part in this. (Oh, these fathers!)<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  I wanted to tell you this sooner, but kept postponing the letter until the date of a concert.  Now I am writing the letter, but the concert is definitively postponed until the autumn.  It will be an evening of “house composers” of the Conservatory, organized as an evening of Conservatory pupils.  I will be represented <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> on the programme with my Variations, and both sonatas.  The gaps that arise will be plugged (as a concession) with songs of my composition colleagues, so that a ray of audience sunshine might fall upon each of them: it is so unbearable to remain in the shadows.  I am never asked when the others organize something.   As the saying goes, “One’s own dog makes no sound, he merely barks.”  The entire concert will be performed by our pupils—the ones with ability—there will be a lot of charm, and I will have a lot of work to do beforehand.</tei:p><tei:p>One of our newest violin teachers asked me to play Beethoven sonatas with me. I accepted, aware of the opportunity to give her a taste of the Urlinie.  On the third evening the light fell upon her, and already she was marching—with far too large steps, as usual—into the new territory.  I shall wait to see how long the inspiration remains before I declare:  Another soul has been saved!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> With the advanced class, I am also doing strict counterpoint and elementary analysis.  Here at the Conservatory it has become fashionable to take part in my lectures at the Conservatory.  The listeners increase in number, to my delight.  (Whether this is also to the delight of the Conservatory theorists is something one cannot say.)</tei:p><tei:p>In general, I am suffering from the consequences of our fabulous financial reforms.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  I still have a roof over my head, and enough to eat.  But many small pleasures have fallen victim to the vulture of bankruptcy.  I would have nothing against leaving Duisburg, should the chance arise.  Recently I have—with support—offered my services to the Conservatory in Charlottenburg (where Schreker is the director),<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> but have not yet had a reply.   If you should hear about anything in Vienna, I would be thankful for a hint.  Duisburg is good enough as a springboard, but it offers no further possibilities for development, except to wait for one’s superiors to die.</tei:p><tei:p>For today, best greetings to you and your wife, and also to the Türtschers,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> from</tei:p><tei:p>Your  [ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>