<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [2] : 8-14-26 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2006.
© Translation by William Drabkin 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1926-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 08/14/1926 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated August 14, 1926</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-05-29</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>C is having difficulty getting his father to pay S for lessons given in previous year, and asks S to write firmly to the latter; speaks of his attempts to make contacts within Düsseldorf artistic circles.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard Düsseldorf;  von; Schenker, Heinrich;  Cube, Gustav von;  father;  Urlinie;  Stravinsky;  Düsseldorf;  Sternheim, Carl</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  "Hennenhof"</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated August 14, 1926</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>“Hennenhof”, den 14.VIII.26.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Meine Bitten und Vorstellungen meinem Vater gegenüber haben bisher keinerlei Erfolg gezeitigt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> Cube’s lessons with Schenker, which began in late 1923, were cut short in early 1926 when his father Gustav recalled him to Duisburg, citing financial hardship. Apparently, not all the lessons had been paid for, though Schenker had presumably been in touch with either Cube or his father (or both) about the missing payments.</tei:note> Es liegt dies meiner Meinung nach weniger an mangelndem guten Willen, als an seiner derzeitigen Nervosität, die ihn an falschen Orten geizen lässt. Da er aber faktisch im Stande ist, Ihre Forderungen zu erfüllen, und die Dringlichkeit derselben sich nur nicht plausibel machen lässt, möchte ich Sie bitten, sich einmal selbst in bestimmendem Tone an ihm zu wenden, worauf der Erfolg meines Erachtens nach nicht länger ausbleiben kann! –</tei:p><tei:p>Sie können sich vorstellen, wie unendlich peinlich mir das alles ist, zumal ich es derzeit nicht wagen kann, zwischen meinem Vater und mir bestehende Meinungsdifferenzen auf die Spitze zu treiben, denn die Gefahr einer Entfremdung besteht nun einmal seit seiner Verheiratung, obgleich ich mich mit meiner kleinen Stiefmutter wie mit einer Schwester verstehe, und sie mir auch in der gegenwärtigen Angelegenheit zu helfen sucht, so gut es ihr ihre neunzehn Jahre eingeben. –</tei:p><tei:p>Darf ich Sie also nochmals ersuchen, meine Bemühungen um eine galante Auflösung dieser Dissonanz durch ein Schreiben an meinen Vater zu unterstützen. –</tei:p><tei:p>Mit meinem “Fach” habe ich auch einige Last. Hier sehe ich mich vollends auch mich selbst gestellt. Die hartnäckige Sparsamkeit, die Nervosität und der Zeitmangel meines Vaters lähmen und verzögern viele meiner Unternehmungen; immerhin habe ich in diesen Dingen manches durch resolutes Auftreten meiner “kleinen Mama” erreicht. Ich brauche Bewegungsfreiheit, und die <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> kostet Geld, und solches ist aus dem guten Papa derzeit schwerer herauszuholen, denn die Urlinie aus einem Werk von Strawinsky.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> Schenker’s antipathy to Stravinskian neoclassicism is enshrined in a brief analytical counterexample in <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi> 2 (1926), pp. 17–18. Although Cube did not yet have any copies of Masterwork, he may well have heard the Stravinsky example, and his teacher’s opinion of it, during one of his lessons.</tei:note> –</tei:p><tei:p>Hoffentlich kann ich Ihnen bald etwas Positives bezüglich meiner musikalischen Anstrengungen mitteilen, und sei es auch nur auf einem Gebiet wie Tanz oder Revue. Ich probiere eben <tei:hi rend="italic">alles</tei:hi>. –</tei:p><tei:p>Neuestens habe ich Fühlung mit Düsseldorfer Künstlerkreisen durch die erste Frau meines Onkels Carl Sternheim<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> Carl Sternheim (1878-1942), German playwright and novelist, best known for his comedies, of which <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Hose</tei:hi> (“The Underpants”, 1911) was the most widely acclaimed.</tei:note> bekommen, was mir von Wichtigkeit scheint.  Leider sind noch viel zu viel Leute auf dem Lande. Vor September ist gesellschaftlich nicht viel los. –</tei:p><tei:p>Einstweilen also viele herzliche Grüsse Ihnen und Ihrer Frau, und seien Sie wegen der Dissonanz um Gottes Willen nicht gram</tei:p><tei:p>Ihrem
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Felix v. Cube.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated August 14, 1926</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hennenhof, August 14, 1926</tei:p><tei:p>Most honoured master!</tei:p><tei:p>My pleas and representations to my father have hitherto resulted in no success at all.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> The reason for this, in my opinion, lies less in a lack of good will than in a current nervousness that leads to a misplaced stinginess. Since, however, he is actually in a position to fulfil your demands, and it is only of the urgency of these that he is not convinced, I should like to ask you to address him yourself, in a firm tone, upon which the success will not, in my opinion, have long to wait!</tei:p><tei:p>You can imagine how infinitely painful all this is to me, all the more as I dare not at present carry things too far concerning the differences of opinion between my father and myself; for the danger of alienation now exists since his marriage, although I get along with my little stepmother as if she were my sister, and she also tries to help me in the present matter, so far as her nineteen years will allow.</tei:p><tei:p>May I ask you, then, once more to support my efforts at an elegant resolution of this dissonance by writing to my father.</tei:p><tei:p>I am also having some difficulty with my “profession”. Here, I see myself entirely thrown back on my own resources. My father’s obstinate frugality, nervousness, and lack of time hinder and delay many of my projects; nevertheless I have achieved much in these matters by the resolute intercession of my “little mother”. I need freedom of movement, and this <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> costs money, and at the present time this is more difficult to get out of my good father than the Urlinie from a work by Stravinsky.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/></tei:p><tei:p>I hope I can soon communicate to you something positive concerning my musical efforts, even in a field such as dance or revue. I am actually trying <tei:hi rend="italic">everything</tei:hi>.</tei:p><tei:p>Lately I have had contact with artistic circles in Düsseldorf, through the first wife of my uncle, Carl Sternheim;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> this appears to be of significance.  Unfortunately, far too many people are still on holiday. Until September there is not much going on socially.</tei:p><tei:p>In the mean time, then affectionate greetings to you and your wife; and, for God’s sake, please do not be cross about the dissonance with</tei:p><tei:p>Your
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Felix von Cube</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>