<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [40] : 6-2-34 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2006.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1934-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 06/02/1934 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated June 2, 1934</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-10-09</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Quotes part of a letter from the Reichsmusikkammer regarding grounds for his dismissal, and reports subsequent conversation with the Conservatory administration.  - -Encloses review of a recent lecture.  - -Includes revised Ursatz for Bach Prelude in body of letter.  - -Inquires about Hans Wolf, and reports on Furtwängler. 

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  Reichsmusikkammer;  German Conservatory;  administration;  lecture;  review;  Hoehn, Alfred;  Bach, J. S.;  Well-tempered Clavier;  Prelude;  Ursatz;  fugue;  Wolf, Hans;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Hamburg 13, Mittelweg 126, Ia/^II.^</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, June 2, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hamburg 13, Mittelweg 126, Ia/^II.^
2.VI.34.</tei:p><tei:p><!-- bq. --> Jeder denkt, sie sind perdü,
<!-- bq. --> aber nein, noch leben sie!
<!-- bq. --> (Wilhelm Busch.)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> Wilhelm Busch (1832-1908), artist and poet, most famous for his picture stories, among which <tei:hi rend="italic">Max und Moritz</tei:hi> (1865) became a children's classic.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Hochverehrter, lieber Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich habe weidlich nach verschiedenen Seiten geknurrt und die Zähne gefletscht, nach anderen Seiten hinwiederum aufklärend und überzeugend gewirkt und gearbeitet; item ich in die bröckelnde Mauer des Starrsinnes einen soliden Haken getrieben habe, an dem ich mich vielleicht wieder anseilen kann.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> <tei:hi rend="italic">Haken</tei:hi> (a thin wedge driven into a rockface, used as a safety device in mountaneering) and <tei:hi rend="italic">anseilen</tei:hi> [to tie into a rope] are terms that Schenker, a keen Alpinist, would not only have understood but also have been pleased to see used metaphorically.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Folgendermaßen läutet ein Schreiben, das ich vom Landesleiter der Reichsmusikkammer<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> <tei:hi rend="italic">Reichmusikkammer</tei:hi> (Reich Music Chamber): the body controlling music throughout Germany during the period  of National Socialism, itself subdivided into departments for composition, soloists, orchestras, entertainment music, music education, choral music, church music, concert agencies, etc., and 31 regional offices.  It was one of seven sub-chambers of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Reichskulturkammer</tei:hi> (Reich Culture Chamber), founded in 1933, the year that Hitler came to power, under the authority of the Propaganda Minister Joseph Goebbels.  Its President for the first two years was Richard Strauss.</tei:note> erhielt:</tei:p><tei:p><!-- bq. --> "Sehr geehrter Herr von Cube!</tei:p><tei:p><!-- bq. -->  Ich teile Ihnen mit, dass ich mich über die Gründe Ihrer Kündigung beim Deutschen Konservatorium direkt informieren werde. Eine Stellungnahme zur „Schenker-Theorie" scheint mir zurzeit durchaus nicht erforderlich und ist es mir unerfindlich, weshalb Sie mit einer derartigen Begründung gekündigt wurden.  ........"</tei:p><tei:p>Es folgen dann noch Bemerkungen über die Einflussnahme der R.M.K. auf Anstellungsverträge. Ich habe nach diesem Schreiben meiner Direktion auf den Kopf zu gesagt, dass der Kündigungsgrund um ein fauler Vorwand für unsaubere geschäftliche Machenschaften war, (denn ich kenne jetzt auch meinen Nachfolger!), worauf wir den schönsten Krach kriegten, und ich erst recht rausgeschmissen wurde!  Immerhin habe jetzt +ich+ die reine Weste, und meine +Direktion+ den Fleck auf der Conduite! Was mir allerdings nun ein ehrenvoller, aber leider kein stofflicher Ersatz für die verlorene Verdienstquelle ist. Einige beherzte Schüler sind mit mir "in die Verbannung" gegangen. Aber erst nebelhaft erheben sich am Horizonte die Umrisse einer neuen eventuellen Arbeitsstätte. Jetzt kommen erst die Ferien und mitten darin unser Familienzuwachs, sodass mir alle Haare einzeln zu Berge stehen, und ich ein S.O.S. an die Verwandten losgelassen habe. Obs hilft??? --</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Einliegend finden Sie ferner die Besprechung eines Vortrages, den ich kürzlich mit dem Mute der Verzweiflung gehalten habe. Es schien mir der einzigmögliche Weg, die Wahrheit zur Sprache zu bringen, ohne auf eine a-priori-Ablehnung zu stossen. Der Erfolg übertraf meine Erwartungen, und auch die Besprechung - von mir leicht inspiriert - zeigt, dass es noch Leute gibt, die eine geistige Verantwortung auf sich zu nehmen bereit sind. Curioserweise hatte der Vortrag ein Echo aus - - - - - Frankfurt! Von dort schrieb mir ein Professor Alfred Hoehn (kennen Sie ihn?),<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> Alfred Hoehn: teacher of piano at the Frankfurt Conservatory (taught, among others, the conductor Hans Rosbaud).</tei:note> dass er von diesen Dingen mehr erfahren möchte.  Ich werde ihm ein paar zusammenhängende Notizen und eine "selbstgezogene" Urlinie schicken.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  No paragraph-break in original.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Beim Bachpräludium<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6"> This is a follow-up graph to an analysis sent with Cube's previous letter to Schenker, OJ 9/34, [39], April 29, 1934.</tei:note> habe ich mich zu folgendem Ursatze durchgerungen:</tei:p><tei:p><!-- bq. --> [example: Bach, <tei:hi rend="italic">Well-Tempered Clavier</tei:hi>, I, Prelude in D: short two-stave voice-leading reduction]</tei:p><tei:p>Cum grano salis natürlich! Jetzt arbeite ich auch an der Fuge!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7"> Voice-leading graphs of both the Prelude and the Fugue in D major from the <tei:hi rend="italic">Well-Tempered Clavier</tei:hi>, Book 1, are included in Cube's unpublished <tei:hi rend="italic">Lehrbuch der musikalischen Kunstgesetze</tei:hi>. (They are dated 1956 and 1957, respectively.)</tei:note> Dies ist auch so ähnlich. Im Übrigen bin ich mit "Nestbau" beschäftigt, streiche meine Möbel, tapeziere Wände, zimmere Tische und Garderoben, denn Handwerker bezahlen ist nicht möglich, und ausserdem wird das Selbstgefühl gesteigert! -</tei:p><tei:p>Gott und mein Glaube an die Ewigkeit alles Deutschen - auch im neuen Deutschland - helfe mir weiter! -<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8"> On his "allegiance to the new Germany," see Cube's previous letter, OJ 9/34, April 29, 1934, and also Cube's OJ 9/34, [37], May 11, and S's vC 46, May 14, 1933.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Mit vielen herzlichen Grüssen von uns beiden an Sie und Ihre liebe Gattin bich ich stets</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube.</tei:p><tei:p>Was macht Hans Wolf?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="wolf_hans">Hans Wolf</ref>.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ach so: Furtwängler will sich Mitte Juni mit mir in Verbindung setzen!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10"> Cube's last letter to Schenker, OJ 9/34, [42], October 4, 1934, quotes in full the letter written by Wilhelm Furtwängler in support of his dedication to the teaching of Schenker's theories.</tei:note></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, June 2, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hamburg 13, Mittelweg 126, Ia/^II.^
June 2, 1934</tei:p><tei:p><!-- bq. --> Everyone thinks the game is up,
<!-- bq. --> But, no, there's life in them yet!
<!-- bq. --> (Wilhelm Busch.)<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Most honoured, dear master,</tei:p><tei:p>I have growled and flashed my teeth in many directions, and again been active and at work on other fronts to enlighten and convince, with the result that I have driven a solid hook into the crumbling wall of obstinacy, onto which I may be able to rope myself once more.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/></tei:p><tei:p>A letter, which I received from the provincial leader of the Reichsmusikkammer,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> reads as follows:</tei:p><tei:p><!-- bq. --> "Dear Mr. von Cube!</tei:p><tei:p><!-- bq. --> This is to let you know that I shall inform myself directly concerning the grounds of your dismissal from the German Conservatory. An opinion concerning "Schenkerian theory" seems to me at this time entirely unnecessary, and I cannot understand why you were dismissed on grounds of that sort..."</tei:p><tei:p>There then follow remarks about the extent to which the Reichsmusikkammer exerts an influence over employment contracts. After receiving this letter I spoke face to face with the administration, saying that the reason for my dismissal was a lame pretext for shady business dealings (for I also know now who my successor is!), whereupon we had the fiercest row and I was categorically thrown out! None the less, it is +I+ who wears the clean shirt, and the +administration+ which has a black mark for conduct! This is at any rate for me an honorable, though unfortunately not a material, substitute for the lost sources of income. A few brave pupils went with me "into banishment."  But the outlines of a new possibility for work are rising only hazily on the horizon. Now the summer holidays are intervening, and in the midst of this the new member of our family, so that all of my hairs are standing up like mountains and I have issued an S.O.S. to our relatives. But will that help???</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> I have also enclosed for you the review of a lecture that I gave recently, with the courage of despair. It seemed to me the only possible way of giving voice to the truth, without meeting an <tei:hi rend="italic">a priori</tei:hi> objection. The success exceeded my expectation, and even the review--lightly drawing inspiration from me--shows that there are still people who are prepared to bear intellectual responsibility. Strangely enough, the lecture received an echo from, of all places, Frankfurt! From there a Professor Alfred Hoehn (do you know him?)<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> wrote to me, saying that he wanted to learn more about these things. I shall send him a few related notices and a "self-drawn" Ursatz.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/></tei:p><tei:p>In the Bach Prelude,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> I have arrived at the following Ursatz:</tei:p><tei:p><!-- bq. --> [example: Bach, <tei:hi rend="italic">Well-Tempered Clavier</tei:hi>, I, Prelude in D: short two-stave voice-leading reduction]</tei:p><tei:p>[You may take this,] of course, with a pinch of salt! Now I am also working on the fugue.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> This is also very similar.  Otherwise, I am busy "building a nest," painting my furniture, papering the walls, and building tables and wardrobes, since paying a builder is impossible and, in addition, my self-esteem is thereby increased.</tei:p><tei:p>May God and my belief in the eternity of everything German--even in the new Germany--help me further!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/></tei:p><tei:p>With many cordial greetings from the two of us to you and your dear wife, I am always</tei:p><tei:p>Yours
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube</tei:p><tei:p>PS: What is Hans Wolf up to?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/></tei:p><tei:p>Oh, yes: Furtwängler will get in touch with me in the middle of June!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/></tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>