<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34 [35] : 12-7-32 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2008.
© Translation William Drabkin, 2008.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1932-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 12/07/1932 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated December 7, 1932</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-06-30</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Cube reports on his current state of mind, his work on a Bach graph (commenting on a graph by Angi Elias), promises to send an article on Schenker that has appeared in the Frankfurter Zeitung, on the difficulties of the Schenker-Institut, and on Moriz and Karl Violin. 

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  Bach, J. S.;  Elias, Angi;  Eroica;  Balkung;  beaming;  Brahms;  Frankfurter Zeitung;  Schenker-Institut;  Violin, Moriz;  Violin, Karl; Voss, Erich;  Freier Satz;  Free Composition </dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Hamburg 13, Beneckestrasse 2</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated December 7, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hamburg 13, Beneckestr. 2; bei Alexander Schmidt.
7. XII. 32.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter, lieber Meister!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Receipt of this letter appears not to have been recorded in Schenker's diary.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Lange habe ich nichts von mir vermeldet.  Das lag hauptsächlich daran, dass ich mir meine Nerven immer noch nicht so gut erzogen habe, dass sie mich doch bei diesen herrlichen Zeiten<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Cube is using these words with heavy irony.</tei:note> in etwa nachgegeben hätten, und ich mich von der allgemeinen Apathie anstecken liess.  Der Massendepression kann man immer nur innere Energien entgegenstellen, und dieses Reservoir ist bei mir keineswegs unerschöpflich, wenn man so gar keine äusserlichen Aufmunterungen erlebt.  Nun habe ich mich über Weihnachten doch wieder etwas zurechectgerüttelt, und sehe den weiteren Notverordnungen mit grösserer Gelassenheit entgegen. –</tei:p><tei:p>Die Bachtafel<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Probably a graphic analysis of the Prelude in C from the <tei:hi rend="italic">Well-Tempered Clavier</tei:hi>, Book 1. Reference to the work of Angi Elias later in this letter suggests that Cube is still revising his own work on this piece, though the <tei:hi rend="italic">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln</tei:hi> (which includes an analysis of this prelude) was published in the fall of 1932.</tei:note> habe ich nun in Arbeit genommen, nachdem meine Schüler sie sich eifrigst abgeschrieben haben.  Ganz neu sind mir die Balkungen anstelle der Bogen (wie auch in der Eroica<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  I.e. Schenker’s analysis of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Eroica</tei:hi> Symphony, in <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, vol. 3 (Munich: Drei-Masken Verlag, 1930).</tei:note>), das Bild wird dadurch von bedeutender Klarheit.  Ich glaube, dass an Frl. Elias’ Tafel<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="elias_angelika">Angi Elias</ref>, who prepared many of the fair copies of his analytical graphs.  According to a personal communication from Cube, it was Elias who hit upon the idea of beaming together notes that were conceptually important in the background and middleground, leaving slurs to indicate arpeggiations, linear progressions, etc that were nearer the musical foreground.  See William Drabkin “Felix-Eberhard von Cube and the North German Tradition of Schenkerism,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Royal Musical Association</tei:hi> 111 (1985), 180-207.</tei:note> immerhin noch einige Präzisierungen vorzunehmen sind. Besonders der Verblieb der Mittelstimme g am Schluss.  Derzeit erwäge ich eine Lösung. Meine nächsten Arbeiten werden Brahms gis-moll Walzer, und das Paganini-Thema sein.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Neither the Brahms waltz (Op. 39, No. 2) nor the theme of Paganini’s famous Caprice in A minor, Op. 1, No. 24, is included among the analyses in Cube’s unpublished <tei:hi rend="italic">Lehrbuch der musikalischen Kunstgesetze</tei:hi>. Schenker, however, included a graph of the Paganini theme in <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi>.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Die Frankfurter Zeitung<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="frankfurter_zeitung"><tei:hi rend="italic">Frankfurter Zeitung</tei:hi></ref>.  There are no articles from the <tei:hi rend="italic">Frankfurter Zeitung</tei:hi> from 1932 in Schenker's Scrapbook (OC 2) or clippings collection (OC C). It seems, then, that Cube did not send this to his teacher.</tei:note> brachte einen längeren Artikel über Ihre Werke, den ich Ihnen bald zuschicke.  Besonders weitgegangen fand ich ein Passus, der die Forderung nach Schenker-Unterricht an den Hochschulen ausdrückt, sowie die Bemerkung, dass Ihre Bücher in allen Bibliotheken, Universitäten und Musikschulen gehören.  Sonst manches kunterbunt, und vieles missverstanden. Gesamteindruck erfreulich. –</tei:p><tei:p>Das Institut<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="schenker_institute_h">Schenker Institut, Hamburg</ref>.  </tei:note> kämpft einen <tei:hi rend="italic">schweren</tei:hi> Existenzkampf.  Violin<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="violin_moriz">Moriz Violin</ref>.  </tei:note> hat dem Hauswirt vorsorglich gekündigt, um die Miete zu drücken.  Hoffentlich [ist] der Mann vernünftig!  Es liegt in der Natur der Dinge, dass wir die Abenteur nicht in demselben Maaße zu spüren bekamen, wie die “Betriebs”-Konservatorien. <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi>  Indess sind uns auch grösste Opfer auferlegt.  Ich habe manchen Schüler zum Bleiben [be]wogen, und auch eine neue Schülerin eingebracht, einige weitere Eisen sind im Feuer.  Aber es fehlt uns ein gutes Drittel immer noch an der notwendigsten Rentabilität. –</tei:p><tei:p>Vorträge liegen im Argen! Selbst unentgeltliche.  Es fehlt an Konzentration bei den Hörern.  Die gehen ins Kino und betäuben sich. Die “Konkurrenz” hat gottlob jetzt soviel eigene Zores,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Zores</tei:hi>: Yiddish for troubles, sorrow.</tei:note> dass sie uns in Ruhe lässt.  Ein schwacher Trost.  Ich liege wie ein Luchs auf der Lauer, alle Möglichkeiten einzufangen, aber man greift immer nur ins Leere.  Die nächsten drei Monate bringen meines Erachtens nach die Entscheidung über manche Fragen, die man sich nur ruhig eingestehen soll.  Wenns sein <tei:hi rend="italic">muss</tei:hi>, ich fange noch ein Dutzendmal von vorne an. Hoffen wir, dass <tei:hi rend="italic">dieser</tei:hi> Kelch an uns vorübergeht. –</tei:p><tei:p>Violin sieht müde aus.  Uns allen tut die lähmende Ungewissheit nicht gut. Karli ist gottlob wohlauf.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  A reference to a serious illness that had befallen Moriz Violin’s son Karl in 1931.</tei:note>  Diese Sorge ist wenigstens gebannt.  Ich bin keineswegs ein Pessimist geworden!  Nun das nicht!  Aber ich sehe mit offenen Augen, und was ich sehe ist leider sehr eindeutig.  Dass wir uns im kommenden Vierteljahr auf dem gegenwärtigen Status halten können, ist das Günstigste, was ich zu hoffen wage. –</tei:p><tei:p>In normalen Zeiten wären wir sehr obenauf!  Unsere Schüler sind begeistert, das Unterrichten eine reine Freude.  Die gehen müssen, weil sie nicht mehr können, sind ehrlich verzweifelt.  Aber alle können wir nicht umsonst unterrichten.  Es werden auch wieder andere Zeiten kommen.  Was war eigentlich mit Herrn Voss?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Erich Voss, a music student in Cologne who befriended Cube and travelled to Vienna in the hope of studying with Schenker. (See the correspondence between Schenker and Cube from May 14 to July 18, 1929.)</tei:note>  Das ist auch ein Ungeduldiger Vogel, aber sonst goldrichtig!  Ich höre wenig von ihm, er schei[nt] aber in Münster kräftig für die Sache einzutreten. –</tei:p><tei:p>Mir geht es so leidlich.  Mein persönlichster Schmerz ist, dass ich seit drei Jahren als “ewiger Bräutigam” herumlaufe.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Ewige Bräutigam</tei:hi> (“eternal bridegroom”): Cube had gotten married earlier that year, but was still unable to secure a stable domestic life in Hamburg.  The expression is probably a play on the expression <tei:hi rend="italic">ewiger Jude</tei:hi> (“Wandering Jew”).  </tei:note>  Auch das ist so eine Zeiterscheinung.  Aber das wird auch nochmal klappen.  Was macht der freie Satz?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi> (Vienna:  UE, 1935), on which Schenker was working hard at this time, and which was ultimately published posthumously.  </tei:note>  Und Ihr und Ihrer Frau Gemahlen Wohlbefinden?</tei:p><tei:p>Für diesmal mit allerherzlichsten Grüssen
Ihr
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  Cube.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated December 7, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hamburg 13, Beneckestrasse 2, c/o Alexander Schmidt
December 7, 1932</tei:p><tei:p>Most honoured, dearest master,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>For a long time I have communicated nothing about myself.  This was primarily because I have never trained my nerves well enough that they were able to relax a bit in these splendid times,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> and that I could become infected by the general apathy.  Mass depression can only be combated by internal energy, and my reservoir is by no means inexhaustible, when there is absolutely nothing in the way of external encouragement.  Now, during the Christmas period, I have again been aroused to a somewhat more favourable state of mind, and and view further emergency measures with somewhat greater composure.</tei:p><tei:p>I have begun working on the Bach graph,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> after my pupils copied it down with great zeal.  What is entirely new to me are the beamings that replace the slurs (as are also found in the “Eroica”);<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  the picture will gain significantly in clarity.  I believe that there are, nevertheless, still some things that should be made more precise in Miss Elias’s graph,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> especially the inner-voice g, which is left hanging at the end.  At the moment, I am trying to find a solution.  My next projects will be Brahms’s Waltz in G sharp minor, and the Paganini theme.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/></tei:p><tei:p>The <tei:hi rend="italic">Frankfurter Zeitung</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> published a lengthy article about your works, which I shall send you soon.  I was particularly struck by a passage which expressed the the need for Schenkerian tuition in the high schools, and by the remark that your books belong in every library, university and conservatory. Otherwise, some things were garbled, and much was misunderstood. The overall impression was favorable.</tei:p><tei:p>The Institute<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> is fighting a <tei:hi rend="italic">difficult</tei:hi> battle for survival. Violin<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> gave notice to the custodian, as a precautionary measure, so as to keep the rent down. Let us hope that the man is reasonable! It is in the nature of things that we were not affected by the adventure to the same extent as the “management” conservatories. <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> In the mean time we have had to make the greatest sacrifices. I have persuaded some pupils to remain, and I also have acquired a new pupil;  there are some further irons in the fire.  But just to make ends meet, a good third of our pupils are missing.</tei:p><tei:p>Lectures are in a bad way—even those that are unpaid!  The audience is unable to concentrate.  They go to the cinema and become deaf.  The “competition” has, thank God, just so much trouble<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> of its own that it leaves us in peace.  Small comfort.  I am lying in ambush, like a lynx, to grab at any opportunity, but can only grab at emptiness.  The next three months will, I believe, settle many questions, which one should only accept peacefully. If it <tei:hi rend="italic">must</tei:hi> be, I will begin again from the beginning.  Let us hope that <tei:hi rend="italic">this</tei:hi> cup of sorrow passes over us.</tei:p><tei:p>Violin looks tired. The paralysing uncertainty does none of us any good. Karli is, thank God, in good shape; that sorrow is, at least, banished.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/>  I have by no means become a pessimist!  Not that, for sure.  But I look at things with my eyes open, and what I see is, unfortunately, all too clear.  That we might be able to hold our present position is the most favourable thing that I dare to hope.</tei:p><tei:p>In normal times, we would be in very buoyant spirits! Our pupils are inspired, and teaching is an unalloyed pleasure. Those who must leave because they no longer afford to stay, are genuinely downhearted. But we cannot teach everyone for free. Other times will come again. What actually happened with Mr Voss?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> There’s another impatient bird, but otherwise good as gold. I hear little from him; he seems, however, to be working hard for the cause in Münster.</tei:p><tei:p>I am so very unhappy.  My most personal pain is that I have been moving about for the last three years as the “eternal bridegroom”.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/>  That, too, is so much a sign of the times.  But that too will eventually work out.  How are things going with <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi>?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/>  And your health, and that of your wife?</tei:p><tei:p>For now, with all my most affectionate greetings,</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Cube</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>