<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [36] : 5-1-33 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
©  Transcription William Drabkin 2008.
© Translation William Drabkin, 2008.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1933-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 05/01/1933 03:01:49 PM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated May 1, 1933</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-12-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Thanks Schenker for sending Brahms's Octaven u. Quinten, expresses his longing for Der freie Satz, sends an example of his work, and expresses concern over his future.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  Brahms;  Octaven u. Quinten;  Der freie Satz;  Free Composition;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Hamburg 13, Dillstraße</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated May 1, 1933</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hamburg 13, Dillstraße 1./I.
1.V.33.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter, lieber Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Für die Übersendung der "Oktaven u. Quinten" von Brahms<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Oktaven u. Quinten u. a.</tei:hi>, which was brought out by UE in the centennial year of Brahms's birth, comprises a facsimile of an eight-page manuscript in which Brahms recorded (under this title) all the instances he could find of consecutive fifths and octaves in the works of composers from the 16th to the 19th centuries. Schenker provided a commentary on the examples, and on Brahms's own remarks on them. For an English edition, see Paul Mast, "Brahms's Study, Oktaven u. Quinten u. a.: A Critical Edition of Brahms' Notebook with Schenker's Commentary Translated," <tei:hi rend="italic">Music Forum</tei:hi> 5 (1980), pp. 1-196.</tei:note> sage ich Ihnen mienen herzlichsten Dank!  Ich habe bereits alles mit Begeisterung verschlungen;  es war aber doch nur ein Tropfen auf den heissen Stein meiner Sehnsucht nach dem "freien Satz"!  Meine Arbeit ist sehr durch Ungeduld beinträchtigt, wenn auch ich mir selber andauernd "Gelassenheit" predige.  Heute sende ich Ihnen eine neue Probe meiner Arbeit im Stillen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Literally "breast-feeding work," i.e. providing basic nourishment in Schenkerian theory to his pupils in Hamburg. -- The piece in question is the first-movement theme of Beethoven's Piano Sonata in A flat, Op. 26.  Schenker's reply, and the subsequent exchanges of letters, focus mainly on the analysis.  For a reproduction of Cube's graph and transcriptions and translations of the remaining correspondence, see William Drabkin, "Schenker, the Consonant Passing Note, and the First-Movement Theme of Beethoven's Sonata Op. 26," <tei:hi rend="italic">Music Analysis</tei:hi>, 15 (1996), pp. 149-89. </tei:note>  Ich bin, glaube ich, ordentlich weitergekommen.  Darf ich mir das Blatt (mit allfälligen Verbesserungen) bald zurückbitten, da ich damit Pläne habe. -<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  The analysis does not appear in Cube's unpublished <tei:hi rend="italic">Lehrbuch der musikalischen Kunstgesetze</tei:hi>;  the theme occupies the seventh position in Schenker's list of works to be issued as graphic analyses (nos. 1-5 had recently been published in <tei:hi rend="italic">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln</tei:hi>), but was never included on any of the lists sent to Cube (in 1934) of works that were to appear in a second series.  There are, however, several graphs and music examples for it in <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi>.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ich schreibe Ihnen demnächst mehr über mich.  Heute bin ich noch zu chaotisch im Innern.  Was wird aus mir?  Noch weiss ich nichts.  Der August droht mit Hunger.  Ich habe an Furtwängler geschrieben.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  This is the first of two letters to Furtwängler, asking for assistance in the recognition of Schenkerian theory as teaching discipline in music schools. The second was answered in August of the following year; this reply is copied in full into Cube's letter to Schenker of October 4, 1934.</tei:note>  Verwandte können mir nicht helfen.  Gleichwohl:  ich bin zuversichtlich! -</tei:p><tei:p>Ich will nichts, als arbeiten können. -</tei:p><tei:p>Für heute herzlichste Grüsse, auch von meiner Frau, 
und <tei:hi rend="italic">bald</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  "bald" (soon):  double-underlined by Cube.</tei:note> mehr, von Ihrem</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated May 1, 1933</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hamburg 13, Dillstrasse 1/I
May 1, 1933</tei:p><tei:p>Most honored, dear master,</tei:p><tei:p>I offer you my most cordial thanks for sending me <tei:hi rend="italic">Oktaven u. Quinten</tei:hi> by Brahms!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  I have already devoured everything with gusto;  this was, however, very small in comparison with my yearning for <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi>!  My work has been adversely affected by impatience, even if I constantly preach "calmness" to myself.  Today I am sending you a new example of my pedagogical work.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  I have, I believe, made real progress.  Might I ask you to return the page to me (with any corrections that are necessary), as I have plans to use it.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/></tei:p><tei:p>I will write to you soon, with more about myself.  Today I am feeling internally too chaotic.  What will be come of me?  I still know nothing.  August threatens with hunger.  I have written to Furtwängler.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  My family cannot help me.  Nevertheless, I shall write to your more soon about myself.</tei:p><tei:p>I want nothing other than to be able to work.</tei:p><tei:p>For today, affectionate greetings, also from my wife; and <tei:hi rend="italic">soon</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> you will hear more from your</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>