<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [38] : 9-7-33 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
©  Transcription William Drabkin 2008.
© Translation William Drabkin, 2008.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1933-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 09/07/1933 12:41:14 PM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated September 7, 1933</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-12-16</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Cube reports on his poor health and straitened cirumstances,teaching at two conservatories and private pupils;  he eagerly awaits Der freie Satz, and reports on his investigation of diatonic systems.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  health;  Aleff, Georg;  Steinway &amp; Sons;  Alster;  Deutsches Konservatorium;  Blankenese;  Klaer'sches Konservatorium;  pupils;  German people;  Volk;  Freie Satz, Der;  Harmonielehre;  System;  Mischung;  modal mixture;  Chromatik;  chromaticism; Alteration;  Stufengang;  Kompositionsdiatonien;  diatonic modes;  symmetry;  Verschmelzung;  amalgamation;  Schoenberg, Arnold;  Phrygian mode;  Brahms;  Intermezzo;  Leitton;  leading tone;  Vrieslander, Otto</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Hamburg 13, Dillstraße 1./I</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated September 7, 1933</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hamburg 13, Dillstraße 1./I.</tei:p><tei:p>Neue Adresse ab 26. Sept: Hamburg 37,
Jungfrauenthal 14/II, bei Lepel.
7. IX. 33</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter, lieber Meister!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 4/6, p. 3865, September 10, 1933.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Verzeihen Sie bitte mein langes Schweigen.  Die Zwischenzeit ist etwas turbulent verlaufen, sodass ich erst heute etwas Sammlung und Ruhe zum schreiben habe. -</tei:p><tei:p>Zum ersten Mal in meinem Leben haben meine Nerven den Dienst versagt.  Ich musste eine Zeit im Bett bleiben, und bin noch so halbwegs Rekonvaleszent.  Ein organisches Leiden haben die Ärtzte nicht gefunden;  dafür einen unzulässigen Grad von Unterernährung.  So rasch wird das wohl nicht einzuholen sein, zumal ich lange brauchen werde um mein finanzielles &lt;!--fre--&gt;désastre nach dem Zusammenbruch des Schenker-Instituts<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="schenker_institute_h">Schenker Institut, Hamburg: Prospectus</ref>.   </tei:note> wieder auszugleichen.  Man hat mir von verschiedenen Seiten über das Ärgste geholfen.  Das muss zurückgegeben werden.  Die beste, weil nachhaltigste Hilfe leistete mir Kollege Georg Aleff von Steinway &amp; Sons,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Steinway &amp; Sons [create profile and link].  Georg Aleff: [identify]</tei:note> der mir zwei zwei neue Stellungen verschaffte.  Eine am Deutschen Konservatorium an der Alster,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  The Alster is a large lake in the centre of Hamburg.  </tei:note> eine am Klaer'schen Konservatorium in Blankenese.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Blankenese is a picturesque town situated on the north bank of the Elbe several miles west of the city center.</tei:note>  Material:  Eine Seminar- und zwei Dilettantenklassen, sowie eine Ausbildungsklasse für Klavier, derzeit mit einer Schülerin besetzt.  Das ganze bringt mir rund 55.- Mark ein.  Dazu habe ich noch ein paar Privatschüler.  Eigentlich kann ich nicht davon leben, aber uneigentlich muss ich, und darum geht es auch.  Meine Frau ist nicht besser dran wie ich, so helfen wir einander und tragen es zusammen[,] wie das so sein muss. -</tei:p><tei:p>Meine Wohnung muss ich aufgeben;  ich ziehe wieder in zwei Zimmer, solange, bis ich mir was anderes leisten kann.  Sparen heisst die Parole, zumal da auch Kleidung und manches vom Hausrat endlich ersetzt werden muss, gerade jetzt, wo's am schwersten gehen will. Ich bin überzeugt, dass das Vorbild der Riesen-Kraftleistung <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> des Deutschen Volkes auch mir geholfen hat, mich wieder aufzurichten.  An den beiden Schulen unterrichte ich mit Selbstverständlichkeit nach den Hauptgrundsätzen Ihrer Werke.  Manches ist zuviel für den Durchschnitt, das meiste wird gut und restlos verstanden;  manches muss noch durchdacht und erweitert werden.  Ich warte sehnsüchtig auf den "freien Satz",<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Schenker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi> (Vienna: UE, 1935).  </tei:note> in dem ich <tei:hi rend="italic">alles</tei:hi> zu finden hoffe;  meine eigene Arbeit, die <tei:hi rend="italic">viele</tei:hi> Resultate gezeitigt hat, ist stark &lt;!--eng--&gt;gehandicapt durch das Warten auf Ihre endgültigen Formulierungen.  Meine Hauptschmerzen liegen bei den Begriffen Sÿstem, Mischung, Chromatik, Alteration und auch Stufengang.  Schon heute komme ich im Unterricht nicht ohne Korrekturen nach der Urlinie-Seite hin aus!  Meine Untersuchungen über die Sÿsteme sind abgeschlossen.  Demnach kommen als Kompositionsdiatonien <tei:hi rend="italic">alle</tei:hi> sieben vor;  lediglich als Namensgaber für das ganze Stück haben sich Dur und Moll herausgeschält, wegen der Dreiklangssÿmmetrie.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  What Cube probably means by this is that the triads based on the fundamental (I) and its closest neighbors on the circle fifths (the fifth below = IV, and the fifth above = V) have the same quality: in major or "Ionian" mode they are all major triads, and in minor or "Aeolian" mode they are all minor triads.</tei:note>  Die <tei:hi rend="italic">Siebenzahl</tei:hi> der Töne beruht auf dem Kunstgriff der <tei:hi rend="italic">Verschmelzung von harmonischer und melodischer Logik</tei:hi>, die bei geraden Zahlen, also auch bei Schönbergs 12Tonleiter,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="schoenberg_arnold">Arnold Schoenberg</ref>.  </tei:note> unmöglich wäre; siehe linkstehende Zeichnung:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">diagram and music example</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>Dazu vergleichen Sie bitte als <tei:hi rend="italic">phrÿgisches</tei:hi> Gegenstück aus Brahm's Intermezzo in B-moll (3 Intermezzi)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  The Brahms intermezzo, Op. 117, No. 2, is discussed in Cube's <tei:hi rend="italic">Lehrbuch der musikalischen Kunstgesetze</tei:hi>. See especially pp. 110-13 in the published English translation, <tei:hi rend="italic">The Book of the Musical Artwork</tei:hi>, ed. and trans. David Neumeyer, George R. Boyd and Scott Harris (Lewiston and Queenston: Edwin Mellen, 1988).</tei:note> die Takte 61 bis Schluss;  besonders die Takte 67-71!  Die absonderliche Schreibweise resultiert wohl aus dem, zum B strebenden Leitton a, demzuliebe die Schreibart in # statt in <tei:hi rend="italic">b</tei:hi> gewählt wird!  Eigentlich heisst der Schritt der Stufen in Takt 67-69:  ces-f, nicht h-f!  Ich will Ihnen bei Gelegenheit, und bei mehr Gelassenheit, einmal eine Menge Material zusammenstellen.  Ihre Ausführungen auf Seite 364-365 der Harmonielehre treffen auf Brahms wohl kaum zu.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Schenker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (Stuttgart:  J. G. Cotta, 1906), §145 "Der Tonikalisierungsprozeß als Interpret der zweiten phrygischen Stufe" (Tonicalization as an Explanation of the Phrygian II Scale-Step), Eng. trans. E. Mann Borghese (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1954),  pp. 273-74.  </tei:note>  Tatsächlich stehen meine Ansichten über all diese Dinge den Grundbegriffen[,] die Sie lehren[,] an sich nicht im Mindesten entgegen, sondern stellen eine organische Entwickelung dar.  Davon später mehr. - (Es ist bei mir keineswegs der "Vrieslandersche Abrtrünningkeitspunkt["];<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  In previous letters to Schenker, OJ 9/34, [37], May 11, 1933, Cube had expressed some misgivings about Otto Vrieslander's understanding of Schenkerian theory. Vrieslander, who thought himself more a composer than a theorist or musicologist, was very much formed in Schenker's mold, having studied the works of C. P. E. Bach and made an Erläuterungsausgabe of some of Bach's shorter works. He also wrote a monograph on Bach, which was criticized for adopting a polemical tone similar to Schenker's.  Just how Vrieslander's view of music theory differs--for Cube, unacceptably--from Schenker's is never explained.  </tei:note>  in puncto Beethovenurlinie beuge ich mich Ihrer höheren Einsicht!)  --</tei:p><tei:p>Für heute genug, und <tei:hi rend="italic">bald mehr</tei:hi>, nebst vielen herzlichen Grüssen an Sie und Ihre Gattin</tei:p><tei:p>von Ihrem	
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Cube.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich komponiere wieder!</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated September 7, 1933</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hamburg 13, Dillstraße 1/I
new address from September 26: Hamburg 37,
 Jungfrauenthal 14/II, c/o Lepel
September 7, 1933</tei:p><tei:p>Most honored, dear master,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Please forgive my long silence.  The intervening period has been rather turbulent, so that it is not until today that I have some collectedness and peace in which to write.</tei:p><tei:p>For the first time in my life, my nerves have prevented me from working.  I had to remain in bed for a time, and am still only about halfway to recovery.  The doctors did not find anything wrong with my constitution, but rather an unacceptable degree of undernourishment.  This will not be made good all that quickly, given that I shall need a long time to recover from my financial disaster after the collapse of the Schenker Institute.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  I have been helped over the worst from various sides;  that must now be paid back.  The best help, because it will last longest, came from my colleague Georg Aleff of Steinway &amp; Sons,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> who found two new posts for me:  one at the German Conservatory on the Alster,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> the other at the Klaer Conservatory in Blankenese.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  My work consists of one seminar group and two classes for amateurs, and also a class in piano pedagogy, in which one female pupil is currently enrolled.  The whole thing brings me about 55 Marks per month.  In addition, I still have a few private pupils.  I cannot actually live on that, but I have no choice, and I have to think about this as well.  My wife is no better used to this than I, and so we help each other and bear things together, as it should be.</tei:p><tei:p>I must give up my apartment;  I shall move again into two-room accommodation until I can afford something else.  "Saving" is the key word, since even clothing and many household items must eventually be replaced, especially now, when the going will be toughest.  I am convinced that the model of German people's enormous strength to accomplish things <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> has also helped me to get back on my feet.  In both schools I teach, it goes without saying, according to the basic principles found in your works.  Some of this is too difficult for the average pupil, but most is understood well and thoroughly;  somethings need to be thought through and elaborated.  I wait longingly for <tei:hi rend="italic">Free Composition</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> in which I hope to find <tei:hi rend="italic">everything</tei:hi>;  my own work, which has yielded <tei:hi rend="italic">many</tei:hi> results, is severely handicapped by the wait for your final formulations.  My principal toils lie in the concepts of system, modal mixture, chromaticism, alteration, and also harmonic progression.  Even today, I cannot get by in my teaching without modifying points relating to the Urlinie!  My investigations into the [diatonic] systems are complete.  According to these, <tei:hi rend="italic">all</tei:hi> seven diatonic modes can be used for composition;  major and minor have emerged from the whole thing as name-givers on account of their triadic symmetry.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>  The <tei:hi rend="italic">cardinality of seven</tei:hi> of tones [in each diatonic grouping] is based on the artistic principle of <tei:hi rend="italic">amalgamation of harmonic and melodic logic</tei:hi>, which would be impossible with an even number of tones, i.e. even with Schoenberg's twelve-tone scale;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/>  see the diagram at the left:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">diagram and music example</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>In this connection, compare also measures 61 to the end of Brahms's Intermezzo in B flat minor (Three Intermezzi), as a counterpart in the <tei:hi rend="italic">Phrygian mode</tei:hi>, especially measures 67-71!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/>  The unconventional notation surely results from the leading note A striving for B flat, for which reason a notation is chosen that favors sharps over flats!  In fact, the harmonic progression in measures 67-69 should be: C<tei:hi rend="italic">b</tei:hi>-F, not B-F!  Some time, when I feel a bit calmer, I shall take the opportunity of putting together a large quanity of material.  Your ideas in <tei:hi rend="italic">Theory of Harmony</tei:hi>, pp. 364-65,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> hardly apply to Brahms.  In point of fact, my views on all these things do not contradict the basic principles that you teach, but rather represent an organic development of them.  More on this later.  (With me there is by no means the "Vreislanderian point of disloyalty";<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/>  with regard to the Beethoven Urlinie I bow to your superior insight.)</tei:p><tei:p>Enough for today, and <tei:hi rend="italic">more soon</tei:hi>, together with many cordial greetings to you and your wife.</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Cube</tei:p><tei:p>P. S.:  I am composing again!</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>