<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [34] : 9-12-32 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2008.
© Translation William Drabkin, 2008
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1932-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 09/12/1932 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker","ViolinM ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated September 12, 1932</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-06-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Cube outlines the conflict between Moriz Violin and the school authorities over inspection of the Hamburg Schenker-Institut, portrays his own differences of opinion with Violin, and asks for Schenker's opinion. 

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  Violin, Moriz;  Schenker-Institute, Hamburg;  conflict;  school authorites;  inspection;  Reichsverband</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Hamburg 37, Innecentiastraße 11</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated September 12, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hamburg 37, Innecentiastraße 11.
12. IX. 32.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Meister!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Receipt of this letter is recorded in (click on) &lt;a href="../../../../../diary/oj<tei:hi rend="italic">45</tei:hi>p<tei:hi rend="italic">3772</tei:hi>91532.html"&gt;Schenker's diary, OJ 4/5, p. 3772&lt;/a&gt;, September 15, 1932.  It gives Schenker's reaction to the content of Cube's letter.   </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ein Jahr ist nun nach der Eröffnung des Schenker-Instituts<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="schenker_institute_h">Schenker Institut prospectus</ref>.  </tei:note> vergangen.  Ein Jahr voll Mühen, Sorgen, Opfer, enttäuschter Hoffnungen, aber auch reicher Erfahrungen, zielbewusster Pionierarbeit und einiger tröstender Erfolge, so uns durch und mit dem Häuflein Aufrechter beschieden waren, die mit uns trotz aller Unbill der Zeit und ihres Un-Geistes bei unserer Aufgabe ausgeharrt haben.  Es ist noch zu früh für Rückblicke!  Gegenwart und Zukunft erfordern alle Aufmerksamkeit – insbesondere in diesem Augenblick, da sich Wichtiges entscheidet.  Ich nehme an, dass Sie, sehr verehrter Meister, durch Violin<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="violin_moriz">Moriz Violin</ref>.  </tei:note> über alles genauestens informiert sind, und wende mich an Sie, um Ihr Urteil zu hören, bevor ich zu den Dingen, die demnächst akut werden, endgültig Stellung nehme. –</tei:p><tei:p>Wie Sie wohl wissen, befindet sich Violin in einem Konflikt mit der Oberschulbehörde, wegen der Beaufsichtigungsfrage.  Die von ihm bewirkte Feststellungsklage ist in erster Instanz zu seinen Ungunsten entschieden worden.  Violin ist sich noch nicht schlüssig, ob er den Weg zum Oberverwaltungsgericht beschreiten soll, oder auch durch persönliche Aussprache mit dem Schulsenator zu einer amicalen Lösung zu gelangen versuchen soll.  In letzter Zeit aber beginnt er eine Lösung zu erwägen, die bei mir sowohl gefühlsmässig als auch intellektuell grossen Widerstand hervorruft.  Er will bei Fehlschlagen der letzteren Versuch auf den offiziellen Rang der öffentlichen Musikschule verzichten, und privatim als Violin, Cube, etc. unsere Arbeit fortführen, unbehelligt von den Behörden. <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Sein Standpunkt ist mir völlig klar. Er lehnt aus persönlich durchaus verständlichen Gründen einfach die Möglichkeit einer Einmischung jener Kreise ab, die ihm derart übel mitgespielt haben, ohne dass ihn selber ein Vorwurf  treffen könnte, ausser vielleicht dem einzigen, (seid aufrichtig, oh Freunde!) dem Gegner die Möglichkeit zu ihrem Schachzuge überhaupt <tei:hi rend="italic">gelassen</tei:hi> zu haben.  Es ist überaus schwierig für mich, zu ergründen, wo die Grenze zwischen persönlicher und sachlicher Gefolgschaft liegt!  Ich stehe Violin nahe genug[,] um seine Persönlichkeit mit immer neuer Bewundering in der Sache aufgehen zu sehen.  Aber ich habe durch mein Neuhinzukommen genug Distanz bewahrt, um mir gegebenfalls die Frage vorzulegen, wie weit die Sache in der Persönlichkeit aufgehen darf!  Ich halte mich nicht für befugt, diese Frage mir alleine zu beantworten.  Andererseits brauche ich zum Arbeiten ein sauberes Gewissen.  Deswegen bitte ich Sie um Ihr Urteil, das mir allein maaßgeblich sein kann.  Ich ging nach Hamburg, um dem <tei:hi rend="italic">Schenker-Insitut</tei:hi> meine Dienste zu weihen.  Innerhalb eines Jahres ist dies Institut in Hamburg ein <tei:hi rend="italic">Begriff</tei:hi> geworden.  Wird dieser Begriff von heute auf morgen ausgelöscht, so wird meines Erachtens allen unseren hiesigen Ambitionen ein tödlicher Schlag veretzt!  Ich kenne die Psyche der Norddeutschen, insonderheit die der Niedersachsen.  Ein Aufgeben unserer “Hausmarke” ist ihnen gleichbedeutend mit dem Eingeständnis unserer Niederlage.  Wir wären erledigt.  Ich baue nicht auf die Hilfe der Menge.  Aber – bei Gott! – ich <tei:hi rend="italic">fürchte</tei:hi> ihre <tei:hi rend="italic">Dummheit</tei:hi>!  Keinen der eventuellen Beweggründe würden sie verstehen.  Ich höre schon ihr:  “Also doch!”. –  Brauchen wir auch nicht die Menge, so brauchen wir doch ihr Vertrauen für unsere Zwecke.  Und jetzt gerade mehr, denn je!  Ein neuer Winter[,] eine neue Arbeitssaison – Resignation jetzt im Augenblick bedeutet den Teufel!  Eine Illustration:  Meine Vorträge im Reichsverband<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> Click on <ref cRef="reichsverband_deutsc">Reichsverband deutscher Tonkünstler und Musiklehrer</ref>. </tei:note> sind <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> so gut wie perfekt.  Ich habe mich <tei:hi rend="italic">sehr</tei:hi> bemüht, sie ins Schenker-Institut zu verlegen, stiess aber auf geschlossene Ablehnung.  Ich habe nachgegeben.  Die Vorträge finden auf neutralem Boden statt.  Die Fronde<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> Fronde:  the seventeenth-century protest  by the French aristocracy against absolute monarchy, hence any zealous political opposition.</tei:note> kämpft verbissen.  Ihre Methoden kennzeichnen ihre Einstellung.  Das Institut und Violin sind das rote Tuch.  Andererseits können sie ihre Neugier nicht bezähmen, und kamen, und kommen wohl wieder, scharenweise in meine Vorträge.  Ich meine, wir sollten daraus lernen, und in der Schulamtsfrage – scheinbar – nachgeben (praktisch können <tei:hi rend="italic">die</tei:hi> die <tei:hi rend="italic">Sache</tei:hi> nicht schädigen) und dafür den weitauswichtigeren Posten halten, nämlich den “öffentlichen Institutscharacter”.  Der Triumph der Gegener wäre ein Pyrrhussieg, nicht zu vergelichen mit <tei:hi rend="italic">dem</tei:hi> Triumph, den wir ihnen mit Aufgabe des “Instituts” <tei:hi rend="italic">freiwillig</tei:hi> liefern würden!  Dies sind meine Argumente.  Ich habe sie Violin gegenüber bereits vertreten.  <tei:hi rend="italic">Ihre</tei:hi> Stellungnahme wird mir indes ausschlaggebend sein.  Nichts liegt uns ferner, als Palastrevolution!  Aber nichts liegt mir näher, als der Dienst an <tei:hi rend="italic">Ihrem</tei:hi> Werke! –</tei:p><tei:p>Für diesmal ist dies alles.  Die Urlinien, für die ich bestens danke, habe ich noch nicht alle durchgearbeitet.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6"> These may include a revised version of a graph of Schubert’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Doppelgänger</tei:hi>, which Cube had sent Schenker on May 8, 1932, and further clarification of the Prelude in C from Bach’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Well-Tempered Clavier</tei:hi>, Book 1, of which publication in the <tei:hi rend="italic">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln</tei:hi> was imminent.</tei:note> Nächstens werde ich wieder ein paar rein künstlerische Fragen haben.  Manchmal möchte ich am liebsten wieder ein paar Stunden bei Ihnen nehmen.  Vorläufig bleibt’s ein Wunschtraum. –</tei:p><tei:p>Mit den herzlichsten Grüssen an Sie und Ihre Frau Gemahlin, denen sich meine Frau unbekannterweise anschliesst, bin ich immer</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Cube.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated September 12, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hamburg 37, Innecentiastraße 11.
September 12, 1932</tei:p><tei:p>Most esteemed master,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>A year has now passed since the opening of the Schenker Institute.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  A year full of difficulties, worries, sacrifices, and disappointed hopes;  but also of rich experiences, pioneering work that is conscious of its goals, and a few comforting successes as were granted to us by and with the small band of upright people, who kept us going in our mission in spite of all the injustice of the time and its malaise.  It is still too early for retrospectives!  Present and future require all our attention, especially at this moment, since crucial things will be decided.  I take it that you, most honoured master, have been informed by Violin<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> about everything in the most precise way; and I turn to you, to hear your judgement, before I take up my final position with regard to the things that will soon come to a head. –</tei:p><tei:p>As you probably know, Violin finds himself in conflict with the high school authorities, on account of the question of  inspection.  The complaint he raised regarding the evidence for this has, in the first instance, gone against him.  Violin has still not made up his mind whether he should take the path to the higher administrative court, or whether he should try to reach an amicable solution by speaking personally with the school senator.  Recently, however, he has begun to contemplate a situation which arouses great opposition in me, both emotionally and intellectually.  If the latest attempt fails, he wants to abandon the official position of a public music school and carry on our work privately, as Violin, Cube, etc., without the interference of the authorities.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> His point of view is entirely clear to me.  For reasons that seem to me entirely understandable, he rejects the possibility of getting mixed up in those circles that have played foully with him, without any criticism of him hitting their mark, apart perhaps from the only one (be sincere, oh friends!), which is to <tei:hi rend="italic">allow</tei:hi> his opponent any opportunity whatever of making a move against him.  It is extremely difficult for me to determine where the boundary between personal and objective persecution lies.  I am close enough to Violin to see, with ever greater wonderment, his personality shine as regards our cause.  But I have, from my recent awareness, kept enough distance to ask myself how far the cause should shine in the personality!  I do not regard myself as having the authority to answer this question alone, for myself.  On the other hand, I need a clear conscience in order to be able to work.  That is why I ask you for your judgement, which alone can be authoritative. I went to Hamburg to devote my services to the <tei:hi rend="italic">Schenker Institute</tei:hi>.  In that year, this institute has made a <tei:hi rend="italic">name</tei:hi> for itself in Hamburg.  Were this name suddenly to be extinguished, that would represent for me a death-blow to all our ambitions here! I know the psyche of the north Germans, in particular the Lower Saxons.  To give up our “brand name” would be tantamount to admitting defeat.  We would be finished.  I do not count on the help of the masses. But—by God!—I <tei:hi rend="italic">fear</tei:hi> their <tei:hi rend="italic">stupidity</tei:hi>!  The would not understand any of our motives.  I can already here their “Now, then!”  But even if we do not need the masses, we still need their faith in our purposes. And now even more than ever!  A new winter, a new season of work: to resign now at this moment would mean the devil! To give an illustration: my lectures at the Society [for German Composers and Music Teachers]<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> have gone just about perfectly.  I took a great deal of trouble to have them take place at the Schenker Institute, but was met with absolute refusal.  I gave in: the lectures will take place on neutral ground.  The opposition<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> is putting up a nasty fight.  Its methods characterize its position.  The Institute, and Violin, are like a red rag to a bull.  On the other hand, it cannot curb its curiosity; and came to my lectures, and will probably come again, in droves.  What I mean is that we should learn from this, and to—pretend to—yield on the matter regarding the school authorities (in a practical sense, <tei:hi rend="italic">these</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">people</tei:hi> cannot harm the <tei:hi rend="italic">cause</tei:hi>), and thereby hold onto the far more important situation, namely, the “public institute character”.  Our opponents’ triumph would be a pyrrhic victory, not to be compared with <tei:hi rend="italic">the</tei:hi> triumph, which we would hand them <tei:hi rend="italic">of our own free will</tei:hi> were we to dissolve the “Institute”!  These are my arguments.  I have explained them already to Violin.  Your view would, nevertheless, be decisive for me.  Nothing is further from our thoughts than a palace coup. But nothing lies closer to my thoughts than to serve <tei:hi rend="italic">your</tei:hi> work! –</tei:p><tei:p>For now, this is all.  I have not yet worked my through all the Urlinie graphs,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> for which I thank you most warmly.  The next time, I shall again have some purely artistic questions.  Sometimes I feel most like taking a few lessons from you:  For now, this must remain a dream. –</tei:p><tei:p>With most cordial greetings to you and your wife, to which are joined those of my wife (without being known to you), I am always</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Cube</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>