<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [14] : 10-4-28 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2006.
© Translation by William Drabkin, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1928-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 10/04/1928 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated October 4, 1928</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-07-18</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>C acks vC 18 and 19, and comments; reports on his own recent activities and plans, and on events in the Conservatory, on a forthcoming Schubert festival, and Radio Vienna.  He is about to return the Hammer etching.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  Hamburg;  graphs;  Beethoven;  Moonlight Sonata;  Chopin;  etude;  Well-tempered Clavier;  Mozart;  Werden;  folk dancing;  choral singing;  Albrecht, Hans;  Köln;  Cologne;  Conservatory;  Blech, Leo;  Reichenberger;  Schillings, Max von;  Busch, Fritz;  Duisburg;  Schubert;  Radio Vienna;  Tautenhayn;  Grock;  Wood, Henry;  Hindemith;  Hammer, Victor</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Duisburg, Rhineland, Pulverweg 41</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated October 4, 1928</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Duisburg/Rhld.
Pulverweg 41.
4.X.28.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Recht vielen Dank für Ihre beiden Karten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> vC 18 and 19, September 6 and 29, 1928.</tei:note> Die Sache in Hamburg<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  In vC 18, September 6, 1928, S reported that the Hamburg Tonkünstlerverein had used graphs on “large boards” for teaching purposes, also more specifically in vC 29, July 22, 1929.</tei:note> ist <tei:hi rend="italic">sehr</tei:hi> erfreulich! Diese natürlich-proportionale Ausbreitung Ihrer Lehre ist wiederum ein schöner Beweis ihrer Natur-Gültigkeit. Die Idee mit den Riesentafeln ist gut. Ich selbst pflegte in ähnlichen Fällen bisher die Stimmführungsbilder mit weisser und roter Kreide auf richtigen Notenschultafeln zu entwickeln. Das langsame Entstehen der Bilder von den Augen der Zuhörer hat, so glaube ich, auch sehr viel für sich. Zuletzt brachte ich den ersten Satz der op.27 N^o^ 2 von Beethoven, eine Chopin-Etüde, ein Präludium aus dem Wohlt. Klavier, eine Mozart-sonate und ähnliches mehr – auch direkt aus dem Stegreif.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Some of these analyses were set out formally in Cube’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Lehrbuch der musikalischen Kunstgesetze</tei:hi>, begun in Hamburg in the mid-1930s and used there for teaching purposes.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Die Werdener Escapade<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> A small town on Lake Balden, just south of Essen.</tei:note> ist tragikomisch verlaufen. Ich musste annehmen, dass es sich um eine ernste, wissenschaftliche Zusammenkunft handle, statt dessen geriet ich in eine Versammlung halbwüchsiger Seminaristen, die hauptsächlich Volkstänze und Choralsingen exerzierten. Ein einziger Theoriefachmann hatte sich gleich mir dorthin verirrt – den habe ich noch schnell bekehrt. Als ihm die Schuppen von den Augen gefallen waren, und sein Staunen sich in heftiges Interesse gewandelt hatte, verliess ich ihn und die ganze Schulmusikwoche mit Segenswünschen, und begab mich wieder nach Hause.  Der Name des jungen Mannes ist Dr. Hans Albrecht.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> Hans Albrecht (1902–61), German musicologist who studied at Essen Conservatory 1912–21, then in Berlin, after which he taught in several places over the following twelve years.  He was active in the <ref cRef="reichsverband_deutsc">Reichsverband Deutscher Tonkünstler and Musiklehrer</ref>.</tei:note> Er ist Theorielehrer am Konservatorium in Essen.</tei:p><tei:p>Meine nächsste Aufgabe besteht in einer Reise nach Köln, die etwa in 14 Tagen fällig ist, um mit Braunfels<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6"> Walter Braunfels (1882–1954), German composer and pianist.  In 1925, he established the Hochschule für Musik in Cologne, and remained its director until forced out of office in 1933.  </tei:note> über die mögliche Aufstellung einer Arbeitsgemeinschaft für Ihre Theorien zu sprechen. Das dürfte der beste Weg sein, um eines Tages unversehens in die Hochschule hineinzurutschen. Das hiesige Musik- und Konservatoriumsleben wird mehr und mehr zur Farce. Daran ändern auch die pompösen Konzerte nichts mehr. Trotz Leo Blech,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7"> Leo Blech (1871–1958), German conductor and composer, conductor at the Berlin Staatsoper 1926–37.  </tei:note> Reichenberger,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Reichenberger [identify]. </tei:note> Schillings<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Max von Schillings (1868–1933), German composer and conductor, most recently Intendant at the Berlin Opera 1918(?)-25. </tei:note> und Busch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Fritz Busch [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> bilanzieren wir Minus. Der <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Duisburger Stahl- und Kohlensklave ist veredelungsunfähig.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  <tei:hi rend="italic">veredelungsunfähig</tei:hi>: Cube is playing on the double meaning of <tei:hi rend="italic">edel</tei:hi>. In describing the people of Duisburg as being incapable of understanding the refinements of art, he alludes to the process whereby the city’s chief industrial product, steel, is refined to become <tei:hi rend="italic">Edelstahl</tei:hi> (“stainless steel”).</tei:note> Das Musikleben ein Koloss auf tönernen Füssen. Ich lamentiere nicht darüber, wie die Kollegenheit ringsum, (auch mein Einkommen hat sich um 40% verringert) aber ich suche mich mit aller Energie zu verändern – und zu verbessern. Also auf nach Köln!</tei:p><tei:p>Reichenberger, der meine Eltern kennen lernte, will Composition von mir lesen. Ich will ihm etliches schicken. (Schaden kann es nie). An meiner zweiten Sonate fehlt ein Stück vom letzten Satz.  Es ist schwer, und will nicht recht geraten. Allzulange wird’s nicht mehr dauern. Dann kommt Kammermusik dran. Alles hübsch der Reihe nach. Wenn es so weit ist, will ich Sie um Rat bitten, wie man an die Verleger herankommt. Meine erste Sonate ist zum Componistenwettbewerb eingereicht.</tei:p><tei:p>Demnächst ist hier ein Schubertfest. Dazu werde ich über Aufforderung die einleitenden Worte sprechen, und mich durchaus nicht scheuen, den Phäakenseelen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Carefree people who enjoy the good life. The Phaecians inhabited the mythical island of Scheria,  where Odysseus was lavishly enteretained before making the final leg of his voyage to Ithaca.</tei:note> hier ein bischen die Wahrheit zu sagen.</tei:p><tei:p>Mein Rundfunk-Ohr ist durch einen neuen, sehr guten Lautsprecher bereichert. Radio Wien höre ich oft und gern. Immer die Sinfoniekonzerte, und die lieben Tautenhayns.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13"> Tautenhayn:probably a musical presenter for Radio Vienna (see OJ 9/34, [3], November 25, 1926 (Cube to Schenker) and vC 21, November 20, 1928 (Schenker to Cube).</tei:note> Ausgezeichnete Musik machen die Engländer. Der Clown “Grock” stellte sich als Cellist vor.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">. Stage name of the American actor Adrian Wettach.</tei:note> Weit das beste, was ich seit langem gehört habe! Die Conzerte unter Henry Wood<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15"> Henry Wood (1869-1944), creator of the Henry Wood Promenade Concerts given in the Royal Albert Hall, London and broadcast by the British Broadcasting Corporation.</tei:note> sind eine Ohrenweide. Dagegen erinnert der neue Hindemith mehr und mehr an einen losgelassenen Hühnerhof.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn16"> Cube may be playing here to his teacher’s antipathy towards the music of Paul Hindemith, as expressed in the “Miscellanea” of the recently published second volume of <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>. </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Die Hammer-Radierung<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn17">  S had supplied C with two engravings of himself by Victor Hammer [create biogfile and link] for the exhibit in the Scheuermann bookstore in Duisburg in June for S’s 60th birthday, and instructed him not to return the second of these to him in Vienna until October. vC 19, July 13, 1928.</tei:note> geht mit gleicher Post an Sie ab.  Nochmals herzlichen Dank dafür.</tei:p><tei:p>Für heute die besten Grüsse Ihnen und Ihrer Frau Gemahlin. Nach der Kölnerreise wieder mehr von</tei:p><tei:p>Ihrem
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Cube.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated October 4, 1928</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Duisburg, Rhineland
Pulverweg 41
October 4, 1928</tei:p><tei:p>Most honoured master,</tei:p><tei:p>Very many thanks for your two cards.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> The Hamburg idea sounds very agreeable.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> This naturally proportional dissemination of your theory is an elegant proof of its validity in nature. The idea of gigantic graphs is a good one. Hitherto, in similar situations, I myself used to develop voice-leading graphs with white and red chalk on proper school blackboards with staves. The slow evolution of the graphs before the eyes of the audience also has, I believe, a great deal to recommend it. Most recently I rendered the first movement of Beethoven’s “Moonlight” Sonata, a Chopin etude, a prelude from the <tei:hi rend="italic">Well-Tempered Clavier</tei:hi>, a sonata by Mozart, and more of that sort of thing—sometimes directly out of my head.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/></tei:p><tei:p>The Werden escapade<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> came off in tragicomic fashion. I had assumed that it would be a serious meeting of scholars; instead I joined a gathering of half-educated students who mainly practised folk dancing and choral singing. A single expert in theory had, like myself, erroneously made his way there; I quickly converted him. As his eyes were opened wide, and his amazement changed into the most vivid interest, I took my leave of him, and the entire school music week, with my kindest wishes and returned home. The name of the young man is Dr Hans Albrecht.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> He is a theory teacher at the conservatory in Essen.</tei:p><tei:p>My next assignment consists of a trip to Cologne, in about a fortnight, to talk with Braunfels<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> about the possibility of setting up a working group for your theories. This may be the best way to slip into the Conservatory one day, unexpectely. The local music life, and that of the conservatory, is becoming increasingly farcical; even the pompous concerts do not change things any more. In spite of Leo Blech,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> Reichenberger,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> Schillings<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> und Busch<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> we are making a loss. The <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> slaves who are employed by the Duisburg steel and coal works are incapable of dignification.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> The musical life is a collosus built on clay feet. I do not lament this situation, like my colleagues around me (even though my income has gone down by forty percent); but I try with all my might to change my lot, and to improve myself. So on to Cologne!</tei:p><tei:p>Reichenberger, who made the acquaintance of my parents, wants to read my compositions. I will send him various things. (It cannot do any harm.) In the last movement of my second sonata a section is missing; it is difficult, and just does not come out right; but it will not take me too much longer to finish. Then I will turn to chamber music: everything slowly, one at a time. When I have progressed far enough, I shall ask you for advice about approaching publishers. My first sonata has been submitted in the composer’s competition.</tei:p><tei:p>There is soon to be a Schubert festival here. For this I have been invited to give the opening address; and will by no means shy away from telling the truth a bit to the Phaeacians.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/></tei:p><tei:p>I have upgraded my radio receiver with a new, very good loudspeaker. I listen to Radio Vienna often, and with pleasure: all of the symphony concerts, and the charming Tautenhayn programmes.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> The English perform music excellently. The clown “Grock”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/> presented himself as a cellist:  by far the best that I have heard in a long time. The concerts directed by Henry Wood<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn15"/> are a feast for the ears. By contrast, Hindemith’s latest music reminds me increasingly of a liberated chicken farm.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn16"/></tei:p><tei:p>Die Hammer etching<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn17"/> will be sent in the same posting as this letter; once again, my  heartfelt thanks for it.</tei:p><tei:p>For today, best wishes to you and your wife. After the trip to Cologne you will hear again from</tei:p><tei:p>Your
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ]  Cube</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>