<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [41] : 6-7-34 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin 2006.
© Transcription William Drabkin 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1934-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 06/07/1934 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated June 7, 1934</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-10-10</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Acks [non-extant] letter in which S had expressed dismay at a review [enclosed with OJ 9/34, [40]] of a recent lecture by C, who explains the circumstances under which he had to disguise the source of some of his ideas: Schenkerian theory is regarded as "Jewish rubbish," and is no longer discussed; one has to choose one words carefully.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  lecture;  review;  Jewish propaganda;  Jewish rubbish;  Hamburg;  Violin, Moriz</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Hamburg 13, Mittelweg 126, Ia/^II.^</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated June 7, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hamburg 13, Mittelweg 126, Ia/^II.^
7.VI.34.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter, lieber Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich danke Ihnen für Ihren Brief,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> A letter from Schenker to Cube, written on June 4 or 5, 1934, has been lost. Nor does the newspaper review of Cube’s public lecture in Hamburg, which is the subject of Schenker’s letter and Cube’s reply here, survive in the Schenker scrapbook. It can only be inferred that Schenker took exception to the way in which some of his ideas were explained in the lecture, and censured his former pupil for having exploited them for his own benefit.</tei:note> den ich in diesem Augenblick erhielt.  Ich ersehe daraus, dass eine Bemerkung in der Besprechung Ihnen eine Betroffenheit verursacht hat, die ich mir mit Ihrer Unkenntnis der hiesigen Verhältnisse und Zusammenhänge erkläre.  Ich darf daher zu Ihrer Aufklärung folgendes feststellen:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  S continues writing without paragraph-break.  (This letter, written as one single long paragraph, has been broken up into shorter paragraphs for ease of reading on-screen.  In a print edition, one would leave it undivided.)</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Den Vortrag hielt ich in der Zeit der wildesten Gerüchtsmacherei, die mich bedrängte, und mich auch meine Stellung kostete.  Die Kritik erschien erst einige Wochen darauf, und gekennzeichnet das Anfangsstadium der Sache!  Ich bin dem Kritiker<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  The identity of the reviewer is unknown.</tei:note> für seine Eingangsbemerkung zu Dank verpflichtet, <tei:hi rend="italic">denn er hat mir dadurch Luft verschafft</tei:hi>, den Leuten gegenüber, die jedes Wort aus meinem Munde in Hamburg als +Judenpropaganda+ ausposaunten!  Ich fand es auch ganz in der Ordnung, dass er Ihrer in der Kritik in dem Umfange erwähnte, wie ich von Ihnen zu sprechen in meinem Vortrage wagen konnte, ohne mir ganz unvorsichtigerweise eine nicht wieder gutzumachende Gegnerschaft zuzuziehen, was sowieso in einigem Umfange geschehen ist.  Man kann dem Kritiker nicht mal eine Notlüge vorwerfen, denn ich habe mit Absicht diejenigen +Ihrer+ Wahrheiten, die ich zu bringen für notwendig fand, in ein pädagogisches Vortragsgewand +eigener+ Provenienz +so+ gekleidet, wie man es heute bei uns +gerne+ hört, und hoffe damit der Wahrheit einen besseren Dienst geleis[t]et zu haben, als wenn ich nur dickköpfigerweise ein Redeverbot geholt hätte (wie gewisse andere Leute).  Es hat mir genügt, dass unser geschäftsführender Vorsitzender den Vortrag als “nicht geeignet” bezeichnet hat.  Warum brauche ich wohl nicht zu sagen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  S continues writing without paragraph-break.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Dass die Schenker-Theorie heute nicht diskutiert wird (“vorläufig” heisst es im Brief der Landesleitung) liegt wohl zum guten Teil daran, dass ich die Landesleitung persönlich, und auch durch Mitwirkung einiger anderer, vernünftiger Leute vom Inhalt und Werte Ihrer Lebensarbeit erst in Kenntnis gesetzt habe! Noch vor kurzer Zeit war die Schenker-Theorie ”jüdischer Kram”, und die betreffenden Herren hatten weder eine Ahnung von Ihrer Arbeit, noch wussten sie, das Sie noch leben!  +So+ stand und steht es um Ihre Bekanntheit hier im hohen Norden! Die Geltung, die Sie in Hamburg geniessen, habe ich Ihnen grösstenteils durch meine Arbeit erworben, und auch Violin will ich hier nennen!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="violin_moriz">Moriz Violin</ref>.</tei:note>  Es gibt noch mehrere Leute hier, die aus <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi>Ihren Werken Nutzen ziehen, aber diese haben das Maul nicht mehr aufgemacht, als es nicht mehr opportün schien!  Absurd aber wäre, zu denken, ich wollte mich auf Ihre Kosten dick tun!  Auf “Schaden” oder “Erfolg” für mich kommt es +überhaupt garnicht+ an, sondern +einzig+ auf die Wahrheit!  Und die Art und Weise, wie ich für diese kämpfe ergibt sich ganz und gar aus den hiesigen Verhältnissen, die zu überblicken Ihnen von dort wohl nur schwer möglich sein dürfte!  Das einzige, was ich für mich in Anspruch nehme, ist die Freiheit, +eigene+ Gedanken zu entwickeln; und wo und wann ich diese äußere, muß wohl meinem Ermessen überlassen bleiben. –<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  S inserts an emdash, then continues writing without paragraph-break.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Noch eins: meine “Hilfe” bei der Kritik erstreckte sich auf das Gedächtnis des Kritikers in Bezug auf einige, mir wichtig erscheinende Punkte, auf dass sie nicht vergessen würden.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  S continues writing without paragraph-break.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Zum Schluss, lieber, verehrter Meister, ein aktuelles Wort: “Deutsch sein, heisst eine Sache um ihrer selbst willen tun!”  Verlangen Sie nich mehr von mir!  Hätten Sie an meiner Stelle das erdulden müssen, was ich hier um der Wahrheit also auch um Ihretwillen erduldet habe, so hätten Sie Ihre Worte vielleicht ein wenig anders gesetzt! –</tei:p><tei:p>Meine Frau und Ich danken herzlichst für Ihre guten Wünsche, und wünschen Ihnen und Ihrer Gattin recht gute Erholung! –</tei:p><tei:p>Mit besten Grüssen
Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ]  Cube</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated June 7, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hamburg 13, Mittelweg 126, Ia/^II.^
June 7, 1934
		
Most honoured, dear master,</tei:p><tei:p>I thank you for your letter, which just arrived.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  From it I see that a remark in the review has caused dismay, which I shall explain, given your ignorance of the current conditions and relations. I can thus state, by way of explanation, the following:<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/></tei:p><tei:p>I gave the lecture at a time when I was besieged by the the wildest rumor-mongering, which oppressed me, and even cost me my position. The review appeared only some weeks later, and marks the initial phase of the matter!  I am indebted to the reviewer<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> for his introductory remarks, <tei:hi rend="italic">for in so doing he created a breathing-space for me</tei:hi> with respect to those people who trumpeted every word that came from my mouth in Hamburg as <tei:hi rend="italic">Jewish propaganda</tei:hi>!  I also found it entirely appropriate that he mentioned you to some extent in the review, as I could dare to speak about you in my lecture without my attracting, entirely inadvertently, an opposition that could not be overcome, and which to some extent surfaced anyway. One cannot accuse the reviewer even of telling a white lie, since I intentionally disguised those of +your+ truths that I regarded as important to bring out in a pedagogical guise of +my own+ making, as one is +accustomed+ to doing here these days, and hope that I have thereby given better service to the truth than if I had, stupidly, refused to have a discussion [period following the lecture], as certain other people do.  It was enough for me that our master of ceremonies deemed the lecture “unsuitable.”  Why that was the case is something I hardly need to explain.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/></tei:p><tei:p>That Schenkerian threory is not discussed today (“for the time being,” as it says in the letter of the provincial director) probably has to do in part with the fact that I have only now—personally, and also through collaboration with other, reasonable people—made the provincial director aware of the content and value of your life’s work! Even a short time ago, Schenkerian theory was “Jewish rubbish,” and the gentlemen in question neither had an inkling of your work, nor did they know that you were still alive!  So +this+ is the way things were, and are, regarding your reputation here in the great North! The standing that you enjoy in Hamburg is largely the result of my efforts, and here I will mention Violin’s name, too!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  There are still other people here who draw profit from <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> your works, but they stopped opening their mouths when it no longer seemed opportune to do so! Yet it would be absurd to suppose that I would show off, at your expense!  For me the question of “damage” or “success” is +entirely irrelevant+; the +only+ thing that matters is the truth!  And the way in which I fight for these results entirely and exclusively from the present circumstances, which would certainly be very difficult for you to observe!  The only thing that I ask for myself is the freedom to develop +my own+ ideas, and where and when I express these must be left to my judgement.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/></tei:p><tei:p>One more thing: my “help” with the review extended [only] as far as reminding the reviewer of a few points that seemed important to me, so that they would not be forgotten.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/></tei:p><tei:p>Let me conclude, dear, honored master, with a contemporary saying:  “To be German is to do something for its own sake!” Ask nothing more of me!  If you were in my shoes and had to put up with what I have had to put up with here for the sake of the truth, i.e. also for your sake, you would have perhaps chosen your words a little differently! –</tei:p><tei:p>My wife and I thank you most cordially for your good wishes, and wish you and your wife a good rest! –</tei:p><tei:p>With best greetings,
Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>