<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [33] : 7-2-32 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1932-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 07/02/1932 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated July 2, 1932</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-06-19</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Cube outlines, with music examples and graphs, a theory of tonal system and modal mixture based on "the series of 5ths," "the closed-up circle of 5ths," and "differentiation of the resultant intervals in a diatonic projection" as a scale.   He asks for Schenker's reaction.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  Mixtur;  modal mixture;  Tonalität; tonality;  diatonic projection</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Hamburg 37, Innocentiastrasse 11</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated July 2, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hamburg 37, Innocentiastraße 11.
2.VII.32.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter, lieber Meister!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary, OJ 4/5, p. 3745, July 4, 1932 as "a treatise with carefully-drawn graphs."  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Dieser Brief mag lang genug werden, daher gehe ich gleich in medias res:  es handelt sich um eine Gedankenreihe, die ich Ihnen unterbreiten möchte, um zu erfahren, ob sie stichhaltig genug sei, um weiter verfolgt zu werden.  Kardinalpunkte sind Sÿsthem<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  From 1932 onwards, Cube used the “Greek” y in German words with an umlaut. He eventually stopped transliterating theta as “th” (as in “Sÿsthem”); but “Analÿse” appears regularly in later writings.</tei:note> und Mischung!  Mehr noch sogar der aus beiden resultierende Begriff der Tonalität.  Ich lasse meine Gedankenskizze hier in Schlagworten folgen, so können Sie am besten sehen, dass selbe durchaus Ihrer Theorie konsequent ist, und auch, ob und wo allenfalls ein Denk- oder Hörfehler stecken könnte:</tei:p><tei:p>Die menschliche Hörweite und Begriffsbeschränkung stellt an das Sÿstem in der Tonkunst drei Hauptförderungen: a.) lückenlose Quintenfolge, b.) in sich geschlossener Quintenkreis, c.) Unterschiedbarkeit der in diatonischer Projektion (Ordnung nach relativen Tonhöhen) entstehenden Intervalle. –<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  By “diatonic projection,” Cube means the formation of a scale, the reordering of notes initially determined by a cycle of fifths to form a stepwise series.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Das “Zwölfquintensÿsthem” ist das einzig denkbare, das alle drei Forderungen erfüllen kann.  Beim 53- und 41-Quintensÿsthem sind die Intervalle der enstehenden “Tonleiter” nicht mehr unterschiedbar.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Cycles of 41 and 53 “pure” fifths (i.e. an exact frequency ratio of 3:2) will come nearer to closing the tonal circle than a cycle of 12 fifths, i.e. the end point will be more nearly an exact multiple of an octave. But when either of these sequences are reconfigured as a series ascending tones, the distance between them is barely perceptible as an interval.</tei:note>  Ein 24-Quintensÿsthem (eigentliches Vierteltonsÿsthem) ist untemperierbar und nicht in sich geschlossen.  (Die landläufigen Vierteltonsÿstheme sind zwei um einen Viertelton differierende Zwölfquintenzirkel, die keine Verbindung haben.)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Probably a reference to the quarter-tone music of Alois Hába, founder of a department of microtonal music at the Prague Conservatory in the 1920s.</tei:note>  Notabene: Gäbe es noch eine andere Möglichkeit, als die bestehende, die Genies hätten sie <tei:hi rend="italic">gewiss</tei:hi> ausgenutzt!</tei:p><tei:p>Aus der chaotischen Überfülle der natürlichen Möglichkeiten <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> entnahm man vielmehr einen “überhörbaren”, unseren Begriffsbegrenzungen angepassten Quintenausschnitt:</tei:p><tei:p>||Deses||C|His|
||←</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated July 2, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hamburg 37, Innocentiastrasse 11
July 2, 1932</tei:p><tei:p>Most honoured, dear master,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>This letter will probably be rather long, so I will get to the heart of the matter immediately:  it concerns a chain of thought that I should like to amplify for you, in order to learn whether they are logical enough to be worth pursuing further.  The cardinal points are [tonal] system<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> and modal mixture!  And still further:  the concept of tonality resulting from both.  In what follows, I shall outline my ideas in broad terms here, so that you yourself can best see that they are entirely consistent with your theory and also whether, and where, any mistakes in reasoning or listening may be hidden.</tei:p><tei:p>The limitations of human hearing and capacity for abstraction results in three principal requirements of the musical system:  a) an unbroken series of fifths, b) a closed-up circle of fifths, c) differentiation of the resultant intervals in a diatonic projection (as ordered by relative pitch).<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/></tei:p><tei:p>The system of twelve fifths is the only imaginable one that can fulfil all three demands.  In the systems of 53 and 41 fifths, the intervals of the resultant “scale” would no longer be distinguishable.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  A system of 24 fifths (i.e. a quarter-tone system) cannot be tempered, and is not closed in itself.  (The current quarter-tone systems are made up of two unconnected circles of twelve fifths, a quarter tone apart.)<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>   NB: if there were another possibility than the system we have, the geniuses would certainly made use of it!</tei:p><tei:p>From the chaotic superabundance of natural possibilities, <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> it was, rather, preferable to take the “perceivable” series of fifths, which corresponded to limits of our capacity for abstraction,</tei:p><tei:p>||D<tei:hi rend="italic">bb</tei:hi>||C|B#|
||←</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>