<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [12] : 5-24-28 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2006.
© Translation by William Drabkin 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1928-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 05/24/1928 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated May 24, 1928</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-07-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>C acks receipt of the Hammer engravings and reports on the planned Scheuermann exhibit; reports on a forthcoming lecture and seminar, and the growth of his student numbers.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  Hammer, Victor;  engravings;  Düsseldorf Conservatory;  Urlinie;  Scheuermann;  Reger, Max;  Österreichische Nationalbibliothek;  Austrian National Library;  Duisburg;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  Aufruf;  sonata</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Duisburg, Rhineland, Pulverweg 41</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated May 24, 1928</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">letterhead</tei:hi>] FELIX E. VON CUBE
Duisburg./ Rhld.
Pulverweg 41.
24. V. 28.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Die Hammer-Radierungen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  C had requested these in OJ 9/34, [10], January 30, 1928, and again in OJ 9/34, [11], April 24; S responded in vC 14, April 29.  The artist Victor Hammer [create biogfile and link] made an engraving of Schenker’s portrait in 1925; 100 copies of this were printed, and sold by the Viennese art shop of Artaria &amp; Co. The image survives as OJ 72/14, item 7. </tei:note> sind angekommen, und befinden sich bereits unter Glas und Rahmen, um ihrem Zwecke zugeführt zu werden.</tei:p><tei:p>Dass ich eine davon behalten darf, ist eine der seltensten Freuden meines Lebens, und fügt meinen grossen Dankbarkeiten gegen Sie eine neue, nicht weinger schöne und tiefe hinzu!</tei:p><tei:p>Meinen Vortrag werde ich nun auch im Konservatorium der Stadt Düsseldorf, vor einem voraussichtlich recht zahlreichen auditorium halten. Ich musste ihn ein wenig ändern, da ich eine Dosis geistige Regsamkeit zuviel bei den Zuhörern vorausgesetzt hatte.</tei:p><tei:p>Meine Tätigkeit am hiesigen Konservatorium nimmt zu. Als unmittelbare Folge meines Theorie- <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> unterrichtes habe ich als neue Schüler einige “Überläufer” zu verzeichnen, ein Umstand, der nicht angetan ist, die Sympathien der also geschädigten lieben Kollegen zu gewinnen.</tei:p><tei:p>End Juni spreche ich einen ganzen Vormittag lang vor der gesamten Seminarschüler- und Lehrerschaft von Ihren Theorien, der Urlinie und der wahren Art das Klavier zu spielen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> A quotation from the title of C. P. E. Bach’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Versuch über die wahre Art, das Clavier zu spielen</tei:hi>; for Schenker, Bach’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Versuch</tei:hi> was the most important treatise on music ever written.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Die Buchhandlung Scheuermann macht die Ausstellung<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> Scheuermann, the leading bookseller in Cube’s home town of Duisburg, had undertaken to mount an exhibit to mark Schenker’s 60th birthday.  Schenker’s antipathy toward Reger was well-known to his circle, and to readers of his work.</tei:note> gleich nach einem hier stattfindenden “Regerfest”, solange die Gemüter noch musikalisch erregt sind. Die Firma hat nach Wien an das Archiv der Nationalbibliothek geschrieben, aber keinerlei Antwort erhalten. Ich würde sehr gerne wissen, ob wir damit rechnen können, bereits einige Handschriftenabzüge der Musikerschaft Duisburgs zugänglich machen zu können.  Interesse und Erwartung sind genugsam vorhanden.  Der Aufruf Hobokens<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>; <ref cRef="aufruf_november_1927">Aufruf</ref>.</tei:note> hat seine Wirkung nicht verfehlt.</tei:p><tei:p>Der dritte Satz (der letzte) meiner zweiten Sonate ist in Arbeit; beide Sonaten beteiligen sich im Winter am Komponisten-Wettbewerb. –</tei:p><tei:p>Für heute die besten Grüsse Ihnen und Ihrer Frau Gemahlin</tei:p><tei:p>von Ihrem
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated May 24, 1928</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">letterhead</tei:hi>] FELIX E. VON CUBE
Duisburg, Rhineland
Pulverweg 41
24 May 1928</tei:p><tei:p>Most honoured master,</tei:p><tei:p>The Hammer engravings<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> arrived, and are already under glass and in frames, in order that they may serve their purpose.</tei:p><tei:p>That I may be permitted to keep one of them is one of the rarest joys of my life, and adds to my great thankfulness to you in a new and no less beautiful or profound way!</tei:p><tei:p>I shall give my lecture now also in the Conservatory of the City of Düsseldorf, in front of what is expected to be a large audience. I had to change it a bit, as I had anticipated an extra measure of intellectual alertness among the listeners.</tei:p><tei:p>My activity at the local conservatory is growing. As an immediate consequence of my theory <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> instruction, I may reckon among my new pupils a few “transfers”: a situation that is not likely to win the sympathies of my dear colleagues who have thus been injured.</tei:p><tei:p>At the end of June I shall speak for an entire morning to all the pupils and teachers in the Seminar about your theories, the Urlinie, and the true art of playing the piano.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/></tei:p><tei:p>The bookstore Scheuermann will mount the exhibition<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> immediately after a Reger festival that is taking place here, so long as the spirits are still musically excited. The firm wrote to the archive of the National Library in Vienna, but did not receive any reply at all. I would love to know if we can therefore count on making available several copies of manuscripts of Duisburg’s musicians. Interest and expectation are in sufficient supply. Hoboken’s<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> appeal did not go amiss.</tei:p><tei:p>The third movement (the finale) of my second sonata is in progress; both sonatas will take part in the composers’ competition this coming winter.</tei:p><tei:p>For today, my best greetings to you and your wife</tei:p><tei:p>from your
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>