<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [37] : 5-11-33 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
©  Transcription William Drabkin 2008.
© Translation William Drabkin, 2008
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1933-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 05/11/1933 02:27:35 PM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated May 11, 1933</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-12-14</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Cube, in response to vC 45, defends his choice of a descent from ~3, with neighbor-note ~4, in his analysis of the first theme of Beethoven Op. 26, mvt 1, with graphs as "proof";  he also defends political developments in Germany, and attributes his threatened hunger to Violin's return to Vienna.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  Gesetz;  law;  Nebennote;  neighbor-note;  Urbild;  Ursatz;  Durchgang;  passing note;  Urlinie;  Anstieg;  ascent;  Volkshymne;  national anthem;  Stufengrundton;  Zug;  progression;  Oktavsprung;  octave leap;  Kadenz;  cadence;  Deutschland;  Germany;  politics;  Stravinsky;  Hindemith;  welfare;  Violin, Moriz</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Hamburg 13, Dillstraße 1./I</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker,date May 11, 1933</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hamburg 13, Dillstraße 1./I.
11.V.33.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter, lieber Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Mit vielen Dank für Ihre Zeilen beginne ich meine neulich versprochene, längere Epistel.  An den Anfang setze ich wie immer die Kunst, und zwar nochmals unseren Beethoven!  Abgesehen davon, dass ich, wie Sie offenbar auch darin einen typischen "Grenzfall" (ob ~3 oder ~5) sehe, kann ich nicht umhin, einige schwerwiegende Erwägungen geltend zu machen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  This letter is a direct response to Schenker's critique (vC 45) of Cube's analysis of the theme from the first movement of Beethoven's Sonata, Op. 26.</tei:note>  Es geht hier um das Gesetz an sich so gut, wie um seine Formulierung. Ich meditiere:</tei:p><tei:p>Das Spiel der ~3 versuchte ich durch eine Darstellung in einer besonderen Étage zu verdeutlichen, ohne deshalb auf die ~5 zu verzichten.  Letztere ist mir zu stark belegt, als dass ich sie theoretisch ignorieren könnte. Zum Beweis:</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">music example 1</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>Dies <tei:hi rend="italic">kann</tei:hi> es meiner Ansicht nach <tei:hi rend="italic">nicht</tei:hi> geben!  Ist die Nbn. wirklich <tei:hi rend="italic">nur</tei:hi> Nbn., so hiesse das Urbild so:</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">music example 2</tei:hi> ].</tei:p><tei:p>Es ginge aber gegen alle Erfahrung, wenn eine Sept sich im Ursatz selbständig macht;  die 7 ist Dg. und muss es bleiben.  Daher auch <tei:hi rend="italic">Ihr</tei:hi> 8-7!!  Ist die 8 aber da, so ist sie es <tei:hi rend="italic">von Anfang an</tei:hi>!!!  Es gibt da nur zwei Möglichkeiten.  Entweder</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">music example 3</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>oder</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">music example 4</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>das heisst im letzteren Falle musste man der Url. einen Anstieg zubilligen.  Dies ist von Ihrer Seite einmal in der Volkshÿmne geschehen!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  i.e. Haydn's "Emperor Hymn," the subject of a short analytical essay in <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</tei:hi> 10 (1924).</tei:note>  Im Interesse der felsenfesten Fundamentierung <tei:hi rend="italic">Ihrer</tei:hi> Lehre ist es vonnöten, dass über die <tei:hi rend="italic">Notierungsfrage</tei:hi> absolute Klarheit und Übereinstimmung herrsche!!!  Es ist aber nicht einmal notwendig, eine Nbn. oder eine  ~4 in Takt 26 anzunehmen.  Ich bin nämlich auch mit den drei Anstiegen nicht einverstanden. Der Inhalt der ersten 16 Takte lautet grundsätzlich so:</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">music example 5</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>man kann nun, vorläufig von der Frage ob Ober- oder Mittelstimme abgesehen, nicht auf der einen Seite ohne weiteres einen Stufengrundton supponieren, wie Sie es hier tun:</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">music example 6</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>denn ich nehme hier an:</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">music example 7</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>Ich finde, dass letzteres doch den gegebenen Tatsachen <tei:hi rend="italic">mehr</tei:hi> entspricht!  Das erste des^2^ in Takt 5 ist sehr dünn besetzt mit dem f des 4-Zuges über liegendem as!  das zweite des^2^ ist schon kräftiger - Takt 13 - , da der Bass eine wirkliche IV Stufe in Sextlage ist. <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Das dritte des^2^ endlich, worin ich die ~4 der Url. höre, ist schon durch die doppelte Besetzung der Stimmen - Takt 31 - von den beiden anderen ausgezeichnet. Warum also ist nicht <tei:hi rend="italic">gerade hier</tei:hi> die Supposition der IV Stufe weil angebrachter als in den Takten 1-16, wo sie in Takt 5 doch in keiner Weise stichhaltig ist?  Takt 1-8 bringen vielmehr eine 3-4-4-3 vor der 2.  Der Oktavsprung f-f^1^ täuscht über 8-8 der Mittelstimmen! [ <tei:hi rend="italic">double-headed arrow points to the next example</tei:hi> ]   Von dieser Warte</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">music example 8: two parts, vertically aligned</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>aus gehört, wird der "dritte Anstieg" gar zu einem nicht minder reizvollen Spiel der Mittelstimme, oder, zu einem wirklichen "Anstieg" der ~3 zu ~5!!  Hier ist noch die grundsätzliche Anstiegsfrage zu klären.  Zu klären ferner die Frage, ob einerseits das <tei:hi rend="italic">des</tei:hi> in Takt 26, (Ihr <tei:hi rend="italic">des</tei:hi>!), oder das des^2^ in Takt 31 als ~4 der Url. anzunehmen wäre. Ohne die ~5 kommen wir schon deshalb nicht aus, da eine ~3 in den Takten 23 bis 26 <tei:hi rend="italic">nicht durchzuhören ist</tei:hi>, vielmehr als Mittelstimme nach b absinkt!!  Ich bin alles in allem der Ansicht, dass es sich allenfalls um:</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">music example 9</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>handeln kann, sich doch wohl aber um</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">music example 10</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>handelt!!!  Wenn nicht gar:</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">music example 11</tei:hi> ]  ? ? ?</tei:p><tei:p>Die Kadenz um die ~5 herum schliesst an dieser Stelle die ~3 aus [ <tei:hi rend="italic">arrow pointing to e (flat) in previous example</tei:hi> ]!!!</tei:p><tei:p>q.e.d.</tei:p><tei:p>PS: Oder 2-Étagen-Notierung [ <tei:hi rend="italic">arrow to next example</tei:hi> ]:	
				
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">music example 12</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>Oder: P.S. II.</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">music example 13</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Ich werde das ganze nochmahl behorchen. - -</tei:p><tei:p>Nun zu Anderem:  Die Vorgänge in Deutschland sind <tei:hi rend="italic">Geist von demselben Geiste</tei:hi>, den Sie so oft gepriesen haben!  Lassen Sie sich <tei:hi rend="italic">nicht</tei:hi> durch revolutionäre Nebengeräuche hier über die geniale Urlinie täuschen!  <tei:hi rend="italic">Deutschland denkt die Welt neu</tei:hi>!  Da noch die Berufs-<tei:hi rend="italic">Musiker</tei:hi> sich noch nicht zu Beethovens und Bachs Sphären gefunden haben, kann man's von der <tei:hi rend="italic">Politik</tei:hi> nicht, oder noch weniger verlangen.  Wagner dünkt mich<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  "Wagner dünkt mich":  an old-fashioned construction, often found in Wagner's own libretti.</tei:note> ein Fortschritt vor Stravinskÿ und Hindemith!  <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Weg zeigt</tei:hi> zu Bach und Beethoven. Das ist schon etwas!</tei:p><tei:p>Was den "Tisch"<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  "Tisch":  a direct reference to the end of Schenker's previous letter (vC 45), expressing the hope that Cube will find the means to continue his work.</tei:note> anbelangt: Vom Himmel wird er mir nicht so wahrscheinlich kommen, wie von der Wohlfahrtsbehörde.  Denn der Tisch der mich hier all die Zeit über - kümmerlich genug - ernährt hat, fährt mit Violin nach Wien, und wird dort ihn und Sie ernähren.  Violins Flucht nach Wien rechne ich zu den Irrtümern, die heutigentags so vielfach aus dem Widerstreit von Geist und Blut triebhaft begangen werden.  Ich werde darunter in <tei:hi rend="italic">mehr</tei:hi> als einer Beziehung leiden, und mit Stolz leiden, da ich <tei:hi rend="italic">Deutscher</tei:hi> bin!  Ich halte der Sache die Treue wie bisher.  Ich habe nicht geklagt, als ich hier manches anders fand, als mir's versprochen war,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Moriz Violin had previously painted a much more optimistic picture of Cube's prospects in Hamburg than turned out to be the case.  See Violin's letter to Cube of March 31, 1931; Cube brings this up again in his letter to Schenker of October 4, 1934 (OJ 9/34, [42]). </tei:note> und klage nicht, da ich heute um eine der schmerzlichsten Erkenntnisse meines Lebens reicher bin. - -</tei:p><tei:p>Rechnen <tei:hi rend="italic">Sie</tei:hi> weiter auf mich, als auf einen Streiter, der nur die Sache kennt (die aber gründlich!) und nicht sich!</tei:p><tei:p>Für Ihre und Ihrer lieben Frau gute Wünsche danke ich auf's herzlichste!  Im selben Sinne darf ich <tei:hi rend="italic">sie</tei:hi>, auch im Namen meiner Frau, erwiedern[ <tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi> ], und verbleibe wie stets</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr
sehr ergebener
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker,date May 11, 1933</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hamburg 13, Dillstraße 1/I
May 11, 1933</tei:p><tei:p>Most honoured, dearest master,</tei:p><tei:p>I begin this rather long epistle, which I recently promised you, with many thanks for your communication.  I place Art at the beginning of it, as always, and indeed again our Beethoven!  Apart from the fact that I see this example as posing a typical "boundary case" (~3 or ~5?), as you apparently do, I cannot let things stand as they are without offering some serious reflections.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  It is as much a matter of the law itself, as of its formulation. I meditate as follows:</tei:p><tei:p>I attempted to clarify the play about ~3 by representing it at a special level, without rejecting the ~5 on account of it.  The latter seems to be marked out too strongly for me to ignore it from a theoretical standpoint.  My proof:</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">music example 1</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>In my view this is <tei:hi rend="italic">cannot</tei:hi> be possible!  If the neighbour note is in reality <tei:hi rend="italic">only</tei:hi> a neighbor note, then the original representation would be as follows:</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">music example 2</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>It goes against all experience, however, to have an independent seventh in the Ursatz;  the 7 is a passing note and must remain so.  Therefore also <tei:hi rend="italic">your</tei:hi> 8-7!  But if the 8 is present, it must be present <tei:hi rend="italic">from the beginning</tei:hi>!!!  There are then only two possibilities, either</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">music example 3</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>or</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">music example 4</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>In the latter case, one would have to concede that the Urlinie is preceded by an initial ascent. This happened once, as you showed, in the [Austrian] National Hymn.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  In the interests of the rock-solid foundations of <tei:hi rend="italic">your</tei:hi> theory it is of paramount importance that <tei:hi rend="italic">matters of notation</tei:hi> be governed by absolute clarity and agreement!!!  It is by no means necessary, however, to posit a ~4 in m. 26.  That is, I also do not agree with your idea of the three linear ascents.  The content of the first sixteen measures is basically as follows:</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">music example 5</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>Leaving aside the question of whether we are speaking of an upper or inner voice, one cannot on the one hand suppose a harmonically important root without further ado, as you indicate here:</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">music example 6</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>for I understand things as follows:</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">music example 7</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>I find that the latter interpretation actually corresponds more to the given facts!  The first d<tei:hi rend="italic">b</tei:hi>^2^ in m. 6 is very thinly supported by the f of the fourth-progression over a stationary a<tei:hi rend="italic">b</tei:hi>!  The second d<tei:hi rend="italic">b</tei:hi>^2^ (measure 13) is already stronger, since the bass is a true IV in first inversion. <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Finally the third d<tei:hi rend="italic">b</tei:hi>^2^ (measure 31), which I hear as the ~4 of the Urlinie, is indeed set apart from the other two by the doubling of the parts.  Why not posit a IV <tei:hi rend="italic">precisely here</tei:hi>, being more fitting than in measures 1-16, where that harmony is by no means plausible for m. 5.  Measures 1-8 give us instead a 3-4-4-3 before the 2.  The octave leap f-f^1^ gives the illusion of consecutive octaves in the inner voices! [ <tei:hi rend="italic">double-headed arrow points to next example:</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">music example 8: two parts, vertically aligned</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>Heard in this way, the "third ascent" becomes a no less attractive play in the inner voice, or a true "ascent" from ~3 to ~5!!  The basic question of the initial ascent must still be clarified here.  Further clarification must be sought as to whether on the one hand the <tei:hi rend="italic">d<tei:hi rend="italic">b</tei:hi></tei:hi> in m. 26 (your <tei:hi rend="italic">d<tei:hi rend="italic">b</tei:hi></tei:hi>!) or [on the other hand] the d<tei:hi rend="italic">b</tei:hi>^2^ in measure 31 should be taken as the ~4 of the Urlinie.  Without the ~5 we therefore cannot arrive at a satisfactory solution, since a ~3 <tei:hi rend="italic">cannot be heard</tei:hi> as prevailing through measures 23-26 but is rather a note in an inner voice that descends to b<tei:hi rend="italic">b</tei:hi>!!  All things considered, I am of the opinion that the following is possible</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">music example 9</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>but that</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">music example 10</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>is probably correct, if not actually</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">music example 11</tei:hi> ]  ? ? ?</tei:p><tei:p>The cadence built around the ~5 rules out ~3 at this point [ <tei:hi rend="italic">arrow pointing to e (flat) in previous example</tei:hi> ]!!!
Q.E.D.</tei:p><tei:p>PS: Alternatively, two-stage notation [ <tei:hi rend="italic">arrow to next example</tei:hi> ]:</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">music example 12</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>PS 2: Or:</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">music example 13</tei:hi> ]
 
<tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> I shall go over the whole thing carefully once more.</tei:p><tei:p>Now to other matters. The things that are happening in Germany are <tei:hi rend="italic">in essence</tei:hi> what you have so often extolled. Do <tei:hi rend="italic">not</tei:hi> let the revolutionary neighbour-noises deceive you of the genius-conceived Urlinie here!  <tei:hi rend="italic">Germany is conceiving the world anew</tei:hi>!  Since the professional <tei:hi rend="italic">musicians</tei:hi> have not yet made their way to the spheres of Beethoven or Bach, we cannot demand this, or demand this as much, from <tei:hi rend="italic">politics</tei:hi>.  Wagner seems to me<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> a [form of] progress beyond Stravinsky and Hindemith.  The <tei:hi rend="italic">path is pointing</tei:hi> toward Bach and Beethoven.  That is already something!</tei:p><tei:p>As far as my "table"<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> is concerned:  It is less likely to come from heaven than from the welfare authorities.  For the "table" that provided for me here all this time is leaving for Vienna, and will nourish him and you there.  Violin's flight to Vienna is something I count among the errors that are committed so often out of the conflict between spirit and flesh.  I will suffer because of that, and in <tei:hi rend="italic">more</tei:hi> than one respect, and I will suffer with pride, because I am a <tei:hi rend="italic">German</tei:hi>!  I shall remain true to the cause, as I have until now.  I have never complained, having found here much that was different from what I was promised.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  And I do not complain, since today I am richer by one of the most painful realizations of my life.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">You</tei:hi> may count on me further, as a warrior, who only knows his subject (and that very well!), and not himself!</tei:p><tei:p>For your good wishes, and that of your dear wife, I thank you most affectionately! May I reply to <tei:hi rend="italic">them</tei:hi> in the same way, also in my wife's name, and remain as ever</tei:p><tei:p>Your 
very devoted
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>