<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [15] : 11-7-28 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2006.
© Translation by William Drabkin, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1928-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 11/07/1928 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated November 7, 1928</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-07-30</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>C reports his activities in Cologne, esp. his work with Heinrich Lemacher, who is a "connoisseur of the Urlinie"; reports on his compositions. —Will visit Hupka and Albersheim next time.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  Köln;  Cologne;  Braunfels, Walter;  Lemacher, Heinrich;  Hochschule für Musik;  Urlinie;  Conservatory;  Schubert;  Brahms;  Bruckner; piano sonatas;  Vrieslander, Otto;  Hoboken, Anthony van</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Duisburg/Rhineland, Pulverweg 41</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated November 7, 1928</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Duisburg/Rhld.
Pulverweg 41. 						
7.XI.28.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Nunmehr kann ich berichten: Die Sache mit Köln lässt sich über alles Erwarten gut an. Braunfels,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Walter Braunfels (1882-1954), German composer, co-director of the Hochschule für Musik in Cologne 1925-1933.</tei:note> der sich <tei:hi rend="italic">sehr</tei:hi> schön über Ihr Werk äusserte, unterstützte meinen Plan gleich mit aller Autorität. Er attachierte mir als Mitarbeiter Herrn Prof. Lemacher,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> Heinrich Lemacher (1891-1966), German composer, Professor of Theory at the Hochschule für Musik in Cologne, where he had earlier studied. </tei:note> den Theoriegewaltigen der städt. Musikschule, die mit der Hochschule vereinigt ist. Lemacher hat mir die Organisation der Angelegenheit sehr erleichtert. Der Reihe nach stellte er mich seinen Seminaristen, sowie den Schul- und Kirchenmusikern vor, worauf ich mein Sprüchlein sagte, und die Interessenten sofort festgenagelt wurden. Heute Abend, da der “grosse Chor” versammelt war, wurde die letzte Schlacht geschlagen. Braunfels selbst führte den Vorsitz, und sekundierte mir nach Kräften. Auch die Hauptfragen der Zeiteinteilung und Finanzierung wurden geregelt. Die Beteiligung ist sehr erfreulich, ich habe ein Auditorium von etwa hundert Schülern zu erwarten. Es sind vorerst acht Vorlesungen festgesetzt; jede Woche eine. Die ersten vier noch vor Weihnachten (am 28.XI. geht’s los), der Rest nach den Ferien. Je nach Aufnahme und Bedürfnis(!) soll der Kursus eventuell wiederholt werden. Über die Beteiligung der Lehrerschaft bin ich noch im Unklaren, doch denke ich, dass dem Beispiel Prof. Lemachers, der sich alles mitzuhören will (er ist immerhin ein <tei:hi rend="italic">Kenner</tei:hi> der Urlinie), noch andere folgen werden. Meine eigenen Ansprüche habe ich im Interesse der Sache nicht sehr hochgeschraubt, um die finanziell angestrengten Hochschüler nicht von Anfang an durch zu grosse Neubelastung zu vergrämen, immerhin wird mir jeder Monat über hundert Mark einbringen, und ich bin willens und gesonnen, an der Hochschule noch einmal sehr viel mehr zu verdienen. Ich fange gleich mit winzigen Urlinien an, und erläutere Ihre Harmonie- und Stimmführungstheorien gleich am lebenden Objekt. Mit der Zeit kommen dann schwerere Sachen, und nach Möglichkeit – auch auf Wunsch Lemachers – “Gegenbeispiele”, etwa Bruckner, Reger, Hindemith. So wird es ganz von selbst kommen, dass es nicht bei den acht Vorlesungen bleibt. Wer erst einmal den Segen <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> der “Urlinie” erfasst hat, der ist ihr auch fürderhin verbunden und verpflichtet. –</tei:p><tei:p>Damit auch der Humor zu seinem Rechte bekommt, lege ich Ihnen eine Kritik eines Schubertabends bei, den ich gebührend “eingeleitet” habe. Es war eine schöne Predigt. Noch heute klingen den Leute die Ohren davon. Sie haben’s aber nett hingenommen, und zum Schluss sehr lieb geklatscht. Es hat viel Eindruck gemacht, und wildfremde Leute konnten nicht umhin mir ihre Ergriffenheit aus – und die Hand zu drücken. Wie meistens hat der Recensent (er ist übrigens seines Zeichens Nationalökonom) das Wenigste “mitbegriffen”. Das mit Brahms und Bruckner war nur ein halber Relativsatz – dennoch konnte er ihn nicht verdauen. Immerhin können <tei:hi rend="italic">Sie</tei:hi> mit Leichtigkeit aus der Kritik entnehmen <tei:hi rend="italic">was</tei:hi>, und <tei:hi rend="italic">wie</tei:hi> ich’s gesagt habe. Im übrigen waltet in ihr die übliche Hilfslosigkeit dem Kern der Dinge gegenüber. Ein “blutlos-resignierender” Essay voll “grosslinigen” Kleinverstandes.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> Cube may be parodying the words of the review (which does not survive).</tei:note> –</tei:p><tei:p>Sonate Nº 1. befindet sich bereits im Komponistenwettbewerb. Zu Ostern 1929 höre ich wieder davon. Nº 2. geht langsam aber sicher ihrem Ende entgegen. Schon skizziere ich einen Allegro-Entwurf zu einem Klavierkonzert. Ich habe wieder zwei Privatschüler. Die Lage scheint sich in Besserung zu gefallen. –</tei:p><tei:p>Dies für heute. Wie immer werde ich Sie des weiteren über mein “Arbeitszimmer” auf dem Laufenden halten.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit herzlichsten Grüssen Ihnen und Ihrer Frau Gemahlin, auch Vrieslandern<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on<ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.</tei:note> und Hoboken<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> (ihm schulde ich noch Nachricht)</tei:p><tei:p>von Ihrem
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube.</tei:p><tei:p>P.S.  Hupka<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Felix Hupka, pupil of Schenker, conductor at the Cologne Opera House; Cf. vC 20, October 8, 1928.</tei:note> und Herrn Albersheim<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Gerhard Albersheim, pupil of Schenker; Cf. vC 20, October 8, 1928.</tei:note> werde ich besuchen sowie ich einen ganzen Tag in Köln bin.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated November 7, 1928</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Duisburg, Rhineland
Pulverweg 41
7 November 1928</tei:p><tei:p>Most honoured Master,</tei:p><tei:p>I can report to you once again: my dealings with Cologne are going well, beyond all expectation. Braunfels,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> who was <tei:hi rend="italic">highly</tei:hi> complimentary about your work, immediately threw all his weight behind my plan. Er assigned me to work with Prof. Lemacher,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> the theoretical heavyweight at the municipal school of music, which is associated with the Conservatory. Lemacher made the organization of my visit much easier. He introduced his seminar students to me in turn, and also the school and church musicians, whereupon I said my little piece and their interest was immediately nailed down. As the “great chorus” assembled this evening, the last battle was fought. Braunfels himself chaired the meeting, and seconded me to the best of his ability. Even the basic questions of scheduling and financing were sorted out. Participating in this is very agreeable; I can expect an audience of about a hundred students. To begin with, eight lectures have been fixed at the rate of one a week. The first four will take place before Christmas (we start on 28 November), the remainder after the holidays. Depending on how they are received and what the need is (!), the course might possibly be repeated. Whether or not the teachers will take part is still unclear to me, but I believe that others will follow the example of Prof. Lemacher, who wants to attend everything (he is at any rate a <tei:hi rend="italic">connoisseur</tei:hi> of the Urlinie. In the interest of the matter, I did not make my own demands too great, lest I were to antagonize the financially stretched conservatory students from the outset by imposing too great an additional burden. At the very least, however, each month will bring me more than a hundred marks, and I am willing and disposed to earn a great deal more at the Conservatory once again. I start immediately with tiny voice-leading graphs, and explain your theories of harmony and voice-leading as regards the living object. Time will then bring more difficult things, and where possible—at Lemacher’s request—“counter-examples,” for instance Bruckner, Reger, Hindemith. So it may turn out automatically that there will be more than eight lectures. Anyone who has understood what a blessing <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> the “Urlinie” is will, from that time on, be captivated and duty-bound.</tei:p><tei:p>That the humorous side of life may also come into its own right, I enclose a newspaper review of a Schubert evening that I fittingly “introduced”. It was nice sermon, which is still ringing in people’s ears. They were a very appreciative audience, and at the end applauded very warmly. It made a big impression, and total strangers could not help expressing their captivation to me and shaking my hand. As usual, the reviewer “took in” the least (the way he signed the review, moreover, identified him as a national economist). What I said about Brahms and Bruckner was just half of a relative clause; and still he was unable to swallow it. Nevertheless, <tei:hi rend="italic">you</tei:hi> will have an easy time figuring out <tei:hi rend="italic">what</tei:hi> I said and <tei:hi rend="italic">how</tei:hi> I said it; otherwise, the review is marked by the usual helplessness regarding the heart of the matter: a “bloodless, resigning” essay in which the author’s intellectual impoverishment is portrayed “in broad strokes.”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/></tei:p><tei:p>Sonata No. 1 has already been entered in the composers’ competition; I will hear about this again next Easter. No. 2 is moving slowly but surely towards completion. I am already sketching a draft of an Allegro for a piano concerto. I again have two private pupils. Things appear to be getting better.</tei:p><tei:p>So much for today. As always, I shall keep you in the picture regarding further developments in my “workroom”.</tei:p><tei:p>With most affectionate greetings to you and your wife, also to Vrieslander<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> and Hoboken<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> (whom I still owe some news)</tei:p><tei:p>from your
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube</tei:p><tei:p>P.S.  I shall visit Hupka<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> and [Dr.] Albersheim<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> the next time I am able to spend an entire day in Cologne.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>