<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/34, [22] : 11-22-30 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of the Felix-Eberhard von Cube, published with kind permission.
© Transcription William Drabkin 2006.
© Translation William Drabkin 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is published with the permission of the heirs of  Felix-Eberhard von Cube, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1930-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: The heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 11/22/1930 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated November 22, 1930</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-11-04</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>C thinks attending Weisse's lectures would enable him to make contact with "people of stature" in Berlin, where he would like to teach S's theory, and asks S for the time and place, referring to the difficulties of travel in these "catastrophic times."  — Will check up on Reichert.  — Has been invited to give six lectures locally, and has a concert of his compositions coming up.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  Berlin;  Weisse, Hans;  lectures;  Reichert;  Reichardt;  Essen;  Kestenberg, Leo;  Duisburg;  Reichsverband;  Kreuzhage, Eduard;  concert;  compositions</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Duisburg, Rhineland</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated November 22, 1930</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Duisburg/Rhld. Kuhstr. 23–25/^I.^
22.XI.30.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Meister!</tei:p><tei:p>Wenn ich mir die Sache so überlege, scheint es mir nicht allein günstig, mich in Berlin “sehen” zu lassen, sondern ich erblicke darin eine ausgezeichnete Gelegenheit, dort mit gewissen maassgeblichen Leuten Verbindung zu bekommen, die mir noch sehr von Nutzen sein können.  Wenn ich auch diese Stadt so wenig mag wie Sie,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  In vC 30, July 10, 1930, S had remarked: “Berlin would be better [than Vienna, for C], in spite of the fact that I don’t like this city.”</tei:note> erscheint sie mir doch im Augenblick das erstrebenswerteste Arbeitsfeld in Deutschland.  Falls nun tatsächlich die Bildung einer Interessengruppe für Musikarbeit im Sinne Ihres Werkes in Berlin akut würde, würde ich alles in Bewegung setzen, um mit unter den ersten zu sein, die für eine praktische Lehrtätigkeit in Ihrem Sinne für dortige Hochschulen, Seminare und Arbeitsgemeinschaften in Frage kommen.  Um so mehr, als ich jetzt immerhin eine mehrjärige Praxis im Klassen- und Gemeinschaftsunterricht mit sichtbaren Erfolgen hinter mir habe, und ausserdem eine Loslösung von meinem derzeitigen Wirkungskreis mir nicht nur leicht, sondern sogar angenehm wäre; auch ist meine Praxis hier noch nicht so viel wert, als dass man mir in Berlin kein annehmbares Angebot machen könnte.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich würde Sie also bitten, mich rechtzeitig genau zu informieren, wann, wo, und unter welchen Umständen die Vorlesungen Dr. Weisses stattfinden werden,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> In his letter vC 31, November 1, 1930, Schenker told Cube that Hans Weisse had been invited by the Prussian Minister for Education, Dr. Leo Kestenberg, to give a series of lectures on Schenkerian theory to music teachers in Berlin in December 1930.  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.</tei:note> damit ich <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> disponieren kann.  Die Reise ist in der jetzigen katastrophalen Zeit keine Kleinigkeit für mich – (mit einer veritablen “Einladung” durch die verantaltende Körperschaft wird ja wohl nicht zu rechnen sein?) – aber ich will mir diese Chance unter gar keinen Umständen entgehen lassen; und wenn der einzige positive Erfolg der wäre, dass den stumpfsinnigen Westfälingern hier doch endlich ein kleines Nachtlicht aufgeht!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich habe die Absicht, sich einen meiner Schüler an den Dr. Reichert oder Reichardt in Essen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> A music teacher by the name of Reichert (or Reichardt), who professed to be a disciple of Schenker’s.  (Schenker denied all knowledge of the man in his postcard vC 32, November 7, 1930.)</tei:note> schriftlich wenden zu lassen, um genau festzustellen, wie weit er die Dreistigkeit treibt, als Ihr Schüler aufzutreten, um ihm gegebenenfalls den Begriff des unlauteren Wettbewerbs so nachdrücklich ins Gedächtnis zu rufen, dass er es vorzieht seine segensreiche Tätigkeit woandershin zu verlegen. –</tei:p><tei:p>Kestenberg<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Leo Kestenberg (1882-1962), who taught at both the Stern Conservatory and the Klindworth-Scharwenka Conservatory in Berlin, and was appointed to the Ministry of Science, Art, and Education in 1918, rising to a high position in the division of Art.  His name frequently comes up in the correspondence as someone favorably disposed toward the dissemination of Schenker’s ideas by German educators.</tei:note> ist übrigens selbst Musiker, und soll ein sehr feiner Kerl sein!  Ich würde in Berlin mal ganz vernünftig mit ihm reden, auf welche Weise ich meine Hebel am besten ansetze.</tei:p><tei:p>Die Duisburger Ortsgruppe hat mich zu sechs Vorlesungen für den Reichsverband<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> Click on <ref cRef="reichsverband_deutsc">Reichsverband deutscher Tonkünstler und Musiklehrer</ref>.</tei:note> verpflichtet.  Das ist auch ein “Echo” aus Berlin. Dass +ich+ dahinterstecke weiss bloss der Vorsitzende Dr. Kreuzhage.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Dr. Eduard Kreuzhage was one of Cube’s senior colleagues in Duisburg. Cube had made a pencil sketch of him in his letter OJ 9/34, [16], March 26, 1929.</tei:note>  Es ist einer meiner ersten Schachzüge. Mein Kompositionsabend steigt in 14 Tagen.  Dabei werde ich auch ein paar passende Worte sprechen. Im übrigen sitze ich auf glühende Kohlen. Das “geduldige”  Alter habe ich nachgerade noch nicht erreicht. –</tei:p><tei:p>Mit herzlichsten Grüssen Ihnen und Ihrer Frau Gemahlin bin ich
Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cube to Schenker, dated November 22, 1930</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Duisburg, Rhineland, Kuhstraße 23–25/^I.^
November 22, 1930</tei:p><tei:p>Most honoured master,</tei:p><tei:p>When I consider the matter in this way, not only does it appear to me useful to “show” myself in Berlin, but also I perceive therein an excellent opportunity to be in contact with certain people of stature, who can actually be very useful to me.  Even though I like the city as little as you,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> it nevertheless seems to me at the moment to be the workplace in Germany most worth striving to get to.  Should the establishment of an interest group for musical research, along the lines of your work, actually become a reality, I would do everything in my power to be among the first to be considered for a practical post in teaching your theory at the music colleges, seminaries and working groups there.  All the more so, now that I have several years of clearly successful practice in lecturing and small-group instruction behind me.  Moreover, to be free of my current sphere of effect would not only be easy but actually agreeable; also my practice here is not worth so much that I could not be made an acceptable offer in Berlin.</tei:p><tei:p>I would ask you, then, to inform me promptly when, where, and under what circumstances Dr Weisse’s lectures will take place,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> so that I <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> can be available.  In today’s catastrophic times, the trip would be no trivial matter for me—there is not, I suppose, a possibility of an official “invitation” from the group that is being set up?—but I will not miss this opportunity under any circumstances, even if the only positive result were that a little night-light were finally to shine on the dull-witted Westphalians!</tei:p><tei:p>I intend to direct one of my pupils to get in touch by letter with Dr Reichert (Reichardt?) in Essen,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> to determine precisely whether he is so bold as to be appearing as your pupil, in order to remind him emphatically of the notion of unfair competition, so that he might choose to move his blessed activity somewhere else.
	
Kestenberg<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> is, at any rate, a musician himself, and is supposed to be a very fine person!  In Berlin, I would speak with him very sensibly, asking him how I should best direct my efforts.</tei:p><tei:p>The local Duisburger group of the Society [of German Composers and Music Teachers]<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> has made me responsible for giving six lectures.  That, too, is an “echo” from Berlin. That it was I myself who was behind this is known only to the chair, Dr Kreuzhage.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/>  It is one of my first strategic moves.  The concert of my compositions takes place in a fortnight; on that occasion I shall also make a few appropriate remarks.  Otherwise, I am sitting on hot coals.  The age of “patience” is something I have certainly not yet reached.</tei:p><tei:p>With most affectionate greetings to you and your wife, I am
Your
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Cube</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>