<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 5/18, 2 : 11-26-30 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Oswald Jonas (1930-1978)—Special Collections, University of California, Riverside (1978-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: Special Collections, University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 11/26/1930 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated November 26, 1930</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-04-21</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Having misread J in OJ 12/6, [4] as requesting a letter of recommendation to F, S declines to provide such a letter.  Letters of thanks to S from other Berlin musicians have not led to more solid connections. Most musicians have not dared to take a position publicly on S's teaching.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Jonas, Oswald;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm; Weisse, Hans; Riezler, Walter; Berlin; musicians; professors; Munich</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated November 26, 1930</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Daß ich gleich beginne damit, was Sie gewiß am meisten interessiert: <tei:hi rend="italic">Furtwängler</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Se OJ 12/6, [4], November 17, 1930, para. 3, for the request to which this letter is a response.  Wilhelm Furtwängler [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> zu schreiben, wäre, richtiger: ist derzeit eine Unmöglichkeit für mich.  Er hat sich so für <tei:hi rend="italic">Weisse</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.</tei:note> eingesetzt, hat so viel Verdruß wegen <tei:hi rend="italic">Riezlers</tei:hi>’<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Walter Riezler (1878-65), German musicologist.  He had just written a dismissive article “Die Urlinie,” in <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Musik</tei:hi> XXII/7 (April 1930) which bore a dedication to Furtwängler.  See OJ 12/6, [16].</tei:note> gehabt, hat -einen- ^den^ Aufsatz eines Schülers von mir zu lesen gekriegt, na – ich meine, F. hat das Recht, ^von mir^ auf lange hinaus in Ruhe gelassen zu werden.</tei:p><tei:p>Andere Musiker in Berlin, meist Professoren, schreiben mir Briefe des Dankes, aber festere Beziehungen haben sich nicht herausgebildet. <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Es dürfte wohl so sein, daß ich -zunächst- den älteren u. hervorragendsten Musikern ^dort^ zumindest dem Namen nach bekannt bin – meiner Erfahrung nach wird zuweilen ^absichtlich, gegen den Tatbestand^ auch das geleugnet –, aber zu einem Recht, an sie zu schreiben, reicht das nicht aus.</tei:p><tei:p>Ja – alledem kommt noch, daß ich mir kein Bild vom Inhalt Ihrer Vorträge machen kann.  Wohin hat Sie (in München) der weitere Weg von dem (in meiner Person) erwähnten “Ausgangspunkt” geführt?  Es könnte ja sein, daß Sie mir in der Folge nicht zustimmen, anderseits ich Ihnen nicht zustimme, da könnte eine Empfehlung von mir <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> erheiternd wirken . . .</tei:p><tei:p>Es rächt sich zur Zeit eben, daß – bis auf wenige Einzelne, die für mich eintreten, vor allem bis auf mich selbst, der wohl am wirksamsten für meine Lehre eintrat — die übrigen Musiker, nah u. fern, keine Stellung öffentlich zu nehmen wagten.  Ich stand niemals im Betrüb, stehe auch heute nicht drin, müssen da nicht Musiker, die Broterwerb suchen, sich -nicht- lieber von vornherein an solche Musiker wenden, die ihnen aus dem Betrüb heraus ^u. in den Betrieb hinein^ helfen könnten?  (Ich entschuldige sie Alle).  Nun ist es aber, wie es ist, wie <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> es kommen müßte, u. ich kann nur herzlich bedauern, Ihnen den erbetenen Dienst nicht leisten zu können.</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr sehr ergebener
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H Schenker
26.11.30</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated November 26, 1930</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor!</tei:p><tei:p>To begin at once with the matter that is certainly of greatest interest to you: to write Furtwängler<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> would be—more exactly: is—at present an impossibility for me.  He has done so much for Weisse,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> has had so much aggravation because of Riezler,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> has received -an- ^the^ essay by a student of mine to read, well—I think, Furtwängler is entitled to be left in peace ^by me^ for a good while.</tei:p><tei:p>Other musicians in Berlin, mostly professors, write letters of thanks to me, but more solid connections have not developed therefrom. <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> It may be true that I am known at least by name to the older and most prominent musicians there—in my experience even that sometimes, ^intentionally and contrary to the facts of the case^, is denied—but that is not sufficient to give license to write to them.</tei:p><tei:p>Yes, and besides, I cannot form a picture of the content of your lectures.  Where exactly have you been led (in Munich) by the path from the “point of departure” mentioned (in my person)?  It may well be that, later on, you don’t agree with me, or on the other hand that I don’t agree with you; in that case a recommendation from me could <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> seem laughable. . .</tei:p><tei:p>The pity just now is that—except for few individuals who support me, above all except for me myself, who have no doubt most actively promoted my teaching—the other musicians, near and far, dared take no position publicly.  I have never been in distress [<tei:hi rend="italic">Betrüb</tei:hi>], am no more in it today; mustn’t the musicians who try to earn a living prefer from the outset to turn to those musicians who could help them get out of distress [<tei:hi rend="italic">Betrüb</tei:hi>] ^and into administration [ <tei:hi rend="italic">Betrieb</tei:hi> ]^?  (I excuse them all.)  But things are as they are, <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> and as they had to be, and I can only sincerely regret that I am unable to provide the service you request.</tei:p><tei:p>Yours most sincerely,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H. Schenker
November 26, 1930</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>