<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 5/18, 11 : 7-18-32 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Oswald Jonas (1932-1978)—Special Collections, University of California, Riverside (1978-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: Special Collections, University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 07/18/1932 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated July 18, 1932</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-06-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>S tries to account for Furtwängler's unavailability for a conference over the Handel Saul score; he does not need the copy of [Beethoven] Op. 109 offered by Mr. Kromer.  An introduction to his theory would be "in order," but its marketing might be problematic and require a benefactor; regrets that Anthony van Hoboken is not such a person. 

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Jonas, Oswald;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Handel;  Saul;  score;  Beethoven;  Op. 109;  copy;  Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven ... 109;  LfS109;  Erläuterungs-Ausgabe;  Kromer, Julius;  Introduction;  marketing;  subscription;  benefactor;  patron;  Hoboken, Anthony van</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Igls, Tyrol</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated July 18, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Igls Tirol</tei:hi>
18.7.32</tei:p><tei:p>Lieber Herr D^r^ <tei:hi rend="italic">Jonas</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>Lassen Sie mich der Reihe nach antworten, dem Lauf Ihres Schreibens<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  i.e. OJ 12/6, [13], July 14, 1932.</tei:note> folgen.</tei:p><tei:p>Dr Furtw.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Wilhelm Furtwängler [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> verstehe ich nicht: er braucht ja nicht dabei zu sein, wenn Sie die Saul=Part.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Brahms’s arrangement for performance of Handel’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Saul</tei:hi> is among the autograph materials in the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde in Vienna.  Schenker had transcribed and edited this document, which he subsequently gave to Furtwängler (see 5/18, 9), who in turn made it available to Jonas (see 5/18, 21) for study and the writing of a commentary.</tei:note> einsehen u. für Ihre Arbeit nutzen möchten.  Am Ende wehrt -s- er sich dagegen, durch Ihre Arbeit irgendwie im voraus festgenagelt zu werden (in den Ergebnissen u. namentlich vor der Öffentlichkeit!)</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Die Bilder zu op. 109 besitze ich schon seit altersher, sie lagen zugrunde meiner “Erläuterungs=Ausgabe”.  Wollen Sie das, bitte, H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Kromer</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Julius (Ritter von) Kromer (otherwise known as Julo von Kromer) of the Archive for Photographs of Musical Manuscripts of the Austrian National Library: his written communications to S are preserved as OJ 12/24 and OC 30/64, 119; 44/1; A/293.</tei:note> sagen, u. ihn bei dieser Gelegenheit von mir grüßen.</tei:p><tei:p>Daß eine “Einführung”,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  i.e. an introduction to Schenker’s theory: see OJ 12/6, [13].</tei:note> wie Sie sie planen, sehr wohl am Platze ist, d. h. daß die Lehre genug Stoff bietet, um auch in Schulen dargeboten zu werden, daran glaube ich.  Nicht immer stößt ^aber^ die schönste Lehre auch auf schönste Köpfe, daß dann die leeren, nicht zu füllenden Köpfe die Lehre dafür verantwörtlich machen, zeigt seit jeher das Verhalten der Menschheit. Hierin <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> liegt die materielle Schwierigkeit der Frage.  Einer “Subscription” (die sonst so naheläge!) auch nur von 2 S. per Stück würde sich ja der flachköpfige Liebhaber u Musiker entziehen, im untrüglichen Unterbewußtsein, daß er die Auslage von 2 S. zu keinerlei “Kapital” im materiellen oder geistigen Sinne auswerten könnte.  Wo fänden Sie also Subscribenten, wenn die Welt meist aus solchen Flachköpfen besteht?  Nicht einmal als ein geistiger <tei:hi rend="italic">Genußartikel</tei:hi> käme Ihre “Einf.” für sie in frage, – “was habe ich davon, dafür?” sagen ^sie^ u. geben 2 S. wo anders hin.</tei:p><tei:p>Meines Erachtens kann der Weg nur über einen <tei:hi rend="italic">Spender</tei:hi> gehen, gleichsam <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">à fonds perdu</tei:hi>.  (Ein <tei:hi rend="italic">Verlag</tei:hi> will schon zum Voraus gedeckt sein, sei es, daß er des Verfassers andere erfolgreiche Stücke besitzt[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>], an denen er sich schadlos halten kann, u dgl.)  Es ist sehr zu bedauern, daß unser v. Hoboken<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> für einen solchen “Mäzen” nicht in Betracht ^kommt^, <tei:hi rend="italic">was ich übrigens seit Jahren gesagt habe u. immer wiederhole.  Heute wird diese Erkenntnis immer allgemeiner.</tei:hi>  Auch mir selbst wies die Enttäuschung über diesen Mann Wege der Selbsthilfe&lt;strike&gt;,&lt;/strike&gt; oder Wege zu besserwilligen Menschen.  Die nahe Zukunft wird Ihnen bestätigen, was ich hier andeute.  Ich habe viel über eine Organisation gedacht zur Beschaffung von Mitteln für ähnliche Zwecke, komme aber noch nicht voran.  Weit eher bringt man für einen Sportler 4-5000 S. zusammen.</tei:p><tei:p>Von mir u. meiner Frau beste Grüße[.]</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr 
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] <tei:hi rend="italic">H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated July 18, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Igls Tyrol
July 18, 1932</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Dr. Jonas,</tei:p><tei:p>Let me answer seriatim, and follow the order of your letter.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>I do not understand Dr. Furtwängler:<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> he need not be present when you examine the <tei:hi rend="italic">Saul</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> score and put it to use for your work.  At bottom he is protecting himself from being in any way firmly committed in advance by your work (in the results and especially in public!)</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> The photostats of Op. 109 have long been in my possession; they were the basis for my “Erläuterungs-Ausgabe.”  Will you please tell that to Mr. Kromer,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> and give him my greetings on this occasion.</tei:p><tei:p>That an “Introduction”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> like the one you plan is very well in order— that is, that the teaching offers enough material to be presented in schools as well— I do believe to be true.  ^But^ the most perfect teaching does not always find the most perfect brains; that the empty and unfillable brains then hold the teaching responsible for that is shown by the demeanor of mankind through the ages.  Here <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> lies the material difficulty of the question.  A “subscription” (which would otherwise be so accessible!) even at the cost of only 2 schillings each would be abjured by the flat-headed musical amateur with the unerring subconscious conviction that he would never be able to realize any capital in the material or spiritual sense from the expenditure of 2 schillings.  Where would you find subscribers, when the world consists mostly of such flat-heads?  For them your “Intro.” would not even come into question as a mental <tei:hi rend="italic">entertainment-article</tei:hi>—“what do I get out of that, get for it?” ^they^ would say, and spend the 2 schillings somewhere else.</tei:p><tei:p>In my view the only way this can be done is by a <tei:hi rend="italic">benefactor</tei:hi>, as though <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">à fonds perdu</tei:hi>.  (A <tei:hi rend="italic">publisher</tei:hi> wants to be covered in advance, perhaps in that it lists other successful works by the author that can compensate for losses, etc.)  It is most regrettable that our van Hoboken<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> cannot be regarded as such a “patron,” <tei:hi rend="italic">as I have said, incidentally, for years and always repeat.  Today this recognition becomes ever more general.</tei:hi>  I too was shown the path to self-help or paths to more forthcoming people by disappointment with this man.  The near future will confirm for you what I suggest here.  I have given much thought to an organization dedicated to providing means for similar purposes, but have not yet made much headway.  People are much more ready to raise 4–5000 schillings for an athlete.</tei:p><tei:p>Best greetings from my wife and me.</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H. Schenker</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>