<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 5/18, 24 : 3-22-33 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription John Rothgeb 2006.
© Translation John Rothgeb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary John Rothgeb 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Oswald Jonas (1933-1978)—Special Collections, University of California, Riverside (1978-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: Special Collections, University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: John Rothgeb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 03/22/1933 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Jonas ~ H+JSchenker","Jonas ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated March 22, 1933</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-07-06</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>S recounts Joseph Marx's requirements for adapting his Harmonielehre for teaching purposes, and the involvement of Alfred Kalmus at UE. —Refers to Vrieslander's adaptation of Kontrapunkt and Jonas's of Harmonielehre.  Reports Hans Weisse's success; alludes to the Handel-Schenker Saul project.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Jonas, Oswald;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  Marx, Joseph;  Kalmus, Alfred;  UE;  Harmonielehre;  Theory of Harmony;  school edition;  Vrieslander, Otto;  Hertzka, Emil; appendix;  chorale;  form;  modulation;  exercises;  Kontrapunkt;  Counterpoint;  Weisse, Hans;  Urlinie-Tafeln;  Einstein, Alfred;  Handel-Brahms;  Saul</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated March 22, 1933</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>22.III.33</tei:p><tei:p>Geehrter, lieber Herr D^r^ <tei:hi rend="italic">Jonas</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>Einmal unter vier ‚höchstens’ sechs Augen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  That is, in private, with only the two of us (or at most three) present.  The contemplated third party is probably Schenker’s wife Jeanette.</tei:note> werde ich Ihnen all die Zusammenhänge ^erklären^, die <tei:hi rend="italic">Hob</tei:hi>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> in Ihre u. meine Angelegenheiten hineingetragen hat, heute will ich meiner Freude Ausdrück geben, daß es zumindest so weit gekommen ist! Also Glück auf! Und nun zu Ihrer Frage:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  See OJ 12/6, 20.  The question concerned the proposed new edition of <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi>.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Marx</tei:hi>’<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on: <ref cRef="marx_joseph">Joseph Marx</ref>.</tei:note> Anregung gieng zuerst zu D^r^ <tei:hi rend="italic">Kalmus</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Alfred Kalmus [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> (<tei:hi rend="italic">U.E.</tei:hi>), der sie mir schriftlich mitteilte. Der erste Wunsch von <tei:hi rend="italic">Marx</tei:hi> bezog sich auf eine äußerste Kürzung, äußerste Billigkeit.  Nun hat schon vor mehr als 15 Jahren <tei:hi rend="italic">Vrieslander</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.</tei:note> eine solche Arbeit dem Dir. <tei:hi rend="italic">Hertzka</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Emil Hertzka [create biogfile and link].  Hertzka had died ten months earlier, on May 9, 1932.</tei:note> vorge1egt, <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> wovon, versteht sich, auch ich wußte.  Da war nun nicht zu umgehen, das ich D^r^ <tei:hi rend="italic">Kalmus</tei:hi> auf <tei:hi rend="italic">Vriesl</tei:hi>. verwies, es entstand ein sehr reger Briefwechsel. Inzwischen war <tei:hi rend="italic">Marx</tei:hi> auch bei mir zu Hause u. gab noch weitere Wünsche zum Besten (bitte, lachen Sie nicht, es ist ja traurig genug), so z.B. würde er bei aller Kürze (höchstens 100 Druckseiten) doch noch einen „Anhang" wünschen, worin auf <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Choral</tei:hi></tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Form</tei:hi></tei:hi>. <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Modul</tei:hi></tei:hi>. in Kürze hingewiesen würde.  Ich meldete[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] es <tei:hi rend="italic">Vr</tei:hi>., meinte aber, er solle sich durch solche Dummheiten nicht stören lassen. Nachdem die Sache so weit gediehen war, das -vor- eine&lt;strike&gt;r&lt;/strike&gt; Bestellung durch <tei:hi rend="italic">K</tei:hi>. schon in der Luft lag, meldete <tei:hi rend="italic">K</tei:hi>. plötzlich (brieflich), <tei:hi rend="italic">Marx</tei:hi> könne sich nicht verbürgen, da die Einführung nicht von ihm allein abhänge.  (Er kam als "Direktor" in Frage, nun aber ist diese Kombination ins Wasser gefallen.) Daß unter solchen <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Umständen <tei:hi rend="italic">K</tei:hi>. an die Erwerbung nicht mehr denkt, ist klar. An dieser Lage ändert sich nichts dadurch, daß, wie nun <tei:hi rend="italic">M</tei:hi>. mir selbst schrieb, meine Werke als “Lehrmittel” „<tei:hi rend="italic">vorgemerkt</tei:hi>“ werden. Verzeihung, ich vergaß das Heiterste u. Traurigste zu erzählen. <tei:hi rend="italic">K</tei:hi>. meldete mir, <tei:hi rend="italic">M</tei:hi>. möchte auch "<tei:hi rend="italic">Aufgaben</tei:hi>" beigefügt sehen!!!  Mit einem Wort: es lief die Sache ^wieder^ auf einen – „Stöhr”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Richard Stöhr:  See OJ 5/18, 17, November/December 1932.</tei:note> hinaus!  So unselig sieht es<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Originally “So sieht es unselig,” corrected with a transpostion mark.</tei:note> in solchen Köpfen aus, u. die persönliche Bekanntschaft hat mir ein <tei:hi rend="italic">Niveau</tei:hi> enthüllt, wie es tiefer nicht gedacht sein kann.  Da war wirklich nichts ^mehr^ zu machen.  Elend trotzdem: Vriesl., vornehm wie immer bis ins Letzte, erbat von mir die Erlaubnis, <tei:hi rend="italic">doch die Arbeit zu machen</tei:hi>, er sei zu sehr davon überzeugt, daß man ihrer früher oder später bedürfen wird, wozu sich denn gewiß <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> die Mittel finden werden.  (Er denkt auch an eine testamentarische Sicherung.)  Nebenbei: eine ähnliche Arbeit hat er ^für sich u. seine Schüler auch^ am <tei:hi rend="italic">Kp</tei:hi>.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  i.e. <tei:hi rend="italic">NMTP</tei:hi> II.</tei:note> vollzogen, nicht anders offenbar als Sie selbst, wie ich Ihrem Brief entnehme.</tei:p><tei:p>Daß Sie in Ihrer Arbeit an Bd I<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Schenker’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi>.</tei:note> nicht vorbeigehen können, ist klar.  Schon der Stufengang im Vdg wird Sie dazu nötigen.  Und wenn Sie im Zusammenhang mit der Stufe auf die Quint usw. zurückkommen, so müssen Sie doch wohl Bd I streifen, mehr als das: herangreifen.  Mir haftet übrigens ein Weg in Erinnerung,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Originally “in Erinnerung ein Weg,” corrected with a transposition mark.</tei:note> den Sie ^zu den Stufen^ in einem Ihrer Aufsätze eingeschlagen haben.  Ich möchte glauben, daß ein Konflikt gar nicht entstehen kann, <tei:hi rend="italic">Vr</tei:hi>’s Aufgabe ist viel begrenzter, die Ihre freier: Sie -können- ^kennen übrigens^ seine Leistung nicht, er Ihre nicht.</tei:p><tei:p>Haben Sie von D^r^ <tei:hi rend="italic">Weisse</tei:hi>’s<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  Click on: <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.</tei:note> Erfolgen gehört?  90 Hörer (, auch an die “Url.Tf.”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  Schenker’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Fünf Urlinietafeln</tei:hi>.</tei:note>), 450 Doll. für 12 Stunde, hübsch. – Daß Einstein<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15">  Click on <ref cRef="einstein_alfred">Alfred Einstein</ref>.</tei:note> ^Sie^ über „Saul“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn16">  See 12/6, [13], July 14, 1932, note 2.</tei:note> gewähren lässt, freut mich für Sie, für die Sache.  <tei:hi rend="italic">Hob</tei:hi>. schrieb mir, daß es Ihnen besser geht, ist es so, ist es <tei:hi rend="italic">noch</tei:hi> [<tei:hi rend="italic">upside down in upper margin:</tei:hi>] so, so freue ich mich herzlich Ihres wohlverdienten Erfolges!  Mit besten Grüßen von uns Beiden,</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] <tei:hi rend="italic">H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Jonas, dated March 22, 1933</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>March 22, 1933</tei:p><tei:p>Esteemed, dear Dr. Jonas,</tei:p><tei:p>Sometime, “under four (or at most six) eyes,”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> I will tell you about all of the interconnections Hoboken <tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> has intruded into your affairs and mine; today I want [only] to express my pleasure that things have at least progressed so far!  Good luck, then!  And now to your question:<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/></tei:p><tei:p>Marx’s<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> initiative went first to Dr. Kalmus<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> (Universal Edition), who communicated it to me in writing.  The first desideratum of Marx related to maximal brevity, maximal affordability.  Now Vrieslander<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> had already put such a project before Director Hertzka<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> more than fifteen years ago, <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> about which, naturally, I also knew.  As a matter of course, I referred Dr. Kalmus to Vrieslander; a very active correspondence resulted.  Meanwhile, Marx had also visited me here and proposed further desiderata for discussion (please don’t laugh, it is melancholy enough)—thus for example while maintaining all brevity (at most 100 pages) he wanted further an “appendix” with concise references to <tei:hi rend="italic">chorale</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">form</tei:hi>, and <tei:hi rend="italic">modulation</tei:hi>.  I conveyed this to Vrieslander, but suggested that he should not be bothered by such foolishness.  Once the matter had progressed so far that an order by Kalmus was in the offing, K. suddenly announced (by letter) that Marx couldn’t make any assurances, since the Introduction did not depend on him alone.  (He was involved as “Director,” but now this arrangement is a thing of the past.)  That Kalmus, under such <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> circumstances, no longer considers the application, is clear.  None of this is affected by the fact that, as M. himself wrote me, my works are <tei:hi rend="italic">pre-designated</tei:hi> as “teaching materials”!  Excuse me, I forgot to mention the funniest and saddest part.  K. told me that M. also wanted to have “<tei:hi rend="italic">exercises</tei:hi>” included!!!  In a word: the matter ^again^ came down to a:—“Stöhr”!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/>  That is how disastrous it looks in such minds,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> and the personal relationship has shown me a depth beyond which any lower cannot be conceived.  Really, nothing more could be done there.  Pitiful nevertheless: Vrieslander, honorable as always to the end, asked my permission <tei:hi rend="italic">to do the work anyway</tei:hi>, he being so completely convinced that sooner or later it would be needed, for which, at that time, the <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> resources certainly would be found.  (He is considering also a testamentary assurance.)  Incidentally: he has completed a similar study ^for himself, and also for his students,^ on <tei:hi rend="italic">Counterpoint</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> obviously not unlike you yourself, as I gather from your letter.</tei:p><tei:p>It is clear that in your work you cannot bypass vol. I.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/>  Even the scale-degree progression in the forground will require it.  And when, in connection with the scale-degree, you return to the fifth etc., you will surely have to touch on vol. I, more still: invoke it.  By the way, there sticks in my memory<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> a path ^to the scale-degrees^ that you struck in one of your essays.  I would like to think that no conflict at all can arise; Vrieslander’s purpose is much more limited, yours freer: you, incidentally, are not familiar with his achievement, nor he with yours.</tei:p><tei:p>Have you heard of Dr. Weisse’s<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> successes?  Ninety auditors (also for the “Urlinien-Tafeln”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/>), $450 for twelve lessons, not bad. —That Einstein<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn15"/> gives ^you^ free rein concerning <tei:hi rend="italic">Saul</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn16"/> makes me happy for you, and for the work.  Hoboken wrote me that things are better for you; [<tei:hi rend="italic">upside down in upper margin:</tei:hi>] if it is true, <tei:hi rend="italic">if</tei:hi> it is true, then I take great pleasure in your well-earned success!  With best greetings from both of us,</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[signed:] H. Schenker</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>