<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 36/19, [2] : 2-7-49 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Oswald Jonas, published here with kind permission.
© Transcription Christoph Hust 200l.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Christoph Hust, 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> Permission to publish on this website granted by the heirs of Oswald Jonas, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance> Jonas, Oswald (1949-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Oswald Jonas; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Christoph Hust &amp; Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 02/07/1949 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: &quot;Furtw&#195;&#164;ngler ~ Jonas&quot;,&quot;Jonas ~ Furtw&#195;&#164;ngler&quot; --><dc:title>Carbon copy of a typewritten letter from Jonas to Furtwängler, dated February 7, 1949</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-12-03</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>J thanks F for his letter and expresses regret at recent offensive newspaper coverage [of a prospective tour by F?];  he encloses a copy of a letter written but not published;  he will have to make do with recordings.  —J reports that he has been working with a translator on Schenker's Harmonielehre; that he has met Hoboken, and examined the manuscript of Brahms's Violin Concerto in Washington;  he expresses pleasure at F's recently published Conversations about Music, making only one complaint.  —He tells of his invitation to teach at the Vienna Conservatory and subsequent disappointment, and asks if F can help him.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Jonas, Oswald; Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Chicago Sun;  critic;  Beethoven;  Brahms;  Tchaikovsky;  New York;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Harmonielehre;  Theory of Harmony;  Oster, Ernst;  Kreisler, Fritz;  Joachim, Joseph;  Gespräche über Musik;  Conversations about Music;  Helmholtz, Hermann von;  Hindemith;  Unterweisung im Tonsatz;  Craft of Musical Composition;  Traditional Harmony;  Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst;  Vienna Conservatory;  Marx, Joseph;  Mozarteum;  Kultusministerium;  Ministry of Culture;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  Schütz, Herr</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> 1719 North Park Avenue, Chicago 14, Ill.</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Carbon copy of a typewritten letter from Oswald Jonas to Wilhelm Furtwängler, dated February 7, 1949, unsigned</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>7. Februar 1949
1719 North Park Ave.
Chicago 14, Ill.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Herr Dr. Furtwängler!</tei:p><tei:p>Herz[l]ichen Dank für Ihren lieben, lieben Brief, der mir unendliche Freude bereitet hat!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  The letter from Furtwängler to Jonas is not known to survive.  </tei:note> Sie können sich ja kaum vorstellen, mit welchem Widerwillen und Ekel wir all dem Zeitungsgewäsche hier ausgesetzt waren – umso widerwärtiger, als ich bestimmt weiß, daß die ganze Sache nichts mit Politik zu tun hatte, sondern diese wie gewöhnlich nur der Vorschub von gewissen Herrschaften war, die einfach die Konkurrenz – und das mit Recht – fürchten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> Furtwängler had been invited in August 1948 to conduct the Chicago Symphony Orchestra.  After some discussion, he accepted an eight-week contract, whereupon a protest campaign was mounted against him, as he was believed to be a former Nazi. Led allegedly by Arturo Toscanini, the campaign was quickly joined by a number of well-known performers, among them Jascha Heifetz, Vladimir Horowitz, Lotte Lehmann, Nathan Milstein, Gregor Piatigorsky, and Artur Rubinstein. After James Petrillo, president of the American musicians' union became involved, it became clear by January 1949 that Furtwängler would not be granted a work permit for the United States. Cf. Berndt W. Wessling, <tei:hi rend="italic">Furtwängler: Eine kritische Biographie</tei:hi> (Munich: Heyne, 1985), pp. 422-428;  Elisabeth Furtwängler, <tei:hi rend="italic">Über Wilhelm Furtwängler</tei:hi> (Wiesbaden: Brockhaus, 1979), pp. 138-9. For Oswald Jonas's letter of protest to the <tei:hi rend="italic">Chicago Sun-Times</tei:hi>, click on &lt;a href="../../../../../correspondence/letter/oj<tei:hi rend="italic">3662</tei:hi>1949.html"&gt;January 9, 1949&lt;/a&gt;.</tei:note> Der Kritiker des "Sun"<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> Click on <ref cRef="chicago_suntimes">Chicago Sun-Times</ref>. </tei:note> ist ein höchst integrer Mann, aber eben doch nicht &lt;strike&gt;mac&lt;/strike&gt; machtvoll genug, gegen die Herren von "oben" aufzukommen.  So wurde auch der Brief, den ich in Kopie beilege, nicht mehr abgedruckt, vermutlich weil er die Wahrheit sagte.  Was mir und allen meinen Freunden hier Ihr Herkommen bedeutet hätte, werden Sie wohl ermessen. Freilich ob es in Ihrem eigenen Interesse erwünscht gewesen wäre, ist eine Frage, die Sie sich leicht nach dem Erlebten selbst beantworten können. Was wirkliche Kunst im großen und tiefen Sinn ist und bedeutet, das zu erkennen, sind die Leute noch weit, weit entfernt. Und so muß ich mich inzwischen damit begnügen, die wenigen Platten, die erhältlich sind, mit selbst und anderen Leuten vorzuspielen, um in Kontakt mit dem Großen zu bleiben, (Beethoven V., Brahms I. und Tschaikowsk[i.)] Vorige Woche habe ich sie sogar nach Cleveland und N. Y. geschleppt, um den Leuten einen Begriff von dieser vollkommen anderen Welt zu geben.</tei:p><tei:p>In New York, wo ich meine Semesterferien verbracht habe, <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> habe ich auch mit einem Übersetzer<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> Arthur Waldeck, who had prepared a translation <tei:hi rend="italic">c.</tei:hi>1929–32 that had not come to publication.  </tei:note> an der Herausgabe und einem Kommentar zu Schenker's Harmonielehre gearbeitet und ich hoffe, daß wir Glück mit einem Verleger haben werden.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Jonas worked with Arthur Waldeck <tei:hi rend="italic">c.</tei:hi>1948–51 and the resulting translation, with Jonas’s introduction and commentary, was submitted first to Princeton University Press, who turned it down in March 1951, then to Chicago University Press, who in 1952 proposed that a new translator be brought it.  Elisabeth Mann Borgese (1918–2002)—the fifth child and youngest daughter of Thomas Mann, and wife of the Italian historian and writer Giuseppe Antonio Borgese—took this on, and the result, with introduction, footnoted annotations, and appendix by Jonas, was published under the title <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmony</tei:hi> by Chicago in 1954.  For details of this convoluted publication history, see Robert W. Wason, “From Harmonielehre to Harmony: Schenker’s Theory of Harmony and its Americanization,” in <tei:hi rend="italic">Schenker-Traditionen:  Eine Wiener Schule der Musiktheorie und ihre internationale Verbreitung / A Viennese School of Music Theory and Its International Dissemination</tei:hi>, ed. Martin Eybl and Evelyn Fink-Mennel (Vienna, Cologne &amp; Weimar: Böhlau, 2006), pp. 171–201, esp. 180–90.  </tei:note> Dann müßte auch an eine Herausgabe von einigen Sachen aus dem Nachlass gedacht werden, die größtenteils im Besitz eines Schülers und Freundes von mir, Ernst Oster,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6"> Click on <ref cRef="oster_ernst">Ernst Oster</ref>.  </tei:note> in N. Y. sind. Auch Hoboken,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7"> Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.  </tei:note> der in Amerika auf der Suche nach Exemplaren für den Haydn Katalog ist, habe ich in N. Y. getroffen[.]  In Washington sah ich das Manuscript des Brahms Violinkonzertes, das Kreisler<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Fritz Kreisler (1875–1962) [create profile].  </tei:note> gerade der Bibliothek gegeben hat, und das voll hochinteressanter Eintragungen und Verbesserungen von Brahms' und auch Joachim's<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Joseph Joachim (1831–1907) [create profile].  </tei:note> Hand ist. – Ich hatte endlich auch Gelegenheit Ihre (["]Gespräche über Musik" zu lesen, das hier schwer zu bekommen ist.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10"> Wilhelm Furtwängler, <tei:hi rend="italic">Gespräche über Musik</tei:hi> (Zürich: Atlantis, 1948; Eng. trans. as <tei:hi rend="italic">Concerning Music</tei:hi> (London: Boosey &amp; Hawkes, 1953)).</tei:note> Ich habe es mit größtem Genuß gelesen und ich hoffe, daß es vielen etwas Kopfweh verursachen wird. Wenn mir ein Einwand erlaubt ist, möchte ich nur bemerken, daß der Zustand der letzten Jahren [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] bereits vor 40 Jahren von Schenker mit Sehergabe vorausgesagt – und gewußt war. Und wenn Schenker den Tonraum der Tonalität entdeckte und ihn von den "Obertönen" als dem Apriorikum im Genie herleitet, so hat das in diesem Zusammenhang nichts mit Physik zu tun (zum Unterschied von Helmholtz und Hindemith), sondern stellt eben das "Biologische" in der Musik (in Tonalität und Form) vor.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11"> The allusion is presumably to Schenker’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (Stuttgart: Cotta, 1906), pp. 34–44 (Eng. trans., pp. 21–31).  </tei:note> Über all diese Fragen habe ich in den letzten Jahren viel nachgedacht (mehr gedacht und gesprochen als geschrieben) und ich möchte so gerne das alles einmal ausführlich mit Ihnen selbst aussprechen. –<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Schenker inserts a emdash at this point, then writes continuously, without paragraph break.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Das bringt mich auf ein eigenes Abenteuer, das ich gerade mit meinen "Landsleuten" <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> in Wien erlebt habe. Ich hatte voriges Jahr bereits die Aufforderung von der Akademie<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  The Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst, i.e. the Vienna Conservatory.   </tei:note> bekommen, daselbst Vorträge und Kurse zu halten. Knapp vor Weihnachten wieder ein Schreiben, das die Fakultät einstimmig (!) und auch auf besonderen Wunsch von Joseph Marx<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  Click on <ref cRef="marx_joseph">Joseph Marx</ref>.  </tei:note> mich für Vorträge engagieren will, freilich müßte ich, wenn meine Reise rentabel sein sollte, noch andere Sachen unternehmen, bei denen sie mir aber sehr behülflich sein wollten, und ich sollte nur diesbezügliche Vorschläge machen. Meine Vorschläge [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] nun bestanden darin, mir an der Bibliothek [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] und eventuell am Mozarteum<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15">  Mozarteum:  the Mozarteum Salzburg, which had since 1945 been a music highschool (Musikhochschule);  originally founded in 1841, since 1914 a Conservatory, in 1949 it was under the directorship of Berhard Paumgartner.  </tei:note> Vorträge oder einen Kurs zu veranstalten.  Als Antwort, nachdem also alles geregelt war, bekam ich vorige Woche einen Brief des Bedauerns, dass das Kultusministerium jeden Betrag für irgendeine Tätigkeit meinerseits an der Akademie einfach abgelehnt habe!!!!  Ich bekam den Brief nach N. Y. nachgesandt, zeigte ihn Hoboken,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7"> Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.  </tei:note> der sofort [<tei:hi rend="italic">word deleted</tei:hi>] sagte, daß da ein bestimmter Herr dahinter sei, derselbe, der Herrn Schütz sofort in Amt und Würden gesetzt hat.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn16"> Herr Schütz: [identify].  </tei:note> Das Ganze stellt ein nettes Gegenbeispiel zu Ihrem Erlebnis dar! – Glauben Sie, daß Sie selbst irgendetwas in dieser Angelegenheit für mich unternehmen könnten (auch in Salzburg) oder ist es zu unbesche[i]den, wenn ich Sie darum bitte – eventuell an irgendeiner anderen Universität oder Institut, das dafür in Frage käme? – Nun mein Brief ist ziemlich lang geworden – bitte schreiben Sie mir bald wieder und seien Sie noch – sehr herzlichst bedankt.</tei:p><tei:p>In alter Treue</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Carbon copy of a typewritten letter from Oswald Jonas to Wilhelm Furtwängler, dated February 7, 1949, unsigned</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>February 7, 1949
1719 North Park Ave.
Chicago 14, Ill.</tei:p><tei:p>Highly esteemed Dr. Furtwängler,</tei:p><tei:p>Cordial thanks for your delightful letter, which has given me endless pleasure.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  You can really scarcely imagine what antipathy and disgust we felt on being subjected to all the chatter of the newspapers;  all the more offensive since I know for sure that the whole matter had nothing to do with politics, but rather that it was as usual only whipped up by certain influential people who—quite rightly—merely feared the competition.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  The critic of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Sun</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> is a man of great integrity, but even he was not powerful enough to prevail against people “in high places.”  So the letter, of which I enclose a copy, was not even published, presumably because it spoke the truth.  You will easily be able to gauge what your coming here would have signified to me and all my friends.  Admittedly, whether it would have been desirably in your own interests is a question that you yourself will not find difficult to answer in the light of what you have experienced.  People [here] are still far, far from being able to recognize what genuine art is and signifies in the greater and deeper sense.  So I will have in the meantime to be content with playing for myself and other people the few recordings that are available in order to remain in contact with the great [masters] (Beethoven’s Fifth, Brahms’s First, and Tschaikovsky).  Last week I even shlepped them to Cleveland and New York, in order to give people there an idea of this completely different world.</tei:p><tei:p>In New York, where I spent my between-semester holidays, <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> I also worked with a translator<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> on the edition and a commentary to Schenker’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Theory of Harmony</tei:hi>, on which we will try our luck with a publisher.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  Then I ought, in addition, to give thought to an edition of some items from [Schenker’s] surviving papers, which are for the most part in the possession of a pupil and friend of mine, Ernst Oster,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> in New York.  I also met Hoboken,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> who is in America in search of copies for the Haydn catalogue, in New York.  In Washington, I saw the manuscript of Brahms’s Violin Concerto, which Kreisler<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> has just given to the library, and which is full of the most interesting annotations and improvements in Brahms’s and also Joachim’s<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> hand.  — Finally, I also had the opportunity to read your <tei:hi rend="italic">Conversations about Music</tei:hi>, which is hard to get hold of here.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/>  I read it with the greatest enjoyment, and I hope that it will cause many people something of a headache.  If I might be permitted one objection, I should just like to point out that the state of things in recent years was predicted and known about as long ago as forty years with prophetic vision by Schenker.  And if Schenker discovered the tonal space of tonality and derived it from the “overtones” as the <tei:hi rend="italic">a priori</tei:hi> of genius, in this connection it had nothing to do with physics (contrary to what Helmholtz and Hindemith say), but rather represents the “biological” in music (in tonality and form).<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/>  I have pondered long and hard on all of these questions over the last few years (more pondered and spoken than written), and I should so very much like to talk it all through sometime in detail with you.  –<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/></tei:p><tei:p>That brings me to an adventure of my own that I actually had with my own “fellow-countrymen” <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> in Vienna.  I had already, the previous year, received an invitation from the Academy<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> to give lectures and courses there.  Just before Christmas, another letter came seeking to engage me for lectures with the unanimous (!) support of the faculty and also at the express wish of Joseph Marx<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/>;  true, I was going to have, if my trip were to be profitable, to undertake other things as well, but they were willing to assist me in this, and all I had to do was to offer suggestions in this connection.  My suggestions then consisted in organizing lectures or a course for me at the Library, or possibly at the Mozarteum.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn15"/>  In reply, after everything was settled, I received last week a letter of regret that the Ministry of Culture had simply turned down every payment for any activity on my part at the Academy!!!!  I received the letter forwarded on to New York, and showed it to Hoboken,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> who immediately said that a certain gentleman was behind it who had had forthwith appointed Mr. Schütz to high rank and honor.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn16"/>  The whole affair presents a neat mirror-image to your experience!  Do you think that you could yourself undertake something for me in this connection (also in Salzburg), or is it too presumptuous of me to ask that of you—or perhaps at some other university or institute that might be suitable?  —Now my letter has become rather long;  please write back to me soon, and accept my most cordial thanks.</tei:p><tei:p>Yours faithfully</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>