<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 36/19, [1] : 9-10-47 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Oswald Jonas, published here with kind permission.
© Transcription Christoph Hust 200l.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Christoph Hust, 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> Permission to publish on this website granted by the heirs of Oswald Jonas, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance> Jonas, Oswald (1947-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Oswald Jonas; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Christoph Hust &amp; Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 09/10/1947 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: &quot;Furtw&#195;&#164;ngler ~ Jonas&quot;,&quot;Jonas ~ Furtw&#195;&#164;ngler&quot; --><dc:title>Carbon copy of a typewritten letter from Jonas to Furtwängler, dated September 10, 1947</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-12-03</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>J expresses his admiration for F and rejoices that F is back on the podium;  he reports on his own career since they were last in touch, and expresses a desire to return to Austria and his hopes of meeting with F.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Jonas, Oswald; Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Oster, Ernst;  Luzern;  Lucerne;  Tchaikovsky;  Chicago;  Roosevelt College;  Katz, Adele T.;  Weisse, Hans;  Hindemith;  Unterweisung im Tonsatz;  Craft of Musical Composition;  Concentrated Course in Traditional Harmony</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> 1719 North Park Av., Chicago 14, Ill.</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Carbon copy of a typewritten letter from Oswald Jonas to Wilhelm Furtwängler, dated September 10, 1947, unsigned</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>10. September 1947
1719 North Park Av.
Chicago 14, Ill.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Herr Doktor! [<tei:hi rend="italic">handwritten: </tei:hi>Furtwängler]</tei:p><tei:p>Nach langer, langer und harter Pause ergreife ich wieder [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] die Gelegenheit Ihnen endlich zu schreiben – mein Freund und Schüler Oster,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> Click on <ref cRef="oster_ernst">Ernst Oster</ref>.  </tei:note> der Sie in Luzern gehört und gesprochen hat, schrieb mir begeistert über das Konzert und sand [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] mir Ihre Adresse.</tei:p><tei:p>Wenn ich Ihnen schreiben wollte, wie oft, wieviel und mit welchen Gefühlen der Wehmut und Sehnsucht ich an Sie gedacht habe in all den Jahren, seitdem ich Europa hatte verlassen müssen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> Jonas left Vienna in 1938.  From 1941 to 1963, he was Professor of Music Theory at Roosevelt University, Chicago. Cf. John Rothgeb, “Oswald Jonas (1897–1978),” in <tei:hi rend="italic">Schenker-Traditionen:  Eine Wiener Schule der Musiktheorie und ihre internationale Verbreitung / A Viennese School of Music Theory and Its International Dissemination</tei:hi>, ed. Martin Eybl and Evelyn Fink-Mennel (Vienna/Cologne/Weimar: Böhlau, 2006), pp. 121–35.</tei:note> es würde ein ganzes Buch füllen; in all der Zeit sind Sie mir das Symbol geblieben, das Sie immer für mich gewesen sind: das Vorbild von reiner und großer Art, wie Musik zur Darstellung gebracht werden soll. Eine Art, von der man hierzulande keinen Begriff hat und von der ich meinen Schülern hier immer wieder erzählt habe, ohne es ihnen je ganz deutlich und wirklich lebendig machen zu können – selbst die Platten, die hier zu haben sind (Fünfte Symphony and [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Tschaikowski) sind ja nur ein schwacher Ersatz. – Ich habe immer daran gedacht, was Sie wohl in den schweren Jahren gelitten haben mögen und so war ich doppelt glücklich, wenn ich hörte, dass Sie wieder zurück am Podium sind und in Ihrem Element<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> Furtwängler had been granted permission to conduct in Germany again in April 1947.</tei:note> – ich kann mir freilich denken, dass es Zeit und Arbeit kosten wird, die Orche&lt;strike&gt;r&lt;/strike&gt;sters [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] wieder auf alte Höhe zu bringen.</tei:p><tei:p>Von mir selbst will ich Ihnen nur vorläufig in aller Kürze berichten, dass ich nach vielen Versuchen hier in Chicago vor sechs Jahren gelandet bin, dem Theory Department vorstehe (am Roosevelt College) und versuche, was in meinen Kräften steht, der Jugend, die der begeisterungsfähige Teil der Bevölkerung ist, Liebe und Verständnis in der Musik beizubringen. Ich habe auch viele Vorlesungen im <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> ganzen Lande gehalten und zahlreiche Aufsätze geschrieben.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> See the selected work list in John Rothgeb’s article in <tei:hi rend="italic">MGG2</tei:hi>, Personenteil, vol. 9, col. 1162.</tei:note> Ich arbeite noch immer an einem Buch, das nur sehr langsam vorwärtsgeht, da der Unterricht viel Zeit und Energie in Anspruch nimmt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> Probably either the book on Brahms or the commentary to <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi> mentioned in OJ 36/19, [3].</tei:note> Inzwischen ist ein sehr schlechtes Buch über Schenker erschienen – von einer ehemaligen Weisse Schülerin – das mehr geschadet als genützt hat.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6"> Presumably Adele T. Katz (who studied with Hans Weisse at Mannes College 1931–35), <tei:hi rend="italic">Challenge to Musical Tradition: A New Concept of Tonality</tei:hi> (New York: Knopf, 1945), the first English-language book to expound a Schenkerian analytical approach.    </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>So paradox es klingen mag, aber die Schwierigkeit in diesem Lande für meine Arbeit besteht darin, dass alles nach Schema und bestimmten "curriculum" vor sich zu gehen hat – und ich habe gerade jetzt wieder "Anstoss" wegen der Harmonie Lehre [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>], die ich in der alten Form ganz gestrichen habe. (Hindemith hat nach seiner übergeschraubten "Unterweisung" jetzt eine "Traditional Harmony" veröffentlicht!!!!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7"> Vol. 1 of <tei:hi rend="italic">Unterweisung im Tonsatz</tei:hi> had been published in 1937 in the first edn (Eng. trans. New York: Schott, 1942);  <tei:hi rend="italic">A Concentrated Course in Traditional Harmony</tei:hi> followed in 1943.</tei:note>) Und so gibt es immer Kampf. – Wenn ich wieder [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] in meinem Lande – wenigstens [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] für eine Zeit – ald [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte:</tei:hi> als] Lehrer wirken könnte, so wäre das eine wunderbare Sache und ich bin auch dabei zu versuchen, nächstes Jahr hinüberfahren zu können für Gastvorlesungen und Lehrtätigkeit. Wie herrlich wäre es, Sie dann wieder sehen, sprechen ind [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte:</tei:hi> und] hören zu können.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich wünsche Ihnen alles Glück für die kommenden Jahre und wäre sehr, sehr froh, wenn Sie mir einmal ein wenig über sich selbst schreiben würde [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte:</tei:hi> würden]. In immer gleicher dankbarer Verehrung</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr ergebener</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Carbon copy of a typewritten letter from Oswald Jonas to Wilhelm Furtwängler, dated September 10, 1947, unsigned</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>September 10, 1947
1719 North Park Av.
Chicago 14, Ill.</tei:p><tei:p>Highly esteemed Dr. [<tei:hi rend="italic">handwritten:</tei:hi> Furtwängler]</tei:p><tei:p>After a long, oh so long, hard period of silence, I once more seize the opportunity at long last of writing to you.  My friend and pupil Oster,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> who heard and spoke with you in Lucerne, wrote to me inspired by the concert and sent me your address.</tei:p><tei:p>If I were to tell you how often, how many times, and with what feelings of nostalgia and longing I have thought of you, in all the years since I was obliged to leave Europe,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> it would fill a whole book.  In all of that time, you have remained in my eyes the symbol that you ever were for me:  the model of [the] pure and great way in which music ought to be presented—a way of which nobody in this country has the faintest inkling, and which I have constantly,over and over again, recounted to my pupils without ever having been able to bring it to life for them totally clearly and vividly.  Even the records that are available here (Fifth Symphony and [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Tchaikovsky) are only a feeble substitute.  — I have always thought how greatly you must have suffered in the difficult years, thus I was doubly happy when I heard that you were back again on the podium and in your element.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  I can readily imagine that it will take time and work to restore the orchestras to their former glory once again.</tei:p><tei:p>Of myself, I will report to you only provisionally and succinctly that I settled here in Chicago six years ago, after many attempts, that I chair the Theory Department (at Roosevelt College), and that I try with all the strength at my command to convey to the younger generation—that part of the population most susceptible to being inspired—a love for, and understanding of music.  I have also given many lectures all over <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> the country, and have written numerous articles.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  I work constantly on a book that progresses only very slowly, since my teaching demands much time and energy.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  In the interim, a very bad book has appeared about Schenker—by a former pupil of Weisse—that has done more harm than good.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/></tei:p><tei:p>Paradoxical though it may seem however, the difficulty for my work in this country lies in the fact that everything must be done according to a scheme and prescribed “curriculum,” and right now I am conducting a “campaign” as regards harmony teaching, which in its old form I have eliminated altogether.  (Hindemith, after his eccentric <tei:hi rend="italic">Craft of Musical Composition</tei:hi>, has published a <tei:hi rend="italic">Traditional Harmony</tei:hi>!!!!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>)  Thus there is a constant fight.  —If I could work again in my own country—even if for only a time—as a teacher, that would be wonderful, and I am going to try to get over next year for guest lectures and some teaching work.  How splendid it would be to see you then, and to speak with you and hear you.</tei:p><tei:p>I wish you all the best for the coming years, and should be very, very happy if you would sometime write to me about yourself.  In everlastingly grateful admiration.</tei:p><tei:p>Yours truly,</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>