<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 70/3 : undated --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  Heirs of Moriz Violin, published with kind permission.
©  Transcription Christoph Hust, 2007.
©  Translation Ian Bent, 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Christoph Hust &amp; Ian Bent 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission granted by the heirs of Moriz Violin.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Violin, Moriz (1935-1956) - -Heirs of Moriz Violin (1956-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Moriz Violin; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Christoph Hust &amp; Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 01/15/1935 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "RosenthalM ~ ViolinM","ViolinM ~ RosenthalM" --><dc:title>Handwritten draft of a letter from Moriz Violin to Moriz Rosenthal, undated, probably dating from shortly after Schenker's death [=January 14, 1935]</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-09-30</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>V regrets having failed to honor an agreement with R to write an "outpouring from the heart" regarding Schenker's theory, and proceeds to draft a statement on the "presuppositions of the Urlinie," which he will re-draft in light of R's comments.  "Sad news" [presumably that of Schenker's death] has apparently just reached R.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Violin, Moriz;  Rosenthal, Moriz;  Violin, Valerie;  Gastein;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Urlinie;  Tonempfindung;  sensation of tone;  Vordergrundstechnik;  foreground technique;  Hintergrundstechnik;  background technique;  Meisterwerk in der Musik, Das;  Masterwork in Music, The</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten draft of a letter from Moriz Violin to Moriz Rosenthal, undated, probably dating from shortly after Schenker's death [=January 14, 1935]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in another hand:</tei:hi>] Brief an Mor[i]z Rosenthal</tei:p><tei:p>Ihre werte Frau Gemalin<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Valerie (Vally, Wally) Violin.  </tei:note> forderte mich bei meiner gestrigen Verabschiedung in großer Freundlichkeit zu einer musikalischen Plauschwiederholung auf.  Der Zustand meiner Nerven wird mich Montag zur Flucht aus Gastein<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Bad Gastein, Austrian ski resort 47 miles south of Salzburg.</tei:note> veranlaßen.  Die traurigen Nachrichten, die Sie jetzt aus Wien erreichen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  This must surely be the news of S’s death, which occurred on January 14, 1935.</tei:note> gestatten eine Störung ja auch nicht so bald.  Nun stürmt auf mich das Gefühl der unerfüllten Verständigung ein<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Violin appears to have undertaken to write an article before S’s death, and attempts to draft it in the latter part of this letter.  He also contributed “Zur Erinnerung an Heinrich Schenker” (In Memory of Heinrich Schenker) to the <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue Freie Presse</tei:hi>, January 31, 1935, of which a clipping is preserved in S’s scrapbook, OC 2/pp. 90 and 91.</tei:note>; ein Zustand, der für mich unerträglich ist, wenn mir die Tragweite zweie [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] Faktoren bewußt wird.  Erstens meine große Wertschätzung Ihrer Künstlerschaft u. zweitens meine Einschätzung der epochalen theoretischen Ideen Schenkers.  Wird also [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] mein &lt;strike&gt;Gedanke ein&lt;/strike&gt; &lt;strike&gt;u&lt;/strike&gt;Unternehmen Ihnen einen schriftlichen Herzenserguß zu übermitteln, der eine prinzipielle Verständigung herbei führen möchte, auf ein wolwollendes Echo ^bei Ihnen^ rechnen dürfen, oder habe ich zu befürchten[,] daß sich in Ihnen die Gedankenformel von der „unbescheidenen Bescheidenheit“, oder der „bescheidenen Unbescheidenheit“ regt? Im letzten Falle bitte ich Sie in <tei:hi rend="italic">wirklicher</tei:hi> Bescheidenheit, das Unmöglichste möglich zu machen u. diesen Brief als nicht geschrieben zu betrachten. Sie werden meine Ängst[l]ichkeit völlig verstehen, so wie[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] ich, Ihnen sicherlich Bekanntes, wiederschreiben werde. Ich <tei:hi rend="italic">muß</tei:hi> es aber wiederschreiben, weil ich es im Besondern auf die Einstellung gegenüber den Schenker'schen Ideen angewendet wissen will. Ich will mich, &lt;strike&gt;also&lt;/strike&gt;, kürzer gesagt, heute <tei:hi rend="italic">nur</tei:hi> mit den Voraussetzungen der Urlinienidee, mehr als mit ihr selbst, beschäftigen; ich bin also <tei:hi rend="italic">gegen</tei:hi> meine Überzeugung heute mehr Kunst-Philosoph, -Ästhet u. -Ethiker als reiner Künstler.</tei:p><tei:p>Eine Gefahr birgt Musiktheorie immer. &lt;strike&gt;Es hieße Schenker bitteres Unrecht zufügen, denken wir der vor allen Anderen der spekulativen Theoretiker bekämpfte&lt;/strike&gt; Empfindung, Gefühl etc. etc läßt sich nicht durch Empfindung, Gefühl etc. etc. theoretisch darstellen.  [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from the lower margin:</tei:hi> Die reine Tonempfindung, kann ich nur durch Tonempfindung erwidern, die schlechte nur durch Gute, was die Muster reichlich haben. Das ist aber nicht Theorie.] Deshalb müssen wir &lt;strike&gt;in dem&lt;/strike&gt;[<tei:hi rend="italic">overwritten as:</tei:hi> das] &lt;strike&gt;theoretische&lt;/strike&gt; Wort, das wir beim Theoretisieren nur gebrauchen können, immer nur als <tei:hi rend="italic">Transpositionserscheinung</tei:hi> der Empfindung, des Gefühls [<tei:hi rend="italic">phrase deleted</tei:hi>] ^etc. etc.^ <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> &lt;strike&gt;erkennen&lt;/strike&gt; ^nehmen^. Es hieße Schenker bitteres Unrecht zufügen, der vor allen Andern den spekulativen Theoretiker bekämpft, würden wir nicht bemerken, daß <tei:hi rend="italic">jeder</tei:hi> technischer[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Ausdruck seiner Theorien nur die Transponierung dessen &lt;strike&gt;ist&lt;/strike&gt; ^darstellt^, was wir als sinnlichen Eindruck begreifen. &lt;strike&gt;(auch wenn wir von Melodie etc. sprechen&lt;/strike&gt;.</tei:p><tei:p>Es liegt mir eine Bemerkung von Ihnen zur Urlinie tief, tief im Ohr u. Gemüt. Sie sagten ungefähr: „Was sollen denn die einzelnen Noten (Linienführung) gegenüber den undefinierbaren Imponderabilien der Melodie, ja des ganzen Werkes bedeuten?“. Ich verstand da genau was Sie als den empfanden!  Ich muß da tief in Schenkers Ideen hineingreifen. Gleichnisse sollen uns ^dann^ ganz zusammenführen. Schenker unterscheidet quasi die geistige Idee von der sinnlichen Idee. Er spricht von einer musikalischen Vordergrunds u. Hintergrundstechnik u. [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg. deletion</tei:hi>] Ich möchte das präciser durch das Gleichnis einer ewigen Wahrheit ausdrücken:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg. deletion</tei:hi>] Alles Lebende der Welt, lebt von der Vordergrundstechnik des Schöpfers. Seine reizvollen motivischen Kniffe, die Sinnlichkeit, Begierde Wollust, Schönheitsdrang, sind wahrlich nur &lt;strike&gt;die&lt;/strike&gt; Form, ^um^ dem Urgesetz seiner geistigen Idee, der Zeugung, (der Urlinie des Geschehens) Geltung zu verschaffen. Gewiß ist der Vordergrund, das Sekundäre, das Primäre in unserem Leben u. doch sind wir am nächsten dem Schöpfer, wenn wir unsere Urlinie des Lebens, die Liebe, diese wahre geistige Zeugungsidee in uns tragen.</tei:p><tei:p>Wir atmen den Duft der Blumen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Perhaps an echo of “Ich atmet’ einen linden Duft,” first line of a poem by Rückert, set to music by Mahler (1901)?</tei:note>  Das ist sicher nicht die geistige Mission der Blumen.  Der Duft erweckt in uns nur die Liebe zu ihr. Wir kommen ihr u. dem Schöpfer näher wenn wir sie als Botaniker, ^als ....tater[?]^ betrachten. Wir erschauern ^dann^ vor den Zeichen, die uns zeigen, wie das Gesetz der Zeugung, diese geistige Idee, durch &lt;strike&gt;die&lt;/strike&gt; mechanische Zeugungseinrichtungen ewiger Geltung verschafft wurde. Genießen werden wir <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> dann doppelt Duft u. Geist.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich möchte einen[?] Satz[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] Schenker zitieren:</tei:p><tei:p>„Musik ist [lebendige Bewegung von Tönen im naturgegebenen Raum, Auskomponierung (Melodisierung, Horizontalisierung) des in der Natur gegebenen Klanges.  Das Gesetz alles Lebens, die Bewegung, die als Zeugung noch über die Grenze des Einzeldaseins fortwirkt, trägt der Mensch auch in den Klang hinein, den die Natur in seinem Ohr] vorgezeichnet hat“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, vol. I (Munich: Drei Masken Verlag, 1925), p. 25 (from the article „Die Kunst der Improvisation“);  Eng. trans. by Richard Kramer (The Art of Improvisation) in <tei:hi rend="italic">The Masterwork in Music</tei:hi>, vol. I (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1994), pp. 2–3.</tei:note> (Einklang[?])</tei:p><tei:p>Für Schenker ist der Dreiklang der Repräsentant der Zeugungsidee.  Innerhalb eines ^Terz[- ,] Quart[- ,]^ Quint[- ], Sext[- ] oder Oktavraumes, ist der Weg der Urlinie vorgezeichnet. Die Auskomponierung (Motivisches etc. etc.) &lt;strike&gt;Motivik&lt;/strike&gt; kann den Weg nur auffüllen ^u. s. w.^. Bitte lesen Sie speziell Seite 187 u. die Folgenden bis Vermischtes.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  „Fortsetzung der Urlinie-Betrachtungen,“ <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, vol. I (Munich: Drei Masken Verlag, 1925), pp. 187–200;  Eng. trans. by John Rothgeb, “Further Considerations of the Urlinie,” in <tei:hi rend="italic">The Masterwork in Music</tei:hi>, vol. I (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1994), pp. 104–113.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Vielleicht giebt ein gütiges Schicksal uns ein lieblicheres, reines Notengespräch.</tei:p><tei:p>Nun endlich u. wahrhaftig: Vergeßen Sie u. die gnädige Frau <tei:hi rend="italic">jedenfalls</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  “jedenfalls”:  triple-underlined.</tei:note> meine Belästigung u. nehmen den[?] .....[?] von [<tei:hi rend="italic">left blank</tei:hi>].</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten draft of a letter from Moriz Violin to Moriz Rosenthal, undated, probably dating from shortly after Schenker's death [=January 14, 1935]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in another hand:</tei:hi>] Letter to Mor[i]z Rosenthal</tei:p><tei:p>As I was taking my leave yesterday, your dear wife<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> very kindly asked me for a return bout of gossip about music.  The state of my nerves will compel me to flee Gastein<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> on Monday.  The sad news that has now reached you from Vienna<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> really does not permit a disruption so soon.  Now I am assailed by a sense of having failed to fulfill our agreement<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>—a state of mind that is unbearable for me when I call to mind the magnitude of two factors:  first, the great esteem in which I hold your artistry, and second, the value I place on Schenker’s epoch-making theoretical ideas.  So can my &lt;strike&gt;idea&lt;/strike&gt; undertaking to let you have a written outpouring from the heart that might be acceptable in principle count on striking a benign chord ^in you^, or do I have to fear that the turn of phrase “immodest modesty” or “modest immodesty” will spring to your mind?  In the latter case, I beg you in <tei:hi rend="italic">real</tei:hi> modesty to make possible the most impossible of all and regard this letter as never having been written.  You will understand my timidity fully just as soon as I re-draft something that is surely well-known to you.   Re-draft it I <tei:hi rend="italic">must</tei:hi>, however, because I want in particular to know how it accords with [your] attitude toward Schenker’s ideas.  To put it more briefly, I will &lt;strike&gt;thus&lt;/strike&gt; concern myself today <tei:hi rend="italic">only</tei:hi> with the presuppositions of the Urlinie idea, rather than the idea itself.  I am thus [acting], <tei:hi rend="italic">contrary to</tei:hi> my convictions, more [as] an art philosopher, aesthetician, and ethicist than [as] a pure artist.</tei:p><tei:p>Within music theory there always lurks a danger.  Sensation, feeling, etc., etc. do not admit of being represented in theoretical terms through sensation, feeling, etc., etc.  [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from the lower margin:</tei:hi> I can return pure tone-sensation only through tone-sensation, the bad through good[??], in which the models abound.  That, however, is not theory.]  For this reason, we must &lt;strike&gt;identify&lt;/strike&gt; ^adopt^ the word that we can use only in the process of theorising always only as <tei:hi rend="italic">transpositional manifestation</tei:hi> of sensation, feeling [<tei:hi rend="italic">phrase deleted</tei:hi>] ^etc., etc.^  <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> We would do a serious injustice to Schenker, who above all others battles the speculative theorists, were we not to observe that <tei:hi rend="italic">every</tei:hi> technical expression in his theories ^represents^ only a transposition of that which we perceive as sensuous impression.  &lt;strike&gt;(even when we speak of melody, etc.)&lt;/strike&gt;</tei:p><tei:p>For me, a remark of yours concerning the Urlinie sticks deep, deep in my ear and mind.  You said approximately:  “What, after all, can the individual notes (linear formations) signify over against the indefinable imponderabilities of melody, indeed of the whole work?”  I understood then precisely what you were feeling by this!  I have to plunge deep into Schenker’s ideas for that.  Likenesses should ^then^ draw us wholly together.  Schenker distinguishes, as it were, the mental idea from the sensuous idea.  He speaks of a musical foreground and background technique and [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg. deletion</tei:hi>] I should like to express that more precisely through the likeness or an eternal truth:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg. deletion</tei:hi>]  Every living thing in the world lives off the creator’s foreground technique.  His enchanting motivic enfoldings, the sensuality, craving, voluptuousness, the appeal of beauty: all these are in truth only form ^designed to^ gain recognition for the primordial law of his mental idea, of procreation (of the Urlinie of happening).  The foreground, the secondary phenomenon, is indeed the primary thing in our lives and we are in fact closest to the creator when we carry within ourselves our Urlinie of life, love, this true mental procreative idea.</tei:p><tei:p>We breathe the fragrance of flowers.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  That is certainly not the spiritual mission of flowers.  The fragrance awakes in us only a love for it [the flower].  We come closer to it and to the creator when we view it as botanist, ^as ....[?]^.   ^Then^ we shudder before the signs that show us how the law of procreation, this spiritual idea, was provided through mechanical procreative arrangements of eternal value.  Then we will enjoy <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> doubly both fragrance and spirit.</tei:p><tei:p>I should like to quote a sentence from Schenker:</tei:p><tei:p>“<tei:hi rend="italic">Music is</tei:hi> [<tei:hi rend="italic">the living motion of tones in the space given in Nature</tei:hi>:  the composing-out (the rendering in melodic line, the linearization) of the Nature-given sonority.  The law of all life, the motion which, as procreation, issues forth beyond the boundaries of individual being, penetrates into man in this sonority which Nature] has preordained [in his hearing].<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> (Unison[?])</tei:p><tei:p>For Schenker, the triad is the representative of the procreative idea.  The pathway of the Urlinie is preordained within the space of a ^third, fourth,^ fifth, sixth, or octave.   The composing-out (of motivic material, etc., etc) can only fill out the pathway, etc.  Please read particularly pp. 187ff as far as the “Miscellanea.”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/></tei:p><tei:p>Perhaps a kind fate yields for us a more melodious, pure conversation in tones.</tei:p><tei:p>Now finally and truthfully:  let you and your wife <tei:hi rend="italic">at any rate</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> forget the annoyance I caused you and accept the ........[?] from [<tei:hi rend="italic">left blank</tei:hi>]</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>