<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 5/34, [2], vsn 2 : 8-4-34 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  In the public domain.  
© Transcription Ian Bent, 2008.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2008.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1934-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker;  Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 08/04/1934 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Rothschild ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten revised draft letter from Schenker to Alphons Rothschild, undated [August 3-4, 1934]</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-03-28</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Schenker sends Alphons a copy of Jonas's new book, Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks, thanks him again for his past support, and surveys his total output, the repute of his name, and the dissemination of his theory.  —He suggests that his name might by now have been as well known as that of [Albert?] Einstein, had mankind only understood the nature of music better. —He criticizes Vienna for ignoring him, and reports on Furtwängler's adherence to his ideas and loyalty toward him in person. 

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Rothschild, Baron Alphons Mayer von;  Jonas, Oswald;  Wesen  des musikalischen Kunstwerks;  Nature of the Musical Artwork;  Beethoven;  sonatas;  Brockhaus;  Mayer;  Herder; Einstein;  Neue freie Presse;  Walter, Bruno;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Strauss, Richard;  Pernter, Johann Maria Valentin;  Unterrichtsministerium;  Ministry of Education;  Rothschild Orchester;  Rettich, Prof.</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  [Böckstein]</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten revised draft letter from Schenker to Alphons Rothschild, in Jeanette Schenker's hand, undated [August 3-4, 1934]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>An Baron Rothschild<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  The following is the sequence of relevant events, traced from Schenker's diary:  July 11, 1934: Schenker receives five copies of Jonas's book from Saturn Verlag;  August 3: dictates draft letter to Rothschild;  August 5: writes fair copy of letter;  August 6: finishes copying letter;  August 7: the book is wrapped and mailed off;  August 17: the book comes back from Rothschild without response (OJ 4/7, pp. 3924–3935).  Thus, the present version 1 of the draft was produced on August 3, 1934, and the emendations made to it either later that day or on August 4.  The finished letter is not known to survive; however, the receipt of posting survives as OJ 5/34, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Alphons paid the publication costs of the first two volumes of Schenker's <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:hi>:  <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (Stuttgart:  J. G. Cotta, 1906), <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt</tei:hi>, first half-volume (ibid, 1910).  </tei:note>, August 7.  Click on <ref cRef="rothschild_alphons">Alphons von Rothschild</ref>.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Das Erscheinen des gleichzeitig an Sie abgehenden Buches von Dr. Jonas, “Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks, eine Einführung in die Lehre H. Schenkers"<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Oswald Jonas, <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks: eine Einführung in die Lehre H Schenkers</tei:hi> (Vienna: Saturn-Verlag, 1934), which was released on July 3, 1934.  </tei:note> nehme ich zum Anlaß, Ihnen nach mehr als 30. Jahren, zum zweitenmal für Ihre gütige Teilnahme zu danken, die Sie meinem Lebenswerk am Anfang haben angedeihen lassen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Alphons paid the publication costs of the first two volumes of Schenker's <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:hi>:  <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (Stuttgart:  J. G. Cotta, 1906), <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt</tei:hi>, first half-volume (ibid, 1910).  </tei:note>  Heute bin ich nun in der glücklichen Lage Ihnen einen großen künstlerischen u. moralischen Erfolg meiner gesamten Arbeit zu melden, – es sind 11 große Bände nebst vielen anderen größeren u. kleineren Arbeiten, darunter z. B. die vierbändige Gesamtausgabe der Beethoven-Sonaten –,allg[emein] darf ich heute meinen Dank an Sie nicht nur figürlich sondern wirklich im Namen der ganzen musikalischen Menschheit aussprechen.</tei:p><tei:p>Sie haben sich mit Ihrer ersten Tat ein unsterbliches Verdienst um die Musik erworben, denn von der Un<tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> sterblichkeit meiner Leistung darf ich wohl überzeugt sein.  Fern von jeder Prahlerei erwähne ich hier nur daß ohne mein Zutun mein Name u. Werk in sämtliche Lexika wie:  Brockhaus,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Brockhaus: [identify title and first edition in which Schenker appears]</tei:note> Mayer,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Mayer: [identify title and first edition in which Schenker appears]</tei:note> Herder,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Herder: [identify title and first edition in which Schenker appears]</tei:note> versteht sich auch in musikalische u. literarische aufgenommen worden ist, daß ich einen Weltruf erreicht habe. [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from p. 2v:</tei:hi> Wäre die Menschheit der Musik gegenüber nur dies[?] bescheidenes, nicht immer gleich dabei, ihre Gefühlchen schon für wirkliches Verständnis zu halten, würde sie längst auch meinen Namen im Munde führen, wie z.B. den Einsteins,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Einstein: presumably the physicist Albert Einstein rather than the musicologist Alfred Einstein.  Schenker's admiration for Albert Einstein is shown not only in the many articles about him among Schenker's papers (OC) but also in the undated draft of a letter to him (OC 13/18–30).  </tei:note> freudig etw., mit denen ich übrigens in wissenden Kreisen verglichen werde.]   Auch meine Schüler haben es schon zu ansehlichen Namen gebracht u. verbreiten allerorten meine Lehre in Europe, Amerika, Japan usw..</tei:p><tei:p>Daß es gerade nur in Wien um mich herum stiller als in der übrigen Welt ist, hat besondere eigene lokale Gründe:  Die "N. Fr. Presse" hat in den vielen, vielen Jahren weder Namen noch Werk von mir genannt ausgenommen in einem Falle da Bruno Walter,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="walter_bruno">Bruno Walter</ref>.</tei:note> mit den Pressen-Verhältnissen in Wien nicht vertraut, zufällig <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> meinen Namen erwähnte.  Nun, wir hatten zwar niemals eine Diktatur in unserem politischen Leben, aber in der kleinen Welt der Musik-Kritik hat D^r.^ K.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Dr. K.:  [identify]  </tei:note> gar zu gern einen Diktator hervorkehrt, der Alle niedermachte oder verschwieg, die seinen oder seines Sohnes Interessen entgegentrat.  Wie Sie sehen, hat aber seine Diktatur mir nichts anhaben können.  Doch lebt er, aber wir dürfen ihn doch schon zu den Dahingegangenen zählen, während ich, Gott sei es gedankt,  noch die Korrekturen eines soeben abgeschlossenen neuen großen Bandes leite, der bald erscheinen wird.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  i.e. <tei:hi rend="italic">Der frei Satz</tei:hi>, vol. III of <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:hi>, published posthumously (Vienna: UE, 1935).</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Außerdem haben in Wien die Musiker, die Professoren an der Musikakademie<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Musikakademie:  i.e. the Vienna Conservatory, since 1909 officially entitled Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst.</tei:note> u. Universität, die in musikalischen Dingen so vergnügt ihr Schwindelhandwerk treiben sich, wohlweislich vor jeder Verbindung mit mir gehütet, sie taten so, als wüßten sie nicht einmal, ob der inzwischen weltberühmt gewordene Schenker mit ihnen in Wien wohne!  Nur konnten sie sich nicht versagen, meiner gewachsenen Bedeutung doch in der Form Rechnung zu tragen, daß sie mein geistiges Eigentum <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> zumindestst – bestahlen, d. h. ohne Namensnennung abdruckten, ja nicht einmal in Gänsefüßchen zitieren.  Wie oft mögen Sie, was geistig mir gehört hat, für die Münze eines Kritikers genommen haben!  Die übrige Welt benahm sich aber allezeit u. allerorten korrekt u. respektirte mein Eigentum mit <tei:hi rend="italic">Dank</tei:hi> u. Begeisterung.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  No paragraph-break in the original.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Nehmen Sie es nicht übel, hochverehrter Herr Baron, wenn ich, den würdigen Anlaß nützend, der mich heute zu Ihnen führt, noch einiges hinzufüge, das sicherlich auch Ihnen Genugtuung bereiten wird.  Schon bei seinem ersten Erscheinen in Wien, vor etwa 15 Jahren also, hat sich Dr. F.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  Wilhelm Furtwängler: [create profile and link].  </tei:note> an mich, als den Verfasser der Monograpie über Beethoven's IX. Sinfonie<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  Schenker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie:  Eine Darstellung des musikalischen Inhaltes unter fortlaufender Berücksichtigung auch des Vortrages und der Literatur</tei:hi> [Beethoven's Ninth Symphony:  a portrayal of its musical content, with running commentary on performance and literature as well] (Vienna: UE, 1912).  </tei:note> gewendet u. seither in jeder Hinsicht an mich angeschlossen.  In all den Jahren hat er nie versäumt, mich zu besuchen, Stunden bei mir zuzubringen u. allerhand von mir zu lernen.<tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> Er bezeichnet sich selbst als meinen Schüler, was mich mit nicht wenig Stolz erfüllt.  Ihm verdanke ich auch eine Ausbreitung meines Namens u. Werkes in aller Welt, er ist rastlos darin, meine Lehre als das einzige Heil für die Zukunft der Musik zu verkünden.  In einem Brief an einen Wiener Hofrat,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15">  Viennese court counsellor: perhaps the letter from Furtwängler to Ludwig Karpath at the Ministry of Education, OJ 71/11 (1933).  </tei:note> dessen Abschrift vor mir liegt, geht er so weit, mur für die Zukunft der Musik eine größere Bedeutung als selbst einem Rich. Strauß zuzumessen.  Auch als "Preuss. Staatsrat," zuletzt anfangs Juni d. J., hat er mich, wie immer, besucht, trotzdem ich ihm gegenüber aus meinem tief überzeugten Judentum nie ein Hehl gemacht habe.  Sogar hat er seinen Besuch bei mir hier in Böckstein angekündigt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn16">  Böckstein: a health spa in the Gastein valley in the Salzburg region.  At this point, no paragraph-break in original.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Er nennt es einen "Kulturskandal ohnegleichen", wenn das offizielle Wien mir den schuldigen Dank nicht in <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> Form von allen nur erdenklichen Auszeichnungen u. Titeln abstattet, wenn er z. B. einem Gespräch mit Sektionschef D^r.^ Pernter<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn17">  Dr. Johann Maria Valentin Pernter (1887–1951), official in the Austrian Ministry of Education from 1922, later departmental head, then Secretary of State in the Schuschnigg  government, rising to Minister of Educational Administration, survived Dachau and returned to the Ministry of Education as departmental head in 1945.  (http://members.aon.at/desbrosses/ebenhoch.htm — 3-28-2008)</tei:note> entnimmt, daß er meinen Namen gar nicht kennt, obgleich er dem Unterrichtsministerium zugeteilt ist, also, – kennen müsste!  Auf Umwegen hat mir F., auch jenen Traum aus jungen Jahren erfüllt, den ich Ihnen, hochverehrter Herr Baron, einmal vorgeträumt habe:  ich unterbreitete Ihnen damals den Vorschlag eines Rothschild-Orchesters, das ich, um  das bessere Antlitz der Meisterwerke zu zeigen, in die Welt hinausführen wollte.  Nun bereitet mir das Schicksal, die Genugtuung, mittelbar durch F. diesen Wunsch erfüllt zu sehen.</tei:p><tei:p>Wie bedauere ich, daß ich die Freude eines ähnlichen Berichtes nicht auch dem verewigten Prof. Rettich<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn18">  Prof. Rettich:  mentioned several times in Schenker's diary from 1906 on, Rettich seems to have served Alphons as a secretary or personal assistant.  </tei:note> machen kann.</tei:p><tei:p>Meinen tiefstgefühlten Dank so findlich[?] wie möglich noch einmal zum — Ausdruck bringend —</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">unfinished, unsigned</tei:hi>]</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten revised draft letter from Schenker to Alphons Rothschild, in Jeanette Schenker's hand, undated [August 3-4, 1934]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>To Baron Rothschild<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>The publication of Dr. Jonas's book, <tei:hi rend="italic">The Nature of the Musical Artwork: An Introduction to the Theory of Heinrich Schenker</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> which is on its way to you simultaneously, affords me the opportunity of thanking you after more than 30 years for a second time for the kind participation that you bestowed on my life's work at the beginning.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  Today I am now in the happy position of being able to inform you of a great artistic and moral success on the part of my assembled work—it comprises eleven large volumes along with many other works larger and smaller, among them, for example, the four-volume collected edition of the Beethoven [piano] sonatas—overall I should like to express my thanks to you not just figuratively but tangibly on behalf of the whole of musical humanity.</tei:p><tei:p>You have with your initial deed earned undying gratitude in the realm of music, for I can be absolutely certain sure of the <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> immortality of my accomplishment.  Far from wishing to boast, let me mention here just that without any effort on my part my name and work has been taken up in all encyclopedias such as Brockhaus,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> Mayer,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> Herder,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> and of course musical and literary ones, and that I have attained a worldwide reputation.  [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from p. 2v:</tei:hi>  If only mankind were self-effacing enough with regard to music not always to mistake its own petty feelings for genuine understanding, then my name would long ago have been, perhaps joyously, on everybody's lips, as for example [is] that of Einstein,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> and would have been compared with his in well-informed circles.]   Moreover, my pupils have already brought to it considerable repute, and are disseminating my theory all over Europe, American, and Japan.</tei:p><tei:p>That in Vienna, of all places, there is less activity going on around me than anywhere else in the world is due to its own local reasons:  the <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue Freie Presse</tei:hi> has in all these many, many years cited neither my name nor my work, except on one occasion when Bruno Walter,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> who was not well up on Viennese journalistic affairs, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> just happened to drop my name.  Whereas we never had dictatorship in our political life, in the small world of music criticism Dr. K.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> has all too willingly behaved like a dictator who eliminated or silenced anybody who opposed his or his son's interests.  But as you can see, his dictatorial ways have been unable to do me any harm.    He is still alive, but we ought to count him among the already departed, whereas I—thanks be to God!—am still handling the proofs of a recently completed big new volume that will appear soon.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/></tei:p><tei:p>Moreover, in Vienna, musicians, professors at the Music Academy<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> and the University, who in musical matters so merrily ply their fraudulent trade, have very wisely avoided any contact with me;  they act as if they had no idea that Schenker, who has become world famous in the meantime, lives alongside them in Vienna!  But they just could not resist <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> taking into account my increased importance by at least stealing my intellectual property, i.e. they published without crediting me, indeed they never once quoted me between quotation marks.  How often might you have taken what belonged intellectually to me to be the coinage of a critic!  All the rest of the world, by contrast, conducted itself correctly always and everywhere, and respected my property with thanks and enthusiasm.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/></tei:p><tei:p>Please do not take it amiss, highly esteemed Baron, if I take advantage of the occasion that has led me to you today to add one more thing that will surely afford you satisfaction, too.  Already at his first appearance in Vienna, i.e. fifteen years ago, Dr. Furtwängler<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> turned to me as the author of the monograph on Beethoven's Ninth Symphony,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/> and has since then allied himself with me in every respect.  In all these years he has never once neglected visiting me, spending hours in my company, and learning all kinds of things from me. <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> He calls himself a pupil of mine—which fills me with not a little pride.  I have him to thank, also, for spreading my name and work far and wide;  in so doing, he unceasingly proclaims my theory as the sole salvation for the future of music.  In a letter to a Viennese court counsellor<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn15"/> a copy of which lies before me, he goes so far as to attach greater importance for the future of music to me even than to a Richard Strauss.  What is more, as "Prussian State Counsellor" since the beginning of June this year, he visited me as he has always done, despite my having never made any secret to him of my deeply held Jewishness.  He even declared that he would visit me here in Böckstein.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn16"/></tei:p><tei:p>He calls it a "cultural scandal without comparison" when Viennese officialdom does not record the thanks it owes me in the <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> form of all conceivable manner of honors and titles, and when, for example, he gathers from a conversation with department head Dr. Pernter<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn17"/> that my name is completely unknown to the latter, even though he is assigned to the Ministry of Education and so ought to have known it!</tei:p><tei:p>By other means, Furtwängler has even fulfilled for me that dream from early days that I once expressed to you, highly esteemed Baron, as an aspiration.  I put to you then the proposal of a Rothschild Orchestra, which I wanted to present to the world so as to show the masterworks in a better light.  Now fate has given me the satisfaction of seeing this wish fulfilled directly through Furtwängler.</tei:p><tei:p>How I regret that I cannot give the late Dr. Rettich<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn18"/> the joy of a similar report also.  My most deep-felt thanks as ….[?] as possible once again to – giving expression –</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">unfinished, unsigned</tei:hi>]</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>