<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 5/34, [2], vsn 1 : 8-3-34 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  In the public domain.  
© Transcription Ian Bent, 2008.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2008.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1934-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker;  Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 08/03/1934 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Rothschild ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten draft letter from Schenker to Alphons Rothschild, undated [August 3, 1934]</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-03-28</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Schenker sends Alphons a copy of Jonas's new book, Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks, thanks him again for his past support, and surveys his total output, the repute of his name, and the dissemination of his theory. —He criticizes Vienna for ignoring him, and reports on Furtwängler's adherence to his ideas and loyalty toward him in person.   

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Rothschild, Baron Alphons Mayer von;  Jonas, Oswald;  Wesen  des musikalischen Kunstwerks;  Nature of the Musical Artwork;  Beethoven;  sonatas;  Brockhaus;  Mayer;  Herder;  Neue freie Presse;  Walter, Bruno;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Strauss, Richard;  Pernter, Johann Maria Valentin;  Unterrichtsministerium;  Ministry of Education;  Rothschild Orchester;  Rettich, Prof.</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> [Böckstein]</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten draft letter from Schenker to Alphons Rothschild, in Jeanette Schenker's hand, undated [August 3, 1934]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>An Baron Rothschild<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  The following is the sequence of relevant events, traced from Schenker's diary:  July 11, 1934: Schenker receives five copies of Jonas's book from Saturn Verlag;  August 3: dictates draft letter to Rothschild;  August 5: writes fair copy of letter;  August 6: finishes copying letter;  August 7: the book is wrapped and mailed off;  August 17: the book comes back from Rothschild without response (OJ 4/7, pp. 3924–3935).  Thus, the present version 1 of the draft was produced on August 3, 1934, and the emendations made to it either later that day or on August 4.  The finished letter is not known to survive; however, the receipt of posting survives as OJ 5/34, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Alphons paid the publication costs of the first two volumes of Schenker's <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:hi>:  <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (Stuttgart:  J. G. Cotta, 1906), <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt</tei:hi>, first half-volume (ibid, 1910).  </tei:note>, August 7.  Click on <ref cRef="rothschild_alphons">Alphons von Rothschild</ref>.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Das Erscheinen des gleichzeitig an Sie abgehenden Buches von Dr. Jonas, “Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks,”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Oswald Jonas, <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks: eine Einführung in die Lehre H Schenkers</tei:hi> (Vienna: Saturn-Verlag, 1934), which was released on July 3, 1934.  </tei:note> nehme ich zum freudigen Anlaß, Ihnen nach mehr als 30. Jahren, zum zweitenmal für Ihre gütige Teilnahme an meinem Lebenswerk zu danken.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Alphons paid the publication costs of the first two volumes of Schenker's <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:hi>:  <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (Stuttgart:  J. G. Cotta, 1906), <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt</tei:hi>, first half-volume (ibid, 1910).  </tei:note>  Heute bin ich in der glücklichen Lage einen großen künstlerischen u. moralischen Erfolg meiner gesamten Arbeit überblicken zu können, – es sind 11 große Bände nebst vielen anderen Arbeiten, wie z. B. die vierbändige Gesamtausgabe der Beethoven-Sonaten –, u. nicht nur figürlich sondern wirklich im Namen der ganzen musikalischen Menschheit für Ihre erste Tat zu danken.  Sie haben sich ein unsterbliches Verdienst erworben, denn von der Un- <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> sterblichkeit meiner Leistung darf ich überzeugt sein.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  No paragraph-break in original.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Fern von jeder Prahlerei melde ich Ihnen als einigermaßen bestätigende Tatsache, daß ich ohne jegliches Zutun meinerseits einen Weltruf erreicht habe, daß mein Name u. Werk in sämtliche Lexika wie:  Brockhaus,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Brockhaus: [identify title and first edition in which Schenker appears]</tei:note> Mayer,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Mayer: [identify title and first edition in which Schenker appears]</tei:note> Herder,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Herder: [identify title and first edition in which Schenker appears]</tei:note> versteht sich in musikalische u. literarische aufgenommen worden ist, Meine Schüler haben es zu ansehlichem Namen gebracht u. verbreiten allerorten in Europe, Amerika, Japan meine Lehre.  Daß es gerade in Wien um mich herum stiller als in der übrigen Welt ist, hat besondere lokale Gründe:  Die "N. Fr. Presse" hat in den vielen Jahren weder Namen noch Werk von mir genannt ausgenommen in einem Falle da Bruno Walter,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="walter_bruno">Bruno Walter</ref>.</tei:note> mit den Verhältnissen in Wien nicht vertraut, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> meinen Namen aussprach.  Nun, wir haben zwar keine Diktatur in unserem politischen Leben, aber in der kleinen Welt der musikalischen Kritik hat D^r.^ K.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Dr. K.:  [identify]  </tei:note> gar zu gern den Diktator gespielt.  Wie Sie sehen, hat seine Diktatur mir nichts anhaben können.  Doch lebt er zwar, aber wir dürfen ihn schon zu den Dahingegangenen zählen, während ich gerade die Korrekturen eines neuen großen Bandes leite, der bald erscheinen wird.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  i.e. <tei:hi rend="italic">Der frei Satz</tei:hi>, vol. III of <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:hi>, published posthumously (Vienna: UE, 1935).</tei:note>  Außerdem haben sich die Musiker, die Akademie u. Universität, die so vergnügt ihr Schwindelhandwerk treiben, vor jeder Verbindung mit mir gehütet, sie taten so, als wüßten sie nicht einmal, ob der inzwischen weltberühmt gewordene Schenker in Wien wohne!  Nur konnten sie sich nicht versagen, mein geistiges Eigentum zu <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> bestehlen, d. h. ohne Namensnennung, ja nicht einmal in Gänsefüßchen zu zitieren.  Wie oft mögen Sie, was geistig mir gehört hat, für die Münze eines Kritikers genommen haben!  Die übrige Welt benahm sich allezeit korrekter u. respektirte mein Eigentum.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  No paragraph-break in the original.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Nehmen Sie es nicht übel, hochverehrter Herr Baron, wenn ich den würdigen Anlaß nützend, der mich heute zu Ihnen führt, noch einiges hinzufüge, das sicherlich auch Ihnen Genugtuung bereiten wird.  Bei seinem Erscheinen in Wien, vor etwa 15 Jahren also, hat sich Dr. F.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Wilhelm Furtwängler: [create profile and link].  </tei:note> an mich, als den Verfasser der Monograpie über die IX. Sinfonie<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  Schenker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie:  Eine Darstellung des musikalischen Inhaltes unter fortlaufender Berücksichtigung auch des Vortrages und der Literatur</tei:hi> [Beethoven's Ninth Symphony:  a portrayal of its musical content, with running commentary on performance and literature as well] (Vienna: UE, 1912).  </tei:note> gewendet u. jeder Hinsicht an mich angeschlossen.  In all den Jahren hat er nie versäumt, mich zu besuchen, Stunden bei mir zuzubringen u. allerhand von mir zu lernen. <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> Er bezeichnet sich selbst als mein Schüler, was mich mit nicht wenig Stolz erfüllt.  Ihm verdanke ich auch eine Ausbreitung meines Namens u. Werkes in aller Welt, er ist rastlos darin meine Lehre als das einzige Heil für die Zukunft der Musik zu preisen.  In einem Brief, dessen Abschrift vor mir liegt, geht er so weit, mur für die Zukunft eine größere Bedeutung als Rich. Strauß zuzumessen.  Auch als "Preuss. Staatsrat," zuletzt anfangs Juni d. J., hat er mich, wie immer, besucht, trotzdem ich aus meinem tief überzeugten Judentum nie ein Hehl gemacht habe.  Sogar hat er seinen Besuch bei mir hier angekündigt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  In vsn 2, Schenker added "in Böckstein" (a health spa in the Gastein valley in the Salzburg region).  At this point, no paragraph-break in original.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Er nennt es einen "Kulturskandal ohnegleichen", wenn das offizielle Wien mir den schuldigen Dank nicht in <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> Form von allen nur erdenklichen Auszeichnungen u. Titeln abstattet, wenn er z. B. einem Gespräch mit Sektionschef D^r.^ Pernter<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15">  Dr. Johann Maria Valentin Pernter (1887–1951), official in the Austrian Ministry of Education from 1922, later departmental head, then Secretary of State in the Schuschnigg  government, rising to Minister of Educational Administration, survived Dachau and returned to the Ministry of Education as departmental head in 1945.  (http://members.aon.at/desbrosses/ebenhoch.htm — 3-28-2008)</tei:note> entnimmt, daß er meinen Namen gar nicht kennt, obgleich er dem Unterrichtsministerium zugeteilt ist.  Auf Umwegen ist also F., der mir jenen Traum aus jungen Jahren erfüllte, den ich Ihnen, hochverehrter Herr Baron, da Sie noch sehr, sehr jung waren, vorgeträumt habe:  ich unterbreitete Ihnen damals den Vorschlag eines Rothschild-Orchesters, das ich, um der Welt das bessere Antlitz de Meisterwerke zu zeigen, hinausführen wollte.  Nun bereitet mir das Schicksal, die Genugtuung, mittelbar durch F. diesen Wunsch erfüllt zu sehen.  Wie bedauere ich, daß ich die Freude eines solchen Berichtes nicht auch dem verewigten Prof. Rettich<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn16">  Prof. Rettich:  mentioned several times in Schenker's diary from 1906 on, Rettich seems to have served Alphons as a secretary or personal assistant.  </tei:note> machen kann.  Meinen tiefstgefühlten Dank so findlich wie möglich noch einmal zum — Ausdruck bringend —</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">unfinished, unsigned</tei:hi>]</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten draft letter from Schenker to Alphons Rothschild, in Jeanette Schenker's hand, undated [August 3, 1934]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>To Baron Rothschild<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>The publication of Dr. Jonas's book, <tei:hi rend="italic">The Nature of the Musical Artwork</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> which is on its way to you simultaneously, affords me the happy opportunity of thanking you after more than 30 years for a second time for your kind participation in my life's work.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  Today I am in the happy position of being able to look back over a great artistic and moral success on the part of my assembled work—it comprises eleven large volumes along with many other works, such as, for example, the four-volume collected edition of the Beethoven [piano] sonatas— and to thank you not just figuratively but tangibly on behalf of the whole of musical humanity for your first act [of generosity].  You have earned undying gratitude, for I can be certain sure of the <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> immortality of my accomplishment.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/></tei:p><tei:p>Far from wishing to boast, let me report to you as fact, providing some measure of confirmation, that I have without any effort on my part attained a worldwide reputation, that my name and work has been taken up in all encyclopedias such as Brockhaus,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> Mayer,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> Herder,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> and of course musical and literary ones.  My pupils have brought to it considerable repute, and are disseminating my theory all over Europe, America, and Japan.  That in Vienna, of all places, there is less activity going on around me than anywhere else in the world is due to special, local reasons:  the <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue Freie Presse</tei:hi> has in all these many years cited neither my name nor my work, except on one occasion when Bruno Walter,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> who was not well up on Viennese affairs, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> dropped my name.  Whereas we have no dictatorship in our political life, in the small world of music criticism Dr. K.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> has played the role of dictator all too willingly.  As you can see, his dictatorial ways have been unable to do me any harm.    True, he is still alive, but we ought to count him among the already departed, whereas I am right now handling the proofs of a big new volume that will appear soon.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/>  Moreover, musicians, the Academy, and the University, who so merrily ply their fraudulent trade, have avoided any contact with me;  they act as if they had no idea that Schenker, who has become world famous in the meantime, lives in Vienna!  The only thing they could not desist from doing is <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> stealing my intellectual property, i.e. without crediting me, indeed without even putting me in quotation marks.  How often might you have taken what belonged intellectually to me to be the coinage of a critic!  All the rest of the world always conducted itself more correctly and respected my property.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/></tei:p><tei:p>Please do not take it amiss, highly esteemed Baron, if I take advantage of the occasion that has led me to you today to add one more thing that will surely afford you satisfaction, too.  At his [first] appearance in Vienna, i.e. fifteen years ago, Dr. Furtwängler<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> turned to me as the author of the monograph on the Ninth Symphony,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> and has allied himself with me in every respect.  In all these years he has never once neglected visiting me, spending hours in my company, and learning all kinds of things from me.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> He calls himself a pupil of mine—which fills me with not a little pride.  I have him to thank, also, for spreading my name and work far and wide;  in so doing, he unceasingly extolls my theory as the sole salvation for the future of music.  In a letter a copy of which lies before me, he goes so far as to attach greater importance for the future to me than to Richard Strauss.  What is more, as "Prussian State Counsellor" since the beginning of June this year, he visited me as he has always done, despite my having never made any secret of my deeply held Jewishness.  He even declared that he would visit me here.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/></tei:p><tei:p>He calls it a "cultural scandal without comparison" when Viennese officialdom does not record the thanks it owes me in the <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> form of all conceivable manner of honors and titles, and when, for example, he gathers from a conversation with department head Dr. Pernter<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn15"/> that my name is completely unknown to the latter, even though he is assigned to the Ministry of Education.  Furtwängler has by other means fulfilled that dream from early days which, when you were very, very young, I expressed to you, highly esteemed Baron, as an aspiration.  I put to you then the proposal of a Rothschild Orchestra, which I wanted to inaugurate so as to show the world the masterworks in a better light.  Now fate has given me the satisfaction of seeing this wish fulfilled directly through Furtwängler.  How I regret that I cannot give the late Dr. Rettich<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn16"/> the joy of such a report also.  My most deep-felt thanks as ….[?] as possible once again to – giving expression –</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">unfinished, unsigned</tei:hi>]</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>