<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 5/34, [1] : Feb 1911 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  In the public domain.  
© Transcription Ian Bent, 2008.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2008.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1911-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker;  Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 02/15/1911 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Rothschild ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten draft letter from Schenker to Alphons Rothschild, dated February 1911</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-03-25</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Schenker thanks Alphons for"participating" in his "great work," citing the Harmonielehre and first half-volume of Kontrapunkt, describes his own battle against the musical establishment, and informs Alphons of his forthcoming Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Rothschild, Baron Alphons Mayer von;  Harmonielehre;  Theory of Harmony;  Kontrapunkt;  Counterpoint;  plagues;  Egypt;  Pharaoh;  Carnegie, Andrew;  renaissance;  rebirth;  Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie;  Beethoven's Ninth Symphony</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten draft letter from Schenker to Alphons Rothschild, dated "February 1911"</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in Heinrich's hand:</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">Februar</tei:hi> 1911
[<tei:hi rend="italic">in another hand:</tei:hi>]  (Rothschild)</tei:p><tei:p>Hochgeehrter Herr Baron!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  The only diary entry at this time dates from on or after March 2, 1911, and reads (OJ 1/10, p. 125):  "Letter to Baron Alphons (first enclosure)." [Brief an Baron Alphons (1. Blg.)]  Since the next entry in the diary is dated May 18, 1911, the scope for dating the letter in question is March 2 to May 17.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ein hochherziger Akt Ihrer Teilnahme an meinem großen Werke<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  The <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:hi>:  Schenker is crediting Alphons with having undertaken to pay the publication costs of the first half of the second volume of this work, <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt</tei:hi> (Stuttgart:  J. G. Cotta, 1910), and cumulatively with having paid those of the first volume, <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (1906).  However, those costs went unpaid until March 13, 1911 (OJ 9/31, [33] = CA 144), when Alphons finally, over five months late, made the necessary transfer.  The date "February 1911" (in Heinrich's hand) at the head of this draft (which has all the hallmarks of having been intended as the final copy, but the writing of which deteriorates in the final two sentences) is thus called into question.  If it is to be believed, then either the final copy of the letter was sent in February as a reminder to Alphons, or the draft was written in February but deferred until the payment was made in March.  </tei:note> gibt mir freudigsten Anlaß, Ihnen meinen herzlichtsten Dank u. tiefgefühlte Dankbarkeit  auszudrücken.</tei:p><tei:p>In einer Epoche, wie die gegenwärtige, in der die Welt von den "Plagen" des Dunkels, ^der^ Ignoranz, Charakterlosigkeit, des Betruges u. anderen ähnlich heimgesucht wird, wie einmal <tei:hi rend="italic">Aegypten</tei:hi> unter <tei:hi rend="italic">Pharao</tei:hi> von den berüchtigten "10 Plagen," ist es doppelt dankbar zu begrüßen, wenn eine starke Hand den Einen stützt u. fördert, der in die Finsterniß Licht zu bringen, das Land von den Plagen zu befreien sich entschloß.</tei:p><tei:p>Sie kennen mich, hochgeehrter Herr Baron, zur Genüge, um zu wissen, daß ich niemals so sprechen würde, wenn es nicht die Wahrheit wäre, die selbst aus mir spräche.  Scheinbar sind es ja nur zwei Bücher: eine Harmonie- u. ei- <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> ne <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkts</tei:hi>lehre, scheinbar Bücher, wie so viele andere es sind, u. dennoch wage ich es zu sagen, daß Sie mit der Förderung gerade dieser Bände der Welt ein schöneres Geschenk gemacht haben, als ein <tei:hi rend="italic">Carnegie</tei:hi> mit seinen Millionen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Andrew Carnegie (1835–1919), Scottish-born iron and steel magnate in the United States, philanthropist on a huge scale, founding libraries, donating to schools and universities, supporting the arts;  also owner of the Carnegie Hall in New York City.  He is said to have given away over $300M in his lifetime.  </tei:note>  Es wird u. muß mir gelingen, eine <tei:hi rend="italic">Renaissance</tei:hi> der Tonkunst herbeizuführen, u. wenn in absehbarer Zeit der Boden der Tonkunst, der inzwischen brach lag, neuerdings urbarer geworden, bessere u. schönere Kompositionen an's Licht getreten sein, u. damit auch der wirtschaftliche Aufschwung der Interessenten, ^wie^ die Freude bei den Zuhörern eine edlere Grundlage gewonnen haben werden, dann werden Sie die Genugtuung Ihres Werkes der Teilnahme ernten!</tei:p><tei:p>Noch kämpfe ich allein gegen die Akademieen, Professoren, Virtuosen, gegen jeglichen Betrug, der wissentlich oder unwissentlich geübt wird, u. es versteht sich, daß die Musikanten – ein unwissendes Publikum (das das Tonstück sozusagen absitzt, statt es zu hören) u. eine noch unwissendere Presse, (die die Musik misbraucht, um einen <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Tour-jargon</tei:hi> in die Welt zu setzen) nennen sie zu emphatisch "Künstler" – sich gegen ihre Entlarvung wahren.  Es ist so angenehm, Künstler zu heißen, ohne es zu sein, um so angenehmer, als das Publikum u. die Salons hätscheln u. zahlen!  Und dennoch wird es bald klarer sein, daß alles Musikantreiben heute zu einer  – Amusement degradiert wurde.  Man behauptet, daß Schildkröten ein älteres Geschlecht auf Erden seien, als die Menschen:  sieht man ^aber^ des letzteren Geistestempo an, so neigt man eher zur entgegengesetzten Anschauung.  Seit urewigen Zeiten erliegen die Menschen dem Scham, dem Irrtum, u. heute ist es noch so, wie vor Jahrmillionen, noch bevor – die Schildkröten in der Welt waren!</tei:p><tei:p>Erwarten Sie also, hochgeehrter Herr Baron, nicht gerade schon morgen, übermorgen jene Wiedergeburt, von der ich sprach, – solches Wunder gelänge keinem Helden –, wohl aber wird sie eines Tages da sein, u. die Menschen beglücken, soweit diese in Kunstdingen eines Glücks überhaupt nur fähig sind.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Schon in nächster Zeit erscheint von mir eine <tei:hi rend="italic">Monographie</tei:hi> über die <tei:hi rend="italic">IX. Symph</tei:hi>. von <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven</tei:hi>, die aufdecken wird, daß die Begeisterung für dieses Werk mehr Mode war, als auf Verständnis beruhte, die entlarvten Dirigenten werden zu Hause sich schämen, vor der Welt alles &lt;strike&gt;werstexxx.&lt;/strike&gt; wütend tun, das beleidigte Publikum u. die beleidigten Presse werden sich in das Schlupfwinkel der Schweigens zurückziehen, – aber man wird das Werk endlich zum 1. Mal verstehen lernen.   Bis es fertig gedruckt, werde ich nur[?] einladen,[?] Ihre [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">unfinished, unsigned</tei:hi>]</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten draft letter from Schenker to Alphons Rothschild, dated "February 1911"</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in Heinrich's hand:</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">February</tei:hi> 1911
[<tei:hi rend="italic">in another hand:</tei:hi>]  (Rothschild)</tei:p><tei:p>Highly esteemed Baron,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>A high-minded stage of your participation in my great work<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> affords me a most happy occasion to express to you my most hearty thanks and deep-felt gratitude.</tei:p><tei:p>In an age such as the present one, in which the world is visited by the “plagues” of darkness, ignorance, characterlessness, betrayal, and other similar [pestilences], as Egypt once was under Pharaoh by the infamous “ten plagues,” it is doubly thankfully to be welcomed when a strong hand supports and promotes the one person who has decided to bring light to the darkness and to free the land from the plagues.</tei:p><tei:p>You know me sufficiently well, highly esteemed Baron, to know that I would never speak so if it were not the truth that speaks from out of me.  Ostensibly it is really only two books: a harmony treatise and a <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> counterpoint treatise;  ostensibly books just like so many other books, and nevertheless I venture to say that you have bequeathed the world a finer gift with your support of these books than did a Carnegie with his millions.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  I will, I must succeed in bringing about a renaissance in composition, and if in the foreseeable future the soil in which composition grows, which has meanwhile lain fallow, becomes cultivable anew, and better and more beautiful compositions begin to sprout, and with them the economic prospects of the interested parties, ^as also^ the joy of the listeners, take root more nobly, then you will reap the harvest of satisfaction from your work of participation.</tei:p><tei:p>I am still battling alone against the academies, professors, virtuoso performers, against every fraud that is committed, knowingly or unknowingly, and it goes without saying that musicians—whom an ignorant public (which sits out the piece, so to speak, without hearing it) and an even more ignorant press (which abuses music in order <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> to introduce the jargon of the travel-guide) too emphatically label "artists"—protect themselves from being unmasked.  It is so agreeable to be called an artist without being one, and all the more agreeable when the public and the salons adulate [them] and pay money!  Moreover, it will soon become even clearer that the whole music enterprise of today has been reduced to a – form of amusement.  It is claimed that tortoises are a more ancient species on earth than man:  ^but^ when one takes into account the speed of the latter's mental processes, one is actually inclined to the opposite view.  Since time immemorial, men succumb to shame, to error, and it is just the same today as it was millions of years ago, long before tortoises came into existence.</tei:p><tei:p>So, highly esteemed Baron, don't expect to see that rebirth of which I spoke right away tomorrow, or the day after tomorrow—no hero could achieve such a miracle;  but one day, for sure, it will be there, and will bestow fortune upon mankind, insofar as the latter is capable of having fortune in artistic matters at all.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> In the very near future a monograph by me on the Ninth Symphony of Beethoven will be published,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> and this will reveal that the enthusiasm for this work has been a product more of fashion than understanding.  The conductors that it unmasks will skulk at home in disgrace, all the world will be enfuriated, the shamefaced public and shamefaced press will hide themselves away in silence—but people will at long last come to know the work for the first time.  When it is published, I will invite [<tei:hi rend="italic">remainder illeg</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">unfinished, unsigned</tei:hi>]</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>