<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 10/13, [3] : 6-27-26 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  Deemed to be in the public domain.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2007.
© Translation William Drabkin, 2007
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1926-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Deemed to be in the public domain; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 06/27/1926 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Dunn ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten lettercard from Dunn to Schenker, dated June 27, 1926</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-04-30</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Thanks S for copy of Meisterwerk 2, reports that an adaptation of the first volume of S’s Kontrapunkt is complete, and explains how it will be made available in multiple copies. 

</dc:description><dc:subject>Dunn, John Petrie; Schenker, Heinrich;  Jahrbuch;  Yearbook;  Das Meisterwerk in der Musik;  The Masterwork in Music;  Kontrapunkt;  Counterpoint;  adaptation;  translation;  music examples;  typewriter;  Der freie Satz;  Free Composition</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> 42 Murrayfield Avenue, Edinburgh</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Galtür, im Paznauntal, Tyrol</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten lettercard from Dunn to Schenker, dated June 27, 1926</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
LETTER CA[RD]</tei:p><tei:p>Herrn Heinrich Schenker,
Musikschriftsteller,
-Galltür-, +Galtür+,
im Paznauntal
+Tirol+</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>] ||C – AM | 28 JUN [26] ||</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
42, Murrayfield Avenue,
Edinburgh, den 27. Juni, ‘26.</tei:p><tei:p>Hochverehrter Herr Schenker!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Receipt of this letter is recorded in S’s diary, OJ 3/8, p. 2953.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Vor allem spreche ich Ihnen für die Freude und die Ehre, die Sie mir mit der Uebersendung des “Jahrbuches”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, vol. I (Munich: Drei Masken Verlag, 1925), released c. June 15, 1926.  In OC 54/84, June 16, 1926, the publisher acknowledges S’s list of names and addresses for recipients of review copies;  Dunn’s name may have been on that list.</tei:note> erwiesen haben, meinen herzlichsten Dank aus.  Sie haben eine Arbeit unternommen, wie sie mit ähnlicher Gründlichkeit überhaupt noch nie versucht worden ist und somit wünsche ich Ihnen zur Vollendug des letzten Bandes<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi>, the last volume of the <tei:hi rend="italic">New Musical Theories and Fantasies</tei:hi>.</tei:note> den allerbesten Erfolg.  Der Schleier hat sich wahrhaftig gelüftet!</tei:p><tei:p>Was die Bearbeitung des “Kp” anbelangt, habe ich gegen einen schlimmen Feind – den +chronischen+ +Zeitmangel+ – anzukämpfen.  Ausserdem werden Sie wohl begreifen, dass die rein mechanischen Schwiereigkeiten der Vervielfältigung die Ausmasse des Werks stark einschränken.  Wenn ich Ihnen bei Gelgenheit ein Exemplar vorlege, werden Sie es wahrscheinlich für einen recht dünnen Absud des so reichhaltigen Originals erklären! Nun, dass lässt sich eben nicht ändern.  Die Bearbeitung des zweistimmigen Kp. ist jetzt fertig und wird mit der Schreibmaschine vervielfältigt.  Dann müssen die Notenbeispiele handschriftlich eingetragen werden.  Da aber die Rückseite jedes Blattes leer ist, so werde ich von Zeit zu Zeit Bemerkungen[,] Zusätze, und Erklärungen einfügen. Augenblicklich ist es mir aus Gründen, die ich Ihnen später auseinandersetzen werde, hauptsächlich darum zu tun, unser Kontrapunktstudium auf eine feste Grundlage zu stellen. Hiervon später mehr. Mit herzlichsten Dank</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr Ergebenster 
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] J. P. Dunn</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten lettercard from Dunn to Schenker, dated June 27, 1926</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
LETTER CA[RD]</tei:p><tei:p>Mr. Heinrich Schenker,
Writer on music,
-Galltür-, +Galtür+,
in the Paznauntal
+Tirol+</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>] ||C – AM | 28 JUN [26] ||</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
42, Murrayfield Avenue,
Edinburgh, June 27, 1926.</tei:p><tei:p>Most esteemed Mr. Schenker,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Above all, I express my most heartfelt thanks for the joy, and the honor, you have conferred upon me in sending of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Yearbook</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  You have undertaken a work which has never before been attempted with such thoroughness, and for this reason I wish you the very best success in completing the last volume.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  The veil [that has covered music] has indeed been lifted!</tei:p><tei:p>As concerns the adaptation of <tei:hi rend="italic">Counterpoint</tei:hi>, I have to battle against an evil enemy: +chronic lack of time+.  Moreover, you will readily understand that the purely mechanical difficulties of making multiple copies led to a stark curtailment of the scope of the work.  If I take the opportunity of presenting you with a copy, you will take it for a very thin potion compared with the original!  I regret that it could not be done any other way.  The adaptation of two-part counterpoint is now complete, and will be copied with the typewriter.  Then the music examples will have to be entered by hand.  But since the verso of every leaf is empty, I shall add remarks, amendments and clarifications from time to time.  For the moment, what is of principal importance, for reasons which I shall explain to you later, that we provide a solid foundation for the study of counterpoint. More about this later.  With cordial thanks,</tei:p><tei:p>Your most devoted, 
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] J. P. Dunn</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>