<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 10/13, [4] : 2-1-27 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  Deemed to be in the public domain.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2007.
© Translation William Drabkin, 2007
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1927-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Deemed to be in the public domain; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 02/01/1927 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Dunn ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Dunn to Schenker, dated February 1, 1927</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-04-30</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>After long silence, sends S his abbreviated translation of Kontrapunkt, vol. 2, Parts III–IV, expresses regret that Hoboken’s illness prevented him from visiting, hopes that they might meet up in London in June. 

</dc:description><dc:subject>Dunn, John Petrie; Schenker, Heinrich;  Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien;  New Musical Theories and Fantasies;  Kontrapunkt 2;  Counterpoint 2;  adaptation;  translation;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  London;  Beethoven</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> 42 Murrayfield Avenue, Edinburgh</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Dunn to Schenker, dated February 1, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed address (on each recto):</tei:hi>]
42, Murrayfield Avenue,
Edinburgh.
den 1. Februar, 1927.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Schenker!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Receipt of this letter is recorded in S’s diary, OJ 3/9, p. 3032, and the book itself p. 3031.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ueber mein langes Schweigen werden Sie sich wohl einigermassen gewundert haben.  Die Arbeit aber, die ich mir vorgenommen hatte, war viel mühsamer als ich erwartet hatte.  Sie ist aber endlich vollbracht–, und deren Früchte habe ich Ihnen heute zugehen lassen, und zwar im Gestalt von einer kurzgefassten Bearbeitung und Uebersetzung des III.–IV.  Abschnittes des Bandes II^2^ Ihrer “Th. u. Ph.”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  i.e. <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt II</tei:hi>.</tei:note>  Hoffentlich gefällt Ihnen <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> mein Werkchen, auf dessen Vervielfältigung ich sowie meine Frau viel Zeit und Mühe verwendeten.  Das Uebersetzen Ihres Buches war überaus schwierig, denn sein gedanklicher Inhalt ist grössenteils neu ^und tief^ und stellt an den musikalischen Instinkt und die Einbildungskraft des Lesers keine geringen Anförderungen. Sprachlich war es ausserdem riesig schwer –</tei:p><tei:p>Das Allerschwierigste, – so zum Beispiel die Begründung der Abwärtsauflösung des Vorhalts – musste ich notgedrungen weglassen. Ausserdem habe ich mir erlaubt, um es dem Verständnis des jungen Studenten leichter zu machen, einige elementare Erläuterungen mit einzuflechten und ich hoffe, dass das in Ihrem Sinne geschehen ist –</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Es tat uns ausserordentlich leid, dass wir Herrn van Hoboken<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> infolge seiner Krankheit nicht in unserem Hause sehen konnten. Wir hoffen aber, dass wir dieser Vergnügung später haben werden –</tei:p><tei:p>Es würde mir sehr lieb sein, wenn mich Herr van Hoboken zur rechten Zeit von seinem Besuche benachrichtigen könnte, denn möglicherweise könnte ich ihn in London sprechen, da ich ^mich^ im Juni anlässlich eines Radio-Beethovenvortrags eine Woche <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> lang in London aufhalten muss –<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Hoboken visited the Dunns in Edinburgh in September 1927, and reported John Petrie Dunn’s extensive knowledge of Schenker’s writings, and his enthusiasm for his theories, in a letter to Schenker dated September 18, 1927. See Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Nach Tagebüchern</tei:hi> (1985), p. 103. </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>In der Hoffnung, bald wieder von Ihnen zu hören, begrüsse ich Sie mit vorzüglicher Hochachtung.</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr ganz ergebener,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] John Petrie Dunn.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Dunn to Schenker, dated February 1, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed address (on each recto):</tei:hi>]
42, Murrayfield Avenue,
Edinburgh
February 1, 1927</tei:p><tei:p>Most honored Mr. Schenker,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>You will probably have wondered why I have been silent for such a long time;  but the work that I undertook was much more strenuous than I had expected.  It is, however, finally completed, and I have sent the fruits of my labours to you today, specifically in the form of an abbreviated adaptation and translation of Parts III and IV of volume II/2 of your <tei:hi rend="italic">New Musical Theories and Fantasies</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  I hope that you will be pleased <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> by my modest achievement, the preparation of multiple copies of which cost me and also my wife a great deal of time and effort.  Translating your book was especially difficult, for its conceptual content is, for the most part, new ^and profound^ and makes no small demands on the reader’s musical instinct and powers of imagination.  From a linguistic point of view as well, it was enormously difficult.</tei:p><tei:p>The most difficult of all—for example, the justification for the downward resolution of the suspension—I was forced to omit.  In addition, I took the liberty of weaving in a few elementary elucidations, to make it easier for our young students to understand;  and I hope that I have done this in a manner that is compatible with your ideas.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> We were extremely sorry not to be able to see Mr. van Hoboken<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> at our house, on account of his illness.  But we hope that we will have this pleasure at a later time.</tei:p><tei:p>I would be most grateful if Mr. van Hoboken could inform us in good time of his [next] visit, since it might be possible for me to speak with him in London, as I shall have to spend a week in London on account of a radio lecture on Beethoven.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> In the hope that I shall hear from you again soon, I send you my most respectful greetings.</tei:p><tei:p>Your ever devoted
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] John Petrie Dunn.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>