<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 10/13, [6] : 11-14-27 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  Deemed to be in the public domain.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2007.
© Translation William Drabkin, 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2007
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1927-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Deemed to be in the public domain; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 11/14/1927 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Dunn ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Dunn to Schenker, dated November 14, 1927</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-05-02</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Thanks S for copy of Meisterwerk 2 and comments on the clarity with which Bach’s C minor Fugue (WTC I) is revealed;  his musical instincts found confirmation in S’s theories, and after the war he obtained all of S's books;  proposes that they meet some time, perhaps by making a side-trip from to Austria from Leipzig, where his wife grew up.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Dunn, John Petrie; Schenker, Heinrich;  Jahrbuch II;  Yearbook II;  Das Meisterwerk in der Musik II;  The Masterwork in Music II;  Das Organische der Fuge;  The Organic Nature of Fugue;  Bach, J. S.;  C-minor Fugue;  WTC I;  Goethe;  Urlinie;  tonicalization;  Clementi;  Riemann, Hugo;  Debussy;  Ravel;  Reger;  Austria;  Leipzig</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> 42 Murrayfield Avenue, Edinburgh</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Dunn to Schenker, dated November 14, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[University of Edinburgh crest on each <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>]
42, Murrayfield Avenue,
Edinburgh, den 14. November, [/] 1927</tei:p><tei:p>Hochverehrter Herr Schenker!</tei:p><tei:p>Für die Zusendung des zweiten Jahrbuches<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Receipt of this letter is recorded in S’s diary, OJ 4/1, p. 3136; <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, vol. II (Munich: Drei Masken, Verlag, 1926), released in August/September 1927 (OC 54/184, August 17, 1927; OC 54/185, September 27, 1927).  Dunn is not on the list of review copies to be sent (OC 54/193, undated), and it is evident that S sent out the volume personally by registered mail to Dunn and Baumgarten.  </tei:note> kann ich Ihnen nicht genug danken;  Sie haben mir damit eine grosse Ehre erwiesen.  Erst heute komme ich dazu, Ihnen darüber zu schreiben, denn ich hatte mir vorgenommen, mich nicht eher für Ihr unschätzbares Geschenk zu bedanken, als bis ich wenigstens +ein+ abgeschlossenes Kapitel des Jahrbuches sorgfältig durchgearbeitet hätte.  Das ist denn auch heute (Sonntag) Vormittag geschehen;  ich habe Ihre Analyse der C-moll Fuge von Bach Wort für Wort, Zeile für Zeile durchgelesen.</tei:p><tei:p>Der Eindruck, den ich dabei empfangen habe, war eben der, dass -ich- mir das “Organische” an einer <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Bach’schen Fuge noch nie so überzeugend, so einleuchtend klar vor die Augen trat.  Nicht minder wertvoll war die Erkenntnis, dass eine jede Fuge von Bach ihre eigenen Gesetze [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] hat, denen der Komponist – im Sinne Ihres Goethe’schen Zitats<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Dunn is referring to the distinction Goethe makes, in an aphorism in <tei:hi rend="italic">Über Kunst und Altertum</tei:hi>, between treating the specific case on the one hand merely as an instance of a general principle and, on the other, seeking to understand the general principle by “vividly grasp[ing] the specific,” which he takes to be the essence of poetry.  Schenker quotes this towards end of the his essay, where he ponders the question of whether Bach himself was aware of the things that Schenker has been discussion (<tei:hi rend="italic">Meisterwerk</tei:hi> 2, p. 92; Eng. trans., p. 52).</tei:note> – zu gehorchen hat, ungeachtet dessen, was er in einer anderen Fuge und bei anderer Gestaltung der Urlinie, der Stufen, u.s.w. zu tun sich veranlasst sehen mag.</tei:p><tei:p>Meine Schreibfaulheit mögen Sie mir aus besonderen Gründen zugute halten.  Ich habe hier in meiner Heimatstadt eine ganz enorme Praxis, denn alle möglichen Menschen aus Nah und Fern’, die mit verkrüppelten Fingern oder sonstigen körperlichen oder geistigen Fehlern behaftet sind, betrachten mich gewissermassen als ihren Hart.  So kommt es denn, dass ich heute das “Jahrbuch” lese, morgen über “Tonicalization” (das +ganz+ +neue+ englische Wort) rede und übermorgen eine Clementi-Sonatine einpauke!  Meine Frau klagt fortwährend darüber, dass ich so unaufhörlich unterrichten muss und meinen eigenen Studien <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> so wenig Zeit widmen kann, allein es liegt nun einmal in den schwierigen heutigen Verhältnissen begründet, dass man das Eisen schmieden muss, dieweil es warm ist.  Nun, wir hoffen alle beide auf bessere Zeiten;  ausserdem gelingt es mir ja, in grossen ganzen auf den Laufenden zu bleiben.</tei:p><tei:p>Was mir an Ihren Schriften ^persönlich^ so ausserordentlich wohltuend berührt, ist dass -ich- sie mit meinem instinktiven Gefühl so vollständig übereinstimmen. Ich hatte ja immer gefühlt:  Riemann ist nicht überzeugend, Debussy und Ravel sind Geklimper, Reger ist teils gut, teils schlecht, u.s.w. u.s.w. Nun kommen +Sie+ und +beweisen+ das alles.  Aus diesen Gefühl heraus liess ich mir gleich nach Kriegsschluss Ihre Bücher kommen.  Da fand ich gerade das, was ich erwartet hatte und ich bin auf meine <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> gute Witterung nicht wenig stolz.</tei:p><tei:p>Nun aber Schluss.  Mir steht morgen ein sehr anstrengender Tag bevor.  Ich möchte nur noch sagen, dass ich und meine Frau so nach und nach auf dem Standpunkt angelangt sind, dass das viele Geschreibe nichts nützt und man sich persönlich kennen lernen muss.  Da meine Frau in Leipzig zu Hause ist, so würde ein noch viel geringerer Anlass ausreichen, um sie (und mich) zu einem kleinen Abstecher nach Oesterreich zu bewegen!  (Im Spätsommer natürlich.)</tei:p><tei:p>Mit herzlichsten Grüssen, auch an Ihre Frau Gemahlin, und mit innigsten Dank,</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr ganz ergebener
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] John Petrie Dunn.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Dunn to Schenker, dated November 14, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[University of Edinburgh crest on each <tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>]
42, Murrayfield Avenue,
Edinburgh November 14, 1927</tei:p><tei:p>Most honored Mr. Schenker,</tei:p><tei:p>I cannot thank you enough for sending me the second <tei:hi rend="italic">Yearbook</tei:hi>;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  you have thereby conferred a great honor upon me.  I have only just got round to writing to you today, as I had not wanted to thank you for your priceless gift until I had carefully gone through at least +one+ complete chapter of the yearbook.  This I have done this morning (Sunday);  I have read through, word for word, line for line, your analysis of the C minor fugue by Bach.</tei:p><tei:p>The impression that I gathered from it was precisely this:  that never has the “organic” quality of a <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Bach fugue appeared before my eyes so convincingly, and with such clarity.  No less valuable was the recognition that each fugue by Bach has its own laws which the composer must obey—along the lines of the Goethe quotation<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>—not withstanding that which he is required to do in another fugue and in a different construction of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Urlinie</tei:hi>, the harmonic degrees, etc.</tei:p><tei:p>I hope you will make allowances for my laziness as a correspondent on particular grounds:  here in my home town I have an enormous practice, for all sorts of people, from near and far, who are afflicted with crippled fingers or some other bodily or intellectual shortcomings, regard me to a certain extent as their rock.  As things turn out, I am reading the <tei:hi rend="italic">Yearbook</tei:hi> today, tomorrow I shall speak about “tonicalization” (an +entirely new+ English word), and the day after tomorrow I shall be drumming a Clementi sonatina [into someone’s head]!  My wife constantly complains that I must teach unceasingly and can devote so little time to my own studies <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> but this can be attributed simply to the difficult circumstances of today: one must forge the iron while it is hot.  Well, the two of us are hoping for better times;  moreover, I do actually succeed, by and large, in making ends meet.</tei:p><tei:p>What it is about your writings that touches me ^personally^, to such beneficial effect, is that they agree so completely with my instinctive feeling.  I had always felt that Riemann was not convincing, that Debussy and Ravel are shallow, that Reger is partly good, partly bad, etc. etc.  Now +you+ come along and +prove+ all this.  Having received this impression, I got hold of your books as soon as the war ended.  There I found precisely that which I had expected, and I am not a little proud of my <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> good instinct.</tei:p><tei:p>It is time to close.  I have a very strenuous day ahead of me tomorrow.  I would only like to say further that my wife and I have gradually arrived at the point at which we believe that all this writing is of no use, and that one should get to know each other personally.  As my wife comes from Leipzig, then a much less significant occasion would suffice for her (and me) to make a slight detour to Austria! (In the late summer, of course.)</tei:p><tei:p>With most cordial greetings, also to your wife, and with my deepest thanks,</tei:p><tei:p>Your entirely devoted
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] John Petrie Dunn</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>