<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OC A/289 : 12-16-34 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  Heirs of Frieda Guttmann, permission being sought
©  Transcription Ian Bent, 2008
©  Translation Ian Bent, 2008
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2008.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Heirs of Frieda [Guttmann], permission being sought.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1934-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-1938) - -Oster, Ernst (1938-c.1939)—New York Public Library (c.1939-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Frieda Guttmann; Image: New York Public Library, New York; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 12/15/1934 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "GuttmannF ~ H+JSchenker","GuttmannF ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Frieda [née Guttmann] to Schenker, dated December 16, 1934</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-07-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Frieda [formerly Guttmann] acknowledges Schenker's birthday wishes with thanks;  she had hoped to visit Jeanette and him for Christmas, but the exchange rate is prohibitive;  her father's eyesight is now bad;  she reports on her children, her husband(?), and refers to her brothers Hans and Julian;  she inquires after Jeanette.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Guttmann, Frieda; Schenker, Heinrich;  Schenker, Jeanette;  Guttmann, Sophie;  Guttmann, Salo;  Guttmann, Hans;  Guttmann, Julian;  Hilde;  Edith;  Guttmann, Edith</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Cernauli</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Frieda [<tei:hi rend="italic">née</tei:hi> Guttmann] to Schenker, dated December 16, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Cernauti<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> Click on <ref cRef="czernowitz_cernauti">Czernowitz (Cernauti)</ref>.     </tei:note> 16/XII. 1934</tei:p><tei:p>Lieber Onkel Heinrich!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  For the author, click on <ref cRef="guttmann_frieda_daug">Frieda Guttmann</ref>.  Her married last name is not known.  Receipt of this letter is not recorded in Schenker's diary.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Für die lieben Wünsche zu meinem Geburtstage<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Recorded on OJ 4/8, p. 3960, November 19, 1934:  "An Frieda (Br.): Gratulation. –" </tei:note> innigsten Dank.  Ich kann es gar nicht in Worten ausdrücken, wie sehr es mich freut, daß der liebe Onkel an uns denkt.  Mama<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="guttmann_sophie_nee">Sophie Guttmann</ref>.  </tei:note> war auch sehr froh, denn Mama war besorgt, da längere Zeit keine Nachricht kam.  Ich wünschte mir so sehr zu Weihnachten nach Wien fahren zu können, um unseren guten, lieben Onkel Heinrich u. die liebe Tante Lilly<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> Tante Lilly: i.e. Lie-Liechen = <ref cRef="schenker_jeanette">Jeanette Schenker</ref>.  </tei:note> nach so vielen Jahren wieder zu sehen – leider geht es nicht.  Mit unserer Valuta ist es direkt unmöglich hinauszufahren.  Wir müßten <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> für 1 Schilling 30 Lei<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Lei: Rumanian coin.  </tei:note> bezahlen.  Nun heißt es im Lande bleiben.  Mama u. Papa<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="guttmann_salo_dr_hus">Salo Guttmann</ref>.  </tei:note> werden vielleicht für Weihnachten zu uns kommen.  Gerne möchte sich Mama für etwas längere Zeit hier behalten, Papa kann aber unmöglich allein sein.  Papa sieht leider nicht gut, und kann schwer lesen etc. Natürlich leidet er auch seelisch darunter u. wir fühlen mit ihm mit.  Bei diesem Augenleiden ist es so, man muß sich nur [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] wünschen, daß es nicht ärger wird.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  No paragraph-break in the original at this point.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Mama u. Papa haben viel Freude an den Kindern.  Hilde<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Hilde: presumably Frieda's elder daughter.  </tei:note> besucht schon den <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Kindergarten u. lernt Rumänisch.  Auch Edith<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Edith: presumably Frieda's younger daughter.  </tei:note> plappert alles nach.  Sie ist ein heiteres gutmütiges Kind, das jeder gleich liebgewinnt.  Oskar<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Oskar: presumably Frieda's husband.  His brother is unknown.  </tei:note> ist nicht in Bukarest, sein Bruder hat ihn dort vertreten.  Hans<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Click on <ref cRef="guttmann_hans">Hans Guttmann</ref> (Frieda's elder brother).  </tei:note> ist ein Vater, der gar nicht genug von seinem Kinde schwärmen kann.  Auch Julko<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13"> Julko: click on <ref cRef="guttmann_julian_julk">Julian Guttmann</ref> (Frieda's younger brother).  </tei:note> bestätigt es, daß die Kleine ein reizendes, gutes Kind ist.  Ich bin froh, daß Hans glücklich ist.  Materielle Sorgen, daß er die nicht überwinden kann, ist bei der Lebensweise begreiflich.  Hans ist nicht berechnet u. Edith<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  Edith:  presumably Hans Guttmann's wife.  </tei:note> wahrscheinlich auch nicht. –<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15">  No paragraph-break in original at this point.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Wie geht es dem <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> lieben Onkel u. der lieben Tante?  Hat Tante Lilly ein gutes Mädchen, das sie bei der Wirtschaft entlastet?  Wenn man selbst so tüchtig ist, findet man schwer ein Mädchen, das einen zufrieden stellt.  Ich weiß, daß Tante Lilly sich nicht auf das Mädchen verläßt u. selbst alles so fein herrichtet.  Papa konnte nicht genug erzählen[,] wie fein das Eßen bei der Tante Lilly war.  Wie fühlt sich der liebe Onkel?  Gibt es noch immer so viel Arbeit?</tei:p><tei:p>Mehrmals vielen, vielen Dank und  herzliche Grüße u. Küße
von
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Friedl</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Frieda [<tei:hi rend="italic">née</tei:hi> Guttmann] to Schenker, dated December 16, 1934</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Cernauti<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> December 16, 1934</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Uncle Heinrich!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/></tei:p><tei:p>My most heartfelt thanks for your good wishes on my birthday.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  I cannot express in words how delighted I am that my dear uncle thinks of us.   Mama<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> was also delighted, for Mama was concerned since there had been no news from you for so long.  I really wanted so much to be able to travel to Vienna for Christmas, in order to see our dear uncle Heinrich and dear Auntie Lilly<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> after so many years—alas it is not to be.  With the exchange rate,  it is simply impossible for us to leave the country.  We would have had to pay 30 Lei<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> for one Schilling.  For the present, we just have to stay in the country.  Mama and Papa<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> will perhaps come to us for Christmas.  Mama would dearly love to stay here a bit longer, but Papa cannot possibly be on his own.  Papa's eyesight is sadly not good, and he can read only with difficulty, etc.  Naturally, he suffers in spirit as a result, and we feel for him.  With this eye sickness, one just has to wish that it does not get any worse.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/></tei:p><tei:p>Mama and Papa enjoy the children very much.  Hilde<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> is already going to <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> kindergarten, and is learning Rumanian.  Even Edith<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> repeats everything [that she hears].  She is a cheerful, good-natured child, of whom everyone is very fond.  Oskar<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> is not in Bucharest;  his brother has been representing[?] him there.  Hans<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> is a father, and he just can't stop raving about his child.  Also, Julko<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> confirms that the little one is a charming, good child.  I am delighted that Hans is so happy.  It is obvious from his mode of life that he cannot overcome his financial worries.  Hans is not good with money,[?] and neither apparently is Edith<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/>. –<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn15"/></tei:p><tei:p>How is my <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> dear uncle, and my dear Aunt?  Does Auntie Lilly have a good maid who can take the housekeeping off her hands?   When someone is as skilled as she is, it is hard to find a maid who is satisfactory.  I know that Auntie Lilly does not depend on the maid, and arranges everything so splendidly herself.  Papa could not stop telling us how splendid the food was that Auntie Lilly prepared.  How is my dear uncle feeling?</tei:p><tei:p>A thousand thanks, and heartfelt greetings and kisses,
from
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Friedl</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>