<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 5/15, [4] : Sept/Dec 1908 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain. 
© Transcription Ian Bent and Lee Rothfarb 2006.
© Translation Lee Rothfarb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Lee Rothfarb, 2007.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1908-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 10/01/1908 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Grunsky ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Incomplete handwritten letter draft from Schenker to Grunsky, undated, probably between September 23 and December 31, 1908</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-03-23</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Reports progress on his Kontrapunkt. — The main problem in music is "how length can be produced." — Recollects his love for the pious Bruckner, and his admiration for the latter's music, but speaks of its "defects," comparing the music favorably with that of Tchaikovsky. Bruckner's stumbling block was form. [letter incomplete]

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Grunsky, Karl;  Kontrapunkt;  Counterpoint;  Cotta, J. G.;  Reger;  Streicher;  Klose;  Bruckner; Vienna Conservatory;  Wiener Konservatorium;  piety;  faith;  Haydn;  Mozart;  Beethoven;  Brahms;  Tchaikovsky;  Symphonie Pathetique;  Marx, Adolf Bernhard;  Riemann, Hugo;  form</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Incomplete handwritten letter draft from Schenker to Grunsky, undated, probably between September 23 and December 31, 1908</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">top margin, in Schenker’s hand:</tei:hi>] 08  an D^r^ Grunsky<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  S’s diary has a pencil insert dating between September 28 and November 15, reading “? Brief an Dr Grunsky (über <tei:hi rend="italic">Bruckner</tei:hi>)” (OJ 1/7, p. 92), which may refer to this letter.  This letter is incomplete, therefore presumably either an aborted letter or a draft later completed, copied, and sent.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Mein <tei:hi rend="italic">Contrapunkt Man.</tei:hi> ist zu 3/4 Theilen bereits bei <tei:hi rend="italic">Cotta</tei:hi>;<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  S’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt</tei:hi> was still at this stage conceived as a single volume.  Eventually, the first half-volume was published in 1910.  This first sentence is indicative for the dating of the letter: S had still not sent any of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt</tei:hi> manuscript on September 13, 1908 (CA 80;  OJ 12/27, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Friedrich Klose (1862–1942), German-Swiss composer of symphonic poems, choral works, Lieder, and one opera.  He studied with, among others, Bruckner 1886–89, and, as Thuille’s successor, taught at the Munich Academy of Music 1907–1919.</tei:note>), and informs Cotta on September 23 that he has “just sent off the manuscript” (CA 82; OJ 12/27, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Perhaps S means G’s article “Musik und Musikgeschichte,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Schwäbische Kronik</tei:hi>, December 18, 1907, a review of S’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi>, of which S received prior notice from Cotta on December 13, 1907 (OJ 1/6, p. 53), a copy of which he received on January 6, 1908 (OJ 1/7, p.58), commenting “[I] have worked up a justifiable vexation against this man,” and which he clipped and placed in his scrapbook (OC 2/p. 20).</tei:note>); then on October 8, 1908, he states that he has not been able yet to send “the remainder of the book” (CA 85), and at this point proposes that the book be split into two half-volumes.  However, Cotta recommends against the proposal (OJ 12/27, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  S took Bruckner’s course in harmony at the Vienna Conservatory in 1887/88 and counterpoint in 1888/89.  </tei:note>, October 9, 1908), and S acquiesces, continuing to work on the remainder, called “Section 3.”  Then proofs start arriving by October 31 (WSLB 24).  Not until May 26, 1909 does S again raise his two-half-volume solution (CA 96–98), and Cotta agrees to this on June 1 (OJ 9/31, [23]).  Taking these statements together with S’s own (probably later) dating of the letter to 1908 results in a time-frame of September 23 to December 31, 1908.</tei:note>  meine Schüler u. Schülerinnen (d.i. meine Brotgeber) arbeiten begeistert um die Wette in Theorie u. Klavier, u. so habe ich, nachdem die Hauptsachen im besten Rollen sind, eine Sekunde Zeit gewonnen, Ihnen für Ihren l. letzten Brief<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  OJ 11/29, [3], September 10, 1908, as shown by S’s quotation of the word “embryonal,” used in OJ 11/29, [3].</tei:note> zu danken, u. darauf zu erwidern.</tei:p><tei:p>Wenn ich zu Ihnen schreibe, so nehme ich Ihren Schönheitssinn, vor Allem Liebe zum Schönen in allen Formen u. Erscheinungen als erwiesene Vorraussetzung an, u. Sie müssen dasselbe auch mit mir thun.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  This is presumably a reference to G’s book <tei:hi rend="italic">Musikästhetik</tei:hi>, published the previous year: Leipzig: Göschen, 1907.</tei:note>
 
Auch nehme ich Ihre Ehrlichkeit als erwiesen an, u. ich erwarte von Ihnen auch zu meinen Gunsten diesselbe Annahme.</tei:p><tei:p>Und wir sprechen beide von jener Kunst, die +über+ den Einzelnen Komponisten steht, von ihrem Gesamtbesitz, ihren technischen Fortschritten in Bezug auf das Hauptproblem der Musik, wie die Länge erzeugt werden könne, also weniger von der Kunst bei den Einzelnen.  Wir schalten daher Liebe, Stimmungen lieber aus, denn Sie wissen, daß es kein noch so schlechtes Werk gibt, das nicht bei irgend- <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> wie freundschaftlich oder gar sexuell entgegenkommend disponierten Mitmenschen Liebe u. beste Stimmung erwecken könnte.  Auch die <tei:hi rend="italic">Reger</tei:hi>’s,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Max Reger (1873–1916), German (Bavarian) composer of orchestral, choral, chamber, and instrumental music, pupil of Hugo Riemann, also pianist, who taught at Leipzig University from 1907;  his works were published by Universal Edition from 1904 as a result of the latter’s having taken over the catalogue of Joseph Aibl-Verlag of Munich.  Despite Reger’s being an advocate of absolute over program music, and being based in the German tradition of composition, his work was associated in S’s mind with that of R. Strauss and Mahler and generally condemned, most notably in the critique of Reger’s Piano Quintet Op. 64 in his <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (1906), pp. 220–26 (not included in Borgese translation). </tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Streicher</tei:hi>’s,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Theodor Streicher (1874–1940), Austrian composer, mostly of Lieder and choral works.  </tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Klose</tei:hi>’s<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Friedrich Klose (1862–1942), German-Swiss composer of symphonic poems, choral works, Lieder, and one opera.  He studied with, among others, Bruckner 1886–89, and, as Thuille’s successor, taught at the Munich Academy of Music 1907–1919.</tei:note> haben ihre Anhänger u. Freunde von wegen der Stimmung.  Dieser letztere Artikel<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Perhaps S means G’s article “Musik und Musikgeschichte,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Schwäbische Kronik</tei:hi>, December 18, 1907, a review of S’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi>, of which S received prior notice from Cotta on December 13, 1907 (OJ 1/6, p. 53), a copy of which he received on January 6, 1908 (OJ 1/7, p.58), commenting “[I] have worked up a justifiable vexation against this man,” and which he clipped and placed in his scrapbook (OC 2/p. 20).</tei:note> darf nicht unsere Sache sein. 
 
Denn, sehen Sie, als ich <tei:hi rend="italic">Bruckner</tei:hi> am <tei:hi rend="italic">Conservatorium</tei:hi> zum Lehrer hatte,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  S took Bruckner’s course in harmony at the Vienna Conservatory in 1887/88 and counterpoint in 1888/89.  </tei:note> liebte ich ihn maßlos wegen seiner – echten Frömmigkeit, diese erinnerte mich an die Frömmigkeit meines eigenen Vaters, der, trotzdem er Arzt war, von echtester Religiosität erfüllt war, u. nichts genoß ich an ihm so sehr, als die Kraft des Glaubens.  In die entsetzliche Großstadt aus der Provinz verpflanzt, war es mir eine Wohltat, bei <tei:hi rend="italic">Bruckner</tei:hi> – zumal einem Komponisten – den Glauben, voll[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] wunderbarer Wirkungen, wieder anzutreffen.  Ich empfand es dankbar gegen das Schicksal, das mir vergönnt hat, zu sehen, welche Kraft im Glauben steckt, die den Weg der Kunst geht, u. dachte an die echt gottesfürchtigen <tei:hi rend="italic">Haydn</tei:hi>’s, <tei:hi rend="italic">Bach</tei:hi>’s, <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven</tei:hi>’s, <tei:hi rend="italic">etc</tei:hi>.  Nichtsdestoweniger war ich schon damals in der Lage zu sehen, daß der Glaube den Künstler denn doch nicht alles geben kann, u. daß die Kunst sich ihm durchaus in allen ihren Mitteln offenbaren muß, wenn er ihr gerecht werden will.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Ich vermag also bei <tei:hi rend="italic">Bruckner</tei:hi>, bei aller Liebe zu seiner Person, auch technische Defekte zu empfinden, die mir bei Anderen, z.B. bei <tei:hi rend="italic">Beeth.</tei:hi> nur deshalb nicht auffallen, weil sie einfach bei ihm auch nicht vorhanden sind.</tei:p><tei:p>Hören Sie nur aber, wohin Sie Ihre Liebe zu <tei:hi rend="italic">Br.</tei:hi> führt[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>]: Ihm zu Liebe (Sie ahnen davon selbst sicher gar nichts) erklären Sie die <tei:hi rend="italic">Symphonien</tei:hi> wie die <tei:hi rend="italic">Beeth.</tei:hi> fur „<tei:hi rend="italic">embryonal</tei:hi>,“ blos weil Sie, was in einer Verbindung aufzuzeigen ist, wirklich verbunden bringen.  Es ist ja wirklich ein Glück, daß <tei:hi rend="italic">Br.</tei:hi> nicht auch Streichquartette geschrieben hat, denn sonst müßten Sie auch die letzten Quartette trotz ihrer technischen Vollendung für nur <tei:hi rend="italic">embryonal</tei:hi> erklären, u. doch ahne ich hier, daß Sie es nicht leichten Herzens tun würden.  Auch müßten Sie ferner da <tei:hi rend="italic">Tschaikowsky</tei:hi>’s Arbeiten einen Fortschritt über <tei:hi rend="italic">Beeth.</tei:hi> hinaus erblicken, da er – vgl. z.B. <tei:hi rend="italic">Symph. path.</tei:hi> ^Pt.^ S.20, Klv. Konz. Bm (<tei:hi rend="italic">recte</tei:hi> Des dur ^im ersten Satz^) Part. S.19, ebenso, wie Bruckner, die Gedanken blos nebeneinander setzt, u. Pausen an den entscheidenden Stellen gebraucht.  Und doch werden Sie <tei:hi rend="italic">Tsch.</tei:hi> nicht dieselbe Bedeutung beilegen wollen, wie <tei:hi rend="italic">Br.</tei:hi>, u. zw. nur, weil – mit Recht – die Gedanken <tei:hi rend="italic">Br</tei:hi>’s ja eine unendlich <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> höhere Welt, als die <tei:hi rend="italic">T.</tei:hi> darstellen.  Aber in der Liebe zu<tei:hi rend="italic">Br</tei:hi>’s Gedanken sind wir ja Beide einig, – alle meine Schüler machen die Schönheiten mit mir in Partitur u. 4-h. Spiel durch – so bleibt denn doch noch übrig ^zu erklären^, weshalb die Technik <tei:hi rend="italic">Br</tei:hi>’s mehr bedeuten sollte, als die <tei:hi rend="italic">Tsch.</tei:hi>, wenn es, wie Sie glauben, Sinn der <tei:hi rend="italic">Sonatenform</tei:hi> ist, ^nur^ einfach die Gedanken nach einander zu bringen, gleichviel[<tei:hi rend="italic">alt from</tei:hi> gleichwie?] wie, u. weshalb eine <tei:hi rend="italic">Potpourri</tei:hi> nicht auch den Wert eines organischen Ganzen haben könnte.</tei:p><tei:p>Als <tei:hi rend="italic">Haydn</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Mozart</tei:hi> u. <tei:hi rend="italic">Beeth.</tei:hi> schufen, waren keine Lehrbücher von <tei:hi rend="italic">Marx</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Adolf Bernhard Marx, <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Lehre von der musikalischen Komposition</tei:hi>, 4 vols (Leipzig: Breitkopf &amp; Härtel, 1837–47), of which S possessed vols 2–4 in Riemann’s revised edition (1888–90).  (See <tei:hi rend="italic">Musik und Theater, enthaltend die Bibliothek des Herrn Dr. Heinrich Schenker, Wien</tei:hi> (Antiquariat Heinrich Hinterberger, n.d.), item 189.) </tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Riemann</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Hugo Riemann:  S may be referring to Riemann’s revised edition of Marx’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Lehre</tei:hi>;  however, S possessed copies of eighteen of Riemann’s books, including the <tei:hi rend="italic">Musik-Lexikon</tei:hi> (3/1887) and the <tei:hi rend="italic">Große Kompositionslehre</tei:hi> (1902–03).  (See <tei:hi rend="italic">Musik und Theater, enthaltend die Bibliothek des Herrn Dr. Heinrich Schenker, Wien</tei:hi> (Antiquariat Heinrich Hinterberger, n.d.), items 223–40.)</tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">etc.</tei:hi> auf dem Markte;  wenn je ein Mensch, so waren es sie, die blos dem Instinkt ^zu^folgen hatten.  <tei:hi rend="italic">Bruckner</tei:hi> aber fand die <tei:hi rend="italic">Form</tei:hi> vor, u. hatte mit vollstem Bewußtsein, wie oft sprach er doch selbst davon zu den Schülern! – die <tei:hi rend="italic">Form</tei:hi>, freilich wie er sie sah (– –u. er sah sie schlecht, das ist es eben! – –) sich anzueignen u. fortzusetzten gesucht.  Ich denke, bei <tei:hi rend="italic">Bruckner</tei:hi> waltete weniger Instinkt zur <tei:hi rend="italic">Form</tei:hi>, als bei den erstgenannten Meistern, u. nun wollen Sie Jemand, der von den Anderen nimmt, die Kraft zuerkennen, einen Fortschritt über die Gebenden hinaus zu erzielen: das halte ich für ebenso naturwidrig als un-</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">lacks ending</tei:hi>]</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Incomplete handwritten letter draft from Schenker to Grunsky, undated, probably between September 23 and December 31, 1908</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">top margin, in Schenker’s hand:</tei:hi>] 08  to Dr. Grunsky<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Three quarters of my <tei:hi rend="italic">Counterpoint</tei:hi> manuscript is already at Cotta<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>.  My students (i.e. my employers) compete enthusiastically in theory and piano instruction, and thus, since the main items [of <tei:hi rend="italic">Counterpoint</tei:hi>] are well under way, I have a bit of time to thank you for your kind recent letter<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>, and to answer it.</tei:p><tei:p>When I write to you, I take for granted your sense for beauty, above all love for beauty in all forms and manifestations, and you must grant me the same.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/></tei:p><tei:p>I also take for granted your honesty, and I expect the same assumption from you for my benefit.</tei:p><tei:p>And we are both speaking about that art which stands +above+ the individual composer, about their full assets, their technical advancements with respect to the main problem of music, how length can be produced, thus less about art of individual composers.  We should preferably set aside love, moods, for you know that there is no work so bad that it could not somehow <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> awaken love and good mood for amicably or even sexually disposed fellow human beings.  Even the Regers<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>, Streichers<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/>, Kloses<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> have their devotees and friends on account of mood.  That last item<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> ought not to be our concern.</tei:p><tei:p>For, you see, when I had Bruckner as a teacher at the Conservatory,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> I loved him tremendously because of his genuine piety.  It reminded me of the piety of my own father who, despite his being a doctor, was filled with genuine religiosity.  I enjoyed nothing as much about him as the strength of faith.  Transplanted from the province into the horrid big city, it was a relief for me to find such faith again in Bruckner—particularly in a composer—full of wonderful effects.  I felt it, gratefully, in light of the fate granted me to see what strength of faith that follows the path of art, and thought of the genuinely God-fearing Haydns, Bachs, Beethovens, etc.  Even then I was nevertheless in the position of seeing that faith certainly cannot furnish an artist with everything, and that art must necessarily reveal itself to him in all of its means if he wants to do it justice.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> With all love for Bruckner as a person, I am therefore also able to perceive technical defects in him that I do not notice with others, for example, with Beethoven simply because they are not present with him.</tei:p><tei:p>But just listen where your love for Bruckner leads you.  For his benefit (you yourself surely don’t even sense anything of it) you declare the symphonies, like those of Beethoven, to be “embryonic” merely because you present as actually connected that which can be demonstrated as a connection.  It is truly fortunate that Bruckner did not also write string quartets, for otherwise you would have also have to declare the last quartets [of Beethoven] as merely embryonic, despite their technical perfection.  And yet I sense here that you would not do it lightly.  You would then also have to see Tchaikovsky’s works as progress beyond Beethoven since he too—see for example the <tei:hi rend="italic">Symphonie Pathétique</tei:hi>, ^score^ p. 20, Piano Concerto in Bb minor (correctly: Db major ^in the first movement^), score p. 19—just like Bruckner, merely sets ideas next to one another, and uses rests at decisive places.  And you surely do not want to assign Tchaikovsky the same significance as Bruckner simply because—rightly—Bruckner’s ideas present an infinitely <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> higher world than those of Tchaikovsky.  But we are both agreed on love for Bruckner’s ideas.  All my students work through the beautiful passages with me in score and [playing] four-hands.  But it still remains for us ^to explain^, then, why Bruckner’s technique should be more significant than Tchaikovsky’s if, as you believe, the sense of sonata form is ^merely^ to present ideas in succession, no matter how and wherefore a potpourri could not also possess the value of an organic whole.  When Haydn, Mozart and Beethoven were creative there were no texts by Marx,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> Riemann,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> etc., on the market.  If ever anyone had to follow only instinct, it was they.  However, Bruckner stumbled on form, and tried in fullest consciousness—how often did he speak of it himself to the students!—to acquire and develop form, as he viewed it, of course (and he viewed it poorly, that is just the thing!).  With Bruckner, I think less instinct for form prevailed than with the aforementioned masters, and now you want to confer on someone who takes from others the power to achieve progress beyond the givers.  I consider that no less contrary to nature than un-</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">lacks ending</tei:hi>]</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>