<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 6/6, [10] : 8-17-19 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  In the public domain
©  Transcription Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin, 2009
©  Translation Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin, 2009
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin 2009
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Violin, Moriz (1919-1956) - -Heirs of Moriz Violin (1956-197?) - -University of California, Riverside (197? - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker;  Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent and William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 08/17/1919 04:56:17 PM --><!-- MT Tags: "ViolinM ~ HSchenker","ViolinM+V ~ HSchenker","ViolinM+V+F ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Heinrich Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated August 17, 1919</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-06-04</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Schenker hopes that colleagues will support Moriz Violin.  - - The court has favored Emil Kornfeld unduly.   - - A move to Germany might save Schenker money, but he is uncertain how many of his pupils would follow him there (only Pairamall has indicated willingness).  - - He asks Weisse to act as an intermediary in booking a supply of wood for burning.  - - Dahms and Weisse are due for simultanous visits.  - - He is glad to hear Valerie Violin is better.   

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Violin, Moriz;  colleagues;  Löwe, Ferdinand; Vienna;  Warsaw;  Lemberg;  Attingi;  Lieliechen;  Kornfeld, Jeanette;  Kornfeld, Emil;  court proceedings; separation;  Glässner, Dr.;  Germany;  move;  emigration;  Elia, Angi;  Hupka, Felix;  Weisse, Hans;  Holzkarte;  wood permit;  Winternitz;  Baumann;  Dahms, Walter;  violin, Valerie</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - - </marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Heinrich Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated August 17, 1919</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Fl!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  The writing of this letter, which is done at the Schloß Tantalier, Altenmarkt, in the Pongau, on vacation, is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/14, p. 2118-2119 (=37-38): </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Hoffen will ich doch, daß deine ehemaligen Kollegen, die dir die Adresse zukommen ließen, ein kräftiges Wort mitreden werden;  beinahe will ich Ähnliches auch von Löwe<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="lowe_ferdinand">Ferdinand Löwe</ref>.  The issue addressed in this first sentence is that of Violin's re-employment at the Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst (=Vienna Conservatory), of which Löwe had appointed Director on May 31, 1919.  </tei:note> erhoffen - - Potz Teufel!  mir reimt sich schon lange nicht, welcher Art Hinderniß denn noch immer da obwalten mag!  Das ist ja nicht mehr Wien, sondern Warschau, Lemberg,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="lemberg">Lemberg</ref>.  </tei:note> Attingi[?], so was.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich selbst würde[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] den Schritt beherzter riskieren, wenn ich nur recht wüßte, wieviel meiner Schüler mitzögen, die mir so übers Erster hinweghälfen.  Wie gut würde sich die Übersiedlung in den schönen Zeitpunkt einfügen, da mein Lieliechen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="schenker_jeanette">Jeanette Schenker</ref>.  </tei:note> in allernächster Zeit den Namen Kornfeld<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Click on <ref cRef="kornfeld_emil_186619">Emil Kornfeld</ref>.  </tei:note> wird abtun dürfen, um nach „Gesetz." meinen eigenen Namen dafür einzutauschen!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  The separation between Jeanette and Emil Kornfeld was authorized on November 10, 1919, and the marriage ceremony was conducted the same day, so these remarks are made only three weeks before the event (see the account in Schenker's diary, OJ 3/1, pp. 2173-2175).  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Glässner<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="glassner_dr">Dr. Glässner</ref>.  </tei:note> hat die Eingabe vor paar Wochen gemacht, u. kraft <tei:hi rend="italic">einfachen</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Gerichtsbeschlusses</tei:hi> wird die Trennung ausgesprochen.  Wegen der Mitgift u. Möbel muß noch gekämpft werden, u. man darf, da die neuen Gesetze hierüber sich noch nicht &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;geäußert haben (nicht tschechisch &lt;/sup&gt;, wohl auf das Resultat <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> gespannt sein.  Daß K. nicht einen Heller freiwillig herausgeben wird, obgleich getrennt, obgleich ihm noch immer an 30.000 K. Reingewinn verbleiben (bei normaler Verzinsung), obgleich er zu großem Kriegsgewinn gelangt ist, steht für mich fest, der ihn von Anfang an im Gegensatz zu Allen als solcher Züge fähig befunden hat.  Anderseits ist kaum anzunehmen, daß ihm das Gericht auch noch jetzt Alles zuerkennt, - unter welchem Titel wäre es möglich, außer dem rein tschechischer Aneignungstechnik?</tei:p><tei:p>Wie gesagt, würde ich bei einer Übersiedlung sogar Geld sparen, statt daß ich jetzt in Wien zunächst meinen Ofen umsetzten lassen muß, Liel. noch bei B. belassen, u.s.w.  Und sollte ich nach einer Wohnung mich umsehen, nach Möbeln, wenn ich Hoffnung hätte, eine Wohnung in Deutschland zu nehmen?  Schon daraus ersuchst du, welches Interesse ich daran habe, die Frage zur ehester Entscheidung zu bringen.</tei:p><tei:p>Frau <tei:hi rend="italic">Pairamall</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="pairamall_evelina">Evelina Pairamall</ref>.  Pairamall appears in the lessonbooks as having lessons from Schenker in 1919/20 season, although her entry is much shorter than that for 1918/19 studying only three works, so it is possible that he dismissed her at some stage;  however, she continued lessons the following season.  </tei:note> schrieb mir, sie wäre bereit, mit mir nach D. zu gehen, allerdings, nachdem ich sie wegen Schmutzes in Geld- u. sonstiger Gesinnung hinaus- <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> geworfen habe.  Würden <tei:hi rend="italic">Elias</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="elias_angelika">Angi Elias</ref>.  </tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Hupka</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Click on <ref cRef="hupka_felix">Felix Hupka</ref>.  </tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Weisse</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.  </tei:note> mitkommen, so würde ich auch sie mitnehmen, um fürs Erste einige Deckung zu haben.  Aber leider weiß ich es von den Erstgenannten nicht bestimmt:  ich vermute blos, daß sie mitgingen, u. das ist zu wenig.  Im Herbst will ich sondieren, - brieflich geht so was nicht recht.  So muß ich mich bis dahin noch Wiener Sorgen anheimgeben . .   Und da komme ich mit einer Frage, die, sobald du intervenieren könntest, sich automatisch in eine Bitte um Intervention verwandelt, nämlich:</tei:p><tei:p>Wir lesen von einer Holzkarte<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  A <tei:hi rend="italic">Holzkarte</tei:hi> was a decorative card made of wood;  but Schenker is clearly referring to a system of rationing, and a permit required to obtain wood for burning.  </tei:note>!  Was ich im Winter unter Wärmemangel gelitten habe, war weniger an sich entsetzlich, &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;als&lt;/sup&gt; daß es mich ganz u. gar in der Arbeit am Tisch zu Hause[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>], wo nebenan die Bücher u. Bibliothek sind, u. auch Raum zu den Millionen Notizen, lahmgelegt hat.  Zu der Kohle, die ich habe (hoffentlich ist während meiner Abwesenheit nichts davon abhandengekommen) brauche ich Holz, 10 Säcke à 50 Kg. hartes in Ofenscheiten.  Gleichzeitig habe ich bei <tei:hi rend="italic">Winternitz</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  Winternitz:  presumably not the musicologist Emanuel Winternitz, but rather a fuel merchant in Vienna.  </tei:note> der mir mehrere Jahre lang Kohle in größeren Quantitäten lieferte, u. auch bei Baumann<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  Baumann:  presumably a fuel merchant in Vienna.  </tei:note> angefragt, ob u. zu welchem Preise sie mir zwischen 15-20 IX jenes[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] Quantum liefern wollten.  Die Schwierigkeit <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> scheint mir in der <tei:hi rend="italic">Voraus</tei:hi>bestellung allein zu liegen, sofern die Holzhändler nur erklären könnten, daß es ihnen um jene Zeit <tei:hi rend="italic">vielleicht nicht mehr erlaubt sein</tei:hi> könnte, die Lieferung auszuführen.  Vielleicht weißt du einen Holzhändler aus <tei:hi rend="italic">eigenem</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Gebrauche</tei:hi>, dem du mündlich mit einer Erklärung nachhelfen könntest, (die ich ja zu Papier nicht so gut bringen kann,) der eine solche Vorausbestellung dir zu lieber [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte</tei:hi> zuliebe] auf sich nähme.  Das wäre sehr sicher, jedenfalls werde ich die allerhöchsten [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte</tei:hi> allernächsten?] Entscheidungen der obererwähnten Herren dir zur Kenntnis bringen.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Dahms</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15">  Click on <ref cRef="dahms_walter">Walter Dahms</ref>.  </tei:note> u. <tei:hi rend="italic">Weisse</tei:hi> dürften beide erst am 25^ten^ hier sein u. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;mehr&lt;/sup&gt; durch Zufall zusammentreffen, als durch meine Hand.</tei:p><tei:p>Daß es der l Frau Wally<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn16">  Click on <ref cRef="violin_valerie">Valerie Violin</ref>.  </tei:note> besser geht, darf man aus deinem Schreiben wohl entnehmen, also was war denn das?  So seid denn gegrüßt herzlich wie immer</tei:p><tei:p>2 : 5 [<tei:hi rend="italic">unsigned</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>17. Aug. 1919</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Heinrich Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated August 17, 1919</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Floriz,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>I very much hope that your former colleagues, who let you have their addresses, will put in a strong word [on your behalf].  I hope for something similar from Löwe,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> too - - Confound it all! I have not for a long time been able to understand  what sort of obstacles could continue to prevail!  This is certainly no longer Vienna, but Warsaw, Lemberg,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> Attingi[?], and such like.</tei:p><tei:p>I myself would be more courageous about taking the step if only I knew for sure how many of my pupils would move with me and help me get over the initial stages.  How well the timing of the move would fit with that magical moment when my Lieliechen<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> will be permitted shortly to discard the name Kornfeld<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> and by "law" exchange it for my own name!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/></tei:p><tei:p>Glässner<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> filed the petition a few weeks ago, and the separation will be pronounced by <tei:hi rend="italic">simple court decree</tei:hi>.  We still have to fight over the settlement and furniture, and we may be kept in suspense for the result, since the laws on this have not yet &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;been articulated (not in Czech terms)&lt;/sup&gt;.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> That K[ornfeld] will not of his own free will hand over a single penny--even though he is separated,  even though he is left with 30,000 Kronen of clear profit (at the normal rate of interest), even though he has achieved a great victory--is quite clear to me who, in contrast to all the others, found him capable of such actions from the very start.  On the other hand, it is hard to believe that the court is still persisting in awarding him everything--under what other authority is that possible than the purely Czech technique of appropriation?</tei:p><tei:p>As I have said, I might even save money by moving, instead of having to have my oven replaced and leaving Lieliechen with B., etc.  And should I look around for an apartment, for furniture, when I might have hoped to find a place to live in Germany?  Even from these remarks you can work out the interest that I have in reaching the earliest possible decision.</tei:p><tei:p>Mrs. Pairamall<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> wrote telling me she was prepared to go with me to Germany, but only after I had thrown her out on account of her sordid attitude toward money and other matters. <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi>  If Elias,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> Hupka,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> and Weisse<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> would come with me I would take them, too, in order to provide some initial cover.  But unfortunately I do not know it for sure about the first-mentioned:  I only suspect that they would go with me, and that is insufficient.  I will take soundings in the autumn--this sort of thing is not so easily done in writing.  So until then I shall just have to entrust myself again to Viennese tribulations . .   And this brings me to a question that would automatically be converted into a request for intervention as soon as you were able to intervene, to wit::</tei:p><tei:p>We have read about a wood permit!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/>  My suffering for lack of warmth last winter was less horrific in itself &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;than&lt;/sup&gt; that it utterly and completely crippled me in my work at my desk at home, with my books and library and also space for millions of notes close to hand.  In addition to the coal that I have (I hope none of it has gone missing during my absence), I need wood:  ten sacks, 50 Kg each of hardwood[?], split for the stove.  At the same time, I have inquired of Winternitz,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> who for several years supplied me with large quantities of coal, and also of Baumann,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/> whether they can supply me with that quantity between September 15 and 20, and if so, at what price.  The difficulty <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> seems to me to lie solely in ordering <tei:hi rend="italic">in advance</tei:hi>, in as much as that the wood merchants could only tell me that, <tei:hi rend="italic">around that time</tei:hi>, they would <tei:hi rend="italic">probably no longer be allowed</tei:hi> to fulfill the delivery.  Maybe you know of a wood merchant whose services <tei:hi rend="italic">you yourself</tei:hi> use, to whom you could help me out by explaining the situation in person (which I really could not achieve on paper), who would undertake it as a favor to you.  That would make things very secure [for me]; in any event, I will bring to your attention the decisions of the above-mentioned gentlemen at the very earliest opportunity.</tei:p><tei:p>Dahms<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn15"/> and Weisse are due here not until the 25th, and will coincide, &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;more&lt;/sup&gt; by accident than by design.</tei:p><tei:p>I gather from your letter that dear Wally<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn16"/> is better.  So what was it?  Please accept my cordial greetings</tei:p><tei:p>As ever,
2 : 5 [<tei:hi rend="italic">unsigned</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>August 17, 1919</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>