<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 6/6, [9] : 7-15-19 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  In the public domain
©  Transcription Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin, 2009
©  Translation Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin, 2009
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent &amp; William Drabkin 2009
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Violin, Moriz (1919-1956) - -Heirs of Moriz Violin (1956-197?) - -University of California, Riverside (197? - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker;  Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent and William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 07/15/1919 04:59:42 PM --><!-- MT Tags: "ViolinM ~ H+JSchenker","ViolinM ~ HSchenker","ViolinM+V ~ H+JSchenker","ViolinM+V ~ HSchenker","ViolinM+V+F ~ H+JSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten double-letter from Jeanette Kornfeld and Heinrich Schenker to Valerie and Moriz Violin, dated July 15, 1919</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-05-28</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Jeanette to Wally:  Expresses sympathy at Wally's illness.   - - Description of Schloß  Tantalier. 
Heinrich to Wally:  Advocates extravagant eating as cure for stomach trouble.
Heinrich to Moriz:  Reinforces advice to Wally.  - - Inquires about sitation at the Vienna Conservatory (Akademie).  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Kornfeld, Jeanette;  Schenker, Jeanette;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Violin, Valerie;  Violin, Moriz;  illness;  Schloß Tantalier;  Radstadt;  Altenmarkt;  Pongau;  Klammerth;  Kunigund;  Pechacek, Jenny;  Goethe;  Wilhelm Meisters Wanderjahre;  Buddha;  Wilson, Woodrow;  Austerlitz, Friedrich;  Adler, Friedrich;  Sulden;  Schenker, Moriz;  Guttmann, Hans;  Guttmann, Sophie;  Riemann, Hugo;  Zell am See;  Violin, Genovefa;  Löwe, Ferdinand</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten double-letter from Heinrich and Jeanette Kornfeld and Heinrich Schenker  to Valerie and Moriz Violin, dated July 15, 1919</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in Jeanette's hand:</tei:hi>] 
Liebste Frau Vally!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Writing of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/14, p. 2101 (=20):  "An Frau Wally (Br.):  Lie-Liechen troestend, ich den Rat erteilend, so viel als möglich zu essen." (To Wally (letter):  Lie-Liechen consolingly, I imparting the advice to eat as much as possible.").    It was preceded by a postcard written on July 7 (the day after their arrival, recorded in the diary at OJ 2/14, p. 2097: "An Floriz (K.):  erste Eindrücke, Erkundigung nach seiner Frau." (To Floriz (postcard): first impressions, inquiry after his wife."), which is not known to survive.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Es hat mich sehr betrübt zu hören, daß Ihr Unwohlsein nun doch mehr als eine bloß nervose Indisposition ist<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  The letter referred to is not known to survive, but its receipt is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 2/14, p. 2100 (=19), July 14, 1919:  "Von Fl. (Br.):  über Erkrankung der Frau."  ("From Floriz (letter):  concerning his wife's illness.").  </tei:note> - doch, Sie sind jung u. kräftig u. werden mit Ihrer bewährten Widerstandskraft bald wieder im Vollbesitze der Gesundheit sein;  wenn wir uns wiedersehn, erzählen Sie uns davon, wie von einem verwehten bösen Spuck.  Hoffentlich ist Ihr Mädchen indessen wieder eingerückt u. mit ihr normalere, ruhigere Zeiten für Sie.  Vielleicht ist die Attacke überhaupt nur ein Er- oder Uebermüdungszustand u. schwindet bei entsprechender Ruhe.  Wenn nur bald auch die äußeren Verhältnisse sich zumindest so weit bessern würden, daß die Befriedigung der primitivsten <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Bedürfnisse &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;nicht&lt;/sup&gt; so viel Schweiß kostet.  Und wenn ich hier sonst nichts gefunden hätte, als die Erlösung von der quälenden Magensorge - so wäre das an sich schon unbezahlbar.</tei:p><tei:p>Und so will ich denn unter Zurücksetzung der Romantik zuerst die Frage Ihres lieben Gatten nach dem Essen, Essen, Essen beantworten.  Wir essen viel - das steht im Vordergrund:  Fleisch, Nocke&lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;r&lt;/sup&gt;ln , Gemüse, Mehlspeisen - alles in über-dimensionirten Portionen, wir haben neben der Pension noch einen Liter Milch täglich u. können im Hause Butter kaufen - was verschlägt es da, daß alles ein wenig nach Dorf schmeckt u. den verwöhnten (noch immer verwöhnten!) Großstadtgaumen nicht immer kitzelt.  Aller Magensorgen ledig, können wir hier gut ausruhen, in tiefster Ruhe arbeiten u. bei Lektüre  feiern - was bliebe da zu wünschen übrig, läge nicht paar Stunden westwärts das verlorene Paradies - Tirol.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Jeanette is referring to the <ref cRef="tirol">South Tyrol</ref> (Südtirol; Alto Adige), in which she and Heinrich used to spend summer vacations.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Noch etwas vom Schloß:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Schloß Tantalier, bei Radstadt, im Pongau (Salzburg), where the Schenkers had been on vacation since July 6.  Click on <ref cRef="klammerth_snr">Klammert (snr)</ref>.  Federhofer that the castle belonged to the family of the industrialist Klammert, at whose invitation the Schenkers were staying there (<tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern und Briefen ...</tei:hi> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), p. 89).  </tei:note>  Es ist ein wirk- <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> liches altes Schloß mit allen seinen Attributen;  hat zwei runde u. zwei Ecktürme, in denen Scharen von Turmschwalben hausen, meterdicke Mauern, riesige Zimmer - die paar Möbelstücke ertrinken förmlich in der Weite - Fenster die knarren u. schlecht schließen, ein schweres, mit Eisen besch[l]agenes Tor, das schlecht aufgeht - fehlt nur die weiße Frau;<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> The White Lady: in rural mythology, the ghost of a woman whose life was cut short by an unfortunate event and who, in Romantic literature (e.g. in the novels of Walter Scott) ,often appears to those living in a castle.</tei:note>  es liegt mitten im Tal, umgeben von weiten Wiesen u. wenn vom Altenmarkter Turm das Aveglöckchen läutet,  müßte einem eigentlich eine Ballade gelingen vom Fräulein Kunigunde u. ihrem edlen Ritter,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Reference is presumably to Lady Kunigunde, abbess of the St. George Convent in Prague (1302-21), daughter of Queen Kunigunde of Bohemia, and the parable of "The Brave Knight," in which a beautiful lady is abducted and hidden in a dark dungeon from which the brave knight rescues her after thirty years.  </tei:note> den [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte:</tei:hi> der] fern in Fehde liegt - u. gerade tritt mein lieber Heinrich ein u. fragt:  Hast Du schon von der Pechaĉek geschrieben?  Jenny Pechaĉek<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="pechacek_jenny">Jenny Pechaĉek</ref>.  </tei:note> heißt nämlich die Näherin u. wohnt VII, Bernardgasse 7.  Machen Sie einen Versuch;  ich habe ihr ja nur alte Stücke zum Umarbeiten gegeben, sie hat sich als recht geschickt erwiesen, - ob  ich ihr Neues, Kostbares anvertrauen würde, müßte ich mir noch überlegen.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Schicken Sie bald über Ihr Befinden u. seien Sie mit allen Ihren Lieben herzlichst gegrüßt, von</tei:p><tei:p>Ihrer
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  Lie-Lie</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in Heinrich's hand:</tei:hi>]  
Liebste Frau Wally!</tei:p><tei:p>Lachen Sie micht nicht aus:  ich bin (ohne jegliche genaue Kenntnis der Psychologie) doch eine Art „Makarie"<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8"> <tei:hi rend="italic">Wilhelm Meisters Wanderjahre</tei:hi> [Wilhelm Meister's Journeyman Years], the sequel to Goethe's <tei:hi rend="italic">Wilhelm Meisters Lehrjahre</tei:hi>, was published in 1821 (and substantially revised in 1829). Wilhelm is taken to the home of a distant aunt, named Makarie, a strange character with special insights into the workings of the solar system, insights that are proven correct by the researches of an astronomer-friend of hers.</tei:note> (Goethe: Wilh. Meister, zweiter Theil) des Organismus.  Ich habe meinem LieLiechen recht viel Beschwerden wegkuriert u. allen „Schmuntzeln" [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] (Buda)  zum Trotz würde ich Ihnen verordnen:</tei:p><tei:p>In <tei:hi rend="italic">Ruhe</tei:hi> - <tei:hi rend="italic">viel</tei:hi>, sehr viel <tei:hi rend="italic">essen</tei:hi> u. <tei:hi rend="italic">trinken</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>Sie haben nicht <tei:hi rend="italic">fressen</tei:hi> &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;(!)&lt;/sup&gt; gelernt u. das rächst sich bei Jedermann anders, bei Ihnen eben so.  (Fl.!  lache mich nicht aus).  Sie hatten Kinder[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>], haben Mühe mit Ihnen [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte:</tei:hi> ihnen], essen zwar sehr gut, aber Sie <tei:hi rend="italic">fressen</tei:hi> nicht.  Sie hätten sich seinerzeit die Kilos nicht &lt;del&gt;nicht&lt;/del&gt; verdrießen lassen &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;sollen&lt;/sup&gt;;  sie fehlen Ihnen &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;heute&lt;/sup&gt;, da Sie offenbar doch von Natur aus auf meinesgleichen (80-90 Kg) angelegt sind.  Ich treibe nicht Scherz, wenn auch scheinbar der Form nach:  ich rate gut u. meine es gut:  fressen u. Fett ansetzten.  Sofort ändern sich die Gallensäfte u.s.w.   Gegengifte mobilisieren!  Vor lauter Wilson<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="wilson_woodrow">Woodrow Wilson</ref>.  </tei:note> u. Austerlitze<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Click on <ref cRef="austerlitz_friedrich">Friedrich Austerlitz</ref>.  For a similar statement, see WSLB 302, May 18, 1919.  </tei:note>-Adler<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Click on <ref cRef="adler_friedrich">FriedrichAdler</ref>.  </tei:note> hätte ich schon ähnliches erlitten, wenn ich nicht alles Geld aufgefressen hätte.  Meine Theorien, <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> die ich Lieliechen namentlich in Sulden<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Click on <ref cRef="sulden">Sulden</ref>.  </tei:note> vortrug u. diktierte, u. die die <tei:hi rend="italic">Wissenschaft</tei:hi>[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] erst in <tei:hi rend="italic">letzter Zeit</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  "letzter Zeit":  double-underlined.  </tei:note> &lt;del&gt;sich&lt;/del&gt; zu <tei:hi rend="italic">bestätigen</tei:hi> sich anschickt, lautet:  der Magen muß in <tei:hi rend="italic">Tätigkeit</tei:hi> bleiben, die Mühle muß immer klappern!  Meinetwegen übergroße Bissen, Unverdautes, unedle Speisen, Alles ist dem Magen recht, nur langweilen dürfen sich nicht, weil er in Langweile ähnliche Dummheiten macht, wie der Mensch überhaupt.  Hol der Teufel die verlogenen, verlogenen Kalorien u.s.w.. der Magen will immer beschäftigt sein, sonst treibt er böse Allotria.  Heute ist, &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;wie gesagt[,]&lt;/sup&gt; auch die Wissenschaft draufgekommen, - selbst das „N. W. Tgb"<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  Click on <ref cRef="neues_wiener_tagblat"><tei:hi rend="italic">Neues Wiener Tagblatt</tei:hi></ref>.  </tei:note> hat in einer Artikelserie darüber Aufklärung gebracht.</tei:p><tei:p>Fl!</tei:p><tei:p>Dich bitte ich, wegen dieser Theorie nicht gleich zu schreien:  Ja, der Mann weiß ja nicht, was Magen ist!  Falsche Schlusse zieht er von sich u. dgl.  Du hast gesehen, daß auch mein Magen sehr empfindlich ist, weniger sogar auf Qualität, als auf Nervendepressionen überhaupt.  Während des Krieges habe ich an 15 Kg eingebüßt (die ich jetzt wieder einhole), weniger etwa, weil ich schlechter gegessen, als wegen der Aufregung, - ja, <tei:hi rend="italic">eine</tei:hi> Aufregung <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> im Juli 1918 (Mozio<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15">  Click on <ref cRef="schenker_moriz">Moriz Schenker</ref>.  </tei:note>-Hans<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn16">  Click on <ref cRef="guttmann_hans">Hans Guttmann</ref>.  </tei:note>-Sophie<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn17">  Click on <ref cRef="guttmann_sophie_nee">Sophie Guttmann</ref>.  </tei:note>) hat mir (binnen 4 Wochen) 2 Kg abgezapft.  Auch ich weiß also etwas davon, wie selbst eine Überfülle des Magens nicht immer das Wohlsein begründet, aber noch mehr weiß ich davon, wie Nicht<tei:hi rend="italic">fülle</tei:hi> gesundheitsschädlich ist, möge sie der Zahl der Kalorien nach genau dem entsprechen, was die <tei:hi rend="italic">Riemanns</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn18">  Click on <ref cRef="riemann_hugo">Hugo Riemann</ref>.  Schenker is poking fun at Riemann's overly prescriptive, mechanical concept of music theory.</tei:note> des Magens theoretisch vorschrieben.</tei:p><tei:p>Im Übrigen laß mich etwas davon hören, was die Aerzte vorschreiben.  Ist es denn ganz augeschlossen, daß Frau Wally, wenn es sein muß, allein für paar Wochen fortgeht, um zu ruhen u. zu essen?  Zell a/See<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn19">  Click on <ref cRef="zell_am_see">Zell am See</ref>.</tei:note> ist ja frei;  ganz frei!  Vielleicht könntet Ihr hier bei uns Platz nehmen, wegen der Milch?  Was sagt Ihr dazu?  Ich würde morgen bei Kl. anfragen, . .</tei:p><tei:p>Wie es das „Mädi"<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn20"> "Mädi":  click on <ref cRef="violin_genovefa">Genovefa Violin</ref>.</tei:note> hält, so sollte es die Mutter machen, - Wenn nur auch schon die Akademiefrage<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn21"> "Akademiefrage": Violin had resigned his post at the Vienna Conservatory in 1912, in protest at the way in which the director, Wilhelm Bopp, was treating some of the older, more established professors. With the resignation of Bopp in 1919, and a new director in place (Ferdinand Löwe), he may have been reapplying for a position there. </tei:note> gelöst wären,damit du freien Ausblick gewännst!  Wer retardiert denn jetzt?  Löwe<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn22"> Click on <ref cRef="lowe_ferdinand">Ferdinand Löwe</ref>.</tei:note> dürfte es doch kaum sein.</tei:p><tei:p>Für jetzt genug.  Seid alle gegrüßt mit der stehenden Kabale - Chiffre</tei:p><tei:p>2 : 5  [<tei:hi rend="italic">unsigned</tei:hi>]
15. Juli 1919</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten double-letter from Jeanette Kornfeld and Heinrich Schenker to Valerie and Moriz Violin, dated July 15, 1919</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in Jeanette's hand:</tei:hi>] 
Dearest Vally,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>I was greatly distressed to hear that your illness is really more than a purely nervous indisposition.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  Still, you are young and strong, and with your proven powers of resistance will soon be back in full possession of your health.  When we see each other next, you will be telling us about it as if it were a horrible nightmare that has been blown away.  I do hope that, in the meantime, your maid has returned, with her more normal, more peaceful times for you.  Perhaps the attack is really no more than a state of fatigue or total exhaustion, which will disappear when you have the required amount of rest.  If only the external conditions were soon to improve, sufficiently for the most basic <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> necessities ^not^ to cost so much effort.   And had I found nothing else here than the release from the agonizing stomach ailments, then that in itself would be a priceless blessing.</tei:p><tei:p>And so, setting aside all romanticizing, I will first answer your husband's question about eating, eating, eating.  We do a lot of this--eating is a foreground activity:  meat, dumplings, vegetables, desserts, all in mammoth portions;  we get an extra liter of milk a day close by our boarding-house, and can buy butter in-house--what does it matter if everything tastes a bit rustic and never for a moment tickles the pampered (forever pampered!) metropolitan palate.  Free of all stomach ailments, we are able to get thoroughly rested here, work in total peace and quiet, and rejoice in reading.  -- The only regret we have is that less than two hours westward lies the lost Paradise--the Tyrol.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/></tei:p><tei:p>Now a bit about the castle:<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  It is a genuine, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> old castle with all its appurtenances:  it has two round and two corner towers in which flocks of house martins nest, meter-thick walls, gigantic rooms--the few items of furniture are completely dwarfed by its vastness;  windows that creak and do not shut properly, a heavy, iron-banded door that doesn't open properly.  The only thing that is missing is the White Lady!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  It lies at the heart of the valley, surrounded by distant meadows, and when the angelus bell rings out from the Altenmarkt tower, one really must conjure a ballad about Kunigund and her noble knight,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> who is far away in battle--and at this very moment my dear Heinrich enters and asks "Have you yet written about the Pechaĉeks?  Jenny Pechaĉek<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> is the name of the seamstress who lives at Bernardgasse 7 in the VIIth [district of Vienna].  Do give her a try; I have given her only old items to be altered, and she has shown herself to be skilled;  whether I would entrust something new and valuable to her is something I must yet consider.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Send word soon as to how you are.  Heartfelt greetings to you and all your loved-ones, from</tei:p><tei:p>Your
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  Lie-Lie</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in Heinrich's hand:</tei:hi>]  
Dearest Vally,</tei:p><tei:p>Don't make fun of me:   I am (without any precise knowledge of psychology) a sort of Makaria of bodily functions (see Goethe's <tei:hi rend="italic">Wilhelm Meisters Wanderjahre</tei:hi>)<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/>.  I have completely cured my LieLiechen of many, many infirmities, and in defiance of all Buddha-like smiles, I would prescribe for you:</tei:p><tei:p>In <tei:hi rend="italic">peace and quiet</tei:hi> -- to <tei:hi rend="italic">eat</tei:hi> and <tei:hi rend="italic">drink</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">a lot</tei:hi>, a whole lot!</tei:p><tei:p>You have not learned to <tei:hi rend="italic">gorge yourself</tei:hi> &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;(!)&lt;/sup&gt;, and [failure to do so] will take its toll on you, as with everyone else.  (Floriz, don't poke fun at me.)  You have had children, and have difficulties with them; and while you eat very well, you do not <tei:hi rend="italic">gorge yourself</tei:hi>.  You &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;ought&lt;/sup&gt; not to have let the kilos bother you in times past;  you are lacking them &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;now&lt;/sup&gt;, since evidently by nature you are built exactly the same way as people like me (80-90 kilograms).  I am not joking, even if it looks like it:  I advise you well, and mean well:  gorge yourself and put on fat.  The bile juices will change immediately, etc.  Mobilize the antitoxins! From the likes of Wilson<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/>, Austerlitz<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> and Adler,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> I would already have suffered similarly, had I not spent all my money on food.  My theories, <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> which I expounded and dictated to Lieliechen, especially in Sulden,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> and which <tei:hi rend="italic">science</tei:hi> is only in <tei:hi rend="italic">recent times</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> getting round to confirming, runs as follows:  the stomach must remain <tei:hi rend="italic">active</tei:hi>, the mill must clatter on incessantly!  For my part, gigantic bites, undigested things, unrefined foods:  all of this is fit for the stomach, so long as the latter does not get bored, because when bored it commits the same kinds of stupidities that man does in general.  The mendacious, mendacious calories, etc., can all go to the Devil; the stomach must always keep busy, otherwise it will start to play up.  These days, &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;as I say,&lt;/sup&gt; even science has come round to it, -- even the <tei:hi rend="italic">Neues Wiener Tagblatt</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/> has published a series of articles on the subject.</tei:p><tei:p>Floriz!</tei:p><tei:p>As to this theory [of mine], please don't shout "Oh, dear, the man does not have the faintest idea what the stomach is!  He draws false conclusions from his own experiences, and such like."  You have seen that my stomach, too, is very delicate, susceptible less to the quality [of food] than to nervous depression.  During the War, I lost 15 kilograms (which I am now putting on again), not so much perhaps because I ate less well than on account of agitation--yes, a single [period of] agitation <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> in July 1918 (Mozio,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn15"/> Hans,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn16"/> and Sophie<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn17"/>) cost me two kilograms (in the space of four weeks).  So I too know something of how a surfeit [of food] in the stomach does not always in itself foster good health, but I know still better that an <tei:hi rend="italic">insufficiency</tei:hi> is deleterious to health, even if it corresponds--in numbers of calories--precisely to what the Riemanns<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn18"/> of the stomach prescribe theoretically.</tei:p><tei:p>For the rest, do let me know what your doctors prescribe.  It is not beyond the bounds of possibility that Vally, if need be, could go for a couple of weeks on her own, so that she can rest and eat?  Zell am See<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn19"/> definitely has room, plenty of room!  Perhaps you could both stay here with us, on account of the milk?  What do you think of that?  I can ask  Kl[ammert] about it tomorrow, . .</tei:p><tei:p>What is good for the daughter<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn20"/> should also be good for the mother.</tei:p><tei:p>If only the matter concerning the Conservatory<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn21"/> were also resolved, so that your prospects could open up. Who is stalling things now? Surely not Löwe.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn22"/></tei:p><tei:p>Enough for now.  Greetings to all of you, with the usual number cabal</tei:p><tei:p>2 : 5  [<tei:hi rend="italic">unsigned</tei:hi>]
July 15, 1919</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>