<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:vC 10 : 6-1-27 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2006.
© Translation William Drabkin, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance> Felix-Eberhard von Cube (1927-87) - -Heirs of F.-E. von Cube (1987-present day)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: Heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 06/01/1927 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated June 1, 1927</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-06-17</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Congratulates Cube on appointment to professorship; reports that Oppel has been appointed to a professorship at the Leipzig Conservatory, and on the spread of S's theory elsewhere; looks forward to visit from Cube.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Cube, Felix-Eberhard von;  congratulations;  professorship;  Oppel, Reinhard;  Leipzig Conservatory;  Edinburgh;  New York;  Stuttgart;  Vienna;  Weisse, Hans;  Vrieslander, Otto;  Munich;  Duisburg;  Halm, August;  Schoenberg;  Hindemith;  Vienna Akademie für Musik und Darstellende Kunst;  Vienna Conservatory;  visit;  Galtür;  Paznauntal;  Landseck;  Wiesberg;  Altmann, Wilhelm;  Berlin;  Hoboken, Anthony van</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated June 1, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Lieber Herr <tei:hi rend="italic">v. Cube</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>Zu der nun offiziell gewordenen Professur wünsche ich u. meine Frau Ihnen das Allerbeste! Von Gottes Gnaden ist zwar mehr als von Professoren Gnade, aber die Welt hält auf Professoren (und muß es wohl auch tun, da Gott ihr ununsichtbar u. unhörbar bleibt), da tun Sie also gut, auch ihr Zeugnis hinzunehmen. Den Rest haben Sie mit Gott abzumachen, der Sie reichlich ausgestattet hat. Auf dem von Ihnen zu beschreitenden Weg wird Sie ermüntern zu hören, daß H. Prof. Dr. <tei:hi rend="italic">R. Oppel</tei:hi> - den ich Ihnen wohl genannt haben mag - -auf-  ^an^ das <tei:hi rend="italic">Leipziger</tei:hi> Konservatorium <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> als Prof. für Theorie berufen worden, in welcher Eigenschaft er, wie er mir mitteilt, mein <tei:hi rend="italic">System</tei:hi> offiziell lehren wird.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> Click on <ref cRef="oppel_reinhard">Reinhard Oppel</ref>.</tei:note> Die Wirkung breitet sich mehr u. mehr aus: <tei:hi rend="italic">Edinburgh</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> Click on <ref cRef="dunn_john_petrie">John Petrie Dunn</ref>.</tei:note> (auch <tei:hi rend="italic">New-York</tei:hi>),<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> The dissemination of Schenker's work in the USA seems to have begun earlier than is generally reckoned. In the postcard vC 15, May 28, 1928, Schenker refers to "American (English-speaking) teachers in New York and San Francisco who have been teaching the Urlinie in their schools for some time."</tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Leipzig</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Stuttgart</tei:hi>, Wien (ich und <tei:hi rend="italic">Weisse</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.</tei:note>), <tei:hi rend="italic">Vrieslander</tei:hi> in München (er schreibt eine große <tei:hi rend="italic">Monographie</tei:hi> über mich),<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.  He never published a full-length monograph on Schenker, but articles entitled "Heinrich Schenker" appeared in <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Musik</tei:hi> (October 1927) and the <tei:hi rend="italic">Deutsche Tonkünstlerzeitung</tei:hi> (March 5, 1928).  (In Schenker's scrapbook, OC 2, Jeanette Schenker gives October 1926 for date of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Musik</tei:hi> article.) </tei:note> Sie in Duisburg, u. Halm<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6"> August Halm (1869-1929)--see correspondence between Schenker and Halm [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> usw usw. Das Alles zeigt, daß - trotz <tei:hi rend="italic">Schoenbergs</tei:hi> und <tei:hi rend="italic">Hindemiths</tei:hi> - auch unsere Stunde schlägt; diese Stunde aber dauert eine Ewigkeit, weil sie die Wahrheit, nicht blos eine Mode, trägt. <tei:hi rend="italic">Oppel</tei:hi> erhält bei 20 Stunden 700 MK,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7"> This is, presumably, a monthly salary and workload.</tei:note> - das zahlt ^die^ Wiener Akademie gewiß nicht. Haben Sie schon Schüler im Privat-Unterricht?</tei:p><tei:p>Wir reisen schon am 25.6 nach Galtür.  Daß Sie uns besuchen wollen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8"> See Cube's letter OJ 9/34, [8], May 28, 1927.</tei:note> macht uns <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Freude schon zum Voraus, sie wird noch größer sein, wenn Sie die Absicht wirklich ausführen werden. Ich weiß nicht, ob Sie Wien oder Galtür meinen, jedenfalls merke ich an: Galtür im Paznauntal, erreichbar auf einer Fußwanderung von der Voralberger Seite, oder am besten mit Auto aus <tei:hi rend="italic">Landeck</tei:hi> (oder <tei:hi rend="italic">Wiesberg</tei:hi>). Prof. <tei:hi rend="italic">Oppel</tei:hi> wird uns ebenfalls in Galtür besuchen, auch Direktor <tei:hi rend="italic">Altmann</tei:hi> (<tei:hi rend="italic">Berlin</tei:hi>),<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9"> Wilhelm Altmann (1862-1951), retired Director of the Music Division of the Prussian State Library (19154-27) in Berlin. The editor of many miniature scores. Altmann was also a keen supporter of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Erläuterungsausgabe</tei:hi>, and wrote a favorable review of the first <tei:hi rend="italic">Tonwille</tei:hi> pamphlet.</tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Hoboken</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> (vielleicht mit <tei:hi rend="italic">Vrieslander</tei:hi>).</tei:p><tei:p>Nun auf Wiedersehen. Unser Beider beste Grüsse sendet</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] <tei:hi rend="italic">H Schenker</tei:hi>
1.6.27</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated June 1, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Mr. von Cube,</tei:p><tei:p>Regarding your professorship, which has now become official, my wife and I offer you our very best wishes. The grace of God is, of course, more than the grace of professors, but the world relies on professors (as it surely has to, since God remains invisible and inaudible to it). You are thus doing the right thing to take up your credentials.  For the rest, you will have to settle your accounts with God, who has endowed you richly. As you follow the path that has been set out for you, it will give you encouragement to hear that Professor Reinhard Oppel, whose name I have probably mentioned to you, has been appointed <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Professor of Music Theory at the Leipzig Conservatory, in which capacity--so he tells me--he will officially teach my system.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> The effect continues to broaden: Edinburgh<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> (also New York),<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> Leipzig, Stuttgart, Vienna (myself and Weisse<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>), Vrieslander in Munich (he is writing a long monograph about me),<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> yourself in Duisburg, and Halm,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> etc., etc. All this shows that, in spite of Schoenberg and Hindemith, the hour has struck for us, too, but this hour will last an eternity because it bears the truth, not merely a fashion. Oppel will receive 700 marks for twenty hours of teaching;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> the Vienna Academy certainly does not pay as well. Do you already have private pupils?</tei:p><tei:p>On June 25, we are travelling to Galtür. To hear that you are hoping to to visit us<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> fills us <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> with delight, which will be all the greater if your intentions are actually realized. I do not know whether you mean Vienna or Galtür, but let me note in any event: Galtür in the Paznaun Valley, accessible by footpath from the Vorarlberg side, or (better) by automobile from Landeck (or Wiesberg). Professor Oppel will likewise visit us in Galtür, so will Director Altmann (Berlin),<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> and Hoboke<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> (possibly with Vrieslander).</tei:p><tei:p>Until we see each other again, I send best greetings from the two of us.</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H Schenker
June 1, 1927</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>