<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:vC 17 : 7-13-28 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2006.
© Translation by William Drabkin 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance> Felix-Eberhard von Cube (1928-87) - -Heirs of F.-E. von Cube (1987-present day)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: Heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 07/13/1928 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated July 13, 1928</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-07-18</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>S offers consoling words for low turn-out to Düsselforf lecture; praises recent article by C, but corrects overstated connection between himself and Brahms and Joachim.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cube, Felix-Eberhard von; Schenker, Heinrich;  Düsseldorf;  lecture;  attendance;  Dehn;  Vienna;  Liszt;  Ysaÿe, Eugène;  Duisburg;  Joachim, Joseph;  Brahms;  Meiningen;  Bülow, Hans von;  Messchaert, Johannes;  Bach, C. P. E.;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  Hammer, Victor;  Oppel, Reinhard;  Galtür</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated July 13, 1928</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Galtür, 13. Juli 1928</tei:p><tei:p>Mein lieber Herr <tei:hi rend="italic">v. Cube</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>Nun ist es doch nach Ihrem Wunsch gegangen!  Die gewissen 10 Zuhörer in <tei:hi rend="italic">Düsseldorf</tei:hi> ändern daran nichts; solche 10 hatte z.B. auch die Dehn<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> die Dehn: a female musician, perhaps a singer.</tei:note> in Wien (ich selbst war zufällig unter den 10), oft genug Liszt, <tei:hi rend="italic">Ysaye</tei:hi>[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Eugène Ysaÿe [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> u.s.w. Ihre Mühen fanden ihre Krönung u Sie haben sich Verdienste um die Musik in <tei:hi rend="italic">D.</tei:hi> erworben, mögen die Duisburger selbst auch nichts davon ahnen: alle Verdienste sehen sich namentlich darin gleich, daß die Nutznießer lange nichts merken, im Großen wie im Kleinen, in welchem Stoff immer; auch geht übrigens in den Gemütern der Nutznießer die Sonne des ersten <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Dankes nie so recht auf.</tei:p><tei:p>Wir beide zahlen nicht zu den Nutznießern, gerade deshalb danke ich -Ihnen- sozusagen ^nur^ als Sachwalter meiner Gedanken auch Ihnen als Sachwalter für die tausendfachen Mühen um das Zustandekommen, von Mensch zu Mensch, von Künstler zu Künstler.</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr Aufsatz zeigt, wie der frühere, ein leicht bewegliches Denken u. Schreiben. Die Ungenauigkeit <tei:hi rend="italic">puncto Joachim</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Joseph Joachim [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Brahms</tei:hi> ("Zusammenarbeit") stelle ich auf meine Rechnung, da Sie vermutlich meine Schrift schwer lesen könnten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> Cube wrote a biographical article about Schenker for a Duisburg newspaper--presumably ""Heinrich Schenker," unknown newspaper, June 28, 1928 (clipping preserved OJ 58/3)--to promote the exhibition of his teacher's writings at Scheuermann's bookshop. To assist him with this, Schenker wrote a highly personal letter, vC 14, April 29, 1928, giving some details about the musicians who inspired him in the early stages of his career, among them Joachim, Brahms, and Messchaert.</tei:note> Ich meinte blos: in Bezug auf <tei:hi rend="italic">Joachim</tei:hi>, er sei sein Lebenlang mir immer Vorbild in Sachen des "Vortrags" gewesen (persönlich kannte ich ihn gar nicht) u. in Bezug auf <tei:hi rend="italic">Brahms</tei:hi>, seine Erscheinung überhaupt, als Träger einer so gewaltigen <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> künstlerischen Summe (war doch <tei:hi rend="italic">meine</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">erste</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Brahms-Sinfonie</tei:hi> schon <tei:hi rend="italic">seine</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">dritte</tei:hi>, die Bülow<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Hans von Bülow [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> mit den Meiningern zur Erstauff. in Wien brachte!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6"> The first performance of Brahms' Third Symphony took place on December 2, 1883.</tei:note> Der <tei:hi rend="italic">Brahms</tei:hi>-Gipfel war schon für alle Ewigkeit getürmt, als ich ihn zu sehen, zu hören erst begann!), die kostlosen Bemerkungen zur Musik, die ich aus seinem Munde zu hören das Glück hatte u.s.w.</tei:p><tei:p>Das Wort „Zusammenarbeit" greift also zu weit. Die Richtigstellung war ich <tei:hi rend="italic">Ihnen</tei:hi> schuldig. Gelegentlich mal können auch Sie, je nach dem Gesprächspartner, die Richtigstellung vorbringen, müssen aber nicht. Es war ja nur ein Misverständnis, das sich jederzeit zutragen kann, u. alle Welt weiß, daß ich nicht zu denjenigen zahle, die sich <tei:hi rend="italic">Joachim</tei:hi> oder <tei:hi rend="italic">Brahms</tei:hi> anbiedern, blos weil sie todt sind u. nicht widerlegen können. Wien wimmelt heute von <tei:hi rend="italic">Brahms</tei:hi>-"<tei:hi rend="italic">Freunden</tei:hi>"! Die <tei:hi rend="italic">Meschaërt</tei:hi>[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="messchaert_johannes">Johannes Messchaert</ref>.</tei:note>- <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Angelegentheit stimmt genau.</tei:p><tei:p>Davon abgesehen finde ich Ihren Aufsatz geschickt u. umfassend, <tei:hi rend="italic">gut</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">gruppiert</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8"> <tei:hi rend="italic">gut gruppiert</tei:hi>: Schenker is alluding to the <tei:hi rend="italic">Gruppenbildung</tei:hi>, the putting together of large sections of a cyclic form (e.g. the first, second or closing group of a sonata form) from a variety of contrasting ideas. <tei:hi rend="italic">Gruppenbilding</tei:hi> is an important concept in Schenker's earlier writings, especially the long essay <tei:hi rend="italic">Über den Niedergang der Kompositionskunst</tei:hi> (c.1906-7).</tei:note> u. plastisch einleuchtend. Vielen, vielen Dank! Mit Freude stelle ich fest, daß Sie Ihre Kräfte erproben u. <tei:hi rend="italic">bewähren</tei:hi>.</tei:p><tei:p>Ihre Anregung betreffs des <tei:hi rend="italic">Exampel</tei:hi>buches zu <tei:hi rend="italic">Ph. Em. Bach</tei:hi> finde ich sehr beachtenswert;<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9"> C. P. E. Bach examples: mentioned in Cube's previous letter, OJ 9/34, [13], July 6, 1928, para. 4.</tei:note> ich werde sie mit <tei:hi rend="italic">v. Hoboken</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> durcharbeiten.</tei:p><tei:p>Das 2. Bild von Hammer<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Victor Hammer [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> erbitte ich nach <tei:hi rend="italic">Wien</tei:hi>, aber erst im <tei:hi rend="italic">Oktober</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>Prof. <tei:hi rend="italic">Oppel</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Reinhard Oppel [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> kommt wieder nach Galtür. Schade, wenn Sie wegbleiben müssten.</tei:p><tei:p>Meine Frau, die meine Freude an Ihrer Leistung teilte, grüßt herzlichst, wie grüße auch ich</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] <tei:hi rend="italic">H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated July 13, 1928</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Galtür, July 13, 1928</tei:p><tei:p>My dear Mr. von Cube,</tei:p><tei:p>Now things have gone as you had planned!  The fact that there were just ten in the audience in Düsseldorf does not change things in the slightest. For instance, Dehn<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> had such an audience of ten in Vienna  (I myself had fewer than ten, at times), and Liszt, Ysaÿe<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> and others often enough. Your troubles were rewarded, and you have made great contributions to music in Düsseldorf, however little the people in Duisburg themselves have an idea of them: all contributions look alike, indeed insofar as the profiteers observe nothing for a long time, either in the large or small, regardless of the material. Moreover, the profiteers are unlikely, because of their character, to be the first to rise and offer <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> thanks.</tei:p><tei:p>The two of us do not belong to the profiteers; precisely for this reason I--^merely^ as the guardian of my ideas--thank you, too, as guardian, for the thousandfold efforts for bringing them to light, as man to man, as artist to artist.</tei:p><tei:p>Your essay, like the earlier one, shows a lightly agile way of thinking and writing. The imprecision regarding Joachim<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> and Brahms ("collaboration") is something for which I take responsibility, since you probably had difficulty reading my handwriting.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> I meant merely: with regard to Joachim, he was always my model in matters of performance (I did not know him personally); and with regard to Brahms, his manifestation in general, as the bearer of such a magnificent <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> artistic sum (<tei:hi rend="italic">my first</tei:hi> Brahms symphony was already <tei:hi rend="italic">his third</tei:hi>, which Bülow<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> brought with the Meinigen [Orchestra] to Vienna for its first performance!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> The Brahms peak was already crowned for all eternity when I first began to see him, to hear him!: the priceless remarks on music, which I had the good fortune to hear from his mouth.</tei:p><tei:p>The word "collaboration" is thus an overstatement. To put this right is something I owed <tei:hi rend="italic">to you</tei:hi>. From time to time, of course, you can come up with the right interpretation yourself, depending upon whom you are conversational terms with, but that is not necessary. It was just a misunderstanding that could happen at any time, and everyone knows that I am not reckoned among those who ingratiate myself with Joachim or Brahms simply because they are dead and cannot contradict me.. Vienna is swarming <tei:hi rend="italic">today</tei:hi> with"<tei:hi rend="italic">friends</tei:hi>" of Brahms! <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Your account of the opportunity of working with Messchaert<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> is absolutely correct.</tei:p><tei:p>In spite of this, I find your article attractive and comprehensive, <tei:hi rend="italic">well put together</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> and vividly illuminating. Many, many thanks! I can affirm, with joy, that you are testing and <tei:hi rend="italic">proving</tei:hi> your powers.</tei:p><tei:p>Your proposal regarding the book of music examples for C. P. E. Bach is something I find very commendable.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> I shall go through it with van Hoboken.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/></tei:p><tei:p>Please send the second Hammer<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> portrait to <tei:hi rend="italic">Vienna</tei:hi>, but not until <tei:hi rend="italic">October</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>Professor Oppel<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> is coming again to Galtür. A pity that you could not be there.</tei:p><tei:p>My wife, who shares my joy in what you have accomplished, sends her most affectionate greetings, as also do I.</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H. Schenker</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>