<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:vC 12 : 11-9-27 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2006.
© Translation William Drabkin, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance> Felix-Eberhard von Cube (1927-87)—Heirs of F.-E. von Cube (1987-present day)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: Heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 11/09/1927 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated November 9, 1927</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-06-22</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>S thanks C for the pictures enclosed with OJ 9/34, [9] and expresses pleasure at C's reports of his teaching, composition, listening to the radio, Urlinie studies, and advocacy of good editions; refers to Vrieslander's planned monograph on S, the prospectus for Meisterwerk I and II, and the call [for the Photogrammarchiv].

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Cube, Felix-Eberhard von;   pictures;  Galtür;  teaching;  Urlinie;  Urmutter;  broadcasting;  composition;  Zusammenhang;  coherence;  Vrieslander, Otto;  Meisterwerk in der Musik;  Masterwork in Music;  prospectus;  Aufruf;  call;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  Photogrammarchiv</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated November 9, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Mein lieber Herr von Cube!</tei:p><tei:p>Da haben Sie uns mit Ihrem Geschenk<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> i.e. OJ 9/34, [9], October 29, 1927, with its enclosures, report of C’s teaching of S’s theory, work in composition, membership of the Reichsverband Deutscher Tonkünstler und Musiklehrer, and his recent contact with John Petrie Dunn.</tei:note> eine große, sehr große Freude bereitet, wir danken herzlichst!</tei:p><tei:p>Nicht nur unser Zwie-Satz, sondern auch der Vierstimmen-Satz das allgemeiner <tei:hi rend="italic">chorus</tei:hi> ist <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">unisono</tei:hi></tei:hi> der Meinung, daß Ihr Bildchen die besten sind, die <tei:hi rend="italic">je</tei:hi> von uns angefertigt sind, die ^also^ nicht ausgenommen, die mit Recht seinerzeit als die besten galten. Ihr “Rekord” greift[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] am höchsten. Ein eigener u. freier künstlerischer Wille drängt aus allem hervor, was Sie treiben, u. so auch aus den Bildchen u. Bildern. Vielen Dank für diese Erinnerung der Galtürer Tage!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  In OJ 9/34, [9], C says he has enclosed "two enlargements of portraits I made in Galtür", together with a number of postcards.  See the explanatory footnote to that statement.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Aber eine fast noch größere Freude bereiten Sie mir mit der Schilderung Ihres derzeitiges Standes, der zu besten Hoffnungen berechtigt. Ihre zwei Theorieklassen, denen bald eine dritte zuwachsen wird, Ihre Urlinie-Anweisungen, Ihre Mühen um gute “Ausgaben”, Ihre Sonatenarbeiten, das stille Sich-bilden am Rundfunk (der den Anderen ja nur ein Müßiggangsbehelf ist), Alles das gibt das Bild schönsten Strebens, dem der Lohn gewiß nicht ausbleiben wird.</tei:p><tei:p>Sonate II u. der Vortrag, falls es zu einem solchen kommen sollte, erbitte ich zur An- und Einsicht, (womit zugleich die Ermächtigung gegeben ist, frei von der gesunden Musikleber weg zu sprechen).<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> Cube sent both his piano sonatas to Schenker a couple of years later, detailed commentary on them appears in Schenker’s letter to Cube of August 10, 1929.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Hauptsache bleibt, die jungen Menschenkinder dazu zu verhalten, endlich mit dem <tei:hi rend="italic">wirklichen Notenlesen einen Anfang zu machen</tei:hi>, d.h. <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> sie <tei:hi rend="italic">zumindest zu den “Zügen”</tei:hi> zu führen (wenn sie der letzthintergründigen Urmutter “Urlinie” nicht zu folgen vermögen), als den <tei:hi rend="italic">Trägern eines Zusammenhangs</tei:hi>, wie er in der Sprache durch Satzbau usw. gegeben ist. Daß man erst jetzt, nach mehrhundertjährigem Bestande der Tonkunst, mit dem Lesen anfangen muß, ist die Schande der Menschheit, sie wird nur dadurch entschuldigt, daß die Tonsprache als “Sprache” eben schwieriger als alle anderen Menschen- u. Tiersprachen sind. Daß Sie hiebei aller meiner Verdienste, die ja die ersten sind, -G- “ausdrücklich” gedanken, kommt der Sache nur zugute. Vrieslander arbeitet gegenwärtig, wie er mir sagte, an -zu- einer größeren “<tei:hi rend="italic">Monographie</tei:hi>” über mich,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.   His “monograph” is also mentioned in Schenker’s letter vC 10,  June 1, 1927.  It was never published.</tei:note> das bedeutet einen Stoß in die Verheimlichungsintrigen unserer Kollegen, <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> die ich übrigens ebenfalls entschuldige u. zw. damit, daß sie weder die Musik noch mich verstehen.</tei:p><tei:p>Von <tei:hi rend="italic">Vriesl.</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.   His “monograph” is also mentioned in Schenker’s letter vC 10,  June 1, 1927.  It was never published.</tei:note> erhalten Sie demnächst einen von ihm verfaßten “<tei:hi rend="italic">Prospekt</tei:hi>” zu den Jbüchern I u. II<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>; vols. 1 and 2 came out in 1926 and 1927, a year later than is indicated on the title page. The “prospectus” may be similar to an article by Vrieslander entitled “Heinrich Schenker”, published in the <tei:hi rend="italic">Deutscher Tonkünstler-Zeitung</tei:hi> (March 5, 1928) “on the occasion of the appearance of Yearbook II”.</tei:note> u. dazu ein Briefchen, das ich nicht gelesen habe. Solcher Briefchen schrieb Vr. an 100, an alle “Prominenten” des Reiches, jedem nach seiner Art, u. so hoffe ich, Ihnen ein liebes nach Ihrer lieben Art.</tei:p><tei:p>Ende des Monats erreicht Sie Hobokens “Aufruf”[.]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="aufruf_november_1927">Aufruf</ref>. This was a printed appeal to manuscript collectors and and libraries, the idea being to bring together as many as possible photographic reproductions of autographs by major composers, and house them in a special archive at the Austrian National Library in Vienna. The project was financed by Schenker’s pupil and patron Anthony van Hoboken, himself a collector of autographs and early editions of music: click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note>  Freitag halten wir noch eine Kuratoriumstagung ab, u. dann geht das Werk los.</tei:p><tei:p>Und nun mit herzlichsten Grüßen von mir u. meiner Frau an Sie</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr 
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H Schenker</tei:p><tei:p>Zu dem Neugeborenen wünschen wir dem Elternpaar viel Glück.</tei:p><tei:p>9. 11. 27</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated November 9, 1927</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>My dear Mr. von Cube,</tei:p><tei:p>Your present brought us great—very great—joy; we offer you our most heartfelt thanks.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Not only our strange two-voice counterpoint, but also the four-part harmony is of the <tei:hi rend="italic">unanimous</tei:hi> opinion that your little pictures are the best that have <tei:hi rend="italic">ever</tei:hi> been made of us, ^i.e.^ not excluding those that were rightly regarded in their own time as the best. Your “record” reaches the highest level. An original and free artistic will springs forth from everything that you undertake, and thus also from these smaller and larger pictures. Many thanks for this souvenir of your time in Galtür!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> But I take almost greater pleasure from the account of your present situation, which justifies the highest hopes. Your two theory classes (which will soon grow to three), your studies in the Urlinie, your efforts in support of good “editions,” your composition of sonatas, your quiet self-education at the radio (an object that, of course, makes it easy for others to be lazy): all this gives a picture of the most beautiful striving, which will certainly not go unrewarded.</tei:p><tei:p>Regarding your second sonata and a peformance [of it], should that come to pass: please let me me have a look at it, so that I can study it closely (whereby I may have the authority to speak freely and frankly about them).<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/></tei:p><tei:p>The main thing remains to get the young children of mankind finally to <tei:hi rend="italic">make a start in reading music correctly</tei:hi>, that is <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> to lead them <tei:hi rend="italic">at least to the “linear progressions”</tei:hi> (even if they are unable to follow the “Urlinie” as primeval mother at the very deepest background level), as the <tei:hi rend="italic">bearers of a coherence</tei:hi> of the sort that is granted to speech by means of sentence construction, etc. That only now, after music has been in existence for several hundred years, one must begin with the act of reading is the disgrace of mankind, which can only be excused by the fact that the language of music, as a “language,” is actually more difficult than any other human or animal languages. That you intend in this endeavor “expressly” to make use of all my accomplishments, which are really the first, can only be of benefit to the cause. Vrieslander, so he tells me, is currently working on a rather large “monograph” about me;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> that will be a blow to the secret intrigues on the part of our colleagues, <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> whom I, moreover, likewise excuse, and indeed on the grounds that they understand neither music nor me.</tei:p><tei:p>From Vrieslander<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> you will soon receive a “<tei:hi rend="italic">prospectus</tei:hi>” for Yearbooks I and II,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> together with a short letter that I have not read. Vrieslander writes a hundred such letters, to all “prominent people” of the realm, each tailored to the recipient, and so I hope that has written a dear one to you, too, tailored to your dear character.</tei:p><tei:p>At the end of the month, Hoboken’s “appeal”<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> will reach you. On Friday we are holding a trustees’ conference; then the work will get going.</tei:p><tei:p>And now, with most heartfelt greetings from me and my wife,</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H. Schenker</tei:p><tei:p>[P.S.] We wish the parents of the newborn child much happiness.</tei:p><tei:p>November 9, 1927</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>