<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:vC 21 : 11-20-28 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2006.
© Translation by William Drabkin, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance> Felix-Eberhard von Cube (1928-87)—Heirs of F.-E. von Cube (1987-present day)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: Heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 11/20/1928 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated November 20, 1928</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-07-30</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Sends best wishes for Cologne lecture-series; is planning to issue a folder of Urlinien for use by teachers, and may deposit his handwritten Urlinien in the Photogrammarchiv, which will be officially opened on November [25]. The "counter-examples" are going slowly.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Cube, Felix-Eberhard von;  Köln;  Cologne;  lecture-series;  Urlinie;  folder;  Riemann, Hugo;  Der freie Satz;  Free Composition;  Beethoven;  Eroica;  Erläuterungsausgabe;  Op. 106;  Universal Edition;  UE;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  Photogrammarchiv;   Vrieslander, Otto;  Dahms, Walter;  Oppel, Reinhard;  Kinsky, Georg;  Albersheim, Gerhard;  Gegenbeispiele;  counter-examples</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated November 20, 1928</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Mein lieber Herr <tei:hi rend="italic">von Cube</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>Zum 28ten herzlichsten Wunsch und Segen!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> On November 28, 1928, Cube was to give the first of a series of eight lectures on Schenkerian theory at the Hochschule für Musik in Cologne. </tei:note> Sie greifen wacker aus, nur so weiter! Doch möchte ich auch darüber hinaus ^Ihnen^ ein Wörtchen <tei:hi rend="italic">anvertrauen</tei:hi>, um Sie für die bevorstehende Kämpfe zu stählen:</tei:p><tei:p>Sie mögen sich wohl erinnern, daß ich oft die Überzeugung aussprach, der Weg zur Wahrheit wäre auch Vielen, ja Allen gangbar, wenn ich nur erst die Lehrer aus der[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Verlegenheit-Risse,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> <tei:hi rend="italic">Verlegenheit-Risse</tei:hi>: an example of Schenker’s use of mountaineering terms in a metaphorical sense. <tei:hi rend="italic">Riss</tei:hi> is the term for a crack in a rock, including a large crack in which a limb or entire body can accidentally become caught. (Schenker is using a feminine form of the word, <tei:hi rend="italic">die Risse</tei:hi>, instead of the correct form, <tei:hi rend="italic">der Riß</tei:hi>.)</tei:note> wenn ich durch umfangreiche Veröffentlichungen von Urlinien sie von jeder Angst oder Scham befreite. Ich pflegte auf <tei:hi rend="italic">Riemann</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Hugo Riemann [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> hinzuweisen, der den Lehrern ganze Banquette gab, sie mit Allem versah, so daß sie nur zu greifen u. zu essen hätten. Mir gieng ^es^ aber vor Allem um <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> die erste Andeutung der Urlinie, der Baßchiffren usw. usw. Nun, da der “fr. S.” in Vollendung begriffen ist,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> The near-completion of Schenker’s final published work, <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi>, is a common theme of many letters of the late 1920s.  The work was published Vienna: UE, 1935).  </tei:note> der alle Fragen so gründlich met[h]odisch (in §§) u. so umfangreich löst, ist die Zeit gekommen, die ich auch an meine Url.-Mappen denke.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> This project was initially realized as the <tei:hi rend="italic">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln</tei:hi> or <tei:hi rend="italic">Five Analyses in Sketchform</tei:hi> published in 1932 by Universal Edition (Vienna) and the David Mannes Music School (New York). Further “Urlinie-Mappen” were projected but never realized; some draft analyses from these appeared in <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi>.</tei:note> Noch steht nicht fest, wie viel Urlinien der Beispiel-Band des “fr. S” verschlingen wird, ob nicht zuvor <tei:hi rend="italic">Beeth</tei:hi>’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Eroica</tei:hi> mit Url. als besonderes Bändchen erscheint<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6"> The analysis of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Eroica</tei:hi> Symphony eventually became the centerpiece of the third and final yearbook of the series <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi> (1930).</tei:note> (op. 106 gehört der “<tei:hi rend="italic">U-E</tei:hi>”, muß also ebenfalls besonders mit Url. behandelt werden),<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7"> An <tei:hi rend="italic">Erläuterungsausgabe</tei:hi> of Beethoven’s “Hammerklavier” Sonata, Op. 106, was planned for the 1910s but held up—and eventually abandoned—because the autograph score could not be traced.</tei:note> jedenfalls erwäge ich den Plan, in absehbarer Zeit eine <tei:hi rend="italic">Urlinie-Mappe</tei:hi> (ohne Text) folgen zu lassen, um den Lehrern recht viel <tei:hi rend="italic">Material</tei:hi> in die Hände zu spielen. Auch habe ich H. <tei:hi rend="italic">v. Hoboken</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> mitgeteilt, daß ich, wenn es nicht anders sein könnte, meine Urlinien <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> handschriftlich dem Photogram[m]-Archiv<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="photogrammarchiv">Photogrammarchiv</ref>.</tei:note> übergeben werde, um es unter allen Umständen durchzusetzen, daß Musiker den Weg zu ihnen auf die billigste u. bequemste Weise gehen könnten. Wir wollen sehen, was möglich wird.</tei:p><tei:p>Am 26. [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte:</tei:hi> 25.] wird das Archiv offiziell durch den Minister eröffnet, daran schließt sich eine sog. <tei:hi rend="italic">Schubert</tei:hi>forschertagung mit weiteren Empfängen beim Bundespräsidenten u. Minister.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10"> The name of the Austrian Minister for Education, Richard Schmitz, is frequently mentioned in the foreword to the proceedings of the symposium (see note 16). </tei:note> Trotz dem Verdienst meiner ersten Anregung, sonstiger Förderung in Schrift u. Tat, ^trotz der Kurator-Würde[,]^ trotz allen offiziellen Einladungen, trotz aller Geneigtheit, mich aufs äußerste hoch “auszuzeichnen”, trotz allem halte ich mich von den Dingen gänzlich fern. Ich bleibe zu Hause. Unsere Regierung, unsere Musikerschaft hat zu viel auf dem Gewissen, <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> als daß ich ^auch^ mit ihnen zu ihren Spässen verbünde.  Nur zu dem (übrigens ebenfalls von mir angeregten) <tei:hi rend="italic">Tautenhayn</tei:hi>-Abend<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11"> Tautenhayn was probably a musical presenter for Radio Vienna whose name comes up frequently in the Schenker-Cube correspondence (OJ 9/34, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  Reinhard Oppel, pupil and correspondent of Schenker’s [create biogfile and link].</tei:note>, October 4, 1928), and may have been Carl Tautenhayn, a composer of Viennese popular music (<tei:hi rend="italic">Schrammelmusik</tei:hi>) who was praised by Schenker in his diary (Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker: Nach Tagebüchern</tei:hi>, p.269) . The name E. Tautenhayn appears in the proceedings of the Schubert symposium (see note 10), as the designer of a Schubert medallion which was presented to all participants in the symposium.</tei:note> bei <tei:hi rend="italic">Hob</tei:hi>. gehe ich hin (26.), dort treffe ich noch <tei:hi rend="italic">Vriesl</tei:hi>.,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.</tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Dahms</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  Click on <ref cRef="dahms_walter">Walter Dahms</ref>.</tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Oppel</tei:hi> (Leipzig),<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  Reinhard Oppel, pupil and correspondent of Schenker’s [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Kinsky</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15"> Click on <ref cRef="kinsky_georg">Georg Kinsky</ref>. </tei:note> u.a.  Nur das tue ich.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn16"> Although Schenker did not contribute to the Schubert symposium, he received a copy of the proceedings, a publication that specifically mentions the support of the Photogram Archive: <tei:hi rend="italic">Bericht über den internationalen Kongress for Schubertforschung Wien 25. bis 29. November 1928, veranstaltet mit Unterstützung des Archivs für Photogramme musikalischer Meisterhandschriften an der Musiksammlung der Nationalbibliothek in Wien</tei:hi> (Augsburg: Bennor Filser, 1929). The <tei:hi rend="italic">Bericht</tei:hi> is one of the very few books (other than Schenker’s own) that remained in his <tei:hi rend="italic">Nachlass</tei:hi> (Oster Collection: Books and Pamphlets, 1)</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Der junge <tei:hi rend="italic">Albersheim</tei:hi> hat seine Eltern in Köln von ihrer[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Absicht, sie zu besuchen, verständigt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn17">  Gerhard Albersheim [create biogfile and link].   When Schenker first learned of Cube’s plans to go to Cologne, he asked him to visit the parents of a pupil of his, Gerhard Albersheim, who lived there. See vC 20, October 8, 1928.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Lassen Sie recht bald hören, wie es Ihnen in Köln ergangen ist.</tei:p><tei:p>Die “Gegenbeispiele” müssen <tei:hi rend="italic">langsam</tei:hi> erobert werden! Keinen Snobismus treiben lassen. Zuerst das Gute, dann das Schlechte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn18"> Cube had previously written of his intention to include counter-examples in his Cologne lectures, i.e. examples of (contemporary) works that did not give evidence of the clear  tonal structure that his teacher’s theory insisted upon. Schenker himself had himself done this twice in the recently published second volume of <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi> (dated 1926 but not issued until 1927): an extract from Stravinsky’s Piano Concerto and (in an essay devoted to the work and specifically calling it a “Gegenbeispiel”) Reger’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Variations and Fugue on a theme of Bach</tei:hi>, Op. 81.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Und nun Mut. Alles ist ehrenvoll auf dem Wege, den Sie gehen, jeder Irrtum ist von vornherein entschuldigt.</tei:p><tei:p>Beste Wünsche u. Grüße von uns Beiden</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr 
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H Schenker
20. Nov. 28</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated November 20, 1928</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>My dear Mr. von Cube,</tei:p><tei:p>Most cordial wishes and blessings for the 28th.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> You are making steady progress; keep at it! But, above and beyond this, I should also like to <tei:hi rend="italic">entrust</tei:hi>^ you^ with a few words, to harden you for the struggles that stand before you:</tei:p><tei:p>You may well remember that I often spoke of my conviction that the path to the truth was accessible to many, indeed to everyone, if only I could free the teachers from the fissure of embarrassment,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> of all anxiety or shame, by extensive publications concerning Urlinien. I used to point to Riemann,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> who furnished the teachers with sumptuous banquets, provided them with everything so that all they had to do was to take and to eat. For me, however, what mattered above all was <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> the first notion of the Urlinie, the bass figures, and so on. Now that <tei:hi rend="italic">Free Composition</tei:hi> is essentially complete,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> resolving all questions in such a thorougly methodical way (in numbered sections) and so comprehensively, the time has come in which I am also thinking of a folder of Urlinien.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> It is not yet clear how many Urlinien the volume of music examples can embrace, and whether it should be preceded by [my analysis of] Beethoven’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Eroica</tei:hi> Symphony, with Urlinien, as a separate publication<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/>—the Erläuterungsausgabe of Beethoven’s Op. 106 belongs to Universal Edition, and must likewise be treated in a special way, with Urlinien<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>—in any event I am contemplating the plan of issuing a <tei:hi rend="italic">folder of Urlinien</tei:hi> (without text), to provide teachers with a quite substantial amount of material. I have also communicated to Mr. van Hoboken<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> that, if things cannot be done any other way, I would entrust my Urlinien <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> in handwritten form to the Photogram Archive,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> so that I might insist that, in all circumstances, musicians can have access to them in the cheapest and most convenient way possible. We shall see what is possible.</tei:p><tei:p>On the 26th [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte:</tei:hi> 25th], the Archive will be officially opened by the Minister; this will be followed by a kind of symposium for Schubert scholars, with further receptions given by the the President of the Republic and the Minister.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> In spite of the services I have given through my very early involvement, and by promoting [the Archive] in word and deed, ^in spite of a curator’s dignity,^ in spite of all official invitations, in spite of all inclination to “distinguish” myself as highly as possible, in spite of everything I shall firmly keep my distance from these things. I shall stay at home. Our government and our musical profession have too much on their conscience <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> that I should ^also^ join with them in their amusements. I shall only take part in the evening with Tautenhayn<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> at Hoboken’s (which, moreover, I likewise promoted) on the 26th; there I shall meet up with Vrieslander,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> Dahms,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> Oppel (from Leipzig),<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/> Kinsky,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn15"/> and others. That is all that I shall do.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn16"/></tei:p><tei:p>Young Albersheim has notified his parents of your intention to visit them in Cologne.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn17"/></tei:p><tei:p>Let me know very soon how things went for you in Cologne.</tei:p><tei:p>The “counter-examples” must be conquered <tei:hi rend="italic">slowly</tei:hi>! Do not allow yourself to practise any snobbery. First that which is good, then the bad.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn18"/></tei:p><tei:p>And now: take heart. Everything along the path that you take is honorable; every mistake is excused in advance.</tei:p><tei:p>Best wishes and greetings from the two of us</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Heinrich Schenker
November 20, 1928</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>