<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:vC 22 : April 1929 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2006.
© Translation William Drabkin, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance> Felix-Eberhard von Cube (1929-87)—Heirs of F.-E. von Cube (1987-present day)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: Heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 04/10/1929 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, date not visible (April 1929)</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-08-01</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>S expresses pleasure at what C has sent him in OJ 9/34, [16] and [17], and offers advice and a warning: ordinary people are not interested in beauty in art, but look for quick, easy judgments.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Cube, Felix-Eberhard von;  programme;  critical notices;  reviews;  opposition;  Reger;  Hindemith;  Wagner;  Sauerbrey, Edith</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, date not visible (April 1929)</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Lieber Herr (Professor) <tei:hi rend="italic">von Cube</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>Eine reizende Überraschung war das!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  From the postscript to this letter, it is evident that Schenker was replying to both of Cube’s recent letters, OJ 9/34, [16] and [17], March 26 and April 5, and probably very soon after receiving the second of them.</tei:note>   Der Programm,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> The programme of music by Duisburg composers.</tei:note> die Kritiken,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> The newspaper reviews of the concert; only one of these was found among Cube’s letters to Schenker.</tei:note> die Bilderchen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> Pencil caricatures of Dr Eduard Kreuzhagen and Alfred Ahrens, Cube’s colleagues in Duisburg, drawn at the start of Cube’s letter OJ 9/34. [16], March 26, 1929.</tei:note> u. das Briefchen, kurz: ein sehr heiteres Beruf-Stilleben im Briefumschlag. Nur so weiter!</tei:p><tei:p>Die Kritiken finde ich ja sehr gut, auch Sie dürfen damit sehr zufrieden sein.  Erfreulich ist auch Ihr Erfolg in Köln zu nennen. An den Widerstand ist die Sache (auch ich in ihrem Namen) gewohnt aber sie <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> schreitet darüber hinweg u. fort. Die Menschen, verankert in Schlafen, Essen u. Zeugen, wollen die unangestrengt angenehme Art, mit der sie diese Triebe der Natur erledigen, auch auf die künstlichen Produkte des Geistes (Kunst, Wissenschaft, ja sogar die sozialen u. politischen Gebilde) übertragen: wie sie ohne Vorbildung u. Vorgreifung schlafen, essen u. zeugen, genau so wollen sie ohne Vorschule auch auf dem Gebiete des Geistes sich tummeln. Aber eine Komposition ist doch noch etwas anderes als der Geschlechtsakt: dort liegt die Sache doch schwieriger als hier. Namentlich die Musik wird in die “Gefühle” herabgezogen, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> als wäre sie ein Naturprodukt.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich sage das zur Warnung: Aus Ihrem Schreiben geht nämlich hervor, daß Ihre Zuhörer offenbar auch Ihnen die übliche Falle gelegt haben. Mit der oben dargestellten Art der Menschen hängt es zusammen, daß sie nicht so sehr die Wahrheit u. Schönheit der Kunst suchen, als ein in kürzester Form u. ^auf^ leichtfassliche Weise geprägtes “Urteil” über den oder jenen Komponisten, dies oder jenes Werk.  Worin ist zB <tei:hi rend="italic">Reger</tei:hi> oder Wagner schlechter als die grossen Meister, fragen sie ^schon^ in der 2. Minute der Unterhaltung, kaum daß sie das erste Wort von einem Hintergrund, ^der^ Url., einem Zug gehört haben. Nichts von alldem interessiert <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> sie; nur die Frage, ob <tei:hi rend="italic">Reger</tei:hi> schlechter ist. Die Enscheidung über den Wert ist ihnen das Wesentliche. Zuletzt ist das eine Machtfrage: hinter <tei:hi rend="italic">Reger</tei:hi> stehen heute noch Tausende, Millionen von Menschen(eseln), ich aber stehe noch schlank da – also stoßen heute die Menschen lieber noch, sozusagen in Eile, zu der großen Herde als zu mir. Außerdem sind Sie selbst ja noch so jung, stellen somit für Ihre Zuhörer nicht einmal noch eine “<tei:hi rend="italic">physische</tei:hi> Macht” vor, die sie beugte!  In Hamburg wollten die Zuhörer ebenso etwas von <tei:hi rend="italic">Reger</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Hindemith</tei:hi> hören, u. ^auch^ ich würde so lange (auch von Furtwängler<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Wilhelm Furtwängler [create biogfile and link].</tei:note>) wegen <tei:hi rend="italic">Regers[</tei:hi>] und Wagners gequält, – ich werde davon reden, wenn ich es an der Zeit halte, u. Ihnen rate ich, solchen  Gelüsten  sowenig</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in upper margin, inverted:[</tei:hi>] 
als möglich nachzugeben: zunächst einmal sollen die Leute die Grundbegriffe lernen, dann . .  Von mir u. meiner Frau beste Wünsche u. Grüße</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr 
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ]<tei:hi rend="italic"> H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">p.1 upper margin:[</tei:hi>]
Die Adresse des Frl. S.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6"> Edith Sauerbrey, mentioned in Cube’s letter OJ 9/34, [17], April 5, 1929, a music student in Duisburg who was intending to meet Schenker during a three-week trip to Vienna. </tei:note> werde ich Ihnen bekanntgeben, sobald sie erscheint.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, date not visible (April 1929)</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Mr. (Professor) von Cube,</tei:p><tei:p>What a delightful surprise!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> The programme,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> the critical notices<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> the drawings<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> and your nice letter: in short, a very agreeable still-life of the profession inside an envelope. Keep at it!</tei:p><tei:p>The critical notices I found very good; and you, too, ought to be very satisfied with them. Success in Cologne must also be numbered among your joys. The cause (and I, in its name) is accustomed to encountering opposition, but it <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> strides above it and goes its own way. Ordinary people, anchored as they are in sleeping, eating and procreating, want to transfer the agreeable manner in which they despatch these drives of nature also to the artistic products of the intellect (art, science, indeed even the social and political structures); just as they sleep, eat and procreate without prior training or attention, so also in the realm of the intellect they wish to splash about, without prior education. (But a musical composition is something very different from the sex act: in the former, the matter is indeed more difficult.) Specifically, music is dragged down to the level of feelings, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> as if it were a product of nature.</tei:p><tei:p>I am saying this by way of warning. From what you have written, it is clear that your listeners have evidently set the usual trap for you, too. The type of person that I have described above is disposed not so much to look for truth and beauty in art but rather to imprint a “judgment,” in the shortest terms and in the most easily graspable way, of this or that composer, or this or that work. In what respect Reger or Wagner, for example, is worse than the great masters is something they will ask already in the second minute of the discussion, hardly having heard the first thing about a background layer, the Urlinie, or a linear progression. None of all this is of any interest to <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> them; only the question of whether Reger is worse. Determining the value of something is the crucial thing for them. In the end it is a question of power: today Reger still has the support of thousands, even millions of people(-asses), but my support is still thin. Today, then, the people would rather meet up—in haste, so to speak—with the great herd than with me.  Moreover, you yourself are still so very young, and thus do not even represent a “<tei:hi rend="italic">physical</tei:hi> force” that would bend them!</tei:p><tei:p>In Hamburg the listeners likewise want to hear something about Reger, Hindemith; and I ^too^ have been pestered for a long time (even by Furtwängler<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>) about Reger and Wagner; I shall speak about this when time permits, and I advise you to give in to such cravings as little [<tei:hi rend="italic">in upper margin, inverted:</tei:hi>] as possible. First, people should learn the basic principles; then . . .</tei:p><tei:p>From me and my wife best wishes and greetings.</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H .Schenker</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">p.1 upper margin:</tei:hi>]
I shall give you the address of Miss S.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> as soon as she appears.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>