<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:vC 23 : 5-15-29 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2006.
© Translated by William Drabkin, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance> Felix-Eberhard von Cube (1929-87) - -Heirs of F.-E. von Cube (1987-present day)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: Heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 05/15/1929 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated May 15, 1929</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-08-03</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Gerhard Albersheim will leave a space in S's calendar that S offers to Erich Voss; will teach him himself because Weisse may not be up to date with Der freie Satz; Voss to contact him.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Cube, Felix-Eberhard von;  Albersheim, Gerhard;  Voss, Erich;  Weisse, Hans;  Vrieslander, Otto;  Köln;  Cologne Der freie Satz;  Free Composition</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated May 15, 1929</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Lieber Herr <tei:hi rend="italic">von Cube</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>Es fügt sich, daß H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Albersheim</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> Gerhard Albersheim, a pupil of Schenker's in the late 1920s. See Schenker's postcard, vC 20, October 8, 1928, note.  [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> nach eifrigstem 3-jährigem Studium (à 12 Stunden monatlich) heiratet (!) (was <tei:hi rend="italic">er</tei:hi> sich schon in so jungen Jahren zu tun wohl erlauben darf), ^zwar in^ Wien bleibt, aber voraussichtlich die stramme Disziplin als junger Ehemann nicht mehr wird mitmachen können, daß ich also für Ihren Hörer H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Emil</tei:hi> [<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">Voss</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> In OJ 9/34, May 14, Cube mentioned that an Erich (not Emil) Voss, who had attend his lectures in Cologne, expressed an interest in studying with Schenker in Vienna.</tei:note> Platz gewinne, ohne mir u. den anderen Herren u. Damen besondere Gewalt anzutun. Es wäre mir aber sehr <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> lieb, wenn H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Voss</tei:hi> sich ehebaldigst mit mir in Verbindung setzte, damit ich, wie immer, die Einteilung des nächsten Kurses zum Voraus treffen kann. Und wenn ich Wert darauf lege, daß H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Voss</tei:hi> nicht erst zu. D^r^ <tei:hi rend="italic">Weisse</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.</tei:note> geht, so hängt das damit zusammen, was Sie öfter von mir gehört haben, daß ich gern selbst den Jünger als Erster einführe, um ihm Irrtümer zu ersparen, u. daß bei D^r^ <tei:hi rend="italic">Weisse</tei:hi> die Gefahr besteht, daß er ja gegenüber dem "fr. Satz" im Rückstande ist u. also H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Voss</tei:hi> den wesentlichsten Dienst nicht leisten könnte. (Etwas ähnliches ereignete sich in Ihrem Leben mit H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Vrieslander</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Click on <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref>.</tei:note> den Sie mit ihren [<tei:hi rend="italic">recte:</tei:hi> Ihren]  Kentnissen schließlich <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> überholt haben.)</tei:p><tei:p>H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Voss</tei:hi> habe nur keinen Angst vor mir u. meiner Lehre, der Begriff von "Vorbereitung" u. "Assistent" ist mir völlig fremd u. widerstrebt auch die Sache. Ihren Anfang u. ^ihr^ Ende wickele ich am liebsten selbst aus.  Jede Disziplin begleite ich gern mit Anmerkungen, die in das Ganze gehen.</tei:p><tei:p>Und besonders heiter wäre es, wenn wieder ein Köllner dem Kölner den Platz übergäbe.</tei:p><tei:p>Wie Sie sehen, schreibe ich postwendend, um für beide Teile, für mich u. H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Voss</tei:hi> die besondere Gunst des Zufalls <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> fristbar zu machen.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit besten Grüßen an Sie von mir u. meiner Frau</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H Schenker</tei:p><tei:p>Prof D^r.^ <tei:hi rend="italic">Reinhard Oppel</tei:hi> (Theorieprof. in <tei:hi rend="italic">Leipzig</tei:hi> u. Kiel) hielt kürzlich im Tonkünstlerverein <tei:hi rend="italic">Halle</tei:hi> einen Vortrag über "<tei:hi rend="italic">Bach-Schenker</tei:hi>" ebenfalls mit Zugrundelegung von Urlinien.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> Click on <ref cRef="oppel_reinhard">Reinhard Oppel</ref>.  Oppel's early attention to the analysis of Bach is consistent with his interest in the Baroque period in general, and figure-bass harmony.  [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> Er geht wieder hin; eröffnet sogar Kurse.</tei:p><tei:p>15.5.29</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated May 15, 1929</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Mr. von Cube,</tei:p><tei:p>It turns out that Mr. Albersheim,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> after a most intensive three-year period of study (at twelve lessons per month), is getting married(!)--something that <tei:hi rend="italic">he</tei:hi>, being so very young in years, may surely allow himself to do. He will ^at any rate^ remain ^in^ Vienna, but for the time being will not, as a young husband, be able to carry on with the strict discipline. Thus I am gaining space for your auditor Erich Voss,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> without upsetting things very much for myself and the other gentlemen and ladies. I would be very grateful, however, <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> if Mr. Voss would get in touch with me at the earliest opportunity, so that I can, as always, plan the next course of lessons ahead of time. And if I set store on Mr. Voss not going first to Dr. Weisse,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> that has to do with the fact that, as you have often heard me say, I would like to be the first introduce the beginner, to spare him mistakes, and that with Dr. Weisse there is the danger that he is not up to date with respect to <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi> and thus cannot offer Mr. Voss the most essential service. (Something similar happened in your life with Mr. Vrieslander,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> whom you have, in the end, overtaken in your knowledge of things.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Mr. Voss need have no fear of me and my theory; the concepts of "preparation" and "assistant" are thoroughly alien to me and also contradict the subject matter, whose beginning and end I prefer most of all to develop myself.  I prefer to accompany each discipline with observations that lead toward the whole.</tei:p><tei:p>And it will be a special joy if someone from Cologne gave his place to another person from the same city.</tei:p><tei:p>As you can see, I am writing by return of post, so that for both parties, myself and Mr. Voss, this special blessing of fortune {4} may become a reality.</tei:p><tei:p>With best greetings to you from me and my wife,</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H. Schenker</tei:p><tei:p>[P.S.:] Prof. Dr. Reinhard Oppel (professor of theory at [the] Leipzig [Conservatory] and [the University of] Kiel) recently gave a lecture to the Society of Musicians in Halle on "Bach-Schenker," likewise underpinned by Urlinie [graphs].<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> He will be returning there, even setting up courses.</tei:p><tei:p>May 15, 1929</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>