<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:vC 27 : 8-10-29 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2006.
© Translation William Drabkin, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance> Felix-Eberhard von Cube (1929-87) - -Heirs of F.-E. von Cube (1987-present day)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: Heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 08/10/1929 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated August 10, 1929</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-10-14</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>S reponds, on information from Reinhard Oppel, to C's question in OJ 9/34, [19] about finding a publisher; advises C to seek friends who will play his music, after which publication should ensue.  - -S gives detailed comments, with music examples, on C's two piano sonatas, praising them highly and making suggestions for improvement.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Cube, Felix-Eberhard von;  Oppel, Reinhard;  Schulze-Prisca String Quartet;  Pauer, Max;  Peters;  Breitkopf &amp; Härtel;  Zilcher, Hermann;  Altmann, Wilhelm;   Preussische Staatsbibliothek Berlin;  Hindemith;  Krenek;  Hertzka, Emil;  Weisse, Hans;  Simrock;  Universal Edition;  UE;  Chopin;  Schubert;  Beethoven;  Schusterfleck;  Parallelismus;  Thema;  theme;  Melodie;  melody;  Sonatenform;  sonata form;  glockenspiel</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Galtür</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated August 10, 1929</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Mein lieber Prof. <tei:hi rend="italic">v. Cube</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>Zunächst die verleger-technische Angelegenheit, die Sie begreiflicherweise heute am meisten interessiert.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  This is in response to OJ 9/34, [19], July 18, 1934, fourth paragraph.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ich sprach mit Prof. <tei:hi rend="italic">Oppel</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Reinhard Oppel [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> ^über die Verhältnisse^ in Deutschland.  Er erzählte: <tei:hi rend="italic">Nach einer Aufführung</tei:hi> seines jüngsten Streichquartettes durch Schulze-Prisca<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  The Cologne-based Schulze-Prisca Quartet (Walter Schulze-Prisca, vln I, Will Smit, vln II, Eugen Körner, vla, Hans Münch-Holland, vcl), which had premiered Oppel's Fourth String Quartet in F minor at the Leipzig Conservatory on January 7, 1928, Oppel's last work in that genre.  (Information supplied by Timothy Jackson.)</tei:note> schrieb Dir. <tei:hi rend="italic">Pauer</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> Probably Max Pauer (1866-1945), piano teacher at the Stuttgart Conservatory. </tei:note> an <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Peters</tei:hi></tei:hi> wegen der Drucklegung; <tei:hi rend="italic">Peters</tei:hi> hat sich dem Konservat.-Direktor bequemt, <tei:hi rend="italic">Oppel</tei:hi> aber ging honorierlos aus.  Bei <tei:hi rend="italic">Br. &amp; H.</tei:hi> ist, wie Sie wissen, <tei:hi rend="italic">Zilcher</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> Probably Hermann Zilcher (1881-1948), German composer and pianist: from 1908 on he was professor of piano at the Akademie für Tonkunst in Munich, from 1920 to 1944 Director at the Bayerisches Staatskonservatorium in Würzburg.  He took on Cube as a piano pupil at the age of 10 (in 1913). When and why Zilcher and Cube fell out is not clear; Cube may have explained this to Schenker in person, possibly when he came to Vienna in 1923 to have lessons with him.</tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Lector</tei:hi> (mit fixem Gehalt), doch zu ihm ist ja Ihr Weg verrammelt, nicht? Auch würde er sich bei diesen <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Stücken, wie ich befürchten muß, zu einem beifälligem Gutachten kaum verstehen, so fremd muß ihm die Art der Inhaltsführung sein. Von Dir. <tei:hi rend="italic">Prof. Dr. Altmann</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Wilhelm Altmann (1862-1951), retired Director of the Music Division of the Prussian State Library (1915-27) in Berlin. The editor of many miniature scores. Altmann was also a keen supporter of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Erläuterungsausgabe</tei:hi>, and wrote a favorable review of the first <tei:hi rend="italic">Tonwille</tei:hi> pamphlet. See OJ 5/18, 55, September 13, 1934.</tei:note> dem alten Direktor der Preussischen Staatsbibl. Berlin, hörte ich u. las ich öfter, die deutscher Verleger könnten sich solch ein Luxus nicht mehr gönnen, die Komponisten müssten sich an den Druckkosten zumindest beteiligen usw. usw. Hindemit[h] geht gar +nicht+, Krenek<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="krenek_ernst">Ernst Krenek</ref>.  </tei:note> auch +nicht+, das -sich- sind öffentliche Geheimnisse.</tei:p><tei:p>Wohl aber weiß ich von Dir. <tei:hi rend="italic">Hertzka</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Emil Hertzka, Director of Universal Edition 1907-32, with whom Schenker had had difficult relations from the late 1900s through to the complete break in 1924, when Schenker transferred to the Drei Masken Verlag, Munich.</tei:note> worauf er (u. wohl auch jeder andere Verleger) seinen Entscheidung stützt: er forscht nach den Beziehungen des Komponisten, er drückt, ohne mit der Wimper zu zucken, sobald er merkt, daß so[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] eine <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> organisierte Partei (wie heute die der Antimusiker) steht oder eine gesellschaftliche <tei:hi rend="italic">Clique</tei:hi>, die den Verkauf von 50-80 <tei:hi rend="italic">Ex.</tei:hi> als sicher annehmen läßt. So hat Dr <tei:hi rend="italic">Weisse</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.</tei:note> für seine Gesangsquartette mit Klv.-Bgl. Hertzka 200 Subscribenten angeboten, worauf H. meinte: "100 sind auch genug, u. da erhalten Sie noch 10% Tant."</tei:p><tei:p>Wenn Sie also den Weg einer Beteiligung an den Druckkosten oder der Subscript. nicht gehen wollen, - meine Empfehlung sagt den heutigen Verlegern nichts, die noch immer, ^durch den "Fortschritts"befehl hypnotisiert^, an das Kapitalwunder der "neuen", "fortschrittlichen" Musik glauben, u. eher eine atonale Komp. drucken, ehe sie eine Kunstgenüße aufnehmen [<tei:hi rend="italic">Weisse</tei:hi> weiß da ein Liedchen von Simrock (!) zu erzählen]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Square brackets in original. --The exclamation mark beside the name of Simrock presumably refers to the firm's close association with Brahms, who was for Schenker the last German master (i.e. the last "modern" composer of artistic merit).</tei:note> - so würde ich Ihnen den Rat geben:</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Betrachten Sie die Welt dieser Tage als <tei:hi rend="italic">tabula rasa</tei:hi>, lange kann es ^ohnehin^ nicht mehr dauern, daß ein Ruckschlag kommt, u. in dieser Zwischenzeit suchen Sie Freunde Ihrer Stücke zu erwerben, die Ihre Stücke auch +spielen+: erreichen Sie das, so stellen sich endlich auch die Verleger u. Kritiker als die 100<tei:hi rend="italic">1</tei:hi>ten oder 566ten ein, nur die wirklich Ersten zu sein, das geht über  -ihren- ^den^ Horizont ihres Geistes, folglich auch der Brieftasche.  Erneuere ich meine Beziehung zur "<tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">U.E.</tei:hi></tei:hi>" (Anfang 1930),<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Schenker did not write to Hertzka himself between  May 21, 1924 (WSLB 328) and November 27, 1928 (WSLB 400).  During the intervening time, there was much correspondence, but it was addressed to UE impersonally, or to the Administrative Director Hugo Winter or editorial subordinates.  Reciprocating, Hertzka did not write to him between December 5, 1924 (OC 52/608) and December 21, 1928 (OC 52/847), letters at that time coming either from the administration or from Hertzka's assistants, Barbara Rothe and Alfred Kalmus.  Correspondence between them resumed on November 27, 1928, and continued until November 1, 1931, Hertzka dying in 1932, hence Schenker's "at the start of 1930" is somewhat anomalous.</tei:note> so werde ich selbstverständlich für Sie eintreten. Indessen bitte ich, wie gesagt, fortzufahren in der Komposition, <tei:hi rend="italic">nicht rasten!</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  <tei:hi rend="italic">nicht rasten!</tei:hi>:  double-underlined.</tei:note> . .</tei:p><tei:p>Hiemit moduliere ich zum künsterlischen Teil.</tei:p><tei:p>Zunächst danke ich herzlichst für Ihre frdl. Absicht[,] mir Ihr erstes Werk zu schenken.  Darüber <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> bin ich umso mehr erfreut, als es die Perle beider Sonaten<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  i.e. the two piano sonatas enclosed with Cube's letter OJ 9/34, [19], July 18, 1929, and already acknowledged in vC 26, July 22, 1929.</tei:note> enthält, u. zw. das Rondo„thema" in As. Überaus lieblich, poetisch, +gesättigt+ mit +Kunstgeist+ (<tei:hi rend="italic">überlegen</tei:hi> Sie, ob in T. 2 das 4. Achtel es oder f sein sollte, wegen</tei:p><tei:p>&lt;span class="mt-enclosure mt-enclosure-image" style="display: inline;"&gt;&lt;img alt="vC27p5image1&amp;amp;2 ger.PNG" src="http://mt.ccnmtl.columbia.edu/schenker/images/cube/vC27p5image1%262%20ger.PNG" width="213" height="57" class="mt-image-center" style="text-align: center; display: block; margin: 0 auto 20px;" /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</tei:p><tei:p>stellt das „Thema" das Ideal einer Erfindung vor, die nicht „Melodie" im allgemeinen Unverstande ist, dennoch aber singender ist, als die gewisse Melodie, u. für die Sonatenform, ich meine auch ^für^ ein Rondo als Teil einer Sonate, vorzüglichste Eignung besizt.  Schon um dieser Noten willen müssten ein Verleger danken u. zahlen - doch das hatte immer seine weiten Wege u. hat es immer noch.  Vorläufig Nebensache auch.  Vorzüglich im Rondo auch +Anschluß+ System 6, +Vorbereitung+ +u.+ +Fortsetzung+ System 8 (hier gienge auch die Balkung</tei:p><tei:p>&lt;span class="mt-enclosure mt-enclosure-image" style="display: inline;"&gt;&lt;img alt="vC27p5image3.PNG" src="http://mt.ccnmtl.columbia.edu/schenker/image/cube/vC27p5image3.PNG" width="95" height="49" class="mt-image-center" style="text-align: center; display: block; margin: 0 auto 20px;" /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</tei:p><tei:p>zu je 4 Achteln), wiederum alles auf wünschenswerteste +sonatenhaft+ glücklich, löblich, ja sehr löblich die Kürze des Es. Schon mit diesem Wenigen <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> will ich Ihnen herzlichst Beifall spenden zu der ersten Formgebung im höheren Sinne der Sonatenform, der nicht einmal „Themen" oder „Melodien" von <tei:hi rend="italic">Chopin</tei:hi>, Schubert usw. willkommen sind, wenn sie so aussehen wie die in den beiden Sonaten von <tei:hi rend="italic">Chop.</tei:hi> u. so manche bei Schubert.  Pflegen Sie also mit aller Ihren verfügbaren Energie die Leichtigkeit u. Unbefangenheit Ihrer Hervorbringungen immer ^nur^ nach +dieser+ +Richtung+ hin, es wird immer mehr lohnen.  S. X (Forts. des Rondo): preludierenhafte Einführung des Gegensatzes (errinnert an den Gegensatz in B's op. 26, Rondo, +macht+ <tei:hi rend="italic">nichts</tei:hi>!), erläutert durch den Parallelismus (IX ob.), ^ist ein^ guter Einfall zur <tei:hi rend="italic">Form</tei:hi>.  Die Lagerung der Dinge auf XI ist nicht durchsichtig genug, zierlich so manches aber (System 2), hübsch auch die Dim. von Syst. 4 ab. Usw. usw.</tei:p><tei:p>Nun zurück zum III Satz: ein solcherart improvisierende Satz kann (<tei:hi rend="italic">muß</tei:hi> +auch+ +vielleicht+, je nach dem Stoff) auf eine Wdh. +verzichten+, er kann improv.^isatorisch^ <tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> fortgehen, kurz, nur -zur- ^der^ +Überleitung+ zum letzten Satz ^dienen^, zumal wenn wie hier die +Eröffnung+ auf einem Kunstgriff (=V) beruht; jedenfalls sind ^dann^ die Parallelismen von kürzerem Umfange, keinesfalls so breit ^wie hier^ = a&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;-a&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, da durch diese Form die Improv.ungen gestraft wird.  Schön aber Ihr "Mut" -VI- VII Syst. 3-5, niederzuschreiben, so etwas muß +immer+ seine Wirkung behalten, mag sich Mode, Aufgeblasenheit zeitweilig noch so sehr dagegen sträuben.</tei:p><tei:p>Son. II, S. I: die +Absicht+ auf die +Form+ deutlich u <tei:hi rend="italic">richtig</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  <tei:hi rend="italic">richtig</tei:hi>:  double-underlined.</tei:note> der Dim.-Stoff tritt, wenn man so sprechen dar, zurück, einmal gelangt er besser, das andermal ^(wie hier)^ weniger gut.  In der Mdp. +nicht+ <tei:hi rend="italic">Wdh</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn15">  i.e. <tei:hi rend="italic">Modulationspartie nicht Wiederholungen</tei:hi>.</tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">häufen</tei:hi>: [ge]schmiedig[?] überqueren mit kräftig geschnittenem Baßgang, mit den einzelnen ^Klängen des Baßganges^ kann eher die Dim. +wechseln+, die Führung[?] des Basses^, von der Linie der Oberst. abgesehen,^ trägt auch den Wechsel.  Glücklich II System  2-4 ("Glockenspiel"?). Überflüssige Längen meiden!  Lieber kurz, charakteristisch, redend, spielend.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> (II Satz): +Notierung+: VI, Syst. 2 von unten, T. 3 u. 4. ausbessern. S. VII: die Verkleinerung von T. 1-2 +gut+, hält die Beziehung fest. (III. Satz): Anfang +famos+, voll +bester Laune+ in den Umkehrungen u. im Oktavenwechsel. S. IX, S. 5-6 u. an anderen Stellen Notierung +erleichtern+ durch Umschreibung! Was ist es mit ^dem^ Übergang von X [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] zu XI?  Was gilt?  In diesem Satz nun vieles noch zu +kürzen+, wie denn überhaupt so <tei:hi rend="italic">manches in beiden Stücken zu schleifen wäre</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>Doch auf alles das kommt es mir im Augenblick gar nicht an, nur auf den +Sonatenhabitus+, auf die Befähigung, Musik nicht in Melodiechen, nicht in Periodisierungen zu atmen, was alles in Tänzen, Opern, Potpourris gehört, - u. diese Befähigung +finde ich bei Ihnen+ u. empfehle Ihnen, sei trotz dem entgegenstehenden ^Zeitgeist^ zu pflegen.  Namentlich nehmen Sie sich bei den +Wdh. der Dim.+ in Acht, -was- ^die^ man ehemals "Schusterfleck" nannte: Nur was sein muß, als notwendigster Parallelismus, lehren Sie eigens daraufhin die Meisterwerke!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{9}</tei:hi> Noch ein Wort zu Ihrem u. meinem Schutze:</tei:p><tei:p>Sollte Jemand meine +Anerkennung+ ^für Sie^ vielleicht im Widerspruche finden zu den Mängeln, die ich andeute, so lachen Sie ihm ins Gesicht u. sagen Sie ihm in meinem Namen: "Suchen Sie zuerst die Meister zu verstehen, die Inhaltsfühurng in einer Sonate (Sinf. usw) überhaupt), dann -verstehen- würden Sie auch zu +loben+ +wissen+, was lobenswert ist."  Ich kann Sie im Grunde nicht hoch genug loben.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{10}</tei:hi> Für so manchen im Geiste der Sonatenform wirklich gelungenen Zug, so musste nun derjenige, der über mein Urteil zu urteilen sich anmaßen möchte, mit mir wissen, um was für schwierigen Dinge es da geht.</tei:p><tei:p>Sollten Sie einen Kopisten haben u. es einmal der Mühe wert finden, die Stücke so [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg. word</tei:hi>] kopieren zu lassen, so würde es mich freuen, eine solche Kopie zu besitzen.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit dem recht Tiroler'schen <tei:hi rend="bold">{11}</tei:hi> "Zeit lassen", mit besten Grüßen von mir u. meinem Lie-Liechen <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn16">  Schenker's affectionate name for his wife, &lt; href="../../../profile/person/schenker_jeanette.html"&gt;Jeanette Schenker&lt;/a&gt;, </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] <tei:hi rend="italic">H Schenker</tei:hi>
Galtür, 10. Aug. 29</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated August 10, 1929</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>My dear Professor von Cube,</tei:p><tei:p>To begin with, the technical matter concerning publication, which will understandably interest you most these days.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>I spoke with Professor Oppel<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> ^about conditions^ in Germany. He recounted that, +after a performance+ of his most recent string quartet by Schulze-Prisca,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> Director Pauer<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> wrote to +Peters+ concerning publication. Peters condescended to the director of the Conservatory; but Oppel came out of this without any honorarium.  At Breitkopf &amp; Härtel, as you know, Zilcher<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> is the lector (on a fixed salary); if I am not mistaken, however, your path to him is blocked.  With regard to these <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> pieces, he too, I fear, would hardly be well disposed to a favourable reference, given the way in which the material is developed.  From Professor Dr. Altmann,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> the venerable director of the Prussian State Library in Berlin, I have often heard and read that the German publishers cannot afford such a luxury; composers ought to contribute at least a part of the printing costs, etc. etc. This applies +no less+ to Hindemith and Krenek<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>; these are well-known secrets.</tei:p><tei:p>But I know quite well about Director Hertzka,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> the way in which he (and probably every other publisher) bases his decision: he will publish, without batting an eyelash, as soon as he sees that there exists an <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> organized society (like that of the anti-musicians of today), or a social clique, which can be counted upon for the sale of between fifty and eighty copies. Thus, Dr Weisse<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> offered 200 subscribers for his vocal quartets with piano accompaniment, upon which Hertzka replied: "a hundred will, in fact, suffice, and you will also receive a royalty payment of 10%."</tei:p><tei:p>If, as it seems, you do not wish to take the path of contributing to the printing costs or organizing a subscription--my recommendation would say nothing to today's publishers, who still ^, hypnotized by the demand for "progress,"^ continue to believe in the economic miracle of "new," "progressive" music, and would rather print an atonal composition than take on the good things of art.  [Weisse could sing us a pretty song about Simrock (!) in this regard.]<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/>--then I would offer you the following advice:</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Consider the world of today as <tei:hi rend="italic">tabula rasa</tei:hi>--it can ^at any rate^ not be much longer before a reversal of fortune comes, and in this meantime seek to gain friends for your works, who will also +play+ your works: if you achieve this, then in the end even the publishers and critics will line up, as the 100<tei:hi rend="italic">1</tei:hi>st or 566th,  to be the real first;  that goes beyond the horizon of their intellect, and consequently of their briefcases, too.  If I renew my relationship with +Universal Edition+ (at the start of 1930),<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> then I shall certainly intervene on your behalf.  In the meantime, I ask you, as I've said, to continue to compose, <tei:hi rend="italic">do not stop</tei:hi>!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> . .</tei:p><tei:p>With this, I modulate to the artistic part of my letter.</tei:p><tei:p>First I thank you for your kindly intention to dedicate your first work to me.  For this <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> I am all the more pleased, since it contains the pearl of the two sonatas,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> namely, the Rondo "theme" in A flat. Thoroughly delightful, poetic, +saturated+ with +artistic spirit+.  You might, however,  +consider+ whether, for sake of parallelism, the fourth eighth-note in bar 2 should be F instead of E flat:</tei:p><tei:p>&lt;span class="mt-enclosure mt-enclosure-image" style="display: inline;"&gt;&lt;img alt="vC27p5image1&amp;amp;2 eng.PNG" src="http://mt.ccnmtl.columbia.edu/schenker/images/cube/vC27p5image1%262%20eng.PNG" width="213" height="57" class="mt-image-center" style="text-align: center; display: block; margin: 0 auto 20px;" /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</tei:p><tei:p>The theme represents the ideal of an invention that is not "melody" in the sense in which the term is generally misunderstood, and yet has a more singing quality than what is taken to be melody and is most excellently suitable for sonata form, i.e. ^for^ a rondo as a part of a sonata. For the sake of these notes alone, a publisher ought to be grateful, and willing to pay--but that has been a long road to travel, and will always be one.  For the time being, it is also of secondary importance.  Another excellent feature in the rondo is the +connection+ in system 6, and the +preparation and continuation+ in system 8.  Here, however, you could have also beamed every four eighth notes:</tei:p><tei:p>&lt;span class="mt-enclosure mt-enclosure-image" style="display: inline;"&gt;&lt;img alt="vC27p5image3.PNG" src="http://mt.ccnmtl.columbia.edu/schenker/image/cube/vC27p5image3.PNG" width="95" height="49" class="mt-image-center" style="text-align: center; display: block; margin: 0 auto 20px;" /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;</tei:p><tei:p>Again, everything is successful +in terms of sonata style+ in the most desirable sense, and praiseworthy; the brevity of the E-flat section is especially praiseworthy.  For this small amount of material alone <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> I would offer you my warmest congratulations on your first achievement in the higher realm of sonata form, in which not even "themes" or "melodies" of Chopin [and] Schubert are at home, at least as they appear in the two sonatas by Chopin and in so much of Schubert.  Cultivate, then, with all the energy you have at your disposal the lightness and naturalness of your creations, always and ^only^ along +these lines+, it will bring ever greater profit. Page X (continuation of the Rondo): the prelude-like introduction to the contrasting theme (which reminds me of the contrasting theme in Beethoven's Op. 26:  <tei:hi rend="italic">that doesn't matter!</tei:hi>), clarified by the parallelism (p. IX, above), ^is a^ good idea for the <tei:hi rend="italic">form</tei:hi>.  The arrangement of the materials on p. XI is not sufficiently transparent, though much is delicate (system 2).  The diminution beginning at system 4 is also attractive.  Etc., etc.</tei:p><tei:p>Now, let us go back, to the third movement. A movement that has the effect of being improvised in this way can (<tei:hi rend="italic">and sometimes must</tei:hi>, depending on the material) +dispense+ with a repetition.  By proceeding in an improvised way, it can, <tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> in short, ^serve^ only the +transition+ to the final movement, all the more so when, as here, the +opening+ is based on an artifice (=V).  At any rate, the parallelisms would ^then^ have to be of shorter scope, and in no way as broadly conceived (as here) as a&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;-a&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, since the improvisations will be damaged by this formal plan.  But it is nice that you have written down your "courage" on p. -VI- VII, systems 3-5; something of this sort will +always+ retain its effect, even if fashion and self-importance are, for the time being, so greatly ruffled by it.</tei:p><tei:p>Sonata 2, p. I: your +intentions+ regarding the +form+ are clear and +correct+,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/> but the diminution material lags behind, if I may put it this way: sometimes it works better, elsewhere ^(as here)^ not so well.  In the modulatory section, <tei:hi rend="italic">do not pile repetitions</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn15"/> <tei:hi rend="italic">upon one another</tei:hi>: pass over these smoothly with a strongly cut bass progression.  The diminution can +change+ more easily at each ^chord in the bass progression^; the conduct of the bass ^, regardless of the line of the upper voice^, also supports the change. Page II, systems 2-4, work well (are you trying to convey the sound of a glockenspiel?). Avoid unnecessary lengths!  It is better to be brief, characteristic, conversational, playful!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> (Second movement): improve the +notation+ in bars 3-4 on p. VI, second-to-last system. Page VII: the rhythmic diminution in bars 1-2 is +good+, and preserves the relationship. (Third movement):  The beginning is +excellent+, entirely in the +best spirits+ with its inversions and change of octave. On p. IX, systems 5-6 and in other places, rewrite, to make the notation <tei:hi rend="italic">simpler</tei:hi>!  What about the transition from p. X to p. XI: what is the intention?  In this movement there is still much that should be +shortened+, as in general there is still so <tei:hi rend="italic">much that needs refinement in both pieces</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>But all of this does not concern me for the moment, only the <tei:hi rend="italic">sonata style</tei:hi>: the ability to breathe music not in ,elodic snippets, not in periodic constructions--all the things one finds in dances, operas and potpourris--and this ability +I find in your work+, and I recommend that you cultivate it in spite of the ^ <tei:hi rend="italic">Zeitgeist</tei:hi> ^ that stands opposed to it.  Specifically, take care in +repetitions of the diminution+, which used to be called "cobbler's patch." The masterworks specifically teach us to use only that which must be, as the most important parallelism!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{9}</tei:hi> A final word, for your protection as well as mine:</tei:p><tei:p>Should someone perhaps find my +recognition+ ^of your work^ to be in contradiction to the shortcomings that I indicate, laugh in his face and say, on my behalf: "Seek first to understand the masters, how the content of a sonata, symphony, etc, unfolds; then you too +will be able to+ -understand- +praise+ that which is worthy of praise."  Basically, I cannot praise you highly enough. <tei:hi rend="bold">{10}</tei:hi> because there are so many successful features in the spirit of sonata form, anyone who might be so presumptuous as to pass judgement on my judgement should know, from me, what difficult things are at stake.</tei:p><tei:p>Should you know of a copyist, and can take the trouble at some point to have these works copied so [<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg. word</tei:hi>] it would please me to have  such a copy.</tei:p><tei:p>With the genuine Tyrolean saying, <tei:hi rend="bold">{11}</tei:hi> "Take your time," with best wishes from me and my Lie-Liechen,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn16"/></tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H. Schenker</tei:p><tei:p>Galtür, August 10, 1929</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>