<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:vC 47 : 7-18-33 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  In the public domain.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2008.
© Translation William Drabkin, 2008.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2008.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance> Felix-Eberhard von Cube (1933-87) - -Heirs of F.-E. von Cube (1987-present day)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: Heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 07/18/1933 09:51:17 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated July 18, 1933</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-12-16</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Schenker reports on a newspaper article and abortive radio program about his theory, by Theo Goos;  also on Jonas's forthcoming book, on van Hoboken, Moriz Violin, and Hans Wolf; and on progress with Der freie Satz.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Cube, Felix-Eberhard von;  Oppel, Reinhard;  Goos, Theo;  Jonas, Oswald;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  Violin, Moriz;  Wolf, Hans;  Der freie Satz;  Free Composition</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Schloß Reigersberg, Ilz, East Styria</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated July 18, 1933</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Schloß Reigersberg
Post Ilz,
Ost-Steiermark</tei:p><tei:p>Lieber Prof v <tei:hi rend="italic">Cube</tei:hi>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> The writing of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diaryOJ 4/6, p. 3851.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Prof <tei:hi rend="italic">D^r^ R. Oppel</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="oppel_reinhard">Reinhard Oppel</ref>. </tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Leipzig</tei:hi>, sandte mir kürzlich einen kleinen Aufsatz zu meinem 65. Geburtstag aus der Feder eines ehemaligen Schülers von ihm <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Theo Goos</tei:hi></tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Neumünster</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Goos's article is not preserved in Schenker's scrapbook (OC 2), nor are there any articles by him elsewhere in the Oster Collection.  See also Schenker to Jonas, OJ 5/18, 38, April 7, 1934, OJ 5/18, 39, April 10, 1934, and Jonas to Schenker, OJ 12/6, [31], April 15, 1934.  </tei:note> einen rührenden Aufsatz - die Zeitung, in der er erschienen [ist], ist nicht ersichtlich gemacht -, dessen letzte Zeilen läuten:  „Die Musikschule Gebr. <tei:hi rend="italic">Goos</tei:hi> gedachte in zwei Feiern (für Kinder u. Erwachsene) der Verdienste des großen <tei:hi rend="italic">Musikforschers</tei:hi>. [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from lower margin:</tei:hi> Der Rundfunkvortrag über mich wurde abgelehnt!]  Daraus entnehme ich, daß <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> die Schule dort ernstlich meine Lehre betreibt, ob mit wirklichem Verständnis u. guter Einfühlung, weiß ich freilich nicht.  Wissen Sie etwas davon?</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">D^r^ Jonas</tei:hi>, den Sie (wie ich glaube) von <tei:hi rend="italic">Berlin</tei:hi> her kennen, veröffentlicht im Herbst ein Buch „Eine Einführung in Schenkers Lehre" oder ähnlich, mit wesentlicher Unterstützung von H. v. <tei:hi rend="italic">Hoboken</tei:hi>.  Das Erscheinen ist also materiell gesichert, hoffentlich wird <tei:hi rend="italic">D^r^ Jonas</tei:hi> zum vorgehabten Termin &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;auch&lt;/sup&gt; fertig.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> Click on <ref cRef="jonas_oswald">Oswald Jonas</ref>.  Jonas's <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks: eine Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers</tei:hi>, was not published until the following year.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>H. v. <tei:hi rend="italic">Hoboken</tei:hi> hat Wien schon vor einem Jahr verlassen, hat aber eine Entscheidung über den nächsten Platz meines Wissens noch nicht <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> getroffen.  Daß er wieder geheiratet hat, dürften Sie wohl wissen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.  Schenker himself told Cube about Hoboken's having remarried, in his letter of May 14, 1933.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Prof. Violin</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="violin_moriz">Moriz Violin</ref>.  </tei:note> habe ich noch nicht zu Gesicht bekommen, wir giengen am 15.VI ab, er aber traf erst später in Wien ein. Wolf<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7"> Click on <ref cRef="wolf_hans">Hans Wolf</ref>.</tei:note> ist schon bei mir erschienen, hatte sogar 6 Stunden &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;noch&lt;/sup&gt; vor meiner Abreise, wie sich die Sache aber im Herbst gestalten wird, ist mir noch unbekannt, ändern sich doch die Verhältnisse heute von Tag zu Tag.</tei:p><tei:p>Wie geht es Ihnen?  Lassen Sie, bitte, etwas von sich hören.</tei:p><tei:p>Wir haben uns diesmal ganz wo andershin gewendet, teils aus Zwang, teils aus <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Überzeugung.</tei:p><tei:p>Der „fr S" geht dem Ende zu!  Hoffentlich halten die Augen durch!  Schmerzlich entbehre ich einer Hilfe bei der Niederschrift, Durchsicht der vielen Notenbeispiele, u. was erst meiner bei den Korrekturen harrt!  Meine Frau waltet aller übrigen „Belange", sehr zu meinem Glück, wohl auch zum Glück meiner Lehre.</tei:p><tei:p>Nun herzlichste Grüße Ihnen von uns Beiden!</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>18.VII.33</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated July 18, 1933</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Schloß Reigersberg
Ilz, 
East Styria</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Prof v Cube,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Professor Dr R. Oppel<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> of Leipzig recently sent me a short essay for my sixty-fifth birthday, written by one of his former pupils, <tei:hi rend="italic">Theo Goos</tei:hi> of <tei:hi rend="italic">Neumünster</tei:hi>:<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  a touching essay--the name of the newspaper in which it appeared was not visible.  The last lines read:  "The music school of the Goos brothers paid homage, in two celebrations (for children and adults), to the services of the great <tei:hi rend="italic">music scholar</tei:hi>." [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from lower margin:</tei:hi> The radio broadcast about me was refused!]   From this I gather that <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> the school takes my theory seriously;  whether they really understand and have a feeling for it is something that I, of course, do not know.  Do you know anything about it?</tei:p><tei:p>Dr. Jonas, whom you know (so I believe) from [your trip to] Berlin, is publishing a book about me in the autumn, entitled <tei:hi rend="italic">An Introduction to Schenker's Theory</tei:hi> or something like that, with significant backing from Hoboken.  Its appearance is thus financially assured;  I hope that Dr Jonas will &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;also&lt;/sup&gt; complete his work by the expected deadline.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/></tei:p><tei:p>Mr. van Hoboken left Vienna a year ago, but, so far as I know, has not yet made up his mind where he will settle. <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi>  That he has remarried is something you probably know.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/></tei:p><tei:p>I have not yet seen Professor Violin;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/>  we left on June 15, but he arrived in Vienna only after that date. Wolf<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> has already been to see me;  he has, in fact, &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;already&lt;/sup&gt; had as many as six lessons before I left;  how things will work out in the Fall I still do not know, since nowadays the situation changes from day to day.</tei:p><tei:p>How are you? Please let me hear from you.</tei:p><tei:p>This time we have taken [our vacation] in an entirely different place, partly on account of pressure, partly from <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> conviction.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Free Composition</tei:hi> is nearing completion!  I hope that my eyesight will survive until the end of the work.  With pain, I can manage without help with the writing and the checking of the numerous music examples, and that which awaits me with the proofreading!  My wife is in charge of all other "business," much to my joy, and probably also to the joy of my theory.</tei:p><tei:p>For now, most cordial greetings to you from the two of us!</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] H. Schenker
.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>