<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:vC 46 : 5-14-33 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
©  Transcription William Drabkin 2008.
© Translation William Drabkin, 2008
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2008.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance> Felix-Eberhard von Cube (1933-87) - -Heirs of F.-E. von Cube (1987-present day)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: Heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 05/14/1933 12:28:51 PM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated May 14, 1933</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-12-15</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Schenker disagrees with Cube's assertion in OJ 9/34, [37] that the Urlinie of the theme of Beethoven, Op. 26, first movement, was a third-progression, not a fifth-progression, giving graphic proofs and explaining Cube's misuse of the neighbor note.   - - Hitler has done "historical service" in getting rid of Marxism;  someone is needed to get rid of musical Marxists; Schenker has created the tools.  - - He provides background to Moriz Violin's departure from Hamburg, reports on Jonas, Weisse, and Oppel, and inquires whether Cube has heard from Furtwängler.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Cube, Felix-Eberhard von;  Tonraum;  tonal space;  strenger Satz;  strict counterpoint;  Gattung;  species;  Durchgang;  passing note;  Ursatz;  Urlinie;  Bassbrechung;  bass arpeggiation;  Schicht;  layer;  Nebennote;  neighbor note;  Vordergrund;  foreground;  Unterbrechung;  interruption;  Quinte;  fifth;  Sext;  sixth;  Anstieg;  linear ascent;  Parallelismen;  parallel constructions;  Erläuterungen;  elucidations;  Auskomponierung;  composing out;  Quintzug;  fifth-progression;  Quartzug;  fourth-progression;  Instinkt;  instinct;  Hitler;  Marxism;  French;  English;  Germany;  Violin, Moriz;  Weisse, Hans;  Oppel, Reinhard;  Furtwänger, Wilhelm;  Hoboken, Anthony van</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated May 14, 1933</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Lieber Prof v Cube!</tei:p><tei:p>Alles im Briefe,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  = OJ 9/34, [37], Cube's letter to Schenker dated May 11, 1933.</tei:note> Ausführungen, Bekenntnis zeigt ein ungewöhnliches Maß von Können u. Charakter, wie es nur ganz wenige mit Ihnen heute teilen. Sagte ich, schrieb ich Ihnen das schon öfter, so wiederhole ich auch noch dieses:  wenn Jemand, wie Sie, solchen Grad von „Abhorchen" u. Darstellung zeigt, hat sozusagen das Recht auch auf einen gelegentlichen Irrtum:  ein Irrtum auf der Base der Wahrheit ist noch immer wertvoller als ein Irrtum auf einer Base, die selber ein Irrtum ist.  Wie leicht könnte es Ihnen widerfahren, was auch mir so oft widerfahren ist, daß Sie, nach Monaten, nach Jahren plötzlich den Blick ganz frei bekommen auch für Dinge, die Sie, durch Tumult des Tages, Mißstimmung, <tei:hi rend="italic">Hast</tei:hi> &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;!&lt;/sup&gt;, abgezogen zunächst wenig beachtet haben.  Übrigens ist die Frage ~3 oder ~5, ~5 oder ~8, &lt;del&gt;u dgl..&lt;/del&gt; ~8 oder ~3 eben die <tei:hi rend="italic">Tonraum</tei:hi>-Frage, ob 3, ob 5, ob 8, die zu enscheiden wohl als Schwierigste gelten mag. Nun zur Sache:</tei:p><tei:p>1) Der strenge Satz (vgl. II^1^, 2. u. 3. Gattung) lehrt, daß die Nbn genau so <tei:hi rend="italic">frei</tei:hi> eintritt, wie der Bruder Durchgang</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 1</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>In unserem Falle wäre nach dem <tei:hi rend="italic">Ursatz</tei:hi>, {[<tei:hi rend="italic">treble clef</tei:hi>] Url. [<tei:hi rend="italic">placed below that:</tei:hi> [<tei:hi rend="italic">bass clef</tei:hi>] Bassbr.], also einfach:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 2</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>schon in der <tei:hi rend="italic">1. Schicht</tei:hi>, die in das Besondere abzweigt, schon zum geahnten Vdg hin die Nbn. aufzuzeigen, <tei:hi rend="italic">streng nach dem st. S</tei:hi>:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 3</tei:hi>]  %.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  This symbol appears among Schenker's corrections to Cube's original graph, which probably accmpanied all four pieces of correspondence between Hamburg and Vienna in May 1933.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Nach Willen des Komponisten ist <tei:hi rend="italic">diese</tei:hi> Nbn hier aber <tei:hi rend="italic">formweisend</tei:hi>, sie gibt hier, wie so oft, Veranlassung zu: a&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;) - b) [<tei:hi rend="italic">below:</tei:hi> (Nbn)] - a&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) im Vdg.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Wenn &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;nun&lt;/sup&gt; für die erste ~3 ein Terzz. verbraucht wird:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 4</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>u. gar in der folgenden Schicht der Terzz. durch einen <tei:hi rend="italic">Unterbrechung</tei:hi> ausgestaltet wird:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 5</tei:hi>],</tei:p><tei:p>so ist es unmöglich, den schon in Fluß geratenen Baß wegen der Nbn des^2^ &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;plötzlich&lt;/sup&gt; in die Starrheit des c.f. zurückzubeordern [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">nicht</tei:hi>:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 6</tei:hi>].</tei:p><tei:p>Nichts natürlicherer, als daß der Baß, zumal unstatthaft ist:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 7</tei:hi>]
 
doch &lt;zu&lt;del&gt;m Quinteter&lt;/del&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;Quinte&lt;/sup&gt; emporsteigt, die 8-7 stützt, u. so&lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;mit&lt;/sup&gt; die Nbn stützt.</tei:p><tei:p>2) Dazu kommt eine Unwägbarkeit:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 8</tei:hi>]
 
("Anstieg" <tei:hi rend="italic">u.</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Par.</tei:hi> kommen sehr häufig vor). Hiebei wäre es nicht einmal fehlerhaft zu lesen:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 9</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>da die Parall. anders als der „Anstieg", <tei:hi rend="italic">der immer</tei:hi> &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;nur&lt;/sup&gt; <tei:hi rend="italic">den 1. Url.Ton</tei:hi> zum Ziel hat, von einem solchen Ziel entbunden sind, &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;hier&lt;/sup&gt; also auch andere Zielen, als &lt;del&gt;hier&lt;/del&gt; des^2^, es^2^ &lt;sub&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;hätten&lt;/sub&gt; haben &lt;del&gt;konnten&lt;/del&gt; können.</tei:p><tei:p>3) Über die Auskomp. T. 5-8 s. "Erläuterungen", Jb I 203, fig 4 c, die letzten 3 Beispiele,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  The "Erläuterungen" ("Elucidations"), preliminary material to <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi> in its definitive form, are published in <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</tei:hi> 8/9 and 10 (both 1924) and in <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, vols. 1 (1925) and 2 (1926).</tei:note> u. Tw. 2 Moz. Son. a^m^. letzter Satz, T. 5-8,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Schenker is referring to the essay on Mozart's Sonata in A minor, K. 310 in <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</tei:hi> 2; in that analysis, the supposed consonant passing tone is treated as part of the main harmony, i.e. a tonic</tei:note> usw.  Der &lt;del&gt;zur der&lt;/del&gt; einer solchen Auskomp. zugeteilte Baß Kp. dient <tei:hi rend="italic">nur ihr</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  "nur ihr" (only that elaboration): double-underlined by Schenker.</tei:note> gleichviel ob er auf den „kons. Dg" von oben (Sext) oder von unten (Terz) zugeht.  Also ist es unstatthaft, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> so zu lesen &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;nicht „Quintzug"&lt;/sup&gt;:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">example 10</tei:hi>],</tei:p><tei:p>da unter <tei:hi rend="italic">allen</tei:hi> Umstände nur</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 11</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>zusammengehören.  <tei:hi rend="italic">Beeth.</tei:hi> leistet sich hier übrigens eine Kombination <tei:hi rend="italic">beider</tei:hi> Zugänge (auch wieder ein Beweis):</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 12</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>also zu as von oben: <tei:hi rend="italic">f&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;-as</tei:hi> u. von unten: <tei:hi rend="italic">f-as</tei:hi> [.]  Somit entfällt Ihr Quartzug.</tei:p><tei:p>4) Es geht nicht an, aus der Auskomp:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 13</tei:hi>]:
 
die Nbn des^2^ zu&lt;del&gt;r&lt;/del&gt; Url-Zwecken herauszuzapfen, wie Sie es - - in Not, &lt;!--Latin--&gt;<tei:hi rend="italic">deus ex machina!</tei:hi> - tun.  Dann hätten Sie dasselbe wohl auch schon zu Anfang tun dürfen, wodurch Sie sogar 5 4 3 2 [<tei:hi rend="italic">slur over</tei:hi>] || 5 4 3 2 1 [<tei:hi rend="italic">slur over</tei:hi>] erzielt hätten. Und doch hat Sie ein sehr sicherer <tei:hi rend="italic">Instinkt</tei:hi> vor diesen Misgriff bewahrt.  Das ist eben ein Zug, der sehr <tei:hi rend="italic">für Sie</tei:hi> spricht.</tei:p><tei:p>5) T. 21-22 bringen eine Abkürzung von T. 5-8</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 14</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>für:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 15</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>(die das metrische Schema gesprengt hätten.[)]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Endlich zu Ihrem schönen dritten Blatt!  Das geschichtliche Verdienst <tei:hi rend="italic">Hitlers</tei:hi>, den <tei:hi rend="italic">Marxismus</tei:hi> ausgerottet zu haben [<tei:hi rend="italic">alt from:</tei:hi> auszurotten], wird die Nachwelt (einschließlich der Franzosen, Engländer, u. all der Nutznießer der Verbrechen an Deutschland) nicht weniger dankbar feiern, als die Großtaten der größten Deutschen!  Wäre nur der Musik der Mann geboren, der die Musikmarxisten ähnlich ausrottet:  dazu gehörte vor Allem, daß sich die Massen dieser in sich versponnenen Kunst näherten, was aber eine - &lt;!--Latin--&gt;<tei:hi rend="italic">contradictio</tei:hi> [<tei:hi rend="italic">corr.</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">in adjecto</tei:hi> ist u. bleiben muß.  "Kunst" und <tei:hi rend="italic">Massen</tei:hi> haben nie zusammengehört,  werden nie zusammengehören.  Woher nun aber die Qu<tei:hi rend="italic">an</tei:hi>titäten der Musik-"Braunhemden" nehmen, mit denen es gelingen müsste, die Musikmarxisten hinauszujagen?</tei:p><tei:p>Die Waffen habe ich bereitsgestellt, aber die Musik, die wahre deutsche der Großen, findet kein Verständnis bei den Massen, die die Waffen tragen sollten.</tei:p><tei:p>Fast habe ich den Eindruck, als nähmen Sie an, ich sei von dem Weltumlauf unberührt.  Ich habe sehr schmerzliche 3 Jahre hinter mir, voll Sorgen um die Kunst, um uns Beide, um die Mitwelt.  Die Sorgen haben meinen Körper stark in Mitleidenschaft gezogen u. wiederum ist die <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> Einsamkeit unserer großen Musik die Ursache, weshalb auch ihre Priester mitgerissen werden.  Woher sollte den Menschen auch nur Mitleiden kommen, wenn sie wirklichen Musikern begegnen, &lt;del&gt;wenn&lt;/del&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;da&lt;/sup&gt; sie schon an der Musik keinerlei Interresse empfinden?!  Die Priester werden so selber zum &lt;del&gt;Got&lt;/del&gt; Opfer der Göttin!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Violins</tei:hi>' Lage ist mir, ohne daß er es wußte, von Zeit u.[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Zeit durch seine Schwester<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="violin_fanny">Fanny Violin</ref>. </tei:note> bekannt gemacht worden, sie erzählte schaudervolle Sachen!  Er schwieg, erst jetzt gestand er seine übergroße Nervosität ein.</tei:p><tei:p>Doch wußte auch seine Schwester sehr wenig, - das Wenige war erschütternd traurig - so daß ich über seinen Schritt<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Probably the decision to flee Hamburg, and leave Cube to manage the Schenker-Institut as best he could.</tei:note> zu urteilen mir versagen muß.  Vielleicht war Niemand so fern seiner Lage, wie ich.  Was er Ihnen <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> seinerzeit versprochen, dann, wie ich höre, leider nicht gehalten hat, ist mir bis zur Stunde verborgen.  Auf die Übersiedlung habe ich keinerlei Einfluß genommen, wie hätte ich es dürfen, wenn ich ihm nicht einmal in seinen ärgsten Nöten beispringen konnte!  Er hat mir 2 Schüler angekündigt u. die Honorare selbst - in Kenntnis der Sachlage - ausgemacht.  (Ich hätte es nicht getroffen.)  Aber, wenn die reichsten Schüler finanziell zusammenbrechen, [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from lower margin:</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">v. Hb.</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.  </tei:note> ist schon seit einem Jahr nicht mehr in Wien, ist übrigens seit März wieder verheiratet] so daß ich in Bemerkung ihrer Treue (25-30 Jahre!) 20 Stunden des Monats gratis geben muß, will, was bedeutet jene Kleinigkeit gegenüber solchen Verlusten!  Und doch wird es mir eine große Freude sein, meine Ankömmlinge aus dem Reich in die Musik einzuführen, wie eine dritte Generation.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> Sie sehen, wie schwer sich auch bei mir das Leben inzwischen gestaltet hat, wie doch bei fast allen Musikern allüberall.  Der Weg zur Genesung, der künstlerischen wie materiellen, kann nur über meine Lehre führen, gerade aber diese fällt den Leuten genau so schwer, wie die Meisterwerke selbst.</tei:p><tei:p>Von <tei:hi rend="italic">D^r^ Jonas</tei:hi> kommt das Buch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  (Click on) <ref cRef="jonas_oswald">Oswald Jonas</ref>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerkes: eine Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers</tei:hi> (Vienna: Saturn-Verlag, 1934).</tei:note> dann doch im Herbst heraus.</tei:p><tei:p>Von <tei:hi rend="italic">Weisse</tei:hi> höre ich nichts.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  It is by no means true that (click on) <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref> was out of touch at the time:  Schenker received letters from him in February, March and May 1933, and regular reports about Weisse's composing activities and teaching at the Mannes School.  The letters of 1933 were, however, critical of Vrieslander's compositions and Schenker's unalloyed praise for them, and this may be why Schenker appears to be repressing them here.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Prof. Oppel</tei:hi> leitet in <tei:hi rend="italic">Leipzig</tei:hi> - er ist Hauptmann mit Eisernem Kreuz &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;gerufen&lt;/sup&gt;! - eine national-soz. "Zelle", in der er nach wie &lt;del&gt;fort&lt;/del&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;vor&lt;/sup&gt; nach Tunlichkeit <tei:hi rend="italic">Schenker</tei:hi> weitergibt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Prof. Reinhard Oppel, who had been awarded a chair in music theory for the express purpose of teaching Schenker's theories.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> Hat Ihnen Furtwängler geantwortet?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  (Click on) <ref cRef="furtwangler_wilhelm">Furtwängler</ref> did not reply to Cube's request for a reference until the summer of 1934.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Nun.  Ihnen Beiden von uns Beiden wärmste Wünsche u. Grüße</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">H Schenker</tei:hi>
14.V.33</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated May 14, 1933</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor von Cube, 
	
Everything in your letter<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>--your arguments, your declaration--shows an extraordinary measure of capability and character, which very few people today share with you.  If I have already told you, written to you that many times, let me also reiterate the following:  anyone who, like yourself, has demonstrated such a degree of "attention" and presentation has, so to speak, the right to make an occasional mistake:  a mistake made on the basis of the truth is always more valuable than a mistake made on a basis that is itself a mistake.  How easily it could befall you, as it so often befalls me, that things to which you had paid too little attention--and had remained concealed by the hectic pace of daily life, by feelings of depression, or by doing things in a <tei:hi rend="italic">rush</tei:hi>&lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;(!)&lt;/sup&gt;--all of a sudden become crystal clear. Moreover, the question of ~3 or ~5, ~5 or ~8, &lt;del&gt;and the like&lt;/del&gt; ~8 or ~3 is that very question about <tei:hi rend="italic">tonal space</tei:hi>, whether 3 or 5 or 8, that is perhaps the most difficult to decide. Now to the matter itself:</tei:p><tei:p>1) Strict counterpoint  (see <tei:hi rend="italic">Counterpoint</tei:hi>, vol. 1, chapters on the second and third species) teaches us that the neighbor note may be introduced just as <tei:hi rend="italic">easily</tei:hi> as her brother, the passing note:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 1</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>In our case, following the <tei:hi rend="italic">Ursatz</tei:hi> comprising Urlinie in the treble clef, supported by bass arpeggiation in the bass clef, thus in its simple terms:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 2</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>the neighbor note, <tei:hi rend="italic">strictly in accordance with strict counterpoint</tei:hi>, is to be shown as early as in the <tei:hi rend="italic">first layer</tei:hi>,</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 3</tei:hi>] %.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/></tei:p><tei:p>which will branch off into the particulars [of the composition]. By the will of the composer, <tei:hi rend="italic">this</tei:hi> neighbor note here is, however, <tei:hi rend="italic">determinative for the form</tei:hi>;   gives rise to a&lt;sub&gt;1&lt;/sub&gt;)--b)--a&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) in the foreground.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi>  If &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;now&lt;/sup&gt; a third-progression is used for the first ~3:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 4</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>and the third-progression is actually <tei:hi rend="italic">developed</tei:hi> in the following layer by an <tei:hi rend="italic">interruption</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 5</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>then it is impossible &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;suddenly&lt;/sup&gt; to recall the bass, which has already been set in motion, to its earlier, rigid role as the cantus firmus, in order to support the neighbor note d-flat^2^.  This would be incorrect:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 6</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>Nothing would be more natural than that the bass, given that</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 7</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>is impossible, nonetheless rises to the 5th, which supports 8-7 and in this way supports the neighbor note.</tei:p><tei:p>2) To this an imponderable is added:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 8</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>(Linear ascents are often associated with <tei:hi rend="italic">parallel constructions</tei:hi>.)  In this case even the following reading would not have been erroneous:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 9</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>since the parallelisms--unlike the [initial] "ascent," <tei:hi rend="italic">whose</tei:hi> &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;only&lt;/sup&gt; <tei:hi rend="italic">goal is always the first tone of the Urlinie</tei:hi>--are released from such a goal, and &lt;del&gt;could&lt;/del&gt; can also have other goals &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;here&lt;/sup&gt;, such as d<tei:hi rend="italic">b</tei:hi>^2^ and e<tei:hi rend="italic">b</tei:hi>^2^.</tei:p><tei:p>3) Regarding the elaboration, mm. 5-8, see "Elucidations," <tei:hi rend="italic">Yearbook</tei:hi>, vol. 1, p. 203, Fig. 4c, last three illustrations,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> and Mozart's Sonata in A minor, last movement, mm. 5-8, in <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Tonwille</tei:hi>, vol. 2.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  The bass counterpoint assigned to such an elaboration serves <tei:hi rend="italic">only that elaboration</tei:hi>,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> regardless of whether the "consonant passing tone" is approached from the sixth above or the third below. Thus the following reading is incorrect &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;not "fifth-progression"&lt;/sup&gt; <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi>:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 10</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>since in <tei:hi rend="italic">any</tei:hi> event only</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 11</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>belong together.  Moreover, Beethoven achieves a combination here of <tei:hi rend="italic">both</tei:hi> approaches to a<tei:hi rend="italic">b</tei:hi> (which is yet more proof)</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 12</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>i.e. from above, f^1^-a<tei:hi rend="italic">b</tei:hi>, and from below, f-a<tei:hi rend="italic">b</tei:hi>. On these grounds, your fourth-progression must be rejected.</tei:p><tei:p>4) It is not permissible, given the following elaboration:</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 13</tei:hi>]:</tei:p><tei:p>to force the neigbor note to take on a role in the Urlinie, as you do (when in need, &lt;!--Latin--&gt; <tei:hi rend="italic">deus ex machina!</tei:hi>). Otherwise you would have certainly been able to do the same thing at the very beginning, by which you would have actually aimed at 5 4 3 2 [<tei:hi rend="italic">slur over</tei:hi>] ||  5 4 3 2 1. [<tei:hi rend="italic">slur over</tei:hi>]. And yet a very reliable <tei:hi rend="italic">instinct</tei:hi> protected you from making this error; that is itself very much a point in <tei:hi rend="italic">your</tei:hi> favor.</tei:p><tei:p>5) Measures 21-22 represent an abbreviation of measures 5-8</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 14</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>stand for</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">music example 15</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>(The latter would have shattered the metric structure.[)]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Finally, your beautiful third page!  Hitler's historical service, of having got rid of Marxism, is something that posterity (including the French, English, and all those who have profited from transgressing against Germany) will celebrate with no less gratitude than the great deeds of the greatest Germans!  If only the man were born to music who would similarly get rid of the musical Marxists;  that would require that the masses were more in touch with our intrinsically eccentric art, which is something that, however, is and must remain a contradiction in terms.  "Art" and "<tei:hi rend="italic">the masses</tei:hi>" have never belonged together and never will belong together.  And where would one find the <tei:hi rend="italic">huge</tei:hi> numbers of musical "brownshirts" that would be needed to hunt down the musical Marxists?</tei:p><tei:p>I have prepared the weapons, but the music--the true German music of the greats--finds no understanding among the masses who should bear the weapons.</tei:p><tei:p>I almost have the impression that you believe I am untouched by the course of the world.  I have endured three painful years, full of troubled thoughts for art, for the two of us [myself and my wife], for my friends.  These thoughts have affected me physically, and the <tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> isolation of our great music is once again the cause, for which reason its priests are dragged along.  How can one expect people to feel empathy, if they encounter true musicians, if &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;since&lt;/sup&gt; they already feel no interest in music in the slightest. The priests will thus themselves become a sacrificial offering to the goddess!</tei:p><tei:p>I have been informed of Violin's situation from time to time by his sister,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> without his knowing it;  she recounted terrifying things!  He was silent, and only now did he admit the extent of his nervous condition.</tei:p><tei:p>Yet even his sister knew very little--the little that she knew was distressingly sad--so that I had to refrain from making a judgment about the steps he took.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>  Perhaps no one was more ignorant of his situation than I myself.  What he promised you, <tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> for his part, but then--so I hear--failed to make good, has to this time been unknown to me.  Regarding his move, I exerted no influence whatever;  how could I have done so if I was unable to rush to help him in his hour of greatest need?  He informed me of two [new] pupils and arranged the fees himself--in recognition of the situation.  (I would not have managed this.)  But when the wealthiest pupils suffer financial collapse, [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from lower margin:</tei:hi> Hoboken<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> has been away from Vienna for a year;  moreover, he has been married again since March.] so that I must, or will, teach twenty hours a month free of charge in recognition of their loyalty (they have been with me for twenty-five to thirty years!), what is such a trivial matter compared to such losses?  And yet it will be a great joy to me, to introduce music to my newcomers from the Reich, as a third generation</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> You see how difficult life has become even for me, as it is for nearly all musicians wherever one looks.  The path to recovery, artistic as well as material, can lead only by way of my theory;  but precisely this is something people find as difficult as the masterworks themselves.</tei:p><tei:p>Dr Jonas's book<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> will now be published in the fall.</tei:p><tei:p>From Weisse I hear nothing.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/></tei:p><tei:p>Professor Oppel in Leipzig--he has been made Captain, with the Iron Cross!--leads a national-socialist "cell," in which he continues to teach Schenker, now as before, insofar as this is possible.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> Did Furtwängler answer your letter?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/></tei:p><tei:p>Well, that is how things are.  Warmest wishes and greetings from the two of us to you both.</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] H. Schenker</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>