<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
    xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
    xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">

    <sdo:collectionDesc>
        <sdo:source>
            <sdo:other mfID="1979" sdoID="OC-2-20_4">OC 2/p. 20, [4]</sdo:other>
        </sdo:source>
        <tei:handNotes>
            <tei:handNote xml:id="pr" scope="sole">printed</tei:handNote>
        </tei:handNotes>

        <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
            <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
            <tei:resp>Transcription, 2007, 2017</tei:resp>
            <tei:resp>Translation, 2007, 2017</tei:resp>
            <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2017</tei:resp>
        </tei:respStmt>

        <tei:respStmt xml:id="TL">
            <tei:persName>Tamara Lopez</tei:persName>
            <tei:resp>XML Encoding, Model 2010</tei:resp>
        </tei:respStmt>

    </sdo:collectionDesc>


    <sdo:record ID="r0001">
        <sdo:itemDesc>
            <dc:title>Review by Karl Grunsky of Schenker's Harmonielehre, dated December 18,
                1907</dc:title>
            <dc:type>Review</dc:type>
            <dcterms:created>1907-12-18T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
            <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2017-07-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted>

            <dc:description>Grunsky summarizes the content of Harmonielehre, supports Schenker's
                criticisms of Richard Strauss and Max Reger, and approves of Schenker's underlying
                principles.</dc:description>
            <dc:subject/>
            <marcrel:author key="entity-000311">Karl Grunsky</marcrel:author>

        </sdo:itemDesc>

        <tei:div type="transcription">

            <tei:opener>
                <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1907-12-18">18. Dezember
                    1907</tei:date>.</tei:dateline><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
                <tei:title><tei:hi rend="bold">Musik und
                    Musikgeschichte.</tei:hi></tei:title><tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01"
                    type="editorial" place="foot">On December 12, 1907 (<tei:ref
                        type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-12-27_10">OJ 12/27, [10]</tei:ref>), <tei:rs
                        type="organization" key="entity-002405">Cotta</tei:rs> forwarded to Schenker
                    a letter from Grunsky "offering the prospect" of a review of <tei:title
                        level="m">Harmonielehre</tei:title> for the <tei:title level="j">Schwäbische
                        Merkur</tei:title>, and asking how they should respond. Schenker (diary
                    December 13, OJ 1/5, pp. 53–54) suspected Grunsky was trying to elicit his
                    identity, so on December 16 (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="CA-71">CA
                        71</tei:ref>) he wrote Cotta refusing to let his name be divulged for the
                    time being, but expressing respect for Grunsky's work. Then on January 3, 1908
                        (<tei:ref type="correspondence" cRef="CA-73">CA 73</tei:ref>), Schenker
                    asked <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002405">Cotta</tei:rs> to supply a
                    copy of the review, and on January 6 noted in his diary (OJ 1/7, p. 58) receipt
                    of the review, commenting: "So I have harbored unfounded suspicions of this
                    person." ("Habe also gegen diesen Menschen an gerechtfertigten Verdruß
                    gesetzt"). Thereafter, a lively correspondence ensued which lasted for the
                    remainder of 1908.</tei:note><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
                <tei:title><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000311">K. G.</tei:rs> (<tei:hi
                        rend="sperr">Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:hi>. Von einem
                    Künstler. I. Bd. Harmonielehre. Stuttg. und Berlin. J. G. Cottas Nachfolger.
                </tei:title><tei:lb/>
            </tei:opener>

            <tei:div>
                <tei:p>Der Inhalt bestätigt den Titel, es handelt sich um den Vortrag teilweise
                    neuer Auffassungen in phantasievoller, nicht streng systematischer, doch
                    angenehm geordneter Form. Das Wesentliche und Erfreuliche ist, daß der
                    unbekannte Verfasser enge Fühlung mit dem Kunstwerk nimmt; seine 379, zum Teil
                    sehr umfangreichen Beispiele sind Bach, Mozart, Haydn, Beethoven, Schubert u. a.
                    entnommen. Die Klavierliteratur ist vielleicht zu sehr bevorzugt. Aus der
                    reichen Gedankenwelt sei hier einiges angedeutet: Moll gilt dem Gegner Riemanns
                    mehr als Eigentum der Künstler, Dur als klangliche Gegebenheit; die
                    Kirchentonarten werden sehr lehrreich und lichtvoll behandelt. Die aufgestellten
                    Mischungsreihen von Dur und Moll verdienen allgemeine Beachtung. In der Lehre
                    von den Intervallen wird Harmoniefähigkeit als Voraussetzung des Intervalls
                    angesprochen und nachgewiesen, daß es nicht mehr und nicht weniger als 20
                    Intervalle gibt; ihre Mehrdeutigkeit bringt der Verfasser auf klare Formeln.
                    Geradezu prachtvoll lesen sich sodann die Ausführungen über Begriff und Wert der
                    harmonischen Stufe: die formbildende Kraft der Harmonie kommt dadurch aufs
                    anschaulichste zum Verständnis. Die Einwände gegen Reger und R. Strauß sind
                    wohlbegründet und jedenfalls nicht durch Redensarten zu entkräften. Deutlich
                    tritt der Unterschied zwischen Harmonie und Kontrapunkt hervor, aus welchem
                    Melodie und Rhythmus ausscheiden. Die meisten Musiker werden auch einverstanden
                    sein, wenn Chromatik und Diatonik endlich wieder energisch als
                    zueinandergehörend gedacht werden: je stärker das Streben nach der Tonika, desto
                    straffer die Spannung, zu deren Ausdruck eben das Chromatische, die Alteration,
                    Vorausnahme, der Vorhalt usw. dienen; daher z.B. Mozart als einer der
                    bedeutendsten Chromatiker gelten muß. —Daß die Form etwas Lebendiges, Spannendes
                    ist, daß die Aufgaben der Form einer Harmonie erst die rechte Bedeutung geben,
                    ist an verschiedenen Stellen eingehend und mit ursprünglichem Verständnis
                    dargetan. Dem gebildeten Musiker wird das Buch sehr willkommen sein; möge bald
                    die Fortsetzung erscheinen!</tei:p>
            </tei:div>

        </tei:div>


        <tei:div type="translation">

            <tei:opener>
                <tei:dateline><tei:date when="1907-12-18">December 18,
                    1907</tei:date>.</tei:dateline><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
                <tei:title><tei:hi rend="bold">Music and Music History</tei:hi></tei:title><tei:ptr
                    corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/><tei:lb/><tei:lb/>
                <tei:title><tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000311">K. G.</tei:rs> (<tei:hi
                        rend="sperr">New Musical Theories and Fantasies. By an Artist</tei:hi>. By
                    an Artist. Volume 1, Theory of Harmony. Stuttart and Berlin. J.G. Cotta's
                    Successor.</tei:title><tei:lb/>
            </tei:opener>

            <tei:div>
                <tei:p>The content confirms the title. It is a matter of a presentation of, in part,
                    new interpretations in imaginative, not strictly systematically but conveniently
                    ordered form. The essential and welcome feature is that the unknown author makes
                    contact with the work of art. His 379, at times very copious examples are drawn
                    from, among others, Bach, Mozart, Haydn, Beethoven, Schubert. Piano literature
                    is perhaps favored too much. We allude here to a few aspects from the rich
                    conceptual world: for the opponent of Riemann, minor mode is considered more as
                    the property of artists, major mode as an acoustical given; the ecclesiastical
                    modes are covered very instructively and illuminatingly. The proposed scales
                    mixing major and minor merit general attention. In the theory of intervals, the
                    capacity for harmony is addressed as a requirement of the interval, and it is
                    proven that there are no more and no fewer than twenty intervals. The author
                    summarizes their multiple meanings in clear formulas. Thereafter the discussions
                    on the concept and function of the harmonic scale steps read absolutely
                    splendidly. The form-building power of harmony is thereby understood most
                    vividly. The objections to Reger and R. Strauss are well founded and in any case
                    not weakened by empty phrases. The distinction between harmony and counterpoint
                    emerges clearly, by which melody and rhythm are differentiated. Most musicians
                    will agree when chromaticism and diatonicism are at last vigorously conceived as
                    belonging together. The stronger the tendency toward tonic, the more taut the
                    tension, whose expression is served precisely by the chromatic element,
                    alteration, the anticipation, the suspension, etc. Mozart must therefore be
                    considered one of the most significant practitioners of chromaticism. That form
                    is something animated, captivating, that the obligations of the form first grant
                    harmony its true significance is laid out in detail and with primal
                    understanding. The book will be very welcome to the educated musician. May its
                    sequel appear soon!</tei:p>
            </tei:div>

        </tei:div>
    </sdo:record>

</sdo:recordCollection>
