<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
    xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
    xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">

    <sdo:collectionDesc>
        <sdo:source>
            <sdo:other mfID="3346" sdoID="OC-54-337-39">OC 54/337-39</sdo:other>
        </sdo:source>
        <tei:handNotes>
            <tei:handNote xml:id="pr" scope="sole">printed</tei:handNote>
        </tei:handNotes>

        <tei:respStmt xml:id="WD">
            <tei:persName>William Drabkin</tei:persName>
            <tei:resp>Transcription, 2023</tei:resp>
            <tei:resp>Translation, 2023</tei:resp>
        </tei:respStmt>

        <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
            <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
            <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2023</tei:resp>
        </tei:respStmt>

        <tei:respStmt xml:id="TL">
            <tei:persName>Tamara Lopez</tei:persName>
            <tei:resp>XML Encoding, Model 2010</tei:resp>
        </tei:respStmt>

    </sdo:collectionDesc>


    <sdo:record ID="r0001">
        <sdo:itemDesc>
            <dc:title>Proof-sheets for an article summarizing Schenker’s achievements in works and
                editions published by Universal Edition</dc:title>
            <dc:type>Other</dc:type>
            <dcterms:created>1923-09-30T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
            <dcterms:dateSubmitted>2023-12-08</dcterms:dateSubmitted>

            <dc:description>Publicity material for Schenker's complete edition of the Beethoven
                piano sonatas and his Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien, vols I-II/2:
                galley-proofs (Universal Edition)</dc:description>
            <dc:subject/>
            <marcrel:author key="entity-000632">Heinrich Schenker</marcrel:author>

        </sdo:itemDesc>

        <tei:div type="transcription">


            <tei:div>

                <tei:note type="editorial" place="pre-text">Editorial note: This printed essay is in
                    two parts, the first devoted to Schenker’s edition of the Beethoven piano
                    sonatas, the second to his major theoretical works. The pages are numbered “8,
                    9, and 10” but give no clues as to the publication for which they were intended.
                    Schenker wrote the text himself, in the autumn of 1923 (see the diary entries of
                    September 15 and 28–30), after all 32 sonatas had appeared individually and as a
                    four-volume collected edition neared completion. The title of the first part
                    echoes that of the collected edition: <tei:title level="m">L. van Beethoven:
                        Klaviersonaten: Nach den Autographen und Erstdrucken rekonstruiert von
                        Heinrich Schenker</tei:title>. <tei:lb/>A similar piece of writing,
                    summarizing his achievement in the three <tei:title level="m"
                        >Meisterwerk</tei:title> yearbooks for Drei Masken Verlag, dates from
                    December 1931 (<tei:ref type="other" cRef="OJ-21-22_2">OJ 21/22, [2]</tei:ref>).
                    The two documents are otherwise unrelated.</tei:note>
                <tei:lb/>

                <tei:div type="par_1">
                    <tei:head>EINFÜHRENDE BEMERKUNGEN ZU DER REKONSTRUKTION DER
                        BEETHOVEN-SONATEN</tei:head>

                    <tei:ab><tei:pb n="1a"/> Aus Briefen <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055"
                            >Beethoven</tei:rs>s und sonstigen anderen Zeugnissen wissen wir, daß
                        der Meister mit den Drucken seiner Werke durchaus unzufrieden war. Sein
                        Tadel und Zorn kamen für das gedruckte Werk schon zu spät, nützten aber auch
                        gar nicht den noch zu druckenden Werken, obgleich er ausdrücklich darauf
                        hinwies, wie die Schreibart für den Inhalt wesentlich sei.<tei:note
                            xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">The correspondence
                            with publishers in which Beethoven complained his intentions were not
                            observed include, famously, a letter of May 6, 1811, to Breitkopf &amp;
                            Härtel concerning the Fantasia Op. 80 for piano, chorus and orchestra:
                            “Fehler – Fehler – sie sind selbst ein einziger Fehler – da muß ich
                            meinen Kopisten hinschicken, dort muß ich selbst hin, wenn ich will, daß
                            meine Werke – nicht als Bloße Fehler erscheinen.” (“Mistakes – mistakes
                            – you yourselves are a unique mistake – and so I must send my copyist
                                <tei:supplied reason="clarity">to Leipzig</tei:supplied> or go there
                            myself if don’t want my works to appear as mere mistakes.”)
                                    <tei:bibl><tei:title level="m">Ludwig van Beethoven:
                                    Briefwechsel Gesamtausgabe</tei:title>, ed. <tei:editor>Sieghard
                                    Brandenburg</tei:editor> (Munich: Henle, 1996), vol. 2, p. 187
                                (letter 496)</tei:bibl>. But Beethoven could be equally explosive
                            about his copyists failing to read his manuscript accurately.</tei:note>
                        Die Erstausgaben scheiterten einfach daran, daß die Setzer und Korrektoren
                        die Beziehung von diesem Inhalt und dieser Schreibart nicht begriffen, weil
                        beide durchaus neuartig waren.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>Die nach <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>s
                        Tode zunehmende Verbreitung seiner Werke schuf eine noch mißlichere Lage;
                        mit ihr kam eine Verflachung der musikalischen Instinkte, einem Naturgesetz
                        zufolge, gegen das sich der Mensch vergeblich aufzulehnen sucht. Hätte es
                        bloß gegolten, geringfügige drucktechnische oder orthographische
                        Verbesserungen durchzuführen – um ein Beispiel aus der Sprache anzuführen,
                        etwa „bei“ für „bey“, „Not“ für „Noth“ u. s. w. – aber da ging es um tiefste
                        Fragen der <tei:term>Synthese</tei:term>, <tei:term>Form</tei:term>,
                            <tei:term>Stimmführung</tei:term>, <tei:term>Rhythmik</tei:term>,
                            <tei:term>Artikulation</tei:term>, <tei:term>Dynamik</tei:term>, die
                        weder dem Instinkt, noch dem Bewußtsein der Herausgeber vertraut waren.
                        Zudem gingen die wenigsten von ihnen auf die Originale selbst zurück,
                        sondern maßen ihre Empfindung und Einsicht nur an den Ausgaben anderer
                        Herausgeber, mutwillig-persönlich, „auffassungslüstern“, wie wir das heute
                        an Dirigenten und Virtuosen sehen, die sich unbekümmert um die Sache
                        gegeneinander auszuspielen pflegen. Daß sich dann aber auch Musiker und
                        Liebhaber diesem Zustand gegenüber vollständig gleichgültig verhielten, darf
                        nicht weiter befremden: glaubten sie doch alle, in jeder Ausgabe den echten
                            <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> vor sich zu
                        haben, sodaß sie gar nicht in die Lage kamen, ihr Unterscheidungsvermögen
                        ins Feld zu führen; sie genossen, wie eigentlich immer, vor allem sich
                        selbst und erst in zweiter Reihe <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055"
                            >Beethoven</tei:rs>.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>Den ersten Schritt zur Besserung hat die Gesamtausgabe der
                            Beethoven-Werke,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial"
                            place="foot"><tei:bibl><tei:title>Ludwig van Beethovens Werke:
                                    vollständige kritisch durchgesehene überall berechtigte
                                    Ausgabe</tei:title>, 24 vols. (Leipzig: Breitkopf &amp; Härtel,
                                1862–65)</tei:bibl>; a supplementary volume was published in
                            1888.</tei:note> wie später die Urtext-Ausgabe<tei:note
                            xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial" place="foot">By <tei:hi
                                rend="italic">Urtext-Ausgabe</tei:hi>, Schenker is probably
                            referring to performing editions made directly from the collected
                            edition of 1862–65.</tei:note> gemacht als Ausgaben, die seit <tei:rs
                            type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>s Tode zum erstenmal
                        die Originale zu Rate gezogen. Indessen stand die Einsicht der Herausgeber
                        noch immer nicht auf der nötigen Höhe, so daß noch viel, sehr viel Schuld an
                        die Erstfassung abzutragen übrigblieb.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>Im Zusammenhang nun mit dem Rettungswerk, als das Schenker seine
                            „<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001723"><tei:title>Neue musikalische
                                Theorien und Phantasien</tei:title></tei:rs>“ auffaßt, stellte er
                        sich auch noch die Aufgabe, das unschätzbare <tei:rs type="person"
                            key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>-Gut endlich zu bereinigen. Unter
                        großen Opfern verschaffte er sich Einblick in alle heute nur irgend
                        erreichbare Originale, sei es Handschriften, Erstausgaben oder vom Autor
                        revidierten Abschriften, um nach Möglichkeit <tei:pb n="1b"/> die erste
                        Fassung zu ermitteln. Er äußert sich darüber in der <tei:rs type="work"
                            key="entity-001737"><tei:title>Erläuterungsausgabe</tei:title> von op.
                            101</tei:rs>, S. 19: <tei:cit>
                            <tei:q>Beethovens kräftiges, unmittelbares, sozusagen tonkörperliches
                                Denken bringt ihm von selbst eine auch das Auge des Lesers sinnlich
                                überzeugende Schreibart heran: <tei:lb/>das Steigen und Fallen der
                                Linien: hier sieht man sie aus dem unteren ins obere Notensystem
                                ziehen, dort vom oberen ins untere sinken; <tei:lb/>das tiefsinnige
                                Spiel der Balken: sie künden dem Auge, was im Inneren der Töne
                                vorgeht, den Willen zur Zusammengehörigkeit bei diesem
                                Trennungszwang bei jenen; <tei:lb/>die geheimnisvolle Beredsamkeit
                                der Bogen: einmal, was auch über Balken und Taktstriche hinweg Bezug
                                aufeinander atmet, absetzend, um Gegengewichten Platz zu machen,
                                öfter gleichzeitig auch in verschiedener Spannweite gegeneinander
                                wirkend, vermitteln sie das Bild wohlgepflegter und gesättigter
                                Gerechtigkeit im Gefüge der Teile und des Ganzen; <tei:lb/>das Auf-
                                und Abwärtsstreichen der Notenhälse: sie lassen uns die Töne als
                                gleichsam gegeneinanderwirkende Schauspieler wahrnehmen, scharf
                                umrissen im Mit- und Gegenspiel, am schönsten wohl dort, wo z. B.
                                ein Abwärtsstreichen lange voraus das Gegenspiel
                                aufwärtsgestrichener Tonfolgen (oder umgekehrt) so spannend
                                ankündigt; <tei:lb/>das Register der Pausen: sie fehlen zuweilen, um
                                dem Auge das Stimmganze luftiger zu zeigen und das Kommen und Gehen
                                mancher Stimme nicht mehr als nötig zu unterstreichen; und so vieles
                                andere mehr, wovon ich zahlreiche Beispiele schon in „<tei:rs
                                    type="work" key="entity-001734">op. 109</tei:rs>“, „<tei:rs
                                    type="work" key="entity-001735">110</tei:rs>“, „<tei:rs
                                    type="work" key="entity-001736">111</tei:rs>“, angeführt habe
                                und ebenso zahlreiche auch hier wieder bieten werde. <tei:lb/>Nicht
                                alle diese Unwägbarkeiten haben aber im Erstdruck Platz gefunden und
                                man kann es nur Zufall nennen, wenn manche zum Vorschein gekommen,
                                wie man freilich trotzdem alle Ursache hat, sich zu freuen, wenn
                                etwaige Verstöße der Originalausgabe sich bloß eben auf die hier
                                gemeinten Züge beschränken.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04"
                                    type="editorial" place="foot">
                                    <tei:bibl><tei:editor>Heinrich Schenker</tei:editor>, <tei:title
                                            level="m">Beethoven’s Last Piano Sonatas: An Edition
                                            with Elucidation</tei:title>, vol. 4 (Op. 101), ed. and
                                        trans. <tei:editor>John Rothgeb</tei:editor> (New York:
                                        Oxford University Press, 2015)</tei:bibl>, pp. 4–5
                                    (translation lightly modified).</tei:note></tei:q>
                        </tei:cit>
                    </tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>Demgemäß hat der Herausgeber auch berichtigt, was sonst noch an
                        Verstößen wider Taktstrich, <tei:term>Stimmführung</tei:term>,
                            <tei:term>Motiv</tei:term>, <tei:term>Dynamik</tei:term>,
                            <tei:term>Pedalisierung</tei:term> und <tei:term>Fingersatz</tei:term>
                        in den Ausgaben <tei:choice>
                            <tei:sic>rerbreitet</tei:sic>
                            <tei:corr>verbreitet</tei:corr>
                        </tei:choice> war. In diesem Sinne stellen nun die neugewonnenen Ergebnisse
                        – und darauf kam es dem Herausgeber im Zusammenhang seines Gesamtwerkes wohl
                        am meisten an – mittelbar auch einen neuen Beitrag zur Erkenntnis der
                            <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>’schen
                        Kunst, der Tonkunst überhaupt vor. Nur der Vergleich mit anderen Ausgaben
                        kann die unendliche Summe und Vielfalt dieser Ergebnisse deutlich machen.
                        Wer sich noch außerdem deren künstlerischen Wert zum Bewußtsein bringen
                        will, sehe des Herausgebers <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001733"
                                ><tei:title>Erläuterungsausgabe</tei:title></tei:rs> (<tei:rs
                            type="organization" key="entity-002408">Universal-Edition</tei:rs>) oder
                        die „<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001739"
                            ><tei:title>Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs>“-Hefte
                        (Tonwille-Flugblätter-Ver- <tei:pb n="2a"/> lag, Wien, I. Opernhaus –
                            <tei:rs type="organization" key="entity-002456">Albert J. Gutmann G. m.
                            b. H.</tei:rs>; Leipzig, Karlstraße 10 – <tei:rs type="organization"
                            key="entity-004628">Friedrich Hofmeister G. m. b. H.</tei:rs>) ein,
                        worin er <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>s
                        Inhalt und Schreibart erklärt und gegen die Herausgeber <tei:choice>
                            <tei:sic>verteitigt</tei:sic>
                            <tei:corr>verteidigt</tei:corr>
                        </tei:choice>.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>Schenker hat die Sonaten mit einem <tei:term>Fingersatz</tei:term>
                        versehen, die wenigen Stellen ausgenommen, die in Handschrift oder
                        Erstausgabe des Meisters <tei:term>Fingersatz</tei:term> aufweisen. Über die
                        Art seines <tei:term>Fingersatz</tei:term>es äußert er sich in der <tei:rs
                            type="work" key="entity-001735"
                                ><tei:title>Erläuterungsausgabe</tei:title> von op. 110</tei:rs>, S.
                        30: <tei:cit>
                            <tei:q>Mit der Freiheit des Rhythmus hängt endlich auch die Art meines
                                Fingersatzes organisch zusammen, weshalb es nicht anginge, diesen
                                etwa von abstrakten Gesichtspunkten aus zu beurteilen. So gut jede
                                einzelne Situation im Kunstwerk ihre {2b} eigene Freiheit aufweist,
                                die nicht aus allgemeinen Prinzipien, sondern eben nur aus den
                                besonderen Gründen der Situation hergeleitet werden kann, so gut hat
                                auch der <tei:term>Fingersatz</tei:term>, ohne auf allgemeine
                                Gesetze Rücksicht zu nehmen, die Besonderheit der Situation
                                auszudrücken. In diesem Sinne möge nun der Spieler, wie gesagt,
                                meinen <tei:term>Fingersatz</tei:term> mit als organischen Schlüssel
                                zur jeweiligen Situation betrachten; und hat er erst etwaige
                                Vorurteile vom Standpunkt des gangbaren
                                    <tei:term>Fingersatz</tei:term>es überwunden, so wird er bei
                                aufmerksamer und wohldurchdachter Ausführung sich selbst davon
                                überzeugen, wie geboten, ja notwendig er sich auch dort erweist, wo
                                er fürs erste nur den Eindruck eines sonderbaren macht.<tei:note
                                    xml:id="r0001-fn05" type="editorial" place="foot"
                                            ><tei:bibl><tei:editor>Heinrich Schenker</tei:editor>,
                                            <tei:title level="m">Beethoven’s Last Piano Sonatas: An
                                            Edition with Elucidation</tei:title>, vol. 2 (Op. 110),
                                        ed. and trans. <tei:editor>John Rothgeb</tei:editor> (New
                                        York: Oxford University Press, 2015)</tei:bibl>, pp. 20–21
                                    (translation lightly modified).</tei:note></tei:q>
                        </tei:cit></tei:ab>
                </tei:div>

                <tei:div type="part_2">

                    <tei:head>EINFÜHRENDE BEMERKUNGEN ZU DEN NEUEN MUSIKALISCHEN THEORIEN UND
                        PHANTASIEN</tei:head>

                    <tei:ab><tei:pb n="2a"/> Die „<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001723"
                                ><tei:title>Neuen musikalischen Theorien und
                            Phantasien</tei:title></tei:rs>“ stellen ein auf vier Bände berechnetes
                        Werk vor. Der erste Band ist der <tei:term>Harmonielehre</tei:term>, der
                        zweite und dritte Band der Lehre vom <tei:term>Kontrapunkt</tei:term> als
                        der <tei:term>Stimmführung</tei:term> an sich, endlich der vierte dem
                            <tei:term>freien Satz</tei:term> als den
                            <tei:term>Prolongation</tei:term>en der
                            <tei:term>Stimmführung</tei:term> bei <tei:term>Stufe</tei:term> und
                            <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> gewidmet. (Durch eine weitere Folge von
                        losen Bänden unter dem Titel „<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001756"
                                ><tei:title>Entwurf einer neuen Formenlehre</tei:title></tei:rs>“,
                            „<tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001759"><tei:title>Niedergang der
                                Kompositionskunst</tei:title></tei:rs>“, „<tei:rs type="work"
                            key="entity-001757"><tei:title>Kunst des Vortrages</tei:title></tei:rs>“
                        u. s. w. soll das Hauptwerk vervollständigt werden.)<tei:note
                            xml:id="r0001-fn06" type="editorial" place="foot">Of these, the <tei:rs
                                type="work" key="entity-001759"><tei:title level="m">Decline of the
                                    Art of Composition</tei:title></tei:rs>, initially conceived as
                            an appendix to the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724"><tei:title
                                    level="m">Theory of Harmony</tei:title></tei:rs>, existed as a
                            near-complete text in 1907. The studies of performance and musical form
                            also have their origins in that year, but <tei:rs type="work"
                                key="entity-001757"><tei:title level="m">The Art of
                                    Performance</tei:title></tei:rs> remained a work in progress in
                            Schenker’s life, and was published under that title, <tei:bibl>ed.
                                    <tei:editor>Heribert Esser</tei:editor>, transl.
                                    <tei:editor>Irene Schreier Scott</tei:editor> (New York: Oxford
                                University Press, 2000)</tei:bibl>, and a theory of form – very much
                            in outline – is included as the final section of <tei:rs type="work"
                                key="entity-001728"><tei:title level="m">Free
                                    Composition</tei:title></tei:rs>.</tei:note></tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>Von sämtlichen älteren und neueren Lehrbüchern unterscheidet sich
                        Schenkers <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724"
                                ><tei:title>Harmonielehre</tei:title></tei:rs> schon äußerlich
                        dadurch, daß sie keine Aufgaben führt, und die <tei:rs type="work"
                            key="entity-001725"><tei:title>Kontrapunktlehre</tei:title></tei:rs> (1.
                        und 2. Halbband) wieder dadurch, daß sie fortlaufend durch Ausblicke auf den
                            <tei:term>freien Satz</tei:term> gefördert wird, wo allein die
                            <tei:term>Stimmführung</tei:term> – allerdings in prolongierter Form –
                        anzutreffen ist. Im <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001725"
                                ><tei:title>Kontrapunkt</tei:title></tei:rs> werden dann freilich
                        Aufgaben gebracht, mehr sogar als in anderen üblichen Lehrbüchern des
                        Kontrapunktes. Zu dem Inhalt der Bände im einzelnen ist zu sagen:</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>An die Spitze der <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724"
                                ><tei:title>Harmonielehre</tei:title></tei:rs> ist der Grundgedanke
                        vom biologischen Eigenleben der Tonkunst gestellt: die Musik wurde erst zur
                        Kunst, als sie in <tei:term>Wiederholung</tei:term> und
                            <tei:term>Motivbildung</tei:term> die unentbehrliche Assoziation aus
                        sich selbst hervorzubringen gelernt hat. Daß der Gedanke vom Eigenleben der
                        Musik bis heute <tei:pb n="2b"/> weder gefaßt noch erfaßt worden, hat sich
                        als das eigentliche Hindernis eines wahren Fortschrittes in Ausübung und
                        Erkenntnis bei Musikern, Philosophen und Ästhetikern erwiesen. In der
                            <tei:term>Wiederholung</tei:term> liegt zugleich schon der Keim aller
                        Formen. Wenn die Musik auch nur vorübergehend auf die
                            <tei:term>Wiederholung</tei:term> verzichtet hört sie auf Musik zu sein
                        und nähert sich vielmehr dem Wesen der Sprache.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>Zum erstenmal – der Band erschien im Jahre 1906 – wird der Begriff eines
                            <tei:term>Tonsystem</tei:term>s überhaupt und unserer beiden
                        Tongeschlechter im besonderen erkannt und geformt: Die Natur stellt die
                        Quint („… eine höhere Einheit, gleichsam das Meter des
                            Tonkünstlers“)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn07" type="editorial"
                            place="foot">See <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724"><tei:title
                                    level="m">Harmonielehre</tei:title></tei:rs>, part I, section 1,
                            chapter 1, paragraph 12 (p. 39; p. 26 in Elisabeth Mann Borgese’s
                            English translation). The text here differs slightly, however, from that
                            in the book, where Schenker had written <tei:hi rend="italic">eine
                                Höreinheit</tei:hi>, “an auditory unit.”</tei:note> bei, während die
                        Bedürfnisse der <tei:term>Wiederholung</tei:term> den Zusammenschluß von
                        sieben verschiedenen Tönen als rein künstlichen Teil bestimmen. Das
                        Künstlerische des Systems zeigt sich noch in der
                            <tei:term>Inversion</tei:term> als einem Gegenstück des
                        Quinten-Aufwärtstriebes der Natur: sie führt zur Entstehung der
                        Unterquint-Tonika, Ober- und Unterdominante beseitigen nun alle
                        Widersprüche, die sich aus dem naturhaften Dur der Töne als Systemglieder
                        ergeben mußten. Das ist nun das Dur-System, das natürliche. Ihm wird
                        künstlich das Moll-System nachgebildet, mit durchgängiger Nachahmung alles
                        dessen, worin das Dur-System begrifflich begründet ist.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>Die alten Kirchentonarten werden dagegen als Systeme zurückgewiesen: der
                        knappe Inhalt der damaligen Musik duldete erst eine horizontale Auffassung
                        der <tei:term>Tonart</tei:term> und könnte <tei:pb n="3a"/> zu einem
                        wirklichen System noch gar nicht drängen, dessen erste Voraussetzung ja
                        Reichtum der <tei:term>Auskomponierung</tei:term> mit weitgreifendem
                            <tei:term>Außensatz</tei:term> ist.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>Auch in der Mischung von Dur und Moll sieht Schenker ein biologisches
                        Zeichen, das reichere Sichausleben eines Toninhaltes.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>Als wesentliches Merkmal des Intervall-Begriffes wird – anders als
                        bisher – die Diatoniefähigkeit hingestellt. Damit wird von vornherein ein
                        Riegel vorgeschoben, aller Spintisiererei über „neue“ Klänge, Tonarten u. s.
                        w., die das Ohr um das gute Hören und Schaffen bringt.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>Die <tei:term>Stufe</tei:term> wird als eine höhere Einheit erkannt: sie
                        ist zwar ein Dreiklang, aber nicht jeder Dreiklang ist eine
                            <tei:term>Stufe</tei:term>. Schenker zeigt an vielen Beispielen diese
                        überragende Erscheinung und gibt aus der Fülle der Bedingungen, die sie
                        bestimmen, eine beträchtliche Auswahl, vorbehaltlich noch weiterer, die erst
                        im vierten Band zur Darstellung gelangen sollen. Der Begriff der
                            <tei:term>Stufe</tei:term> wird sodann gegenüber den
                            <tei:term>Stimmführung</tei:term>sklängen im <tei:term>strengen
                            Satz</tei:term>, die keine <tei:term>Stufe</tei:term>n sind, erhärtet
                        und auch noch in seiner historischen Herkunft erläutert. Hieran schließt
                        sich endlich eine Kritik der Harmonielehrbücher.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>Es folgt die Lehre von den Drei- und Vierklängen, die Fünfklänge werden
                        verneint und grundsätzlich zu den Vorhälten gezählt.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>Nun wird in neuer Weise gezeigt wie
                        <tei:term>Tonikalisierung</tei:term>, <tei:term>Chromatik</tei:term>,
                            <tei:term>Alteration</tei:term> in den Dienst der
                            <tei:term>Diatonie</tei:term> sich stellen und dabei der Grundsatz
                        ausgesprochen „daß man schon um der <tei:term>Diatonie</tei:term> willen
                        nicht genug chromatisch schreiben kann.“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn08"
                            type="editorial" place="foot"><tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724"
                                    ><tei:title level="m">Harmonielehre</tei:title></tei:rs>, part
                            II, section 2, chapter 4, paragraph 155 (p. 380; p. 289). In the book,
                            Schenker had written <tei:hi rend="italic">um der Diatonie selbst
                                willen</tei:hi>, “for sake of the diatonicsm
                        itself.”</tei:note></tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>Endlich wird die Modulation auf eine breitere Grundlage gebracht und
                        entgegen dem billigen Wahn von heute der Begriff des Präludierens als einer
                        freien Phantasie im Sinne der älteren improvisationskündigen Meister
                        richtiggestellt. Zur praktischen Bewertung seiner <tei:rs type="work"
                            key="entity-001724"><tei:title>Harmonielehre</tei:title></tei:rs> konnte
                        übrigens Schenker schon im Jahre 1910 in der Vorrede zum <tei:rs type="work"
                            key="entity-001726"><tei:title>Kontrapunkt</tei:title></tei:rs>, S.
                        XXXIV, Stellung nehmen. <tei:cit>
                            <tei:q>Im Übrigen wurde der Inhalt zwar vielfach als „geistvoll“
                                bezeichnet, dabei aber der Zweifel geäußert, ob meine Lehre gerade
                                in dieser Form praktischen Wert haben könnte? Nun, ich glaube sagen
                                zu dürfen, daß es doch ungleich praktischer ist, einem Kunstjünger
                                zu zeigen, woher er – von der Urquelle der Inspiration freilich
                                abgesehen – seinen Inhalt zu beziehen habe, als ihn bloß mit
                                Tonpuppen spielen zu lassen, was doch nur einen Müßiggang bedeutet,
                                obendrein einen teuer erkauften. Hat der Schüler im Kontrapunkt
                                vorerst die Kunst der Stimmführung gelernt, so mag es ihm dann in
                                der Welt der Stufen genügen zu sehen: wer sie seien, wie sie an
                                Inhalt eintragen, wie sie sich zur Form verhalten, wie viel an
                                Stufengang der eine, der andere Gedanke verbraucht, wie man an
                                Stufen sparen und dennoch zugleich den Gedanken weit bauen kann u.
                                s. w., u. s. w.“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn09" type="editorial"
                                    place="foot">See pp. xxxi¬–xxxii of Rothgeb and Thym’s English
                                    edition (translation modified). </tei:note></tei:q>
                        </tei:cit></tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab><tei:pb n="3b"/> Im <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001726">ersten
                            Halbband des <tei:title>Kontrapunkt</tei:title></tei:rs>es entwirft
                        Schenker zunächst den Unterschied seiner neuen Lehre gegenüber der in den
                        Hauptwerken der vokalen und <tei:term>Generalbaß</tei:term>-Epoche (<tei:rs
                            type="person" key="entity-000269">Fux</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person"
                            key="entity-000025">Ph. Em. Bach</tei:rs>): sie will die grundlegenden
                        Begriffe der <tei:term>Stimmführung</tei:term> auch ohne die störende
                        Beimengung von Gesichtspunkten des <tei:term>freien Satz</tei:term>es
                        vermitteln, um dann erst recht die Prolongationen entwickeln zu können. Er
                        behält zwar die Einteilung des Stoffes nach <tei:rs type="person"
                            key="entity-000269">Fux</tei:rs> bei, drängt aber bei der Bildung der
                        einzelnen Begriffe auf deren tiefsten, unzerstörbaren Kern unter ständiger
                        kritischer Beleuchtung und Berichtigung der Ergebnisse in den bekannten
                        Lehrbüchern.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>So wird der Begriff des <tei:term>cantus firmus</tei:term> bereinigt, in
                        der 1. Gattung die Frage der Quart<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10"
                            type="editorial" place="foot">That is, the status of the interval of a
                            fourth as a consonance or dissonance.</tei:note> zutiefst und der
                        parallelgeraden, wie unparallelgeraden Folgen der Lösung zugeführt, in der
                        2. Gattung der Begriff des Durchganges, und in der 4. Gattung der der
                        Synkope in ihren unabänderlichen Merkmalen erläutert.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>Im <tei:term>dreistimmigen Satz</tei:term> (2. Halbband) werden als neu
                        die wesentlichen Begriffe der Grundtonhaftigkeit und des
                            <tei:term>Außensatz</tei:term>es aufgestellt. Im letzteren läuft der
                        ursprüngliche <tei:term>zweistimmige</tei:term> als der alleinige Träger des
                            <tei:term>strengen Satz</tei:term>es fort. Bei den Schlüssen im
                            <tei:term>dreistimmigen Satz</tei:term> wird auf die Entstehung der V.
                            <tei:term>Stufe</tei:term> hingewiesen. Im Verlauf der weiteren
                        Gattungen des <tei:term>dreistimmigen Satz</tei:term>es werden die schon im
                            <tei:term>strengen Satz</tei:term> möglichen
                            <tei:term>Prolongation</tei:term>en aufgezeigt, so die neuen Begriffe
                        der Knotenpunkte überhaupt, zunächst des Terzknotenpunkten, sodann des
                            <tei:term>Quartzug</tei:term>es.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>Zum erstenmal werden Mischungsaufgaben methodisch ausgebaut<tei:note
                            xml:id="r0001-fn11" type="editorial" place="foot">By “mixed species”
                            Schenker means the combination of two or more species lines against the
                                <tei:hi rend="italic">cantus firmus</tei:hi> in counterpoint
                            comprising three or more voices. In <tei:title level="m">Gradus ad
                                Parnassum</tei:title>, there is just one such example, in which each
                            of the four voices is in a different species of counterpoint: whole
                            notes (the <tei:hi rend="italic">cantus firmus</tei:hi>), half notes,
                            quarter notes, and tied notes. </tei:note> und darin die Entstehung der
                            <tei:term>Durchgang</tei:term>sklänge (nicht nur einzeln durchgehender
                        Töne) erwiesen, hierbei die <tei:term>Prolongation</tei:term>en des
                        springenden <tei:term>Durchgang</tei:term>es, eines
                            <tei:term>Stimmentausch</tei:term>es des dissonanten Zusammenstoßes u.
                        s. w. vorgeführt. Die Mischung der Synkopengattung mit anderen Gattungen
                        insbesondere erhärtet den bedeutsamen Unterschied der Syncope 9–8 und 4–3
                        als wirklicher Vorhälte gegenüber den anderen überbundenen Erscheinungen,
                        die zweideutig sind, d. h. unter Umständen Vorhälte, aber auch
                        vierklangähnliche Bildungen sein können.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>Die Beflissenheit, zur letztmöglichen Klarheit und Sicherheit der
                        Begriffe zu gelangen, die eine Kritik der verschiedenen andern Methoden und
                        Lehrbücher einschloß, führte von selbst zu einer enzyklopädischen
                        Darstellung des <tei:term>Kontrapunkt</tei:term>es, die jedem Leser
                        ermöglicht, an Ort und Stelle die Verschiedenheit in der Auffassung der
                        Begriffe zu überprüfen.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>Als Stoff des letzten Bandes, der in Vorbereitung begriffen ist, kündigt
                        Schenker den <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title>freien
                                Satz</tei:title></tei:rs> an, worin die
                            <tei:term>Prolongation</tei:term>en im weitesten Ausbau gezeigt und
                        namentlich der Anteil der <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term> ins Licht gerückt
                        werden soll.</tei:ab>

                </tei:div>

            </tei:div>

        </tei:div>


        <tei:div type="translation">


            <tei:div>

                <tei:div type="par_1">
                    <tei:head>INTRODUCTORY REMARKS ON THE RECONSTRUCTION BEETHOVEN’S
                        SONATAS</tei:head>

                    <tei:ab><tei:pb n="1a"/> From letters by <tei:rs type="person"
                            key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> and various other witnesses, we
                        know that the master was thoroughly dissatisfied with the printed editions
                        of his works.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> His reproach
                        and anger came too late for a work that had already been published, but they
                        were also of no use whatever for works still to be published, although he
                        expressly pointed out how his manner of writing was significant for the
                        content. The first editions failed simply because printers and editors did
                        not understand the relationship between this content and this manner of
                        writing, as both were completely new.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>The increasing dissemination of <tei:rs type="person"
                            key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>’s works after his death created
                        an even more unfortunate situation; it resulted in a levelling of musical
                        instincts, in accordance with a law of Nature against which it is futile to
                        rebel. If only it were just a matter of making minor typographical or
                        orthographical changes, such as using <tei:hi rend="italic">bei</tei:hi> for
                            <tei:hi rend="italic">bey</tei:hi> or <tei:hi rend="italic">Not</tei:hi>
                        for <tei:hi rend="italic">Noth</tei:hi>, to give examples from written
                        language. What was at stake, however, were the most profound questions of
                            <tei:term>synthesis</tei:term>, <tei:term>form</tei:term>,
                            <tei:term>voice-leading</tei:term>, <tei:term>rhythm</tei:term>,
                            <tei:term>articulation</tei:term>, and <tei:term>dynamics</tei:term>,
                        which the editors understood neither instinctively nor consciously.
                        Moreover, only a very few of them referred to the original materials;
                        instead they measured their feeling and understanding only on the editions
                        of other editors in an arbitrarily personal way, with what could be called
                        “interpretive wantonness.” We can see this today among conductors and
                        virtuoso artists who like to play themselves off against one another,
                        untroubled by the matter. That ordinary musicians and amateurs, however,
                        were entirely indifferent to this situation should come as no surprise: for
                        they all believed that, in every edition, they had the true <tei:rs
                            type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> in front of them.
                        And so they never were able to exercise their discriminatory powers; they
                        enjoyed themselves above all, as it always happens to be the case, and
                            <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs> only in
                        second place.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>The first steps towards improving the situation were taken by the
                        collected edition of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055"
                            >Beethoven</tei:rs>’s works,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02"
                            type="footnote"/> and later by the <tei:hi rend="italic">Urtext</tei:hi>
                            edition,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03" type="footnote"/> editions which,
                        for the first time since <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055"
                            >Beethoven</tei:rs>’s death, consulted the original sources.
                        Nonetheless, the insight of the editors was still never at the necessary
                            <tei:supplied reason="clarity">musical</tei:supplied> level, so that a
                        great deal of responsibility still lay with the original version.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>Then, in connection with his rescue work, as he understands his <tei:rs
                            type="work" key="entity-001723"><tei:title level="m">New Musical
                                Theories and Fantasies</tei:title></tei:rs>, Schenker also undertook
                        the task of finally cleaning up the inestimable collective work of <tei:rs
                            type="person" key="entity-000055">Beethoven</tei:rs>. Making great
                        sacrifices, he gained insight into all original sources that were somehow
                        accessible today, whether autograph manuscripts, first editions, or
                        handwritten copies revised by the composer, in order to determine the
                        original version. <tei:pb n="1b"/> He explains this in the <tei:rs
                            type="work" key="entity-001737"><tei:title level="m"
                                >Erläuterungsausgabe</tei:title> of Op. 101</tei:rs>, on p. 19: <tei:cit>
                            <tei:q>Beethoven’s powerful, direct, one might say “tone-physical”
                                thinking presents him with a way of writing that is sensually
                                convincing even to the reader’s eye: <tei:lb/>the rise and fall of
                                lines: here we see them rise from the lower to the upper staff, and
                                fall back into the lower; <tei:lb/>the profound play of the beaming:
                                they convey to the eye what is happening inside the notes: the will
                                towards relatedness on the one hand, the compulsion towards
                                separation on the other; <tei:lb/>the mysterious eloquence of the
                                slurs: by uniting what breathes of association even across beams and
                                bar-lines, and by separating in order to provide space for
                                counterweights, often acting against one another across different
                                time-spans, they convey a picture of a well ordered and mature
                                justice in the structure of the parts and the whole; <tei:lb/>the
                                upwards and downwards stemming of noteheads: they allow us to
                                perceive the notes almost as actors playing themselves off against
                                one another, sharply projected in collaboration and opposition, most
                                beautifully where, for example, a downwards stemming announces so
                                grippingly the opposition of an upward-stemmed series of notes (or
                                vice versa) long in advance; <tei:lb/>the registral specification of
                                the rests: they are sometimes omitted, so as to make the overall
                                picture of the voices clearer to the eye and to underscore the entry
                                and exit of several voices no more than is necessary; <tei:lb/>and
                                much else besides, as I have already shown in my editions of <tei:rs
                                    type="work" key="entity-001734">Op. 109</tei:rs>, <tei:rs
                                    type="work" key="entity-001735">Op. 110</tei:rs>, and <tei:rs
                                    type="work" key="entity-001736">Op. 111</tei:rs>, and shall do
                                so again here in great number. <tei:lb/>Not all of these
                                imponderables, however, have made their way into first editions; and
                                one can say that it is only by chance that some have appeared, as
                                one has every reason, nevertheless, to be happy if any offenses
                                committed in original edition are restricted to the characteristics
                                enumerated here.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"
                                /></tei:q>
                        </tei:cit>
                    </tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>Accordingly, the editor also corrected what had otherwise continued to
                        be disseminated as infringements against the barline, the
                            <tei:term>voice-leading</tei:term>, <tei:term>motive</tei:term>s,
                            <tei:term>dynamics</tei:term>, <tei:term>pedaling</tei:term> and
                            <tei:term>fingering</tei:term> in <tei:supplied reason="clarity"
                            >later</tei:supplied> editions. In this respect the newly gained results
                        also represent indirectly – and this is what mattered the most to the
                        editor, in connection with his overall work – a new contribution to the
                        recognition of <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055"
                        >Beethoven</tei:rs>’s art, and of the art of music in general. Only a
                        comparison with other editions can make the infinite totality and variety of
                        these results clear. Anyone who wishes, in addition, to generate an
                        awareness of their artistic worth should look at the editor’s <tei:rs
                            type="work" key="entity-001733"><tei:title level="m"
                                >Erläuterungsausgabe</tei:title></tei:rs> (<tei:rs
                            type="organization" key="entity-002408">Universal Edition</tei:rs>) or
                        the issues of <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001739"><tei:title level="j"
                                >Der Tonwille</tei:title></tei:rs> (issued by the
                        Tonwille-Flugblätter publishing house, Vienna I, State Opera House: <tei:rs
                            type="organization" key="entity-002456">Albert J. Gutmann
                            p.l.c.</tei:rs>; Leipzig, Karlstraße 10: <tei:rs type="organization"
                            key="entity-004628">Friedrich Hofmeister p.l.c.</tei:rs>), <tei:pb
                            n="2a"/> in which he explains <tei:rs type="person" key="entity-000055"
                            >Beethoven</tei:rs>’s content and writing style and defends himself
                        against the <tei:supplied reason="clarity">other</tei:supplied>
                        editors.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>Schenker has furnished the sonatas with a <tei:term>fingering</tei:term>
                        which, except in a few places, displays the master’s
                            <tei:term>fingering</tei:term> in his autograph manuscript or in the
                        first edition. Concerning the nature of his <tei:term>fingering</tei:term>,
                        he writes as follows on p. 30 in the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001735"
                            >elucidatory edition of Op. 110</tei:rs>: <tei:cit>
                            <tei:q>There is also, finally, an organic connection between freedom of
                                rhythm and the nature of my <tei:term>fingering</tei:term>. For this
                                reason it is not appropriate to judge the latter from, say, abstract
                                perspectives. As surely as any individual situation in a work of art
                                exhibits its {2b} own freedom, which cannot be derived from general
                                principles but verily only from the particular reasons connected to
                                the situation, so my <tei:term>fingering</tei:term> should just as
                                surely express the individuality of the situation without taking
                                heed of general principles. Seen in this way, the player, as I have
                                said, must consider my fingering as the organic key to the situation
                                at hand; and once he has overcome any possible prejudices from the
                                standpoint of a viable <tei:term>fingering</tei:term>, he will, with
                                attentive and well thought-out execution, convince himself of how
                                practical, even how necessary, my fingering proves to be, even where
                                it initially gave the impression of being something merely
                                    idiosyncratic.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn05" type="footnote"
                                /></tei:q>
                        </tei:cit></tei:ab>
                </tei:div>

                <tei:div type="part_2">

                    <tei:head>INTRODUCTORY REMARKS ON THE NEW MUSICAL THEORIES AND
                        FANTASIES</tei:head>

                    <tei:ab><tei:pb n="2a"/> The <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001723"><tei:title
                                level="m">New Musical Theories and Fantasies</tei:title></tei:rs>
                        present a work comprising four volumes. The first is devoted to the
                            <tei:term>theory of harmony</tei:term>, the second and third to the
                        discipline of <tei:term>counterpoint</tei:term> considered as
                            <tei:term>voice-leading</tei:term> in and of itself; the fourth and
                        final volume is dedicated to the study of <tei:term>free
                            counterpoint</tei:term> as <tei:term>prolongation</tei:term>s of the
                            <tei:term>voice-leading</tei:term> within the context of
                            <tei:term>harmonic function</tei:term>, and
                        <tei:term>Urlinie</tei:term>. (This main work will be rounded out by a
                        series of separate volumes entitled <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001756"
                                ><tei:title level="m">Outline of a New Theory of
                            Form</tei:title></tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001759"
                                ><tei:title level="m">The Decline of the Art of
                                Composition</tei:title></tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="work"
                            key="entity-001757"><tei:title level="m">The Art of
                                Performance</tei:title></tei:rs>, and so on.)<tei:ptr
                            corresp="#r0001-fn06" type="footnote"/></tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>Even from its outward appearance, Schenker’s <tei:rs type="work"
                            key="entity-001724"><tei:title level="m">Theory of
                            Harmony</tei:title></tei:rs> is distinguished from all other harmony
                        textbooks in that it contains no exercises; and his <tei:rs type="work"
                            key="entity-001725"><tei:title level="m"
                            >Counterpoint</tei:title></tei:rs> (first and second half-volumes) is
                        likewise different in that it is constantly supported by making reference to
                        examples of <tei:term>free composition</tei:term>, in which
                            <tei:term>voice-leading</tei:term> alone – albeit in extended form – is
                        encountered. In <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001725"><tei:title level="m"
                                >Counterpoint</tei:title></tei:rs>, assignments are of course
                        offered, actually more than one finds in the other common textbooks on
                        counterpoint. The following points may be said about the particular content
                        of the volumes:</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>At the forefront of the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724"
                                ><tei:title level="m">Theory of Harmony</tei:title></tei:rs> is the
                        basic idea of the independent life of the art of music: music became an art
                        only when it learned to create important relationships from within itself,
                        through <tei:term>repetition</tei:term> and <tei:term>motivic
                            construction</tei:term>. That the idea that music has a life of its own
                        has hitherto <tei:pb n="2b"/> been neither grasped nor understood has been
                        shown to be the real impediment to a true progress in its practice and
                        understanding among musicians, philosophers, and aestheticians.
                            <tei:term>Repetition</tei:term> already contains the seed of all forms:
                        if music forgoes <tei:term>repetition</tei:term>, even if only temporarily,
                        it ceases to be music and instead approaches the character of speech. </tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>For the first time – the volume appeared in 1906 – the concept of a
                            <tei:term>tonal system</tei:term> in general, and our two musical modes
                        in particular, was understood and expressed: Nature provides the interval of
                        a fifth (“… a higher unity, so to speak the composer’s yardstick”),<tei:ptr
                            corresp="#r0001-fn07" type="footnote"/> whereas the needs of
                            <tei:term>repetition</tei:term> determine the affiliation of seven
                        different tones as a purely artificial component. The artistic part of the
                        system is still manifest in <tei:term>inversion</tei:term>, as a counterpart
                        to the upwards striving of the fifth in nature: it leads to the genesis of
                        the tonic of the lower fifth, the upper and lower fifth now eliminating all
                        contradictions that would have resulted from the natural major quality of
                        the tones as components of the system. That is, then, the major system, the
                        natural one. The minor system is copied from it, artificially, with passing
                        imitation of all the elements on which the major system is conceptually
                        based.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>The ancient church modes, on the other hand, are rejected as systems:
                        the limited content of the music of that time tolerated only a horizontal
                        understanding of <tei:term>tonality</tei:term> and <tei:pb n="3a"/> was not
                        at all able yet to achieve the status of a true system, whose first
                        requirement is indeed the richness of <tei:term>elaboration</tei:term> with
                        a far-reaching <tei:term>outer-voice counterpoint</tei:term>.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>The mixture of major and minor is also something Schenker understands as
                        a biological sign, the richer, fuller life of a musical content.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>The property of diatonicism is proclaimed – differently from before – as
                        an essential sign of the concept of interval. In this way one can at the
                        outset put a stop to all fantasizing about “new” chords and tonalities, and
                        so on, which prevent the ear from hearing and creating well.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>The <tei:term>essential harmony</tei:term> (<tei:hi rend="italic"
                            >Stufe</tei:hi>) is understood as a higher entity: it is, to be sure, a
                        triad, but not all triads can be understood as <tei:term>essential
                            harmonies</tei:term>. Schenker demonstrates this far-reaching phenomenon
                        with many examples; and from the multitude of conditions that determines it
                        he presents a considerable selection, more of which will be introduced in
                        the fourth volume. The concept of <tei:term>essential harmonies</tei:term> –
                        as opposed to harmonies resulting from <tei:term>voice-leading</tei:term> in
                            <tei:term>strict counterpoint</tei:term>, which are not essential – is
                        then strengthened and also elucidated even in its historical origins. At
                        this point a critique of harmony textbooks is finally appended.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>There follows the theory of triads and seventh chords; the ninth chord
                        is rejected as a chord in its own right and reckoned as a chord with a
                        suspension.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>It is then shown, in a new way, how <tei:term>tonicization</tei:term>,
                            <tei:term>chromaticism</tei:term>, <tei:term>alteration</tei:term> are
                        used in the service of the <tei:term>diatonic system</tei:term> and thus how
                        the basic principle “that one cannot write chromatically enough even for
                        sake of the <tei:term>diatonicism</tei:term>"<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn08"
                            type="footnote"/> can be expressed.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>Finally, modulation is provided with a broader foundation; and, in
                        opposition to the cheap delusions of today, the idea of creating a prelude
                        in the manner of a free fantasy – as the masters of old, who were skilled in
                        improvisation, understood it – is put right. The practical evaluation of
                        Schenker’s <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001724"><tei:title level="m"
                                >Theory of Harmony</tei:title></tei:rs> is something about which
                        Schenker could say something as early as 1910, on p. xxxiv of the forward to
                            <tei:supplied reason="clarity">the first volume of</tei:supplied>
                        <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001726"><tei:title level="m"
                                >Counterpoint</tei:title></tei:rs>: <tei:cit>
                            <tei:q>Moreover, the content was actually described on numerous
                                occasions as ‘intellectually stimulating,’ but doubt was then
                                expressed as to whether my theory had any practical value in this
                                form. I believe that I may now say that it is in fact incomparably
                                more practical to show a disciple of the art of music <tei:supplied
                                    reason="clarity">the principles</tei:supplied> upon which he
                                should base his content – apart, of course, from the original source
                                of his inspiration – rather than letting him merely play with
                                musical puppets, something which would signify merely laziness, and
                                a dearly bought laziness at that. If a counterpoint student has
                                first of all learned the art of voice-leading, then it will suffice
                                for him to see, in the realm of essential harmonies, what they are,
                                how they gain in content, how they are related to form, how long a
                                progression of essential harmonies is needed for one or another
                                musical theme, how one can be sparing in the use of essential
                                harmonies and still be able at the same time to expand that theme,
                                etc., etc.”<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn09" type="footnote"/></tei:q>
                        </tei:cit></tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab><tei:pb n="3b"/> In the <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001726">first
                            volume of <tei:title level="m">Counterpoint</tei:title></tei:rs>,
                        Schenker begins by differentiating his new theory from the principal works
                        of the period of vocal music and <tei:term>thoroughbass</tei:term> (<tei:rs
                            type="person" key="entity-000269">Fux</tei:rs>, <tei:rs type="person"
                            key="entity-000025">C. P. E. Bach</tei:rs>); it seeks to communicate the
                        basic concepts of <tei:term>voice-leading</tei:term> without the harmful
                        effect of admixture from the viewpoint of <tei:term>free
                            composition</tei:term>, in order to then be able to properly develop
                            <tei:term>prolongation</tei:term>s. He adheres to <tei:rs type="person"
                            key="entity-000269">Fux</tei:rs>’s arrangement of the material, but in
                        forming the individual concepts he searchs for their deepest, indestructible
                        meaning with constant critical examination and correction of the results in
                        the well-known theory books.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>Thus the concept of <tei:term><tei:hi rend="italic">cantus
                                firmus</tei:hi></tei:term> is clarified; in the first species, the
                        status of the interval of the fourth<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn10"
                            type="footnote"/> and the matter of parallel and anti-parallel
                            <tei:supplied reason="clarity">fifths and octaves</tei:supplied> are
                        examined most deeply; the passing note in the second species and tied notes
                        in the fourth species are explained in accordance with their immutable
                        properties.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>In <tei:term>three-voice counterpoint</tei:term> (second volume
                            <tei:supplied reason="clarity">of <tei:title level="m"
                                >Counterpoint</tei:title></tei:supplied>), the essential concepts of
                        roothood and <tei:term>outer-voice structure</tei:term> are presented. In
                        the latter, the original <tei:term>two-voice counterpoint</tei:term>
                        proceeds as the sole bearer of <tei:term>strict counterpoint</tei:term>. In
                        the discussion of cadences in <tei:term>three-voice counterpoint</tei:term>,
                        it is shown how the dominant harmony (V) is arrived at. In the course of
                        further species in three voices, the <tei:term>prolongation</tei:term>s that
                        were already possible in <tei:term>strict counterpoint</tei:term> are
                        revealed, thus the new concepts of nodal point in general, firstly nodal
                        points of the third, then of fourth-progressions.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>For the first time, exercises in mixed-species counterpoint are expanded
                            methodically,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn1" type="footnote"/> and in this
                        way the origins of <tei:term>passing harmonies</tei:term> (not simply
                        individual <tei:term>passing tone</tei:term>s) are shown; in this connection
                            <tei:term>prolongation</tei:term>s of a leaping <tei:term>passing
                            note</tei:term>, of a <tei:term>voice exchange</tei:term> with a
                        dissonant clash, etc. are introduced. Mixing the species of tied notes with
                        other species, in particular, confirms the significant difference between
                        ~9–8 and ~4–3 configurations, which are true suspensions, and the other
                        tied-over phenomena, which are ambiguous: they could be suspensions in
                        certain circumstances, but they could also be like seventh-chord
                        constructions.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab> The author’s keenness to arrive at the ultimate clarity and security of
                        the concepts, which embraces a critique of the various other methods and
                        teaching manuals, led automatically to an encyclopedic presentation of
                            <tei:term>counterpoint</tei:term>, which enables every reader to verify
                        on the spot the variety in the interpretation of the concepts.</tei:ab>

                    <tei:ab>As subject of the last volume, which is in progress, Schenker introduces
                            <tei:rs type="work" key="entity-001728"><tei:title>Free
                                Composition</tei:title></tei:rs>, in which prolongations in their
                        most far-reaching expansion will be demonstrated and, in particular, the
                        role of the Urlinie will be presented in its proper perspective.</tei:ab>

                </tei:div>


            </tei:div>

        </tei:div>
    </sdo:record>



</sdo:recordCollection>
