<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../schema/local/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
    xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/"
    xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/local/schenker.xsd">

    <sdo:collectionDesc>
        <sdo:source>
            <sdo:other mfID="1306" sdoID="OJ-11-22_4">OJ 11/22, [4]</sdo:other>
        </sdo:source>
        <tei:handNotes>
            <tei:handNote xml:id="pr" scope="sole">printed</tei:handNote>
        </tei:handNotes>

        <tei:respStmt xml:id="IB">
            <tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName>
            <tei:resp>Transcription, 2007</tei:resp>
            <tei:resp>Translation, 2007</tei:resp>
            <tei:resp>XML Encoding, 2014</tei:resp>
        </tei:respStmt>


        <tei:respStmt xml:id="TL">
            <tei:persName>Tamara Lopez</tei:persName>
            <tei:resp>XML Encoding, Model 2010</tei:resp>
        </tei:respStmt>

    </sdo:collectionDesc>


    <sdo:record ID="r0001">
        <sdo:itemDesc>
            <dc:title>Press announcement by the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde in the Neue Freie
                Presse, dated September 15, 1912</dc:title>
            <dc:type>Announcement</dc:type>
            <dcterms:created>1912-09-15T12:00:00Z</dcterms:created>
            <dcterms:dateSubmitted/>

            <dc:description>Announces new series of popular lectures to be presented by the
                Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde.</dc:description>
            <dc:subject>zyklisch; cyclic; Vorträge; lectures; Bildung; education; populärer
                Charakter; popular character; Künstler; artists; Gelehrte; scholars; Schrift-
                steller; writers; Einzelvorträge; single lectures; Vortragsserien; lecture series;
                Aufführungen; performances, Illustrationen; illustrations</dc:subject>

            <marcrel:author key="entity-002430">Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde</marcrel:author>

        </sdo:itemDesc>

        <tei:div type="transcription">

            <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">The typography makes extensive use of spaced
                type (<tei:hi rend="italic">Sperrdruck</tei:hi>). That which is used for emphasis
                has been rendered here in bold type; that used consistently throughout for names of
                persons and the organization has been rendered here by normal type.</tei:note>
            <tei:lb/>
            <tei:lb/>

            <tei:ab rend="first">— Mit Beginn dieser Saison nehmen die von der Gesellschaft der
                Musikfreunde veranstalteten <tei:hi rend="bold">zyklischen Vorträge</tei:hi> ihren
                    Anfang.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn01" type="editorial" place="foot">Schenker
                    records his reaction to this announcement in his diary at OJ 1/11, p. 228,
                    September 15, 1912: "Die Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde kündigt die Namen der
                    Vortragenden an: Eine echt Wiener Lumpigkeit von Perfektionierung eines
                    Vertrages Namen für Geschäftszwecke zu mißbrauchen." ("The Society of the
                    Friends of Music announces the names of the lecturers. A typical Viennese shabby
                    trick, to misuse names for commercial purposes before finalizing the
                    contract."). The events announced here were to form part of the centenary
                    celebrations of the Society.</tei:note> Diese Unternehmungen verfolgen den
                Zweck, die musikalische Bildung den weitesten Schichten der Bevölkerung zugänglich
                zu machen, und werden zum größten Teil <tei:hi rend="bold">populären
                    Charakter</tei:hi> tragen. Eine große Menge von in- und ausländischen Künstlern,
                Gelehrten und Schriftstellern wird sich mit den verschiedenartigsten Themen in
                Einzelvorträgen oder Vortragsserien an diesen Unternehmungen beteiligen, die schon
                von Anfang Oktober ab im kleinen, in Ausnahmsfällen auch im großen Musikvereinssaale
                stattfinden werden.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn02" type="editorial" place="foot">No
                    paragraph-break in source.</tei:note></tei:ab>

            <tei:ab rend="first">— Für die Saison 1912/13 haben folgende Persönlichkeiten ihre
                Vorträge angemeldet: Geheimrat Dr. Max Friedländer (Berlin), Direktor August
                Göllerich (Linz), Dr. Hugo Leichtentritt (Berlin), Dr. Paul Marsop (München), Dr.
                Heinrich Rietsch (Prag), Dr. Leopold Schmidt (Berlin), ferner von Wiener Namen Dr.
                D. J. Bach, Doktor Johannes Brandt, Otto Erich Deutsch, Dr Max Dietz, Dr Max Graf,
                Richard Heuberger, Dr. Robert Konta, Dr. Eusebius Mandyczewski, Max Morold, Richard
                Robert, Dr. Heinrich Schenker,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn03" type="editorial"
                    place="foot">In OJ 5/14, [2], September 27, 1912, Schenker objected strongly to
                    the inclusion of his name here.</tei:note> Dr. Ferdinand Scherber und Richard
                    Specht.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn04" type="editorial" place="foot">No
                    paragraph-break in source: em-dash only.</tei:note></tei:ab>

            <tei:ab rend="first">— Nebst diesen Aufführungen, die fast ausschließlich durch
                musikalische Illustrationen eine besondere Belebung erfahren werden, sind in dem
                Rahmen der zyklischen Vorträge auch Volkskonzerte, populäre Liederabende,
                Kammermusikaufführungen und ähnliche, durchaus von erstklassigen Künstlern
                ausgeführt, mitinbegriffen; unter anderen auch der Vortragszyklus „Vom Hörenlernen“
                von Gisela Springer, der am 6. Oktober beginnt und sich über sechs
                Sonntagsnachmittage erstreckt. Wie im Vorjahre hat auch heuer zu diesem Zweck eine
                Reihe hervorragender Künstler sich zur Mitwirkung bereit erklärt.</tei:ab>

        </tei:div>

        <tei:div type="translation">

            <tei:note type="editorial" place="inline">The typography makes extensive use of spaced
                type (<tei:hi rend="italic">Sperrdruck</tei:hi>). That which is used for emphasis
                has been rendered here in bold type; that used consistently throughout for names of
                persons and the organization has been rendered here by normal type.</tei:note>
            <tei:lb/>
            <tei:lb/>

            <tei:ab rend="first">— With the beginning of this season, the <tei:hi rend="bold"
                    >lecture series</tei:hi> arranged by the Society of the Friends of Music will
                    commence.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn01" type="footnote"/> These undertakings
                have the aim of making musical education available to the furthest reaches of the
                population, and will for the most part be <tei:hi rend="bold">popular in
                    character</tei:hi>. A large number of native and foreign artists, scholars, and
                writers will participate in these undertakings on the widest possible range of
                topics in single lectures and lecture series, which from the beginning of October
                onward will take place in the small hall, in isolated cases even the large hall, of
                the Musikverein.<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn02" type="footnote"/></tei:ab>

            <tei:ab rend="first">— For the 1912/13 season, the following people have offered their
                lectures: Privy Councellor Dr. Max Friedländer (Berlin), Director August Göllerich
                (Linz), Dr. Hugo Leichtentritt (Berlin), Dr. Paul Marsop (Munich), Dr. Heinrich
                Rietsch (Prague), Dr. Leopold Schmidt (Berlin), and in addition from Vienna the
                names Dr. D. J. Bach, Doctor Johannes Brandt, Otto Erich Deutsch, Dr Max Dietz, Dr.
                Max Graf, Richard Heuberger, Dr. Robert Konta, Dr. Eusebius Mandyczewski, Max
                Morold, Richard Robert, Dr. Heinrich Schenker,<tei:ptr corresp="#r0001-fn03"
                    type="footnote"/> Dr. Ferdinand Scherber and Richard Specht.<tei:ptr
                    corresp="#r0001-fn04" type="footnote"/></tei:ab>

            <tei:ab rend="first">— In addition to these presentations, virtually all of which will
                be specially illustrated by live music examples, in connection with the lecture
                series there will also be interspersed popular concerts, popular evenings of song,
                chamber music performances and the like, performed by artists of the highest
                caliber; Among others, <tei:supplied reason="clarity">there will</tei:supplied> also
                    <tei:supplied reason="clarity">be</tei:supplied> the lecture series “On Learning
                to Hear,” by Gisela Springer, which begins on October 6 and will be spread over six
                Sunday afternoons. As in previous years, an array of prominent artists have this
                year again committed themselves to collaborate for these purposes.</tei:ab>

        </tei:div>
    </sdo:record>



</sdo:recordCollection>
