<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="brunauer_robert">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Robert Br&#xFC;nauer</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="brunauer_robert">Br&#xFC;nauer, Robert</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>13/11/2005</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Br&#xFC;nauer ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">brunauer_robert</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Robert Br&#xFC;nauer</head>
      <div>
        <p>Industrialist, chocolate manufacturer, possibly German; long-time pupil of Schenker's. </p>
        <p>Dr. Robert Br&#xFC;nauer owned and managed a chocolate manufacturing company. Nothing
          is known of him or his company.  From Schenker's diary, we know that c. 1907 he was married
          and lived in Heiligenstadt (OJ 1/6, p. 44), that he did not have to do military service in
          World War I, that his marriage had evidently broken up by 1919, when his wife and children
          were living in Berlin (OJ 2/14, p. 2051), that he re-married in September or October 1920
          (OJ 3/1, p. 2279), and that this wife left him in 1923 (OJ 3/4, p. 2512). We also know
          that his "family" were living in Tutzing, Germany, around 1914, though whether this was
          his first wife and childen or his own blood relatives is not clear. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Br&#xFC;nauer and Schenker</head>
        <p>Schenker first entered the Br&#xFC;nauer home on October 4, 1902; he became a regular
          visitor thereafter and often went to the theater and concerts with Br&#xFC;nauer,
          sometimes together with the latter's first wife. Br&#xFC;nauer had become a pupil by
          October 1906, when he embarked on study of the Beethoven Sonata Op. 109 with Schenker. He
          was still a regular pupil in the last surviving lessonbook, 1930/31, and the draft lesson
          notes for 1931/32 (OC 3/1-4; OC 16/19-24, 47). He thus belongs with <ref
            cRef="elias_angelika">Angelika Elias</ref> and <ref cRef="kahn_marianne">Marianne
          Kahn</ref> (who herself gave piano lessons to Br&#xFC;nauer's mother), who began
          lessons with Schenker in the mid-1900s and apparently continued until Schenker's death. He
          also belongs with <ref cRef="deutsch_sofie">Sofie Deutsch</ref>, who was taking lessons
          from c. 1902, and whose house he frequently visited along with Schenker. </p>
        <p>Br&#xFC;nauer was evidently generous to Heinrich and Jeanette, supplying them with
          candy (which, since Schenker was diabetic, they seem to have used for barter), and in 1918
          offered Schenker 5,000 Kronen to assist with the publishing costs of <ref
            cRef="kontrapunkt_2">
            <title level="m">Kontrapunkt 2</title>
          </ref> (which Schenker rejected because Elias had already offered more for the same
          purpose: OJ 2/10, pp. 896–97, 898, June 1, 1918). He was also involved that year in the
          abortive plan for a Festschrift to mark Schenker's 50th birthday. It was
          Br&#xFC;nauer, too, who suggested to Schenker that he sit for the artist <ref
            cRef="hammer_viktor">Viktor Hammer</ref> (OJ 2/10, pp. 900–01, June 11, 1918).
          Contrarily, he was often late in paying his fees, sometimes paying at the previous year's
          rate and having to be reprimanded. Thus Schenker had an ambivalent relationship with him.
          The two men had frequent conversations, and disagreed sharply on social and political
          issues. </p>
        <p>Judging from the repertory that he played (solo piano works, piano concertos, much
          Brahms), and from the length and detail of his lessonbook entries, Br&#xFC;nauer was a
          considerable pianist, and commanded Schenker's serious attention. The lessons, two per
          week, appear to have been purely pianistic, with no sign of theoretical studies, and
          little sign of analytical studies of orchestral or chamber works before 1929, after which
          Br&#xFC;nauer prepared analytical graphs. Moreover, there is evidence that Schenker
          himself prepared materials in advance for Br&#xFC;nauer, and that his lessons with the
          latter were fertile for Schenker's own analytical thinking (OC 38/73, filed among papers
          for <title level="m">Der freie Satz</title>, can be traced to lessons with
          Br&#xFC;nauer in 1929). </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>
        <p>From Schenker's diaries, it is clear that the two men corresponded a great deal; however,
          only three items survive, OC 52/636 (1925 – gathering information on sales of <title
            level="j">Der Tonwille</title>), 44/15, 16 (1934 – written from the Grand Hotel and the
          Hotel Imperial, both in Vienna); additionally, OC 52/638 is a receipt from Albert J.
          Gutmann for payment of his 1924 subscription to <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>. One
          undated letter from Br&#xFC;nauer to Otto Vrieslander survives as OJ 71/37, and a
          carbon copy (with corrections in Jeanette Schenker's hand) survives of an article by him
          entitled "Die Urlinie: Eine Entgegnung," which was apparently a reply to an article by
          Walter Riezler in <title level="j">Die Musik</title> for April 1930, as OJ 21/24. Works by
          Br&#xFC;nauer survive also as OC 41 (Waltz, Op.39/1) and OC 42 (arrangement of a
          keyboard piece by C. P. E. Bach, with Schenker's emendations).</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Ian Bent</author>, with <author>Marko Deisinger</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
