<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-000445">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Karl Klindworth</title>
        <title type="sub">born Hannover, Sept 25, 1830; died Stolpe, July 27, 1916</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="klindworth_karl">Klindworth, Karl</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/06/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">klindworth_karl</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Karl Klindworth</head>
      <div>
        <p>German pianist and conductor. </p>
        <p>Klindworth was a pupil of Franz Liszt, and his career as a concert artist extended from
          1848 to 1910. In 1868, he was appointed a piano professor at the Moscow Conservatory; in
          1884 he moved to Berlin, where he was for a time the conductor of the Berlin Philharmonic,
          and where he founded his own piano school, which in 1893 merged with the Scharwenka
          Institute to form the Konservatorium Klindworth-Scharwenka. He was an advocate of the
          "modern" musical trends of his time, notably the music of Berlioz, Wagner, Liszt, Brahms,
          and Bruckner. He wrote many instructional manuals for the piano.</p>
        <p>As a friend of Wagner, Klindworth created the vocal scores for the latter's music dramas
          from <title level="m">Rienzi</title> to <title level="m">Parsifal</title>. He also edited
          or arranged the keyboard works of numerous composers, including J. S. Bach's <title level="m">Well-Tempered Clavier</title> (Mainz: Schott, 1894), the complete works of
          Chopin and the piano sonatas of Beethoven (both Berlin: Bote &amp; Bock, no dates), and
          many of these editions remain in use today.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Klindworth and Schenker</head>
        <p>Schenker criticized Klindworth's editions for their failure to understand the composer's
          intentions, as for example in Chopin's in B-flat major, Op. 71, No. 2: "[Klindworth] does
          not grasp the genuine gist of the voice-leading [...] What arrogance he shows toward
          Chopin!" (<title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>, Heft 3 (1922), p. 25; Eng. trans., vol.
          I, p. 120). Of Beethoven's sonata Op. 109, for example, he included Klindworth's edition
          when commenting: "You will be <hi rend="italic">utterly astonished</hi> at the discrepancy
          between the editor and Beethoven in light of his original autograph manuscript." (letter
          to Emil Hertzka, WSLB 144, January 22, 1913).</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
