<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000866">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Karl Straube</title>
        <title type="sub">born Berlin, Jan 6, 1873; died Leipzig, April 27, 1950</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="straube_karl">Straube, Karl</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>15/03/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Straube ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">straube_karl</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Karl Straube</head>

      <div>
        <p>German organist, teacher, choral conductor, and interpreter of J. S. Bach and Handel.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>

        <p>In 1895, Straube became deputy organist at the new Kaiser-Wilhelm-Gedächtnis-Kirche in
          Berlin, then in 1897 cathedral organist in Wessel. In 1903 he was appointed conductor of
          the Leipzig Bachverein, in 1907 organ teacher at the Leipzig Conservatory, and in 1918
          Kantor of the Thomaskirche there (formerly J. S. Bach's position). He toured
          internationally with the Thomas choir. In 1919, he founded the department of church music
          (Kirchenmusikalische Institut der Evangelisch-Lutherischen Landeskirche Sachsen) of the
          Leipzig Conservatory. In 1920, he amalgamated the Bachverein and the Gewandhaus choirs,
          conducting them until 1933, and giving regular performances of Bach's music with the
          Thomanerchor and the Gewandhaus Orchestra.</p>

        <p>Although situated within the Romantic German interpretative tradition of <ref
            cRef="entity-000110">Hans von Bülow</ref>, Straube became a strong advocate of the
          performance of the music of Bach and Handel, showing an interest in approximating original
          forces.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>

        <p>Only one letter survives from Straube to Schenker (OC 54/218, May 14, 1930), written at
          the instigation of Straube's close friend, <ref cRef="entity-000268">Wilhelm
            Furtwängler</ref>. In 1921, Straube sounded Felix Hupka out on whether Schenker might be
          interested if an offer of a position in Leipzig were to come his way (<ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-1_4">OJ 14/1, [4]</ref>). </p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">MGG</title></bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">NGDM2</title></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>

  </text>
</TEI>
