<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000460">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Maria Komorn (<hi rend="italic">née</hi> Rebhan)</title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, January 13, 1883; died Riga?, after December 3, 1941</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="komorn_maria">Komorn, Maria</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">komorn_maria</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Maria Komorn (<hi rend="italic">née</hi> Rebhan)</head>
      <div>

        <p>Pianist, writer on music, pupil of Heinrich Schenker 1923‒25; previously pupil of <ref
            cRef="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</ref>.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Life Summary</head>
        <p>Maria Rebhan was born in Vienna on January 13, 1883, daughter of Samuel, bookkeeper with
          the textile firm of Ernst Mauthner. In 1908, Samuel Rebhan and Richard Komorn, who worked
          for the private banking house Brüder Feldmann, both moved into apartments in Vienna IX/2,
          Bleichergasse 15. The date at which Maria and Richard Komorn were married is unknown.
          Richard died on June 12, 1933 (his death notice described him as "accounts director,
          Phoenix Life Assurance Society). Maria had become the occupant of record at the
          Bleichergasse address already in 1929, and she remained at that address until 1938, after
          which she disappears from the Vienna street directory.</p>

        <p>She seems to have been well acquainted with <ref cRef="entity-000268">Wilhelm
          Furtwängler</ref> and his <ref cRef="entity-003001">wife</ref>, and occasionally acted
          as a go-between with Schenker. She held musical tea parties on the first day of every
          month. She gives her occupation as "pianist, writer on music." As a writer, she
          contributed articles to several papers and journals, and authored two books, one
          comprising reminiscences of Bruno Walter, and the other on Brahms as choral conductor in
          Vienna (copy in Schenker's private library at his death: Hinterberger).</p>

        <p>Maria ("Marie"), who is listed in Herbert Gerigk's infamous <title level="m">Lexikon der
            Juden in der Musik</title> (1940), was deported on the first transport from Vienna to
          Riga on December 3, 1941, her address at that time being Vienna IX, Berggasse 25/22. After
          an eight-day rail journey, she will have been placed in the recently emptied Riga ghetto;
          her death date is not known, but the likelihood is that she either was gassed in a gas van
          or shot, or possibly died from the conditions in the ghetto. (Unlike Maria, Richard's
          married sister, Ernestine Lowie, emigrated to the USA and lived in New York City, where
          she died in 1932, and her son, Robert Heinrich ("Harry") Lowie died on September 24, 1957
          in California.)</p>
      </div>


      <div>
        <head>Komorn and Schenker</head>
        <p>Komorn first asked Schenker to take her on as a piano pupil in April 1923 ‒ on grounds
          that she was suffering a "pianistic-technical crisis." She had previously been a pupil of
            <ref cRef="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</ref>, who warned Schenker that she was a "clingy,
          pathological being" (diary May 4, 1923), and who claimed to be at the same time both
          "offended" and "liberated" at Schenker's acceptance of her (September 25, 1923). Schenker
          insisted on regular lessons rather than the occasional basis that she requested (although
          she seems to have got the better of him on that).</p>

        <p>She studied with him throughout <ref type="lessonbooks" cRef="OC-3-3_1923/r0008"
            >1923/24</ref> and 1924/25, her repertory being mostly short pieces by Beethoven,
          Schubert, and Schumann. Although the lessonbook records no instruction in theory or source
          studies, she did attempt an analysis of one recitative from the <title level="m">St.
            Matthew Passion</title> at Furtwängler's request, in which she had, according to
          Schenker, "gone all astray" (diary, March 22, 1924) ‒ the 1923/24 lessonbook records:
            "<title level="m">St. Matthew Passion</title> — concerning chorale in general and the
          two great chorale fantasies in connection with Furtwängler; recitative as task." Schenker
          declined to teach her beyond summer 1925, whereafter she reiterated her gratitude for all
          that he had taught her and lauded his unique way of thinking about music. She continued to
          the end of his life to send him greetings at Christmas and New Year, and communicated by
          letter and telephone with Jeanette Schenker until May 10, 1938, when Jeanette had been
          trying to visit her.</p>
      </div>


      <div>
        <head>Correspondence</head>
        <p>Ten letters, postcards, and a calling card from Komorn to Heinrich Schenker survive over
          the period 1923 to 1934 (OJ 12/17, [1]‒[9], OC A/291) and two letters to Jeanette
          Schenker, 1935 and 1938 (OJ 12/17, [10]‒[11]). No written communications from Heinrich or
          Jeanette Schenker to Komorn are known to survive, nor are any between Komorn and
          Weisse.</p>
      </div>

    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Bibliography</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Was wir von Bruno Walter lernten: Erinnerungen eines ausübenden
              Mitgliedes der Wiener Singakademie</title> (Vienna: Universal Edition, 1913)</bibl>

          <bibl><title level="m">Johannes Brahms als Chordirigent in Wien und sein
              Nachfolger</title> (Vienna: Universal Edition, 1928)</bibl>

          <bibl><title level="a">Gustav Mahler und die Jugend,</title>
            <title level="j">Neues Wiener Journal</title> (August 31, 1930)</bibl>

          <bibl><title level="a">Die Jahrhundertfeier für Josef Joachim,</title>
            <title level="j">Neues Wiener Journal</title>, June 27, 1931 (OC File C/210)</bibl>

          <bibl><title level="a">Josef Joachim, ein Kirchenkonzert und ein Autogramm,</title>
            <title level="j">Neues Wiener Journal</title>, June 28, 1931 (OC File C/209)</bibl>

          <bibl><title level="a">Ein ungedruckter Brief Glucks,</title>
            <title level="j">Zeitschrift für Musik</title> 99 (1932), 672‒75</bibl>

          <bibl><title level="a">Minnie van Beethoven,</title>
            <title level="j">The Musical Quarterly</title> XVIII/4 (October 1, 1932), 628‒33</bibl>

          <bibl><title level="a">Brahms, Choral Conductor,</title>
            <title level="j">The Musical Quarterly</title> XIX/2 (April 1, 1933), 151‒57</bibl>

          <bibl><title level="a">Alte Musik in einem Palast des Lukas v. Hildebrandt,</title>
            <title level="j">Der Wiener Kunstwanderer</title>, May 1933 (OC 2/p. 87)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Adoph Lehmann's allgemeiner Wohnungs-Anzeiger [...] Wien u.
              Umgebung</title> (Vienna: Friedrich Förster, 1859‒1942)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Musik und Theater enthaltend die Bibliothek des Herrn Dr. Heinrich
              Schenker, Wien</title> (Vienna: Heinrich Hinterberger, n.d. [1936]), item 76</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="j">Neue freie Presse</title>, 24698 (June 17, 1933), p. 11 <note
              type="editorial" place="inline">death notice of Richard</note></bibl>
          <bibl><author>Weissweiler, Eva</author>, <title level="m">Ausgemerzt! Das Lexikon der
              Juden in der Musik und seine mörderischen Folgen</title> (Cologne: Dittrich-Verlag,
            1999), p. 256</bibl>
          <bibl><ref type="external"
            target="http://www.holocaustresearchproject.org/ghettos/riga.html">Holocaust Education and Archive Research Team: The Killings at
              Riga</ref></bibl>
          <bibl>Shoa zur Suche: "Komorn Marie"</bibl>
          <bibl>Communications from Dr. Robert Kosovsky</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
