<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000946">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Josef Weinberger</title>
        <title type="sub">born Lipto St Miklos, Moravia, May 6, 1855; died Vienna, November 8,
          1928</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="weinberger_josef">Weinberger, Josef</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">weinberger_josef</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Josef Weinberger</head>
      <div>

        <p>Leading Viennese music publisher; pioneer in publishing and performing rights.</p>
        <div>
          <head>Career Summary</head>
          <p>Josef Weinberger was the son of Samuel Weinberger, Jewish goldsmith. Josef was an
            accomplished pianist, and also a fine singer, much involved with local choral societies.
            He established a joint music-publishing company, Josef Weinberger &amp; Carl Hofbauer,
            in Vienna in 1885, then another joint with Carl Günther in Leipzig in 1889, but
            eventually set up his own company, <ref cRef="entity-006149">Josef Weinberger</ref>, on
            the Kohlmarkt in Vienna in 1890, rapidly becoming a leading publisher of choral and
            light theatrical music (including that of Johann Strauss II and for a time Wolf-Ferrari
            and Franz Léhar), as well as publisher of more serious music, notably of <ref
              cRef="entity-000556">Gustav Mahler</ref>.</p>

          <p>Josef Weinberger became an influential figure in the establishment of publishing and
            performing rights in Austria. In 1897, he was a founder-member of the Society for
            Authors, Composers and Music Publishers in Vienna [Gesellschaft der Autoren, Komponisten
            und Musikverleger in Wien (AKM)], of which he remained either chairman or honorary
            president for the rest of his life, and was instrumental in the recognition in Austria
            of the Berne Copyright Convention. He also established a pension and welfare fund for
            Austrian composers. He was awarded the rank of Imperial Counsellor [Kaiserlicher Rat] in
            1903, and in 1908 was invested with the order of the Prussian Eagle [Preußischer
            Adlerorden].</p>

          <p>Between 1896 and 1900, Weinberger discussed with <ref cRef="entity-000359">Bernhard
              Herzmansky</ref> (of Vienna publisher <ref cRef="entity-004002">Doblinger</ref>) and
              <ref cRef="entity-000720">Adolf Robitschek</ref>, the establishment of a new Austrian
            music publishing company to rival those of Peters Edition and Breitkopf &amp; Härtel in
            Germany. The new company, <ref cRef="entity-002408">Universal Edition</ref>, was
            launched in 1901 on the basis of producing new collected editions, and also music for
            educational purposes. This company very quickly became the leading publisher of modern
            music in Austria, and one of the most powerful and influential music publishers in the
            world, and was housed in Weinberger's new premises at Maximiliamstraße (now
            Mahlerstraße) 11. Weinberger continued to be involved with Universal Edition for some
            time, and his name appears as signatory to many UE letters.</p>

        </div>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Josef Weinberger and Schenker</head>
        <p>The two men were in contact between c. 1897 and 1905, exchanging correspondence and
          holding meetings. In all, twenty-six items of correspondence to Schenker survive with
          Weinberger as sole or joint signatory, or on his behalf (OJ 15/12, [1]‒[8], and [11], OC
          52/1‒2, 8, 11, 13, 15‒17, 19, 381, 386‒387, 391‒393, 442‒443) on either Weinberger or
          Universal Edition business:</p>

        <p><hi rend="bold">Weinberger business (9):</hi> three undated calling cards (OJ 15/12,
          [1]‒[3]) probably from the late 1890s; five letters with the Weinberger letterhead, OJ
          15/12, [5] from 1900, OJ 15/12, [6]‒[8] and [11] from 1903; one letter with the UE
          letterhead, OC 52/11 from 1903 (the latter six all concerning <title level="m">Syrian
            Dances</title>).</p>

        <p><hi rend="bold">Universal Edition business (17):</hi> one postcard (OJ 15/12, [4]),
          fifteen letters (OC 52/1, 2, 8, 13, 15, 16, 17, 19, 386, 387, 381, 391, 393, 442, and 443)
          and one handwritten note (OC 52/392) dating from 1901‒05. (The Universal Edition business
          concerned the commissioning of <ref cRef="entity-000724">Julius Röntgen</ref> as a J. S.
          Bach editor, Schenker's <ref cRef="entity-001720"><title>C. P. E. Bach Keyboard
              Works</title></ref> and <ref cRef="entity-001721"><title level="m">A Contribution to
              the Study of Ornamentation</title></ref>, <ref cRef="entity-001722"><title>Handel
              Organ Concertos</title></ref>, and rejection of his <ref cRef="entity-001724"><title
              level="m">Harmonielehre</title></ref>.)</p>

        <p>No correspondence from Schenker to Weinberger is known to survive.</p>
      </div>

    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>

        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Grove Music Online</title> (<title level="a">Weinberger,
              Josef</title>)</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Johann Michel</author> and <author>Richard Toeman</author>, <title level="m"
              >100 Jahre Bühen- und Musikalienverlag Josef Weinberger 1885‒1985</title> (Vienna:
            Weinberger, 1985)</bibl>

          <bibl><title level="m">100 Years Remembered: A History of the Theatre and Music Publishers
              Josef Weinberger Vienna, Frankfurt am Main, London, 1885‒1985</title> (London:
            Weinberger, [1985])</bibl>

          <bibl><title level="m">Heinrich Schenker: Selected Correspondence</title>, ed. <editor>Ian
              Bent</editor>, <editor>David Bretherton</editor>, and <editor>William Drabkin</editor>
            (Woodbridge: The Boydell Press, 2015), esp. pp. 34, 41, 43, 59‒60, 62</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Ian Bent</author></bibl>
          <lb/>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
