<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000381">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Franz von Hoesslin</title>
        <title type="sub">born Munich, December 31, 1885; died near Sète, September 25, 1946</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="hoesslin_franz_von">Hoesslin, Franz von</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>25/05/2006</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">HoesslinF ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">hoesslin_franz_von</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Franz von Hoesslin</head>

      <div>
        <p>German conductor, notably of the music of Richard Wagner.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>

        <p>Franz Hoesslin was the second child of Gustaf Adolf Balthasar von Hoeßlin, MD, and Maria
          Magdalena Auguste Rüdinger. After completing secondary school at the humanistic Royal
          Theresia Secondary School in Munich in 1904, Franz Hoesslin studied composition under Max
          Reger and orchestral conducting under Felix Mottl. His conducting career started in 1908,
          with positions as conductor of the Riga Symphony Orchestra and of the Danzig city theater,
          but was interrupted by the First World War, in which he served as an officer right to the
          end. After the war, he continued his career at the Bayreuth Festival as Ring Cycle
          interpreter in 1927, 1928, and 1940. In 1934, 1938 and 1939 he conducted <ref
            cRef="entity-002899"><title level="m">Parsifal</title></ref> there. He also directed
          concerts and operas in nearly all musical hubs in Germany, guest conducting the Berlin
          State Opera and the Berlin Philharmonic Orchestra several times. Starting in 1923, he was
          the musical director in the theater at the Royal Hippodrome in Dessau. From 1926 to 1932,
          he was the general musical director of the city of Wuppertal. In 1932 he transferred to
          Breslau, where he also taught at the Conservatory. His students include Günter Wand, Franz
          Pabel, and Heinz Schubert.</p>

        <p>Hoesslin's second wife, the Jewish mezzo-soprano Erna Liebenthal, was first prevented
          from performing in 1933 and the couple came under increasing pressure by National
          Socialist cultural politicians. In June of 1936, Hoesslin therefore had the orchestra play
          the <title>Horst Wessel Song</title> at a state event without his participation. He was
          immedately discharged and told to leave Breslau within twenty-eight days. As a farewell
          concert on June 26, 1936, he conducted Beethoven's <ref cRef="entity-001269"><title>Ninth
              Symphony</title></ref> to a packed house. That night, Hoesslin took his wife to
          Florence. Erna Hoesslin stayed in Italy until the end of the Second World War and was the
          only one of three siblings in her family to survive the holocaust. Hoesslin himself was
          supported by his friend Winifred Wagner, who invited him to conduct at the Bayreuth
          Festival several times. He also guest-conducted in European cities outside Germany, such
          as Amsterdam, London, Stockholm and The Hague.</p>

        <p>In September 1946, Hoesslin missed a flight from Barcelona to Geneva, where he was to
          conduct <title level="m">Così fan tutte</title> that evening. He then took a private
          airplane, which crashed into the sea near Sète, killing Hoesslin and his wife.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Bamberger and Schenker</head>

        <p>The two men seem first to have been in contact in 1913. Hoesslin, then in Riga, evidently
          inquired about the manuscript of Beethoven’s <ref cRef="entity-001269"><title>Ninth
              Symphony</title></ref>; Schenker replied on July 20 that he had not himself seen the
          manuscript. In November 1922, <ref cRef="entity-000034">Carl Bamberger</ref> persuaded
          Schenker to attend a concert conducted by Hoesslin, whom Schenker met for the first time
          after the concert in the dressing room. In November 1927, Hoesslin invited Schenker to
          attend a performance of Brahms’s <ref cRef="entity-001350"><title>First
            Symphony</title></ref> (Schenker seems not to have accepted), and the same work again in
          October 1928, which Schenker attended on November 8, with meetings before and after the
          concert, Schenker praising Hoesslin’s performance warmly in his diary in preference to
          that of <ref cRef="entity-000268">Furtwängler</ref>. The relationship seems always to have
          been cordial and respectful, despite Hoesslin’s strong ties to the music and family of
          Wagner.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence</head>

        <p>Two letters and one postcard survive from Hoesslin as OJ 11/55, [1]–[3], the first (1913)
          with the letterhead of conductor of the Riga Symphony Orchestra, the latter two (1927)
          with that of the General Music Director of Barmen and Elberfeld.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>

      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Hellmut Federhofer</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
              Tagebüchern …</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms Verlag, 1985), pp. 157–58</bibl>

          <bibl><title level="j">wikipedia</title> (German)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributors</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Marko Deisinger</hi></author> and <author><hi rend="bold"
                >Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

    </back>

  </text>
</TEI>
