<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000738">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Alfred Rothberger</title>
        <title type="sub">1873-1932</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="rothberger_alfred">Rothberger, Alfred</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>07/07/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Rothberger ~ H+JSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">Rothberger ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">Rothberger ~ JSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">rothberger_alfred</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Alfred Rothberger</head>
      <div>
        <p>Austrian tailor and businessman, also engraver of medals.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Alfred Rothberger was one of the four sons of the Viennese garment manufacturer Jakob
          Rothberger. After the death of his father in 1899, together with his brothers Moritz and
          Heinrich he took over the paternal firm. The "Rothberger Geschäftshäuser" [Rothberger
          houses of business] were located on the Stephansplatz at Nos. 1 and 9-11. Between 1917 and
          1926, Alfred and Hilda Rothberger lived at Vienna IV, Wohllebengasse 4 (close to the
          Schwarzenbergplatz), and before that at Vienna I, Augustinerstrasse 8.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Rothberger and Schenker</head>
        <p>Clearly, Alfred Rothberger, like his brother Moritz (who was also a professional
          sculptor), was artistically gifted, too, and became a designer and engraver of medals and
          plaques (<hi rend="italic">Medailleur</hi>). A bronze medallion (<hi rend="italic"
            >Medaille</hi>) of Schenker survives in several copies with Schenker's profile on one
          side and a depiction of "tonal space" surrounded by laurel leaves and an inscription on
          the obverse. A larger version of this as a one-sided plaque (<hi rend="italic"
            >Plakett</hi>) was also made, and a copy of this survives as OJ 73/2 (photographs as OJ
          72/14, No. 18). An announcement of the medallion was placed in the <title level="j">Neues
            Wiener Journal</title> for June 28, 1925: <cit>
            <q>(A Heinrich Schenker medal) The medal engraver Alfred Rothberger has made a portrait
              medal of the celebrated Viennese music theorist Heinrich Schenker, which, cast in
              bronze, will be issued in the form of a circular medallion and, greatly enlarged, as a
              plaque. On the reverse of the Schenker medal is rendered Schenker's beautifully
              expressed maxim: "Music is the living motion of tones in nature-given space." The
              finely executed bronze medal, which reproduces with great care the features of
              Schenker's profile, intellectually so animated, will surely be welcome to the numerous
              admirers and friends of the greatest music theorist of the present day.</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>The medal was created between January and April 1925. Schenker's portrait was based on a
          photograph taken at a studio on January 9, 1924 (OJ 3/6, p. 2618). Between March and May
          1925 there was a much correspondence between Schenker, Rothberger and recipients of the
          medallion. A diary entry (OJ 3/7, p. 2775, January 20) suggests that Schenker devised the
          quoted "maxim" specially for the medallion. Initially, twenty-five copies were made of the
          smaller medal, while the larger plaque, of which one copy was supplied that Jeanette hung
          on her bedroom wall, was available only to order. Schenker distributed copies to his close
          pupils and friends. The medal was also available at music stores for 100,000 Kronen (OJ
          3/7, p. 2823, May 27).</p>

        <p>Alfred Rothberger is also known to have created a plaque of the respected singing teacher
          Otto Iro (1890-1971) a medallion bearing the portrait of Gustav Mahler, and according the
          Schenker also "plaques not only of Eusebius Mandyczewski, but also d'Albert, Sarasate
          [and] Leschetizky" (diary OJ 3/9, p. 3001, November 14, 1926).</p>

        <p>Of him on the day of his death, Schenker recorded in his diary (OJ 4/5, p. 3732):
          "Whenever he came or wrote, he forever conveyed joy, out of sheer joy toward us and in
          himself. He deserves heartfelt thanks."</p>

        <p>The Rothbergers' son <ref cRef="entity-000740">Karl</ref> took lessons with Schenker
          beginning April 4, 1934.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>
        <p>No correspondence between Alfred Rothberger and Schenker is known to survive, but letters
          from his wife <ref cRef="entity-000739">Hilda Rothberger</ref> to Heinrich and Jeanette
          Schenker (enclosing letters from Karl Rothberger) survive as OJ 13/31 (1929-38: 30
          items).</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">schneidern und sammelm: Die Wiener Familie Rothberger</title>, eds
              <editor>Christina Gschiel</editor>, <editor>Ulrike Nimeth</editor>, <editor>Leonhard
              Weidinger</editor> (Vienna: Böhlau Verlag, 2010), esp. p. 55.</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Hann, Edith</author>, <title level="a">Herrenkleider-Magazin Jacob
              Rothberger,</title> in: <edition>Andreas Lehne</edition>, <title level="m">Wiener
              Warenhäuser 1865-1914</title>, with contributions by Gerhard Meißl and Hann, Edith
            (Forschungen und Beiträge zur Wiener Stadtgeschichte 20, Vienna, 1990), pp.
            85-122</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="j">Das Jahrbuch der Wiener Gesellschaft 1928</title>, ed.
              <editor>Franz Planer</editor> (Vienna 1928), p. 286</bibl>

          <bibl><title level="m">Rebell und Visionär: Heinrich Schenker in Wien</title>, ed.
              <editor>Evelyn Fink</editor> (Vienna: Verlag Lafite, 2003), p. [54] [reproduction of
            both sides]</bibl>

          <bibl><editor>Czeike, Felix</editor>, ed., <title level="m">Historisches Lexikon
              Wien</title>, vol. 4 (Vienna 1995), p. 704</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
              Tagebüchern und Briefen...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), p. 76</bibl>

        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Marko Deisinger</author> (additions by <author>Ian Bent</author> and
              <author>William Drabkin</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
