<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000798">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Arnold Schoenberg [Schönberg]</title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, Sept 13, 1874; died Los Angeles, July 13, 1951</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="schoenberg_arnold">Schoenberg, Arnold</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>26/10/2006</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Schoenberg ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">schoenberg_arnold</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Arnold Schoenberg [Schönberg]</head>
      <div>
        <p>Austrian composer, earliest representative of Viennese musical modernism, creator of the
          twelve-tone method of composition, teacher of Alban Berg, Anton von Webern, and other
          composers in Vienna, Berlin, and, from 1934 on, in the USA.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Relations between Schoenberg and Schenker</head>
        <p>Contact between Schenker and Schoenberg was made first by the latter on September 12,
          1903, after he had been engaged by Busoni to orchestrate Schenker's <title level="m"
            >Syrische Tänze für Pianoforte zu 4 Händen</title> (Vienna: Weinberger, c.1899). The
          orchestration was not to Schenker's taste because it "suggests the style of Richard
          Strauss," but he evidently approved it, for the resulting performance took place on
          November 5, 1903. Schoenberg subsequently tried between November 10, 1903 and early 1904
          to enlist Schenker's participation in forming the <ref cRef="entity-003012">Vereinigung
            schaffender Tonkünstler</ref> (Association of Creative Musicians). Communications
          between the two continued into 1907, when Schoenberg drew Schenker's attention to two
          concerts of his music (both of which Schenker attended and reported in his diary) and
          invited him to one of music by his pupils. The two evidently met several times, and were
          apparently on cordial terms until around 1910, when their relationship deteriorated.</p>
        <p>Although Schoenberg's musical style had its origins partly in Brahms and the Viennese
          Classical composers, Schenker became increasingly antagonistic toward him from around 1910
          because he saw him as advancing the stylistic innovations of Richard Strauss and Gustav
          Mahler, abandoning the Classical tonal tradition, and in the realm of theory espousing
          developing variation over repetition.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Breakdown of Cordialities</head>
        <p>The breakdown between the two men was perhaps impelled by <ref cRef="entity-000356">Emil
            Hertzka</ref>'s contracting Schoenberg for <ref cRef="entity-002408">Universal
            Edition</ref> in 1909 along with Mahler, Schreker, and Foerster; the issuing of UE's
          1910 catalogue announcing Schoenberg's Second <title>String Quartet</title> and <title
            level="m">Drei Klavierstücke</title>, Op. 11 may have been the catalyst for Schenker's
          antagonism. First private signs of this were Schenker's allusion to "a publisher that
          places its main emphasis these days on anti-musical music" in his letter to Hertzka of
          February 7, 1910, WSLB 52, which conveys Schenker's disillusionment with Hertzka's break
          from UE's original 1901 commitment to an Austrian edition of the "classics." His
          resentment at what he saw as Hertzka's promotion of Schoenberg's <title level="m"
            >Harmonielehre</title> over his own works emerges in WSLB 75, May 17, 1911, and three
          years later he suggests that UE should use its profits from Mahler's and Schoenberg's
          music to subsidize its publication of his own writings, OJ 5/16, [2], May 1914
          (draft).</p>
        <p>The first step in the <hi rend="italic">public</hi> confrontation between the two,
          Schoenberg's response to Schenker's diatribes against Strauss and Reger in <title
            level="m">Harmonielehre</title> (1906) and the Foreword to <title level="m">Kontrapunkt
            1</title> (1910), was delivered in his own <title level="m">Harmonielehre</title> (1911
          and lengthened in the 1921 edition). Schenker's most sustained, personalised critique, of
          the chordal treatment of passing-tones in Schoenberg's <title level="m"
            >Harmonielehre</title>, appeared in <title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der
            Musik</title>, vol. II (1926), pp. 30-37 (Eng. transl., vol. II, 12-16).</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Correspondence between Schoenberg and Schenker</head>
        <p>Correspondence between the two men comprises twelve personal letters from Schoenberg to
          Schenker, which survive only in photocopies in OJ 14/15 (see also OJ 60/2), plus one
          circular letter from Zemlinsky, Gutheil, and Schoenberg, and two invitations; none are
          known to have survived from Schenker to Schoenberg.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Bibliography: See especially:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Dahlhaus, Carl</author>, <title level="a">Schoenberg and Schenker,</title>
            <title level="j">Proceedings of the Royal Musical Association</title> 100 (1973/74),
            209-15; reprinted in <editor>Puffett, D.</editor> &amp; <editor>Clayton, A.</editor>,
            eds, <title level="m">Schoenberg and the New Music: Essays by Carl Dahlhaus</title>
            (Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1987), pp. 134-40</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Simms, Bryan R.</author>, <title level="a">New Documents in the
              Schoenberg-Schenker Polemic, </title>
            <title level="j">Perspectives of New Music</title> xvi/1 (1977), 110-24</bibl>
          <bibl><editor>Erwin, Charlotte E.</editor> &amp; <editor>Simms, Bryan R.</editor>, <title
              level="a">Schoenberg's Correspondence with Heinrich Schenker,</title>
            <title level="j">Journal of the Arnold Schoenberg Institute</title> v (1981), 23-43 </bibl>
          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="a">Heinrich Schenkers Verhältnis
              zu Arnold Schönberg,</title> in <title level="j">Mitteilungen der Kommission für
              Musikforschung</title>, No. 33 (1981), 369-90</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Eybl, Martin</author>, <title level="m">Die Befreiung des Augenblicks:
              Schönbergs Skandalkonzerte 1907 und 1908</title> (Vienna: Böhlau, 2004)</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Bent, Ian</author>, <title level="a">'That Bright New Light': Schenker,
              Universal Edition, and the Origins of the Erläuterung Series, 1901-1910,</title>
            <title level="j">Journal of the American Musicological Society</title> 58/1 (Spring
            2005), 69-138</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
