<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-003943">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Edith Guttmann (?née Schwartz)</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="guttmann_edith">Guttmann, Edith</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">guttmann_edith</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Edith Guttmann (?née Schwartz)</head>
      <div>

        <p>Wife of Heinrich Schenker's nephew, <ref cRef="entity-000316">Hans Guttmann</ref>, thus
          daughter-in-law of <ref cRef="entity-000319">Sophie</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-000318"
            >Salo</ref> Guttmann.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <p><ref cRef="entity-000316">Hans</ref> announced his engagement on April 2, 1929, and <ref
            cRef="entity-000319">Sophie</ref> sent first details of his fiancée to Heinrich and <ref
            cRef="entiy-000771">Jeanette</ref> the next day (the letter does not survive). The
          invitation to the wedding came on April 10, the wedding taking place in <ref
            cRef="entity-004271">Agram</ref> (= Zagreb, capital city of Croatia, then part of
          Yugoslavia) on May 27. Heinrich and <ref cRef="entiy-000771">Jeanette</ref> did not
          attend. Heinrich’s diary for January 13, 1931 refers to <ref cRef="entity-000316"
            >Hans</ref>’s “brother-in-law Dr. Schwartz,” leading to the supposition that Edith’s
          maiden name may be Schwartz.</p>

        <p><ref cRef="entity-000316">Hans</ref> and Edith visited Vienna on January 25, 1929 and the
          Schenkers met Edith briefly on the 26th as they were departing for <ref
            cRef="entity-002292">Galtür</ref>. In June 1930 <ref cRef="entity-000316">Hans</ref> and
          Edith booked a hotel in <ref cRef="entity-002292">Galtür</ref> for three weeks, during
          which they spent time with the Schenkers. Her pregnancy was announced in May 1932 and a
          girl was born on November 3 or 4.</p>

        <p>Adverse indications of Edith’s character appear in Heinrich’s diary for July 19, 1933:
            <ref cRef="entity-000319">Sophie</ref> “confirms Edith’s innate unchasteness; I
          [Heinrich] am more convinced than ever that her child is not her husband’s,” though
          already on November 17, 1930 his diary records <ref cRef="entity-000316">Hans</ref>
          writing that a cut in his wages made it difficult for him to “send Edith ‘to a metropolis
          for a couple of weeks’ – troubles are beginning to brew!” On January 6, 1938, <ref
            cRef="entity-000319">Sophie</ref> wrote to <ref cRef="entiy-000771">Jeanette</ref>: <cit>
            <q>where is [Hans] to get money, with a wife who puts on so many airs and graces (<hi
                rend="italic">solch’ pretensiös</hi>)? Just imagine: she was operated on for
              gallstones; soon after the major operation she traveled to Paris, she stayed in the
              finest hotel, etc.; from there, she traveled with a family that she knew to Vienna;
              he, the imbecile, went home alone. She stayed [with] us for three weeks, to make some
              purchases. Having got home, she went off to the coast, etc. It was a long story . . .
              So where is the silly fool to get money? It's a scandal! </q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>On November 24, 1938, <ref cRef="entity-000319">Sophie</ref> again wrote to <ref
            cRef="entiy-000771">Jeanette</ref>: “[Hans] has an extremely fashion-conscious (<hi
            rend="italic">sehr mondaine</hi>) wife who is very, very extravagant. He has a charming
          little girl of six, whom, alas, we do not know.”</p>

        <p>By 1939, <ref cRef="entity-000316">Hans</ref>, Edith, and their child (name unknown) were
          living in <ref cRef="entity-006012">Belgrade</ref> (capital city of Serbia, part of
          Yugoslavia). With the end of Heinrich’s diary in January 1935 and the tiny handful of
          communications with <ref cRef="entiy-000771">Jeanette</ref> in 1938 and 1939, all
          information about the Guttmann family ceases. In 1941 Belgrade was subjected to heavy
          bombing by the Lufwaffe, a puppet government was established and the city was declared
          “free of Jews.” Nothing is known of the family’s fate.</p>

        <p>There is no known correspondence between Edith and Heinrich or <ref cRef="entiy-000771"
            >Jeanette</ref>, and no photographs of the Guttmann family in OJ 72/18 include
          Edith.</p>
      </div>

    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>

  </text>
</TEI>
