<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000207">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Walter (Albert) Engelhardt</title>
        <title type="sub">born Hannover, 1894; died 1983</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="engelhardt_walter">Engelhardt, Walter</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">engelhardt_walter</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Walter (Albert) Engelhardt</head>
      <div>

        <p>German Evangelical Church vicar in the Rhineland, friend of <ref cRef="entity-000643"
            >Reinhardt Oppel</ref>.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Walter Albert Engelhardt was born in Hannover. After war service and a period of study,
          in 1925 he moved to the Rhineland. From 1929 to 1940, he served as the vicar (<hi
            rend="italic">Pfarrer</hi>) of Leisel (village about 80km (50 miles) west of <ref
            cRef="entity-002495">Frankfurt-am-Main</ref>), then Essen-Altenessen 1947–49, then as a
          hospital chaplain 1951–59. Engelhardt published extensively on music and liturgical
          history. He was also involved in reform of the Evangelical Church Hymnal. His papers are
          preserved in the Archive of the Evangelical Church in the Rhineland, Düsseldorf.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Engelhardt and Reinhardt Oppel</head>
        <p><ref cRef="entity-000643">Reinhardt Oppel</ref> once referred to Leisel as “a small
          Hunsrück eyrie” (<hi rend="italic">Hunsrücknest</hi>) – the area around Hunsrück being
          what <ref cRef="entity-000643">Oppel</ref> called his “ancestral land,” to which he
          regularly returned in vacations. Like Engelhardt, <ref cRef="entity-000643">Oppel</ref>
          was a protestant Christian; in his correspondence with Schenker in 1933 and 1934 <ref
            cRef="entity-000643">Oppel</ref> referred to Engelhardt as a “theologian” as well as a
          “friend.” <ref cRef="entity-000643">Oppel</ref> reports that Engelhardt was planning to
          edit a new edition of <ref cRef="entity-000814">Albert Schweitzer</ref>’s book <title
            level="m">J. S. Bach: Le Musicien-Poète</title> (Leipzig: Breitkopf &amp; Härtel, 1905),
          which <ref cRef="entity-000814">Schweitzer</ref> had rewritten in two volumes in German in
          1908. <ref cRef="entity-000643">Oppel</ref> advised Engelhardt against doing so on the
          grounds that <ref cRef="entity-000814">Schweitzer</ref> was “not sufficiently musical to
          deal thoroughly with Bach,” and the project was thus “entirely futile” (<ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-13-10_164">OJ 13/10, [164]</ref>). <ref
            cRef="entity-000643">Oppel</ref> gave Engelhardt instruction in Schenker’s theory, and
          when it was published Engelhardt was “very impressed by” <ref cRef="entity-000412"
            >Oswald Jonas</ref>’s book <title level="m">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks</title>
          (1934).</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Engelhardt and Schenker</head>
        <p>No correspondence between Engelhardt and Heinrich Schenker is known to have taken place,
          but on at least one occasion <ref cRef="entity-000643">Oppel</ref> forwarded a letter that
          he had received from Engelhardt. In his diary, Schenker called him a “music theologian.”
          Two letters from Engelhardt to <ref cRef="entity-000771">Jeanette Schenker</ref> are
          preserved as OJ 10/21, [1] and [2], from 1938 and 1939.</p>
      </div>

    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Source</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <ref type="external"
              target="https://archiv.ekir.de/inhalt/7nl-101-pfarrer-walter-engelhardt/"
                ><title>Archiv der Evangelischen Kirche im Rheinland: 7NL 101</title></ref></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
