<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000224">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Richard Figdor</title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, February 8, 1881</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="figdor_richard">Figdor, Richard</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>24/11/2007</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">figdor_richard</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Richard Figdor</head>
      <div>
        <p>Pupil of Heinrich Schenker's between May 1919 and May/June 1921.</p>

        <p>Richard Figdor was the son of Jakob Carl Figdor (died 1902) and <ref cRef="entity-000223"
            >Ernestine Mendl</ref> (1857–1925). Ernestine was the sister of <ref
            cRef="entity-000591">Heinrich Mendl</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-000590">Fritz
            Mendl</ref>, and also of the long-term Schenker pupil <ref cRef="entity-000165">Sofie
            Mendl (Deutsch)</ref>, of all of whom therefore Richard was a nephew.</p>

        <p>Between 1917 and at least late 1923, the Figdor family contested the will of <ref
            cRef="entity-000165">Sofie Deutsch</ref>, opposing the substantial bequests that the
          latter made to Schenker.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Richard Figdor and Schenker</head>

        <p>Schenker’s diary records that Richard first approached him for lessons on March 26, 1919,
          stating the next day that he had been a pupil of <ref cRef="entity-000802">Franz
            Schreker</ref>, and was currently taking piano lessons with <ref cRef="entity-006281"
            >Malvine Brée</ref>. Schenker records that he brushed Figdor off until the following
          season; however, on April 22, he instead accepted him as a pupil for the final two months
          of the 1918/19 season, lessons beginning on May 1, 1919, Wednesdays and Saturdays, Fidgor
          working on the Chopin Nocturne in F-sharp major, Op. 15, No. 2.</p>

        <p>For the 1919/20 season, Figdor took two lessons a week, on Mondays and Thursdays at 5.30
          to 6.30 p.m., studying piano repertory (J. S. Bach, Haydn, Mozart, Beethoven, Chopin),
          also strict counterpoint, and thoroughbass. In 1920/21, taking only one lesson a week, he
          played two Beethoven sonatas, but primarily made analyses of Brahms’s “Intermezzo in
          F-sharp minor” (perhaps F minor, Op. 118, No. 4 or C-sharp minor, Op. 117, No. 3, or the
          Capriccio in F-sharp minor, Op. 76, No. 1), the Beethoven Piano Sonata Op. 2, No. 1, and
          String Quartet Op. 59, No. 1. He withdrew at the end of the season.</p>

        <p>Judging from a remark in the 1920/21 lesson notes, and Schenker’s diary for February 9,
          1921, he was simultaneously a student in <ref cRef="entity-000003">Guido Adler</ref>’s
            <ref cRef="entity-007565">Musikhistoriches Seminar</ref>, in the University of
          Vienna.</p>

        <p>Schenker records writing a letter to Figdor on January 24, 1925 to New York.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence</head>
        <p>No correspondence is known to survive between Figdor and Schenker.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Ian Bent</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
