<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000165">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Sofie [Sophie] Deutsch (<hi rend="italic">née</hi> Mendl)</title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, June 22, 1858; died Vienna, January 5, 1917</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="deutsch_sofie">Deutsch, Sofie</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>12/12/2007</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">DeutschS ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">deutsch_sofie</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Sofie [Sophie] Deutsch (<hi rend="italic">née</hi> Mendl)</head>

      <div>
        <p>Wealthy Viennese-Jewish widow, pupil of Heinrich Schenker from c. 1902 to 1917.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Life summary</head>

        <p>Sofie Deutsch was the third daughter of Samuel Mendl (c. 1823–98) and Babette (<hi
            rend="italic">née</hi> Bettelheim) (c. 1826–1909). Her siblings were Anna Mendl (Fried)
          (1853–1931), <ref cRef="entity-000591">Heinrich Mendl</ref> (1855–1917), <ref
            cRef="entity-000223">Ernestine Mendl (Figdor)</ref> (1857–1925), Emma Mendl (1862–65),
          and <ref cRef="entity-000590">Fritz Mendl</ref> (1864–1925). Samuel Mendl was a dealer in
          agricultural produce; brothers Heinrich and Fritz were initially suppliers of alcoholic
          beverages, coffee, and tea, but in 1891 founded the Wiener Brot- u. Gebäck-Fabrik (Vienna
          bread and baked goods factory) with the brand name <ref cRef="entity-002420"
            >Ankerbrot</ref> (Anchor Bread), having numerous branches throughout Vienna.</p>

        <p>She married Heinrich Deutsch (1850–99), a dealer in silk, velvet, and woollen goods, Head
          of Heinrich Deutsch &amp; Comp. of Concordiaplatz 2 in Vienna’s First District, on
          September 18, 1881. The couple, who lived at Neuthorgasse 13 in central Vienna, had no
          children. At his death at the early age of 49, Heinrich's business was continued by his
          brother Simon, perhaps with involvement of Sofie herself. From 1903 to her death, Sofie
          lived at Albrechtsgasse 3, directly off the Opernring, almost opposite the Opera House –
          the apartment from which Schenker and others watched the funeral procession for Emperor
          Franz-Josef on December 30, 1916, as amply recorded in his diary (“At 2 p.m., the head of
          the cortege came in sight. We stood at the open window and the sun spread its glorious
          warmth over the powerful scene that now unfolded before our eyes. …”).</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Piano lessons</head>
        <p>Sofie Deutsch was a pupil of Schenker's apparently from c. 1902 until her death (when she
          is described by Schenker as having been "a pupil of 15 years' standing"), working mostly
          on solo piano repertory (Beethoven, Chopin, Brahms) and the keyboard parts of piano trios,
          quartets, and quintets, which she would play privately, and occasionally in public, with
          fellow musicians. While not being strictly a theory pupil of Schenker's, she nonetheless
          engaged in a great deal of formal analysis in and between lessons.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Patronage and personal acquaintance</head>
        <p>She was also one of Schenker's principal patrons. Schenker was frequently to be seen
          having meals with her in the coffee-house, and spending evenings at her home with a circle
          of guests in elevated conversation (meticulously, sometimes scornfully, recorded in
          Schenker's diary) or playing chamber music. Schenker was always trying to improve her
          character, lecturing her on matters of morality, commending improving reading to her. He
          once described her as "An eternally restless person, sinking into the dirt over and over
          again, a genuine Hedda Gabler character" (diary, November 2, 1908).</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>The Bequests</head>
        <p>In her will, she settled on Schenker an annual pension of 2,000 Kronen to be paid in
          half-yearly instalments (on the basis of which Schenker turned down an offer from <ref
            cRef="entity-002408">Universal Edition</ref> of 200 Kronen a month for the future <ref
            cRef="entity-001758"><title level="m">Kleine Bibliothek</title></ref>), and an outright
          legacy of 5,000 Kronen (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-12-52_1">OJ 12/52, [1]</ref>,
          January 12, 1917). Her benefaction was intended to make possible the publishing of
          Schenker's <ref cRef="entity-001727">
            <title level="m">Kontrapunkt 2</title>
          </ref>. She also left money to provide stipends for "impecunious skilled composers and
          similarly qualified composition pupils," of which Schenker was to be the sole life-long
          arbiter, awarding two stipends per year. This money constituted a quarter of a sum willed
          to a charity in which she was involved, the <ref cRef="entity-002425">Verein zur Speisung
            und Bekleidung hungernder Schulkinder in Wien</ref> (Association for the Feeding and
          Clothing of Hungry Schoolchildren in Vienna); after the Association was wound up in 1924,
          the stipends were transferred to the <ref cRef="entity-002591">Vienna Akademie
            (Hochschule) für Musik und Darstellende Kunst</ref> as the "Sophie Deutsch Music
          Stipend” on the basis that the <ref cRef="entity-002591">Akademie</ref> would present
          Schenker with a slate of three candidates per stipend on which he was to adjudicate; the
          transfer was hotly contested by Schenker, who preferred to allocate the stipends privately
          and on a secretive basis rather than publicly through an institution (<ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-24_1">OJ 5/24, [1]</ref> July 8, 1924). The <ref
            cRef="entity-002591">Akademie</ref> conceded his case, but ultimately Schenker placed
          the adjudication of the stipends entirely in the hands of the <ref cRef="entity-002591"
            >Akademie</ref> in time for the award on January 6, 1928, arguing that the value of the
          stipends had, through hyperinflation, become incommensurate with the calibre of intended
          composer (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-4_4">OJ 5/4, [4]</ref>, December 31,
          1927).</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Lesson Records and Correspondence</head>
        <p>Details of her lessons are recorded in Schenker's lessonbooks 1912/13-1916/17 (OC 3/1-3
          -- all now available on this site). Schenker's correspondence and encounters with her are
          extensively reported in the diaries from 1906 to her death. There is only one letter from
          her to Schenker (OJ 10/4, [1], January 26, 1916), in which she announces that she is
          settling on him 10,000 Marks in annual withdrawals of up to 3,000 Marks "for the purpose
          of publishing your future works," but there is much correspondence to and from Schenker
          with <ref cRef="entity-000590">Fritz Mendl</ref>, and attorneys <ref cRef="entity-000902"
            >Siegfried Türkel</ref> (OJ 14/40; OC 1 B/23, 36; 10/6; 16/27-28, 30-31, 33, 36-40,
          146), <ref cRef="entity-000502">Ernst Lamberg</ref> (OJ 5/24, 12/31), and <ref
            cRef="entity-000257">Hugo Friedmann</ref> (OC 1 B/19-20; 16/32).</p>

        <p>It was at her house that Schenker first met <ref cRef="entity-000164">Otto Erich
            Deutsch</ref>, who seems to have been unrelated to Sofie.</p>
      </div>
    </body>


    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
              Tagebüchern und Briefen ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), pp. 38, 97, et al </bibl>

          <bibl><editor>Eybl, Martin</editor> &amp; <editor>Fink-Mennel, Evelyn</editor>, eds.
              <title level="m">Schenker-Traditionen</title> (Vienna: Bohlau, 2006), p. 241</bibl>

          <bibl><ref type="external"
              target="https://www.geni.com/people/Sofie-Deutsch/6000000011471835103">"Sofie Deutsch
              (Mendl)"</ref></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>


  </text>
</TEI>
