<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-000695">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Max Reger</title>
        <title type="sub">born Brand, Bavaria, March 19, 1873; died Leipzig, May 11, 1916</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="reger_max">Reger, Max</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>27/10/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">reger_max</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Max Reger</head>
      <div>
        <p>German composer, organist and pianist, editor, and writer on music. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Reger was a composition pupil of Hugo Riemann from 1890 and later the latter's teaching
          assistant in Wiesbaden. After a period working at the Munich Conservatory, he was
          appointed music director and teacher of music theory with the title of Royal Saxon
          Professor at Leipzig University in 1907. Having been grounded in Riemann's theory books
          himself, his teaching of harmony there was based on Riemann's theory of harmonic function.
          In addition to teaching, he gave concert tours throughout Europe, and was conductor of the
          court orchestra at Meiningen (1911–13). </p>
        <p>Reger was a prodigious composer, in his day widely known, with a large output of
          orchestral, sacred choral, chamber, solo vocal, piano, and organ works (committed to
          "abstract" music, he wrote no stage works), all produced in the space of some twenty-six
          years. He also edited and arranged a broad range of music, notably much by J. S. Bach, and
          wrote one theoretical work: <title level="m">Beiträge zur Modulationslehre</title>
          (Leipzig: Kahnt, 1903). </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Reger and Schenker</head>
        <p>Reger was the frequent object of Schenker's criticism throughout much of the latter's
          life. Of the <title level="m">Beiträge zur Modulationslehre</title>, which was published
          at the time Schenker was formulating his own <title level="a">Das Tonsystem,</title> the
          precursor to his <title level="m">Harmonielehre</title>, Schenker wrote in his diary in
          1907: <cit>
            <q>a small work that nothing in the world can excuse: limited, sloppily done; foolishly
              complacent and childish: and yet nevertheless the author was appointed professor of
              theory at the Conservatory in Munich, and has even just now become music director at
              the University of Leipzig. (OJ 1/3, p. 8d = 1/4, p. 11b) </q>
          </cit></p>
        <p>But already before that, Schenker had had Reger in his sights. Reger is the first
          contemporary composer to be criticized in his <title level="m">Harmonielehre</title>
          (1906). Spanning seven pages is a footnote presenting in score an excerpt from Reger's
          String Quintet, Op. 64, with the annotation: <cit>
            <q> As a deterrent example, I give here the opening of the Quintet Op. 64 of a modern
              composer. This opening is by far the most supple passage in the first movement, what
              comes after that is many, many degrees more confused. But I ask: Do we really hear C
              minor, or is it not perhaps E-flat major? In particular, what do measures 6–8 signify,
              in themselves, and in the context of the whole? [. . .] One can only ask: What is this
              succession of scale-steps trying to say? Where is it coming from, where is it going
              to? [. . .] What is the solution to this problem? There isn't one. There isn't a
              passage in the work that informs us as to the principal key. [. . .] There is no logic
              to the keys, no logic to the apparent keys – just merely one big, singular, irrational
              on-going mass. And in German lands, people are seriously getting ready to celebrate
              this composer, devoid as he is of all musical instincts, as a "master of composition."
              – Just a few years after the death of Brahms – Oh what indolence on the part of the
              German public, what cowardliness on that of writers about music and the powers that be
              in the musical world! (pp. 220–226, omitted from English transl.)</q>
          </cit>
        </p>
        <p>In June 1911, writing about the poet Rainer Maria Rilke, Schenker remarked: <cit>
            <q>What comes to mind is, for example, Reger's insipid way of writing: with Reger, chord
              after chord, unmanifested (<hi rend="italic">unerwiesen</hi>) by any sort of motive,
              the chord progression in consequence operating only externally. What is unmanifested
              is constantly merely dumped at the first portals of our consciousness. Only that which
              is manifested is capable of penetratating into the depths. It is just the same with
              Rilke [. . .] (OJ 1/10, p. 134)</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>In similar vein, Schenker wrote in 1925 of the "lifelessness of a progresssion [in
          Reger's <title level="m">Beiträge</title>] dreamed up from an exercise-book and derived
          from unelaborated (<hi rend="italic">unauskomponiert</hi>) chords" (<title level="j">Meisterwerk</title>, vol. II, pp. 190–91, Eng. transl., p. 117). At Reger's death,
          Schenker wrote in his diary: <cit>
            <q>The obituaries of Reger declare almost unanimously that he was an inheritor of the
              legacy of Bach, Beethoven, and Brahms. If so, then Reger must have been three times
              richer than each of the other named masters individually – whereas in truth he was
              infinitely smaller, indeed never once came close to those masters. (OJ 2/2, p.
            246)</q>
          </cit>
        </p>
        <p>Schenker's most sustained attack on Reger's music came in <title level="j">Das
            Meisterwerk in der Musik</title>, vol. II (1925), in the essay <title level="a">A
            Counter-Example: Max Reger's Variations and Fugue on a Theme by Bach, Op. 81, for
          piano,</title> in which Schenker analyzes Bach's theme and each of Reger's fourteen
          variations and fugue in turn, concluding: <cit>
            <q>That a poor compositional technique like Reger's is not a true polyphony surely needs
              no further proof. And if Reger had written in a hundred more voices, his writing would
              never have become polyphonic, for that requires an organic treatment of the voices.
              Still less can his style claim to be complex, [. . .] for all complexity presupposes,
              at the least, coherence. (p. 192; Eng. transl., p. 117)</q>
          </cit>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">MGG</title>
          </bibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">NGDM</title>
          </bibl>
          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
              Tagebüchern und Briefen ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), pp. 246–7, 292</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</title>, vol. II (Munich: Drei Masken
            Verlag, 1925), p. 173–92; Eng. transl. by <editor>John Rothgeb</editor> (New York:
            Oxford University Press), pp. 106–17</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Ian Bent</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
