<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-000331">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Eduard Hanslick</title>
        <title type="sub">born Prague, Sept 11, 1825; died Baden nr. Vienna, Aug 6,
          1904</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="hanslick_eduard">Hanslick, Eduard</term>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt><sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc></fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">hanslick_eduard</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Eduard Hanslick</head>
      <div>
        <p>German music critic, aesthetician, and musicologist. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Hanslick studied piano in Prague with Václav Tomášek, and law first at Prague University
          and then in 1846 at Vienna University, gaining the doctorate of law in 1849. He began
          writing music criticism in the 1840s, contributing at first to the <title level="j">Wiener
            Musikzeitung</title>, the <title level="j">Sonntagblätter</title>, and the <title level="j">Wiener Zeitung</title>. In 1854, he published his celebrated aesthetic
          treatise <title level="m">Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</title>, and in 1855 he began writing
          reviews for the <title level="j">Presse</title>, which became the <title level="j">Neue
            Freie Presse</title> in 1864, Vienna's leading liberal daily newspaper, as the chief
          music critic of which until his death in 1904 he came to exert enormous influence not only
          over Viennese musical life but also in Germany and internationally. He taught music
          appreciation at Vienna University, rising in status over the years to full professor in
          music history and aesthetics in 1870. In 1862, he became friends with Brahms and a member
          of the Brahms circle. In the then current Brahms–Wagner controversy, he took Brahms's
          side, polemicizing against Wagner's music and music drama as well as the views expressed
          in his writings. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Hanslick and Schenker</head>
        <p> During the 1890s, Hanslick and Schenker corresponded and met, Schenker consulting him in
          1894 on a plan to write a "History of Melody," in which Hanslick expressed an interest. It
          is perhaps significant that when Schenker came to write a tribute in <title level="j">Die
            Zeit</title> to Hanslick on the latter's 70th birthday in 1895, he recited the facts of
          Hanslick's career but avoided any expression of opinion, instead quoting extensively from
          Hermann Helmholtz. In a letter of 1933, Schenker reminisced that "With [Moriz] Violin, I
          played selections from [my <title level="m">Syrian Dances</title>] for old Hanslick, both
          in the Bösendorfer Salon and in many private houses." In a letter to Eberhard Baron von
          Waechter in 1918, he praised Waechter's own writing, contrasting it as "a world away from
          Hanslick, Kretzschmar, Bekker – x, y, z, etc.." (OJ 5/43, [1]), an association which is
          striking because the latter two figures excited great animosity on the part of Schenker.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Correspondence</head>
        <p>Three letters, one postcard, and one calling card, from Hanslick to Schenker, dating from
          the period 1894–99, survive as OJ 11/39, typed transcripts of these by Oswald Jonas
          surviving as OJ 59/7. One calling card from Hanslick to Eduard Bacher at the <title level="j">Neue Freie Presse</title>, recommending Schenker, survives as OJ 71/14. In his
          private library, Schenker had many of Hanslick's books. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Bibliography:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Vom Musikalisch-Schönen: Ein Beitrag zur Revision der Ästhetik der Tonkunst</title>
            (Leipzig: Weigel, 1854, 2/1858, 3/1865, 4/1874, 5/1876, 6/1881, 7/1885, 8/1891, 9/1896,
            10/1902, 11/1910, 12/1918, 13-15/1922; Fr. trans. 1877, Ital. trans. 1884, Eng. trans.
            1891, Russ. trans. undated)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Geschichte des Concertwesens in Wien</title> (Vienna: Braumüller,
            1896–70)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Aus dem Concertsaal: Kritiken und Schilderungen aus den letzten 20
              Jahren des Wiener Musiklebens, 1848–1868</title> (Frankfurt, 1872)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Die moderne Oper</title>, in 9 parts (Berlin: Hofmann, 1875, 1880,
            1884, 1888, 1889, 1892, 1896, 1899, 1900)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Virtuosen der letzten 15 Jahren, 1870–1885</title> (Berlin: AVdL,
            1886)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Aus meinem Leben</title> (Berlin: AVdL, 1894)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Wer ist Musik?</title> (Berlin: Paetel, 1895)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">NGDM</title>
          </bibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">MGG</title>
          </bibl>
          <bibl>
            <editor>Federhofer, Hellmut</editor>, ed., <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker als
              Essayist und Kritiker </title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1990), pp. 280-81 </bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Musik und Theater enthaltend die Bibliothek des Herrn Dr. Heinrich
              Schenker, Wien</title> (Antiquariat Heinrich Hinterberger, [1936])</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Ian Bent</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
