<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-000961">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Karl von Wiener (Hofrat)</title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, Oct 26, 1891; died Vienna, April 12, 1942</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="wiener_dr_karl_von">Wiener, Karl von</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>08/04/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Conservatory ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">Wiener ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">wiener_dr_karl_von</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Karl von Wiener (Hofrat)</head>
      <div>
        <p>Music administrator, first President of the Vienna Conservatory of Music (Akademie
          für Musik und darstellende Kunst), 1909-19, with whom Schenker had a number of
          dealings.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>From 1872 on, the Conservatory -- founded as a private institution by the Gesellschaft
          der Musikfreunde in 1812 -- became increasingly dependent on state funding; moreover, in
          1896 the Conservatory introduced a teachers' training course (<hi rend="italic">Lehrerbildungskurs</hi>) the faculty for which required state accreditation. The
          oversight that the Austrian Ministry of Education established over the Conservatory as a
          result led in 1901 to the addition of one of the Ministry's officials to the Board of
          Directors of the Gesellschaft: that official was Dr. Karl von Wiener. When in 1907 a
          special committee oversaw the conversion of the Conservatory to a state institution, von
          Wiener played a central role in its work; then, at the granting of the new status on
          January 1, 1909, von Wiener became the first President of the now newly-named Akademie
          für Musik und darstellende Kunst. <ref cRef="entity-000089">Wilhelm Bopp</ref> had
          been appointed Director in 1907, with the brief to steer the Conservatory through the
          transition, and was then appointed Director of the Akademie from January 1, 1909.</p>
        <p>Von Wiener resigned on March 17, 1919 in face of demands from the faculty for the
          abolition of the post of President and reforms to the institution. (Bopp was voted out by
          the faculty on March 27.) In 1930-32, as functionary of the Ministry of Education, von
          Wiener served as the chairman of a commission to review the double status of the
          institution since 1925 as Musikakademie (under its Director) and Hochschule für Musik
          und darstellende Kunst (under a Rector); in 1931, von Wiener was appointed over the two
          bodies as Government Commissioner (Regierungskommissär), with Franz Schmidt as head
          of the faculty. Von Wiener retired in 1932.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Von Wiener and Schenker</head>
        
        <p>The prospect of Schenker's being appointed to a professorship in music theory at the
          Conservatory is first hinted at in a postcard from Schenker's pupil Ludwig Karpath, of
          February 9, 1908 (OJ 12/9, [1]): <cit>
            <q>Have just come from Wiener. Have tried to reach you in vain by telephone. Must talk
              to you and Floriz [Moriz Violin] <hi rend="italic">urgently</hi>. Konzertverein [?].
                <hi rend="italic">Say nothing</hi>! <hi rend="italic">Not to anybody</hi>!!
              Greetings, Karpath</q>
          </cit></p>
        <p>Next day Schenker records (OJ 1/7, p. 74): <cit>
            <q>Mr. Karpath alerts me in a postcard open for all to see to the beginning of
              negotiations within the Ministry concerning the post of professor.</q>
          </cit></p>
        <p>The following day he reports in comic-dramatic fashion (ibid): <cit>
            <q>At Karpath's place with Floriz. Chandelier comes crashing down, all the globes dashed
              to smithereens -- by the laws of superstition, a most auspicious portent. Meaning: I
              must now go and see Court Counsellor Wiener myself.</q>
          </cit></p>
        <p>This "difficult interview" took place on February 15, 1908. When Von Wiener objected that
          Schenker's approach to theory might lead students "to acquire a taste for anarchy,"
          Schenker countered that the "unities of [music's] higher laws" were easier to grasp than
          the "faulty rules" currently taught (OJ 1/7, p. 78 February 15, 1908). No further action
          on this is recorded (other than a non-extant letter from Schenker to von Wiener dated
          August 27 accompanying a complimentary copy of the second edition of his <title level="m">Beitrag zur Ornamentik</title> (cf. WSLB 18)), but a remark by Schenker to the
          publisher J. G. Cotta on December 2, 1909 suggests that the matter had not rested there
          (OJ 5/6, [4] = CA 106-107): <cit>
            <q>I might possibly be in a position, even for the first half-volume [of <title level="m">Kontrapunkt 1</title> (1910)], to put in front of my name the title of a
              Royal-Imperial Professor of Composition and Theory at the Vienna Highschool (Academy).
              There is a possibility that I may be selected for this leading post, with all the
              attendant advantages in honor and remuneration, to open up my theories unfettered to
              the Academy, and such like.</q>
          </cit></p>
        <p>Conflict between Schenker and von Wiener arose in June 1911, when Schenker was summoned
          to a meeting over prospective editions of Bach and Beethoven and refused to attend,
          instead posting notices in the newspapers announcing of a series of lectures in which he
          would deliver a critique of "the way in which [music] education is conducted today."  (OJ
          1/10, pp. 131r-131a).</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>
        <p>One draft letter from Schenker to von Wiener dated October 30, 1915 survives (OJ 5/4,
          [1]), responding to a now non-extant letter from von Wiener of October 21, 1915 concerning
          the devolvement upon the Akademie of stipends bequeathed in the will of <ref cRef="entity-000165">Sofie Deutsch</ref> after Schenker's death. (Five letters from
          Wilhelm Bopp from 1910-11 also survive (OJ 9/18).)</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">OeML Online</title></bibl>
          <bibl><author>Tittel, Ernst</author>, <title level="m">Die Wiener Musikhochschule</title>
            (Vienna: Elizabeth Lafite, 1967)</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Bent, Ian</author>, <title level="a">'That Bright New Light': Schenker,
              Universal Edition, and the Origins of the Erläuterung Series, 1901-1910,</title>
            <title level="m">Journal of the American Musicological Society</title> 58/1 (Spring
            2005), 69-138</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
