<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000107">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Robert (Albrecht) Brünauer, Dr.</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="brunauer_robert">Brünauer, Robert</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>13/11/2005</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Brünauer ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">brunauer_robert</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Robert (Albrecht) Brünauer, Dr.</head>

      <div>
        <p>Industrialist, chocolate manufacturer; long-time pupil of Schenker's. </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Business Career</head>

        <p>The Brünauer chocolate company, Jacques Brünauer &amp; Co, traded under the name
          "Chocolaterie Française." Its factory was located in the 18th district (Währing) of
          Vienna, at Währinger Gürtel 15. The company is recorded in Lehmann's Vienna directory at
          that address from 1903 to 1933. From 1903 to 1915 its proprietors were Jacques and Camilla
          (Kamilla) Brünauer – presumably Robert's parents – Robert being a signatory (<hi
            rend="italic">Prokurist</hi>). In 1916, Jacques and Robert were cited as the managing
          partners, from 1917 Camilla and Robert, and by 1933 Robert alone. </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <p>From Schenker's diary, we know that around 1907 Robert Brünauer was married and living in
          Heiligenstadt (OJ 1/6, p. 44), that he did not have to do military service in World War I,
          that his marriage had evidently broken up by 1919, when his wife and children were living
          in Berlin (OJ 2/14, p. 2051), that he re-married in September or October 1920 (OJ 3/1, p.
          2279), and that this wife left him in 1923 (OJ 3/4, p. 2512). We know also that in 1925 he
          had a daughter, Ulrike (OJ 3/7, p. 2810. His "family" was living in Tutzing, Germany
          around 1914, though whether this was his first wife and childen or his own blood relatives
          is not clear. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Brünauer and Schenker</head>
        <p>Schenker first entered the Brünauer home on October 4, 1902; he became a regular visitor
          thereafter and often went to the theater and concerts with Robert, sometimes together with
          the Robert's first wife. Brünauer had become a pupil by October 1906, when he embarked on
          study of the Beethoven Sonata Op. 109 with Schenker. He was still a regular pupil in the
          last surviving lessonbook, 1930/31, and the draft lesson notes for 1931/32 (OC 3/1-4; OC
          16/19-24, 47) include materials relating to his lessons as late as May 23, 1932. He thus
          belongs with <ref cRef="entity-000201">Angi Elias</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-000416"
            >Marianne Kahn</ref> (who herself gave piano lessons to Brünauer's mother), who began
          lessons with Schenker in the mid-1900s and apparently continued until Schenker's death. He
          can also be likened to <ref cRef="entity-000165">Sofie Deutsch</ref>, who was taking
          lessons from c. 1902, and whose house he frequently visited along with Schenker. </p>

        <p>Brünauer was evidently generous to Heinrich and Jeanette, supplying them with candy
          (which, since Schenker was diabetic, they seem to have used for barter), and in 1918
          offered Schenker 5,000 Kronen to assist with the publishing costs of <ref
            cRef="entity-001727">
            <title level="m">Kontrapunkt 2</title>
          </ref> (which Schenker rejected because Elias had already offered more for the same
          purpose: OJ 2/10, pp. 896–897, 898, June 1, 1918). He was also involved that year in the
          abortive plan for a Festschrift to mark Schenker's 50th birthday. It was Brünauer, too,
          who suggested to Schenker that he sit for the artist <ref cRef="entity-000327">Viktor
            Hammer</ref> (OJ 2/10, pp. 900–901, June 11, 1918). Contrarily, he was often late in
          paying his fees, sometimes paying at the previous year's rate and having to be
          reprimanded. Thus Schenker had an ambivalent relationship with him. The two men had
          frequent conversations, and disagreed sharply on social and political issues. </p>

        <p>Judging from the repertory that he played (solo piano works, piano concertos, much
          Brahms), and from the length and detail of his lessonbook entries, Brünauer was a
          considerable pianist and commanded Schenker's serious attention. The lessons, two per
          week, appear to have been purely pianistic, with no sign of theoretical studies, and
          little sign of analytical studies of orchestral or chamber works before 1929. After this
          time, however, Brünauer began preparing analytical graphs; moreover, there is evidence
          that Schenker himself prepared materials in advance for Brünauer, and that his lessons
          with the latter were fertile for Schenker's own analytical thinking (OC 38/73, filed among
          papers for <title level="m">Der freie Satz</title>, can be traced to lessons with Brünauer
          in 1929). </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>"Die Urlinie: Eine Entgegnung"</head>

        <p>In 1930 Walter Riezler, a young friend of Furtwängler, wrote an article expressing
          skepticism about the recent course of Schenker's theoretical work. This was published as
            <title level="a">Über die 'Urlinie',</title>
          <title level="j">Die Musik</title> xxii/7 (April 1930), 502–10 (clipping preserved as OC
          2/p. 80, [5]). As Schenker was unwilling to reply himself, Furtwängler suggested that Hans
          Weisse write a response; however, in the meantime Brünauer volunteered, his response was
          discussed in his lessons of April 10, 17, and 24, and Schenker approved it. A nine-page
          carbon copy of the typescript text, with pencil corrections and Jeanette Schenker's
          inscription "Riezler–Brünauer," is preserved as OJ 21/24. The typescript was probably sent
          by Weisse to Furtwängler, for the latter to submit to <title level="j">Die Musik</title>;
          but the response never appeared in print.</p>

        <p>In it, Brünauer distinguishes crucially between the "theorist" (Riezler) and the
          "practical artist" (Schenker). Riezler, who thinks in terms merely of motives and labeled
          harmonies, lacks the capacity to understand Schenker's visionary concepts of Urlinie and
          Ursatz, hence is unable to detect "the breath of diminution, which speeds the composition
          through the tonal space that it has itself created, speeding it in such away that the
          entire outpouring of a masterwork rushes past like a single outburst." </p>

      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>
        <p>From Schenker's diaries, it is clear that the two men corresponded a great deal; however,
          only three items survive, OC 52/636 (1925 – gathering information on sales of <title
            level="j">Der Tonwille</title>), 44/15, 16 (1934 – written from the Grand Hotel and the
          Hotel Imperial, both in Vienna); additionally, OC 52/638 is a receipt from Albert J.
          Gutmann for payment of his 1924 subscription to <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>. One
          undated letter from Brünauer to Otto Vrieslander survives as OJ 71/37. Compositions by
          Brünauer survive as OC 41 (Waltz, Op.39/1) and OC 42 (arrangement of a keyboard piece by
          C. P. E. Bach, with Schenker's emendations).</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Ian Bent</author>, with <author>Marko Deisinger</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
