<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-004931">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Richard Benz</title>
        <title type="sub">born Reichenbach im Vogtland, June 12, 1884; died Heidelberg, November 9,
          1966</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="benz_richard">Benz, Richard</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">benz_richard</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Richard Benz</head>
      <div>

        <p>German cultural historian and writer; Schenker's source for a bogus statement by
          Mozart.</p>

        <div>
          <head>Career Summary</head>
          <p>Richard Benz was the son of a Lutheran pastor ministering in Dresden. From 1902 Richard
            studied successively in Heidelberg, Leipzig, and Munich, receiving his PhD from
            Heidelberg University in 1907 with a dissertation on <title level="m">Fairy-tale Poetry
              of the Romantic Era</title>. From 1910 to the end of his life he worked in Heidelberg
            as a independent scholar. His principal interests lay in the fields of medieval folk
            literature, German culture, and the cultural history of the city of Heidelberg. </p>

          <p> He had a long-standing interest also in the place of music in German culture,
            believing that music was the highest expression of the German spirit. His writings on
            music include: <listBibl>

              <bibl><title level="m">Die Stunde der deutschen Musik</title> (Jena: Diederichs,
                1923‒27, 2/1930) [a copy of which was in Schenker's library at his death]</bibl>
              <bibl><title level="m">Das Ethos der Musik</title> (Offenbach: Gerstung, 1926)</bibl>
              <bibl><title level="m">Franz Schubert, der Vollender der deutschen Musik</title>
                (Jena: Diederichs, 1928)</bibl>
              <bibl><title level="m">Die Stunde des Wiederklanges</title> (Jena: Eugen Diederichs,
                1934)</bibl>
              <bibl><title level="m">Bachs Passion ‒ Die Nordische Tragödie</title> (Leipzig:
                Reclam, 1935)</bibl>
              <bibl><title level="m">Bachs geistiges Reich</title> (Munich: Beck, 1935)</bibl>
              <bibl><title level="m">Die deutsche Romantik</title> (Leipzig: Reclam, 1937)</bibl>
              <bibl><title level="m">Goethe und Beethoven</title> (Stuttgart: Reclam, 1942)</bibl>
            </listBibl>
          </p>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>Benz and Schenker</head>
          <p>There are many references to Benz in Schenker's diary between 1924 and 1933. Like
            Schenker he was an independent scholar who distanced himself from academia; and as a
            deeply conservative thinker believing that music had been in decline since Schubert and
            that music in the 20th century had forfeited the right to exist he must have seemed to
            Schenker someone with whom he had an affinity. Benz's article "Das Spiel des Dämons,"
              <title level="j">Deutsche Allgemeine Zeitung</title>, January 25, 1931 (preserved as
            OC 50/20) was the source of an alleged statement by Mozart (from a letter to Baron von
            Swieten included in the Schiedermair edition of Mozart letters in 1914 but shown to have
            been a forgery) that he heard a piece of music initially in a single instant. Benz
            writes: <cit>

              <q>Mozart war sich über den bildhaft-plastischen Charakter seiner Gestaltungen
                vollkommen klar und hat die räumlich-visuelle Konzeption seiner Musik als den
                gleichen Eindruck beschrieben, der uns im vollendeten Werke zuteil wird: „Das
                erhitzt mir nun die Seele, da wird es immer größer; und ich breite es immer weiter
                und heller aus; und das Ding wird im Kopfe wahrlich <hi rend="italic">mit einem
                  Blick</hi>, gleichsam wie ein schönes Bild oder einen hübschen Menschen im Geist
                übersehe, und es auch gar nicht <hi rend="italic">nacheinander</hi>, wie es hernach
                kommen muß in der Einbildung höre, sondern wie <hi rend="italic">gleich alles
                  zusammen</hi>.“<lb/> Mozart was completely clear about the graphic-physical
                character of his imageries, and has described his spatial-visual conception of his
                music as making the same impression as is conveyed to us in the finished work: "My
                spirit is enthralled, as it gets ever bigger; and I apply it ever wider and
                brighter; and the thing appears in my head truly <hi rend="italic">in an
                  instant</hi>, as if I see in my mind at a glance a beautiful picture or an
                attractive person, and I hear it in my imagination not at all <hi rend="italic"
                  >successively</hi>, as is bound to occur afterward, but <hi rend="italic">as if
                  all together</hi>."</q>
            </cit>
          </p>

          <p>So taken was Schenker with this statement ‒ "a divine passage from a letter by Mozart"
            ‒ that he created a calling card with an excerpt, had it printed by <ref
              cRef="entity-005007">Jahoda &amp; Siegel</ref>, and distributed it to pupils and
            others. He also wrote an article about the letter: <bibl><title level="a">Ein
                verschollener Brief von Mozart und das Geheimnis seines Schaffens,</title>
              <title level="j">Der Kunstwart</title> 44 (July 1931), pp. 660–66</bibl>, copies of
            which are preserved as OJ 20/10 and OC 50/12, a draft in Jeanette's hand with Heinrich's
            emendations at OC 16/8‒24, 26, and a response to it at OC 2/p. 84.</p>

          <p>Four other articles by Benz are preserved as OC 49/14 and 15, and OC C/1 and 2.</p>

          <p>In 1924, <ref cRef="entity-000164">Otto Erich Deutsch</ref> proposed asking Benz to
            give a series of lectures (diary February 1, 1924), to which Schenker replied: "if need
            be, the only format welcome to me would be a conversation at the piano in a private
            house, with well-meaning persons participating, directly or almost directly associated
            with me."</p>
        </div>


      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Die Musik in Geschichte und Gegenwart</title> (1949 - Karl Laux) </bibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Wikipedia</title> (consulted Sep 27, 2018) </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributors</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author><hi rend="bold">Marko Deisinger</hi></author> and <author><hi rend="bold">Ian
                Bent</hi></author><lb/>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
