<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-000357">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Jella [Yella] Hertzka (née Fuchs) </title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, Feb 4, 1873; died Vienna, Nov 13, 1948</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="hertzka_jella">Hertzka, Jella</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">hertzka_jella</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Jella [Yella] Hertzka (née Fuchs) </head>
      <div>
        <p>Horticulturist, important figure in the women's movement in Austria, wife of <ref cRef="entity-000356">Emil Hertzka</ref>. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p> Jella Hertzka trained at the horticultural school in Bad Godesberg (Rhineland), and in
          1913 founded the first two-year horticultural school for young women in the 19th district
          (Döbling) of Vienna, and directed it until 1938, in which year she emigrated. In 1903, she
          co-founded the New Viennese Women's Club (Neuer Wiener Frauenklub: Vienna I, Tuchlauben
          11), of which she was President 1909–33. She served the National Council of Women Austria
          (Bund Oesterreichischer Frauenvereine) on the commissions for agriculture and for
          horticulture and small animal breeding, and was President of the Austrian branch of the
          Women's International League for Peace and Freedom (Internationale Frauenliga für Frieden
          und Freiheit) from 1921 to its disbanding in 1938. After the war, she was active in the
          repatriation of prisoners of war. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Jella Hertzka and Schenker</head>
        <p>Jella Hertzka was the wife of Emil Hertzka (married 1897), Director of Universal Edition
          Vienna 1907–32, with whom Heinrich Schenker had almost daily dealings throughout that
          time. At her husband's death in 1932, she became a member of the Board of Trustees of the
          publishing house, involving herself in the encouragement of young musical talent; and
          after her return in 1946, she was engaged in the re-establishment of the company, from
          1947 was its public administrator. </p>
        <p>There is no known correspondence between Schenker and Jella Hertzka. He mentions her once
          in a letter of July 9, 1923 (OJ 6/7, [5]), at which time he felt great animosity toward
          Emil Hertzka. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Source:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Österreichisches Biographisches Lexikon</title> (online edition)
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Ian Bent</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
