<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-003019">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Anton [von] Webern</title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, Dec 3, 1883; died Mittersill, Sept 15, 1945</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="webern_anton">Webern, Anton (von)</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">webern_anton</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Anton [von] Webern</head>
      <div>

        <p>Viennese-born composer, pupil of <ref cRef="entity-000798">Schoenberg</ref>, and a
          principal member of the so-called Second Viennese School. </p>

      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career summary</head>
        <p>Webern studied harmony, counterpoint and musicology at the University of Vienna from 1902
          to 1906. Between 1904 and 1908 he also studied composition with Arnold Schoenberg, and by
          the end of his studies Webern had produced the pair of compositions that became his
          published Op. 1 and Op. 2 – the <title level="m">Passacaglia</title> for orchestra and a
          short choral canon. Both these works were accomplished demonstrations of the kind of
          extended tonality that Schoenberg himself was moving beyond in 1908, and in various sets
          of songs, like his Opp. 3 and 4 (1908-09), Webern – remaining personally close to
          Schoenberg – soon showed what was in some respects an even more radical approach to form
          and texture, abandoning all but the more rarefied allusions to traditional harmony and
          thematic process. The kind of brooding intensity to be found in such early post-tonal
          instrumental miniatures as the <title level="m">Sechs Bagatellen</title> for string
          quartet (1911, 1913) and the <title level="m">Drei kleine Stücke</title> for cello and
          piano (1913) is continued into the more serene but no less concentrated expressive world
          of Webern’s twelve-tone compositions, culminating in the Variations for Orchestra, Op. 30
          (1940), and the two Cantatas, Op. 29 (1938-39) and Op. 31 (1941-43). </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Webern and Schenker</head>

        <p>No direct contact or correspondence between Webern and Schenker is known to have
          occurred, nor do we know whether Schenker ever heard any of Webern's music. No doubt
          Webern was implicitly included in Schenker's frequent jibes at atonal composers (e.g.
          "about the atonalists: the impotent should not be allowed to call themselves unfeminine":
          diary OJ 3/6, p. 2615, January 3, 1924). </p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Arnold Whittall</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
