<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000401">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Henrik Ibsen</title>
        <title type="sub">born Skien, Grenland, March 20, 1828; died Kristiani [Oslo], Mary 23,
          1906</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="ibsen_henrik">Ibsen, Henrik</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">ibsen_henrik</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Henrik Ibsen</head>
      <div>

        <p>Norwegian playwright and poet, one of the founders of modernism in European theater.</p>

        <div>
          <head>Ibsen and Schenker</head>
          <p>Schenker had a wide-ranging interest in the world of literature and drama, for which
            his diaries served as the vehicle ‒ notably his comments on Shakespeare, especially on
              <title level="m">King Lear</title> and <title level="m">Hamlet</title>, but also on
            Goethe and Schiller, and also on poetry and drama in general. </p>

          <p>It is perhaps paradoxical, since he was so antagonistic toward all forms of modernism
            in music throughout his career, that Schenker harbored a special interest in the works
            of the modernist dramatists Henrik Ibsen, <ref cRef="entity-003409">Gerhard
              Hauptmann</ref>, and <ref cRef="entity-000797">Artur Schnitzler</ref> (Federhofer
            suggests that in this he was influenced by his literary-minded friend <ref
              cRef="entity-000542">Ferdinand Löwe</ref>), and also <ref cRef="entity-000824">George
              Bernard Shaw</ref>.</p>

          <p>Schenker attended several of Ibsen's plays when they were produced in Vienna, as well
            as reading them privately. On most such occasions, he wrote short, considered essays in
            literary style in his diary. The first of these occurs on November 24, 1898 and
            discusses Ibsen's <title level="m">An Enemy of the People</title>: <cit>
              <q>Excellent first and foremost is his projection of incident, thus of the poetic
                problem, directly into the close relationships that exist among the people of a
                small bathing resort, who, because fewer in number, are so much more on public view
                to one another. Ibsen avoids letting his hero shine as always entirely in the right
                vis-à-vis his fellow citizens. Instead he shows him to be unable to find a practical
                solution to this eminently practical question. An idealist by nature! In this lies
                the antithesis to the older dramatic technique.</q>
            </cit></p>

          <p>In 1919, Hans Weisse asked Schenker's opinion of Ibsen, and Schenker's reply is
            recorded in his diary for August 26: <cit>
              <q>I portray him as a master of his trade who always executes his works the way he
                intended, which is the trademark of a master. With regard to the choice of material,
                there is a noticeable difference vis-à-vis classic German authors: what the latter
                quickly discard because it may appear superfluous, what they handle in at most a few
                sentences or lines of verse containing the solution to the question, is in Ibsen
                officially the material of the drama. In most cases, the fault – he illustrates and
                teaches – lies in an at first seemingly unimportant event of which no one takes
                notice, like a minor point in a <hi rend="italic">curriculum vitae</hi>, and it is
                apparently his opinion, that no improvement in fate can be expected until people pay
                attention to their paths at such moments as well. To conjure up an image from the
                New Testament: thus shall the last moment be the first, as one has the chance to see
                in retrospect, unfortunately too late for those affected. Our masters, on the
                contrary, have placed individual fate on a broad horizon, allowing outwardly more
                significant events to play a role as levers, etc.</q>
            </cit></p>

          <p>Schenker attended performances of the following plays (most or all at the Theater an
            der Wien), and noted his attendance or wrote substantive essays in his diaries: <listBibl>
              <bibl><title level="m">The Wild Duck</title> May 22, 1906 (OJ 1/5, p. 13)</bibl>
              <bibl><title level="m">Hedda Gabler</title> October 31, 1906 (OJ 1/5, p. 23)</bibl>
              <bibl><title level="m">Rosmersholm</title> October 31, 1906 (OJ 1/5, p. 24)</bibl>
              <bibl><title level="m">The Lady from the Sea</title> February 1[?], 1910 (OJ 1/9, p.
                110).</bibl>
            </listBibl>
          </p>

          <p>There are also several other more general commentaries on Ibsen's work: (undated) 1899
            (three pages), September 23, October 18, December 6 and December 30, 1912, November 7,
            1913, and October 18, 1916. Excerpts from several of these are printed in German in
            Federhofer (1985), pp. 277‒80.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Wikipedia</title> ("Ibsen, Henrik") </bibl>

          <bibl>Federhofer, Hellmut, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern ...</title>
            (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), pp. 10, 277‒80 </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
