<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000399">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Felix Hupka</title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, June 21, 1896; died Amsterdam, Aug 11, 1966</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="hupka_felix">Hupka, Felix</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>21/06/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Hupka ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">hupka_felix</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Felix Hupka</head>

      <div>
        <p>Austrian conductor, pianist, teacher; pupil of Schenker's.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>The son of Hungarian-Jewish concert pianist Sigmund Hupka and grandson of the
          composer-performer Ignaz Brüll (on his mother's side), Felix Hupka studied piano, harmony,
          and counterpoint with Leon Erdstein 1905-11, then piano with Eugen d'Albert (1911-12),
          before moving to Schenker in October 1912. By then, he had already begun appearing as a
          concert pianist in 1910, at the age of 15.</p>

        <p>Hupka was active as an opera conductor from 1922 in Frankfurt, Berlin, and Cologne, and
          then in Paris 1930-33. In 1939 he emigrated to Holland, where after the war he was active
          as a teacher at the Amsterdam Sweelinck-Konservatorium, among his pupils being Bernard
          Haitink. (Felix Hupka was the uncle of the celebrated photographer and recording engineer
          Robert Hupka.)</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Hupka and Schenker</head>

        <p>Hupka was proposed to Schenker as a prospective pupil by Eugen d’Albert in early May
          1912. He visited Schenker on May 11, and was formally accepted in June. He was a pupil of
          Schenker's from October 2 of that year to the 1921/22 season. Schenker, who often called
          him "the little Hupka” (d’Albert had called him an “elf” (“Kobold”)), took evident delight
          in his youthful enthusiasm (so much so that Hans Weisse showed signs of jealousy), and was
          sympathetic to the fact that he was poor. In addition to working on piano repertory and
          interpretation, Hupka underwent a year's study of harmony, at least one year of
          counterpoint, and also use of instruments, and form.</p>

        <p>Hupka's sister, <ref cRef="entity-000422">Frau Kaposy</ref>, was also a pupil of
          Schenker's.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>
        <p>Much correspondence between Hupka and Schenker is recorded in Schenker's diary; only two
          items are known to survive from Hupka to Schenker (misfiled with the correspondence from
          Felix Salzer to Schenker in OJ 14/1). </p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><editor>Fink, Evelyn</editor>, ed., <title level="m">Rebell und Visionär: Heinrich
              Schenker in Wien</title> (Vienna: Lafite, 2003)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="a">Felix Hupka,</title> in <title level="m">Schenker-Traditionen: Eine
              Wiener Schule der Musiktheorie und ihre internationale Verbreitung</title>, ed.
              <editor>M. Eybl</editor> &amp; <editor>E. Fink-Mennel</editor> (Vienna: Böhlau, 2006),
            pp. 242-43</bibl>
          <bibl>Private communication from Robert Kosovsky (July 9, 2008)</bibl>
          <bibl>Private communication from Hedi Siegel (August 10, 2009)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>

  </text>
</TEI>
