<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000090">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Bösendorfer, Ludwig</title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, April 10, 1835; died Vienna, May 9, 1919</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="bosendorfer_ludwig">Bösendorfer, Ludwig</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>24/11/2007</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Bösendorfer ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">bosendorfer_ludwig</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>

      <head>Bösendorfer, Ludwig</head>

      <div>
        <p>Austrian piano manufacturer. </p>

        <p>Ludwig Bösendorfer trained at the Vienna Polytechnic Institute, then worked at his father
          Ignaz's piano manufacturing firm (<ref cRef="entity-002421">Bösendorfer</ref>), taking
          over the company in 1859 and directing it until selling it to Carl Hutterstrasser in 1909.
          It was Ludwig who brought the company's pianos to the peak of their international fame,
          patenting an improved action, and retaining the artisan system of manufacture, resisting
          mass-production methods. </p>

        <p>Ludwig was a familiar, distinctive, top-hatted figure in Viennese society, and a patron
          of the city's musical life. He was made an honorary member of the <ref
            cRef="entity-002430">Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde</ref> in 1870, and a member of its
          governing body from 1878. He was a member of the committee of the Wiener Tonkünstler
          Verein at its inception in 1879, and later an honorary member. The Bösendorfer Piano
          Competition, which he initiated in 1889, continued annually until 1944, and since 1949
          takes place every other year. </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Bösendorfer and Schenker</head>

        <p>During the academic year 1888/89, Ludwig Bösendorfer paid half of Schenker's fees at the
          Vienna Conservatory. At about the same time, on the recommendation of Schenker's teacher
            <ref cRef="entity-000545">Ernst Ludwig</ref>, he made a Bösendorfer piano available to
          him for his studies; the earliest known letter in Schenker's hand dates from 1889/90, is
          addressed to Ludwig Bösendorfer, and asks for its replacement by a superior instrument
          (GdM Briefe, [1]; Federhofer, 6). (By the 1910s and 1920s, Schenker had a Blüthner grand
          in his music room.)</p>

        <p>In his diary for March 10, 1914, Schenker offers an amusing portrayal of Ludwig: <cit>
            <q>On the way back [from the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde Archive], encountered Mr.
              Bösendorfer. The conversation with him gave rise to quite curious, amusing moments.
              So, for example, the elderly gentleman, merely because two days earlier he had read my
              name in <title level="j">Die Zeit</title> in connection with Beethoven, wanted to
              impress upon me that he had mastered the entire secondary literature and possessed the
              most important books in his library "even if he doesn't read them." And in order to
              reinforce in me his familiarity with the secondary literature, this characteristically
              Viennese upright gentleman gave his opinion: Was it not true that the last things
              written about Beethoven were those by Ambros and Helm? Now that's what I call a point
              of view, and knowledge of Beethoven! -- Nevertheless, I seized the favorable
              opportunity that presented itself to recount to him the affair of Lafite and Marchet
              [with whom Schenker had had a recent disagreement], whereupon with genuine Viennese
              falsehood he opined: "Marchet surely knows nothing of all this; the blame lies with
              Lafite and Habida.</q>
          </cit></p>
      </div>

    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">NGDM1</title> and <title level="m">2</title></bibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">OeML Online</title>
          </bibl>
          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
              Tagebüchern und Briefen ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985)</bibl>

        </listBibl>
      </div>

    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
