<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000878">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Paula Szalit [Paulina Szalitówna]</title>
        <title type="sub">born Lemberg [L'viv] 1886 or 1887; died 1920</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="szalit_paula">Szalit, Paula</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">szalit_paula</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Paula Szalit [Paulina Szalitówna]</head>

      <div>
        <p>Polish pianist and composer, pupil of Schenker's for a short period 1896‒97.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Paula Szalit was born in Lemberg and studied at the Lemberg Conservatory and then in
          Vienna with Robert Fischof, Josef Hofmann, Heinrich Schenker, <ref cRef="entity-000150"
            >Eugen d'Albert</ref>, and <ref cRef="entity-000523">Theodor Leschetizky</ref>. She was
          celebrated as a child prodigy. Harold Schonberg writes of her: <cit>
            <q>The one with the greatest promise as a youngster was Paula Szalit, whom Artur
              Schnabel believed to have been the greatest child wonder in history. She came to
              Leschetizky at thirteen, and her fellow pupil Arthur Shattuck flatly said that even at
              that age she was "the sublimest recreative talent of her time." But Szalit went back
              to her native Poland and little was heard of her.</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>As a composer she wrote short character pieces for piano. She died in 1920, at the age of
          about 34.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Szalit and Schenker</head>
        <p>Schenker reviewed what was probably her public debut in Vienna on February 14, 1896 ‒ at
          which time Szalit was being taught by Robert Fischhof ‒ beginning his remarks with: <cit>
            <q>On February 14 a nine-year-old child, Paula Szalit, demonstrated her wondrous talent.
              The little girl performed so astoundingly that ‒ to put it directly‒ she surpassed the
              audience's expectations. The best of her qualities, which inhabit the wonderful depths
              of her instinct, did not permeate into the public's awareness, and this reiterated (at
              this, the little girl's first public foray) the well-known fact that the contact of
              the audience with a significant talent ceases at precisely the point at which that
              talent reveals its best and most subtle features. The most conspicuous qualities of
              her playing gave them pleasure: its splendid rhythm and its elegantly developed finger
              dexterity; but the way in which her refined feeling for mood, melody and harmony took
              effect passed them by. They overlooked her utterly subtle pedal technique, which she
              has in common, quite simply, with the most mature of mature virtuosos. This pedal
              technique is for her not a jolly pumping of the foot, but enables her, in a way that
              for most pianists is still a highly secret art, to realize her feeling for melody and
              harmony. [...]</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>He went on to compare her improvisation favorably with that of the 14-year-old prodigy
          violinist <ref cRef="entity-000393">Bronislav Hubermann</ref>.</p>

        <p>On April 5 of that year, <ref cRef="entity-000150">Eugen d'Albert</ref>, who was
          expecting to teach her in the near future, wrote to Schenker (OJ 9/6, [12]), saying: <cit>
            <q>I wholeheartedly concur with the idea that she should study with you for the time
              being, for you are a serious musician and will point the young lady in the right
              direction. [...] I should very much like to know as soon as possible whether the young
              lady is definitely coming to me, and if so when. [...] So would you take over the
              continuation of the young lady's study on my behalf in the intervening period?</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>Schenker's 1897 diary (date unstated) records: "Paula Szalit prepared for concerts: among
          other things, J. S. Bach's Fugues in C-sharp minor (for 5 voices) and E-flat minor." A
          review (in which these works are not mentioned, so probably of a different concert) from
          November 28, 1897 begins: <cit>
            <q>Paula Szalit, still very young, possesses a freely headlong-rushing, crackling
              technique that exhibits great temperament and a touch of genius. Dr. Heinrich Schenker
              introduced her to music with his unique thoroughness and instructional power, and her
              nature is now tamed in Leschetizky's appropriately named masterclass. (<title
                level="j">Wiener Abendpost</title>: OC 2/p. 20)</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>On September 2, 1906, Schenker recorded in his diary: "Paula Szalit teacher in Lemberg" ‒
          that's the last of the 'wonderchild'?!"</p>

        <p>On November 13, 1918, Schenker recorded in his diary: "<ref cRef="entity-000655">Mrs.
            Pairamall</ref> passes on to me a letter from Miss Szalit, in which the latter requests
          a conversation with me, pressurized as she is by her very difficult predicament"; and two
          day's later: "To Miss Szalit (letter): I recommend patience: indefatigability when giving
          lessons is a tried and proven recipe."</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence</head>
        <p>One letter of 1918 from Szalit to Schenker survives, with two undated calling cards (OJ
          14/37, [1]‒[3]). A full-length portrait of her by the photographer "Zaklad Michala
          Friedmana, Nowy Sacz" and inscribed "Paul Szalit, 15.7.95" survives in Schenker's papers
          as OJ 72/22, No. 1.</p>
      </div>

    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
              Tagebüchern ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), p. 60</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker als
              Essayist und Kritiker ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1990), pp. 321‒22 [complete
            review of February 14, 1896 concert, in <title level="j">Die Zeit</title>, February 22,
            1896]</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Schonberg, Harold</author>, <title level="m">The Great Pianists</title> (New
            York, Simon &amp; Schuster, 1963), p. 353</bibl>

          <bibl><title level="m">Heinrich Schenker: Selected Correspondence</title>, ed. <editor>Ian
              Bent</editor>, <editor>David Bretherton</editor> and <editor>William Drabkin</editor>
            (Woodbridge: The Boydell Press, 2014), pp. 4‒5 [complete letter of April 5, 1906 from
            d'Albert to Schenker]</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
