<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000149">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Walter Dahms [Gualterio Armando]</title>
        <title type="sub">born Berlin, June 9, 1887; died Lisbon, Oct, 5, 1973</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="dahms_walter">Dahms, Walter</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>16/12/2005</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Dahms ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">dahms_walter</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Walter Dahms [Gualterio Armando]</head>
      <div>
        <p>German music critic, writer on music, and composer.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>
          <figure>
            <head>Walter Dahms (Cristina Teixeira Coelho)</head>
            <graphic url="Dahms_W-book.jpg" xmt:type="thumb-caption" rend="left-img" width="150px"
              height="113px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <graphic url="Dahms_W-book.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img" width="800px"
              height="600px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <figDesc>Photograph of Walter Dahms.</figDesc>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <p>Dahms studied literature, philosophy and fine arts at Berlin University, and composition
          with, among others, Max Reger and Ferruccio Busoni. While in Berlin, he was a professional
          violinist in theaters, a conductor, and also music critic of the <title level="j">Kleines
            Journal</title> (1912) and the <title level="j">Neue Preussische Kreuz-Zeitung</title>,
          and wrote for, among other publications, the <title level="j">Ostdeutsche
            Rundschau</title>, the <title level="j">Allgemeine Musik-Zeitung</title>, the <title
            level="j">Münchner neueste Nachrichtungen</title>, at least between 1913 and 1928; in
          1926, he launched and edited the periodical <title level="j">Musikus-Almanach</title>,
          which survived only one issue.</p>
        <p>The books that Dahms published during Schenker's lifetime, all of which were in
          Schenker's private library at his death, are:</p>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Schubert</title> (Berlin &amp; Leipzig: Schuster &amp; Loeffler,
            1912) </bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Schumann</title> (Berlin &amp; Leipzig: Schuster &amp; Loeffler,
            1916)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Mendelssohn</title> (Berlin &amp; Leipzig: Schuster &amp; Loeffler,
            1919)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Die Offenbarung der Musik: Eine Apotheose Friedrich
              Nietzsches</title> (Munich: Musarion, 1922)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Musik des Südens</title> (Stuttgart &amp; Berlin: Deutsche
            Verlags-Anstalt, 1923)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Johann Sebastian Bach</title> (Munich: Musarion, 1924)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Chopin</title> (Munich: Otto Halbreiter, 1924)</bibl>
        </listBibl>

      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Private life and change of identity</head>
        <p>
          <figure>
            <head>Walter &amp; Margarete Dahms (OJ 10/1, [91])</head>
            <graphic url="OJ-10-1_91-Dahms.jpg" xmt:type="thumb-caption" rend="left-img"
              width="150px" height="113px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <graphic url="OJ-10-1_91-Dahms.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img" width="800px"
              height="600px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <figDesc>Photograph of Walter and Margarete Dahms.</figDesc>
          </figure>
        </p>
        <p>Dahms married Agnes Matulke in 1910, and lived in Berlin. Some years later he separated
          from her, and lived with Margarete Ohmann. Between October 1921 and August 1926 the two of
          them lived in Italy, and in 1927‒28 Nice ‒ according to Dahms pursued by the German police
          and judiciary (OJ 10/1, [90] and [95]). A letter of November 1928 states that he had
          appealed to the Minister of Justice and the President of the Weimar Republic and had been
          turned down (OJ 10/1, [103]). Not until 1929 did Walter obtain a divorce from Agnes. In
          February 1931 he wrote that his marital affairs had finally been settled, and continued
          with bitterness: "The wonderful Germans have, after the crime of justice they committed
          against me, made me wait eighteen years for my basic human rights" (OJ 10/1, [104]). He
          and Margarete married on June 6, 1931 (though in his letters from the 1920s he often sends
          greetings "from me and my wife [<hi rend="italic">Frau</hi>]") in Paris, where they lived
          for several years. (One wonders whether Schenker sympathized with Dahms in view of
          Jeanette's nine-year struggle to obtain a divorce from Emil Kornfeld, 1910‒19.) </p>

        <p>In the mid 1930s, Walter became a Honduran citizen, changed his name to Gualterio Armando
          (his wife to Margarita Armando), apparently foreswore all connections with Germany, and
          moved to Lisbon in 1935, where he continued to publish books and compose music. </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Dahms and Schenker</head>
        <p>Dahms became one of Schenker's strongest supporters and advocates. He first came to
          Schenker's attention in May 1913. His review of Schenker's <title level="m">Chromatic
            Fantasy &amp; Fugue</title> edition (July 15, 1913) pleased the latter, several other
          reviews at that time drew attention to Schenker's ideas, and his review of <title
            level="m">Die letzten fünf Sonaten ... op. 109</title>, "Beethoven redivivus," December
          31, 1913, and the cordial response from Schenker that it evoked, encouraged him in April
          1914 to express the desire (reported in WSLB 202) to move from Berlin to Vienna in order
          to become a pupil of Schenker's. He did study briefly with Schenker's pupil <ref
            cRef="entity-000922">Otto Vrieslander</ref> (who was based in Munich) c.1919, but
          decided to discontinue this and sought Schenker's advice on further study. Schenker
          regularly arranged for him to receive complimentary copies of his publications, from
            <title level="m">Die letzten fünf Sonaten ... op. 109</title> to <title level="j">Das
            Meisterwerk in der Musik</title>, vol. III (1930).</p>

        <p>In 1918, he was involved with Vrieslander, Halm and <ref cRef="entity-000737">Herman
            Roth</ref> in an attempt to launch a Festschrift for Schenker's fiftieth birthday,
          through Universal Edition. In 1919, Schenker stated his intention to grant him one of the
          stipends "for impecunious skilled composers" that were in his gift from the estate of <ref
            cRef="entity-000165">Sofie Deutsch</ref>; the award was deferred for a year, and seems
          to have been paid in the summer of 1920.</p>

        <p>Dahms was conservative in outlook, applauded Schenker's uncompromising pronouncements on
          contemporary music, and shared his German nationalist and anti-democratic political views
          (though he disagreed with him hotly over Germany's militarism, and became increasingly
          disenchanted with many aspects of contemporary German culture).</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="bold">Correspondence</hi>
        </p>
        <p>105 items of correspondence survive from Dahms to Schenker in OJ 10/1 (1913 to 1931), and
          one letter from UE to Dahms with annotations by Schenker (OC 52/617, undated). No
          correspondence from Schenker to Dahms is known to survive. There are also many references
          to Dahms in Schenker's diary.</p>
        <p>In addition, clippings of eight reviews by Dahms of Schenker's publications are preserved
          in Schenker's scrapbook (OC 2/pp. 38, 41-42, 49, 54, 61, 67, 72, 75, the last of these
          also at OJ 58/5). Of these, two more general articles about Schenker are:</p>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="a">Heinrich Schenker: zu seinem 50. Geburtstag am 19. Juni
              1918,</title>
            <title level="j">Konservative Monatsschrift</title>, June 1918, 647-49</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="a">Heinrich Schenkers Persönlichkeit,</title>
            <title level="j">Allgemeine Musik-Zeitung</title>, Aug 3, 1923, 511-12</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Source:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Baker's1971</title>
          </bibl>
          <bibl>Communication from Dahms's granddaughter, Cristina Teixeio Coelho</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
