<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-006864">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Hermann Graedener [jnr.]</title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, April 29, 1878; died Vienna, [unknown]</title>
        <title type="sub"/>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="graedener_hermann_jnr">Graedener, Hermann [jnr.]</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">graedener_hermann_jnr</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Hermann Graedener [jnr.]</head>
      <div>

        <p>Son of the composer and music theorist <ref cRef="entity-000301">Hermann Graedener</ref>
          and <ref cRef="entity-000582">Irene Graedener (<hi rend="italic">née</hi>
            Mayerhofer)</ref>. Possible early pupil of Schenker’s.</p>

        <div>
          <head>Life</head>
          <p>Hermann, who was a serving officer in the Austrian army during World War I, was a poet,
            writer, and dramatist; his first collection, appearing after the war, was <title
              level="m">Weltweihe, ein Weg in Versen</title>. After a series of further publications
            his volume <title level="m">Ein Volk geht zu Gott</title>, a mixture of prose pieces and
            poems, was released in 1939, drawing high praise from the Nazi authorities. He had
            already been fêted at his 60th birthday on April 29, 1938, the following being reported
            in several newspapers: <cit>
              <q>Dr. Seyß-Inquart in the presence of the Education Minister university professor Dr.
                Manghin and the national cultural director Stuppäck [presented] to poet Hermann
                Graedener in celebratory fashion the Goethe Medal, which was awarded to him in
                recognition of his preeminent creative artistry on the occasion of his 60th birthday
                by the Führer and Reich Chancellor with a handwritten letter. A congratulatory
                telegram was received from Reich Minister Dr. Goebbels.</q>
            </cit>
          </p>

          <p>Also in 1939 his play <title level="m">Sickingen: ein Kampf ins Künftige</title> was
            performed at the Burgtheater in Vienna. On April 20, 1942, Hermann wrote a poem, <title
              level="a">Herr überm Heer</title> in celebration of Hitler’s 53rd birthday. And after
            a public poetry reading by him in Bad Ischl, when his wife, Magda von
            Rattingberg-Graedener performed Bach and Liszt at the piano, he was awarded the
            Prinz-Eugen Medal by the City of Vienna.</p>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>Hermann Graedener and Schenker</head>
          <p>In a eulogy to his former piano teacher <ref cRef="entity-000545">Ernst Ludwig</ref> in
            his diary for March 24, 1915, Schenker stated that Ludwig had provided him [in the late
            1880s] with his first “better-paying pupils,” and goes on: <cit>
              <q>He […] introduced me many years later also to Graedener, whose son I was to teach
                  (<hi rend="italic">zu unterrichten hatte</hi>).</q>
            </cit>
          </p>

          <p>Not only is the chronology vague, but whether Schenker did actually teach Hermann is
            itself not wholly clear. If so, it was certainly before the beginning of Schenker’s
            first lessonbook in January 1912. Hermann appears in an entry in Schenker's diary for
            April 27–28, 1909: <cit>
              <q>I dream bad things about Irene Mayerhofer, and ‒ suddenly in the morning her son
                turns up, to the utmost astonishment even of the mother herself.</q>
            </cit>
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Source</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><ref type="external"
              target="https://anno.onb.ac.at/anno-suche#searchMode=simple&amp;query=%22Hermann+Graedener%22&amp;from=1"
              >ANNO-Suche : Österreichische Nationalbibliothek</ref></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
