<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000137">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Toni [Tony] Colbert (<hi rend="italic">née</hi> Huber)</title>
        <title type="sub">born Hanover, 1865; died 1944</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="colbert_toni">Colbert, Toni</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>18/02/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Colbert ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">colbert_toni</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Toni [Tony] Colbert (<hi rend="italic">née</hi> Huber)</head>

      <div>
        <p>Piano pupil of Schenker's between 1906 and 1916, and wife of newspaper proprietor <ref
            cRef="entity-000136">Carl Colbert</ref>.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career</head>
        <p>Apparently born Caroline Huber, but known by Antonie Wolff and other names, she married
          journalist and newspaper proprietor and editor <ref cRef="entity-000136">Carl
            Colbert</ref> in 1887. Before her marriage, she was already known as a pianist. There
          are many reports of her involvement in chamber concerts and as an accompanist in the <ref
            cRef="entity-004396">Musikverein Building</ref>, the Ehrbach Recital Hall, and many other
          venues, accompanying singers from the Vienna Opera House in Lieder recitals and
          professional instrumentalists. Her caliber may be gathered from reports that she played
          the Dvořák <title>Piano Quintet in A major</title> with the <ref cRef="entity-000727">Rosé
            Quartet</ref> (<title level="j">Wiener Sonn- und Montags-Zeitung,</title> November 20,
          1899) and the Brahms <title>Piano Quintet in F minor</title> (<title level="j">Neue freie
            Presse</title>, November 8, 1908). Socially progressive, she played popular concerts for
          the Vienna Adult Education Association (<hi rend="italic">Volksbildungsverein</hi>) and
          for charitable organizations. During World War I she was active on committees for the
          assistance of impoverished women and children (<hi rend="italic">Frauenhilfsaktion</hi>).
        </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Toni Colbert and Schenker</head>
        <p>Toni Colbert first asked Schenker for lessons on December 5, 1906 (diary), and may have
          studied with him first in the 1906/07 season (diary, June 28). She may well have taken
          further lessons in the 1907/08, 1908/09, 1909/10, and 1910/11 seasons (though there are no
          lessonbooks to substantiate this), for on May 30, 1911 Schenker declined to give her
          further lessons, recording in his diary that he had intended to prepare a special program
          for her in view of her "advancing age," but that although her letters spoke glowingly of
          her love of music she was obsessed with money. In September 1912 he turned her down again,
          but after further correspondence he accepted her on strict stated conditions, and she
          recommenced lessons on October 4, 1912, continuing through to mid-June 1916 (lessonbooks
          1912/13, 1913/14, 1914/15, 1915/16), taking only one lesson per week--an arrangement of
          which Schenker sharply disapproved and which was probably the primary cause of the
          previous difficulties. She appears to have been somewhat unreliable in attendance and
          dilatory in payment of fees. Between 1912 and 1916 she worked with him on chamber works
          such as the Beethoven <title>“Archduke” Trio, Op. 97</title> and the Brahms <title>D minor
            Violin Sonata, Op. 108</title>, and among solo works the Beethoven <title>Piano Sonata
            in E major, Op. 109</title>, Brahms <title>Variations on a Theme of Handel, Op.
            24</title>, and a group of Chopin Etudes specifically noted as “for public
          performance.”</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence</head>
        <p>Unusually for a pupil, there survive twelve items in all: eight letters, one calling card
          and one invitation from Toni and Carl Colbert to Schenker (OJ 9/30, [A], [C], [1]–[6],
          [6b], [7]: 1912–20), and two letters from Schenker to Toni (OC 1B/15 and 13, 1912, 1916),
          as well as many references to others in Schenker’s diaries.</p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
