<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000064">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Hector Berlioz</title>
        <title type="sub">born La Côte-St-André, Isère, December 11, 1803; died Paris, March 8,
          1869</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="berlioz_hector">Berlioz, Hector</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">berlioz_hector</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Hector Berlioz</head>
      <div>

        <p>One of France's leading composers, and a principal representative of the Romantic
          movement in European music. </p>

        <div>
          <head>Berlioz and Schenker</head>
          <p>In his writings as a newpaper music critic between 1891 and 1901 Schenker showed
            himself well acquainted with Berlioz's writings on music by quoting from them. His
            library at the time of his death included <title level="m">Les grotesques de la
              musique</title> (1859) and <title level="m">Les soirées de l'orchestre</title> (1852)
            in German translations by Richard Pohl (1864). In his important article <title level="a"
              >Impersonal Music</title> (<title level="j">Neue Revue</title>, April 9, 1897),
            Schenker launched an early attack on Berlioz and Liszt as founders of the genre of
            program music, alleging that they and their "school" had artistic personalities that
            were too small (hence "<hi rend="italic">im</hi>personal"), consequently were unable to
            express themselves musically and had to resort to words and images. Two weeks later he
            wrote of the "little" Berlioz, who "through his sheer ambitiousness rendered music sick"
            and "in endless orchestral miscalculations exhausted his personal insignificance." </p>

          <p>In the same article, he said that music must "explain itself by its own means"; and in
            his <ref cRef="entity-001724"><title level="m">Harmonielehre</title></ref> of 1906 he
            illustrated this analytically, discussing a passage from the <title level="a">March du
              supplice</title> of Berlioz's <title level="m">Symphonie fantastique</title> in which
            the triads of D<hi rend="italic">flat</hi> and G are directly juxtaposed. While the
            juxtaposition resembles a Phrygian progression in C minor, Schenker says, Berlioz forces
            it into the key of G minor, producing a deficiency in which he has "neglected to compose
            out the harmonies D<hi rend="italic">flat</hi>‒F‒A<hi rend="italic">flat</hi> and G‒B<hi
              rend="italic">flat</hi>‒D in any way, motivically or thematically, as a result of
            which, as unverified sonorities, as it were hanging in the air, they are bound to give
            rise to doubts in our minds" (pp. 147‒48, Eng. transl., pp. 112‒14).</p>

          <p>In his <ref cRef="entity-001729"><title level="m">Instrumentation Table</title></ref>,
            Schenker included works by Berlioz among the citations, mostly for non-standard
            orchestral instruments such as E<hi rend="italic">flat</hi> clarinet, cornet,
            ophicleide, and bass tuba. Evidently in preparation for the <title level="m"
              >Table</title> Schenker drew on Berlioz's <title level="m">Grand traité
              d'instrumentation</title> (1843, though he may have used the 1904‒05 enlargement by
            Richard Strauss as <title level="m">Instrumentationslehre von Hector Berlioz</title>),
            but he rather audaciously regarded his three-page introduction as superior to Berlioz's
            massive work.</p>

          <p>But it was in his unpublished "<ref cRef="entity-001759"><title level="u">Decline of
                the Art of Composition</title></ref>" (c.1906‒09) that Schenker launched a
            full-scale attack on Berlioz (who "possessed from the outset very few musical red blood
            cells"). The requirement for music to "explain itself" was now replaced by the criterion
            of "synthesis" as exhibited by Beethoven. Literature has its own laws, which are
            different from those of music. When admitted into music, literature disables the
            "autochthnous rule of music laws," and so makes synthesis of music's elements impossible
            to achieve: "The briefest of Haydn keyboard sonatas has more musically synthesis-bearing
              <hi rend="italic">esprit</hi> than the entire life's work of Berlioz." (Use of the
            French word <hi rend="italic">esprit</hi> here was ironic.) Moreover, Berlioz believed
            that he was achieving musical "progress" ‒ a notion that Schenker regarded as
            delusional.</p>

          <p>In 1914, in an unpublished article "<ref type="other" cRef="OJ-21-2_1"><title level="u"
                >German Genius</title></ref>," Schenker remarked: "Never did Berlioz have it in his
            power to write a distinctive, let alone symphonic, bass line!"</p>

          <p>By 1922, doubtless in the aftermath of World War I and the Versailles Treaty,
            Schenker's language had become sharper. "The artistic director has no idea that Berlioz,
            purely on his own terms, let alone measured beside a Beethoven, is not even a rank
            beginner when it comes to musical composition. What is so laughable, so derisory, about
            his conduct is that sheer downright ignorance leads him to the extremity of cavassing
            for French art, or for the cosmopolitan mentality, or both, in a form that casts a false
            light not only on a respected institution but on the nation, or at least on the premier
            musical city" (<ref cRef="entity-001742"><title level="j">Tonwille</title> 3</ref>,
            deleted at proof stage; restored in the Eng. transl., vol. I, p. 137). In his essay on
            Beethoven's Fifth Symphony in 1923, he invoked Mendelssohn's disparaging remarks about
            Berlioz's orchestral writing (<ref cRef="entity-001744"><title level="j"
                >Tonwille</title> 5</ref>, p. 19, fn.; Eng. transl., vol. I, pp. 189‒90, fn.
            21).</p>

          <p>It is not surprising that, when he came to compile his music examples for <title
              level="m">Free Composition</title> (1935), he ignored Berlioz's music completely.</p>
        </div>

      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Ian Bent</author>
          </bibl>
          <lb/>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
