<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000424">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Ludwig Karpath</title>
        <title type="sub">born Budapest, April 27, 1866;died Vienna, Sept 8,1936</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="karpath_ludwig">Karpath, Ludwig</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>25/07/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Karpath ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">karpath_ludwig</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Ludwig Karpath</head>
      <div>
        <p>Viennese writer on music and administrator, early student of Schenker who was twice
          involved in attempts to procure an official post in Vienna for the theorist.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Karpath studied at the Budapest Conservatory and embarked on a career as a singer. After
          moving to Vienna in 1894, he became music critic for the <ref cRef="neues_wiener_tagblat">
            <title level="j">Neues Wiener Tagblatt</title>
          </ref>, a position he held until 1921, while working also as a chief editor at <ref
            cRef="merker_der">
            <title level="j">Der Merker</title>
          </ref> from October 1914 to March 1917 (see OJ 12/9, [21]), and later worked as a
          freelance writer. As a critic he was an influential figure.</p>
        <p>Although ostensibly a promoter of young musical talents, Karpath shouted during the
          première of Schoenberg's Second String Quartet (December 21, 1908) for the performance to
          be stopped, then wrote a hostile (unsigned) review in the <title level="j">Neues Wiener
            Tagblatt</title>, followed by a (signed) statement in the <ref
            cRef="signale_fur_die_musi">
            <title level="j">Signale für die musikalische Welt</title>
          </ref> (January 2, 1909); the latter prompted Schoenberg to write an open letter to him,
          which Karl Kraus published in <ref cRef="fackel_die">
            <title level="j">Die Fackel</title>
          </ref>.</p>
        <p>From 1922, he was artistic adviser to the Austrian Ministry of Education (OJ 12/9, [29]);
          however, he must at least have had contacts in the Ministry by 1908 (see below), which is
          perhaps why he was involved in the conversion of the Vienna Conservatory from private to
          public institution in 1909. He had also been involved in the founding of the Vienna
          Volksoper in 1898, and later in the building of the Vienna Konzerthaus (1912/13). By 1933,
          he bore the title of Hofrat (Court Counsellor). Karpath was a close friend of Richard
          Strauss (who dedicated his ballet <title level="m">Schlagobers</title> (1924) to him, and
          the correspondence between the two men survives), and knew also Brahms, Reger, Puccini,
          Mahler, Hans Richter, and many other prominent musical figures. He wrote a number of
          books, including a biography of Siegfried Wagner.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Karpath and Schenker</head>
        <p>Karpath was an early student of Schenker's: his was the first lesson of the 1906/07
          season on September 4, 1906 (diary, OJ 1/5, p. 19). That Karpath was by then a member of
          Schenker's close circle of friends is indicated by the use of the codes "Kp." and "rp."
          for him in Schenker's diary in reports of their lunching together and discussing musical
          topics. Karpath was also one of those to whom review copies of Schenker's earlier
          publications were sent at the author's own request. However, from 1913 the tone of
          Schenker's references to him become progressively less favorable (WSLB 154, OJ 56/27,
          etc.).</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Search for a Position for Schenker</head>
        <p>On two widely separate occasions, Karpath was involved in attempts to obtain an official
          position for Schenker.</p>
        <p><hi rend="bold">1908:</hi> The diary for February 10, 1908 (OJ 1/7, p. 74) records: "Mr.
          Karpath alerts me in a postcard open for all to see that the wheels have been set in
          motion in the Ministry [of Education] regarding the professorship."</p>
        <p>And the following day, hilariously: "With Floriz [Moriz Violin] at Karpath's place.
          Chandelier comes crashing down, all the globes dashed to smithereens—by the laws of
          superstition, a most propitious omen. Meaning: I must now go and see Hofrat Wiener
          myself."</p>
        <p>The disastrous interview with <ref cRef="entity-000961">Karl von Wiener</ref>, who was
          shortly to become President of the Vienna Conservatory (= Akademie), regarding a
          professorship at that institution is recorded in the diary on February 15 (p. 78),
          concluding with "Report of it given to rp. [Karpath] after lunch."</p>
        <p><hi rend="bold">1932/33:</hi> Between November 1932 and February 1933, Karpath was
          involved in trying, with Furtwängler's support, to find a position for Schenker in Vienna,
          while Furtwängler was trying simultaneously to secure a position for Schenker in Berlin;
          there is a three-way correspondence on this, involving others as well, and there are
          reports in Schenker's diary (e.g. OJ 4/6, p. 3792, November 18, 1932). At that time,
          Furtwängler speaks of Karpath's untrustworthiness, overweening vanity, and diminished
          influence (OC 18/37-38), and Schenker refers to Karpath's scheme as a "hapless idea" (OC
          18/49), and of his "incorrigible vanity, his ignorance" (OJ 4/6, pp. 3812-3813). In the
          end, Karpath reported that the initiative was "impossible," but that Karl Kobald,
          President of the Akademie (and artistic adviser to the Education Ministry 1906-32), "has
          recommended you strongly for the Austro-American Course that is now coming into existence,
          and that you would certainly be granted this post." (OC 18/54). Of that—which Schenker
          characterized scornfully as "the American club" (OJ 4/6, pp. 3814-3815)—nothing came.</p>
        <p><hi rend="bold">1913:</hi> Between those two occasions, in a review of Schenker's <title
            level="m">Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie</title> dated April 7, 1913, Karpath said of
          Schenker: <cit>
            <q>A researcher with so profound a knowledge, with so outstanding an analytical
              intellect as Schenker, a teacher of such towering significance, is consigned in
              Austria to making a living from private funds. Schenker's place is the University. It
              is there that he ought to be conducting his work so that his lofty gifts can develop
              in the right way. (OC 2/p. 29, unsigned).</q>
          </cit></p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Correspondence</head>
        <p>Correspondence between Karpath and Schenker survives as OJ 12/9 (24 items including
          letterheads of <title level="j">Neues Wiener Tagblatt</title> and <title level="j">Der
            Merker</title>, 1908–32), OC 18/40–45[b], 51–54 (1931–33), and correspondence between
          Wilhelm Furtwängler and Karpath as OJ 35/4, OJ 71/11 (1933), and OC 18/27–28, 46–47, 52
          (1933); one letter from Emil Kammerer to Karpath with letter from Karpath to Schenker on
          reverse as OJ 71/19a; one letter to Josephine Violin as OC 18/45[a] (1933).</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Reviews</head>
        <p>Reviews by Karpath in the <title level="j">Signale für die musikalische Welt</title> of
          performances involving Schenker are preserved in Schenker's scrapbook at OC 2/p. 17
          (November 30, 1904) and p. 19 (February 7, 1906), of a publication mentioning Schenker at
          OC 2/p.8 (December 23, 1903), and of performances by Moriz Violin, Schenker and others at
          OJ 70/66 (1904, 1906), also in the <title level="j">Neues Wiener Tagblatt</title> at OC
          2/p. 16 (November 15, 1904) and p. 19 (March 1905). Karpath's review of Schenker's <title
            level="m">Harmonielehre</title> in the <title level="j">Neues Wiener Tagblatt</title> is
          preserved at OC 2/pp.20-21 (May 18, 1908). According to Schenker, Karpath had reviewed the
          first edition of <title level="m">Ein Beitrag zur Ornamentik</title> [1903] in 1908, and
          requested a copy of the second edition in September 1908 (WSLB 19). In 1912, Karpath
          complained that he had not been sent a review copy of <title level="m">Beethovens Neunte
            Sinfonie</title> (WSLB 138, OC 52/101).</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head> Bibliography:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Karpath, Ludwig</author>, <title level="m">Siegfried Wagner als Mensch und
              Künstler</title> (Leipzig 1902)</bibl>
          <bibl><editor>Karpath, Ludwig</editor>, ed., <title level="m">Zu den Briefen Richard
              Wagners an eine Putzmacherin</title> (1906—object of Schenker's ridicule in WSLB 154,
            April 22, 1913)</bibl>
          <bibl>
            <editor>Karpath, Ludwig</editor>, ed., <title level="m">Richard Wagner: Briefe an Hans
              Richter</title> (Berlin 1924)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><editor>Czeike, Felix</editor>, <title level="m">Historisches Lexikon Wien</title>,
            vol. 3 (Vienna 1994), p. 470</bibl>
          <bibl><editor>Eybl, Martin</editor>, ed., <title level="m">Die Befreiung des Augenblicks:
              Schönbergs Skandalkonzerte 1907 und 1908: Eine Dokumentation</title> (Vienna: Böhlau
            Verlag, 2004), pp. 40–42, 133–34 , 182–84, 211–12, 239–40, et al</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
              Tagebüchern und Briefen ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), 40–42</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">OeML</title> Online,</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
