<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-003633">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Georg Dohrn</title>
        <title type="sub">born Bahrendorf nr Magdeburg, May 23, 1867; died Munich, March 9,
          1942</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="dohrn_georg">Dohrn, Georg</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>13/02/2006</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">dohrn_georg</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Georg Dohrn</head>
      <div>
        <p>German conductor and pianist.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Georg Dohrn studied law at the universities of Leipzig, Munich, and Berlin. After
          receiving his doctorate in 1891, he studied music at Cologne Conservatory 1891‒95, his
          piano teacher there being Isidor Weiß. In 1895, he worked as solo repetiteur at the court
          theater in Weimar, and in the same year took up the parallel position at the royal court
          theater in Munich, working under Hermann Levy. His first post as a conductor came in 1897
          at the city theater in Flensburg. From 1898 to 1901 he was joint second conductor with
            <ref cRef="entity-000341">Siegmund von Hausegger</ref> with the private Kaim Orchestra
          in Munich under its chief conductor, <ref cRef="entity-000948">Felix von
          Weingartner</ref>. During those years he directed many orchestral concerts in Munich and
          Bavaria, while also appearing as pianist in chamber music engagements. </p>

        <p>In 1901 he moved to Breslau, where he took over the direction of the Breslau Orchestra
          Society and Breslau Choral Society. In 1910 he was accorded the title of Professor. It was
          thanks to him that at that time Breslau achieved a level comparable to other leading
          musical centers in Germany. Among the virtuoso instrumentalists who played under his baton
          were Eugen d'Albert, Ferruccio Busoni, Arthur Schnabel, Wilhelm Backhaus, Rudolf Serkin,
          Wilhelm Kempf, Eduard Erdmann, Vladimir Horowitz or Fritz Kreisler, Bronislaw Hubermann,
          Adolf Busch, and singers such as Ilona Durigo and Maria Ivogün. In 1936 he was forced by
          chronic illness to withdraw from public life, and spent his final years in Seeshaupt on
          the Starnberger Lake.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Dohrn and Schenker</head>
        <p>Dohrn ‒ evidently a reader of Schenker's writings ‒ wrote to the theorist from Breslau in
          April 1926 to seek advice on the performance of the opening motive of the second movement
          of Beethoven's Ninth Symphony (OC 82/27-28), to which Schenker replied in generous detail
          the same day (Rothg, 1).</p>

      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><editor>Müller, Erich H.</editor>, ed., <title level="m">Deutsches
              Musiker-Lexikon</title> (Dresden: Wilhelm Limpert, 1929)</bibl>
          <bibl><editor>Frank, Paulo</editor> and <editor>Wilhelm Altmann</editor>, <title level="m"
              >Kurzgefaßtes Tonkünstler-Lexikon</title> (Regensburg: Gustav Bosse Verlag,
            1936)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Marko Deisinger</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
