<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-000934">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Gerald F. Warburg</title>
        <title type="sub">1902-71</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="warburg_gerald_f">Warburg, Gerald F.</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>23/01/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">warburg_gerald_f</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Gerald F. Warburg</head>
      <div>
        <p>American cellist, pupil of Hans Weisse.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>He was a member of the German-Jewish Warburg family which owned the independent bank M.
          M. Warburg (est. Hamburg, 1798), and son of the great American philanthropist Felix M.
          Warburg (whose New York house became the Jewish Museum). Warburg studied at Harvard
          University (at which in 1956 he established the Eda Kuhn Loeb Music Library in memory of
          his aunt), then pursued a career as a professional cellist, studying in Paris and Vienna,
          making his solo debut with the New York Philharmonic under Walter Damrosch in 1927.
          (Warburg founded the Stradivarius Quartet using four Stradivarius instruments from his
          father's collection, his own being the "Duport" of 1711.)</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Warburg and Schenker</head>
        <p>Warburg was already a pupil of <ref cRef="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</ref> in Vienna by
          the summer of 1922 (diary August 24, 1922). Schenker evidently knew of Warburg by January 12,
          1923, when, at Weisse's request, he agreed to receive him "since he is after all a
          student," but comments that "I would never accept any financial support from Warburg for
            <title level="j">Tonwille</title>" (OJ 3/4, p. 2489). The blazing row between the two
          men a year later at Schenker's home (and perhaps also the fact that the Warburg Bank had
          been heavily involved in the Versailles Treaty of 1919) supplies the reason for this:
          Warburg criticized the Germans, and (as Schenker reports): <cit>
            <q>he would like to help me if I would adjust to the American standpoint! I stick with
              my views; he chokes with anger. Finally, however, I assert my rights by throwing the
              American out, i.e. by my not relying on him, the American learns subordination toward
              a man of the spirit, who turns his back on his money and character." (OJ 3/6, p. 2723,
              September 12, 1924).</q>
          </cit></p>
        <p>Five months later, Schenker speaks first of Warburg and then of "another pupil of
          Weisse's," from which we may perhaps deduce that Warburg was studying with Weisse at least
          by that time (OJ 3/7, p. 2785, February 14, 1925).</p>
        <p>Berry says that Warburg seems to have become aware of Weisse's and Schenker's teachings
          by January 1927, but the many references to Warburg in Schenker's diaries of 1923-25
          suggest that such awareness may go back further. Berry surmises that the invitation from
          the <ref cRef="entity-002454">Mannes Music School</ref> to Hans Weisse in 1931 to
          teach there may have arisen out of conversations between Warburg and David and Clara
          Mannes. If so, then Schenker may ultimately have owed him in part the transmission of his
          theory to the United States. Ironic, then, is the 1925 diary entry reading "11:30,
          Warburg; he is going to Casals in Paris; speaks of his 'musical calling'! 'What can I do
          for you in America?' I [reply]: 'Absolutely nothing; I see no possibility.'" (OJ 3/7, p.
          2823, May 29, 1925). Warburg later that year wrote a letter to Weisse reporting that "an
          American, <ref cRef="entity-000939">[George A.] Wedge</ref>, is lecturing on the Urline
          at the <ref cRef="entity-002437">Damrosch Conservatory</ref>" (OJ 3/8, p. 2876,
          October 8, 1925).</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Correspondence</head>
        <p>There is no known surviving correspondence between Warburg and Schenker. One letter
          survives from Oswald Jonas to Warburg as OJ 36/71 (1938). </p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>Schenker's diaries</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">NDGM2</title> (2001 and online)</bibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
              Tagebüchern ...</title> (1985), pp. 86, 217, 356-57 </bibl>
          <bibl><author>Berry, David Carson</author>, <title level="a">Hans Weisse and the Dawn of
              American Schenkerism,</title>
            <title level="j">Journal of Musicology</title> 20/1 (Winter 2003), 104-56, esp. 109-10
          </bibl>
          <bibl><author>Berry, David Carson</author>, <title level="a">Hans Weisse
            (1892-1940),</title> in <editor>Eybl, Martin</editor> &amp; <editor>Fink-Mennel,
            Evelyn</editor>, eds, <title level="m">Schenker-Traditionen: Eine Wiener Schule der
              Musiktheorie und ihre internationale Verbreitung</title> (Vienna: Böhlau Verlag,
            2006), pp. 91-103, esp. 93 </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
