<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-000955">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Egon Wellesz</title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, Oct 21, 1885; died Oxford, England, Nov 9, 1974</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="wellesz_egon">Wellesz, Egon</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>28/04/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">SchiffP ~ H+JSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">wellesz_egon</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Egon Wellesz</head>
      <div>
        <p>Austrian (later British) composer, musicologist, and teacher. </p>
        <p>Wellesz studied law and musicology from 1904 at the University of Vienna, working under
            <ref cRef="entity-000003">Guido Adler</ref> on Baroque and 18th-century opera and
          receiving a doctorate in 1908. In 1911, he produced an edition of Fux's opera <title level="m">Constanza e fortezza</title> for the series <title level="s">Denkmäler der
            Tonkunst in Österreich</title>, and in 1913 a study of Cavalli and Venetian opera
          1640-60. In 1913, too, he began lecturing in music history at the University, becoming a
          professor extraordinary there in 1920; he also taught at the <ref cRef="entity-002451">Neues Wiener Konservatorium</ref> 1911-15, and served for a time as music critic for
            <title level="j">Der Neue Tag</title>. </p>
        <p>He is perhaps now best known for his work in the fields of early Christian and Byzantine
          chant; in 1916, he solved the problem of deciphering middle-Byzantine neumes; in 1931 he
          founded the series <title level="s">Monumenta Musicae Byzantinae</title>. Being
          part-Jewish, in 1939 he moved to Oxford, was a fellow of Lincoln College 1939-74, becoming
          a British citizen in 1946. He contributed many articles to scholarly journals, wrote a
          monograph on Fux and several monograph studies of Byzantine chant and of Baroque music. </p>
        <p>Wellesz was a private pupil of Schoenberg for a while from 1905, and is considered a
          member of the Second Viennese School. Universal Edition contracted him as one of its
          composers in 1915. Between then and 1934, he composed five operas and four ballets, two in
          collaboration with Hofmannsthal, as well as orchestral works, a piano concerto, four
          string quartets, much music for piano, Lieder, and works for solo voice and instruments.
          After 1939, he composed one further opera, nine symphonies, five more string quartets, and
          much other chamber music, including an octet and a clarinet quintet, and vocal music. In
          his early career, he was a regular contributor to <ref cRef="merker_der">
            <title level="j">Der Merker</title>
          </ref> and <ref cRef="musikblatter_des_anb">
            <title level="j">Musikblätter des Anbruch</title>
          </ref>, and wrote a biography of Schoenberg (1921) ad later a study of the origins of the
          twelve-tone system (1938). </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Wellesz and Schenker</head>
        <p>No correspondence or contact between Wellesz and Schenker is known to have occurred,
          though Schenker undoubtedly knew of him, for Wellesz is occasionally mentioned in his
          diary and correspondence with others. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Source:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">NGDM1</title> and <title level="m">2</title></bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">OemL Online</title></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
