<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000333">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Maximilian Harden</title>
        <title type="sub">born Berlin, 20 October 1861; died Montana, Switzerland, 30 October
          1927</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="harden_maximilian">Harden, Maximilian</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">harden_maximilian</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Maximilian Harden</head>
      <div>

        <p>German actor, critic, journalist, and publicist.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Maximilian Harden (born Felix Ernst Witkowski) trained as an actor in his teens, and by
          the age of fifteen or sixteen had joined a traveling theater troupe. At the age of
          sixteen, he converted from Judaism to Protestantism. He began to write theater criticism
          and political commentary in his early twenties, publishing in numerous magazines and
          journals such as <title level="j">Die Gegenwart</title> and <title level="j">Die
            Nation</title>.</p>

        <p>In 1892, Harden established his own weekly journal in Berlin, <title level="j">Die
            Zukunft</title>, which he continued to publish for thirty years, and through which he
          became one of the most powerful cultural and political opinion-makers in Germany.</p>

        <p>Originally a monarchist and support of Otto von Bismarck, Harden grew critical of the
          Kaiser after Bismarck was dismissed. In 1907 and 1908 he instigated what is known as the
          "Harden-Eulenberg Affair," when he accused members of the Kaiser's personal military
          entourage of homosexual behavior.</p>

        <p>At the outset of World War I, Harden had recovered enough of his erstwhile monarchism to
          support the German invasion of Belgium. But during the course of the war, he once again
          became critical of the nation's political leadership, and instead became an outspoken
          advocate for Woodrow Wilson's policies. He eventually supported the signing of the Treaty
          of Versailles.</p>

        <p>In 1922, he survived an assassination attempt apparently initiated by an antisemitic
          organization in Munich. The brutal attack made it impossible for Harden to continue
          publishing <title level="j">Die Zukunft</title>. He removed to Switzerland, where he died
          in 1927 from long-term consequences of the attack.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Harden and Schenker</head>

        <p>Harden seems to have been introduced to Schenker's work as a critic by a third party at a
          pub sometime in 1892 (OJ 11/42, [1]), shortly after <title level="j">Die Zukunft</title>
          began publication. The first piece of Schenker's that appeared in the journal was <title
            level="a">Mascagni in Wien,</title> on October 15, 1892. Thereafter, Schenker was a
          regular contributor, publishing a total of eighteen articles between 1892 and 1897.</p>

        <p>On April 18, 1896, Harden published Schenker's extremely favorable review of Karl
          Goldmark's <title level="m">Das Heimchen am Herd</title>. This review became a sore spot
          for Harden, who found Goldmark's work execrable when he heard it, and received support for
          his opinion from his more musically literate acquaintances. This resulted in a rift that
          grew until December 1897, when Harden rejected a submission by Schenker, informing him
          that further collaboration would be impossible (OJ 11/42, [30]).</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence</head>

        <p>Thirty-one letters and postcards survive from Harden to Schenker, OJ 11/42, [A],
          [1]‒[30], spanning the years 1892 to 1897. No items of correspondence from Schenker to
          Harden are known to survive, although it is clear that Schenker wrote to Harden as well as
          submitting articles to him. Schenker's diaries do not begin to record day-to-day events or
          provide summaries of correspondence sent and received until 1906, thus they furnish no
          evidence for Schenker's side of the exchange, or for his reactions to that of Harden.</p>

        <p>Schenker's diary only once refers in passing to Harden, at least betwen the years
          1894‒1911. However, he devotes a whole section of his long letter to August Halm on
          September 25, 1922 (DLA 69.930/10), which is worth quoting <hi rend="italic">in
            extenso</hi> here; it is headed "Harden": <cit>
            <q>Already during my earliest years, because I had to support mother, sister, younger
              brother [...] and nieces by giving piano lessons, I gladly accepted an offer from a
              Viennese friend of Harden to write something for him. They were my very first attempts
              and I thank Harden for having the courage to publish them, for the multiple effects of
              the collaboration help in any case to prepare for a better future. From the first
              moment, without having understood anything, he showed me boundless, even stirring
              trust. However, I could not return that love. I soon saw that he had mastered no issue
              independently, consequently is relegated to judge according to unrelated,
              insubstantial, even foreign viewpoints. "Being different than the others" had to be
              the reward, subconsciously, that he pursues up to the present. And then again he was
              precisely for that reason just like the others who conceal their lack of independence
              (= insufficiency) from themselves in the same manner. He scolded the newspaper
              editors, the underlings as though a daily paper without mundane dirt were even
              possible [...] but managed altogether differently himself. Even with me he did not shy
              away from frequently attempting to exert influences depending on how he himself was
              influenced. (But I did not yield.) He has merely always been a pathetic H. Bahr, went
              along with everything that smelled of minority, etc.<lb/><lb/>His "Monarch's
              Education," which got him jail time, had an especially repulsive effect on me. Not
              only did I find the essay boorish but above all too cheap. If only he had had insight
              (at close range) into the life of the historically rich, as even I did back then, it
              would not have occurred to him to seek more "education" than can be achieved according
              to circumstances generally. He would have to object to Masaryk, Harding, Ebert,
              Wilson, etc., with the same authority. The profession, the scope of the dealings draw
              boundaries which one has the strength to transgress only in the rarest cases. Such a
              person does not even have an overview of his own goods, the mundane ones. A majordomo
              has to give a daily report that only bores the owner. Every chairman depends on
              "reports," and it is exactly the same with an emperor, who does not need to know
              everything, know how to do everything. It was an awful misuse by Harden ‒ again
              opportunism ‒ which caused me ‒ pardon the expression ‒ to give him a kick despite all
              necessity. Additionally there was the comprehension that I could not make myself as
              understandable to readers as I might have hoped in some other way. Back then I drafted
              my theories and I felt the powerful urge to develop them. [Eng. transl. Lee
              Rothfarb]</q>
          </cit>
        </p>
      </div>


    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Bibliography</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Berlin als Theaterhauptstadt</title> (Berlin: F. and P. Lehmann Verlag,
            1888) </bibl>

          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Apostata</title> (Berlin: George Stilke Verlag, 1892–93) </bibl>

          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Literatur und Theater</title> (Berlin: Freund &amp; Jeckel Verlag,
            1896) </bibl>

          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Kampfgenosse Sudermann</title> (Berlin: Verlag der Zukunft, 1903) </bibl>

          <bibl>
            <title level="m"> Köpfe</title>, 4 vols. (Berlin: Erich Reiss Verlag, 1911–1924) </bibl>

          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Krieg und Frieden</title>, 2 vols. (Berlin: Erich Reiss Verlag, 1918) </bibl>

          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Von Versailles nach Versailles</title> (Hellerau bei Dresden:
            Avalun-Verlag, 1927) </bibl>

          <bibl>
            <title level="j">Die Zukunft</title>, 30 vols. (Berlin: Verlag der Zukunft, 1892–1922)
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>

        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>William Pastille</author></bibl><lb/>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
