<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-000683">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Raoul Pugno</title>
        <title type="sub">born Montrouge nr. Paris, June 23, 1852; died Moscow, Jan 3, 1914</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="pugno_raoul">Pugno, Raoul</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>21/01/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Pugno ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">pugno_raoul</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Raoul Pugno</head>
      <div>
        <p>French pianist and teacher of Italian descent.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Pugno studied at the Ecole Niedermeyer in Paris, then at the Paris Conservatory
          (1866–69), after which he was organist at the St.Eugène Church (1872–92). He taught
          harmony at the Paris Conservatory (1892–96) then was appointed professor of piano there
          (1896–1901). By that time, he was internationally celebrated as both a virtuouso solo
          recitalist and a chamber player, noted especially for his interpretation of the works of
          Chopin, Mozart, and César Franck. In 1903, he made gramophone recordings, including works
          by Liszt, Massenet, Chabrier, and Chopin. He was active also as a composer, writing
          operas, operettas, ballets, pantomimes, and instrumental works. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Pugno and Schenker</head>
        <p>Schenker did not review performances by Pugno during his years as an active music critic
          (1891–1901), nor is Pugno mentioned in Schenker's early diaries. He seems to have entered
          Schenker's orbit when c. 1901 he was selected by the newly founded Universal Edition as
          its editor of the complete works of Chopin. The two men seem never to have met, and their
          relationship was thus an oblique one. Pugno's name appears along with other members of
          UE's early editing team in a postcard to Emil Hertzka of 1909. Schenker says he is willing
          to meet with Hertzka on condition that there be no criticism of him: <cit>
            <q>since I feel myself more competent in this area [i.e. editing] than your advisers,
              and have at any rate made a better job of it than UE’s other contributors, such as
              Pugno, Röntgen, Door, etc., and Busoni, who were not subjected to criticism. (WSLB 50,
              Dec 22, 1909). </q>
          </cit></p>
        <p>Pugno's edition of the complete works of Chopin for Universal Edition was advertised as
          "revised according to the original sources with fingerings and performance indications."
          We know that Schenker owned copies of Chopin's music in editions by Klindworth, Mikuli,
          Scholtz, and others (OC/Scores 52–67), and the following entries in his lessonbooks
          demonstrate that he occasionally used Pugno's edition in his teaching as a (presumably
          adverse) means of comparison: "Chopin Etude in F minor, fingerings compared with those of
          Pugno" (Oct 18, 1913); "<title level="m">Berceuse</title>, new (compared with Pugno)"
          (1918/19). </p>
        <p>There is no known correspondence between Pugno and Schenker.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Pugno Bibliography </head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Piano pedagogical works:</hi></bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">L'Art de travailler le piano (Etudes des gammes)</title> (Paris: C.
            Pugno, 1908)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Les lecons écrites de R. Pugno: Chopin</title> (Paris: Librairie
            des Annales Politiques, 1910)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Edition of Chopin:</hi></bibl>
          <bibl><title>Chopin: Sämtliche Werke</title> (Vienna: Universal Edition: 4 vols:
            UE1580–1583; also in 12 vols: UE341–352):</bibl>
          <bibl>I: Waltzes, Mazurkas, Polonaises (UE1580)</bibl>
          <bibl>II: Nocturnes, Ballades, Impromptus, Scherzos, Fantaisie (UE1581)</bibl>
          <bibl>III: Etudes, Preludes, Rondos, Sonatas (UE1582)</bibl>
          <bibl>IV: Pieces, Barcarolle, Tarantella, Concertos, etc. (UE1583)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>Also edition of the piano works of Massenet</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">NGDM2</title> (2001 and online)</bibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">MGG1</title>
          </bibl>
          <bibl>Universal Edition catalogs</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Ian Bent</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
