<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000819">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Adalbert Franz Seligmann</title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, April 2, 1862; died Vienna, December 13, 1945</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="seligmann_adalbert">Seligmann, Adalbert</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>28/10/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Botstiber ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">Seligmann ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">ViolinM ~ H+JSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">ViolinM ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">seligmann_adalbert</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Adalbert Franz Seligmann</head>
      <div>
        <p>Austrian art critic, writer, and painter.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Seligmann studied at the Vienna Akademie der Bildenden Künste 1880-84, and with among
          others Christian Griepenkerl 1884-87 at the Munich Akademie der Bildenden Künste. He
          travelled many times to Germany, France, Italy, the Balkans, and Turkey, for purposes of
          study. Thereafter, he worked as art correspondent for various newspapers, including the
            <title level="j">Wiener Sonn- und Montags-Zeitung</title> (1894-1904), <title level="j"
            >Die Wage</title> (1898-99), the <title level="j">Neue Freie Presse</title> (1903-34)
          and <title level="j">Die Moderne Welt</title> (from 1918), in the course of his
          contributions to which, though against contemporary art, he advocated progressive <hi
            rend="italic">plein-air</hi> painting; a collection of this early criticism was
          published under the title <title level="m">Kritische Studien von Plein-Air</title>
          (Vienna, 1904). A second collection, based largely on feuilletons from the <ref
            cRef="entity-002559"><title level="j">Neue Freie Presse</title></ref>, appeared under
          the title <title level="m">Kunst und Künstler von gestern und heute</title> (Vienna: Carl
          Konegen, 1910); he gave a copy to Schenker, who in his thank-you message noted at the time
          that he “already possessed it,” having faithfully collected and carefully arranged all of
          Seligmann’s newspaper articles.) A third collection of later journalism was issued
          posthumously, in 2015. </p>


        <p>For many years, Seligmann taught at the Vienna Conservatory (later designated the
          Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst): from 1889 to 1898 as instructor in "historical
          costume art," from 1910 to at least 1919 as lecturer (<hi rend="italic">Dozent</hi>) in
          "costume art and art history," from 1912/13 with the title of Professor. In 1897, he
          founded the Kunstschule für Frauen und Mädchen (Vienna Art School for Women and Girls),
          later the Frauenakademie (Academy for Women).</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Seligmann and Schenker</head>

        <p>In their three decades of corresponding with one another (1902–33), Seligmann and
          Schenker always addressed each other as their “dear friend” (<hi rend="italic">lieber
            Freund</hi>), and they remained on good terms for almost the whole of the period. Each
          took an interest in the other’s work, and Schenker was especially keen to know whether it
          might be possible to measure the worth of a painting, or the importance of an artist, on
          purely objective criteria, as he claimed he could do for musical works and composers.
          Schenker gave Seligmann a copy of each of his publications, and often asked him to read
          and comment on the non-technical parts of them, including the treatise <ref
            cRef="entity-001721"><title level="m">Ein Beitrag zur Ornamentik</title></ref> (1903),
          the sections on the secondary literature in <ref cRef="entity-001731"><title level="m"
              >Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie</title></ref> (1912), and the essay <title level="a"
            >Rameau oder Beethoven?</title> in the <ref cRef="entity-001752">third <title level="j"
              >Meisterwerk</title> yearbook</ref> (1930). Seligmann, for his part, gave Schenker a
          copy of his <title level="m">Kunst und Künstler</title> and invited him to exhibitions of
          his paintings.</p>

        <p>Seligmann had a good knowledge of music and was an enthusiastic chamber musician (he
          played in a quartet with Schenker in the early 1900s, but his instrument is not
          specified). Because he had held a lectureship in costume design at the Vienna
          Conservatory, he had inside knowledge of the workings of both the Conservatory and its
          parent organisation, the <ref cRef="entity-002430">Gesellschaft der Musik Freunde in
            Wien</ref>, and could thus offer valuable guidance to Schenker when he was desperately
          seeking a teaching post there in 1903; see especially Seligmann’s long letter of late
          summer or early autumn 1903 (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-23_7">OJ 14/23,
            [7]</ref>). He was also on friendly terms with the editorial teams of Viennese
          newspapers, and could help Schenker place a notice about a series of lectures on the
          decline of musical composition, which were proposed in 1911 but never materialized. </p>

        <p>Seligmann greatly admired Schenker’s musical understanding and his skill as a writer; but
          he did not shy away from criticizing his polemical language, pointing out in several
          letters that his friend’s denigration of the writings of his “adversaries” (<hi
            rend="italic">Gegner</hi>) served little purpose and harmed his standing in the academic
          world. He shared Schenker’s artistic conservatism, but generally kept his own critical
          writings, which were often amusing, free from personal attack.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>
        <p>Correspondence from Seligmann to Schenker (including two printed notices) is preserved as
          OJ 14/23 (28 items, 1902-33), that from Schenker to Seligmann at the Wienbibliothek im
          Rathaus, as WSLB-Hds 94475-95664 <hi rend="italic">passim</hi> (17 items, 1903-31). One
          letter from Seligmann to Jeanette Schenker in February 1935 also survives (OJ 14/23),
          making 46 items in total. It is clear from the correspondence itself and from Schenker’s
          diary that there were other items that have not survived.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Österreichisches Biographisches Lexikon 1815-1950</title>, Band XII
            (Wien 2005), pp. 152-153 and online</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="j">Jahresberichte der K. K. Akademie für Musik und Darstellende
              Kunst</title> (Vienna, 1909-19)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Marko Deisinger</hi></author>, <author><hi rend="bold"
                >William Drabkin</hi></author>, and <author><hi rend="bold">Ian
            Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
