<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-007722">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Heinrich [Henryk ; Hersch Leyb] Szalit [Schalit]</title>
        <title type="sub">born Drohobycz, November 15, 1867</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="szalit_heinrich">Szalit, Heinrich</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">szalit_heinrich</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Heinrich [Henryk ; Hersch Leyb] Szalit [Schalit]</head>
      <div>

        <p>Elder brother of pianist <ref cRef="entity-000878">Paula Szalit</ref>.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career summary</head>
        <p>Born in Drohobycz, near <ref cRef="entity-002401">Lemberg</ref>/<ref cRef="entity-002401"
            >Lwów</ref>, Heinrich is said to have given his younger sister <ref cRef="entity-000878"
            >Paula</ref> her early piano lessons. He took her when she was eight years old to
          Vienna, where she studied first with Robert Fischhof, then after April 1896 briefly with
          Schenker followed by <ref cRef="entity-000150">Eugen d’Albert</ref> then <ref
            cRef="entity-000523">Theodor Leschetizky</ref>. In 1902–1904, he – presumably <ref
            cRef="entity-000878">Paula</ref>, too – was living at Vienna IX, Porzellangasse 54, his
          profession stated in the street directory as “pianist” (however, he apparently suffered
          from restricted eyesight and had to relinquish hopes of a performance career). His name
          does not appear in the directory after 1904, and it is likely that he returned to
          Drohobycz. <ref cRef="entity-000878">Paula</ref> was appointed to the piano faculty of the
          Lemberg Conservatory as the head of the advanced piano class in September 1906. Three
          years after that, Heinrich was living in Drobobych, as stated in an entry in the <title
            level="j">Karlsbader Kurliste</title> (<title level="j">Karlsbad</title> [=Karlovy Vary,
          in Bohemia] <title level="j">Court List</title>) for July 22, 1909: <lb/><lb/><cit>
            <q>Name and status: Mr. Heinrich Szalit, piano teacher, with wife Adele and son Emil |
              Usual residence: Drohobycz | Residence here: Amor, Morgenzeile.</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>The <ref cRef="entity-002401">Lemberg/Lwów</ref> address book for 1916 lists him as
          “merchant” and his address as Fumańska 8. The Drohobych directory for 1927 lists him as
          “bank clerk” and gives his address as Romanovicza 9. The 1938 Drohobych directory gives
          his address is Św. [= street] Jana 12, which was his place of business as a dealer in
          pianos, which we know from advertisments such as: <lb/><lb/><cit>
            <q>HENRYK SZALIT Stock of high-quality grand and upright pianos, models of international
              companies BECHSTEIN, IBACH, KAPS, FÖRSTER, as well as the best local companies. <lb/>—
              Convenient repayment terms. — <lb/>DROHOBYCH, Jana Street 12, Tel. No. 192.</q>
          </cit> Nothing is known of his death. </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Heinrich Szalit and Schenker</head>
        <p>In an early but undated calling card, <ref cRef="entity-000878">Paula</ref> sent “best
          wishes from Heinrich,” suggesting that the two men were by then acquainted, perhaps from
          the time <ref cRef="entity-000878">Paula</ref> studied with Schenker in 1896 and 1897.
          Schenker’s diary for April 11, 1915 records: <cit>
            <q>Mr. Heinrich Schalit arrives at my place to inquire if I might perhaps have some
              access to <ref cRef="entity-000743">Rothschild</ref> or Springer, or someone like
              that, who could come with money to the aid of his sister, who was tragically injured
              in an accident. He takes the opportunity to inform me that Mr. Kux, Mrs. Popper, and
                <ref cRef="entity-000199">Mrs. Eissler</ref> together provide 110 Kronen per
              month.</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>No correspondence between the two men is known to survive.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <ref type="external"
              target="https://anno.onb.ac.at/cgi-content/anno?aid=clk&amp;datum=19090722&amp;query=%22Heinrich+Szalit%22&amp;ref=anno-search&amp;seite=5"
                ><title>ANNO-Suche Österreichische Nationalbibliothek</title></ref>
          </bibl>
          <bibl><title level="j">Blatt der Hausfrau</title>, vol. 22 (1902)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Adolph Lehmann's allgemeiner Wohnungs-Anzeiger</title> 1902, 1903,
            1904</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="j">Karlsbader Kurliste</title>, July 22, 1909</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
