<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000316">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Hans Guttmann</title>
        <title type="sub">born July 24, 1898</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="guttmann_hans">Guttmann, Hans</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/07/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Guttmann ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">Guttmann ~ JSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">GuttmannH ~ H+JSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">guttmann_hans</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Hans Guttmann</head>
      <div>
        <p>Elder son of <ref cRef="entity-000319">Sophie</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-000318"
            >Salo</ref> Guttmann, brother of <ref cRef="entity-000315">Frieda</ref> and <ref
            cRef="entity-000317">Julien</ref> Guttmann, nephew of Heinrich and <ref
            cRef="entity-000771">Jeanette Schenker</ref>, godson of Heinrich. See <ref
            cRef="entity-002935">Guttmann family</ref>.</p>

        <p>In his diary for August 17, 1898, Schenker speaks of his being godfather to the
          "first-born" (Hans) of his sister <ref cRef="entity-000319">Sophie Guttman</ref>,
          expressing the hope that he will honor the name of his grandfather (<ref
            cRef="entity-000772">Johann Schenker</ref>). Nothing is known of Hans’s childhood,
          except for the amusing incident when, visiting Vienna aged 16, he saw a crucifix over the
          bed of Jeanette (who was Jewish) and was upset that Heinrich might have to convert to
          Christianity (diary, Oct 28, 1914); or of his education, other than an attempt to enroll
          him in the Piarist secondary school in Vienna (diary, Oct 28, 1914).</p>

        <p>In April 1916, Hans was deemed fit for military service and stationed first in Schönberg
          (Šumperk) in the Sudetenland in 1916–17, on “light duties,” later in <ref
            cRef="entity-002271">Bielitz</ref>, <ref cRef="entity-002318">Wiener-Neustadt</ref>, and
          in 1918 <ref cRef="entity-002364">Szeged</ref>, from where he was able frequently to send
          food parcels to Heinrich. After the war, he studied in Vienna with financial support from
          his uncle, <ref cRef="entity-000774">Moriz Schenker</ref>, graduating in August 1919, then
          moving to <ref cRef="entity-002385">Vinkovci</ref>, in Croatia-Slavonia, from which he had
          access to <ref cRef="entity-004271">Agram</ref> (Zagreb). The only hint of his occupation
          thereafter comes from a letter of 1922, where he speaks of working in an office (<hi
            rend="italic">Büro</hi>) and chancellery (<hi rend="italic">Kanzlei</hi>) (<ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-4_2">OJ 14/4, [2]</ref>), which suggests that he might
          be an attorney’s clerk. In 1922 and 1923, he was living in the Yugoslavian town of St
          Gjurjerovai (location unknown). Hans spent a good deal of time with his <ref
            cRef="entity-000774">Uncle Moriz</ref> at the latter’s house in <ref
            cRef="entity-002394">Baden bei Wien</ref> and occasionally in <ref cRef="entity-002526"
            >Bucharest</ref>, and there may have been a question of <ref cRef="entity-000774"
            >Moriz</ref> finding him a place in a bank. </p>

        <p>Heinrich’s diary for April 2, 1929 records Hans’s engagement to <ref cRef="entity-008425"
            >Edith</ref> (?<hi rend="italic">née</hi> Schwartz). Their marriage followed on May 27
          in <ref cRef="entity-004271">Agram</ref>; Heinrich was invited but did not attend; bride
          and groom visited the Schenkers in Vienna on June 25–26. <ref cRef="entity-008425"
            >Edith</ref> gave birth to a daughter at the beginning of November 1932. <ref
            cRef="entity-008425">Edith</ref>’s character is three times criticized by <ref
            cRef="entity-000319">Sophie</ref>, first in July 1933 speaking of her “unchasteness; I
          am more convinced than ever that her child is not her husband’s,” secondly in a letter to
          Jeanette in January 1938, that she “puts on so many airs and graces” and causes Hans
          financial strain by her extravagant living (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-11-31_1"
            >OJ 11/31, [1]</ref>), reinforced in a letter to Jeanette of November 1938 reporting
          that Hans “has an extremely fashion-conscious wife who is very, very extravagant” (<ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-11-31_2">OJ 11/31, [2]</ref>). Hans was transferred to
          Belgrade in 1939 “after having lived in the countryside for nineteen years” (<ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-11-31_3">OJ 11/31, [3]</ref>), on receiving a promotion.</p>
        
        <p>Thereafter, we have no information as to whether he escaped transportation.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Hans Guttmann and Heinrich and Jeanette Schenker</head>
        <p>In Fall 1914, Heinrich commented that Hans’s “posture and speech are uncultivated” (diary
          Sep 17, 1914), and three years later described him as “unintelligent and headstrong” (Sep
          16, 1917). In the 1920s, living in <ref cRef="entity-002385">Vinkovci</ref>, Hans visited
          Vienna periodically, attending opera and theater and sharing meals with Heinrich and
          Jeanette, who exhibited growing affection for him. Heinrich borrowed money from him
          frequently, while encouraging him to purchase his publications, medallion, and mezzotint
          portrait.</p>

        <p>He visited the Schenkers at their summer resort in <ref cRef="entity-002292">Galtür</ref>
          from August 29 to September 1, 1927, where he proved himself to be a photographer (a skill
          first mentioned in 1918): on the final day, Heinrich records: <cit>
            <q>Around 10 o'clock, we ride down with the automobile; Hans takes a picture of us in
              the car and accompanies us, taking several pictures along the way: one in a very
              well-chosen place, where the Parsei Massif and the castle at the Trisanna Bridge
              provide the background; the driver is photographed with us. [...] Even at the last
              moment, as we are boarding, Hans takes a picture. (diary, Sep 1, 1927)</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>After this, he stayed in Vienna September 8‒18, visiting them each day. In subsequent
          months he delivered prints and enlargements of his photographs (see below, under
          Correspondence). A second visit to <ref cRef="entity-002292">Galtür</ref> took place in
          1930, when Hans and Edith booked themselves into a hotel, staying three weeks, June 29 to
          July 17, and again Hans took photographs, sending prints to the Schenkers.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence and other documents</head>
        <p>One telegram and one letter to Heinrich survive as OJ 14/4, [1] (Nov 29,1918) and [2]
          (May 14, 1922), and one fragmentary letter to Heinrich and Jeanette Schenker is preserved
          as OC 65/56 (Dec 22, 1923), and a fieldpostcard from Moriz Schenker and Hans Guttmann from
          Rumania to Heinrich Schenker survives as <ref type="OJ-14-5_6">OJ 14/5, [6]</ref> (Aug 8, 1918).</p>

        <p>Photographs of Hans survive as OJ 72/18, Nos 9, 10 (in military uniform: 1917), and he
          appears also in Nos 8 and 13 with Frieda and Julien (1912, 1919), and probably No. 11 with
          his parents and siblings (1916/17).</p>

        <p>It is possible that some or all of the photographs OJ 72/15, Nos 2‒4, showing Heinrich
          and Jeanette in a chauffeured car in <ref cRef="entity-002292">Galtür</ref>, were those
          recorded in the diary as having been taken by Hans on September 1, 1927 (see above)</p>
      </div>

    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Marko Deisinger</hi></author> and <author><hi rend="bold"
                >Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
