<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000061">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Alban Berg</title>
        <title type="sub">born Feb 9, 1885; died Dec 24, 1935</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="berg_alban">Berg, Alban</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">berg_alban</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Alban Berg</head>
      <div>

        <p>Viennese-born composer, pupil of Schoenberg, and a principal member of the so-called
          Second Viennese School. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Career summary</head>
        <p>Berg became a pupil of <ref cRef="entity-000798">Arnold Schoenberg</ref>’s in October
          1904, having started to compose at the age of 15. After the performance of exercises in
          fugue and some songs at a concert of music by Schoenberg’s pupils in Vienna on November 7,
          1907 he remained a student until 1911, by which time his musical language had advanced
          from the traditional late romanticism of the early Lieder to the extended tonality of the
          Piano Sonata, Op. 1 (1907‒08) and the post-tonal radicalism of the String Quartet, Op. 3
          (1910). </p>

        <p>Berg’s most celebrated later works, including the operas <title level="m">Wozzeck</title>
          (1917‒22) and <title level="m">Lulu</title> (1929‒35), the <title level="m">Lyric
            Suite</title> (1925‒26) and the Violin Concerto (1935), are notable for their avoidance
          of out-and-out atonality in favor of a sophisticated fusion between post-tonal
          progressiveness (Berg adopted the twelve-tone method during the 1920s) and the kind of
          allusions to earlier music that are most explicit in the Violin Concerto's use of a Bach
          chorale harmonisation. </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Berg and Schenker</head>
        <p>Unlike Arnold Schoenberg, who was a constant object of Schenker's antagonism from at
          least 1910 onward, Berg is rarely mentioned in Schenker's diary or correspondence.
          Schenker was invited by Schoenberg to the concert of his pupils' music referred to above
          (OJ 14/45, [15]), but did not attend. On March 18, 1928, Schenker heard songs ‒ presumably
          the <title level="m">Altenberglieder</title> of 1912 ‒ by Berg on the radio and commented
          in his diary "Berg: Lieder mit Orchesterbegleitung; sehr häufig Wendungen, die nicht nur
          tonal, sondern intonal-trivial sind" ("Berg: songs with orchestral accompaniment: very
          frequently turns of phrase that are not only tonal but [also] intonally trivial": OJ 4/1,
          pp. 3188‒3189) ‒ by which he probably meant that while working with<hi rend="italic">in
            tonal</hi>ity they managed only to make the tonal trivial ("intonal" is not a
          Schenkerian term, but presumably a deliberate neologism). </p>

        <p>Berg must surely have been subject to Schenker's resentment that Schoenberg's pupils
          supported him so publicly, whereas his own did not (e.g. addressing his pupils
          rhetorically: "Were you the pupils of Schoenberg, or Schreker, or Busoni, [...] you would
          be standing on your heads, running into the streets, through every town and society,
          parting with your money in order to be with them and to support them; but so touched are
          you by the truth that you sleep and snore in the broadest daylight, as though I were
          giving you opium rather than the truth.": OJ 6/7, [6], July 20, 1923, to Violin). </p>

        <p>A more remote point of contact between Berg's music and the Schenker circle is provided
          in <ref cRef="entity-000143">Felix-Eberhard von Cube</ref>'s <title level="m">Das Lehrbuch
            der musikalischen Kunstgesetze</title> (1950s, unpublished): Urlinie analyses of Berg's
          two settings of "Schließe mir die Augen beide" ‒ the earlier (1907) deemed the work of a
          gifted musician, the later (1925) a counter-example showing what happens when a composer
          is corrupted by atonality. </p>

      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence</head>
        <p>No correspondence between Berg and Schenker is known to have occurred. Evidently Berg
          wrote to <ref cRef="entity-000380">Anthony van Hoboken</ref> regarding the <ref
            cRef="entity-002452">Photogrammarchiv</ref>, for Schenker records a letter to Hoboken in
          which he remarks: "I recommend him to interpret Alban Berg's letter as irony, since the
          Archive really is in a position to damage the reputation of the so-called 'new music,'
          albeit it pursues first and foremost only the goal of protecting the manuscripts from
          demise": OJ 4/1, p. 3154, December 17, 1927 [= OJ 89/1, [8]]). </p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Arnold Whittall</author>, <author>Ian Bent</author>, <author>William
              Drabkin</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
