<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-000055">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Ludwig van Beethoven </title>
        <title type="sub">born Bonn, bapt. Dec 17, 1770; died Vienna, March 26, 1827</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="beethoven">Beethoven, Ludwig van</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">beethoven</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Ludwig van Beethoven </head>


      <p>German composer. </p>

      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Beethoven grew up and studied in Bonn, but in 1792 left for Vienna, where he remained for
          the rest of his life, coming to be thought of as a Viennese composer, and to be grouped
          with Haydn and Mozart as one of the three leading exponents of the "Viennese classical
          style." Since the early 19th century, his nine symphonies have been pillars of the
          orchestral repertory; his solo concertos, string quartets, sonatas for piano solo, violin
          and piano, and cello and piano, and much else have also achieved canonic status.</p>
      </div>


      <div>
        <head>Beethoven and Schenker</head>

        <div>
          <head>Early Theoretical Works: 1901–11</head>
          <div>
            <head><title level="m">Beitrag</title> and <title level="m">Harmonielehre</title></head>
            <p>Beethoven, as man and artist, was a central preoccupation of Schenker's throughout
              his career. Already in the first edition of his <title level="m">Beitrag zur
                Ornamentik</title> (1903), the title of which includes the phrase "including also
              the ornamentation of Haydn, Mozart, and Beethoven etc.", Schenker devoted time to the
              nature and performance of embellishment in Beethoven's music, and this treatment was
              expanded in the second edition (1908). In <title level="m">Harmonielehre</title>
              (1906), the number of music examples drawn from Beethoven far exceeds that from any
              other composer. </p>
          </div>

          <div>
            <head>Unpublished Works</head>

            <p>Schenker's first declarative statement of Beethoven's status is given in his
              unpublished "Decline of the Art of Composition," the provisional earlier title of
              which was "Beethoven or Wagner?" (CA 27, June 4, 1906), written probably between 1905
              and 1909. Enumerating all the genres in which Beethoven worked, before going on to
              criticize subsequent composers for the insufficiency and lack of breadth of their
              productivity, he remarks: <cit>
                <q>Note [...] the abundance within each genre: nine symphonies, sixteen string
                  quartets, thirty-two piano sonatas, and so on. Every genre comprises quite a few
                  pieces. What a wealth of work! And all this with severe physical affliction, which
                  allowed the master to live a mere fifty-seven years! (134/36) </q>
              </cit></p>

            <p>He speaks of the "wonderful instinct for associations and parallelisms" to be found
              in the masters, citing instances in Beethoven's works and concluding "Beethoven would
              never have dared merely to set down a germ or a series of tones, i.e. without an
              effect for the synthesis" (156/59–60). When speaking of Beethoven's use of instruments
              he remarks "what cannot be accounted for or shown by the synthesis will not yet be
              produced sonically" (157/60). Synthesis is thus the organizing principle by which
              Beethoven worked. Contrasting Beethoven with Wagner, he states that the former "in
              reality thought of form only in absolutely musical terms and, when the occasion arose,
              additionally used impulses of life, moods, and images," and that "it is precisely
              Beethoven who shows most clearly how important it is to organise musical content into
              two or three parts" (201/104). </p>

            <p>In his unpublished treatise on performance <title level="m">Die Kunst des
              Vortrags</title>, which dates from around 1911, Schenker remarks that whereas music
              before the Classical period tended to be "ceaseless," "in a Beethoven movement already
              the rhetorical rests offer the performer the relief of breathing," and talks of
              Beethoven's as a "more 'speaking' manner" in contrast to the "'connected' world of
              Bach" (p. 70). </p>
          </div>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>Monograph and Elucidatory Edition: 1912–21</head>

          <div>
            <head>The Ninth Symphony</head>
            <p>In 1910, Schenker began to envision a series of monographs ("independent repertory
              appendices"), which would amplify in practical terms what was stated theoretically in
              his series Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien. Significantly, his first
              monograph was on Beethoven's Ninth Symphony. Intended initially to be accompanied by a
              score giving only Beethoven's original markings, the monograph sets out to release the
              symphony from the accretions of 19th-century performers and commentators, and to
              present Beethoven as an exemplar of musical genius, uncovering for the first time "the
              laws of tonal construction" governing the work. </p>

            <p>Beethoven, Schenker polemicized in 1914, "is already performed as Viennese children
              in lower school speak Latin; just as Latin is falsified and travestied in the
              Sperlgasse [Gymnasium], so equally dead is the language that is given out on the
              podium as a living musical language" (OJ 5/16, [2]). In his monograph, Schenker
              deploys formal charts and discusses thematic construction using conventional
              terminology, but examines the work in its own terms rather than with reference to
              extra-musical ideas. Schenker grounds this latter claim in the examination of
              Beethoven's sketches for the work by Gustav Nottebohm, which, as Schenker says, "show
              the object from the most interesting aspect – specifically, the initial origin of the
              ideas." </p>
          </div>

          <div>
            <head>The Erläuterunsausgabe</head>
            <p>As Schenker had remarked as early as 1910: <cit>

                <q>I can assure you that it is one of the necessities of artistic life that my views
                  on the Ninth Symphony, which are admittedly so embattled, be heard. As I never
                  tire of reiterating, the rescuing of the last sonatas of Beethoven is a necessary
                  cultural act!" (WSLB 66/67, October 19, 1910). </q>
              </cit></p>

            <p>As soon as his work on the Ninth Symphony was completed, in 1911, Schenker turned to
              his next major enterprise, his elucidatory edition of Beethoven's last five piano
              sonatas, Opp. 101, 106, 109, 110, and 111. </p>

            <p>Instead of relying entirely on Nottebohm, Schenker now embarked on his own research,
              corresponding with librarians and private collectors in order to locate the autograph
              manuscripts and sketches of these five works and to obtain photographic copies of them
              — a pursuit which ultimately led to the creation of the Photogrammarchiv in Vienna.
              Since the autograph manuscript of Op. 106 could not be located, Schenker never
              completed the missing volume of the series, though he was ostensibly intending to do
              so even in the late 1920s. For those that he was able to examine, he made detailed
              notes, also annotating the score that he was using as his base text. Characteristic is
              his visit to the palace of the Wittgenstein family, of which he records: <cit>
                <q>Inspection of the autograph manuscript of Op. 109. Completely unexpected were the
                  most surprising insights, which confirm what I myself have maintained up to now;
                  despite the misrepresentation of the text that a pupil taught, Nottebohm’s and
                  Mandyczewski’s notes prove to be all too superficial and come nowhere near the
                  heart of the matter. (OJ 1/11, p. 277: Nov 12, 1912) </q>
              </cit></p>

            <p> Collating Op. 109 against the engraved proofs: <cit>
                <q>Study of the autograph manuscript undertaken purely from the artistic point of
                  view; on this occasion, […] new and indeed even sensational features of the
                  content uncovered and carried over into the music text. Thus a second close
                  examination of the music text proves in itself far deeper than the first one, full
                  of fruitful insights, with consequences far beyond the immediate occasion. (OJ
                  1/12, p. 379: July 16, 1913). </q>
              </cit></p>
          </div>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head><title level="j">Tonwille</title> and a Performance: 1921–24</head>
          <div>
            <head><title level="j">Tonwille</title> and its precursor</head>

            <p>During World War I, Schenker steadily developed his monograph idea into an integrated
              series to be called "Little Library" (<title level="m">Kleine Bibliothek</title>),
              making proposals to several publishers. In this he planned individual studies of
              Symphonies 3, 5, 6, 7, and 8, and of the Piano Sonatas Op. 27, No. 2 ("Moonlight"),
              Op. 53 ("Waldstein"), Op. 57 ("Appassionata"), Op. 81a ("Les Adieux"), and Op. 90 in E
              minor. </p>

            <p>By 1921, the "Little Library" had become the occasional periodical <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>, in which of the above planned items those for the Fifth
              Symphony and Op. 57 came to fruition, alongside studies of Op. 2, No. 1, and Op. 49
              No. 2. That of the Fifth Symphony became the first fully extended study, occupying
              seventy pages and four <hi rend="italic">Urlinietafeln</hi>, and was subsequently
              published as a separate volume. </p>
          </div>

          <div>
            <head>Beethoven Piano Sonatas: Complete Edition</head>
            <p>During the <title level="j">Tonwille</title> years, Schenker supplied Universal
              Edition with an edition of the complete Beethoven sonatas, the undertaking requiring
              an extended search for early sources, provision of a clean text free of editorial
              interference except for fingerings, and with explanatory footnotes. There were also
              plans in early 1922 for what was provisionally termed an "Urlinie-Ausgabe" of the
              sonatas; these seems to have been first mooted by the Director of Universal Edition,
              Emil Hertzka, as a way of enhancing and distinguishing the new edition. Though the
              Urlinie-Ausgabe would have followed on from the <title level="m">Erläuterungsausgabe</title>, which had been stalled by the failure of the autograph
              of Opus 106 to come to light, it would have been of more limited scope; and it seems,
              moreover, to have drawn its inspiration from Schenker´s essay on Op. 2, No. 1,
              published in <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title> 2 in 1922, in which graphic
              reductions of all four movements of the sonata fit neatly on to a single large sheet of
              paper. In letters to Schenker dated February 11 and 27, 1922 (OC 52/451 and 452),
              Hertzka suggests that each edition of the individual sonatas, and later the collected
              set, could include such "Urlinie-Tafeln," perhaps with a short text offering
              clarification. That the essay on Op. 2, No. 1 is closely connected with his work on
              the sonata edition can clearly be seen at the start of the text-critical commentary,
              which includes the clearest formulation of Schenker´s editorial creed: <cit>
                <q>As little as one may say of Beethoven himself that he was merely practicing
                  musical philology when he sought the best notation, improved slurs, etc., just as
                  little may the work of an editor in this matter be regarded as philology. It is
                  rather of a purely artistic nature, and demands the full interest of all those who
                  want to make the content of the work of art truly their own. (pp. 36–37) </q>
              </cit></p>

            <p>From the commentary on Op. 2, No. 1, we can also infer that Schenker intended his
                <title level="m">Little Library</title> to include an analysis of each of the
              remaining sonatas.</p>

            <p>Around 1920, Otto Erich Deutsch was planning a series of publications entitled
              "Musical Rarities: Viennese Connoisseur Prints," and Schenker was contracted to
              produce the first in the series, a facsimile edition with Foreword of the "Moonlight"
              Sonata. </p>
          </div>

          <div>
            <head>A Historical Performance: 1924</head>
            <p>To celebrate the centenary of its premiere, a re-enactment of the first performance
              of the Ninth Symphony in "authentic" style was given in Vienna on May 7, 1924 under
              the baton of Paul von Klenau. Schenker was consulted in advance, and recorded his
              comments in his diary for that day: <cit>
                <q>Evening, the Ninth Symphony: the program book includes an explanation by Klenau:
                  the elucidation of the historical character, invoking in particular the original
                  tempo and original instrumentation. Sections of the <title level="m">Missa
                    solemnis</title> are played first: the Kyrie well judged at the return in tempo,
                  the Credo good throughout. The forward motion is unmistakable: Klenau handles the
                  choral forces with a sure touch, surer than Furtwängler. The first movement of the
                  symphony good as to tempo, but not free enough in the second and third themes –
                  leaves something to be desired. The second movement very good in the first
                  section, the Trio too slow. The Adagio at the outset manifestly yielding to
                  tradition, at all events timid: the violins still not thought through in long
                  enough terms. Toward the end more animated and more in keeping with the original
                  tempo. The final movement good up to the entrance of the recitative, even very
                  good. Great success for the conductor. The program book mentions my <title level="m">Ninth Symphony</title> monograph in a footnote. (Federhofer, p.
                166)</q>
              </cit>
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>The Mature Years: 1925–35</head>
          <p>No works by Beethoven were studied in the first two volumes of <title level="j">Das
              Meisterwerk in der Musik</title> (1925, 1926), but the third volume was given over
            almost entirely to a study of the "Eroica" Symphony that had initially been planned as
            an independent volume, possibly for publication in Germany by Breitkopf &amp; Härtel
            or Peters. This is the most detailed of all Schenker's analyses, spanning 73 pages of
            text including forty-nine smaller-scale analytical musical examples, together with four
            massively extended fold-out Urlinie graphs, and serves as the ultimate exemplar of
            Schenker's mature critical-analytical method. </p>

          <p>In this, the center of gravity has shifted toward the visual materials, and the text
            into a more supporting role. Its somewhat telegraphic style contrasts with the prefatory
            essay in the volume, "Rameau oder Beethoven?", Schenker’s last major polemical essay, a
            paeon to German musical genius and, to some extent, himself as the one who had revealed
            that genius to the world. In the "Eroica" essay itself, Schenker's view of Beethoven as
            neglected genius and as prototype for Germanity is combined with social polemic in the
            following statement: <cit>
              <q>May the German nation learn from Beethoven to perceive and reject false greatness!
                When Germany has finally liberated itself from the servility in which its
                intellectuals continue to ensnare it, and when the infamy of contemporary
                music-making has disappeared, the sun of Beethoven will shine once more upon a
                Germany that has become aware of what it is. The days of Napoleon have gone for
                ever; but the days of Beethoven remain to be told. (p. 86) </q>
            </cit></p>

          <p>Beethoven played no part in the published first volume of the <title level="m">Fünf
              Urlinie-Tafeln</title> (1932), but two piano sonatas (A-flat, Op. 26, first-movement
            theme; C sharp minor, Op. 27, No. 2, all movements) were planned for the second volume,
            which did not materialize. In Schenker's final work, <title level="m">Der freie
            Satz</title> (1935), examples of Beethoven's work occupy a larger amount of space than
            that of any other composer; it includes examples from all nine symphonies, twenty-four
            of the piano sonatas, five of the string quartets, and other works. </p>
        </div>

      </div>


    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>List of Relevant Works</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Ein Beitrag zur Ornamentik: als Einführung zu Ph. Em. Bachs
              Klavierwerken umfassend auch die Ornamentik Haydns, Mozarts u. Beethovens etc</title>
              [<title level="m">A Contribution to the Study of Ornamentation as an Introduction to
              the Keyboard Works of C. P. E. Bach including also the Ornamentation of Haydn, Mozart,
              and Beethoven, etc</title>] (Vienna: UE, [1903], 2nd edn 1908) </bibl>

          <bibl><title level="m">Harmonielehre</title> [<title level="m">Theory of Harmony</title>]
            (Stuttgart: J. G. Cotta'sche Buchhandlung Nachfolger, 1906) </bibl>

          <bibl><title level="m">Über den Niedergang der Kompositionskunst: Eine technisch–kritische
              Untersuchung</title> [<title level="m">The Decline of the Art of Composition: A
              Technical–Critical Study</title>] [unpublished, written c. 1905–09], ed. W. M.
            Drabkin, <title level="j">Music Analysis</title> XXIV (2005), 131–231 (German text),
            33–129 (English text), 3–31 (Introduction) </bibl>

          <bibl><title level="m">Die Kunst des Vortrags</title> [<title level="m">The Art of
              Performance</title>] [unpublished, written c. 1911], ed Heribert Esser, Eng. transl.
            Irene Schreier Scott (New York: Oxford University Press, 2000) </bibl>

          <bibl><title level="m">Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie: eine Darstellung des musikalischen
              Inhaltes unter fortlaufender Berücksichtigung auch des Vortrages unter der
            Literatur</title> [<title level="m">Beethoven's Ninth Symphony: A Portrayal of Its
              Musical Content, with Running Commentary on Performance and Secondary Literature as
              Well</title>] (Vienna: UE, 1912). </bibl>

          <bibl><title level="m">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven</title> [<title level="m">The Last Five Sonatas of Beethoven</title>] [= <title level="m">Erläuterungsausgabe</title> [<title level="m">Elucidatory Edition</title>] of Opp. 109,
            110, 111, 101] (Vienna: UE, 1913–21) </bibl>

          <bibl><title level="a">Beethovens V. Sinfonie</title> [<title level="a">Beethoven's Fifth
              Symphony</title>], <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title> Heft 1 (1921), 27–37; Heft 5
            (1923), 10–42; Heft 6 (1923), 9–35</bibl>

          <bibl><title level="m">L. van Beethoven: Klaviersonaten: Nach den Autographen und
              Erstdrucken rekonstruiert von Heinrich Schenker</title> [<title level="m">L. van
              Beethoven: Piano Sonatas, reconstructed according to the autograph manuscripts and
              first editions by Heinrich Schenker</title>] (Vienna: Universal Edition, 1921–23) </bibl>

          <bibl><title level="m">L. van Beethoven: Sonata op. 27, n. 2 (Der sogenannte
              Mondscheinsonate), mit drei Skizzenblättern des Meisters, herausgegeben in
              Faksimile-Reproduktion</title> [<title level="m">L. van Beethoven: Sonata op. 27, No.
              2 (The so-called "Moonlight" Sonata), with three sheets of sketches by the master,
              edited in facsimile</title>] (Vienna: UE, 1921) </bibl>

          <bibl><title level="a">Beethoven: Sonate opus 2 Nr. 1,</title>
            <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title> Heft 2 (1922), 25–48 </bibl>

          <bibl><title level="a">Beethoven: Sonate opus 57,</title>
            <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title> Heft 7 (1924), 3–33 </bibl>

          <bibl>
            <title level="a">Rameau oder Beethoven? Erstarrung oder geistiges Leben in der
            Musik?</title> [<title level="a">Rameau or Beethoven? Creeping Paralysis or Spiritual
              Potency in Music?</title>], <title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</title>,
            vol. III (1930), 9–24 </bibl>

          <bibl><title level="a">Beethovens Dritte Sinfonie zum erstenmal in ihrem wahren Inhalt
              dargestellt</title> [<title level="a">Beethoven's Third Symphony: Its True Content
              Described for the First Time</title>], <title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der
            Musik</title>, vol. III (1930), 29–101 and graphs </bibl>

          <bibl><title level="m">Der freie Satz</title> [<title level="m">Free Composition</title>]
            (Vienna: UE, 1935) </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Ian Bent</author> and <author>William Drabkin</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
