<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-003438">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Lisl (Liesl; Lieserl) Schenker</title>
        <title type="sub"/>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="schenker_lisl">Schenker, Lisl</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">schenker_lisl</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Lisl (Liesl; Lieserl) Schenker</head>
      <div>

        <p>Wife of <ref cRef="entity-000774">Moriz Schenker</ref>, maiden name unknown. </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <p>Nothing of Lisl Schenker’s birth or early life is known. She and <ref
            cRef="entity-000774">Moriz</ref> probably married in the 1900s and lived in Egypt, where
          for a time he worked. <ref cRef="entity-000774">Moriz</ref> was Jewish, Lisl apparently
          not so. The couple had two children: <ref cRef="entity-003067">Helga</ref> (born 1907) and
            <ref cRef="entity-000769">Georg</ref> (born 1908). Lisl’s mother is mentioned
          occasionally in the Moriz–Heinrich correspondence by the epithet “mother-in-law.”</p>

        <p>Lisl, described as “bank director’s wife,” first appears in a society list of those
          having “arrived on May 27” at the spa town of <ref cRef="entity-002394">Baden bei
            Wien</ref> with her family and household, at the address Elisabethstraße 17 (<title
            level="j">Cur- und Fremden-Liste ...</title>, May 28, 1912). Her first appearance in
          Heinrich’s diary is in 1913, but not until 1917 is there a promise to introduce her to
          Heinrich, and not until 1926 is a visit from <ref cRef="entity-000774">Moriz</ref>, Lisl
          and the two children to <ref cRef="entity-002826">Keilgasse</ref> 8 recorded; she seems to
          have held herself aloof from the rest of <ref cRef="entity-000774">Moriz</ref>’s
          family.</p>

        <p>News first arrived in 1920 that <ref cRef="entity-000774">Moriz</ref> and Lisl were
          separating (diary, Jan 1, 1920). Their lives seemed after that to fluctuate between being
          together and separation, until in June 1928 she moved from the family home in <ref
            cRef="entity-002394">Baden bei Wien</ref> to Vienna. In September 1928, she finally
          left <ref cRef="entity-000774">Moriz</ref> and transferred her affections to Leopold <ref
            cRef="entity-004819">Richtera</ref>, physicist and pioneer of Austrian radio
          broadcasting. Divorce proceedings began in late December 1929. At the news, Schenker
          commented: <cit>
            <q>Even in this relationship, she will have to do without all conversation day and
              night; in spite of this, she will be able to take part just as little in the
              mathematics and physics of <ref cRef="entity-004819">Richtera</ref> as in the bank
              dealings of Mozio, and without doubt she will come away empty-handed, even erotically
              – thus there remains only a futile ruination for this woman, in every respect a futile
              one.</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>The couple married in April 1930, but two weeks later <ref cRef="entity-004819">Leopold
            Richtera</ref> was taken to a sanatorium suffering from <hi rend="italic">angina
            pectoris</hi>; he died on the night of April 29/30.</p>
      </div>

    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
