<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000655">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Evelina [Eveline, Ewelina] Pairamall (<hi rend="italic">née</hi> Silberstein;
          formerly Birnbaum)</title>
        <title type="sub">born Lodz, Poland, February 27, 1870; died Lodz, April 9, 1939</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="pairamall_evelina">Pairamall, Evelina</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>10/12/2007</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Pairamall ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">pairamall_evelina</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Evelina [Eveline, Ewelina] Pairamall (<hi rend="italic">née</hi> Silberstein; formerly
        Birnbaum)</head>
      <div>
        <p>Long-term pupil of Schenker’s.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Life</head>
        <p>Evelina Pairamall was the daughter of Markus Silberstein and Teresa (<hi rend="italic"
            >née</hi> Cohn). According to Schenker, she was a wealthy Polish Jew and owned
          "twenty-seven or twenty-nine [...] properties and houses in and around <ref
            cRef="entity-002372">Lodz</ref>" (diary, August 26, 1914), and also factories that were
          demolished by the Germans at the end of World War I (diary, March 23, 1918). A widow by
          the time she knew Schenker, she had first married in 1888 Henryk Rafal Birnbaum (1833–99),
          with whom she had one daughter, <ref cRef="entity-005133">Aniela [Angèle] Birnbaum</ref>,
          and secondly Hinda Pairamall (dates unknown). It is unclear when she established her home
          in Vienna, from where she traveled widely. After some illness in Vienna, she returned to
          Lodz in 1938, where she died in 1939 aged 71.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Lessons: with Schenker</head>
        <p>Mrs. Pairamall’s period of study with Schenker spanned probably October 1911 to May 1931,
          but with multi-year-long absences. The lessonbooks record her attendance for the seasons
          1911/12 through 1921/22 and 1924/25 through 1926/27, a total of fourteen full seasons.
          Although scheduled for lessons in 1927/28, she in fact missed that entire season and the
          following two. She returned briefly in April/May 1931, then disappeared from the
          lessonbooks, although Schenker had prepared for her in 1931/32 (OC 16/38). She took no
          part in <ref cRef="entity-002499">Schenker’s seminar of 1931 to 1934</ref>. Over the
          seasons 1911/12 to 1916/17, her work took in courses on instrumentation, continuo,
          thoroughbass, and chorale writing, with brief reference to counterpoint, while also
          working on repertory by Brahms, Chopin, and Schubert. From Spring 1919 through Summer
          1922, she concentrated on chamber works: violin sonatas, cello sonatas, and piano trios by
          Handel, Mozart, Beethoven, and Brahms, playing with violinists Schiffer and Pullman, and
          cellist Lewin.</p>

        <p>Schenker’s antipathy toward the rich in society caused him frequently to voice harsh
          criticism of her (as of other rich pupils of his), reporting in his diaries her slowness
          to pay, and reluctance to accept fee increases. She was, however, useful to Schenker on
          occasions in drawing his attention to items of interest, sending him bundles of
          newspapers, giving him useful presents such as books, editions, and facsimiles of sources,
          and using her contacts to pass on information to him. In December 1920 and spring 1921,
          she was helpful to the Schenkers in finding a new apartment for them, and on February 14
          identified Keilgasse 8, which became their home from May 21, 1921 until after Heinrich’s
          death. Subsequently, there was a distinct warming of the relationship. She introduced him
          to the gramophone in February 1927, briefly loaning her equipment with several 78rpm
          records, as a result of which Schenker later acquired one himself. </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Lessons: with others</head>
        <p>At some date before 1913 (probably 1910 or earlier), Mrs Pairamall took lessons with the
          harpsichordist <ref cRef="entity-000507">Wanda Landowska</ref> in Vienna and Munich, and
          around 1913 became involved in the feud between <ref cRef="entity-000633">Joachín
            Nin</ref> and Landowska over the greater suitability of harpsichord or piano for early
          keyboard music, supplying Nin with information from German-language sources. She also took
          some lessons from <ref cRef="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</ref> in 1921 (OJ 15/16, [45]).
          She was enrolled at the newly-founded Schenker Insitute at the <ref cRef="entity-002451"
            >Neues Wiener Konservatorium</ref> in 1935/36, at which time she was living at Vienna
          III, Neulinggasse 16/6 (very close to Schenker's Reisnerstraße apartment).</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>
        <p>There are two letters from Schenker to Pairamall: OJ 5/27 (November 12, 1913) and OC 1B/5
          (September 9, 1916, which is written by Jeanette in a system of shorthand known as
          "Gabelsberger" Kurzschrift).</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><editor>Fink, Evelyn</editor>, ed., <title level="m">Rebell und Visionär: Heinrich
              Schenker in Wien</title> (Vienna: Lafite, 2003), pp. 22-23</bibl>
          <bibl><ref type="external"
              target="https://www.geni.com/people/Eveline-Pairamall/6000000037349678822"
                ><title>geni.com</title></ref></bibl>

          <bibl><title>jewishgen.com</title></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
