<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-003244">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Klara [Clara] Schiff [Hatschek]</title>
        <title type="sub">born Aussig, December 30, 1881; died Prague, September 14. 1939</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="schiff_klara">Schiff, Klara</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">schiff_klara</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Klara [Clara] Schiff [Hatschek]</head>
      <div>

        <p>Younger sister of <ref cRef="entity-000771">Jeannette Schenker (<hi rend="italic"
              >née</hi> Schiff)</ref>, thus sister-in-law to Heinrich Schenker from 1919. Wife of
            <ref cRef="entity-000339">Oskar Hatschek</ref>, mother of <ref cRef="entity-008428"
            >Hellmuth Hatschek</ref>.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <p>All five of Jeanette Schenker's sisters were younger than she, and Klara was the fourth
          daughter of <ref cRef="entity-008431">Wilhelm</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-00843">Emilie
            Schiff</ref>. She was married to <ref cRef="entity-000339">Oskar Hatschek</ref>, and the
          couple had one child, <ref cRef="entity-008428">Hellmut</ref>.</p>

        <p>After Jeanette left her first husband, <ref cRef="entity-000466">Emil Kornfeld</ref>, and
          the family home town of <ref cRef="entity-002248">Aussig an der Elbe</ref>, she apparently
          did not see Klara ‒ or any of her other sisters or her three brothers ‒ until sixteen
          years later, in October 1926, when Klara and her husband Oskar visited Heinrich and
          Jeanette in Vienna, on October 6. Klara, <ref cRef="entity-000339">Oskar</ref>, and their
          son <ref cRef="entity-008428">Hellmut</ref>, visited the Schenkers again two years later,
          this time in <ref cRef="entity-002292">Galtür</ref>, arriving on July 30 and departing on
          August 26. Heinrich gives his impressions of her in his diary for August 3: <cit>
            <q>My sister-in-law Clara is a splendid woman; she refuses here – sensibly – to preach
              in her innate way, and also takes care not to express her pacifist and world-blessing
              ideas (<hi rend="italic">pazifistischen u. weltbeglückenden Ideen</hi>), since she
              knows that I am not comfortable with such things. I get the distinct feeling that the
              two of them are respecting my intellectual world, on account of which I willingly
              express my agreement to respect theirs.</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>On August 24 Heinrich and Klara went hiking in the Jam Valley, and Schenker reports their
          conversation: "We intentionally said farewell to all megalomania and communism in
          intellectual matters!" (diary). In bidding farewell to the visitors on the 26th, Schenker
          records in his diary that in spite of their intelligence he could not live "in the
          pretentious world of my Lie-Liechen's siblings," with its provincialism." Klara and <ref
            cRef="entity-008428">Hellmut</ref> took many photographs of <ref cRef="entity-002292"
            >Galtür</ref> and the surroundings that they sent to the Schenkers in the October.
          Contrary to this portrayal, her younger sister <ref cRef="entity-000944">Rosa</ref> wrote
          the following (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-10-2">OJ 14/10, [2]</ref>, November
          1, 1932): <cit>
            <q>I have always marveled at her, her mental and physical vigor, her zest for life and
              strong will, with which she steered toward a goal, and above all her sturdy
              self-examination and self-castigation.</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>Klara’s life was upended on October 9, 1932, when <ref cRef="entity-008428">Hellmut</ref>
          unexpectedly died in a climbing accident (see <ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-10_1"
            >OJ 14/10, [1]</ref>, October 10, 1932). This broke her spirit altogether, and she
          experienced bouts of insanity, pleading on more than one occasion to be given poison so as
          to end her own life. She was placed in the Veleslavin Clinic in <ref cRef="entity-002892"
            >Prague</ref>, and by late 1933 was having to be straight-jacketed. — In April 1936,
          when <ref cRef="entity-000771">Jeanette</ref>, embarking on her six-month voyage to
          Santiago, <ref cRef="entity-005845">Chile</ref> and back, headed first to <ref
            cRef="entity- 002448">Aussig</ref> on the 27th, she visited <ref cRef="entity-000339"
            >Oskar Hatschek</ref>, who gave her some items of Klara’s, and then went to see Klara
          herself, of whom she recorded in her diary of the voyage that she was “ill in bed – time
          has literally stood still there.”</p>

        <p>Her death on <date from="1939-09-13" to="1939-09-14">September 13/14, 1939</date> was
          reported to Jeanette by Arnold Weil (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-10_37">OJ
            14/10, [37]</ref>) and she was buried in a <ref cRef="entity-002892">Prague</ref>
          cemetery.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence</head>
        <p>Heinrich's diary gives evidence that Jeanette maintained correspondence with Klara, but
          no items are known to survive. Between at least 1932 and 1939, information was passed on
          to Jeanette and Heinrich from Rosa and Arnold Weil in letters and postcards (OJ 14/10).
          One letter from Victor Schiff to Klara from 1925 survives in a transcript by Anna Schiff
            (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-9_1">OJ 14/9, [1]</ref>). </p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Source</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><ref type="external"
              target=" https://www.geni.com/people/Klara-Hatschek/6000000026404867766 "><title>geni
                “Klara Hatschek (Schiff)“</title></ref></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Ian Bent</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
