<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-000383">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Josef Casimir [Józef Kazimierz] Hofmann</title>
        <title type="sub">born Kraków, Jan 20, 1876; died Los Angeles, Feb 16, 1957</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="hofmann_josef_casimir">Hofmann, Josef Casimir</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>09/01/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">hofmann_josef_casimir</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Josef Casimir [Józef Kazimierz] Hofmann</head>
      <div>
        <p>Polish pianist, one of the greatest and internationally most acclaimed of his day.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Having begun his concert career in the 1880s, Hofmann studied with Anton Rubinstein in
          Germany for a period from 1897. From 1924, he was head of the piano division at the Curtis
          Institute of Music in Philadelphia and director of the Institute from 1926 (when he became
          an American citizen) to 1938. He retired in 1940. </p>
        
        <p>He was the earliest professional musician to make a recording--on wax cylinder in
          1887--and made a number of commercial recordings. He wrote two books on piano playing and
          left many compositions, under the pseudonym Michael Dvorsky.</p> 
          
          <p>He is not to be confused with
          the Josef Hofmann[link] (1865–1927) who taught at the Vienna Akademie für Musik und
          darstellende Kunst (= Conservatory). </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Hofmann and Schenker</head>
        <p>Schenker evidently had mixed feelings about his playing. After attending a Hofmann
          recital in 1906, and after describing his technique generally, Schenker commented in his
          diary:
          
          <cit><q>Tuesday November 13, [1906] [...] Evening: concert [by] Josef Hofmann.
          Technique of the artist: so to speak, a self-contained physical as well as manual[?]
          unity, hence [makes a] most satisfactory impression. The real nerve-center of the
          composition is however only very seldom captured. [There is] even something shallow about
          the sonority (deriving from the shallow style of playing), and hence only little [that is]
          liberating about even the technique itself. (Gummy[?]) Beethoven, C-minor Sonata, Op. 111
          often childishly distorted (variations), and at its best totally misunderstood. Mumbling
          like an old man who has reverted to childhood. However, in the Liszt, at last the most
          unfettered, freeest playing." (OJ 1/5, p. 26).</q></cit></p>
        
        <p>In 1932, Hofmann evidently expressed skepticism about a planned English translation by
          Arthur Waldeck of Schenker's <title level="m">Harmonielehre</title> (OJ 5/44, [3],
          December 31, 1932).</p>
        
        <p>No correspondence is known to survive between Hofmann and Schenker. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">NGDM2</title> (2001 and online)</bibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Baker's1971</title>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
