<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000888">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Ludwig Thuille</title>
        <title type="sub">born Bozen [Bolzano] (Tyrol), November 30, 1861; died Munich, February 5,
          1907</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="thuille_ludwig">Thuille, Ludwig</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">thuille_ludwig</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Ludwig Thuille</head>
      <div>

        <p>Austrian music theorist, composer, and pianist.</p>

        <div>
          <head>Career Summary</head>
          <p>After being a pupil and chorister at the Benedictine monastery of Kremsmünster and
            studying privately with Josef Pembauer (a former Bruckner pupil), Thuille became a
            student at the Royal Music School in Munich, studying music theory, organ and
            composition with Joseph Rheinberger and piano with Karl Bärmann. In 1883 he was
            appointed a teacher of piano and harmony at the same school, in 1888 was given the rank
            of professor, and in 1893 succeeded Rheinberger as professor of composition, a position
            he retained until his death. In the 1880s he became associated with the "New German
            School" of composition and a focus for the young composers of that group, and founder of
            the "Munich School" of composers.</p>

          <p>Thuille is better know today for the widely circulated and forward-looking <title
              level="m">Harmonielehre</title> (Stuttgart: Carl Grüninger Nachf., 1907, 2/1908,
            3/1910, 10/1933), written jointly with <ref cRef="entity-000540">Rudolf Louis</ref>.
            Thuille contributed the general method and many of the music examples, Louis the
            aesthetic and theoretical sections of the work. The work devotes 200 pages to diatonic
            harmony and 200 pages to chromatic and enharmonic harmony, including 20 pages of
            examples from the music literature (excerpts from Liszt, Bruckner, Wagner, Richard
            Strauss, etc.) with multi-level Roman-numeral analyses and analytical commentaries. An
            important concept is that of "perceptual dissonances" (<hi rend="italic"
              >Auffassungsdissonanzen</hi>), which are "simultaneously both consonances and
            dissonances: the <hi rend="italic">outer ('sensory') ear</hi> hears them as consonances,
            while to the <hi rend="italic">inner ('mental') ear</hi> they are unquestionably
            entirely dissonant' (6th edn, pp. 46‒47).</p>

        </div>

      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Thuille and Schenker</head>
        <p>Schenker showed some sympathy for Louis-Thuille: in his 1907 diary (p. 56) he remarked
          dryly that now that Thuille had died, leaving behind the <title level="m"
            >Harmonielehre</title>, "people suddenly knew that he had been a better theorist than
          composer." Certain recent theorists have claimed that Louis's and Thuille's interpretation
          of some harmonies as the result of complex linear motions rather than vertical
          constructions is closer to Schenker's approach. Schenker's library at the time of his
          death had a copy of the 1907 first edition of the <title level="m">Harmonielehre</title>
          (Hinterberger, <title level="m">Musik und Theater ...</title>, item 181).</p>

      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Bibliography</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">MGG</title> (1989), <title level="a">Thuille, Ludwig</title> (Oskar
            Kaul)</bibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Grove Music Online</title>, <title level="a">Thuille, Ludwig</title>
            [n.a.] </bibl>
          <bibl>Damschroder, David and Williams, David Russell, <title level="m">Music Theory from
              Zarlino to Schenker: A Bibliography and Guide</title> (Stuyvesant, NY: Pendragon
            Press, 1990), pp. 172‒73</bibl>
          <bibl>Wason, Robert W., <title level="m">Viennese Harmonic Theory from Albrechtsberger to
              Schenker and Schoenberg</title> (Ann Arbor: UMI Research Press, 1985), pp. 116‒19,
            121‒32</bibl>
          <bibl>Wason, Robert W., <title level="a"><hi rend="italic">Musica practica</hi>; Music
              Theory as Pedagogy,</title>
            <title level="m">The Cambridge History of Western Music Theory</title>, ed. Thomas
            Christenson (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2002), pp. 66‒67</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
