<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000284">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>François-Auguste Gevaert</title>
        <title type="sub">born Huysse, nr. Oudenaarde, July 31, 1828; died Brussels, December 24,
          1908</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="gevaert_francois_auguste">Gevaert, François-Auguste</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">gevaert_francois_auguste</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>François-Auguste Gevaert</head>
      <div>

        <p>Belgian music historian and theorist, teacher, and composer.</p>

        <div>
          <head>Career Summary</head>
          <p>Gevaert studied piano and theory at the Ghent Conservatory, later becoming organist at
            the Jesuit College in that city. He found early success as a composer. From the early
            1850s he settled in Paris, establishing himself as a significant composer of opera. In
            all, he wrote twelve operas and also sacred and secular vocal works, and orchestral and
            chamber music.</p>

          <p>In 1867 he was appointed director of the Paris Opéra, but soon after returned to
            Brussels to become the director of the Brussels Conservatory, a position he held for
            thirty-seven years, reforming its teaching and organization. He also made important
            contributions to the study of ancient and medieval music.</p>

          <p>In 1863 he wrote a treatise on instrumentation that became his best known work. Revised
            in 1885 as the <title level="m">Nouveau traité d'instrumentation</title>, this was
            translated into German, English, Russian, and other languages. He wrote a second study,
            a course in orchestration, in 1890. His last book was a harmony treatise.</p>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>Gevaert and Schenker</head>
          <p>Schenker's interest in Gevaert's work probably arose c.1906, when first producing his
            own <ref cRef="entity-001729"><title level="m">Instrumentations-Tabelle</title></ref>;
            he possessed a copy of the German translation by Hugo Riemann of Gevaert's 1885 <title
              level="m">Nouveau traité</title>. Schenker spoke of his own introduction to the <title
              level="m">Table</title> (written in 1908) as containing all the information of
            Gevaert's and Berlioz's treatises on orchestration "in a nutshell" (<ref
              type="correspondence" cRef="WSLB-33">WSLB 33</ref>, December 31, 1908). There is no
            known contact between the two men. Schenker would have thought of him as French (despite
            the Flemish name): he thought of France as having only "mediocre music directors," and
            as having produced no music of any great significance (<ref type="correspondence"
              cRef="OJ-5-16_2">OJ 5/16, [2]</ref>, December 25, 1908).</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Bibliography (select):</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Traité général d’instrumentation</title> (Ghent and Liège: Gevaert,
            1863) </bibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Nouveau traité d'instrumentation</title> (Paris and Brussels: Lemoine,
            1885 [revn of <title level="m">Traité</title>]); Ger. transl. by Hugo Riemann as <title
              level="m">Neue Instrumenten-Lehre</title> (Leipzig: Junne Otto, 1887) </bibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Cours méthodique d’orchestration</title> (Paris and Brussels: Lemoine,
            1890) </bibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Histoire et théorie de la musique de l'antiquité</title> (Ghent:
            Annoot-Braeckman, 1875‒81) </bibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Les origines du chant liturgique de l'Eglise latine</title> (Ghent:
            Hoste, 1890); Ger. transl. by Hugo Riemann (1891) </bibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Traité d'harmonie théorique et pratique</title> (Paris and Brussels:
            Lemoine, 1905‒07) </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">MGG</title> (1956) (Albert van der Linden) </bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Grove Music Online</title> (2016) (Anne-Marie Riessauw)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Ian Bent</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
