<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-003244">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Klara [Clara] Schiff [Hatschek]</title>
        <title type="sub">died 1939</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="schiff_klara">Schiff, Klara</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">schiff_klara</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Klara [Clara] Schiff [Hatschek]</head>
      <div>

        <p>Younger sister of <ref cRef="entity-000771">Jeannette Schenker</ref> [<hi rend="italic"
            >née</hi> Schiff; Kornfeld], thus also to Heinrich Schenker from 1919. Wife of Oskar
          Hatschek.</p>

        <p>All five of Jeanette Schenker's sisters were younger than she, and Klara appears to have
          been the third daughter of Wilhelm and Emilie Schiff. She was married to Oskar
          Hatschek.</p>

        <p>After Jeanette left her first husband, <ref cRef="entity-000466">Emil Kornfeld</ref>, and
          the family home town of <ref cRef="entity-002248">Aussig an der Elbe</ref>, she apparently
          did not see Klara ‒ or any of her other sisters or her three brothers ‒ until eighteen
          years later, in the summer of 1928, when Klara, her husband Oskar, and son Helmut, visited
          Heinrich and her at their summer refuge of <ref cRef="entity-002292">Galtür</ref> in the
          Tyrol, arriving on July 30 and staying for most of August. Heinrich gives his impressions
          of her in his diary for August 3 (OJ 4/1, pp. 3238‒3239): <cit>
            <q>My sister-in-law Clara is a splendid woman; she refuses here – sensibly – to preach
              in her innate way, and also takes care not to express her pacifist and world-blessing
              ideas (<hi rend="italic">pazifistischen u. weltbeglückenden Ideen</hi>), since she
              knows that I am not comfortable with such things. I get the distinct feeling that the
              two of them are respecting my intellectual world, on account of which I willingly
              express my agreement to respect theirs.</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>On August 24 Heinrich and Klara went hiking in the Jam Valley, and Schenker reports their
          conversation: "We intentionally said farewell to all megalomania and communism in
          intellectual matters!" (OJ 4/1, p. 3245). In bidding farewell to the visitors on the 26th,
          Schenker records in his diary that in spite of their intelligence he could not live "in
          the pretentious world of my Lie-Liechen's siblings," with its provincialism. Klara and
          Helmuth took many photographs of Galtür and surroundings that they sent to the Schenkers
          in the October (OJ 4/2, p. 3270).</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence</head>
        <p>The diary gives evidence that Jeanette maintained correspondence with Klara, but no items
          are known to survive. One letter from Victor Schiff to Klara from 1925 survives in a
          transcript by Anna Schiff (OJ 14/8). </p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Ian Bent</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
