<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000049">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Agnes N. Becker</title>
        <title type="sub"/>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="becker_agnes">Becker, Agnes</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">becker_agnes</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Agnes N. Becker</head>
      <div>

        <p>Pupil of <ref cRef="entity-000913">Moriz Violin</ref> in Hamburg, Schenker in Vienna, and
            <ref cRef="entity-000143">Felix-Eberhard von Cube</ref> in Hamburg in the 1920s and
          1930s.</p>

        <div>
          <head>Becker and the Schenker circle</head>
          <p>Violin ‒ who had moved to Hamburg in 1921 to teach at the Vogt'sches Konservatorium ‒
            referred to her as a pupil in 1924, noting that she had subscribed to Schenker's <title
              level="j">Der Tonwille</title> (OJ 14/45, [36], October 22, 1924). Two subsequent
            receipts from <ref cRef="entity-002408">Universal Edition</ref> survive relating to
              <title level="j">Tonwille</title> issues 7‒10 (OC 52/645 and 646 ‒ these were sent by
            Becker to Schenker in April 1925 as evidence). Becker had apparently been overcharged,
            and this played into the much broader bitter dispute between Schenker and the publisher.
            Becker continued to be mentioned in correspondence between Violin and Schenker through
            to April 1925, at which time Becker declared herself willing to testify if the UE
            dispute were to go before the courts (Violin to Schenker, OC 52/644, April 21,
            1925).</p>

          <p>On January 12, 1926, Violin informed Schenker that Becker wished to move to Vienna, and
            asked him to take her over, observing: "She is not talented, is merely very smart and
            interested" (OJ 14/45, [50]); Schenker agreed to give her two lessons a week (OJ 6/7,
            [27]), and there is some discussion of her abilities in subsequent correspondence.
            Lessons with Schenker ran from February 3 to June 5, 1926, thirteen session in all,
            working on several Chopin Etudes, the <title>Mozart Sonata in A major, K. 331</title>
            and Schumann's <title level="a">Warum?</title> (OC 3/3). Instruction was not continued
            in the following season. </p>

          <p>In 1933, Violin quit the Schenker Institute that he had founded in 1934, leaving Cube
            in charge. Becker was evidently a pupil around that time, and Cube wrote of her to
            Schenker (OJ 9/34, [28], October 16, 1931): <cit>
              <q>Miss Agnes Becker, whom you also know, is at this moment working together with two
                men (including Dr Brulez, the Belgian) in one of my individual classes. These are my
                most fastidious pupils.</q>
            </cit></p>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>Correspondence</head>
          <p>The only corrrespondence known to survive is one postcard from Oswald Jonas to Schenker
            dated October 2, 1934 (OC 44/46), to which she is a joint signatory with Hans and Ernst
            Wolff.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Ian Bent</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
