<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000592">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Johannes Messchaert</title>
        <title type="sub">born Hoorn, Aug 22, 1857; died Zurich, Sept 9, 1922</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="messchaert_johannes">Messchaert, Johannes</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>14/11/2006</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Messchaert ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">messchaert_johannes</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Johannes Messchaert</head>
      <div>
        <p>Dutch baritone.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>After studies in Cologne and Munich, Messchaert returned to Holland in 1881, where he
          taught at the Amsterdam Conservatory. A frequent collaborator with pianist <ref
            cRef="entity-000724">Julius Röntgen</ref>, Messchaert toured prolifically, establishing
          a reputation as one of Europe's most sought-after singers of Lieder and oratorio. He moved
          to Germany (Wiesbaden) in 1900, and thereafter held various conservatory appointments,
          ultimately attaining the post of professor at the Berlin Hochschule für Musik.
          Messchaert's interpretations were later set down in two volumes: F. Martiensen, ed.,
            <title level="m">Auswahl von Messchaerts Schubert-Repertoire, mit seinen
            Vortragsanweisungen</title> (Mainz: Schott, 1928).</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Messchaert and Schenker</head>
        <p>Schenker first reported, with great enthusiasm, on Messchaert's singing in the Berlin
          weekly <title level="j">Die Zeit</title> (1896; repr. in Federhofer 1990). A mutually
          admiring relationship developed, and Messchaert engaged Schenker as his accompanist during
          a tour of the Habsburg Empire in January and February 1899 (schedule preserved as OJ 35/5,
          48‒49, 52‒55).</p>
        <p>Schenker held Messchaert in the highest regard, as evinced in several of his published
          works, e.g.:</p>
        <p><title level="m">Kontrapunkt I</title> (1910), p. 129, Eng. trans. pp. 91: "Why is [the
          typical pianist of the day] not eager, like a violinist or singer who follows a good
          tradition (Joachim or Messchaert, for example) to rise to the full measure of Bach's art
          of expression?"</p>
        <p><title level="j">Tonwille</title>, Heft 6 (1923), p. 41, Eng. trans. II, pp. 35-6:
          "Permit me, in this connection, to remember, alongside that great poet and great composer
          [Goethe and Schubert], the great singer Johannes Messchaert, recently deceased, who in his
          interpretation of <title level="a">Meeresstille</title> achieved the corresponding effect
          by elongating the notes in so utterly peaceful a way that they sounded like messages
          emerging from the silence rather than notes issuing from the human breast. Only at the
          word "ungeheurn" [immense] did any tone creep into the voice, swelling almost
          imperceptibly, as far as "ungeheure Weite" [immense distance], but pulling back
          immediataely. The effect was to render the silence at the end all the more fearful and
          believable."</p>

        <p>However, Schenker saw a dark side to Messchaert's character, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>
          his diary for January 23, 1908: "Messchaert in Vienna. And again I must withhold from him
          the honor of a visit by me ‒ he is and always will be an incorrigibly thick-skinned
          person, who is able to sing even to a Kahn or Weingartner. ‒ Bad and good are of equal
          worth to him. The fact that, despite this, he is still the greatest singer may no longer
          be surprising: it is clear that such contrived (<hi rend="italic">geartete</hi>) artistry
          does itself permit criminal activity as a sideline! For only at levels of artistry such as
          for example those of a Goethe, Schiller, Haydn, Bach, Handel, and Brahms is perfection of
          the aristocratic mentality now at last organically integrated!" — And yet a month later he
          praised Messchaert's singing in Haydn's <title level="m">Creation</title> as
          "incomparable in every respect, in depth of performance, in strength and freedom of the
          beat at one and the same time" (diary, March 29, 1908).</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>
        <p>Correspondence from Messchaert to Schenker survives as OJ 12/54 (1896-1901: 11 items).
          Other materials survive as OJ 35/5 (concert programs and tour itineraries), OJ 59/11,
          70/27 (Messchaert/Violin correspondence), and 72/10 (portrait).</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
              Tagebüchern und Briefen ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), pp. 18-19,
            178-80</bibl>
          <bibl><editor>Federhofer, Hellmut</editor>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker als
              Essayist und Kritiker ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1990), pp. 318-19</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">NGDM2</title> (2001 and online)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">MGG</title></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Ian Bent and Kevin Karnes</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
