<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-000993">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Edward VII, King of England</title>
        <title type="sub">born London, Nov 9, 1841; died London, May 6, 1910; reigned
        1901–10</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="edward_vii_king">Edward VII, King of England</term>
        </title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt><sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc></fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">edward_vii_king</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Edward VII, King of England</head>
      <div>
        <p>Edward was the eldest son of Queen Victoria and Prince Albert of Saxe-Coburg and Gotha.
          He married Princess Alexandra of Denmark in 1863. The German Emperor Wilhelm II and the
          Russian Tsar Nicholas II were nephews of his. He was a notorious socialiser and womaniser,
          and was considered a worldwide trend-setter of men's clothing fashions.</p>
        <p>At Victoria's death, his official title on acceding to the throne was King of the United
          Kingdom, Emperor of India, and King of the British Dominions. He supported the
          modernization of the British army, and also the reform of the British navy in the face of
          the German naval build-up. In 1903, he visited France and was instrumental in creating the
          Anglo-French <hi rend="italic">Entente Cordiale</hi> as a counterbalancing force to
          Austria-Germany. He also made overtures to the Russian Foreign Minister <ref cRef="entity-000995">Alexander Izvolsky</ref> which resulted in the Anglo-Russian
          Convention of 1907 and a visit to Russia in 1908.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Schenker and Edward VII</head>
        <p>Germany saw Edward VII as the prime architect of the "encirclement" of Germany, and
          Schenker referred to this in <title level="a">The Mission of German Genius</title>: "[...]
          long premeditated maneuverings of the enemy nations, such as King Edward VII's
          encirclement of Germany [...]" (<title level="j">Der Tonwille</title> Heft I (1921), 9).
          In an article entitled <title level="a">German Genius in Battle and Victory,</title>
          submitted to the <title level="j">Frankfurter Zeitung</title> in September 1914 but
          rejected, Schenker alluded to Edward's life-style in the remark: "King Edward VII, who, in
          his lifetime as he still 'traveled' in fraternities, toasts, and waistcoats, was
          prematurely prized as a genius but is nowadays, with the bankruptcy of his work, finally
          unmasked as devoid of talent."</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Source:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Wikipedia</title>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
