<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000463">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Hilde König (Fräulein) [Hilde Rubinraut (Frau)]</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="konig_frl">König, Hilde</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>24/11/2007</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">konig_frl</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Hilde König (Fräulein) [Hilde Rubinraut (Frau)]</head>
      <div>
        <p>Austrian pianist; pupil of Schenker's intermittently March 1915 to June 1926.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <p>Miss König seems to have been a resident of Vienna, during which time she was a pupil not
          only of Schenker but also of “Zirner-Polatschek” (perhaps <ref cRef="entity-003461">Viktor
            Polatschek</ref>, in which case she also studied the clarinet). She married merchant
          Semion Rubinraut on December 8, 1918, and after that lived in Prague for some years,
          perhaps returning to Vienna later. </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>König/Rubinraut and Schenker</head>
        <p>According to Schenker’s diary, Hilde König and her <ref cRef="entity-000462">mother</ref>
          introduced themselves to Schenker on March 15, 1915, and she attended her first lesson two
          days later. Schenker’s 1914/15 lessonbook contradicts this by placing her first lesson on
          the 15th with “further study of Beethoven’s Sonata Op. 109 [and] Chopin’s Etude in C
          major,” which perhaps implies that study with Schenker preceded this date. The lessonbook
          is, however, suspect, March 16–18 being omitted altogether.) Schenker records that he made
          an arrangement identical to that with <ref cRef="entity-000399">Felix Hupka</ref>, which
          was a reduced fee in light of financial circumstances. König then completed most of the
          1915/16 season and all of 1916/17 and 1917/18, in which latter season she took
          counterpoint studies up to “three voices and more.” In 1918/19 she worked on mixed species
          counterpoint, but seems to have ended lessons upon her marriage on December 8, after which
          at some point she moved to Prague. Throughout this period her repertory comprised mostly
          pieces by Chopin and Brahms, with an extended study of Beethoven’s fourth piano concerto. </p>

        <p>After marriage, the lessonbook records no lessons until December 1925. Correspondence
          between Rubinraut and Schenker, however, contradicts this. Rubinraut had asked for lesson
          times as early as summer 1919 (Schenker’s diary), but nothing had come of that until
          January 1922 when she proposed travelling from Prague once every three weeks for lessons
          on two successive days, and suggested she drop the theory lesson, thus taking two piano
          lessons (OJ 13/35, [2]), with payment in dollars. Her first two resumed lessons fell on
          Wednesday and Thursday, October 4 and 5, 1922 (OJ 13/35, [3]), and lessons seem to have
          proceeded thereafter, moving to once every four weeks in December 1922. By January 1923
          she had a permanent visa to enter Austria, and announced that she was expecting a baby (OJ
          13/35, [4]). The 1925/26 lessonbook keeps more detailed notes, together with dates between
          December and March.</p>

        <p>Through all of the special arrangements he made for her, Schenker, unusually, betrays no
          irritation in his diary. Rubinraut kept in contact until October 1932, by which time she
          was seeking pupils herself and asked Schenker for a recommendation.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence</head>
        <p>No correspondence with König is known to survive, and none from Schenker himself. Four
          items of correspondence from Rubinraut to Schenker survive: one calling card and three
          letters, OJ 13/35, [1]–[4], January 1922 to January 1923. </p>
      </div>

    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author><hi rend="bold">Marko Deisinger</hi></author> and <author><hi rend="bold">Ian
                Bent</hi></author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
