<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000327">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Victor [Viktor] Hammer</title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, December 9, 1882; died Lexington, KY, July 10, 1967</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="hammer_viktor">Hammer, Victor</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>28/04/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">HammerV ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">hammer_viktor</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Victor [Viktor] Hammer</head>
      <div>
        <p>Viennese painter, portraitist, sculptor, engraver, print-maker, typographer, book
          illustrator, and craftsman, with a keen interest in music. </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Hammer studied at the Akademie der Bildenden Künste in Vienna, then worked in Vienna as a
          portraitist and sculptor. During World War I, he was a military artist. In 1922, he moved
          to Florence, where he opened a printing workshop, which he later named the Stamperia di
          Santuccio, but maintained a studio in Vienna. He taught at the Vienna Akademie 1936–39,
          then he emigrated to the USA, where he taught at Wells College, Aurora, NY until 1948,
          moving that year to Lexington, KY. It is to his time in the USA that many of his
          publications belong.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Hammer and Schenker</head>
        <p>Hammer first approached Schenker in September 1913, asking him to take on his wife, Rosl,
          as a pupil. Schenker seems to have responded stating his fee, whereupon in his next letter
          ("typically Viennese," scoffed Schenker in his diary), Hammer tried to negotiate a lower
          figure. Nothing seems to have come of this approach. Hammer owned two clavichords, and
          also a piano by Andreas Stein dating from 1820, played clavichord, lute, and clarinet, and
          himself built several clavichords. </p>
        <p>Hammer had had his attention drawn to Schenker's works probably by <ref
            cRef="entity-000922">Otto Vrieslander</ref>, notably the edition of J. S. Bach's <title
            level="m">Chromatic Fantasy &amp; Fugue</title> (1910), and his monograph <title
            level="m">Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie</title> (1912). He was already acquainted with
          several members of Schenker's circle, in particular <ref cRef="entity-000951">Hans
            Weisse</ref>. On March 21, 1914, Heinrich and Jeanette visited an exhibition at the
          Sezession Building in Vienna, where they saw and commented on several Hammer pictures
          favorably, though remarking that "something unduly stiff seems to lie right at the heart
          of his forms"(OJ 1/14, p. 541). </p>
        <p>Schenker's diary for June 11, 1918 records that one of his most long-standing pupils,
            <ref cRef="entity-000107">Robert Brünauer</ref> "presents me now with another proposal:
          to sit for the painter V. Hammer for a drawing; I declare that I have no objections to
          raise to this, at the least out of consideration for Hammer." (OJ 2/10, p. 900). However,
          ten days later, Schenker records that Brünauer "comes back to his proposal that I should
          have my portrait drawn by Hammer, which I likewise refuse." (OJ 2/11, p. 907).</p>
        <p>Hammer and Schenker met in person and became friends around 1921. Although the former
          lived in Florence, he maintained a studio in Vienna and was there not infrequently, thus
          the two had conversations and corresponded. During these contacts, Hammer became
          interested in Schenker's concept of the Urlinie (evidently from reading the first issue of
            <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>, "Die Urlinie: Eine Vorbemerkung"), speculating on
          how it might be applied to painting—to which Schenker responded that there were
          "fundamental differences between painting and music in consequence of which the Urlinie
          clearly signifies different things in the two art forms." (December 19, 1921). In his
          lessonbook for 1921/22, Schenker records that he worked with Hans Weisse on Mendelssohn's
          "Altdeutsches Lied," which Rosl Hammer had been singing, and parenthetically notes that he
          has "sent the line [i.e. Urlinie sketch] to Hammer" (in a letter dating May 25, 1922 —
          reproduced in Siegel, plates 3 and 4, and quoted, p. 83). Hammer went on to attempt an
          equivalent of Urlinie that brought out the "underlying structure" of a picture (see
          Siegel, plates 6–8), and it may be possible to see traces of Hammer's influence on
          Schenker's thinking in the later <title level="j">Tonwille</title> and the <title
            level="j">Meisterwerk</title> essays, as well as of Schenker's influence on Hammer's
          thinking in his writings. </p>
        <p>In 1924, Hammer approached Schenker again about the possibility of sitting for a
          portrait. The sittings began in 1924, and the resulting mezzotint portrait, with the
          rubric, in his characteristic uncial typography, "1 . 9 . v . heinrich schenker . h . 2 .
          5", was completed in October 1925. A hundred copies of this were printed, and sold by the
          Viennese art shop of Artaria &amp; Co. (In 1923, Hammer also made a drawing of Hans
          Weisse, which may have been preparatory to a mezzotint portrait. Letters and diary entries
          indicate that he completed a drawing of Jeanette Schenker in 1927. The latter appears not
          to have survived.)</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>
        <p>Hammer and Schenker corresponded between 1913 and 1931. Letters and postcards from
          Schenker to Hammer survive at the New York Public Library as JOB 94-3 (not part of the
          Oster Collection), photocopies of which are held as OJ 5/15a (30 items: 1921–31) and OC
          1B/46-48 (a copy in Jeanette Schenker's hand of JOB 94-3, [1], 1921), and from Hammer to
          Schenker as OJ 11/36 (28 items: 1913–27). Reproductions of art works, with Urlinie-like
          overlays by Hammer, are preserved among Schenker's papers at OJ 11/37; a mezzotint
          self-portrait of Hammer inscribed to Schenker is preserved as OJ 72/6 (1926), and Hammer's
          mezzotint portrait of Schenker as OJ 72/14, item 7 (of which the original is kept among
          the oversize prints in Special Collections); the drawing of Hans Weisse is preserved in
          the Scherman Music Library, Mannes College the New School for Music, New York . </p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
              Tagebüchern und Briefen ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), pp. 38–9, 149–50 </bibl>
          <bibl><author>Siegel, Hedi</author>, <title level="s">Looking at the Urlinie,</title> in
              <editor>Burstein, Poundie</editor> &amp; <editor>Gagné, David</editor>, eds., <title
              level="m">Structure and Meaning in Tonal Music, Festschrift in Honor of Carl
              Schachter</title> (Hillsdale, NY: Pendragon, 2006), 79–99</bibl>
          <bibl>communication from Robert Kosovsky</bibl>
          <bibl>communication from Hedi Siegel</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Further Reading:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Rothenstein, John</author>, <title level="m">Victor Hammer: Artist and
              Crafstman</title> (Boston, MA: David R. Goodine, 1978)</bibl>
          <bibl><editor>Hammer, Carolyn R.</editor>, comp., <title level="m">Victor Hammer: Artist
              and Printer</title> (Lexington, KY: The Anvil Press, 1981) </bibl>
          <bibl><editor>Hammer, Carolyn R.</editor>, comp., <title level="m">Victor Hammer: An
              Artist's Testament</title> (Lexington, KY: The Anvil Press, 1988)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author><hi rend="bold">Marko Deisinger</hi></author>, <author><hi rend="bold">Ian
                Bent</hi></author>, and <author><hi rend="bold">Hedi Siegel</hi></author>
          </bibl>
          <lb/>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
