<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-003483">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Martin Spörr</title>
        <title type="sub">born Wilten, Tyrol, November 16, 1866; died Gallspach, September 2,
          1937</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="spörr_martin">Spörr, Martin</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">spörr_martin</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Martin Spörr</head>
      <div>
        <p>Austrian musician, conductor and composer.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Spörr received training from Joseph Friedrich Hummel and Josef Pembaur the elder in the
          Musikverein School in Innsbruck 1879–83 and from <ref cRef="entity-000265">Robert
            Fuchs</ref> in Vienna. He played French horn and double bass 1883–85 in the Innsbruck
          City Theater Orchestra, and taught at the music school there 1888–99. In 1893 he founded
          the Innsbruck City Orchestra, which he directed until 1899 and which was called to Graz
          that year to strengthen the recently founded orchestra of the Graz Musikerbund, founded in
          1872, and which existed under Spörr's leadership as the Graz Symphony Orchestra until
          1902. From 1903 to 1905 he was the musical director of the Karlsbad Philharmonic
          Orchestra, guest conducting there for the last time in 1933. In 1903/04 he also conducted
          the Kurkapelle in Baden. </p>

        <p>In 1905 he became the permanent conductor of the <ref cRef="entity-003278">Vienna Concert
            Union</ref> Orchestra (<ref cRef="entity-004431">Wiener Symphoniker</ref>), conducting
          not only the Popular Symphony Concerts series in the Musikverein and in the Volksgarten,
          but also symphonic concerts in Bad Kissingen (Germany) during the summer from 1906 to
          1918. From 1922 to 1932 he was the administrative director of the "Verein Wiener
          Sinfonie-Orchester," a union he founded between musicians from the <ref
            cRef="entity-004192">Vienna Tonkünstler Orchestra</ref> and the <ref
            cRef="entity-003278">Vienna Concert Union</ref>. He conducted the summer concerts in the
          Burggarten in Vienna's first district until 1932, and conducted otherwise only on a
          substitute basis. Spörr was not only highly knowledgeable as a musician, a conductor, and
          an interpreter of numerous modern works, but also valued as an organizer.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Martin Spörr and Schenker</head>
        <p>Spörr is mentioned many times in Schenker's diary between 1908 and 1932. The first
          reference is on January 19, 1908, when clearly the two men knew each other well enough for
          Spörr to comment adversely on <ref cRef="entity-000542">Ferdinand Löwe</ref>'s method of
          conducting. In October 1912 Spörr sent word via <ref cRef="entity-000913">Moriz
            Violin</ref> that Schenker's works were highly acclaimed in <ref cRef="entity-002535"
            >Jena</ref>. On October 26, 1923, Schenker reported: "Encountered Spörr while still on
          the stairs; he tells me that he has become the financial manager of the orchestra and
          saved it from collapse, even put aside the subsidy from the city of Vienna." On February
          1, 1925 Spörr and his wife came to the Schenkers for tea. On February 28, 1928 Schenker
          chatted with Spörr in <ref cRef="entity-002260">Hopfner's restaurant</ref>. In February
          1929 at <ref cRef="entity-000034">Bamberger</ref>'s request he wrote a recommendation on
          his behalf to Spörr.</p>

        <p>Schenker had many opportunities to hear him conduct orchestral concerts either live or on
          the radio. He was often disparaging: of his performance of Mozart's G minor Symphony:
          "hacked to pieces and defiled in the most Turkish manner" (December 1, 1912), a Haydn
          symphony: "thoroughly lifeless" (October 8, 1925), Beethoven's "Pastoral" Symphony:
          "miserably ground out" (November 15, 1925), Mozart's "Jupiter" Symphony: "an
          incomprehensible rattling" (February 10, 1927).</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence</head>
        <p>There is no surviving correspondence between Spörr and Schenker, nor is any recorded in
          Schenker's diary.</p>
      </div>

    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Source:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">OeML Online</title> (Uwe Harten) </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributors</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Marko Deisinger</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></bibl>
        </listBibl><lb/>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
