<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000131">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Israel Citkowitz</title>
        <title type="sub">born Skierniewice, Poland, February 6, 1909; died 1974</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="citkowitz_israel">Citkowitz, Israel</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>03/07/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">citkowitz_israel</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Israel Citkowitz</head>
      <div>
        <p>Polish-born American pianist, composer, teacher and critic, brought to the US at the age
          of 3. After studying composition with Copland and Sessions as a teenager he went to Paris
          to study with Nadia Boulanger (1927–31).</p>
        <p>During the 1930s Citkowitz also published music criticism in <title level="j">Modern
            Music</title> and <title level="j">Musical Mercury</title>. Among his prose pieces was
          the first English-language introduction to Schenker's ideas, <title level="a">The Role of
            Heinrich Schenker.</title> According to Milton Babbitt:</p>
        <p><!--bq start-->"... Schenker entered our lives at almost exactly the same time as
          Schoenberg entered our country, and from a most unexpected source: an article in the
          magazine Modern Music (!) by Israel Citkowitz, already well known as one of Nadia
          Boulanger's protégés, who was even viewed as the possible successor to Aaron Copland in
          the American compositional hierarchy. This article was not a detailed exposition of
          Schenkerian analysis but an understanding, appreciative presentation of what Citkowitz
          termed 'Schenker's lifelong consecration to the music of the Masters.'"<!--bq end--></p>
        <p>Hans Weisse wrote to Schenker, asking him if he had looked at Citkowitz's article,
          probably having heard that it had been brought to his attention by <ref
            cRef="entity-000964">Manfred Willfort</ref>, and that Schenker had even sent it on to
          Jonas (see OJ 15/18, 32; OJ 12/6, [27]; OJ 5/18, 33]. He also reported to Schenker that
          Citkowitz was studying with him: "I mark it down as the jackpot of this year that your
          theory has opened up a breach in the battlefront of radical-modernist American youth. This
          is a very promising beginning." (Weisse to Schenker, March 15, 1934, OJ 15/16, [94])</p>
        <p>In 1939, Citkowitz was appointed teacher of counterpoint and composition at the Dalcroze
          School in New York City, but informal accounts attest to his activity as a teacher of
          piano and Schenkerian theory and analysis throughout the 1930s. Among his students were
          the composer-pianist Leo Smit, and later, the conductor-pianist Richard Kapp.</p>
        <p>It was during the 1930s that <ref cRef="entity-000927">Arthur Waldeck</ref> studied
          Schenker with Citkowitz, allegedly at Carnegie Hall, according to Waldeck's son (who also
          claimed that <ref cRef="entity-000649">Ernst Oster</ref> joined in these studies after his
          arrival in the US in 1938). By 1948, Citkowitz had moved into his Carnegie Hall studio
          after a divorce. At around the same time, Arthur Waldeck's correspondence with Oswald
          Jonas indicates that he was teaching voice in a Carnegie Hall studio as well. Thus, it
          seems likely that the Citkowitz–Waldeck discussions of Schenker went on through the 1930s,
          the War, and beyond. Though Citkowitz never worked with Leon Fleischer, his daughter says
          that his knowledge of piano technique led him to predict years in advance that Fleischer
          would develop problems with his hands.</p>
        <p>There is no correspondence between Citkowitz and Schenker.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Bibliography:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Citkowitz, Israel</author>, <title level="a">The Role of Heinrich
              Schenker,</title>
            <title level="j">Modern Music</title> 11/1 (1933): 18-23 [copies of a typescript German
            translation by <editor>Manfred Willfort</editor> as <title level="a">Die Rolle Heinrich
              Schenkers</title> survive as OJ 58/2, OC 2/pp. 88/89 and OC 30/10]</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Coppock, Jane</author>, <title level="a">A Conversation with Arthur
              Berger,</title> in <title level="j">Perspectives of New Music</title> 17/1 (1978):
            40-67</bibl>
          <bibl><editor>Peles, Stephen</editor>, with <editor>Demski, Stephen</editor>,
              <editor>Mead, Andrew</editor>, and <editor>Straus, Joseph N.</editor>, eds, <title
              level="m">The Collected Essays of Milton Babbitt</title> (Princeton: Princeton
            University Press, 2003), pp. 475–76</bibl>
          <bibl>Personal communications from Israel Citkowitz's daughter, Elena Citkowitz</bibl>
          <bibl>Telephone Conversation with Arthur Waldeck's son, Lewis Waldeck</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Robert Wason</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
