<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-002810">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Dora Kallmus [Madame d'Ora]</title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, March 20, 1881; died Frohleiten/Steiermark, October 30,
          1963</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="kallmus_dora">Kallmus, Dora</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>28/04/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">kallmus_dora</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Atelier d'Ora</head>
      <div>

        <p>Austrian-Jewish fashion and portrait photographer of international fame. Her artistic
          name from 1907 was Madame d'Ora. </p>

      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Summary Career</head>

        <p>Subjects of Kallmus's portraiture included Pablo Casals, Marie Gutheil-Schoder, Lotte
          Lehmann, Alma Mahler, Arnold Rosé and the Rosé Quartet, Moritz Rosenthal, Franz Schreker,
          Richard Strauss, Felix Weingartner, and Paul Wittgenstein in the world of music, and
          others such as dancers Anita Berber and Anna Pawlowa, painter Gustav Klimt, authors Arthur
          Schnitzler and Franz Werfel, and Berta Zuckerkandl-Szeps (a cousin by marriage of <ref
            cRef="entity-000989">Viktor Zuckerkandl</ref>). She also photographed the coronation of
          the new Emperor Karl I in 1916 and made a series of photographs of the imperial family.
          She had close contacts with the fashion department of the Wiener Werkstätte.</p>

        <p>Kallmus moved to Paris in 1927, where she worked with major fashion houses and magazines,
          and continued her portraiture. In hiding in the south of France during World War II, she
          returned to Austria in 1946, where she photographed refugee camps as well as continuing to
          make portraits of famous personalities.</p>

        <p>90,000 photographs by Kallmus are preserved in the Picture Archive and Theater Collection
          of the Austrian National Library and the Museum of Art and Trade in Hamburg. The Albertina
          in Vienna has a collection of her photographs in its online picture databank. There is a
          substantial secondary literature of writings on her work. </p>

      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Kallmus and Schenker</head>

        <p>Jeanette Schenker was photographed on October 7, 1925 at the <ref cRef="entity-002809"
            >Atelier d'Ora</ref>. Heinrich seems not to have been photographed by her.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <head>Sources:</head>
      <div>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>Wikipedia.de (Madame d'Ora)</bibl>
          <bibl>Communication by Eric Milenkiewicz of the Special Collections Library, University of
            California, Riverside</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Reference:</head>

        <p>Austrian National Library Picture Archive:
          http://www.bildarchivaustria.at/Pages/Praesentation.aspx?p_iAusstellungID=1206966&amp;p_iPage=67&amp;p_ItemID=</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Marko Deisinger</author>, <author>Hedi Siegel</author>, <author>Ian
              Bent</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

    </back>

  </text>
</TEI>
