<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000756">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Josef Saphir</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="saphir_josef">Saphir, Josef</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>28/04/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Saphir ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">saphir_josef</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Josef Saphir</head>

      <div>
        <p>Proprietor of the piano manufacturing company Saphir, founded in 1886, located at
          Praterstraße 34 in the 2nd district of Vienna (Leopoldsstadt), and at Radetzkystraße 7 in
          the 3rd district (Landstraße). He was active also as a piano dealer between 1897 and 1909,
          and is part of a long lineage of piano dealers spanning more than a century. His wife was
          Mathilde Saphir.</p>

        <p>Of the eight children born to Josef and Mathilde Saphir, one – Armin – took over the shop
          at Praterstraße 34. After the annexation of Austria by the Nazis, he fled to Shanghai with
          his family, including some of his brothers. After Armin’s death in China, the family
          emigrated to the USA, where one of his sons, Kurt Saphir (1925–2011), established a
          successful piano business in Chicago. (This was later taken over by his son Dennis, based
          in Wilmette, Illinois.)</p>

        <p>Another of Josef and Mathilde’s children, Fritz, is probably “der junge Saphir” to whom
          Schenker refers in a diary entry (October 3, 1924) and a letter to Moriz Violin (May 9,
          1933) as having a piano dealership and concert agency in Palestine. For it is one of
          Fritz’s sons, Uri, who ran the Saphir Music Shop in Jerusalem for many years. (And one of
          Uri’s sons, David, had a retail piano store in California.)</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Saphir and Schenker</head>

        <p>Saphir was in contact with Schenker in May 1918. No correspondence is known to survive
          between Josef Saphir and Schenker, but a letter from his wife is preserved as OJ 14/3
          (1917).</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="j">Das Jahrbuch der Wiener Gesellschaft 1928</title>, ed. <editor>Franz
              Planer</editor> (Vienna 1928), p. 291</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
              Tagebüchern und Briefen...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), p. 250</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Witter, Jens-Uwe</author>, <title level="m">Das Klavier-Lexikon. Namen und
              Fabrikate aus dem Klavier-, Orgel- und Harmoniumbau sowie Handel und Service von
              1788-2000</title>, 2nd edn (Rothenburg ob der Tauber, 2000), pp. 634-635</bibl>
          <bibl>Personal communications from Dennis Saphir (May 9 and 15, 2015)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>William Drabkin</author> and <author>Marko Deisinger</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
