<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-000545">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Ernst Ludwig</title>
        <title type="sub">18??-1915</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="ludwig_ernst">Ludwig, Ernst</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>07/02/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">LudwigE ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">ludwig_ernst</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Ernst Ludwig</head>
      <div>
        <p>Distinguished Viennese piano teacher, professor in the Ausbildungsklasse for piano at the
          Vienna Conservatory (= Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst) from 1883 to 1914.
          His address in 1905 was Vienna III, Streichergasse 3.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Ludwig and Schenker</head>
        <p>Schenker studied piano with him at the Conservatory in the years 1887/88, 1888/89, and
          part of 1889/90. Schenker had much for which to thank him, as his encomium (diary, March
          14, 1915) makes clear:
          
          <cit><q>The fortunate circumstances of his life were in part also fortunate
          circumstances of my own. Originally wealthy, inclined toward education and indeed an
          educated man himself, in contrast to other musicians and others he had the leisure and
          will to take me under his wing when I entered the Conservatory on an imperial scholarship.
          It was he who paid attention to my compositions, introduced me to [Julius] Epstein (who
          from time to time provided me with financial support), in short, it was he who within his
          circle actually provided me with my first better-paying pupils. He passed the Eisslers
          over to me, introduced me many years later also to [Irene] Graedener, whose son I was to
          teach. -- On this day of his death, I cannot shake from my mind the thought, paradoxical
          as it may seem, that Ludwig would have been far more fortunate in life if, when making
          recommendations, instead of teachers such as Jadassohn and Graedener he had chosen me to
          lead [people] to art! But how is one to dictate to Nature, which has decreed the ordering
          of generations in one immutable way, that something go in precisely the opposite
          direction! By the time my <title level="m">Harmonielehre</title> and <title level="m">Kontrapunkt</title> came out, it was far too late for him to enjoy the blessing of the
          truth.</q></cit></p>
        <p>Schenker arranged for Ludwig to receive complimentary copies of his arrangement of Handel
          organ concertos from UE in 1905 (OC 52/17) and <title level="m">Harmonielehre</title> from
          Cotta in 1906 (OJ 1/5, p. 27), but not of <title level="m">Kontrapunkt</title> or other
          publications.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>
        <p>Only one calling card (undated) from Ludwig to Schenker is known to survive (OJ
        12/45).</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
              Tagebüchern und Briefen ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), pp. 5-7
          </bibl>
          <bibl><author>Tittel, Ernst</author>, <title level="m">Die Wiener Musikhochschule
            ...</title> (Vienna: Lafite, 1967)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
