<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000317">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Julian [Julien; Julko] Guttmann</title>
        <title type="sub">born Suczawa, Bukovina, January 1, 1901</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="guttmann_julian_julk">Guttmann, Julian (Julko)</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>05/07/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">GuttmannJ ~ H+JSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">GuttmannJ ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">guttmann_julian_julk</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Julian [Julien; Julko] Guttmann</head>

      <div>
        <p>Youngest child of <ref cRef="entity-000319">Sophie</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-000318"
            >Salo</ref> (Salomon) Guttman, younger brother of <ref cRef="entity-000316">Hans</ref>
          and <ref cRef="entity-000315">Frieda</ref>, nephew of Heinrich Schenker. — For more
          information, see <ref cRef="entity-002935">Guttmann family</ref>.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Life summary</head>
        <p>Nothing is known of Julian’s childhood or early education. The Guttmann family lived in
          the <ref cRef="entity-002347">Sereth</ref> district of <ref cRef="entity-002247"
            >Bukovina</ref> until the outbreak of World War 1, when <ref cRef="entity-000319"
            >Sophie</ref>, <ref cRef="entity-000318">Salo</ref>, and their three children fled to
          Vienna. Heinrich gives a vivid description in his diary of the whole family on September
          17, 1914. After his portrayal of <ref cRef="entity-000316">Hans</ref> and <ref
            cRef="entity-000315">Frieda</ref>, he concluded: <cit>
            <q>Most favorably bestowed is the parents’ darling, Julko, whose sweet, graceful
              expression may be extolled</q>
          </cit>. </p>

        <p>Following that visit, the family moved to <ref cRef="entity-002271">Bielitz</ref>
          (Poland) for the length of World War I. At the end of the war, while his parents and
          sister <ref cRef="entity-000315">Frieda</ref> returned via Vienna and <ref
            cRef="entity-002385">Vincovci</ref> (Croatia) to <ref cRef="entity-002347">Sereth</ref>,
          Julian remained in Vienna with his older brother <ref cRef="entity-000316">Hans</ref>,
          where he passed his school-leaving examination. In October 1919 he entered the Export
          Academy in Vienna XIX/1 (courses on economy, trade, business, commodities, law, etc.). He
          visited his uncle Heinrich regularly every Saturday in the autumn of that year. He was
          also in contact with his uncle, <ref cRef="entity-000774">Moriz Schenker</ref>, the
          banker, through whom the family hoped that he might find employment.</p>

        <p>In October 1920 he moved to <ref cRef="entity-002526">Bucharest</ref> to take up a new
          position, then in December 1921 had a change of job (unspecified). In summer 1923 he
          entered military service, reporting in 1924 that he was “having difficulty in Rumania as a
          Jewish soldier,” but in the October he passed the officer’s exam. In 1928, his hopes of
          getting employment through <ref cRef="entity-000774">Moriz Schenker</ref> were again
          dashed.</p>

        <p><ref cRef="entity-000319">Sophie</ref>’s letters and postcard to <ref
            cRef="entity-000771">Jeanette Schenker</ref> in 1938 and 1939 report that he is looking
          after his parents, and that he is also good with <ref cRef="entity-000315">Frieda</ref>’s
          children in <ref cRef="entity-002375">Czernowitz</ref>; and in September 1939 (in relation
          to the plight of <ref cRef="entity-000771">Jeanette</ref>'s second son, <ref
            cRef="entity-000468">Felix Kornfeld</ref>) that he “has rescued several people entirely
          unknown to him. – But now it is out of the question” (<ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-11-31_4">OJ 11/31, [4]</ref>).</p>

        <p>Nothing is known of how Julian fared during World War 2, and whether he evaded
          transportation. A reference to his having “renounced his RPR citizenship on 31 July 1964”
            (<title>Jewishgen</title>) probably refers to a different person.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with the Schenkers</head>
        <p>One note from Julian with photograph to Heinrich survives at OJ 14/5 (original preserved
          at OJ 72/18, item 12). A photograph of him in a classroom group in 1917 is preserved at OJ
          73/18, item 12, and other photographs in family groups are items 4 (c.1904), 5 (c.1907,
            <ref cRef="entity-002275">Suczawa</ref>), 8 (c.1912, <ref cRef="entity-002347"
            >Sereth</ref>), 11 (c.1916/17), 13 (c.1919), 14 (c.1920), and 15 (c.1922).</p>
      </div>
    </body>


    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><ref type="external"
              target="https://www.geni.com/people/Julian-Guttmann/6000000186487766823"><title>geni
                "Julian Guttmann"</title></ref></bibl>

          <bibl><title>Jewishgen</title>: Bukovina records</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Marko Deisinger</hi></author> with <author><hi rend="bold"
                >Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>


  </text>
</TEI>
