<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000894">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Georg Tomay</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="tomay_georg">Tomay, Georg</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">tomay_georg</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Georg Tomay</head>
      <div>

        <p>Viennese music autographer and calligrapher, who produced many of the finest of
          Schenker's Urlinie-Tafeln. </p>

      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Tomay: man and company </head>
        <p>Tomay's stamped letterhead reads: <cit>
            <q>Spezialanstalt für Musikalische Arbeiten [Special office for musical works] /‒ Georg
              Tomay ‒ / Wien, I., Fichtegasse 1a Tel. R. 22-419.</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>(Fichtegasse crosses the Ringstraße close to the Stadtpark.)</p>

        <p>Georg Tomay originated the extensive graphs and examples for Schenker’s essay on
          Beethoven’s "Eroica" Symphony in <title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</title>,
          vol. III (Munich: Drei Masken Verlag, 1930), also the <title level="m">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln
            / Five Analyses in Sketchform</title> (New York: David Mannes Music School, 1932) and
          all the examples of <title level="m">Der freie Satz</title>.</p>

        <p>Autography (<hi rend="italic">Autographie</hi>) and calligraphy (<hi rend="italic"
            >Kalligraphie</hi>) are both processes that obviate the necessity of incising an image
          into a metal plate (engraving). In <hi rend="bold">autography</hi>, the initial image (in
          Schenker's case music notation or a voice-leading graph) is inscribed the right way round
          (whereas engraving is done in reverse) on a specially prepared paper using a specialized
          greasy ink; the resulting sheet is lightly pressed on to a damp lithographic stone or
          metal plate, causing the image to transfer. — In <hi rend="bold">calligraphy</hi>, on the
          other hand, photography is introduced at the second stage: The hand-drawn original (right
          way round) is first photographed, thus allowing the size of the image to be varied, and
          the resultant photograph is transferred to the stone or plate. In an annotation on OC
          54/224, May 22, 1930, Otto Erich Deutsch states that the latter process was recommended
          for Schenker's "Eroica" essay. However, the final sheet of the graphs and examples is
          signed "Autographie Gg. Tomay Wien I.".</p>

        <p>Schenker's opinion of Tomay's work is expressed upon seeing the finished <title level="m"
            >Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln</title>: he wrote to Felix Salzer: <cit>
            <q>The folios are of the noblest beauty, a new <hi rend="italic">unicum</hi> as a
              publication, quite apart from the content. To express appreciation of the external
              appearance and the content every reader must become ‒ a poet. (FS 40/1, [10], July 16,
              1932).</q>
          </cit>
        </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence between Tomay and Schenker </head>
        <p>Twenty-three items of correspondence survive between Georg Tomay and Schenker, most
          preserved in a folder of correspondence regarding <title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der
            Musik</title> vol. III (OC 54/196‒217) for work on the music examples and graphs of
          Schenker's study of the "Eroica" Symphony, the remainder in a folder concerning the <title
            level="m">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln</title> (OC 54/343, 350): from Tomay to Schenker: 11
          handwritten letters, three monetary receipts and one invoice; from Schenker to Tomay:
          eight postal receipts (for which none of the correspondence items are known to survive).
          These items date between June 23, 1930 and an undated item from June 1932. There are also
          many references to Tomay in Schenker's diaries and correspondence.</p>

      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Hedi Siegel</author> and <author>Ian Bent</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
