<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000782">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Paul Schiff</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="schiff_paul">Schiff, Paul</term>
          <title type="sub">born Ústi nad Labem (Aussig), April 28, 1895</title>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>28/04/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">SchiffP ~ H+JSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">schiff_paul</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Paul Schiff</head>

      <div>
        <p>Younger brother of <ref cRef="entity-000771">Jeanette Schenker (<hi rend="italic"
              >née</hi> Schiff)</ref>, thus from 1919 brother-in-law to <ref cRef="entity-000632"
            >Heinrich Schenker</ref>. His wife was <ref cRef="entity-000781">Anna</ref>; the couple
          had a daughter, <ref cRef="entity-008429">Lisl</ref>. By 1933 the family was living at
            <ref cRef="entity-002892">Prague</ref>, Na Rokytec 1081 (<ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-14-10_5">OJ 14/10, [5]</ref>), and by 1935 at <ref cRef="entity-004561"
            >Karlsbad</ref>, Petersberg 630 (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-10_16">OJ 14/10,
            [16]</ref>), and in 1938 they moved back from <ref cRef="entity-004561">Karlsbad</ref>
          to <ref cRef="entity-002892">Prague</ref> (<ref type="OJ-14-08_15">OJ 14/8, [15]</ref>,
          February 2, 1938).</p>

        <p>Little is known of Paul's early life other than that his parents died when he was very
          young, and that he studied at the Technical High School in <ref cRef="entity-002892"
            >Prague</ref>. He served at the front in Russia, Herzegovina, Albania, and elsewhere in
          World War I in 1915 and 1918–1919. In September 1919, the year in which he enrolled in
          philosophy and chemistry at <ref cRef="entity-002887">Leipzig University</ref>, Paul also
          joined the Social Democrat Party. As a reward for his political activism, in 1920 he was
          appointed political and economic editor for the social democrat newspaper <title level="j"
            >Vorwärts</title>. In 1923 he wrote articles and gave lectures, and was imprisoned for
          three weeks for speaking out on mobilization. He was again imprisoned in 1925, this time
          for three months for incitement to overthrow the government (<ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-18-8_1">OJ 14/8, [1]</ref>, March 19, 1925). In Anna’s words: “He had that
          fervent belief that is lacking in most people who are active in politics but who perhaps
          out of that very lack emerge as victors.” Such views were inimical to <ref
            cRef="entity-000632">Heinrich Schenker</ref>, who on reading that letter responded “Paul
          is apparently traveling a precipitous path, since a feeling of revenge against the state
          will inevitably overcome him, which will lead him to further conflict.” (diary, March 24,
          1925).</p>

        <p>In 1934, <ref cRef="entity-000944">Rosa Weil</ref> remarked “Paul can barely cope with
          wife, child, and mother-in-law" (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-10_15">OJ 14/10,
            [15]</ref>). In 1938 <ref cRef="entity-000944">Rosa</ref> describes him as having for
          many years worked in the insurance business (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-10_34"
            >OJ 14/10, [34]</ref> – with the company Riunione Adriatica), and that his salary had
          been reduced to a level unsustainable for the family. <ref cRef="entity-000944">Rosa</ref>
          also reported that Paul had “mastered gold-working,” and that in late 1939 he was due to
          visit <ref cRef="entity-004528">Palestine</ref> with a group (<ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-14-10_37">OJ 14/10, [37]</ref>). Nothing is known of his life thereafter.</p>

        <p>In April 1936, when <ref cRef="entity-000771">Jeanette Schenker</ref> embarked on her
          six-month voyage to Santiago, <ref cRef="entity-005845">Chile</ref> and back, heading
          first to <ref cRef="entity-002448">Aussig</ref> to see her parents’ old house and the
          town, she spent from teatime on the 27th to 11 p.m. with Paul and Anna, and Paul and Anna
          were at the station on the 30th to see her off on the next leg to Genoa.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with the Schenkers</head>

        <p>Two-way correspondence between Paul Schiff and Jeanette, as recorded in Heinrich
          Schenker’s diary, began much earlier than that with other Schiff siblings. The earliest
          recorded communication from Paul was in 1913 while still at school, making accusations
          against Jeanette, to which she responded. There were at least twenty written
          communications during the period spanning 1915 to early 1919, while Paul was serving in
          World War I. Paul’s antagonism continued throughout that period, Jeanette just striving to
          keep the correspondence going. The relationship warmed later in 1919 thanks to offers of
          help with his future career from Heinrich, becoming cordial as Paul took Jeanette’s side
          in her struggle against her <ref cRef="entity-000466">first husband</ref>’s continual
          legal obstructions in 1920.</p>

        <p>The surviving correspondence between the Schenkers and Paul and Anna Schiff is preserved
          at OJ 14/8 (15 items: 1925-38), the Schenker side of which is unfortunately lost.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Source</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><ref type="external"
              target="https://www.geni.com/people/Paul-Schiff/6000000026405059381 "><title>Geni
                “Paul Schiff”</title></ref></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>

  </text>
</TEI>
