<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000107">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Robert (Albrecht) Brünauer, Dr.</title>
        <title type="sub">born July or August 6, 1876; died Łódź ghetto, June 1 or 2, 1942</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="brunauer_robert">Brünauer, Robert</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>13/11/2005</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Brünauer ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">brunauer_robert</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Robert (Albrecht) Brünauer, Dr.</head>

      <div>
        <p>Industrialist, chocolate manufacturer; long-time pupil of Schenker's. </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Business Career</head>

        <p>The firm of Jacques Brünauer &amp; Comp. was established as a public company in or before
          1883, its trading name being <hi rend="italic">Chocolaterie Française</hi>, its premises
          located at Gürtelstraße 15 in Währing-bei-Wien (later the 18th district (Währing) of
          Vienna). By 1900, Camilla, Robert Brunauer's mother, was partner in the firm with her
          husband Jacques (originally Jakob). Robert Brünauer appeared as a signatory to the firm
          from 1903 onwards. After his father's death in 1916 he became a partner in the company,
          and after his mother's presumed death in 1927 the sole owner. In 1933, after the
          annexation of Austria to Germany, the company was listed as in liquidation. </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Brünauer: Life</head>

        <p>From 1904 to 1916, Robert lived at Eroicagasse 15, in the 19th district (Döbling) of
          Vienna, north of Heiligenstadt. By 1907 he was married (OJ 1/6, p. 44), his first wife
          being Ida. During World War I he did military service in the Vienna arsenal, so was able
          to continue his work in the factory. His marriage had evidently broken up by 1919, when
          his wife and children were living in Berlin (OJ 2/14, p. 2051). He re-married in September
          or October 1920 (OJ 3/1, p. 2279), and this wife left him in 1923 (OJ 3/4, p. 2512). From
          1921 to 1938 he lived at Bartensteingasse 3 in the 1st district (Innere Stadt), close to
          the Rathaus. In 1925 he had a daughter, Ulrike (OJ 3/7, p. 2810). </p>


        <p>Brünauer was deported on October 28, 1941 to the Łódź (Littmannstadt) ghetto, where he
          was housed at Gnesenstraße 26 under conditions of forced labor. He died there, presumably
          of starvation or disease, on June 1 or 2, 1942.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Brünauer and Schenker</head>

        <p>Schenker first entered the Brünauer home on October 4, 1903 (OJ 1/4, p. 10); he became a
          regular visitor thereafter and often went to the theater and concerts with Robert,
          sometimes together with the Robert's first wife. Brünauer had already become a pupil of
          Schenker in the fall of either 1900 or 1902 (OJ 4/1, p. 3151; OJ 6/8, [1]), and thus
          belonged to the cohort of students including <ref cRef="entity-000201">Angi Elias</ref>
          and <ref cRef="entity-000165">Sofie Deutsch</ref>. He is included in the last surviving
          lessonbook, 1930/31, and the draft lesson notes for 1931/32 (OC 3/1-4; OC 16/19-24, 47),
          and maintained lessons with Schenker throughout the 1932/33 season, but did not enroll for
          1934/35. </p>

        <p>Brünauer was evidently generous to Heinrich and Jeanette, supplying them with candy
          (which, since Schenker was diabetic, they seem to have used for barter), and in 1918
          offered Schenker 5,000 Kronen to assist with the publishing costs of <ref
            cRef="entity-001727">
            <title level="m">Kontrapunkt 2</title>
          </ref> (which Schenker rejected because Elias had already offered more for the same
          purpose: OJ 2/10, pp. 896–897, 898, June 1, 1918). He was also involved that year in the
          abortive plan for a Festschrift to mark Schenker's 50th birthday. It was Brünauer, too,
          who suggested to Schenker that he sit for the artist <ref cRef="entity-000327">Viktor
            Hammer</ref> (OJ 2/10, pp. 900–901, June 11, 1918), a plan that came to fruition in
          1924–25. Contrarily, he was often late in paying his fees, sometimes paying at the
          previous year's rate and having to be reprimanded. Thus Schenker had an ambivalent
          relationship with him. The two men had frequent conversations, and disagreed sharply on
          social and political issues.</p>

        <p>In a letter to Hammer on December 2, 1923 (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="JOB-94-3_6"
            >JOB 94-3, [6]</ref>) Schenker made the following disparaging remarks: <cit>
            <q>I have held on to this truly pitiable person out of pure compassion for twenty years
              now, making for him (only for him, and once again out of compassion) the greatest
              sacrifices of time and money [...] I keep Brünauer on just out of compassion ‒ I
              always worry that he will do away with himself, even today I am his only advocate ‒
              but I kick out the other rich men if they don't leave their moneyed pride at my
              door.</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>Judging from the repertory that he played (solo piano works, piano concertos, much
          Brahms), and from the length and detail of his lessonbook entries, Brünauer was a
          considerable pianist and commanded Schenker's serious attention. The lessons, two per
          week, appear to have been purely pianistic, with little sign of theoretical studies
          (though on January 9, 1928, Brünauer asked Schenker to "introduce" him to thoroughbass (OJ
          4/1, p. 3164), which Schenker began on February 9 (lessonbook 1927/28, p. 8)), and little
          sign of analytical studies of orchestral or chamber works before 1929. After this time,
          however, Brünauer began preparing analytical graphs; moreover, there is evidence that
          Schenker himself prepared materials in advance for Brünauer, and that his lessons with the
          latter were fertile for Schenker's own analytical thinking (OC 38/73, filed among papers
          for <title level="m">Der freie Satz</title>, can be traced to lessons with Brünauer in
          1929).</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Brünauer's Intellectual Contribution</head>
        <p>Brünauer studied Beethoven's "Eroica" Variations with Schenker in the first part of the
          1926/27 teaching year. The following year he took Schenker by surprise: <cit>
            <q>Brünauer astonishes me with an extraordinarily elegant, visionary observation about
              the first movement of the "Eroica": the neighbor-note a<g type="flat"/><hi
                rend="supralinear">2</hi>, which Beethoven approaches right from the beginning with
              a [<hi rend="italic">crescendo</hi> mark]; he sees this move, this manifestation of
              diminution, as a driving force through the entire work. I agree with him immediately
              most joyfully, with the reservation that it needs closer investigation. (November 14,
              1927: diary pp. 3134-3135).</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>Soon after this, Schenker resumed work on what was to become his study of the "Eroica"
          Symphony in <ref cRef="entity-001752"><title level="j">Meisterwerk III</title></ref>.
          There, Brünauer's idea, though nowhere acknowledged, became a central structural feature
          in Schenker's interpretation of the first movement. </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>"Die Urlinie: eine Entgegnung"</head>
        <p>In 1930 Walter Riezler, a friend of <ref cRef="entity-000268">Wilhelm Furtwängler</ref>,
          wrote an article expressing skepticism about the recent course of Schenker's theoretical
          work. This was published as <title level="a">Über die 'Urlinie',</title>
          <title level="j">Die Musik</title> xxii/7 (April 1930), 502–10 (clipping preserved as OC
          2/p. 80, [5]). As Schenker was unwilling to reply himself, Furtwängler suggested that <ref
            cRef="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</ref> write a response; however, in the meantime
          Brünauer volunteered, his response was discussed in his lessons of April 10, 17, and 24,
          and Schenker approved it. A nine-page carbon copy of the typescript text, with pencil
          corrections and Jeanette Schenker's inscription "Riezler–Brünauer," is preserved as OJ
          21/24. The typescript was sent to Weisse to be forwarded to Furtwängler (OJ 4/3, p. 3471),
          for the latter to submit to <title level="j">Die Musik</title>; but the response never
          appeared in print.</p>

        <p>In "<ref type="other" cRef="OJ-21-24_1">Die Urlinie: eine Entgegnung</ref>", Brünauer
          distinguishes crucially between the "theorist" (Riezler) and the "practical artist"
          (Schenker). Riezler, who thinks in terms merely of motives and labeled harmonies, lacks
          the capacity to understand Schenker's visionary concepts of Urlinie and Ursatz, hence is
          unable to detect "the breath of diminution, which speeds the composition through the tonal
          space that it has itself created, speeding it in such away that the entire outpouring of a
          masterwork rushes past like a single outburst." </p>

      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>
        <p>From Schenker's diaries, it is clear that the two men corresponded a great deal; however,
          only three items survive, OC 52/636 (1925 – gathering information on sales of <title
            level="j">Der Tonwille</title>), 44/15, 16 (1934 – written from the Grand Hotel and the
          Hotel Imperial, both in Vienna); additionally, OC 52/638 is a receipt from Albert J.
          Gutmann for payment of his 1924 subscription to <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>. One
          letter from Brünauer to Otto Vrieslander survives as OJ 71/37, dating between 1904 and
          1916. Compositions by Brünauer survive as OC 41 (Waltz, Op. 39, No. 1) and OC 42
          (arrangement of a keyboard piece by C. P. E. Bach, with Schenker's emendations).</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Bibliography</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Bent, Ian</author>, <title level="a">Heinrich Schenker and Robert Brünauer:
              Relations with a Musical Industrialist,</title>
            <title level="m">Festschrift Hellmut Federhofer zum 100. Geburtstag</title>, ed.
              <editor>Axel Beer</editor> (Tutzing: Hans Schneider, 2011), pp. 25-37</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Lehmann's Allgemeiner Wohnungs-Anzeiger</title> [street directory
            of Vienna] (Vienna: A. Hölder, 1859-1942)</bibl>

          <bibl>Dokumentationsarchiv des oesterreichischen Widerstandes: http://www.doew.at</bibl>

          <bibl><title level="m">Łódź-Names: List of the Ghetto Inhabitants, 1940-1944</title>,
            volume 5, "Supplementary Volume" :
            http://www.shtetlinks.jewishgen.org/Lodz/statistics.htm </bibl>

          <bibl>Private communications from Robert Kosovsky</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributors</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Ian Bent</author>, with <author>Marko Deisinger</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
