<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000775">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Wilhelm Schenker</title>
        <title type="sub">born Wisniowczyk, March 12, 1862</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="schenker_wilhelm">Schenker, Wilhelm</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>25/06/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">schenker_wilhelm</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Wilhelm Schenker</head>
      <div>
        <p>Third (but first surviving) child ‒ of <ref cRef="entity-000772">Johann Schenker</ref>
          and <ref cRef="entity-000773">Julia, <hi rend="italic">née</hi> Moser</ref>, hence
          Heinrich Schenker's elder brother. Wilhelm was married twice, first to <ref
            cRef="entity-000767">Dodi</ref>, with whom he had a daughter (<ref cRef="entity-008468"
            >Wilma</ref>, born 1915); and second to <ref cRef="entity-008450">Marie</ref> – neither
          maiden name known. Wilhelm was a fully-qualified medical doctor who practised for 43 years
          as a municipal doctor in three towns in Upper Austria.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Children and relationships</head>
        <p>Before his first marriage, Wilhelm evidently formed a close attachment to a <ref
            cRef="entity-008443">Mrs. Schimatowitsch</ref>, who had a son, <ref cRef="entity-000895"
            >Tonschl</ref> (father unknown), who himself in 1907 and 1911 had sons <ref
            cRef="entity-003491">Tonerl</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-008438">Karli</ref> (mother
          unknown); that Wilhelm was not <ref cRef="entity-000895">Tonschl</ref>'s father is
          established by Heinrich’s use of the word <hi rend="italic">Adoptivsohn</hi> (“adoptive
          son”) to describe him (diary, June 27, 1915).) While precise chronology is unclear,
          Wilhelm, and <ref cRef="entity-000767">Dodi</ref> took the two young boys into their home,
          helping educate them and seeking careers for them, in which activities his two brothers,
            <ref cRef="entity-000774">Moriz</ref> and Heinrich Schenker were involved. Then in May
          1915 <ref cRef="entity-000767">Dodi</ref> gave birth to a daughter, <ref
            cRef="entity-008468">Wilma</ref>, after which references to “the children” included <ref
            cRef="entity-003491">Tonerl</ref>, <ref cRef="entity-008438">Karli</ref>, and <ref
            cRef="entity-008468">Wilma</ref>.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Wilhelm and his two wives</head>

        <p>From at latest 1907 Wilhelm lived in <ref cRef="entity-002301">Kautzen</ref>, where he
          and his first wife <ref cRef="entity-000767">Dodi</ref> cared for <ref
            cRef="entity-000773">Julia Schenker</ref> for the last three years of her life
          (1915–17). After <ref cRef="entity-000767">Dodi</ref>'s death in 1923, he moved to <ref
            cRef="entity-004163">St. Bernhard bei Horn</ref>, 25 km (15 miles) from <ref
            cRef="entity-002323">Waidhofen</ref>, where <ref cRef="entity-000773">Julia
            Schenker</ref> was buried. From 1935 to 1938 he and his second wife <ref
            cRef="entity-008450">Marie</ref> lived in Pernegg; subsequently they moved to a small
          apartment in <ref cRef="entity-007336">Korneuburg</ref> upon his retirement.</p>

        <p>Wilhelm is not mentioned in Heinrich's diary before 1914. Like his youngest brother <ref
            cRef="entity-000774">Moriz</ref>, he was relatively well-off, and he figures in the
          diary as providing money to <ref cRef="entity-000773">Julia</ref> (diary, September 1 and
          3, 1914), and in 1918 is involved with funeral and gravestone arrangements for <ref
            cRef="entity-000773">Julia</ref>. Like Heinrich, Wilhelm was diabetic: diets feature
          frequently in Heinrich’s letters to his brother.</p>

        <p>Heinrich's diary for September 3‒5, 1927 records a penetrating portrait of a man who used
          cheerfulness as a device for avoiding life's difficulties and who had never fully tapped
          the "higher resources" that he possessed, a man aloof from his family, even unaware of
          Heinrich's growing stature as a musical thinker and writer. <cit>
            <q>He no longer remembers the evening on which we left our father in <ref
                cRef="entity-002401">Lemberg</ref> after the burial of our eldest brother [1880]
              and, returning to our lodging, shook hands and hugged each other – he doesn't remember
              our brother, not even his death! I recall with horror that hour in which I brought
              him, when he was a medical student, the sad news that our father had died [late 1887].
              To me, a world full of trouble came into being, at any rate a new world; he seemed not
              to be taking any notice, as if even then he had decided once and for all to take no
              responsibility upon himself for those who remained, at least as far as his share was
              concerned.</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>The tone of his letters, on the other hand, suggests that the two brothers were on the
          best of terms, sharing their experiences with physicians, dentists, and eye doctors, and
          exchanging Jewish jokes that they had recently heard or read.</p>
      </div>



      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Heinrich and Jeanette</head>
        <p>Eight letters from the 1930s from Wilhelm to Heinrich and his wife Jeanette are known to
          survive as OJ 14/6 (1930-39) and two as OC 44/38 and OC A/296;, the 106 letters and
          postcards from Heinrich to Wilhelm (OJ 5/38) are spread across nearly 40 years. Wilhelm
          maintained contact with Jeanette after Heinrich's death, his last surviving letter to her
          being dated June 1, 1939 (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-6_8">OJ 14/6,
          [8]</ref>).</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Source:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl> private communication from Heribert Esser </bibl>
          <bibl><title level="j">Wiener Zeitung</title>, March 30, 1920, p.5</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author> and <author><hi rend="bold">Marko
                Deisinger</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
