<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000315">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Frieda [Frida; Friedl] Guttmann</title>
        <title type="sub">born Bossance, Suczawa, Bukovina, November 18, 1899</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="guttmann_frieda_daug">Guttmann, Frieda</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>05/07/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">GuttmannF ~ H+JSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">GuttmannF ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">guttmann_frieda_daug</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Frieda [Frida; Friedl] Guttmann</head>

      <div>
        <p>Daughter of <ref cRef="entity-000319">Sophie</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-000318"
            >Salo</ref> Guttmann, sister of <ref cRef="entity-000316">Hans</ref> and <ref
            cRef="entity-000317">Julian (Julko)</ref>, niece of Heinrich and <ref
            cRef="entity-000771">Jeanette</ref> Schenker.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Life summary</head>
        <p>Frieda was born in <ref cRef="entity-002275">Suczawa</ref>, in the <ref
            cRef="entity-002347">Sereth</ref> district of<ref cRef="entity-002247">Bukovina</ref>,
          on November 18, 1899. Nothing is known of her childhood or schooling. The family had lived
          in <ref cRef="entity-002247">Bukovina</ref> until 1914, when they moved briefly to Vienna.
          Heinrich wrote impressions of the whole family, his remarks on Frieda being: <cit>
            <q>The daughter benefits from a sincere urge to communicate, in which flirtatiousness is
              less in play than one is accustomed to finding among girls of her age who are
              talkative or gossipy.</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>How long the family remained in Vienna is unclear, but by 1917 they were sending food
          parcels to Heinrich from <ref cRef="entity-002347">Sereth</ref> in <ref
            cRef="entity-002247">Bukovina</ref>. </p>

        <p>By July 1921, Frieda was being courted by a Mr. <ref cRef="entity-003412"
            >Goldschläger</ref>, and <ref cRef="entity-000774">Moriz Schenker</ref> agreed to
          contribute 20,000 Kronen for her dowry. <ref cRef="entity-003412">Goldschläger</ref>
          earned his doctorate in law in 1923. In 1926 there is talk of an engagement, but there
          were growing concerns in the family about his suitability, and Frieda turned him down in
          April 1927 in favor of <ref cRef="entity-003932">Oskar Fränkl</ref>, their wedding being
          announced in May 1928. By October of that year Frieda was pregnant, and gave birth to a
          girl (<ref cRef="entity-004741]">Hilde</ref>) in March 1929. Her second daughter (<ref
            cRef="entity-008412">Edith</ref>) was born in May 1932.</p>

        <p>By 1934, she and her husband were living in <ref cRef="entity-002375">Cernauti
            (Czernowitz)</ref>, in Rumania, where they still were in 1939, and where <ref
            cRef="entity-000319">Sophie</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-000318">Salo</ref> were planning
          to move to be with them in their old age. In her letter of December 1934, Frieda tells
          Heinrich that <ref cRef="entity-004741]">Hilde</ref>, aged 5, “is learning Rumanian,”
          which is a reminder that <ref cRef="entity-000319">Sophie</ref> and her siblings were
          brought up speaking principally German, and that this had quite likely passed down to <ref
            cRef="entity-000316">Hans</ref> and Frieda and their families. Nothing is known of how
          Frieda’s family fared during World War 2, but 50,000 Jews of <ref cRef="entity-002375"
            >Czernowitz</ref> were placed in a ghetto and then transported to the camps in 1941 and
          1942.</p>

      </div>


      <div>
        <head>Frieda Guttmann and Heinrich Schenker</head>
        <p>When Frieda first appears in Schenker’s diary in 1914, it is probable that she was
          already well-known to Heinrich and Jeanette, and also to Heinrich’s mother <ref
            cRef="entity-000773">Julia</ref>. In 1921, Frieda borrowed opera glasses from Heinrich,
          suggesting that she had attended either an opera-house or a theater. In April 1934 Frieda
          invited Heinrich and Jeanette to spend the summer in the mountains of <ref
            cRef="entity-002247">Bukovina</ref>, but the Schenkers eventually chose <ref
            cRef="entity-002359">Böckstein</ref> in Austria.</p>

        <p>In the August of that year Schenker sent her a copy of <ref cRef="entity-000412">Oswald
            Jonas</ref>’s <title level="m">Das Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks</title>, Frieda
          responding that she would preserve it “as a sacred object.” </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence and photographs</head>
        <p>Receipt of many postcards and letters from Frieda are recorded in Heinrich’s diary, but
          only one letter survives: <ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-A-289">OC A/289</ref>,
          December 16, 1934, which is informative about the Guttmann family. </p>

        <p>There are two surviving photographic portraits of Frieda: OJ 72/18, items 6 (c.1909
          Suczawa, inscribed to Heinrich), and 7 (c.1911, Sereth, inscribed to Heinrich), and Frieda
          figures in several family photographs, items 3 (c1901), 4 (c.1903), 5 (c.1907 Suczawa), 8
          (c.1912 Sereth, inscribed to Heinrich), 11 (c.1916/17), 13 (c.1919), 14 (c.1920), and 15
          (c.1922).</p>
      </div>

    </body>


    <back>

      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><ref type="external"
              target="https://www.geni.com/people/Frida-Guttmann/6000000186487449835"><title>geni
                “Frida Guttmann”</title></ref></bibl>

          <bibl>JewishGen: Bukovina birth records</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributors</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Marko Deisinger</hi></author> with <author><hi rend="bold"
                >Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>


  </text>
</TEI>
