<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000350">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Hans Heinsheimer</title>
        <title type="sub">born Karlsruhe, September 25, 1900; died New York, October 12,
          1993</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="heinsheimer_hans">Heinsheimer, Hans</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">heinsheimer_hans</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Hans Heinsheimer</head>
      <div>
        <p>German, later American, music publishing executive, author and journalist.</p>

        <div>
          <head>Career Summary</head>
          <p>After law studies in Heidelberg, Munich and Freiburg, Heinsheimer joined the editorial
            staff of <ref cRef="entity-002408">Universal Edition</ref> in Vienna in 1923, As head of
            its opera department from 1924 to 1938, he supported and published the works of such
            composers as <ref cRef="entity-000061">Alban Berg</ref>, Leoš Janácek, <ref
              cRef="entity-000482">Ernst Křenek</ref> and Kurt Weill, and contributed many articles
            to the in-house journal <ref cRef="entity-002555"><title level="j">Musikblätter des
                Anbruch</title></ref> (later <title level="j">Anbruch</title>). After the death of
            the firm's director <ref cRef="entity-000356">Emil Hertzka</ref>, he directed the
            company jointly with <ref cRef="entity-000968">Hugo Winter</ref> and <ref
              cRef="entity-000420">Alfred Kalmus</ref> from 1932 until he emigrated to the USA in
            1938. With Paul Stefan he edited the first memorial volume on UE's history: <bibl><title
                level="m"> 25 Jahre Neue Musik: Jahrbuch 1926 der Universal-Edition</title> (Vienna:
              UE, 1926)</bibl>.</p>

          <p>He joined the staff of Boosey &amp; Hawkes in New York, supporting the music of, among
            other composers, Béla Bartók, Aaron Copland and Igor Stravinsky. He moved to G. Schirmer
            in 1947, becoming its director of publications in 1957, then vice-president in 1972,
            particularly involved with the works of Menotti, Bernstein and Barber. He retired in
            1977.</p>

          <p>While in the USA, Heinsheimer wrote a book about his life in publishing, <bibl><title
                level="m">Menagerie in F sharp</title> (Garden City, NY: Doubleday, 1947)</bibl>,
            later reworked as <bibl><title level="m">Best Regards to Aida: the Defeats and Victories
                of a Music Man on Two Continents</title> (New York: Alfred A. Knopf, 1968)</bibl>.
            He also wrote <bibl><title level="m">Fanfare for Two Pigeons</title> (Garden City, NY:
              Doubleday, 1952)</bibl>. After retirement, he contributed many articles to the
            encyclopedia <title level="m">Die Musik in Geschichte und Gegenwart</title>.</p>
        </div>


        <div>
          <head>Heinsheimer and Schenker</head>
          <p>Schenker and Heinsheimer corresponded on practicalities, mostly concerning the
            marketing of <ref cRef="entity-001739"><title level="j">Der Tonwille</title></ref> in
            1923‒24. Five items of correspondence in all survive: three from Heinsheimer to
            Schenker: OC 52/360 (October 5, 1923), OC 52/364 (November 7, 1923), OC 52/591 (April
            30, 1924); and two from Schenker to Heinsheimer WSLB 324 (April 29, 1924), WSLB 329
            (June 6, 1924). The diary records other correspondence and occasional meetings, but
            contact between the two men ceased once Schenker became embroiled in his 1924‒25 legal
            dispute with Universal Edition.</p>

          <p>Jeanette Schenker's contacts with Universal Edition in looking after his affairs
            post-1935 seem to have been with <ref cRef="entity-000420">Alfred Kalmus</ref> (OJ 12/8,
            [1]‒[4], July 1935 to January 1936). However, Schenker's pupil <ref cRef="entity-000412"
              >Oswald Jonas</ref>, who maintained contact with her, was evidently in touch with
            other officials at Universal Edition: <ref cRef="entity-000968">Hugo Winter</ref>, <ref
              cRef="entity-000737">Herman Roth</ref> and Hans Heinsheimer. Significantly, a postcard
            to Jeanette dated February 17, 1938 (OJ 12/6, [48]) states: "Dr. Heinsheimer leaves next
            week for America and will inquire about the market conditions for a possible English
            edition." This was apparently a routine business trip (his first to the USA); but while
            there the <hi rend="italic">Anschluss</hi> occurred (March 12), consequently he made New
            York his home. (In <title level="m">Menagerie</title>, pp. 8‒9, he describes his arrival
            in New York, but gives no date.)</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>

      <div>
        <head>Source</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="j">Wikipedia</title>: <title level="a">Hans Heinsheimer</title>: <ref
              type="external" target="YOURURL"
              >http://www.lexm.uni-hamburg.de/object/lexm_lexmperson_00000779</ref></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Ian Bent</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
