<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000264">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Alois [Aloys] Fuchs</title>
        <title type="sub">born Raase, Moravia, June 22, 1799; died Vienna, March 20, 1853</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="fuchs_alois">Fuchs, Alois [Aloys]</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">fuchs_alois</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Alois [Aloys] Fuchs</head>
      <div>

        <p>Austrian musicologist and collector of autograph manuscripts and early printed
          editions.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Fuchs studied philosophy and law at the University of Vienna (1816‒23), becoming a civil
          servant. In 1836 he was also appointed a bass singer in the Vienna Court Chapel. In 1829 he was
          elected to the Board of the <ref cRef="entity-002430">Gesellschaft der Musifreunde</ref>
          in Vienna.</p>
        <p>Fuchs compiled catalogues of the works of Gluck, Haydn, and other 17th- and 18th-century
          composers, and wrote biographical sketches of Gluck, Mozart, and other composers, and
          numerous other scholarly articles.</p>
        <p>His library, comprising over 1,400 items, was built from 1820 onwards, and included an
          important collection of Mozart autograph manuscripts and printed editions, several
          Beethoven sketchbooks, and sketch materials for operas by Gluck, and manuscripts of
          members of the Bach family, Handel, Haydn and other composers, as well as theoretical
          works by Forkel, Gerber, Kirnberger, Marpurg, and Mattheson. Many of the items went
          eventually to the Staatsbibliothek in Berlin, others to the Benedictine Monastery of
          Göttweig in Austria, several were given by Fuchs as presents to friends, others have since
          been sold through the antiquarian trade to libraries and individuals.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Source:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Grove Music Online</title>
          </bibl>

          <bibl>
            <title level="m">MGG</title>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
