<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000324">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Julian (Julius) Halberstam, Dr.</title>
        <title type="sub">born Warsaw, August 11, 1879; death (unknown)</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="halberstam_julian">Halberstam, Dr. Julian</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">halberstam_julian</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Julian (Julius) Halberstam, Dr.</head>
      <div>

        <p>Jewish-Polish medical doctor. Director of the <ref cRef="entity-002881">Sanatorium
            Löw</ref> in Vienna. Heinrich Schenker's physician from 1922 to his death in 1935.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Dr. Julian Halberstam was the son of Henryk (Heinrich) and Pauline Halberstam. The family
          came from Bialystok (north east Poland), but Julian was born in Warsaw. He first appears
          in the Vienna street directory in 1906, living at Hörigasse 10 in Vienna IX/1. Since this
          address is very close to the <ref cRef="entity-002881">Sanatorium Löw</ref> on
          Mariannengasse and Pelikangasse, he was probably already working at that institution, of
          which he became the Director c. 1924, remaining so until 1937 or 1938, in which latter
          year the sanatorium was closed by order of the Nazi party. </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Halberstam and Schenker</head>
        <p>Schenker's first encounter with Julian Halberstam and first appointment at the Sanatorium
          Löw occurred on April 4, 1922, after which seven further visits took place that year. In
          all, some 300 entries in Schenker's diary have items relating to Halberstam, who kept a
          close eye on Schenker's sugar levels, prescribing medications as necessary, advising on
          other conditions, and also occasionally advising on <ref cRef="entity-000771"
            >Jeanette</ref>'s health.</p>

        <p>Within a few months, the two men had established a common interest in music. One result
          of this was that Schenker ordered copies of his works to be sent Halberstam: the facsimile
          of the <title>"Moonlight" Sonata</title>, <title level="m">Beethovens Neunte
            Sinfonie</title>, issues of <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title> and <title level="j"
            >Das Meisterwerk</title>, articles in several journals, <title level="m">Fünf
            Urlinie-Tafeln</title>, also Oswald Jonas's book <title level="m">Das Wesen des
            musikalischen Kunstwerks</title> and several articles about himself, as well as <ref
            cRef="entity-000327">Victor Hammer</ref>'s portrait and <ref cRef="entity-000738">Alfred
            Rothberger</ref>'s medallion.</p>

        <p>The two parties also invited each other to their homes on several occasions. Most
          notably, Schenker invited Halberstam and his attorney, Dr. Theodor Baumgarten, for
          February 22, 1928, announcing "a Schubert evening! I name my [duet] partner as Dr.
          Brünauer." Jeanette produced a magnificent dinner, after which things did not go as
          intended: <cit>
            <q>The conversation proceeded with difficulty; it moved unavoidably in recollections of
              common acquaintances or of famous people who were known to all from their reputation.
              It proved still more difficult to establish a relationship between the players and the
              audience; we played Schubert and added only Mozart's Andante in G major – but we were
              not met with an appreciativeness commensurate with our devotion to the task. My wish,
              to offer Dr. H. a great joy, ran aground on his incapacity for great joy.</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>On several occasions at Keilgasse 8 Schenker played to him and others into the early
          hours: "I play from 9.30 to 12.45" (April 6, 1927), "they stay until after 1 o’clock; at
          midnight I play Bach – utterly and deeply exhausted" (May 9, 1934). On one occasion
          Schenker played to Halberstam and Baumgarten from 8.15 to 2 a.m., commenting "Halberstam
          falls asleep at the first note of music" (February 5, 1930).</p>

      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence</head>
        <p>Schenker's diary attests to Schenker and Halberstam having written each other many
          letters, and sent holiday postcards, Christmas and New Year's greetings, and delivered
          calling cards. None of these are known to survive, except for one letter from Halberstam
          to Schenker of 1934 (OJ 11/34, [1]).</p>
      </div>

    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Siegel, Hedi</author>, <title level="a">Schenker at the Piano,</title>
            <title level="j">Music Analysis</title> 34/2 (July 2015), 165‒79</bibl>

          <bibl><ref type="external"
              target="https://www.geni.com/people/Dr-Julian-Halberstam/6000000061230867821">Geni:
              "Dr. Julian Halberstam"</ref></bibl>

          <bibl>Communications from Itai Hermelin (author of Geni entry)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>


    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
