<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-003629">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Heinrich Hinterberger</title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, 1892; died 1970</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="hinterberger_heinrich">Hinterberger, Heinrich</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">hinterberger_heinrich</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Heinrich Hinterberger</head>
      <div>

        <p>Austrian antiquarian book dealer who sold Schenker's library of sheet music and books on
          music in 1936.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Having worked in bookstores in <ref cRef="entity-002777">Graz</ref> and <ref
            cRef="entity-002479">Leipzig</ref> before serving and being wounded in World War I,
          Heinrich Hinterberger worked for the antiquarian dealer Gilhofer und Ranschburg in Vienna
          at the end of the war, and then for many years served as managing director of the
          antiquarian firm of <ref cRef="entity-000345">V. A. Heck</ref>, on the Kärntner Ring. </p>

        <p>In 1935 Hinterberger opened his own antiquarian dealership at Hegelgasse 17 in the Inner
          City of Vienna. In quick succession, he issued lists and catalogs in many fields,
          specializing particularly in rare books and autograph manuscripts. Through the contacts
          that he had cultivated during his years with Heck he succeeded in attracting some major
          clients and drawing them to his new business.</p>

        <p>Hinterberger acquired valuable collections from the estates of a variety of book and
          autograph manuscript collectors. He acted in the sale of, among others, Stefan Zweig's
          collection of autograph manuscripts, the music library of Édouard Ganche (who had edited
          the works of Chopin), and parts of the library of Sigmund Freud. There was scarcely a
          catalog in which he was not able to offer several important autograph manuscripts of
          Goethe, Beethoven, or Mozart.</p>

        <p>Of Hinterberger's antiquarian business during World War II and the post-war years little
          is known. Evidently after 1940 no further catalogs were issued. During the post-war period
          he developed a trade in graphics, but was unable to recapture the success of the pre-war
          period before finally giving up the business in the 1960s. </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Hinterberger and Schenker</head>
        <p>While viewing autograph manuscripts by Bach, Mozart, Beethoven, and Brahms at <ref
            cRef="entity-000345">V. A. Heck</ref> on November 30, 1926, Schenker met and talked with
          Hinterberger; he recorded the conversation (notably remarks about <ref
            cRef="entity-000380">Hoboken</ref> and the <ref cRef="2entity-00452"
            >Photogrammarchiv</ref>) in his diary for that date. After Schenker's death,
          Hinterberger offered his books and collection of sheet music for sale. The books,
          numbering 394 titles, were presented in his printed catalog XII, which remains an
          important bibliographical tool for Schenker research. This catalog is undated, but in the
          diary of her travels to Chile and back Jeanette wrote about the sale to Hinterberger on
          June 8, 1936. For the sheet music, on the other hand, comprising over 750 items, offered
          for 1,250 Swiss francs, only a card index (<hi rend="italic">Zettelkatalog</hi>) was made
          (information on the last page of the book catalog XII), and this is not known to survive. </p>

        <p>A short time after those sales, in his catalog No. XX under the title "interesting
          autographs" (item 468), Hinterberger offered for 5 Swiss francs a calling card of
          Schenker's with fourteen lines of writing. </p>

      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">750 Autographen aus der Sammlung Heinrich Hinterberger, Wien und
              anderem Besitz. Mit einer Einleitung von Oliver Matuschek</title> (Vienna: Tutzing,
            2003), pp. 3–4</bibl>

          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Katalog XII. Musik und Theater enthaltend die Bibliothek des Herrn Dr.
              Heinrich Schenker, Wien</title> (Vienna: Antiquariat Heinrich Hinterberger, n.d.
            [1936])</bibl>

          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Katalog XX. Interessante Autographen aus zwei bekannten
              Sammlungen</title> (Vienna: Antiquariat Heinrich Hinterberger, n.d.), p. 45</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Marko Deisinger</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
