<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-003455">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Otto Jahn</title>
        <title type="sub">born Kiel, June 16, 1813; died Göttingen, September 9, 1869</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="jahn_otto">Jahn, Otto</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">jahn_otto</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Otto Jahn</head>
      <div>

        <p>German musicologist and biographer, initially a classicist, philologist, and
          archaeologist.</p>

        <p>Author of the first scholarly biography of Mozart: <listBibl>
            <bibl><title level="m">W. A. Mozart</title>, 4 vols (Leipzig: Breitkopf &amp; Härtel,
              1856‒59), rev. 2nd edn, 2 vols (1867), 3rd edn, ed. and rev. H. Deiters, 2 vols
              (1889).</bibl>
          </listBibl></p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Jahn and Schenker</head>
        <p>Schenker's library at his death included a copy of the two-volume third edition (along
          with Köchel's catalog of Mozart's works and Nottebohm's <title level="m"
            >Mozartiana</title>).</p>

        <p>Schenker took a reserved view of Jahn's work. His diary for December 1906 recounts a bet
          struck with <ref cRef="entity-000328">Paul Hammerschlag</ref> as to how many lines Jahn
          had devoted in his biography to Mozart's G minor Symphony: "I guessed 40; in actuality
          there are 60, but when it comes down to it there isn't a single one." </p>

        <p>Schenker's attitude comes through also in the following passages from <ref
            cRef="entity-001739"><title level="j">Der Tonwille</title></ref>: <cit>
            <q>An instinctive humility before genius could still lead an Otto Jahn, the first to
              attempt a full account of his life, to attribute sacred powers to so incomprehensible
              a being, and he exhibits grateful enthusiasm where knowledge would have actually
              intensified his gratitude and enthusiasm. (<ref cRef="entity-001740"><title level="j"
                  >Tonwille 1</title></ref>, p. 17; Eng. transl., vol. I, p. 65)
              <lb/><lb/>[N]aturally, all of his investigations must fail, because he cannot
              comprehend the purely musical content of Mozart's brilliance (the new type of
              synthesis, the art of voice leading, and so on), not to say anything of presenting it.
                (<ref cRef="entity-001741"><title level="j">Tonwille 2</title></ref>, p. 22, fn;
              Eng. transl., vol. I, p. 69, fn.17)</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>In a letter to <ref cRef="entity-000356">Emil Hertzka</ref> dated January 18, 1915,
          Schenker grouped Jahn scornfully with what he elsewhere called the "hermeneuticists" (i.e.
          those who wrote about music in romantic terms): <cit>
            <q>In this, the ultimate truth would be told about our masterworks, and all the
              Kretzschmars, Spittas, Jahns, etc. would be confronted. (WSLB 236)</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>Nevertheless, Schenker worked through Jahn's biography during the preparatory stages of
          his long essay on the G minor Symphony in <ref cRef="entity-001751"><title level="j"
              >Meisterwerk II</title></ref>, as recorded in his diaries.</p>

        <p>In 1931 Schenker had a calling card printed on which he reproduced a passage from a
          letter allegedly by Mozart describing the composer's method of composition, and
          distributed it to his friends as an anticipation of his own theories. (No copy of the
          calling card is known to survive.) Schenker openly admitted at the time that Otto Jahn had
          questioned the letter's authenticity as early as the 1850s; nevertheless he persisted in
          writing an article on the "lost letter." </p>

      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Grove Music Online</title> ("Jahn, Otto") (Alec Hyatt King) </bibl>

          <bibl><author>Schenker, Heinrich</author>, "Ein verschollener Brief von Mozart und das
            Geheimnis seines Schaffens," <title level="j">Der Kunstwart</title> 44 (July 1931),
            660‒66 (copies preserved at OJ 20/10, item 3 and OC 50/12, and a draft in Jeanette
            Schenker's hand with emendations by Heinrich at OC 16/8‒26) </bibl>

          <bibl><author>Jahn, Otto</author>, <title level="m">W. A. Mozart</title>, 4 vols (Leipzig:
            Breitkopf &amp; Härtel, 1856‒59); rev. 2nd edn, 2 vols (1867); 3rd edn, ed. and rev. H.
            Deiters, 2 vols (1889); 5th edn, ed. Hermann Abert (1923‒24); 7th edn, ed. Anna Amalie
            Abert (1955‒66); Eng. transl. Pauline Townsend (1891)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
