<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000783">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Victor [Viktor] Schiff</title>
        <title type="sub">born Aussig on the Elbe (Ústí nad Labem), December 11, 1885</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="schiff_victor">Schiff, Victor</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">schiff_victor</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Victor [Viktor] Schiff</head>
      <div>

        <p>Brother of <ref cRef="entity-000771">Jeanette Schenker (<hi rend="italic">née</hi>
            Schiff)</ref>, hence from 1919 brother-in-law of <ref cRef="entity-000632">Heinrich
            Schenker</ref>.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Life Summary</head>

        <p>Victor Schiff was the seventh of the ten children of <ref cRef="entity-008431">Wilhelm
            Schiff</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-008432">Emilie(<hi rend="italic">née</hi>
            Strasser)</ref>: <ref cRef="entity-000771">Jeanette [m. Kornfeld; m. Schenker]</ref>
          (1874–1945) – <ref cRef="entity-006733">Louis</ref> (b. 1875) (wife: <ref
            cRef="entity-008463">Hermine Hahn</ref>) – <ref cRef="entity-008433">Emil</ref> (b.
          1877) – <ref cRef="entity-003245">Friedrika (Frieda) [m. Glässner]</ref> (1878–1933) –
            <ref cRef="entity-006478">Emma [m. Winternitz]</ref> (1880–c.1943), <ref
            cRef="entity-003244">Klara [m. O. Hatschek]</ref> (1881–1939) – <ref
            cRef="entity-000944">Rosa (Růžena Rejle) [m. Weil]</ref> (1883–1942) – <ref
            cRef="entity-003920">Helene (Hella) [m. E. Hatschek]</ref> (1887–c.1941) and <ref
            cRef="entity-000782">Paul</ref> (b. 1895) (wife: <ref cRef="entity-000781">Anna
            Schiff</ref>).</p>

        <p>Nothing is known of Victor’s early life. During part of World War I he spent time in <ref
            cRef="entity-003029">Sweden</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-002507">Switzerland</ref>, then
          almost five years in Bolivia (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-9_1">OJ 14/9,
            [1])</ref>. To <ref cRef="entity-000782">Paul Schiff</ref> he explained his business in
          Bolivia: <cit>
            <q>I left my wife in sole charge of the business, on the property I had rented. My mule
              laden with wares, I set off on the trail. Through swamp, virgin forest, over steppes
              and highland, I trekked into uncharted territory where the natives were still
              unacquainted with money. For items of low value they exchanged gold dust and precious
              stones. (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-9_2">OJ 14/9, [2]</ref>)</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>Thereafter he moved to <ref cRef="entity-005845">Chile</ref>, working in business and
          then, until 1925, in the building trade (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-9_1">OJ
            14/9, [1]</ref>, to Klara). <ref cRef="entity-003244">Klara</ref> was “disappointed in
          him” and <ref cRef="entity-000782">Paul</ref> criticized him “for his business dealings;”
          but <ref cRef="entity-000632">Heinrich</ref> countered: “In his independence, his daring
          and above all his warm-heartedness, Victor appears to exceed his siblings <ref
            cRef="entity-000782">Paul</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-003244">Klara</ref>” (diary,
          February 4, 1926).</p>

        <p>Victor was an enthusiastic Zionist. <ref cRef="entity-000632">Heinrich</ref> comments: <cit>
            <q>he has hated the Germans since his youth, but at the same time condemns German
              anti-Semitism, as if it were forbidden by nature for Germans to hate in the same way
              that they themselves are hated. In general, he is lacking in knowledge of the
              historical background; he does not understand the difficult position of the Germans in
              the world, and does the same injustice to these eternally threatened and betrayed
              people as do other enemies of Germany, though a national Jewish interest ought instead
              to bind him to Germany: the persecuted, the dispossessed, shoulder to shoulder!
              (diary, October 16, 1926)</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>Already in October 1925 Victor declared: <cit>
            <q>I have long nurtured a resolve to go to the land of Israel and to settle down there,
              just to buy a farmstead in a fruitful area near a small town, and to live out the
              years that are still allotted me. [...] I have not assimilated; I have nowhere where I
              can or want to assimilate, I am drawn by a secret power to the land which is the true
              home of our people. For a long time, I have been pursuing the study of the Hebraic as
              well as Arabic language, so that it will not be hard for me to acclimate there. I am
              thinking of embarking on my journey at the end of next year or even earlier – that
              will be the last journey of my life. (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-9_1">OJ
                14/9, [1]</ref>, to Klara)</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>Three years later, <ref cRef="entity-000632">Heinrich</ref> records: “he is sticking with
          his intention to move to Palestine” (diary, April 30, 1928); and two years later still, of
          a letter from Victor, “he is taking his leave of South America, is traveling around the
          world, and will land in <ref cRef="entity-004528">Palestine</ref>” (diary, March 31,
          1930). Yet in 1933, of a letter from <ref cRef="entity-000944">Rosa</ref>
          <ref cRef="entity-000632">Heinrich</ref> recorded: “Victor is back in <ref
            cRef="entity-005845">Chile</ref>” (diary, August 29, 1933).</p>

        <p>A year later, of a letter from Victor enclosing five photographs, <ref
            cRef="entity-000632">Heinrich</ref> reported: “he wanted to visit us, but the conditions
          in Europe prevented him – nonetheless, he hopes for a reunion” (July 2, 1934), to which
            <ref cRef="entity-000632">Heinrich</ref> replied inviting him to visit. The last
          surviving letter from Victor was, as reported: “cheerful and touching, he thinks of <ref
            cRef="entity-000771">Lie-Liechen</ref> as just twenty years old since she still writes
          so beautifully; he remembers her as an odalisque (of sixteen!), he being six years
          old!”</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Jeanette's Travel to Chile</head>

        <p>It was perhaps this abortive plan for a reunion that prompted <ref cRef="entity-000771"
            >Jeanette</ref> to depart on April 27, 1936 on a six-month journey by sea to <ref
            cRef="entity-005845">Chile</ref> and back. She kept a travel diary (OJ 35/9). On the
          very <ref type="diaries" cRef="OJ-35-09_1936-04:r0002">day of departure</ref> she wrote: <cit>
            <q>Two airmail letters arrive from Victor, one to <ref cRef="entity-000944">Rosl</ref>
              and one to me, apart from the envelopes full of the most offensive indignities and
              even threats, which are intended to put me off my trip at the last minute. <ref
                cRef="entity-000944">Rosl</ref> reads the letters to me in the bathroom; […] the
              letters make no impression on me whatever. I had never intended to travel to see my
              brother; do I even know him?</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>In August, in Santiago, she went with two new acquaintances to the address that she had
          been given for Victor: <cit>
            <q>Almost promptly, at 5 o’clock (we had arranged to meet at 4:30) the Eisenberg couple
              arrive. We go to „Lira 107,“ the young people enter and learn that “people” had moved
              out the previous day. I take it that my brother has had the postbox for a long time,
              but has not for a long time lived at the flat whose address he had communicated to the
              post office. So much the better!</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>In the end, she left <ref cRef="entity-005845">Chile</ref> having not made contact, but
          having taken steps to promote her husband’s work in the country.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Personality and Reactions of Schiff Siblings</head>

        <p>In 1925 Victor gave <ref cRef="entity-003244">Klara</ref> a self-portrait: “I am an
          inconspicuous person, don’t smoke, don’t go to the theater, not even to the coffee-house,
          I’ve never played cards, and have for many years not associated with unsavory company.”
            (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-9_1">OJ 14/9, [1]</ref>). He was by far the most
          observantly Jewish of the ten Schiff siblings, his letters containing long screeds about
          the land of Israel and the history of its people.</p>

        <p><ref cRef="entity-000944">Rosa</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-000943">Arnold Weil</ref>,
          while giving Victor credit for his independent spirit, tired of his letters. In 1934 she
          remarked: “<ref cRef="entity-000943">Arnold</ref> will never again read a letter from
          Victor; he refuses to listen to his claptrap” (<ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-14-10_15">OJ 45/10, [15]</ref>), and in 1935 she herself wrote: <cit>
            <q><ref cRef="entity-003920">Hella</ref> wrote me enclosing a letter from Victor with
              some photographs from the seaside resort. Where the florid language ceases the wall
              begins, the wall with which he shuts us out, and which gets ever thicker and thicker.
              More than a generation, an ocean separates us.</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>Of his later life and the circumstances of his death, nothing is currently known.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence and Photographs</head>

        <p>Only one item of correspondence between Victor and Jeanette is known now to survive (<ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-9_3">OJ 14/9, [3]</ref>). However, a substantial
          correspondence between the two had taken place before 1903, Victor’s side of which was
          still in Jeanette’s possession as late as 1926, and Jeanette’s side of which had been lost
          before that date. A complete break then ensued until 1926, when Jeanette wrote to <ref
            cRef="entity-003629">Valparaiso</ref> on February 7, 1926 (received by Victor on March
          8), to which he replied on March 21 (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-9_3">OJ 14/9,
            [3]</ref>). Thereafter an intermittent correspondence continued until 1934, none of
          which now survives: 1. Jeanette to Victor July 8, 1926, describing their life in Vienna;
          2. Victor to Jeanette, partly in Hebrew, received October 27, 1926; 3. Victor to Jeanette,
          received April 30, 1928, expressing his intention to emigrate to Palestine; 4. Jeanette to
          Victor, June 24, 1928, about their siblings; 5. Jeanette to Victor, July 11, 1929; 6.
          Victor to Jeanette, received March 31, 1930, about to travel round the world ending in
          Palestine; 7. Victor to Jeanette, enclosing five photographs, received July 2, 1934,
          hoping for a reunion with Jeanette; 8. Jeanette and Heinrich to Victor, July 4–5, 1934,
          inviting him to visit and stay; 9. Victor to Jeanette, received October 6, 1934,
          reminiscing on their childhood together.</p>

        <p>Victor corresponded with his siblings <ref cRef="entity-003244">Klara</ref>, <ref
            cRef="entity-000944">Rosa</ref>, <ref cRef="entity-003920">Hella</ref>, <ref
            cRef="entity-000782">Paul</ref>, and their spouses, he sent photographs of himself, and
          they corresponded with him. These letters were passed around the siblings, and some of the
          exchanges are reported in Heinrich’s diary. Only one letter to <ref cRef="entity-003244"
            >Klara</ref> (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-9_1">OJ 14/9, [1]</ref>) and one to
            <ref cRef="entity-000782">Paul</ref> (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-9_2">OJ
            14/9, [2]</ref>) survive, from 1925. One photographic portrait of him is preserved as OJ
          72/21, dated “Spring 1926”.</p>
      </div>

    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Source</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <ref type="external"
              target="https://www.geni.com/people/Victor-Schiff/6000000026405799522"><title>geni
                “Victor Schiff”</title></ref>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
