<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000144">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Gustav von Cube</title>
        <title type="sub">born 1874; died March? 1931</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="cube_gustav_von">Cube, Gustav von</term>
        </title>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">CubeG ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">cube_gustav_von</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Gustav von Cube</head>

      <p>German architect and archaeologist, father of <ref cRef="entity-000143"
          >Felix-Eberhard von Cube</ref>.</p>

      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>

        <p>The son of a medical doctor, Gustav von Cube was born on the French Riviera and studied
          architecture at the Technische Hochschule in Hannover, where his son was born in 1903. He
          moved to Munich a year later, and initially worked as an archaeologist, where he came into
          contact with (among others) the father of <ref cRef="entity-000268">Wilhelm
            Furtwängler</ref>. </p>

        <p>He then set up a private practice in architecture in Munich, and his early years in the
          profession seem to have been successful. This may have partly been the result of his
          marriage into the Sternheim family: among his early projects was Schloss Bellemaison,
          built for his brother-in-law Carl Sternheim, the playwright and short story writer. The
          Cubes moved into a small house on the Sternheims' estate in 1906. At this time they became
          acquainted with <ref cRef="entity-000922">Otto Vrieslander</ref>, who was living with
          the Sternheims and working as their librarian and who became a kind of mentor to young
          Felix. After moving to Duisburg in the 1920s, Gustav formed a partnership with fellow
          architect Arthur Buchloh. </p>

        <p>Little else is known about his career, other than that after the death of his first wife
          (Felix's mother) he married for a second time only to find himself professionally
          ostracized because his bride was a teen-age dancer at an opera house in the Rhineland (OJ
          9/34, [1]) – a much younger woman by whom he subsequently had one child. It was presumably
          under the strain of his professional situation that he eventually committed suicide by
          shooting himself. </p>

        <p>Felix described his father as "stingy" – he once stated that it was harder to get money
          out of his father than an Urlinie out of a work by Stravinsky (OJ 9/34, [2]). </p>

      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Gustav von Cube and Schenker; Correspondence</head>
        <p>While the two men never met, they corresponded on two occasions, both prompted by Cube’s
          financial worries. Four letters survive: two from Gustav to Schenker: OJ 9/35, [1], Sept
          7, 1925, and OJ 9/35, [2], Aug 24, 1926; two from Schenker to Gustav: OJ 5/7a, [2], Sept
          13, 1925, and OJ 5/8, [1] (= OJ 5/7, [1], incomplete draft in Jeanette's hand and postal
          receipt), Aug 18, 1926. The first, cordial exchange concerns a request for Schenker’s help
          in finding some paid teaching work for his son in Munich (which was, in part, honored). In
          the second, which was acrimonious, Schenker demanded the long-delayed payment of lesson
          fees, to which Cube reluctantly agreed. A letter also survives from Felix to his father
          (Jan 21, 1924, uncatalogued), with a cartoon showing Schenker in full command of his
          polemics regarding contemporary music (reproduced in full Drabkin, 1984–85, and in cropped
          form at the right-hand end of the <hi rend="italic">Schenker Documents Online</hi>
          banner).</p>
      </div>

    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Felix-Eberhard von Cube</author>, <title>Todeskampf oder Wiederauferstehung
              der deutschen Musik: ein autobiographisch-historischer Essay</title> (unpublished
            typescript: Hamburg, 1984)></bibl>

          <bibl><author>William Drabkin</author>, <title level="a">Felix-Eberhard von Cube and the
              North-German Tradition of Schenkerism,</title>
            <title level="j">Proceedings of the Royal Musical Association</title> cxi (1984–85),
            180–207.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>William Drabkin</author>, <author>Marko Deisinger</author>, <author>Ian
              Bent</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>

      </div>

    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
