<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000110">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Hans von Bülow</title>
        <title type="sub">born Dresden, January 8, 1830; died Cairo, February 12, 1894</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="bulow_hans_von">Bülow, Hans von</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>17/12/2007</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">bulow_hans_von</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Hans von Bülow</head>
      <div>
        <p>One of the greatest German conductors and pianists of his age; editor of music.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Hans von Bülow took piano lessons with Friedrich Wieck, and later studied in Dresden with
          Plaidy and Hauptmann. He read law at Leipzig University; having met Liszt in 1849 he
          studied piano with him, embarking on a career as a concert pianist in 1853. In 1864, he
          became conductor at the Court Opera in Munich, where he conducted Wagner music dramas for
          the first time. He became a champion of the "new school" of German composers, and also of
          Tchaikovsky. Subsequently he took up conducting positions in Hanover, Meiningen, and
          Berlin, and taught at conservatories in Frankfurt and Berlin.</p>
        <p>Von Bülow worked also as an editor of keyboard music, and it is instructive to itemize
          some of this work and the publishers concerned: of J. S. Bach, the Italian Concerto, the
            <title level="m">Chromatic Fantasy &amp; Fugue</title>, and the Fantasies in C minor and
          A minor (Berlin: Bote &amp; Bock); of C. P E. Bach, six sonatas (Leipzig: Peters); of
          Handel, selected pieces (Vienna: UE); of Haydn, the C-major Fantasy (Vienna: UE); of
          Scarlatti, eighteen pieces (Leipzig: Peters); of Beethoven, the piano sonatas Opp. 53-111
          (Stuttgart: Cotta, in the firm's <title level="s">Instruktive Ausgabe klassischer
            Klavierwerke</title>), the piano sonatas Opp. 13, 26, 27/2, 31/3 (Vienna: UE), the
          C-minor Variations and Fantasy, Op. 80, and Variations on a Russian Dance Theme (Vienna:
          UE); of Chopin, the collected Etudes, four impromptus, and the Tarantella (Vienna: UE); of
          Cramer, the Etüdes (Vienna: UE), and works by Weber, Field, and others. (Those published
          by UE were taken over from other publishers in 1904 and after.)</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Von Bülow and Schenker</head>
        <p>As a critic in the 1890s, Schenker praised von Bülow's work. In addition to passing
          references he offered two substantive critiques of von Bülow, in "Konzertdirigenten"
          (1894) and "Bülow-Weingartner" (1895). In the former, he wrote: <cit>
            <q>He is for me an epochal man who frequently had the power to release the performing
              musician from the naiveté of his instincts, who had the gift of capturing and
              communicating in clear, most purposefully chosen words the essence of music, the soul
              of music. [...] It is only a pity that this genius of a man did not communicate more
              of his ideas on works.</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>The above summary of von Bülow's editing shows how closely it intersected with Schenker's
          own editorial activities as well as the publishers with whom he worked. It seemed
          essential, perhaps, to Schenker that he prove the higher caliber of his own work. Hence,
          from early on can be found critical remarks about von Bülow as editor. In 1901, he spoke
          of him as "a figure less worthy of beatification, less worthy of being taken seriously,
          than the great star-struck masses believe" (NMI C 176-01, April 13, 1901). In 1908, he
          used <ref cRef="entity-000724">Julius Röntgen</ref>, the Director of the Amsterdam
          Conservatory, as leverage in the eyes of Emil Hertzka at Universal Edition: <cit>
            <q>Prof. Röntgen (Amsterdam) has asked me personally to arrange for him to receive [a
              copy of] my <ref cRef="entity-001720">[C.P.E.] Bach edition</ref>--i.e. U.E. No.
              548--for him. He tells me that he has been constantly dissatisfied with the Bülow
              edition (Peters), and I think it would be prudent, in the light of this
              dissatisfaction, to see whether Prof. Röntgen would replace the Bülow edition by the
              UE edition, at least at the Amsterdam Conservatory. (WSLB 20, September 28, 1908).</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>Already the <ref cRef="entity-001721"><title level="m">Beitrag zur
            Ornamentik</title></ref> (1903, 1908) offers extensive criticism of the Foreword to von
          Bülow's C. P. E. Bach edition for Peters, exposing its misunderstanding of the function of
          ornamentation and the nature of instrumental sonority by juxtaposing Bach's own words
          against von Bülow's (1903, pp. 4-6; Eng. trans., pp. 16-22, and in the individual ornament
          sections). Over the crux between his and von Bülow's edition of the <title level="m"
            >Chromatic Fantasy &amp; Fugue</title>, Schenker wrote to Hertzka: "if it were a choice
          of playing the sonatas either according to von Bülow or according to me, I can assure you
          the musical world, those who hang around the Konzertgebäude as well as those who tickle
          the ivories in their own homes, will turn to me alone--once, that is, they catch sight of
          my edition." (WSLB 116, June 2, 1912)</p>
        <div>
          <head>Schenker's Later Criticism of von Bülow</head>
          <p><ref cRef="entity-001733"><title level="m">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von
                Beethoven</title></ref> (1913-21) provided an obvious battleground against von
            Bülow, the attacks appearing in the main analytical sections (e.g. "But when von Bülow
            explains that his 'new presentation of the [music] text is more vivid also for
            determining its thematic meaning,' then this is as laughable as it is absurd ...,"
              <title level="m">Op. 110</title>, p. 70), and a single, sustained assault in the
            "Preliminary Remarks" to <title level="m">Op. 110</title> (1914, pp. 23-25, ed. Jonas,
            pp. 7-10). The attacks are kept up in <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>, as in
              <title level="a">Die Kunst zu hören</title> (The Art of Listening), where Schenker
            quotes von Bülow's edition of a Scarlatti sonata then belittles the latter's aural
            ability ("Bülow has no ear for the multifarious processes of elaboration in cases where
            voices move below the root of the chord," <title level="j">Tonwille 3</title>, p. 24;
            Eng. trans., vol. I, pp. 119-20), and also in <title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der
              Musik</title> (vol. I, pp. 143-44; Eng. trans., vol. I, pp. 79-80). Schenker liked to
            report Brahms's remark, made in the context of a plan for a von Bülow national monument,
            that Bülow was "only a Kapellmeister."</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Bibliography:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Schenker, Heinrich</author>, <title level="a">Konzertdirigenten,</title>
            <title level="j">Die Zukunft</title>, vol. 7 (1894), pp. 88-92, ed. <editor>Federhofer,
              Hellmut</editor>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker als Essayist und Kritiker
              ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1990), pp. 75-82, esp. 77-79</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Schenker, Heinrich</author>, <title level="a">Bülow-Weingartner,</title>
            <title level="j">Musikalisches Wochenblatt</title>, Yr. 26 (1895), pp. 610-11, ed. ibid,
            pp. 171-75</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
              Tagebüchern und Briefen ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), pp. 222-25 <hi
              rend="italic">et passim</hi></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">NGDM2</title> (2001 and online)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">MGG1</title></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
