<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000002">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Emil Preetorius</title>
        <title type="sub">born Mainz, June 21, 1883; died Munich, January 27, 1973</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="preetorius_emil">Preetorius, Emil</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">preetorius_emil</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Emil Preetorius</head>
      <div>

        <p>German book illustrator, graphic artist, and collector of South and East Asian works of
          art.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>After studies in Munich, Berlin, and Giessen, and briefly at the Munich School of Applied
          Arts, Emil Preetorius self-trained as a painter and draftsman. In 1909 he co-founded a
          school for illustration in Munich, and taught at the University of Fine Arts in Munich
          from 1926, becoming a professor there in 1928. He provided illustrations for many works of
          fiction, including three by Thomas Mann. In the late 1920s he began designing sets for
          productions of <ref cRef="entity-000924">Wagner</ref>’s stage works at <ref
            cRef="entity-003993">Bayreuth</ref>, including <title level="m">Meistersinger</title>
          and the <title level="m">Ring</title>, in conjunction with <ref cRef="entity-000268"
            >Wilhelm Furtwängler</ref>, and his work was highly praised by Hitler. From 1944 he
          designed opera sets for Salzburg.</p>

        <p>He was also a collector of artworks of China, Japan, Persia, and India. His large
          collection is now owned by the Preetorius Foundation. </p>

        <p>He is not to be confused with <ref cRef="entity-000680">Ernst Praetorius
            [Preetorius]</ref>.</p>
      </div>


      <div>
        <head>Emil Preetorius and Heinrich Schenker</head>
        <p>Preetorius wrote an article for the Rotary Club journal <title level="j">Der Rotarier für
            Deutschland und Österreich</title> in January 1931, to which <ref cRef="entity-000643"
            >Reinhard Oppel</ref> drew Schenker's attention as making favorable comment on
          Schenker’s work. On February 9, 1931 Preetorius gave a lecture in Vienna, which was
          attended by Schenker and his pupils <ref cRef="entity-000107">Robert Brünauer</ref> and
            <ref cRef="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</ref>. Weisse identifed deficiencies in the
          lecture, while Schenker was disappointed that it failed to consider music. Nonetheless,
          Schenker approached Preetorius after the lecture, and subsequently arranged for a copy of
            <ref cRef="entity-001752"><title level="m">Meisterwerk</title> III</ref> to be sent to
          him, and followed that with a letter (a draft of which survives as <ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-30_1">OJ 5/30, [1]</ref>, February 12–13, 1931),
          asserting that his theory of cohesiveness (<hi rend="italic">Zusammenhang</hi>) in music
          addressed a question raised in Preetorius's article and could become a model for
          exploration of unity in other arts.</p>
      </div>

    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Source:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">wikipedia</title> (02-12-2023) </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
