<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000913">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Moriz Violin</title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, March 30, 1879; died San Francisco, April 1, 1956</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="violin_moriz">Violin, Moriz</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>07/11/2005</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">ViolinM ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">ViolinM+V+F ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">violin_moriz</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Moriz Violin</head>
      <div>
        <p>Concert pianist, composer, and teacher; Schenker's closest friend.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p><figure>
            <head>Moriz Violin, c. 1901 (OJ 72/23, No. 6)</head>
            <graphic url="B72F23_2.jpg" xmt:type="thumb-caption" rend="left-img" width="150px"
              height="113px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <graphic url="B72F23_2.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img" width="800px" height="600px"
              mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <figDesc>Photograph of Moriz Violin.</figDesc>
          </figure></p>
        <p>Violin was winner of the Brahms Prize in composition of the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde
          in 1894, and a founding member of the Violin-Fischer-Klengel trio in Vienna and the
          Violin-Van den Berg-Buxbaum trio in Berlin. Violin taught in the piano Ausbildungsklasse
          at the Vienna Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst (= Conservatory) from 1908 (or
          1909) to 1912, in which year he resigned from the Conservatory staff in protest at the way
          in which the new administration was forcing established professors into retirement,
          treating other members of staff, and at their not appointing Schenker to a professorship
          in theory. He published his letter of protest as a 34-page pamphlet, <title level="m">Die
            Zustände an der k. k. Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst: Ein offenes Wort über
            die Leiter der Anstalt Herren v. Wiener und Bopp</title> [Conditions at the
          Imperial-Royal Academy for Music and Performing Arts: a word about the leaders of the
          institution, Messrs von Wiener and Bopp] (Vienna: self-pubd, 1912 = OJ 70/49a); a letter
          regretting his resignation was signed by fifty-three of his colleagues (OJ 70/59).</p>
        <p><figure>
            <head>Moriz Violin, c. 1960 (Eva Violin Windsor)</head>
            <graphic url="ViolinMoriz-piano.jpg" xmt:type="thumb-caption" rend="left-img"
              width="150px" height="113px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <graphic url="ViolinMoriz-piano.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img" width="800px"
              height="600px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <figDesc>Photograph of Moriz Violin playing the piano.</figDesc>
          </figure>In 1921, Violin moved to Hamburg, taking up a position at the Conservatory
          (presumably the Vogt'sches Konservatorium) on April 1 and teaching there through the
          1920s. In 1931, he established a private music school in Hamburg devoted to Schenker's
          theory: the Schenker-Institut, at which he taught piano and Felix-Eberhard von Cube
          theory. Violin fled Hamburg with the rise of Nazism c.May 1933 (see, e.g. OJ 9/34, [37],
          May 11, 1933, Cube to Schenker), leaving Cube to continue until the institute was closed
          down in 1934. In 1939 Violin moved to the USA, settling in San Francisco.</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="bold">Violin and Schenker</hi>
        </p>
        <p>Violin, variously nicknamed "Floriz," "Fiorello," and "Florizello," was Schenker's oldest
          and closest friend (Schenker's own nickname to Violin may have been "Ophelius"). Their
          friendship began in 1896 and ended only with Schenker's death in 1935. He gave
          performances of Schenker's piano compositions, and he and Schenker gave the first
          performance of the latter's <title level="m">Syrian Dances</title> for two pianos on
          January 26, 1900. Federhofer maintains that Schenker's pseudonym for his <title level="m"
            >Instrumentations-Tabelle</title>, "Artur Niloff," is in part an approximate anagram of
          "Violin".</p>
        <p>Violin's booklet <title level="m">Über das sogenannte Continuo</title> (Vienna: UE, 1910
          - copies are preserved at OJ 70/49 and OC 6/2) was originally written as a program note
          for a "historical concert" that was to take place in the Akademie in 1910 but was
          cancelled.</p>

        <p>Schenker characterized Violin's qualities in a letter of recommendation that he wrote to
            <ref cRef="entity-000268">Wilhelm Furtwängler</ref> on November 5, 1919 (Sbb 55 Nachl.
          13, [1]): <cit>
            <q>He has an ear such as very few musicians of today possess. In keeping with the
              quality of his ear and of his intellect, he really should be in a permanent position,
              but fighting is not his forte, although, as is so often nature's way, he himself
              believes that he has the fighting spirit. […] his ear is unique, a masterstroke of
              nature, exactly what is needed for the connoisseur these days.</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>A glimpse of his personality, or of the two men's interaction, is perhaps given in a
          postcard by Schenker while he was waiting in Steinach in the Tyrol for Violin to turn up
          and comments: "All that was missing at today's first restaurant service were your
          criticisms and a readiness to find fault" (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-7-4_52">OJ
            7/4, [52]</ref>, July 7, 1909).</p>

        <p>
          <hi rend="bold">Correspondence and Other Documents</hi>
        </p>
        <p>The Moriz Violin Papers are held as Box 70 of the Oswald Jonas Memorial Collection at the
          University of California, Riverside, Speciall Collections; biographical materials
          concerning Violin are OJ 70/57-66.</p>
        <p>Surviving correspondence between Moriz and Valerie Violin and the Schenkers is in excess
          of 1,000 items. That from the Violins to the Schenkers is preserved as OJ 14/45 (1900-38:
          96 items) and OC OC 24/4-5, 38/155, 346, 341, 415 (1921-31: 5 items); that from the
          Schenkers to the Violins as OJ 6/1-8, 7/1-4, and 8/1-5 (1896-1935: 921 items).
          Correspondence between Violin and others (including d'Albert, von Cube, Furtwängler,
          Mandyczewski, Messchaert, Schoenberg, Bruno Walter, and Weisse) is preserved as OJ
          70/1-48a (1898-1953), and one item from Jonas to Violin as OJ 36/65 (1916); letters of
          recommendation for Violin by Busoni, Furtwängler, Goldschmidt, Schalk, Schoenberg, and
          Walter are preserved as OJ 70/67-72.</p>
        <p>Violin's obituary for Schenker, "Zur Erinnerung an Heinrich Schenker," survives as OJ
          70/54. Seventeen photographs of Violin are preserved as OJ 72/32, some of them including
          his mother, his brother, his son Raphael, and his daughter Eva, others showing him in
          groups.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>Oster Collection Finding List</bibl>
          <bibl>Jonas Memorial Collection Checklist</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
              Tagebüchern und Briefen ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985) </bibl>
          <bibl><author>Tittel, Ernst</author>, <title level="m">Die Wiener Musikhochschule
            </title>(Vienna: Lafite, 1967)</bibl>
          <bibl>Documents on this website</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
