<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000773">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Julia Schenker [née Mosler]</title>
        <title type="sub">born c. 1826; died Kautzen, Dec 22, 1917</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="schenker_julia">Schenker, Julia</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>19/12/2007</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">schenker_julia</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>28/10/201</date>
        <desc>revision of text</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Julia Schenker [née Mosler]</head>
      <div>
        <p>Mother of Heinrich Schenker.</p>
        <p>Julia's father had been a tailor, "but always devoted himself to Hebrew literature, in
          which he was very well-versed"; and in her "parental house there existed that spiritual
          atmosphere that is peculiar to the Jews" (OJ 2/9, p. 812: pp. 812-17 contain an extended
          tribute to her by Heinrich on her burial day, December 23, 1917).</p>
        <p>Julia and her husband, <ref cRef="entity-000772">Johannes</ref>, Heinrich's father, lived
          in <ref cRef="entity-002333">Wisniowczyk</ref>, in <ref cRef="entity-002355"
          >Galicia</ref>, where they had at least six children, of whom four survived: Wilhelm,
          Shifre, Heinrich, and Moriz. After her husband's death in late 1887, she moved with her
          impoverished family to Vienna, to be near Heinrich. Of this he later recorded: <cit>
            <q>Already during my earliest years, because I had to support mother, sister [Schifre,
              later Sophie Guttmann], younger brother (today the so ungrateful billionaire) [Moriz],
              and niece [Frieda?] by giving piano lessons, I gladly accepted an offer from a
              Viennese friend of [Maximilian] Harden to write something for him. (DLA 69.930/10,
              September 25, 1922, to Halm)</q>
          </cit></p>
        <p>Heinrich took his responsibilities toward his mother seriously ("for [September] 19
          (Jewish holidays) : a few pennies for Mama, seats in the synagogue etc.": OJ 6/4, [],
          Schenker to Violin, September 15/18, 1906), and taking care of her when she was ill. Julia
          Schenker provided a vital link to Heinrich's Jewish heritage, coming out with Jewish
          sayings, and reminding him of customs and holy days: <cit>
            <q>Evening with mother at Uncle and Aunt Einschenk's, for Passover. Old memories!: The
              ritual meal unexpectedly remedies an upset stomach that has persisted for several
              days! (OJ 1/6, p. 36: March 30, 1907 ‒ the first seder in 1907 took place on Friday
              March 29)</q>
          </cit></p>
        <p>During the period after <ref cRef="entity-000771">Jeanette Kornfeld</ref> left her first
          husband to be with Heinrich (1910-), Julia accepted and befriended Jeanette when others in
          Heinrich's circle ostracized her.</p>
        <p>Julia was housed with <ref cRef="entity-000775">Wilhelm Schenker</ref> and his wife <ref
            cRef="entity-000767">Dodi</ref> in <ref cRef="entity-002301">Kautzen</ref> iin the three
          years leading to her death on December 22, 1917, and Heinrich was much involved in the
          burial ritual (in <ref cRef="entity-002323">Waidhofen an der Thaya</ref>, a town not far
          from Kautzen that had a Jewish cemetery), the saying of Kaddisch, and the erection of the
          gravestone (diary for December 1917, January/February 1918, <hi rend="italic"
          >passim</hi>). In 1918, Schenker tried to have the coffin transported from Waidhofen to
          Vienna, but the cost proved too high.</p>

        <p>Heinrich and Jeanette visited Julia's grave for the first time on September 13, 1923 (OJ
          5/45, [4]) and recorded the following description: <cit>
            <q>The gravestone is simple, but dignified; since the marble slab and the engraving
              break with orthodoxy, Lie-Liechen is right in wishing for a frame and ivy decoration.
              It made me uneasy to feel that my poor mother, who was the one to hold us together for
              so long after the death of my father, lies far from us children, as if unreachable!
              Fate played a bad enough role in the very last years, so it would have been fair if it
              had granted her a resting place where the purpose of her life could have continued as
              if symbolically. (OJ 3/4, p. 2567)</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
              Tagebüchern und Briefen ...</title> (Hildesheim: G. Olms, 1985) </bibl>
          <bibl>Schenker's diaries, esp. OJ 2/9, pp. 812-17 (Dec 22-23, 1917) and OJ 2/10, pp.
            822-24 (Jan 3, 1918)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Ian Bent and Marko Deisinger</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
