<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000643">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>(Julius) Reinhard Oppel</title>
        <title type="sub">Grünberg, Oberhessen, November 13, 1878; died Leipzig, November 21,
          1941</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="oppel_reinhard">Oppel, Reinhard</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>17/06/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Oppel ~ H+JSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">Oppel ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">Oppel ~ JSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">oppel_reinhard</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>(Julius) Reinhard Oppel</head>

      <div>
        <p>German composer, music historian, theorist, and performer; friend of, and collaborator
          with, Heinrich Schenker.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>

        <p>Oppel was born in 1878 in Grünberg, 80km (50 miles) north of <ref cRef="entity-002495"
            >Frankfurt-am-Main</ref>, his father being a local school teacher and amateur musician.
          In 1884 the family moved to Groß-Gerau, south of <ref cRef="entity-002495">Frankfurt</ref>
          and close to <ref cRef="entity-004486">Darmstadt</ref>, where Reinhard attended the
          Gymnasium. During this period he became proficient in piano, organ, and violin.
          Thereafter, he studied at the <ref cRef="entity-002625">Hoch Conservatory in
            Frankfurt</ref> (1897–1900) under the music theorist <ref cRef="entity-000452">Iwan
            Knorr</ref>. At this time he also became acquainted with <ref cRef="entity-008291"
            >Arnold Mendelssohn</ref>, church music director in <ref cRef="entity-004486"
            >Darmstadt</ref>, who had a life-long influence upon him, and through him became
          acquainted with <ref cRef="entity-006121">Josef Knettel</ref>, who was to be his closest
          friend and advocate. Oppel subsequently worked as organist and choirmaster at a Lutheran
          church near <ref cRef="entity-002603">Bonn</ref> (1903–09), then completed a doctorate at
          the University of Munich with a dissertation on the Renaissance composer Jacob Meiland
          (1911).</p>

        <p>From 1911 to 1924 he taught composition and theory at the <ref cRef="entity-002608">Kiel
            Conservatory</ref>, his work there interrupted by war service on the eastern and western
          fronts (1914–19) – Schenker remarks that “Captain” Oppel “was decorated with the Iron
          Cross” and fought “in the trenches on the front line” (<ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-6-8_9">OJ 6/8, [9]</ref>, December 24, 1931, to <ref cRef="entity-000913">Moriz
            Violin</ref>). One of his colleagues at the <ref cRef="entity-002608">Kiel
            Conservatory</ref> was <ref cRef="entity-000287">Richard Glas</ref>, head of the piano
          masterclass, who became a long-term friend and exponent of and advocate for his
          compositions.</p>

        <p>Having completed his <hi rend="italic">Habilitation</hi> (<title level="m">Beiträge zur
            Melodielehre</title>) in 1924, he taught music theory and history as a Privatdozent at
          the <ref cRef="entity-002968">University of Kiel</ref> (1924–31). Overlapping with his
          time at <ref cRef="entity-002757">Kiel</ref> was a post at the <ref cRef="entity-002872"
            >Leipzig Conservatory</ref> (1927–38), where one of his more gifted pupils was <ref
            cRef="entity-000299">Theo Goos</ref>, who took a keen interest in Schenker’s theories,
          and where through the <ref cRef="entity-005889">Leipzig Gewandhaus</ref> he befriended
            <ref cRef="entity-000268">Wilhelm Furtwängler</ref>. At the <ref cRef="entity-002872"
            >Conservatory</ref>, where in Schenker’s words he was to “implement my system completely
          – harmony, counterpoint, analysis etc." (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-89-1_2">OJ
            89/1, [2]</ref>, August 12, 1927, to Anthony van <ref cRef="entity-000380"
          >Hoboken</ref>), he took a reactionary stance against the modernism of the “<ref
            cRef="entity-000695">Reger</ref>-clique,” and in 1937/38 relinquished his position in
          protest at the removal from the <ref cRef="entity-002887">University of Leipzig</ref> of
          another friend, philosophy professor Theodor Litt, by the National Socialists. In <ref
            cRef="entity-002479">Leipzig</ref> itself, he played the organ at evangelical and
          catholic churches, and until 1938 one of its synagogues. Oppel was a keen swimmer and
          mountain hiker, and loved the <ref cRef="entity-002334">Tyrol</ref>, something that he
          encouraged in his sons.</p>

        <p>Oppel was married four times: to <ref cRef="entity-008528">Käthe Brebeck</ref> (1906-10),
            <ref cRef="entity-006150">Gertrud Bandelow</ref> (from 1911 until her death in 1925),
            <ref cRef="entity-008529">Käthe Eggeling</ref> (1926–28), and <ref cRef="entity-005266"
            >Elfriede Dey</ref> (1930–41 at his death). He had a total of eight children, two of
          whom were adopted. (For further details, see <ref cRef="entity-004801">Oppel
          family</ref>). Despite debilitating travel between <ref cRef="entity-002757">Kiel</ref>
          and <ref cRef="entity-002479">Leipzig</ref> in the overlap years 1927–1931, he was very
          much a family man; the correspondence documents a special fondness for his sons <ref
            cRef="entity-000644">Ulrich</ref>, <ref cRef="entity-003957">Walter</ref> and <ref
            cRef="entity-008523">“Bepo” (Kurt)</ref>. He had for some years suffered from <foreign
            xml:lang="lat">angina pectoris</foreign> and died in 1941 of a heart attack; his grave
          is in the main cemetery in <ref cRef="entity-002495">Frankfurt</ref>.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Oppel and Schenker</head>

        <p>Oppel was not formally a pupil of Heinrich Schenker: he appears in Schenker's lessonbooks
          as receiving instruction only between August 7 and 12, 1931 (OC 3/4), when he visited the
          Schenkers during their summer holiday, though he is mentioned there briefly in February
          1914 (when Schenker seems to have shown <ref cRef="entity-000201">Elias</ref> and <ref
            cRef="entity-000951">Weisse</ref> an Oppel composition). However, his correspondence
          with Schenker had begun in October 1913, and contact between the two men was particularly
          strong in the 1920s and 1930s, and after Schenker's death he maintained the correspondence
          with <ref cRef="entity-000771">Schenker’s widow</ref> (1935–39). As an avid and
          knowledgeable reader not only in the field of music but of philosophy, politics, history,
          and also of literature, he regularly drew Schenker’s attention to items that might
          interest him, sometimes sending him copies of books he had recently read.</p>

        <p>Most particularly, Oppel assisted Schenker in the preparatory work for the latter's <ref
            cRef="entity-003331"><title level="m">Brahms, Oktaven und Quinten u. a.</title></ref>
          (1929–33). He obtained Brahms autograph manuscript in August 1930 and set to work until
          January 1931 and again February to March, locating the cited passages of parallel fifths
          and octaves in published editions, commenting on them, conducting searches in libraries,
          and sending material to Schenker. Oppel and Schenker had a final consultation when Oppel
          visited <ref cRef="entity-002292">Galtür</ref> in August 1931. The work was published in
          April 1933, with no acknowledgment of his contribution.</p>

        <p>Oppel shared Schenker's belief in the place of aristocracy in society and his fervent
          nationalism. At times he expressed enthusiasm for <ref cRef="entity-003109">Adolf
            Hitler</ref>’s actions – even as late as April 1938 (<ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-13-10_198">OJ 13/10, 198</ref>), when he welcomed the annexation of Austria to
          National-Socialist Germany (though he did this largely for personal reasons) – but he
          became disenchanted with German politics soon after the Nazis seized power. He appears to
          have resisted joining the Party, although in 1933 he served as the chair of a cell (<hi
            rend="italic">Zellenobmann</hi>) of the party rewriting the history of the <ref
            cRef="entity-002872">Leipzig Conservatory</ref>.</p>

        <p>He was the first to give officially advertized university and conservatory courses in
          Schenkerian theory, in both <ref cRef="entity-002757">Kiel</ref> and <ref
            cRef="entity-002479">Leipzig</ref>, preceding by several years those given by <ref
            cRef="entity-000913">Moriz Violin</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-000143">Felix-Eberhard von
            Cube</ref> in <ref cRef="entity-002589">Hamburg</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-000951"
            >Weisse</ref> in <ref cRef="entity-002873">New York</ref>, and he planned, but never
          completed, a manual of Schenkerian analysis. He had aspirations to bring Schenker to <ref
            cRef="entity-002479">Leipzig</ref> to teach, but circumstances in <ref
            cRef="entity-002479">Leipzig</ref> prevented it.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Oppel as Composer and Historian</head>

        <p>Oppel’s body of compositions embraced orchestral (all only fragmentary), chamber and solo
          instrumental music, song with piano accompaniment, and choral works sacred and secular.
          His music was taken seriously by several publishers and reached the public in concert and
          radio performances. His chamber music included four string quartets (No. 4 published by
            <ref cRef="entity-002422">Edition Peters</ref>), widely promoted by the Schulze-Prisca
          Quartet, a String Quintet, a Wind Serenade (Op. 30), an Oboe Quartet, works for solo
          violin, solo viola, solo cello (Opp. 12, 14, 19), violin with piano (Opp. 20, 24, 36),
          sets of solo piano pieces (Opp. 21, 26, 27, 28 published by <ref cRef="entity-002890"
            >Breitkopf &amp; Härtel</ref>, Opp. 30, and 31 published by <ref cRef="entity-008512"
            >Mühlau</ref>, some promoted by <ref cRef="entity-000287">Richard Glas</ref>), and three
          piano sonatas. His vocal works included sets of solo songs, male-voice and mixed-voice
          secular choruses, and sacred choral works, some published by Vandehoeck &amp; Ruprecht and
          several promoted by <ref cRef="entity-006121">Josef Knettel</ref> in the Rhineland. Oppel
          also composed a set of waltzes for <ref cRef="entity-000771">Jeanette Schenker</ref> in
          gratitude for her kindness, which she and Heinrich had decoratively bound as a sign of
          their appreciation of their artistic and personal value.</p>

        <p>Oppel published articles on many Renaissance and Baroque subjects in journals including
          the <title level="j">Zeitschrift für Musikwissenschaft</title>, the <title level="j">Neue
            Zeitschrift für Musik</title>, and the <title level="j">Bach-Jahrbuch</title>.</p>

      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Schenker and Others</head>

        <p>Correspondence with Heinrich Schenker spans 1913–35, and with <ref cRef="entity-000771"
            >Jeanette Schenker</ref> 1933–39, survives as OJ 13/10 (approximately 215 letters,
          postcards, and other items), and three other letters as OC 24/9 (1921), 52/637 and 52/640
          (1925). Only one letter from Schenker to Oppel (from 1932) is known to survive; its
          length, at eleven pages (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="ROC-K-5-14">ROC K/5, 14</ref>),
          perhaps indicates the value Schenker placed on this correspondence. One letter survives
          from Oppel to <ref cRef="entity-000412">Oswald Jonas</ref> as OJ 36/198, [1] (1935), and
          one letter from Oppel to <ref cRef="entity-000913">Moriz Violin</ref> as OJ 70/30, [1]
          (1931). Seven photographs of him, with and without family, survive as OJ 72/11, ranging
          from 1907 to 1938.</p>

        <p>Oppel's surviving papers, including compositions and substantial sets of correspondence
          to other recipients, are preserved in the Reinhard Oppel Collection at the University of
          North Texas, Denton, Willis Library (ROC).</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Bibliography:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>Articles in the <title level="j">Bach-Jahrbuch</title> (of which <title level="a"
              >Das Thema der Violinchaconne und seine Verwandten,</title>
            <title level="j">Bach-Jahrbuch (1918)</title>, 97-116 is preserved as OJ 34/6)</bibl>

          <bibl>Articles in the <title level="j">Neue Zeitschrift fur Musik</title></bibl>

          <bibl>Articles in the <title level="j">Zeitschrift für Musikwissenschaft</title></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="a">(Julius) Reinard Oppel,</title> in <title level="m">Schenker
              Traditionen: Eine Wiener Schule der Musiktheorie und ihre internationale
              Verbreitung</title>, eds. <editor>M. Eybl</editor> &amp; <editor>E.
              Fink-Mennel</editor> (Vienna: Böhlau, 2006), p. 244</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Jackson, Timothy L.</author>, <title level="a">Heinrich Schenker as
              Composition Teacher: The Schenker-Oppel Exchange,</title>
            <title level="j">Music Analysis</title> 20/1 (March 2001), 1-115</bibl>


          <bibl><title level="m">MGG</title></bibl>

          <bibl><title level="m">NGDM2</title> (2001 and online)</bibl>

          <bibl><ref type="external"
              target="https://www.lexm.uni-hamburg.de/object/lexm_lexmperson_00001361%3Bjsessionid=mjipyniv254?wcmsID=0003&amp;XSL.lexmlayout.SESSION=lexmperson_act"
              >University of Hamburg, Institute for Historical Musicology, LexM, “Reinhard
              Oppel”</ref> [biography, list or compositions, list of writings, sources]</bibl>

          <bibl><ref type="external"
              target="https://digital.library.unt.edu/explore/collections/OPPEL/">Reinhard Oppel
              Collection in UNT Digital Library. University of North Texas Libraries</ref></bibl>

          <bibl><ref type="external" target="https://txarchives.org/untmlsc/finding_aids/00101.xml "
              >UNT Music Library: Reinhard Oppel Collection</ref></bibl>

        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>

  </text>
</TEI>
