<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-003210">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Josef Redlich</title>
        <title type="sub">born Göding, June 18, 1869; died Vienna, Nov 11, 1936</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="redlich_josef">Redlich, Josef</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>27/10/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">redlich_josef</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Josef Redlich</head>
      <div>

        <p> Austrian-Jewish jurist, politician, and academic, with the rank of Privy Counselor
          (Geheimrat); father of Hans Ferdinand Redlich. </p>

        <div>
          <head>Career Summary</head>
          <p>Josef Redlich studied law at the University of Vienna and received his doctorate in
            1891, thereafter pursuing a career in constitutional and administrative law. From 1901
            he lectured in law at the University of Vienna, being appointed associate professor
            (außerordentlicher Professor) in 1907, and later full professor, and from 1908 he taught
            constitutional and administrative law at the Technical Hochschule in Vienna. In 1907 and
            1911‒18 he served in the Austrian parliament, and was briefly Minister of Finance in
            1918. In 1918‒19 he was a delegate in the provisional assembly for the formation of a
            German-Austrian state. 1931‒36 he was a deputy judge at the International Court of
            Justice in the Hague, and in 1931 served briefly again as Minister of Finance in the
            Austrian federal government. Between 1926 and 1935 he also taught at Harvard
            University.</p>
          <p>He was a man of culture, in close touch with such leaders at Hermann Bahr, Hugo von
            Hoffmannsthal, and Theodor Herzl. His son was the musicologist Hans Ferdinand Redlich
            (1903‒68), specialist in the music of Monteverdi and of Austria in the late 19th and
            early 20th centuries. </p>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>Redlich and Schenker</head>

          <p>Redlich is mentioned in Schenker's diary on November 6, 1906 ("At the home of Dr.
            Spieler (Grandmaster of the lodge): clarification given regarding his withdrawal from
            the lodge: for personal (Redlich-Gärtner) as well as substantive reasons, engaged in the
            most candid critique; stayed there for two hours."), December 29, 1926 ("Gärtner invites
            C.[?] Redlich; he declines."), and February 17, 1907 ("Exceptionally, at Privy Counselor
            Redlich's place, played with companions' quartet. Unbearable atmosphere; good looks made
            for bad playing.") </p>

        </div>
      </div>
    </body>


    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources: </head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="j">Wikipedia</title> ("Josef Redlich") (April 30, 2010)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="j">MGG1</title> ("Redlich, Hans Ferdinand") </bibl>
          <bibl><title level="j">Oxford Music Online</title> ("Redlich, Hans Ferdinand") (Arthur D.
            Walker) </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Ian Bent</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

    </back>



  </text>
</TEI>
