<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-000356">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Emil Hertzka</title>
        <title type="sub">born Budapest, August 3, 1869; died Vienna, May 9, 1932</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="hertzka_emil">Hertzka, Emil</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>26/01/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Hertzka ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">UE ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">hertzka_emil</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Emil Hertzka</head>
      <div>
        <p>Viennese music publisher.</p>
        <p>As Director of <ref cRef="entity-002408">Universal Edition</ref> from 1907 to 1932,
          Hertzka fashioned the company into one of the leading music publishing houses of the 20th
          century, his fame resting primarily on his advocacy of the more progressive composers at
          the turn of the 20th century, and especially of the members of the Second Viennese School
          (Schoenberg, Berg, Webern), Weill, Bartók, and Janáček.</p>
        <p>
          <hi rend="bold">Hertzka and Universal Edition</hi>
        </p>
        <p>Born in Budapest, Hertzka studied chemistry, and also music and literature, at the
          University of Vienna. In 1893, he joined the music publishing firm of Weinberger (some
          sources say that he first joined the publisher and concert agency Gustav Léwy,
          which sold out to Weinberger in 1897), the proprietor of which, Josef Weinberger, was one
          of the founding subscribers of Universal Edition, Vienna. UE was formed in 1901 through
          the collaboration of three existing publishers, Josef Weinberger, Adolf Robitschek, and
          Bernhard Herzmansky (of Ludwig Doblinger), with the aim of creating Austrian editions of
          Classical composers, and providing educational materials for schools. After six years, the
          company was on the brink of failing when, in 1907, Hertzka was brought in to rescue it.
          While maintaining the two original lines, he moved contemporary music to the center of its
          enterprise. By sound judgement, a keen sense of publishing politics, and skillful
          negotiation, he identified many of the leading progressive and avant-garde composers. By
          entering into agreements with other companies (e.g. Eberle, Josef Aibl, Fürstner,
          Bote &amp; Bock, Simrock) in the first few years, offering contracts to progressive
          composers (e.g. Mahler, Schoenberg, Schreker, Foerster), with many of whom he forged
          strong personal bonds, and adopting aggressive advertising strategies, Hertzka brought to
          UE the profile that it has had ever since as the leading publisher of contemporary music.</p>
        <p>Later, Hertzka launched in-house journals--<ref cRef="musikpadagogische_z">
            <title level="j">Musikpädagogische Zeitschrift</title>
          </ref> (1911), <title level="j">Musica divina</title> (1913), <ref cRef="musikblatter_des_anb">
            <title level="j">Musikblätter des Anbruch</title>
          </ref> (1919), <title level="j">Pult und Taktstock</title> (1924), and <title level="j">Schrifttanz</title> (1927)--which offered publicity and forums for discussion of UE's
          catalog, and by acquiring the publishers <ref cRef="entity-002456">A. J. Gutmann</ref>
          in 1920 and Philharmonischer Verlag in 1927 he extended UE's range significantly. As a
          result of all these developments, UE became a principal publisher of the music of Reger,
          Richard Strauss, Mahler, Bruckner, Szymanovski, Zemlinsky, Schreker, Josef Marx, Godowsky,
          Delius, Milhaud, Respighi, Krenek, Weill and other late-19th and early-20th-century
          composers, in addition to almost all of the leading "modern" composers (with the notable
          exceptions of Stravinsky and Hindemith).</p>

        <p>Ernst Roth, who worked with him at Universal Edition for seven years, has the following
          description of the man: <cit>
            <q>Emil Hertzka was a strange man, a mixture of commercial astuteness and rash idealism.
              [. . .] His appearance seemed to contradict his actions: he looked as old-fashioned as
              any <hi rend="italic">fin-de-siècle</hi> artist, with his long hair, long beard, brown
              velvet jacket and large black tie – a majestic figure, half Wotan and half Brahms, who
              contrasted strangely with the revolutionary music […]; his thin, sharp voice seemed
              not to belong to his imposing figure. He was not a kindly or genial man but displayed
              a biting and often cynical sarcasm [. . .]. [H]e did what no other music-publisher at
              that time dared to do, and considerable sums of money were spent not only on
              engraving, printing, paper, binding and publicity but also on supporting financially
              the struggling prophets of the new art. All this was done without charm, grace or
              warmheartedness, without any evident generosity – and yet it was still a unique
              undertaking. </q>
          </cit></p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Hertzka and Schenker</head>
        <p>Schenker was recruited as an editor in 1901 to UE, with whom he published his edition of
          C. P. E. Bach keyboard pieces and <title level="m">Beitrag zur Ornamentik</title> (1903).
          His first publication under Hertzka was the <ref cRef="entity-001729">
            <title level="m">Instrumentations-Tabelle</title>
          </ref> (pseudonymous author "Artur Niloff") (1908), followed by his edition of J. S.
          Bach's <title level="m">Chromatic Fantasy &amp; Fugue</title> (1910). Herztka's
          arrival in 1907 rapidly created an environment wholly inimical to Schenker, and it was
          inevitable that the two men would come into conflict. Schenker goaded Hertzka with such
          remarks as that UE was a publisher "that places its main emphasis these days on
          anti-musical music" (WSLB 52, February 7, 1910). Hertzka's driven management style and use
          of modern publishing techniques (of which the typewriter was a symbol) irked Schenker, and
          it was perhaps the advertising of Schoenberg's Second String Quartet and <title level="m">Klavierstücke</title>, Op. 11 in the 1910 catalog that marked the first
          decisive moment at which Schenker turned against the Director. Hertzka clearly valued
          Schenker's work, and was unfailingly courteous in his dealings with him; nevertheless
          Schenker showed increasing acrimony toward him throughout the 1910s, alternating with
          brief reconciliations during which Schenker articulated his vision for UE as the leading
          music publisher in Europe. At the same, time, Schenker always insisted on corresponding
          only with Hertzka rather than with other officials of UE.</p>
        <p>Hertzka's slowness to take up Schenker's planned <ref cRef="entity-001758">
            <title level="m">Kleine Bibliothek</title>
          </ref> (first mooted in 1912) brought the two men to another crisis point in 1914 (diary,
          OJ 2/9-10, pp. 821-23, December 24, 1914). When the project eventually came to publication
          in 1921-24 as <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>, Hertzka used A. J. Gutmann as a
          shield for UE, employing the fictional imprint "Tonwille-Flugblätterverlag."
          Schenker resented this and Hertzka's exerting of editorial control, calling him "wrong,
          biased, and terroristic" (OC 52/574, February 20, 1923), and accusing him of censorship as
          well as of administrative incompetence and falsifying accounts. Schenker resorted to an
          attorney in Fall 1924 in preparation for legal proceedings against UE, but after a year of
          recriminations, a settlement was agreed on December 10, 1925 that resulted in <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title> being continued with Drei Masken Verlag of Munich under
          the title <title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</title> (1925, 1926, 1930). After
          a four-year silence between the two men, correspondence began again in December 1928, and
          eventually normal civilities were restored; UE became Schenker's principal publisher
          again, issuing <title level="m">Der freie Satz</title> posthumously in 1935, three years
          after Hertzka's death.</p>
        <p>Hertzka was Jewish. Like Schenker, and most Viennese Jews at the time, he sought to
          assimilate into German culture. He was, however, a cosmopolitan Jew, nurturing an
          international network of business and cultural relationships within and beyond Europe, and
          traveling frequently to forge deals, develop personal contacts, and attend important
          performances; Schenker, conversely, was a German nationalist, detested the Romance and
          Anglo-Saxon nations, and saw commerce and trade as detrimental to the world of the mind
          and to the arts. Hertzka was a pacifist and believed in democracy; Schenker had
          militaristic tendencies and believed in rule by an enlightened aristocracy. Hertzka was
          optimistic about the future of music; Schenker saw all about him only signs of its
          downfall.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>
        <p>Correspondence between Hertzka and Schenker is one of the largest exchanges of letters
          among Schenker's papers. It covers 1908 to 1931, and survives as most of the items from
          Schenker to UE, WSLB 1-444, and much of correspondence from UE to Schenker, OC 52/1-939.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="a">Hertzka, Ehepaar,</title> in <title level="m">OeML</title> Online</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Simeone, Nigel</author>, <title level="a">Universal Edition,</title>
            <title level="m">NGDM2</title> (2001 and online)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">25 Jahre Neue Musik: Jahrbuch 1926 der Universal-Edition</title>,
            eds. <editor>H. Heinsheimer</editor> &amp; <editor>P. Stefan</editor> (Vienna: UE,
            1926)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">UE: Universal Edition 1901-2001</title> (Vienna: UE, 2000)</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
              Tagebücher ...</title> (Hildesheim: Olms, 1985), esp. pp. 31-34 (biography),
            320-23 („Kaufmannsstand-Handel")</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Bent, Ian</author>, <title level="a">'That Bright New Light': Schenker,
              Universal Edition, and the Origins of the Erläuterung Series, 1901-1910,</title>
            <title level="j">Journal of the American Musicological Society</title> 58/1 (Spring
            2005), 69-138</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Drabkin, William</author> &amp; <author>Bent, Ian</author>, General
            Prefaces to <title level="j">Der Tonwille: Pamphlets in Witness ...</title>, ed.
              <editor>William Drabkin</editor> (New York: Oxford University Press, 2004, 2005, I,
            v-viii, II, v-xii [recounts conflict over <title level="j">Tonwille</title>]</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Roth, Ernst</author>, <title level="m">The Business of Music: Reflections of
              a Music Publisher</title> (London: Cassell, 1969), pp.60–61; Ger. edn, <title level="m">Musik als Kunst und Ware: Betrachtungen und Begegnungen eines
            Musikverlegers</title> (Zürich: Atlantis, 1966), pp. 66–67</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
