<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000767">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Dodi (Dorothea?) Schenker</title>
        <title type="sub">died c. 10 July, 1923</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="schenker_dodi">Schenker, Dodi</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>28/10/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">schenker_dodi</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Dodi (Dorothea?) Schenker</head>
      <div>
        <p>First wife of <ref cRef="entity-000775">Wilhelm Schenker</ref>, thus Heinrich's
          sister-in-law; mother of <ref cRef="entity-008468">Wilma</ref>. Nothing is known of Dodi’s
          family history; however, in a letter of 1938, <ref cRef="entity-000775">Wilhelm</ref>
          refers to <ref cRef="entity-000053">Jetty Bednař</ref> as “our sister-in-law,” and since
            <ref cRef="entity-000053">Jetty</ref> first appears in Heinrich Schenker’s diary in
          1915, and is a regular presence there from then on, frequently in connection with Dodi, it
          is likely Dodi and <ref cRef="entity-000053">Jetty</ref> were sisters. Their maiden names
          are unknown.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Children and relationships</head>
        <p>Before his first marriage (date unknown), <ref cRef="entity-000775">Wilhelm</ref>
          evidently formed a close attachment to a <ref cRef="entity-008443">Mrs.
            Schimatowitsch</ref> who, around 1879, had a son, <ref cRef="entity-000895"
            >Tonschl</ref> (father unknown), who himself in 1907 and 1911 had sons <ref
            cRef="entity-003491">Tonerl</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-008438">Karli</ref> (mother
          unknown). While precise chronology is unclear, Dodi and <ref cRef="entity-000775"
            >Wilhelm</ref> took the two young boys into their home and helped educate them and seek
          careers for them.</p>

        <p><ref cRef="entity-000775">Wilhelm</ref> and Dodi had, so far is known, just one child:
            <ref cRef="entity-008468">Wilma</ref>, born May c.27, 1915. She is named only once in
          Heinrich’s diary, on May 28, 1917: <cit>
            <q>
              <ref cRef="entity-000775">Wilhelm</ref>'s name day [William of Acquitaine died May 28,
              812] is celebrated, at the same time as that of little <ref cRef="entity-008468"
                >Wilma</ref>, in keeping with the custom of the village and the house, with personal
              congratulations, cakes, and the like. <ref cRef="entity-008468">Wilma</ref> was given
              flowers by her little brothers.</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>Nothing further is heard of <ref cRef="entity-008468">Wilma</ref>, though in 1918
          Heinrich hears from the parents that “the children” (presumably <ref cRef="entity-003491"
            >Tonerl</ref>, <ref cRef="entity-008438">Karli</ref>, and <ref cRef="entity-008468"
            >Wilma</ref>) have mumps (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-38_1">OJ 5/38,
          [1]</ref>, January 24, 1918). </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Dodi and Wilhelm</head>
        <p>Neither Dodi nor <ref cRef="entity-000775">Wilhelm</ref> appears in Heinrich’s diary
          before 1915. The couple took <ref cRef="entity-000773">Julia Schenker</ref>, who had been
          living in Vienna, into their home in <ref cRef="entity-002301">Kautzen</ref> from February
          1915 and cared for her until her death on December 20, 1917, during which Dodi reported
          increasingly erratic behavior on <ref cRef="entity-000773">Julia</ref>’s part (perhaps
          signs of dementia). After <ref cRef="entity-000773">Julia</ref>’s death, there was
          dissension among family and friends as to whether she had been properly cared for at that
          time. From 1916 for several years, Dodi supplied Jeanette with butter, eggs, and other
          foodstuffs, which were scarce in Vienna (as too did <ref cRef="entity-000319">Sophie
            Guttmann</ref>). </p>

        <p>In addition to the <ref cRef="entity-002936">Bednař family</ref>. Dodi and <ref
            cRef="entity-000775">Wilhelm</ref> also used <ref cRef="entity-003354">Mr. and Mrs.
            Grueber</ref>, who lived in Vienna, as intermediaries to Heinrich and Jeanette, and may
          have stayed at their address.</p>

        <p>Between 1920 and 1923 there is no word of Dodi in Heinrich’s diary. Then on June 3, 1923
            <ref cRef="entity-000051">Albin Bednař snr</ref> reported in person to Heinrich and <ref
            cRef="entity-000772">Jeanette</ref> “Dodi’s serious illness” and on June 10 her
          death.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence</head>
        <p>Heinrich’s diary records twenty-four letters and postcards received from Dodi during
          1915–20, and many written to her. None of these are known to survive, but among the
          letters from Heinrich and Jeanette to Wilhelm (OJ 5/38) are paragraphs addressed directly
          to her. </p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
