<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000201">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Angelika [Angelica; Angi] (Rifka) Elias</title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, September 25, 1882; died Ravensbrück, January 13,
          1944</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="elias_angelika">Elias, Angelika</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>19/06/2006</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Elias ~ H+JSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">Elias ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">Elias ~ JSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">elias_angelika</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Angelika [Angelica; Angi] (Rifka) Elias</head>
      <p>Turkish-born Austrian-Jewish pianist and music teacher. Schenker's longest-term pupil and
        one of his most devoted patrons.</p>

      <div>
        <head>Life</head>
        <p>Angi [pronounced An-dj-i] Elias (the diminutive form of name seems to have been almost
          universally used) was Jewish and of Turkish citizenship, born in Vienna. Her parents were
          Heinrich Menachem Elias (c.1841‒1901) and <ref cRef="entity-000202">Rachel</ref> (<hi
            rend="italic">née</hi> Russo) (1853‒1934). Angi had five older sisters, Valerie Grassia,
          Ida, Melanie Miriam, Sofie Anna, and Elsa Ester (all later married), and two younger
          brothers, <ref cRef="entity-000203">Manolo Menachem</ref> and Jacques, all born in either
          Vienna or Bucharest.</p>

        <p>Her father Heinrich and his two brothers, Abraham Menachem (1839‒1908) and Jacques
          Menachem (1844‒1923) were proprietors of the firm A. H. Elias Brothers, wholesale
          merchants of Turkish goods, located, at the time of Angi's birth, at Vienna I, Hafnersteig
          5. By 1890 the firm had moved to Augustengasse 4 (both addresses close to the Josefs-Kai
          and Danube canal). The firm steadily prospered, becoming by 1910 a registered "bank and
          commissioning business." It continued through World War I under Jacques as the sole
          propietor, but seems to have collapsed in 1920.</p>

        <p>In 1921 Jacques moved to the nearby Gölsdorfgasse 4, which is the address given in the
          earliest letters of Angi to Heinrich Schenker. Angi continued to live at that address, and
          after Jacques' death became the resident of record. Her mother's death in August 1934 is
          referred to in <ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-10-18_8">OJ 10/18, [8]</ref> and
          Schenker's diary. In 1936 she moved to Vienna XIII, Nikolausgasse 1, and remained there
          until 1941 after which she disappears from the Vienna street directory. She perished in
          the Ravensbrück concentration camp in 1944. (Of her sisters, Melanie died in the camp in
          Riga, and Sofie committed suicide in Vienna in 1938.)</p>

        <p>First evidence of Elias giving lessons herself occurs early in 1918, the lessons in
          question being in music theory (diary, February 28, March 2, 9, 16). Schenker probably
          steered other pupils in her direction, and certainly advised her on what fees to charge.
          Her close friend, <ref cRef="entity-000416">Marianne Kahn</ref>, with whom she
          occasionally took holidays, and after Schenker's death visited his grave every June 19,
          was also a piano teacher.</p>

        <p>Schenker’s diary for Mary 16, 1916 casts some light on the life style of the Elias
          family: <cit>
            <q>Miss Kahn tells me some things about the Elias family that can probably be regarded
              as the most shocking effect of wealth. Their day does not begin before 12:30 in the
              afternoon; at this time they have breakfast, at 2:30 they eat lunch, and after the
              meal they chat in the presence of countless aunts, so that only a short span of time –
              from about 4:30 to 7 o’clock – remains for actual work or errands. In the evening they
              eat very late and again talk, and talk, and play cards until nearly 1 o’clock at
              night. Now I finally understand why the young lady so often arrives late and is always
              apologizing, and why she adopts a slow tempo in the fulfillment of her
              assignments.</q>
          </cit>
        </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Elias and Schenker</head>
        <p>Elias's first lesson with Schenker occurred in late January 1905 (Schenker's diary for
          January 28, 1925 records that Elias brings a present "in remembrance of her first lesson
          twenty years ago") ‒ lessonbooks do not exist prior to 1912. She continued having lessons
          with him to his death in 1935, taking the full package of three lessons a week, and a
          comprehensive range of instruction in piano, theory, analysis, and source studies.
          Schenker's table of her intended lessons for 1934/35 shows her still having three lessons
          per week (Tuesday morning, Thursday afternoon, Friday morning) ‒ more than any of his
          other pupils that year (Oster Collection A/262, A/259 and A/264). After Schenker's death
          in January 1935, Elias does not seem to have taken lessons at the Schenker Institute which
          operated in the <ref cRef="entity-002451">Neues Wiener Konservatorium</ref> between 1935
          and 1938.</p>

        <p>Elias was a patron of Schenker, known to have given him 10,000 Kronen in 1917 for his
          next publication, and to have offered him a yearly subvention and further support for his
          publications. She also often raised the honorarium for her lessons voluntarily, as well as
          being generous with presents, not only at Heinrich's birthday and Christmas/New Year but
          at other times. On one occasion, she also offered to give financial assistance to
          Schenker's secretarial assistant <ref cRef="entity-000599">Aron Mittelmann</ref> (diary,
          November 27, 1912). For much of her life she was evidently a wealthy woman; however, in
          1932 she experienced what <ref cRef="entity-000416">Marianne Kahn</ref> described to
          Schenker as an "extreme financial decline" (diary, June 1, 1932). Thereafter, Schenker
          reduced his fees in order to retain her. Searforce makes a case that he taught her free of
          charge in the final years (2004, pp. 10‒11).</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Elias and Voice-leading Graphs</head>
        <p>Inclusion of theoretical materials in her instruction began in 1916/17; in 1920/21
          Schenker began "Linie-Studien" with her, and discussion of the Urlinie in 1921/22. The
          year 1924/25 seems to have been a turning-point. In that year she produced "graphs" (<hi
            rend="italic">Bilder</hi>), notably "Urlinie-graphs," of which after correction she made
          "fair copies" (<hi rend="italic">Reinschriften</hi>). Between October 1924 and June 1925
          she produced graphs and fair copies of Beethoven's Piano Sonata Op. 106: then on June 24
          brought "the Urlinie graphs of movements 1, 2 and 3, together with music examples (<hi
            rend="italic">Klischees</hi>)," and in the following November produced fair copies of
          the four "sections" (<hi rend="italic">Sätze</hi>) of the fugue, followed by a "Grundplan"
          of the whole movement. Many of these materials are preserved in OC File 65, notably items
          4‒6, 12‒15 (mvt 1), 24‒25 (mvt 2), 28‒29 (mvt 3), and 43‒47 (mvt 4). The end of the work
          came on February 9, 1926, when the lessonbook records "Fugue finished," and Schenker's
          diary records: "Finished with the fugue from Op. 106 (first check though of the version
          made in <ref cRef="entity-002292">Galtür</ref>)." During the same period she also produced
          graphs of seven of the Chopin Etudes Op. 25 and Berceuse Op. 57, Brahms Waltzes Op. 39,
          and works by J. S. Bach, most of which are preserved in OC Files 10 and 34. This was a
          remarkably productive year!</p>

        <p>In the following years she produced graphs of Brahms, Intermezzo in E minor Op. 119, No.
          1 (OC 34/1), Capriccio Op. 76, No. 2 (OC 34/41‒44), and Paganini Variations, the Christe
          eleison of J. S. Bach, B minor Mass, "Ich bin's" from the <title level="m">St. Matthew
            Passion</title> (OC 81/4 and 48/18), and Keyboard Suite in E major (OC 70/4, 7‒8,
          12‒17), Beethoven, Piano Sonata in C# minor Op. 27, No. 2, movement 1, and Piano Sonata in
          E minor Op. 90, movements 1 and 2 (OC 64/46, 125‒126, 128; 129‒131), Chopin, Etudes, Op.
          10, Nos 8 and 12 (OC 10/134‒138, 147‒151), Impromptu in F# major Op. 36 (OC 10/223‒224),
          Mazurkas Op. 17, No. 4, Op. 24, Nos 1 and 3 (OC 32/5‒9, 11, 20, 22), Schenker's own
          Capriccio Op. 1, No. 2 and Andante Op. 4, No. 1 (OC 15/15‒17, 18‒22), and many other
          works. The production of all these can be tracked in the lessonbooks for 1926/27 to
          1930/31. Although many of Schenker's pupils worked on voice-leading graphs, none has left
          such a legacy behind (in the Oster Collection, there are otherwise only two graphs by <ref
            cRef="entity-000643">Reinhard Oppel</ref> and one by <ref cRef="entity-000107">Robert
            Brünauer</ref>, though many are unidentified). </p>

        <p>Of her work on Op. 106, Marston remarks: "Elias's achievement was little short of heroic,
          though the extent to which, if at all, she had any intellectual influence on Schenker's
          analysis of op. 106 cannot be ascertained. Nonetheless, her efforts mean that preserved in
          OC 65 are complete voice-leading graphs for the entire 'Hammerklavier' Sonata." (2013, p.
          38). A measure of Elias's intellectual input may perhaps come in 1928 with her work on one
          of Schenker's own pieces: The diary records: "Miss Elias brings, as an extension of her
          Christmas present, an Urlinie for my Op. 4, No. 1 that already at first glance reveals an
          excellent solution" (June 15), and "To Miss Elias, having had a better opportunity to look
          at her graph of my Op. 4 I have found it good in all but trifling details. I bestow praise
          for her perseverance, which has led her so far" (June 21).</p>

        <p>That she was not a participant in Schenker's <ref cRef="entity-002499">1931‒34
            seminar</ref> is self-explanatory: its members were all former <ref cRef="entity-000951"
            >Hans Weisse</ref> pupils: <ref cRef="entity-000754">Salzer</ref>, <ref
            cRef="entity-000473">Kral</ref>, <ref cRef="entity-002498">Kraus</ref>, and <ref
            cRef="entity-000964">Wilfort</ref>, taken over at Weisse's departure for the USA. She
          had her individual lessons with him during those years. However, there are graphs in her
          hand of four of the works comprising the <ref cRef="entity-001755"><title level="m">Fünf
              Urlinie-Tafeln / Five Analyses in Sketchform</title></ref> produced by the seminar and
          published in 1932; and on one occasion Schenker's diary (October 29, 1931 ‒ nine months
          before publication) speaks of his having "sent [...] Elias's copy" of the C major Prelude
          from Book I of the <title level="m">Well-tempered Clavier</title> to Weisse. That gives
          some credence to the widely held view that she acted as a copyist for Schenker (though in
          all four cases, she had herself studied and graphed the works in lessons). Searfoorce
          makes a case that she became more: his personal assistant (Cadwallader and Gagné suggested
          the same in 2006, p. 46), even an "equal scholar" (2004, p. 15); but there is
          tantalizingly little evidence of that. Schenker never credited her in his publications,
          but neither did he credit any of his other students.</p>

        <p>Elias made three verbal (as apart from notational) contributions to the Schenker
          literature (see Bibliography). Between April 8, 1930 and April 23, 1931 under Schenker's
          guidance she wrote a response to an article by Walter Riezler that had incorrectly
          understood Schenker's theory of the Urlinie. This, like an article of choral studies with
          Schenker, remained in typescript. Her only published article, on two piano pieces by
          Schumann, appeared in Der <title level="j">Dreiklang</title> for 1937.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>
        <p>Elias's correspondence with Heinrich Schenker is preserved as OJ 10/18, [1]‒[9] (1922–34:
          10 items), and OC 38/338, 44/18–19, 52/483, 631 (1923‒34: 5 items); that to <ref
            cRef="entity-000771">Jeanette Schenker</ref> as OJ 10/18, [10]‒[20] (1935‒39: 11 items,
          two joint with <ref cRef="entity-000416">Marianne Kahn</ref>); and that from her brother
            <ref cRef="entity-000203">Manolo</ref> to Heinrich Schenker as OJ 10/19, [1] (1934: 1
          item). </p>
      </div>
    </body>


    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Bibliography:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="a">Zwei Klavierstücke aus Schumanns 'Album für die Jugend',</title>
            <title level="j">Der Dreiklang</title> 7 (October 1937), 161-64 </bibl>
          <bibl><title level="a">Choral-Studien bei Heinrich Schenker</title> [typescript, c. 1934:
            OJ 58/7]</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="a">Widerlegung des in der 'Musik' erschienen Aufsatz 'die Urlinie' von
              Walter Riezler ‒ Stettin</title> (manuscript in Elias's hand: after OC 15/22)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>


      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>

        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Bent, Ian</author>, <title level="a">Schenker and Bach's French Suite in E
              major,</title>
            <title level="j">Music Analysis</title>, 34/2 (July 2015), 155‒74</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Cadwallader, Allen</author> and <author>Gagné, David</author>, <title
              level="a">The Spirit and Technique of Schenker Pedagogy,</title> in <title level="m"
              >Structure and Meaning in Tonal Music: Festschrift in Honor of Carl Schachter</title>,
            ed. <editor>L. Poundie Burstein</editor> and <editor>David Gagné</editor> (Hillsdale,
            NY: Pendragon Press, 2006), pp. 43‒53</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Cadwallader, Allen</author> and <author>Pastille, William</author>, <title
              level="a">Schenker's Unpublished Work on the Music of Johannes Brahms,</title> in
              <title level="m">Schenker Studies 2</title>, ed. <editor>Carl Schachter</editor> and
              <editor>Hedi Siegel</editor> (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1999), pp.
            26‒46</bibl>

          <bibl>
            <editor>Eybl, Martin</editor> &amp; <editor>Fink-Mennel, Evelyn</editor>, eds, <title
              level="m">Schenker-Traditionen</title> (Vienna: Bohlau, 2006), pp. 241-42</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Marston, Nicholas</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker and
              Beethoven's 'Hammerklavier' Sonata</title>, <title level="s">RMA Monographs</title>,
            23 (Farnham, Surrey: Ashgate/Royal Musical Association, 2013)</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Searfoorce, Michaela</author>, "<title level="u">Introducing Angelika Elias
              ‒ A Discovery in Schenkerian Studies</title>" (MMus diss., Graduate School of Ohio
            State University, 2004)</bibl>

          <bibl><ref type="external" target="http://www.orpheustrust.at/datenbank.php">Orpheus
              Trust; Datenbank NS-verfolgte Musik Primavera Gruber Wien</ref></bibl>

          <bibl><ref type="external"
              target="https://www.geni.com/people/Angelica-Elias/6000000010298758612?through=6000000010041998613"
              >Geni: "Angelica Rifka Elias" (and other family members)</ref></bibl>

          <bibl><ref type="external" target="https://www.wikitree.com/wiki/Elias-297">WikiTree:
              "Jacques Menachem Elias"</ref></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>


      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
