<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000431">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Leo Kestenberg</title>
        <title type="sub">born Rosenberg, Hungary, Nov 27, 1882; died Tel Aviv, Jan 14, 1962</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="kestenberg_leo">Kestenberg, Leo</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>08/02/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">kestenberg_leo</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Leo Kestenberg</head>
      <div>
        <p>Hungarian pianist and music educator. Kestenberg studied piano with Kullak and Busoni,
          embarked on a career as a concert pianist and taught at the Stern and
          Klindworth-Scharwenka Conservatories in Berlin.</p>

        <p>In 1918, Kestenberg became music adviser to the Prussian Ministry of Science, Culture and
          Education, and in 1922 Director of the music department of the Zentralinstitut für
          Erziehung und Unterricht (Central Institute for Education and Teaching) in Berlin. His
            <title level="m">Musikerziehung und Musikpflege</title> (Music Education and the
          Cultivation of Music) (Leipzig, 1921, 2/1927), <title level="m">Schulmusikunterricht in
            Preussen</title> (School Music Instruction in Prussia) (Berlin, 1927) and several other
          books expressed his reforming ideas about music education, many of which were incorporated
          into government policies. In the 1930s, he and <ref cRef="entity-000809">Georg
            Schünemann</ref> were involved in reforming every aspect of music education in Prussia.
          He played a role also in the development of Gebrauchsmusik, declaring that it was
          "artistically as important as, and nowadays materially more promising than, concert
          music."</p>

        <p>As a Jew, he left Germany for Prague in 1934, and in 1938 moved to Tel Aviv, where he
          became general manager of the Palestine Symphony Orchestra while continuing his
          music-educational work.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Kestenberg and Schenker's Circle and Correspondence</head>
        <p>It was Kestenberg who, at the instigation of <ref cRef="entity-000268">Wilhelm
            Furtwängler</ref>, invited <ref cRef="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</ref> to deliver a
          lecture at the Central Institute in 1930. Copies in <ref cRef="entity-000771">Jeanette
            Schenker</ref>'s hand of two letters from him to Weisse, in which he evinces sympathy with
          Schenker's ideas, are preserved at OJ 71/20, [1] and [2] (July 15 and August 4, 1930).
          (Weisse's replies are not known to survive. There is no known correspondence between
          Kestenberg and Schenker.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Source:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">NGDM2</title></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>


  </text>
</TEI>
