<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000748">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Lothar Riedinger</title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, November 8, 1888; died Vienna, October 2, 1964</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="riedinger_lothar">Riedinger, Lothar</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>20/02/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">riedinger</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Lothar Riedinger</head>
      <div>
        <p>Austrian musicologist, singer (tenor), conductor, and composer. </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>

        <p>Riedinger studied musicology at the University of Vienna with <ref cRef="entity-000003"
            >Guido Adler</ref>. He completed his doctorate in 1913 with a dissertation "Carl von
          Dittersdorf als Opernkomponist." Although self-taught as a composer, Riedinger must have
          received training as a singer because he made numerous appearances as a concert soloist in
          the Vienna Konzerthaus between 1914 and 1930. He was engaged at the Brno Opera as a lyric
          tenor 1918–20 and subsequently in Cologne, Hamburg, Stuttgart, Hannover as well as at the
          Theater an der Wien and the Vienna Volksoper. From about 1928 on, he worked for the
          Austrian Radio, was instrumental in studio performances of rarely performed operas and
          operettas, and also occasionally at the popular music department at the Austrian Radio. </p>

        <p>Riedinger composed, among other things, incidental music for radio productions of
          theatrical works, and his broadcast series of radio potpourris was a success. His Symphony
          in E-flat major, composed 1914 (rev. 1927) had its first performance in Vienna in the
          Großer Musikvereinsaal. </p>

        <p>Riedinger was a friend of <ref cRef="entity-000274">Eduard Gärtner</ref>, at whose death
          he wrote the obituary "Aus Eduard Gärtners Leben" for the <ref cRef="entity-002561"><title
              level="j">Neues Wiener Tagblatt</title></ref> (No. 200 July 26, 1918). </p>
      </div>


      <div>
        <head>Riedinger and Schenker</head>
        <p>Riedinger is referred to in Schenker's diary (where his name is incorrectly spelled
          "Rüdinger"), but always in connection with either Eduard Gärtner or Hans Gärtner. Hans
          Gärtner approached Schenker to procure for Riedinger a spoken or written recommendation to
            <ref cRef="entity-000098">Paul Breisach</ref>, who was, in his turn, to act as an
          intermediary to Richard Strauss.There seems to have been no direct contact between
          Riedinger and Schenker, nor is any correspondence known to have existed. </p>
      </div>


    </body>
    <back>

      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">OeMl</title> (online)</bibl>
          <bibl>Wikipedia ("Nederlands")</bibl>
          <bibl>private communication from Prof. Gary Tucker</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>


      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Marko Deisinger</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
