<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000420">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Alfred Kalmus</title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, May 16, 1889; died London, Sept 25, 1972</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="kalmus_alfred">Kalmus, Alfred</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>10/09/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Kalmus ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">kalmus_alfred</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Alfred Kalmus</head>
      <div>
        <p>Austrian (later English) music publisher.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Kalmus was Jewish, and was related to the Wittgenstein family (see <ref
            cRef="entity-000970">Leopoldine Wittgenstein</ref>). Trained in law at Vienna
          University,and after studying musicology with <ref cRef="entity-000003">Guido Adler</ref>,
          Kalmus joined <ref cRef="entity-002408">Universal Edition</ref> in 1909 under the then
          director, <ref cRef="entity-000356">Emil Hertzka</ref>, and worked there until 1936
          (though with a period working for Wiener Philharmonischer Verlag 1923-25), running the
          company jointly with Hugo Winter and Hans Heinsheimer after Hertzka's death in 1932.
          Following his emigration to England in 1936, he established and directed Universal Edition
          London.</p>
        <p>Kalmus was Hertzka's nephew: he was the son of Erwine Fuchs (wife of Jacques Kalmus), who
          was the sister (or step-sister?) of Hertzka's wife, Jella Fuchs. He had one younger
          brother, Edwin (b. 1893), who founded the music publishing firm of Edwin F. Kalmus in New
          York in 1926, and one sister, Marianne. (Kalmus was also more distantly related to
          Schenker's pupil, Felix Salzer, who was the son of Leopoldine Wittgenstein's daughter
          Helene.)</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Kalmus and Schenker</head>
        <p>Schenker regarded Hertzka as his exclusive contact with UE. While a trickle of
          correspondence from Kalmus to Schenker exists from 1912 onward (the earliest being OC
          52/89, May 16, 1912), it was only when relations between Schenker and Hertzka began to
          deteriorate in 1921 over the publication of <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title> that
          Kalmus became a regular correspondent with Schenker during 1921-22 and then again from
          1927 to 1932 (OC 52 and OC 18), and presumably in correspondence not surviving from
          1933-35. Just after Schenker's death, he was involved in plans to reissue <title level="m"
            >Harmonielehre</title>.</p>
        
        <p>In a letter to August Halm of April 3, 1924 (DLA 69.930/12), Schenker commented: <cit>
            <q>How the hearts of the Jews Hertzka, Kalmus, and brother, etc, do wallow! Every line
              that you read in <title level="j">Tonwille</title> has been bought with blood.</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>Otto Erich Deutsch described Kalmus jokingly, saying (OJ 10/3, [75], Dec 2, 1927): <cit>
            <q>We need waste no words over the nephew. He is the lyrical edition of the heroic
              uncle, but from the lineage of those Asra who st[eal], if they loves.</q>
          </cit>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Source:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">NGDM2</title> (2001 and online)</bibl>
          <bibl>Private communication from Angelika Glatz (Archivist of Universal Edition,
            Vienna)</bibl>
          <bibl>Private communication from Christopher Hailey</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
