<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000582">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Irene Mayerhofer (Graedener)</title>
        <title type="sub">born April 3, 1854; died August (c. 15), 1923</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="mayerhofer_irene">Mayerhofer, Irene</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>20/03/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">mayerhofer_irene</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Irene Mayerhofer (Graedener)</head>

      <div>
        <p>Member of the Mayerhofer family of the Viennese silver merchants <ref
            cRef="entity-002449">Mayerhofer &amp; Klinkosch</ref>.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Irene Mayerhofer and Schenker</head>

        <p>Irene Mayerhofer was the first wife of the composer <ref cRef="entity-000301">Hermann
            Otto Graedener</ref> (1844–1929), and a patron of Schenker. Schenker taught her son,
            <ref cRef="entity-006864">Hermann</ref> (lesson dates unknown); he also dedicated his
            <title level="m">Zweistimmige Inventionen</title> for piano, Op. 5 (Leipzig: Breitkopf
          &amp; Härtel, 1898, 1901) to her, with the implication that her patronage of him preceded
          1898.</p>

        <p>Correspondence with <ref cRef="entity-000913">Moriz Violin</ref> reveals that in the
          summer of 1900 Schenker vacationed with the <ref cRef="entity-008348">Mayerhofer
            family</ref> (at least Irene, daughter Irene, and Hermann) in a house in <ref
            cRef="entity-008347">Lunz am See</ref>, and took charge of accommodation. </p>

        <p>Never openly named in his early diaries, always cryptically referred to as "Frau I. M.",
          "I. M." "Ir.", or just "I.", Irene Mayerhofer played an important part in Schenker's life
          as supporter and occasional benefactor. The first diary reference to her occurs on August
          6, 1906, and he first visited her on September 4 of that year. He went to her home for
          tea, and frequently for the evening.</p>

        <p>Their relationship was apparently a stormy one, for there are remarks such as "I. M. in
          her reply harks on kindness and sympathy: feminine burlesque--even rudeness" (December 4,
          1906); "Conflict with I. M.. Acute attack of nerves. Bad night." (February 8, 1907);
          "Conflict with I. M. [...] Resolution of the conflict with I. M." (April 25, 1907).</p>

        <p>Conversely, Schenker had reason to be grateful to her, though he often expressed it
          churlishly: "Frightful months without money finally behind me. I. M. willing to help if
          possible, but obviously, even characterlessly, jittery" (November 1, 1907). When doubtful
          whether <ref cRef="entity-000743">Alphons Rothschild</ref> would honor his commitment, he
          turned to her, only to be rebuffed: "Mrs. I. M. refuses to inspect the 'planned' further
          volumes of my work (vols. II, III, IV). How childish." (April 20, 1907).</p>

        <p>At her death, Schenker wrote in his diary (August 16, 1923): <cit>
            <q>When I look over my early life, I can safely say that, with the exception of my
              parents, there is nobody to whom I owe so much as I do to this lady. In her house, I
              was permitted to breathe the torments that would surely have prostrated me. I have to
              thank her for the precise training in my profession, above all the feeling that a man
              sometimes is to be found among men. It comforts me that even I gave her and her
              children some happy years. Perhaps the only blot on her pesonality was that she
              favored her son over her daughter to such an extent as to irk those who were close to
              her, her friends. In contradiction to that, she was one of the most zealous fighters
              for women's rights.</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>No correspondence between Schenker and Irene Mayerhofer is known to survive.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Bibliography</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Graedener, Irene</author>, <title level="a">Die Firma Klinkosch,</title>
            <title level="j">Die Zeit</title>, No. 4069, January 25, 1914, p. 8 [in reply to <title
              level="a">Die Firma Klinkosch,</title>
            <title level="j">Die Zeit</title>, No. 4062, January 18, 1914, p. 7]</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
              Tagebüchern und Briefen ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), pp. 7-8</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>

  </text>
</TEI>
