<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000093">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Eva van Hoboken (<hi rend="italic">née</hi> Hommel), <hi rend="italic">pseud</hi>.
          Eva Boy</title>
        <title type="sub">born Fiesole, July 28, 1905; died Zurich, December 3, 1987</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="boy_eva">Boy, Eva</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">boy_eva</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Eva van Hoboken (<hi rend="italic">née</hi> Hommel), <hi rend="italic">pseud</hi>. Eva
        Boy</head>
      <div>

        <p>German dancer and writer, second wife of <ref cRef="entity-000380">Anthony van
            Hoboken</ref>.</p>

        <div>
          <head>Career Summary</head>

          <p>Eva was the daughter of Carolina and the painter Conrad Hommel. She was born
            illegitimate in 1905, but her birth was retrospectively legitimized at her parents'
            marriage in 1908. At the age of 18 she worked as an "expressional dancer" (<hi
              rend="italic">Ausdruckstänzerin</hi>) in Munich under the pseudonum "Eva Boy." Hommel
            having left the family some years earlier, Eva found in the German-Jewish novelist and
            playwright Lion Feuchtwanger (1884‒1958) a new father figure. In 1925 Eva moved to
            Berlin at the same time as Feuchtwanger and his wife Marta, and there, under his
            tutelage, she began to contribute short feuilletons to the newspapers <title level="j"
              >Berliner Tageblatt</title>, <title level="j">Berliner Bösen-Courier</title>, <title
              level="j">Tempo</title>, and the <title level="j">Münchner Illustrierte
            Presse</title>.</p>

          <p>On March 30, 1933 Eva married <ref cRef="entity-000380">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>, who
            had recently separated from and divorced his first wife, <ref cRef="entity-002742"
              >Annemarie Seidel</ref>. For a time, she now adopted Hoboken's last name, and took
            Dutch citizenship. Feuchtwanger having been a fierce critic of National Socialism from
            as early as 1920 and having been targeted by the Nazis and his works publicly burned in
            1938, fled first with his wife to France and then to the USA. At this time, he produced
            a novel, <title level="m">Die Geschwister Oppermann</title>, which portrayed the
            relationship between Hoboken and Boy, not entirely flatteringly, using the names "Dr.
            Gustav Oppermann" and "Sybil Rauch." In 1953 Eva became preoccupied with Zen Buddhism
            and studied in Japan.</p>

          <p>With this, she drifted away from Feuchtwanger's influence. However, she maintained an
            epistolary friendship, keeping up a correspondence until his death in 1958. She died in
            Zurich in 1987.</p>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>Eva Boy and Schenker</head>

          <p>Eva Boy first appears in Schenker's diary for July 30, 1932, recording a letter in
            which Hoboken suggests that he visit the Schenkers in Igls with Miss Boy, to which
            Schenker replies in welcoming fashion. The visit took place four days later, on August
            3, and a second visit on August 30, on which occasion Schenker refers to them as
            "Hoboken and his bride" (diary). After the marriage, the two men routinely sent
            greetings to and from their respective wives at the ends of letters, and postcards.</p>

          <p>The only direct surviving correspondence is one letter from Eva Boy (now van Hoboken)
            to Jeanette Schenker, dated December 15, 1935, OJ 11/54, [45]-[46].</p>
        </div>

      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Source2</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Wikipedia</title>, "Eva van Hoboken" </bibl>

          <bibl><title level="m">Lion Feuchtwanger, Briefe an Eva van Hoboken</title>, ed. Nortrud
            Gomringer (Vienna: Splitter, 1996)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>
              <hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi>
            </author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
