<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-008443">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Frau Schimatowitsch</title>
        <title type="sub"/>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="schimatowitsch_frau">Schimatowitsch, Frau</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">schimatowitsch_frau</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Frau Schimatowitsch</head>
      <div>

        <p>Mother of <ref cRef="entity-000895">Anton (Tonschl) Schimatowitsch</ref>, grandmother of
            <ref cRef="entity-003491">Anton (Tonerl) Schimatowitsch</ref> and <ref
            cRef="entity-008438">Karl (Karli) Schimatowitsch</ref>. Apparently <ref
            cRef="entity-000775">Wilhelm Schenker</ref> became attached to her, thereby becoming, in
          effect, <ref cRef="entity-000895">Tonschl</ref>’s “adoptive father” and the two boys’
          “adoptive grandfather.” The boys’ mother (name unknown) died in January 1921 (diary,
          January 10, 1921). In the Vienna street directories there is a possible candidate for her
          husband (the sole person with precisely this surname), and perhaps father of her children,
          in “Anton Schimatowitsch, butcher, of Vienna V, Gartengasse 22” (and other addresses)
          between 1878 and 1907.</p>

        <p>The primary evidence for <ref cRef="entity-000775">Wilhelm</ref>’s involvement with the
          Schimatowitsch family lies in Heinrich Schenker’s summary of, and comment on, a letter
          from <ref cRef="entity-000775">Wilhelm</ref>, dated December 19, 1924: <cit>
            <q>Von Wilhelm (Br.): […] lebt nur für die Pflichten gegenüber den Kindern, denen er
              Großvater u. Großmutter, Vater u. Mutter zu ersetzen hat. […] Sein Schicksal ist
              überaus hart, in letzter Linie Auswirkung ererbter Not. Zuerst verfiel er dem Onkel,
              dann der Frau Sch., u. damit kam er um eigene Nachkommenschaft.<lb/><lb/> From
              Wilhelm: […] lives only for his duties toward the children, for whom he has to
              substitute as grandfather, grandmother, father, and mother. [...] His fate is
              exceedingly hard, ultimately the consequence of inherited necessity. First he fell
              prey to his uncle, then to Mrs. Sch., and with that he lost out on having progeny of
              his own.</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>The only other mention of Frau Schimatowitsch is in a letter to <ref cRef="entity-000775"
            >Wilhelm</ref> of c.1897, in which Heinrich concludes with “Cordial greetings to dear
          Mrs. Schimatov[ich] (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-38_0b">OJ 5/38,
          [0b]</ref>).</p>

        <p><ref cRef="entity-000895">Tonschl</ref> was married and had two children, <ref
            cRef="entity-003491">Tonerl</ref>, born 1907 and <ref cRef="entity-008438">Karli</ref>,
          born 1911, by her. He left his wife (name unknown) and children, apparently in 1919 (diary
          January 11, 1920), and since that time <ref cRef="entity-000775">Wilhelm</ref> seems to
          have felt that, though unrelated to the children, he bore chief responsibility for their
          upbringing and oversight.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author> and <author><hi rend="bold">William
                Drabkin</hi></author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
