<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000443">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Paul (August) von Klenau</title>
        <title type="sub">born Copenhagen, February 11, 1883; died Copenhagen, August 31,
          1946</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="klenau_paul_von">Klenau, Paul von</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">klenau_paul_von</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Paul (August) von Klenau</head>
      <div>

        <p>Danish conductor, composer, and writer on music.</p>

        <div>
          <head>Career Summary</head>
          <p>Klenau began his music studies at the Copenhagen Conservatory (Otto Malling,
            composition, F. Hilmer, violin), continuing them at the Hochschule für Musik, Berlin
            (with Karl Haliř, violin, Max Bruch, composition), in Munich (Ludwig Thuille), and
            Stuttgart (Max von Schillings). During World War I he returned to Denmark. After 1918,
            he undertook studies with Arnold Schoenberg in Vienna. His career as a professional
            conductor began at the Freiburg Opera in 1908; from 1922 to 1926 he conducted the Danish
            Philharmonic Society, of which he was a co-founder; from 1922 to 1930 he was director of
            the Konzerthaus Gesellschaft in Vienna, where he also conducted the Singakademie. Later
            he withdrew from practical musical work on account of increasing deafness, and in 1940
            he returned permanently to Copenhagen.</p>

          <p>He composed seven operas, seven symphonies and a violin concerto, other orchestral
            works, chamber music, solo piano pieces, and orchestral songs. Despite having taken
            lessons with Schoenberg, and become a close friend of Alban Berg, his style was largely
            that of the late Romantic era.</p>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>Klenau and Schenker</head>
          <p>Having read the <ref cRef="entity-001734"><title level="m">Erläuterungsausgabe</title>
              of Op. 109</ref>, Klenau first approached Schenker in September 1923 in search of
            advice on the correct performance of orchestral works by Beethoven. The two men met on
            many occasions between 1923 and at least 1930 to discuss performance issues, their main
            focus being the third, fifth, and ninth symphonies and the <title level="m">Missa
              solemnis</title>.</p>

          <p>Klenau's most significant act in Schenker's eyes was his historical reconstruction on
            May 7, 1924 of the concert that had taken place in the Kärntnertor Theater on May 7,
            1824, comprising three movements of the <title level="m">Missa solemnis</title>, the
              <title>Overture "The Consecration of the House,"</title> and the <title>Ninth
              Symphony</title>. To these works, he sought to restore Beethoven's original tempi and
            instrumentation, on the basis of Schenker's advice and the monograph <ref
              cRef="entity-001731"><title level="m">Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie</title></ref>. The
            description in Schenker's diary for the same day is generally laudatory. (A copy of
            Klenau's program book ("Fest-Konzert Programmbuch") for the concert is preserved at OC
            B/84 with Schenker's annotations.) In <ref cRef="entity-001747"><title level="j">Der
                Tonwille</title> issue 8/9</ref>, Schenker remarked: <cit>
              <q>The jubilee performance ‒ I was present at it ‒ achieved an effect that exceeded
                the usual standards [...]. It confirmed Beethoven's creation in its unity of
                synthesis, notation, and all detailed instructions. [...] In short, the conductor's
                intentions exceeded all expectations. (p. 54 (122))</q>
            </cit></p>

          <p>In a postcard to <rs type="person" key="entity-000913">Moriz Violin</rs> of February
            26, 1927 (OJ 8/4, [46]), when the latter was using Schenker as an intermediary with
            Klenau's father-in-law in pursuit of a job in Frankfurt, Schenker remarked "Klenau is a
            thoroughly magnificent person." Klenau, when passing on advice to others that he had
            received from Schenker, was meticulous in giving credit (e.g. "Klenau sends an article
            about the Ninth Symphony, in which he insures that justice is done to me." ‒ diary May
            20, 1924). In the meetings of the two men, Schenker was generous in advice, showing
            Klenau photographs of autograph scores and explaining editorial issues and notational
            matters. There is little doubt that Schenker saw Klenau as a potential vehicle for his
            performance principles ‒ though not to the extent of <rs type="person"
              key="entity-000268">Wilhelm Furtwängler</rs>. The countless hours he spent advising
            Klenau, and the length of the diary entries he wrote concerning him, would attest to
            this. </p>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>Correspondence</head>
          <p>Fourteen items in all survive: eleven items from Klenau to Schenker, 1923‒27 (OJ 12/11,
            [1]‒[11]), two copies of letters from Schenker to Klenau, 1923‒24 (OC 54/333-336, OC
            12/249), and one memorandum of a conversation between Klenau and Schenker (OC 82/10),
            which reveals the sort of advice Schenker gave (as do many of the diary entries). Other,
            non-extant items are recorded in Schenker's diary. Several articles by Klenau are
            preserved in the folders of the Oster Collection.</p>

          <p>In February 1930, <ref cRef="entity-000380">Anthony van Hoboken</ref> evidently asked
            Schenker to write something on the <title level="m">Missa solemnis</title>. The result
            was a four-page essay (OC 82/3‒6), dated February 22, 1930. This makes no mention of
            Klenau; however, in a letter of the same date to Hoboken (<ref type="corrrespondence"
              cRef="OJ-89-4_1">OJ 89/4, [1]</ref>), Schenker recalled: "With Klenau I rushed through
            the score – i.e. the form in the large and most overall sense – in 2‒3 hours [September
            21, 1923, cf. <ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-82-10">OC 82/10</ref>]"; and in his
            diary for the same day he remarked: "It pleases me to see that my improvisation proceeds
            along paths similar to those that I had previously taken in my instructions to
            Klenau."</p>
        </div>

      </div>
    </body>

    <back>

      <div>
        <head>Bibliography</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>Concert program of Klenau's Beethoven centenary performance, May 7, 1924 (OC
            B/84)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="a">Die 'Klassische' Neunte,</title>
            <title level="j">Pult und Taktstock</title> iv (July 4, 1924) (OJ 41/6)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="a">L. v. Beethovens Symphonie nr. 5 C-moll,</title>
            <title level="j">Frankfurter Zeitung</title> Oct 14, 1924 (OC 2/p. 65)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="a">Albert Schweitzer,</title>
            <title level="j">Frankfurter Zeitung</title> Dec 2, 1925 (OC C/500)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="a">Albert Schweitzer, Träger des Goethepreises,</title>
            <title level="j">Frankfurter Zeitung</title> Aug 29, 1928 (OC C/505)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="a">'Zeitgemässe'-Oper,</title>
            <title level="j">Frankfurter Zeitung</title> Dec 22, 1928</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Schenker, Heinrich</author>, <title level="j">Hundert Jahre IX. Sinfonie
              (Zur Festaufführung der Wiener Konzerthaus-Gesellschaft am 7. Mai 1924)</title> (One
            Hundred Years of the Ninth Symphony: On the jubilee performance of the Wiener
            Konzerthaus-Gesellschaft, May 7, 1924), <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title> IV/2‒3 (=
            8/9) (April/Sept 1924), pp. 53‒4 (121‒22)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Source:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">MGG</title> (1958) </bibl>
        </listBibl>

        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Grove's Dictionary of Music and Musicians</title> (1980) </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
