<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000824">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>George Bernard Shaw</title>
        <title type="sub">born Dublin, July 26, 1856; died Ayot St Lawrence (Herts, UK) November 2,
          1950</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="shaw_george_bernard">Shaw, George Bernard</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">shaw_george_bernard</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>George Bernard Shaw</head>
      <div>

        <p>Irish playwright, literary critic, music critic, and polemicist, writer of sixty plays,
          many of them dealing with difficult social issues and adopting controversial attitudes. </p>

        <div>
          <head>Shaw and Schenker</head>
          <p>Schenker can hardly have approved of Shaw's Marxist past, his left-wing political
            opinions, or his unconventional views of religion, marriage, and other social issues;
            but perhaps he admired Shaw's use of polemic ‒ a mode of rhetoric in which Schenker
            himself engaged robustly, and which he defended vigorously. We know that Schenker either
            saw, or heard or read ten of Shaw's plays: <list type="simple">
              <item><title level="m">Mrs. Warren's Profession</title>: Raimundtheater, November 2,
                1906 (OJ 1/5, p. 25)</item>
              <item><title level="m">Don Juan in Hell</title>: read in the <title level="j">Neue
                  Deutsche Rundschau</title>, November 11, 1906 (OJ 1/5, p. 26)</item>
              <item><title level="m">Man and Superman</title>: Deutsches Volkstheater, May 1, 1907
                (OJ 1/6, p. 39)</item>
              <item><title level="m">The Doctor's Dilemma</title>: Deutsches Volkstheater, December
                7, 1909 (OJ 1/8, p. 103)</item>
              <item><title level="m">Candida</title>: [unknown theater], November[?] 1910 (OJ 1/9,
                p. 120)</item>
              <item><title level="m">Fanny's First Play</title>: Johann Strauss Theater, September
                28, 1912 (OJ 1/11, pp. 240‒41)</item>
              <item><title level="m">Caesar and Cleopatra</title>: Burgtheater, February 18, 1913
                (OJ 1/12, pp. 311‒315 ‒ long!)</item>
              <item><title level="m">Saint Joan</title>: Deutsches Volkstheater, March 27, 1925 (OJ
                3/7, pp. 2802‒2804)</item>
              <item><title level="m">The Apple Cart</title>: Josefstadt Theater, January 30, 1930 OJ
                4/3, pp. 3436‒3437)</item>
              <item><title level="m">Misalliance</title>: Radio Wien, March 4, 1933 (OJ 4/6, pp.
                3817‒3818).</item>
            </list>
          </p>

          <p>His reaction to <title level="m">Don Juan in Hell</title>, which he read in the <title
              level="j">Neue Deutsche Rundschau,</title> was that the play: <cit>
              <q>lifted me suddenly and forcefully out of a mood of dejection. An original,
                high-spirited, skeptical yet kind, clever play, full of spirit and surprises.</q>
            </cit></p>

          <p>His reaction more than twenty years later to <title level="m">The Apple Cart</title>,
            in which a mythical king defeats the attempt of his popularly elected Prime Minister and
            others to deprive him of the right to influence public opinion, to quote it in full, was:<cit>
              <q>We already eat at 6 o'clock, then to the Josefstadt Theater: <title level="m">The
                  Apple Cart</title> by Shaw, with [lead actor] Waldau. Apart from an interpolation
                of an erotic production a thoroughly magnificent play! With a courage that today is
                unequalled, Shaw expresses his outright condemnation of minister, union leaders,
                women. He sees no path to the future, for America as the future is, for him, the end
                of all civilization and culture. Behind the King's cleverness is concealed that of
                the author. The only thing that is puzzling is that Shaw calls himself a democrat
                and probably feels like a democrat – possibly because he has even less trust in the
                upper classes than in the lower ones. The King's long speech is not to be refuted in
                any point; Waldau recites it with the most regal intonation and at the same time
                without emphasis, as only he can do it. I had the impression that he wished to sweep
                the audience along with him, not merely to applause but to agreement with that which
                was put forth – the riff-raff sat there, unmoved. I now attempted, as I have so
                often done in the concert hall, to help out with cries of "Bravo": I was on my
                own.</q>
            </cit></p>

          <p>Excerpts from several of Schenker's other comments are printed in German in
                <bibl><author>Federhofer</author> (1985), pp. 294‒96</bibl>.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Wikipedia</title> ("George Bernard Shaw") </bibl>

          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
              Tagebüchern ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), pp. 10, 277‒80 </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
