<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000750">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Ernst Friedrich Karl Rudorff</title>
        <title type="sub">born Berlin, Jan 18, 1840; died Berlin, Dec 31, 1916</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="rudorff_ernst">Rudorff, Ernst</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>06/11/2005</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Rudorff ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">rudorff_ernst</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Ernst Friedrich Karl Rudorff</head>

      <div>
        <p>German pianist, conductor, teacher, composer, and editor; member of the Brahms
          circle.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>After studying theology, philosophy and philology at the universities of Berlin and
          Leipzig, Rudorff embarked on studies in piano with Moscheles, Plaidy, and Reinecke, and
          composition with Moriz Hauptmann, E. F. Richter and Julius Rietz at the Leipzig
          Conservatory. Having taught for four years at the Cologne Conservatory, he was appointed
          through Joseph Jachim in 1869 to the newly founded Royal Hochschule for Music in Berlin as
          professor of piano, which position he retained until 1910. With Brahms, Joachim and
          Nottebohm, he was involved in the collected edition of Mozart's works (1876‒1907), and
          with Brahms the collected edition of Chopin's works, especially the Ballades, Waltzes and
          Etudes, (1879‒80) as well as being a member of the editorial committee of the Denkmäler
          Deutscher Tonkunst. As a composer he wrote symphonies and other orchestral works, piano
          music, solo songs and choral music.</p>

        <p>Rudorff's wife was Gertrud (<hi rend="italic">née</hi> Rietschel), and the couple had one
          son, and two daughters, <ref cRef="entity-006861">Elisabeth</ref> and Melusine. In
          addition to his professional musical career, Ernst Rudorff was also an early campaigner
          for protection of the countryside in Germany, a passion which <ref cRef="entity-006861"
            >Elisabeth</ref> was to pursue throughout her adult life.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Rudorff and Schenker</head>

        <p>Schenker first approached him in January 1908 about a rhythmic interpretive issue in
          Chopin's second Ballade. He subsequently sent him copies of his <title level="m"
            >Harmonielehre</title>, <title level="m">Beitrag zur Ornamentik</title>, J. S. Bach,
            <title level="m">Chromatic Fantasy &amp; Fugue</title>, <title level="m">Kontrapunkt
            1</title>, and <title level="m">Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie</title>, and the two men
          corresponded vigorously between 1908 and August 1912. In thanking Schenker for the first
          of these works, Rudorff remarks: "When I put together what you have told me of your plans
          as a whole with what I have imbibed so far from your <title level="m"
            >Harmonielehre</title>, I believe and hope that you are the longed-for chosen one who
          will finally hurl the burning torch into the Tower of Babel [i.e. Wagner's world and
          'modern' music]." (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-13-37-3">OJ 13/37, 3</ref>). The
          two men disagreed strongly on the merits of Gluck, whom Rudorff rated highly, but agreed
          in their critiques of Wagner and Bruckner; they were in agreement that a "disintegration"
          was taking place "socially and morally," and that an artistic regeneration was unlikely to
          occur (Federhofer, pp. 205‒06). These sentiments were reflected in the <ref
            cRef="entity-001759"><title level="m">Niedergang der Kompositionskunst</title></ref>
          (Decline of the Art of Composition), on which Schenker was working and set great store at
          the time, though it ultimately remained unpublished. </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>

        <p>In all, twenty-four items of correspondence between Schenker and Rudorff survive: OJ 5/35
          (1908-09: draft letters by Schenker to Rudorff : 7 items), OJ 13/37, 1‒5, 7‒10, 10a‒13
          (1908-10: Rudorff to Schenker : 13 items), and from Gertrud, Elisabeth, and Melusine
          Rudorff to Schenker as OJ 13/36, [1]‒[3], OJ 13/37, 6 (1909–17: 4 items). In addition,
          there is an annotated inventory in Oswald Jonas's hand: OJ 59/15.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Baker's1971</title>
          </bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">NGDM2</title> (2001 and online)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">MGG</title> (1963) (Imogen Fellinger)</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
              Tagebüchern und Briefen ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), pp. 199-210 <hi
              rend="italic">et passim</hi></bibl>
          <bibl>
            <ref type="external" target="https://www.umwelt.uni-hannover.de/1108.html"><title
                level="a">Elizabeth Rudorff ‒ ein Leben für den lth</title></ref></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <listBibl>
          <head>Contributor</head>
          <bibl><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>

  </text>
</TEI>
