<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000287">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Richard Glas</title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, August 14, 1890; died London, December 12, 1973</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="glas_richard">Glas, Richard</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">glas_richard</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Richard Glas</head>
      <div>

        <p>Austrian pianist and teacher.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Richard Glas was born in Vienna in 1890. Nothing is known of his earliest life. He was a
          member of the Piano Masterclass (<hi rend="italic">Meisterschule</hi>) of the virtuoso
          performer <ref cRef="entity-000293">Leopold Godowsky</ref> at the <ref
            cRef="entity-002591">Vienna Conservatory</ref>, receiving the highest award in 1908: a
            <ref cRef="entity-002421">Bösendorfer</ref> parlor grand piano together with the <ref
            cRef="entity-002430">Society [of the Friends of Music]</ref>’s Silver Medal (<title
            level="j">Welt Blatt</title>, July 7). He was spoken of at the time as <ref
            cRef="entity-000293">Godowsky</ref>’s “best pupil,” and <ref cRef="entity-000293"
            >Godowsky</ref> wrote a recommendation for him: “I am extremely cautious when
          recommending an artist, but in the case of Glas I have no hesitation in doing so” (<title
            level="j">Musical Times</title> April 1952, p. 183); around that time, he was appointed
          professor by the Imperial-Russian Society of Music of Tbilisi in Georgia. Glas married the
          Russian pianist Inna Alexandrowna Fedorowa on November 12, 1914. The couple were both
          Jewish. Thereafter Richard was imprisoned in Siberia for most of World War I.</p>

        <p>After the war, Glas was appointed Head of the Piano Masterclass of the <ref
            cRef="entity-002608">Kiel Conservatory</ref>, where he became acquainted with <ref
            cRef="entity-000643">Reinhard Oppel</ref>, who had been teaching music theory there
          since 1911. Glas was a keen advocate for <ref cRef="entity-000643">Oppel</ref>’s
          compositions, and included the latter’s piano works in his concert programs and lobbied
          others on <ref cRef="entity-000643">Oppel</ref>’s behalf, <ref cRef="entity-000643"
            >Oppel</ref> reciprocating in 1920 by dedicating to Glas his second piano sonata, Op.
          25. In 1925 <ref cRef="entity-000643">Oppel</ref> wrote a four-hand sonata for Richard
          and Inna (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-52-637">OC 52/637</ref>), and in the same
          year an Etude in D-flat major for Inna.</p>

        <p><ref cRef="entity-000643">Oppel</ref> and Glas both quit the <ref cRef="entity-002608"
            >Kiel Conservatory</ref> in 1924 in dissatisfaction at working conditions. Glas remained
          in <ref cRef="entity-002757">Kiel</ref> making headway in his career as a concert pianist,
          while <ref cRef="entity-000643">Oppel</ref> moved to <ref cRef="entity-002968">Kiel
            University</ref> to teach from 1924 to 1931 and thereafter to <ref cRef="entity-002479"
            >Leipzig</ref> until his death in 1941. In 1932 Glas was appointed Director of the
          Schleswig-Holstein Conservatory of Music; by 1933, however, he was already encountering
          difficulties from the Nazi authorities and was forced to relinquish the directorship of
          the Conservatory. In 1935 he and his wife moved to <ref cRef="entity-002892"
          >Prague</ref>.</p>

        <p>Glas maintained a Europe-wide concert career for many years, playing mainly Classical and
          Romantic repertory (Beethoven sonatas and concertos, Brahms concertos and piano pieces,
          Schubert, Chopin and Liszt pieces). In February 1913 he scored a major success in <ref
            cRef="entity-002906">St. Petersburg</ref> playing with the Court Orchestra; he was by
          then also performing evening piano recitals (<hi rend="italic">Klavierabende</hi>) the
          first recorded of which, in April 1913, took place in the Beethoven-Saal in Vienna and
          included Beethoven’s “<title>Appassionata</title>” Sonata and the Liszt
            “<title>Mephisto</title>” Waltzes. After his difficult war years, Glas had resumed his
          concert work by 1921, performing throughout the 1920s and first half of the 1930s.
          Presumably excluded from German concert halls from 1933, he continued to play in Austria
          in 1936 and 1937</p>

        <p>After the annexation of Austria in March 1938, Richard and Inna emigrated to <ref
            cRef="entity-002643">London</ref>. By 1939 their address was “Knip Hill,” Eaton Park
          Road, Cobham, Surrey. With the onset of World War II Glas was interned as a “male enemy
          alien” in June 1940, then released in December of that year (UK World War II Alien
          Internees). In 1948 Richard received his British naturalisation papers (National Archives
          HP 334/204.39027). He taught for a time at Wynstones School in Gloucester, and then at the
          London College of Music, Great Marlborough Street in central <ref cRef="entity-002643"
            >London</ref>, where by 1951 he was Head of the Piano Masterclass. At the same time he
          tried to rebuild his concert career; however, as one former pupil of his reported, he
          faced a lot of “racial prejudice.” He and Inna also gave private lessons and coaching at
          their home, 28a Landsdowne Road, Holland Park. Nothing more is known of his career or of
          the remainder of Inna’s life. At his death in 1973, Richard was living in Kensington,
          London.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Richard Glas and Schenker</head>
        <p>Schenker learned of Glas first from <ref cRef="entity-000643">Oppel</ref>’s
          correspondence in 1921, and thereafter received frequent reports. Glas visited Schenker in
          Vienna on two occasions, in June 1922 and in April 1929, with an attempt also in September
          1924 that did not come to fruition. Schenker also wrote to Glas on one occasion in 1926.
        </p>
      </div>

    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
