<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-000089">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Wilhelm Bopp</title>
        <title type="sub">1863?–1931</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="bopp_wilhelm">Bopp, Wilhelm</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>07/04/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Bopp ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">Conservatory ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">bopp_wilhelm</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Wilhelm Bopp</head>
      <div>
        <p>Director of the Vienna Conservatory of Music (Akademie für Musik und darstellende
          Kunst), 1907–19.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Bopp succeeded Richard von Perger as Director just as the Conservatory was undergoing
          transformation from a private institution under the aegis of the Gesellschaft der
          Musikfreunde to a state institution with the title Kaiserlich-königliche Akademie
          für Musik und darstellende Kunst (Imperial-Royal Academy for Music and the Performing Arts). It fell to Bopp to propel that transformation
          forward, and to steer the Conservatory through the war years. The statutes having been
          promulgated on November 22, 1908, the new institution came into existence on January 1,
          1909.</p>
        
        <p>Bopp was a reformer who sought to bring the Conservatory's teaching faculty and
          curriculum up to date, and saw the institution's role as a synthesis between historical
          consciousness and engagement with contemporary musical idioms. His new syllabus was under
          review from March 1909 and came into force in time for January 1910. After twelve years,
          Bopp was voted out of his position by the faculty on March 27, 1919. He subsequently
          worked as a music critic in Mannheim.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Bopp and Schenker</head>
        <p>Schenker disagreed intensely with Bopp's modernizing policies at the Akademie, and
          complained bitterly at the enforced retirements—particularly of those who had
          belonged to the Brahms circle—during the transitional years. In December 1908,
          Bopp, via <ref cRef="entity-000356">Emil Hertzka</ref>, invited Schenker to provide the Conservatory with a new edition of
          Bach's <title level="m">Well-tempered Clavier</title>, Book II. Schenker declined.</p>
        
        <p>This issue re-emerged in early June 1911, when an interview took place with Bopp
          regarding the coordinated publication by <ref cRef="entity-002408">Universal Edition</ref> of editions by Schenker of
          Bach's <title level="m">Well-tempered Clavier</title>, Book II, and the last five piano
          sonatas of Beethoven, allegedly endorsed by the President of the Academy, <ref cRef="entity-000961">Karl von
          Wiener</ref>. In reaction to what he saw as foot-dragging by the two officials, Schenker
          published a notice on June 3 in several newspapers announcing a series of lectures
          designed as a veiled attack on the Academy. This sequence of events is recorded in a long
          diary entry (OJ 1/10, pp. 131r–131a). The dispute
          simmered through the summer, dying down in mid-September, the long-term outcome being
          Schenker's <title level="m">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von Beethoven</title>
          (1913, 1914, 1915, 1920), published by UE but not in association with the Academy.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>
        <p>Correspondence between Schenker and Bopp survives as OJ 9/18 (5 letters,
          1910–11). Correspondence with the Conservatory from Bopp's time survives as OJ 5/4
          (4 letters, 1915–27).</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Tittel, Ernst</author>, <title level="m">Die Wiener Musikhochschule: Vom
              Konservatorium der Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde zur staatlichen Akademie für
              Musik und darstellende Kunst</title> (Vienna: Elizabeth Lafite, 1967)</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Bent, Ian</author>, <title level="a">'That Bright New Light': Schenker,
              Universal Edition, and the Origins of the Erläuterung Series,
            1901–1910,</title>
            <title level="j">Journal of the American Musicological Society</title> 58/1 (Spring
            2005), 69–138</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
