<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-000404">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Joseph Joachim</title>
        <title type="sub">born Kittsee, nr. Pressburg [Bratislava], June 28, 1831; died Berlin, Aug
          15, 1907</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="joachim_joseph">Joachim, Joseph</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>28/04/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">joachim_joseph</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Joseph Joachim</head>
      <div>
        <p>Austrian-Hungarian violinist, one of the greatest exponents of that instrument; also
          conductor, teacher, composer, and editor.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Joseph Joachim, who was a first cousin of Fanny Wittgenstein (née Figdor; he was thus
          distantly related to <ref cRef="entity-000754">Felix Salzer</ref>), and had been adopted at
          the age of 12 by Fanny and her husband Hermann, studied violin at the Vienna Conservatory
          (1841–: Georg Hellmesberger, Josef Böhm). In 1843, the Wittgensteins sent him to Leipzig
          to study with Mendelssohn; he began giving concerts there and in London, rising rapidly to
          international fame. In addition to his solo career, he was also a fine chamber music
          player, founding the Joachim Quartet in 1869 and leading it until his death in 1907. From
          1868, he was director of the Hochschule für Ausübende Tonkunst in Berlin. </p>
        <p>Joachim was closely associated with Mendelssohn, Liszt, and Schumann in the first part of
          his career. From 1850 on, he came to be associated also with Brahms, the two performing
          together, Brahms dedicating his Violin Concerto (1878) to him; after a rift between the
          two in 1881 there was a reconciliation and Joachim was the violin soloist in the first
          performance of the Double Concerto (1887). </p>
        <p>In addition to compositions in many genres, and arrangements, Joachim made editions of
          the solo violin works of J. S. Bach, the Beethoven sonatas for violin and piano, and the
          Beethoven string quartets (score and parts, with Andreas Moser). </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Joachim and Schenker</head>
        <p>In his early years as a music critic, Schenker wrote in laudatory terms of Joachim's own
          playing and that of his quartet, e. g., in 1894: <cit>
            <q>"In the course of recent years, since Hellmesberger senior, the great quartet
              connoisseur and player, we found only one single quartet that could do complete
              justice to the demands of Beethoven, Mozart, and Schumann—that quartet was the Joachim
              Quartet from Berlin." </q>
          </cit></p>
        <p>Joachim's association with Brahms in itself perhaps disposed Schenker (who considered
          himself a late-comer to the Brahms circle) toward Joachim. Moroever, Schenker saw Joachim,
          like the singer <ref cRef="entity-000592">Johannes Messchaert</ref>, as an exemplary
          advocate of authenticity in interpretation, and this comes through many times in his
          writings, diaries, and correspondence, e.g. in <title level="m">Kontrapunkt 1</title>
          (1910): <cit>
            <q>"Why is he [the typical pianist of the day] not eager, like a violinist or singer who
              follows a good tradition (Joachim or Messchaert, for example) to rise to the full
              measure of Bach's art of expression?" (p. 129, Eng. trans. p. 9)</q>
          </cit>
        </p>
        <p>in his diary for December 8, 1915, of the Brahms Violin Concerto: <cit>
            <q>"How often did the master Joachim himself perform the work, how often did he teach it
              to countless pupils, and yet nowadays what is passed off as the Brahms Concerto no
              longer bears any relation to that [work]."</q>
          </cit>
        </p>
        <p>or in a letter to <ref cRef="entity-000380">Anthony van Hoboken</ref> in 1927
          concerning their newly-founded <ref cRef="entity-002452">Photogrammarchiv</ref>: <cit>
            <q>"The Archive in spirit represents what we have seen with Joachim, Messchaert, [etc.],
              but which regrettably is lacking today." (OJ 89/1, [8]) </q>
          </cit></p>
        <p> and those to Felix-Eberhard von Cube in 1928: <cit>
            <q>"Further blessings of my life: Joachim, Messchaert as models of the very difficult
              art of performance." (vC 14); "with regard to Joachim, he was always my model in
              matters of performance (I did not know him personally)." (vC 17).</q>
          </cit>
        </p>
        <p>In his article <title level="a">Weg mit dem Phrasierungsbogen,</title> in <title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</title>, vol. I (1925), Schenker quotes
          extensively from Joachim's correspondence with Brahms about notational issues (pp. 55–58;
          Eng. trans. 27–28). </p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">MGG</title>
          </bibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">NGDM</title>
          </bibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Baker's 1971</title>
          </bibl>
          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
              Tagebüchern und Briefen ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), pp. 202, 209, 225,
            248, 304, 345</bibl>
          <bibl><editor>Federhofer, Hellmut</editor>, ed., <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker als
              Essayist und Kritiker …</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1990), pp. 130, 270, 273</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Monk, Ray</author>, <title level="m">Ludwig Wittgenstein: The Duty of
            Genius</title> (London: Vintage, 1991), pp. 5–6</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Marko Deisinger</author> and <author>Ian Bent</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
