<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000380">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Anthony van Hoboken</title>
        <title type="sub">born Rotterdam, March 23, 1887; died Zurich, Nov 1, 1983</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="hoboken_anthony_van">Hoboken, Anthony van</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>07/07/2006</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Hoboken ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">hoboken_anthony_van</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Anthony van Hoboken</head>

      <div>
        <p>Dutch collector and bibliographer.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Hoboken as Collector</head>

        <p>Hoboken's private collection, amassed from 1919 onward, includes first and early editions
          of music from the Baroque to the late Romantic--notably over 1,000 items of Haydn--and
          early theory and literature (Otto Erich Deutsch was the librarian of the collection
          1926-35; catalogue, ed. G. Brosche, Tutzing, 1982-98). This collection was transferred to
          the Austrian National Library in 1974. Hoboken's principal publication was <title
            level="m">Joseph Haydn: thematisch-bibliographisches Wekverzeichnis</title> (Mainz,
          1957-78).</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Hoboken and Schenker</head>

        <p>Originally trained as an engineer, Hoboken studied music in Holland, then in Frankfurt
          and Munich, where he studied with <ref cRef="entity-000922">Otto Vrieslander</ref>, before
          moving to Vienna, where he became a pupil of Schenker's, beginning lessons on October 15,
          1925 twice a week (initially Thursdays and Saturdays) and continuing through at least to
          June 29, 1932 (when the Lesson Books OC 3 cease).</p>

        <p>The exhaustive preparatory work that Schenker did for all of his publications in many
          cases entailed acquiring photographic copies of the autographs of works to be studied. It
          was thus at Schenker's instigation that, in November 1927, Hoboken announced the founding
          of an archive of photographic negatives and photostatic prints (at original size) of
          autographs of works by the masters, at the same time putting out an appeal (<ref
            cRef="entity-002418">Aufruf</ref>) to librarians, private collectors, and dealers to
          make manuscripts in their possession available for photography. The collection was named
          the <ref cRef="entity-002452">Photogrammarchiv musikalischer Meister-Handschriften</ref>,
          and was held in the Music Department of the Austrian National Library.</p>

        <p>Additionally, in the latter part of Schenker's life, Hoboken--a wealthy man--became
          Schenker's principal patron, on a par with Baron Alphons Rothschild in the earlier part of
          his life. He subvented the printing costs of <title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der
            Musik</title>, vol. II (1926), and paid those of <title level="m">Der freie Satz</title>
          (1935). Hoboken was involved in other plans, such as a monthly periodical devoted to
          Schenker's theory, in late 1927, and books in honor of Schenker, none of which came to
          fruition. Hoboken gave the eulogy at Schenker's funeral and published tributes to him (OC
          2/pp. 90/91). Schenker himself paid tribute to Hoboken at the end of the Foreword to the
          first edition of <title level="m">Der freie Satz</title>: <cit>
            <q>For the fact that so exalted a work should find its way into the world at all in this
              godless time, the author, and the whole musically-interested world, thanks the
              generous act of patronage of an inspired musician, a true and faithful adherent and
              friend of the new teaching. His name, <hi rend="bold">Anthony van Hoboken</hi>, is for
              all time inseparably associated with this work, and the amateur for whom C. P. E. Bach
              wrote his <title level="m">Versuch</title> in times past celebrates his
              resurrection.</q>
          </cit></p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Schenker and Others</head>

        <p>The correspondence between Hoboken and Schenker survives at OJ 11/54 and OC 14/1 (Hoboken
          to Schenker: 1924-35: 49 items), and OJ 89/1-8 (Schenker to Hoboken: 1927-35: 79 items);
          that between Hoboken and Oswald Jonas at OJ 36/31 (Jonas to Hoboken : 1939-54; 11 items)
          and OJ 36/152 (Hoboken to Jonas: 1938-54: 14 items).</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
              Tagebüchern und Briefen ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), pp. 154-57 <hi
              rend="italic">et passim</hi></bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">NGDM2 </title></bibl>
          <bibl>Documents on this website</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>


  </text>
</TEI>
