<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-000970">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Leopoldine (Poldi) Wittgenstein</title>
        <title type="sub">1850-1926</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="wittgenstein_leopold">Wittgenstein, Leopoldine</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>02/09/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Wittgenstein ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">wittgenstein_leopold</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Leopoldine (Poldi) Wittgenstein</head>

      <div>
        <p>Mother of pianist <ref cRef="entity-000971">Paul Wittgenstein</ref> and philosopher
          Ludwig Wittgenstein.</p>


        <p>She was born Leopoldine Kalmus (thus was related to <ref cRef="entity-000420">Alfred
            Kalmus</ref>); her father, Jakob Kalmus, was descended from a prominent Prague Jewish
          family, her mother, Maria Stallner, from an established family of Austrian Catholic land
          owners. In 1873, she married Karl Wittgenstein (1847-1913), a leading figure in the iron
          and steel industry, and a patron of the arts. Their house, Alleegasse 4, Vienna IV (bombed
          in World War II), became a lively center for musical life, regularly frequented by
          distinguished composers, performers, and critics. The couple had five sons and three
          daughters (one of whom, Helene, was the mother of Schenker's pupil<ref cRef="entity-000754"> Felix Salzer</ref>), all of whom received musical instruction.</p>

        <p>Leopoldine was herself an excellent pianist, having studied with Karl Goldmark; and her
          son Paul became a professional concert pianist.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Leopoldine and Schenker</head>

        <p>Leopoldine inherited a valuable collection of musical manuscripts, including works by J.
          S. Bach, Brahms, and Beethoven, notably the autograph manuscript of Beethoven's Piano
          Sonata in E major, Op. 109. Schenker worked on this autograph at the Wittgenstein house on
          November 12 and 19, 1912 when preparing his <title level="m">Die letzten fünf
            Sonaten von Beethoven ... op. 109</title> (Vienna: UE, 1913) (OJ 1/11, pp. 277, 282).
          While Paul Wittgenstein was Schenker's contact, it was clearly his mother who had control
          of the manuscript collection, and it was with her that Schenker experienced difficulty
          obtaining permission to have the Op. 109 source photographed by Court Photographer Schramm
          (OJ 1/12, pp. 367, 372, 378, 380, June 25 and 28, July 7, 13, and 19, 1913, see also WSLB
          167, December 19, 1913).</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>

        <p>No correspondence is known to survive between Leopoldine Wittgenstein and Schenker, but
          OJ 15/24 contains his correspondence with her son, Paul.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">OeML Online</title>
          </bibl>
          <bibl>various websites</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Monk, Ray</author>, <title level="m">Ludwig Wittgenstein: The Duty of
            Genius</title> (New York: Penguin Books, 1991)</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Waugh, Alexander</author>, <title level="m">The House of Wittgenstein: A
              Family at War</title> (London: Bloomsbury, 2008)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
