<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000025">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Carl Philipp Emanuel Bach</title>
        <title type="sub">born Weimar, March 8, 1714; died Hamburg, December 14, 1788</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="bach_carl_philipp_emanuel">Bach, Carl Philipp Emanuel</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">bach_carl_philipp_emanuel</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Carl Philipp Emanuel Bach</head>
      <div>

        <p>German composer and theorist.</p>

        <div>
          <head>Career Summary</head>

          <p>The second surviving son of J. S. Bach and his first wife Maria Barbara Bach, Carl
            Philipp Emanuel was trained in music by his father and, at the age of 24, entered the
            service of Crown Prince Frederick (later King Frederick the Great) at the Court of
            Berlin, where he spent nearly thirty years. In 1768 he was made director of sacred music
            in Hamburg and remained in that city for the rest of his life; for this reason he is
            sometimes referred to as the "Hamburg" Bach.</p>

          <p>Bach was a prolific composer; more than 1,000 works are attributed to him, of which the
            vast majority are solo and chamber works for or involving keyboard instruments; his
            output also includes concertos and symphonies, and some sacred and secular vocal music.
            He is perhaps best known for his solo keyboard music, which includes important early
            published sets, for the King of Prussia (1742–43) and the Duke of Württemberg (1744);
            but the collections that Schenker knew best are his six volumes of sonatas, rondos, and
            free fanatasies <hi rend="italic">für Kenner und Liebhaber</hi>, published between 1779
            and 1787.</p>

          <p>While renewed interest in his music among performers and critics has grown steadily in
            recent times, he is still best remembered for his two-volume theoretical treatise
            written in Berlin, the <title level="m">Essay on the True Art of Playing Keyboard
              Instruments</title> (1753–62), often referred to by the first word of its German
            title, <title level="m">Versuch über die wahre Art das Clavier zu spielen</title>, which
            covers not only playing technique and figured bass realization but also matters of
            composition and improvisation.</p>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>C. P. E. Bach and Schenker</head>
          <p>For Schenker, Carl Philipp Emanuel was the only son of J. S. Bach worthy of serious
            study; he was also the only composer whom the theorist elevated to a higher rank than
            posterity had previously accorded him, admitting him into his highly selective circle of
            musical geniuses. His engagement with C. P. E. Bach may be divided into three phases,
            the first of which begins with his edition of ten selected works "for connoisseurs and
            amateurs." This was published in a single volume in 1902, entitled <ref
              cRef="entity-001720"><title level="m">Phil. Em. Bach: Klavierwerke (kritische
                Ausgabe)</title></ref>, and subsequently issued in two half-volumes. Two years later
            Schenker completed a comprehensive study of ornamentation in mid- and late 18th-century
            keyboard music,<ref cRef="entity-001721"><title level="m"> Ein Beitrag zur
                Ornamentik</title></ref>, whose subtitle, however, explains its origins as "An
            Introduction to the Keyboard Works of Carl Philipp Emanuel Bach ...." </p>

          <p>In the second phase, which dates from the mid-1920s, Schenker analyzed three works by
            Bach: the sonata that inaugurated the "connoisseurs and amateurs" series and Schenker's
            1902 edition, a didactic piece from a collection that his pupil <ref
              cRef="entity-000922">Otto Vrieslander</ref> had edited, and the "free fantasy" in D
            major which Bach had used in the <title level="m">Versuch</title> to exemplify
            improvisation from a harmonic-contrapuntal plan. (It hardly needs stressing that Bach's
            presentation of such a plan alongside the finished work resonates strongly with
            Schenker's notion of <term><hi rend="italic">Auskomponierung</hi></term> and with his
            later analytical practice: the <term><hi rend="italic">Urlinie-Tafeln</hi></term>, or
            "analyses in sketchform.")</p>

          <p>Finally, in 1930, Schenker lent his support to a project to bring out a collected
            edition of Bach's works under the auspices of the <ref cRef="entity-002452">Photogram
              Archive</ref> at the Austrian National Library. Plans for this undertaking loom large
            in his diary entries, and an editorial assistant (Ernst Friitz Schmid) was engaged for
            the project; Schmid was later to achieve renown as a C. P. E. Bach scholar in his own
            right. But the edition was ultimately abandoned, partly because the Archive's patron,
              <ref cRef="entity-000380">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>, was unwilling to invest
            sufficient financial resources and partly because Schenker, in declining health and
            desperate to complete <ref cRef="entity-001728"><title level="m">Free
                Composition</title></ref>, was reluctant to take on a heavy editorial
            responsibility.</p>

          <p>In spite of backing away from the collected edition, Schenker continued to express his
            admiration for Bach. In correspondence with <ref cRef="entity-000913">Moriz Violin</ref>
            from the 1920s and '30s, he often remarked how their spiritual union was reinforced by
            his friend's residence in the German city most closely associated with Bach. And in a
            letter to the physicist Albert Einstein from the early 1930s (drafted but never sent),
            he described <ref cRef="entity-001728"><title level="m">Free Composition</title></ref>
            as the most important treatise on music since the <title level="m">Versuch</title>. One
            of his pupils, <ref cRef="entity-000922">Otto Vrieslander</ref>, took up the C. P. E.
            Bach cause with great enthusiasm. Later, largely through the influence of <ref
              cRef="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</ref> in the 1930s, William J. Mitchell in New York
            developed an avid interest in the <title level="m">Versuch</title> and published the
            first complete English translation in 1949.</p>

          <p>In the course of his career, Schenker accumulated three copies of the <title level="m"
              >Versuch</title>, all of which existed in his library at his death in 1935: his
            annotated copy of the 1787-98 edition (Leipzig: Schwickert ‒ purchased by <ref
              cRef="entity-000754">Felix Salzer</ref> from <ref cRef="entity-000771">Jeanette
              Schenker</ref> in 1936, now in the Felix Salzer Papers, New York Public Library,
            Series II Heinrich Schenker Nachlass, b.57/f.2, 6/156); the 1856 edition of both parts
            by G. Schilling (Berlin: Stage); and the 1906 abbreviated edition by W. Niemann
            (Leipzig: Kahnt), which Schenker refers to in the Preface to the abbreviated second
            edition of his <ref cRef="entity-001721"><title level="m">Beitrag zur
              Ornamentik</title></ref>, 1908. The latter two items were sold in c.1936. Schenker's
            lessonbooks demonstrate that the <title level="m">Versuch</title> was a valuable tool
            in his teaching.</p>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>Schenker's Publications</head>
          <listBibl>
            <bibl>(ed.) <title level="m">Phil. Em. Bach: Klavierwerke (kritische Ausgabe)</title>
              (Vienna: Universal Edition, [1903])</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="m">Ein Beitrag zur Ornamentik. Als Einführung zu Ph. Em. Bachs
                Klavierwerken mitumfassend auch die Ornamentik Haydns Mozarts u. Beethovens
                etc.</title> (Vienna: Universal Edition, 1903, 2/1908); Eng. trans. as <title
                level="a">A Contribution to the Study of Ornamentation,</title> by <editor>Hedi
                Siegel</editor> in <title level="j">The Music Forum</title> IV, ed. <editor>F.
                Salzer</editor> (New York: Columbia University Press, 1976), pp. 1–139</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">C. P. E. Bach's Allegro in G Major</title> and <title level="a"
                >C. P. E. Bach's Keyboard Sonata in C Major,</title>
              <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>, vol. 1, pp. 148–52; Ger. orig. in <title
                level="j">Tonwille</title> 4 (1923), 8–11</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">The Art of Improvisation,</title>
              <title level="j">The Masterwork in Music</title> I, pp. 2–19; Ger. orig. in <title
                level="j">Meisterwerk</title> I, 11–40</bibl>
          </listBibl>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>Vrieslander's Publications</head>
          <listBibl>
            <bibl>(ed.) <title level="m">C. P. E. Bach: Kurze und leichte Clavierstücke: Neue
                kritische Ausgabe mit erläuterndem Nachwort</title> (Vienna: Universal Edition,
              1914; 2d edn rev. Oswald Jonas, 1962)</bibl>

            <bibl>(ed.) <title level="m">C. P. E. Bach: Lieder und Gesänge</title> (Munich: Drei
              Masken Verlag, 1922)</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="m">Carl Philipp Emanuel Bach</title> (Munich: Piper, 1923)</bibl>

            <bibl><title level="a">Philipp Emanuel Bach als Theoretiker,</title> in <title level="m"
                >Von neuer Musik</title>, ed. <editor>H. Grues</editor>, vol. 1 (Cologne, 1925), pp.
              222–79</bibl>

            <bibl>(ed.) <title level="m">C. P. E. Bach: Vier leichte Sonaten</title> (Hannover:
              Nagel, 1932)</bibl>
          </listBibl>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>Salzer's Publication</head>
          <listBibl>
            <bibl><title level="a">Über die Bedeutung der Ornamente in Philipp Emanuel Bachs
                Klavierwerken,</title>
              <title level="j">Zeitschrift für Musikwissenschaft</title> 12/7 (1930), 398‒418</bibl>
          </listBibl>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Literature:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m"><title level="m">The New Grove Dictionary of Music and
                Musicians</title> (<title level="m">Grove Music Online</title>)</title>
          </bibl>

          <bibl>
            <author>E. Eugene Helm</author>, <title level="m">Thematic Catalogue of the Works of
              Carl Philipp Emanuel Bach</title> (New Haven: Yale University Press, 1989) </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>William Drabkin</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
