<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000415">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Trude Kaff</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="kaff_trude">Kaff, Trude</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>27/06/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Kaff ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">kaff_trude</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Trude Kaff</head>

      <div>
        <p>Pupil of Schenker from January 1912 to summer 1919.</p>

        <p>Trude [Gertrud?] Kaff lived in Brno (Brünn), capital of Moravia. She lived with her
          parents, travelling by train to Vienna as needed, until the Fall of 1918, when she
          considered moving to Vienna and establishing herself as a piano teacher in the City (which
          she had presumably done by March 1919, when she sent a message by her maid). But she is
          not to be found in the Vienna Street Directory at that time. The newspaper <title
            level="j">Der Tag</title>, on March 21, 1931 under <title level="a">Musik und
            Theater,</title> reported the performance of songs by her in the recital hall of the
            <ref cRef="entity-004396">Musikverein Building</ref>, together with a photograph, the
          same concert being reported in <title level="j">Der Tag</title> for March 29: “Hilde
          Tometschek-Hofmann gave a varied program of songs by unknown young female composers. Among
          others, three atmospheric songs by Trude Kaff were performed". Kaff sent Schenker a letter
          with tickets for this event (“to a concert at which three songs of hers will be
          performed!”, which he returned on March 11 (diary).</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Trude Kaff and Schenker</head>
        <p>Trude Kaff appears in Schenker's earliest lessonbook (1911/12), the first recorded lesson
          taking place on January 25, 1912, taking one lesson a week, the middle slot between <ref
            cRef="entity-000201">Elias</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-000655">Pairamall</ref>, lessons
          continuing through 1913/14, then after a three-year gap, 1917/18 and 1918/19. She does not
          appear in Schenker's diary before 1912, but does so thereafter in 1913, 1914, 1918 and
          1919. On January 14, 1919 she requested to transfer from Schenker to <ref
            cRef="entity-000732">Moriz Rosenthal</ref> (whom she had encountered on a train from
          Brno to Vienna on December 17, 1913), but she continued with Schenker for a further four
          months. In May 1913 Trude’s father bought her a piano; and after her move to Vienna she
          bought or hired an upright piano (<hi rend="italic">pianino</hi>). Trude’s mother was a
          source of frequent annoyance to Schenker.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>
        <p>One letter survives from Kaff to Schenker, OC 30/40, December 31, 1932 (to which OC 30/41
          is an incomplete draft reply), sending New Year's wishes and speaking in glowing terms of
          her lessons long ago with Schenker, which she appropriately described as “keenly pleaded
          and fought for,“ and quaintly as “put in commercial terms, the one single thing in my life
          that has continued to amortize to this very day.” </p>
      </div>
    </body>


    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Ian Bent and Marko Deisinger</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>


  </text>
</TEI>
