<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-007656">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Edith Schreier Jonas</title>
        <title type="sub">born Lötzen, East Prussia/Giżycko, Poland, January 23, 1891; died
          Lenggries, Bavaria, September 13, 1974</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="schreier_jonas_edith">Schreier Jonas, Edith</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">schreier_jonas_edith</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Edith Schreier Jonas</head>
      <div>

        <p>German Jewish pianist and teacher.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Edith Schreier was born Edith Jacoby on January 23, 1891 in East Prussia, daughter of
          Daniel Jacoby, dealer in fur goods, and his wife Martha (<hi rend="italic">née</hi>
          Rosenthal). She attended school in Königsberg, where she studied piano with Conrad
          Hausburg, and Berlin. In 1912 she married Fritz Ascher, with whom she lived in <ref
            cRef="entity-002589">Hamburg</ref> and had a son, Ernst Joachim Ascher, in 1913. Fritz
          was killed in the war in 1917.</p>

        <p>At the recommendation of <ref cRef="entity-000794">Artur Schnabel</ref>, Edith embarked
          on piano studies with <ref cRef="entity-000913">Moriz Violin</ref>, who had moved from
          Vienna to <ref cRef="entity-002589">Hamburg</ref> in 1921. <ref cRef="entity-000913"
            >Violin</ref> introduced her to fellow-pupil <ref cRef="entity-007655">Otto
            Schreier</ref>, suggesting that they would make a good four-hands duet partnership. The
          two married in 1928, but <ref cRef="entity-007655">Otto</ref> died aged 28 on June 2,
          1929. Edith immediately moved to Vienna so as to be close to <ref cRef="entity-007655"
            >Otto</ref>'s parents; and on July 1, 1929 she gave birth to <ref cRef="entity-007504"
            >Irene Schreier</ref>. In 1930 Edith enrolled for the state examination in piano as an
          exterrnal student at the Vienna <ref cRef="entity-002591">Academy for Music and Performing
            Arts</ref>, qualifying as a professional piano music teacher.</p>

        <p>After the National Socialist annexation of Austria, Edith emigrated in 1939 with <ref
            cRef="entity-007504">Irene</ref>, arriving in the USA on March 4, 1939 and settling in
            <ref cRef="entity-002921">San Francisco</ref>, where her son Ernst was a student at U.
          C. Berkeley. After unsuccessfully attempting to support herself and her child by teaching,
          she learned to cook and eventually, together with refugee friends, started a cooperative
          house which soon turned into a boarding house. When the <ref cRef="entity-002938">Violin
            family</ref> also emigrated to <ref cRef="entity-002921">San Francisco</ref>, <ref
            cRef="entity-007504">Irene</ref>'s lessons with the teacher who had brought her parents
          together, recommenced. Another refugee from the Nazi terror also appeared: <ref
            cRef="entity-000412">Oswald Jonas</ref>,<ref cRef="entity-000913">Violin</ref>'s
          erstwhile student and closest friend.</p>

        <p><ref cRef="entity-000412">Jonas</ref>'s main purpose however was fulfilled when Edith and
          he married after he was offered a position at Chicago's YMCA College School of Music
          (later Roosevelt University) in 1942. Once settled in Chicago, Edith worked at various
          jobs before substituting for a well-known piano-teaching colleague during her absence.
          This developed into a permanent situation: she became the beloved teacher of countless
          students of all ages, eventually joining the faculty of the Music Center of the North
          Shore under the originally Viennese director and conductor, Dr.Herbert Zipper.</p>

        <p>After <ref cRef="entity-000412">Oswald</ref>'s retirement from Roosevelt University, he
          and Edith regularly visited Europe. He was frequently invited to lecture in Germany and
          Austria, often by his former students. His great interest in music manuscripts led to work
          in various music libraries. Undecided where to settle, the question was solved when an
          invitation in 1965 to be Regents' Professor at the University of California, Riverside,
          turned out to be so mutually rewarding that it became their new home. Soon Edith had a new
          circle of friends and pupils and although annual visits to Europe continued, Riverside
          became home. It is presently the location of a permanent Oswald Jonas Memorial Collection
          (OJ) in the University's library, well used by Schenker scholars.</p>

        <p>Their last trip to Europe, in 1974, included a lengthy stay with <ref
            cRef="entity-007504">Irene</ref> and her family in Oxford, where Dana Scott, Irene's
          husband had the chair of Mathematical Logic. Not feeling her energetic self, Edith sought
          improvement in a cure in Lenggries in Bavaria. Instead she died there on September 13.
          Oswald returned to Riverside until his death there in 1978.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Documentation</head>
        <p>No correspondence is known to survive between Edith Schreier and either Heinrich Schenker
          or Moriz Violin. The Oswald Jonas Collection holds her certificate of naturalization
          (1944) at OJ 69/1, item 2.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Source:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <ref type="external"
              target="https://www.lexm.uni-hamburg.de/object/lexm_lexmperson_00007171"
                ><title>University of Hamburg LexM</title>
              <title level="a">Edith Schreier Jonas</title></ref>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributors</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author> and <author><hi rend="bold">Irene
                Schreier Scott</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
