<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000774">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Moriz [Maurice; Mozio; Moses] Schenker</title>
        <title type="sub">born Podhajce, Galicia, Auguat 31, 1874; died September 1936</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="schenker_moriz">Schenker, Moriz</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>07/07/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">SchenkerM ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">schenker_moriz</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Moriz [Maurice; Mozio; Moses] Schenker</head>

      <div>
        <p>Younger brother of Heinrich Schenker, and also of <ref cRef="entity-000319"
            >Shifre/Sophie</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-000775">Wilhelm</ref> Schenker; youngest
          child of <ref cRef="entity-000772">Johann</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-000773">Julia</ref>
          Schenker, both Jewish. </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career summary</head>

        <p>Following his father’s death in 1887, Moriz Schenker was brought to Vienna, where,
          according to Oswald Jonas, Heinrich Schenker was “responsible for the sustenance of his
          destitute family” (<bibl><title level="a">H. Schenker,</title>
            <title level="m">MGG</title> vol. 11 (1963), col. 1670</bibl>). Moriz worked first for
          the lumber company of the <ref cRef="entity-003218">Eissler family</ref>, who were patrons
          of Heinrich, until the latter encouraged him to go to business school. After that, he went
          into banking (diary, April 4, 1915) with the <ref cRef="entity-002467">Österreichische
            Länderbank</ref>, in which he served for some years at its office in Egypt, where his
          daughter <ref cRef="entity-003067">Helga</ref> and son <ref cRef="entity-000769"
            >Georg</ref> was born in 1907 and 1908 (he later remarked: "Egypt is my second home
          [...] unfortunately a continuous life there is impossible." ‒ diary Nov 17, 1926). Later
          he moved to the Rumanian subsidiary of the bank, becoming Bank Director there by 1912. He
          established the family home at <ref cRef="entity-002394">Baden bei Wien</ref>,
          Elisabethstraße 17, which he occupied until his death. In December 1913 the Kaiser awarded
          him the Officer Cross of the Order of Franz-Josef for services to banking in Rumania
            (<title level="j">Reichspost</title>, Dec 10). His work entailed much travel, during
          which in November–December 1918 he was interned in Bucharest.</p>

        <p>In 1924 he moved to the recently founded Vienna-based import-export <ref
            cRef="entity-004196">Treuga Bank</ref> (diary, Nov 10) with the title “General
          Director.” In that year he was appointed to the board of directors of the Reinhardt
          Theater Company (<title level="j">Der Tag</title>, April 24), In 1925 he was appointed to
          the board of the Austrian Credit Bank (<title level="j">Wiener Zeitung</title>, May 5),
          and became a board member of the Vienna Volksoper (<title level="j">Der Montag</title>,
          June 15), and he occupied seats on several other industries and businesses. </p>

        <p>At the height of his career he amassed considerable wealth (Heinrich spoke of him as a
          “billionaire”), and in 1929 he purchased a property in <ref cRef="entity-004104"
            >Reichraming</ref> in <ref cRef="entity-005929">Upper Austria</ref> for investment
          purposes, into which Heinrich invested money. </p>

        <p>The date of Moriz’s marriage to the non-Jewish <ref cRef="entity-003438">Lisl</ref>
          (maiden name unknown) probably took place in the 1900s. The couple had two children: <ref
            cRef="entity-003067">Helga</ref> (b. 1907) and <ref cRef="entity-000769">Georg</ref> (b.
          c.1908). One small insight into family life is recorded in Heinrich’s diary: <cit>
            <q>Dr. Baumgarten [Heinrich’s attorney] at our place; he confirms what we have long
              suspected: that Mozio is keeping his Jewish origins a secret from his children! He,
              Dr. Baumgarten, alerted [Mozio’s] wife to the danger that his children could learn the
              truth from some other quarter; their mother declines to tell the children the truth
              for the time being. Dr. Baumgarten gets worked up over Mozio's speaking German with
              Yiddish thrown in, even in front of the children. (diary, Nov 1, 1924)</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>Signs of a deterioration in the marriage appeared 1920, and <ref cRef="entity-003438"
            >Lisl</ref> left him in September 1929 for the radio pioneer <ref cRef="entity-004819"
            >Leopold Richtera</ref>; she obtained a divorce and married <ref cRef="entity-004819"
            >Richtera</ref> in April 1930, only for her new husband to die two weeks later. </p>

        <p>In 1927, Moriz appears to have been out of work. In 1930 he formed his own company, M.
          Schenker &amp; Cie. Autohandel (<title level="j">Wiener Zeitung</title>, Aug 30),
          apparently providing finance for automobiles and parts; by 1934 that had become M.
          Schenker &amp; Reicher. With the Great Depression, and the collapse of the Vienna <ref
            type="organization" cRef="entity-004959">Creditanstalt</ref> in May 1931, his control
          over his business affairs deteriorated.</p>

        <p>There are indications in the early 1930s that his mental health was suffering; he was a
          patient at the University of Vienna’s Clinic for Nervous and Mental Diseases in December
          1934 <ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-A-285">(OC A/285</ref>) and urged Heinrich to
          avail himself of its shortwave radiotherapy. His depression seems to have worsened leading
          to suicide on September 17, 1936. The <title level="j">Neues Wiener Journal</title>, Sep.
          18, reported: <cit>
            <q>Yesterday night in Baden General Director Moritz Schenker, an erstwhile
              extraordinarily well-known personality in Vienna banking and finance circles,
              committed suicide. The 62-year-old man was found dead in his house at Elizabethstraße
              17 filled with lighting gas. Pecuniary difficulties were the likely motive for his
              state of desperation.</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>On the last page of the diary she kept of her journey to Santiago, Chile in 1936 (OJ
          35/9), <ref cRef="entity-000771">Jeanette Schenker</ref> recorded on September 30:<cit>
            <q>I do not regard it as out of place to add what I learned from the director of the
                <ref cRef="entity-004061">Merkur Bank</ref> on the way back from [visiting
              Heinrich’s grave in] the cemetery: that only a few days before, the younger brother of
              my beloved husband voluntarily left this life! A highly gifted person, he gained
              importance and respect from his own powers, and also wealth. But for years he was
              dogged by bad luck; and his need for peace is something that I can well understand. He
              was kind to me after my beloved husband passed away: may his memory be honored.</q>
          </cit></p>

      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Relationship with Heinrich</head>
        <p><figure>
            <head>Moriz (standing), Heinrich (seated), 1901 (OJ 72/14, No. 4)</head>
            <graphic url="B72F14_4.jpg" xmt:type="thumb-caption" rend="left-img" width="150px"
              height="113px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <graphic url="B72F14_4.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img" width="800px" height="600px"
              mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <figDesc>Photograph of Moriz and Heinrich Schenker.</figDesc>
          </figure></p>
        <p>Together with <ref cRef="entity-000775">Wilhelm</ref> and Heinrich, Moriz contributed
          money to the upkeep of his mother, <ref cRef="entity-000773">Julia Schenker</ref>, at
          least from January 1914 (when Heinrich had to resort to an attorney to force him to
          contribute adequately – <ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-11-26_5">OJ 11/26, [5]</ref>)
          onwards to her death in 1917. Later, he became effectively financial adviser to the whole
          Schenker family, supporting <ref cRef="entity-002935">Sophie’s family</ref>, even
          supplying a dowry for her daughter <ref cRef="entity-000315">Frieda</ref>; and providing
          Heinrich with money whenever he needed, especially over the summers, when the latter had
          no other income. During the legal proceedings between Heinrich and <ref
            cRef="entity-002408">Universal Edition</ref> in 1925 he acted as intermediary to the
          disputing parties in a crucial meeting, and the agreed compensatory payments from <ref
            cRef="entity-002408">UE</ref> to Heinrich were to be paid into Moriz’s account.</p>

        <p>Being for a time relatively wealthy, he fell victim to Schenker's general detestation of
          "the rich." For example, Moriz's behavior on the occasion of his decoration (see above)
          was dubbed by Heinrich "an unequaled piece of Schenker shenanigans" (<hi rend="italic">ein
            Schenkerei ohnegleichen</hi>) and "damnable." Having invested in Moriz’s property in
            <ref cRef="entity-004104">Reichraming</ref>, Heinrich strove to retrieve his money,
          ultimately embarking in January 1931 on litigation against his brother for non-return of
          his property investment.</p>

        <p>Moriz played the violin well enough to have played chamber music informally with
          Heinrich. His son <ref cRef="entity-000769">Georg</ref>, a cellist, had lessons in theory
          with Heinrich before joining the Baden theater orchestra.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Heinrich and Others; Photographs</head>

        <p>Correspondence from Moriz to Heinrich Schenker survives as OJ 14/5 (1918–30: 42 items
          (including two items to Julia Schenker, 1912, one from Julia to Heinrich, 1914, and one
          from Moriz and Hans Guttmann to Heinrich, 1918), and OC 54/31 and 32 (1925), A/284 and 285
          (1934). Some correspondence with Universal Edition exists as OC 52/466 and 467 (1924), and
          with the attorney Theodor Baumgarten, OC 52/703 (1925), regarding the dispute with UE. OJ
          35/8 contains "financial transactions between Heinrich Schenker and Moriz Schenker, Anny
          Wollner and Drei Masken-Verlag, 1922–31." </p>

        <p>Two photographic portraits survive, as OJ 72/18, No. 2 (postcard: Moriz alone, c. 1901)
          and OJ 72/14, No. 4, standing with Heinrich seated, 1901).</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
              Tagebüchern und Briefen ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985)</bibl>
          <bibl>Private communication from Elizabeth Brinsden (October 18, 2011)</bibl>
          <bibl><title>ANNO – Historische Zeitungen und Zeitschriften</title></bibl>
          <bibl>correspondence and diaries</bibl>

        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Marko Deisinger</hi>, revised <hi rend="bold">Ian
              Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>

  </text>
</TEI>
