<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-007504">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Irene Schreier Scott</title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, July 1, 1929</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="schreier_scott_irene">Schreier Scott, Irene</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">schreier_scott_irene</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Irene Schreier Scott</head>
      <div>
        <p>Austrian-born American pianist and teacher, pupil of <ref cRef="entity-000913">Moriz
            Violin</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-000412">Oswald Jonas</ref>.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Irene Schreier was born in Vienna on July 1, 1929, the daughter of mathematician <ref
            cRef="entity-007655">Otto Schreier</ref> (1901‒29) and his wife <ref
            cRef="entity-007656">Edith</ref> (<hi rend="italic">née</hi> Jacoby, 1891‒1974). From
          the age of six she took piano lessons with <ref cRef="entity-000913">Moriz Violin</ref> in
          Vienna, 1935‒39. Her father had studied with <ref cRef="entity-000913">Violin</ref> in
          Vienna prior to 1920 and again between 1923 and 1929 in <ref cRef="entity-002589"
            >Hamburg</ref>, where he worked at the Mathematical Seminar of the University; and her
          mother had studied with <ref cRef="entity-000913">Violin</ref> in <ref
            cRef="entity-002589">Hamburg</ref> between 1921 and 1929. Her parents' married in 1928
          but <ref cRef="entity-007655">Otto</ref> died on June 2, 1929 and <ref
            cRef="entity-007656">Edith</ref> immediately returned to Vienna for Irene's birth a
          month later.</p>

        <p>In January 1939, Irene and <ref cRef="entity-007656">Edith</ref> emigrated to the <ref
            cRef="entity-002510">USA</ref> following <ref cRef="entity-002482">Germany</ref>'s
          annexation of <ref cRef="entity-002506">Austria</ref>, as they were of Jewish origin.
          Likewise, the <ref cRef="entity-002938">Violin family</ref> emigrated, the two families
          meeting in <ref cRef="entity-002921">San Francisco</ref>. Irene resumed lessons with <ref
            cRef="entity-000913">Violin</ref>, who presented her in public for the first time when
          she was 11, in a fund-raising event for new refugees at the city's Temple Emanuel, of
          which <ref cRef="entity-000913">Violin</ref> wrote to <ref cRef="entity-000798"
            >Schoenberg</ref>: "It was an extraordinary success for the child" (<ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="LC-ASC-27-45_22">LC ASC 27/45, [22]</ref>, October 23,
          1940).</p>

        <p>Having been taught in <ref cRef="entity-000913">Violin</ref>'s Schenker-oriented approach
          to the piano, it was a natural step for Irene eventually to be introduced to Schenker's
          theory: in 1942 <ref cRef="entity-007656">Edith</ref> married <ref cRef="entity-000412"
            >Oswald Jonas</ref> and moved to <ref cRef="entity-007400">Chicago</ref>. In due course,
            <ref cRef="entity-000412">Jonas</ref> became Irene's teacher, along with pianist Leonard
          Shure. After finishing school, Irene was awarded a fellowship which enabled her to travel
          to Europe. She participated in the Edwin Fischer Master Classes in Switzerland ‒ another
          source of inspiration ‒ and an award at the First Munich International Piano Competition
          brought radio and concert engagements throughout <ref cRef="entity-002482">Germany</ref>
          and <ref cRef="entity-002506">Austria</ref> as well as in Scandinavia, the Netherlands,
          and England. After returning to the <ref cRef="entity-002510">USA</ref>, she performed
          repeatedly in <ref cRef="entity-002873">New York</ref>'s Carnegie Recital Hall (now Weill
          Hall), in <ref cRef="entity-007400">Chicago</ref>, <ref cRef="entity-002921">San
            Francisco</ref>, and many smaller venues. </p>

        <p>Her career continued after her marriage to mathematician Dana Scott in 1959. During the
          years he occupied the chair of Mathematical Logic in Oxford she toured in Israel as well
          as Mexico, where she also gave lecture recitals. This became a new part of her work after
          the family returned to the <ref cRef="entity-002510">USA</ref> in 1981, Dana having been
          invited to Carnegie Mellon University in Pittsburgh, where he occupied the chair of
          Computer Science, Philosophy, and Mathematical Logic 1981‒2003. After introductory
          concerts there, Irene was offered the position of Artist Lecturer in the School of Music
          and also taught Schenker's theory, using <bibl><ref cRef="entity-000412">Jonas</ref>'s
              <title level="m">Introduction to the Theory of Heinrich Schenker</title> (Eng. transl.
            John Rothgeb, 1982)</bibl> as her text. It was during this time that she translated
          Heribert Esser's edition of Schenker's <ref cRef="entity-001757">Die Kunst des
            Vortrags</ref>. <ref cRef="entity-000412">Jonas</ref>, who owned the materials for this
          oft-announced but ultimately unfinished work, had planned to publish it, but died before
          the complicated task could be completed. Esser's edition in Irene's translation, with
          Esser's introductory history of the project and source materials, was published by Oxford
          University Press in 2000 as <ref cRef="entity-001757"><title level="m">The Art of
              Performance</title></ref>.</p>

        <p>At <ref cRef="entity-000412">Oswald Jonas</ref>'s death in 1978, Irene inherited the
          large body of Schenker's posthumous papers that he had taken to the <ref
            cRef="entity-002510">USA</ref> after World War II, together with his own substantial
          library. These (which included Schenker's diaries and much correspondence) she entrusted
          to the Special Collections Library of the University of California, Riverside as the
          Oswald Memorial Collection.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Schreier Scot and Moriz Violin</head>
        <p>As already stated, Irene was one of <ref cRef="entity-000913">Moriz Violin</ref>'s pupils
          in Vienna from the age of 6, 1935 to 1939, and in <ref cRef="entity-002921">San
            Francisco</ref> from 1939 to 1942. She comments in <title level="m">The Art of
            Performance</title> (2000, p. vii): <cit>
            <q>Violin was Heinrich Schenker's younger colleague and closest friend, in whom Schenker
              confided and with whom he shared his musical ideas. Having intuitively assimilated
              these concepts, Violin imparted them in his own teaching along with a special,
              unforgettable approach to the piano. From the age of six, therefore, I was shown a
              natural way of playing entirely at one with the music and, perhaps because Violin had
              never taught a child before, I was spared any of the "piano methods" most beginners
              are taught.</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>When she later came to teach piano herself, Irene naturally incorporated the teachings of
            <ref cRef="entity-000913">Violin</ref>, hence to some extent those that Schenker himself
          taught to his pupils, into her approach to teaching.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Schreier Scott and Oswald Jonas</head>
        <p>As a pupil of <ref cRef="entity-000412">Oswald Jonas</ref> in <ref cRef="entity-007400"
            >Chicago</ref> from 1942 for some years, Irene became acquainted with Schenker's
          theories through the original edition of his introduction, <bibl><title level="m">Das
              Wesen des musikalischen Kunstwerks</title> (Vienna, Saturn Verlag, 1934)</bibl>. As
          outlined above, she later used this in English translation as the basis of her teaching at
          Carnegie Mellon University.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Bibliography</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="a">Oswald Jonas (1897–1978),</title> in: <author>Oswald Jonas</author>,
              <title level="m">Introduction to the Theory of Heinrich Schenker</title>, Eng. transl.
              <editor>John Rothgeb</editor> (New York: Longman, 1982; 2nd edn Ann Arbor: Musicalia
            Press, 2005), pp. v–vi</bibl>

          <bibl>Eng. transl., <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker, The Art of Performance</title>,
            ed. <editor>Heribert Esser</editor> (New York: Oxford University Press, 2000)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>


      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <ref type="external" target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dana_Scott"><title level="m"
                >Wikipedia</title> "Dana Scott"</ref></bibl>

          <bibl> Private communications from Irene Schreier Scott</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
