<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000951">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Hans Weisse</title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, March 31, 1892; died New York, Feb 10, 1940</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="weisse_hans">Weisse, Hans</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>17/12/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Weisse ~ H+JSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">Weisse ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">Weisse ~ JSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">weisse_hans</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Hans Weisse</head>
      <div>
        <p> Austrian (later naturalized American) teacher, theorist, and composer.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Life, Teaching, Compositions, Impact</head>
        <p><figure>
            <head>Hans Weisse with Brahms portrait, c. 1913 (OJ 72/24, No. 1 -Franz Hofer)</head>
            <graphic url="B72F24_1.jpg" xmt:type="thumb-caption" rend="left-img" width="150px"
              height="113px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <graphic url="B72F24_1.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img" width="800px" height="600px"
              mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <figDesc>Photograph of Hans Weisse.</figDesc>
          </figure></p>
        <p>Weisse studied with Schenker between 1908 and 1919, taught for ten years in Vienna and,
          after contemplating prospects in Germany, opted to emigrate to the USA, teaching in New
          York until his premature death. He, more than anyone else, deserves credit for initiating
          the wide dissemination of Schenker's theory that took place in the USA in the mid-20th
          century, his impact coming not through publications but through his teaching, his pupils
          including Oswald Jonas, Adele T. Katz, William J. Mitchell, and Felix Salzer.</p>
        <div>
          <head>Period of Study</head>
          <p>Son of the distinguished actor and theater director <ref cRef="entity-000949">Adolf
              Weisse</ref>, Hans Weisse studied theory and composition with Schenker from 1908. He
            was initially a piano pupil of <ref cRef="entity-000913">Moriz Violin</ref>, but in
            August 1912 (OJ 15/16, [8]) asked Schenker to take over these lessons, too, and after
            some awkwardness the transfer occurred on June 3, 1913 (OJ 1/11, p. 359). Weisse
            continued lessons with Schenker until 1915, then served as an officer in the Austrian
            army before returning in 1919 to Vienna, where he spent a further half year with his
            teacher. During the 1920s, he continued to take occasional lessons (entries in
            Schenker's lessonbooks span January 1912 to January 1927). Weisse's notebooks containing
            ‒ with <hi rend="italic">lacunae</hi> ‒ his counterpoint exercises for lessons with
            Schenker 1912‒13 and with corrections in Schenker's hand, and for his "review" course in
            counterpoint 1918‒19, survive among his papers now in the possession of his descendants.
            Details of these are given in Jackson (2010).</p>
          <p>During the 1910s Weisse was also enrolled at the University of Vienna, where he studied
            with <ref cRef="entity-000003">Guido Adler</ref>. He was awarded the Ph.D. degree in
            1919 for a thesis on the "artistic waltz," though much of this had been completed before
            his military service, and probably more under Schenker's eye than Adler's. (A typescript
            of "Der Kunstwalzer und seine bedeutendsten Vertreter," inscribed to Schenker and dated
            February 1915, is in the Oster Collection -- in 1914, Schenker tried to persuade <ref
              cRef="entity-002408">Universal Edition</ref> to publish the work (WSLB 235, December
            29), and again in 1919 (WSLB 302, May 18).</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Teaching in Vienna</head>
          <p>After formally and effusively thanking Schenker in June 1920 for the tuition he had
            given him (OJ 15/16, [41]), Weisse set up as a teacher himself, and was successful in
            attracting a large number of gifted pupils, including some Americans (the cellist <ref
              cRef="entity-000934">Gerald Warburg</ref>, the organist <ref cRef="entity-000550"
              >Victor Vaughan Lytle</ref>), through whom he was eventually to gain an entrée into
            American music education. Weisse's gifts as an educator were also recognized by Adler,
            who in 1921 recommended him as a teacher for the Institute for Rural Reconstruction
            founded by the Nobel prizewinning Indian poet and philosopher, Rabindranath Tagore, in
            West Bengal. (Weisse declined this invitation, partly on the grounds of being unable to
            speak English fluently.)</p>
          <p>By the mid-1920s his pupils included <ref cRef="entity-000754">Felix Salzer</ref> and
              <ref cRef="entity-000412">Oswald Jonas</ref>, who were to study with Schenker after
            Weisse's departure for New York, and who followed him to America to cement the
            foundations of Schenkerian theory there. He seems to have had a particularly close
            relationship with Jonas, one that mirrored that between himself and Schenker (whom he
            repeatedly acknowledged as his "spiritual father"). In 1927, he conceived a journal,
              <ref cRef="tonkunst_die">Die Tonkunst</ref>, devoted to Schenkerian theory, which was
            to be edited by Jonas; this project fell through for lack of sponsorship, but a similar
            enterprise was successfully launched by Jonas and Salzer in 1937. In 1931, he put Jonas
            on to the task of compiling all of Schenker's early journalism (c. 1891-1901) and
            preparing a general preface charting the progress of Schenker's thinking between 1900
            and 1930. Though this project, too, did not reach fruition, Jonas was nonetheless able
            to complete a book-length introduction to Schenkerian theory in 1934.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Prospects in Germany</head>
          <p>The year 1930/31 marked a turning point in Weisse's life. Through the efforts of <ref
              cRef="entity-000268">Wilhelm Furtwängler</ref>, with whom he had long been on friendly
            terms, he was invited to give a series of three lectures on Schenkerian theory at the
              <ref cRef="entity-003058">Central Institute for Musical Education in Berlin</ref> in
            December; a further series, given to the <ref cRef="entity-002445">Society for Music
              Pedagogy in Vienna</ref> in February, included the lecture <title level="a">What is
              Counterpoint?</title> (A typed essay with this title is preserved in the Oster
            Collection (OC 17/3); but, as he remarks in several letters, Weisse extemporized before
            his audiences, rather than reading a prepared text.) Around this time, Violin asked
            Weisse to teach theory at his new Schenker-Institut in Hamburg; Weisse contemplated this
            proposal for a while but ultimately accepted the offer of a year's teaching at the <ref
              cRef="entity-002454">David Mannes Music School</ref> in New York.</p>
          <p>That spring, in spite of the pressures of preparing for a new teaching post in a
            foreign country he had never before visited, Weisse expended considerable energy
            mobilizing Furtwängler to raise 3,000 Marks to defray the printing costs of Schenker's
            "Eroica" Symphony analysis for <title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</title>,
            vol. III. (Weisse may have also been instrumental at that time in obtaining from the
            Viennese industrialist <ref cRef="entity-005758">Paul Khuner</ref> a further 5,000
            shillings toward the publication of <title level="m">Der freie Satz</title>.) Despite
            the occasional innuendo from within Schenker's circle that he was exploiting his
            teacher's work, Weisse consistently insured that Schenker received just remuneration for
            his work; and when, after Schenker's death in 1935, Weisse learned that his widow
            Jeanette was facing poverty, he devised and successfully executed a scheme whereby his
            pupils contributed to a kind of pension fund, thus guaranteeing her a monthly income of
            200 shillings for the year 1935/36, this in spite of the hardship that he, and many of
            his pupils, faced during the Great Depression (OJ 15/16, [98]).</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>New York</head>
          <p>Arriving in New York in late September 1931, he introduced himself to his new
            colleagues at Mannes with a successful half-hour talk on "the relationship of a music
            theory teacher to the other teachers in a school of music" (OJ 15/16, [82]), and he
            quickly confirmed his reputation as a gifted educator. Many of the letters of this
            period describe the success he had in communicating the importance of music theory for
            the way music should be listened to and, especially, performed.</p>
          <p>Weisse's family joined him in New York the following season, during which he was also
            engaged at Columbia University. They maintained a European household, speaking
            exclusively in German at home, and spent the summer holidays in the country: there are
            letters from Lake Placid, New York, from 1933, and from Tenant's Harbor, Maine, from
            1934 and 1935. Weisse devoted the summers as much as possible to composition. Despite
            the difficult economic conditions in America, which for a time meant a reduction in
            teaching and a cut in salary, he succeeded in implanting Schenker's views on music in a
            new generation of Americans, including the composers <ref cRef="entity-000131">Israel
              Citkowitz</ref> and Arthur Berger, and the writers Adele T. Katz and William J.
            Mitchell. After his untimely death, at the age of 48, he was succeeded at Mannes by
            Salzer, the title of whose seminal textbook <title level="m">Structural Hearing</title>,
            1952) resonates with that of the first course Weisse taught at Mannes, "Creative
            Hearing."</p>
          <p>Weisse's time in New York is characterized by a growing independence of thought, in
            particular a concern with communicating Schenker's most advanced ideas in the most
            pragmatic way, rather than allowing this to be guided by cultural or political ideology.
            His involvement in the publication, jointly in New York and Vienna in 1932, of the
            textless (and thus polemics-free) <title level="m">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln/Five Analyses in
              Sketchform</title> is emblematic of this stance. He wrote frankly to Schenker that the
            early <title level="m">Harmonielehre</title> was a poor choice for a first
            English-language textbook on Schenkerian theory; and when, in the summer of 1935, he
            made a long, intensive study of <title level="m">Der freie Satz</title>, he was
            unrestrained (and, later, unrepentant) in his condemnation of a book that, in his view,
            was misconceived and failed to give a coherent account of its subject matter. This
            critique is expressed in two long letters to Jeanette Schenker (OJ 15/16, [100]-[101]
            and one to <ref cRef="entity-000913">Moriz Violin</ref> (OJ 70/46, [12]). For some of
            Schenker's followers, including <ref cRef="entity-000922">Otto Vrieslander</ref> and
            Violin, the American Weisse was an apostate, having betrayed Schenker and his "cause";
            but Weisse continued to defend his position, insisting that communicating the "idea"
            underlying Schenker's views of music was what mattered, not whether Schenker would have
            approved of his approach.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Weisse's Compositions</head>
          <p>Among the pieces composed by Weisse mentioned in the letters -- from which we are able
            to assign dates of composition -- are a string quintet (1912; new first movement, 1913),
            a string quartet (performed by the Rosé Quartet on November 3, 1921), a clarinet sonata
            (1921), vocal quartets with piano accompaniment (published by UE in 1924), a clarinet
            quintet (1926), a cycle of bagatelles for piano (1929), a string sextet and an octet
            (1930), some three-voice piano pieces (1931) and a violin sonata (1932) in "Bachian"
            style, a set of variations and fugue on a "popular American song" (1933), and a second
            string quartet and a set of six-voice madrigals on texts by Goethe (both 1934). From
            1912 on, Schenker repeatedly recommended UE to publish his works ("very, very fine
            works; they will surely [...] bring you commercial success" -- WSLB 116, June 2, 1912);
            in letters to other pupils of his, Schenker often expressed praise for Weisse's
            compositions, particularly the Octet and the pieces in Bachian style.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Correspondence</head>
        <div>
          <head>with the Schenkers</head>
          <p>His correspondence with the Schenkers survives as OJ 5/45 (Schenker to Weisse: 7 items,
            1915-31), OJ 15/15-16 (Weisse to the Schenkers: 177 items, 1910-35), and OC 18/32-33,
            20/402, 24/85-86, 97, 100, 44/41, 52/650-651 (Weisse to Schenker: 8 items, 1921-34). In
            addition, there is a letter from Weisse to Otto Vrieslander regarding a planned Schenker
            Festschrift (OJ 71/40), and four photographs of Weisse, one with his children (OJ
            72/24).</p>
          <p>Several of Weisse's early letters to Schenker include analytical material on the
            waltzes Op. 39 and other compositions by Brahms. After 1915, there are few such
            discussions, but one of Bach's short preludes surfaces at the time of the 1930-31
            lectures.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>with Moriz Violin</head>
          <p>Only the Weisse side of the Weisse/Violin correspondence is known to survive, and it
            divides into three groups. The first, OJ 70/46, [1], [3]-[5], is a series of short notes
            dating from January and February 1912, when Weisse was a piano pupil of Violin's; they
            mostly concern a recital given by Violin in which some of Weisse's compositions were to
            be performed. The second, OJ 70/46, [6]-[11], comprises six letters written in 1931, a
            year in which Weisse was actively seeking to obtain regular employment outside of Vienna
            and Violin was in the process of setting up a Schenker-Institut in Hamburg. The last
            group comprises a single letter of 1935, OJ 70/46, [12], in which Weisse defends his
            critical stance with regard to <hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</hi>, which had been
            published earlier that year.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>with Oswald Jonas</head>
          <p>There are early letters from Weisse to Jonas, and a brief two-way correspondence dating
            from 1938, after Jonas had left an Austria annexed to Germany by the Nazis (OJ 36/73: 2
            items: Jonas to Weisse; OJ 36/246, 6 items: Weisse to Jonas). These show that Weisse was
            successful in obtaining from <ref cRef="entity-000934">Gerald Warburg</ref> an affidavit
            that would enable Jonas to emigrate to America; in one of these letters (OJ 36/246,
            [6]), he urges his former pupil to cast off the ideological and polemical aspects of
            Schenker's teaching, as these were alienating to "the American psychology" and could
            only inhibit the spread of Schenker's ideas in the New World.</p>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>with Leo Kestenberg</head>
          <p>Copies of two letters from Kestenberg to Weisse, dated July 15 and August 4, 1930, are
            preserved as OJ 71/20, [1] and [2]. Weisse's replies, though referred to in Schenker's
            diary, are not known to survive.</p>

        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <div>
          <head>Bibliography</head>
          <listBibl>
            <bibl><author>Weisse, Hans</author>, <title level="a">Was ist Kontrapunkt?</title> OC
              17/3 [22-page typescript, with emendations in Weisse's and Schenker's hands, c.
              1931/32]</bibl>
            <bibl><author>Weisse, Hans</author>, <title level="a">The Music Teacher's
                Dilemma,</title>
              <title level="j">Proceedings of the Music Teachers National Association</title>
              (1936), 122-37; repr. in <title level="j">Theory and Practice</title> x (1985),
              29-48</bibl>
            <bibl><author>Hans Weisse</author>, <title>Music</title> [interview with Irving Kolodin]
                <title level="j">Arts Weekly</title> i (New York, 1932) [preserved in OC 2/p. 86,
              pp. 86/87]</bibl>
          </listBibl>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Sources:</head>
          <listBibl>
            <bibl><author>Berry, David Carson</author>, <title level="a">Hans Weisse and the Dawn of
                American Schenkerism,</title>
              <title level="j">Journal of Musicology</title> xx/1 (Winter 2003), 104-56</bibl>
            <bibl><editor>Eybl, M.</editor> &amp; <editor>Fink-Mennel, E.</editor>, eds, <title
                level="a">Hans Weisse (1892-1940),</title> in <title level="m">Schenker-Traditionen:
                Eine Wiener Schule der Musiktheorie und ihre internationale Verbreitung</title>
              (Vienna: Böhlau, 2006), pp. 91-103</bibl>
            <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
                Tagebüchern und Briefen ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), pp. 50-55,
              116-19, <hi rend="italic">et passim</hi></bibl>
            <bibl><author>Grünzweig, Werner</author>, <title level="s">Vom 'Schenkerismus' zum
                'Dahlhaus-Projekt': Einflüsse deutschsprachiger Musiker und Musikwissenschaftler in
                den Vereinigten -- Anfänge und Ausblick,</title>
              <title level="j">Österreichische Musik Zeitschrift</title> iii-iv (1993),
              161-70</bibl>
            <bibl><author>Jackson, Timothy L.</author>, <title level="a">
                <hi rend="italic">Punctus contra punctus</hi> ‒ a Counterpoint of Schenkerian and
                Weissian Analysis and Hans Weisse's Counterpoint Studies with Heinrich
                Schenker,</title>
              <title level="j">Journal of Schenkerian Studies</title>, iv (2010), pp. 87‒186
              [includes details of Weisse's lesson notebooks, and a preliminary list of his
              compositions]</bibl>
            <bibl><author>Kurth, Ulrich</author>, <title level="m">Die Auswirkung der Lehre Heinrich
                Schenkers und seiner Schüler in den USA</title>, <title level="s">Deutsche
                Forschungsgemeinschaft SP "Exilforschung" (DFG-Az. 8/9-1), Wiener Schulen in den
                USA</title> (Schwerte: typescript report, April 1985), pp. 98-104 <hi rend="italic"
                >et passim</hi></bibl>





          </listBibl>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Contributor:</head>
          <listBibl>
            <bibl><author>William Drabkin</author></bibl>
          </listBibl>
        </div>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
