<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-000922">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Otto Vrieslander</title>
        <title type="sub">born Münster, July 18, 1880; died Tegna, Dec 16, 1950</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="vrieslander_otto">Vrieslander, Otto</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>16/07/2006</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Vrieslander ~ H+JSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">Vrieslander ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">Vrieslander ~ JSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">vrieslander_otto</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Otto Vrieslander</head>
      <div>
        <p>German composer, teacher, theorist, pupil of Schenker's.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Vrieslander studied piano and composition in Düsseldorf 1891-1900, at the Cologne
          Conservatory 1909-02, and composition in Munich 1904-1911. After brief study with Schenker
          in Vienna, he taught composition, piano, and theory in Ebersberg, nr. Munich 1912-24, then
          in Naples and Vienna. From 1929, he lived in Switzerland.</p>
        <p>Vrieslander was a composer notably of Lieder (including a setting of poems from Giraud's
            <title level="m">Pierrot lunaire</title> in O. E. Hartleben's translation, dating from
          1904 - eight years before Schoenberg's melodrama cycle: both settings were commissioned by
          Albertine Zehme, but whereas Zehme performed Schoenberg's setting, she was dissatisfied by
          that of Vrieslander and never performed it).</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Vrieslander and Schenker</head>
        <p>Vrieslander was a pupil of Schenker only during the 1911/12 season: records survive only
          for January 5 to March 5, 1912, and Vrieslander took lessons twice a week (Mondays and
          Thursdays) between January 15 and February 29. He remained in contact with Schenker for
          the rest of the latter's life as a member of the inner circle of long-time friends, former
          students, and supporters (others include, e.g., <ref cRef="entity-000107">Robert
            Brünauer</ref>, <ref cRef="entity-000149">Walter Dahms</ref> (a pupil of
          Vrieslander), <ref cRef="entity-000737">Herman Roth</ref>, <ref cRef="entity-000951">Hans
            Weisse</ref>, Viktor Zuckerkandl, and <ref cRef="entity-000643">Reinhard Oppel</ref>).</p>
        <p>Vrieslander advocated several projects (all ultimately abortive): in 1915, a second
          edition of Schenker's <title level="m">Harmonielehre</title> (which he used in his own
          teaching, and on which he wrote three unpublished commentaries between 1910 and 1925 and
          for which he compiled a list of typographical errors), and adding exercises and
          assignments (which Schenker resisted); in 1918, a Festschrift for Schenker's 50th
          birthday; in 1919-20, the founding of a Schenker Institute in Munich; in 1921, with
          Hoboken, the publishing of inexpensive Urtext editions and a periodical; in 1926-27, a
          Festschrift for Schenker's 60th birthday; in 1927-28 a monthly <ref cRef="tonkunst_die">Schenker periodical</ref> planned by Weisse, Salzer, and Jonas; around 1927, a Schenker
          monograph-cum-anthology; and in 1932 a student edition (<hi rend="italic">Schulausgabe</hi>) of <title level="m">Harmonielehre</title> (of which he was then making
          a "concentrated" version) for use by <ref cRef="entity-000577">Josef Marx</ref> at the
          Vienna Hochschule für Musik und darstellende Kunst (=Conservatory). After Schenker's
          death, Jeanette Schenker wished Vrieslander to produce a new edition of the <title level="m">Harmonielehre</title>, gave him Schenker's personal annotated copy for this
          purpose from which he copied out Schenker's numerous additions, and in 1938 signed a
          contract with him at UE for which he was paid an advance--but the annexation of Austria
          intervened.</p>
        <p>It was Vrieslander who recommended <ref cRef="entity-000737">Herman Roth</ref>, and <ref cRef="entity-000380">Anthony van Hoboken</ref> to Schenker. He also advised
          Hoboken in the building up of the latter's collection of first editions. In 1920,
          Vrieslander served as intermediary with the publisher <ref cRef="entity-002405">J. G.
          Cotta</ref> of Stuttgart by delivering the manuscript of <title level="m">Kontrapunkt
          2</title> to them; and more importantly in 1924 as an intermediary with the Drei Masken
          Verlag of Munich in dealings that resulted in the publication of Schenker's <title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</title> (1925, 1926, 1930), the proofs of which
          he assisted in correcting.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Impact of Schenker on Vrieslander</head>
        <p>After encountering Schenker's <title level="m">Hamonielehre</title>, Vrieslander
          underwent a sharp break with his previous compositional style (even destroying copies
          wherever possible), his new beginning occurring in 1916. Schenker thought highly of
          Vrieslander's work from that time on, describing his Lieder as "the best since the death
          of [Hugo] Wolf," and "among the best that the Lieder repertory has to offer from the
          post-Brahms era." Schenker states in 1917 that he commissioned a work from Vrieslander and
          subsequently paid him money from the stipend fund created by <ref cRef="entity-000165">Sofie Deutsch</ref>.</p>
        <p>Under Schenker's influence, Vrieslander made a "critical edition with elucidatory
          appendix" (dedicated to Schenker) of C. P. E. Bach's <title level="m">Kurze und leichte
            Clavierstücke: Neue kritische Ausgabe mit erläuterndem Nachwort</title> (Short
          and easy keyboard pieces: new critical edition with elucidatory afterword) (Vienna: UE,
          1914), which the cover title significantly characterized as: <title level="m">Erläuterungsausgabe</title> (elucidatory edition: the term that Schenker himself
          used for his publications on the late Beethoven piano sonatas); he also published the
          edition <title level="m">C. P. E. Bach: Lieder und Gesänge</title> (Munich: Drei
          Masken Verlag, 1922) and wrote the monograph <title level="m">Carl Philipp Emanuel
          Bach</title> (Munich: Piper, 1923), and contributed the article <title level="a">Carl
            Philipp Emanuel Bach als Theoretiker</title> to <title level="m">Von neuer Musik</title>
          (Cologne 1925) and <title level="j">Ganymed</title> iv (1922). Vrieslander also wrote
          articles about Schenker and his work: <ref cRef="musikblatter_des_anb"><title level="j">Musikblätter des Anbruch</title></ref>, February/March 1923; <ref cRef="musik_die"><title level="j">Die Musik</title></ref>, xix/1 (October 1926), 33-38;
            <title level="j">Deutsche Tonkünstler-Zeitung</title>, March 5, 1928; and <title level="j">Der Kunstwart</title> xliii (1930), 181-189.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Correspondence</head>
        <p>The majority of the correspondence between Schenker and Vrieslander forms part of the
          Vrieslander Nachlaß, which is privately owned by Heribert Esser (the letters from
          Vrieslander to Schenker having been mostly returned by Jeanette Schenker). There are 18
          letters from Vrieslander to Schenker in the Oster Collection (OC 18/5-22 <hi rend="italic">passim</hi>; OC 54/11-140 <hi rend="italic">passim</hi> (Cotta-Verlag); OC 69/2-3:
          1925-26, 1932-33); 2 letters from Schenker to Vrieslander and 12 from Otto and Helene
          Vrieslander to Schenker in the Jonas Collection (OJ 5/42 and OJ 15/4: 1912, 1917-20,
          1935-39), and 5 from the Vrieslanders and Herman Roth to Schenker (OJ 13/30: undated); 1
          from Vrieslander to Violin (OJ 70/43: 1912), 1 from Vrieslander to Robert Brünauer
          (OJ 71/37: undated), 1 from Hans Weisse to Vrieslander (OJ 71/40: [1918], concerning the
          50th birthday Festschrift), and a portrait of Vrieslander and Roth (OJ 72/13). The
          Vrieslander correspondence is an invaluable repository of biographical information about
          Schenker himself, his pupils, and contemporaries.</p>
        <p>Vrieslander's list of errors in, and his copy of a portion of Schenker's additions to,
            <title level="m">Harmonielehre</title> survive as OJ 18/6; his three commentaries (72pp,
          468pp, 472pp), are in the possession of Mr. Esser.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Baker's1971</title></bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">NGDM2</title> (2201 and online)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="a">Otto Vrieslander,</title> in <editor>Eybl, M.</editor> &amp;
              <editor>Fink-Mennel, E.</editor>, eds, <title level="m">Schenker-Traditionen: Eine
              Wiener Schule der Musiktheorie und ihre internationale Verbreitung</title> (Vienna:
            Böhlau, 2006), pp. 246-47, also pp. 188-89, 196-99 <hi rend="italic">et passim</hi>
          </bibl>
          <bibl>Oster Collection Finding List</bibl>
          <bibl>Jonas Memorial Collection Checklist</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Wason, Robert</author>, <title level="a">From 'Harmonielehre' to 'Harmony':
              Schenker's Theory of Harmony and its Americanization,</title> in <editor>Cadwallader,
              A.</editor>, ed., <title level="m">Essays from the Fourth International Schenker
              Symposium</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 2008), pp. 213-58 </bibl>
          <bibl>Private communications from Heribert Esser</bibl>
          <bibl>Private communication from Robert Wason</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
