<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000774">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Moriz [Maurice; Mozio; Moses] Schenker</title>
        <title type="sub">born Podhajce, Galicia, Auguat 31, 1874; died September 1936</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="schenker_moriz">Schenker, Moriz</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>07/07/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">SchenkerM ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">schenker_moriz</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Moriz [Maurice; Mozio; Moses] Schenker</head>

      <div>
        <p>Younger brother of Heinrich Schenker, and also of <ref cRef="entity-000319"
            >Shifre/Sophie</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-000775">Wilhelm</ref> Schenker; youngest
          child of <ref cRef="entity-000772">Johann</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-000773">Julia</ref>
          Schenker, both Jewish. </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career summary</head>

        <p>Following his father’s death in 1887, Moriz Schenker was brough to Vienna, where,
          according to Oswald Jonas, Heinrich Schenker was “responsible for the sustenance of his
          destitute family” (<bibl><title level="a">H. Schenker,</title>
            <title level="m">MGG</title> vol. 11 (1963), col. 1670</bibl>). Moriz worked first for
          the lumber company of the <ref cRef="entity-003218">Eissler family</ref>, who were patrons
          of Heinrich, until the latter encouraged him to go to business school. After that, he went
          into banking (diary, April 4, 1915) with the <ref cRef="entity-002467">Österreichische
            Länderbank</ref>, in which he served for some years at its office in Egypt (he later
          remarked: "Egypt is my second home [...] unfortunately a continuous life there is
          impossible." ‒ diary Nov 17, 1926). Later he worked in the Rumanian side of the bank,
          often in Bucharest, which entailed much travel, during which in November–December 1918 he
          was interned in Bucharest. In 1914, there is reference to his receiving a "decoration"
            (<hi rend="italic">Dekorierung</hi>) there (diary, Sep 16, 1914). From 1924 he moved to
          the recently founded Vienna-based import-export <ref cRef="entity-004196">Treuga
            Bank</ref>.</p>

        <p>He acquired a villa in <ref cRef="entity-002394">Baden bei Wien</ref> in 1913 (diary, Nov
          29, 1913), which he apparently retained for the rest of his life while having business
          premises elsewhere, including an office in Vienna. At the height of his career he amassed
          considerable wealth (Heinrich spoke of him as a “billionaire”), and in 1929 he purchased a
          property in <ref cRef="entity-005929">Upper Austria</ref> for investment purposes, into
          which Heinrich put money. </p>

        <p>The date of Moriz’s marriage to the non-Jewish <ref cRef="entity-003438">Lisl</ref>
          (maiden name unknown) is unclear. The couple had two children: <ref cRef="entity-003067"
            >Helga</ref> (b. 1907) and <ref cRef="entity-000769">Georg</ref>. One small insight into
          family life is recorded in Heinrich’s diary: <cit>
            <q>Dr. Baumgarten [Heinrich’s attorney] at our place; he confirms what we have long
              suspected: that Mozio is keeping his Jewish origins a secret from his children! He,
              Dr. Baumgarten, alerted [Mozio’s] wife to the danger that his children could learn the
              truth from some other quarter; their mother declines to tell the children the truth
              for the time being. Dr. Baumgarten gets worked up over Mozio's speaking with German
              with Yiddish thrown in, even in front of the children. (diary, November 1, 1924)</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>Signs of a deterioration in the marriage appeared in the early 1920s, and <ref
            cRef="entity-003438">Lisl</ref> left him in September 1929 for the radio pioneer <ref
            cRef="entity-004819">Leopold Richtera</ref>; she obtained a divorce and married <ref
            cRef="entity-004819">Richtera</ref> in April 1930, only for her new husband to die two
          weeks later. </p>

        <p>In 1927, Moriz appears to have been out of work. In 1930 he formed his own company,
          apparently providing finance for automobiles; by 1934 that had become M. Schenker &amp;
          Reicher. With the Great Depression, and the collapse of the Vienna Creditbank in May 1931,
          his control over his business affairs deteriorated.</p>

        <p>There are indications in the early 1930s that his mental health was suffering, and we
          know that he was a patient at the University of Vienna’s Clinic for Nervous and Mental
          Diseases in December 1934 <ref type="correspondence" cRef="OC-A-285">(OC A/285</ref>) and
          urged Heinrich to avail himself of its shortwave radiotherapy. Evidence that he took his
          own life in September 1936 comes in a tribute to him written by <ref cRef="entity-000771"
            >Jeanette Schenker</ref> on the last page of the diary she kept of her trip to Santiago,
          Chile in 1936 (OJ 35/9): <cit>
            <q>My travel report should really end here. But I do not regard it as out of place to
              add what I learned from the director of the <ref cRef="entity-004061">Merkur
                Bank</ref> on the way back from [visiting Heinrich’s grave in] the cemetery: that
              only a few days before, the younger brother of my beloved husband voluntarily left
              this life! A highly gifted person, he gained importance and respect from his own
              powers, and also wealth. But for years he was dogged by bad luck; and his need for
              peace is something that I can well understand. He was kind to me after my beloved
              husband passed away: may his memory be honored. — September 30, 1936.</q>
          </cit></p>

      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Relationship with Heinrich</head>
        <p><figure>
            <head>Moriz (standing), Heinrich (seated), 1901 (OJ 72/14, No. 4)</head>
            <graphic url="B72F14_4.jpg" xmt:type="thumb-caption" rend="left-img" width="150px"
              height="113px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <graphic url="B72F14_4.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img" width="800px" height="600px"
              mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <figDesc>Photograph of Moriz and Heinrich Schenker.</figDesc>
          </figure></p>
        <p>Together with <ref cRef="entity-000775">Wilhelm</ref> and Heinrich, Moriz contributed
          money to the upkeep of his mother, <ref cRef="entity-000773">Julia Schenker</ref>, at
          least from January 1914 onwards to her death in 1917. Later, he became effectively
          financial adviser to the whole Schenker family, supporting <ref cRef="entity-002935"
            >Sophie’s family</ref>, even supplying a dowry for her daughter <ref
            cRef="entity-000315">Frieda</ref>; providing Heinrich with money whenever he needed; and
          during the legal proceedings between Heinrich and <ref cRef="entity-002408">Universal
            Edition</ref> in 1925 he acted as intermediary to the disputing parties in a crucial
          meeting, and the agreed compensatory payments from <ref cRef="entity-002408">UE</ref> to
          Heinrich were to be paid into Moriz’s account.</p>

        <p>Being for a time relatively wealthy, he fell victim to Schenker's general detestation of
          "the rich." For example, Moriz's behavior on the occasion of his decoration (see above)
          was dubbed by Heinrich "an unequaled piece of Schenker shenanigans" (<hi rend="italic">ein
            Schenkerei ohnegleichen</hi>) and "damnable." Heinrich even embarked in January 1931 on
          litigation against his brother for non-return of his property investment.</p>

        <p>He played the violin well enough to have played informally with Heinrich; his son <ref
            cRef="entity-000769">Georg</ref>, a cellist, had lessons in theory with Heinrich before
          joining the Baden theater orchestra.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Heinrich and Others; Photographs</head>

        <p>Correspondence from Moriz to Heinrich Schenker survives as OJ 14/5 (1918–30: 42 items
          (including two items to Julia Schenker, 1912, one from Julia to Heinrich, 1914, and one
          from Moriz and Hans Guttmann to Heinrich, 1918) and OC 54/31 and 32 (1925), A/284 and 285
          (1934). Some correspondence with Universal Edition exists as OC 52/466 and 467 (1924), and
          with Schenker's attorney Theodor Baumgarten, OC 52/703 (1925), regarding the dispute with
          UE. OJ 35/8 contains "financial transactions between Heinrich Schenker and Moriz Schenker,
          Anny Wollner and Drei Masken-Verlag, 1922–31." </p>

        <p>Two photographic portraits survive as OJ 72/18, Nos. 1 (Moriz in military uniform with
          wife, c. 1897) and 2 (Moriz alone, c. 1901).</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
              Tagebüchern und Briefen ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985)</bibl>
          <bibl>Private communication from Elizabeth Brinsden (October 18, 2011)</bibl>
          <bibl>correspondence and diaries</bibl>

        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Marko Deisinger</hi> and <hi rend="bold">Ian
              Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>

  </text>
</TEI>
