<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000989">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Viktor [Victor] Zuckerkandl</title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, July 2, 1896; died Ascona, Switz., April 24, 1965</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="zuckerkandl_viktor">Zuckerkandl, Viktor</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>07/02/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Zuckerkandl ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">zuckerkandl_viktor</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Viktor [Victor] Zuckerkandl</head>
      <div>
        <p>Austrian musicologist, critic, and writer on music.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>The son of Viennese-Jewish intellectuals – his father, Otto, being a medical doctor and
          Professor at the University of Vienna – Zuckerkandl studied piano with <ref
            cRef="entity-000718">Richard Robert</ref>, and embarked on the study of musicology and
          art history at the University of Vienna in 1914. Those studies were interrupted by war
          service first in Italy (1915–16), then on the Russian front (1916–18, during which time he
          reports having seen his father and mother in <ref cRef="entity-002401">Lemberg</ref> (OJ
          2/3, p. 393)). The war over, he married Marianne Bachrach in 1918. From then until 1927,
          he was active as a conductor in the opera house and concert hall in Barmen, Elberfeld, and
          Vienna, and directed the Philharmonic Chorus in Vienna 1926–29. In 1927 he took his PhD
          with a dissertation <title level="m">Prinzipien und Methoden der Instrumentation in
            Mozarts Werken</title> [Principles and Methods of Instrumentation in Mozart Works] under
            <ref cRef="entity-000003">Guido Adler</ref>. From 1927 to 1933, he worked as music,
          literature, and art critic in Berlin for the <title level="j">Ullstein Blätter</title>,
          and thereafter taught briefly at the Vienna Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst. He
          was acquainted with, among others, the conductors Bruno Walter, Otto Klemperer, and
          Wilhelm Furtwängler.</p>
        <p>In 1938 he left Austria for Stockholm, and in late 1939 emigrated to the USA, where he
          taught mathematics, philosophy, and music theory variously at Wellesley College, near
          Boston (–1942), the New School of Social Research in New York (1946–48), and St. John's
          College, Annapolis, Maryland (1948–64). For the latter institution, he developed and
          taught a course especially for the liberal arts student—a course that has been taught
          there with its accompanying textbook, <title level="m">The Sense of Music</title>, ever
          since. He received six years of scholarships from the Bollingen Foundation for research
          into "the nature, structure, and significance of the tonal language [of] the great
          composers," which resulted in two of his book publications. In 1960–64, he gave lectures
          at the Casa Eranos, in Ascona, Switzerland, where he settled in 1964. After the death of
          his first wife, he married Gertrude (Gerty) Bamberger (1904–65: former pupil of Felix
          Salzer at the <ref cRef="entity-002451">Neues Wiener Konservatorium</ref>, sister of the
          Schenker pupil <ref cRef="entity-000034">Carl Bamberger</ref>, and who had taught
          ear-training at the <ref cRef="entity-002454">David Mannes Music School</ref> in New York)
          in the 1964, following a thirty-year acquaintance. </p>
        <p>In the open letter for Gustav Mahler a digest of which was published in the <title
            level="j">Neue Freie Presse</title> for May 25, 1907, seeking to persuade Mahler not to
          resign his position at the Vienna Court Opera House, among the 69 signatories (which
          included Schenker, Moriz Violin, and Schoenberg and many other distinguished names in
          music, literature, the theater, and visual arts) appear the names of his famous anatomist
          uncle and journalist aunt "Hofrat Professor Dr. Emil Zuckerkandl [and] Bertha
          Zuckerkandl."</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Zuckerkandl and Schenker</head>
        <p>Zuckerkandl's initial introduction to Schenker, perhaps by Richard Robert, was on
          September 24, 1914 (OC 1/16, p. 720). Sometime in 1914 he took counterpoint lessons
          briefly with <ref cRef="entity-000562">Eusebius Mandyczewski</ref> (OJ 1/7, p. 840), but
          then embarked upon study with Schenker in October 1914, taking lessons throughout the
          1914/15 season, until in August 1915 he was called up and sent to the Italian front line.
          While at the front, he read Schenker's latest work, kept abreast of music journals, and
          corresponded with Schenker, visiting him on at least one period of leave. After the war,
          he seems not to have resumed instruction with Schenker. In June 1919, <ref
            cRef="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</ref> reported that Zuckerkandl, with <ref
            cRef="entity-000098">Paul Breisach</ref>, was taking instruction in "modern
          instrumentation, especially that of Richard Strauss," from the conductor Georg Szell (OJ
          2/14, p. 2080). </p>

        <p>In the acknowledgements to his first book, <title level="m">Musikalische
            Gestaltung</title> (1932), Zuckerkandl states: "For the musical conception that
          ultimately lies at the heart [of this book] I have the teaching of the great theorist
          Heinrich Schenker to thank" (p. VII), in reaction to which Schenker remarked: "A great and
          delightful surprise to me was Viktor Zuckerkandl's new book and his commitment to me as
          expressed in the Foreword. I conclude from it that [mentioning] Schenker clearly no longer
          signifies peril for life and limb, but instead a protection" (OJ 89/5, [13], December 17,
          1932). In his <title level="m">Sound and Symbol</title>, vol. 1 (1956), Zucherkandl
          declares: "While Hanslick connected the concept of motion with a shallow and rigid concept
          of form, we find a far more fruitful linking of the two ideas, form and motion, in the
          work of the greatest musical theorist of our time, Heinrich Schenker, who understood the
          musical work of art as a complex kinetic organism." (p. 78). Later in the same book, he
          speaks of repetitions that "are hidden in the inmost depths of the very tones, whose
          presence was first pointed out by Heinrich Schenker, and in which the miracles of the
          organic formation of great masterpieces are revealed." (pp. 212–13). </p>

        <p>Under the pseudonym Viktor Zauner, Zuckerkandl wrote the article <title level="a">Wort
            und Ton bei Mozart</title> in <title level="j">Der Dreiklang</title> ii (May 1937),
          41–52. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>
        <p>Of the correspondence from Zuckerkandl to Schenker, three letters survive as OJ 15/34
          (undated, probably 1912/13; undated, probably 1914/15; January 14, 1918). At least two
          non-extant postcards from Schenker to Zuckerkandl are recorded in Schenker's diary, the
          tone of one of which ("some jokes about Adler’s latest presumptuousness: a 'double-eagle
          joke'", December 10, 1916) suggests cordiality between the two men. Their communications
          while Zuckerkandl was fighting on the front line, especially OJ 15/34, [3] and diary
          entries, are of great interest. </p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Bibliography : Zuckerkandl's Book Publications:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Musikalische Gestaltung der grossen Opernpartien:
              jugendlich-dramatisches Fach</title> (Berlin: Max Hesse, 1932)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Die Weltgemeinschaft der Juden </title>(Zürich: Die Liga,
            1938)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Sound and Symbol</title>, vol. 1: <title level="m">Music and the
              External World</title>, transl. <editor>Willard R. Trask</editor> (Princeton, NJ:
            Princeton University Press, 1956, 2/1973; Ger. orig., Zürich: Rhein-Verlag, 1963, as
              <title level="m">Die Wirklichkeit der Musik: Der musikalische Begriff der
              Aussenwelt</title>)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">The Sense of Music</title> (Princeton, NJ: Princeton University
            Press, 1959)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Vom musikalischen Denken: Begegnung von Ton und Wort</title>
            (Zürich: Rhein-Verlag, 1963)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Sound and Symbol</title>, vol. 2: <title level="m">Man the
              Musician</title>, trans. Norbert Guterman (Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press,
            1973)</bibl>
          <bibl>(and many articles in journals)</bibl>

        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">NGDM2</title> (2001 and online)</bibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">OeML Online</title>
          </bibl>
          <bibl><editor>Fink, Evelyn</editor>, ed., <title level="m">Rebell und Visionär: Heinrich
              Schenker in Wien</title> (Vienna: Lafite, 2003), p. 22</bibl>
          <bibl><editor>Eybl, Martin</editor> &amp; <editor>Fink-Mennel, Evelyn</editor>, eds,
              <title level="m">Schenker-Traditionen: Eine Wiener Schule der Musiktheorie und ihre
              internationale Verbreitung</title> (Vienna: Böhlau, 2006), pp. 137–47
              (<author>Wolfgang Suppan</author>), 250–51</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>Marko Deisinger and Ian Bent</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
