<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000177">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Aline Petrie Dunn</title>
        <title type="sub"/>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="dunn_aline_petrie">Dunn, Aline Petrie</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">dunn_aline_petrie</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Aline Petrie Dunn</head>

      <div>
        <p>Wife of <ref>John Petrie Dunn</ref>.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <p>Aline Dunn (unmarried name not known) was originally from Leipzig. It is thought that she
          met John as a pupil of his while he was teaching at Kiel Conservatory between 1909 and
          1914; Hoboken, who met the couple in 1927, reported: “His wife, who was also there [in
          Edinburgh], is much younger; she is German, and was his pupil when she married him.” She
          was, according to John’s obituary, an accomplished pianist. The two of them played piano
          duets: she reported that shortly before John’s death they had been working on J. S. Bach’s
          “C major Concerto” (perhaps BWV 1061 for two harpsichords and strings) in preparation for
          a performance with orchestra.</p>

        <p>It is clear that she assisted her husband in his work; For example, when John Petrie Dunn
          produced his abbreviated translation of parts of Schenker’s <ref cRef="entity-001727"
              ><title level="m">Kontrapunkt</title> 2</ref>, Aline helped him with the production of
          multiple copies for his students.</p>

        <p>The Dunns and Schenkers had planned to meet in the Tyrol in summer 1929 while the Dunns
          were attending the Bayreuth Festival, but this came to nothing. It was Aline who wrote
          informing Schenker of her husband’s sudden death in a street accident in February
          1931.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence</head>
        <p>Two letters from her to Schenker survive as OJ 10/12, [1] and [2], both from 1931 after
          her husband’s death. Schenker sent a letter of condolence to her on February 23. A
          photograph showing both John and Aline, inscribed “Marienbad, August 1930,” which she sent
          to Jeanette Schenker, is preserved as OJ 72/4, item 2.</p>

      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
