<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-003304">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Bertha [Berta] Jahn-Beer</title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, January 3, 1883; died Milton, Massachusetts, January 22,
          1942</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="jahn-beer_bertha">Jahn-Beer, Bertha</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">jahn-beer_bertha</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Bertha [Berta] Jahn-Beer</head>

      <p>Hungarian-Austrian pianist and teacher in Vienna, later the USA, pupil of Schenker's in
        1907.</p>

      <div>
        <head>Career summary</head>
        <p>Bertha Jahn studied initially with the conductor Bernhard Jahn. Schenker accepted her as
          a pupil on April 3, 1907, and she returned with a request for further study in the
          October. She had previously studied with <ref cRef="entity-000523">Theodor
            Leschetizky</ref>, later becoming his assistant, and also with <ref cRef="entity-000794"
            >Artur Schnabel</ref>. She was already playing chamber music evenings in the Bösendorfer
          Recital Hall in Vienna by 1905, and her career as a solo recitalist and performer in
          chamber ensembles and with orchestras developed across Austria, German, France, and Spain
          in the following years. She taught piano at the <ref cRef="entity-002591"
            >Akademie/Hochschule für Musik und darstellende Kunst</ref> between 1927 and 1938,
          losing her post as a consequence of the annexation of Austria by the National Socialists.
          She emigrated to the USA in 1939, from the summer of which she was on the faculty of the
          Longy School of Music in Cambridge, Massachusetts until her death in 1942. A Jahn-Beer
          Scholarship was set up in her memory at the School, for pianists seeking a career as a
          concert soloist.</p>
      </div>


      <div>
        <head>Jahn-Beer and Schenker</head>
        <p>Jahn-Beer was a pupil of Schenker’s from April 3, 1907 for an undetermined number of
          months. Much later, he reports in his diary having heard her on Radio Wien, on May 20,
          1925 playing ballades by Brahms and Chopin (“rather leisurely, swollen”), and on May 30,
          1929 the Beethoven G major violin sonata Op. 96.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Tittel, Ernst</author>, <title level="m">Die Wiener Musikhochschule</title>
            (Vienna: Elisabeth Lafite, 1967), p. 93</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Oesterreichisches Musik-Lexikon ONLINE</title></bibl>
          <bibl><ref type="external"
              target="https://anno.onb.ac.at/anno-suche#searchMode=simple&amp;query=Berta+Jahn-Beer&amp;from=1"
                ><title>ANNO-Suche Österreichische Nationalbibliothek</title></ref></bibl>
          <bibl>With thanks to Dr. Roy Rudolph, archivist of the Longy School, for valuable
            information about Jahn-Beer's years at Longy (email August 25, 2021)</bibl>
          <bibl>With thanks to Irene Schreier Scott for information about Jahn-Beer’s time both in
            Vienna and in the USA (emails August 13 and 14, 2020)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Ian Bent</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
