<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-002742">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Annemarie Seidel (van Hoboken)</title>
        <title type="sub">born 1895; died 1959</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="seidel_annemarie">Seidel (van Hoboken), Annemarie</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">seidel_annemarie</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Annemarie Seidel (van Hoboken)</head>
      <div>

        <p>German actress, younger sister of the poet and novelist Ina Seidel, wife of Anthony van
          Hoboken 1922-32. </p>

        <p>Annemarie Seidel grew up in Munich and built her acting career at the beginning of the
          Weimar Republic. It was at this time that she met Carl Zuckmayer, with whom she had an
          affair during 1921/22. Her life threatened by illness, she had to leave Zuckmayer's damp
          basement apartment at Matthäikirchstraße 4 in Berlin. Her rescuer in this predicament was
          the Dutch millionaire <ref cRef="entity-000380">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>. Hoboken became
          Seidel's first husband, the marriage lasting from 1922 to 1932. Hoboken married <ref
            cRef="entity-000093">Eva Hommel (Eva Boy)</ref> in the following year, while Seidel
          married Peter Suhrkamp in 1935.</p>

        <p>She retained her friendship with Zuckmayer for many years; the correspondence between
          them continued to 1950 and was eventually published. The marriage with Suhrkamp suffered
          in later years from Seidel's alcoholism. Suhrkamp died only a few months before his wife. </p>

      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Annemarie Seidel and the Schenker circle</head>

        <p>Correspondence from Anthony van Hoboken gave frequent reports of the traveling that his
          wife and he did, with glimpses of their ‒ to Schenker ‒ extravagant life style. The two
          couples visited each others' homes in Vienna; for example, in April 1927 the Hobokens came
          to the Schenker's for afternoon coffee on the 9th (OJ 3/4, p. 3055), and the Schenker's
          went to the Hobokens for a musical evening of the 28th ‒ though Mrs. Hoboken was lacking,
          it gives a sense of the Hobokens' home life: <cit>
            <q>At 9 o'clock, to Hoboken (we stay there until 3:45!): present are the mother-in-law
              with one of her granddaughters, the Deutsches, Hammer, and Vrieslander. The Tautenhayn
              ensemble plays! Not until 11 o'clock does Hoboken tell me that his wife is lying in
              the hospital, however the matter is not serious. The evening passed extremely well;
              the complete naturalness in the social gathering, and in our relationship to the
              musicians; the rooms; the beautiful, sumptuous meal and its presentation (for which we
              offered the chef a toast, with applause): these made an exceptional impression on us
              all. (OJ 3/4, p. 3060)</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>On January 25, 1928, the Schenkers attended a performance on Gantillon's play <title
            level="m">Maya</title>, in which Seidel played the leading role, and Schenker commented
          on her acting in his diary (OJ 4/1, p. 3168). </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence</head>
        <p>One note is known to survive from Annemarie to Jeanette Schenker (OJ 11/54, [11], January
          20, 1927), and this resulted in a visit recorded in Schenker's diary: "Mrs. van Hoboken
          from 5 to 7:30 for afternoon snack" (OJ 3/4, p. 3029). One double letter survives,
          Heinrich to Anthony, Jeanette to Annemarie (OJ 89/1, [9], Dec 27, 1927).</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Source:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Wikipedia</title> (German) </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Marko Deisinger</author> with <author>Ian Bent</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
