<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000148">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Carl Czerny</title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, 21 February 1791; died Vienna, 15 July 1857</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="czerny_carl">Czerny, Carl</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">czerny_carl</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Carl Czerny</head>
      <div>

        <p>Austrian pianist, composer and teacher. </p>

        <div>
          <head>Career Summary</head>
          <p>Carl Czerny was taught first by his father Wenzel Czerny, then by Wenzel Krumpholtz and
            Antonio Salieri, and in 1800–03 by Beethoven himself. He gave his first public
            performance as a pianist in 1800, and came to be considered the authoritative
            interpreter of the piano works of Beethoven.</p>

          <p>As a teacher, Czerny wrote a large number of didactic piano pieces (exercises, studies,
            etc.), many of which are still in use today, in volumes such as <title level="m">The
              School of Velocity</title>, Op. 299, <title level="m">The Art of Finger
              Dexterity</title>, Op. 740, and the <title level="m">Complete Theoretical and
              Practical Pianoforte School</title>, Op. 500 (1839). He also wrote important treatises
            on improvisation, of which the <title level="m">Systematic Introduction to
              Improvisation</title> (<hi rend="italic">Fantasieren</hi>) <title>at the Piano</title>
            (1829) is highly informative for performance practise purposes. He also wrote a <title
              level="m">School of Embellishments, Turns, and Shakes</title>, Op. 335, which it is
            unlikely that Schenker knew when writing his <ref cRef="entity-001721"><title level="m"
                >Ein Beitrag zur Ornamentik</title></ref>. Among the many pupils that Czerny taught
            were Beethoven’s nephew, Karl, Sigismond Thalberg, <ref cRef="entity-000523">Theodor
              Leschetizky</ref>, Stephen Heller, and <ref cRef="entity-000533">Franz Liszt</ref>. </p>

          <p>As a composer, Czerny produced sonatas, sonatinas, variation sets, and shorter pieces
            for piano two hands and four hands, much chamber music (piano and string trios and
            quartets), orchestral music (symphonies, concertos, and concertinos), and sacred choral
            music (masses, requiems, offertories, etc.). He was one of the first composers to use
            “étude” ("study") as a title. His opus numbers (which included didactic and theoretical
            works as well as compositions) number well over 800. Many of his treatises were
            translated into English in the 19th century.</p>

          <p>Czerny was also a significant music theorist, notably with his <title level="m">School
              of Practical Composition</title>, Op. 600, and he edited and translated into German four
            treatises by Antonín Reicha, as his <title level="m">Complete Textbook of Musical
              Composition</title>.</p>

          <p>Czerny was also active as an editor of works by J. S. Bach, Domenico Scarlatti, and
            others.</p>

          <p>In his will, he divided his estate between the <ref cRef="entity-002430">Gesellschaft
              der Musikfreunde</ref> and three other institutions in Vienna. </p>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>Czerny and Schenker</head>
          <p>In 1912–13, Schenker used “Czerny Etudes” (for which there are many possible candidates
            among Czerny’s didactic works) for two of his pupils (<ref cRef="entity-000861">Mrs.
              Stirling</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-000628">Miss Newlov</ref>), alongside studies by
            Brahms (“Czerny-Brahms Etüden”). In 1920 Schenker twice went into the archives of the
              <ref cRef="entity-002430">Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde</ref> to consult Czerny’s
            treatises.</p>

          <p>Among the extant editions of Bach’s <title level="m">Well-tempered Clavier</title>,
            Book II that Schenker rejected in 1908 was that by Czerny (OC 52/399–401).</p>

          <p>No works by Czerny appear in the list of books in Schenker’s library at his death
                (<bibl><title level="m">Musik und Theater enthaltend die Bibliothek des Herrn †Dr.
                Heinrich Schenker, Wien</title> (Vienna: Heinrich Hinterberger, [1936])</bibl>), but
            there may have been some among Schenker’s sheet music, of which no list survives.</p>
        </div>

      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Österreiches Musiklexikon Online</title> (“Czerny Familie”) </bibl>

          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Österreich Lexikon-online</title>
          </bibl>

          <bibl>
            <title level="m">The New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians</title> (1980) </bibl>

          <bibl>
            <title level="m">wikipedia</title> ("Carl Czerny") [November 3, 2022] </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributors</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Marko Deisinger</hi></author> and <author><hi rend="bold"
                >Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>


    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
