<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-000143">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Felix-Eberhard von Cube</title>
        <title type="sub">born Hannover, Jan 27, 1903; died Hamburg, March 12, 1988</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="cube_felixeberhard_v">Cube, Felix-Eberhard von</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>31/05/2006</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Cube ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">CubeG ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">cube_felixeberhard_v</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Felix-Eberhard von Cube</head>

      <div>
        <p>German music theorist, teacher, and composer, pupil of Schenker's.</p>
                
        <p>Son of the architect and archaeologist Gustav von Cube, Felix-Eberhard grew up in Munich
          and studied music privately with <ref cRef="entity-000922">Otto Vrieslander</ref>, a
          family friend who was for a time the private librarian to the playwright Carl Sternheim,
          Cube's maternal uncle. On Vrieslander's recommendation, Cube went to Vienna in late 1923
          to study with Schenker.</p>
        
        <p>The first lesson recorded in Schenker's lessonbooks (OC 3/3) is dated January 23, 1924,
          the last was June 4, 1926, with one postal lesson on January 27, 1927. Cube's instruction
          began with the final section of Schenker's <ref cRef="entity-001727"><title level="m">Kontrapunkt 2</title></ref>, continuing
          with a year of thoroughbass, fugal technique, analytical studies (mostly keyboard
          repertory), source studies, and work on Cube's own compositions.</p>
        
        <p>After a period of five years' teaching at the Rheinisches Musikseminar, a provincial
          conservatory in Duisburg in Germany's industrial area, he was recommended by Schenker to
          help <ref cRef="entity-000913">Moriz Violin</ref> set up a Schenker-Institut in Hamburg in
          1931. The Institute had a shaky existence for about two years, closed down in 1934 and
          reopened after the War as the Heinrich-Schenker-Akademie, though with only modest success,
          continuing for another decade and a half.</p>
        
        <p>Unswervingly loyal to Schenker and his cause, Cube attempted to put his teacher's
          theories into a useful pedagogical form for German-speaking musicians, in a 
            <title level="m">Lehrbuch der musikalischen Kunstgesetze</title>, a typewritten treatise first
          conceived around 1934 but not finished until 1953 (and periodically augmented thereafter
          with further graphic analyses); an English version of this appeared in 1987 as 
            <title level="m">The Book of the Musical Artwork</title>. A second book, 
            <title level="m">Todeskampf oder Wiederauferstehung der Deutschen Musik</title> (Mortal Struggle, or the
          New Resurrection of German Music), is essentially a diatribe against modernism, but
          includes anecdotal information about his upbringing, his studies with Schenker, and his
          career as a teacher in Duisburg and Hamburg. Cube also wrote a quantity of chamber music,
          songs, and concertos, some of which were performed by North German Radio.</p>
        </div>
        
        <div>
          <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>
        <p>Cube and Schenker corresponded extensively between 1924 and 1934: OJ 9/34 (Cube to
          Schenker: 1925-34: 42 items) and letters in family possession: vC (Schenker to Cube:
          1924-34: 51 items); correspondence between Schenker and Violin comprise OJ 70/2 (1 item)
          and 70/11 (1931: 3 items).</p>
        </div>
    </body>
          
          

        <back>
          <div>
          <head>See also:</head> 
            <listBibl>
              <bibl><editor>Eybl, Martin</editor> &amp; <editor>Fink-Mennel, Evelyn</editor>, eds, 
            <title level="m">Schenker-Traditionen</title> (Vienna: Bohlau, 2006), pp. 156, 240-41</bibl>
            </listBibl>
          </div>
          
          <div>
            <head>Contributor:</head>
            <listBibl>
              <bibl><author>William Drabkin</author></bibl>
            </listBibl>
          </div>
        </back>

  </text>
</TEI>
