<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000416">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Marianne Kahn</title>
        <title type="sub">born Prague, November 26, 1878; died after July 21, 1939</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="kahn_marianne">Kahn, Marianne</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>07/11/2005</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Kahn ~ H+JSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">Kahn ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">Kahn ~ JSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">kahn_marianne</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Marianne Kahn</head>
      <div>
        <p>Czech Jewish piano teacher; long-time pupil of Schenker's.</p>
        <p>Kahn first introduced herself to Schenker on January 17, 1907 (diary), became a pupil of
          his on September 23, 1907 (diary OJ 1/6, p. 48) and remained so right up to Schenker's
          death in January 1935 (tables of student hours 1934/35: OC A/259 and A/264). She appears
          in the lesson books 1913-31 (OC 3/1-4) and there are lesson notes for her from 1931-32 (OC
          16/35-37). Her Vienna address from at least 1907 to 1938 was XIX, (Döblinger) Hauptstraße
          70. She is recorded as having left Vienna for Sanremo in Italy on July 21, 1939, and
          nothing is known of her thereafter.</p>

        <p>She was a piano teacher in her own right, and Schenker occasionally passed students on to
          her (including, e.g., the mothers of <ref cRef="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</ref> and <ref
            cRef="entity-000107">Robert Brünauer</ref>). She was a close friend of <ref
            cRef="entity-000201">Angi Elias</ref>; the two saw each other frequently, sometimes went
          on holiday together, and after Heinrich Schenker's death visited his grave together on his
          birthdays, June 19. Schenker reported in 1930 (I.N. 191.566) that Marianne's brother was a
          professor of psychology at the University of Prague, and that her sister (possibly <ref
            cRef="entity-006282">Trude</ref>) was a senior official at the Sanatorium Löw in
          Vienna.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Kahn and Schenker</head>

        <p>Schenker's diaries show signs of irritation with Marianne Kahn from 1927 onward,
          including this depth analysis of her (Nov 17, 1928): <cit>
            <q>Miss Kahn unexpectly gives me cause for resistance, expecially in the repeat of
              "Träumerei," which she requested for a pupil of hers. I lost my patience; I saw myself
              confronted by the failure of my personal kindness, my pedagogical effort, to produce
              any results after more than twenty years. I was disgusted by a truly dissolute vanity,
              which treats the greatest masters of the world and their most faithful servant – who
              is in his own way also a master – as a support-beam, pushing itself to the forefront
              over and over again. Ultimately, an erotic cause would have made the will to power of
              such a vanity understandable; but a vanity that has no purpose whatever and yet
              demands such holy sacrifices allows me to keep my patience no longer. I rebuked her
              severely and reminded her that she is coming to a musician whose job consists
              precisely in determining the unconditional in performance, so that there is no more
              room for the pupil. Whereupon I put her under duress; and she cooperated – not
              willingly, but nonetheless. She even remarked: "I cannot force myself" – whereupon I
              replied curtly: "You must." The depravity of this narcissism, which is all the more
              objectionable the more it is the natural state of affairs – thus in a certain sense
              belongs to the innocence of her sex life, i.e. there is something bestial about it –
              consists specifically of her being unwilling to be compelled even by the greatest
              master, but on the other hand wishes to force the masters and their servants down to
              her low level. I hope that this harsh rebuke will have good consequences, at least for
              myself. It is sad enough that the young lady, on account of her opposition, has lost
              so many years of the best opportunity to learn free of charge and finally, in spite of
              all help, may herself be satisfied with what she cannot do at all. Yet it is time to
              look away from this picture; the young lady deserves nothing better. Whether or not
              this is animalistic innocence, as soon as she causes such harm it must, according to
              general custom, be utterly destroyed.</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>Such adverse comments as this by Schenker should perhaps not be taken at face value. When
          asked by <ref cRef="entity-000164">Otto Erich Deutsch</ref> to recommend a piano teacher
          for his brother two year later, he responded: <cit>
            <q>For your brother I would recommend Miss Marianne Kahn, who has been my pupil for over
              twenty years (still is), is a more than capable concert pianist, is thoroughly
              educated in [music] theory, but has had to refrain from presenting herself to the
              public on account of nerves. She plays from memory at one sitting Brahms's Paganini
              Variations, Chopin's complete Etudes Op. 10 and Op. 25, Beethoven's [Piano Sonata] Op.
              106, etc., etc. [...] She has always served well wherever I have recommended her.
              (I.N. 191.566, August 5, 1930)</q>
          </cit>
        </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence</head>
        <p>Only one of the many letters and postcards recorded in his diary that Heinrich Schenker
          wrote to Marianne Kahn survives (OC 44/23); none from Kahn to Heinrich are known to
          survive. One postcard from her to Jeanette Schenker, countersigned by Angi Elias, survives
            (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-10-18_16">OJ 10/18, [16]</ref>, April ?3,
          1938).</p>
      </div>

      <div> </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head> Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>Datenbank NS-verfolgte Musik Primavera Gruber Wien</bibl>
          <bibl>Documents on this website</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
