<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-000269">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Johann Joseph Fux</title>
        <title type="sub">born Hirtenfeld, Styria, 1660; died Vienna, Feb 13, 1741</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="fux-johann_joseph">Fux, Johann Joseph</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>27/10/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">fux-johann_joseph</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Johann Joseph Fux</head>
      <div>

        <p> Austrian music theorist and composer, author of the <title level="m">Gradus ad Parnassum</title> (1725), one of
          the most influential manuals of counterpoint. </p>

        <p><title level="m">Gradus ad Parnassum</title> (Steps to Parnassus) was written in Latin and in dialog form between
          master (Aloysius) and pupil (Josephus) – a pedagogical device that goes back to the middle
          ages). It is the "classic" presentation of species counterpoint based on the modal system
          rather than on major–minor tonality. It covers cantus firmus construction, the five
          species of counterpoint for two, then three, then four voices, then mixed-species
          counterpoint, fugue in two, three, and four parts, and double counterpoint, concluding
          with a chapter on the modern recitative style. The book was very widely distributed in its
          time, was translated into German, Italian, English, and French already in the 18th
          century, and profoundly influenced counterpoint teaching and manuals thereafter, notably
          those by Albrechtsberger, Cherubini, Bellermann, and Schenker. </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Fux and Schenker</head>
        <p>Schenker owned a copy of Mizler's German translation of the <title level="m">Gradus ad Parnassum</title>, and knew
          the work intimately. His diary shows that he was studying it particularly closely in the
          summer of 2006, in preparation for the writing of the first half-volume of his own
          <ref cRef="entity-001725"><title>Kontrapunkt</title></ref>. The structure of the latter work to a great extent mirrors that of the
          <title level="m">Gradus</title>, however Schenker was not without his criticism of Fux's approach; stating that
          Fux's "theory of voice leading was based on a purely vocal foundation," he identifies
          Fux's principal fault as: "By elevating voice leading to the rank of a binding theory of
          composition [...] he unfortunately closed the door to instrumental music from the outset"
          (Eng. trans. John Rothgeb, pp. xxvii–xxviii). </p>
      </div>

    </body>


    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Bibliography: </head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Gradus ad Parnassum: sive manductio ad compositionem musicae regularem
              ...</title> (Vienna: van Gherlen, 1725) </bibl>

          <bibl> Ger. trans. <editor>Lorenz Christoph Mizler</editor>, <title level="m">Gradus ad
              Parnassum; oder, Anführung zur regelmässigen musikalischen Composition ...</title>
            (Leipzig: Mizler, 1742) [of which Schenker owned a copy] </bibl>

          <bibl>Facsimile edn:  <title level="s">Monuments of Music and Music Literature in
            Facsimile</title>, Ser. II, No. 24 (New York: Broude Bros, 1966)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Ian Bent</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

    </back>



  </text>
</TEI>
