<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000878">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Paula [Paulina] Szalit [Szalitówna; Schalit]</title>
        <title type="sub">born Drohobycz, near Lemberg [Lwów], November 25, 1885; died Kulparkov,
          near Lwów, February 7, 1942</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="szalit_paula">Szalit, Paula</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">szalit_paula</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Paula [Paulina] Szalit [Szalitówna; Schalit]</head>

      <div>
        <p>Galician/Polish pianist and composer, pupil of Schenker's for a short period in
          1896‒97.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Born Paulina, but publicly and privately styled Paula, Szalit was the daughter of Simon
          Szalit (1844–), accountant, and Reisel (<hi rend="italic">née</hi> Bressler) (1846–) of
          Drohobycz, a town in what was then <ref cRef="entity-002355">Galica</ref> and is now in
          the Ukraine. Until aged 8, she was taught music solely by her brother, <ref
            cRef="entity-007722">Heinrich</ref>, who was eighteen years her elder. In about 1893
            <ref cRef="entity-007722">Heinrich</ref> took her to Vienna, where she studied first
          with Robert Fischhof, giving her first public recitals in 1895 to instant acclaim, and at
          some point with Josef Hofmann. In 1896 she was due to study with <ref cRef="entity-000150"
            >Eugen d'Albert</ref>, but at the latter’s suggestion she worked with Heinrich Schenker
          for a short period before d’Albert took her over. Subsequently she studied with <ref
            cRef="entity-000523">Theodor Leschetizky</ref>.</p>

        <p>She was celebrated as a child prodigy. <ref cRef="entity000331">Eduard Hanslick</ref>
          described her in 1896 as “the rarest of musical phenomena” (<title level="j">Neue freie
            Presse</title>, February 13). Indicative of her European reception in 1896 and 1897 is: <cit>
            <q>Our season, already underway, has now acquainted us also with a wonder child, the
              ten-year-old pianist Paula Szalit. […] She has already made a big splash in several
              cities, such as Vienna and Berlin. Here in Leipzig, too, she has caused a sensation
              and established herself as a genuine phenomenon, through the astounding level of her
              achievements, both in the remarkable advancement for such a young person of her
              technical facility, and in the clarity and secure accuracy of her development, then
              also through the sheer innate musicality of the little girl […] (<title level="j"
                >Signale für die musikalische Welt</title>, November 9, 1897).</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>Her career in playing not only solo recitals but also concertos with leading orchestras
          and piano chamber music with major ensembles continued through to 1906, appearing in
          Austria, Germany, France, England, and Russia. Then in September 1906 she was appointed to
          the Lemberg Conservatory as the head of the advanced piano class – on hearing which
          Schenker commented in his diary: “‘Paula Szalit teacher in Lemberg’ ‒ that's the last
          we’ll see of the 'wonderchild'?!”. Thereafter, as the <title level="j">Wiener
            Hausfrauen-Zeitung</title> for 1912 reported, “to the great regret of the many admirers
          of her superb artistry, [she] has in recent times disappeared from the public eye.”</p>

        <p>Schenker was in indirect contact with her in 1914, 1915 and direct contact in 1918 (see
          below). Szalit advertised in Vienna in 1918 that she had again taken up giving piano
          lessons, citing her address as Porzellangasse 19 (<title level="j">Neues Wiener
            Tagblatt</title>, October 17). In 1921 she again advertised, setting the bar lower:
          “Piano instruction: the well-known pianist Paula Szalit offers first-class tuition, now
          also including lessons in piano accompaniment and repetiteur work. Rotenlöwgasse 7”
            (<title level="j">Neue freie Presse</title>, March 27). Thereafter, she presumably
          returned to Lemberg (by then Lwów).</p>

        <p>Her death is recorded as on February 7, 1942 and her burial (“without coffin”) five days
          later, aged 56; the place of death was the Kulparkov mental hospital (near Lwów), where
          she may have been incarcerated for many years.</p>

        <p>As a composer she wrote short character pieces for piano, in particular her four books of
            <title level="m">Morceaux pour piano</title>, Op. 2 and her <title level="m"
            >Clavierstücke</title>, Op. 3, which continued to be played well into the 1930s.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Szalit and Schenker</head>
        <p>Schenker reviewed what may have been her public debut in Vienna, in the Bösendorfer
          Recital Hall, on February 14, 1896 ‒ at which time Szalit was being taught by Robert
          Fischhof ‒ beginning his remarks with: <cit>
            <q>On February 14 a nine-year-old child, Paula Szalit, demonstrated her wondrous talent.
              The little girl performed so astoundingly that ‒ to put it directly ‒ she surpassed
              the audience's expectations. The best of her qualities, which inhabit the wonderful
              depths of her instinct, did not permeate into the public's awareness, and this
              reiterated (at this, the little girl's first public foray) the well-known fact that
              the contact of the audience with a significant talent ceases at precisely the point at
              which that talent reveals its best and most subtle features. The most conspicuous
              qualities of her playing gave them pleasure: its splendid rhythm and its elegantly
              developed finger dexterity; but the way in which her refined feeling for mood, melody
              and harmony took effect passed them by. They overlooked her utterly subtle pedal
              technique, which she has in common, quite simply, with the most mature of mature
              virtuosos. This pedal technique is for her not a jolly pumping of the foot, but
              enables her, in a way that for most pianists is still a highly secret art, to realize
              her feeling for melody and harmony. [...]</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>On April 5 of that year, <ref cRef="entity-000150">Eugen d'Albert</ref>, who was
          expecting to teach her in the near future, wrote to Schenker (OJ 9/6, [12]), saying: <cit>
            <q>I wholeheartedly concur with the idea that she should study with you for the time
              being, for you are a serious musician and will point the young lady in the right
              direction. If you see <ref cRef="entity-007722">Mr. Szalit</ref>, please give him my
              best thanks for his kind letter. I should very much like to know as soon as possible
              whether the young lady is definitely coming to me, and if so when. [...] So would you
              take over the continuation of the young lady's study on my behalf in the intervening
              period?</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>Schenker's 1897 diary (undated) records: "Paula Szalit prepared for concerts: among other
          things, J. S. Bach's Fugues in C-sharp minor (for 5 voices) and E-flat minor." A review
          (in which these works are not mentioned, so probably of a different concert) from November
          28, 1897 begins: <cit>
            <q>Paula Szalit, still very young, possesses a freely headlong-rushing, crackling
              technique that exhibits great temperament and a touch of genius. Dr. Heinrich Schenker
              introduced her to music with his unique thoroughness and instructional power, and her
              nature is now tamed in Leschetizky's appropriately named masterclass. (<title
                level="j">Wiener Abendpost</title>: OC 2/p. 20)</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>Szalit was evidently in Galica from 1906 for some years. In 1914, her mother (Reisel
          Szalit) informed Schenker that her daughter had been “stricken with religious mania.”
          Schenker, commenting “Thus ends a life that had begun more brilliantly and promisingly
          than any other,” laid the blame on <ref cRef="entity-000523">Leschetizky</ref> (diary,
          June 18). In 1915, Szalit’s brother <ref cRef="entity-007722">Heinrich</ref> informed him
          that she had been “tragically injured in an accident,” stating that well-wishers were
          supporting her financially (diary, April 11), and asking if Schenker had contacts who
          might help her.</p>

        <p>On November 13, 1918, Schenker recorded in his diary: "<ref cRef="entity-000655">Mrs.
            Pairamall</ref> passes on to me a letter from Miss Szalit (<ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-14-37_3">OJ 14/37, [3]</ref>), in which the latter requests a meeting with me,
          constrained as she is by her very difficult predicament." This harrowing letter speaks of
          the lack of practice facilities to prepare for concert performance, the intensity of
          competition, and the difficulty in obtaining pupils. Schenker’s unsympathetic response <hi
            rend="italic">by letter</hi> was: "I recommend patience: indefatigability when giving
          lessons is a tried and proven recipe."</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence</head>
        <p>One letter of 1918 from Szalit to Schenker survives, with two undated earlier calling
          cards (OJ 14/37, [1]‒[3]). A full-length portrait of her by the photographer "Zaklad
          Michala Friedmana, Nowy Sacz" and inscribed "Paula Szalit, 15.7.95" survives in Schenker's
          papers as OJ 72/22, No. 1.</p>
      </div>

    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><ref type="external"
              target="https://anno.onb.ac.at/anno-suche#searchMode=simple&amp;query=%22Paula+Szalit%22&amp;from=1"
              >ANNO-Suche: Österreichische Nationalbibliothek</ref></bibl>

          <bibl><author>Massarek, H.</author>, <title level="a">Paula Szalit,</title>
            <title level="j">Blatt der Hausfrau</title> (Vienna &amp; Berlin), vol. 22 (1902 year
            review), p. 541 [with photograph]</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
              Tagebüchern ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), p. 60</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker als
              Essayist und Kritiker ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1990), pp. 321‒22 [complete
            review of February 14, 1896 concert, in <title level="j">Die Zeit</title>, February 22,
            1896]</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Schonberg, Harold</author>, <title level="m">The Great Pianists</title> (New
            York, Simon &amp; Schuster, 1963), p. 353</bibl>

          <bibl><title level="m">Heinrich Schenker: Selected Correspondence</title>, ed. <editor>Ian
              Bent</editor>, <editor>David Bretherton</editor> and <editor>William Drabkin</editor>
            (Woodbridge: The Boydell Press, 2014), pp. 4‒5 [complete letter of April 5, 1906 from
            d'Albert to Schenker]</bibl>

          <bibl>Research conducted in the Ukraine by Alex Denisenko; assistance gratefully received
            from Lee A. Rothfarb</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
