<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-004819">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Leopold Richtera</title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, September 23, 1887; died Vienna, April 30, 1930</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="richtera_leopold">Richtera, Leopold</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">richtera_leopold</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Leopold Richtera</head>
      <div>

        <p>Austrian radio engineer, pioneer in Austrian broadcasting.</p>


        <div>
          <head>Career Summary</head>
          <p>Leopold Richtera studied physics at the University of Vienna 1907–12, receiving his PhD
            in 1912, after which he became an assistant at the Physics Institute of the University.
            From 1920 to 1925 he taught the theory of colors (<hi rend="italic">Farbenlehre</hi>) at
            the Graphic Teaching and Research Institute in Vienna, his interest in this field
            culminating in publication of his <title level="m">Die Farbe als wissenschaftliches and
              künstlerisches Problem</title> (Halle: Wilhelm Knapp, 1924). From 1923 to 1927 he
            taught low voltage technique at two technical colleges in Vienna. </p>

          <p>His interest in the problems of radio engineering led to his co-authoring with H.
            Pfeuffer a three-part study of the radio receiver (<title level="m">Der
              Radio-Empfangsapparat</title>) between 1924 and 1928, and also to his becoming
            co-founder of and scientific adviser to the public radio company <ref
              cRef="entity-004436">Radioverkehrs AG (RAVAG)</ref>, which began broadcasting on
            October 1, 1924. In 1927 he was appointed director of science programming (in parallel
            with Max Ast, who was director of music programming).</p>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>Richtera and Schenker</head>
          <p>No contact between the two men is known before 1927. The installation of the Schenkers’
            first radio set had occurred on October 19, 1924, after which a regular stream of
            entries in Heinrich’s diaries appeared noting the music and talks to which they
            listened. Then on February 14, 1927 Leopold Richtera demonstrated – presumably more
            advanced – radio equipment to the couple, and this was duly delivered on February 25
            with a payment of 139.07 shillings, a loudspeaker being added in late October.</p>

          <p>In the December, Schenker wrote asking Richtera to request <ref cRef="entity-004436"
              >RAVAG</ref>’s permission for <ref cRef="entity-000164">Otto Erich Deutsch</ref> to
            read out on air an appeal (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-10_2">OJ 9/10,
              [2]</ref>) for donations to establish an <ref cRef="entity-002452">Archive of
              Photographic Images (<hi rend="italic">Photogrammarchiv</hi>)</ref>. In response to
            this, Richtera invited Deutsch to give a “proper lecture with pictures for the RAVAG
            magazine,” <ref cRef="entity-002755"><title level="j">Radio Wien</title></ref>. A
            lecture entitled <title level="a">Das Archiv für Photogramme musikalischer
              Handschriften</title> was broadcast by <ref cRef="entity-000320">Dr. Robert Haas</ref>
            on February 4, 1928, and appeared with illustrations in the magazine, outlining
            ambitions for the archive (clipping preserved in Schenker’s scrapbook, OC 2/p. 74).</p>

          <p>There is also an indirect family connection concerning Schenker’s younger brother the
            banker <ref cRef="entity-000774">Moriz</ref>. During the summer of 1929 Moriz’s wife,
              <ref cRef="entity-003438">Lisl</ref>, left him for Richtera, who had at one time lived
            in their house. Schenker’s reaction is illuminating: <cit>
              <q>Even in this relationship, she will have to do without all conversation day and
                night; in spite of this, she will be able to take part just as little in the
                mathematics and physics of Richtera as in the bank dealings of Mozio, and without
                doubt she will come away empty-handed, even erotically – thus there remains only a
                futile ruination for this woman, in every respect a futile one.</q>
            </cit>
          </p>
          <p>Richtera died seven months later, on April 30, 1930. Moriz Schenker commited suicide in
            1936.</p>
        </div>

      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Österreichisches Biographisches Lexikon 1815–1950</title></bibl>

          <bibl><author>Hewlett, Kirstie</author>, <title level="a">Heinrich Schenker and the
              Radio,</title>
            <title level="j">Music Analysis</title>, Special Issue on Schenker Documents, 34/2 (July
            2015), 244‒64</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Hewlett, Kirstie</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker and the
              Radio</title> (PhD diss., University of Southampton, 2015)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributors</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Marko Deisinger</hi></author>, <author><hi rend="bold"
                >William Drabkin</hi></author>, <author><hi rend="bold">Ian
            Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
