<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-004943">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Harold Samuel</title>
        <title type="sub">born London, May 23, 1879; died Hampstead, London, January 15,
          1937</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="samuel_harold">Samuel, Harold</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">samuel_harold</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Harold Samuel</head>
      <div>

        <p>English pianist, pedagogue and composer. He was one of the first pianists of the 20th
          century to focus purely on the works of Johann Sebastian Bach, and known for his academic
          and cerebral approach.</p>

        <div>
          <head>Career Summary</head>
          <p>Samuel studied at the Royal College of Music, piano with Edward Dannreuther and
            composition with Sir Charles Villiers Stanford. Later he was on its faculty as professor
            of pianoforte. Samuel was particularly distinguished as an interpreter of Bach, whose
            entire keyboard oeuvre he learned by heart. At his London debut in 1898 he played Bach's
              <title>Goldberg Variations</title> (BWV 988), unknown at that time in London. To make
            a living Harold Samuel taught, did vocal coaching, and became a sought-after accompanist
            (performing especially with violinist Isolde Menges). His solo career, however, was at a
            standstill until 1919 when he played an all-Bach programme in London. He soon found a
            ready audience for large amounts of Bach's keyboard works in their original form. In
            1921 he gave six successive Bach recitals in London and a similar cycle in New York. He
            toured the USA regularly from 1924. Samuel wrote a musical comedy, <title level="m"
              >Hon'ble Phil</title>, songs and piano pieces.</p>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>Samuel and Schenker</head>
          <p>There is no known contact between the two men, but Schenker heard him on Radio Wien on
            October 14, 1928, recording in his diary: "Harold Samuel from London (not using Busoni's
            arrangement, but the original score); the embellishments in the slow second movement not
            badly played; otherwise, bad as usual." <ref cRef="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</ref>
            wrote to Schenker on March 17, 1933 from New York, referring with irony to: "Harold
              Samuels[<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>], who is regarded here as the 'best performer of
            Bach'," and recounting how he ridiculed Samuel's playing in class by the standards of
            Schenker's theory (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-15-16_90">OJ 15/16,
            [90]</ref>).</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Source:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">Wikipedia</title>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Marko Deisinger</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>

      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
