<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000772">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Johann Schenker [Szenker]</title>
        <title type="sub">born Podhajce, Galicia, 1828; died late 1887</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="schenker_johann">Schenker, Johann</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>09/02/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">schenker_johann</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Johann Schenker [Szenker]</head>

      <div>
        <p>Father of Heinrich Schenker; medical doctor.</p>


        <p>Nothing is known of Johann Schenker's early life other than that he was born in 1828 and
          brought up in an assimilated Jewish family in <ref cRef="entity-002355">Galicia</ref>, a
          province of the Austrian Empire then at the height of Germanization and under a despotic
          rule and repressive educational system, a state of affairs which gave way after 1848 to
          gradual social, educational, and linguistic liberalization during the later part of his
          life. </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Marriage</head>
        <p>Schenker records on January 3, 1918 ‒ some 60 years after the event referred to ‒ that a
          friend of the Schenker family, <ref cRef="entity-000569">Marcus Marienberg</ref>,
          "remembered quite precisely [my father's] first meeting with my mother in <ref
            cRef="entity-002333">Wisniowczyk</ref>," but gave no hint of the date. </p>

        <p>Of the marriage of Johann to <ref cRef="entity-000773">Julia Mosler</ref>, Schenker wrote
          to <ref cRef="entity-000913">Moriz Violin</ref> on December 29, 1927 (OJ 6/7, [36]): <cit>
            <q>My father had originally married according to the Jewish rite; only much later were
              such marriages recognized also by the state. Later, when rectification was made, it
              was possible to adjust the official records to suit oneself. I know this because my
              parents told me so.</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>Since the synagogue records do not survive, the date of their Jewish marriage cannot be
          ascertained; but it must have taken place before 1859, the year in which the couple's
          first child, <ref cRef="entity-003791">Marcus</ref>, was born. The official state
          recognition of their marriage did not occur until April 30, 1876 (JRI-Poland), on which
          date, when Johann was 43 and Julia 42, a civil marriage ceremony may have taken place.
          (See the <ref type="external"
            target="http://agadd.home.net.pl/metrykalia/300/sygn.%20993/pages/PL_1_300_993_0010.htm"
            >official record</ref> ‒ right-hand page, sixth entry from the top.)</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Profession</head>
        <p>On the day of <ref cRef="entity-000773">Julia</ref>'s burial in 1917, Schenker, in
          commenting that his mother's family was characterized by a "specifically intellectual
          atmosphere," goes on to say: <cit>
            <q>This also explains why two or three of her brothers became doctors, and obviously it
              was their company that brought my father into the house.</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>When and where Johann received his medical training ‒ at the time probably a three-year
          course followed by internships ‒ is unknown. Lee Rothfarb states that he most likely took: <cit>
            <q>a two- or three-year course of study in the lower medical arts. Such a curriculum led
              to certification as a <hi rend="italic">Wundarzt</hi> ("surgeon"), someone trained in
              the basics of medicine, but not a fully trained M.D. in the modern sense. Typically
              [such persons] served as town doctors (<hi rend="italic">Stadtärzte</hi>), which was
              precisely Johann Schenker's designation in <ref cRef="entity-004091">Podhajce</ref>.
              ("Henryk Szenker," p. 25, fn. 83)</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>Of this work as a doctor in <ref cRef="entity-004091">Podhajce</ref> all that is known is
          that in the Spring of 1916 the town council chose to name a street after him (see below ‒
          no street so-named exists today).</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Children</head>
        <p>According to a record in the registry of the Jewish Religious Community in Vienna dated
          January 23, 1895, Johann and <ref cRef="entity-000773">Julia</ref> had six children: <ref
            cRef="entity-003791">Marcus</ref> [1859‒79], Rebecka [d. 1889], <ref
            cRef="entity-000775">Wilhelm</ref> [1862‒19??], <ref cRef="entity-000319">Schifre
            [Sofie] [Guttmann]</ref> [c.1864‒19??], Heinrich [1868‒1935] (all born in <ref
            cRef="entity-002333">Wisniowczyk</ref>), and <ref cRef="entity-000774">Moriz</ref>
          [1874‒1936] (born in <ref cRef="entity-004091">Podhajce</ref>).</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Character</head>
        <p>Heinrich Schenker, when speaking of the piety of Anton Bruckner, once alluded to his
          father (letter to <ref cRef="entity-000311">Karl Grunsky</ref>, <ref type="correspondence"
            cRef="OJ-5-15_4">OJ 5/15, [4]</ref>, September/December 1908): <cit>
            <q>It reminded me of the piety of my own father who, despite his being a doctor, was
              filled with genuine religiosity. I enjoyed nothing as much about him as his strength
              of faith.</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>When he heard that a street in <ref cRef="entity-004091">Podhajce</ref> had been named
          after his father (see above), Heinrich was moved to say: <cit>
            <q>If an honor of this kind in most instances represents nothing short of a demoralizing
              honoring of wealth, even if the rich man has left an endowment for the benefit of the
              poor, then in this instance the otherwise so discreditable honoring is, exceptionally,
              a declaration by the town of a rare mark made upon it by an impoverished doctor, but
              by a doctor who has stridden through life with incomparable majesty. Though it was my
              father's most cherished wish to work among mankind not for the sake of personal vanity
              but in order to offer it increased advantages of all kind, he certainly had no inkling
              that the very manner of his life and medical practice in itself clearly represented a
              realization of his wish of which he alone knew nothing because he would gladly have
              wished to offer far and away more. He always harbored fantasies of one day going to
              Vienna in order to complete his scientific education, and to do one or two other
              things. He was clearly of the opinion that only by this means could his ardent wish to
              benefit mankind be fully realized. In the meantime, his town council has also availed
              itself of what he modestly offered, and is now honoring ‒ admittedly too late ‒ its
              ideally-minded, exemplary doctor.</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>In a Festschrift prepared for Schenker's 50th birthday but never published, <ref
            cRef="entity-000913">Moriz Violin</ref>, Schenker's most intimate friend, compared the
          characters of Heinrich's parents (OJ 70/53 = OC 2/p.53): <cit>
            <q>Intellectually, his father's serious-mindedness; emotionally, his mother's thoroughly
              hot-blooded temperament.</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>In a diary entry of January 29, 1930, where Schenker is recalling incidents about his
          mother and father, he records: <cit>
            <q>I was even younger when an experience with my father – when we still lived in <ref
                cRef="entity-002333">Wisniowczyk</ref> [before 1874] – introduced me to moral
              behavior in the most practical way. He suspected me of taking some medical papers out
              of the house and giving them to the neighborhood children while at play. After some
              time, the paper he was looking for resurfaced; and my father then took the trouble to
              come to me, though I had already forgotten everything, and most formally to ask for my
              forgiveness for his unjustified suspicions!</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>Schenker recounts a dream in which first his mother and sister appear, then (diary, June
          13, 1914): <cit>
            <q>All of a sudden [...] an opening appeared in the setting [a rock face] which, without
              being a door, released the image of my father. Completely clothed, wearing a blue
              jacket and eyeglasses, he moved along the wall a few steps in a direction that
              apparently led to my mother, who wanted to approach him in the greatest haste. I
              myself, frightened and shocked, was standing nearly opposite him, and wanted to
              approach him and speak with him; but he gestured, making it impossible to take just
              these few steps sideways – whereupon I awoke.</q>
          </cit>
        </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Death</head>
        <p>Johann Schenker died in 1887 at the age of 59. Heinrich was not present (being in Vienna
          by that time); nor did he begin his personal diaries until 1896, so for accounts of it we
          have to resort to fragmentary references recorded in subsequent diaries and in later
          correspondence.</p>

        <p>In his diary for January 3, 1918 Schenker writes that a friend of the Schenker family
          present at Johann's death remembered: <cit>
            <q>that father called <ref cRef="entity-000774">Mozio</ref>, who had been summoned from
                <ref cRef="entity-003996">Buczacz</ref>, to his bedside and said: "Sadly, I am dying
              while still young, and I am leaving nothing behind; but love one another ‒ that is my
              best legacy.</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p> Johann's death had serious consequences for the 19-year-old Heinrich, who had moved to
          Vienna in 1884 to study and had not yet finished his student years. (His 1887 application
          to study at the <ref cRef="entity-002591">Conservatory</ref> survives and is quoted in
          Federhofer (1985), p. 5, as do his application for exemption from fees, declaration of
          lack of means, and other documents, all prepared jointly by Johann and Heinrich.) In a
          letter to <ref cRef="entity-000326">August Halm</ref> Heinrich wrote on September 25, 1922
            (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="DLA-69.930-10">DLA 69.930/10</ref>): <cit>
            <q> Already during my earliest years, because I had to support mother, sister, younger
              brother (today the so ungrateful billionaire), and niece by giving piano lessons, I
              gladly accepted an offer from a Viennese friend of <ref cRef="entity-000333"
                >[Maximilian] Harden</ref> to write something for him [for the journal <ref
                cRef="entity-002566"><title level="j">Die Zukunft</title></ref>].</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>This offer led to Heinrich's eleven-year career, 1891‒1901, as a music journalist. Thus
          the death of Johann impelled two important strands of Schenker's career.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
              Tagebüchern und Briefen ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), pp. 1‒3, 5,
            342‒45</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Fischer, Isidor</author>, <title level="m">Medizinische Lyzeen: ein Beitrag
              zur Geschichte des medizinischen Unterrichtes in Österreich</title> (Vienna/Leipzig:
            Wilhelm Braumüller, 1915)</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Friedmann, Filip</author>, <title level="m">Die galizischen Juden im Kampfe
              um ihre Gleichberechtigung (1848-1868)</title> (Frankfurt a.M.: J. Kauffmann,
            1929)</bibl>

          <bibl><title><ref type="external" target="https://jri-poland.org/"
              >JRI-Poland</ref></title></bibl>

          <bibl><author>Rothfarb, Lee</author>, <title level="a">Henryk Szenker, Galitzianer: The
              Making of a Man and a Nation,</title>
            <title level="j">Journal of Schenkerian Studies</title>, 11 (2018), 1‒52</bibl>

          <bibl>Communication from Robert Kosovsky</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributors</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author> and <author><hi rend="bold">Lee
                Rothfarb</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>


  </text>
</TEI>
