<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000556">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Gustav Mahler</title>
        <title type="sub">born Kalischt, Bohemia, July 7, 1860; died Vienna, May 18, 1911</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="mahler_gustav">Mahler, Gustav</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>29/01/2006</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Mahler ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">mahler_gustav</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Gustav Mahler</head>
      <div>
        <p>Austrian-Jewish composer and conductor.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Born in Bohemia, Mahler came to Vienna to study at the Conservatory, 1875-78, with Julius
          Epstein (piano), Robert Fuchs (composition), and Franz Krenn (theory). After a series of
          appointments in other cities, he served as Music Director (Kapellmeister) of the Vienna
          Hofoper for ten turbulent years, 1897-1907, where he raised the standard of the opera
          house to among the finest in Europe, and established himself particularly as a conductor
          of Mozart and Wagner, later also of Richard Strauss, Puccini, Pfitzner and others,
          numbering among his assistant conductors Bruno Walter and Franz Schalk. After his enforced
          resignation, partly out of anti-semitism, in 1907 he was succeeded by Felix Weingartner.
          He was also Director of the Vienna Philharmonic Concerts 1898-1901. From 1907, he worked
          in New York at the Metropolitan Opera House and also as conductor of the New York
          Philharmonic, returning to Vienna for the last few months of his life.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Mahler and Schenker</head>
        <p>Federhofer comments: "We do not know what kind of relationship [Schenker] had with Mahler
          ..., for Schenker expressed his views only briefly and very rarely regarding his works and
          achievements as a conductor. He valued him as a conductor, but he rejected his works"
            (<title level="m">Nach Tagebüchern</title>, p.62). Schenker described a performance of
          Smetana's <title level="m">Dalibor</title> in 1897 as "excellent, and under G. Mahler's
          direction, to whom we take this opportunity to pay tribute also for his truthful
          performances of the <title level="m">Nibelungen</title> tetralogy, the <title level="m"
            >Marriage of Figaro</title>, <title level="m">Don Giovanni</title>, <title>Czar und
            Zimmermann</title>, etc." (Federhofer, <title level="m">Essayist</title>, p.358).</p>
        <p>Schenker's diary comments include the following: <cit>
            <q>[1898]: G. Mahler. (Symphony) Annoyingly immature, and good-for-nothing, its
              irreverent pretentiousness all the more ridiculous ..." (OJ 1/4, p.6) [January 3,
              1907]: "open rehearsal of Mahler's Sixth Symphony: a work completely devoid of
              culture, childishly grotesque. A glittering barn-full of percussion instruments, and
              in the Finale the composer as a musical clown. (OJ 1/5, p.32)</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>Directly after the publication of his <ref cRef="entity-001721"><title level="m">Ein
              Beitrag zur Ornamentik</title></ref> in July 1903, Schenker set his sights on a
          professorship at the <ref cRef="entity-002591">Vienna Conservatory</ref>, and in
          correspondence with <ref cRef="entity-000819">Adalbert Franz Seligmann</ref> discussed
          seriously the possibility of approaching Mahler for a recommendation to the Conservatory
          (WSLB I.N.95664, OJ 14/23, [5] and [6]). Whether this happened, and if so whether an
          application was submitted, are unclear. Already in 1906 Schenker was critizing Mahler’s
          conducting at the opera house (diary April 5; WSLB I.N.95662, August 29).</p>

        <p>At the height of opposition against Mahler, in the press and in other quarters, Schenker
          lent him his support, as noted in his diary: <cit>
            <q>[May 22, 1907]: Open letter to Mahler signed on a deliberate whim; situation not
              without humor. (OJ 1/4, p.41)</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>Four days later there was a stir in the press over this, and Schenker, in a heavily
          reworked entry of which this is the final version, wrote: <cit>
            <q>[May 26, 1907]: "ttack by Dr. Robert Hirschfeld in the Feuilleton of the <title
                level="j">Extrablatt</title> over the signing of the Mahler open letter: in this he
              shows himself quite simply incapable of understanding that, even though I may have
              serious criticisms to level against Mahler in the most forceful manner, that does not
              mean that I should at the same time make him suffer for the highest, highest
              conceivable standards to which I hold him, [standards] that could indeed still less be
              applied to the other musicians around him. It is, however, quite futile to try to
              instruct on such a subject someone who thinks that taste alone governs art, especially
              a virtually uneducated taste. People want to speak only of a "genius" (on account of
              their own vanity!) or to criticize the artist (as it were, out of desire for revenge,
              because "genius" has not manifested itself in him); but they cannot understand how one
              might seriously criticize someone's achievement without also thereby ... wanting
              directly to press for their personal removal, especially when, as was the case with
              Mahler, removal would be bound to cause greater disadvantage than gain. (OJ 1/6,
              p.42)</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>Mahler himself wrote thanking Schenker; this is the only item of correspondence that
          exists between the two men: OJ 12/48, undated note: <cit>
            <q>Dear Doctor, My heartfelt thanks to you for your friendly good wishes. Yours most
              truly, Mahler.</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>Following Mahler's resignation, Schenker wrote the somewhat self-righteous entry
          (undated, probably October/December 1907), perhaps with Hirschfeld's attack in mind: <cit>
            <q>Gustav Mahler: People acclaimed him, people rated him as a genius in all that he
              thought, undertook and completed. In the end, many, many years later, it dawned on
              them—over the course of time—what he really represented. Now all those who have
              extricated themselves from their error are angry with—of all people!—me, who from the
              very beginning had taught them to perceive how all-too-lowly the extent of artistic
              mastery in Mahler was. Isn't it a merry qui pro quo that they consider me to be
              contradictory instead of realizing that it is they themselves who are contradictory?
              It is just like the illusion that the fields are rushing past one, while in fact it is
              the train in which one sits that is doing the rushing past. The person who is moving
              believes the unmoving to be in motion." (OJ 1/4, p.27 = OJ 1/6, p.50)</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>Later in his career, Schenker continued to make adverse entries in his diary about Mahler
          as a composer.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Mahler in Schenker's Writings</head>
        <p>Surprisingly, there is no reference to Mahler in the unpublished <title level="m"
            >Niedergang der Kompositionskunst</title> (Decline in the Art of Composition)
          (c.1905-09) —Schenker's first sustained public attack on Wagner and his legacy in
          Bruckner, Wolf, and Richard Strauss. In <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>, Schenker
          refers to Mahler's "touchings-up" of Beethoven's Ninth Symphony (Heft 8-9, p. 54; Eng.
          trans., vol. II, p. 122), which had previously been the subject of a brief aside in his
          1901 article <title level="a">Beethoven-'Retouche'</title> (Federhofer, <title level="m"
            >Essayist</title>, p. 266).There is one reference to him in <title level="j">Das
            Meisterwerk in der Musik</title>, vol. III, p.18 (Eng. trans., p.6).</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
              Tagebüchern und Briefen ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985)</bibl>
          <bibl><editor>Federhofer, Hellmut</editor>, <title>Heinrich Schenker als Essayist und
              Kritiker ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1990)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">NGDM</title></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
