<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-003212">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Thorsch (family)</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="thorsch_family">Thorsch (family)</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">thorsch_family</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Thorsch (family)</head>
      <div>

        <p>Jewish family of bankers and merchants, initially in Prague, later also in Vienna.</p>

      </div>
      <div>
        <head>The family</head>
        <p>The Thorsch family bank was established in Prague by Markus Isak Thorsch (1770‒1819). The
          business, which also encompassed a wholesale goods company, passed to Markus's son Ephraim
          Markus Thorsch (1800‒63), and subsequently jointly to the latter's sons, Philipp Thorsch
          (1831‒1905) and David Eduard Thorsch (1832‒83). This last married <ref
            cRef="entity-006226">Anna Behrend</ref> (1844‒1923), and the couple had four children:
          Marie Charlotte, Melanie, Alfons, and Nanette.</p>

        <p>David Eduard Thorsch moved with his family to Vienna in 1871 and established a branch of
          the business there at Vienna I, Schottenring 12, while Philipp remained in Prague. The
          banking arm of the business rapidly became the second largest and most important privately
          owned bank in Vienna after the Rothschild Bank. Following the death of Philipp, David
          Eduard's son Alfons became the sole proprietor, and the company continued to thrive until
          the late 1930s. Alfons and his wife emigrated in February 1938, and the business was
          seized by the Gestapo in May 1939, along with the Thorsch Palace in Vienna III,
          Metternichgasse.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>The Thorsch family and Schenker</head>
        <p>The name Thorsch is mentioned four times in Schenker's diary for 1906 and 1907. It would
          seem that Schenker was trying to obtain 400 florins in financial support from <ref
            cRef="entity-006226">Mrs. Thorsch</ref> for his friend <ref cRef="entity-000913">Moriz
            Violin</ref> (Floriz). Schenker was at the Thorschs' home on December 19, 1906
          ("desultory music-making at the Thorsch family place"), January 5 (a quartet evening) and
          April 10, 1907 ("evening at the Thorschs'"); then on April 17, 1907 he wrote an angry note
          in his diary that <ref cRef="entity-006226">Mrs. Thorsch</ref> had disregarded the needy
          and gifted <ref cRef="entity-000913">Floriz</ref> and given large amounts of money to a
          less worthy cause (OJ 1/6, p. 38).</p>

        <p>In 1931 and 1932, Schenker invested money in Thorsch &amp; Klein.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author> and <author><hi rend="bold">Marko
                Deisinger</hi></author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
