<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-000562">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Eusebius Mandyczewski</title>
        <title type="sub">born Czernowitz, Bukowina, Aug 18, 1857; died Vienna, July 13, 1929</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="mandyczewski_eusebiu">Mandyczewski, Eusebius</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>06/11/2005</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Mandyczewski ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">mandyczewski_eusebiu</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Eusebius Mandyczewski</head>

      <div>
        <p>Romanian musicologist and archivist working in Vienna.</p>
      </div>
      
      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        
        <p>Mandyczewski studied at Vienna University taking courses with Hanslick and Nottebohm,
          became a friend of Brahms, and was archivist of the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde
          1887-1927. He also taught music history and organology at the Vienna Conservatory (=
          Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst) 1894-1924, and was on the administration there. He was a member of the Brahms
          circle. His name is particularly associated with the Schubert collected edition, to which
          he contributed the ten volumes of Lieder; he was also joint editor of the Brahms collected
          edition, and contributed three volumes to the Haydn collected edition.</p>
        </div>
        
        <div>
          <head>Mandyczewski and Schenker</head>
       
        <p>As a frequent user of the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde Archive, Schenker encountered
          Mandyczewski regularly. In 1908, Mandyczewski requested a complimentary copy of Schenker's
            <title level="m">Harmonielehre</title> (OJ 1/7, p. 94). In 1912, he proposed Schenker's
          name as a speaker in a forthcoming lecture series promoted by the Gesellschaft (OJ 11/22,
          [2]). During his preparation of <title level="m">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von
            Beethoven</title>, Schenker sought Mandyczewski's assistance in locating autograph
          manuscripts and early editions of the late Beethoven sonatas, for which Schenker expressed
          his thanks in print, e.g. in <title level="m">Op. 109</title>:  "I am especially gratefully indebted to Prof. E. Mandyczewski (Vienna), who
          not only pointed me to the whereabouts of the autograph manuscript, but also very kindly
          placed the above-mentioned notes by Nottebohm at my disposal." (p. 25)</p>
        </div>
      
        <div>
          <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>
       
        <p>Correspondence from Mandyczewski to Schenker survives as OJ 12/49 (1898-1928: 11 items),
          one letter from Otto Erich Deutsch to Mandyczewski, Schenker, and others as OC 52/486
          (1922), one postcard from Mandyczewski to Moriz Violin as OJ 70/25 (1899), and he was a
          signatory to the letter regretting the resignation of Moriz Violin from the Vienna
          Akademie, OJ 70/59 (1912).</p>
        </div>
    </body>    
          
          <back>
            <div>
             <head>Sources:</head>
             <listBibl>
             <bibl><title level="m">NGDM2</title> (2001 and online)</bibl>
             
             <bibl><author>Tittel, Ernst</author>, <title level="m">Die Wiener
             Musikhochschule</title> (Vienna: Lafite, 1967)</bibl>
              </listBibl>
            </div>
          </back>


  </text>
</TEI>
