<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000771">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Jeanette (Jeaneth) (Jenny) Schenker [neé Schiff] [Kornfeld]</title>
        <title type="sub">born Aussig an der Elbe (Ustí nad Labem), August 31, 1874; died
          Theresienstadt, January 8, 1945</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="schenker_jeanette">Schenker, Jeanette</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>23/11/2007</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">KornfeldJ ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">SchenkerJ ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">schenker_jeanette</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Jeanette (Jeaneth) (Jenny) Schenker [neé Schiff] [Kornfeld]</head>

      <div>
        <p><figure>
            <head>Jeanette Schenker (OJ 72/16, No. 1 - Atelier Kosel)</head>
            <graphic url="B72F16_2.jpg" xmt:type="thumb-caption" rend="left-img" width="150px"
              height="113px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <graphic url="B72F16_2.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img" width="800px" height="600px"
              mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <figDesc>Studio portrait photograph of Jeanette Schenker as a young woman.</figDesc>
          </figure></p>
        <p>Wife first of <ref cRef="entity-000466">Emil Kornfeld</ref>, secondly of <ref
            cRef="entity-000632">Heinrich Schenker</ref>.</p>

        <p>The oldest of the ten children of Wilhelm (Wolf) Schiff and Emilie (<hi rend="italic"
            >née</hi> Strasser), Jeanette – known to family and friends as "Jenny" – was born in
            <ref cRef="entity-002248">Aussig</ref>. She had four brothers, <ref cRef="entity-006733"
            >Louis</ref>, Emil, <ref cRef="entity-000783">Victor</ref>, <ref cRef="entity-000782"
            >Paul</ref>, and five sisters, <ref cRef="entity-003245">Frieda</ref> (who married
          Theodor Glässner), Emma (who married Eduard Winternitz), <ref cRef="entity-003244"
            >Klara</ref> (who married <ref cRef="entity-000339">Oskar Hatschek</ref>), <ref
            cRef="entity-000944">Rosa</ref> (Ružena, who married <ref cRef="entity-000943">Arnold
            Weil</ref>), and <ref cRef="entity-003920">Hella</ref> (Helena, who married <ref
            cRef="entity-003921">Hans Delmonte</ref>).</p>

        <p>On July 30, 1893, Jeanette married <ref cRef="kornfeld_emil_186619">Emil Kornfeld</ref>,
          a business man, with whom she had two sons, <ref cRef="entity-000467">Erich</ref> and <ref
            cRef="entity-000468">Felix</ref> (the latter died in Auschwitz in 1945), and Felix had a
          son, <ref cRef="entity-000469">Tomás</ref>.</p>

        <p>On July 30, 1928, Klara, with husband and son, came to visit the Schenkers at their
          summer retreat in the Tyrol, and Heinrich writes an extensive commentary on the "turmoil"
          that this causes Jeanette (OJ 4/1, pp. 3236‒3237): <cit>
            <q>My Lie-Liechen [...] has five sisters and three [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>]
              brothers, about whom she finally has the opportunity of receiving some information.
              She did not leave her home town until she was thirty-six years old; thus she lived as
              an adult with many people whose fates she now learns about. [...] [T]here is something
              oppressive when one who has become something new returns to one's earlier life, so to
              speak – there are spaces between them, which make a connection between the two worlds
              impossible – [...] A return is especially impossible if it is undesirable to the
              person concerned.</q>
          </cit></p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Jeanette and Heinrich</head>
        <p><figure>
            <head>Jeanette &amp; Heinrich, wedding Nov 30, 1919 (OJ 72/15, No. 1)</head>
            <graphic url="B72F15_1.jpg" xmt:type="thumb-caption" rend="left-img" width="150px"
              height="113px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <graphic url="B72F15_1.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img" width="800px" height="600px"
              mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <figDesc>Photograph of Heinrich and Jeanette Schenker.</figDesc>
          </figure></p>
        <p> Heinrich and Jeanette must have become acquainted by at least c. 1903, and may even have
          known each other before then since Heinrich and Jeanette's husband had been friends
          (Tomás/Esser). Jeanette left her husband and sons and moved to Vienna on September 30,
          1910, staying first in the Hotel de France, Schottenring 3 (OJ 3/4, p. 2576). In
          1918-1921, she lived at Streichergasse 5, apartment 15, a few minutes' walk from
          Heinrich's Reisnerstraße apartment. From 1910 on, with Heinrich's help, she long sought a
          separation from Kornfeld, but only on November 10, 1919, after a change in the laws, were
          Heinrich and Jeanette eventually able to marry (Federhofer, p. 37, and n.57).</p>

        <p>Jeanette never became a regular student of Heinrich's, having only occasional lessons
          from him, and those only up to 1913. She not only served as Heinrich's amanuensis from
          early on but also was a constant collaborator in all his work (as he frequently attests in
          letters), as well as close companion. Heinrich remarked of Jeanette when studying the
          autograph manuscript of Beethoven Op. 109, that she "often shows a surprising
          resourcefulness" as a result of which new insights emerged (diary OJ 1/12, p. 379, July
          16, 1913); elsewhere he declared that she "stands fully equipped at my side
          intellectually" (DLA 69.930/11, November 2, 1922, to Halm); he dedicated <title level="m"
            >Der freie Satz</title> to her with "MEINER GELIEBTEN FRAU," having previously
          stipulated the form of words in a codicil to his will, adding: "Without her practical help
          down to the very last detail, the work would not be completed." (OJ 35/6, [1], May 20,
          1934). Heinrich's private names for her included "Lie-Lie" (which led some to refer to her
          erroneously as "Lilly"), "Lieliechen," "Lie-Liechen," and "Liecherl."</p>

        <p>After Heinrich's death she actively promoted his works with publishers and editors,
          catalogued his huge <hi rend="italic">Nachlaß</hi>, and entrusted parts of it to pupils
          and disciples, notably two trunks of materials in August 1938 to Ernst Oster (who
          emigrated to the USA, taking them with him to New York) and one trunk to Erwin Ratz (who
          remained in Vienna and passed it after the war to Oswald Jonas, who took those materials
          to Riverside, California). As a Jew, Jeanette was persecuted by the Nazis in the early
          1940s; despite having allegedly twice been rescued from the Nazis by Erwin Ratz (Fink, p.
          22), she was eventually deported from Vienna on transport IV/2-48 on June 29, 1942, and
          died in Theresienstadt concentration camp on January 8, 1945.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Jeanette's Contribution</head>
        <p><figure>
            <head>Jeanette Schenker, 1927 (OJ 72/16, No. 4 - F.-E. von Cube)</head>
            <graphic url="B72F16_1.jpg" xmt:type="thumb-caption" rend="left-img" width="150px"
              height="113px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <graphic url="B72F16_1.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img" width="800px" height="600px"
              mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <figDesc>Photograph of Jeanette Schenker.</figDesc>
          </figure></p>

        <p> Jeanette's distinctive, upright handwriting is familiar to all who work on Heinrich's
          papers. As his eyesight deteriorated, she took over writing his diaries, fair-copying his
          essay-style entries (as far back as 1896), and then taking over the daily record of events
          from about June 1911 on. In the correspondence, the more important letters were taken down
          by her from dictation in shorthand ("Stenogramm"), written out by her in a draft copy
          ("Urschrift") that Heinrich would then correct in his own hand (e.g. OJ 5/16, [2], May 5,
          1914, to Hertzka), after which he would himself write out the fair copy ("Reinschrift"),
          which was then mailed out. Whenever he had a bout of severe eye-strain, she would write
          the fair copy, which Heinrich then signed and dated (e.g.: WSLB 245, May 4, 1915, to
          Hertzka). She wrote up Heinrich's lessonbooks (OC 3) from January 1912; many of his
          unpublished analyses, and material for articles and theoretical works, are in her hand;
          she seems only to have copied text, not graphs. As Schenker once remarked: "Lie-Liechen
          accompanies me at all meetings" (OJ 6/7, [7]), and his diary bears frequent witness to
          this statement. After his death, she maintained correspondence with many of Heinrich's
          pupils and friends into the first half of 1942.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence</head>

        <p>Only one letter survives from Jeanette to Heinrich (OC 31/421, November 27, 1911) and
          none in return. Some interesting personal notes between the two are preserved as OC
          49/138-65, and others probably in Heinrich's hand as OJ 5/37 (1926-30). A small amount of
          correspondence to her from others from before Heinrich's death survives in OC; much
          correspondence sent or received jointly by Heinrich and Jeanette is preserved in OJ, most
          notably to and from Moriz and Valerie Violin (the first postcard to them in Jeanette's
          hand dates from September 23, 1909) and members of the Schenker and Kornfeld families. A
          good deal of correspondence to her after Heinrich's death survives, from <ref
            cRef="entity-000201">Angi Elias</ref> (11 items), <ref cRef="entity-000319">Sophie
            Guttmann</ref> (4 items), <ref cRef="entity-000922">Otto Vrieslander</ref> (63 items),
          and others.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <p><figure>
            <head>Jeanette Schenker, passport 1941 (OJ 35/1, No. 2b)</head>
            <graphic url="B35F1_2b.jpg" xmt:type="thumb-caption" rend="left-img" width="300px"
              height="226px" mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <graphic url="B35F1_2b.jpg" xmt:type="full" rend="left-img" width="800px" height="600px"
              mimeType="image/jpeg"/>
            <figDesc>Photograph of Jeanette Schenker's passport.</figDesc>
          </figure></p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Other Surviving Documents</head>

        <p>Jeanette left a travel diary for a journey made to Chile, April 27 to September 30, 1936
          (OJ 35/9). There survive ten photographs of her with Heinrich (OJ 72/15), three studio
          photograph portraits of her alone (OJ 72/16, 1-3) and one taken by <ref
            cRef="entity-000143">von Cube</ref> (OJ 72/16, 4 - see above), also one of her brother
          Victor (OJ 72/21), and one of her grandson Tomás (OJ 72/9). Her citizenship certificate
            (<hi rend="italic">Heimatschein</hi>) dated March 23, 1939, and her passport dated June
          11, 1941, also survive (OJ 35/1). Her death certificate is now posted on the
          Theresienstadt website, at <ref type="external"
            target="https://www.holocaust.cz/en/database-of-victims/victim/57594-jeanette-schenker/"
            >Toten-Begleitschein</ref>.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>Private communications from Heribert Esser</bibl>

          <bibl>Private communication from Robert Kosovsky</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>
            <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern und Briefen</title> (Hildesheim:
            Olms, 1985)</bibl>

          <bibl><editor>Fink, Evelyn</editor>, ed., <title level="m">Rebell und Visionär: Heinrich
              Schenker in Wien</title> (Vienna: Lafite, 2003)</bibl>

          <bibl>Terezin [=Theresienstadt] Memorial Archive</bibl>

          <bibl>Correspondence between Heribert Esser and Tomás Kornfeld (OJ 71/10a and 21a)</bibl>
          <bibl>Photographs used by permission of Special Collections &amp; Archives, University of
            California, Riverside Libraries, University of California, Riverside, CA.</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
