<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-005306">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Ernst Fritz Schmid</title>
        <title type="sub">born Tübingen, March 7, 1904; died Augsburg, January 20, 1960</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="schmid_ernst_fritz">Schmid, Ernst Fritz</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">schmid_ernst_fritz</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Ernst Fritz Schmid</head>
      <div>

        <p>German music historian and editor.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Ernst Fritz Schmid studied biology at the universities of Tübingen and Göttingen 1922‒24,
          turning thereafter to the study of music at the State Academy for Music in Munich,
          followed by a period as a viola player with the Düsseldorf City Symphony Orchestra. He
          subsequently studied musicology with Willibald Gurlitt at the University of Freiburg, with
          Wilhelm Fischer, Robert Haas, Alfred Orel and Robert Lach at the University of Vienna, and
          at Tübingen University, taking his doctorate at the latter with a dissertation <title
            level="m">Carl Philipp Emanuel Bach und seine Kammermusik</title> in 1929 (published by
          Bärenreiter in 1931).</p>

        <p>He worked as an independent musician and scholar between 1929 and 1934, in which year he
          completed his habilitation at the University of Graz and took up a private lectureship
          there. In 1935 he was appointed to a chair in musicology at the University of Tübingen. At
          that institution, he founded the Swabian Music Archive. He published books on Haydn,
          Mozart, and aspects of Swabian music history. In 1953, he was made general editor of the
            <title level="m">Neue Mozart Ausgabe</title>.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Schmid and Schenker</head>
        <p>In 1930, Schenker and <ref cRef="entity-000380">Anthony van Hoboken</ref> initiated a
          plan to publish a complete edition of the works of <ref cRef="entity-000025">C. P. E.
            Bach</ref> over a period ten years under the auspices of the <ref cRef="entity-002452"
            >Photogram Archive</ref> at the Austrian National Library. In June 1930 Ernst Fritz
          Schmid was engaged as editorial assistant for the project, and was said already to have
          "done much preparatory work" for it. Schmid was also put in charge of the <ref
            cRef="entity-002452">Photogram Archive</ref> itself when its, <ref cRef="entity-000320"
            >Robert Haas</ref>, was unavailable. However, the Bach edition was aborted in December
          1930. </p>

        <p>Schenker kept in touch with Schmid to within three months of his death, and on July 27,
          1932 had a copy of his <ref cRef="entity-001755"><title level="m">Fünf
              Urlinie-Tafeln</title></ref>, published two days earlier. In a diary entry for June
          10, 1933, Schmid is mentioned as "the latest candidate for a regular stipend," though it
          is unclear for what. Schmid also retained friendly relations with <ref
            cRef="entity-000380">Hoboken</ref>, and is mentioned in Hoboken-Schenker correspondence.
          The final communication from Schmid informs Schenker of his appointment as a private
          lecturer (Privatdozent) at the University of Graz.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence</head>
        <p>One letter from Schmid to Schenker, dated 1932, survives as OJ 14/13. In addition, one
          letter from <ref cRef="entity-000412">Oswald Jonas</ref> to Schmid dated 1955 and one from
          Schmid to Jonas of the same year survive as OJ 36/56 and OJ 36/221.</p>
      </div>

    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Source</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">MGG</title>, (1963), vol. 11, pp. 1845-46 (Waltraud Strnad)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
