<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000470">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Erich Wolfgang Korngold</title>
        <title type="sub">born Brno, May 29, 1897; died Hollywood, USA, November 29, 1957</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="korngold_erich_wolfgang">Korngold, Erich Wolfgang</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">korngold_erich_wolfgang</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Erich Wolfgang Korngold</head>
      <div>

        <p>Austrian‒Hungarian, from 1943 American, composer, conductor, and pianist.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Son of leading Viennese music critic <ref cRef="entity-000471">Julius Korngold</ref>,
          Erich Wolfgang Korngold was identified at the age of six as a remarkable musical talent.
          In 1907 he began the study of composition with <ref cRef="entity-000265">Robert
            Fuchs</ref>, but in 1909 the latter withdrew upon recognizing the modern tendencies in
          the boy's music and, on the recommendation of <ref cRef="entity-000556">Gustav
            Mahler</ref> (who deemed the boy a "musical genius"), Korngold embarked on composition
          study with <ref cRef="entity-003005">Alexander von Zemlinsky</ref>, and from 1911
          continued studies with <ref cRef="entity-000301">Hermann Grädener</ref>, <ref
            cRef="entity-000542">Ferdinand Löwe</ref>, and others. His pantomime <title level="m"
            >Der Schneemann</title> (1908), performed in Vienna in 1910 and published by <ref
            cRef="entity-002408">Universal Edition</ref>, caused a sensation and, orchestrated by
          Zemlinsky, was performed at the Vienna Opera later that year. His <title>Piano Sonata No.
            2 in E major </title>(1910) was played throughout Europe by <ref cRef="entity-000794"
            >Artur Schnabel</ref>. After a string of successes, his third opera <title level="m">Die
            tote Stadt</title> (1920) was hailed internationally after its dual premiere in Hamburg
          and Köln. A further opera followed in 1927, alongside orchestral, chamber, and solo piano
          works, and solo songs. In 1927 he was appointed to a professorial position at the Vienna
            <ref cRef="entity-002591">Academy for Music and Performing Arts</ref>.</p>

        <p>In 1934, at the encouragement of Max Reinhardt, he emigrated to the USA, where he wrote
          scores for sixteen films between 1936 and 1946, winning two Oscars, and contributing to
          the establishment of the "Hollywood sound," while also continuing to produce and perform
          orchestral, chamber, and vocal works.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Korngold and Schenker</head>
        <p>There was no known contact between the two men. Schenker attended concerts with works by
          Korngold, and later heard his music by the radio. In his diary he occasionally expressed
          his views of Korngold's work. Of the Piano Quintet he remarked "unusual striving after
          special timbral effects, deliberate simplicity, a constant fluctuation that betrays not
          only lack of talent but also significant dishonesty, despite youth. Undeniably a certain
          fluency, which unfortunately only benefits the triviality; the case is hopeless." (March
          1, 1923). Of the Entr'acte from the opera <title level="m">Das Wunder der Heliane</title>,
          he remarked, "makes frightening efforts at – non-music!" (November 10, 1927).</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
