<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000628">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Fräulein Newlov</title>
        <title type="sub"/>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="newlov_fräulein">Newlov, Fräulein</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>13/11/2005</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Newlov ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">newlov_fräulein</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Fräulein Newlov</head>

      <div>
        <p>Pupil of Schenker's from at least as early as January 15, 1912 ‒ probably earlier because
          this is the first page of Schenker's series of lessonbooks; on the other hand, she does
          not appear in Schenker's diaries before November 1912. She continued lessons only until
          June 26, 1913.</p>

        <p>Evidently Schenker was acquainted with Miss Newlov's mother, for he sends greetings to
          her in all three of the surviving letters to Miss Newlov, using the informal term "Frau
          Mama" rather than "Mutter."</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Lesson Studies</head>
        <p>In the latter part of the 1911/12 season, Newlov took two one-hour lessons a week,
          occupying the second slot on Mondays and Thursdays (Otto Vrieslander preceding her on both
          days, and Angi Elias following her on Mondays). In 1912/13 she again took two lessons a
          week (now preceded by Sofie Deutsch on both days and followed by Angi Elias on Mondays and
          Tony Colbert on Thursdays). Throughout this season and a half she attended unfailingly,
          being marked "absent" on only one occasion.</p>

        <p>Through these two seasons she studied polonaises, etudes and waltzes by Chopin. By
          November 1912 she had covered the “entire collection of etudes,” after which “in place of
          the etudes” she worked on the Beethoven <title>Fifth Piano Concerto</title>, studying it
          section by section in detail between December 1912 to March 1913; and from April to June
          1913 she worked on the Beethoven <title>Piano Sonata Op. 110</title>. — In August 1913 she
          asked Schenker if she could move to a single lesson a week, and he refused, after which a
          rather acrid exchange of letters ensued and she disappeared from the lessonbooks.</p>

        <p>Schenker's view of her after that exchange can be conveyed by a diary entry of September
          28, 1913 (OJ 1/13, p. 430) upon receipt of a letter from her: <cit>
            <q>The reply of an aristocrat who was caught out attempting to deceive me and therefore
              suddenly pushed her aristocratic rank to the fore, signing her letter of thanks with
              yet another forename!! This addition is supposed to form the counterbalance to her
              agreement in the text that the June lesson fees are not to be paid until – November.
              The usual trick of liars and swindlers who have been caught out! Mrs. Stirling, too,
              puffed herself up when I accused her of unspeakable money-grubbiness, with the words:
              "I am a lady!"</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>Miss Newlov evidently kept in touch, for diary entries between 1914 and 1920, coming from
          Italy and the South of France, send greetings, and one from August 1922 refers to a
          walking stick given to him by her.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>
        <p>Three letters survive from Schenker to Miss Newlov. All three are carbon copies of
          handwritten letters: OC 1A/16-17, 25-26, and 27-29, all from September 1913. Schenker
          states in OC 1A/25-26 and 27-29 that he has received all her letters and notes and still
          has them in his possession. However, the diary indicates four letters and a postcard from
          Newlov, dating from approximately November 21, 1912, July 24, 1913, August 20, 1913, and
          September 16, 1913, none of which survive among Schenker's papers.</p>

      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <lb/>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
