<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000775">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Wilhelm Schenker</title>
        <title type="sub">born Wisniowczyk, March 12, 1862</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="schenker_wilhelm">Schenker, Wilhelm</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>25/06/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">schenker_wilhelm</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Wilhelm Schenker</head>
      <div>
        <p>Third child ‒ first surviving child ‒ of <ref cRef="entity-000772">Johann</ref> and <ref
            cRef="entity-000773">Julia</ref> Schenker, hence Heinrich Schenker's elder brother, who
          became a medical doctor. He was married twice, his second wife's first name being <ref
            cRef="entity-000767">Dodi</ref>, and had a number of children, perhaps the oldest being
            <ref cRef="entity-000766">Anton [Tonschl]</ref>. In the 1910s he lived in <ref
            cRef="entity-002301">Kautzen</ref>, where he and his wife cared for Julia Schenker for
          the last three years of her life (1914–17). </p>

        <p>Wilhelm does not appear to be mentioned in Schenker's diary before 1914, when Heinrich
          comments that Wilhelm is due to take his pension in 1915. Wilhelm ‒ like Moriz, the
          youngest child ‒ was relatively well-off, and he figures in Schenker's diary as providing
          money to Julia (OJ 1/15, pp. 677, 679, September 1 and 3, 1914), and in 1918 is involved
          with funeral and grave-stone arrangements for Julia.</p>

        <p>In 1927, Wilhelm was living in Sankt Bernhard, near Horn, 80 km (50 miles) north-east of
          Vienna, and only 25 km (15 miles) from <ref cRef="entity-002323">Waidhofen</ref>, where
          Julia Schenker was buried. Schenker's diary for September 3‒5, when the Schenkers visited
          him, gives a penetrating portrait of a man who used cheerfulness as a device for avoiding
          life's difficulties, and who had never fully tapped the "higher resources" that he
          possessed, a man aloof from his family, even unaware of Schenker's musical interests. <cit>
            <q>He no longer remembers the evening on which we left our father in Lemberg after the
              burial of our eldest brother [1880] and, returning to our lodging, shook hands and
              hugged each other – he doesn't remember our brother, not even his death! I recall with
              horror that hour in which I brought him, when he was a medical student, the sad news
              that our father had died [late 1887]. To me, a world full of trouble came into being,
              at any rate a new world; he seemed not to be taking any notice, as if even then he had
              decided once and for all to take no responsibility upon himself for those who
              remained, at least as far as his share was concerned. (OJ 3/9, pp. 3109-3110)</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>The Schenker's visited him again on September 3, 1929, but decided to cut short their
          visit and left on the 5th.</p>

        <p>The children from his first marriage having left home, Wilhelm was looked after in later
          years by his housekeeper ‒ an arrangement which Heinrich felt to have brought little
          comfort to his brother on account of his "domineering" personality (something he inherited
          from their mother). </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Heinrich and Jeanette</head>
        <p>Eight letters from Wilhelm to Heinrich and his wife Jeanette are known to survive as OJ
          14/6 (1930-39) and two as OC 44/38 and A/296 (1934), and 106 letters and postcards from
          Heinrich to Wilhelm as OJ 5/38. Wilhelm maintained contact with Jeanette after Heinrich's
          death, his last surviving letter to her being dated June 1, 1939 (OJ 14/6, [8]).</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Source:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl> private communication from Heribert Esser </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Ian Bent</author> and <author>Marko Deisinger</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
