<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000812">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Eduard Schütt</title>
        <title type="sub">born St Petersburg, October 22, 1856; died Obermais, South Tyrol, July 26,
          1933</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="schuett_eduard">Schütt, Eduard</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">schuett_eduard</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Eduard Schütt</head>
      <div>

        <p>Russian composer, pianist, and conductor, who lived in Vienna from 1879 to his death.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>After receiving initial musical training from his father, a cellist, Schütt studied piano
          and composition at the conservatories in St. Petersburg and Leipzig (1876–78 with Ernst
          Friedrich Richter, Salomon Jadassohn and <ref cRef="entity-000702">Carl H.
          Reinecke</ref>). He moved to Vienna in 1879, where he studied piano with <ref
            cRef="entity-000523">Theodor Leschetizky</ref>. He toured Austria-Hungary, Bohemia,
          France and Russia from 1880 until 1882. From 1881 until 1887, Schütt directed the Vienna
          Akademischer Wagner-Verein, and in 1887 Cosima Wagner attempted without success to engage
          him to conduct the Bayreuth Festival. Schütt dedicated himself increasingly exclusively to
          composing and wrote very well-loved and popular works for piano.</p>

        <p>In 1892 he bought the Mon Repos villa in Obermais bei Meran, where he then took up
          residence, after having previously lived in Paris, Leipzig, Vienna, and other places. In
          Meran, Schütt taught harmony, aesthetics, composition and piano. His students included
          Antonio Cornoldi, Emil Hornof and Franz Villgrattner. Some of his friends and
          acquaintances included Franz Liszt, Johannes Brahms, <ref cRef="entity-000150">Eugen
            d'Albert</ref>, <ref cRef="entity-000746">Anton Rubinstein</ref>, <ref
            cRef="entity-000363">Richard Heuberger</ref>, <ref cRef="entity-000310">Alfred
            Grünfeld</ref>, <ref cRef="entity-000727">Arnold Rosé</ref>, <ref cRef="entity-000090"
            >Ludwig Bösendorfer</ref> and Géza von Zichy-Vásonykeő.</p>
      </div>


      <div>
        <head>Eduard Schütt and the Schenker circle</head>
        <p>The first known occurrence of Schütt’s name in the Schenker correspondence occurs on
          August 31, 1897 (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="Sbb-B-II-4415">Sbb B II 4415</ref>,
          letter to Ferruccio Busoni), when he is coupled with Leschetizky as recommenders of
          low-quality music to publishers. According to Schenker's diary, Schenker and Schütt
          encountered each other in <ref cRef="entity-002396">Steinach am Brenner</ref> on July 19,
          1907, this being the only mention of Schütt in the diaries before 1912. — Schenker, in a
          letter to <ref cRef="entity-000356">Emil Hertzka</ref>, reports Schütt often recounting
          that Brahms once said to him “The best person writing about music is the young Schenker”
            (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="WSLB-133">WSLB 133</ref>, August 26, 1912). Schenker’s
          diary for November 6, 1924 records an allegation that Schütt had prevented <ref
            cRef="entity-000515">Marianne Leibl</ref> from continuing her lessons with Schenker
          because he wanted to teach her himself.</p>
      </div>

    </body>

    <back>

      <div>
        <head>Source</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Österreiches Musiklexikon Online</title> (Christian Fastl)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributors</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Marko Deisinger</hi></author> and <author><hi rend="bold"
                >Ian Bent</hi></author>
          </bibl>
          <lb/>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
