<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000164">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Otto Erich Deutsch</title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, September 5, 1883; died Vienna, November 23, 1967</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="deutsch_otto_erich">Deutsch, Otto Erich</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>21/01/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">DeutschOE ~ H+JSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">DeutschOE ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">DeutschOE+H ~ H+JSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">deutsch_otto_erich</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Otto Erich Deutsch</head>

      <div>
        <p>Austrian musicologist. Although he is chiefly known as a Schubert scholar, Deutsch’s
          publications include important studies of Handel, Haydn, Mozart and Beethoven; he ranks
          among the leading music bibliographers of the twentieth century.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Career Summary</head>
        <p>Deutsch studied history of literature and art at the Universities of Vienna and Graz, and
          worked as an art critic 1908–09. He served in the Austrian Army during World War I, before
          working for a time in the book trade, first as an employee of Seidl’s Buchhandlung, then
          from 1919 as its owner. In 1926 he became music librarian to the private collector and
          musicologist <ref cRef="entity-000380">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>, a position he held for
          nearly a decade, which included the preparation and maintaining of a card-file for what
          was the largest private collection of musical prints. His first major publication was a
          two-volume documentary biography of Franz Schubert (1914). This was followed by further
          studies of Schubert, which led to Deutsch being given the title of Professor in 1928, the
          centennial year of Schubert’s death.</p>

        <p>Less than a year after the annexation of Austria by Germany, Deutsch, who was Jewish,
          left Vienna (July 1939) for England, becoming a British citizen in 1947; but he returned
          to Vienna in 1952. While in England, he co-authored the standard catalogue of Schubert’s
          works and applied the principles of the documentary biography to Handel (1955) and Mozart
          (1961). Many offprints and clippings of articles by Deutsch are preserved among Schenker’s
          papers (OC File C), including several on Schenker’s desk at the time of his death (OC File
          30).</p>

        <p>Not only did Deutsch’s music scholarship range widely, but he was also on friendly terms
          with music scholars, antiquarian dealers and publishers in Europe, especially in England,
          Germany, and Switzerland. He frequently took part in broadcasts on <ref
            cRef="entity-002755">Radio Vienna</ref>, as organizer and presenter, and was a regular
          reviewer of events at the Salzburg Festival.</p>

        <p>Deutsch lived from 1913 at Nibelungengasse 13, Vienna I; from 1920 at Valeriestraße 26,
          Vienna II; and then at Böcklinstraße 26, Vienna II, from 1921 until 1939.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Deutsch and Schenker</head>
        <p>Deutsch shared Schenker’s belief in the ability of original documents to speak for
          themselves, as is exemplified by his volume on the original editions of Schubert’s Goethe
          songs (1926), his facsimile of Schubert’s diary (1928), and his edition of Mozart’s
          handwritten catalog of his works (1956), as well as the transcriptions in his documentary
          biographies. He was the general editor of a series of "connoisseur prints" (<hi
            rend="italic">Liebhaberdrucke</hi>) published by <ref cRef="entity-002408">Universal
            Edition</ref>, to which Schenker contributed a facsimile edition of <ref
            cRef="entity-001754"><title>Beethoven's "Moonlight" Sonata</title></ref> (1921) with
          reproductions of three sketches, and a Foreword (contract: OC 52/238). (For the series
          list, see below.)</p>

        <p>The earliest document linking Deutsch and Schenker is a press announcement by the <ref
            cRef="entity-002430">Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde in Wien</ref>, dated September 15,
          1912, announcing a series of public lectures, the list of speakers including both men
            (<ref type="other" cRef="OJ-11-22_4">OJ 11/22, [4]</ref>). The first reference to him in
          Schenker’s diary appears on February 24, 1913, when, after attending a lecture by
          Schenker’s pupil <ref cRef="entity-000165">Mrs. Sofie Deutsch</ref> (no relation to Otto
          Erich), Heinrich and <ref cRef="entity-000771">Jeanette (Kornfeld)</ref> spent the evening
          in company with <ref cRef="entity-000165">Sofie</ref> and Otto Erich (diary). Thereafter,
          Schenker met him not infrequently at the houses of <ref cRef="entity-000165">Sofie
            Deutsch</ref> and her brother <ref cRef="entity-000590">Fritz Mendl</ref>. From the
          mid-1920s onwards, Schenker and Deutsch often invited each other (with their spouses) to
          afternoon snack (<hi rend="italic">Jause</hi>) or the evening meal in their homes; they
          also met in the <ref cRef="entity-002259">Café Aspang</ref> to discuss urgent matters.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>

        <p>The Schenkers’ correspondence with Deutsch and his wife <ref cRef="entity-000163"
            >Hanna</ref>, of which the earliest items date from 1913, continued to 1939. Over 320
          items of correspondence are known to survive, in the Wienbibliothek im Rathaus, Vienna,
          Manuscript Division, the New York Public Library, Oster Collection (files 12, 18, 24, 39,
          44, 50, 54, and A), the University of California, Riverside, Oswald Jonas Collection (
          files 5/9; 10/3, 14/21, 71/19, and 71/ 21), the University of California, Berkeley,
          Hargrove Library (BerkAE, [4]), and in private hands. From 1927 until Schenker’s death,
          Deutsch was involved in some intermediary capacity in nearly all of his friend’s
          publications. He helped Schenker with the contracts for these, and often smoothed the
          relationship between author and publisher with carefully worded letters. He advised on the
          formatting and printing of music examples and proofread the texts for the <ref
            cRef="entity-001749">second and third <title level="m">Meisterwerk</title>
            yearbooks</ref> and the Foreword to the <ref cRef="entity-001755"><title level="m">Fünf
              Urlinie-Tafeln/Five Analyses in Sketchform</title></ref>. As late as 1934 he was
          advising Schenker on the contract for <ref cRef="entity-001728"><title level="m">Der freie
              Satz</title></ref> and offering to read the proofs when they were ready.</p>

        <p>The last eight years of their voluminous correspondence thus provides considerable
          insight into the genesis of some of Schenker’s most important publications. But it is
          actually dominated by another topic: the difficulties both men encountered in their
          dealings with <ref cRef="entity-000380">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>. Both men felt betrayed,
          at times, by <ref cRef="entity-000380">Hoboken</ref>’s cavalier lifestyle and his wavering
          attitude toward a number of things that affected their lives in significant ways: piano
          studies with Schenker, financial support for Schenker’s publications, the fee for
          Deutsch’s services as <ref cRef="entity-000380">Hoboken</ref>'s librarian, interest in and
          support for a journal to promote the <ref cRef="entity-002452">Photogram Archive</ref> and
          a proposed collected edition of the works of C. P. E. Bach; the maintenance of <ref
            cRef="entity-000380">Hoboken</ref>’s music library, and even of his Viennese residence.
          The correspondence from 1927 onward documents these vicissitudes in considerable
          detail.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Selective Bibliography (to 1951 only)</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Franz Schubert: Die Dokumente seines Lebens und Schaffens</title>:
            II/1 <title level="m">Die Dokumente seines Lebens</title> (Munich: G. Müller, 1914), III
              <title level="m">Sein Leben in Bildern</title> (ibidem, 1913); Eng. transl. <title
              level="m">Schubert: A Documentary Biography</title> (London: Dent, 1946)</bibl>

          <bibl><title level="m">Franz Schuberts Briefe und Schriften</title> (Munich: G. Müller,
            1919)</bibl>

          <bibl><title level="m">Die historischen Bildnisse Franz Schuberts</title> (Vienna, 1922,
            2/1928)</bibl>

          <bibl><title level="m">Die Originalausgaben von Schuberts Goethe-Liedern</title> (Vienna:
            Heck, 1926)</bibl>

          <bibl><title level="m">Franz Schuberts Tagebuch</title> (Vienna: Heck, 1928)</bibl>

          <bibl>with <editor>D. R. Wakeling</editor>, <title level="m">Schubert: A Thematic
              Catalogue of All his Works in Chronological Order</title> (London: Dent, 1951)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head><hi rend="bold"><title>Musikalische Seltenheiten: Wiener Liebhaberdrucke</title>, gen.
            ed. Otto Erich Deutsch:</hi></head>

        <listBibl>
          <bibl><note type="editorial" place="inline">Note: Only the first six are known to have
              been published.</note></bibl>

          <bibl>I: <title level="m">L. van Beethoven, Sonate op. 27 Nr 2 in Cis Moll</title>, ed.
              <editor>H. Schenker</editor> (UE 7000: 1921)</bibl>

          <bibl>II: <title level="m">Joseph Haydn, Zwölf schottische Volkslieder</title>, ed.
              <editor>E. Mandyczewski</editor>, German transl. <editor>Hugo Engelbert
              Schwarz</editor> (UE 7001: 1921) (English edition: <title level="m">Twelve Scotch
              Popular Songs for one voice with the accompaniment of pianoforte, violin and
              violoncello)</title>
            <note type="editorial" place="inline">not facsimile</note></bibl>

          <bibl>III: <title level="m">Johannes Brahms, Drei Lieder</title>, ed. <editor>M.
              Kalbeck</editor> (UE 7002: 1921)</bibl>

          <bibl>IV: <title level="m">Franz Schuberts fünf erste Lieder</title>, ed. <editor>O. E.
              Deutsch</editor> (UE 7003: 1922) </bibl>

          <bibl>V: <title level="m">Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart, Zwei Rondos</title>, ed. <editor>H.
              Gál</editor> (UE 7004: 1923)</bibl>

          <bibl>VI: <title level="m">Johann Sebastian Bach, Präludium und Fuge H moll für
              Orgel</title>, ed. <editor>G. Kinsky</editor> (UE 7005: 1923)</bibl>

          <bibl>VII: <title level="m">Richard Strauss, Tod und Verklärung</title> (UE 7008)</bibl>

          <bibl>VIII: <title level="m">J. S. Bach, Kaffeekantate</title> (UE 7009)</bibl>

          <bibl>IX: <title level="m">Mozart, Jupiter-Symphonie</title> (UE 7010)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Festschrift Otto Erich Deutsch zum 80. Geburtstag</title>, ed.
              <editor>Walter Gerstenberg</editor>, <editor>Jan LaRue</editor>, and <editor>Wolfgang
              Rehm</editor> (Kassel: Bärenreiter, 1963)</bibl>

          <bibl><title level="m">NGDM2</title> (2001 and online)</bibl>

          <bibl>
            <title level="m">MGG1</title> (1954) </bibl>

          <bibl>Oster Collection (OC): Finding List</bibl>

          <bibl>Oswald Jonas Memorial Collection (OJMC): Checklist</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributors</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">William Drabkin</hi></author> and <author><hi rend="bold"
                >Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

    </back>


  </text>
</TEI>
