<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-005758">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Paul Khuner</title>
        <title type="sub">born Sechshaus, near Vienna, February 5, 1884; died Vienna, November 3,
          1932</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="khuner_paul">Khuner, Paul</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">khuner_paul</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Paul Khuner</head>
      <div>

        <p>Austrian industrialist, and a major Schenker benefactor in the early 1930s.</p>

        <p>Paul Khuner was the son of Gottfried Friedrich Khuner (1854–1912) who, together with his
          father Emanuel Mendel Khuner (1829–85) founded a company that manufactured cooking fats.
          At their factory in Atzgersdorf, established in 1895, they invented and produced an early
          form of margarine which they named "Kunerol"; the family fortune was based on this
          product. A monument to the family survives in the form of a country house in Payerbach,
          near the town of Semmering in Lower Austria, which was designed by Adolf Loos (in
          collaboration with another Moravian-born architect, Heinrich Kulka) in 1928 and completed
          in 1930.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Khuner and Schenker</head>

        <p>Paul’s wife Hedwig (<hi rend="italic">née</hi> Sommer) was a piano pupil of <ref
            cRef="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</ref>; it is through this connection that Schenker
          received from Khuner, on November 27, 1931, the sum of 5,000 Austrian shillings to help
          defray the production costs of <title level="m">Der freie Satz</title> (this is mentioned
          briefly in <bibl><author>Federhofer</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker, nach
              Tagebüchern und Briefen</title>, p. 38</bibl>). His name appears several times in <ref
            cRef="entity-000951">Weisse</ref>'s letters to the Schenkers; Khuner and Schenker also
          corresponded, but a proposed meeting never came to fruition in the year between Khuner's
          act of generosity and his untimely death at the age of 48. </p>

        <p>The money from Khuner arrived around the time that <ref cRef="entity-000268">Wilhelm
            Furtwängler</ref> raised a similar sum, 3,000 marks, to help cover the production costs
          of the "Eroica" Symphony essay (<ref cRef="entity-001752"><title level="j"
              >Meisterwerk</title> III</ref>). Both payments were received when Schenker's life was
          in financial crisis: the theorist was taking legal action against his brother <ref
            cRef="entity-000774">Moriz</ref> over the non-repayment of a large loan. But Schenker
          never acknowledged the generosity of either benefactor, and <ref cRef="entity-000951"
            >Weisse</ref> was particularly aggrieved that Khuner’s name went unrecorded in <title
            level="m">Der freie Satz</title>: <cit>
            <q>The end of the foreword is more than a little alienating, in that it gives the
              illusion that the publication of the book was due entirely to Anthony van Hoboken; and
              Mr. Khuner does not get so much as a syllable's worth of thanks. I must admit that
              this touched me most painfully. (OJ 15/16, [99], July 14, 1935 to Jeanette
              Schenker)</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>In a letter to Hoboken of September 17, 1932, when announcing that <title level="m">Der
            freie Satz</title> was at last finished, Schenker commented with reference to Khuner: <cit>
            <q>I have [...] lived to see the contribution of a local industrialist (procured by Dr.
              Weisse), despite all precaution by me and by my attorney, substantially dwindle! (OJ
              89/5, [6])</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>Khuner’s widow emigrated to the United States in 1938, the year that Austria was annexed
          to Nazi Germany. Weisse died two years later, six weeks short of his 48th birthday.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>William Drabkin</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
