<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000895">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Tonschl (Anton) [Schimatowitsch]</title>
        <title type="sub">born c. 1879; died May c. 24, 1924</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="schimatowitsch_tonschl">Schimatowitsch, Anton [Tonschl]</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/05/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">schimatowitsch_tonschl</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Tonschl (Anton) [Schimatowitsch]</head>
      <div>
        <p>The son of <ref cRef="entity-008443">Mrs. Schimatowitsch</ref>, and an unknown
          father.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Identity</head>
        <p>“Tonschl” – the name is a diminutive of “Anton” – figures numerous times in Schenker’s
          diary and in family correspondence, but much ambiguity surrounds his identity. The clue to
          the latter lies in an entry in Schenker’s diary for March 30, 1920: “The newspapers report
          Tonschl’s arrest.” At least five newspapers of that date report the arrest of an “Anton
          Schimatowitsch” and of no one else named “Anton” or any of the diminutive forms of that
          name, for example: <cit>
            <q><title level="j">Reichspost</title>, March 30, 1920: “Corrupt Officials”<lb/> The
              purchaser at the economic department of Baden, Anton Schimatowitsch, of
              Reinprechtsdorferstraße 54, [Vienna] District V, was arrested on the 26th of the
              month. He confessed, together with the head of the economic department [of Baden bei
              Wien], [Karl] Theiner, to having over approximately a year and a half given official
              [Adolf] Pordes [of the Austrian War Office for Grain] sums of money in the amount of
              200,000 Kronen in return for a larger supply of potatoes. After extensive questioning,
              Schimatowitsch admitted that he and Theiner had also retained a portion of this money,
              approximately 20,000 Kronen. […] Earlier inquiries revealed that Porges had received
              roughly a million [Kronen] in bribes, while Theiner and Schimatowitsch had each
              accepted around 100,000 Kronen. In order to recoup these sums, 1 Krone 20 Heller has
              been added to the price per kilogram of the potatoes.</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>The parallel report in the <title level="j">Neues Wiener Journal</title> provides
          Tonschl’s age as “41 years old.” By April 25, he had been released, claiming “injustice.”
        </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Parenthood, relationship to Wilhelm Schenker</head>
        <p>A remark in Heinrich’s diary for December 19, 1924 provides a framework: <cit>
            <q>First [Wilhelm] fell prey to his uncle, then to Mrs. Sch., and with that he lost out
              on having progeny of his own.</q>
          </cit>
        </p>

        <p>This clearly indicates that Wilhelm was not the father of Tonschl, but that he had at
          some time become emotionally attached to <ref cRef="entity-008443">Mrs.
            Schimatowitsch</ref>, which left him feeling partly responsible for the boy, and later
          for Tonschl’s children. Wilhelm could thus at best be described as Tonschl’s “adoptive
          father.” Nothing is known of Tonschl’s true father.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Life Summary</head>
        <p>Nothing is known of Tonschl’s birth, upbringing, or education, though a remark in
          Heinrich’s diary (November 22, 1917) suggests he may have been brought up in <ref
            cRef="entity-002323">Waidhofen an der Thaya</ref>, with which the Schenker family was
          associated. The first reference to him is in Heinrich’s diary for September 3, 1914,
          indicating that though eligible for war service he had “by a trick [...] succeeded in
          staying far from the battlefield.” He seems to have been close to the <ref
            cRef="entity- 002936">Bednař family</ref> in Vienna, as well as to <ref
            cRef="entity-000775">Wilhelm</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-000767">Dodi
          Schenker</ref>.</p>

        <p>In March 1917, Tonschl moved to <ref cRef="entity-002394">Baden bei Wien</ref> to be
          close to <ref cRef="entity-000774">Moriz</ref>, Heinrich Schenker’s younger brother and a
          wealthy banker, “in order to ingratiate himself with him,” since he did not “have the
          slightest professional pre-education” (diary, November 22, 1917). A month after <ref
            cRef="entity-000767">Dodi</ref> died, in July 1923, Heinrich commented on the “mother
          tragedy Dodi–Tonschl” (August 6, 1923), remarking that Tonschl “has a strong feeling of
          gratitude for the deceased, who doubtless made the critical contribution to his career
          training and later wealth.”</p>

        <p>Oblique allusions in Heinrich’s diary seem to indicate that Tonschl was married with
          children, that by 1920 he had left his wife and children, and that <ref
            cRef="entity-000775">Wilhelm</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-000767">Dodi</ref> had urged
          “the husband back to his wife, the father back to his children” (diary, January 11, 1920).
          A reference by Heinrich to “Tonschl-the-father” and “Tonschl-the-son” (<ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-38_4">OJ 5/38, [4]</ref>, August 18, 1923) suggests
          that one child was named “Anton” after his father; this leads to the likelihood that the
            “<ref cRef="entity-003491">Tonerl</ref>,” referred to often in Schenker documents, was
          Tonschl’s son. Baptismal certificates record an Anton Schimatowitsch born in 1907 and a
          Karl Schimatowitsch born in 1911, both in <ref cRef="entity-002340">St. Pölten</ref>. This
          in turn leads to the likelihood that the “<ref cRef="entity-008438">Karli</ref>” mentioned
          several times in correspondence with Wilhelm Schenker was Tonschl’s second child.</p>

        <p>Heinrich and Tonschl met not infrequently to exchange family information and to discuss
          financial deals of some kind (e.g. “Tonschl encountered; he promises to send us Wilhelm
          regarding the diamonds and other gold items” – diary, September 6, 1921; “[Moriz] recounts
          that Tonschl picks up 1–2 million from him every month” – April 7, 1924).</p>

        <p>There is a suggestion of a medical condition: “Dodi tells us [...] Tonschl betrays the
          character of disease: acute arteriosclerosis” (diary, January 11, 1920). His death came in
          mid-May 1924: Heinrich’s diary records: “Death notice of Tonschl arrives; I instantly
          assume suicide” (May 24, 1924). Four days later he wrote to <ref cRef="entity-000775"
            >Wilhelm</ref>: “Again, a heavy stroke of fate has befallen you, against all human
          expectation! [...] for a long time I suspected that the poor fellow took his own life,
          until Moriz related the true circumstances.” (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-5-38_45"
            >OJ 5/38, [45]</ref>).</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence</head>
        <p>Heinrich’s diary gives evidence that he and Tonschl corresponded, but no material is
          known to survive.</p>
      </div>

    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="j">Deutsches Volksblatt</title>, March 30, 1920</bibl>

          <bibl>
            <title level="j">Neue freie Presse</title>, March 30, 1920</bibl>

          <bibl>
            <title level="j">Neues Wiener Journal</title>, March 30, 1920</bibl>

          <bibl>
            <title level="j">Reichspost</title>, March 30, 1920</bibl>

          <bibl>
            <title level="j">Wiener Zeitung</title>, March 30, 1920</bibl>

          <bibl>
            <title level="m">St. Pölten Catholic Church Records 1626–1955</title>: <ref
              type="external"
              target="https://www.findagrave.com/memorial/241268908/anton-schimatowitschschimatowitsch"
              >Anton Schimatowitsch [Tonerl]</ref>
          </bibl>

          <bibl>
            <title level="m">St. Pölten Catholic Church Records 1626–1955</title>: <ref
              type="external"
              target="https://www.findagrave.com/memorial/101748065/karl-schimatowitsch">Karl
              Schimatowitsch [Karli]</ref>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributors</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author>, <author><hi rend="bold">Marko
                Deisinger</hi></author>, and <author><hi rend="bold">William
            Drabkin</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
