<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000754">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Felix Salzer</title>
        <title type="sub">born Vienna, June 13, 1904; died New York, Aug 10, 1986</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="salzer_felix">Salzer, Felix</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>16/05/2006</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Salzer ~ H+JSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">Salzer ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">salzer_felix</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Felix Salzer</head>
      <div>
        <p>Music theorist, musicologist, teacher, pupil first of Hans Weisse, then of Schenker.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Career Summary; Association with Schenker</head>
        <p>Born in Vienna into the Wittgenstein family (his mother, Helene Salzer, was the sister of
          the philosopher Ludwig Wittgenstein and the pianist <ref cRef="entity-000971">Paul
            Wittgenstein</ref>), Salzer began his studies with Schenker in 1931. His earlier studies
          in theory and analysis were with <ref cRef="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</ref>, starting in
          the 1920s. After Weisse's emigration to New York in 1931, he and three other former pupils
          of Weisse (Trude Kral, Greta Kraus, and Manfred Willfort) became Schenker's students,
          forming a "seminar" that met weekly. The published result of their studies was the <title
            level="m">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln/Five Analyses in Sketchform</title> (New York: David
          Mannes Music School, 1932; repr. New York: Dover, 1969, as <title level="m">Five Graphic
            Music Analyses</title>). On the dissolution of the seminar in 1934 he began private
          study with Schenker.</p>
        <p>Salzer also studied musicology with <ref cRef="entity-000003">Guido Adler</ref> at Vienna
          University, writing a dissertation "Die Sonatenform bei Franz Schubert," and receiving a
          doctorate in 1926. He was a piano pupil of Malwine Brée (assistant to Theodor
          Leschetizky). In 1935 he received a diploma in conducting (with Oswald Kabasta) from the
          Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst (= Vienna Conservatory).</p>
        <p>Salzer was to have been co-editor with Oswald Jonas of a monthly periodical (entitled
            <ref cRef="entity-002563">
            <title level="j">Die Tonkunst</title>
          </ref>) devoted to Schenker's theory. The plan for this periodical had been proposed by
          Weisse in 1927, but it never came to fruition. After Schenker's death, Salzer and Jonas,
          who were both teaching at the newly established Schenker-Institut in the <ref
            cRef="entity-002451">Neues Wiener Konservatorium</ref>, founded the journal <title
            level="j">Der Dreiklang</title> (nine issues, 1937-38) in order to further the
          dissemination of Schenker's ideas.</p>
        <p>In 1940, shortly after settling in New York, Salzer joined the faculty of the <ref
            cRef="entity-002454">David Mannes Music School</ref>, taking over the position left
          vacant on Weisse's death. He served as Director from 1948 through 1955; under his
          leadership the school became a degree-granting college, and he was largely responsible for
          developing the "Techniques of Music" curriculum, based on Schenker's approach. He became
          Professor of Music at Queens College of the City University of New York in 1963; he taught
          there and later at the City University Graduate Center until the mid 1970s. He also
          continued to teach at Mannes, from 1962 to 1981.</p>
        <p>Salzer's major publications include <title level="m">Sinn und Wesen der abendländischen
            Mehrstimmigkeit</title> (Vienna: Saturn-Verlag, 1935), <title level="m">Structural
            Hearing: Tonal Coherence in Music</title> (New York: Boni, 1952; reprinted New York:
          Dover, 1962 and 1982), and <title level="m">Counterpoint in Composition: The Study of
            Voice Leading</title>, with Carl Schachter (New York: McGraw-Hill, 1969; reprinted New
          York: Columbia University Press, 1989). He contributed important articles to <title
            level="j">The Music Forum</title>, which he founded in 1967 with co-editor William J.
          Mitchell.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Correspondence</head>
        <p>The Schenker/Salzer correspondence survives partly among the Salzer papers now deposited
          at the New York Public Library (27 items from Schenker to Salzer, 1930-1934, FS 40/1),
          partly in the Ernst Oster Collection at the New York Public Library (3 items from Salzer
          to Schenker, 1934, OC 44/2, 36, 37), and partly in the Oswald Jonas Memorial Collection at
          University of California, Riverside, Special Collections (2 items from Salzer to Schenker,
          1932, 1934, OJ 14/1, one from Salzer to Jeanette Schenker, 1938, OJ 14/1, joint
          Salzer-Jonas correspondence with Jeanette Schenker, 1935, OJ 5/36, 12/6 [copy in 14/1],
          and correspondence between Salzer and Jonas, Oster, and Siegfried Müller, OJ 36/53, 169,
          188, 214, 71/31). The legal agreement between Salzer and Jeanette Schenker over the
          Schenker papers, 1936, is preserved as FS, 40/2.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources and Further Reading:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Baker's1971</title></bibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">NGDM2</title> (2001 and online - Saul Novack, includes list of
            writings)</bibl>
          <bibl><editor>Fink, Evelyn,</editor> ed., <title level="m">Rebell und Visionär: Heinrich
              Schenker in Wien</title> (Vienna: Lafite: 2003), pp. 19-26 [Schenker-Institut]</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Schachter, Carl</author>, <title level="a">Felix Salzer (1904-1986),</title>
            and [anon.] <title level="a">Felix Salzer,</title> in <editor>Eybl, M.</editor> &amp;
              <editor>Fink-Mennel, E.</editor>, eds, <title level="m">Schenker-Traditionen: Eine
              Wiener Schule der Musiktheorie und ihre internationale Verbreitung</title> (Vienna:
            Böhlau, 2006), pp. 105-11, 245-46 <hi rend="italic">et passim</hi></bibl>
          <bibl><author>Slottow, Stephen</author>, <title level="a">Schenkerian Pedagogy in the
              Salzer and Oster Teaching Lines: An Oral History Approach,</title> in
              <editor>Cadwallader, A.</editor>, ed., <title level="m">Essays from the Fourth
              International Schenker Symposium</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 2008), pp.
            258-78</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Hedi Siegel</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
