<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="kornfeld_family">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Kornfeld family</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="kornfeld_family">Kornfeld family</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>09/04/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Kornfeld ~ JSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Person</term>
          <term subtype="basename">kornfeld_family</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Kornfeld family</head>
      <div>
        <!-- BODY: -->
        <p><hi rend="bold">Kornfeld family:</hi>  family into which <ref cRef="schenker_jeanette">Jeanette</ref> (<hi rend="italic">n&#xE9;e</hi> Schiff; by second marriage, Schenker), married first.</p>
        <p><hi rend="bold">Kornfeld, Emil (1866&#x2013;1937),</hi> first husband of Jeanette (known in the Kornfeld family as Jenny);  the couple were married on July 30, 1893, and had two sons, Erich and Felix.  Little is known of Emil's firm, Klaber &amp; Kornfeld;  it may perhaps have been a chemical manufacturing company;  both sons were involved in it, and possibly Jeanette, too.  Emil and Schenker were apparently very close friends from sometime in the early 1890s to 1910, and between 1903 and 1908 they spent several summer holidays together, probably including Jeanette.   Jeanette left her husband and sons for Schenker on September 30, 1910, moving to Vienna;  from that time all mention of her was forbidden by Emil, although Jeanette is known to have made attempts to contact her sons.  Emil resisted petitions for separation on the part of Jeanette for at least seven years (the attorneys being Dr. Steinitz (for Jeanette), Dr. H&#xFC;bsch, and Dr. Glassner), insisting that Jeanette return to him.  Only after changes in the laws did Jeanette succeed: the petition was approved on November 10, 1919, and Heinrich and she married later the same day.</p>
        <p><hi rend="bold">Kornfeld, Erich,</hi> son of Emil and Jeanette Kornfeld.</p>
        <p><hi rend="bold">Kornfeld, Felix (1899&#x2013;1945),</hi> son of Emil and Jeanette Kornfeld.  Jeanette and Felix met only once after 1910: in the Theresienstadt concentration camp in 1944.  Felix died in Auschwitz in 1945.  &#x2014; One letter from Felix to Jeanette survives as OJ 14/7 (1939).</p>
        <p><hi rend="bold">Kornfeld, Tom&#xE1;s (Thomas) (1932&#x2013;??),</hi> son of Felix Kornfeld, grandson of Emil and Jeanette Kornfeld. &#x2014; Correspondence between Heribert Esser and him survives in photocopy as OJ 71/10a and 21a (1988).</p>
        <p><hi rend="italic">Sources:</hi>
Correspondence with Heribert Esser (2007)
Correspondence between Heribert Esser and Tom&#xE1;s Kornfeld (OJ 71/10a and 21a)</p>
        <!-- EXTENDED BODY: -->
        <!-- EXCERPT: -->
        <!-- KEYWORDS: -->
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
