<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/42, [1] : 10-11-92 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Permission applied for.
© Transcription William Pastille 2006.
© Translation William Pastille 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Pastille, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> Permission to publish on this website applied for</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1892-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: under investigation; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Footnotes, Commentary: William Pastille.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 10/11/1892 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Harden ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Harden to Schenker, dated October 11, 1892</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-12-07</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Since there has been no response to an earlier letter requesting major revisions in a submitted article, Harden has made the changes himself; he asks S to write a second article on the omitted material; and he begs S’s pardon for having to act unilaterally.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Harden, Maximilian; Schenker, Heinrich;  article;  editing;  Mascagni in Wien</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Berlin W 9, 27 Köthener Straße</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Maximilian Harden to Schenker, dated October 11, 1892</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">Printed letterhead, with date partially handwritten:</tei:hi>]
[<tei:hi rend="italic">left:</tei:hi>]
DIE ZUKUNFT
HERAUSGEBER:						
MAXIMILIAN HARDEN</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">right:</tei:hi>]
BERLIN W. 9., den <tei:hi rend="italic">11 Oktober</tei:hi> 189<tei:hi rend="italic">2</tei:hi>
27. Köthener Str.</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">decorative rule</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr,</tei:p><tei:p>die erste Brief, die ich Ihnen schrieb,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  This appears not to have survived.</tei:note> harrt noch die Antwort und ich fürchte, da Sie vergaßen, Ihre Adresse anzugeben, ich fürchte er hat Sie gar nicht erreicht. Deshalb diesmal der Umweg <tei:hi rend="italic">via</tei:hi> Lokal, das mir von Ihnen sprach.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich hatte Sie um die Erlaubniß zu einem Gewaltakt gebeten, zu einer sehr einschneidenden Operation an Ihrem Artikel,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  “Mascagni in Wien,” the first article of Schenker’s published by Harden, which appeared in Die Zukunft on October 15, 1892, four days after the date on this letter. The article is reprinted in Hellmut Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker als Essayist und Kritiker</tei:hi> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms Verlag, 1990), 26-30.</tei:note> der mir einen merkwürdig empfindenden Geist zeigte, der aber in seiner mir vorliegenden Form für meine besondren Zwecke nicht brauchbar war. Aus tausend Gründen, die ich schreiben und wiederholen würde, wenn ich nicht totmüde wäre und immer noch hoffte, in ersten Brief hätten Sie Alles gelesen. Hauptgrund: Ihr Berliner Debut sollte nicht verschnörkelt werden.</tei:p><tei:p>Inzwischen habe ich, da der Artikel sonst unbrauchbar geworden wäre und Ihre Entscheidung nicht eintraf, die lebensgefährlich Operation selbst vollzogen und kann Sie nur nachträglich um Absolution bitten. Ich gebe Ihnen nicht nur das Recht, sondern ich bitte Sie ausdrücklich darum, mir in dem zweiten Artikel das Theoretische – dummer Ausdruck, aber ich arbeite seit 14 Stunden – zu schreiben, das Sie diesmal allzu locker streiften und das ich tilgte. Und ich füge die Bitte hinzu, mich durch einige Zeilen vorher wissen zu lassen, was Sie schreiben wollen – so ungefähr –, damit wir uns verständigen. Herzlich freue ich mich unserer Verbindung und meine, Sie sollten hier herkommen, wo es noch nicht einmal einen Hanslick<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Eduard Hanslick (1825–1904), German music critic and aesthetician, who came to Vienna in 1846 and served as music critic for the <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue Freie Presse</tei:hi>, Vienna’s leading liberal daily newspaper, from 1855 to 1904, in that position weilding huge influence not only in Vienna but also in Germany and internationally.  He also taught aesthetics at the University of Vienna, and is best known for his <tei:hi rend="italic">Vom Musikalisch-Schönen</tei:hi> (Leipzig, 1854).  Some correspondence exists between Hanslick and Schenker covering the years 1894–99 (OJ 11/39, 59/7, and 71/14).  [create biogfile and link]</tei:note> giebt u. die Musikkritik einfach zum bejammern ist.</tei:p><tei:p>Also entsetzen Sie sich gefl. [gefälligst] nicht über die arge Verstümmelung, wir werden Zeit genug, uns auszusprechen, haben.</tei:p><tei:p>In herzl. Hochachtung
Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Harden</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Maximilian Harden to Schenker, dated October 11, 1892</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">Printed letterhead, with date partially handwritten:</tei:hi>]
[<tei:hi rend="italic">left:</tei:hi>]
DIE ZUKUNFT
EDITOR:						
MAXIMILIAN HARDEN</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">right:</tei:hi>]
BERLIN W. 9, <tei:hi rend="italic">Oktober 11,</tei:hi> 189<tei:hi rend="italic">2</tei:hi>
27 Köthener Straße</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">decorative rule</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Sir,</tei:p><tei:p>The first letter I wrote to you<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> is still awaiting a reply, and I fear, since you forgot to specify your address, I fear  it just didn’t reach you. Hence the alternative route this time by way of the restaurant where they told me about you.</tei:p><tei:p>I had asked your permission for an act of violence—an extremely invasive operation on your article,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> which seemed remarkably perceptive to me in substance, but was not serviceable for my particular purposes in its existing form. For a thousand reasons, which I would repeat in writing if I were not dead tired and did not still hope you had read it all in the first letter. Principal reason: your Berlin debut should not be overelaborate.</tei:p><tei:p>In the meantime, since the article would have been unserviceable otherwise and your decision was not forthcoming, I completed the dangerous operation myself, and can now only belatedly beg your forgiveness. I not only give you the right, but I expressly entreat you to use the second article to write the theoretical stuff—clumsy expression, but I’ve been working for fourteen hours—which you skated over all too casually this time, and which I deleted. And I ask in addition that you send a few lines to let me know in advance what you want to write—roughly—so that we have an understanding. I am delighted that we are collaborating, and I think you should come here, where there is still not even a Hanslick<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> and the musical criticism is downright deplorable.</tei:p><tei:p>So please don’t be offended by the horrible disfigurement; we will have time enough to talk it through.</tei:p><tei:p>In sincere esteem,
Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Harden</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>