<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/42, [19] : 10-11-1894 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription William Pastille 2006.
© Translation William Pastille 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Pastille, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> In the public domain</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1894-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: in the public domain; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Footnotes, Commentary: William Pastille.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 10/11/1894 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Harden ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Harden to Schenker, dated October 11, 1894</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-03-06</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Harden rebuffs accusations by Schenker that seem to involve a delay in Harden’s response to a submission that Schenker hopes to move to another publication, and he accuses Schenker of reneging on a promise to write about Strauß’s Jabuka.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Harden, Maximilian; Schenker, Heinrich;  Breitkopf;  Humperdinck, Engelbert;  Strauß, Johann;  Jabuka</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Berlin W.9, 27 Köthener Straße</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from  Harden to Schenker, dated October 11, 1894</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead with handwritten date:</tei:hi>]
DIE ZUKUNFT
HERAUSGEBER:  [–]  BERLIN W. 9, den <tei:hi rend="italic">11.10</tei:hi> 189<tei:hi rend="italic">4</tei:hi>
MAXIMILIAN HARDEN  [–]  27 Köthener Str.
[<tei:hi rend="italic">decorated printed rule</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">Handwritten:</tei:hi>]
Sehr geehrter Herr,</tei:p><tei:p>ich muß Ihre unmotivirten Vorwurfe sehr entscheiden zurückwerfen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  No letter from Schenker corresponding to this is known to survive. </tei:note>  Ihre Verhandlungen mit Herrn Breitkopf<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Breitkopf &amp; Härtel, Leipzig, publishers.  What the negotiations might be is unclear. (Schenker would later have several of his compositions published by Breitkopf in 1898–99.)  </tei:note> interessiren mich gar nicht und es ist Ihre Sache, ob Sie einen noch nicht angenommenen Artikel als schon angenommen bezeichnen wollen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">   [identify] </tei:note>  Ich bekomme täglich Stöße von Briefen und kann, namentlich da ich 3 Wochen krank war, nicht stets so prompt arbeiten, wie die herrische Laune eines Mitarbeiters es heischt.  Sie werden solche Pünktlichkeit nicht leicht anderswo finden.  Ihr Artikel über Humperdinck<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  There is no article by Schenker devoted to Huperdinck in <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Zukunft</tei:hi> or any other journal at this time.  Schenker does deal with <tei:hi rend="italic">Hänsel und Gretel</tei:hi> in the article "Deutsch-Oesterreichischer Musikverkehr," <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Zukunft</tei:hi>, vol. XI (1895), pp. 182–85, transcribed in Hellmut Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker als Essayist und Kritiker</tei:hi> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms Verlag, 1990), pp. 129–34.   </tei:note> war nicht gut, war ganz unklar, nach m. subjektiven Ermessen, darum gab ich ihn zurück.</tei:p><tei:p>Sie versprachen, für die Straußwoche über ihn u. seine neue Operette zu schreiben.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  The Strauß Week, October 12–15, 1894, celebrated the "Artistic Jubilee" of Johann Strauß the Younger (1825–99), October 15, 1894 marking the exact 50th anniversary of his public début as conductor and composer at Dommayer's Casino in the Viennese suburb of Hietzing.  The festival opened with the premiere of his new operetta <tei:hi rend="italic">Jabuka (Das Apfelfest)</tei:hi> on October 12.  In connection with this, the Vienna Court Opera staged a special production of <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Fledermaus</tei:hi> on October 28, and the newspapers were full of articles and reminiscences of the composer around this time.   (Information kindly privately supplied by Peter Kemp of the Johann Strauss Society of Great Britain.)  (There is no article by Schenker in <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Zukunft</tei:hi> on Johann Strauß.)  See Peter Kemp, <tei:hi rend="italic">The Strauss Family</tei:hi> (Southborough: Baton Press, 1985; rev. 2nd edn London: Omnibus Press, 1989).</tei:note>  Sie haben nicht Wort gehalten u. vermessen sich nun[,] mir die bittersten Vorwürfe zu machen.</tei:p><tei:p>Drei Wochen, nachdem <tei:hi rend="italic">Jabuka</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Jabuka (Das Apfelfest)</tei:hi>, operetta by Johann Strauß the Younger, which premiered at the Theater an der Wien in Vienna on the day after this letter was written, October 12, 1894. [Was there an “out of town” trial in Berlin three weeks earlier?]</tei:note> hier durchgefallen ist, scheint mir ein Artikel darüber nicht mehr am Platz.  Ohne Ihr Versprechen hätte ich einen Anderen aufgefordert.</tei:p><tei:p>In vorzügl. Hochachtung
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Harden</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from  Harden to Schenker, dated October 11, 1894</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">printed letterhead with handwritten date:</tei:hi>]
DIE ZUKUNFT
EDITOR:  [–]  BERLIN W. 9, <tei:hi rend="italic">October 11</tei:hi>, 189<tei:hi rend="italic">4</tei:hi>
MAXIMILIAN HARDEN  [–]  27 Köthener Str.
[<tei:hi rend="italic">decorated printed rule</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">Handwritten:</tei:hi>]
Dear Sir,</tei:p><tei:p>I must unequivocally reject your unmotivated accusations.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> Your negotiations with Mr. Breitkopf<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> are of no interest at all to me, and it is your affair if you want to pass off an article that has not yet been accepted as one that is already accepted.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  I receive piles of letter every day, and, especially since I was ill for three weeks, I cannot work as quickly as is demanded by the imperious caprice of a contributor.  You will not easily find such promptness elsewhere.  Your article on Humperdinck<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> was not good, was completely unclear according my subjective estimate, and that is why I returned it.</tei:p><tei:p>You promised that for the Strauß week you would write something about him and his new operetta.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> You have reneged, and now you presume to upbraid me in the most acrimonious terms.</tei:p><tei:p>Three weeks after <tei:hi rend="italic">Jabuka</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> flopped here, it seems to me that an article about it is no longer acceptable. Without your promise, I would have engaged someone else.</tei:p><tei:p>Most respectfully,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Harden</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>