<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-002545">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title><hi rend="italic">Die Zeit</hi> (Vienna)</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="zeit_die_wien">Zeit, Die</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>25/07/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Bahr ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">Singer ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Title</term>
          <term subtype="basename">zeit_die_wien</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Die Zeit (Vienna)</head>
      <p>Viennese journal, self-described as a "Viennese Weekly for Politics, Economics, Science,
        and Art."</p>
      <div>
        <head>The Journal and its Editors</head>
        <p><title level="j">Die Zeit</title> was founded in October 1894 by Isidor Singer, professor
          of economics at the University of Vienna, Heinrich Kanner, formerly an editor at the
            <title level="j">Frankfurter Zeitung</title>, and Hermann Bahr, an enterprising writer
          on literature and the visual arts who oversaw cultural contributions to the paper. Bahr,
          who had settled in Vienna only three years earlier, had previously helped found two other
          journals devoted to the work of young artists, <title level="j">Die freie B&#xFC;hne
            f&#xFC;r modernes Leben</title> in Berlin and <title level="j">Moderne Dichtung</title>
          in Br&#xFC;nn (now Brno). In his inaugural essay in <title level="j">Die Zeit</title>,
          Bahr declared that the paper would attempt a "revolution" by refusing to cater to the
          public's taste and views. "Those people who think differently from today's masses," he
          wrote, "and who flatter themselves that tomorrow the whole world will think in the same
          way, will voice their convictions here, unconcerned with pleasing [their readers]. . . .
          They will issue directives, not take them. They will lead the subscribers, not follow
          them" ("Der Abonnent," 7).</p>
        <p><title level="j">Die Zeit</title> featured an impressive roster of contributors,
          including the writers Hugo von Hofmannsthal, Arthur Schnitzler, Hermann Hesse, Oscar
          Wilde, Leo Tolstoy, and Henrik Ibsen. Its editorial offices were a meeting place for many
          of Vienna's most promising young intellectuals (Daviau, 1991, p. xxiii).</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head><title level="j">Die Zeit</title> and Schenker</head>
        <p>Between September 7, 1895 and September 5, 1896, Schenker devoted his critical energies
          almost exclusively to <title level="j">Die Zeit</title>. Unquestionably, this was the most
          influential and renowned journal for which he wrote. Schenker's correspondence with Singer
          reveals that he was eager to accept an invitation to write for the journal (OJ 14/25).
          Over the course of the year he wrote for <title level="j">Die Zeit</title>, Schenker
          penned forty-six articles, nearly half of his total critical output. In contrast to those
          he published in the <title level="j">Musikalisches Wochenblatt</title>, the articles he
          published in <title level="j">Die Zeit</title> were mostly short reviews of concerts and
          newly published books.</p>
        <p>While the surviving correspondence between Schenker and Bahr is sparse, there can be
          little doubt that Bahr, a notoriously combative critic, appreciated Schenker's opinionated
          disposition. He seems to have had some trouble, however, with the Schenker's prose. On one
          occasion, Bahr cautioned the writer: "I sincerely regret that I have apparently
          misunderstood you. But if even I, who after all read you more closely and thoughtfully
          than the average reader, can misunderstand you, how will you be misunderstood when the
          public sees it?" (OJ 9/10a, July 25, 1895). Though prolific, Schenker's work for <title
            level="j">Die Zeit</title> was short-lived, and within a year he returned to the staff
          of the <title level="j">Neue Revue</title>. While the circumstances of his departure are
          unknown, Schenker's replacements on the staff of <title level="j">Die Zeit</title>,
          Richard Wallaschek and Max Graf, held views that were much more closely aligned with
          Bahr's own passion for experimental art.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>
        <p>Only three letters from <title level="j">Die Zeit</title> to Schenker are known to survive: two from Bahr (OJ 9/10a: 1895), one from Singer (OJ 14/25: 1895), and none from Schenker
          to <title level="j">Die Zeit</title> or either editor.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Bibliography:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Hellmut Federhofer</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker als Essayist
              und Kritiker</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1990) [all of Schenker's articles
            1891&#x2013;1901]</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        <div>
          <head>Sources:</head>
          <listBibl>
            <bibl><author>Caph.</author> [<author>Hermann Bahr</author>], <title level="a">Der
                Abonnent,</title>
              <title level="j">Die Zeit</title> 1/1 (1894), 6&#x2013;7</bibl>
            <bibl><editor>Castle, Eduard</editor>, ed., <title level="m"
                >Deutsch-&#xD6;sterreichische Literaturgeschichte. Ein Handbuch zur Geschichte der
                deutschen Dichtung in &#xD6;sterreich-Ungarn</title> (Vienna: Carl Fromme, 1937),
              vol. 4, pp. 1649&#x2013;72</bibl>
            <bibl><author>Daviau, Donald G</author>., <title level="m">Hermann Bahr</title> (Boston:
              Twayne, 1985)</bibl>
            <bibl><editor>Daviau, Donald G</editor>., ed., <title level="m">Major Figures in
                Turn-of-the-Century Austrian Literature</title> (Riverside, CA: Ariadne,
            1991)</bibl>
            <bibl><editor>Rast, Nicholas</editor>, ed., <title level="a">A Checklist of Essays and
                Reviews by Heinrich Schenker,</title>
              <title level="j">Music Analysis</title> 7/2 (July 1988), 121&#x2013;32</bibl>
          </listBibl>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Contributor:</head>
          <listBibl>
            <bibl><author>Kevin Karnes</author></bibl>
          </listBibl>
        </div>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
