<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-002537">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Frankfurter Zeitung</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="frankfurter_zeitung">Frankfurter Zeitung</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>16/06/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Title</term>
          <term subtype="basename">frankfurter_zeitung</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Frankfurter Zeitung</head>
      <div>
        <p>Leading German newspaper.</p>
        <p>Founded in 1856 as the <title level="j">Frankfurter Gesch&#xE4;ftsbericht</title> but
          known as the <title level="j">Frankfurter Zeitung</title> for most of its existence,
          1866&#x2013;1943, the newspaper became a major liberal forum for cultural and political
          opinion, and its contributors included a great many of Germany's leading 20th-century
          philosophers and novelists; many of its columnists were forced to resign when the National
          Socialists came to power in 1933, and the newspaper's influence declined sharply during
          the last decade of its existence. (The <title level="j">Frankfurter allgemeine
          Zeitung</title> is generally considered to be its successor.)</p>
        <p>Prominent writers on music included Karl Holl, a Verdi scholar, and <ref cRef="entity-000057">Paul Bekker</ref>, who was
          the chief music critic from 1911 to 1923. Bekker's book <title level="m">Beethoven</title>
          (1911) provoked severe critical reactions from Schenker in the secondary literature
          sections of his analytical essays, and his articles on music criticism for the <title
            level="j">Frankfurter Zeitung</title> were the subject of an essay planned for <title
            level="j">Der Tonwille</title>, issue 2 (1922) but withdrawn shortly before publication.
          (For an English translation of this, see <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>, vol. 2,
          ed. William Drabkin [New York: Oxford University Press, 2005], pp. 161&#x2013;65.</p>
        <p>Clippings from the <title level="j">Frankfurter Zeitung</title> ranging from 1912 to 1931
          are preserved in Schenker's scrapbook and file of clippings (OC 2; OC C), with articles on
          music written by Hermann Wetzel, Hugo Ganz, Paul Bekker, Karl Holl, Leo Kestenberg, Artur
          Bogen, B. Sekles, Bernhard Diebold, Luigi Russolo, Erich Steinhard, Eugen d'Albert, Ludwig
          Rottenberg, and numerous articles on literary and other topics.</p>
        <p>Schenker himself submitted a political diatribe entitled "German Genius in Battle and
          Victory (Reflections <hi rend="italic">sup specie aeternitatis</hi>)" (OJ 21/2) to the <title level="j"
            >Frankfurter Zeitung</title> on September 7,1914, and received a rejection on September
          26 from the paper's editor, Rudolf Geck (OJ 11/18). </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
