<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-002559">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Neue Freie Presse</title>
        <title type="sub">New Free Press</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="neue_freie_presse">Neue Freie Presse</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>04/06/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Korngold ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">Neue Freie Presse ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">journal</term>
          <term subtype="basename">neue_freie_presse</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>
        <hi rend="italic">Neue Freie Presse</hi>
      </head>

      <div>
        <p> Vienna's leading liberal daily newspaper, founded by Max Friedl&#xE4;nder in 1864.</p>

        <p>The paper appeared from September 1, 1864 until January 31, 1939. It had a distinguished
          array of contributors, was modern in its style of journalism and technology, and was at
          its height a newspaper of world rank, issuing morning and evening editions (<title
            level="j">Morgenblatt</title> and <title level="j">Abendblatt</title>) on some days of
          the week. The paper covered international news, local news, business, the world's stock
          markets, culture, and the arts. An important feature was its feuilleton, which occupied
          the bottom inches of the first few pages of the morning edition on several days a week,
          running continuously from page to page. The heart of the artistic coverage appeared in the
          daily section "Theater and Art News" (Theater- und Kunstnachrichtung).</p>

        <p>Its chief editor from 1908 to his death in 1920 was <ref cRef="entity-000060">Moriz
            Benedikt</ref>, whose association with the paper extended back to 1872. Its Paris
          correspondent from 1891 was the founder of Zionism, Theodor Herzl. Its music critic from
          1864 to his death in 1904 was Eduard Hanslick; Julius Korngold succeeded him, serving from
          1904 to 1934. All were men of great influence in their different capacities.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>The <title level="j">Neue Freie Presse</title> and Schenker</head>

        <p>Schenker read the <title level="j">Neue Freie Presse</title> every day, and his diaries
          are full of quotations from and reactions to its articles. He read the world news
          assiduously; he also read the feuilletons and kept abreast of the cultural news and in
          particular of musical events. On at least one occasion, he inserted an announcement (June
          3, 1911). Schenker also instructed his publishers to send a review copy of each of his
          newly published works to the paper.</p>

        <p>Only one postcard from the paper's editors to Schenker is preserved (OC 50/13: 1931), and
          no correspondence in the reverse direction is known to survive.</p>

      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
