<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-002566">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Die Zukunft</title>
        <title type="sub">The Future</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="zukunft_die">Zukunft, Die</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>08/01/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Harden ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Title</term>
          <term subtype="basename">zukunft_die</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Die Zukunft</head>
      <div>
        <p>Literary and political weekly founded by the German cultural critic Maximilian Harden, to
          which Schenker contributed regularly from 1892 through 1897.</p>
        <p>Harden, sole editor of <title level="j">Die Zukunft</title>, began his career as a
          theater critic in the 1880s and became intensely occupied with political and social issues
          after 1890. Regarding contemporary German cultural criticism as lacking in integrity and
          pandering to advertisers, he founded <title level="j">Die Zukunft</title> as a financially
          independent paper, financed by the Harden family, in October 1892. In his lead essay, he
          invited contributors to the journal by declaring that "in Germany and in Europe there must
          still be . . . fifty or so men who have the courage to proclaim the truth here
          unreservedly, without fear of excommunication by party bigwigs and advertisers, and to
          interpret the signs of the future."</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head><title level="j">Die Zukunft</title> and Schenker</head>
        <p>Schenker began his work for <title level="j">Die Zukunft</title> in its inaugural year
          with a series of articles critical of the Viennese enthusiasm for the operas of Mascagni
          and other <hi rend="italic">verismo</hi> composers. Between then and 1897, he contributed
          a total of eighteen essays to the journal, mostly short reflections on contemporary
          musical life. Harden and Schenker remained on good terms until the autumn of 1896. Their
          falling-out revolved around aesthetic differences, brought to a head over Schenker's
          review of Karl Goldmark's <title level="m">Das Heimchen am Herd</title> and an unpublished
          essay on Engelbert Humperdinck, rejected by Harden and now lost. Schenker's last article
          for <title level="j">Die Zukunft</title>, an obituary for Johannes Brahms, appeared in May
          1897.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>
        <p>Thirty items of correspondence to Schenker from Maximilian Harden, more than half under
          the <title level="j">Die Zukunft</title> letterhead, are preserved as OJ 11/42
          (transcripts of excerpts from these typed by Oswald Jonas exist also at OJ 59/8), and one
          letter from Hermann Wolff to Harden concerning an article by Schenker as OJ 71/42; no
          letters from Schenker to Harden are known to survive. Photocopies of all eighteen of
          Schenker's articles, with annotations and detailed notes by Oswald Jonas are preserved as
          OJ 20/2.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Bibliography:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><editor>Federhofer, Hellmut</editor>, ed., <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker als
              Essayist und Kritiker ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1990) [all eighteen of
            Schenker's articles]</bibl>
          <bibl><editor>Rast, Nicholas</editor>, ed., <title level="a">A Checklist of Essays and
              Reviews by Heinrich Schenker,</title>
            <title level="j">Music Analysis</title> 7/2 (July 1988), 121-3</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Apostata</author> [<author>Maximilian Harden</author>], <title level="a">Von
              Bel zu Babel,</title>
            <title level="j">Die Zukunft</title> 1/1 (1892), 33-40</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Young, Harry F.</author>, <title level="m">Maximilian Harden, Censor
              Germaniae. Ein Publizist im Widerstreit von 1892 bis 1927</title> (M&#xFC;nster:
            Regensberg, 1971)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        
        <div>
          <head>Contributor:</head>
          <listBibl>
            <bibl><author>Kevin Karnes</author></bibl>
          </listBibl>
        </div>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
