<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-002554">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Musikalisches Wochenblatt</title>
        <title type="sub">Musical Weekly</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="musikalisches_wochen">Musikalisches Wochenblatt</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>23/07/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Fritzsch ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Title</term>
          <term subtype="basename">musikalisches_wochen</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head><hi rend="italic">Musikalisches Wochenblatt</hi></head>
      <p>Weekly musical journal published in Leipzig, 1870&#x2013;1906, to which Schenker
        contributed six articles.</p>
      <div>
        <head>The Journal and its Editors</head>
        <p>The <title level="j">Musikalisches Wochenblatt</title> began publication in January 1870
          under the editorship of the music historian Oscar Paul. The paper, aimed&#x2014;as its
          masthead declared&#x2014;at both "Musicians and Enthusiasts" (<hi rend="italic">f&#xFC;r
            Tonk&#xFC;nstler und Musikfreunde</hi>), featured a diverse array of articles, from
          reviews of concerts and new books and scores to essays on aesthetic questions and
          biographical portraits. Its appearance thus represented a conspicuous challenge to
          Leipzig's other musical weekly, the similar yet older and more widely read <title
            level="j">Neue Zeitschrift f&#xFC;r Musik</title>, with which it merged in October 1906,
          shortly after which its name disappeared from the masthead of the "united" (<hi
            rend="italic">vereinigte</hi>) weekly.</p>
        <p>Paul, who taught music history and theory at the University of Leipzig and piano at the
          Leipzig Conservatory, was most widely known for his <title level="m">Lehrbuch der
          Harmonik</title> (1880) and five-volume translation of Boethius's <title level="m">De
            Musica</title> (1872). The range of essays published in the first issue of the <title
            level="j">Musikalisches Wochenblatt</title> reflected Paul's diversity of interests. In
          his own lead article, <title level="a">Das musikalische Streben in der Gegenwart,</title>
          Paul argued that present-day musicians can acquire a clear sense of the proper course for
          future advances only if they simultaneously endeavor to understand the musical innovations
          of previous eras and generations. Paul's essay was accompanied by Wilhelm Tappert's
          analytical study of the folk tune "Aennchen von Tharau," a translation of an anonymous
          16th-century treatise on mensural notation, and the first installment of a serialized
          analytical review of Brahms's <title level="m">German Requiem</title>. Only three months
          after founding the <title level="j">Musikalisches Wochenblatt</title>, Paul retired from
          the editor's post, citing health concerns. He passed his duties on to Ernst Wilhelm
          Fritzsch, who would edit the journal for over three decades.</p>
        <p>Fritzsch, a Leipzig publisher, entrepreneur, and amateur musician, did not contribute any
          essays to the <title level="j">Musikalisches Wochenblatt</title>, but he did recruit some
          of the period's most prominent writers on music to write for it. These included Friedrich
          von Hausegger, Theodor Helm, Hugo Riemann, Richard Wallaschek, and even Richard Wagner. At
          the time Fritzsch assumed Paul's duties, his publishing house was producing the first
          edition of Wagner's collected writings, and under his direction the <title level="j"
            >Musikalisches Wochenblatt</title> took on a decidedly Wagnerian tone. Several of
          Wagner's essays made their first appearance in the paper, and, in the years immediately
          following the composer's death in 1883, essays on Wagner, his writings, and his music came
          to dominate its pages.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head><title level="j">Musikalisches Wochenblatt</title> and Schenker</head>
        <p>In October 1891, Fritzsch's journal published Schenker's debut critical essay: his
          analytical review of Brahms's songs, Op. 107. Over the course of the next four years,
          Schenker would publish five more articles, among them his most ambitious to date, in
          Fritzsch's paper. These included his serialized analytical review of Brahms's choral
          pieces, Op. 104, which appeared on the front page of three consecutive issues in 1892, and
          his 1895 University of Vienna lecture, <title level="a">Der Geist der musikalischen
            Technik,</title> which was subsequently reprinted, as a separate pamphlet, by Fritzsch's
          firm. The <title level="j">Musikalisches Wochenblatt</title> is the only specialist music
          journal to which Schenker contributed during this period.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>The <title level="j">Musikalisches Wochenblatt</title> and Schenker</head>
        <p>One letter survives from Fritzsch to Schenker under the journal's letterhead: OJ 11/11
          (1892).</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Bibliography:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><editor>Federhofer, Hellmut</editor>, ed., <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker als
              Essayist und Kritiker &#x2026;</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1990) [all six of
            Schenker's articles]</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Schenker, Heinrich</author>, <title level="a">The Spirit of Musical
              Technique,</title> trans. <editor>William Pastille</editor>, <title level="j"
            >Theoria</title> 3 (1988), 86&#x2013;104; rev. edn. in <author>Nicholas Cook</author>,
              <title level="m">The Schenker Project</title> (New York: Oxford University Press,
            2007), pp. 319&#x2013;32</bibl>
          <bibl><editor>Rast, Nicholas</editor>, ed., <title level="a">A Checklist of Essays and
              Reviews by Heinrich Schenker,</title>
            <title level="j">Music Analysis</title> 7/2 (July 1988), 121&#x2013;3</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="a">An unsere Leser!,</title>
            <title level="j">Musikalisches Wochenblatt/Neue Zeitschrift f&#xFC;r Musik: Vereinigte
              Leipziger musikalische Wochenschriften</title> (4 October 1906), 1</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Jost, Christa and Peter</author>, <title level="m">Richard Wagner und sein
              Verleger Ernst Wilhelm Fritzsch</title> (Tutzing: Hans Schneider, 1997)</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Paul, Oscar</author>, <title level="a">Das musikalische Streben in der
              Gegenwart,</title>
            <title level="j">Musikalisches Wochenblatt</title> 1/1 (1870), 1&#x2013;3</bibl>
          <bibl><editor>Riemann, Hugo</editor>, <title level="m">Musik-Lexikon</title>, 4th ed.
            (Leipzig: Max Hesse, 1894), 796</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Kevin Karnes</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
