<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:NMI [C 176-03] : 10-3-08 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription Kevin Karnes, 2007.
© Translation Kevin Karnes, 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Kevin Karnes, 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> In the public domain; reproduced with kind permission of the Nederlands Muziek Instituut, Den Haag.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: in the public domain; Image: Nederlands Muziek Instituut, Den Haag; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Kevin Karnes.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 10/03/1908 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: &quot;R&#195;&#182;ntgen ~ HSchenker&quot; --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Röntgen, dated October 3, 1908</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-05-10</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>S reports on inquiries he has made about performing and publishing R's piano quintet; encourages him to think of publishing it in Germany.  —S's Beitrag zur Ornamentik agrees with R's instinct regarding placement of ornaments other than apoggiaturas. —Hopes to hear Andriessen play.

</dc:description><dc:subject> Schenker, Heinrich;  Röntgen, Julius;  Wiener Konzertverein;  Löwe, Ferdinand;  Munich;  Herzmansky, Bernhard;  Dohnányi;  chamber music;  publishing;  Germany;  Schnitzler, Arthur;  Bahr, Hermann;  Hofmannsthal, Hugo von;  Brahms;  Dvořák;  Goldmark, Karl;  Beitrag zur Ornamentik;  Contribution to the Study of Ornamentation;  Vorschlag;  appoggiatura;  Andriessen, Willem;  Violin, Moriz;  Steiner</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Röntgen, dated October 3, 1908</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Herr Professor!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Thanks are due to Maximilian Aue and Peter Höyng for their help with a particularly difficult passage in this letter.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Voran</tei:hi> die Sie zumeist interessierende Sache.  Ich habe mich darnach erkündigt, ob der Konzertverein Ihre prämiierte Komposition<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  S responds here to R’s request in OJ 13/27, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  <tei:hi rend="italic">recte</tei:hi> Schnitzler: Arthur Schnitzler (1862-1931), Austrian playwright and author, including the play <tei:hi rend="italic">Professor Bernhardi</tei:hi> (1912) and the novel <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Weg ins Freie</tei:hi> (1908).</tei:note>, August 8, 1908, and <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Hermann Bahr (1863–1934), Austrian playwright and novelist, for whom S worked and with whom he corresponded.</tei:note>, September 23, 1908, for help in securing a Viennese publisher for his quintet, which had been awarded a prize by the Wiener Konzertverein. The identity of R’s quintet is unclear. The complete list of R’s compositions maintained by the Julius Röntgen Stichting in The Hague (www.juliusrontgen.nl/composities.html) includes only a single piano quintet upon which R seems likely to have been working around this time: an unpublished quintet for flute, clarinet, horn, oboe, and piano, reportedly completed in 1911.</tei:note> zu drücken vorhat, u. da erfahr ich – Löwe<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="lowe_ferdinand">Ferdinand Löwe</ref>. Löwe was a founding director of the Wiener Konzertverein and founding conductor of the Verein’s orchestra. S may have known Löwe since his years at the Conservatory, where Löwe taught piano beginning in 1884. In any case, S seems already to have been acquainted with Löwe in the summer of 1894, when he appears to have acted as an intermediary between Eugen d’Albert and the conductor (see Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Nach Tagebüchern ...</tei:hi> (1985), p. 57;  on Löwe and the Konzertverein, see Hans Jancik, “Ferdinand Löwe,” in <tei:hi rend="italic">MGG</tei:hi>, ed. Friedrich Blume [Kassel: Bärenreiter, 1949-86], vol. 8, cols. 1105-06;  and Margaret Notley, “<tei:hi rend="italic">Volksconcerte</tei:hi> in Vienna and Late Nineteenth-Century Ideology of the Symphony,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Journal of the American Musicological Society</tei:hi> 50 [1997], 449-50).</tei:note> ist augenblicklich in München – von einem mir befreundeten Direktionsvorstand, daß das Werk durchaus nur Ihr Eigentum sei.  So ging ich dann zu dem einzigen hier in <tei:hi rend="italic">Wien</tei:hi> überhaupt in Frage kommenden Verleger, H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Herzmansky</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Bernhard Herzmansky (1852-1921), Austrian music publisher.  Having acquired the Viennese publishing firm Doblinger in 1876, Herzmansky and his son, also Bernhard (1888-1954), transformed it into one of Austria’s leading music publishing houses.  Doblinger’s catalog would eventually include works by Bruckner and Dohnányi, as well as Mahler’s Fourth Symphony and Lehár’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Die lustige Witwe</tei:hi>.  Doblinger also published S’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Zwei Clavierstücke</tei:hi>, op. 1 (Vienna: Doblinger, 1892). Herzmansky became a founding partner in UE in 1901. (Alexander Weinmann and Nigel Simeone, “Doblinger,” in <tei:hi rend="italic">NGDM2</tei:hi> [2001].)  Most recently, Doblinger was to have published S’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Instrumentations-Tabelle</tei:hi> in 1906, but S backed out because of unsatisfactory royalty provisions, after dealings that stretched from October 1905 to September 1906 (OJ 1/5, p. 19, September 13, 1906; OJ 15/8, [4], September 18, 1908).</tei:note> (dem Verleger <tei:hi rend="italic">Dohnanyis</tei:hi>’<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Ernő (Ernest von) Dohnányi (1877-1960), Hungarian pianist and composer.  After graduating from the Budapest Academy of Music and completing subsequent studies with Eugen d’Albert, Dohnányi attained overnight stardom as a pianist with an 1898 performance of Beethoven’s Fourth Piano Concerto, under the direction of Hans Richter in London.  A prolific and accomplished composer from early adolescence (Brahms had become an advocate in 1895), Dohnányi’s published catalog of chamber works included, by 1908, two string quartets, a piano quintet, a serenade for string trio, and a cello sonata. (Bálint Vázsonyi, “Ernő Dohnányi,” in <tei:hi rend="italic">NGDM2</tei:hi> [2001].)</tei:note>), u. trug ihm den Fall vor.  Er meinte zunächst, Kammermusik, die in <tei:hi rend="italic">Wien</tei:hi> ausgegeben wird, trage nicht nach Deutschland hinüber, es wäre das traurig genug, aber dennoch eine Thatsache; er erkundigte sich gleichwohl nach Ihren Honoraransprüchen, u. als ich ihm diesbezüglich Beruhigendes mitteilen konnte, meinte er, denn wäre es doch am besten, daß er das Werk irgendwie öffentlich zu hören bekäme, um ein eigenes Urteil (<tei:hi rend="italic">?sic!</tei:hi>) zu gewinnen.  Darauf ich: ich glaube, daß der K-Verein doch selbst das Werk zur Aufführung bringen wird, sonst hätte <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Aufforderung, Jury, Prämie etc. keinen Sinn. Desto besser, erwiderte H. <tei:hi rend="italic">H</tei:hi>., dann höre ich es an u. gebe Ihnen Auskunft. Soweit unser Dialog.</tei:p><tei:p>Nun meine ich, Löwe zur baldigsten Aufführung Ihres Werkes zu bewegen, fiele mir vielleicht gar nicht schwer, dennoch würde ich Sie einladen, über die dem Verleger nur so entschlüpfte Wahrheit nachzudenken, inwiefern es sich nämlich überhaupt lohnen, Kammermusik in <tei:hi rend="italic">Wien</tei:hi> zu publizieren.  Unsere Verleger leben mit der Operette, -mit- ^von^ ihr, für sie, u. haben in Deutschland kein Ansehen.  Während Alles u. Jedes aus dem Auslande zu uns den Weg findet, vermögen die hier edierten Werke nur unter den günstigsten Umständen ins Ausland zu dringen.  Kein Geld!  Keine Reklame!  <tei:hi rend="italic">Schnizler</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  <tei:hi rend="italic">recte</tei:hi> Schnitzler: Arthur Schnitzler (1862-1931), Austrian playwright and author, including the play <tei:hi rend="italic">Professor Bernhardi</tei:hi> (1912) and the novel <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Weg ins Freie</tei:hi> (1908).</tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Bahr</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Hermann Bahr (1863–1934), Austrian playwright and novelist, for whom S worked and with whom he corresponded.</tei:note> <tei:hi rend="italic">Hoffmanstal</tei:hi>[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>],<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  <tei:hi rend="italic">recte</tei:hi> Hofmannsthal: Hugo von Hofmannsthal (1874–1929), Austrian poet, dramatist and librettist, the last of these notably in his 23-year collaboration on six operas with Richard Strauss.  </tei:note> Alle[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] erscheinen sie im Ausland, <tei:hi rend="italic">Brahms</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Dvořak</tei:hi>[,] <tei:hi rend="italic">Goldmark</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Karl Goldmark (1830-1915), Hungarian composer who lived in Vienna from 1860, composed six operas and much orchestral, chamber, and solo music.</tei:note> sind auch durch Ausland zu uns gekommen.  Überlegen Sie diese Schwierigkeit, u. treffen Sie Ihren Entschluß darnach.  Daß ich jederzeit mit Vergnügen u. mit aller Kraft Ihnen hier den Weg leicht machen möchte, wollen Sie nicht bezweifeln.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Nun eine kleine Richtigstellung.  Meine Ausgabe ist schon einige Jahre alt, u. wurde bei ihrer Geburt eben vom “Beitrag z. Orn.” begleitet, deren II Auflage eben in Ihren Hände ist.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Schenker, <tei:hi rend="italic">Ein Beitrag zur Ornamentik</tei:hi> (Vienna: UE, 1903, 2/1908). Here S corrects Röntgen’s belief—expressed in OJ 13/27, [7], September 23, 1908—that S’s edition of selected keyboard works by C. P. E. Bach, <tei:hi rend="italic">Klavierwerke von Philipp Emanuel Bach: Neue kritische Ausgabe von Heinrich Schenker</tei:hi> (Vienna: UE, [1903]; UE 458), had not yet been published.</tei:note>   Hier finden Sie auch durchgehends betont, daß der Abzug ^nur^ +des Vorschlages+ auf Kosten der nachfolgenden Note zu geschehen habe, &lt;sup&gt;daß dagegen der [<tei:hi rend="italic">turn symbol</tei:hi>] u.&lt;/sup&gt; sonst alle Ornamente <tei:hi rend="italic">voraus</tei:hi>gehen, ganz so, wie ^auch^ Sie es offenbar empfinden.  Ich habe dieser Empfindung ihre psychologische u. historische Begründung beigegeben[.]   Es ist also so, wie Ihre Empfindung es braucht, auch theoretisch richtig, – [(]vgl. z.B. S. 59, § 2, S. 60, § 3ff., S. 63, § 6, S. 66[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>], § 9, u.s.w; S. 71, §1!),<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  S’s references are to <tei:hi rend="italic">Beitrag</tei:hi> (2/1908); Eng. trans. (1976), pp. 115, 116, 121, 126, 137.</tei:note> u. es freut mich, daß wir in dieser Frage eins sind.</tei:p><tei:p>H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Andriessen</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Willem Andriessen (1887-1964), Dutch pianist and composer.  A student of R at the Amsterdam Conservatory, Andriessen went on to cultivate a significant career as a solo pianist and as a staunch advocate of new music in the Netherlands.  He was appointed to the piano faculty of the Conservatory in The Hague in 1910. In OJ 13/27, [7], September 23, 1908, R asked S to meet Andriessen during the latter’s trip to Vienna.  (Jos Wouters and Ronald Vermeulen, “Willem Andriessen,” in <tei:hi rend="italic">NGDM2</tei:hi> [2001].)</tei:note> scheint ein ganz prächtiger Junge zu sein.  Ich habe ihn leider noch nicht hören können, doch hoffe ich bald dazu zu kommen, – Prof. <tei:hi rend="italic">Violin</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  Click on <ref cRef="violin_moriz">Moriz Violin</ref>.</tei:note> u. H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Steiner</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn14">  See OJ 13/27, [6], August 8, 1908, and [7], September 23, 1908;  perhaps the Franz Steiner who corresponded with Schenker in 1908 and 1913 (OJ 14/34);  clearly a singer, and suggested by Schenker.</tei:note> erzählen mir von seinen Fähigkeiten jedenfalls das Beste.</tei:p><tei:p>So viel in Eile!</tei:p><tei:p>Bestens grüßend
Ihr herzlich ergebener
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] <tei:hi rend="italic">H Schenker</tei:hi>
3.10.08.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Röntgen, dated October 3, 1908</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Very honored Professor,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>First, the subject of greatest interest to you.  I inquired whether the Konzertverein plans to publish your prize-winning composition,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> and I learned from a friend who is on the board of directors—Löwe<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> is in Munich at the moment—that the work is entirely and exclusively your property.  So then I went to the only publisher in question here in Vienna, Mr. Herzmansky<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> (Dohnányi’s publisher<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>), and told him about the situation.  First he said that chamber music published in Vienna does not make its way over to Germany—sad enough, but a fact nonetheless.  But he asked nevertheless about your requirements regarding the honorarium, and when I was able to tell him reassuring things about the matter he said that it would then be best if he could somehow hear the work in public, in order to form his own opinion (<tei:hi rend="italic">?sic!</tei:hi>).  To this I replied: I believe that the Konzert-Verein will certainly bring the work to performance itself.  Otherwise, <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> the invitation, jury, prize, etc. would have made no sense.  All the better, replied Mr. H[erzmansky], I will listen to it and give you the news.  That was the extent of our dialogue.</tei:p><tei:p>Now I think that it would not be so difficult for me, perhaps, to persuade Löwe to give the earliest possible performance of your work. But I would encourage you to think about the truth that slipped out a bit to the publisher, about the extent to which publishing chamber music in Vienna is generally worthwhile.  Our publishers live with operetta—they live -with- ^off^ of it and for it—and have no standing in Germany.  While anything and everything finds its way to us from abroad, works edited here can penetrate abroad under only the most favorable of circumstances.  No money!  No advertising!  Schnitzler,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> Bahr,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> Hofmannstahl,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/>—they are all published abroad. Brahms, Dvořák, Goldmark<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> also come to us from abroad.  Think about this difficulty, and make up your mind about it.  You need not doubt that I will work gladly, incessantly, and with all of my strength to assure that your path here is a smooth one.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Now a small correction. My edition is already a few years old, and was accompanied at its birth by <tei:hi rend="italic">Contribution to the Study of Ornamentation</tei:hi>, the second edition of which is now in your hands.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> There you will find it emphasized repeatedly that the subtraction for +the appoggiatura+ ^only^ is made from the following note, &lt;sup&gt;thus in contrast the [<tei:hi rend="italic">turn symbol</tei:hi>] and&lt;/sup&gt; all other ornaments go +beforehand+, just as you ^too^ obviously feel. I have provided the psychological and historical basis for this feeling.  It is thus theoretically correct, just as your feeling requires (cf., e.g., p. 59, § 2; p. 60, §3ff.; p. 63, §6; p. 66, §9 etc.;  p. 71, §1!),<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> and it makes me happy that we are in agreement on this question.</tei:p><tei:p>Mr. Andriessen<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> seems to be a completely splendid young man.  Unfortunately I have not been able to hear him yet, but I hope to soon.  Prof. Violin<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/> and Mr. Steiner<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn14"/> have certainly spoken most appreciatively to me about his abilities.</tei:p><tei:p>So much in haste!</tei:p><tei:p>With best greetings, 
Yours very truly,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H Schenker
3.10.08</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>