<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 5/15, [2] : ?6-1-08? --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In be the public domain. 
© Transcription Ian Bent and Lee Rothfarb 2006.
©  Translation Lee Rothfarb 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Lee Rothfarb and Ian Bent, 2007.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1908-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 06/01/1908 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Grunsky ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten draft letter from Schenker to Grunsky, undated possibly dating c. June 1(?), 1908</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-03-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Apologies for late reply to G's letter:  the revised edn of his Beitrag zur Ornamentik  has upset his work-schedule;  S rates Bruckner's themes and "good composition" more highly than those of any others (with exceptions), yet he does not class Bruckner as a master, for he relies too much on pathos, ecstasy, and grandiosity;  he lacks invention.  (draft incomplete)

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Grunsky, Karl;  Beitrag zur Ornamentik;  Contribution to Ornamentation;  Bach, C. P. E.;  sonata form;  Aestetik;  Aesthetics;  Bruckner;  Löwe, Ferdinand;  Schalk, Franz;  Brahms;  Dvorak;  Wolf, Hugo;  Hummel;  Matabele jargon;  Beethoven;  Leonore;  Egmont;  invention;  pathos;  ecstasy;  Ländler</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten incomplete letter draft from Schenker to Grunsky, undated, possibly dating from c. June 1(?), 1908</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in top margin, in pencil in S’s hand:</tei:hi>]  An Grunsky [/] über Bruckner</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Doctor!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  The suggested date for this letter, c. June 1, 1908, is based on: a) S’s request to Hertzka (UE) of July 22, 1908 (WSLB 12) to send a copy of <tei:hi rend="italic">Beitrag zur Ornamentik</tei:hi> to G (see para. 2, below), said to have been promised “some time ago,” b) the date of OJ 11/29, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Probably in OJ 11/29, [1], May 3, 1908, which asks: “May I ask you for your objective view on Bruckner?  Why are his organ points poorly executed? “.</tei:note>, June 5, in which G acknowledges a “detailed letter” and says he has to “delay a bit” in responding, and c) S’s statement here that he has been “hindered” from replying immediately.  However, the subsequent discussion of proof corrections for <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt</tei:hi> casts this in some doubt. This letter is incomplete, therefore presumably either an aborted letter or a draft subsequently completed, copied, and sent.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Verzeihung!  Das <tei:hi rend="italic">Sujet</tei:hi>, das Sie mir aufgaben,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Probably in OJ 11/29, [1], May 3, 1908, which asks: “May I ask you for your objective view on Bruckner?  Why are his organ points poorly executed? “.</tei:note> lockte mich zwar unwiderstehlich, Ihnen sofort zu antworten, jedoch hinderten mich stärkere Verhältnisse, es auch zu tun.  Sie sollen aber später einmal sehen, daß ich ein völlig anderer bin, als mich Ihnen gegenüber widrige Umstände derzeit leider noch erscheinen lassen müssen.</tei:p><tei:p>Auch mir widerfuhr – es kam plötzlich am 1. April<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  April 1 letter:  first word of from UE that it proposed to issue a second edition of <tei:hi rend="italic">Ein Beitrag zur Ornamentik</tei:hi> is in the letter of March 24, 1908 (OC 52/383), to which S replied on March 25 (WSLB 1), as recorded also in S’s diary for the same date (OJ 1/7, p. 85). The order for the new edition was placed on April 8, and UE took delivery of the 500 copies on August 24.</tei:note> – der Auftrag einer 2. Aufl. einer bereits einige Jahre alten Arbeit,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Ein Beitrag zur Ornamentik</tei:hi> (Vienna: UE, [1903], 2/1908).  </tei:note> u. so dringend war zugleich die Ausfertigung derselben geworden, daß ich sogar die Schlußbogen des „<tei:hi rend="italic">Cp.</tei:hi>“ darüber zur Seite schieben mußte.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Preparing revisions for the second edition of <tei:hi rend="italic">Ein Beitrag zur Ornamentik</tei:hi> occupied S from March 25 to early April 1908 (WSLB 1, March 25; WSLB 3, April 9; WSLB 4, April 22);  and proofs from late April or early May to June 23, 1908 (WSLB 4, April 22; WSLB 5, May 21; WSLB 9, June 23).  S was in the Tyrol from June 30 (OJ 1/7, p. 89) to late August or September.  On the dating of the present letter, cf. „The first proofs of my second <tei:hi rend="italic">Counterpoint</tei:hi> volume have just started coming in from Cotta—I have suffered three whole months' delay while occupied with <tei:hi rend="italic">Ornamentation</tei:hi>, time that I ultimately forfeited” (WSLB 24, Schenker to Hertzka, October 31, 1908), and “We have so far still not received back from you any of galley-proofs 1–89 of [<tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt</tei:hi>] that we have been sending you in batches since the beginning of November, as a result of which the printers can, for lack of type, go no further with type-setting” (OJ 9/31, [21], Cotta to Schenker, December 30, 1908),  and “In looking forward with pleasure to receiving further corrected galley-proofs, we remain ...” (OJ 9/31, [22] = CA 93, Cotta to Schenker, January 14, 1909), and “...at the moment (despite the fact that printing [of <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt</tei:hi>] began on October 1) I am only just on p.150 of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Counterpoint</tei:hi> volume—at the imprimatur stage ...” (WSLB 37, Schenker to Hertzka, March 28, 1909).  On that basis, this letter might therefore postdate late October 1908;  however,, if we are to take “Schlußbogen” at face value, its date might be as late as January or February 1909. But cf. earlier discussion. </tei:note>  Ich werde die „<tei:hi rend="italic">Universal-Edition, Wien</tei:hi>“ beauftragen, Ihnen sofort dieses Werk (meine Ausgabe des <tei:hi rend="italic">Ph. Em. Bach</tei:hi>, samt dem „<tei:hi rend="italic">Beitrag zur Ornamentik</tei:hi>“) zukommen zu lassen<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  S wrote to Hertzka on July 22, 1908: “Should a copy of <tei:hi rend="italic">Ornamentik</tei:hi> be already available, may I ask you kindly to send it to Dr. Carl Grunsky (a very well known writer on music and reviewer), Stuttgart, Stitzenburgstraße 1?  I promised him one long ago.” (WSLB 12).  Hertzka agreed on August 11, stating that the new edition was expected “in the next few days” (OC 52/397).  S also included G in the list of recipients of complimentary copies of the same work on August 19 (WSLB 14).  There appears to be no request for C. P. E. Bach keyboard works.  </tei:note> (hoffentlich spätestens binnen 2–3 Wochen möglich), da ich wohl Interessse habe, daß Sie mindestens die ersten Seiten davon lesen, um derentwillen allein ich mich eigentlich der Mühe der übrigen, mir im Grunde völlig fernliegenden Arbeit unterzog.  Denn schon dort versuchte ich, die Gelegenheit nützend, eben betreffs der Sonaten„form“ einige allgemein geglaubte Vorurteile technischer Natur zu zerstreuen, was freilich viel ausführlicher im III[.] Band m. Arbeit zu erledigen sein wird.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  This may be either his “Über den Niedergang der Kompositionskunst” or his <tei:hi rend="italic">Formenlehre</tei:hi> : (1) originally intended as the Nachwort to his <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi>, but not published there, he had high hopes for the “Niedergang,” seeing it as vol. III of <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</tei:hi>, to be published after <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt</tei:hi>.  The work remained unpublished, and survives in typescript (OC 31/28–153) under the provisional title of “Über den Niedergang der Kompositionskunst: eine technisch-kritische Untersuchung,” in which sonata form is a central focus;  an edition and English translation with introduction, by William Drabkin, is available in <tei:hi rend="italic">Music Analysis</tei:hi> 24/1–2, 3–232;  (2) in OJ 5/15, [1] to G, January 21, 1908, S speaks of vol. III as being his <tei:hi rend="italic">Formenlehre</tei:hi>, to which his diary for July 11, 1907 (OJ 1/6, p. 45) refers: “ Ideen zu einer ‚neuen Formenlehre’” (ideas toward a “new theory of form"). </tei:note>   Sie aber möchte ich ersuchen, mir inzwischen Ihre Aestetik zukommen <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> lassen zu wollen, die ich leider noch nicht kennengelernt habe.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Karl Grunsky, <tei:hi rend="italic">Musikästhetik</tei:hi> (Leipzig: Göschen, 1907).  A copy of this book is listed among S’s library at the sale of his music books (<tei:hi rend="italic">Musik und Theater, enthaltend die Bibliothek des Herrn Dr. Heinrich Schenker, Wien</tei:hi> (Antiquariat Heinrich Hinterberger, n.d.), item 129).  That S was unacquainted with the book when writing this letter may perhaps date the letter prior to that beginning “Mein Contrapunkt Man.”, where he seems to be familiar with some of G’s aesthetic concepts.  </tei:note>   Ihre <tei:hi rend="italic">Bruckner</tei:hi> Arbeiten besaß ich schon früher, in einzelnen Heften, danke aber nichtsdestoweniger herzlichst für die Übersendung des nunmehr abgerundeten Ganzen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  S’s library contained a copy of G’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Bruckners Symphonien erläutert mit Notenbeispielen</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Meisterführer</tei:hi> No.4 (Berlin, 1908), but nothing earlier on Bruckner.  The library also contained copies of <tei:hi rend="italic">Musikgeschichte der 17. und 18. Jahrhunderte</tei:hi> (Leipzig: Göschen, 1905) and <tei:hi rend="italic">Musikgeschichte des 19. Jahrhunderts</tei:hi> (ibid., 1902).  (See <tei:hi rend="italic">Musik und Theater, enthaltend die Bibliothek des Herrn Dr. Heinrich Schenker, Wien</tei:hi> (Antiquariat Heinrich Hinterberger, n.d.), items 79, 127, 128.)</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ihr rückhaltsloser Brief<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Probably in OJ 11/29, [1], May 3, 1908, which asks: “May I ask you for your objective view on Bruckner?  Why are his organ points poorly executed? “.</tei:note> macht auch mich offener, u. ich will Ihnen gegenüber alle Wahrheit <tei:hi rend="italic">in puncto Bruckner</tei:hi> gerne so sagen, wie ich es bisher nicht einmal gegenüber meinen, leider durch die Öffentlichkeit, wie hauptsächlich auch durch ihre eigene Vergangenheit gebundenen Freunden Löwe<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Click on <ref cRef="lowe_ferdinand">Ferdinand Löwe</ref>.</tei:note> u. Schalk<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Click on <ref cRef="schalk_franz">Franz Schalk</ref>.</tei:note> (die Sie ja kennen?) je zu sagen Lust fand.  Jede Zeile von Ihnen sagt mir, daß Sie – einer heute so selten anzutreffenden u. nicht hoch genug einzuschätzenden Charakterveranlagung gemäß – durch kein Amt, keinerlei Rücksicht gegenüber Publikum, Partei oder Presse sich derart gebunden fühlen, daß Sie darüber ablehnen könnten, die Wahrheit ^in Kunstfragen^ zu hören u. zu vertreten.  Nun zur Sache!</tei:p><tei:p>Nicht nur um mich Ihnen näher zu bringen, sondern in ehrlicher Dankbarkeit schicke ich voraus:  <tei:hi rend="italic">Bruckners</tei:hi> +Thematisches+ habe ich stets höher bewertet, als alle Erfindung aller übrigen Komp. (natürlich ^die^ eines <tei:hi rend="italic">Brahms</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Dvořák</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">Wolf</tei:hi> ausgenommen), u. dabei bleibt es noch heute.  Die Distanz von <tei:hi rend="italic">Bruckner</tei:hi> zu den anderen ist so groß, daß diese gar nicht erwähnt zu werden verdienen neben ihm.  Und wofür ich noch mehr danke, ist der richtige, typisch +gute Satz+ <tei:hi rend="italic">Bruckner’s</tei:hi>, worin er Alle, Alle von heute himmelhoch überragt!  -Xxx- Mit ihm, dem <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> wirklichen Tonsetzer, verglichen erscheinen die Komp. von heute, – keinen Einzigen ausgenommen! – einfach nicht mehr als Musiker: er schrieb unsere Musikschriftsprache -sozusagen- ^wovon die Hummel-Komp. aber nichts wissen^ ^wirklich u. gut^, diese stammeln irgend einen „<tei:hi rend="italic">Matabele</tei:hi>-Jargon“,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  “Matabele“: anglicized form of “amaNdebele,” the name of a constituent people of the Zulu that established a kingdom in Matabeleland, now a province of Zimbabwe, in 1834.  Hence “Matabele jargon” is an unintelligible language, with derogatory overtones, the equivalent of “gobbledygook.”</tei:note> der erst weiterer 8–10 Jahrhund. ^der Entwicklung^ brauchen konnte, um endlich als Kunstsprache dienen zu können, zugleich aber, erst dort zu gelangen, wo unsere Musiksprache schon seit langem sich befindet.</tei:p><tei:p>Gleichwohl -muß- ^kann^ ich <tei:hi rend="italic">Bruck.</tei:hi> -aus der Gruppe wirklicher- ^noch keinen^ Meister -ausschließen-, -xxxxx- ^nennen^, -bin also noch weniger in der Lage- ^geschweige^ in ihm gar einen Fortschritt in irgendeiner Hinsicht erblicken.  Die Gründe sind rein technischer Natur, u. werden ausführlich im III[.] B. ihren Platz finden;<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn13">  See above;  the “Niedergang” contains a section on Bruckner (=OC 31/107–111; Drabkin, pp.  212–15, 114–17).  </tei:note>  ich kann sie daher hier nur flüchtig ^u. vorläufig nur für Sie^ skizzieren.</tei:p><tei:p>Was würden Sie sagen, wenn uns <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven</tei:hi> z.B. nur in den grandiosen Anfängen der IX., V., der <tei:hi rend="italic">Leon.-, Egmont-Ouvt.</tei:hi>, -oder- u. in so vielen anderen ebenso pathetischen Stellen in der Mitte der III., V., der letzten <tei:hi rend="italic">Klv. Son.</tei:hi> u. <tei:hi rend="italic">Strqu.</tei:hi> enthalten wäre,  wir ^[<tei:hi rend="italic">illeg</tei:hi>]^ aber sonst die übrige unermeßliche Welt des Anmutigen bei ihm, des Spielenden u. Verbindenden, des Rein-Klavieristischen, Rein-Violinmäßigen, Rein-Orchestralen u. dgl. zu vermissen hätten?  Macht es Ihnen <tei:hi rend="italic">Br</tei:hi>’s Erfindung nicht verdächtig, daß sie stets nur im <tei:hi rend="italic">Patos</tei:hi>, in der <tei:hi rend="italic">Extase</tei:hi>, oder – im Ländler steckt?  Weiß man es obendrein nicht richtig abzuschätzen, <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> welchen Schaden eine so geartete Erfindungsgabe gerade der Symphonie zufügen muß, ist man <tei:hi rend="italic">bona fide</tei:hi> sicher zunächst geneigt, die Erfindung desto höher einzuschätzen je patetischer, je extatischer sie in Erscheinung tritt.  Man meint, je grandioser das Themenmaterial, desto himmlischer u. reicher offenbar auch der Urquell, aus dem jenes erfließt.  Und doch ist das alles ein Trugschluß.</tei:p><tei:p>Gab ich oben gerne zu, daß die einzelne Momente bei <tei:hi rend="italic">Br.</tei:hi> groß, u. erhaben sind,  so mache ich mich gleichwohl noch keines Widerspruches schuldig, wenn ich behaupte, daß <tei:hi rend="italic">Br.</tei:hi> trotz alledem nur eine sehr geringe Erfindungskraft besaß.  Denn <tei:hi rend="italic">Br.</tei:hi> fehlte es nämlich an jenem spezifischen Kompositionstalent, das man in der Literatur die spezif. schriftstellerische Begabung nennt, an jener flüssigen Disposition, wie -fin- bei allen Meistern die erste Vorraussetzung stets gewesen, u. bis ans Ende der Welt eine solche bei allen schöpferischen Wesen bleiben wird.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit diesem Mangel an Erfindungsgabe hängt es fürs Erste zusammen, daß sich <tei:hi rend="italic">Br.</tei:hi>’s Erfindung ^blos^ in periodischen Anfällen von Extase äußerte, zwischen denen ein Nichts lag.</tei:p><tei:p>Der Moment der Extase bescherte ihm die Takte 8 bis 12;  nun begann die Unsere: was weiter?</tei:p><tei:p>Es liegt in der Natur solcher Momente, daß sie wohl weniger eine fortlaufende Stimmung des Komp. bilden;–wohin käme auch nur die physis- [<tei:hi rend="italic">incomplete</tei:hi>]</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten incomplete letter draft from Schenker to Grunsky, undated, possibly dating from c. June 1(?), 1908</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in top margin, in pencil in S’s hand:</tei:hi>]  To Grunsky about Bruckner</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Pardon!  The subject that you assigned me<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> did lure me irresistibly to answer you immediately, but quite difficult conditions hindered me in doing it.  You should see later, though, that I am a completely different person than adverse circumstances must have made me appear to you, unfortunately, at the time.</tei:p><tei:p>Further, the contract for a second edition of a work already several years old<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> came up suddenly—it happened on April 1<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>—and its completion had also become so urgent that I even had to put aside the final sheets of <tei:hi rend="italic">Counterpoint</tei:hi> because of it.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  I am going to direct UE, Vienna, to have that work sent to you right away (my edition of C. P. E. Bach, complete with the <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Beitrag zur Ornamentik</tei:hi></tei:hi>)<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> (I hope [this will be] possible within two-to-three weeks at the latest), because I am interested for you to read at least the first pages of it, for which sake alone I actually subjected myself to the trouble of the remaining work, which in principle would not have even occurred to me.  For already there, seizing the opportunity, I tried to dispel several generally held prejudices of a technical nature regarding sonata "form," which will of course be addressed much more fully in the third volume of my project.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>  In the meantime, though, I would like to request that you have your <tei:hi rend="italic">Aesthetics</tei:hi> sent to me <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi>, which I unfortunately have not yet gotten to know.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/>  I already have your Bruckner works, in individual booklets, but thank you nevertheless for sending the now completed whole.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/></tei:p><tei:p>Your frank letter<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> causes me also to be more open, and I will gladly tell you the whole truth in the matter of Bruckner such as up to now I have never had the desire to tell even my committed friends Löwe<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/> and Schalk<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> (whom you know?) because of the public, unfortunately, as well as mainly also because of their own past.  Every line from you tells me that—in acccordance with a disposition of character encountered so rarely today and not evaluated highly enough—you do not feel bound by any office, by any sort of deference to the public, party, or press such that you would have to decline to hear and to represent the truth ^in questions of art^.  Now down to business!</tei:p><tei:p>Not just to bring me closer to you but rather in honest gratitude I say up front:  I have always evaluated Bruckner’s +themes+ more highly than all invention of all other composers (^that^ of a Brahms, Dvořák, Wolf excepted, of course), and so it remains still today.  The gap from Bruckner to the others is so great that they don’t even deserve to be mentioned alongside of him.  And what I am yet more thankful for is Bruckner’s genuine, typical +good composition+, in which he stands sky high above all, all of today!  Compared with him, the <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> real tone craftsmen, the composers of today—not a single one excepted!—simply no longer appear as musicians.  He wrote in our musical language ^of which, however, the Hummel-composers know nothing^ ^genuinely and well^; the others babble some kind of „Matabele-jargon,“<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> which could need another eight-to-ten centuries ^of evolution^ before it can finally serve as a language of art, at the same time, however, to reach the stage where our musical language has been for some time.</tei:p><tei:p>Nevertheless I ^still cannot call^ Bruckner a master, ^let alone^ see in him an advancement in any regard whatsoever.  The reasons are of a purely technical nature and will find their place extensively in the third volume.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn13"/>  Here I can therefore sketch them only fleetingly ^and provisionally for you^.</tei:p><tei:p>What would you say if for us Beethoven were contained, for example, only in the grandiose openings of the Ninth, Fifth, of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Leonore</tei:hi>, the <tei:hi rend="italic">Egmont</tei:hi> Overture, and in so many other equally dramatic passages in the middle of the Third, the Fifth, of the last piano sonatas and string quartets, but we otherwise were to miss in him the other, unfathomable world of the charming, of the playful, the engaging, of the purely pianistic, the purely violinistic, purely orchestral, and the like?  Does it not make you suspicious that Bruckner’s invention resides always only in pathos, in ecstasy, or—in the Ländler?  If we do not know from the outset how properly to assess <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> what damage such a gift of invention must do to the symphony in particular, we are in good faith certainly inclined, at first, to assess the invention as higher the more dramatically, the more ecstatically it manifests itself.  We think the more grandiose the thematic material, all the more heavenly and rich, apparently, also the source from which it flows.  And yet all of that is a fallacy.</tei:p><tei:p>Although I gladly conceded above that isolated moments in Bruckner are grand and sublime, I am nonetheless not guilty of any contradiction if, despite all of that, I assert that Bruckner possessed only a very minimal powers of invention.  For Bruckner lacked namely that specific compositional talent which in literature we call the specific literary talent, that fluent disposition as has always been the first condition with all masters, and up to the end of the world will always remain so for all creative beings.</tei:p><tei:p>First of all, the fact that Bruckner’s invention expressed itself ^purely^ in periodic stretches between which emptiness lay is linked to that defect in inventive talent.</tei:p><tei:p>The moment of ecstasy granted him measures 8 through 12.  Then ours began:  what next?</tei:p><tei:p>It resides in the nature of such moments that they surely form less a sustained mood of the composer—to what point would then come the physi... [<tei:hi rend="italic">incomplete</tei:hi>]</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>