<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OC 18/29 : 1-5-33 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  Under inquiry. 
©  Transcription Robert Wason, 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Robert Wason 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission being sought.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1933-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-1938) - -Oster, Ernst (1938-c.1939)—New York Public Library (c.1939-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Frederick Auslander; Image: New York Public Library; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Robert Wason.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 01/05/1933 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Auslander ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Typed letter in English from Auslander to Schenker, dated January 5, 1933</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-01-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Introduces himself and seeks permission to translate some of Schenker's works into English.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Auslander, Frederick;  Schenker, Heinrich;  translation</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> 1163-47th Street, Brooklyn, New York</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Vienna, Keilgasse 8</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Typed letter in English from Auslander to Schenker, dated January 5, 1933</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>1163-47^th^ Street
Brooklyn, New York
January 5, 1933<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> Schenker notes that he has written to Auslander, presumably in answer to this letter, in a diary entry of January 28, 1933 (OJ 4/6, p. 3,808).  The letter is not known to survive.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Dr. Heinrich Schenker
Wien, 3 Keilgasser[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] 8
Austreich[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Sir:</tei:p><tei:p>To introduce myself, permit me to state that I am privileged to study with your colleague, Dr. Weisse,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>. </tei:note> in the Composers’ Class which he directs at the David Mannes School of Music.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> Click on <ref cRef="mannes_music_school">Mannes Music School</ref>.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>It is through Dr. Weisse that the writer has become initiated, as it were, into the mysteries of your startling and quite revolutionary theory of music analysis.  Imbued as I am with the most sincere enthusiasm for the intellectual enlightenment which your theory offers, I conferred with Dr. Weisse as to the possibility of my translating into English some of your works from the original German.  He appeared more than pleased and assured me that he would be happy to assist me in a material way, especially in the problem of terminology.</tei:p><tei:p>I should deem it a privilege to be the medium through which your works may be presented to the English-speaking world. On the other hand, I should like to receive your permission and the permission of your publishers to undertake this project so that I may feel assured that my work would not merely duplicate another’s who may have already commenced along similar lines.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> It seems that Auslander was not unaware of the interest in translating Schenker’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> expressed by Arthur Waldeck to Schenker in a letter of September 22, 1932 (see OC 18/34).  After conferring with UE, Schenker set up the necessary conditions for such a project in a letter to Waldeck of November 8, 1932 (NYma, [2]).  By this point, Schenker must have asked Hans Weisse what he knew about Waldeck, for Weisse writes to Schenker, in a letter of November 28, 1932 (OC 18/32–33), that he remembers Waldeck as having attended his lectures of the previous year.  Among Schenker’s conditions was a sample of Waldeck’s efforts, of which he noted receipt in his diary on December 27, 1932 (OJ 4/6, p. 3,800).  In a letter of December 31, 1932 (OJ 5/44, [3]), Schenker told Waldeck that he was sending the sample on to Weisse for his expert judgment on the quality of the translation, noting that he had done so in the diary (OJ 4/6, p. 3,801).  In a letter to Schenker of February 15, 1933 (OJ 15/16), Weisse voices skepticism regarding Auslander’s ability to carry out the project, writing that “he will have to study for a good while before he will even be able to approach the translation of any of your works.  I even have some doubt as to whether he has sufficient mastery of German that he will really to be able to understand what you have written.” Though Weisse’s opinion of Waldeck’s sample translation has apparently not survived (if indeed he ever wrote to Schenker on the matter), the complete translation itself (two copies of which are at NYma) demonstrates a competent command of the language, even if it is not entirely unproblematic.</tei:note> I should also like to inquire which of your many works you would prefer to have the writer translate at this time.</tei:p><tei:p>Please accept my very heartiest congratulations on your brilliant work, and believe me to be</tei:p><tei:p>Very respectfully yours
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]	Frederick E.  Auslander
Frederick E.  Auslander<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> Nothing is known about Auslander, though it has recently been asserted that he was 22 years old when he wrote to Schenker (David Carson Berry, “Hans Weisse and the Dawn of American Schenkerism,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Journal of Musicology</tei:hi> 20/1 (Winter, 2003): 104-56; see p. 152).</tei:note></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>